hello everyone and welcome back to Cale
office hours I am Daniela ruse the
director of Cale where we are inventing
the future of computing and making the
world better through Computing today our
Focus will be on health and how
Computing and AI can help with
diagnosing monitoring and treating
disease Dina you have made so many
impactful contributions to communication
and to understanding Wireless signals
how did you think to move from studying
networking to applying Wireless signals
to the healthcare sector maybe about
eight years ago we started looking into
how we can use um radio signals to
monitor physiological signals so that
was the early set of results basically
just understanding that radio signal
bounce around and they bounce out the
human body because we are made of water
so signal comes and reflects and then if
you analyze those Reflections
particularly if you analyze them with
the power of neural network in machine
learning you can start learning things
that you couldn't imagine that these
radio signals around us have or carry
about us such as of course our
respiration the pulsing of our blood
even when you go to sleep we can tell
whether you are in the dreaming stage
for example ra versus you are in light
sleep or deep sleep and then that took
us to the Next Generation not just
monitoring the physiological signals of
people using radio signals without
touching them but also collecting that
data and starting to develop neural
network model for uh diagnosing and
tracking like what's called biomarkers
of diseases for Parkinson's for other
newgeneration diseases and the final
the most recent thing is Gen AI for uh
Medical Data with your algorithms and
your insights in Wireless networking you
can see what we cannot see with a naked
eye how does this work it takes many
years to diagnose Parkinson like
somebody may had Parkinson 10 years ago
and they haven't been diagnosed because
one of the issue is that you wait for
the motor symptoms you know in Parkinson
the Tremor the stiffness of the motion
and these motor symptoms
appear late in the Disease by the time
the motor symptoms appear the uh the
dopamine neurons which are the neurons
involved in in Parkinson about 40 to 80%
are already damaged when we learned this
we were just like oh but can we diagnose
it from other signals now that we have
these devices in people's home and we
just take the wireless signal maybe from
warless we know that we can get people
breathing let me just try to detect
whether they have parking from their
breathing because there are some
hypotheses that breathing like is
impacted by the uh basically that
Parkinson comes from the GS along the
vagus nerve and then it has the
breathing area in the brain so breathing
changes earlier but actually it turned
out that you can diagnose or machine
learning algorithm can diagnose
Parkinson with high accuracy from
someone's breathing what is it that the
intersection of understanding Wireless
signals and understanding machine
learning what is it at this intersection
that helps you solve this problem we are
not trained to look at radio signals but
machine actually when you train them
with the right output they they first
they can sense the signal and they can
start seeing patterns that the human
brain is not trained to see from sensory
signals that we don't have like
electromagnetic waves where does this
data come from the data that you use to
train your models we designed a device
that looks very much like your Wi-Fi box
at home so sit in the background of the
home and it's like analyzing these
radial reflection transmit very low
power Wireless signal analyzing the
reflection and analyze them neural
network and from that it can be like you
don't have to wear devices on yourself
people can live their lives and you can
just get all of that insight to clinical
data but it also convey the information
to the medical doctor to the
practitioner who's the expert and can
help them can this model monitor for
multiple diseases or is it finally tuned
for Parkinson's U monitors multiple
diseases particularly interested also I
find the the biggest opportunity is in
neurology and Immunology so it's very
hard to to study neurological diseases
even things like depression we ask
people how do you feel but give you like
a drug or treatment he said there's no
actual concrete measurements to do that
that's where we are seeing like our
results from being able to concretely
and objectively measure the physiology
of the person and how it changes we can
see a major uh opportunity to have a um
what's called biomarket in this context
digital biomarker for these complex
diseases can you tell us a little bit
more about Immunology what are you
looking at in the space one essential
thing of the immune system is that you
are talking about a dynamic system a
that is changing like it's just your
immune response it's a response flare up
there are flares you change you are in
remission if you have like an autoimmune
disease you are in remission and then
you have a flare but in the whole
medical system we don't have a the like
all of the tests that we do are
snapshots like when we talk in computer
science we talk about snapshots ver
versus like continuous tracking we don't
have the continuous tracking and
clinical data for that continuously can
track a dynamic system like the immune
system there is a hugee opportunity here
to be able to move from snapshots
particularly when you are talking about
inflammatory response immune response to
continuous data and where we can see
where we are using our devices and Ai
and to track these changes so are you
finding that the Wi-Fi signals reflect
differently if there is an immune system
flare up when they bounce off my body
your body the environment they change
based on everything your respiration the
pulsing of the blood the twitching of
your eyes like different muscles all of
the behavior that we have and things
that we don't even think as of as
Behavior so the physics of how the
reflections happen don't change but when
you extract this information from those
Reflections now those change your
respiratory system response to
inflammation is going to be different
your sleep and sleep patterns will
change if somebody has a particular
disease or taking particular drug so
those then you can think about Ai and
two levels one level is like taking
radio signals and extracting from the
physiological signals and then another
level of neural networks that takes
those physiological signal continuously
extract it from the radio signal and
start talking does this person have
Alzheimer does this person have
Parkinson how did their Parkinson change
are they taking anti-depressant are they
responding to is anti-depressant how do
you use generative AI to get to better
results being able to to take some
simple signals or let's say like
something from your Fitbit or some like
your your pulse or something and
transform that using generative AI to
clinical test that was the use of
generative AI that we are looking at and
we actually do have initial data that
shows that this is doable and the
generated data is very much similar to
the actual real data from the medical
test for that person your generative AI
system for medical data is it um what is
the raw data used to train it we move
from one medical modality that is cheap
to a medical modality that is expensive
a cheap medical modality it's it's kind
of like a wellness modality like if I
take the the PPG from uh like the puling
from like AR device
or uh the breathing from radio signal
these are cheap available and easily and
from that I generate something that is
expensive like an EEG signal for example
for the brain Dina it sounds like you
have invented a new technology that is
noninvasive and that gives doctors a
kind of a superpower because it allows
them to see things that are impossible
to see with today's Technologies
medicine I think there's a huge
potential for competition in general I
think even without a there are plenty of
opportunity for competition but with
machine learning also the the
opportunities go even higher thank you
for putting so much thought and effort
in making healthc care better let's go
meet MIT professor John gag John has
been working with artificial
intelligence and machine learning to
develop the field of healthcare
information
and he has been looking at how machine
learning can enhance the diagnosis of
cardiac
disease my first work in healthc care
and AI was in in cardiovascular medicine
and I had the good fortune that Colin
staltz who's a member of cesil and a
faculty member in eecs is also a
practicing cardiologist Colin and I have
been looking a lot at can we use
non-invasive signals to get good
approximations of data that is usually
gathered invasively so the best example
is probably an ECG measures the
electrical activity of the heart every
patient in the hospital is typically has
an ECG connected to them what's been
interesting is the things you might not
expect to be able to get out of that
signal but we think you can with the
right kind of Technology machine
learning machine learning to learn it
but then of course when you're running
it in practice you have to have forward
passes that run fast the role of machine
learning is to train a model that will
give the right predictions is that right
we use machine learning in healthc care
in a lot of different ways sometimes
it's used to train models that we'll
actually
deploy but other times we use it to do
what I'll call science and and learn
about things
and once we've learned about them then
the model maybe you don't need it
anymore you you you've learned something
you've done some experiments it's helped
you learn things if we think of
experience learning as you generating
hypotheses that can then be tested in
clinical settings or in the
lab then you don't have to trust the
model because all the model is doing is
giving you things that you're going to
test once the model generate finds
hypotheses
you can then maybe look for uh
mechanistic
explanations or look for rules maybe
it's just discovering a rule and you can
explain the rule to somebody and oh yeah
that's a sensible Rule and so I think a
lot of the use of machine learning today
in
healthcare is in the science part of it
where we're discovering things that can
then be used in the clinic we started
with communicable diseases and we did
that in conjunction with MGH with the
infection control Department there so
the infection control Department's
responsibility is to reduce the
incidence of healthc care Associated
infections in the hospital we were
approached to look at the question of
could we use machine
learning to find ways to reduce the
prevalence of Health Care infections in
in the hospital and the one we focus on
to start with was uh CI the most common
one it's an intestinal disease bacterial
disease our
models
predicted which patients were most
likely to contract the disease if you
know that someone is likely to contract
the disease you'll be more aggressive
about knowing when to test them and that
will let you discover they have it
sooner and our treatment sooner and so
what we did is we built models that were
quite effective at determining which
members of the population were most
vulnerable so if we look at what makes
people susceptible uh some of what we
found was already known when the uh ant
some
antimicrobials uh increase the
likelihood of Contracting
sedi and some more than others we
found zip code
was important now he said how on Earth
can where a patient lives matter some of
what they think of Hospital acquired was
actually the bacterium was already in
the patient system and then something
that happened in the hospital allowed it
to flourish and get worse and so the
bacterium came from the community and it
was say the treatment in the hospital
that made it flourish suddenly it made
sense and we looked at these zip codes
and for example there were often zip
codes that had a lot of nursing homes in
them so John for this uh work in
communicable diseases can you tell us a
bit about the techniques that you have
used about the computational aspects of
the solutions one of the things that's
interesting about a communicable disease
is is the fact that you need exposure
and that means you have to look at
Network
effects and a lot of machine learning
algorithms don't really deal with
Networks
and so a lot of what we did was was
looking at at connectivity networks to
try and and and build models based upon
that and you use machine learning for
that yes how did you train your models
we were able to get access to all of the
MGH patient records you can look at the
patient record and see which nurses are
visiting which patients which doctors
are visiting which patients where they
are we actually looked at the
architecture of the hospital but the
most important network was the caregiver
Network what are you working on right
now the biggest investment in my lab
right now is in medical imaging and
machine learning has is in the process
of totally revolutionizing Medical
Imaging so if you think of the amount of
data produced by an
MRI it's three-dimensional high
resolution typically and it's more data
than a human can possibly look at there
are a small number of tasks that you
have to do for any kind of image one of
them is
segmentation so that involves you take
an image and you find Regions that are
anatomically significant and separate
them from the rest of the image so
segmentation is very important but not
just for things like tumors for a lot of
say neurological diseases you want to
look at the shape of say the hippocampus
you know what is this exact shape is the
shape changing and to do that you have
to find it and segment it very precisely
we have built something which we call
univers EG Universal segmentor it's
important because the other Universal
segmentors that are out there and there
quite a few work only for natural images
really they don't work very well for
medical images and you need something
that's very Broad
because there are an enormous number of
different modalities ultrasound to x-ray
to to Mr to Optical to ooc all sorts of
things he collected an enormous amount
of data from many different Medical
Imaging modalities many different tasks
we then invented ways to generate
synthetic data if you look at our
synthetic data it doesn't look like any
medical image anyone has ever seen or
any task anyone has ever seen but it
makes it prevents the model from
overfitting to the actual tasks you show
it during the training other thing we've
done with Universe egg is is it's what's
called context based learning at
inference time when someone is trying to
say segment something that they don't
know how to segment what we do is you
give it a small number of examples and
that's used as a prompt to say oh that's
the kind of that's what they're looking
for and then based upon that small
context and all of the other examples
that's been trained on it then can
generate quite good
segmentations and we think eventually
will be as good right now if you train a
a one of model for one modality and one
Anatomy it's slightly better than the
universal segmentor as you think about
computational tools
and their potential in healthare where
do you see us going in the next 3 to 5
years the large population studies will
be the first thing impacted I think by a
lot of the machine learning technology
and I think it'll have enormous impact
on things like tele medicine instead of
having a person move to the clinic we
acquire data and send the data to a
computer and the data the computer looks
at it and I think we can make very quick
inroads in using machine learning to
build models that will
improve the health care system if Health
Care gets less expensive we'll get
better outcomes an awful lot of people
don't get the treatment they need today
because they can't afford it if we can
reduce the cost it isn't just saving
money it will give us better
outcomes John thank you so much for
sharing with us your work your results
and your wisdom about the use of
computational tools in healthcare now
let's go to see what Professor marier
gasmi has been up
to I want to start by asking you about
your work in rule violations and so you
have shown that AI models fail to
reproduce human judgment in identifying
rule violations what is this all about
well the issue is that when we label
machine learning data sets in standard
settings we're always asking people if a
feature exists is a dog big or is a meal
sugary but that's not actually why we
train machine Learning Systems we
usually train them to predict a
violation of some rule is this meal too
sugary for the school rules or is this
dog too large for the building's Rule
and so in that setting it's really
important that we tell people you're
going to be judging whether a dog is
large for a rule violation because what
we found is that people's Judgment of
whether a dog is large actually flips
when you tell them that it's being used
to create a rule in a machine Learning
System how does this translate to
medicine if we have labels that don't
reflect the ultimate judgment that's
being made it's possible that some
people will be denied services that a
human judgment would have given them in
the first place so what can we do about
this we can look at giving more uh
specific prompts to people who are
judging whether a feature is present in
an image or in text or in tabular data
and let them know that this judgment
will be used in a specific human rule
setting and when they have that context
we think that they'll make better
judgments so we can have machine
learning systems that mimic human
judgments what we found is that when you
try to improve the models that are using
this data you have to make assumptions
about how harsh the system should be and
so when we looked at algorithmic
improvements if you can make good gu
guesses about where the threshold might
be for the data so for example I know
you've labeled this feature about a
large dog factually but if I asked you
subjectively whether it's a large dog in
violation of a rule if you can guess
what that would do to somebody's
judgments then you can try to fix some
of this on the algorithm side but
couldn't you tweak it too much the other
way so couldn't the system be abused
then that's why we think there needs to
be a holistic difference in How We
Gather these labels in machine learning
data sets you can't fix it all with the
algorithm this is something we really
need to change from the ground up and
how would this look for medicine well in
medicine what we've been looking at
recently is how we can give doctors
descriptive or prescriptive
recommendations for different kinds of
actions when you think about the ways
that you could give advice to somebody
usually it's based on an if then rule so
if the meal is sugary then it's a rule
violation or if the patient has a risk
of mental illness then refer them to a
psychiatrist and so we want to to look
at whether these descriptions of whether
a meal is sugary or a dog is large were
the right thing to give a patient or
their Advocate versus the Judgment this
prescriptive action of saying that a dog
is in violation or a meal is in
violation or a patient should see a
psychiatrist and so what we did is we
looked at different settings such as
Mental Health crisis lines where you
could either say that a patient has a
risk of violence or that you should call
the police to help that patient and we
wanted to look at what happened when we
gave very biased advice from an AI
system to doctors either descriptively
saying there's always a risk of violence
for minorities or prescriptively saying
you should call the police on minorities
consistently what we found is that if
you give really biased AI advice to
doctors in a descriptive way you just
say that there's a high risk of violence
for all the minority patients doctors
don't listen to it they retain their
original Fair judgment but when you tell
them to call the police
disproportionately then they do listen
to it so this prescriptive
recommendation that tells what to do
somehow short circuits critical thinking
skills and so in health specifically we
need to think carefully about not only
what predictions were making but also
exactly how we deliver those predictions
and what we find is with these
descriptive systems you're giving them
the rules and they're able to follow
through on these judgments and have
really good critical thinking skills but
when we give them the end result just
shortcut to the answer they don't
actually go through the process and so
they miss mistakes that the model might
make and so it's crucial that when you
have a system helping people it helps
them through the thinking process not
through this sort of efficient shortcut
that they could have we find that when
people are very good at the task then
you can train a machine learning system
based on past labels in this data and
then that model will be so good that you
could probably just use a prescriptive
system and say go ahead and follow the
model we think that most of the data we
have while it's good it has errors it
has flaws there's variation and so we
want people to continue to understand
how to make these decisions with advice
but not always follow it now in addition
to descriptive and prescriptive
Solutions you're also considering
normative Solutions normative Solutions
are things that we believe that people
should do in most cases that others have
judged as being the right decisions to
make this doesn't always happen in a
health care setting but there are some
really wellestablished care pathways you
can look at in machine learning for
health where we know the right things to
do we want to reduce the variation in
how different patients are treated and
have a more normative solution because
we know the right answer so how do you
go from descriptive and prescriptive to
normative for many chronic conditions
there's huge variation one person's
diabetes is not another person's
diabetes one person's pregnancy is not a
person's pregnancy and so because
there's a length of time over which you
have different complications there's
going to be so much room for variation
but a septic patient is often a septic
patient they're so acutely ill that the
way that you can treat them the number
of levers you have to pull they're very
small and the variation is also very
small and so we'd like to have more
normative actions this work is so
important and it raises such profound
ethics issues with deploying AI in
medicine when you give advice to
somebody who's already Bound by an
Ethics code as all clinical staff and
clinicians are are what is your
additional responsibility as a technical
person who's contributing to their
interaction with a human system there's
no easy answer but what we're trying to
do right now is understand where all the
biases in the process are from
collecting the data to defining the
labels to developing the algorithm to
deploying specific advice and we think
by codifying those and auditing them and
letting the people actually using the
systems know what's happening we can
have a better end to-end system where
doctors make those judgments what else
are you excited about what's the future
in your lab having systems that can flag
incorrect data from the get-go in large
systems in an unsupervised way this is
definitely a problem in health it's also
a problem in places like computer vision
where we know that images of abuse and
inappropriate treatment make it into
large image data sets and then if you're
not looking through these huge sets of
images they can make it into Downstream
models so if we have systems that can
successfully audit data sets then we can
have a better set of data to learn from
from the beginning and then all the way
on the other side I'm really excited
about understanding how we can take
deployments and deliver advice in a way
that doesn't perpetuate biases but helps
clinicians create more Equitable
Healthcare Systems within their practice
we don't want to create supervised
systems for identifying bad quality or
inappropriate data Within These large
data corpora because that just doesn't
scale instead what we want to do is look
at the different views of data that
exist within large scale embedding
spaces and then use these different
views as self-supervised learning where
one view of an image is contrasted with
another view and we think that
differences between the ways that
different models view data will
highlight when data is inappropriate or
incorrectly labeled marsia that sounds
so interesting and important and I can't
wait to hear about the new results thank
you for having me