okay good
afternoon okay
so the last time we defined
the diffusive and convective
flaxes
I I want to review this um
definition with some uh
Graphics uh the idea is that
uh we have a a
Continuum with all the assumptions that
go under this this
description and uh suppose that anywhere
somewhere inside your Continuum you will
set up a small um surface area
with a an
oriented normal
n and then you look at uh what
properties and here we are talking about
uh the extensive properties those that
we said that can be described as
integrals over
volume uh
of densities of those of that properties
like energy entropy Mass
momentum so this is pro how much of that
property crosses uh the um that uh
area and which and with which um U speed
so how much it transfers it goes across
divided by the area of this surface that
we call uh
D
Omega and divided by
the time interval during which we
measure the amount that
crosses
that uh defines the
flux
uh so let's consider first the flux the
measurement in terms of the reference
frame of the
laboratory and that we call it J
Zer I also call it lren but maybe the
term lent is not really appropriate but
in any case it's it's the flux with
respect to the laboratory reference
frame and once I have done that and I
know the um density which means the
property per unit uh uh volume that
prevails in that
position that defines also a
velocity which is the velocity of
transport of that
property which is this Vector
here okay so multiply so the long Vector
is is the flux the short Vector is the
velocity one of the properties is
Mass so if I do that same measurement
for mass I get the flux of
mass which is what we call
Momentum momentum density and
uh and the velocity associated with with
that flux we call it bicentric velocity
of the flow it's the velocity of fluid
mechanics
okay then we Define also a a uh for
property a we go back to property a and
we Define a relative velocity so the
difference between VA
and the velocity with which uh fluid
Parcels uh cross that
surface which is the ventric
velocity so the difference you compute
since these are vectors the this way
know like the typical Vector
construction so this blue Vector is the
difference between the two it's the
relative velocity it's the velocity of
transport of property a relative to the
bicentric
velocity and then you
multiply by the same factor that goes
between the short and the long Vector
here so the density of property a and
that gives you the diffusive flux of
property a
and the
difference between j z and the diffusive
flat is flux is the convective flux
which is this Vector red Vector which of
course by construction is directed in
the same direction as
the velocity bicentric
velocity and so you can take it also as
the bicentric velocity times the density
of property a so it's this Vector
here
okay then we have defined uh this
extension or generalization of the idea
of a heat
interaction to when of the same in the
same way as we did heat we
approach the interactions between
systems that uh uh are
almost in mutual equilibrium so exactly
or almost exactly the same temperature
and the same chemical
potentials and they
exchange not only energy but also
amounts of
constituents and the relation Q overt
for heat generalizes to this relation
between the flux of entropy the flux of
energy the flux of uh
constituents
here we
are introducing also this variables that
are sort of
shorthand instead of carrying all the
times one over the temperature we just
call it
tow which I know it's a bit
unfortunate nomenclator because then we
will use to double underline also for
the stress tensor
but that double underline will will keep
the difference and also
Lambda Lambda J denotes uh minus the the
potential over T so we use Lambda or
Lambda tot for the chemical potential or
the total
potential and so the relation
between
energy will
energy entropy and uh
n is is can be written this way so once
we have this relation between vectors
we're going to use it for example in the
balance equations where there is a
Divergence of of the
flaxes um well we can take the the
Divergence of these and that's how it
goes it's typically a product so the
Divergence of a product of a scalar
times a vector is given by these two
terms the gradient of the scalar dotted
into the vector times the scalar times
the Divergence of the
vector now remember that
energy in our model has a several
components one is uh the internal energy
proper of the stable equilibrium state
that is underlying that is there that
would be the only thing if we view our
fluid element from a reference frame
that moves with uh the bicentric
velocity and therefore with respect to
that reference frame there is no uh
kinetic energy and also an accelerated
frame where you don't also see the
potential gravitational energy and then
here you have the additional
contribution for the
electrostatic um
energy if you
multiply this by row and I I put all the
stars just to be pedantic but at least
we know that we're talking what we're
talking about
uh um we get this um expression
here the total po potential therefore is
Define this way it's the derivative of e
with respect to n uh is given by these
contributions the chemical potential
plus uh this potential for
kinetic
um gravitational and
electrostatic
potentials
okay so this is where we were I guess
and of course we the next step is to uh
substitute uh these assumptions about
the interactions between fluid
elements into the uh energy uh entropy
constituent balance and here I've also
done although I'm not going to talk too
much about it but I also written the
momentum balance that this is the fluid
mechanics uh
part for reference and uh as you
remember I have written the balance
balance equation in the two equivalent
forms that we have
derived one in terms of the lent
flues with the partial derivative of Ro
with respect to time the other with
respect to the diffusive flaxes with the
material
derivative uh of of the mass specific
properties we
proved the last time that these are
equivalent
from these equations
here and
possibly um well no from these equations
here you can obtain also these other
equations below that I'm skipping uh the
details but it's
simply uh for example uh the equation
for the conservation of mass which
derives from this one of the amounts
multiplied by the molecular masses this
is the so-call continuity equation of
mechanics which you can also write this
way and so this is the the Divergence of
V
represents uh the rate of change of the
volume of your fluid element as you
follow it during the motion during the
flow along its
path and typically uh
unless the flow is very Speedy so unless
the the mark number is is is
high uh you can assume incompressible
flow and so this Divergence is equal to
zero but for example from the momentum
balance equation if you dot it
into VM the velocity you can obtain a
balance for the kinetic
energy and then you can also get a
balance for the gravitational potential
energy and and a balance for the
electrostatic potential energy so
that you can uh
subtract from the overall energy of your
fluid
uh uh uh
the um the internal
energy and so that difference is made up
of just kinetic potential gravitational
and electrostatic so the sum of these
three gives you
this and it's the rate of change of the
mechanical
energy uh content of uh of your uh
fluid
okay and now we can put them all
together so we have
assumed the local simple system
equilibrium so that we can
write uh the energy this way that we
just just
described uh the simple system Model
includes the oiler relations so that
together it allows you to write the Gibs
relation in this
way remember T is 1 / T and Lambda is
minus mu over
T which as you uh
recall gets rid of the
pressure so that the if you need the
pressure need to go to the Gibs do
relation to get you the pressure from
the uh concentrations and temperature
gradients uh so we are going to assume
this relation between the properties of
the particles and notice this is the
internal energy just this part of the
energy so we assume this relation holds
as You Follow the the fluid particle
along its
path so that assume that it is
valid uh for the material
derivatives that
means that uh the left hand side of the
balance equations uh that we have in the
previous slide where we have these uh
material derivatives they are related we
can essentially uh substitute the
balance equations into this one and we
get an
extra
relation
plus we are going to
assume the mode of interaction that we
call heat and
diffusion to
be uh
valid and holding between uh
fluid
elements as they move
along so it's the
diffusive fluxes that are related in
that way that we have
discussed with the exclusion
though of the flux of energy which is uh
related which is which is
work because when you have the fluid
element that deforms
especially uh it changes in in
volume uh that change in volume against
uh the normal components of the
stress uh imply work that is a kind of
interaction between adjacent fluid
elements that is not of the Heat and
diffusion kind so we
excluded that's why I call this uh NW
non work so the nonwork component of the
heat transfer between uh the fluid
elements as they move along the path
line uh is related to entropy flux and
constituent flux as in the heat
diffusion mode of
interaction but energy has an additional
contribution which is the work
component given by the stress tensor
into the
velocity okay this one as we said we
take uh since in the balance equations
there appear divergencies all this stuff
all these
fluxes um we can combine those with the
Divergence of this uh relation which is
here and a few things will come cancel
out and here are the terms that
survive and we write what
survives as an expression we took on the
left hand side only the rate of entropy
production the density of entropy
production so the rate of entropy
production per unit volume
Sigma and we have on the right hand side
all the terms that contribute to that
entropy
production this is the most General uh
form it uh includes all sorts of terms
one is an old friend of from chemical um
kinetics this term here will give rise
as you will see to the dissipation
function of fluid mechanics we see it in
a
moment the first term
is the one that U uh gives
the the Fier uh expression when you have
only uh heat and not also diffusion and
these are terms that we have to see what
they do because they do important uh
effects for many Publications
now the other time we
also
uh have seen how to uh
recognize uh in the
um heat I'm sorry energy uh in the
energy flux a portion of the energy flux
that we can still recognize as and call
heat or we call it the measurable heat
more properly but essentially it's the
part that we
can identify with the heat of heat
transfer so again with this Q double
prime
notation so if we take the nonwork part
of the energy flux it's given by the
heat
plus a portion which is related to the
flux so it's this is the energy which is
carried by uh the particles
uh
in just because they are
diffusing this is not convective because
this is a
diffusive part so this is part particles
that are moving different at a different
velocity than the bicentric velocity so
they diffuse away or into our fluid
element and as they do so they carry
with them their backpack of internal
energy and plus they also have to
um advance and face the the pressure
that is present and therefore there is
also this
uh there is this pure work which is p
times the the uh partial volume which is
hidden here because you remember the
enthalpy is U plus PV so this is a
partial enthalpy so it's partial energy
plus uh P times partial volume and uh
and that P times partial volume is the
pulsion work equivalent to what you
would have in a bulk flow
situation but here we are in diffusion
okay so we can
substitute this terms here into our
expression and this is a very typical
procedure that uh we
like uh somehow to
express uh to rewrite every time you
formulate a a problem in non equilibrium
thermodynamics you typically typically
start and it's the safer way to do it uh
start from the entropic point of view so
you write it in this way you identify
these gradients as
the degrees of non-e equilibrium related
to the various transport of the various
properties but then you like to
translate this into a more common and
familiar language and we since we
consider more familiar talking about
heat because it's related to q and Q
over t uh we often go back to these and
then also the fluxes of particles um and
and the chemical
potentials uh so we substitute this to
there we also use a relation that uh I
think we we've we' we've
discussed that you can write uh when you
write the differential of the chemical
potential you can separate the part that
depends on temperature and the parts
that uh changes that constant uh
temperature so it depends on pressure
and concentrations and so we we keep
that uh
part written this way and so the bottom
line is that we can write
uh the entropy production density Sigma
in this way so here we have more
explicitly the Fier kind
of entropy
production here you have a similar term
related to diffusion here we still have
the usual uh term related to chemical
kinetics and uh what is left here is the
dissipation function one over the
temperature times the dissipation
function and here are the details of the
dissipation functions if you like if you
are a fluid
mechanist uh it has two contributions
it's not just the devor deviator part of
the stress tensor and the theoric
component of the
strain temperature I'm sorry
tensor but it has also this term which
is related to the Divergence of
B and it's true that for most flu flows
like low ma number flows this is zero so
this is really not important
but uh in principle this is one of the
dissipative terms and in fact notice
also that in our doing the the procedure
here there was a
pressure uh which is which came in uh
here and there is a PM which is a
mechanical pressure that is the the the
trace over oneir of the trace of the
stress
tensor uh they're not
necessarily uh the
same and so they give rise their
difference gives rise to this
uh uh entropy production
term you can still view each of these uh
terms as a
product of a rate and an affinity or a
degree of this equilibrium so the
gradient in
temperature more properly minus one / T
squ times the gradient in temperature
can be interpreted as the degree of this
equilibrium associated with heat
uh
transport uh similarly minus one /t
times the gradient of the chemical
potential done at constant
t uh
is the degree of dise equilibrium with
respect to uh diffusion of
particles the affinities in chemical in
chemistry one / R they are already being
recognized as the degrees of the execu
equilibrium and here for for for the
fluid part we have a degree of thise
equilibrium which is related to the rate
of
strain just the symmetric part of the
rate of strain of the local stress
tensor I'm sorry velocity of the local
velocity field it's the gradient of the
Velocity field and uh whereas the
conjugated flux is the flux of momentum
which is related to
uh the stress tensor but then there is
also this one so
the Divergence of velocity which as we
said it's is the rate of change of
volume as you FL as You Follow the flu
the fluid
element that is also an
affinity for a for a
dissipation for which the flux is given
by these uh difference between the
thermodynamic pressure and the uh
mechanical
pressure if we also have um
charged particles so if some of the
constituents of our fluid that are uh
charged
particles and we still we talk
electrostatics not the electrodynamics
is is even more complicated because of
course then you get the Maxell equations
the magnetic field the vector potential
and so on too complicated to to to cover
uh and but in any case so here we have
just
electrostatics and uh so Fe is the
electrostatic
field
JQ okay JQ
is the
diffusive
component of the electric current
density because if this fluid element
contains
charges and these fluid element moves
with the bicentric
velocity okay there is a convective part
of the charge which produces an electric
current okay we're not talking about
this part we talking about the part of
uh charge exchange between adjacent
fluid elements due to the fact that they
have uh the diffusion the diffusion with
respect to the bicentric velocity so
this is diffusion flux of
charge and in fact so the total current
density would May denote it with I
double
Prime and it is the uh the flux of
charge with respect to the laboratory
frame so it's the flux with a zero on
top and it's made up of the diffusive
plus the convective
term and r q is the density of
charges the local density of
charges
so
uh the work part of the diffusive energy
flux is related to
heat to the diffusion of particles and
to the diffusion of of part of of of
charge okay so we have this extra term
which uh we can um sort of single out in
here when you do the same procedure as
before to write this expression in terms
of the familiar
variables so here
the entropy
production is related also to U minus
one / T times the gradient in the
electrostatic field is the degree of
dise equilibrium with respect
to to moving charges and the associated
or the conjugated
flux is this difference here which is
just the diffusive flux of charge
that's again the same
equation now the next step to introduce
the next notion is to group these
terms uh in order of increasing
tensorial character so some of these are
Scholars like chemistry
and
also uh inside the dissipation function
there is a scolar term which is the one
that we described before and then there
is a tensorial term which is the one
related
to uh the the contraction between the uh
deviatoric parts of stress and strain
tensors and the rest are
vectorial um terms heat
flux uh
current flux of particles these are
vectors why is that
important all right now so I I started
with um some coloring here just to
single out
the
uh the degrees of the dise equilibrium
are the red stuff and the flues are the
blue and so you see H1 is written is a
is a product of a degree of this
equilibrium time times a
flux and if we recall what we said about
exergy you can also read this uh
expression as a a representation of how
locally your uh
fluid or Continuum is dissipating exergy
multiply that by the temperature of the
environment with respect to which you
want to or the reservoir which respect
to which you want to measure
exergy and so these terms tell you that
um you have dissipation whenever you
drive like I read here you drive a
chemical
reaction uh down the direction of a
decreasing affinity and that gives you
entropy production you drive a heat flux
down great temperature
gradient also you you D you drive a
diffusion flux down a chemical potential
gradient or an electric current down a
voltage drop or a momentum flux down a
velocity uh gradient which is the rate
of
strength
okay uh you may find if you uh look into
papers that deal with nilium
thermodynamics that expression up there
this one with all these terms written in
a compact form in this way as a sum of
products of fluxes and
uh instead of degrees of dise
equilibrium they're called
forces fluxes and forces so this is a
force flux representation of the same or
or short hand notation and um this
symbol here is that is is whatever is
appropriate to use when you have to
multiply a scalar flux times a scalar um
degree of dise equilibrium it's just a
simple
multiplication like
here uh when you have to
multiply a vector another Vector it is
the dot it's the vector product I'm
soorry not sorry the dot the dot product
because the vector product is something
else and U if you have uh to multiply
the tensor two tensors and get a scal
it's the contraction so if you take the
two matrices of the two tensors you
multiply them and then you take the
trace and that's the equivalent of of
this double dot
operation okay so we will we'll proceed
uh now for a
while uh I mean for today uh for the
rest of today I guess uh with this um
more abstract and short end
notation because we want to
discuss
some geometry of these uh uh of the
relations that um we we can write in
order to model how a flux is related to
a the force or vice
versa uh yeah um actually maybe should
go back a
moment
I I miss there was one slide that I
don't know where it got where it went
but in any case uh What uh maybe it will
come up later but uh uh what I need to
say at this moment is that uh
this
relation is what I called an extrinsic
relation extrinsic
means uh that it has been obtained using
only uh
assumptions about the Continuum the
balance equations things that all in
general it doesn't contain anything that
has to do with how the material behaves
it doesn't yet contain any property of
the material for example here the
property of the material when you do
heat transfer comes in when you write
the for LA and therefore you U insert
the thermal conductivity tensor which is
uh um the description of which contains
how your system behaves and so that
takes me
here in other words
uh once we have written the extreme IC
General relation for Sigma then we have
to go into the detail of the particular
problem and the particular material or
materials that we are dealing with and
each material has its own
way of um
reacting uh to fluxes and
forces the principle in general is that
the material tends to um
spontaneously uh go if it can uh towards
a uh stable equilibrium but sometimes if
it is subjected to uh permanent forces
it will reach a steady
state because that those uh um fluxes
and forces that are imposed by the by
the exterior or by the adjacent fluid
Elements by the flow situation by the
boundary conditions
uh
those uh prevent the system from
relaxing spontaneously to equilibrium so
it will keep the the state of of
equilibri and typically uh boundary
conditions most of the
times uh impose either the forces or the
fluxes uh but there sometimes you also U
impose a related a relation between
force and flux like when you do
convective heat transfer the that is a
boundary condition of U Robin
type
uh in any case you can
view uh there is a dual point of
view you can uh describe
your material resistance to flux by
saying uh how it is how it
reacts uh when you impose some flaxes uh
in
it and the material typically reacts to
a
flux by building up a degree of this
equilibrium remember the chatelier brown
theorem degree of this equilibrium that
will enhance its tendency to uh
contrast that flux and return to
equilibrium so your model for for the
material will be a relation that gives
you the force as a function of the flux
and the gamma gamas are the other
properties like equilibrium properties
if you are near equilibrium like
temperatures chemical potentials
electrostatic
field but of course you can also view it
in the opposite way it's just the
inverse function or the dual point of
view you impose Force for example you
impose a gradient in temperature on a
specimen of a piece of
metal and uh the
this the material reacts by building up
a
flux which will try to go in the
direction of reestablishing a a flat so
of of killing that temperature gradient
that you are
imposing again
uh in this case you write the relation
flux as a function of
force and clearly then you have uh you
put it
into the extrinsic formula for the
entropy production that we just uh
uh obtained and and uh here comes
a relation in in this picture the
entropy production is related to the
fluxes that you have imposed or this one
it's related to the forces that you have
imposed
and then you
start particular
models particular but pretty
General uh for example here we uh if you
want to model the relation between force
and flux in heat transfer you adopt the
fu
law which for an isotropic material is
doesn't have a tensor here is just a
scalar but if it is anisotropic we have
seen that this should become a tensor a
symmetric tensor due to the onager
reciprocity the relation
between the difference between
mechanical and thermodynamic pressure
and
the Divergence of the velocity
is called the lamb law of for nutonian
fluid and the constant between the two I
mean the yeah the the constant of
proportionality between the two is
called The Bu
viscosity in
U fluid
mechanics the relation between
deviatoric part of the stress tensor and
deviatoric part of the rate of strain
tensor is what we call is this linear
relation and uh the proportionality
relation is called the sheer viscosity
we typic just call it
viscosity and with this plus
lamb you may rewrite the stress tensor
in this
way where notice here that I'm using the
thermodynamic pressure not the
mechanical pressure because the
difference between the two has been uh
shifted on this
side to use the
lamb
law and so here you have the standard
stuff and here you have the stuff that
you usually neglect
because this
is
typically zero but this is the second
coefficient of
viscosity and then if you have
electricity
conduction diffusion you have a ohms
law the coefficient proportionality
between the charge diffusive flux and
the gradient in the so minus the
gradient in the electrostatic field is
the is the electric
field so this is you could also write it
as
e and in any case this is the inverse of
the uh electrical resistivity of your
material and this is one way of
proceeding and it is
it has been the way for most of
uh uh the
applications
however there is some
arbitrariness
in saying as we've seen
here that for example the heat transfer
is not related to some other U degrees
of dis equilibrium
and in fact there is this possibility
and the Matrix of possibilities is is
this
one so here is all your degrees of this
equilibriums possible ones and here is
all the
flues and those laws that we have seen
uh in the previous slide are just the
diagonal terms in these Matrix of
coupling they presume a direct
coupling between I mean chemical
reaction rate and the Affinity of the
reaction uh coupling between these
mechanical rate of change of velocity
I'm sorry of volume of the fluid
elements and this
difference in
pressures or these and the the heat
transfer and so on so but as you
see at least part of this Matrix is
filled with other
possibilities that have names so they
correspond to effects that have been
observed and long ago as you see they're
talking about the 19th century
still uh these are typically called
cross effect effects because because
they happen in the off
diagonal terms of these coupling
Matrix and also you may have noticed
that I haven't put anything in these
parts so why don't I fill completely
this matx
Matrix okay well in
principle you you
should except that there are
uh many applications in which your uh
fluid is is
isotropic okay if the fluid is isotropic
if the symmetry of your problem uh the
like the
material as well as the boundary
conditions are
isotropic uh
then there is this princip symmetry
U takes
[Music]
uh uh it's uh it's saying and it uh it
it implements what what what what Pier
KY described in with this word that the
symmetry of the cause must be preserved
into its
effects
so what this means is that if you are in
isotropic conditions there is no way you
can couple a phenomenon which is of say
vectorial character with one which is of
a different character like a scalar or a
tensor so tensors and couple on only
with
tensors uh and scolars only with
scolars and sorry here the scolars and
vectors only with
vectors
so for but but remember also that this
is true only for isotropic conditions
uh because for example and uh
um there is an important uh aspect when
you have
a for example a
uh an interface so this supposed to
represent an interface between two
phases for example uh let's
say F on one side and G on the other
side
okay two different phases separated by
an
interface and an
interface okay let's view it also in
this other point of
view
F and let's plot the
density now as we know if we plot the
density uh uh of
um of a liquid
and the
density of a vapor there is a big
difference the vapor is about for water
it's about a thousand times less dense
than the
liquid so in the
interface things are not sharp things
are
smooth there is a smooth inter interface
there is a lay there is
a a a small layer in which there is this
a
huge gradient in
density and this is at
equilibrium so this is not a kind of
gradient that would cause
uh uh fluxes it's not it's not a degree
of this equilibrium this happens at
equilibrium but still you have a
gradient
there
and the description of this situation
can be done in several ways Gibbs did it
by assuming a sharp
equivalent jump from this value to that
value which is a good uh approach and uh
uh I will direct you to a very nice
paper
by uh bed mazour and another author I
forget the name now uh that um does
writes exactly the equations that we
have written here
this this um
extrinsic relation for
Sigma uh in the case of a jump
description between two
uh between two
phases
okay uh in in this situation here
definitely there is no uh isotop
because one thing is to move uh
across uh this interface and one thing
is move to move along the interface so
uh if you if you sit on the interface
and move uh on the on the interfacial
region okay
maybe that is isotropic
in the tangent
Direction but it's not uh in the uh
orthogonal Direction so for example in
this
case uh the the stress
tensor which is a you know you can
represent it uh in as a 3X3 Matrix
splits uh and and so you you have uh a a
a pressure an orthogonal pressure and a
tangent pressure and a tangent tensor uh
tensor field so you have a
two-dimensional uh tensor field which is
um
isotropic represents the stress
component in the tangential part plus a
scalar a scalar for the the orthogonal
pressure becomes a
scalar and uh so in this
situation this is very interesting
because that scalar now since it is a
scalar it can
couple with all these scalars
here so you may have the possibility at
interfacing and interfaces to
couple uh chemistry
and uh the flow field and the the
pressure field the the orthogonal
pressure and that is uh used that is um
I think uh used in models also for
biological biological systems because
that that coupling is
important so it's mechanical mechanical
and chemical uh
coupling but you need to break the
isotropic the isotropy uh in order to
have this kind
of say exotic
couplings
now we have already talk uh talked about
Saga relations and you remember that we
we did it in the context of chemical
reactions and we did it we
proved the the reciprocity on sag
reciprocity theorem you we've shown that
in the linear regime we could prove it
as a consequence of the principle of
Maximum entropy production by
Ziggler
here I'm not
discussing this slide a lot a lot
because essentially it is exactly the
same slide that we had then where I
changed some of the symbols here instead
of Sigma we had entropy production s
dot
irreversible here we had the reaction
rate so the Epsilon dots and here we had
the affinities of the reactions and
instead of of uh
this
super dot symbol we just said nothing
because they were
Scholars and the procedure was just the
same we we we proved we we
assumed that the
material in the linear regime so we
assume a linear
relation and the linear relation is
therefore uh in terms of this um tensor
here
L it's actually a super tensor because
it's uh it's it has as many entries as
that metrix that we just uh had in the
previous
slide uh with some zeros around but uh
it's it's not a full because of the K
principle but it's
still okay so this
is what we assume a linear
relation and the bottom line will be
that this super tensor has to be
symmetric and uh the Assumption in order
to obtain this
result is that the uh entropy production
should be maximal subject to the
constraint given by the extrinsic
relation and in in passing we uh obtain
this
orthogonality uh Ziggler orthogonality
relation that we also described
graphically in one of the previous
lectures
okay so okay fine you can proceed this
way U Ziggler actually introduced this
this um idea of Maximum entropy
production because his uh objective was
to he was a material science I guess uh
person and uh he wanted to be able to
describe things like
plasticity uh and
plasticity doesn't have a linear regime
so he wanted to extend uh on Sager
reciprocity to uh nonlinear regimes and
in fact here is how you do it again I
just skip the details but just to give
you a
flavor all it takes is to instead of
assuming like we did in the previous
Slide the linear relation
between forces and flaxes we assume a
generic relation
J and still apply the principle of
Maximum entry production so maximize
Sigma subject to to the extrinsic uh
relation for
the between forces and
flaxes and you come up with an
orthogonality
condition in terms of the lrange
multiplier which is still only one
because it's still only one
constraint the only problem is that
now remember when you have a in the
method of lrange multipliers you in
order to find the value of the lrange
multiplier you have to uh substitute
back into the constraint so you take
this orthogonality relation this way put
it back in the constraint and this is
done
here and then solve for uh
Lambda in the case of linear case we
found that Lambda is equal to two here
it's more complicated because Lambda is
a is this
function of whatever functional form you
have chosen for your uh um relations
between forces and fluxes which is
nonlinear in
general so you can substitute this into
here and you get this complicated stuff
which nevertheless is a is an
orthogonality it's a
condition that must be satisfied by the
functional relation of your uh of your
um that you have chosen here so it tells
you that you don't have complete freedom
in choosing these functions they have to
satisfy
this for example if you if you choose
the the linear relation which is this
one this
expression uh reduces to the
one that required the symmetry of the
Dion Sager conductivity uh
tensor in a general case you get
something else uh which is a sort of a
generalization to nonlinear case
of
of of on Saga relation Al
Ziggler there is another uh way of
viewing uh things they're all sort of
equivalent and uh let me try to explain
it in this
uh heat transfer
example they are all equivalent and uh
there's so much and as you see I'll I'll
say a little bit later about this uh u i
collected this point of view in in a
paper couple of years
ago
uh and u
let's let's do it for the heat transfer
case so
consider this anisotropic material made
of so that micr structure is made of
layers um
sandwiched of high conductivity and low
conductivity
materials and so suppose you
subject this
material to a you impose a gradient in
temperature so material then is
under I shouldn't say stress but in any
case it's it has to decide all right how
do I react to that um gradient in
temperature that you
impose uh
definitely want to react in a way that
will allow me to uh like Brown says H to
reduce that gradient in temperature and
try to reestablish
equilibrium
but you see here what I'm am showing is
that there are many possibilities it
could uh decide to move heat in One
Direction or in another and how come it
chooses this particular
direction in some
sense uh it's like um suppose you are in
a in a in a crowd you're in the middle
of a lot of people uh maybe at a concert
or
going into or out of a soccer stadium
lots of people and everybody wants to
reach or get next to the the podium or
to the entrance or go or go to your car
but you have a crowd in front of you and
so uh even
though uh the
direct path would be apparently shorter
but it would require less effort for you
to move in another Direction where you
see less uh resistance to to to your
motion okay
so this is a this is what happens here
so there is you you
evaluate and the
material uh does a a local
evaluation uh
sensing okay how much would would it
cost me to move in in terms of effort no
or in terms of uh yes effort in order to
move in the crowd how how much would it
cost me to go in this direction or in
that
direction and so there is a this tensor
G which I would call a
metric it's the driver of that logic it
measures
uh uh how dissipative is uh moving in
the various
directions and if you write an equation
like this
you
you this is a quadratic form with with
that
g uh for given um heat
fluxes and that it equal to some
constant that gives you an equation of
an
ellipsoid and that ellipsoid represents
the locus of all
the uh tips of the vectors that uh would
cost the material the same effort so the
same
um
dissipation and so it turns
out
that you know the the entropy production
is the scalar product between the blue
vector and the red vector
okay and the scalar product
here between two vectors is given by the
projection of one vector onto the onto
the other one so for example this blue
one you see that this blue one the
actual uh full not the dotted ones is
the one that has the maximum projection
onto the red Vector so the maximize it
maximizes among all these possibilities
that have equal
effort the one that uh maximizes the
sigma is this blue one and that's the
one that the material
chooses uh it turns out that g is the
inverse of the conductivity
tensor so you can read for
law with the for an anisotropic material
in in this way that the material
is is choosing the direction
of maximal entropy production for a
given
effort like in your crowd you choose the
Direction with with which you feel that
you are moving uh farther away with this
with with a given effort for a given
amount of effort that you put into that
movement
okay so these are words just to explain
what
uh what I just
said
and so if
you so you you could have a an isotropic
material for an isotropic material
that ellipsoid becomes a
sphere a
hypersphere all directions are
equivalent and if all directions are
equivalent which one is the direction of
steepest entropy scent it's the same as
the gradient of of T because Vector
Q
uh as the maximal projection of on on on
on the red Vector when they are Co
colinear and so here's
the the construction in the same diagram
for which we have seen
the uh the
orthogonality
Ziggler
relation so we have
a an ex y or one and
two
versors so think of it X and Y I impose
a gradient in temperature which has two
components and
uh uh that places me the two
components places me somewhere not at
equilibrium if there if there are zero
I'm at the center so I'm already in an
equilibrium State and nothing happens
but if you I'm off equilibrium these are
the lines of Contours of constant
entropy no so the higher the gradient
the farther I am and the highest is the
uh
entropy I'm sorry the the highest is the
degree of this equilibrium
this is the maximum entropy so this is
the uh the entropy goes decreasing as I
go
further so if I um am here
and and that degree of dis equilibrium
has been generated at one instant of
time and then the system is allowed to
evolve by itself as if were isolated
nothing else uh no constraints just
you can go to
equilibrium it doesn't go to
equilibrium in the straight path it
follows the path that is dictated by its
local metric now true the uh isotropic
material is
um doesn't favor any direction so these
although it doesn't show exactly as a as
a sphere it should be a circle in any
case uh it has to um evolve though in a
scenario in
which the entropy contour lines may not
be also circles if they were also
circles you would go down straight but
if they are not like here they are
ellipses then uh it it would choose no
among uh the ones that are all
equivalent effort you chooses the one
that takes you to the highest entropy
possible so it's the one that is tangent
here and that is also for this other
metric and then of course you can
proceed and go on as you at each
point you you sort stop and pause I it
doesn't happen of course but stop and
consider which one is the direction in
which I should go next step and that's
how it how it gets to equilibrium they
all get to equilibrium of course but
along different paths and if I start
even from this exactly same state but
with a material that is uh uh that has a
that is oriented
differently and therefore uh for for it
the the
the metric uh and these ellipsoids of
equal dissipation or equal effort is
oriented in a different way and
therefore it would move there and then
it will search again and it will move
maybe even overshoots a little bit and
then goes back to equili okay so this is
U the role of uh
the
metric that uh
describes this is for a heat transfer
problem but you can also view it in a
more General
context and that is what I I I like to
call it the fourth
flow simply because it is a something
that
has emerged let me see do I have oh I
think I had a
uh keep missing slides today uh there
there will be a slide somewhere
sometime with a list
of uh many different theories of non
equilibrium over the last 40 years H in
which people uh in different languages
different mathematics different uh
Frameworks often they don't talk to each
other they completely ignore each other
uh they admit that they're doing the
same thing but they are doing the same
thing and that is uh what I was trying
to to point out to to the community here
by calling it The for forth flow and why
why do
I uh why do I dare uh elevating it to
such a high level in the hierarchy of of
of physical laws okay that's
because uh because of the generality you
know remember the great great
conservation principles
are are great the greatness comes from
the
generality should should hold for every
model of physical reality well it turns
out that in every model of non-e
equilibrium uh Dynamics U there is
something that maybe you don't call it a
metric uh but it is it has the
properties of a
metric and uh uh
and therefore it is it appears to be an
essential feature of any
model and
also uh I like also the fact that it is
a is a statement of existence like like
the first law is a statement of
existence of energy the second law is a
statement of existence of entropy this
is a statement of existence of a metric
in non-e equilibrium States another it's
a
property like this thermal
conductivity uh that has to be
defined at every uh state every
non-equilibrium state of your system for
it to decide in which direction to move
when you let it alone and want to and
let it go towards
equilibrium yeah uh
here this is to show that this same
construction can be also uh
done more formally and mathematically
again with the method of lrange
multipliers you you see you maximize the
scalar product between the X and the
J subject
so that's the the lrange multiplier to
the constraint given by an equal effort
ellipsoid so if I have so it expresses
exactly
mathematically uh the worthy description
that I
gave there is a matric that descri
describes this ellipsoid tells you for a
given distance I want to move which one
is the best Direction and best is in
terms of maximizing the rate of entropy
production from this
one using the method the gr multiplier
setting the derivative equal to
zero U substituting back into constraint
and so on you get a relation between
forces and
fluxes we can you can always write it in
in this way which looks like a linear
relation but it's not because this R
which is a
resistance
um it's
not constant in general but it's just a
function of the fluis which is given by
the solution of this problem
here so this is a nonlinear
relation and of course you can do the
exact uh same in the uh Force picture
pause the the
X and there is a a metric also from that
point of view and the two are related to
one another they the inverse
somehow so you also
maximize these projection subject to
this other blue ellipsoid which also
represents the
effort at this time it's the effort for
the system to set up
uh a a gradient in temperature so as to
contrast the flux
of heat that you have imposed in it and
of course when you get close to
equilibrium when you get close to
equilibrium then you go to the linear uh
regime you get on Saga relations and of
course these two are um the metric
becomes
the uh onager
generalized
conductivity for the L's or resistivity
for the r for the
RS one is the inverse of the
other ah there is okay here is the the
list
of uh
theories uh that
uh converge
to the four
FL
uh of course we contributed to
it but u in the same period already you
have Gela morison cavman who did the
uh completely from completely different
point of view so in fact I I met
Miroslav Gela
only maybe 30 years
later and so these all
are uh independent uh
contributions uh generic has become very
popular because some Compu some
communities are more effective than
others to propagating and
Publishing
U I will say a few words also about the
Constructor law Bean
although he would be unhappy if I
say that he belongs here because I think
he believes that his uh point of view is
more General and I think I agree with
him uh I'll explain a moment I mean
later when why
uh these other also some
mathematicians from the point of view of
certain classes of partial differential
equations have
developed uh now it's already 25 years
uh ago um this theory of gradient
flows uh
they in order to do that they have
introduced a part particular metric
pretty complicated mathematical but it
is a metric that regularizes those
differential equations and make make
them fit into this same scheme so that's
very
interesting uh okay then there is also
more modern stuff like large deviation
Theory
Theory and not only that but also there
is some people
um that are
applying
this notion to solve in original way
uh complicated
problems in a much simpler way than um
the traditional
descriptions
because this view uh geometrical
View ER you know the power of
mathematics and of geometry is if you if
you can uh view something from a
geometrical point of view you have you
you've captured the essence and youve
also often simplified uh the uh even the
numeric uh numerical uh Solutions of
your
problem I'll give you some references
here just for for fun if you're
interested
in now regarding Bean Constructor
law
uh if you haven't uh come across uh
Adrian Bean was a graduate of this
department uh two or three years before
me I guess he did PhD in mechanical
engineering
here and U is
um you see his Focus
is
uh uh
on design and evolution in nature the
role of design now
design uh for
example uh the structure of the tree
structure of uh
lungs or even the structure of trees
which are sorts of U optimiz the result
of
optimization
of of uh of two con contrasting
Tendencies and the system is trying to
find the best direction in which to uh
to to build and to uh but uh in which to
make things
flow and things flow to me is also uh
translated
into uh
choose uh the way in which you can
produce as much as possible your entropy
uh at the at the fastest rate compatible
with the constraints and so for this
part I think that we're saying the same
thing so he also fitting into the forlow
but what the uh what's beyond that and I
think is right is that uh he's saying
that u in nature
things
evolve uh and uh also the design of uh
natural things including the design for
example of the wings of
animals and how they uh how um they
are related
to to Evolution so how
um the from the I forget the names of uh
the the ancient uh
Birds uh when you had the
T-Rex and uh and and how that evolved
and that evolution is an evolution in
the design of how uh structures are
built in nature they always have the
purpose of uh favoring flows that means
uh favoring entropy generation and
making it as as as effective as possible
because as you know uh life is
impossible without entropy generation
and we need that uh that is the the
driving force while you produce entropy
you also produce useful
things so entropy production is not
completely
negative it's not just a waste of exergy
it's you need it because if you didn't
have it you nothing useful would
happen uh but what Bean says is that
also uh structures
evolve and
uh
uh the choice there is some Randomness
in how uh a particular
structure uh is given
birth it was nonexistent and then all of
a sudden perhaps because of of of of a
fluctuation or
perturbation uh uh it becomes
possible uh now regarding structure
though for example there is this problem
of the it's
called Berard
uh conduction it's it's a problem in
which you um you
hit you have a
fluid and like you have a pan with some
oil and you have Heen from below and
cooled from
above
uh now
typically if
you if your heating is is is is not
strong enough you would have just a
conduction but
then there is also the possibility
because of the instability uh due to the
fact that uh the stratification is you
get hot stuff below and cold above and
and they like to switch so this uh
movement which requires uh moving a flow
therefore it involves friction so if
you
if if if you have
enough uh motivation for doing it
eventually that flow will start and
therefore you'll get U convective it you
will switch from conductive heat
transfer to convective roles of uh heat
conduction which will
enhance the heat conduction it's more
effective so you here it is a a
situation in which you you build
structure gets built in order to uh make
uh the entropy production more
effective and in this
paper uh you view it from the point of
view of U um of of Maximum entropy
production
so you see for example here you have a
situation in which uh like you
are for example you have the the rolls
so you have the high non-e equilibrium
situation high flux in which you have
the Riley Berard rols and those that
structure is the one that maximizes the
the entropy so among all the
possibilities the system chooses that
one maximizes the entropy product
ction but as you turn uh the heat off
and here you're
going so as time goes on you reduce that
the heat from Bel
below
uh
that tendency goes down
until uh it becomes
comparable or or even less efficient
than the the direct simple conduction
and then what happens the system
switches and the convection gets uh
stopped and the the system switches into
just to another to the to another
maximum so this is also a
jump in configuration so it's a
construction
of it's a design so so to speak a design
choice that your system has made in
order to move from one maximum to
another
maximum and this of course
corresponds to a critical value of the
rile number that is uh the onset number
for uh this Riley
benar
instability which is very very famous
problem in fluid mechanics and heat
trans
and by the way Adrian
ban has
written hundreds of papers but also many
books including one at the beginning
which is entropy production in heat
transfer which is uh very good
let me uh conclude today with this um um
last
idea just to add to the confusion if you
[Music]
want
um the idea that there is a there is a
theorem famous theorem proved by
glandorf and
PRI called minimum entropy production PR
so many people uh we are facing simply
the the words in a superficial way they
say well is it minimum or is it
maximum
okay all right so the difference in the
key is local and
Global so the the system
locally chooses
uh so the material locally chooses to
react in a in a direction that goes
towards the steepest entropy asent so
it's the local maximal entropy
production this theorem instead looks at
a global situation like an integral over
a volume of many pieces of material and
it takes it does the integral not of
Sigma that which is the rate of but of
the rate of change of
Sigma and it
proves
that the rate of change of
Sigma under a broad set of boundary
conditions and assumptions that are
listed
there very larger set of
conditions
is negative
so that means that Sigma if you if you
start like in the previous slide if you
start
uh from a situation in which in
your control volume there is a um a lot
of entropy
production and you let it go if it is
not already in a steady
state it will change
evolve towards a less a lesser and
lesser entropy production situation
until it gets to
zero and the zero will be either a
steady state if it is sustained by the
boundary conditions or the equilibrium
State instead of doing the details here
that are not really essential for us let
me give you this
example consider one dimensional heat
transfer
problem and that suppose that you have a
a Time equal equal zero you have
imposed this temperature
profile and your boundary conditions are
that the temperature here is is given
fixed so you you fix the temperatures
left and
right of course that is not a steady
state the system will evolve you can
solve this with any uh with the for year
equation or any software that does this
solution and you you see it will evolve
and will at the end it will reach the
steady linear uh solution of the typical
heat transfer problem now if you compute
the entropy production rate
here it's it's this much
if you compute it here it's this much
it's a
half so the system as it moves from here
to
there has goes has an an overall Global
entropy production that goes down in
time until it reaches a minimum uh at
steady state if you start this is
another example in which you have a
different boundary conditions that would
allow an equilibrium state so you start
from this one and you have an entropy
production right which is given by this
you let it go it will reach a flat
temperature profile which is equilibrium
zero entropy production again a
minimum so
globally it has gone
down but
locally at every instant at every local
uh
each material element here has followed
for Law and
therefore at any time chosen the
direction of a flow that is compatible
with that the
gradient imposed all right so we're just
on time and just
uh finished