First, there were hunters and gatherers.
Everyone contributed and their business
was basically to survive. Eventually,
people began to tame plants and animals,
allowing for larger and larger
settlements. This opened up new kinds of
work. Then, industrial and capitalist
revolutions changed everything. The
development of computers, the worldwide
web, and widespread education ushered us
into the knowledge-based economy. As
fewer people and fewer hours are needed
to do the work of yesterday, people are
adapting again. How you live and work
will invent the future. You'll rely on
your networks and connections to help
you out, and you'll help others, too.
Maybe you'll specialize in something no
one has thought of before. Maybe you'll
make your voice heard among those who
find themselves excluded from today's
economy. So, keep on working, creating,
and inventing the future of work.
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learnmit.edu.
[Music]