Hi everyone, thank you for joining
today's seminar. It this will be our
last seminar and it's my great pleasure
to be able to introduce today's uh
seminar speaker, Professor Deep Gerbala
from UPEN. Uh, professor Jerbala is an
associate professor and the Peter and
Suzanne Armstrong distinguished scholar
in the electrical and systems
engineering as well as material science
and engineering at UPEN. He completed
his PhD material science and engineering
at Northwestern University and was a
post-doal fellow at Caltech before
starting at UPEN.
uh his group's research uh interest uh
is broad and it lies at the intersection
of new material surface science and
solid state devices for computing opto
electronics and energy harvesting
applications in addition to the
development of correlated and functional
imaging techniques. His research has
been widely recognized with tremendous
number of awards. I'm just going to name
a few of them here. Um so these awards
include uh the Optica Adolf Lump Medal,
the Bell Labs Prize, the AVS Peter Mark
Memorial Award, I Photonic Society Young
Investigator Award, IA Nanotechnology
Council Young Investigator Award, the
SBIE Early Career Achievement Award and
the Sloan Fellowship.
Um, professor Jeriala serves as the
associate editor for ACS nano letters
and has been appointed as a
distinguished lecturer for the ITE
nanotechnology council for 2025. So it's
a pleasure to have him here today with
us. I h the floor is yours. I just
remind everyone in the room if you want
to ask questions feel free to raise your
hand directly ask. We do have audience
over zoom. Please type your questions
and I'll help moderate. Please help me
welcome our speaker. Okay, great.
All right, thank you Fernas for the very
kind introduction and thank you all for
making it here. It's a great pleasure to
speak uh here for the MIT Nano seminar
series. Um I realize that my pointer is
not going to work in this specularly
reflective screen. So I'm just going to
use my hands to point to various things
on the slides. Okay. Um so uh let me get
started by uh thanking the people who
actually do the work. uh I often say at
the beginning of my talk I'm a
professional pan handler who goes and
seeks for resources to run my research
and actually this the students and
postocs who end up doing all the
important work in the lab. So definitely
uh uh none of the work would be possible
without them. Certainly we have been
very fortunate to be funded by a wide
number of uh funding agencies both in
the government as well as uh uh uh
industries and some private foundations.
And finally, all the work that I'm
presenting, especially the three nitride
work has been done in collaboration with
professor Troy Olsson and Eric Stack uh
who have been my partners in crime in
this uh in this amazing new area of
research. Uh Troy Olsson used to work in
nitride pzole electrics for a long time
and so uh together with him we were able
to switch to nitride federals. So with
that let me introduce the broad
divisions in the research group. The
research group is divided into three
major sections.
The first one is what I'm going to be
focusing most of my talk on today which
is nano electronics. Here we look at
both the logic and memory devices which
means transistors as well as meristers
of some sort that can do either logic
functions or data storage functions.
Certainly I won't be able to talk much
about logic today. It'll be focused on
the memory aspect. Um then the other
part of the research which actually is
very quite closely related to Farna's
professor Tisdale professor Bulovich's
research um is in the area of novel
exotonic materials for opto electronic
applications and and that's another very
active area of research certainly in one
hour I cannot cover both of them so I'll
be focusing my efforts on a portion of
this area and finally we also synthesize
new materials via both MOCVDs coating um
as well as some solution phased
chemistry
again much of that uh I mean the
sputtering part I will introduce in a
slide but uh uh won't be able to cover
most of it today hopefully another
seminar another venue uh I'll be able to
cover that okay so let me uh harp in on
the focus of today's talk it's all on
three nitride federals I'll first given
this is a broad seminar talk I'm hoping
there's audience from various uh
departments at various stages of their
careers so some amount of u broad
introduction would be helpful uh on what
are nitride federals why are
interesting? Why are they useful? Why
could they potentially open up some very
interesting applications including
commercialization of the technology? And
then I'll focus uh or the second part of
the work on on ferroelectric uh memory
devices that you can make out of them uh
namely uh both for uh in terms of
transistors as ferlectric fed devices as
well as ferlectric meristers or or um uh
you could say ferlectric diode memory
devices, right? And then finally if time
permits and I may I may just rush across
this large portion if I don't have
enough time is why these nitride
federals are kind of a match made in
heaven for data storage in extreme
environments. Okay. So let me start with
the big picture question which is grand
challenges in modern classical
computing. I
know a lot of you would be probably
working on quantum computing and have
heard a lot about quantum computing.
Certainly quantum is very exciting, very
interesting. There is lot of interest in
it. Probably a lot of hype in it, right?
Um but I should say that classical
computing is a moving frontier. It is
something that is evolving uh uh with
every day or every every month, right?
And new challenges come up and there are
sort of two major or central challenges
to classical computing. One of them is
power consumption. And this graph uh was
created by the SRC, Semiconductor
Research Corporation, which shows you
how uh ICT applications which is
information and communications
technologies um are consuming energy uh
on on a global scale year after year.
And you can see that uh the computing
and communication graphs are quite
nonlinear compared to the global energy
production which is rather linear on a
lock scale or rather straight line on a
lock scale which which means the global
energy production does not increase by
more than five or 6% a year unless MIT
or some other university works out
fusion right in which case that graph's
slope can recre increase uh uh much more
rapidly
or we figure out a way to uh do
computing and communication much more
energy efficiently. We are going to face
some kind of crisis and not too far away
from now, right? We're around here 2025.
By mid 2030s, data centers are energy
for AI compute is going to consume a
vast fraction of electricity or energy
that humankind produces. There's a
second problem which is sort of
connected with the first problem which
is current big data compute or AI
compute which is largely driven by
crunching vast amounts of data,
searching, pattern matching, inferences,
right? uh is uh quite inefficient both
in terms of time and in terms of energy
and the central bottleneck for it is
what popularly known as the memory
bottleneck. What is this bottleneck? Let
me try and explain. Now this is a graph
taken from a startup company's website
but this is also widely available on
several government websites. Now there
are two graphs over here. One is a
rather nonlinear
looking exponentially increasing graph.
That is the graph telling you how many
number of parameters each of these the
progressing number of AI models that are
coming out right these parameters run
into the trillions now for example GPT4
is up there I'm sure many of you are
using it to do your homeworks or writing
papers right it's in the few trillions
right that's the number of parameters
GPT4 uses uh you can call it the weights
right in the model this line over here
which is somewhat uh less slope linear
looking that's the amount of memory
available to today's best AI processors
this is the DAM memory which basically
stores the weights and then the model is
running through these weights and so you
can see that the amount of memory
available versus the amount of
parameters required there is a large
exponential gap between them and it's
only going to increase right so this is
the quote unquote memory wall that slows
down or makes AI computing more energy
hungry more energy inefficient and
somehow this needs to get solved so the
bottom line is there is latency between
the logic and memory units and that's a
major bottom neck known as the void
nomen bottleneck which leads to
increased power consumption and sort of
these problems are in some sense
connected. Why is this important?
Certainly we as a society especially as
academics do care about energy right uh
and what we are going to face is this
kind of a scenario based on the previous
slides graph which is if you look at our
whole society uh together uh today we
are doing certain amount of computes uh
uh in terms of jewels per year right and
these uh green graph tells you how many
compute operations you are doing right
and these compute operations are
measured in what is known as zips which
is za input output or operations per
second. um za means 10 the^ 21 certainly
we have MIT as 10 the^ negative9 but
it's 10 the^ negative plus 21 right and
so um again this graph was created by
the src prehat GPT revolution but this
is only going to accelerate further and
if we continue to go across this
trajectory as a society um we will have
to saturate our computing needs at some
point to about a thousand zips I mean
these numbers vary depending on who you
ask what type of people are doing
estimates of is but uh we we do need
electricity or energy for other things.
Uh even if you drive all electric cars,
you need some energy to charge them. Uh
heating up, running these lights, right?
So there has to be some delta between
the green graph and the and the world's
energy production. And so that's uh so
that this essentially is going to lead
to computing saturation. So the only way
forward for us is either you increase
the slope of the yellow graph which
means bringing along fusion or some
other transformative new energy source
in the next 5 to 10 years seems highly
unlikely or reduce the energy required
for computing per bit or per bit of
compute right and then you can get in
the blue trajectory and have uh much
larger amount of compute possible now as
a society we have been doing this for a
long time okay if you look at this graph
again taken from a very nice perspective
by Marinara and Agura a few years ago.
The y-axis is again exponential scale
showing you the energy efficiency of
compute per bit or per bit operation.
Right? If you look at the top most
point that's eniac that was invented in
my department the first general purpose
computer made out of vacuum tubes right
so when used to be turned on the whole
of electricity of of uh uh university
city area of Philadelphia used to be
shut down just to power any right
comprised of vacuum tubes it used to
come consume about a few hundred jewles
per bit of energy look what happens on
the y-axis there's a break in the y-axis
before the next point which is IBM PC
there's a trunk transformative change in
the hardware technology. You move from
vacuum tubes to semiconductors. It's a
six orders of magnitude jump in the
computing efficiency right there. Right?
You went from vacuum tubes to
semiconductors. By that time integrated
circuits were realized which went to the
IBM PC. It was pretty clear to people
the game is simple now. Scale down more
law scaling takes over. That helps you
out until mid 2005 right here. And for
those of you who are in the computer
architecture field, you would know this
is around the time when Intel's
processors which are dual core, quad
core and all these started coming out
around 2005. Why? Because at a single
core level computing was not the speed
was not increasing any further.
Efficiencies were not getting gained. So
therefore the so-called architectural
revolution started around mid 2005 right
here. That that is going on all the way
until today. Apparently, this is also
the time when GPUs were introduced and
so-called GPU era started and GPUs
progressively started becoming more
important and CPUs started becoming less
and less important and today we know how
fortunes of Intel versus Nvidia has
flipped, right? And so that's because
GPUs have become way more relevant than
CPUs, right? But here we are today
somewhere close to 2025. If you look at
the compute energy per bit of Nvidia's
best processors, they are in the couple
hundred fejoules per bit. very close to
the thermodynamic limits that silicon
camass presents. Right? This is physics.
You can't cheat with physics. You can
cheat with architecture. You can cheat
with engineering and scaling. It very
hard to cheat with physics. This is
where we need a transformative new
technology to continue to increase our
effic energy efficiency for compute.
What is that? We don't know. Some people
say photonics, some people say quantum.
All kinds of names are being thrown
around, right? All kinds of technologies
are being thrown around. Uh we don't
know. Maybe it's completely new state
variable. Maybe it's completely new
physics. Or it could be the same
technology but integration of new
materials and devices. Right? This is
sort of the shortest term solution is to
introduce in new materials and devices
to enhance architectures even further.
And this is where our community mostly
sits which is design uh designing new
materials, devices and systems that
maximize bit operations per watt of
power while sticking to this electronics
platform. Right? And that is why a bunch
of people in our community including u
uh a fernas and many others in MIT are
focusing on new materials uh to do
computing much more efficiently uh and
not just computing but also other
variants of computing like generating
light modulating light which is the
photonic aspects uh that involves
communication and so on. So in that
sense uh certainly u novel optical
material novel materials sorry
lowdimensional materials both optical
electronic materials have sort of
dominated the research community. Um
here is a long list of those materials
or long u chart of many of those
materials. My group ends up working on
all of them by the way. Right. Um
certainly I cannot talk about all of
them today. Going to focus on these two
over here. among them I'm going to focus
further on uh the three nitrites okay so
let's try and get into it a little bit
further uh and try to understand where
this problem can be solved by three
nitride mater ferlectric materials so as
I already mentioned or alluded to in the
few previous slides dense integration of
memory and logic is necessary if you
look at the current computer
architecture including the latest and
greatest chips out there they are like a
strip mall parking lot right like you
would like you would see when you go to
Chicago or well Illinois or in the
middle of nowhere in the country, right?
They're all spread out, right? So the
processor cores or and the memory units
are all separated out. They are all
connected in two dimensions and the rate
of data transfer is limited by this two
dimensional connectivity or bandwidth,
right? And and so this basically creates
a traffic jam when you're trying to run
models with extremely large number of
parameters requiring extremely large
amounts of memory, right? So the
solution to this is something that has
been wellnown for a long time which is
going 3D basically New York style
architecture right tall skyscrapers with
bottom floors being the computer
microprocessor right the logic and all
the above floors being memory units that
store the data and now instead of one or
two or three elevators you have a 10,000
elevators going across those building
right that will lead to uh data transfer
rates or the bandwidth of data transfer
could be extremely fast you're moving
data from millimeter or centimeter
scales to micron scales when you're
building 3D. So there's a giant gain and
there's a giant gain also in the
bandwidth of access of data that you can
get. Right? So this has been the holy
grail or in some sense from the computer
architectures perspective going 3D and
to go 3D you need something that is back
end of line compatible memory. Once you
make the silicon secret sauce, you want
to make memory on top of the silicon
secret sauce, which means it has to be
compatible with silicon process. And
therefore, it's called back end ofline
compatible. Silicon is called front end
of line. And so back end of line
compatibility means it should be able to
sustain certain number of elements that
are allowed in silicon foundry
temperatures, reaction gases, all those
things should be compatible with silicon
processing. Right? For example, the
temperature limitation is about 400°C.
You cannot more than move more than that
otherwise the dopens and other layers
inside the silicon process get disrupted
and all your processes a waste. Okay. So
in this space there has been an intense
competition for memory for the past 30
years and several technologies have been
tried. Many at MIT have also made huge
strides in many of these technologies.
Right? There are four major ones. I
don't want to debate about all of them.
I'll pull up a chart later that may ri
up a few people but we'll talk about
that at that time. First one is RAM or
standard memorers. Second is phase
change RAM that Intel tried to
commercialize and then wrote off their
entire business for a few billions. That
was a couple years ago. And then there
is MTJ which is still under
commercialization has not made it into
mainstream right magnetic tunnel
junctions or ferroagnet base. So ferro
based technologies and the last one is
ferroelectric. Right? If you were to ask
me personally, one of the two Pharaoh
technologies will ultimately win out for
various reasons. But I would like to
highlight why this is a very challenging
problem and why it has taken so long to
solve. Because memory is a much more
brutal market than
transistors. For memory, the device
performance requirements are extremely
stringent. You need very low energy. You
need very high density. You need them to
be extremely fast. You need to be back
end offline process compatible. And you
need to them to be extremely reliable.
Getting all of these things together in
a single technology is extremely
difficult. This is why no single
technology is one together to date. We
hope the technology that I'm going to
show you potentially has a chance. There
are other competing technologies too,
but we are definitely betting on our
horse. All right. So, let's go into
ferro electric technology and why that
is so
special. It's not a new technology.
Ferro have been known for a long time.
The year 2022 marked 100 years of
ferroelect electricity. Does anybody
know who came up with the word
ferroelectric? Does everybody know Irvin
Schroinger? Well, he also came up with
the word federal, but he's known for
better things than federal electric,
right? Okay. So, he came up with the
word. So, it's a very old word, very old
uh technology. If you've taken Tokyo
Transit, you have used the Tokyo Transit
cards, they have a chip inside them that
actually contains this memory. So,
peroskite based federals have already
been commercialized. They have a problem
with scaling and they also have chemical
compatibility problems. They have lead
and bismouth. No silicon foundry wants
lead and bismouth in them. Also they
cannot be scaled below 50 nometer in
thickness. They self depolarized and
cease to exist as a ferroelectric.
Hafneia another or halfna based
ferctrics another very exciting class of
ferroelectrics. Professor Chima he's not
here right now but I met him earlier.
He's been working on them for a while.
Um they have their own problems too but
they have they have made it quite far in
terms of uh uh process control and
engineering. They were first discovered
in 2006. They're slowly trying to make
their way into commercialization. They
have other problems which I can talk
about later. And then the last ones
which were only realized as a federal in
2019. These are the nitride ones. They
also have their problems. I'm going to
try and show you one by one. We have
tried to solve or address most of these
problems. Okay. So what are these
ferroelectrics? Now these are the same
structure as gallium nitride or aluminum
nitrite. It's a woodside crystal
structure. I'm sure and any of you from
material science departments or people
who work with 35 materials, you know
about the woodside crystal structure.
You can have either a metal polar or a
nitrogen polar state and that basically
stores your up or down polarization of
this federal and therefore your memory
zero or memory one. Right? So it's very
simple as you're switching the ferrotric
from one polar state to other polar
state. All the unit cells move half all
the atoms moved half a unit cells up
half a unit cell down. That's it. And
the polarization flips. There are no
weird pathways or circling around or
anything like like that involved which
is true in many other ferctrics. Compare
the hysteresis loops of these
ferroelectrics aluminum scandium nitride
first reported by this group in Franhaer
Institute in in uh and KE University in
Germany. They're almost ideal square
shaped hysteresus loops as compared to
lead zirconium titanate which is you
know very very small and tiny in the
center as compared to it. But the even
more exciting part over here is that the
remnant polarization the amount of
charge uh remaining behind in the
fereral extremely large of the order of
100 microcoolums per centime square or
more. This is so much charge that it can
lead to some very dramatic uh
performance enhancements in devices uh
which you'll see uh as we move forward.
Uh by the way I should mention over here
that this is not some exotic uh material
that was just discovered and uh you know
a hard time making its way into
commercialization. If you all bought a
phone after 2020 or 2021 it's likely in
your phone as a PZO electric bar filter.
So the PZO electric properties of these
materials are already commercialized.
Now we are trying to commercialize or
discover and report the memory storage
or data storage properties of this
material.
Okay. All right. There are many other
advantages. I'll go over them very
briefly. We have summarized them on this
review article. It's a full class of
materials. It's not just an isolated
material. Aluminum scandium variant is
the most mature successful one. But
there is gallium scandium nitrite, zinc,
magnesium oxide, aluminum boron nitrite,
aluminum
nitride. The list goes on, right? Um the
key features are the following. Large
coarse fields, large remnant
polarizations.
Okay. A second very important property,
extremely high stability. You cook this
thing up to thousand degrees CC, keep it
for days, bring it back down, the data
just stays there. Nothing happens to it.
Very rare property, not there in most
systems, right? Extremely important for
data storage, information storage in
high temperature environments, which
I'll talk about towards the end if time
permits. Finally, it's also one of those
materials which has low dialectric
constants combined with the ferro
electricity. means it's uh you to switch
it the energy required required is very
low. Last couple points I'll mention
it's a unifiasic material. It only
exists in one phase the woodside phase.
Normally in many other ferroelectrics
you have to compete for phases which is
a problem if you want phase homogeneity
over entire wafers. And uh finally this
material is fully back end of line
compatible. You can deposit these films
even at 100°C or even at lower
temperatures. The Japanese do it at a
room temperature and they turn out to be
perfectly
ferroelectric. Okay. So it's also done
in a process that is quite friendly and
used in industry at scale. We do
sputtering of this. Certainly most other
groups also do sputtering. But there are
also groups that do MBE MOCBD of this
matter. Even PLLD pulse laser
deposition. I'm hearing reports that
aluminina uh atomic layer deposition or
ALD also works but we'll see. We haven't
seen any conclusive reports here yet.
But you can deposit on full 6-in wafers.
We can we are poor. We can only afford
6-in tools. So that's the maximum we can
grow up to. But there are there are
companies out there that can uh do this
up to 12 in, right? And so certainly
it's scalable outside the university
into actual commercial flaps.
Okay. The substrates are usually uh
silicon wafers, sapphire wafers or
silicon carbide wafers, whatever wafer
you want. The typical preferred
substrate is hexagonal crystal plane.
Symmetry is preferred right. Uh we can
do films all the way from centimeter by
centimeter to full 6 inch wafers.
Thickness is from five to two microns.
Uh temperature range of our temperature
range of differs between 250 to 500 C
depending on the
application. Okay. Let me go to the
first application of the memory device
application of these uh ferro which is
the ferroelectric field effect
transistors. Sper electrics as a whole
have several device applications that
few of them are shown on the screen over
here. I won't be able to go through all
of them. This is the classic or
conventional femorry where you have a
ferroelectric capacitor connected to a
transistor which senses out the current.
This is a ferroelectric field effect
transistor where the ferroelectric is uh
direct contact with the semiconductor is
the gate dialectric in direct contact
with the semiconductor. Okay. So that
moves to me to the second part of the
talk. So naturally if you have a
transistor you need a semiconductor
channel. This semiconductor channel in
our case is 2D materials. And so the
question is why do I care about it over
here? The short answer is half of my
group works on 2D materials. Other half
works on aluminum scanning nitride. So
combine the two. That's a perfectly
wrong answers. That's not how you're
supposed to do research right. There's
actually a deep fundamental reason
behind picking these two materials as a
combination. But let me highlight the
advantages of 2D semiconductors. They
are potentially back end of line
compatible. You can transfer them or
directly grow them on wafer. Uh uh they
can be extremely high quality as uh at
very small thicknesses without the need
for epidoxy. This is important. Most 35
semiconductors are going to need epidox.
2D materials not need epidoxy. This is
going to be their main advantage for
future integration for commercialization
purposes. And this the very thin channel
of the 2D materials can mean it can they
can support or you can induce
electrostatically large carrier density
which will lead to very low resistances
and therefore very high speeds of
operation. Um if you want to take my
perspective unfiltered perspective on
the future of 2D semiconductors
um we've wrote a perspective article um
u last year on it. Uh we have written it
quite critically in both domains
electronics and photonics. You're
welcome to take a look at it. Again I
won't have time to go into the details
of why 2D why not 2D in today's talk. Uh
we've also written an article on 2D
ferroelectrics and ferroelectric
semiconductors. A large number of 2D
materials have now found to be
ferroctctors. There's a lot of
excitement over there too. I encourage
you to see that article. But the
argument of why you want to combine
aluminum scandium nitride with 2D
channels actually came from a paper more
than 22 23 years ago now written in n
EDL. My students don't like to read
these journals. because they have very
low impact factor they tell me right
they only want to read nature and
science which are mostly fake
but but
nonetheless there are there are gems
hidden in these journals right and there
was a gem written by TPMA about 22 years
ago as to why is a non-volatile feat
still elusive was a purely theory paper
and he basically outlined with the help
of two equations that if you want to
have data preservation inside an FAT
You want a low depolarization field EDP
and you also want a low rate of loss of
polarization which is DP over DT. And to
achieve that you want a high CIS which
is interfacial state capacitors in the
semiconductor. And you in the
ferroelectric you want large EC and low
K. This means you need thin
semiconductor channels and large EC and
low K means they are possible with
aluminum scandium nitride. In 2002,
neither 2D materials were known nor all
scan was known. In 2020, when we started
this research, we immediately identified
this combination and went to DARPA and
they took the bet on a very unlikely
research such as this and they funded
us, right? And so that sort of uh
started a lot of this stuff. Okay. Um so
we we went ahead and started making
these devices. The early devices were on
quite thick materials such as uh 100
nanometers of thick aluminum scandium
nitride grown on platinum which is also
sputtered. You can do platinum. You can
do aluminum. We can do various other
metallic electrodes. They have to be
hexagonal phase. Platinum is templated
111. Therefore woodite aluminum scanning
nitrate grows very well on it. This is
approximately 100 nanometers thick. You
made transistor devices. They had very
nice hysteresis loops almost square
shaped. I should mention these
hysteresis loops now are in current and
voltage not polarization electric field.
So you can actually sense them out and
program them in circuits. It's very
important. Okay. Um again these devices
look extremely well in terms of
switching numerous times storing data
for a very long time. I'm only showing
you 10^ 5 seconds over here but we have
gone through months now without loss of
data which is extremely good. If you
normalize the memory window of these
devices to other competing technologies
including that of Hafnea and silicon,
this sort of wins out in many respects.
This is again old data. This has only
become better over time. Certainly 2D
materials are now scalable. Professor
Palasios and various others have grown
these materials over wafer scales. They
have also grown it at b compatible
temperatures. So all this makes it very
appealing. Certainly we have not grown
them at b compatible temperatures but
professor redwing who is a two three
hours drive away from us at Penn State
she grows these films over sapphire
wafers. We can transfer whole wafers of
this material onto wafers of aluminum
scandium nitride and make hundreds and
hundreds of devices and then you can get
uh some very nice performing
transistors. These transistors u u uh
can be reduced in their operating
voltages. For instance, um if you in
reduce the thickness of the aluminum
scandium nitrite, the operating voltage
reduces. If you increase the scandium
concentration, the coarser field reduces
and therefore the operating voltage also
reduces. You can see a comparison of a
uh aluminum scanium nitrate feed with
compared to a silicon oxide with similar
thickness as silicon oxide uh feed has
about a few hundred times lower current
uh uh even at larger uh uh sweep range
of gate voltage. So this highly
nonlinear behavior comes from the ferro
electricity of the aluminum scanium
nitrite. Again just to show you can make
nanocale devices really shrink down the
channel lens. You don't really see any
effect in the transistor performance.
You can measure hundreds of these
devices. They can have very large memory
window and on-state conductivity very
important for fast operation. You can
partially polarize these ferroelectrics
and if you can partially polarize the
ferroelectrics uh you can partially
change the conductance of the
semiconducting channel which means you
can potentiate it and depress it just
like an artificial neuron. Again people
who are interested in using hardware
implementations of uh neurons for
neuromorphic computing. This is a great
avenue or people who just want to use
these devices in analog memory. This
would be a great approach to that. We
have published several more works on FET
devices or field effect transfer devices
out of aluminum scanium nitride and 2D
materials. I don't have the time to go
over all of them but I'll just mention
them. We have made them using tungsten
dicelenide wherein we can also get very
high onstate current density. Again the
ferroelectric introduces very large
carrier density which means the on-state
conduct conductance or current density
can be very large. Similarly, the
channel resistance can drop
significantly if you have a very highly
doped channel. And uh we've also
demonstrated the negative capacitance
effect. This was work actually the Sri
Krishna Coled who's now in Palasio's
group. And so we have uh we've
demonstrated all the major phenomena
that you would get uh using uh by by
pairing ferroelectrics with a novel
semiconductor. So with that I'm going to
switch gears and move to a different
type of federal memory device namely the
federal diode memory device. Okay, this
is very similar to a memorister device.
This does not have three terminals now.
It has only two terminals. This does not
need a semiconductor
anymore. So the ferroelectric diode
device is nothing but a sandwich of
aluminum scandium nitride or it could be
any other
ferroelectric in between two metallic
electrodes with an interfacial layer
which is a non-ferctric insulator. It
could be an oxide insulator, it could be
another nitride, what have you. Right
now the way this device works is
depending on the polarization of the
ferroelectric the conductance or the
leakage through the ferroelectric is
widely different by orders of magnitude.
Right? And so this gives it the
memoristive or resistive memory
phenomenon. Right? Not only that it is
also highly nonlinear and highly
asymmetric. Therefore the diode like
behavior. This is very advantageous for
various reasons. One it becomes a
voltage switch device rather than a
current switcher. A lot of the RAM and
phase change RAM are current switch
devices. You are actually passing a
certain amount of current basically
jewel heating the the thing until the
filament forms or breaks, right? You
don't need that over here. So this is
much less power consuming as compared to
RAM and PC RAM. PC RAM is already sort
of dying out slowly. RAM is still uh
used in some circles but uh scaling it
is going to become a big challenge.
Okay. Uh let's see. Okay. uh this ferro
diode effect or fed effect as we call it
is uh has been shown in other uh
ferroelectrics too. For example, in
Haphnneia people have shown it a few
years ago. Uh professor Chima just
showed me he was working on similar
effects in his his films as well as this
2D ferctrics like copper indium
phosphorus sulfide have shown the same
effect as well. So it's it's widely
known now. It's not something uh uh
obscure or absurd or one-off thing that
we are seeing. Um compared to the
standard resistive memory again like
phase change RAM or RAM which are this
quite symmetric and linear devices this
is highly nonlinear and highly
asymmetric. This means that unlike any
of these devices which would require a
pairing or selector transistor in the
underlying silicon hardware you don't
quite need it over here. This reduces
the hardware complexity quite a bit and
the hardware overhead you need in the
underlying silicon making it way more
energy efficient in terms of in-memory
compute or compute inmemory operations.
uh just to give you a very simple
illustration or example over there. You
could build an architecture known as
turnary content addressable memory or
TCAM. Right? This is a typical
architecture used in searches. Like if
you want to do search and pattern
matching over large bodies of data, you
would do this. If you wanted to do it in
silicon semos, you would need two SRAMM
cells, which means 16 transistors. If
you want to do it with standard
resistive memory devices, you'll need
two two memory, which are those
resistive elements that you see, and two
transistors. But if you wanted to do it
in ferro diodes, you'll just need two
ferctric diodes. And depending on how
you polarize them, you can get charge
discharge or don't care states over
here. Again, I'm happy to go over the
details of this later on. You can also
refer to the paper if you're interested.
So then if you project that into the
search delay versus cell area required,
you can see that it wins out over all
the other uh memory technologies that
you want to use for search and pattern
matching applications. Certainly the
energy consumption also drops by a
significant amount. this concept uh won
the Bell Labs prize a couple of years
ago uh which prompted us to think
further into commercializing this whole
area. Naturally, you can shrink down the
dimensions of the ferroelectric quite a
bit. When we first started this field, a
lot of people would not believe that you
can scale down the ferroelectrics to
such small thicknesses and maintain
ferctricity. The oxide community was
hellbent on believing themselves that u
uh this material was refused to remain
as a ferroelectric when you scaled it
down to below 10 nanometers in
thickness. Turns out even at 5
nanometers these diodes work pretty
well. Um I have data showing they can
this material itself can switch at about
2 volts or so as well. I can share that
later. You can also have program into
multiple memory states like about 32
states over here. Very linearly you can
program it and deprogram it. Again very
useful for synaptic behavior in
neuromorphic computing. Here are some
other data showing that when the field
started several years ago, people were
making a micron thick devices which are
not even on the scale. But then in like
five short years uh give or add another
year thanks to co you can shrink it down
to uh we have managed to shrink down the
um device thickness to about 5
nanometers and the important thing is
even at 5 nanometers in thickness the
remnant polarization of this material
stays quite close to the bulk remnant
polarization. This is an important
parameter showing that uh uh you can
truly scale the material and preserve
its fer electricity at the same levels
at bulk. There are many important
challenges to solve over there. Namely,
reducing the course of field at small
voltages which we'll talk about. Okay, I
want to mention a couple more things.
This has now been scaled up. You can
definitely make crossbar arrays instead
of individual devices. We are making
full 2 to 10 kilobyte chips. Here's a
4in wafer of 10 kilob chips. uh we are
dicing them out, wire bonding and
packaging them and sending them to
companies for testing. I'll tell you why
they would want such low memory uh u um
sort of density chips uh in a few
slides. But even in the bad clean room
that we have which uh you know all
genistic clean rooms are bad but ours is
way worse than yours right yours is much
newer too and much better maintained. So
anyways you can see that even in the few
hundred devices that we measured the
yield is about 99.4% 4% at 10 micron
device sizes right done using you know
the mask aligner
photoiththography and then the
distribution of switching voltage is
what is important to note if if you try
to compare resistive RAM or phase change
RAM memory this distribution is much
wide of the order of a couple of volts
we're talking about switching voltage
distribution under a 100 molt or so
which means excellent uniformity of the
material over large area wafers right
and again the on-off ratio has more
distribution But that is because of the
interfacial layer uh you made using ALD
which is not ideal. Um the next question
we get is can you really scale these
devices down to extremely small
nanometric dimensions and maintain phys
lateral dimensions and maintain their
memory performance. Turns out yes. This
graph shows you that 50 micron and 50
nanometer devices have an area scaling
of about a million times. But then if
you take that area scaling and convert
into current density actually all the
graphs overlap on top of each other.
This shows you it's a hyper ununiform
material from the micron scale down to
just a few tens of nanometers. This
would be unthinkable in case of RAM for
example where you are forming filament
and the ferin formation becomes more
stochastic the smaller dimensions you go
to. Okay. All right. The last thing that
people ding us upon all the time is
you're never going to be able to make a
ferroelectric switch billions and
billions of times because that has
always been the problem in
ferroelectrics. In the oxide fereralis
people have overcome it after 8 10 years
of work but here there's a huge
advantage that we are trying to that we
were not exploiting so far which is the
large polarization if the total
polarization is 100 microous perm square
you don't have to switch the full
polarization from top to bottom you have
to only switch a fraction of it if you
switch only a fraction of this
polarization you get your uh your memory
readout quite well and if you do so if
you partially polarize the aluminance
scandium nitride you can actually reach
cycling enduranceances is exceeding a
billion, right? We have data showing in
some devices we have data showing
exceeding 10 billion as well. And this
is still being done at device dimensions
of about 10 microns or so. These are the
smallest device dimensions. We hope that
when we start doing endurance
measurements on even smaller dimensions
like 100 nanometer, 50 nanometer
diameter devices, we should be able to
break uh uh the the sort of thresholds
that are required for commercialization
which is typically around 10 to the 11
10 to the 12. Okay. So what's the memory
landscape look like? Memory is a very
tight landscape. There are many
parameters on people which people
evaluate memory. Um again I'm I've
listed many of this. This table can rile
up a lot of people because of the
numbers. I've tried to go with very
conservative numbers over here. Um some
people tell I'm giving too much leeway
to other technologies over here uh given
what they offer commercially. But you
can see that the Alcan ferro diodes is
kind of beating all of the technologies
in most metrics. Right. The endurance
one is still something we are working
on. We expect that to even cross 10 to
the 10, 10 to the 11 in the coming
years. HBM DM is the volatile memory
currently used in most high-end GPUs or
Nvidia chip if you will. If you want to
compare federal diode memory to
commercially available RAM from TSMC or
Skywater again on most metrics, we are
we have we have beaten these
commercially available technologies with
the exception of voltage and this is
something that we are trying to solve
now. uh we are hoping with the help of
Intel and others we'll be able to
address that too in a year year and a
half of time and we'll be ready for
prime time commercialization at that
time but even without that there is a
particular application where this
material could have uh could could use
uh this uh memory technology right now
and that is an extreme environment
computing. Why? Because as you can see
from this chart, this is one of the few
thin film ferroelectrics, probably the
only one available that is extremely
stable at elevated temperatures. Now,
why do you need to store data in those
temperatures? There's a whole field of
electronics in extreme environments. We
wrote a review article on that recently
and there are several material
challenges over there in various
domains, packaging, interconnects,
logic, inst uh you know gate,
dialectrics, memory, etc. The memory
problem is particularly severe because
there has never been a commercially
available nonvolatile memory that can
operate more than 250C. Today, if you go
in the market and ask someone, I want a
nonvolatile memory to store data at
upwards of 250°C, they'll tell you it's
not possible. The best available is a
flash memory by Texas Instruments or
some other small companies that also
needs to be refreshed every 100
milliseconds at 250°C. So there's no way
to reliably store data today at elevated
temperatures. So and there are many
applications for that. I don't need to
go into it but many defense and nuclear
power applications but also in oil oil
and gas exploration automotive
industrial electronics and so on
certainly space applications. Now if you
want to think about just logic
transistors they have been quite well
achieved or solved at elevated
temperatures like silicon carbide
technology is pretty mature over there.
NASA has worked on it for several years,
right? And they have 800° CCelsius
transistors working quite well. This is
how some of NASA's processors that they
wanted to use on Venus look like they
don't have too many transistors as you
can see about,000 to 10,000 transistors.
This is a few years old, but about
thousand to 10,000 transistors is what
they have on silicon carbide dies. And
most of the transistors are used as
SRAMM volatile memory leaving extremely
few number of transistors to do actual
compute. So in this case, if you had a
nonvolatile memory device where you
stored the data and forgot about it and
only just went and accessed it when you
needed it, the amount of computing power
could grow by leaps and bounds at
elevated temperatures. And the prime
such application to begin with would be
jet engines um uh and and downhole
drilling exploration in in uh in in oil
and gas
exploration. Um and so we have now
tested ferctric diodes, the same concept
that I showed you a few slides ago. It
works extremely well up to 600°C. I have
unpublished data that is going up to
800°C. You can see the resistive memory
effect sustained quite well up to 600°C.
The on-off ratio drops a bit, but we
have now used interfacial layer
engineering to also bump this up to
about 50 or so. At 800°C, you can see
very clear ferroelectric stitching. In
fact, fer electricity becomes better in
this material because the course of
field reduces as you increase
temperature and you see extremely sharp
uh ferroelectric displacement currents
coming up in pund measurements even at
elevated temperatures. Right? You can
keep store the memory state and read it
out millions of times at
600°C. You can keep it for hours. Here
is a 60-hour data. We have now tested
with AFRL for several weeks. The that
data is not included here. Again, no
change in the memory state after weeks
at elevated temperature like 600 C. And
then if you compare it with the compete
any competing technologies out there,
there's almost nothing out there. There
was one data point out here. This one
over here, this is platinum wires which
are made and u which are broken and
resoldered by passing current at
elevated temperatures. They can only
last a couple hundred cycles at the very
most, right? and they can only store
data only for a certain amount of time
as well. So really only this federal
memory technology that is the only
viable one out there uh at elevated
temperatures and now with our new data
we have also pushed this up over here.
So it becomes pretty much the most
dominant technology. I should mention
that this can also work at very low
temperatures up to 12 Kelvin. So all the
way from 12 Kelvin to 1200 Kelvin it
works out pretty fine. It also works
quite well under gamma radiation
exposure. This was done with Sandia
National Lab. And in the last couple of
minutes that I had, I want to mention
that aluminum scandium nitride is also
very well lattis matched or quasi well
latis matched to silicon carbide because
aluminum nitride is extremely well latis
matched. Aluminum scanning nitride is uh
um reasonably latis matched to silicon
carbide. So you can grow on it directly
and you can switch uh capacitive
devices, ferroelectric capacitor devices
on silicon carbide all the way up to
1000 C, no problem. Um you'll see as you
keep increasing the temperature the
number of cycles they'll switch before
they fail starts reducing slightly but
that's not a huge deal because at
elevated temperature mostly you want
reliable read operations and reliable
write operations over millions of times
okay that brings me to the end and I
want to make a point that if you look at
high temperature compute technology or
in general any extreme environment
compute these are sort of the current
technologies available at elevated
temperatures 250C silicon high silicon
300 00 C SOI technology and 900C NASA's
JFAT and if you compare them to the
mainstream silicon technology this is
more law line basically we are stuck in
the 2000s or late 90s as compared to the
high high temperature uh electronics
technology is concerned that because
thermodynamics takes over at some point
and you can't just arbitrarily scale
things and expect it to operate in the
same reliable fashion as you get it to
do at low temperatures or at room
temperatures right and so the only way
forward if you want to augment computing
at elevated temperatures is you will
have to do memory enhanced computing and
therefore having a reliable non-volatile
memory at elevated temperatures become
very important in this niche but very
important area of electronics. So that
I'd like to end and mention that
aluminum scanny n is a very promising
back end of line compatible
ferroelectric material. The resistive
ferro diode memory is quite uh promising
for commercialization. I already shown
you some 2 to 10 kilobyte chips. You can
also made very nice 2D FE feds with it
or 2D channel FETSS. The key scientific
challenge is reducing course of field at
small thicknesses and it's also very
viable candidate for high temperature
extreme environment nonvortile memory.
With that I would like to thank you all
again. Thanks Fernas for inviting and
I'm happy to take any questions. Thank
you.
Thanks for a great talk. We have time
for a few questions. Um any question
from the audience?
Uh thank you a very impressive talk. I
have two questions. Uh first one is um
regarding the uh scalability and uh
energy consumption. Could you briefly
compare the file electric fat and ferro
diode and in which real application
which one is better and second one is u
can we also use lscan for capacitor
based memories or are there any uh
difficulties or challenges behind it?
Thank you. Okay, great. Um first
question is can you compare these two
devices in terms of energy the top one
over here and the bottom one? Um my
sense is it it depends on the
architecture a lot right for instance um
if you want to think about the first
device a three terminal device if you
want to at a circuit level it's always
going to have more capacitors more
parasitic capacitors because of the
capacitive nature of the gate in the
transistor. So in terms of reading and
in terms of reducing the uh terms of
ultimate frequency of operation that is
a limiting factor uh in this is a simple
two terminal device. So if you want to
compare again at a circuit level in
terms of read energies and read speeds
this is going to present much lower LCR
or parasitic LCR and therefore the
energy consumption is going to be much
lower than the than the above one. Okay.
But there are also other challenges.
That one is actually much better because
it has a semiconductor channel whose
on-off ratio can be arbitrarily
increased or jacked up. Over here you're
kind of limited by that. I mean you have
to do some engineering to get on-off
ratios of 10 ^ 5 6 and so on. There you
get 10^ the 7 10 the 8 quite easily
right and it has a non-destructive read
already built in. Even this one has a
non-destructive read but at extremely
low voltages we don't know what's going
to happen. Right? Right. So there are
advantages and disadvantages. The other
advantage this one has is very easy to
make and fabricate in back end of line.
It's just a simple three layer
structure. That one always involves the
semiconductor dialectric interface. One
heck of an interface if you ask the
semiconductor industry. The hardest one
to optimize typically right. So always
more challenging. And the second one can
you use aluminum scan matter as a simple
ferlectric capacitor memory? Yes, you
can. And like all ferroelectric
capacitors, you can certainly use it and
then switch it like a ferroelectric
capacitor like I showed over here.
Right? When you switch it like a
ferrolectric capacitor, it's called a
pund pd
measurement positive up negative down
when you are switching up you get this
ferctric current and you then you again
switch up there is no current because
ferctctor switching has already happened
you switch it down you get current and
you get no current. So based on this
this current signal intensity and and
the uh direction you can tell whether
memory zero memory one certainly you can
do it but there's a problem then how
much can you scale it because when you
scale below a certain dimension the
displacement current is going to scale
with the volume of the ferroelectric at
some point it's going to become
comparable to a leakage current so you
cannot really scale it down that much
unless you start making 3D capacitors
which is very hard to make right the
second issue is every time you are
trying to read you are also switching
the material. So there is read disturb
or you're writing the material as you're
reading it too. So that means the amount
of endurance that is available to you is
limited. But certainly you can yeah
nothing is stopping you from using it as
a capacitor memory.
Great. So there's a question
online. Can you comment on whether
there's an understanding why the
material maintains its fair electricity
at extremely thin thickness and also at
high temperatures? Okay.
Um so I don't have like a quantitative
answer to this like the qualitative
answer to I have is that the woodside
structure is the thermodynamically more
stable state that this material goes
into and I think the if you look at the
energetics of the uh of the the various
phases it seems like the barrier to
cross over to the other phase which is
the rock salt phase is pretty large
right so this is the only stable
structure it can go into And there is no
other structure it goes into even at
very small thicknesses or at very high
temperatures. And so that's I think the
main reason why uh it stays
ferroelectric because the polar state
the woodside polar state is the only
state it knows. Now um we don't know
what happens at the u phase diagram
boundary uh at around 40% scandium or so
you start getting some evidence of rock
salt phase coming in. And so if you are
making an aluminum scandium nitride film
at say 40 or
42%. Whether or not it'll stay stable in
the woodside structure phase at elevated
temperatures or a very small thickness
is unclear. We are we are trying to do
some experiments over them. We're not
100% sure. But this is a good
theoretical question to figure out
right. I'm pretty sure the computational
material scientists can tell you what is
the energy barrier between the rock salt
state and the woodside structure at at
elevated temperature under a certain
amount of strain for very thin films
which is what thin film very thin films
experience in this material. Great.
Thank you.
Oh hi. Thanks for the nice talk. So you
mentioned that the aluminum scandium
nitrite can be grown like coaraxially
um like silicon carbide. So I'm just
curious have uh how did your engineering
that or have you done any studying to
how this like coat will influence your
EC or uh other okay yeah so the thing
I'll mention we we didn't do any special
engineering we just took a silicon
carbide wafer out of the box put it in
the reactor film came out right um the
the course of field on the so silicon
carbide was uh endoped so put so of
field on the negative side did not
change at all on the positive side the
course of voltage increase because of
the depletion region formed in silicon
carbide. So you have to be careful how
how doped is your semiconductor sample
because the depletion layer adds other
extra voltage across or extra region
across this voltage drop happens before
switching happens but otherwise it's
comparable to what you do on metal
electrodes like platinum was one
question here I guess yeah
Sorry. Uh can you repeat that? Uh would
you foresee that uh for electric uh
transistors and like for example RAM
would be integrated directly or would
you rather use silicon for one or the
other? Well, so silicon I think will
remain as the base layer of compute. I
don't think it's going anywhere. Right.
So the com logic layer will remain
silicon camos. The question at what goes
on top of it and this is where I think
ferroelectrics have a very strong chance
which ferroelectric again somewhat
debatable if you ask me for high
temperature extreme environment we have
a clear choice right now which is
aluminum scandium nitrite for leading
edge nodes like 45 nanometers and below
Hafne is doing pretty well but again I
I'm yet to see a commercial product or
wide wide market product that has used
halfneia for its ferro electricity not
for other properties like enhanced
dialectric properties or something like
that. uh so it remains to be seen you
know maybe may you know afia makes its
way to the market and eventually over
several years can also improve in terms
of switching voltages that eventually
there's a transition over to nitride fry
thank you
any other questions
thanks for the talk uh there have been a
lot of recent reports on back end of
line compatible fetss and fifetss made
from various amorphous oxide channels.
So, I was wondering if you could compare
uh 2D and oxide channels for back end of
line transistors. Yeah, it's a great
question. You know, I I don't have a
clear answer to what will win out over
there, right? I mean, 2DS are still
pretty naent. Oxide semiconductors have
been around for a long time. They are
already quite commercial from the
display application, right? So, there's
a lot more research gone into oxide
channels for a longer time. The issue
with amorphous oxides is that they are
amorphous and therefore subject to
oxygen movement at the interface right
and so how much does this present a
reliability issue is something that I
don't know uh 2D charco on the other
hand should not have this reliability
issue because again they are vander
walls sort of passed but how good of a
quality can you maintain of 2D materials
and uniformity and reliability at the
same temperatures of growth as oxides I
think those are the key questions to
answer if The answer to both of those
questions is affirmative for the 2D and
oxides are like meh then 2D would likely
win out but that's a big if again we
don't know.
Excellent. If there are no more
questions here, let's thank the speaker.
Thanks a lot for a wonderful Thank you.