Hi everyone. Um, thank you for joining
the Renee Salazar speaker series hosted
by the Latinx at Broad Affinity Group at
the Broad Institute. My name is Adana
Nves. Um, and I have the pleasure of
welcoming our speaker, Dr. Julian
Abilacho. Um, and before the
presentation, I would like to talk a bit
about the Latinx community and our
special collaboration with out at Broad.
So the Renee Salazar speaker series is
meant to highlight researchers within
different scientific fields and
disciplines, foster collaboration,
highlight role models for from varied
personal and professional backgrounds,
give opportunities to network and
promote research. So we're really
excited to have you all here and learn
from one of our very own. Um, following
this mission, we created the Latinx
speaker series with the purpose of
building community amongst broadies as
well as offering opportunities for
connection, learning, and belonging. So,
we hope that you feel the vibes here
today. Um, before we kick off, this is a
special collab with Out at Broad. So, I
will give it to my collaborator Julian
Pausnak just to give us a bit intro on
out at Broadro. Thanks so much. Uh, I
won't take up too much time. I just
wanted to say how uh grateful we are to
be uh partnering with Latin X at Broad
for today's session. Um when we were
planning for Pride Month, we thought it
might be really nice to uh reach out to
a whole bunch of different groups and
collaborate and Latin exit broad um
immediately came to mind especially for
their speaker series. uh we've been
looking to dive into scientific
presentations more ourselves and we
thought that this was a perfect
opportunity to uh dip our toe in that
pool so to speak. Um, and as we started
thinking about who might join us, um, I
connected with, uh, Julian Aila Pacheco
a while ago, um, for those of you who
don't know, not only is he one of the
broad senior scientists, but uh, he was
also one of the original co-founders of
Outit. So, we thought that this was kind
of a perfect opportunity for us to uh,
partner on this. And personally, not
only has he really been um a great
mentor in helping me and the rest of the
out at Broad steering committee think
about what we might do and what the
group uh how the group can help members
of the out community at Broad. Um but he
was also um
he's also just been immensely supportive
of of what we're doing. So uh without
further delay, I'll let him take it
away. Yeah. Before we get started, I
just want to like um highlight the
agenda for today. So, and give a little
bit of a bio on Julang A. Um so, Julang
Abil Pachka is a senior research
scientist in the metabolomics platform
at the Broad Institute of MIT and
Harvard where he works under the
direction of Clary Kush. His research
interests lie in developing methods for
the analysis and interpretation of
metabolomics data generating generated
using liquid chromatography, tandem mass
mass spectrometry. A key focus of his
research is discovering and
characterizing novel metabolites
associated with a broad range of
disorders such as inflammatory bowel
disease, metabol metabolic disease and
cancer. Um, Julang actively collaborates
in numerous metabolic uh profiling
projects within the institute and the
external community. Today Julian will be
talking about GABA arginine, a novel
brain metabolite associated with
survival in tubercular menitis patients.
Um after the talk we'll give it about 15
minutes for a Q&A and the chat will be
open for folks to engage. So without
further ado, welcome Julian Abacho
and and both thank you Adriana and Julie
and I I it's it's really nice to to get
invited to give this talk. have been
involved with out and and shades in
different capacities over the past what
like 10 years since we got involved in
getting out of room started and so it's
really nice to see like the efforts to
just have a space for us to get together
and share our work. Um
uh can we switch the to my slides now?
I'm still seeing the All right. Well,
thank you everyone for for being here uh
today. Uh I'm happy to share this story
we have been working on at the
metabolomics platform in the broad
institute. Um I don't know how familiar
everyone is with with the platform. Uh
so I I figure I would give you a small
introduction of who we are and where we
are compared to many groups at the
broad. We're relatively small group. We
are around 1920 people now. and and
primarily we have um scientists who are
in the lab running this instrumentation
to generate data at at at a at scale. We
also have a small team of software
engineers developing tools to process
the data, QC it, visualize it, organize
large amounts of information and we have
a small admin team of of one person. Uh
there are also a couple scientists
currently working on on expanding our
imaging mass spectrometry efforts and
identifying compounds which will be the
the topic of today's talk. Uh we used to
be in the American building in the
seventh floor but now we we we are in
Beanie Street in the third floor. Uh we
moved last February. We expanded our
footprint. So now we have this beautiful
lab space you're seeing there on the
right. Uh so if you feel like you would
like to come by and visit and learn more
about what we do, please let me know. We
would love to have you and give you a
tour. Uh so I'm just going to jump right
into what we do in the in the platform.
And and I appreciate this talk is it has
a broad audience. So the way I structure
it is we're going to go into a very
general um introduction to the
technology we use to smell sorry measure
small molecules or metabolites
and and hopefully we'll we'll all get on
the same page as to how we we do what we
do. Uh so if you're an expert in LCMS
please bear with me. So what we do in
the platform as metabolomics may
indicate is is measure small molecules
of metabolites. Um our our primarily
primary primary focus is to measure uh
samples biological samples obtained from
from primarily humans but we also have
samples obtained from animal models uh
cell cultures either ukarotic or
bacterial
uh tissues media and sometimes we
profile uh different samples that uh
don't fall into these categories.
profile in the past tense like beer and
juice and and different different
things. Uh and then we have an
analytical methodology that primarily uh
relies on liquid chromatography uh
coupled to high resolution mass
spectrometry and we use that to generate
those uh measurements and we'll go into
more detail into how we do that in the
next couple slides. In the platform we
also do some very simple um analytical
statistical analysis on the data we
generate. Uh we do all of the data
processing and generate uh sort of
completed data sets that are then shared
with our collaborators so they can date
then take that data and and just do
different things with it. Primarily
trying to find uh associations of small
molecules with disease. try to discover
perhaps molecules that may help you
predict uh the onset of of disease. Uh
classify patients or samples based on
those metabolic phenotypes try to
understand the mechanisms behind
disease. Uh figure out drug activity and
efficacy and in general discover new
metabolites that may help us understand
disease and that that's where where I
come in. Uh traditionally the work we've
been doing in the platform uh focus on
these large cohorts uh where uh we're
trying to identify metabolites that may
help us u predict disease or understand
the early symptoms of of someone
developing a particular condition. And
to do that we rely on this collection of
longitudinal cohorts. There are many out
there where where uh participants are
recruited, samples are biobanked, could
be plasma, urine, tissues, and then
they're followed up over the spans of
years, sometimes decades, and sometimes
generations. So you can essentially look
in back in time and see in a population
for those people who develop a
particular condition test to see if
there were any metabolites that were
more abundant or less abundant that
could help us predict and diagnose u
disease before it actually um happens.
So with with this we have to date
profiled over 40,000 individuals from
from these cohorts and the interesting
thing is that many of these cohorts have
additional layers of of omic data. So
they're many of them have exom
sequencing. So in addition to generating
uh the measurements of so small
molecules we have access to the genetic
background of each individual. So we can
start integrating uh different types of
information to understand sort of the
the complexity of disease in a more
individual individualized way.
Now since it's a broad audience uh I'm
just going to go with a very uh simple
introduction to uh metabolism and how we
measure metabolites. So I I assume that
most people who are in the seminar right
now are familiar with the work we do in
the institute. uh there's quite a bit of
uh genomic uh transcrytoic work uh so I
wanted to frame metabolism and small
molecules within this central dogma
which is the concept of DNA in the
nucleus of the cell being transcribed
into RNA which is then translated to
proteins and those proteins are act
enzyatically on on substrates which are
small molecules and and the proteins are
usually uh converting different uh
molecules into different uh molecules
that are necessary for central
processes. So we can start from sugars
and then break them down to generate
energy or we can start from sugars and
uh make some fats and proteins and and
other components that make us who we
are. So so I like to see this as as just
small binding blocks metabolites and I I
used to love playing with Legos when I
was a kid. So I do really like this this
analogy. uh seeing metabolizes as just
building blocks that make up essentially
everything in in a biological sample. Uh
and the question that we often get asked
is how many metabolis are are there?
Because if you if you think about it, it
it's relatively easy to estimate how
many genes you may run into a human
genome that are at least coding for uh a
particular protein. Uh and you can also
start looking into how many transcripts
you can detect at a given time. in in a
cell type or a tissue. And it gets a
little bit more complicated when you
start looking at the potential universe
of variance you have in proteins,
protein isoforms. And if you add
modifications to those proteins, it
starts getting really complicated. And
when you get to metabolizes, I would
argue a little bit more complicated than
that. So according to the human
metabolum database which is a pretty
comprehensive uh database that tries to
index all the possible metabolites that
you would expect to see or that have
been detected in human biofluids. There
are about 200,000 potential human
metabolites
with about over 40,000 that have been
referenced or or described as detected
or quantified in human bofluids.
So that's quite quite a few. But in
reality, uh if you think about
metabolites, they're small molecules.
And we're not only thinking about the
small molecules that your body is making
via transcription protein activity,
endogenous metabolites, but you're
thinking about compounds that you may be
getting exposed to either because you
are consuming them in your food or drugs
or maybe because you're getting exposed
to them as in pollutants or chemicals
that are in things you put on your body.
And it gets even more complicated when
we think about the variability of
bacteria in your stomach, on your skin,
and the contributions of those metabolic
activities that may transform molecules
that we're expecting to see in someone
into new molecules that we may not know.
Uh so that expands the universe of
potential molecules that you could
detect. And if you weren't to see how
many rearrangements of different atoms
of carbon, nitrogen, oxygen, hydrogen,
uh the numbers start ballooning
significantly and you could start going
to like potential millions of
combinations of different um arranges.
Not necessarily that you would detect
all of these in a bofluid but it's a
potential universe based on like where
are you are where you are what you're
consuming and what compounds you may see
in someone in a population. So that
that's sort of the question of what are
metabolites where do they come from u
the next question is how do we measure
them here in the metabolomics platform.
So, so the the the great challenge with
measuring metabolites is unlike
sequencing and unlike other
technologies, um there is no universal
way to measure all of the metabolites
under the sun. And to complicate this
even more, we have metabolites that can
be found in a sample at very very small
concentrations at the same time as other
metabolites are present in super high
concentrations. So that's called a
dynamic range. you have to have a
technology that lets you measure very
small amounts but also just really great
concentrations of them. And the next I
would argue most challenging part of it
is that small molecules vary
tremendously in their physical and
chemical properties. Uh and I think
everyone is familiar with this. There
are molecules that are very sticky,
non-polar. They don't like water like
lipids, fats, cholesterol. And they're
molecules that are water soluble.
they've been solved very easily such as
sugars, amino acids. So those different
characteristics makes them really hard
to measure at the same time. So usually
we have to generate different analytical
methods that lets us cover the broad
range of chemical classes uh and cover
their metabolism. I would argue that
although many labs that measure
metabolisms have a variety of methods to
measure all of them, usually there are
areas of the chemical space that are
very hard to detect no matter how many
methods you have. So even though we're
measuring we're claiming to measure
everything everything that's possibly
observable, there may be things that are
always left um behind.
So the way we measure uh metabolites
here in the platform is using liquid
chromatography and mass spectrometry. I
imagine many of you have heard
chromatography from this like
experiments that I think every kid or at
least hope every kid would uh would do
in school where you have a collection or
a mixture of different dyes and you spot
them on some filter paper and you put
them in water or alcohol and then the
the the solution as it moves through the
paper starts pulling those pigments
apart and separating them based on their
ability to interact with the with the
paper which in this phase would be the
stationary phase and and their affinity
for the mobile phase or the liquid in
this case is uh dictated by their
chemical characteristics. So we take
advantage of that same principle except
we don't have paper in the in the
instruments we use. We instead use these
columns of material that has been
tightly packed in it that has chemical
properties like the paper that are
designed to interact with certain
molecules based on their uh chemical
properties and they're packed in these
metal columns because then we are going
to push these liquids faces at
incredibly high pressures to to make
sure they separate as much as possible
and they're resolved as as best as
possible. And I'm showing you this like
industrial size column. But in reality,
these are very thin and very narrow. At
least the analytical columns that we use
routinely. Uh so in essence, a package
of of molecules extracted from a sample
will enter this column, get pushed with
a mobile phase and based on its ability
to interact with those beads uh and the
the chemical on it, then they will get
separated. And the ones that stay in the
column for the longest period of time,
they're more attracted to it. And the
ones that come off first or elute first
are the more attractive to the solvent.
Now I added a more realistic example of
this. This is a silica particles. So
those tiny beads are covered in silica.
And if you had a combination of these
types of molecules where those like
benzene ring containing ones that eluded
first would be pretty hydrophobic and
not able to interact with the silica
really well. So those would come off the
column first. And the other ones which
have like this nitrogen uh element in
them would be able to interact with the
silica with higher affinity and would
take longer to get out of the column and
and that essentially gives us uh the
concept of the retention time. So
molecules that are coming off the column
really fast in this case very early are
molecules that did not interact very
well with with the column and then
molecules that elude later are molecules
that were bound tightly to the column.
And then by switching those model faces
to something that they like better, they
come off the column and they elute
later. So the first dimension of
separation we have when we run a complex
mixture of compounds is the
chromatography phase.
The next part uh well no before the next
part uh so if you're running a very
complex mixture let's say in this case u
a plasma sample uh the reality is that
we have many many many molecules in a
plasma sample that will interact very
similar to to each other and will get
retained very similarly. So in reality
we have many many molecules that maybe
is different in size but chemically
they're very similar. So end up coming
off at the same time. So we still have a
pretty messy mixture of compounds here.
So retention time chromatography is not
enough for us to just characterize
everything that is in a sample and
separate it fully. So that's where mass
mass spectrometry comes in. So mass
spectrometry uh it is a technology that
requires molecules to be ionized. And in
the lab we rely heavily on on this
particular technology of mass
spectrometers that has uh an orbit trap
analyzer. It looks kind of like that in
the palm of your hand. The instruments
look like this. They're these big boxes
uh so take up quite a bit of room. And
we have currently about 15 that that
rely on this technology. Um they there's
been like several iterations of this.
They're very creative with the
nomomenclature. Oh, it's just Q Exactive
plus a bunch of different names. And
we're currently transitioning to sort of
a newer platform called Explorers 240.
And we have one of those committed to
imaging as well at the moment. And we
have uh in comparison only four
instruments that uh unlike this orbit
trap technology are using a different
type of profiling to measure compounds.
the targeted instrumentation uh that
right now we're using for very specific
applications but but most of the studies
that I've that I mentioned before they
have they're being acquired with this
technology that I'm going to describe in
very general terms here so this cartoon
representation would be sort of a
cross-section of these one of these
machines u not all of them are designed
this way uh but the idea is as the
compounds are eluding from your column
the the ones that are interacting with
it poorly will come out first the ones
that get tightly bound in um elute
later. So you have this package of of
compounds that are eluding in the
solvent. So they're in this liquid phase
and they get to the stage where there is
a u a process where they get ionized and
they get vaporized. So there's a
technology here where there's energy
being applied to them. There's heat that
vaporizes the molecule. So the molecules
pass from being in liquid to being in
gas and forming ions. So getting charged
and this machine essentially what it's
doing is using just this electromagnetic
fields and this uh rods charged rods
called um quadruples or um yeah
quadruples primarily. Let's leave it at
that. Uh so they're guiding all these
charged molecules through these optics
and then they're sending them to the
orbit trap analyzer which is a detector
that does a couple things. It does one
thing. It separates all of this package
of ions based on Mars 2 charge and then
it gives us the abundance of each one of
them. That's critical because I
mentioned as these uh packages of
compounds are coming off the column you
still have a pretty complex mixture and
as they enter the mass spectrometer the
mass spectrometer is able to separate
them based on their size and then is
able to tell us how much of each one of
those it found. So as as this process is
is coupled and and happening, you start
having compounds that are coming off and
you start seeing signals, mass to charge
signals separated every time the
molecule is coming off and you start
plotting their intensities. Uh you start
getting these like nice profiles for for
the peaks and and this happens over the
span of a whole run which in our methods
is usually anywhere between 16 to 30
minutes.
and and that's and essentially you end
up getting something like this. This is
just the same representation. This is a
real real file obtained from profiling
stool and it would be this uh peak map
that I'm showing you here observed from
above. So each one of these like little
dots and speckles would be one of those
features that the masspec was able to
resolve as the compounds were coming off
the the column. And there could be many
of these uh in stool we can get 20,000
to 40,000 of these peaks and and all of
them ideally they're not necessarily
true but the majority of these come from
compounds and molecules that were found
in this sample. So the next question
would be well how can we tell what they
are? Uh so there are two main steps
these are sort of a gold standards to
figure out what the compound may be. The
first one is we have to buy a compound.
We have to get a compound to uh test
first of all if it interacts the same
way with the column the the liquid
chromatography column we used and if
there is a match for the compound the
mass to charge of the molecule has to
match the retention time of our unknown
in the sample. And there's a second
dimension to uh annotating these
compounds which is we need to break down
the molecule and look at the fingerprint
that it generates to make sure that
whatever molecule or whatever known peak
in the sample matches that unique
commercially available standard we we
have. What does that mean? Let's say we
have two molecules. Uh these two
molecules for instance have the same
formula. We're just rearranging the
little elements in it in different uh
configurations. They're called isomers
because of that. And going back to the
Lego example, you may have different uh
units that you could break by applying
some energy. And this fmentation I
showed you is capable of doing this. And
and this energy will break the molecule
in different patterns based for based on
each individual uh structure that you
have. And that's because some of the
substructures may be more stable in some
molecules than in others. So let's say
in this case you have one that will
produce this um fragment at 10. But this
molecule over here may fragment
differently and generate this uh product
ion spectrum that is different from this
one. So in a way we like to think of
this as a fingerprint for each
individual molecule. And you could use
this information to figure out how the
pieces come together, but also you could
use it to confirm that the molecule
you're actually working with is indeed a
match for that signal, the mass
spectrometer. So,
so the whole point of this talk is just
to highlight the the importance of
identifying these compounds and the the
way I describe this process, it it is
very expensive. It is time consuming uh
and it's primarily biased towards
metabolites that we already knew about.
So think about amino acids, sugars,
carnitines, everything you may have seen
in your biochemistry books when you took
biochemistry.
Uh but that in reality is just a
fraction of all these thousands of
thousands of signals that you could run
in in a in a in a sample. And you could
think about many of them being quite
rare because maybe this person traveled
to Mexico and ate something that we
didn't have here and ate something that
you would never expect to see in the
human metabolum database or maybe even
pumpkin. So the question is how do we go
about uh characterizing those molecules
and how why is is there a point in
trying to do so? So so hopefully I will
convince you at the end of this talk
that it is something worth investing in
and something worth looking into.
All right. So you're all experts now in
liquid chromatography, mass spectrometry
and metabolomics. So I'm just going to
go now into the topic of the talk which
is tuberculosis menitis.
So tuberculosis menitis is a type of um
menitis which is just inflammation of
the meningas. And if you're not familiar
with the word meningis is is the lining
of of your brain and your spine. It it
is a very important region of the brain
that sort of regulates the movement of
cerebral spinal fluid. It sort of acts
as a barrier to control what comes into
contact with the brain and protects the
brain. It's a very unique ecosystem in
your body. So the inflammation of the
meninjas causes all sorts of different
symptoms that you don't want once it is
uh swollen or inflamed and and this
disease is caused by uh mcoacterium
tuberculosis which you may have heard of
it as causing uh pneumonia attacking
primarily the lungs but TB is is is just
really it's really incredible of a
pathogen and it can uh occur in many
other places other than the lungs lungs
it can it can infect different tissues
in the body and the brain is one of
them. And and while the brain infections
are not as common as the pulmonary, uh
they are quite bad once people get them,
especially bad in in young children and
individuals infected with HIV. You could
understand that, you know, within a
compromised immune system, this is quite
quite a bad outcome. And even even
though it can be cured in some cases,
this still has a pretty high mortality
rate, much higher than pulmonary
tuberculosis. And even if it is treated
and cured, it usually leaves at least
half of the survivors with with
permanent squella permanent
complications.
Uh and the additional challenge is is
that it's just really hard to diagnose
it. you patients usually present to the
clinic with very very general symptoms
like fever, headache, feeling sick uh
usually for a long period of time and to
get a full full comprehensive diagnosis
you have to sample the CSF uh and to get
the CSF is not easy. you usually have to
go into your spine and do a tab uh which
is quite invasive and sometimes the
person is so ill you cannot do that and
even when you have the CSF you have to
either grow it to see if TB grows or you
have to do some PCR testing which is
sometimes not sensitive enough to find
it because you you don't have an out of
control infection in the CSF you
probably have fewer cells in there um
and the other thing is causes all sorts
of weird symptoms so it's really hard to
if you see a patient to say is this the
course of treatment for it. So treatment
is often delayed making it really hard
and I'm showing this case that I run
into uh that was uh reported for a 24
year old uh man in Pakistan someone who
had been having headaches for 3 months
and finally came to the hospital after
uh suffer from uh neck stiffness and
started having seizures. So he went to
the clinic and they couldn't really
figure out what was going on. did a PCR
on sputin blood to see if there was TB
or any other infections. It all came
back negative. When they did an MRI,
they did see this like um really uh
these ring lesions in the brain as well
as somewhere here in the spine which is
quite bad and there's inflammation as
well in in in the in the spine. So at
the end of the day it was not confirmed
that this patient had TB but because of
these characteristics the person was
given a cocktail of four antibiotics and
improved quite a bit. So the assumption
was that TB was the cause for these
symptoms and these uh nodules. The
patient responded positively, was
discharged. But even after three month
and six month follow-ups, this patient
was still moving in crutches, still had
a catheter because could not um uh could
not control uh urination. So, so what I
was trying to do here is just illustrate
how this is pretty debilitating. is hard
to diagnose and even though the the
response to treatments is sometimes uh
appropriate, it can leave uh lasting
consequences in people. So we uh and by
we I mean Clary uh almost 10 years ago
uh got involved in in starting this
project and I just wanted to tell the
story of how this project came to be
because in the platform we work with
collaborators uh in many different
spaces and people often ask us how how
do I work with you? How do I get to do
this really cool work and and this is an
example of how this happened. So uh
Ronnie Xavier which many of you are
familiar with he works in the infectious
disease and microbiome program he had
some collaborators at this university in
the Netherlands Rodba University and
these collaborators had collaborators of
their own there and one of his
collaborators of theirs uh is this uh
doctor infectious disease physician
Rhina Vancrievel. So through this
collaboration he learned about us uh
about the work of Clary and the
metabolomics platform and he reached out
to Clary and asked hey we have this very
interesting cohort of uh TBIS patients
and in Bandung Indonesia and we would
like we have this hypothesis about this
family of molecules that we believe are
disregulated in people with TB menitis
in the CSF we believe there's this
immune misregulation that is killing
people. So we would like to uh use
metabolomics to answer that question. At
the time there was no funding. So Clara
said, "Well, we never profiled CSF."
Hopefully I'm not misrepresenting what
actually happened. You can correct me if
I'm wrong. Uh uh we had never profiled
CSF with the methods we have. Not sure
we'll be able to do this. So let's try
to get these samples and try to profile
them and see what what we find. So we
had this this catalytic pilot project
where we got a subset of samples and
this these are the characteristics of
those samples. Uh it was a small set of
uh controls. uh and the controls are
subjects who uh presented to the clinic
with with with symptoms but after doing
the testing and the the culture of of
the CSF they were found not to have
bacterial menitis or microacterial
menitis as well as uh 15 samples from TB
menitis patients who survive after
treatment and 17 of those who did not
survive. And then there was another set
of samples that that we profiled that we
deemed the validation cohort for for
some of these findings in the first set
of samples.
H so we collected uh four LCMS profiling
methods. In this case, we we use uh
three different types of chromatography.
Uh so now you're all experts in
chromatography. The ones I show you were
were helic essentially. But we have
other types of chromatography that are
good at resolving uh uh compounds that
are very uh uh lipidy, very very
non-polar, such as lipids and fatty
acids. And and then there's different
ionizations that that track uh molecules
that are more likely to ionize in
positive mode and some that are more
likely to ionize in negative mode. From
this effort, uh, there were 351
molecules that were able to annotate
after removal of some of them that did
not pass QC's. And the first thing I'm
showing you here, this is work that was
done by one of at the time, one of the
um the trainees at Robot University,
Arian Vartan Hovven. So he he was a
medical trainer u doctor there and he he
was the one who one who analyzed this
data. So here I'm showing you a PCA
which is essentially trying to capture
the contribution of all of those
metabolites and how they help separate
the samples that we profile. So each one
of these squares or dots represents one
patient and the ones in green are people
who uh were the controls that we used
and over here in blue and red we have
the TV cases the the CSF or the timing
menitis people and you can see there's a
separation between those two. So that
was really encouraging. Made it think
that out of these 351 metabolites we
profiled, there were differences
pronounced enough to tell those groups
of groups apart. And then you just do
some universe statistics to try to uh
then see how the levels of each
metabolite, in this case each one of
these bubbles is represents one
metabolite, how they're changing. And
what you can see here is that on the
right are metabolites that are increased
in the CSF of sick people, people who
have menitis and on the left you see the
ones that are low. And from looking at
this you can see like oh wow there's a
lot that is just increasing out of
control in the CSF of people with TB
menitis and and the the current
hypothesis uh is that the reason why
we're seeing so much in the CSF of
people with menitis is because that that
blood brain barrier the meninjas are
swollen and that is compromising their
ability to filter molecules and
determine what makes it to the brain and
what doesn't. So those are not super
interesting but but the the the the
other thing that Arian did is he he then
started looking at survival and and sort
of stratified all of these molecules
that are either high in TBM or low in
TBM. And we added another dimension and
looked into like what is high in
survivors and what is low in survivors.
And the first thing that you see and
this is known clinically because the
glucose is pretty easy to be measured is
that glucose drops dramatically in the
in the brain of someone with TB menitis
and non-survivors tend to have lower
glucose levels. There was another
molecule called lucotryan B4 and
lucatryan B4 is just essentially a cell
sorry a molecule produced by your immune
system or your white blood cells and
it's kind of a flare that attracts the
migration of of other immune cells and
it causes triggers more inflammation and
more of an immune response. So not
surprisingly uh people who have menitis
have much higher levels of this and even
those those who don't survive have even
higher levels of it. And the one finding
that was completely unexpected and novel
for this study was tryptophan. So
tryptophan is an essential amino acid.
That's that means it's an amino acid
that we cannot make and we have to
consume. And and what was interesting is
that it has this like paradoxical
uh change where you have a little bit
lower of it in tib menitis but people
who survive have much lower levels than
those who don't survive.
uh and this uh was validated with that
larger cohort that I show you first. And
this right here is is a survival plot or
capliner curve where you can classify or
stratify the patients in that population
into people who have high levels of
tryptophan here mean intermediate levels
of tryptophan or low and you can see how
they do over time. And as this line
drops, what that's telling you is that
the probability of their survival drops
dramatically over time, especially if
you have a high amount of tryptophan in
the brain. So sometime you're benefiting
from having really low tryptophan and
thus helping you survive. So the current
hypothesis that we have is that
tryptophan is very important in immune
function. It gets broken down rapidly
immune system stimulation by this enzyme
called IDO.
And in part what that does is depletes
tryptophan. So you drop the tryptophan
dramatically and you manage to do that
you may limit tryptophan access to the
microacteria which usually infects uh
cells intracellularly. So the idea is
that you may be having an increased
immune response in these people who have
low tryptophan but you would may also be
starving TB in some way. Uh and this was
at the time a pretty novel observation.
Nobody had reported that. uh in in
addition to that we had some genomic
information. So we had um many of the
patients in this study or the
participants of the study had their exom
sequence I believe uh and we were able
to find 11 uh lossi or like regions in
the genome that were associated with the
levels of tryptophan and we found that
most of those were primarily in in cells
and brain tissues immune cells and brain
tissues which makes sense and if you
make a score combining all these genomic
locations you can classify people in
into those who do really poor and
genotypes for those who do much better.
So what what we did here is integrate
the results of metabolite levels and
individual genetic variation that may
contribute to having better outcomes
after a TV infection. Oops. I see where
okay we still have some time. All right.
So because of these findings, because of
that small catalytic project, we
actually uh were able to secure funding
into uh NIH funded grants to that sought
to expand this work and include more
participants and generate more multiomic
layers to understand this variability in
the response to treatment uh and
outcomes in TB. And we added a couple of
additional sites, one in Jakarta and
there were a couple of additional team
members added the University of Oxford
and the Oxford University Center for uh
clinical research in Vietnam. Uh so that
now we have two additional cohorts or
one additional cohort uh of Vietnamese
patients with TB menitis. And this is
what that cohort looks like. uh there's
now about almost a thousand participants
and we are working on getting some of
this data out there. Uh there's already
two publications. One is currently in
press. We're starting to see different
metabolites and their contributions to
TB menitis. But the the point of this
talk and in the last 10 minutes of it uh
I just wanted to go into the story of
how we found this new molecule that had
now been described in CSF. So what I
described so far was this collection of
annotated compounds that is are higher
in the CSF of people with tibmenitis.
But in reality if you look at all the
signals we measure in the sample that we
cannot annotate you see that there are a
lot of signals that we're leaving behind
that are quite significant. They're
probably higher in TV but also lower in
TV. And if you look at tryptophan, which
is located over here, uh there's one
over here in green that is much better
in terms of having probably better fold
changes and more robust associations
with TB that we decided to pursue and
we're calling that TF21.
Now TF21 is associated with uh TB. So
it's much lower in subjects with TBI
menagitis. And now we have a much bigger
cohort in from Indonesian and Vietnamese
patients. So this means that this
observation is validated in two
different populations and this molecule
is also associated with survival. It is
much lower in people who don't survive.
And if you look at the survival plots,
interestingly for both the Vietnamese
and the Indones Indonesian cohorts, the
abundance um those subjects who have
very low levels of this molecule have
increased mortality but or probability
of uh mortality but those who have
medium or high levels do pretty similar
to each other.
So we are in this quadrant. So there
very few the only molecule that we have
in this quadrant was glucose. So it was
very interesting for us to try to figure
out what is this unknown molecule that
is going down in TB menitis and is also
going down in non-servivors. Is there
anything protective about it?
So in addition to that we we have some
associations of this unknown molecule to
uh clinical characteristics. So it's a
molecule that is associated with immune
uh anti-correlated with immune function.
So somehow we believe that the levels of
this molecule are dropping off as an
immune response or inflammatory response
is kicking in.
Uh all right. So then how do we go about
trying to figure out what this unknown
is? So the first thing we do is break
the molecule down like I told you uh
before in that intro slide and this is
the fragmentation that that molecule
produces. We can also isolate one of
those fragments that it produces and
then generate more subfragments for it.
And then essentially it becomes sort of
a riddle where you have all these pieces
that the molecule is making and then you
have to put back together the structure
of the molecule. Uh and we use this
tool. is sort of a machine learning
informed tool where you can give it all
these fragments and it tries to create a
fragmentation tree to to help address
that puzzle and then tries to see in in
all these candidate molecules in a
database in this case Popkin figure out
how many of them may explain the
fragmentation tree and then we have to
buy them to try to confirm that the
unknown TF21 matches them. And the thing
is these are quite expensive and I I
just wanted to show you how much they
are because this is one of the bigger
limitations in trying to do component
identification. So just buying those
molecules was over $10,000.
So to try to tackle that we've been
working with uh Connor Kolius group and
there's an initiative to try to generate
better training data for these models
and try to uh
improve our ability to rank and predict
these matches so we can save ourselves
some time and some money in trying to
predict them and even even scale it up.
So these are the results of that
validation. uh on the left the first
step I told you we had to do which is we
run the compounds and then we confirm
they come off the column at the same
retention time as the unknown. So this
is the peak of interest in CSF and then
we can break down the molecule and make
sure that the the fragments match the
the fragment of that unknown in the
sample. So the one molecule that
actually match was this GABA arginine.
So GABA is a a neurom modulating
molecule. I don't know if you've heard
of it. is called gamma aminobuteric acid
and it corresponds to the green part of
the molecule here and arginine
corresponds to the other part of the
molecule. Arginine is an amino acid that
I hope you're familiar with. So we then
asked when when you find something novel
we try to say is where is this found? Is
this found only in the brain? And
luckily we have some materials from a
different project where we had profiled
a collection of tissues in animals part
of this uh project trying to understand
the the molecular signatures of exercise
and and and we have all of these uh
different tissues that we profiled. And
just to summarize this, I I can tell you
that we see the peak of interest that
corresponds to GABA arginine primarily
in three tissues. The cortex, the
hippocampus and hypothalamus indicating
that this molecule is just primarily
detected in brain tissues which is quite
quite interesting since it is found in
the cerebral spinal fluid.
Then we started asking well what could
this molecule be doing and the easiest
thing for us to do since we had the data
is try to correlate it to other
molecules and see what these other
molecules do. So what we found is that
it's anti-correlated with u a collection
of carnitines and asocarnitines uh and
we knew from other studies in TB menitis
that these carnitines are disregulated
in TB menitis pointing at a
mitochondrial dysfunction. So carnitines
are intermediate steps in in the
breakdown of fatty acids to generate
energy and they start to build up once
you have uh mitochondrial dysfunction.
So somehow gaba arginine is the opposite
of this process indicating that perhaps
it is being um produced or perhaps it is
dropping when there's oxidative stress.
Funny enough or not funny but
interesting enough it was not correlated
with arginine levels even though we
believe arginine is part of its
synthesis. And then looking at the
molecules it was very well correlated
with uh we found that it was uh very
well correlated with homocarnosine homos
serin which uh not coincidentally enough
but uh are actual deptides as well of
GABA with in this case histadine another
amino acid and GABA and methylhistadine
and that is very interesting because
these two have been studied in some
detail homocarnosine
even though the the evidence is a bit
shaky in my opinion There's some
evidence indicating homo carnosine may
be a neurom modulator.
It is found like gabarogenine primarily
in in the central nervous system perhaps
gabaragic neurons and there's some very
small pilot studies where it's shown
that supplementation with homocarnosine
may prevent seizures. So that maybe
gives it an idea it gives an idea of
perhaps gabaragginine being involved in
a similar process. Uh the other line of
evidence we have from these two
compounds that have been studied is that
they have this uh histadine this um
emitazol containing ring and that makes
them uh potential antioxidants. They're
highly abundant their homologous
versions are highly abundant in muscles
and and brain tissues. So they're
thought to be of antioxidant properties.
Uh and for these family compounds we
know what enzymes are making them. So we
suspect the symptoms may also be making
up argin. But the reality is that I
don't know what it does. So I can't tell
you what it does. But it's very
interesting because you opening up all
these possibilities for us to study what
it may be doing and how it may be
involved in survival in TV menitis.
While these two molecules were this one
was lower in TB menitis, gabardinine is
the only one that is actually associated
with survival. uh makes makes it making
it something special and perhaps unique.
So to summarize uh I hope you um well we
we we found this new deptide and it had
never been described anywhere. Uh it's
not in the uh human metabolum database.
It has not been reported in any CSF
before.
uh is interesting because we did not
know GABA could be attached to another
amino acid and it's very interesting
because it seems to have a biological
role in tuberculosis menitis and now we
have many ideas on what we could do to
try to understand what it does but I
think one of the more important messages
I want to send out is that the
technology we use while it lets us
measure many compounds that we can very
robustly annotate and and and and
identify there is an entire universe of
unknown chemistry that we're seeing in
these samples that we had never profiled
before that may capture a lot of very
interesting biology that we're leaving
behind. So while it is a space of great
challenges, we believe is a space that
can provide quite nice biological
findings.
Uh and I would like to thank again the
metabolomics platform uh for being
awesome and generating fantastic data
and being just such lovely people to
work with and the ultimate consortium.
This the these cohorts are not easy to
put together and require an immense
amount of of work and dedication from
physicians, doctors, nurses across
different regions of the planet, 12 time
zones apart and we still managed to get
this all together. Uh so with that I
would like to uh yeah give it up to
Adriana for some questions. Thank you.
Amazing. Thank you so much for that
talk. I really appreciate that. Um I'll
kick off with the first question and
then I ask everybody in the audience to
please submit theirs. We'll try to get
us through as many before the 3:00 mark.
Um I think I guess my first question I
was I don't I was very excited for you
when you got to the conclusion of your
story and said arginine is like the
thing that we found and I'm like great
what does it do? Um so in your mind um
how do we move forward once we have like
these like I guess starting points um
what is the progression of like the
research from there I guess from like a
biological perspective do you go to
mouse do you go to cell lines um or are
you thinking about patients and how this
could be like a marker um just things
like that yeah it's a great question so
so we do I did uh we have been working
with a group here at abroad rather the
name is group so they they can uh
culture. We're going the invitro way. So
we we're trying to nail down where it is
made. So we know we now know it's
primarily in the brain. We want to
confirm if it is neuronal, astroite, gal
and and we've grown neurons and
astroytes and we we did see it in
neurons in one of the experiments but
then we stopped seeing it. So so that's
why I didn't show it but we are working
on trying to figure that one thing. The
other thing we want to know is how it is
made. So there are a couple things we're
trying and I the the fact that we had
the enzymes described for homologous
molecules gives us some idea. In fact I
ordered one of the enzymes that had been
described but it was like expressing
bacteria and we did some enzyatic assets
in vitro but it was not good. The other
thing we're trying is there there is
sequencing data for this participant. So
we tried to look for associations
between LOSI and the levels of GABA
arginine and so far we could not find
anything that that would associate
because it would be great if we could
say oh the enzyme carnosin synthes is
perfectly
variants in that in that are correlated
with this we don't we don't have that
yet um so yeah that that's sort of where
we are and I think in part giving this
talk is if people have ideas or would
like to work with us I think is is
fantastic fantastic opportunity to do
some basic biology and trying to
understand where it's coming from and
what it may be doing. Wonderful. Thank
you,
Julian. Yeah, let me jump in. Um,
there's a question in the Q&A uh asking
if everyone uh does everyone have the
presence of this GABA arginine in their
brains or is it just found in folks with
uh TBM? Good question. Yeah, it is
present in everyone. it is in everyone
and we have now other cohorts of
unrelated we have another CSF project
with Alzheimer's disease a large set of
samples and we see it in everyone. So
what is dramatic about some of these
participants in this study who are very
ill is that it disappears completely.
So, so it goes away and as it goes away
then subjects who have less of it or
where it has gone away completely are
the ones who far worse like the ones who
usually don't survive. But yeah, it
seems to be just always there.
Great.
Well, I will I will jump in with another
one myself. Um actually didn't expect to
have a sort of oblique personal
connection to the story. My parents are
both radiologists.
Uh my dad two years ago or so was over
the moon because for the third time ever
in his career, he caught someone. He I
diagnosed someone with spinal TB. Um
he had studied in Mexico and he was
like, "Oh, I you know, never saw it in
the US." But um in any case, what I was
curious about is um you've talked about
the potential therapeutic um you know,
next steps of what this could lead to.
I'm curious about whether or not the
pipeline that you talked about earlier
in the presentation um specifically with
regard to this case or just more
generally if that potentially could
evolve into like diagnostic tools if
there's a possibility that you know the
sensitivity of the stuff you're working
with can catch this where other tests
might not.
Yeah, we thought I think it's there was
some idea behind trying to get to uh
well find molecules that were directly
produced by by the the pathogen the
microacterium. But the amounts I think
the expected levels of the pathogen are
so low that even having technology so
that you amplify their nucleic acids to
find them sometimes fail to see them.
Right? Uh so for us the the the other
question getting to your point of can we
use metabolites to classify people as
these people for a fact have TB. I think
it's really challenging because what
we're seeing is that many of these
changes in metabolites are seen in other
conditions. So you could have them be
perhaps like menitis like viral menitis
or nonspecific menitis but there could
also be changes um in in other
neuroinflammatory conditions and think
of Alzheimer's or chronic inflammatory
conditions like those. The one thing
that we haven't done and I actually have
to do is is try to figure out this
change in gaba arginine specific to this
microacterial tuberculosis like the
microacterial
menitis or do we see the same changes
let's say in cryptocal menitis and other
types of menitis and we have actually
data to do that analysis we haven't done
it yet so I guess the answer is like I'm
skeptical we may be able to use this as
a diagnostic tool but maybe we we'll be
able to use it as she's trying to figure
out what pathways need to be targeted to
increase someone's probability of
surviving or someone's probability of
not experiencing long-term neurological
squa.
Great. Thank you. And we just have time
for one more question and it just came
in through the chat. So um they asked is
gaba arginine finding more of a cause or
an effect of TBM in your mind or
according to your read. So finagarding
seems to be just a biologically
functional
uh deptide that is present in everyone.
So so what we're seeing is it goes away
because of the infection and I don't
know if that is happening because of
increased inflammation or impaired GABA
signaling. So, so, so this
neurotransmitter biology, neuromodulator
biology requires a pretty synchronized
dance between different cell types in
the brain. So, is usually secretion of
the neurom modulator uptake by a um
astroytes that then converted to their
molecules. So if that balance is broken
in some way due to inflammation or cells
that are metabolically struggling then
we may be seeing the changes caused by
that process. Um but it's not gargin is
not we I don't suspect it being made by
the pathogen itself or being made as a
response to attack the pathogen. It
seems like it's the fact that it's in
everyone makes me think that it's just
normal brain function function that
somehow gets compromised when you when
you have an infection.
Wonderful. Um, so with that, uh, I want
to thank our speaker one more time,
Julian. Thank you so much for being here
and sharing your knowledge. Um, and
thank you, Julian, for your
collaboration in, um, this special,
special Latinx speaker series. Uh, we
wish everybody a great day. Thanks
everybody. Thank you so much.