Hi everyone. I'm Sarah Remson, the CEO
and co-founder of Melody, and we help
companies understand how well their
agentic AI conversations are actually
going. I graduated from MIT in a program
called the integrated design and
management uh program, and I'm putting a
lot of my human center design background
and technical expertise into this
product. So, one of the things that you
may notice as you interact with a bunch
of different types of AI agents is that
you now have this new conversation
interface, which is really exciting
because it opens up totally new
opportunities for use cases and ways of
applying this so that you can do things
that you've never been able to do
before. But this also introduces a ton
of new challenges when it comes to
actually monitoring and understanding
the performance of those AI
conversations. Not just from a technical
standpoint of latency and cost and
tokens, but actually is this answer
relevant? Is this working for your
customer? And part of the challenge
there is that while these conversations
all seem like they are different, they
might actually be the same. And so it
can be really challenging to understand
this unstructured conversation data.
What are your users doing? Are they
having success? And so we see teams
reaching for data scientists and doing a
ton of manual analysis to just get that
picture. So this is the problem that
Melody solves automatically. We have our
own proprietary model that we run
inhouse and essentially for our
customers, we look at all of the
conversations that your customers or
your users are having with an assistant
that you have built. So, we're LLM
agnostic or AI agnostic. We just need
the transcripts and we analyze and
identify the places where conversations
are going really well and places where
conversations may not be going really
well. And we provide specific
recommendations for you about things
that you could do on your team to
actually improve those. So, we heard a
lot about source documentation as a key
part of a lot of AI systems today.
That's one of the first places that our
customers reach for. So we can
automatically identify for example like
you should update your source
documentation when your users from your
northeast region ask about billing
because those are the conversations that
are struggling the most. So, uh, and
like just one more thing on our on the
tech side of things. Um, my co-founder
used to lead AI at HubSpot and built
their conversation intelligence product.
And so, we're leveraging a lot of that
technical expertise in order to deliver
a solution that's very low cost, um,
very fast and has delivered a ton of
great results for our existing
customers. So, you know, the types of
things that we're seeing, we're working
with a bunch of publicly traded
companies. We're five times cheaper than
hiring a data scientist, 30 times faster
than doing manual analysis. Our
customers love us. And the specific use
cases that our customers are often
working on are things like an AI powered
product or feature, their own internal
work, like their own internal assistant
for knowledge management or for sales or
for customer success. And so we're able
to provide those metrics and um AI
identified issues to help them actually
improve those models and deliver on the
ROI that uh that they need to. So we um
are looking to connect with folks if
you're building any of these AI
assistants or AI agents inhouse. If
you're looking for a new type of
analytics tool um or if you're thinking
about expanding your offerings uh and
extending them, we're also looking for
partners. I should also add we're
industry agnostic. The key thing here is
that you are building these AI agents or
assistants in house. So thank you.
So do you take the uh ground truth from
customers to validate and also how do
you compare with tools like lang etc for
the validation? Yep. So tools like
Langmith are perfect for teams that
really care about the engineering
metrics again like latency and things
like that. So pretty much all of our
customers often choose a platform like
that first and then they realize that
they need Melody for those like product
and operations teams to actually report
ROI that's relative to the customers
like are the customers having success.
So we sit on top of a link or someone
else like that and then in terms of how
our tech actually works we um we look at
an initial sample of conversations. We
look at all of the ones that have
feedback from external users or internal
users and we use that to effectively
like calibrate our model according to
like what is good like what where a
conversation is successful and where a
conversation is not successful that we
can then extrapolate onto new
conversations and it's customized to
every user or sorry every customer and
every use case.