Um, but I am really glad to uh invite
Nikki Bruno up to speak not about what
keeps her awake at night in the middle
of the night, but instead Well, I guess
it is the same thing, isn't it?
>> Different twist. Yes. Uh so thank you so
much for for sharing uh your perspective
on scaling.
>> Yeah,
>> thank you and hi everyone. Um thank you
for having me. This has been a wonderful
wonderful day. Um and you know when you
think about the utility what I came into
was the power of the people panel. Um I
missed the the very first one. Um but
you know there there is a general
mistrust and a general dislike or even
like even worse negligence about the
utility, right? like I I don't know if
it's better to be loved or hated, but if
you don't feel anything, you know, so um
you know, and I before coming to work at
the utility, I kind of fell accidentally
into the energy space. I have a degree
in environmental science. Um but you
know, life goes on, right? And it looks
beautiful on a resume and all stitched
together, but um you realize the energy
is just such a it's a commodity. It's so
needed. And I never knew all the work
that the utility workers, gas or
electric, do, water for that matter. Um
but I think it's on us to continually
change and evolve the perspective of
right we have to earn our keep. Um we
have a lot of beautiful touch points
with the customer that many people do
not. Um and that's a privilege and I
think there you would find uh was just
on the phone earlier this morning about
it. A lot of people have ingrained and
don't sleep at night around the fact
that they have to provide safe and
reliable service and and I know um
gentleman earlier was mentioning what
does reliable mean? When I say reliable,
it's there for them all the time 247
365. Um so that's why some of us don't
sleep. Um, but you know on the geo front
it's it's been such a happy discussion
and I'm going to be blending in kind of
when we talk about scaling scaling
technical systems certainly how we're
thinking about our pilot in Framingham
and what's next how it went what we can
learn but also how we can scale that
change management because there has to
be a cultural shift in not only the
utility but the um folks we interact
with whether they're stakeholders,
community partners, customers,
regulators Everybody has to adjust and
we're in this enormous transition
period, right? And I think, you know,
we've always said this in various
places, but this pictorial example does
not get built with one group. Um, and
the reason this it may not feel like
it's fast if you look like at this
timeline, but being the first time we've
certainly done this, it it is fast and
it only happened because there were a
lot of groups involved. Um, you know,
certainly Zanab and the heat team right
at the forefront really, I would argue
before I even came to Eversource putting
it out there in front of the DPU at the
time to say, "Hey, the gas company could
do this. Let's give them a shot." Um,
and so what you see here is from 2019
when this was initially proposed to we
commissioned the system in Framingham in
2024, a lot of blood, sweat, and tears.
And you know, when we um maybe when you
hopefully when you're picking up news
articles online or otherwise, you see
all the great um heralding about how
this has been successful. I will tell
you it's it's been tough. Um there's a
lot of learning, a lot of scars. Uh but
everybody has done so with such grace.
And what I mean by that is they are
willing and they want to show up to do
this. So I was asked earlier, the gas
companies want to do this? are they
excited about this? Like how how do they
feel? Um and you know I think there
again even within your own internal
company constituents you have to earn
trust. You have to earn that this is
additive. This is a positive and a
benefit. Um and then when you talk about
the pace of change, how things can scale
and take off. Um we have a lot of folks
that we brought in that were gas
personnel. That's all they did all day
long and we're very proud of it. um had
a skill set, had a passion, had a
career. Um and when we put them on
things like Oversight for Construction,
um it was amazing to see just how they
delved in open-minded and took it on as
if it were their own gas project. Um and
at the end of it, um the most gratifying
thing certainly is to hear like, wow,
this was a pretty amazing project to
work on. That's what that's the
ultimate, right? Um so we're
consistently trying to educate
internally and ed and even our electric
brethren. I'll say now that doesn't you
know that goes beyond gas right
electric's got their work to do on the
utility side and because this is a true
hybrid and has benefit across all
systems got to educate them too and
they've got a lot going on. So anyway,
um just you know when you think about
milestones on the timeline you say oh
this is a project right normal course of
business you do the feasibility you get
the budget the estimate put it together
you get customers you start construction
you put it online all of these steps um
we that flying the plane as you're
building it that that was what was going
on um and not to shake anybody's
confidence in the utilities ability or
the partners contractors etc teammates
ability to do this um but as as you
heard from um many speakers today a lot
of this is art and science. So when we
think about site selection and
evaluating we had about 20 sites that we
looked at um and it was really unique
because I think from the get-go one of
the big lessons learned about um these
networks and the ability to scale is we
had a crossf functional group of people
in the room. So where maybe our a
traditional infrastructure gas or
electric you'd go to the DPW you'd go to
the permitting agencies then you engage
the community maybe at some level
depending on the project size we were
with the community and key folks in
government community representatives in
some cases in one location we didn't go
with there was an active resident who
petitioned her legislator um gathered
the neighborhood it was that was an
awful phone call to make by the way to
call her and say I'm sorry we're not
bringing it to your city um but she
respected the engagement and I think
that early engagement troubleshoots a
lot of problems down the road. So that's
something we want to do to continue
building on, you know, the success that
we think we've had with the community um
in Framingham. Um we talk about
permitting, right? I heard a lot in the
last presentation about rules and
regulations. The US is a little bit of
the wild west, right? I mean, we don't
even have the nomenclature set out. Um
and that's confusing for people. Um, and
so I think what what kind of
environmental permits do we need? What
kind of city like planning zoning type
permits do you need? This gets very
local very fast. Um, and I think what
happened in Framingham is really a
testament to the city in this case
figuring it out with us. So we spent a
ton of time meeting with them. In fact,
um, I would argue in in all truth, we
talk to them more than daily. And um,
you know, we know what's everyone knows
what's going on on the project in their
personal lives. It's like the customers.
And with that kind of trust, we were
able to say, okay, we don't know what
permits apply. This is a closed loop
system. Do we really need to go for that
board of health, you know, water type
permit? Do we really need to go for
that? Um, we'll gladly come before
whatever council or permitting body, but
maybe maybe it doesn't apply right now.
And they were like, you know, maybe
that's right. Okay. And in with the
right protections, with the right
construction methodology, we avoided a
lot of time I feel like spent on
permitting or if we had to get a permit,
we had educated so much that it moved
through in a manageable fashion. And and
certainly in the state of Massachusetts,
there was recent legislation passed. I
was really excited about the geo work.
Um, but within that a lot of expedited
permitting and sighting for clean energy
um because it is it does bog down
schedule and timelines. And so I really
enthused from that perspective and again
another another component from a scaling
um perspective that we want to take and
bring forward.
When we think about what we're going to
learn here though that's that's really
what excites me and I I want to spend
just a few minutes talking about the
customer side of this. Um, Eric Bosworth
will be here tomorrow to talk about all
the tech, commissioning, construction,
drilling, all of that, which is very
important. But to me, it's I should say
and to me, it's a combination of
customer and technical. Um, it it kind
of is playing out that way in a lot of
the dockets and a lot of the discussion
around NPA around integrated planning.
The planning is crucial um and and needs
to be sound based on data, etc. You need
to have the customer piece. you need to
have the execution ability to go out
there and actually build what you're
talking about because otherwise we're
just talking about it. And so in in
Framingham as I move to the next slide
here um we have taken the momentum of
the pilot and are now on a grant um that
even you know optimistic even with the
administration geothermal is a very
bipartisan discussion and because I
think we've we've thought about it from
a customer perspective just on our in
our um world in Massachusetts and
Connecticut if it can make fiscal sense
and provide environmental benefits if we
can get this whole thing to work. Um, it
doesn't just have to work for climate
advocates. It doesn't just have to work
for folks concerned about future
generations. It's going to be an ant.
It's going to be for people who want
effective heating and cooling from a
cost perspective. So, what we're trying
to do on this grant um, in effect is get
data back from both a customer
perspective, technical performance
perspective to see those economies of
scale as you build on this. And we've
already seen it in our design. Um, costs
have come down. We're smarter, leaner,
faster, all that good stuff. Um, and I'm
so excited and and hope the grant comes
in certainly, but you know, at
Eversource at least, we're thinking
about how do we make a coherent rate
proposal, project proposal using
examples. We still have to learn, but to
make sure that we're advancing this so
it can stand on its own eventually. It's
not on subsidies.
Just a pictorial of it. Um, doubling the
size of the pilot. This is the
expansion. And um we don't talk a lot
about delivered fuels customers, oil,
propane, a lot of them here. So this
could be accretive to a business, right?
We could gain customers that we're not
cannibalizing or we're not netting out
net neutral, right? We are actually
adding. Um and you know, for folks like
me that like to build things. That's
exciting.
So let me just wrap with some of the
opportunities and challenges and I'm
happy to take questions later. um strong
emissions goals here, targets here in
Massachusetts and in a lot of the states
we operate in. Um regardless of where
the federal government goes, we see, you
know, being good stewards, right, that
we want to provide solutions and options
for our customers. And when you go into
more of a I call it like the subsidy
verse tax. If you go into more of a
positive mindset to give customers more
choice, we find that that naturally puts
them it doesn't back them into a corner,
right? We talked about obligation to
serve and customer choice. It gives them
more to choose from and they feel like
they are in control of their destiny.
Um, a lot of customers and communities
have expressed interest. We had to turn
people away with the pilot. Now, we were
paying for quite a bit on our tab um or
on the rateayers collectively tabs, but
it, you know, it begs the question of
who else will go into this with us and
how can we leverage that excitement,
that momentum, that desire to bring this
to whatever municipality we're in. the
data will provide the learnings and you
know I think the DOE liftoff report was
really key new construction we have all
these policies right to kind of styy gas
growth and what do we replace it with if
folks don't want airsource heat pumps
this is like a natural fit we see so
we're trying to attack the new
construction market work with our
existing relationships with those
customers in this case builders
developers who give them another option
give them hopefully a better option
right the challenges I think on the
other side as you think about scaling
are really things that have been
mentioned already. Um but certainly
workforce who can do this work. Um
there's a variety of work streams that
we know how to do that are transferable.
Something like drilling, we don't have
that skill set, right? And that's
largely the bottleneck. Um the cost
certainly too. This is an upfront capex
investment that you make um that that
you know we have to figure out a way to
manage and spread um so that folks can
enjoy the savings on the back end. And I
think the utility is actually a great
vehicle because folks were talking about
putting in their own systems. It's
expensive. Um it really is. And so um in
wrapping, you know, we're trying to
identify locations that are best suited
from a technical perspective to deploy
that the customers want that we can make
the argument for them on a couple of
different fronts, not just environmental
emissions reductions. Um so that we
could ultimately lower the cost of the
project on on a whole. And so with that,
um, I guess I'll say we're we're already
seeing kind of acceleration here. We're
still in that data collection. I'm a
scientist, so we're still in that data
collection mode certainly. Um, but the
company, um, and I certainly am very
very excited to be bringing this to more
and more communities.
[Applause]