Problems are not catastrophes.
We humans have a penchant for drama.
We love to present problems as if they
were catastrophes and talk about them as
if there was only one way to solve them.
Some silver bullet or some magic pill.
Let me give you some examples of what I
mean. A few years ago, students in an
MIT dorm came up with a system to grow
lettuce in a closet. Soon, they were
persuaded to present their invention as
the start of a movement that would yield
a solution to food distribution,
obesity, chemical runoff, climate
change. Even by the same logic in 2025,
if you were concerned about say
declining math literacy, you might be
tempted to talk about a more grandio
problem like soon even computers will
start making addition mistakes or AI
will kill us all unless we learn to
divide by zero or something involving
climate change. These last examples are
a bit silly, but they help me make my
point. The drama distracts you from
actually understanding the problem
you're solving. You may be inclined to
talk about problems this way so they'll
be taken seriously enough to solve. But
this isn't how you solve them. Real
world problems are more interesting. So
let's talk about what are real problems
and how to solve them. It's not what you
did in math class. Love them or hate
them. Those math class problems had a
readymade problem statement and the
variables were all spelled out, all
handed to you by the teacher. One thing
was clear, there was just one solution.
This was pretend play problem solving.
Problems in the real world that matter.
Problems you are truly motivated to take
on. And maybe that's why you are
watching these videos. They don't have
readymade problem statements. Not until
you produce them. You do not need
clarity about the problem. Scratch that.
You can't have clarity unless you commit
to explore the actual problem. At first,
real world problems might look like a
nuisance, an obstacle, an impediment, or
a collection of symptoms that is hard to
diagnose. In the new mindset, we
appreciate that solving the problem and
understanding it are the same thing. No
matter the problem, you can come up with
a technology that makes it easier to
understand. You can take that as a new
definition for what we mean by
technology. Technology helps us reach
further. It removes obstacles. It solves
problems. And just like technology
creates options, what makes real
problems interesting is that there are
many ways to chip at them. If you
remember only one thing about this
video, let this be it. You have options.
Here's an example of what I mean. At the
start of my career, I worked on a system
to locate cell phones in case of
emergency. The regulator, the Federal
Communications Commission, was worried
that as cell phones replace landlines,
they would lose the ability to locate a
call to emergency services. Landlines
were easy to locate. Each number was
associated with an address already. But
how to get a location estimate for a
mobile phone. In fact, there are many
options. One could install GPS in all
phones or find ways to triangulate
signals. We found yet another way using
AI and found that Polar is wireless. But
there were other parts of the problem
too, like supplying emergency services
with a medical record so emergency
respondents could be readier. The
problem was not limited to locating
phones. Rather, it was fielding
emergency response calls placed from a
cell phone timely. Each of those ways to
chip at the problem led to at least one
company. Your first task in doing
genuine innovation is not solving the
problem. It isn't guessing a single
solution either. It is figuring out what
the problem actually is. There's a way
to do this systematically. It's called
prototyping a problem. the subject of
the next video.