Please welcome Kronos AI enable precise
3D geocation leveraging virtually all
existing and emerging wireless protocols
and infrastructures.
Let me see how it works here. Uh my name
is Marco Ganuna. I am um leading the
founder and CEO of Kronos AI. This is
our team. Uh basically we are all not me
all from IBM, Intel and uh Microsoft
um
we 25 each 25 years of experience at
least. So what we do what what we do we
saw we are GPS alternative solution. So
um GPS has limitation as we know it
doesn't work indoor it doesn't work on
the ground and especially doesn't work
during war zone because all the the GPS
is jammed um
we basically come up with this solution
which is uh the way GPS works you have
four satellite GPS satellite 20,000
kilometer high and a cheap receiver on
your phone or other devices here we
replace the satellite with these little
devices. So when you put four of those
on the floor on the wall, it will
selfcalibrate
form a mesh network of indoor 20 m up,
down, left, right, front, back within
which it detects and locate badge or
tags can be smaller than that. um in
three dimension with an accuracy of 50
cm
and 10 times a second refresh rate
without GPS satellite, without cell
towers, without internet, without
nothing. It just forms a mesh and
actually it's a v the visualization is
by any authorized screen. When you
connect with the mesh via Bluetooth, you
see all the people going up and down all
the tags. So you can put the tags on
people and equipment and you'll see you
have situation awareness of everything
around indoor but most importantly
because we selfc calibrate in few
seconds you can put those on drones. So
when you put four drones you fly them
above a building. So you and you're
going to be able to detect locate uh
tags on people and equipment outdoor but
also inside the building in three
dimension. So when you have the the
anchors and tax this is called active
tracking. What we do also is that we we
working on passive tracking to be able
to detect locate cell phone signals.
Everybody should uh I mean have a cell
phone usually and um basically the
accuracy of the cell phone signals is
not as good as 50 cm is around three to
5 mters but you are able to basically
see heat maps of people that are you
know in a building or outside. Um
so so I mean the first market we have I
mean I always forget to
yeah how it works. So I I just said how
it works. Uh technology readiness active
tracking is TRL7. This means that we
have pilots going. Um the passive
tracking is TRL 4 and five. It's
basically detecting any radio frequency
around. Um when you put those on drones
outdoor the um we can the coverage is
1.8 8 kilometer.
And that's quite interesting. And the
most import most important is that when
you have those drones up and you have
people moving or troops or firefighters
moving around, you can just move the
drones above the the area you desire and
in few seconds you will see all the
movements.
Um we have many project in development.
Um actually very interesting. Um what
our focus right now and it is our lowest
hanging fruit is military. Uh we are
working with uh the Navy. We have a
Kada. We signed with them. We have seven
projects with them. We are working
closely with with uh DARPA with SOCOM.
Actually next week we're going to be in
Fort Campbell. Um and most importantly
we are also in public safety. We signed
with 3M. 3M owns 70% of North American
market for first responders.
Hopefully by mid next year to end of
next year, every firefighter will be
able to geocate each other in burning
buildings, but they're going to be able
to detect and locate the victim's cell
phone signals. Perfect for FEMA. You
send those drones and you find people
that are uh you know in trouble.
avalanche. It goes, we think it's going
to go with 3 mters deep. So, you are
able to find people that are in in in
distress. Um,
so that's what I said. I'm always aware
and we have also smart cities. Uh so you
can basically place those uh you can
preset those anchors into buildings and
you're going to be able to detect and
locate uh movement of people and assets
with where when maybe you hate it but
this is where we're going uh and um and
it's for security but also being having
a location situation awareness of
movements and I think this is the the
future
um So that's about uh us. I still have
137 uh minutes. Um so if you have any
questions, please do. Uh something I
didn't say is that um we we've done some
very interesting test in u firefighters
burning buildings. And despite the the
thickness of the walls, it was 3 ft
reinforced concrete walls and all the
ceilings were metal plates which is very
bad for very difficult for radio
frequency. We were able to see everybody
going in three floors with four anchors.
Um placing the anchors outside
the building. Uh the business model
there is going to be that every
hopefully every fire uh firefighter
trucks will have two of those and as
there is always at least two trucks in a
fireplace and when there is a fire
they're going to basically the form the
mesh network.
[applause]
>> Thank you Marco. Any questions from the
audience? Yes.
>> Thank you. Can you clarify what is that
in your hand?
>> It's an anchor.
>> Okay. What you have in there?
>> Yeah.
>> Is what you have in your phone.
>> Okay.
>> It's ultra wideband
>> with it's no secret ultra wideband uh
Bluetooth and Wi-Fi in there. And um we
have uh eight categories of patents, 41
granted patents on this geocation.
So the goal is basically to migrate into
the phone. So if we were able to have
access to the ultra wideband in the
phone, so every four phones here will
form automatically mesh network.
>> Yeah. Okay.
>> So that's the idea.
>> And and in your right hand, that's a
tag, is it?
>> It's a tag. It's basically a Bluetooth
Bluetooth power on and there is a
battery in there.
>> Okay.
>> A year and basically we can design it.
We are designing even smaller tags.
>> Okay. And some go.
>> Yeah. You said the location is uh
calculated locally is on one of those
devices.
>> Yes.
>> So basically you have those four the the
four anchors that calculates uh 10 times
a second of every tags.
>> No cloud.
>> No cloud. No nothing. You have just a
knuck that collects all the data
location that is connected to your user
interface and just you process the
information on the edge. You don't need
anything out. Now if you have you need
more edge processing and you have a
connection you can connect it to to the
cloud and do whatever you want. So we
give an API to our customers so they can
process it. Thank you. The other thing
that is something important also um
[clears throat] the tags the the anchors
those anchors become
a tag when they move.
>> Yeah. So this means that what we're
doing is we're going to a 3D morphic had
oak indooroutdoor mesh network. That's
where we're going.
>> So you may have mentioned earlier uh the
diameter of the network. So once the
four-point network is the mesh is made
what's the maximum diameter of control?
>> The maximum
>> diameter
>> 1.8 kilometer
>> 1.8 kilmters
>> outdoor.
>> Outdoor.
>> Yes. Uh we have a few developments right
now actually one specific development
that will increase tremendously
uh the diameter.
Um but I mean this for DoD so I cannot
speak very much about it.
>> Two more questions.
>> I'm just curious if these have been
tested underwater. I know you mentioned
maritime deployment. Has that been
proven yet or
>> we are working on this and we just
started it's going to be like submarine
drones
>> I think
>> one more and move to the next one
>> in in the mode where the tag is is a
passive device.
>> Mhm.
>> The there I'll I'll form it as a
question. Is there a mode where the tag
the moving tag is a completely passive
device without a battery? It could and
it will light up only when
when
>> is that one of the modes you've been
testing?
>> Yes.
>> How much power do you need to be
transmitting?
>> Okay, that's a very good question. It's
a we uh do 50 mill watt but uh we have
also the the pot on on a spot do up to
50 mill 500 mill. So we are able to go
through walls and
uh one the same development is asking
for four watts but uh but already at 500
millwatts we are um we are above FCC
approval.
>> Yeah. Yeah. [laughter]
>> Okay. Thank you.
[applause]
>> Great questions. Thank you so much
Marco.