I'm not sure I learned this when I was
at Apple, but I learned it based on the
data when I was at Apple. I now take a
longer term view on people. In other
words, when I see something not being
done
right, my first reaction isn't to go fix
it. We're building a team here and we're
going to do great stuff for the next
decade, not just the next year. And so
what do I need to do to help so that the
person that's screwing up learns versus
how do I fix the problem? And uh that's
painful sometimes. And my and I still
have that first instinct to go fix the
problem. But that's taking a longer term
view on people is probably the biggest
thing that's changed. For more MIT
moments from MIT Open Learning, like,
subscribe, or follow.