So good morning um and um welcome to
this first day of our RD conference. I'm
Gatri Shiniasan, executive director of
MIT corporate relations.
So at MIT we define innovation as a
process of taking an India for taking an
idea uh taking an idea to impact right
so that's how we define uh innovation we
are not just about conducting research
we are solving the world's most pressing
challenges across every discipline
imaginable from material science to
economics from energy to healthcare MIT
consistently transforms breakthrough
ideas into real world solutions that
reshape industries and improve their um
improve lives.
Here we have in this example
nanoarchchitected
carbon that can uh withstand supersonic
impacts. So that's literally um
materials that can face in the uh face
in the sorry laugh in the face of
physics. Um we are solving and working
with um uh commercializing plasma fusion
and clean energy because why not solve
energy crisis while we are at it right
um and also you have an example of paper
thin solar cells with very thin margins
now we also have profess professor Bob
Langanger who is pretty much um a
walking patent factory um we have uh
professor Mongji Bendi who won the Nobel
price for quantum um dots, which by the
way exists in all your TVs and makes
your Netflix Netflix binging experience
good or much better than what it used to
be. Oh, and we have sent a few uh people
to space because I think they found
Earth was not challenging enough. So,
there's that. And last year, we had um
Darren Aimoglue as well as Simon Johnson
who won the Nobel Prize in economics.
And so yeah, we are covering everything
from atoms to astronauts to economic
systems.
So um here are some examples of
companies that were formed by MIT folks.
And when I few when I say a few
companies, here they are. And I'm not
even listing Campbell Soup. Um so yeah,
we have MIT DNA in your chicken noodle
soup. So when you have it, think about
that. So the point is that MITers don't
just form companies, we start
industries.
And I just want to throw some numbers at
you while uh you stare at the screen. Um
we have 105 Nobel laureates. That's not
a typo. That is 105 Nobel laureates. We
have 84 MacArthur Fellows. That's the
gener Genius Awards that you may have
heard of. We have 64 National Medal of
Science. And then of course what would
matter to you as industry partners is
that we have 700 companies working with
MIT faculty and students on research
opportunities. We have 593 invention
disclosures last year. That's pretty
much one and a half groundbreaking
inventions every single day including
weekends. And 362 US patents issued last
year. That means one patent every day
and maybe 2 days of vacation. That's it,
right? And the largest number here is
our alumni have founded over 30,000
companies since we started our we we uh
existed as MIT. That's about 400 4.6
million people employed, 1.9 trillion in
revenue. So basically our MIT grads have
accidentally created an economy. That's
the size of Italy. And get this, 40% of
those alumni are serial entrepreneurs.
Uh, which is a fancy way of saying that
they couldn't stop just creating one
world changing company because
overachievement basically runs in every
MIT grad here.
Now, you may be wondering, what is MIT
up to right now, right? What is MIT
focusing on? And that's a great
question. And let me walk you through
some of President uh Conbble's
priorities because this is where we are
doubling down and we are trying to solve
and make impact climate. We are
marshalling our uh expertise to lead
technological behavioral and policy
solutions because someone has to and we
have the kinds of expertise experts and
scientists to do it.
Second, we have health, health and life
sciences bringing together world-class
expertise to catalyze discovery
innovation for human health. Remember
Mona that also came from MIT, right?
Human insight
elevating human- centered research. Yes,
when you think about MIT, you think
about all the engineers. Yes, we are
engineers. But we also remember that
humans are the ones that are using all
this technology. artificial intelligence
providing leadership as society
navigates AI implications. We are
literally the people who helped invent
the field. So we figure we should help
figure out how to use and what to do
with AI. Education designing curricula
for the digital and AI age.
manufacturing defining the future of
manufacturing with higher productivity,
higher wages, lower carbon footprint,
better jobs, and greater resilience.
Basically, making things that matter
better. Quantum amplifying quantum
research and driving innovation to
unlock capabilities that redefine what's
computationally possible. Guess regular
computing was getting boring. Um, now
you may wonder what is special here?
What uh is it the water? Is it the
weather? I can tell you it's definitely
not the water or the weather. Absolutely
not. Uh, our secret sauce is not really
that secret. We tackle problems that
change the world first. We identify the
challenges that matter most and marshall
resources to solve them. We always put
impact before everything else. Second,
we encourage risk-taking. In fact, we
actually expect failures on the way to
success. We don't just tolerate
failures. We celebrate it on the as a
learning opportunity. And celebrating
failures, try that as an as a cor in the
corporate environment. And third, we
have a well staffed office
that is MIT corporate relations and we
are always tasked towards putting
industry in the room uh exploring
opportunities to connect. We are
literally here to make connections
happen. And fourth, all key ecosystem
leaders are within walking distance.
Entrepreneurs, government, corporate,
risk capital and MIT researchers all in
the same neighborhood. You can't have a
serendipitous coffee meeting while being
in different uh time zones. And um so
it's not just about MIT being great in
isolation. It's about MIT being the
catalyst that brings everyone together.
And we are like the yeast in the bread
of innovation. Now that's a very um uh
weird metaphor, but I'm a
microbiologist. It works for me. Um
so let me uh tell you about the two
integrated programs within MIT corporate
relations that are your tickets into
this ecosystem. The MI MIT industrial
leazison program. This is industry's
most comprehensive portal to MIT. We've
got over 200 member companies who use
this as their front door to everything
MIT has to offer.
Then we have MIT startup exchange
through which we promote and pro promote
collaboration between MIT connected
startups and industry. We've got over
800 technology- based startups in that
system and or in that network and each
one is a potential gamecher in in its
field. Now that's a lot of disruption
waiting to happen.
Now you may wonder how do we go about
doing this right we have this rise
framework and what what that means is
you get the opportunity to connect with
MIT around research opportunities
innovation students and education you
can do this through our webinars
in-person events across the globe
meeting with faculty and learning
journeys with researchers and experts in
the field meet with networks of students
s 800 plus startups and also your peer
members across the globe. You can also
upskill, reskill and new skill your
employees via professional education,
execed and open learning.
We drive impact across every industry.
So 200 plus members where are they? They
are all in these different industries.
And I don't want to talk about the
different industries. You can see it.
This is all you all that participate
through this network.
Now, where are these companies located?
It's a global um it's not bos it's not a
Boston thing. Yes, many of you are here,
but the companies are all global. And we
have regional network across every
continent and pretty much every country
except a few. And because innovation
transcends geographic boundaries and so
does MIT's re reach,
I wanted to showcase a couple uh
research success stories um through ILP
Lonza which is one of the world's
largest pharmaceutical CDMOs connected
with MIT faculty and are collaborating
around micrfluidic platform that
analyzes single cell properties in real
time. This is helping them um monitor
production quality enabling faster
process adjustments and consistent
manufacturing. Another example is our M
mineral stewardship consortium where
four global mining leaders came together
through the ILP to s uh to tackle
sustainable mining challenges.
collaborating with MIT faculty. They are
developing the digital tools for mine uh
decision making and ESG metrics that
will transform entire the entire
industry. These are the kinds of
breakthroughs that happen when you bring
together brilliant minds, tough problems
and partners willing to invest in the
future. Here are a few
success stories that involve startups
and startups connecting with our uh 200
plus members. I'm not going to walk
through all of them. You'll have an
opportunity to hear from a few of the
startups uh today.
And lastly, before I thank you, I did
want to uh leave with the bottom line.
MIT is not just about producing great
research. We do do that. It's not just
about creating startups. We do that too.
It's about building the ecosystem where
problems get solved, where failure leads
to learning, where industry and academia
actually work together. Um, not instead
of just talking about it, and where the
next big breakthrough is probably
happening right now in a lab that you've
never heard of. To the ILP member member
companies, I'm glad we are working
together.
And to the ILP curious, we'd love for
you to start working with us. Please um
work uh we you'll see see my colleagues
here, Eileena uh and others. Can you
please stand up? Uh other program
directors from the industry leazison
program and startup exchange.
So please you can meet with them with
that. Thank you.
Thank you, Geth. Uh, welcome everyone.
Good morning. Uh, my name is Arena
Sigalowski. I'm director at the MIT
Office of Corporate Relations. It's my
pleasure to host you here today. Um, why
are you here today? So, I personally
think that there is a lot of noise uh in
the world. uh a lot of hype about
technologies, about job politics, about
resources, about economic shifts uh and
a lot of uncertainty. So hopefully today
uh nobody pretends to have a crystal
ball uh but we do have a lot of great
minds here on campus and a lot of
top-notch experts. And so I hope you
will leave this conference uh with very
useful insights about how to understand
the world today and also how to prepare
for the world tomorrow. So before we
begin the conference I want to just make
few logistical notes. Uh first of all
we're going to use pigeon hole
application for questions. So you can
connect to pigeonhole from your browser
if you type um let's see pigeonhole.atat
and a password for for this conference
is capital RD25
or you can simply scan QR code on your
printed agendas. Uh people online
welcome welcome too. Uh you can simply
click the Q&A link on the event homepage
to participate. Uh uh the Wi-Fi
information is also on your printed
agendas. Uh it's 2025_rd
Wifi and the password is MIT ILP25.
Uh a very important note tomorrow we're
going to have four tours after the
conference ends at 1. So at 1:15 there
are four tours MIT campus tour uh MIT
museum tour, innovation trail tour by
our friends from innovation trail and
MIT that nana tour. There is no option
to sign up uh online. The only way to
sign up is tomorrow morning. There will
be sign up boards next to the
registration table. So tomorrow morning
please sign up. Uh there are limited
spots. Last but not least, I'd like to
thank you my colleagues. Uh first of
all, Peter Bashard, uh my partner in
crime. You'll meet him in the afternoon.
Uh but also Ron Klouse, Peter Losa, Dave
Martin, Jim Flynn, Natalie Kim, amazing
startup exchange team, especially Ari,
you'll meet her uh too. Our amazing
events and communications team, Quan,
Katrina, James, and Liz, and MIT AV
team. It takes a village to put an event
like this.