all right thanks everybody I am uh Kent
senson Chief technology officer at
alonia we are a bioen company really
taking inspiration from nature and
especially biology to work to solve some
of the world's most challenging
environmental issues um I am MIT uh
graduate student from further back than
I care to admit especially after uh the
last few presentations but it has been a
while but alonia was also um a spin out
of gko bioworks which is another MIT
startup so um couple of connections
there so while we're working on a number
of different environmental challenges I
really want to focus on sustainable
Mining and metals and specifically
bioextraction of rare Earths this is one
of the things that uh we're advancing
fairly rapidly just in the last year and
you've heard a lot this morning about
demands for electricity and needs for
electrification particularly in terms of
decreasing carbon emissions well you
can't do all of that today without a lot
more metals so specifically The Rare
Earth elements and what the department
of energy calls critical materials or
critical minerals things like copper
lithium Cobalt Etc nickel um we we need
a lot more of those Metals so how do we
mine those sustainably considering that
the mining industry is something like 10
to 20% of global carbon emissions today
um depending on how you do that
accounting so we'd like to decrease that
while while still meeting the
electrification needs one way to do that
is to upcycle waste certainly but we
also from a security standpoint need
domestic Supply chains of these
materials and currently 90 to 95% of the
rare earth Global Supply is controlled
by China using a very environmentally
intensive chemical intensive process to
separate those rare Earths and we so
we'd like to decrease the environmental
footprint but also secure domestic
supply chain so we're focused on
recovering Rees from uh potentially a
variety of different waste streams uh we
are also looking at Copper and other
critical materials but clearly using
biology we want to decrease the volume
of toxic reagents but also as has been
pointed out by some of the other
presenters here do this in a way that is
a little more plug andplay to reduce
capex costs and allow for faster return
on investment so what specifically is
the technology well we are using
proteins and as a benchmark we have a
protein called land modulin which we can
attach to beads and put in a column very
similar to an ion exchange column and
when we run water through those beads uh
with the rare earth metals and and
specifically these are some of the
lodide metals what you see is really
interesting because biology biological
proteins are very good at sequestering
very specific metals because they either
need them for metabolism or to reduce
toxicity or a variety of other
biological processes so you have all
this other metal that's in water like
acid mine drainage that's passing
directly through the column with no
sorption to our protein or our beads the
three rare Earths are the lines here you
see about 30 to 40 bed volumes before we
start to see breakthrough of those so
we're seeing really good specific
sorption of those compounds in that
column and then what's great is when we
elute the metals off of that we're
getting a concentration of about 10 to
45x with some of our preliminary data
here at something north of about 90%
Purity for those mixed rare Earths so
very very different solution coming out
than went
in now where we go from here is we're
partnered with a global Mining Company
already at a US mine site uh actually a
copper mine for initial testing uh with
a mine impacted water that looks
something like the one in the picture
that's only about less than 10 parts per
million of rare Earths but has thousands
of parts per million of things like iron
and aluminum and other competing Metals
so we want to remove those and we're
we're very excited that we are seeing
now um some very good pre-treatment
results that allow us to easily remove
things like aluminum and iron and then
in the previous chart I already showed
you how calcium magnesium and a lot of
other metals that are in that uh
material go right through the column and
what we're showing on the bottom here is
in addition to that we're able to see
multiple cycles of reuse of the protein
so we can regenerate the protein right
now we've got no loss of capacity after
five cycles of absorption and desorption
um when you get to about 10 Cycles you
are starting to lose some capacity there
and this is where some of our protein
engineering will come in we do need need
to increase that to make the economics
start to look really good but it's very
promising to be at this stage right now
uh we plan to go to the field in uh the
first quarter of 2025 and actually be on
the M site doing this at a small Scale
Pilot scale so we're certainly
interested in Partners who are end users
um whether that's mining companies
energy companies uh electronics
companies and and defense also uses a
lot of rare Earths we we need access to
more Wast streams that contain these
materials so that could be E-Waste Urban
mining um other Industrial Waste streams
produced uh waters for example from the
fracking industry have Rees and then
there's a number of different waist
streams that have these Metals in them
and of course deployment Partners we're
not going to be the whole solution we're
going to be part of an integrated system
at some point and so other partners who
want to work with us on this are are of
great interest and I've been focused on
on just the rare earth Market but just
to let you know we are also very much
involved in emerging contaminants
especially past treatment from water um
as well as a couple of other sustainable
mining Solutions so uh hope to see you
stop by our table over in the other room
and uh thank you appreciate the time
[Applause]