I have two black cylinders in my hands
here and I will tell you that one of
them is a magnet and the other one is
not over here I have two pipes this one
is acrylic and this one is aluminum
neither is magnetic but now I'm going to
drop these through the two pipes so
let's start with the acrylic
one now I'll do the other
one so that is how strong gravity is so
now let's try the aluminum pipe so here
we
go same let's try this
one where is it there it is what's
happening is that as this magnet is
falling through the pipe that's changing
the magnetic flux through this Loop of
pipe when you change the magnetic flux
through a loop of aluminum or a loop of
pipe it induces a current that's
Faraday's law the fact that the current
that I induce exerts a force which slows
the magnet down this is this actually
gets a special name it's called lens's
law lens's law in action there you go
it's kind of amazing actually for more
MIT moments from MIT open learning like
subscribe or follow