awesome well it's great it's great to be
here thank you for having me uh my name
is Evan hos I'm co-founder and CEO of
Helix carbon and I co-founded this
company actually out of out of MIT like
like everyone else here and along with
my co-founders Ariel first who's a
professor uh in chemical engineering and
Dave Brown who who was a graduate
student with me um I was I was a
graduate student in mechanical
engineering and also in business and we
spun this out a lot a lot of the work we
were doing and sort of around materials
decarbonization and specifically how do
you use electrochemistry to produce
materials with no carbon impact and
within that we're we're focusing first
on the Iron and steel industry and this
is one that you know obviously has a
huge presence here in Japan uh but it
also has a presence globally in terms of
emissions you know it's roughly 7 to 10%
of global greenhouse gas emissions it's
a$2 trillion dollar industry and the
vast majority of those emissions come
from the very first step primary iron
making turning iron ore into metallic
iron and if you look at the way this
process works today those emissions come
from the fossil fuels that we use as a
feed stock so those fossil fuels usually
natural gas or coal are fed into a
reformer that that chemical those
compounds are converted into carbon
monoxide and hydrogen which each can
strip and oxygen off your iron oxide
your iron ore and is emitted as CO2 and
water
and it is really this CO2 that is the
source of those two gatons of emissions
globally and the challenge with
decarbonizing this is these plants these
furnaces there's about a trillion
dollars of them deployed globally and
many of them have Decades of operating
life left so how do you decarbonize an
industry without decarbonizing the
facilities that you already have you
have to develop a technology that is
compatible with the process that you're
using and so our answer was instead of
letting this CO2 get emitted let's
actually close this cycle let's take the
CO2 and water vapor that's being emitted
pull it into our proprietary
electrochemical cell and Co electroly
the CO2 back into carbon monoxide and
the water vapor back into hydrogen now
the the key here is this feed stock is
chemically identical to what you're
already getting from fossil fuels and so
it's a dropin solution A Drop In
chemical at existing iron making
facilities
and at the end of the day you get you
know the same identical sponge iron
product so in order to do this we had to
solve Three core technical challenge
which challenges which will really sort
of form the base of our business the
first was electrochemical stability so
there's a lot of CO2 conversion uh you
know a lot of CO2 conversion
electrolyzers out there the core
challenge that many of them share is
stability many of them will fail after
20 or 30 hours and we've been able to
demonstrate hundreds of hours of
continuously stable production
and that's key to some kind ofcial deoy
the second is if you want to do this
this of ccle that I just show you in an
Ecom way you have to be tolerant to
everything else that's that's in this in
this stream here and that includes
excess carbon monoxide hydrogen uh
methane nitrogen there there's so many
other compounds in there that in many
cases are toxic to today's CO2
conversion systems and so we had to
develop a system that is able to be
resilient to all of those and operate in
low concentrations of CO2 and then the
last one which is ironically the easiest
is just having a very tight control over
the ratio of hydrogen and carbon
monoxide that you're producing being
able to very reliably keep consistent
with that because that's what those
those furnaces are sensitive to is the
ratio of carbon monoxide and
hydrogen and so that's the cell that we
built it's a gaseous it's a gaseous
phase carbon dioxide conversion system
that pulls in flu gas whether it's from
an iron plant or or any other industrial
facility
and can coel the components of that flu
gas into the chemicals that those
facilities already use and so in the
Contex of iron obviously that's carbon
monoxide and hydrogen and we also make a
lot of oxygen as you might guess at the
anode and that's also something that has
a ton of value at at an industrial
facility and so we've already talked a
little bit about stability and and also
this the the the core piece of that is
not just stability of output of how much
you're producing but also stability
again in that ratio of hydrogen to
carbon monoxide and so we've shown that
we can actually produce a gas blend that
is exactly what you would get from
natural gas or even coal but with this
electrochemical closed loop
process and so as you might guess you
know that we're starting in Iron but
this is not a a technology that is
limited to just this industry you know
the ability to produce carbon monoxide
is a ubiquitous chemical feed stock and
has a lot of applications in things like
chemicals production for polymers
polycarbonates polyurethanes acetic acid
as well as a variety of metals like
copper for example that also go through
a similar kind of reduction process
we've also developed a catalyst that
uses the exact same cell that's a copper
based Catalyst for conversion of CO2 to
ethylene which we heard a little bit
about earlier and that cell is is
fundamentally the exact same system that
is all allows us to take dilute CO2 and
produce that chemical feed stock and so
the reason we're here in Japan is
because Japan is a leader in these
spaces we've already spoken to many of
you but both in steel and chemicals the
you know the many of the leading
companies are based here and we're
excited to partner with you so for us
where we are right now is looking for
some of those first deployments we have
a couple Pilots we're developing in the
United States but we're looking to
expand particularly with pilots in sort
of this uh one ton per day range as well
as joint development agreements and if
you're a buyer of green steel we'd love
to talk with you about how we can how we
can support that so with that thank you
for having me and uh hopefully come by
and chat with us later