So uh that gives me the opportunity to
introduce uh Carrie COY uh who's the
Sheila Ed Evans Whitnol Professor uh
within the MIT department of aereroastro
um she leads the space
telecommunications astronomy and
radiation star lab where
>> I'm sorry let her walk away with
>> no I won't go too far. um where her team
develops small satellite technologies
for laser free space optical
communications, weather sensing, earth
observation and astrophysics space
telescopes.
And her talk today is titled compute
above the clouds laser comms and 5G NTN
for AIdriven constellations.
So join me in welcoming Professor Carrie
Cahooy.
[applause]
Let's see.
Still driving here. All right. Well,
it's great to be here and I've enjoyed
all of the presentations so far. I feel
like I'm learning a lot. So, thanks for
having me. Um, I'm here to talk about uh
compute above the clouds and this is
kind of a
I don't know watching a creation of
something moment for me because I'm I'm
seeing we've been talking a lot about
how the internet evolved. Um, and then
we're talking about the fiber backbone
that we have now. And we're seeing that
happen in space. And so I'm excited to
tell you what I'm seeing and a little
bit about how I see it coming together
and some directions that I think we can
go with it. Um, so this talk is comput
above the clouds. Kind of envisioning
what's happening um, above literal
clouds. There's computing clouds and I
think we're seeing that literally above
the clouds in space and orbit. Um, so
we're going to talk a little bit about
how that's happening. Um, some of the
enablers that I'm going to talk about
today are laser communications, which
are one of the things that my group
works on. I'm in the aereroastro
department. I run the space
telecommunications, astronomy and
radiation or star lab here. Um, and we
also do radio, we do RF, we do weather
sensing, we do earth observation
imaging. And, um, we've gotten into, um,
using AI for remote sensing, too. So,
lots of fun things coming together, and
I think there's a lot of excitement
happening.
All right. So, this is um just my you
don't have to read through this, but
this is kind of keeping track of where
we are. So, if you're really bored, you
can just watch the little lines go bold
and then we'll get to the end at some
point. Um [laughter]
but the motivation is I was saying here
um historically when we're doing Earth
observations for for agriculture, for
energy mining, for industry, for
communications, we have this modality
where we have the sensor that's on orbit
and it's looking down at Earth. We take
the picture, we store it on board. When
we fly over the ground station, we down
link it and then it makes its way
through analysis anal an analysts into
the cloud or what we're calling the
cloud now. You know, our our network of
computers um where we use this data um
AWS, whatever it is. Um what we're
seeing happen is more exciting than
that. So we're seeing the compute move.
Um we're seeing compute being used on
orbit. So, those sensors that are taking
images, we're using compute on board now
to decide whether or not we got the
picture of what we wanted. Was it
cloudy? Did we get the red barn? Were we
following the train? Were we following a
plane? What were we looking at? Did we
see the flood? Um, if it's the image we
wanted, we can save it. If it's not, we
can put those images in a different
queue and we can accelerate the down
link and distribution of the thing that
we really cared about. Um, even better,
once we figured out that we saw it, we
can start talking because we now have
laser come cross links, which I'll talk
about in a second, to all of the other
satellites in orbit and tell them, "Hey,
I got it. It's over here." Um, and we
can retask and replan. So, all of these
things didn't used to be possible at all
and they're just coming into fruition
now. And it's very exciting. It's kind
of like a birth. Um, so what we're
seeing is this dynamic tasking,
allocating the sensor time. The sensor
is looking at its own data, deriving the
insights, shuttling it to where it needs
to go, letting everybody else know about
it, allowing them to dynamically task
and replan again, and down linking it to
where it needs to go. If it does need to
go down, may not need to go down, maybe
just enough information to replan the ne
next task and follow the next thing. So,
this is all very exciting. So, I'm
calling that the cloud above the clouds
because I think that's what we're seeing
now. Um,
so, um, why now and why is it happening?
How'd we get here finally to this point
where I think we're really at this this
edge of really exciting things happening
with our ability to sense and um, use
Earth observation data and
communications. We have these um, low
Earth orbit or LEO mega commmunication
constellations that now exist. Um, we
have also enormous data volumes from
synthetic aperture radar which can see
through clouds anyway. So, they don't
care quite as much, [laughter] but they
have enormous amounts of data and they
are still looking for things whether
it's deformationations or moving objects
and they'll want to identify them
quickly. Um, we have a lot of Earth
observation imagery. We're starting to
look at different colors and different
bands and be able to tell materials
properties on orbit. Um, which is also
very exciting. Um, we have advances in
onorbit compute because these
constellations are in low Earth orbit.
The um, how do my colleagues call them?
Pew pew pew space particles um
[laughter] that like to take out the
electronics um, the radiation, the
ionizing radiation is less of a concern.
It still happens and you still have to
recover from it, but you're able to use
commercial um compute and commercial
processors on orbit much more
successfully than you can um at higher
altitudes or at further distances from
the Earth where there's a lot more um
pew pew pew. I see radiation. It doesn't
work quite as well if I'm not at a high
voice. I have to get my pitch higher. Um
okay, so so we have this AI on board and
having the eye on board and having the
inferences really
kind of makes your brain twist around
this whole
communications bottleneck and capacity
limits problem because
maybe it doesn't exist anymore.
You know, maybe we don't need to down
link gigabits of data per second. Maybe
flying things around at high speed isn't
the problem. Um bits may just need to be
more strategically routed and we may not
need quite as many of them piped
everywhere. We may still want a lot of
data but um it may may make us rethink
this whole um you know communication
capacity problem that we've been dealing
with. Um so we might have be in a
situation we're deciding and delivering
from on orbit um how we manage our data
and what we talk to and what we're
coordinating because we can do it across
great distances which we have a really
hard time doing from the ground.
Um so so these in laser inter satellite
links that are connecting nodes on orbit
are really enabling um and they're
augmenting radio down links and up links
for commanding and this is leading us to
a era where I think we really are
getting more programmable capability in
space where space is something that we
can coordinate we can program we can
task we can control much better than
we've ever been able to do before. Um,
so this means that we can have more
targeted satellite services, not just
sensor data dumps and um, be a lot
smarter about this. So some of the
images on the slide are SpaceX Starlink.
So that is a stack of satellites um, in
a in a in a payload fairing about to be
deployed on orbit. Um, the next image
down is the reusable launch vehicles.
Um, I think a lot of people have seen
the Falcon 9's land. And then um, we're
looking at this happening globally. So
in China even we have similar
constellations that are flatpacked um
with similar communications capability
and crossling capability happening and
so we are having a scenario where we're
going to have multiple large players
competing for space. So I think there's
a lot of interesting things that some of
my colleagues are working on in
Aereroastra as well with respect to um
space use and space congestion. Um but
that that all only helps motivate some
of the um secure laser um communications
links arguments. um even more so
exciting. Um so the things that we have
to come overcome, the problems that
we're solving with these space systems
that we we for the most part have
solved. So not a lot of these are really
drivers anymore as just things that
we're aware of. Power is limited. Um so
we're we're operating off of batteries.
We're operating in solar. There are some
power beaming technologies that are
exciting, but they're still expensive
and hard to do. So, [laughter]
so if you want to get um power in
eclipse when you're on the dark side
when you're not in the sunlight that
that can you have to plan for that and
have batteries for that [gasps] when
you're in space. Um everybody has this
mental image of your computers and your
towers and they have the fans and the
fans make noise and they cool the chips,
right?
We don't have fans in space. It's
vacuum. You have to radiate or conduct
heat away. There's no convection. And so
it's one of the things that we do have
to do is be really cognizant of thermal
loading when we're running processors in
space. So we use power but when we use
power we get hot and we need we
[laughter] need to manage that somehow.
So thermal materials will also be um and
thermal management are things that are
important. Um in order to have the laser
cross links between nodes we use um
laser links and the pointing for those
is really really super precise. Um, and
I'll talk a little bit more about that.
Um, we're also moving fast. 7 kilometers
per second flying across the sky. It
takes about 10 minutes to go from
horizon to horizon. That's fast. Um,
that causes Doppler shifts in our
signals. And we'll talk a little about
that because when we're dealing with
that and we're trying to incorporate and
make this even more accessible, starting
to connect to commercial handheld
devices, cell phones, which I I showed
in one of the the overview slide. We're
going directly from satellite towers and
we're treating satellites like base
stations now directly to your cell
phone. Um the Doppler shift caused by
those high velocities is a factor and we
need to plan that into our standards and
and think about that and how to manage
it. We don't really want our cell phones
to have to deal with it. Um [laughter]
we'd much rather have the towers deal
with that. So we'll talk more about that
um and how regulatory um plays a role um
in these untopability standards. And
then um weather is still going to affect
ground down links. So that's one of the
reasons we don't really use optical um
for down links. Clouds still are a
problem. So this is a scenario where we
do need hybrid networks. We're still
going to need radio. And um making
decisions about what to use when is
something that the on-orbit compute will
really help enable.
Um autonomy that is reliable and
cost-effective. So, we talked about this
vision of having them make decisions
based on what they see on orbit and
updating plans, replanning things,
retasking. Um, it needs to be
cost-ffective and reliable. Nobody's
going to want to spend, you know,
enormous amounts of their budget on the
software and on the processing. It needs
to be reusable. It needs to be
repeatable. It needs to not be custom
every time. So, we need ways of doing
that that um are reliable and cost-
effective. And we also need
interoperability across fleets and
platforms because even though we have
some dominant players in space, the same
people aren't making all of the
hardware. And even if they were the same
people making all of the hardware, um
things going obsolete is a really good
way of making sure that you can't talk
to yourself in a later generation. So
interoperability is still really
important to plan even if you have
dominant players and and we we do have
multiple players in the market. Um and
then of course there's security. So
security is still very much an issue. Um
we we worry a lot about who's getting
what information when. And I'm going to
talk a little bit about federated AI on
orbit to address that. So just as a prep
um um um of ways that you can manage um
improving everybody's overall
performance without necessarily giving
away all the data. Um all right so I I I
mentioned briefly so this is an image of
um Apple connecting to a global star
satellite. These are global star is kind
of an established player for decades in
the space communications business if if
you're not familiar with global star. Um
but um we're going to talk a little bit
about the building blocks next. So the
the things that really led up to this
this kind of birth of capability that
we're we're right on the edge of right
now. Um so I just want to make this
statement [laughter] with flashing
lights. Lasercom what I see happening
here is laser is not replacing radio. It
is the high-capacity spine the backbone
like terrestrial fiber that is going to
make modern satellite networks able to
behave like cloud backbones do here on
Earth. So it's fast, secure, it's
scalable. RF is going to keep us being
able to do that last hop down to the
ground through the clouds for the most
part if you're learn frequency um and
make it universally available. So this
is really about hybrid. So it's it's not
really replacing RF, it's augmenting it
and it's making it more like what we
have here on Earth for our ground cloud
networks.
All right. So we have um laser
interatellite links which are our
backbone. um the space equivalent of
optical fiber networks on the ground.
Again, precision pointing is key and and
like our fiber networks on the ground.
Um it's really pointto-point, right? It
it you you can steer your beam to
different things, but you need to know
where you're pointing to. It's not like
a radio where you can just broadcast or
multiccast right now. There's not really
a great way to do that with optical. So,
it's really the equivalent of optical
fiber. And then what's happening now um
talking about 3GPP and all the G's for
[laughter] communications for our our
our devices um they have some new
releases um from 5G with what's called
the non-aterrestrial network. They're
making modifications and I'll talk in
more detail about that. They're making
specific modifications that allow our
devices as built your cell phone to
connect directly to satellites and
mobile platforms more easily.
So um on on satellites on aerial mobile
platforms they're just
implementing things that allow reduced
capability that allow the Doppler
management um and connect to multiple
devices and allow directtodevice
connectability. So these are all things
that are that are happening. Um and then
the the last thing that's really
enabling this like I mentioned is the
onboard AI and edge compute. So we're
flying in lower earth orbit. We've
discovered that, you know, we can get
away with flying commercial components
in orbit successfully. We build in some
redundancy. We build in some, you know,
triple modular redundancy voting and we
we can do this. So, we're flying GPUs,
we're flying commercial FPGAAS, we're
flying AS6, and we've got more compute
on orbit, more capability now than we'll
we've ever had before. Um, so this is
allowing us and and our students have
done this here. you know they have
cubats nano satellites just for
demonstration. ISA had one. There are
some um that the US have now where you
can literally you know upload code and
run your own AI models on their
processors have it grab images, have it
do the identification and demonstrate
that your algorithms work. So you can do
classification, you can do feature
recognition. This is this is happening.
Um laser angel satellite winks are
great. The top image here is showing
kind of like a large radio beam in the
green with a narrower laser beam.
They're actually even narrower than that
a lot of the times. Um when you have a
spacetospace link, you don't have to
worry about clouds, just space to space.
What you do have to worry about is tiny
terminal to tiny terminal with tiny beam
and you have to find each other. So they
do all these fun spiral search
algorithms. That's a whole another
optimization fun problem where you're
trying to find each other and hit each
other with, you know, blinky the wide
thing. Okay, I see you. Okay, narrow
thing coming. Okay, now I'm going to spy
around and tell you, okay, I got it. Um,
back and forth only. You don't really
have a coms link to tell each other
anything until you get it working.
[laughter] It's it's a fun problem. Um,
but um, all of the devices and all the
capability to do that are established.
Um, SpaceX Starlink is making something
like 300,000
um, contacts between spacecraft per day
of their interatellite links. It's it's
we're doing this at at scale. So, this
is this is happening. it's no longer
like a science project. Um, this allows
spatial reuse. So, because they're so
narrow, we don't really have to worry
about, like we do with radio,
interfering with somebody else's
spectrum. Um, and it it really is very
secure. If you don't know where the
signal is pointing, you're not going to
get it. Um, it it's very difficult for
you. Unless you have like a giant
detector that's very sensitive, you're
you're you're just not going to find it.
Um, so security is improved. Um and um
one of the things my lab works on, this
is just an example of one of our
projects where we're using micro
electromechanical systems and fine
steering mirrors to do the precision
pointing. So this is technology that you
know we've pioneered. We're using it's
kind of state-of-the-art right now and
it's enabling this connectivity, this
backbone to exist between spacecraft. Um
the laser terminal here is an example of
a of a small laser terminal that SpaceX
is now um making available for trial. I
assume they'll begin selling it soon to
third party spacecraft to connect with
their network on orbit instead of just
ground terminals. So, they're going to
have space terminals as well. So, these
are these are exciting things that are
happening.
Um, so 5G naterrestrial networks, I'm
going to kind of talk through the the
diagrams here. Um, they're a little
they're a little busy. So, when we're
talking about 5G nontrestrial networks,
they're talking about including things
like satellites and aerospace platforms
as well as other mobile platforms as
part of the network that can talk to
your handheld devices, to your internet
of things devices. Um, so these are
these are things that they're they want
to enable and they're modifying their
standards to make it possible. So, in in
the standard you're going to see these
red boxes here are the new things that
they're changing. So I'm gonna I'm going
to go through a couple of them, but um
satellite and high altitude platforms.
That's what HAPS is here. So satcom
infrastructure.
Um and then ground stations. So
incorporating the ground stations that
talk to the mobile platforms, the high
altitude platforms, making those part of
the system. Um and it it's just adding
the control for these non-aterrestrial
networks to deal with the latency.
Sometimes things don't connect quite as
quickly. Sometimes they're very resource
constrained. Like I said, you're moving
very fast. You have to handle the
frequency shifts due to Doppler, but you
don't want your cell phone to have to
deal with that. So, you want that
handled on the other end. Um, you also
when you're transmitting things, you you
have this um automatic repeat request
where like it didn't get the packet, so
it asks for you to send it again. Doing
that over and over again is a really
good way to use up a lot of power and
resources. And some of these mobile
systems don't want to do that. So, you
want to have the ability to operate and
be like, "Didn't get the packet. Oh,
well, too bad. Um, move on. Maybe I'll
get it from the next station or maybe
they'll the user will resend it." So,
um, there there are ways that they're
they're implementing that to conserve
resources. Um, and then normally when
you're transmitting, you kind of have to
let people know. So, you kind of have to
like wave and be like, "Can I send now?"
Um, and that takes resources, too. So
they're now allowing um grant free um
packets to be sent without all of the
same with less they're still scheduling
overhead but it's a lot less than it
used to be. So these are the ways that
they're modifying existing protocols to
make it possible for your existing
device at the existing cost to have this
expanded capability and be part of this
great new network that is forming in
front of us. So these these are exciting
things.
Um this is just a couple of the the um
releases that are kind of in process. So
this is um releases 17 and 18. This is
mimicking what we do with communication
satellites. So communication satellites
historically have been what are called
bent pipes. Literally bent pipes. When I
was um learning this as an electrical
engineer, I was like, what are you
talking about pipes? I'm not a plumber
when pi pipes. And then I realized that
wave guides look just like pipes um
[laughter] for the high power systems.
But what it means is that you send a
signal up and it pretty much just goes
up and through and comes right back
down. You don't do anything to it,
right? It goes up and then back down
somewhere else. So the whole point of
this, you know, satellite communications
is to send the signal up from somewhere
else and have other people get the exact
same signal, right? So that's kind of
what is going on with the
non-aterrestrial networks with releases
17 and 18. They're doing that with your
devices now where they're allowing your
signals to be sent up to satellites and
come down to your devices as a in bent
pipe form. The release 19 is allowing
what's called um regenerative um
capability on board. So now you can send
signals up and instead of just piping it
through, it can save them, manipulate
them, redirect them, amplify them,
change the frequency, change the
modulation, and send them somewhere
else. So it's a lot more capable. And
that's kind of where where they are now
on 19. And they're going to keep going
from there. So, um, that's that's kind
of what you're seeing here. So, this is
the bent pipe for 17 and 18 through GGPB
releases 17 and 18. And this is release
19 where you're seeing the inter
satellite links and the regenerative
capability that's being enabled.
So, this is this is where we are now.
Um, it's it's a sign that we're we're
hitting the accelerator to do even more
things with this. Um, which is exciting.
So, I wanted to talk about it, but it is
one of the enabling things for this
cloud capability that I'm seeing
happening in space. So, we're seeing
non-aterrestrial networks, the laser com
links, the AI on board. We're going
somewhere with us. It's exciting.
All right, [laughter] this is an eye
chart. We're only going to look at the
bottom row, just like in the optometrist
office. If you can see the bottom row,
cover one arm. Um, [laughter]
but the point of this slide was we had
students go through this and we wanted
to think about, okay, we're Earth
observation aerospace engineers. what
are the things that we can do with AI on
board satellites.
So first of course we're MIT students
and we we we have to go through all the
things. So we start with AI machine
learning as a subset of AI you know
supervised learning unsupervised
learning reinforcement learning the
evolutionary algorithms constraint
satisfaction these are all kind of the
high level things. So we go through the
type of AI, the methods, the different
tasks, the algorithms that you can use
for each of them, um, and then the the
if there are deep learning algorithms,
which there are, um, which ones go with
each category. And then we thought
about, okay, for each of these things,
what are the example applications that
we could use this for in a space cloud
network? So the example applications
operation planning, navigation,
scientific um predictions, cloud
filtering, feature extractions, which I
kind of emphasized before. You can look
for floods, you can look for wildfires,
you can follow that train. Um
and that that is quite a few of them.
Spacecraft health management. One of the
most exciting things that I can think of
to do with AI on orbit is to have the
satellite look at its own telemetry and
figure out what's wrong with itself. um
and try to take actions to mitigate it
without incorporating the ground in the
loop if it if it doesn't need to or only
flagging us when there are high concerns
especially with radiation damage and
things like that. Um, and I'll talk more
about this, but the other exciting thing
that I can really think to do with AI on
orbit, how many people here do not like
writing interface driver software?
Wouldn't it be great if it just
monitored the bits coming in and could
see from the pattern what the protocol
was and write its own software for
whatever that was at the time? That
would be fantastic. So like things like
that we can imagine happening and
enabling all this interoperability that
we'd like to see as part of the space
cloud. Right? So these are spacecraft
health management getting rid of having
to write so much software [laughter]
just having [clears throat] it be aware
of what what's coming in um long-term
navigation and tracking
and um configuring and optimizing its
own orbit and its own um you know
management of its onboard resources. So
all of these things you can do um and
and are are very exciting. There's a lot
going on here. This is just another
example. Um on the left here we're
talking about like an instrument level
application where you have an instrument
that activates it collects data. It
stores the data and then it you know
decides what to do with it. It was the
data good enough? No. It'll collect more
data. Better data. Wait for the better
data. Send down only when it's good
enough. Um so you send down less data.
you'd only send the good data. You'd
prioritize the data down links. Um, so
you you'd use things like image
recognition, object detection, change
detection, um, prioritization. And the
way that this works on orbit is your
input is literally your images and you
can have lots of input. This this
multimodal AI where you can put in all
the colors. You can put in thermal data
plus optical data plus, you know, your
radar data all at the same time and have
it really infer something about the
scene. if you're training the models to
handle this. Um, training the models is
another story, but I only have time for
one talk.
[laughter] So, so you put these these
this data into the learning networks and
you have your classified features as an
output and then you can make decisions
based on on what you've got. Um, so this
is this is all all very exciting and we
have some the URL links are to some of
the work that we've done in this area.
Lots of other people are working on this
onboard autonomy resource scheduling.
So, I like my little Lego satellite
here. What it's doing is the green beam
is it's kind of looking out and forward
first looking along its horizon
and it's seeing okay what's in front of
me and it's deciding based on what it
sees in this case cloudy or not where it
wants to use the red beam to take the
picture and the beams in this case are
field of views of cameras. So it's just
looking ahead making decision and then
taking the picture at exactly the right
time when it passes over the clear spot.
Um, so this is this is an example of of
something that we've written algorithms
to do. This is kind of a another eye
chart. Sorry, [laughter]
not quite as easy as the other one. Um,
where we have um this is kind of a the
from the field of view of a from the
mind of a satellite, right? This is what
it sees. It sees the horizon of the
Earth in front of it. Um, all of the
black dots are things that it it knows
are targets. It's been told are targets,
but it can't it it hasn't looked at them
yet.
um when when we see have a cloud map and
we have that image of the clouds and we
can plan for clear and cloudy. The reds
are things that we won't be able to see
on this pass. The greens are things that
we will be able to see on this pass from
our target list. And um the green dot
here is where my satellite would look if
we're looking straight down. And the the
kind of bumpy line here is like how I'm
using my onboard reaction wheels or my
thrusters to tip and tilt my satellite
to make sure I take pictures of the
right thing. That could be a gimbal on
your camera if you don't want to tilt
your whole satellite. There are lots of
different ways to do this. So, um I'm
just gonna play that for a second. So,
you can write an optimizer
to get this look ahead data and to plan
to hit as many green dots. It's just
like, you know, playing a video game.
[laughter]
So, so if the internet is for gamers,
then the space the space cloud's also
for gamers. Um we we like this. So, and
it's it's just chasing the green dots
and it's doing the most highv value
green dots it can um the best it can
with this one look ahead camera, right?
You can imagine not just its own look
ahead camera, but maybe it talks to the
guys in front of it or the guys behind
it and it coordinates with them because
you've got this um space internet thing
going now. So, lots of exciting things
can happen with on orbit autonomy.
This is kind of what I was talking about
about the fault handling. We've tried
this too. It does work. you can um
[laughter]
so what we did with this is supervised
and I know we want to get it to more
unsupervised but for the moment we
basically took a bunch of really grumpy
um myself included engineers and grad
students who are former spacecraft
operators and we thought about all the
different ways that we've seen telemetry
mean that things are not working on
board. So so we're we're doing something
good. We're making lemonade with all the
times that things didn't work for us,
right? And so we made a simulator tool
and we used that simulator tool of all
the bad things that could happen in
telemetry and what they mean and we used
it to train a model and then we took
actual satellite telemetry and we're
like hey tell us what's happening based
on all the the bad stuff that happened
to us all the years that we created the
model to train you about and it did. So
it was able to um leverage in this case
we used an autoenccoder GMM long long
short-term memory PCMCI and a common
filter and XG boost tree to just help us
decide what was going on on board that
satellite based on the telemetry in our
own like grumpy model is what I'll call
it our grumpies satellite telemetry
model and and it works great. So you can
you can do this and um that's why I'm
excited about it happening in the future
because I I see this as possible.
um federated with learning in low Earth
orbit. So this I think is a really
exciting idea.
So federated means that you know we may
have constellations and they're not all
owned by the same entity. Maybe they're
kind of friendly kind of like you know
states or the EU. I'm not sure. You know
I I don't I don't know. Maybe talk to
football fans. Um but the different
parts have come together for this common
purpose. They have a shared purpose, but
they don't really want to share all
their data, right? But they have a
shared goal or shared purpose that
they're in they're operating with each
other for. They have this agreement that
they're they have some shared purpose
that they're all operating towards.
Maybe it's wildfire detection. They're
all going to look at all their images
and they're going to look for wildfires.
Um
what they can do is instead of trying to
you know send all their data down for
analyst for analysts to use or to train
a model on the ground, what they could
do is share a model across multiple
satellites where instead of you know
sending their data down or sending their
data amongst each other or all running
the same model, they each send models to
the data. So you would share your model
and your parameters between your nodes
and they would train it on board with
the data that they have and then they
could share their weights and um
everything that they got their learned
weights and their learn gradients with
other nodes. In that case you're just
improving the overall performance of
your federated system by sharing your
model tuning without actually
necessarily even sharing your data.
Right? So you're enabling a common goal
without having to give away all the
data. So something like this would be
really exciting too where where you have
these federated systems that could work
together and this is a way they could
work together um that wasn't possible
before um while retaining privacy. So
there there are a lot of fun things that
you could do you could do with this. So
um I'm gonna wrap up because there's
there's there's a lot to do here that's
exciting and I I want to have time for
discussion and questions. Um so where we
are now we've got optical cross links
we've got NTN happening we have AI and
autonomy starting to be on board what we
want to do is develop multi-satellite
and groundstation routing um advanced
autonomy so that based on the decisions
that are made from AI models on board
looking at the data you can do dynamic
tasking you can do routing you do
optimization you can get more value to
your users um more quickly and you can
have a better use of your resources and
have a more robust system overall. So
this is this is fun. Um I would love to
see people add federated learning. So
sharing of models um the weights and
gradients or the tunable parameters of
your models across different types of
networks and constellations. Maybe
they're not all you know collaborators
are part of the same group but they're
willing to coordinate with each other
and they have this as a method for doing
so. Um then there's the actual hardware
part where you really need to test for
interoperability. Um having all these
great ideas is one thing but showing
that it works is another. Um so you need
to do the testing for radio
interoperability um using uh mobile
network operators that are cooperative.
There are a lot that are very interested
in this right now. Um I also think it's
really important there is not a lot of
optical interoperability right now. the
optical terminals that exist um are not
really being built to compatible
standards and that's that's a problem.
So we want we want to see optical
interoperability um and standardization
other than just the SDA's um optical um
standards. So we we'd like we'd like
have a little bit more of an industry um
adoption of of that. Um and then I I'd
like to see this self-healing anomaly
resolution. So AI and ML on board doing
the telemetry monitoring trying to
create new ways to identify what has
been damaged or what function is lost
and either manage it gracefully or
correct it um and then um have more
self-aware connectivity to kind of res
reduce this interoperability problem and
the software turn on all the device
driver interfaces that we keep having to
reprogram over and over again. So, um,
that's kind of where I'd like like to
see this all go. Um, we're happy to work
with people on this. Um, we really enjoy
what we do here. If you can't tell
already from earlier today, there's been
so many great talks. So, ILP is
obviously a very good way for engaging
with us because they do a great job of
um, making sure they um, you know, I
don't know, smack around the professors
until we pay attention, show up, do the
things. Um, [laughter]
no, no, they're they're very very polite
and professional. Um, but getting our
attention can be hard and I I I I I
don't want to I don't want to discount
that. Um, sponsoring graduate research
on campus is a really good way of um
engaging with MIT. Um, you can sponsor
graduates or undergraduates. There's an
undergraduate research pro program that
you can bring in undergrads to work with
um to work with you. Um there's also a
even younger than undergraduate, high
school, and middle school outreach
program that MIT is a part of called the
Beaverwork Summer Institute. Um we're
happy to collaborate on calls for
proposals. Um you can hire MIT students
as interns. Um there's even a January in
between semester period that um students
will will happily go somewhere else for
um and you can even sometimes get them
over the semesters if they're grad
students who are done with their
classes. If grad students um have gotten
through their degree progress to the
point where they're done with their
classes, there's something called
non-resident graduate student status
where we have graduate students go work
at companies on their thesis problems
once they finished classes and that can
be very effective for companies as well.
Um we're happy to have you in to give
seminars. We're happy to have you talk
to undergrad or grad courses. Um we're
happy to go talk to you. Um so you can
invite us places and um um every few
years not nearly often enough we get
sbaticals and um on occasion we will
spend them at um a company or another
institution. So that's another great way
to work with us. Um but starting with
ILP is a great place. They know all
these things and are happy to help
connect you to the ones that you like
best. And um yeah, I'm happy to take
questions with that. So I I just that's
want to end with my tagline
[applause]
and happy to take questions.
>> Any questions out there?
>> Thanks.
>> Hi, it's great to hear about the smart
satellites. No, not to disparrage the
existing ones, but [laughter]
is is this sort of backwards compatible
or is it something where new satellites
are the ones that are going to be this
amazing?
>> Um, I think that the ability to
reprogram some of the existing
satellites is kind of limited. Um if
they are reprogrammable there's no
reason that they can't run algorithms on
board but getting the um configuration
set up so that
um they can route things to the right
buffers um after they run their you know
algorithms on the images um is a bit of
a big ask for for a lot of what many
operators build for. So I won't say no
but it's it's it's definitely a
challenge.
>> Okay. And a follow on uh so this sky
internet or Skynet
um we know that the internet is subject
to hacking. So if you're doing more
analysis on a satellite hopefully
someone's thinking about how to keep
that from getting compromised or
captured by somebody else.
>> Yeah. Yeah. No. Um
there is cyber security issues. Um
optical communication is a great initial
start, right? Because it's it's pretty
difficult to um contact things that you
don't know where they are, where to
point to exactly. So so that that's it's
not the only thing, right? But cyber
security and in integrating security
protocols is going to be um some
overhead that's necessary um and would
need to be incorporated in this. Um
training the eye to know friend or foe
commands would be very interesting. um
training it to know passwords and um
certain sequences of information um and
knowing when to send alerts when it's
asked to do interesting sequences of
things would be also something that you
can do with it. Um so I would I would
say that there's there's opportunity to
leverage that for security as well.
Hi. Uh, the satellite to satellite
communications is not super not a super
new idea.
>> No.
>> But the ability for
passing the information and then having
the satellites themselves make some
decisions, that is a new idea.
>> Yes.
>> Um, how far back does the satellite to
satellite go? I mean we know that SpaceX
has been doing it for
handling calls you know cell phone
calls.
>> Yeah.
>> But does that have a history?
>> It does. Um it goes back to um I mean
even before Aridium which was one of the
first in satellite to satellite um
constellations that the earlier ones
there was I think um Tellesat Global
Star which is still in existence you
know kudos to them. Um [laughter]
um so so the radio frequency um
intersatellite links have been in
existence for a while their their data
rates have been limited um the
interoperability has been limited um and
it's only just now that we're seeing
some of these NTN standards come in that
help break it open um to direct to
devices and make it both more
interesting and more potentially
profitable because you're talking about
not just contacting you know a limited
customer base but literally everyone
could use it. So that I think that's
kind of the the exciting part now
>> for for those guys. Anyway,
>> hi. Thank you, Professor Kai. As you
know, we're really excited our team uh
with what your team at Starlab is doing.
I was wondering, could you say more
above the clouds? Uh what do you see for
that opportunity with data data centers
or ways that the uh above the clouds
could be used both for Earth and also
for missions to moon, Mars, Aremis or to
Venus.
>> Oh, okay. One at a time. [laughter] So,
so for Earth, um I I think it's not
going to just be about finding what you
wanted to look for. Um but also being
able to
generate on the fly what's valuable at
that time to the people who are in your
service region, right? Um which is not
what we normally do. We normally
broadcast and send up the same thing and
pipe it down. So, I think I think
there's going to be an that that that
part is going to be exciting for for
Earth, I think. um for beyond Earth um
for exploration. Um yeah, I think having
that type having
247 reasoning and redundancy built into
some of our exploration initiatives is
going to be really enabling, right?
because right now we need mission
control running everything all of our
operations and um and everything is I
mean these poor groups I I don't say
poor they're very lucky I would have
killed to be them but like when you're
running on Mars time to operate your
Mars rovers and you're off by an hour
every day and you watch that kind of
go through a team's life that that's not
that's not easy and making it easier to
explore making it easier for these
things to um connect and alert us to
things I I mean, from autonomous
AI based sunflare monitoring networks,
right? You could you could set up those.
You could have asteroid monitoring
networks that are more self-aware and
self-reporting than just waiting for
something to get to an alert level and
for somebody's telescope to trigger on
it, right? So, like I I think these are
these are all exciting things that can
happen.
>> Yeah.
>> Um, thank you very much for the for the
presentation. It was really amazing to
hear all of the exciting things you work
on now particularly to the anomaly
detection end of things that you
mentioned. I was wondering in terms of
data because I can imagine there isn't
as much data right now available for
training models. So how do you go about
it like how was the data gathering? Do
you use synthetic data and how large are
the models we're talking about because I
think also there are constraints in term
of compute as well. Yeah.
>> Yeah. So the model that we were running
was able to run on a Raspberry Pi. It
was but it was supervised, right? So is
supervised trained on like a simulation
model. You're right that um people are
notoriously unwilling to separate
themselves from their data when things
go wrong. Um [laughter] they don't
really want that to get out. So um one
of the things that I was first when I
first started at MIT in 2011 that I was
really interested in was the effect of
radiation on satellites, right? But
getting anomaly data from satellite
operators, even though I worked at one
and I knew they had a bunch, um was very
difficult. People don't like to give it
up. So um so I think creating anonymized
agreements where you have access to some
of the data but it's it's anonymized and
you know abstracted in a way that you
still can get value out of it without
identifying you know the process IDs
from the satellite operators that tells
you oh it was a Lockheed Martin bus and
you know they had this problem all the
time like that that not that they did
I'm just making that up. Um um
[laughter] just an example um
um but but you see what I'm saying like
they wouldn't want that to get out right
so so if there was a effort to try to
have something like an MIT or a neutral
party that could guarantee anonymity and
abstraction to a collection of that
data. Um although there are companies
right now that actually charge money to
get access to anomaly data third party c
companies as well. So like it's it's you
either you work with them or you create
your own. But there are ways to do that.
The other way is to you know get enough
expert operators that they can tell you
what the key anomalies are and then like
we did create a a simulation set. So
yeah
>> thank you very much.
>> Great. Okay. Thanks. [applause]
>> So I don't want to keep anybody from the
uh the networking time for very long but
we uh we covered a lot of ground today.
uh everything from David Clark talking
about 300 kilobits per second dialup um
connecting mainframe computers to uh um
professor uh go here talking about uh
lasercom at satellites and putting AI in
space as well. So thanks for hanging in
there those of you who have hung with us
the whole day. Really appreciate it.
Please enjoy the networking session and
thanks for coming.