Originally from Africa, I grew up in America
and I always had the love of going back. When
I went back, I worked as a software developer, I
worked as a entrepreneur, I started a business,
and I worked as a policy adviser in government. I
got to see the country from many different angles.
One of the things I realized, the economic
models that I studied while I was in college,
I didn't have the opportunity to learn
how to apply those models to these poor
contexts. And that's what the DEDP program has
done for me. It has taken the everyday lives
of the people around me and has turned that
into so much more. It's given me the tools,
the frameworks to really understand
their lives from a deeper perspective.
MIT is one of the top universities in the
world. By studying in this DEDP program,
you can do very great things for your life, and in
turn, you can do very great things for the world.