[Music]
here I have a circuit with a battery
light bulb and GAP if I fill this Gap
with a metal the light comes on if I
fill this Gap with glass the light stays
off but what happens when I fill this
Gap with a silicon
wafer the light stays off so you might
think the silicon's an insulator but
what if I heat it
up it lights up
the Silicon is insulating at room
temperature but conducts electricity
when it's very hot it's a semiconductor
whose conductivity changes based on the
environment semiconductors have enabled
Electronics to become smaller faster and
more reliable you can cheaply add
transistors to almost any device you can
think of from spaceships to servers to
maybe even your toaster for more MIT
moments from MIT open learning like
subscribe or follow