In Mexico, I just have one sister. Here,
I have 30 sisters.
Coming here
and found these amazing women, amazing sisters,
has been very critical in my journey.
It’s a privilege to be surrounded by such an amazing group of people.
I felt much more alone before coming here.
And then when I met my female cohort, I felt,
“oh, wow, I'm not alone.”
Everybody has their own battles to fight.
And, you know, and it's not easy to get to where they are.
Usually,
you don't have
that example
that it's easy to relate to.
So these networks of women
helping women are very important.
The women in our cohort, I think they are,
in every dimension, unique and brilliant.
They are brave.
Very diverse.
And I think that's what makes us powerful.
Has like a lot of effort.
Extra effort. Has to be comparing to men.
I'm sorry to say that.
Interviewer: “Oh no, I take no offense.”
Smart and
funny and amazing and has done
so much in her life
and in her career that I'm just in
awe of, of all of them.
Kind of hard to articulate
what words to use.
They each have their story
and such a diverse background.
that when you hear them, it just really moves you and inspires you.
I remember
them telling us, like,
you are going to learn so much from your peers.
More than from professors or other people.
I was like,
okay, but like
we are all kind of the same.
But after some time
I was admiring so much
my friends, I never imagined
that I would admire so much
my peers.
You get examples of incredible leaders who are very humane, like really good people.
You're going to have people that come from like a science background,
military background, social sciences or entrepreneur background,
but all of them are really committed
to doing things better.
I just saw how everybody is committed
with ambitions,
with their desires to make an impact in the world.
So that's very powerful. The vibe is different
when you consider that.
People told me that this is a very collaborative place.
I didn’t really believe at the beginning, to be honest because I always
heard stories about those great MBA classes and schools where people are competing with each other.
At Sloan Fellows, it’s so different. It’s completely the opposite.
I love it.
There's a camaraderie of women
that are all strong women
who have really good careers and who want
to make a good impact in the world.
And we are working together as a group.
It's really important not just to have
them, but to have them for everything.
We have a logo that is “No Fellow Left Behind.”
And we do work with that.
We have an amazing woman in our program that graduated in economics
and she gave extra classes to help us with the exam.
You are safe to experiment anything.
You are safe to open up.
You are safe to say exactly how you feel.
We do cry sometimes.
And it’s impressive, like if one day you are down
there is a list of many names you can call just to come and help you and comfort you and hear you.
Many of us
come in to the program as
a blank sheet of paper.
That helped me to build the community of trust
so we can always rely on each other,
being able to share,
you know, what we are going through.
Either it's like the pressure from family.
“Why are you doing this?” Still when you're adapting to the new life.
Being a mid-career professional
a lot of the time means you have a spouse
and you have a family
and for woman, even in 2023
or 2024
for a woman to be the one
to take her family through this shift,
especially if they're not from the U.S.
and not from Boston,
and most of the program
isn't because we're super international.
Taking the family through that shift,
being a woman is still something
that is not very common and not
not a lot
of societies and not a lot of,
communities will accept that.
Everybody was very courageous
and has to be courageous for everyone
to actually pause their career.
Say no to the promotion.
For a woman to come here, for a mid-career
woman to come here,
there are so many hurdles
she had to go through in her life.
There was a moment of time
that people experienced doubts.
“Am I doing the right thing?”
You know, “would I be able
to continue my progression when I go back?”
“Would I be able to pivot to
to where I want to go?”
So we support each other by that.
We bounce ideas off each other.
One of the things that I've appreciated
the most was to hear,
to experience the
background, the culture, the perspective
of so many different people.
And that gives you a different awareness
about where you are,
about what you do.
We need to surround ourselves with people that our actually going to bring us
forward and not backwards.
So that was something I learned in the program.
As we share, we are learning.
We are learning from each other.
We are learning
from completely different experiences.
Very diverse industries,
very diverse type of lifestyles.
But at the same time
we share meaningful stories
of the way we see life.
Sometimes I think we we make up excuses
to have coffee together,
just to have those type of conversations
and laugh about ourselves.
I think about Victoria
and I think about Diana.
When I look at them, you know,
they really inspire me to want to be
better and, you know, see life
like they see it from their point of view.
They motivate me
and they bring that youthfulness
type of energy out of me
when I'm around them.
And they have really just pushed me to
like, for example, today I went sailing.
I've never done sailing in my life.
So they both took me in.
They were like, Erika, you cannot be in
Boston and not do sailing.
I probably would have never done it
on my own just because,
hey, it's not a priority for me,
but, doing it with them
just brought so much more meaning to it.
we like us so much that you're
trying stuff different just because
we want to get closer or we want to...
we want to know better each other.
And you're doing stuff
that you are not going to do by yourself.
When you see your peers, alumni,
the people that came before you
and you see all the incredible
accomplishments that they've done,
it makes you feel very good about yourself.
Like, oh, I'm in, this is a nice club.
but also, it makes me think that this is a tool
that I can use to create impact.
Whenever you have the opportunity
to get to other networks, scopes
greater or bigger than the ones
that you have previously experience,
go for them because you don't know
how they are going to affect you,
but they will change you, for sure.