Thank you. Hello, I'm Peter Schmidt,
co-founder, CEO at Fluent Metal, where
we inventing the future of metal 3D
printing.
What carried me away was watching our
advisory co-founder, John Hart, speak
just a couple of minutes ago, freely
walking around the stage. I'm sorry.
3D printing in general, metal 3D
printing as well still has a very strong
promise.
It is very useful and it going to be
needed in fusion reactors, hypersonics,
electric vehicles, server farms,
consumer products, all of those need
complex
metal components made from special
metals with integrates design.
The problem we're seeing is current
manufacturing and that involves metal
additive as it's practiced today cannot
deliver on those materials geometries
and they cannot deliver at an
economically feasible um cost.
What does fluent metal do? If there's
one thing I want you to take away from
the five minutes we have together today,
I want you to remember fluent metal is
printing metal differently just like
inkjet printers but with molten metal
droplets instead of ink droplets. So
what we're doing is we take a fine
microwire. We heat up the tip of the
fine microwire with a plasma within
several milliseconds grows into a ball.
We go through a hygiene event, separates
the ball into an airborne droplet, flies
to the substrate. We introduce
a heat budget, meaning more more we're
printing at higher temperatures than
melting, and that enables the drop to
have a metallergical bond at the
substrate.
We can do that with any metal that comes
in wire form. And we can do this in
parallel with the same metal or we can
do this in different metals, multi
metals.
So what are the advantages of practicing
metal additive metal 3D printing this
way? We are really really cost
efficient. Our system architecture uh
allows uh for scalable um throughput
and
large reduction in cost. We have a
materials portfolio that no other metal
additive process has. We can print
straight off of wire. So we can print
anything in wireform including all the
alloys that everyone is looking after
which cannot be delivered by powder bed
processes.
We and that also includes uh high metal
high high melting temperature metals
like refractory metals. It also includes
amorphous metals. Um just had a really
um promising collaboration there with um
with a team a research team in in
amorphous metals. We can print on many
different um substrates. Um we could
print on plastics, we can print on
metal, we can print on single on
straight double curved surfaces. Um
everything no problem. And then the most
important point, we're not moving a melt
pool around. So we're not putting a lot
of heat into any um substrate substrate.
So that it's also a big advantage of our
process. We do have an industrial uh
approved um use case. Um it's uh an OEM
manufacturer where we are applying a
layer of bronze onto an existing layer
of stainless steel which is part of an
assembly
and that's the reason why the
requirement is there to not heat up the
top surface more than 80° centigrade
which with um a direct energy deposition
or a part of laser is is is not
achievable. uh our process works uh no
problems for the metallergy and we've
proven um sample parts and going into a
pilot production with this uh OEM
currently.
We're here today looking for
partnerships um seeking uh
collaborations.
We're looking for partners in the energy
defense and automotive industry
ideally with experience in metal
additive and with problems that we
hopefully be able to solve better than
what you're currently doing. We do have
a desk next door. Uh my colleague Mario
uh myself will be there. Um would love
to yeah for you guys to stop by have
some conversations. Thank you very much.