Okay. So let's so assume that again that
we have a so this here is a sequence
then we can form from a sequence we can
find we can form another sequence. So
from
from a end we can form
another sequence.
uh at least if um at least
if a end is bounded from above.
So we can form another sequence and
that's what we we take
uh bn
is going to be the soup of the set
of a starting at n. So this here is is
oops this here is the the sequence bn.
Okay.
And so right again implicitly here we
are assuming so assume
that uh that there exist
some c so that for all n
uh a n is less than c in other words c
are bounded from above right so if we If
we if the sequence a n is bounded from
above then this here gives us a real
number
uh and we see
and we see that since if you're looking
at uh bn + one this is now soup of a n +
one a n + 2
and this here is soup over a smaller
set. So this here is less than the soup
where we do it over where we take soup
over a larger set.
Right?
And that here is BN.
So we have that if you take any sequence
then you can and let's say that that
sequence is bounded from above then you
can find another you can form another
sequence BN and BN here is mono
decreasing right
if
if also if the sequence
BN is bound from below
then uh then the BN here in the sequence
here converge and it converts to the
infam right this is this uh with mono
convergent sequences it's converging to
the infimum of the BI
like that.
Okay.
Now, um
[Applause]
and and likewise, so likewise, although
we won't really use this here. So,
likewise, but likewise,
Um again if you take if a n is any
sequence any sequence
this time I want it to be bounded from
below
then you can find a sequence then you
can form from a n you can form a
sequence uh cn and cn is just where
you're taking the infam one starting at
a end,
right? And you see that if you're
looking at CN + one, then you take the
infom over a smaller set.
So this is a smaller set and so this
here is bigger than where you're taking
the info from a end
and that's CN. So the sequence CN is
therefore monotone increasing and if it
is bounded. So if CN is bounded from
above
is bounded from above.
Then the sequence CN converge to some C.
And that sea is just a soup of the of
the seas,
right?
And so and we talked a little bit about
this earlier, right? And the thing is
that but now we will use it in just a
second.
The thing is so that in the first case
here we call B here B is written as a
lem
soup of of the of the an
and in the second case it's called the
lem in
uh of of the a
okay
now
so why is this relevant here for us so
what we were looking at last time So
last time and I'm only going to use the
lem soup. So last time
we had a sequence. So a n is a sequence
or was a sequence
and we looked we defined what we call a
power series. And again power series
think about that x as being just some
fixed number
and you have the sequence a n x is some
fixed number and then you form the
sequence a n xn right
and so for each x fixed this gives you
some number maybe if it converge I mean
you can ask for each x you can ask does
this sequence converge or
And this here is called a power series.
So you're suming from zero to whatever
or you're signing from one or whatever
you're starting with up to infinity. So
this here is a power series.
And so now it for power says the the the
question is
how serious is the question is what
about for which
for which
X does it converge.
Okay, so that's what we're interested in
and what we looked at last time.
So just let me remind you because we're
going to use that anyway in a minute
last time. So example
from last time
Well, the example we looked at last time
was we're looking at xn. I mean, we
looked at some other examples too, but
this was the one we focused on.
So, this here is a power series. The a n
in this case here
are one over n factorial, right?
So now uh and we and for each fixed x so
for for x fixed
we looked at whether or not this
sequence converge and so we defined we
think about this thing here we thought
this here we thought about it as just a
sequence like this
sum of of a sequence so this is as a
series like is where the dn here is now
x to the n / n factorial right
and so in order to determine for which x
it converge so just think about x as
being fixed we use the ratio test
so we use the ratio test
and the ratio test um said that If
you're looking at dn + 1 / dn,
this here is well dn is just x to the n
+ 1 / n + 1 factorial divided by x to
the n / n factorial.
And that's the same, right? So when you
divide by a fraction, you just switch,
right? So this is the same as x to the n
+ 1 / n + 1 factorial * n factorial * x
to the n. And you just think about this
the top here as x n * x * n factorial.
And the denominator you think about as n
+1 * n factorial * x. You see that this
here and this here cancel with those two
and so you get x / n +1
and this here converts to zero right so
therefore the power series is convergent
for all x
now so that was a particular example of
a power series right but so uh and and
and it worked uh well with ratio test,
but but the root test actually is
better. And this was related to a point
somebody raised uh last time. And the
point was like you know like for the
ratio test it was you know implicitly
somehow in the ratio test was something
about that from a some stage on the next
element is smaller than the previous one
and you don't really need to have that
uh uh you know I mean you certainly
don't need it for a series to converge
but but it's not even necessary if you
apply the right test right
and so
so this come this this this bring us to
what's called the radius of convergence
so so this is a a crucial concept
and why it is crucial concept because
you see appro what you could imagine so
suppose you just take
suppose you just write down a power
shares like this
appro
maybe like that it's convergent for at
when x is equal to 5 it's divergent when
x is equal to 10 and maybe it's
convergent again if x is equal to 20
right that's not actually going to be
the case so there's something called
radius of convergence
and the radius of convergence
And the thing is that what you get out
of this radius of convergence is that a
power series like this is convergent on
some interval and then outside this
interval it's divergent.
So it's not like you have some that is
convergent here it's divergent there and
then it's like converging again. Right?
That's not what's going to happen. Okay,
part of this is also we already saw this
in the different test that there is at
the boundary of this interval it's it's
not it's it's the test is inconclusive.
So you have to check the boundary
separately. Okay.
And so so the idea is that you take so
you you have a power series like this
and you think about again you're
thinking about dn as x to the n x again
is is thought of being fixed and now you
apply the root test. So apply the root
test but I'm going to apply it in a in a
better form than what we did last time.
Maybe I'll just state first first the
better form of the root test. So here's
the sort of
um
here's the the real version of the root
test.
So suppose you take a series.
Suppose you have some serious here.
This is let's call it the end.
Suppose you take a series like this
if you're looking at so now you the root
test right you took dn you took the
absolute value and you took the nth root
right
when I looked at the root test last time
we looked at whether this is convergent
or not right so we said if it was
converging to something, right? But you
could just take you could form this
thing here. So you could form from from
this here you could form this. This is
now a sequence and you could look at lim
soup of this.
This these here are all non- negative
numbers. Right? So um so uh and this le
soup here is now going to be either
infinite or it's going to be some real
non- negative number right this here is
going to be infinite usually we don't
talk about that it's converging if it's
infinite or it's it's some number
um let's call it let's call it d I guess
but
Okay.
And the thing is that if you're looking
at if you set r equal to 1 /d
right sorry no if you're setting uh if
so so so this is just the root test the
sort of adult version of the root test
because this apply to all sequences
right for any sequence you have this for
any sequence dn if you're looking at
this series you can look at this right
and it's either infinity or d
and then if d here is less than one then
the series is convergent.
If d is bigger than one, the series is
divergent.
And if d is equal to one, it's
inconclusion,
right? The difference between this and
what we talked about last time was that
last time we assume that this thing here
converge here I'm not assuming it but
I'm then I'm looking at the lem soup
instead. Right? So this is does give us
a number.
Okay. And it's just a matter of whether
the slim soup is smaller than one
and then it's convergent or bigger than
one then it's divergent.
Okay. Now I'll come back to to the proof
but the proof is really kind of the same
as the one we gave. the one we gave
really, you know, the if you kind of
mimic what we did uh in the special case
last time, then the proof would still
apply to this case here and give this
result.
Okay. So now, but let's let's take this
this more fancy version of uh the root
test. Let's take that for granted.
And so
so now
so now I have
a power shares like this. I just for for
you know for for clarity I define dn to
be just a n
time xn and I'm interested in is for
what x
for what x
does it converge does the power series
convert
Okay. Now,
so now you see that so lem soup.
So you you were looking at lim soup of
the nth root of d n is a n * xn
and you take the absolute value of that
right that's that's what you're looking
at and you asking is this smaller than
one or bigger than one
but this thing here
right this is the same as sou right if
you're looking at this thing here let's
do a
side calculation. If you're looking at
the nth root
of uh a n * xn,
this thing here is the same as the nth
root of this product here. Absolute
value is the same as this times x
absolute value to the n.
And when you take the nth root, you may
as well take the nth root of each of
those two factors individually.
So this is what you get.
But this thing here, you see this thing
here, the end root, this here is
whatever it is.
Can't do much about that.
But this thing here, that's just the
norm of x, right? The norm of x has the
property that when you raise it to the n
power you're getting this right. So this
is the end.
Okay. So this means that this thing here
is the same as the norm of x limb soup
of the nth root of a n.
Right?
Often you do it like this. You don't
have to do this. It's usually clear
anyway. But it off you write like that.
Okay. So now what you do is so you you
want you asking when is this number here
smaller than one when is it bigger than
one right? And so you have that you see
now you define something that's called
the radius of convergence.
And so this is the following. So the
radius of convergence
is oops
radius of convergence is
so this is just radius
of convergent.
The radius of convergence is just a
number
and that number is radius of convergence
and we have to just interpret it a
little bit. So it's one over lim super
of of the nth root.
This thing here could of course be
infinite.
If this here is infinite then the radius
by definition this here would be zero.
Right? Right? Where this here is equal
to zero. If
there's lean soup uh
is infinite and otherwise right it's a
it's always a right otherwise yeah
there's one other case you have to
define that if uh it's infinite if the
lem soup
sorry this should be absolute value if
this lem soup
is true and otherwise otherwise it's a
you know otherwise there's nothing to
you know it's a well you know that's the
only thing you have to comment right
because otherwise it's it's it's always
a non- negative number but it could be
zero or it could be infinity but if it's
any other number then it is just what
you think it should be is one over that
number
okay so this gives you this is this here
r here is the radius of convergence okay
and Now the the thing is that now we
have the following symbol picture.
So now we have that. So you have this
power series
again it doesn't matter what you start
with the sum matters what you start with
but not the convergence. So you have
this power series you are forming a
This is the radius of convergence.
And then the claim is and again this
could be zero it could be infinity but
often it's just a a real number non-
negative real positive real number and
so it say that if you take the interval
here around zero in the interval
from minus r to r then inside this
interval here inside here when x is in
here then the Power series
is convergent
and when X is here or here
power series is divergent
and then when X's is here or here at
those two points then it's and clear and
further test is needed.
Further test is needed.
Test are needed.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
less than one.
>> Yeah. So that's right. So so let's come
to the proof. Yeah. So this is what
you're talking about. So
So this is this is the the radius of
convergence, right? And so as you say
um all we need to do is right but we
know from this from the more fancy
version of the ratio test that is in
terms of leap soup we know that so so
prove here
power series is convergent by the ratio
test by the by the ratio test,
not a ratio test. Sorry, the root test
by the root test.
So again, the version the version the
lem soup version,
not the one I talked about last time,
but this one we just talked about, but
the lem soup version of the ratio root
test,
then the power series is converging. If
this thing here, so this means that this
thing here. So if this thing here
li
of a nth
root
if this thing here is less than one,
it's divergent.
If this thing here
is bigger than one and it's inconclusive
and it's and it's inconclusive if this
thing here
is equal to one here it's inconclusive.
But now you see that this here this here
just means that the norm of X should be
smaller than one over that. Right? So
this here is is is
the same as saying that the norm of X is
smaller than R the radius of
convergence. Right?
This here is saying this is equivalent
to saying that the norm of x is bigger
than uh than r
right and this here is equivalent to
saying that the norm of x is equal to r.
Okay. So so that is the that is the so
that's a radius of convergence. So you
see so this is like you know a pure this
is not at all clear
that it couldn't be that a power series
couldn't be convergent for like you know
some sort of discrete set of of x but
that's not the case right it's it's
convergent on some interval it's unclear
at the at the end of that interval but
it is convergence on an interval and
divergent outside that interval now that
interval could be just zero
Or it could be all of R. Right.
But it is also symmetric around zero.
Yeah.
>> Right. So it's so it's one over this
here. But remember how R was defined. R
is up there.
>> Yeah.
Okay.
Now
um let me just say a word
about why does the proof from last time
why does it really prove this more you
know I mean the sort of argument we gave
last time
why does it give you this much more sat
I mean it's much more satisfying this
version of the root test because it
apply to any series right the because
otherwise we talk about whether some
ratio was convergent but it may not
converge right so this is much more
satisfying so suppose again you have a
series like this
and so now you form you're looking at
lem soup so this here is again this is
the root test
root
test
version, let's call it version 2.0,
right? And so it take um series like
this and it's
it's looking at le soup and then the nth
root of the absolute value of dn
and again it say that if this thing here
is e is less than one it's convergent.
If it's bigger than one, it's diverging
and if it's equal to one, it's
inconclusion.
Okay. Now let's let's try to see why
this here why this here is the case. So
proof of
of root test
version 2.0.
So now may maybe I won't do all of it
but let's just say let's just look at
because you see in a minute you see that
it's really kind of super similar to
last time. So suppose that this limit
suppose
that this limb soup
of the nth root here of dn suppos
supposed that this thing here
is equal to some d which is strictly
less than one.
Okay. So this means that there exist
uh
they exist.
So choose if you will choose
uh d
bar
will
uh d less than d bar strictly less than
strictly less than one.
Right? So I can choose it like this.
But now you see that if I choose it like
this then there exist
that so remember that let's just remind
ourselves that
how was the lim soup defined
the limb soup was defined
to be
that you take this new sequence so
you're taking this sequence here
to You're taking
these guys here.
So you're looking at now these guys here
and you are taking a you define a
sequence that is like the soup starting
at the nth guy
and like this here.
Sorry this here is n plus one
etc. Right.
Right. This is the soup of the tail,
right? And so this was this was that it
was soup on as you're going further out,
you're taking soup over a smaller set.
So these this sequence going down,
right? So now if this limit here is some
D which is strictly less than D bar then
it means that there exist so there exist
capital N. So that if little n is bigger
than capital n then all of these guys
here is less than d bar. Right? So this
here is so that so if this here then all
of these guys here is less or equal to d
bar this is if little n if you starting
that far out right
but so now you see that so you have that
when n is bigger than this you have that
this so you have that for all these guys
here dn the nth root is less then d bar
less or equal to d bar.
But now you take the nth root the nth
power on both sides. So you have that dn
absolute value is less than d bar the n
power. This here is d is is and n is
this is even actually not negative. So
you don't even need this absolute value
sign. So you're having this but this is
a number that is strictly less than one.
So this here is a geometric series right
geometric series
with where where where
d bar is less than one. So it's is a
convergent geometric series. Right? So
this is you see that it was it's
basically the same proof we did last
time but last time we were assuming that
some ratio was convert you know or some
we were consuming assuming that this
this here converge to something but you
don't need it to converge you just need
that this soup is is um is is less than
one
and so likewise if you examine what this
case here say then just like last time
it's going to say that if this here is
bigger than one then the ordinary
element doesn't even go to zero. Okay.
So it it fails the most basic test for
being convergent. Okay. So and that was
just like last time also and and again
the advantage is saying you were the one
that was asking yesterday. Yeah. I mean
like last time this with a ratio test
and the root test and and like in the
ratio test it's something about that the
next element is some you know is going
down with some fraction right and here
and you very much see that like this
here works for all series right and it's
really just because you don't compare
the element to the next but you're
comparing it to this fixed um
series which is a geometric is
okay.
So that's that's like the
uh that's the the the the real version
uh so to speak of the of the boot test.
So now let's
let's talk a little bit more about power
series.
So
and I want to talk about so like there's
one function that is particular
important
and I mean like all of these sort of
basic functions are of course important
but they are somewhat similar and uh the
one I want to talk about is the
exponential function
And and there's various way that you
could define so what is the exponential
function? There's various ways that you
could define the exponential function.
You can define it, you know, like two
that comes to mind, but there's others
too. One is that you could define it to
be a function that's satisfying a
certain differential equation and that
would be a good way of defining it.
Another way of defining it which is more
relevant to what we're doing here is
defining it as a power series.
So I'm looking at
but at e to the x
and um and I'm looking at e to the x. So
I define e capital e of x as this power
series that we looked at before.
Okay.
Now I want to prove that this here is
really what you should think of this.
This here is the exponential function.
So so I want to show but what does it
mean that it is expon want to show
that
this is
the exponential function. So what do I
mean by I mean of course I could
you know I could define any function to
be the exponential function but there
are certain properties of the
exponential function that you would want
right and so um well the first thing I
observe is that e of zero
is equal to if if all of these if x is
zero then all of these are zero except
when n is equal to zero and then x to
the zero this here is by definition one
okay and this here is is zero factorial
is by definition one so this here is is
one by definition
and we know already by the way that this
here we have already seen that the
radius of convergence for this power
series
of convergence
is equal to infinity right we have
already seen that right so it's a well-
definfined function for all x okay now
I'm later going to prove so next time
we will show
that if you define it like that that
that that this function here defined
like that has a property that x e to x +
y
is equal to this product here.
Okay.
Now uh using this well the first thing I
can observe is I haven't really gotten
to the property yet but I'm just at the
moment I'm just examining that
particular function you know some
properties that it has
and so the first thing I will observe is
that if x here is positive or non-
negative right then all of these numbers
are non- negative so you're summing non-
negative numbers so the sum is non-
negative
So if
x is bigger equal to zero then it
implies that e of x is big is actually
strictly positive
right in fact the smallest one is where
you x was equal to zero but in that case
you got one right
now if x here is negative then it's not
super clear right if x is negative you
know some of these numbers that you'll
be summing are positive and some of them
are negative. So it's not at all clear
what happened to the sum. But if if you
grant me this for the for the moment
this relationship here then we would
have that e to the x minus e to minus
sorry e in x - x. So that's the same as
let me just make a little more space
here. So e of zero which I already know
is one. This here can think about that
as x - x
or if you will you could think about it
as x + - x.
And now if you grant me this this thing
here that we prove next time then I can
write this here as e
of x * e of minus x right
uh yeah sorry yeah
okay and now if x here is negative then
of course minus x is positive
So this thing here. So now I know by
this thing here that this here is
positive.
And so since the product of these two
things is one, this here must be
strictly positive as well. Right? So
this imply that e to the x is also
strictly positive.
Okay?
So this is just a couple of observation.
Now, of course, I'm using that
relationship that I haven't established
yet, but I will establish that next
time.
The next thing is that I want to define
the number E.
And so I define this.
So E that is 2.7 whatever I don't
remember. Uh but so E we define so
little E. So I define it as this
function here
evaluated in one. Okay.
Now I want to define so I have my
function capital E but I want to define
a second function that is E. So, so want
to define
a second function
and that is e to the x like this, right?
And that should have the kind of
properties that you uh that you think it
should have. Okay? So but first before I
do that let me just think if if you take
e to the power m m here
m is let's say that m here
uh let's say that m is a is a integer
if if um this here this here should just
be
e * E
M*s
right
note that this here is this here I can
of course write as E
this is what E is so I can write it as
this here
M times
but now I can use this hair that I will
prove next time again. So if I take E of
1 * E of 1 then that's E of two. And if
I take E here three times then it's E of
three. Right? So this thing here is
actually the same as capital E of M.
Right?
So I have that.
I also by definition so
e to the zero this here I'm setting
equal to one but I already have that one
was equal to this capital e in in in
zero right
okay now what about if m here is a
negative integer
So suppose that m here is a negative
integer. Suppose that m here is
negative.
So sorry what should e to the m here be?
This here is just one over e to the
minus
uh m. Okay, minus m is a positive
integer, right? So this so this makes
sense.
Now
if you're looking at
E
to the again using this relationship
here E the one and in fact the one we
just did.
So this is on integers
um this here is now equal to E of zero
which is equal to one.
And so this imply and this is by this by
that relationship over there. It's E of
M * E of minus M. And so you see that
this implies that E of minus M is equal
to 1 / E of M by just dividing this on
both sides. So you have this and this
thing here. But this thing here,
sorry, this is not what I wanted. Uh, if
I take M negative, I just use the other
one. Sorry, e of M
is equal to 1 / E of minus M like that,
right?
M is M was supposed to be negative. So,
this means that minus M is a positive
integer. And this one here is then this
one. I know that this here already agree
with uh
with um with uh this little function of
e. So you see that this thing here is
agrees with e to the power m. Right.
Right. Because we we defined it like
this. And now just checking that also on
the negative integer this function here
and this function here agree. Okay. So,
so I now have these two different
functions. Well, one I haven't really
defined yet. I've only defined it now on
all integers.
But, but so far these two functions
agree.
Now what I also should have is that I
should have so suppose you're looking at
a rational number.
So suppose you take a rational number.
Remember we usually write a rational
number. So suppose that Q here is a
rational number. We usually write a
rational number as
a
as an element in set. So it could be
negative, it could be zero and n here is
a positive integer. So fraction like
this.
Now what should E
of Q be? Right?
Well, E of Q um this here should be
right how you would think about it is
that it really should be something
it should be something this here should
be a number should be a number alpha and
this should have the property that is
positive
and it should have the property so let's
just write it so so E of Q this is m /
n. It should have the property that if
you raise it alpha here suppose you were
raising it to the power n then you
should get this number that we have
already defined right. So should have it
should be positive and when you raise it
like this um then it should give you
that and just like with square root of
two it's just one element with this
property
okay so that's defined uh what it so so
this way you see this way we have now
defined
this function e on all rational numbers
but now we need to check right we need
to check that this thing here need to
check. So
that that
EQ
is equal
like that. Right? So I need to check
that. Okay?
So
I want to say that that E to the Q is
that alpha, right?
So this means that
I want to show
so I need to show two things
E
to Q is positive. Well, I've already
checked that right because you check at
at E capital E at anything is positive.
So this is okay. The second thing I need
to check is that it has the property
that if you raise it to the n power then
you're getting uh then you're getting e
um e to the to the m
right now e to the m that's an integer.
It could be negative
but e to any negative integer whether
it's ne positive or or negative we
already checked that this is equal to
capital e of m.
Okay.
So now I need to so this here is so now
what is this? So what do I need to
check? So I need to check
that e
to the m / n. This thing here raised to
the power n is equal to this. But but
what is this here? This here is just e
to the m / n
time multiply itself n times.
So this is now n times.
But now I can use again this thing that
I proved next time that when I do it
like here I'm just doing it two times
and here I'm just doing it for I'm doing
it for different x and y. But if I do it
n times with the same x then I'm just
adding that x together n times.
Right?
And so this thing here is the same as e
by that rule over there n * m / n but
this is just e of m as it should be
right. So you see that these two
functions here. So the conclusion so far
is
the conclusion now is that
this function here
is equal to this function here for all
Q
for all rational numbers. Okay.
Now what other property should this
exponential? So this here you know so
far this is kind of the property that
you want of the exponential function
right but what other property should the
exponential function have it should have
one other property and that's enough to
determine it and that is it should be
continuous. So one more property is that
this function e to the x when x is
defined like this this function
should be continuous
and we'll talk a little bit more about
continuous function in just a second.
Okay. Now, now then I have a theorem
that we prove next time
one of the next times and and that is
that suppose you take two functions.
So so we then can appeal to the
following theorem.
If f and g are two
continuous functions
on a
that agree
on all
of do.
So if you have two continuous functions
and they if you restrict it to the
rational number then the two functions
are the same.
If they're both continuous then the
function has to be the same. So this
implies that f is equal to g everywhere
not just on the rational function
rational numbers.
Okay. So we'll prove that either next
time or the following time. Let me just
go back and remind you
about what it means for a function to be
continuous.
Uh so
so this is the fine
so continuous.
So suppose you take a function and the
function uh is it doesn't even need to
be defined on an interval. Um
I but you may as well assume that it's
interval but it doesn't need to be
defined on the interval.
So a function here f is set to be
continuous
be continuous
at x here
in the domain where it's defined.
If
for all
epsilon greater than zero
there exist
delta greater than zero such that
if x - x0
is smaller than delta then the images
are epsilon close to each
And so again this delta typically
depends not just on epsilon but also on
x0 right and so the function so this is
so it's continuous at a point x0 if this
here is the case and the function f here
is set to be continuous
If
it is
continuous
at all points.
Okay.
Now let's just let's let's look at two
simple examples and and and and
then once we have those
uh then together with some algebraic
rules that are similar to the algebraic
rules that we had for sequences
then we get a huge
number of examples of you get a large uh
collection of examples of continuous
functions.
So the first example is like the
simplest of all example
where f here is is the constant
function.
So I'm thinking about f here is to be
defined from r into r and for each x in
r it's equal to the same constant. Okay.
So that's f. I want to show that this f
is that a constant function is
continuous. So given so proof
of continuity.
So given epsilon
given epsilon greater than zero in this
part says you can pick any delta you
want. I'm just picking
let
delta be equal to one but you could pick
anything you want. It has to be positive
but you can pick anything you want. Then
you have that if x minus x0
is less than one.
Well then of course f ofx
minus f of x0 both of these numbers is
c. So the difference so this is c minus
c.
So this is zero. So this is surely less
than epsilon. Right? So they show that
it's the function is continuous at all
point. And you see that you could pick
delta anything you want. And of course
in particular it's it's doesn't even
depend on x0. It doesn't depend on
epsilon and it doesn't depend on x0.
Okay. So the constant functions are for
continuous.
What about then next simple the next
simplest function would be the linear
function or just x function x.
So suppose you take
because you're looking at
at the function f on r to r
where f of x is equal to x. So this is
also continuous
and the proof of that
given epsilon
set
delta equal to epsilon
then you see that if x - x0
is less than epsilon then
uh f ofx minus f of x0 but f of x is
equal to x and f of x0 is equal to x0 so
this thing here is of course less than
epsilon not right
so this is so so so that's kind of
trivial okay
now the next thing is that we have uh
the algebraic uh property of continuous
functions. So we have some as a break
property.
properties
of continuous function
and I will prove a couple of these and
but the proofs you see in just a second
that the proof is like I mean the
properties is is is and There's good
reasons for that. They're very similar
to the property we had for for limits of
sequences and the proofs are are very
similar to those proofs. So the first
one is that if
f and g are continuous
then the sum of these two functions is
also continuous.
The next one is that if um
f is continuous
and and c is a constant
then c * f is continuous.
The third property is
that again if
uh f comma g are continuous
then the product
then the product f * d is continuous.
The fourth property is that if
f is continuous
and and uh and f is never equal to zero
then
1 / f is continuous.
And the fifth property that's a little
bit different and we didn't have that
for sequences.
The fifth property is that if you take a
map f of take a function f.
Let's think about it as a function from
R to R. And then you have another
function G from R to R.
And now you could look at where you take
first. You could look at the
composition. So you could look at the
function H of X which is where you first
apply F of X F to X and then you apply G
to it. Right? So if both f so if this
here
and the function g are continuous
then the composition here is also
continuous.
When you have a composition of function
you always have to be careful that it
makes sense. So to make sense means that
the function g the one that the second
function that you apply is that the
image of when you use the first function
you have to make sure that what you get
here is uh at some point where G is
defined. Right? So I just for simplicity
I just uh looked at maps into um
functions into R where G also was
defined on all of our but of course it
doesn't have to be defined but you just
have to make sure
that G is defined where F and X end up
right
okay I'll talk a little bit about you
know these uh how to prove these but
it's very similar to what we did for
sequences let me just apply apply it.
So let me look at an example where I
apply it.
So suppose you take x2 + one. Suppose
you take this function here. I'll take
look at two examples.
Suppose you take this function here.
I claim that this here is continuous.
I'm not going to go through the proof
because
because we already actually so if this
here prove at least some of these
properties but once you have that then
you see that well you have that g of x
equal to x this here is continuous.
This is what we proved
just a little while ago. And if you take
the function that is constant and in
this case constant one, we already
proved that that's continuous. Right?
Now this means that if you take a
continuous function
by by by whatever root three or
something like that over there uh and
you take the function where it's like
multiply by itself this function here
right because g is continuous this
function here is also continuous
and then once you have that you can add
another. So you can look at G ^2
plus H.
This is you now have established this is
continuous. This here is a constant
function. So we already proven that this
is continuous. So the sum by rule one
over there this here is continuous.
Okay.
So this means that so okay. So this show
that this function here this quadratic
function is continuous. But in fact of
course this argument gives you that any
polomium any polomial is continuous
right so this here proves that any
polomium
right so this the you know like the
similar argument right so if you're
using so if you're using one two and
three
then just starting at the constant
function and the function x you can get
to any polomium and and and using these
operations and so it means that any
polomial is continuous right so so you
have the following theorem
all polomials
are continuous
Okay. And in fact, so this is just using
one, two, and three over here. If you
now also bring in four
then you have then so so this is this is
proof,
right? So it follows it uses the two
examples that we gave and then
in addition to that it follows from
the algebraic rules
one through uh one through three.
If you bring in alt four, five is
something slightly different. But if you
bring in four here, then you you get
that what's called any rational function
uh any
all rational function
are continuous. So what is a a rational
function?
A rational function is just where you're
taking a polomial
and then you're dividing by another
polinomial.
Right? So we know that any polomial is
continuous. If you take another polomium
and let's look at the that other
polinomial away from the roots away from
where it is zero away from it where it's
zero this is I mean it's of course even
continuous where it's zero but you can't
divide by it right so away from it this
function here is not zero and it's
continuous this is continuous rule four
so this is proved
Uh the theorem above
plus
rule four,
right? Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. In that case, exactly. In that
case, I chose delta to be simply
epsilon. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Anything with that first?
>> That's not a problem, right? But it's
just like if you give me an epsilon,
then I have to pick a a delta. And
typically the delta will depend on
epsilon.
Typically, it also depends on x. Let me
give you an example of the last. I don't
think I I I might not get to to proving
this, but that's fine. I mean they
actually the proof I'm not even sure I
would go through it but the proof is if
maybe maybe if I have a minutes I will
talk about one of them.
So let me give you an example also where
so typically
typically it's it's highly unusual in
the first example with a constant
function that it doesn't really matter
you could pick delta anything. Okay. Now
suppose you're looking at the function f
ofx = 1 /x. This is a rational function
because it's a polomial. In that case
the polomial in the denominator is the
constant function one and then the
denominator is is is x. If you're
looking at this function let's just look
at this function where it's pos strictly
positive. Right? And then you see now
the graphs looks basically like this.
So in particular if you go close to zero
it's not defined as zero but if you go
close to zero then the image varies a
lot right. So if you take some fixed
thing here suppose you take suppose you
take suppose you take you want to prove
that it's continuous at some extreme.
So this means that you have to pick some
delta. So given an epsilon you have to
pick a delta. So that if you are in this
little interval then image lie in that
little interval. But you see that as x0
becomes very close to zero then in any
small interval the function varies a
lot. So this means that that if if you
take some fixed epsilon
then you expect that if the x0 was close
to zero then the delta had to be really
really really small right for this to
work right so typically delta depends
not just on epsilon which it's I mean
it's highly unusual it doesn't it also
depends on x and in fact if it doesn't
depend on x or extra then it has a
particular name. We'll get to that
later. It's called uniform continuity.
Uniform continuity have some nice extra
properties
and and and and you will see later on
that there's a good reason why the
domain here was did not include zero. If
somehow this is would have been a
continuous function defined on an
interval that included the end point
then actually it would automatically be
uniform continuous. So so it was the
good reason this example here it didn't
include the the the point zero. Okay.
Now let me just so I have like three
minutes left. Let me just talk about
one particular of these like the first
one and the second one super easy and
the third one is also easy but and it
uses exactly the same trick that we
looked at before. So let me just talk
about that for a minute just because
it's it's it's a little bit more
interesting than one and two is is
barely interesting. So suppose I'm
looking at the product of these two
functions
and you know so remember that you give
me an epsilon I had to find a delta so I
have to find a delta so that this
difference here
is smaller
I want to find a delta so that if x
minus x0 is smaller if it's smaller than
delta then this difference here is
smaller than epsilon right that's what
I'm supposed to do
just knowing that f and g are continuous
right and so I do so this just like when
we had this for sequences
the similar thing for sequences it's too
much it's too complicated if you just
look at like this. So what you do is
that you take f ofx times g of x. You
insert something and so you insert. It
doesn't really matter which way you do
it, but this is like halfway between
this and that where you take one point
to be x0 the other two x. Of course you
didn't have that. So you have to add it
again.
But now the thing is that what you've
done here is you sort of have split the
difference if you will.
And so now when you want to estimate
this you estimate this thing here first.
So this is g of x * f ofx
- f of x0
and you take the absolute value of this
plus and then this here here you can
factor out f of x0
uh g of x minus g of x0.
And now you see now you can sort of do
like we did before. This here is now
fixed. So you just you can you can also
take the absolute value sign like that.
And now this here is like just x here is
fixed. So this is just some fixed
number. So this means that this thing
here has to be maybe even smaller
depending on what this constant is. But
that's easy to achieve with some delta.
Right? Here it's a little bit more
complicated because this one here is not
fixed. Right? But you have to then say
that once you are close to x0 then this
here there's a bound for this. You see
it's sort of like what we did before. So
we are out of time so I just leave it
there.
So next time we'll talk more about this
with exponential function. Yeah. So a
rational function said to be continuous
or do we not call it continuous? No, a
rational function any rational function
is continuous. It's defined
at points where the where the polinomial
in the denominator
away from the roots of the of the
polomial in the denominator.
>> It's continuous. What
>> are they said to be continu
[Music]
one what yeah I mean any rational
function is continuous. It's just not
defined at the roots.
Okay. Now for some polomium you could
some rational functions if you were sort
of silly and you wrote a if you wrote
this thing here right this is a polomial
that's a polomial this one have a root
as zero but really this function here
you would probably think about as being
the constant function one right so it's
still right but it's not a pure it's
it's continuous
away from the root. It doesn't say
whether it's continuous at the root.
It's just not defined at the root of the
denominator.
>> Yep.
>> Yeah, that's right. That's right. So
that's right. So if you have a polomial
in the denominator, right, there's
there's like finite many points where
where where you have roots and at those
point it's appro defined. You might be
able to extend it in a continuous way to
those points, but typically it's not
defined in those points.