good morning and thank you so much for
coming to MPG primer today um I am very
excited to tell you a bit about some
work we've been doing on amazing species
in my opinion um I want to tell you
about our comparative genomic strategy
to discover mechanisms of cellular
resilience in mammals um and if you've
come into the room and have just been
looking at these pictures I will
acknowledge that yes on the left this is
indeed the honey badger that don't care
um the honey badger among a bunch of
other species is one of the ones we
think is really exciting with regard to
Cellular resilience and what we can
learn from that and today I'm going to
be talking about a framework that we
have used to try or are using to try to
discover um those mechanisms across a
bunch of different mammals um I want to
start with the premise and the argument
that many human diseases result from um
instances of compromised homeostasis and
by that I mean there is something that
happens at the organismal level that
results in an organismal disregulation
of some critical physiological feature
um and
some examples that we may all have
encountered in some contexts are
temperature disregulation classically
fever or hypothermia um glucose
disregulation in the context of diabetes
or oxygen deprivation in the context of
obstructive pulmonary disease and in all
of these cases um there is a you know
wide range of severities but they are
all United by the fact that in the case
of extreme and prolong disregulation
there can be really apparent
consequences for cells that can result
in protein deter
and in some severe and prolonged
instances cell
death um many of the treatments that we
have for these these disease states are
uh aimed at restoring homeostasis and
normal levels at the organismal level so
in the context of temperature
disregulation the idea might be to take
some those hypothermic and warm them up
or take some those a fever and cool them
down um for gluc glucose disregulation
insulin could be used to restore typical
blood glucose levels and in the case of
oxygen deprivation to um pursue
interventions that will restore an indiv
individual to a normal level of oxygen
in which their souls can reside safely
um I think that one of the things to
keep in mind about this is that the
reason we have to do all these things
and the reason these disregulation are
bad for human cells is that under normal
conditions human cells reside in a
pretty reliably good environment um and
so one of the sort of examples that
think is useful is to think about if you
are hiking in the cold your hands might
be cold you might be thinking GE I'd
really like a cup of tea but your body
temperature will stay right around 37c
in spite of being an environment that's
considerably colder than that even more
amazing I think is that that is a bir
directional tolerance so if you happen
to like hiking when it's hot out or in
places where you have to tolerate heat
to get amazing views in the desert or
wherever uh you will again find that
your body is staying at about 37 even
though the external conditions might be
much warmer than that um and I think
this is really interesting because it to
me suggests or indicates that humans are
uh really tightly controlling our
internal conditions and you know on the
one hand you might think that this would
be an easy problem to solve but it turns
out that um to do this at reliably at
population scale has for a long while
been quite difficult and many of us are
wearing on our wrists part of the recent
solution to that problem which is to we
uh various wearable devices that are
collecting temperatures over a long
interval and housemen at all back in
2018 used these as a data source to try
to begin to understand well how much
does human temperature variation really
how much is it a thing basically and so
um this is an interesting paper that
looks at a bunch of different
individuals but the overall um the
overall conclusion is that if you take
all those individuals you take means and
there's some interesting variation be
take means you'll find that yes indeed
there is variation in human temperature
over the course of the day but that bi
axis is pretty tiny and so you might
find if you were to wake up in the
middle of the night at 4:00 a.m. and
stick at the mometer in your mouth you'd
be at at around 36.2 on average uh you'd
be a bit warmer at 5:00 p.m if you did
the same thing so there is some dial
variation but again this is a pretty
small like one degree level level um
Range but there are limits to this and I
was really struck um in a couple years
ago to see a New York Times feature
about exactly this and you know sort we
have evolved olved in um sort of through
human history in environments that have
certain limits on what temperatures are
typically attained in the environments
that we we live in um and this is really
striking to me that in some cases there
are now parts of the world where it's
not all that unusual for temperatures um
in places that humans live to get up to
100 like the well into the 100s
basically and even though again as I
said earlier we are usually working on
the systemic level to keep our internal
conditions thermally pretty constant
those conditions seem in some cases at
least to be sufficient to overwhelm us
and so as New York Times phrased it the
heat of the day can give you a fever so
basically not only is is sort of
excessive um body temperature a disease
state but it's now actually becoming
something that um is not all that
implausible as something that our
environments can impose on us as a
stressor um and so what does this what
does this mean um well I want to think
about what this means in terms of the
following statement which is that humans
are pretty weird in fact as I was
telling you earlier um if you're hiking
in the cold or if you're hiking in the
heat um your body is working pretty hard
to keep you at a constant temperature um
if you were a snake this would be less
likely to be true in fact as we all I'm
sure encountered way back in in
elementary or middle school biology uh
snakes are are um like reptiles in
general um very much conforming to their
their ambient uh the ambient
temperatures and so broadly speaking if
you crank up the temperature um that
your your um snake if you happen to have
a pet snake is living in the the snake's
temperature will go up as well and and
so uh snakes have behavioral strategies
of like seeking out sunspots in order to
to stay warm um and again that's because
they're not really working very hard at
all to keep their internal conditions
constant um but even even mammals even
among mammals uh we are weird I would
argue and so one of my favorite animals
which I sort of anticipated in the very
first slide with a few with a few photos
is the Dromedary camel and I love this
texture because the camel looks so
unaffected by whatever is going on just
just chilling there it turns out that if
you are a a Dromedary camel you have
some uh fluctuation in temperature that
is uh this has been known since that the
mid-50s that is very uh related to the
temperature of your environment and so
you know if if you think back to the
snake where which it was like basically
the snake is the temperature the
environment that's not quite as extreme
for the camel and so if it the camel is
in a freezing environment it's not like
the camel will freeze but you do see
some variation um in terms of the the
body the body temperature that's in
excess like 3.5 degrees which is in
excess of the dial variation I mentioned
earlier for humans where the the camel
is letting its body temperature vary a
bit and the sort of canonical thinking
about this at least is that this is has
evolved as a strategy for water
conservation and so you know if you're
human one of the ways you deal with
keeping or you achieve a constant
internal temperature in a hot
environment is to sweat um that's all
well and good if you have access to
water it's kind of a terrible strategy
if you don't have access to water and so
it seems like sort of an evolutionary
trade-off where where the camel is
tolerating um tolerating internal
variation in temperature as a way or
hand wavy but it seems to preserve water
um and it turns out camels aren't alone
either um if you are familiar with the
process of hibernation you'd also you're
also aware that there are many species
that kind of allow the op temperature
perturbations in the opposite directions
so um I featured two of my my favorite
groups here the the bats and a 13 line
BR squirrel both of which have really
really substantial temperature variation
um over over some cycle during the
winter and and this too is seems to be a
trade-off and so if you um hang out um
in the evening in the summer around here
you'll see and we all benefit from all
those bats that are hanging out and and
eating mosquitoes but it turns out that
come Frost and come the cold weather
around here there aren't mosquitoes
available and so um this is not the
species we have around here in
particular but um the the um the ability
to kind of hang out in the winter and
not need food by letting your metabolic
processes go into a a more depressed
state is actually a really good way to
deal with a lack of a lack of um a lack
of food um one thing that I'm not going
to talk about today that I think is kind
of interesting is the very different
patterns and this is just an aside but
it's it's something we want to know more
about of uh the temperature variation in
different species and so hibernation
isn't necessarily getting cold and
staying cold it's maybe as more in the
squirrel and here having these intervals
during which you're you're fluctuating a
lot but when you are really cold you're
saving all of the resources that you
might otherwise be investing in in
staying really
warm um so in light of this in light of
the camel getting really hot and in
light of the hibernators getting
impressively cold I would argue that
mammals exist along sort of a Continuum
of strategies for coping with ex with um
environmental variation and so as I was
mentioning before humans are kind of
weird on the left I would say that um we
have really strict homeostasis we work
really hard to keep things internally
the same and we do that at the expense
of water we do that at the expense of
needing to spend more energy to preserve
our our rather high body temperature
even when it's cold out um but if you
happen to be a camel or a squirrel or a
bat there are other resources that are
of greater value um in part just because
they're more limited in the environments
that those organisms live in either
because of their dietary habits or
because of water limitation in the case
of camel um and I would call these uh
species that are more on the end of
flexible homeostasis where they are
tolerating internal um internal
conditions that are variable now where
does this place the expense that those
organisms face and I would argue that
it's really sort of again a Continuum
between organismal mitigation and
cellular mitigation so humans are
working hard on systemic level but if
you happen to be a camel or a bat or a
squirrel it's actually your cells that
are directly encountering those variable
conditions and so um this really I
thought was really an intriguing thing
and in fact just as an aside that that a
graph I showed a couple um slides ago of
the camel having variation over the
course of the day was something I
actually encountered in an undergrad um
comparative physiology class and I
thought that was so cool because it
totally violated what I thought I knew
about mammals being very humanlike and
again I think this comes to sort of the
the downsides of having a human Centric
view which is we think we're normal but
we're weird mammals um and if you start
thinking about the the diversity in this
Continuum you suddenly open yourself up
to the possibility of thinking huh if
there are species where it's the cells
that mitigate the stressor then that
allows us to think about this whole
other set of questions which is
basically how do um Maman cells buffer
or cope with
stressors um and this opens up another
set of more specific questions um and
these are the three that we've tried to
use to frame our project right now
although I think as you'll see later in
the talk I'm beginning to realize that
these are not so readily addressable as
I had hoped and that's where I would
love to have your your input on what to
do next because we are um we are we are
uncertain about where to go um so I
think there are you know this can be
broken simply overs simply into a bunch
of ways um one of them is which
responses are Universal across species
that is does it are there certain things
that you do regard of whether you're a
flexible um species like a camel or a
strict species like a human are there
responses that are unique to flexible
species that is are there things that
are um that the camel can do that we
can't um and finally which of those
responses drive all the others like is
there one that sort of precipitates in
any sort of way genomically or otherwise
the set of uh subsequent responses um
and I will say that I I will admit that
my interest in this comes from a very
basic biology perspective I just think
it's really cool that cells can do that
and I want to know why um but um since
we have tried to pitch this to NIH and
currently a funding from NSF um we have
challenged ourselves to think about what
this might mean in the context of what
is this what what might be the insights
for humans um and I really think um one
way to think about it is that instead or
of or complimentary to ideally um
strategies that are meant to sort of
um improve conditions at the systemic
level for States disease states of
temperature glucose or oxygen
disregulation a complimentary strategy
if we can learn from other mammals about
what their cells do that is special and
awesome um we might actually find ways
to intervene to promote cellular
resilience and so you know if you can't
necessarily totally um normalize blood
glucose or you can't normalize
temperature are there other things that
we can do uh that will protect cells
even in a in a more variable environment
than they typically than they typically
live in and this comes from again an
evolutionary perspective that we may not
be drawing on these on these mechanisms
as part of our the typical lives of
ourselves because we are generally doing
a good job of keeping them in in um
pretty constant conditions um but in
these disease States is there something
we could do that can be informed by our
shared evolutionary history with all
these other mels um to approach this we
started thinking about what we might
learn from sort of really classical um
ecology experiments um and um this is
I'm sure um oh I've got a typo there I'm
sorry but um when you take a bunch of
species or a bunch of individuals and
you culture them under the same
conditions there's um as I'm sure many
of us have encountered before a common
Garden approach where you basically do
the same thing to everyone and see how
they differ and and figure out what are
the intrinsic responses um of those
species or individuals that allow them
to cope um in or that allow them to
produce different phenotypes in the same
environment um and we have been um able
to take this approach uh thanks in large
measure to some amazing resources at the
uh San Diego Zoo Global Frozen Zoo which
has stored dermal fiber blasts uh from
thousands of species and this is the key
part including multiple individuals per
species and and so um there's this
amazing room which I would wager to say
has more um viable genomic and genetic
diversity in it than anywhere in the
whole world and it looks kind of
unremarkable in in what it is it's this
is definitely not as exciting to visit
in the sense of oh my gosh I'm going to
observe animal behavior as a zooo but
there's a lot going on here um and we
think that this is especially exciting
for a number of reasons or has been
especially exciting to us for a number
of reasons um one of as I've as I've
indicated here is that rather than
having um one uh one sample so a cell
sample from one individual of each
species the zoo has had the forethought
over many many many decades now to
sample uh cells from multiple multiple
individuals per species and for anyone
who's ever designed any sort of
experiment of course know that this is
really essential because what we don't
want is we don't want to say hey look
this camel is doing this thing human is
not this is a camel thing we of course
want to know about intraspecific as well
as interspecific diversity and responses
and so we've been really fortunate that
there are many species mammals and
otherwise that for which the the Frozen
Zoo has stored cells from from multiple
individuals um I want to give you a
sense uh just starting here of of what
the what the set of species is that we
have um so as with any experiment this
was in part this list the composition of
this list was in part driven by we think
these are the the most exciting possible
study species and in part by the
practicalities of what's available and
what can be what can be cultured um we
have um as you'll see here um the dramer
camel um we also have the bacterian
camel which even though it resides in
much in much colder conditions uh seems
also to have the ability to let its
temperature vary a bit with the
environment um we have a bat and um the
squirrel as at least two hibernators um
we have um a couple species that we
think are really interesting in other
ways um so the the um the gelada for
example is a really high altitude
primate that lives under oxygen limited
conditions and I'll come in a second to
why we think that's important as well um
and the Egyptian fruit bat um survives
basically on a fruit and um a fruit diet
which would obviously not be a super
sustainable strategy glucose regulation
wise for a human and so we think it's
interesting in that way as well um this
uh list is um we have a there's been
some some variation this list but but um
we are happy that we have as many
species as we do and simultaneously
frustrated that we don't have more
because power statistical power is is
always a is always a challenge with any
project of this sort and so as I'll come
to a bit later in the talk um we are
currently um trying to figure out what
what we can do with the data as we have
them and what the limitations are given
power di yes um I might have missed this
but have you thought about introducing
our adding um evolutionary distance
among these species and making sure
you're covering lots of millions of
years of evolution that is a great
question um and there are two answers
that are sort of not really opposed one
of them is we've definitely thought and
maybe more accurately worried about it
and I'll come later to a more explicit
discussion of why we think that's really
important um we um we would love to
have the ideal scenario as I think your
question is alluding to is to have um
multiple species that have the same
types of resilience that are deeply
diverged from one another right like if
you want to know what makes you able to
cope with really variable temperature
conditions you want to be able to
disambiguate hey I'm a camel this is a
thing I do from hey look this is an
essential type of response for to in
order for a mammal to be able to cope
with with variable conditions um in an
Ideal World we would have much greater
coverage of that simply by virtue of
having more species um we did to The
Limited extent possible try to build
that into our design um with with
constraints that we are not super happy
about um so with with some specific
examples as I was saying we think that
the the camels are have some really
interesting thermal stuff going on but
they're close relatives um the the um
the oxygen limitation stuff that'll come
to in a second we have a little bit
better philogenetic spread basically
because the seal and the gelata are on
quite different branches of the tree and
both encounter that as part of their
their normal environment so um in in
summary we did think about it we haven't
coped with we haven't uh accommodated it
as comprehensively as we would like in
an ideally designed experiment but ask
me again in some number of years and I
hope they'll have a different
answer um and again just to to this kind
of was was the question you were
anticipating but it it turns out that um
for the species we've decided to include
um a number of them have U at least one
and and I and in some cases multiple
types of flexibility and so as I was
saying the the hibernators and both
camels seem to be uh thermally flexible
um the gelata and honey badger and an
edytion fruit fat all seem to have some
glucose flexibility um we've got two
diving mammals and then or three diving
mammals rather and then also the gelada
as as organisms that are um that are
tolerant of of hypoxia um and so
hopefully that to some degree gets at
this but and I say hopefully more
emphatically than I would have a couple
years ago I thought we could do more
with it than we can and so um we've kind
of switched from oh we're going to find
all the things to now we're going to try
to accommodate the limitations of our
data set do approve for principal and
hopefully convince someone to give us
more money to do truly all of the all of
the things great are there any other
questions or comments or suggestions
before I go
on cool
great um and just to to um to give us a
sense of what what we mean by by the
variable conditions I've been talking
mostly about temperature but we wanted
to do sort of a a truly comprehensive
framework and so in addition to
temperature flexibility
we considered glucose and oxygen
flexibility um the temperature
conditions are
um selected with constraint and again
this is another one of the kind of comes
back to your question Nicole about the
Practical versus ideal um aspects of of
experimental design so we decided to
choose as Baseline for all of our all of
our stressors the conditions that are
typical for culture of human cells in
the lab and so 37 being human body
temperature that's that's a um a
reasonable starting point we think for
the low temperature in an Ideal World we
actually would have been able to go
lower um because as I showed you before
hibernators get really really low and so
32 isn't just isn't that cold if you're
if you're um one of many species of
hibernators the downside is that we
wanted or the the constraint is that we
wanted to create a truly comprehensive
data set where we had data from every
individual of every species at every
condition and so um it turns out that if
gets too cold some of these cells just
don't grow and so um in this is another
thing that I think is sort of one of the
trade-offs between having a
comprehensive data set and having a
comprehensive set of species because we
can't have we can't figure out how some
cells do it much lower than 32 because
they just don't do anything because they
don't survive um and so that that was
one constraint um for glucose we tried
to model by our choice of conditions the
um the conditions that might be pretty
severe hypoxia sorry not hypoxia um um
low glucose and high glucose um that
might correspond to a hypoglycemic event
versus a hyperglycemic event and then um
for oxygen rather than exposing species
to high ACD in conditions we actually
decided to do short and long exposure to
hypoxia to sort of model what a short um
stint versus a long stint for a for
mamalian diver might be um again this is
a sort of a a less comprehensive set of
conditions and we would like really love
to have a have a more continuous
distribution of of States across or of
conditions across these these extremes
um but we started here um and then for
for uh data types we decided we wanted
to learn about um as many different
features of cellular response as
possible and so our our um collaborators
on this project who are focused on Cell
physiology have a bunch of different
ways I'll mention a couple of those in a
second to figure out how are the cells
doing under these conditions and so for
every every individual of every species
under every condition we asked some
basic things that we think are enabling
us to get at the question of cellular
health for lack of a better word um oops
we also asked about uh gene expression
um which is the analysis that we're
furthest along in but we have still
reached an impass with that and would be
grateful for your input we have some
chromatone accessibility data that we're
very much at the entry stages of of
analyzing
and that same goes for some cell
morphology data where we're trying to
figure out really basic but I think
potentially quite informative things
about how to cell shape change how does
metaconda shape and distribution
spatially change under these different
conditions um so again our collaborators
Ellison hindle and Carla metair um have
been focused on the cellular physiology
aspect of this project and we really for
the self physiology data started out
just by sort of doing a proof of
principle and so our prediction was that
um if if a species is um is flexible in
its temperature range tolerance then it
should be able to better cope with um
with variable temperatures in a way
that's observable at the cellular level
than one that like a human keeps things
really really um tightly controlled
internally and I was very anxious to get
the results of these experiments in part
because if it turned out that we didn't
see any variation between the strict and
flexible species here we'd kind of be in
a bad situation right the whole the
whole sort of premise of the project is
predicated on the idea that cellular
responses to variable conditions in some
way capture or recapitulate um
organismal phenotype and if we couldn't
observe that in culture we would have
been very sad so I am very relieved by
this graph and I think maybe the food is
arriving um so maybe maybe this is a
good time to to pause is that good so I
will I will leave you to think about
this for a second while you grab some
coffee and food and then finish up in
the next the next couple minutes so
great yes please
yeah uh so when infants have an initial
like hypoxia event around the time of
birth we actually cool their core
temperature to
32 um to actually prevent cellular
injury so after hypoxia the cool cooling
actually lowers metabolism enough to
prevent secondary cell death uh so I
just find that really interesting to
think about in the context that our
organ our again what you were saying
about cellular resilience versus
organismal resilience right yes that the
whole organism can be 32 degrees as a
human but that our cells can't be yeah
so I just found that interesting that is
really interesting and it also makes me
wonder about another thing we haven't
yet gotten to which is the combinatorial
thing so it sounds like the scenario
you're mentioning is sort of um the
effect of cooling in the context of
hypoxia and that maybe something that
this I mean not exactly misrepresents
but doesn't get at right because it's
only looking at Cooling in the absence
of hypoxia where there I'm sure there
are tradeoffs at all thank you for
mentioning that yeah but it also makes
me wonder right like many of these
animals that might have a shorter
lifespan might have less genetic
pressure for some later onset disorders
or things relative to those that would
prevent reproduction yeah so I wonder
if just how the kind of t uh life cycle
is integrated into the thoughts of like
what which genetic pressures would be
experienced by each species yeah that
that's a really good point um I think
that there the short answer is we don't
have enough data to include that as a
covariant as comprehensively as we' like
the slightly longer answer is that I
suspect that um if we did have a more
comprehens of species St we could start
to get at questions about whether the
stressors are routine or episodic so for
example if you're a hibernator you have
to be able to deal with cold every year
you're not going to make it to Spring um
whereas if you're a species that lives
in an environment where it's
occasionally really hot that would be
more of a selective sweep on occasion
than a constant pressure and I would
think that that would impose some really
different outcomes that you might be
able to parse apart if you had enough
species that are in those different
uh scenarios basically we cannot get at
that but I we've thought about that a
bit in terms of the hypoxia things and
that's why we've thought about the time
like the time of exposure but yes I
think it's a really good good question
that we can't yet address at all so and
then my last question which is like a
ninth grade biology question is it seems
like you're looking for episodes of
convergent evolution right where like
very different species have come to the
same like noal pathway as their solution
to a stressor what if you looked for
divergent evolution like two species
that because of a a change in ecosystem
specialization like no longer either one
continues to have the stressor and the
other one no longer does yes and if you
found multiple of those pairings that
could also show you what is shared and
change yes definitely um again more
species would be lovely for addressing
that um I think what perhaps you're
talking about is um in an aspect of what
you're alluding to is that there is the
potential for a relief of selective
pressure right and so um there are some
sort of parallel approaches there asking
for specific genes that have had
accelerated Evolution or um stronger
purifying selection for example that
might be more directly able to get at
the when did this happen and how over
what time scale is it continuing to
happen um again another set of amazing
questions that we have worried about and
not been able to address in this context
so yeah thank you so much thank
you so please everyone um feel free to
grab breakfast we really apologize for
the the lateness um Diane if I could ask
you a question that came from an
anonymous attendee online again about
more species um they say have you
considered extending your study to Aven
species to your examples their internal
temperatures Etc is a bit more
constrained than reptiles but not so
well as Mamon species it might give
clues about mechanisms conserved over
much longer evolutionary time scales can
you read that second part again I just
didn't hear one of the keywords oh uh I
think they were just asking about adding
um Aven and then gave some really
interesting biology about how that they
can constrain their temperatures a
little bit intermediate between reptiles
and mammals yes and which of course is
perhaps not surprising given the the
tree structure as well um as with my
maybe unifying answerers to the other
questions yes we have considered it no
we haven't gotten to it yet um but I
think there are some really interesting
things about birds certainly that um I I
might wildly guess that there are some
features about how birds respond that
will be shared with mammals and others
that maybe are unique having to do in
part with their evolutionary distance
and also with the um the extent to they
tightly control things so it's a
wonderful question and I have no answer
so so maybe I'll take like two more
minutes of pause three more minutes of
pause and then get back in
okay alert your pediatrician
I think I may throw that question to to
Sarah C can you ask it again I'm sorry
oh just because like if you have a kid
that's got a you know um infection of
some description and they they actually
can have temperatures of 104 but
pediatrition didn't get upset about that
you know yeah it's actually it's in some
ways it's the rate of rise or the change
in temperature that's more important for
things like s risk of febal seizures um
so you're right that you know uh that
the 10 for in and of itself is actually
makes it more likely to be viral which
is part of why people just don't have
therapies to offer other than
antipyretics but in terms of like
clinical complications of a very high
fever it's really like 106 or higher
where you start to get like cellular
damage uh but it's the the change in
temperature so either fast up or fast
off It's associated with seizures um so
those are the the things we worry about
we telling to be but the temperature is
104 yeah and right and they look
miserable right there's there's there's
uh organismal compromise but not
cellular compromise whereas there would
be for an adult at that temperature is
that right or is that just less commonly
a state attained by adults at all that's
a really good question I think of it as
being something that's more recoverable
as long as it's not sustained right like
I feel like humans very rarely really
sustain a temperature that high it's
usually on that order of hours yep um
but all this is all like phenomenologic
recollection from clinical training
might much more detailed information out
there yeah cool thank
you any other questions while the L
people get their breakfast yes first
first of all this is super interesting
like this comparative biology
perspective is really fascinating but I
was wondering just like um from a
different understanding because these
are all fi blasts like would you expect
something different with hepatocytes or
cardio myocytes or like for yeah it's a
really great question and I think you're
probably detecting a theme here which is
that I have a
ideal idealized response and a pragmatic
response and I'll start with the
idealized response which is that in a
way it might be nice to be able to or
especially nice to be able to get at
some cell that is not so directly
exposed to the environment that it is
you know closer to what the whole
organism and the organism's internal
features are experiencing under these
conditions um so I would love to be able
to do exactly the same experiments in
parallel with one of these other things
because in addition to it there being an
argument that would be better cell type
whatever it also would be really
interesting to compare to see whether
this is is this a camel thing or is this
a camel cell exposed to the out external
conditions thing um so my response there
is yes definitely um my my response
about dermal fiber blasts um in the
pragmatic sense is that uh one of the
things that I really appreciate among
many about the this uh San Diego frozen
zoo is that they are have been dedicated
to minimally invasive sampling and so
all of these cells were collected in the
context of routine vet erary care um and
so you know to collect from an internal
tissue would definitely require invasive
and maybe immediately postmortem
collection um but the reason at the
moment at least that cells are available
from such a great number and diversity
of species is that this is an accessible
cell type there's also I think the
argument that dermal fibr blasts being
outside basically are going to be more
exposed to the environment and so we
might expect that they um they are are
typically experiencing these
fluctuations more directly and so we
think hand baby we we think that maybe
we would have greater opportunity to
observe some of these things and so it
felt to us like a reasonable order of
operations to start with the cell type
likely to yield the greatest effects and
then move later to exactly the ones
you're mentioning when those things
become available um but I would love to
know how many of these things are cell
type specific versus species intrinsic
things and I do not know won't know for
a while I think thank you that's a
really good
question um that sounds great it sounds
like most people have their lunch and
maybe we can wrap up in the next 15
minutes do you think you could finish by
25 great yeah I think I was I was aiming
for 920 so I think we're good yeah thank
you so I've had this slide up here for a
while um basically I just wanted to make
the point that oxygen consumption rate
um our our collaborators who work on
cellular physiology use that as a metric
of how the cells are doing under a given
set of conditions because it is a
reflection mitochondrial respiration
rate um and we were encouraged although
the data are very noisy um to find that
in many cases the and not all obviously
but in many cases the strict species
have more of a change between their
oxygen consumption rate at Baseline
which here is represented here is
represented as the zero so that's no
change from 37 um when you expose them
either the 32 or 41 than do the flexible
species um and so each each of the
symbols here is an individual within
that um within that species and so this
comes to why we thought it was important
to have samples for multiple individuals
per species because they can attempt
with the limitations of n to sort of
disentangle a species feature from a an
anomalous feature of a particular
individual um obviously there are some
exceptions here and we would love to
have more individuals to know what to
make of them but U for example humans uh
don't seem to respond as badly to 32 and
maybe this comes to what Sarah was
mentioning earlier about the potentially
beneficial therapeutic effects of that
um uh but we we just don't know but
anyway as an initial pass we were in
infused to see that the strict species
uh seem to respond with greater change
in oxygen consumption rate to Thermal
perturbation than do the flexible
species uh one other point I wanted to
make is that as I mentioned earlier uh
the camel and the squirrel even though
they're both okay it seems at organal
level with with temperature variation
they're okay with temperature variation
in different directions in their normal
lives and so the camel typically gets
really hot or comparatively warm uh the
squirrel gets cool during hibernation
and yet both of those species are okay
it seems for oxygen consumption rate
both at 32 and at 41 and so one of the
emerging themes that I wouldn't go so
far as to say is a pattern yet but we
are intrigued by is the possibility that
there are some components of thermal
tolerance that are non-directional
meaning that maybe there are some things
you evolve that allow you to deal with
um temperature perturbation that are not
specific to getting warm or getting cool
but just are are are um about being able
to deal with with greater temperature
variation um another aspect of the data
that is very much in its infancy but um
as I was mentioning earlier um our
colleagues who work on Cell
physiology are um are uh also taking um
using microscopy to examine cellular
impacts at various temperatures um the
White Rhino as you'll recall from from
this previous slide is one of the
species that seem is a strict therm
regulator we think um and seems to do
especially badly under both um hot and
cold conditions so it has these
significant changes in its oxygen
consumption rate um and we also noticed
and again these data are very
preliminary I'm sorry that there isn't a
species to compare them to just yet but
it seems that the Rhino cells have a lot
of changes in cells morphology um when
you either cool or sorry in this case
when you warm them um and so we're
interested in asking as the data begin
to emerge which they are doing now um
whether this is a general property of
for example species that have apparent
changes in oxygen consumption rate under
thermal
perturbation um I want to end with
talking a little bit about what we've
done so far with the the RNA sequencing
data um and what we think is a major
constraint right now and what we can do
with those data and ideally ask for your
help in in in in coping with that
problem so when I first started thinking
about this project in this problem I was
like oh this is great we're going to
take all these species expose them to
these conditions we'll find things that
everyone does and that just the strict
or or flexible uh species do when
they're exposed to Thermal perturbation
for example um as Nicole was alluding to
already there's a big problem with that
because we don't just want to know hey
what do strict species do or what do
flexible species do that strict don't we
really want to know are there things
that are surprising given the philogyny
and so I had not thought adequately
about that constraint before we started
this and so right now we are able to say
things like um there are Universal
responses among all study species and by
this I mean if you crank up the
temperature to 41 there are certain
Pathways that are enriched among the
genes that have a significant P change
when you use all five of those uh
individuals per species um that every
single individual does and so some of
those have to do with cholesterol bio
biosynthesis some cell membrane stuff
there maybe not totally surprising in
light of of light of um a response to
higher temperature um there are some
things having to do with protein folding
again not surprising given some of the
the things about protein detrition um so
that was all good these are things we
can say everyone that we've studied so
far does um we can also start to say
things about what our star um flexible
high temperatures species the Dromedary
camel does in terms of uh regulating
Pathways or up or changing the
expression of genes in Pathways that
other species don't do or other um that
strict species don't do and those have
to do with cell cycle proliferation
protein homeostasis DNA repair
production against oxidative stress and
homeostasis of mitochondrial metabolism
this is maybe not surprising these are
all things that might go badly when it's
when it's high temperature um I was
initially really excited about this but
then I started worrying that um this is
just again still very descriptive right
we can say that these are things that
Camel does but we can't really say
whether they are um whether they are
well we can say that in our study
species we're unique we can't say that
they're universally unique and that
things get even worse when we think
about the constraints of our tree um
when we think about trying to find trait
relevant convergent changes in gene
expression which we really think is a
complex Challenge and asteris there um
is to highlight that this is one we have
yet to solve and um I've been talking
with a bunch of people who work on U
philogynes and and um evolution of
traits and it I um have been really
struck that we're kind of maybe as a
field converging on this as an open
question that doesn't yet have a really
satisfying and statistically appealing
answer um so I just want to take us
through this example and again this
comes back to something that Nicole was
mentioning a couple minutes ago so say
that we observe um that um that these
that our two camel species both of which
as far as we know are thermally flexible
have some Gene that is either up or down
regulated significantly in response to
temperature I personally would find that
exciting we can say this is the thing
that camels do when it's really hot um
but there is a problem in that this also
maybe isn't totally surprising because
those camels are closely related to one
another and so those aren't really
independent observations they're a thing
we know about what camels do but we
can't say that this has evolved
independently or this is a response that
is sort of
universally U present among among
species that can tolerate high heat um
um at least in the relative sense I
would be more excited if we were to find
some um some Gene whose expression
changed significantly not just in the
camels but also in the hibernators um
for two reasons one of them is that
camels are Heap tolerant hibernators
seem to be more tolerant of lower
temperatures and there's a much greater
Branch length between our camels and are
hibernators and so that would leave me
comparatively confident also very
handwavy um that this is a a sort of a
convergent trait that exists
independently on these lineages and
isn't just sort of a byproduct if you
will of their their recent evolutionary
relationship um so I um my colleague
Lucas morrera and I have been scaring
the literature to try to find about
whether there are ways to that exist
already to try to understand and put key
values on basic basically a a sharing of
responses across species with a given
phenotype um that is impressive given
their given their philogyny and so um
one of the methods that has begun to get
at some of this is the eve method um
which um the expression variance and
evolution model by rals um and
introduced by rals and then elaborated
more recently in a bunch of other papers
that basically assumes that um Gene
regulation as shown here on on the left
evolves randomly across a tree and so
the intuition here is that if a branch
length between two species is longer
then you'd expect them to be more
diverged than than um than the branch
length in in expression change might be
between two closely related species and
this is like a classic random walk and
so the idea here is that um you just
simulate along the tree and what you're
looking for um is cases where a the
expression change on a given branch is
excess given the length of that branch
which would suggest yep there's
something really really meaningful going
on here in terms of the change in
expression um the this model is also
able to look at a bunch of different
species and their full change in
response to something and ask about
whether there are there's evidence that
there are two different optimal levels
of expression and so this is they call
this the Theta test and so basically you
can ask are there you know is there
evidence that there are um that maybe
High expression is selected one lineage
and low expression is Select CED another
lineage um this was really exciting to
us at first and indeed it's an awesome
method it's super cool um the problem is
that there is not yet as far as we can
tell a way to specifically look for
cases of convergence um and by this I
mean um cases where you again like in as
you might um think about in this example
are there things where in spite of the
Long Branch link comparatively between
the squirrel and the and the camels
there are things that are more similar
in their in their expression change than
you'd expect given that line given that
uh Branch link and so I will just stop
by saying um we've been running um Eve
um which again we think is an exciting
start but it leads us kind of with this
problem and so um we'll see that there
are um that there is evidence for
example for this Gene which I I'm just
using as an example for two different um
Optimum expression levels that is there
are significant differences in the
expression of this Gene for some
lineages as compared to the other
however what we can't do is to say that
the flexible species so here the the
squirrel the bat and the two camels are
more similar than you'd expect given
their given their Branch length and so
we've been trying to figure out are
there Ford simulation ways to get at
this um are there other things that we
haven't thought about um in talking with
a bunch of people as I was saying
recently about sort of a philogenetic
approach to this this seems like a
problem that the field is converging on
in terms of no pun intended but the the
field is converging on in terms of
looking for genes whose um whose
expression is more similar between
diverg lineages that you can annotate AR
priori than you'd expect um I don't know
what to do with this um I will close on
the unsatisfying Note um of saying that
we are still perplexed by this and um
for me it's kind of a a sad note in in
what I think is otherwise a promising
project where we can right now say hey
look these genes change in these species
but I cannot tell you
whether that is surprising given their
philogyny and I hope that not too long
from now we collectively will come to an
answer and I will be able to give you
some greater certainty on that um and
then let's see um so finally this kind
of comes to what I was just saying a
second ago but we want to identify
convergent changes in gene expression
convergent changes in chromatin
accessibility and then in some work I
haven't had a chance to talk about today
um convergent changes in RNA splicing in
the response to to temperature and other
changes and what we really want to do I
think is develop methods to get at these
things um so with that and I think my
timing is okay unsurprisingly given the
diversity of data types that we that
have gone into this project we have a
whole bunch of collaborators working on
a whole bunch of things um so Lucas who
is um up here on the left who was um at
brood and is now at Colossal has done
all of the RNA expression work and has
um been trying to see whether there's a
way we can push the eve model to get at
this question of convergence um Carla
and Allison here have been doing all of
the cell culture work without which none
of this would be possible um Eleanor and
Lucas and I have been focused on the
genomics um uh Jorge and chrisy and
Valerie have been working on some
mathematical modeling to try to get at
the question of genomic drivers of these
responses Daniel is starting to work on
the chromatin accessibility data and
then I also wanted to give a shout out
to the uh bird summer Scholars Program
through which we had the opportunity to
work with two high school students this
summer who really started doing some um
RNA spacing work with our data that um
this was news to me but we just had RNA
expression data and with those and
combination with a with a um a spacing
program called our mats we were able to
infer um instances of differential
spacing and we think that there may be a
lot of instances of differential spacing
thanks to Jordan and Erica's work sorry
Georgia and Eric's work um there may be
many cases of differential splicing that
are also responses to heat that we would
miss if we were just asking about
changes and expression I will end there
and say I'm sorry that I didn't have
more conclusive things to say but this
is where we are in this project and I
hope we will be further along and not
too long and I would be grateful for any
questions and suggestions so