[MUSIC PLAYING]
MEGAN MITCHELL: Hello.
Hello, and welcome to the third
session of the MIT Jameel World
Education Lab's AI
Innovation Series.
I'm Megan Mitchell.
I'm the acting director of
Jameel World Education Lab.
I'm going to abbreviate
that to J-WEL.
The focus of today's session
is on emerging AI innovations,
new tools from
the MIT ecosystem.
So for those of you who
aren't familiar with J-WEL,
is MIT's portal to our
expertise in research, teaching,
and experimentation.
And we work J-We with
ambitious member institutions,
many of whom are here
today from around the world
to bring that mission to life
and for education designed
for everyone to thrive.
J-WEL was created in 2017 as a
connection point and a portal
and a lab for
co-creating new ideas.
And from the start, we've
built active collaborations
with institutions
and individuals who
are really focused on trying to
change education for the better.
I think we all recognize
that AI has the potential
to create important new
opportunities in education
and learning.
And particularly exciting
to me is the opportunity
it has to address challenges
for access to education.
And today's panelists
have new approaches
that they've developed using AI
for this-- just this very goal.
And they've thoughtfully
explored new spaces for design
learning and adapting in
this rapidly evolving field.
So as part of our
panel today, you'll
hear from three panelists
representing two organizations.
The first recent MIT
alumna, Cerine Hamida,
who's the founder of 1for1, a
Tunisian-based company offering
a comprehensive, student centric
science learning system that
actually aligns with Tunisia's
national curriculum and features
state of the art adaptive
learning methodologies.
And really, the key benefit
she's bringing to bear
for the users are personalized
learning experiences tailored
to their proficiency levels,
interactive problem-solving
and 24/7 support from a
generative AI conversational
professor.
So as students are
studying on their schedule,
this tutor is available to them.
And 1for1 is not only designed
to enhance science competencies
but also increase student
motivation and reduce
the financial
burden of families.
So we're looking forward to
hearing some from Cerine.
And then also joining
us are two PhD students
from MIT, Bernardo Garcia
and Salome Augilar.
And they're here to
tell you about JANN,
an NGO dedicated to bringing
bridging the educational gap
in Mexico through a cost
effective tutoring platform that
is leveraging AI to automate the
logistical challenges associated
with managing a very large
scale tutoring program that
they've built and developed and
that has served 23,000 students
through its 7,000
tutors since 2021.
So you can imagine the logistics
and operational back end
to all of that.
And the platform
they've developed
automates everything
from the tutor training
to the student assessment
and to the progress tracking.
So we're excited
to hear from them.
But before I turn it
over to our panelists,
I'd like to invite my
colleague, Bill Bonvillian,
to set the stage for
this conversation.
Bill is the mastermind behind
J-WEL's thinking series
and has had an incredibly
distinguished career working
at the intersection of policy
and the new frontiers of science
and technology.
He's advised senior
US officials.
He's led MIT'S Office
in Washington, DC,
and we're really
fortunate to have him
as a valued
colleague and trusted
member of the J-WEL team.
And he's brought together
these panelists for us today.
So, Bill, can I turn it over
to you for just a few words.
WILLIAM B. BONVILLIAN: Yes.
Thanks very much, Megan.
Just a few words on
the background today.
We're going to see some very
practical applications of AI
for education.
So we've had two
prior programs that
really discuss the theory
and the potential approaches.
Now we're going to have some
really practical applications.
So as Megan mentioned,
Cerine and her company,
1for1 in Tunisia, is attempting
to tackle some of the really
major education
problems in her country,
including sporadic access to
quality science education,
a one size fits all approach
that leads a lot of students
behind and a high cost of
traditional academic supporting
activities.
And she's using an adaptive
learning approach deeply
embedded in an AI system.
So it's a digital
tutoring system,
and the first big use is to
prepare secondary students
for the major exams they face.
In this case, the initial
run is on physics and math.
And the company will
launch on August 31.
And Cerine, I'm sure, has been
losing sleep continuously.
But hopefully, you'll stay
awake through the 31st.
Salome and Bernardo have a
massive tutoring program,
as Megan mentioned,
for students in Mexico
through their NGO, JANN, and
it ties University students
performing their required
hours of public service
to students throughout Mexico.
And they record
tutoring sessions
and are working to
attempt to draw out
through AI the most effective
teaching practices to get
to their tutors.
So we know some of the potential
uses of AI in education.
Personalization of education, it
can be difficult for one teacher
to figure out how to meet
the needs of every student
in his or her classroom.
But AI systems can help
adapt to each student's
individual learning
needs and really
target the instruction based
upon the student's strengths
and weaknesses.
Digital tutoring, AI systems can
gauge a student's learning style
learning approaches and
their preexisting knowledge
to really develop customized
support and instruction.
Grading AI can help grade
simple exams using answer keys,
but it also can compile data
about how students performed
and have the potential to grade
more abstract assessments.
Feedback on course
teaching, if, for example,
a number of students
are answering a question
incorrectly, AI can focus
on this specific information
or concepts that
students are missing.
So, for example,
Salome and Bernardo
are going to be applying this
feedback capability from AI
and improving the performance
of the tutors that reached
their many enrolled students.
And then there's meaningful and
immediate feedback to students.
Some students may be
reluctant to take risks
in a classroom kind of setting.
But with AI, they can feel
more comfortable in making
the mistakes and
making mistakes they
need to do for learning and
receiving the feedback they need
to improve.
So today, we're discussing
actual applications,
and a number of these potential
parts of AI's contribution
education will
come to bear here.
So let me turn it
over first to Cerine.
CERINE HAMIDA: Thank you, Bill.
So I'll start by giving a
brief presentation of 1for1,
and then I'd like to do a
hands on demo of our platform.
So let's start with
the presentation.
So at 1for1, we believe that
every student deserves access
to personalized and
high quality education.
However, this is not the
reality for most high schoolers
around the world.
And in many countries,
such as Tunisia,
college entrance exams,
such as the Baccalaureate,
dictate students whole
life trajectories
from the universities that they
can attend to even the majors
that they are allowed to study.
And despite the
criticality of these exams,
access to quality
education is limited.
Demotivated students are trapped
in a one size fits all system
and are unable to
access quality content.
Even alternative solutions
aren't real solutions.
Group or private tutoring
are often ineffective,
financially burdensome, and
logistically challenging
leaving students without
the support that they need.
In Tunisia, this results in
two out of three students
failing in their first
Baccalaureate attempt,
and many end up dropping
high school altogether.
At 1for1, we created a product
that addresses the three key
issues of quality, access, and
personalization through four key
offerings.
I'll emphasize the first two
as they're heavily driven by.
First, our adaptive
learning system,
built on a four
pillar approach, which
I will later detail, this system
tailors lessons and exercises
to each student's learning
profile through three key steps.
First for each
chapter, the system
analyzes student
interactions and performances
to pinpoint exact strengths
and areas needing improvement.
Then, based on this analysis,
individual learning profiles
and goals are created.
Our adaptive learning
algorithms then guide students
through a customized learning
path, providing multiple choice
questions and
exercises in real time
to ensure appropriate
challenges and support,
helping students from
foundational concepts
to advanced applications.
So this is our AI personalized,
adaptive learning system.
We also have a generative
AI virtual assistant,
which serves as a
24/7 expert teacher.
[INAUDIBLE] So students
can ask it any questions
they have from clarifying
difficult concepts to helping
them work through exercises.
Students can even share
their handwritten work,
and the assistant will analyze
it, provide feedback, and offer
hints and additional resources.
The virtual assistant offers
personalized and contextualized
guidance that is in line
with the national curriculum.
So something that I
didn't mention earlier
is that all our
content on our platform
is built in-house by
our group of teachers.
And so the virtual assistant
is trained specifically
on our content.
And everything
that it works with
is guided by the
national curriculum.
So these are our
first two offerings.
We also have progress
tracking, which
allows students to
monitor their performance,
better understand
the way they learn,
and even set their
personalized goals.
And finally, we
offer a one stop shop
that connects students to a wide
range of external resources.
So from animated concepts
for deeper learning-- so
we have links to
PhET simulations,
for example, to well-being
support and even career
and college planning tools.
So with these core
offerings in place,
it's important to understand
the philosophy that
drives our approach.
At 1for1, our methodology
is rooted in the science
of learning.
So we're really
emphasizing the importance
of structured and
progressive learning
to achieve effective results.
For example, that we
can see over here,
Bloom's taxonomy is
a central concept
in the field of
learning sciences.
So learning occurs in stages
through a hierarchical order.
You start by recalling
basic knowledge.
So that's the bottom
of the pyramid.
Then you move on to
understanding these concepts,
applying them,
analyzing, evaluating.
And finally, you're
able to create
new ideas from that knowledge.
Our four pillar approach
reflects this hierarchy.
First, students build
their competencies
through lessons in
multiple choice questions.
They verify their
competencies, then
do open exercises that emphasize
the teaching of problem
solving methodologies.
They [AUDIO OUT]
through exercises,
through mock exams
that are complete with
minimal and optional hints.
In the early stages of learning,
when students are grasping
material and learning
how to apply it,
maximum guidance is needed.
And this is why our first
two pillars are adaptive,
meaning that 1for1 selects
the multiple choice question,
selects the exercises, the
topics that the student needs
to focus on, and gives
them personalized tips
and methodologies.
However, in later
stages, we want
to foster personal
initiative, and it's
important for the students to
know how to apply knowledge
autonomously.
So that's why the last
two pillars give students
more control.
It allows them to choose their
own exercises from a list that's
given to them and review the
topics that they want to review.
So they get less guidance
than the previous steps.
And with that, I'll
move on to the demo.
But just wanted to shout
out one of my co-founders
who wasn't here today.
Teimurazi is also
a student at MIT,
and we've been really building
all the AI systems together.
So now I'll just jump into
the demo of the platform.
And we'll concretely
show you how
all of these four pillars
and our four offerings
work together.
Upon logging into
your account, students
will find themselves
in the My Space
section, where they can
see the list of subjects
that they're studying.
So for the first
year in Tunisia,
we're offering math and
physics, physics, chemistry
for Tunisian high schoolers.
They can also see
the distribution
of time spent working on
the four pillars here.
Here it's a newly
created account,
so the distribution
isn't quite clear.
But also they can
see the time spent
working on the
platform every month
for the different subjects.
In the sidebar on the
left, they have access
to the four pillars
and also quick access
to the different subjects.
So let's start working in math.
So once you select
a subject, you
get the list of chapters
that are related to it.
And every chapter is
divided into topics
that the student will learn
in chronological order.
So you can see here some
of the topics are locked,
meaning the adaptive
learning systems still
think that the
students need to revise
their prereqs and the previous
topics before giving it to them.
And some topics are unlocked
and students already--
the student is already
working on them.
The student has easy access to
the different pillars over here,
and the last pillar is revised.
It's not linked to
a specific chapter.
It's a whole revision.
So that's why it's just
present on the sidebar.
So let's hop into the first
pillar, which is built
competencies.
So when students
are first learning,
they need to get acquainted
with the lessons.
So they have in the sidebar
access to the full lesson
divided in the different topics.
They cannot view the lessons
of the topics that are still
locked.
So here I'm trying to click
on it, but it won't open.
But I can definitely see the
lesson of the topics that
are unlocked.
The lessons are
very detailed, have
definitions, properties,
even examples.
For more complicated lessons,
we have illustrations also
and even proofs.
If at any time I'm
confused about something,
I have at the top, our virtual
assistant that is present
everywhere in the platform
on all four pillars,
and I can ask it any
questions that I have.
So for example, here,
let's do an example.
And basically, how you can
ask the virtual assistant
any question that you
have to build competencies
with the multiple
choice questions.
So here a student received
personalized multiple choice
questions based on
their learning profiles,
and they have two
attempts to answer them.
So I'm going to purposefully
answer this one wrongly.
If I answer incorrectly,
I'm giving g--
I'm giving a personalized
hint based on the mistake type
that I made.
So here the platform
really guides you
and understands which are the
concepts that you probably
don't understand.
Of course, at any time,
you have at the top right,
the virtual teaching
assistant that you
can ask any questions
that you have,
even upload photos of
your handwritten work,
and it will help guide
you if you're stuck.
So let's answer this one again.
So once you finished
answering it,
it'll give you the explanation.
What's the right answer,
what you selected,
and it will give you another
multiple choice question that's
tailored to your profile.
Now, more interestingly, let's
go to verify my competencies.
So again, like in build
competencies and verify,
you're given personalized
exercises based on your profile.
So the first
interface, the student
will just read the full problem.
But then once you
start working, it's
going to be divided,
step-by-step,
question-by-subquestion, and
subquestion-by-subquestion.
With verify competencies,
we don't just
want to provide students
with learning opportunities.
We want to help them improve
their problem solving skills.
And we do that in multiple
ways, first of all,
by giving them personalized
hints to the type of question
that they're solving, and
these hints are actually
linked to methodologies.
They'll be repeating.
They'll be the same
hints over and over again
for similar question
types as the student
works on the same chapter.
So the student can do the
pattern matching themselves.
Oh, I see a specific
type of question.
I always see that this is the
best methodology to use it,
and automatically they
learn these methodologies
and how to apply them.
Another way we help students
with their methodologies
is by asking them to
submit their work.
And they can either
do that by directly
typing in their mathematical
keyboard, or what they can do
is they can take photos of their
handwritten work and upload
them.
It'll then transcribe students
work and allow the student
to make some corrections
if necessary.
So here there's just a
little bit of notation.
I didn't write it very
clearly, to be honest,
but I can just correct it
and then confirm my answer.
And you'll see here that it'll
give you personalized feedback.
The first line that tell you
is that whether you answered
correctly or incorrectly.
I purposefully forgot
a case in my answer.
I did a small
mathematical error,
so it correctly identified
that this is incorrect.
What it will also do is give
you personalized feedback
on your work.
So for example, here I
answered incorrectly.
It will tell you exactly--
It'll tell me exactly
what the mistake I made
and why and how to rectify it.
And it depends.
Some scenarios, for example,
student answered correctly,
but their composition of
their answer isn't great.
Maybe they skipped
a lot of steps
or just wrote the final answer
without explaining it well.
This will make them lose points
in the Baccalaureate exams.
We actually evaluate how the
students compose their answer
and give them tips on how
to word things better,
on how to make their composition
more logical for Baccalaureate
exam level answers.
And then, finally, we also help
them with their methodologies.
It's possible that you
perfectly answered correctly
in a mathematically
sound methodology,
but that just takes way
too many unnecessary steps.
It'll tell the
student, congrats.
This is good.
This is correct, but there's
a much easier way of doing it.
And it'll explain to
the student how and why.
Again, students have access
to the virtual assistant
on the right.
So this won't-- OK, my
internet is a bit lagging,
but it will open up.
And they can ask any
questions that they have,
even resend their photos
of their updated work,
and it'll help them out.
So these two are
adaptive sections.
Just because of time issues.
I'll just quickly
gloss over Test Myself.
So as you can see, this
is an autonomous section.
So you're not getting one
exercise recommended to you.
You get a whole list of them.
But they are actually sorted
in the order of recommendation.
But it's up to the
student to choose
which one they want to work on.
And unlike verify
competencies, they actually
do the whole exercise in one
go, then send their answer,
and then get the feedback.
It's not broken
down step-by-step
because here we assume
that the student already
has the foundation to be
able to do it themselves.
And with that, this
concludes my demo.
MEGAN MITCHELL:
Thank you, Cerine.
Excellent.
It's great to see it
working and really
get into the nuts and bolts.
It's one thing to hear, but to
be able to see it working really
brings it to life, which I think
is appreciated for all of us.
Let's turn it over now to Salome
and Bernardo to talk about JANN
and share their work
with you as well.
And as I mentioned in the
chat, if you have questions,
I would appreciate if
you put them there.
Include your name and
your organization,
so we all know who you are.
And we will have time.
I have questions, but I'll
also be taking questions
from the audience.
And I know Bill has
some too, so all right.
SALOME AUGILAR LLANES:
OK, sounds great.
Thank you, Megan.
And a very impressive the work
that you're doing, Cerine.
We're going to share our screen.
OK, so we're going to talk
about Jovenes Ayudando A Ninas Y
Ninos, which is this NGO that
Bernardo and I along with two
more friends co-founded in 2021.
And just in short or in
a summary, what we do
is that we provide free
online math tutoring
for children in primaries
and middle schools in Mexico.
And we do this by coordinating
a university students who
volunteer as tutors.
So in Mexico, in order to
graduate from University,
which we have learned is the
case in other Latin American
countries and probably in other
countries around the world,
students in University
need to do a social service
to graduate as a
requirement from University
and to get their
University degree.
So what we do is we
partner with universities
so that students can do
this social service with us.
We don't pay them, but we help
them meet this requirement.
And then we put them in touch
with children to teach math.
So I'm going to dive a little
bit into the details of how
we do this.
On the one side, on
the one side here
to the left, we partner with
elementary education ministries.
In this case, we have done this
with seven states around Mexico
to promote JANN, the NGO.
Children will enroll for
free in our platform.
They can answer-- when
they open a profile,
they will need to answer a set
of initial evaluations, a math
evaluation that will
allow us to measure
the impact of the program.
They will also answer
other demographic services
that we get to the population
that is working with us.
And then on the other side,
we will form agreements
with different universities
around, in this case, in Mexico
so that the University students
can meet these social service
requirements that I was talking
about as tutors in JANN.
So I think the big
value add that we
bring to the table is that we're
able to coordinate these two
groups of people using a
platform that we developed
and that has helped us impact
thousands of students with very,
very little resources.
The way in which we do this
is that students will open up
a profile in our website,
and they will first
be welcomed with a set
of initial trainings
that are asynchronous
that we recorded.
And they're a little bit
similar to a Coursera course
where they can watch a video
and answer a set of questions.
And then we also
will interview them
to get to know them and make
sure that they're [INAUDIBLE]
to work with children.
We then will form
automatically groups
of five students and one tutor.
And we will message both
the students, the parents,
and the tutor to let them know
that they have been matched.
The tutor will then
go to their platform.
They will be able to see
the information of students.
And in this case, they just
see the number and the name,
and they will be able to do a
WhatsApp group with the parents,
with the students, and introduce
themselves as their tutor
and set up a time
and day for meeting.
And usually they will
meet two hours per week
for 12 to 24 weeks.
This depends on the
agreement that we
have with each university.
Then after that, our
system will allow
us to monitor their progress.
So tutors have to upload an
attendance report every time
they teach a class, and we
will be sending them messages
if we notice that they are
not giving their classes.
And also in the case that
it takes a lot of time
since they have
given the last class,
they will maybe be
kicked out of the program
and assigned another
tutor for the same group.
So kind of the idea here
is that we are really
lowering the costs of logistics
and of organizing this program
because all of this check
up is made automatically.
Then towards the end of
the work together, children
will take an online evaluation,
another math exam, which
will allow us to
measure their progress
and their learning
in the platform
but also has been the
reason why we have
been able to do a research.
So Bernardo is going to be
talking a little bit more
about how we do research
in this platform.
And what has been our
impact since 2021, well,
we have coordinated and more
than 7,000 tutors meet with more
than 23,000 students at an
average cost of $2 per month per
classes per student.
And this we have achieved
with a team of two
to six people working in Mexico.
So we think that
using technologies,
we can really scale the
impact of this project.
Because we have seen other
tutoring programs that
don't make use of technology
and then they are capped,
the scale is capped
that they can reach.
And in the first
iteration of our program,
we did an experiment
where we wanted to measure
the impact in learning.
So we had a treatment group
that received tutoring,
and then we had a
control group that
didn't receive tutoring
for one semester
but then received
tutoring after.
But they did do an exam
before and after the months
where we evaluated.
And we measure that, on
average, the students who
received tutoring
improved learning
in 0.14 standard deviations in
the first two months of classes.
And just to put this
number into context,
this is about 15% to 20%
the learning loss caused
by the pandemic in Mexico.
And so we think
in average, people
who participate in
this program are
able to recover the learning
loss in less than one year.
And just to talk about the
scale that this could reach,
we have seen a
lot of willingness
from tutors to connect
with children to help.
And we know that the tutors that
we have right now participating
in the program are less than
1% of the potential tutors
or potential university
students that we
have in Mexico, as well as, on
the other side, the children.
So we really think
of these programs
as a tool that can make the
population of University
students work for
their community
and work to impact education
and also, to some extent,
build this social cohesion among
different groups in the society.
So who is a student in JANN.
In general, students--
most of our students
are attending a public
school, more than 90%
They are also in the first
two quintiles of the income
distribution in Mexico,
more than half of them.
Also more than 40% of them
don't have any family members
who attended University.
So it's very important
and very crucial
for them to meet this tutor
who is going to be meeting
with them for several months.
And also after the
program, more than 70%
report that they're going
to miss their tutor.
So we're talking about deep
connections that are being made.
Another thing that
I don't have here
is that also we know that
more than 40% of our students
connect from a cell phone.
They don't have
access to a computer,
but they're still connecting
to classes with the resources
that they have.
BERNARDO GARCA BULLE
BUENO: Thank you, Salome.
JANN, as Salome
said, we have tried
to reach a really huge
scale and make thousands
of connections in Mexico.
But at the same time,
we believe that JANN
is more than just numbers.
And we get to see this
every time we make events
on a yearly basis, usually
with all our tutors
and all our children.
And hearing the experiences that
they have, we become really--
our passion for this
project rekindles.
Something that really matters
to us is, as Salome said,
only about--
about half of our students have
a relative who went to college.
And what this means is
that maybe a kid in Mexico
can grow up without ever having
a connection with someone who
went to University,
a real connection
where the person feels
trust to ask for advice
and to even see themselves
in their shoes and say,
maybe I can also go to college.
So for us, that's something
that also matters a lot in JANN.
Here are some testimonies
from our program.
And from what you hopefully
can see, we have--
these are fairly representative
from our population.
And students,
parents, and tutors
usually get a really good
experience from JANN.
And on the other
side, JANN is also
a platform where everything
is controlled by a software
that we built ourselves.
And this has allowed us to do
many kinds of randomizations
that usually one cannot do in
a regular educational setting,
such as a school, for example,
making groups where everyone has
the same skill, everyone
has different skills.
It's just girls,
just boys, and even
varying the content
of the class.
So sometimes we have done
RCTs, where half of our kids
receive this supplemental social
emotional learning lessons
along with their math classes.
And after we did JANN
on that first summer,
we realized that hand could
become an education lab,
where we can ask many of these
relevant education questions
that just cannot be asked in
a normal education setting.
Just to highlight two of them,
right now we have recorded more
than 200,000 hours of lessons,
and we are trying to understand
who are the best tutors.
This is not a trivial
question because there have--
as many of you might know
from the world of education,
there have been many
efforts in the past
to try to explain what makes
a good teacher good and using,
for example, standardized tests.
And that has been right now,
I think, about 10% or 15%
of the variance is
explained but not more.
A lot of what makes
a good teacher
doesn't rely on demographics
or even things that
are a bit important
like experience.
So what we're trying to do in
JANN is let's take these 200,000
recordings, and let's pass them
through our machine learning
algorithms and extract what
really makes a good teacher.
This is Alberta.
We're really excited
about that, and we're
trying to finish it
in the next semester.
The other part that
we're excited about is
we have a project where we--
is the one I mentioned
where some kids received
this social emotional education
along with their math content.
We also grouped kids by skills.
This was actually
funded by J-WEL,
so it's really exciting to
talk about in these forums.
And then what we
saw were two things.
Mainly is that in groups of 5,
which is the size of our groups,
the skill heterogeneity
didn't really
affect the progress
of the groups.
And the other
thing that we found
was that giving the
kids the opportunity
to have these social emotional
learning with the tutor
improved their math performance.
And right now we're
doing a follow
up activity trying to
understand exactly, why was it
that they made a better
connection with the tutor,
was it that the tutor improved
their skills in some way
or that the kids
improved their skills.
But so far, what we do
know is that the tutors
made their classes longer when
they were in this treatment
group, even the math classes.
They even gave more classes
than what was required.
And another important
thing is that the emotions
in the audio of the classes were
more positive, more activating.
So we definitely
saw how it is good.
It was a good intervention.
And I think Salome
wanted to add something.
SALOME AUGILAR LLANES:
You say that make
me make the parentheses that
the idea here is that we
have this large scale program.
We have thousands of
hours of recordings,
and we have AI to
process these recordings
and allow us to do
the type of research
that usually qualitative
researchers do in a large scale.
So we want to make this bridge
between quantitative research
that mostly focuses on
dropout rates on scores
and not really on how
students are interacting
and the classroom
atmosphere that
usually is the key of
qualitative research.
So we are really
working and very
excited to be bridging these two
lines of research in education
because we see them
both as very valuable,
and we see an opportunity
here to do this.
And another thing that
we also wanted to mention
is that we have seen--
I think our goal doing JANN
is to impact as many children
as we can.
And we have formed partnerships
with governments in Mexico,
with universities,
and we're trying
to really scale the program
because we see the potential.
But we are sometimes a bit
limited by the resources
that we have to actually reach
enough participants or more
participants.
And we're working on it.
And we know there will
be a lot of opportunity.
But suddenly,
another way that we
thought that can help
us reach this scale
is simply sharing this
software that we already
did with other institutions
so that they can themselves
create programs like
ours designed by them
but with the
advantages of lowering
the logistical costs
and the setup costs,
and that they can impact their
communities in other countries.
Because I guess one question
that we got at some point
was like, would you be
interested in taking JANN
to Colombia.
And I thought about it and
I was like that's so far.
I don't know anything of
the Colombian context.
I don't know people in Colombia.
I wouldn't know where to
start forming relationships
with universities.
But suddenly thinking of we
can actually just reach out
to one University, give them
our software, give them our
know how, and it will
be full of people
who know exactly
who to reach out to,
who know exactly what
the problems are,
and how to help the communities
surrounding the University.
So what we're going to have
more programs like JANN
spread out around the world and
impact thousands of children
and have really the
community involved.
I guess, what we
like a lot about JANN
is that it's forming
all of these connections
in a country like ours that is
very separated and very unequal.
And technology is
providing the safe space
to get together again,
if that makes sense.
Well, we thank you a lot.
And we're leaving here
our contact information.
And I don't know if we
want to add something else,
or we can maybe move
on to the questions.
MEGAN MITCHELL: Fantastic.
Fantastic.
I mean, I don't know.
You can see it from some of
the comments in the chat,
but I know I am, certainly,
inspired by the work
you're doing.
And I think it
really interesting is
the juxtaposition of how you're
approaching impacting people
at scale.
You have Cerine who's
using it for the AI
is touching the students,
right, and working directly
with the students.
You're thinking about
how you can use it
at JANN on the back
end to really reduce
the cost and the resources,
right, that are--
and so that you can get
more people into your system
and still maintain that personal
touch but then learn from it
and accelerate learning.
So there's just so
much rich, really
interesting ways that AI is
being applied that I don't I
really don't believe
people are thinking
about on a day-to-day basis.
And so I have some questions.
And as I mentioned do
if you have questions,
put them in the chat.
I would encourage you
to just mention your--
your first name is
obviously there,
but your institution would be
really helpful for context.
But one of the
things came up even
as you're thinking about
this from two different sides
of the business spectrum,
the backend business
side and the direct to the--
direct to the students.
Trust seems like an
important element
that you need to
think about throughout
the entire development.
I think there's still there
are questions of how much
can we rely on this.
So I'm curious how
you think about--
Cerine, you trust
from the standpoint
of having people believe
that this will help them
and that this automated
tutor is giving them
the support they need.
But then, as you're
pulling out best practices,
Salome and Bernardo,
how are people
saying, how do you
believe that those will
be trusted or responded to from
people who come from a more
traditional background
of teaching and education
and think, no, no, the teacher
needs to be at the center.
SALOME AUGILAR
LLANES: I don't know.
Do you want to start,
Cerine, and then we can--
CERINE HAMIDA: You can
start, and I'll continue.
SALOME AUGILAR LLANES: Sure.
Yeah, so for us, the
work with teachers
has been super important
because we get to students
through teachers.
And something that we have
really tried to convey
is the message that
we see can as a tool
in the toolkit of teachers
to share with their students.
So we are not here to replace
the teacher, not at all.
We're here to help them
go back to the topics
that they might not be
able to cover in class.
So imagine specifically in
Mexico, in the pandemic,
the students didn't go to
class almost for two years.
Like, schools were closed.
And many students did
not have the resources
to connect with their teachers.
So this means that
for two years they
have huge gaps of
knowledge, and these gaps
are all over the place.
So it's not like
the teacher can say
we're going to go back and learn
to multiply because there still
maybe going to be students
that do know how to multiply
but miss the part of how to
divide or how to sum a fraction.
And so the teacher
has a responsibility,
and they have to
cover a curriculum.
And they don't have the time
in the classroom-- usually
classrooms in Mexico
have 30, 40 students.
They don't have the time
to realize or sit down
with each student, know
what they don't, and go
back and teach that.
So here is where
the tutor steps in.
So the tutor only
has five students,
and the tutor will learn
these the gaps of knowledge
that the students have.
And instead of teaching what
the teacher is teaching,
they are free.
They can cover any
part of the curriculum.
They can adapt their
teaching to the student.
And so they're going to go back,
fill these gaps in knowledge
so that the student, when
they come back to class,
they're ready to learn what
the teacher is teaching.
So it's, kind of,
like a teamwork.
And actually our
platform allows teachers
to open a profile and
message the tutor to ask them
to cover the specific topics.
So we really want them to
feel accompanied and helped
by our program more
than challenged.
Yeah, so I guess that's
how we are trying
to build trust with them.
MEGAN MITCHELL: Interesting.
Interesting.
Cerine?
CERINE HAMIDA: So yes, for
us, trust and effectiveness
has really been at the core
of our development approach.
And we've actually been
extensively testing
the platform with students
since day really 15.
And every pillar that we've had
has been introduced and tested
with students separately.
And we've gotten detailed
feedback on all of them.
This includes the
introduction and use
of the virtual assistant,
which was something a bit
scary if you haven't
seen it before
or you haven't interacted with
a virtual assistant before.
But very quickly,
we got the students
to trust it a lot as we were
tweaking it and building it
in a way that really it
interacts with students
and tailors to their needs.
After that initial-- so
we've spent a, kind of,
a year developing this with
our initial group of students.
And then recently
in the summer we
decided to bring in a new
group of students, 35 students.
They're actually going to
be taking the Baccalaureate
this coming school year.
And we got them through two
different types of tests, a user
experience week, where
we got their feedback
on understanding--
their understanding
of the methodology,
their reaction
to the use of new things.
Like, multiple
choice questions are
quite unfamiliar for a
lot of Tunisian students.
And we saw them--
we saw that they really
got the hang of it.
They found the platform
to be really easy
and trusted it from the get go.
Then, of course, we really
had to look at effectiveness.
Is this really working?
Because if it's effective,
then automatically the student
will be hooked and will
know that it will help them.
And what we did for that
is for the second week,
we gave them a test
at the beginning
of the week about a subject that
they haven't studied before,
which is complex numbers.
Then we let them work on
the platform by themselves
after 12 hours of use and gave
them the same test, essentially.
We saw scores going from
a D to an A or a B plus.
There were huge, huge
improvements in performance
just for one week--
after one week.
And so students already
were a lot more confident,
and that made them
trust it more.
A lot of them actually
started recommending it
to their friends.
And this was even before we
haven't officially launched yet,
but they already trusted.
They're already recommending it.
And it's because they
saw these results.
And we actually gave them
pretty difficult tests.
So the fact that many of
them got A's and high B's
proves that this is effective,
and obviously, effectiveness
helps build trust.
MEGAN MITCHELL: Amazing.
Great.
Another question I have--
we've heard-- I mean, we
know there's so much promise
to this the technology and
different ways it can be used.
But there are, including people
in the chat who've mentioned,
the concerns around
does overreliance
on tools like this limit
critical thinking ability,
or connectivity issues, does
this further separate people
who have high bandwidth
connectivity from those
who have lower bandwidth?
I'm curious, like,
where do you see--
where you are cautious about the
unintended consequences of some
of these uses of technology and
how you've thought about that
as you've built and designed.
CERINE HAMIDA: Yes.
So talking about the
accessibility and connectivity
issue, I'll talk
about that one first.
We've made our platform
to be able to be
used even without having
laptops, just with a phone.
It doesn't have to be a
high performance phone.
It works pretty well.
Thankfully, everybody
has access to a phone,
and students are able to work on
the four pillars on their phone.
And we haven't really
seen huge issues.
MEGAN MITCHELL: How about
you, Salome and Bernardo?
BERNARDO GARCA BULLE BUENO: So
I think for us that has been
a question since the start of
how to reach the kids in-- the--
the last mile kids, so the
ones who don't have connection
and don't have any means of
connecting to the classes.
And for that, we have tried
out different strategies.
For example, there
is an institution
with which we did an alliance.
And they said, OK, we
will send you the kits
that you can do tutoring,
who have connection,
and then we're going to take
care of the rest because we--
many institutions they
want to cover, maybe--
I don't know-- 10,000 kids, but
they won't have the staff to do
it anyway.
But they say if JANN take
9,000, then we can take care
of the last 1,000.
So that's something
that we have tried.
Another thing we have tried
is making an alliances
with phone companies
so that they
can give at least free
credits so that the kids can
log into their classes.
Right now, we haven't
finalized any of that,
but we are pushing
to try to do that.
I don't know if you
want to add anything.
SALOME AUGILAR LLANES:
Yeah, during the pandemic,
we had an amazing experience
of teachers in the Sierra
in Puebla, who they themselves
paid for satellite internet
so that students could connect
from the school internet.
So this is something
that we also
see since the
pandemic ended, there
is more potential for students
to go to public spaces,
to libraries, to the
schools themselves
and use their resources
there and also maybe
even connect with friends
who do have the resources.
But there are definitely some--
like a population that
we keep a lot in mind
and where we're trying to
make efforts to include them
in the benefit of the tutoring.
MEGAN MITCHELL:
What about other--
are there other unintended
consequences that you've
specifically designed or you,
kind of, anticipated that you've
designed for or things
you worry about that
might have the opposite effect
of what your intention was
of access or I'm just--
BERNARDO GARCA
BULLE BUENO: So we
always worry about the safety
of the kids, for example.
For that reason,
we try to have--
we do interviews
to all the tutors.
And of course, they
are short interviews,
but there have been cases when
if we see behavior that we think
this person doesn't seem
ready to be teaching kids--
I think just one or two
times it has happened--
we decide to tell them that
we don't think there will
be a good fit for the program.
And then also even for
the safety of the tutors,
because one never knows.
We ask that all the
classes are recorded,
so there is full
transparency, and they
are uploaded in the cloud.
And we have access
to all those classes.
And so that's another point.
And the last one
I think where we
try to be careful
with our population
is that we also ask parents
that whenever it's possible,
whenever the kid is taking
the class in the same house,
there is an adult in the same
room just listening over,
making sure that the
tutoring is go as expected.
And I think with these filters,
we haven't had any problems
so far.
SALOME AUGILAR LLANES: We
have, but we have got them
in time if that makes sense.
Yeah.
No, but and also I would
add that maybe another thing
in terms of
automatization, like, yes,
we have thousands of
participants using a platform.
And this platform
is very automatized,
and we don't see many
of the processes.
So we always need to
keep this human component
where participants
can reach out and be,
like, the platform
is making something
that doesn't make sense to me.
And maybe sometimes it
is because they inputted
the wrong information
or because we
didn't think of the
exact specific case
that this tutor had.
Like, they changed universities
midway, or I don't know.
There are so many cases.
And something that
we have realized
is the more that the
program scales, the more--
so these cases that
are at the beginning,
like, maybe 10 tutors have this
problem, the moment the program
is 10 times as big it
becomes 100 tutors.
And then we think
about this problem,
and we integrate
it to the platform.
So when we say-- when we talk
about sharing the platform is,
like, we have this, we have
done this iteration process
of finding the functionalities
that really suit the tutors
and reducing the--
or maybe making the platform
more robust to all types
of occurrences that can happen.
And we know that they are
not covering all the time.
So we still have
this human component,
which allows us to improve the
future versions of the platform.
So it's very important
to maybe empower the user
to give a channel
of communication
for them to point out
mistakes in the platform
so that we can work on them, no.
And this is what it makes--
makes it a good platform.
I think also it reflects
that we are constantly
integrating the feedback that we
get from the people who use it.
And that's why it's becoming
better if it makes sense.
MEGAN MITCHELL: Absolutely.
Yes, Bill, please.
WILLIAM B. BONVILLIAN: Sure.
I've got a question for Cerine.
You're going to be reaching
students in Tunisia,
but do you have plans
to extend your program
to students in other countries.
CERINE HAMIDA: Yes, absolutely.
So we actually already have
plans for a near-term expansion
in Morocco and Western African
countries and have already
started initial talks to
introduce 1for1 to Latin
America.
WILLIAM B. BONVILLIAN:
That's great.
And a question for
Salome and Bernardo.
You're going to be--
your application of AI, which
you're obviously working on,
is identifying-- as you
told us, identifying
best tutoring approaches with
an aim to set up, kind of, best
practices for your tutors.
How do you plan to bring
that new knowledge developed
through your machine learning
approach to the tutors?
How is that going to work?
BERNARDO GARCA BULLE
BUENO: I think you.
SALOME AUGILAR
LLANES: Think this
is like a very ambitious
research agenda,
but it has a lot of steps.
The first one is what you
were saying like this.
This is a data driven approach
of letting the data speak.
We know who--
which of our tutors
were more effective
on their students.
And we're following
two approaches.
We're using the
transcriptions of the classes
as well as the
frequencies of the classes
to identify patterns that
are related to good teaching.
That's the first step.
But this is all correlations.
And we don't know if
it's going to be causal.
The second step will be to make
sense of these correlations
and of these patterns
that we're identifying
and try to translate them
to teaching practices.
So maybe, for example, by
changing some scenarios
and trying to see if these
changes in scenarios is related,
but now not changes
in frequencies
but actual what
were the words said
or what was the pronunciation
or how did the tutor interact.
So that's the second step.
Then the third step will be to
design an intervention where
we can share this knowledge
with a share of our tutors
and then run an RCT and
test whether actually
these practices helped.
So the RCT is a randomized
control trial where half
of the tutors would have this
additional information that we
gained or extracted
from the recordings,
and half of them wouldn't.
And then we will test if
it's actually working.
And if it is, then we
think this training
would be the way that
we would, like, then
start sharing this training with
all the tutors instead of just
the randomized sample.
Yeah, I don't know if you
want to add something.
BERNARDO GARCA
BULLE BUENO: No, I
think that's a really
good description of how
we're going to use AI to
make our tools better.
WILLIAM B. BONVILLIAN:
So you're going
to move to a train the tutors
kind of effort once you
develop--
as you develop the
best practices.
SALOME AUGILAR
LLANES: Yeah, there
is a potential to do like a--
so it depends on how
we end up doing it.
But there's a potential
to give tutors
feedback on their own teaching,
show them their own recording
and be like, look, there are
these metrics that you could--
if you meet them, then
you could emulate what
a very effective tutor is
doing, so like real time--
not real time because that would
be very stressful for the tutor,
but at least a feedback
on their own recordings.
But I think that is
still some years ahead.
So we haven't finalized
that those details,
but we see the potential
of doing that for sure.
WILLIAM B. BONVILLIAN: Great.
Thank you.
MEGAN MITCHELL:
I'd like to know,
you are clearly all
very talented people.
What was the inspiration?
Why is this what you've
chosen to spend your time on?
What's the origin story
of how you got here?
CERINE HAMIDA: So
I can take that.
So for me, I've always been
passionate about education,
and I believe that it is
the empowerment tool, not
just an empowerment tool,
but the one, the big one.
And a couple of years back, I
got to see some PISA results
and really was shocked
how Tunisia performed.
That led me to ask
questions, and I eventually
discovered a lot of
issues, many of which
I talked about at the
beginning of my presentation.
And when you see issues
that are that big,
you want to find a
solution for them,
especially it was
in education, which
was really important for me.
BERNARDO GARCA
BULLE BUENO: And I
think for us, the story of
JANN started in the pandemic.
I think also, as
Cerine is saying,
there was this big problem.
And Salome had a friend working
at the education ministry.
And he told her one day, OK,
they allowed us to do an RCT,
but they will spend $0 on it.
But you can do
whatever you want,
and you will have the support
of the education ministry.
And it was such a great
opportunity to say,
let's do something
for the pandemic.
There is so much knowledge saved
in the heads of people locked up
in their houses.
Let's just make them
together and make
this a win-win for everyone.
So I think that's the
story of how we started.
And I think, personally,
I don't the--
well, I have some
ideas, but each of us
has different motivations.
I think personally for me
it was finding a way that--
I have always loved
programming and finding a way
to do something that will
help people using a skill that
sometimes feels very
disconnected from society
was amazing.
And it's something that I
have loved for a long time.
And I don't know Salome.
SALOME AUGILAR LLANES: I would
say for me, I have thought--
I have given tutoring
and also worked
in social services
with children.
And I think something that
has been very important for me
is that this moment where
children realize make this ahh
sound of I understood.
And suddenly this thing
that was so, so challenging
and that I didn't understand and
I didn't know how to approach,
it's approachable.
I can do it.
It's actually interesting.
Like, changing this
mindset of it's impossible
and it's something
I will never be
able to do to it to this
is actually entertaining
and I like it and
I can share it.
And I feel like
anyone who likes math
would want to have someone
who doesn't like math
sit down and be like, let
me show you why it's cool
because I think it's cool.
And so I think sharing
this with children,
for me, that was
something super important.
And I guess the
other part was also
like when we grew
up in Mexico, Mexico
has given us so many things.
And then suddenly be thinking,
like, I went to the US.
I'm pursuing my degree.
I'm being successful.
And I'm like leaving
my country behind when
I know it has so many problems.
And I really want to give back.
So JANN has been like
an opportunity for us
and for me to be here and still
be super connected to Mexico
and still be like it makes
sense that I came here.
So yeah, it's something very,
very nice and very good feeling.
MEGAN MITCHELL: I can see
Cerine nodding in agreement.
I think that connection
back to recognizing the
how fortunate you were and
the opportunities you had
and realizing this
is your chance
to help keep moving people
forward and pay it forward,
give back, pay it forward.
So I really-- I love that.
I love that.
But in our conversations
before and you've
alluded to it throughout,
you aren't doing this alone.
Partnerships really seem to
be at the key of scaling.
Have you thought about those--
at the earliest stages
important, but then
also, as you move forward,
were those fortuitous?
Did you plan some of those
partnerships, or did they--
how have you thought
about navigating
the types of organizations
you want to be working
and how you structure
that type of relationship?
SALOME AUGILAR LLANES: OK, if
you want, we can start, Cerine.
I guess, if someone
asked me, I feel
like JANN is the result of
a collage of all the people
who have helped us.
I feel like we just
were knocking on doors
and being, like,
we imagine this.
And people would be
like, I imagine it too.
So I can make something--
like, move something
so that this happens.
So it's like it's
just the result
of so many people
believing in the solution
and working towards
the solution.
And we are just, like, the faces
in the front, who have been
knocking on all of the doors.
But for instance, the first time
that we implemented the program,
we were matched with the
director of Technical Primary
Schools in Baja, California,
which his name is Wenceslao.
And he was the one who contacted
the first universities,
and he was the one who gave
us the list of children.
And he was pushing for
it in the government.
And because he did that, we had
a letter saying, like, we can
do this in other governments
and come and knock
and other governments
and be like,
look what Baja, California did.
You just need to do this.
And on our side, we were
like providing the platform.
So it's really been a
teamwork of so many people
that have helped us.
And I feel like
something that I think
is being open-minded,
talk to people,
understand what they're doing,
see if you can collaborate.
And even if you can't, I think
I always give people in my mind
and try to connect them to other
people who they could help.
I feel like--
I think, again, just part of
forming connections, but really
connecting people can
bring things forward,
if that makes sense.
CERINE HAMIDA: Yeah
and absolutely agree.
Even for us, it was crucial
for us to work with teachers
and to understand the
specific needs of students
and the curriculum.
So we have a big group of
teachers working with us
to understand the
students, to understand
how we need to develop
the curriculum for them.
Also so two things, like,
the context of the student
but also understanding how
exactly we can help them best.
This will differ when we're
going to Morocco, for example,
or other countries.
Every specific country
has its own context,
and you can't do
that by yourself.
You have to partner
with people that
understand the context well.
BERNARDO GARCA
BULLE BUENO: And I
think we'd like to add
something last to our answer.
Because I think, as Cerine says,
we cannot do this by ourselves.
This effort of bringing
education and all the people
here who work in education
know that it's such an effort,
that even with our 7,000 tutors,
we cannot begin covering all
the educational needs we've
seen in Latin America.
So now talking about the future
of our initiative, what we're
trying to do in
JANN right now is
exactly what Salome was saying.
We have done this software.
We have this know how that
allows any institution
with a team between
two to four people
to run a huge scale program
in their own communities
and start making a change.
And for us, it has
been really motivating.
Speaking with many
institutions in Latin America
and in the world,
how they say, I
want to bring this
to my country or I
want to bring this to
my state or my city.
And that's exactly what
we're trying to do now.
Let's just give that
last piece of product
that they need to actually turn
this from an idea to a reality.
I don't know if you want
to add something, Salome.
SALOME AUGILAR LLANES: Yeah,
because there's the willingness
to do something.
Like, there's
passionate people who
want to do something
about education,
who want to help our children.
And we think we
have this tool that
can allow them to do
what they want, like,
to design their own
tutoring program to impact
their own community in the
way that they know best.
And we just would step in the
part of let's lower the cost
from building this from
scratch to a very low
because we can
provide this know how.
We accompany the universities
or the institutions
who want to organize
these programs.
So I think we are in the
stage of planning this.
Like, as Bernardo was saying,
this will be like the next step.
And so adapting our software to
be used by other institutions
and maybe like writing
down this know how
and being able to share it.
MEGAN MITCHELL:
Yeah, Bill, please.
WILLIAM B. BONVILLIAN:
Let me ask you
a question, first, of Cerine.
You've set up a
company, not an NGO.
And why do you think a company
approach is the right answer
for what you're doing in
Tunisia and then potentially
in North Africa?
Why did you pick that as
opposed to an NGO approach?
CERINE HAMIDA: Yes,
it's because of what
students are looking for.
So almost every
student in Tunisia,
Baccalaureate student is doing
something in addition to just
going to their private school.
Either they're paying for
private or group tutoring,
or they're on other one size
fits all edtech platforms.
It's really a cultural thing.
Everybody is paying
for some service,
whether it's in person
tutoring or online.
And so we didn't
want to introduce
the idea of just NGO
or a different model
because that would be
confusing for students.
They're used to already
the system of companies
offering these services.
So this is just related to
culture more than anything.
WILLIAM B. BONVILLIAN:
Thanks, Cerine.
CERINE HAMIDA: And one other
thing is that to be able to--
we are a company, obviously, but
we also want to have some kind
of NGO-like initiatives and
something that we're going to be
doing as we launch actually is
offering 1,000 subscriptions
for free for students in need.
So we're doing a
little bit of both.
But officially,
we are a company.
WILLIAM B. BONVILLIAN:
Thanks, Cerine.
And Salome and
Bernardo, you've told us
about using your machine
learning approach
and your vast
stock of recordings
to identify best practices.
And you're in the
process of doing that.
Do you have any--
can you hint some
of the best practices for us?
Can you give us a glimpse
of what you're starting
to see as best practices?
We're running out of
time, so this will just
have to be the top couple.
SALOME AUGILAR LLANES: Yeah.
So I guess, I think I
would start by saying,
like, this is very early
stage research agenda.
So we don't have any
conclusive information yet.
But the RCT Bernardo
mentioned is very,
I think, shed some light on
the results that we might find,
which is we tested the impact of
social and emotional education
on the learning of children.
And what we observed
was that children
were asking more questions,
that classes were being longer,
that they were being more
exchanges between tutors
and students.
So we think that this
component of these interactions
that students feel
comfortable in the class,
that the tutor is able to
provide an atmosphere where
the student trust themselves to
ask questions is very important.
And the key will be to
understand how and in which
moment they are able to
create this atmosphere, no.
And something that is very
important that we are also
going to test in the follow
up RCT social and emotional
learning.
So what we did, we
had a group that
had social and
emotional learning
and another one
that had history.
Both were learning
math, and we observed
that the group with social
and emotional learning
learned more math and
significantly more.
So the question now is like,
OK, but we treated both students
and tutors simultaneously,
so we don't
know if the tutors gained
skills, emotional skills
to connect with students.
If the students gain the
emotional skills to deal
with frustration
and learn and be
more able to manage the
difficulties of learning math,
or was it that through the
social and emotional learning
activities where they shared
personal details of their lives,
they shared anecdotes,
they suddenly like
recognized each
other, formed rapport
and formed that connection.
And now the tutor cares more
about this specific student,
and this student
cares more about what
the teacher is teaching
because they like them.
And then that's why they
were observing math benefits.
And these three channels have
huge policy implications,
and they differ a lot, no.
So it's very important
to understand
which channel is in place.
And so, yeah, I guess this
could be like a one step
towards understanding what
makes a good teaching strategy.
MEGAN MITCHELL: All right.
Well, I mean, I had such great
inspiration, so much energy
from both teams and
both organizations.
I think you've given us a lot
of great things to think about
and to look forward to
seeing where you bring where
you take these organizations.
And certainly, we'll keep
folks informed and aware
of what you're doing.
And if there's things we can do
always to support you at J-WEL,
please don't hesitate to ask.
Thank you all very much
for joining us today.
And I hope you have
enjoyed this conversation
as much as I know I have.
Have a wonderful morning,
afternoon, evening,
wherever you are in the world.
Thank you very much.
BERNARDO GARCA BULLE
BUENO: Thank you, everyone.
It was really great.
CERINE HAMIDA: Bye, guys.
BERNARDO GARCA BULLE BUENO:
Very good meeting you.
[MUSIC PLAYING]