today we're going to do two really
important things that we uh I really
want to get through uh today and the
first one involves um the final um
project for the class so what I'm going
to ask you to do um is to take a minute
and after I tell you what you're going
to be doing um find a a partner um if
we're not an even number um you can do a
part uh one group of three but I'd
prefer uh groups of two have tended to
work a lot better um that you're going
to be willing to work on a project
starting um next week and start thinking
about what you would like to do it can
be anything related to music theory and
Analysis in the symbolic domain that is
to say working with notes and scores not
primarily working with audio or um
things like that when you want to do
that uh take uh Aran Go's amazing
classes where you can do great projects
on audio um and it can be um it can be a
research type problem you can try to
solve a research um problem you can it
can be more of a business development
and Entrepreneurship type problem trying
to um trying to build a product that
does something interesting with music
theory or it can be a creative project
uh I've mentioned at the beginning of
the semester but I I'll want to say it
again uh the only restriction uh besides
primarily symbolically based is that if
you are doing a creative project I don't
want to it to be based on deep learning
Ai and the reason for that is as a
safety for y'all um I've allowed it in
the past and it hasn't worked very well
um and we'll get to we will do a lecture
on uh AI later on or to a topic on AI
and then I'll be able to explain a
little bit more on U what the constraint
that tends to make those projects not
work very
well so has anybody already been
thinking over the course of the semester
of something that you're interested I'm
not going to ask you to say it but I'm
just just curious who's who's been
thinking a little bit a little bit a
little bit okay so some some over here
um so let's take 10 minutes 5 minutes um
5 minutes to find somebody that you'd
like to work with so let's all stand
up okay we'll get to
um we let's let's uh no actually your
your computers are mostly closed so let
me um just remind us a little bit of the
perative topic for the week and um talk
about some of the things yes yes it's
down thank you just shout when you get
that H I did remember to turn the signal
back on but yep thank you
so we're going to talk about um some of
the other um things that we that we were
talking about last class with
algorithmic composition so first off who
now has been able to access the iliac
suite and recording okay great super so
so we're in a better uh position there
um we talked about um whether or not the
iliac Suite was um was sort of more
written to create music that sounded
like a human or whether was created to
do something very new and what did we
come to this is consensus anyone want to
throw that
out or what you towards doing something
new what's that 7030 toward doing
something new yeah yeah something like
that some some percentage some mixture
of some parts of what they were trying
to do really was about hey this is
something humans do let's see if a
computer do can do it and then there was
the moments um like the one with the
algorithmic putting of claps and and uh
hitting the violins and stuff like that
at different points which um was a
little bit more computery right we also
talked about Markov
chains um in the last class and we'll
get a little bit later on into some of
the more sophisticated statistical
learning that people are doing today
with um with AI learning but a lot of it
is very very similar it's just um a lot
faster or a lot big bigger than things
but but I want to talk about some things
um and we'll get to uh get to that later
pretend I didn't show that
so there's two ways that we can
distinguish um algorithmic composition
one of them is whether it's
deterministic or if it has a random
chance in it um whether or not every
time you play the piece or or run the
piece it will be a different piece or
it'll be the same um so I want to start
by giving I'm going to uh go pretty
egotistically with two pieces that I've
written the first one's not even really
a piece but it's kind of a little
demonstration it starts with um a demo
that you might have seen in a science uh
class or physics class where all the
balls um are moving at different lengths
but um they do kind of some interesting
optical illusion effects at various
times ASMR
oh my
God is there supposed to be a music in
the backr No No Music yet
okay so I thought what what if there was
a musical equivalent of this what if we
could write a computer program that had
um 12 lines or eight lines or something
like that that all started in phase and
then slowly got out of phase and came
back together like the pendulum and so
um this is a little bit what um what I
came up with
[Music]
okay I can't follow my own score um
properly
so what's that like the double dotted
16th rest yeah yeah so sometimes uh when
you when you're making an algorithmic
composition maybe you want to um you
know think a little bit about the
notation or maybe it would better just
to hear it without seeing the notation
at all so one of the questions is what
is um if the computer is just setting it
up so that each note comes in at a
slightly different time from the
previous what what kinds of things does
the composer have for her or his or
their um
creativity yeah go Jason which notes
which pitches show up so pitching which
pitches show up good good up um that
could in fact let me um let me do it
here is with instead of using I think I
used eight notes out of the octave here
is all uh 12 notes
[Music]
and that sounds a little bit more
familiar a little maybe a little bit
closer um why might I not have wanted to
use this as my main
[Music]
piece it has something to do with the
duration of the piece for me that that
that it ended up being a little bit too
long so yeah definitely what notes we
use okay um we can even go to weird
things that a human can't usually play
on a
piano so this is 19 tone division of the
octave let's you use a few more notes
per
octave oh oh blanking it stops stops the
music um good yeah yeah I think it's a
19 I don't think it would be 24 or
something yeah um sure it's a little
degression but it's it's kind of cool if
anybody's interested in it a 19 tone uh
division of the octave has uh has two
pretty cool properties one is that it um
it has major and minor Triads that are
very very close to acoustically or major
and minor thirds very close to
acoustically um correct while also
having perfect force and uh perfect fths
are pretty good so that's one reason the
other reason for it is a lot of 19 tone
piano uh a lot of 19 tone music is
written for Two Piano Duets where you
keep um the five yeah that's that yeah
the five Black Keys the same between
each of the pianos and then you um
retune the the white keys so that you
have a separate note for um for for each
of the is that right five seven 77 14
and five yeah yeah can't remember it's
been a long time since I wrote for 19
tone piano they don't like retuning our
pianos for that very much um but yeah so
it makes it a little bit more human
there other other choices you could
do
instruments you could do it how long it
goes how whether it's going to be slower
faster so these are some things we can
do um okay so let's
um then we'll get into
non-deterministic um things and so let's
let's code one up first so go a and grab
up before I get to um particular pieces
that are like that
um so let's try some of the things that
we might do and see how aesthetically
interesting it is oops uh where' that go
is that over here
okay got look move this over as much as
I can okay
good great
so what's the module you hope I've
unlocked it's not part of Music 21 it's
part of python in order to do
non-deterministic
composition random great so let's import
random and for now let's just import
everything from music 21 is that yep
that's good you can see that
good um who has
who has worked with the random module
before
not okay there's basically everybody you
know that random.
random gives
you between Z between Zer and one yep Oh
shoot no that's not the same as as I
might have mistyped I I I have it here
and it says it should be02
three okay okay good good good we all
know that random so um in a lot of
language is of course you'll do uh in
order to get between 0 and 100 say you
would just multiply by 100 we did pretty
well on that played the lottery today um
you just multiply by 100 python also has
this Rand
int from 1 to 100 and um this is one of
the older modules in Python so it
um it has a little bit of of uh
inconsistency with the rest of python in
that
um well this if I do this three times on
average I should be able to see the
inconsistency that it's an um it
includes the final number right so if
you do range one to 100 in Python your
last one will be 99 in most languages
but this one will include
that um really useful this is um this
might be all review for somebody is that
you can um you know do random choice so
if you have a list of things or any
other um algorithm you can randomly
choose one from that and
um you can do a Wade choice in this
simply by putting in
something oops uh I hit the wrong key
putting in something a lot of
times now there there's probably if
you're going to do this 10,000 by 10,000
there's other more efficient algorithms
you can do for this right
okay questions on Randomness outside of
music by the way there is also there's a
way that you can set it up so that it's
random at first but then you can
reconstruct your Randomness by doing uh
it's called a deterministic seed which I
often do when I'm um writing
compositions so that if there's
something I really really like I can
reconstruct up until the point I didn't
like it um
okay we're going to so let's write first
off what we call a random walk
composition so we're just going to start
by doing something pretty stupid and try
to make it better so we're going to
randomly walk around the scale um we'll
start let's create um something that's
going to be a useful heler
function which is uh I'll call it
multi-show you you can skip the
annotations while you're doing this so
what this does is just going to take in
a stream and show
it as um as both an image and midi so if
we you know Bo we'll just do our
favorite Bo piece just a demo BWB
66.6
multi-show Bo this I find helpful for um
for anytime I'm working with something
always takes for a lot longer when I'm
projecting and the first time but you
get the
score and then below oops that never
looks right on the video
oops yep that's a piece we know okay so
that's just a useful helpful function so
um one of the uh one of the parts of of
the pitch that of pitches that I find
really helpful for not being completely
random here is this um thing that would
have been really helpful on that problem
set where you um had to determine the
number of lines the generic intervals
between uh notes if you remember that
that's something called dionic note
number dionic note number and this is a
concept that I couldn't um that I was
really really surprised I was like
somebody must have named this and it
didn't didn't seem to have a name before
it's simply just like
has I don't think I went over this in
class right now think so that C4 middle
C is arbitrarily assigned to MIDI number
60 um arbitrarily assigned middle C to
dionic note number that's midi 60 29
it's not neither of these are completely
arbitrary there's a reason for them and
the notion is that all C's CS except Etc
have dionic note num 29 so C
sharp and that just tells you um see
double sharp yep okay so on see
flat great and so this is helpful for
writing dionic music that you can just
manipulate the dionic note number of a
note and you don't have to worry um
making it um sound a little bit better
or something we should have a pentatonic
note number also because that that's
makes it even better to do something
okay so what I'm going to do is um and
then we can just do n.
pitch. diatonic not Nom plus equals
4 and move things around that
way if you haven't seen it yet one of
the um things in music 21 that's not uh
so good is that you'll often need to
copy things so we'll get to that in just
a little bit but I'm going to import
copy and if you've never used this um
copy
and oops copy is a module copy.
copy so I did turn n into a g and so now
it's a g there's two things um who who
has never who has used the copy module
in in Python before no not too many okay
good so so because cuz for the most part
you might just want to do you know just
create another note if you wanted to do
that don't need to type that um but you
can also copy an existing one and what
you'll use much more is a something
called Deep
copy and the difference you can see that
copying the note gives you a a note
that's G deep copying gives a note
that's G the difference is that um well
here easier to easier to just show than
tell right um n c is no is going to be
the copy of
N and we'll say DC is the
Deep my computer just froze there we go
uh DC is the Deep copy of
n the difference is so if here we'll
just make sure that they're all here
they're all yep three
notes difference is if we take n it's
pitch
dionic note
num and go up four
more
that the copy of n also
changes whereas the um the Deep copy
doesn't change and so what uh some
people might think of this as um you you
you end up working with this with a
arrays in a lot of other languages and
stuff that copying an array you still
have references to the internal pointer
so anything that is itself an object
like n.
pitch and nc.
Pitch will still be the same under a
shallow or normal
copy but with a deep copy they're
different
deep copies
pitch so you'll find when you're when
you're manipulating things and you you
get to a particular point in the score
and now you want to add something else
that's a manipulation of what came
before you'll want to make a deep copy
of it beforehand does that make sense
cool are we questions yeah what did you
show with the last part so like the
pitch is going to be different by
definition um oh sure sure I think it's
a little bit hard because this is part
here so when you make a shallow copy and
you change some and you change some
nested structure within there like a
pitch or a duration it will not be
um they're they're all shared so so what
you do is sort of think of it as um I
don't know what's what's something else
is not sh so N is a note and N has I
wish I had set this before ID equals
note and
pitch equals some sort of a pitch. pitch
object and Dot uh duration I say dur is
some kind of duration
object when you do a shallow copy
NC will be NC's ID equals n's ID and
NC's pitch
equals NC uh n's
pitch and so since ID is just a string
or something like that once it's copied
over they have no connection to each
other but since we've copied the pitch
over and it's uh it's a complex object
when you change something on this when
this manipulates this
manipulates so with a but with a deep
copy we you do is dc.
pitch oh hold that first let's do a deep
copy of the pitch and so you keep going
down and you make sure that nothing is
connected between the
two that this also slightly misleading
right because you like there's nothing
that actually says nc. pitch is equal to
n. pitch in fact like that's the whole
point like if it did that that would be
an example of deep copy right no because
you're you're referencing the same
object in pointer So when you say n.
pitch it's actually thinking in the
computer oh that is the complex object
being stored at some random memory
location somewhere okay so pointing to
the label so it's still pointing to the
same label yeah so exactly for for
people who know that kind of terminology
um it's pointing to the same label
whereas this one goes to the label and
copies everything and makes a new new
pointer uhh
so th that ends up being pretty
important and if anybody wants to make
their um final project making music 21
faster you could find places that we
deep copy more than we have to because
that's s of the slowest thing in that um
in what what's happening okay too much
of an aside back to some music great so
we'll get back to our random walk
composition once I find where this went
yeah here we
go great so we're going to be copying
things uh pretty soon but first let's
just create we'll create a generic
stream which we rarely do nowadays besid
maybe we want to make it a part or
something but generic stream will work
pretty well and let's just say for I in
range
30 let's just append 30 random
notes or no let's let's do let's do this
no let's start on C
current well just we'll just call it
Curr that's current datomic note number
um when we're coding fast we don't need
my obsession with long variables right
so we'll say note equals note.
note and Pitch dionic note num equals
the current
one and that works pretty well um stream
append sorry thank you that's why I
shouldn't do that thank you please all
always just do that I appreciate that
big help um and we'll just say we're
going to choose between going down a
step going up a step and so on so our
first note will always
be c c C4 and now let's multi-show
that pretty boring piece
but here we go oh this one went down
this
[Music]
time Etc anybody's more interesting
anyone's go up and want just hit
play yeah okay so not a great piece uh
the easiest thing I could do to make it
a little bit better by the way would be
make my number of notes I attached be um
a what do you call it a multiple of four
right but okay so let's let's move on to
do some things that are a little bit
more interesting um maybe we could do
something like this let's um I'm going
to copy and paste a lot on this so we
can go ahead and just tweak what we're
doing you in fact probably don't even
need to copy and paste you can just keep
tweaking the same cell forever so what's
something we should do to make this a
little bit more
interesting Rhythm great so let's um
have each note and. duration do
something what do we want to do
think about um something for it wasn't
for a duration okay then hold it hold it
when we get to let's let's finish the
duration and then then yeah then we'll
get to the John a choice
variable quarter half and duration great
so Random Choice what's while I start
typing this out what goes after the endu
duration
do quarter half
E I don't remember What's this
called unhelpful it's called the type
the type quarter length we'd have to say
we could put it in as one two2 yep one
let's see if that makes it a little
bit nicer
[Music]
it's actually already
nicer usually this doesn't help as
[Music]
much
okay next Improvement I'm just going to
keep going on this yeah you
can what's that up a third go yep it can
go up a third or down a third now do we
want to make it a weigh probability at
all so how much more we want it up a
third is minus two because we're
thinking um in computer think not in
music theory think so that would be
unweighed and how do we want away this
to make it feel more
musical higher weight on stepwise motion
higher weight on
stepwise 1 negative 1 one one okay let's
try that
[Music]
he that's our first
step not not so good okay so we still
need some things that's that's definite
Improvement thank you uh another another
thing to improve let's
keep yeah Jon decrease the weight on
staying on the same note decrease the
weight on staying on the same note okay
so what we can do is the easiest way
when you're programming really fast in
front of a class do that is cut and
paste don't do this in your actual
things you turn in but cut and paste and
just delete the that zero is that
good it's already looks a little bit
better I want next let's do another
Improvement on rhythm
yeah it's they have not starting
on
on okay good so we want to try to weigh
it somehow so that we're we have notes
that start on the downbeat more talk
with your neighbor on how you might
Implement
that okay let's let's come back together
uh
anybody okay let's let's jump in while
well and we'll try to program it
together because we'll do this in class
somebody I haven't heard from yet want
to give a
suggestion hasn't
spoken try to keep track of an offset
and then based on the offset so have a
different probability based on the
offset What What offsets In currently
with the default time signature 44 why
do we make that default very hit demonic
but okay um what what offsets represent
the
um the uh
downbeat anybody
can zero zero definitely represents a
downbeat what other
offsets so have we been creating
measures by the way first off let's look
at that so we've kind of um taking uh
advantage of Music 21 or some something
creating measures for us so our offsets
we start with zero and then we're just
appending so so what's our next
downbeat four good good and somebody
else what's what's our general formula
we're going to find
for
downbeat Zer
mod yeah then uh we could check if the
if the um off offset is um mod 4 is zero
right so let's so we'll get to before we
um before we do that so let's say what's
our
current offset so one of the things we
can do is we can keep track of our
current offset now we're going to wish
we had um 0.0 now we're going to wish we
had done this as quarter lengths so I'm
going to rewrite this as quarter
length why because it's easier to add
quarter lengths than it is types right
so one to 0.5 and we'll just
say ql
equals random
Choice okay so what we can do
is well now I'm just going to make sure
that I still have a current thing and
Cur offset plus equals ql
so I haven't done anything to adjust our
probability yet just making sure that
this works yep it still generate sign so
how how can we use this to implement the
great suggestion that we want to have
things that fit on the downbeat more
often um do something else so we'll say
is on
downbeat equals uh Cur
offset per
zero you got say equals um here we could
say true this is the easiest way if
current offset Mod 0 equals 0 else false
um you can do it you can realize that
that Boolean expression will be you know
reduce itself but I like to be explicit
when I'm thinking um so now we know if
something's on the downbeat what do we
want to how do we want to do it
differently do you need to brainstorm
torm thanks Adam I want to want to hear
from some some more voices um even
though you're doing great good Vanessa
yeah uh and if it's not on the downbeat
it as what it was before you leave it as
what it was before let's try that um oh
yeah so we have a last Q so we'll Define
ql outside of here uh will be pretty
pythonic uh equals what we'll say our
last one is zero was one we're actually
not going to um because we all will
always start on the downbeat ql will be
defined but let's do good programming
techniques and Define it outside good so
if is on if not is on
downbeat okay let's see if that
otherwise we're just going to stay on
whatever we were on before let's see
we'll think it through first will that
did I get one ql will have a not defied
error I think
it oh sorry yep that's why we that's why
I was talking about defining it good
good catch though um always don't no
crashed 787s because of not defined
errors that's a famous story um okay so
let's make um let's make sure that we're
not going to end up permanently like uh
syncopated or something we start on the
downbeat and then we choose between
maybe I should put these in some sort of
logical order 2 1 0.5 we randomly choose
between half note quarter note and
eighth note and we're on the Down Beat
and so we're going to stay on that for a
bit will we always end up back on a down
be at some
point we start on a Down Beat we choose
2 1 0
.5 in this particular piece who votes
yes who votes we might be permanently
syncopated
ah spend more time reading code than
writing
code it looks like we might yeah because
like it only switches the quarter length
if
we're not on the down did I do that
wrong do we want to keep it we wanted to
do I have a misplaced
knot so that's what we wanted a little
bit right if we if we're on the downbeat
we can change to a new Rhythm if we're
not we
can't think let's let's run let's
generate
this yeah so so what's the consequence
of this somebody else
y it's the same type of notes uh it's
the same type of notes every measure you
know what I'm going to change that over
oh no no we can't determine the length
of the piece right so we might um so we
might have that yeah every measure will
always have um the same type of thing I
it's kind of nice for a lot of my junior
high atude books were like this right
that you only switch rhythms but but
maybe what's what's one way that we can
switch a little bit better more often we
could just say um I mean we should
rename our variables but maybe this will
feel much more unified we'll just do it
on every two
[Music]
does okay that's enough that's already
becoming more more unified so what what
are some things that we could hack into
this
we're not we're done for a little bit
but
um what's some things that we can make
it sound a little bit more
human Harmony we could add Harmony good
we could add random or appropriate
probably more appropriate yeah Jason we
could allow it to occasionally break
these rules by well probably by random
chance but so certain random chance that
would break the rules yeah uh one of the
things here I'm not going to do this but
I gave a particular random chance that
um that something might uh go up an
octave in another time when I did this
and um there was some danger in allowing
that um this is a particular problem
with Muse score that if you overflow
256 uh it jumps it's uh unsigned which
is kind of cool that that the world of
notation wraps around um but yeah but so
I obviously was what was allowing this
one random seven is an octave if you're
adding to it to happen a little too
often so that that can be a danger but
it happens thanks for gra that um yeah
so those are some of the other things
you can do maybe we want it to sound a
little less now I'm going to start doing
this I just need to not make it full
screen you can make it a little bit less
human and make it do these weird micro
tones or not less human but less um sort
of traditional right and and where' that
go uh here here we can hear it these
[Music]
unfortunately so there there are ways
that you can do something things um that
allow you to you know be more
experimental if you want or less
experimental great
um so we'll keep playing with that what
you'll probably um realize one of the
things we're building up to so you're
given a problem Set uh problem set 78 as
I said it's um not in the 78 time that'd
be too lops side it's in um but what it
is is it gives you um some work with
scales and with Roman numerals and then
there's two parts for you to do an
open-ended thing one is we're going to
be asking you in the first half to write
a Roman numeral analyzer just for
Triads um in
major and it's just going to be for
Block chords I'll be I'll give you I'll
give you three notes you tell me what
ran numeral it is uh if you've if you're
a little bit behind uh if you sorry if
you if it's been a while since you've
done Roman numeral analysis or you feel
a little bit weak on it you know
collaborate talk with other people on
that make sure that you're really clear
what a diminish Triad and all that
things is um so grab somebody before you
leave the room and then there's a little
open-ended thing where I just ask you do
something a little bit more maybe you
have something that works in minor maybe
you have it do seventh chords maybe you
work in jazz and popular music and you
think Roman numer rals oh that's only
for classical music I'm going to have it
do chord symbols C and things like that
instead so whatever you want there'll be
just a small uh part of it I should have
it open in fact I think I no I only have
it with all the answers open never
mind and then the last part is
um I want an algorithmic conf opposition
that you like it could be multi-art it
could be single part if it's interesting
it could be with chords without chords
but just something where you've done
some sort of interesting music theory
I'll I'll say that what we've given here
is the quential D minus so far try to go
better than n maybe it's a d actually by
this point we're getting to we're
getting a little bit better don't spend
the entire semester on it this is not
meant to be the gigantic project that
you take forever on um the only
restriction I'm giving is um that I'd
like it to be about a minute long not
two minutes long not 12 minutes long
because uh I have to uh if everybody
turns in a 10-minute composition then
I'll be listening to algorithmic
compositions uh forever um so if you can
uh do that that's going to be that main
part um any questions about what we did
with kind of playing around with
algorithmic composition
today okay uh then I'm going to be uh
little egotistical for a second and um
and talk about um what one of my first
uh algorithmic compositions that got per
that at some point people were
performing um and it's a piece for this
group called The bang Onan Allstars
which uh some of you might recognize the
clarinetist is zorin so another
professor who's here um who does a lot
of things and um it was based on Markoff
chains so the notion uh that what I
wanted was some kind of a Melody that
was a little bit boring a little not
boring but but just sort of
undistinguished except it had these
weird bumps in it some things that
sounded a little bit weird like this
opening
trone and then some these weird gestures
Y and so some things that you hear
enough times you're like okay I know
that that's what the piece is about and
try to see if in the um this is I can't
remember when is from 2005 it was a
little bit it was pre- deep learning and
things so just probability Theory um
whether or not the computer would the
Markoff chain would do some interesting
things with this and then one of the
things I really wanted was someplace
like an old record player that would get
stuck in a in a loop and um need to be
judged out of it so I have a few play
where um the same thing happens over and
over and over again if you're thinking
about what we were talking about the end
of last class about the probability of B
given a the next note or we could say N2
given
N1 uh this is what order markof chain
are we talking about
here first order right based on one
previous note I used a bunch of
different orders in this U piece
depending on how random I wanted
it to be um I wanted that when you got
to that note
a that the probability given a was very
high that you
would do another a so I sort of weighed
the probability so the probability of an
a given an a was I don't know something
like 0.9 or something so the computer
would get stuck in this particular
Groove at some
points um and we'll see what I would do
at some points is just keep the melody
um just keep the notes and let the
rhythms be out but uh if this is treble
cleff that's an opening gesture of b f
comes back a lot BF and
there's you'll hear that a lot and then
getting stuck in that a Groove
again you you'll hear
that and what I did was back the old
days I just had it generate a whole
bunch of Melodies and I kept the ones I
wanted so I wanted to do my computer um
type of
thing uh one last little thing is that I
had this sort of
um progression that begins one beat per
second so 60 BPM then moves there was a
section of 1.5 beats per second two
three four and then the final note is a
dissonance that vibrates five beats per
second so that's kind of the little
Easter egg in the piece and then I took
the 1.5 beats per second and moved it
because that's what composers
do uh when I when when the piece was
premiered uh they'll never be happy with
me at the printing office again um I
gave every person in the audience a
different set of program notes that
began by saying the end the opening of
the piece is rather straightforward and
then I wrote about 10 pages is worth of
program notes and everyone got a markof
chain of the program notes so it has U
something kind of looks like something
then uh it ended with but always with a
hint of order no matter what they had so
um I'm just going to be indulgent and
play a little bit of something I wrote a
while back
[Music]
okay
ch
[Music]
and here's where I let the computer
start taking over
[Music]
sh
I think I told the computer to multiply
the intervals by two for more leapy
[Music]
[Applause]
this is completely markof chained here
[Music]
you can kind of hear where it's stuck
again
[Music]
anytime you see a two measure repeat the
timing didn't work
[Music]
[Applause]
let's do this
to yeah thanks everybody you don't need
to write that much please don't write
that much for your algorithmic
composition but feel free to have a
mixture of your own personality and your
own desires and let the computer do some
things that kind of inspires you