go uh my name is Brian Anthony I'll I'll
chare the session really what that's
going to mean for this session is I'll
give you a case example of what we mean
in this case about talking about
modeling of matter as you'll see we're
going to talk a lot about Imaging uh
Imaging of matter and how we use that to
characterize or control the the
production of matter in this session um
we won't have a panel discussion at the
end so after each speaker we should have
time for one or two questions so each
person will have about 15 minutes or so
I'll try to keep mine under that um but
be ready with your questions for each
speaker after after they
go okay so um with that um our prior
session was talking about novel
computation novel computers the the the
stuff on which we run algorithms so it's
nice to sort of connect to there um we
heard a little bit as well about sort of
the applications in in medicine um so
we'll make some connections to there so
Imaging of matter um what we're going to
talk about though is is in many ways
computational Imaging or or modern
Imaging in some sense so computational
Imaging is the intersection of
collecting data and processing that data
um to make an image right unlike what
you think of maybe the way that your
cell phone works uh you don't actually
see the raw data that comes off of your
image sensor uh you see a highly
processed image and often with their
modern phones they're taking multiple
images to sort of create something that
is sort of rich in experience and allows
you to rapidly segment and and have
multiple focal
planes so um and I don't Advocate this
new selfie stick but you know we we we
benefit a lot from the the types of
computation that we can intersect with
imaging and image is a function of our
data um so there are many forms of
computational Imaging tomography whether
it be x-ray or or
ultrasound imaging off of of disperse
and non-reflective surfaces seeing
around corners for example High dynamic
range Imaging and many other
examples what I want to do is I'll use
start with ultrasound tomography I'll
use ultrasound as a motivating case
example for how we think about this
session being the intersection of
Imaging physics Imaging data for
characterization and for process control
where we're exploring or creating novel
materials so I'm going to start with the
macro scale I'm giving you an example of
the space of of computational Imaging um
what we're seeing in the middle is a a a
lowcost um ultrasound imaging tank where
we have what's moving is a single
transducer uh that is receiving the
sound that is currently being generated
by the stationary transducer which is on
the other white frame the data that's
being collected in this is the
transducer that's stationary sends out a
sound wave that you can see represented
sort of in the bottom image of it's
playing yeah there it goes and that
sound wave goes into the medium that is
in the water tank in this case it's a
it's a replica of a human limb it
balances off of the interfaces and then
goes out to be received by all of the
virtual receivers that are around this
tank in this case that those virtual
receivers are the the moving platform
and the the left and right images are
the the raw data that we collect now
those data can be put into a the wave
equation uh and we can iteratively solve
the wave equation to take those
observations and say well what did the
thing that the sound was propagating
through need to be to explain our
observations so that's sort of a
classical inverse problem where I'm
going to collect all these data I'll go
through this iterative process of
forming this image that's shown in the
center to result in a final speed of
sound image now in doing that though um
it goes through this algorithm this
computation the punchline of this
algorithm though is what is happening is
I'm comparing my observations the data
that I've collected I'm iteratively
running those data through a simulation
comparing the those data to a simulation
of a the medium the the the water tank
with something in the center of the
water tank where I've
simulated what the distributions of the
density and the speed of sound are in
that Medium propagate synthetic data so
simulated data through that to generate
a a synthetic or a fake data set and I
compare that data set to the things that
I've observed and I sequentially over
time converge until I figure out well
what was that map what was that image of
what is in our
domain now um I can do that I can apply
it to a lot of different processors and
because I'm iterative applying a a very
complex with lots and lots of data full
waveform a physics model um it takes me
a lot of time 3 to 6 hours just to
collect one the data set can be acquired
in 10 minutes but it takes many hours to
actually robustly solve that iterative
problem that's potentially a challenge
um but I do get something nice and
beneficial by having all these data
coming at different angles I'm actually
able to break what you might normally
think of as the wavelength resolution of
the wave that we're using so the speed
of sound in a medium has a certain
wavelength that should be the limit of
the resolution that we're able to
resolve but since we have these data
from different orientations around it
we're able to actually get something a
little bit better than wavelength
resolution now if we had that data in
real time though we could actually use
it to control a process so what type of
process could that water tank
potentially be used for so we can sort
of do characterization and we can do
online or sort of real-time
characterization
so in this case the one of the
motivating applications for this water
tank uh phenomena is can we collect data
of an from an ampute te um in sitting on
a comfortable table with their leg
residual limb in a water tank have this
ultrasound thing spin around them and
come up with an image that characterizes
both the geometry of their limb in three
dimensions not just a slice and also the
tissue properties of the limb if we have
that type of data and if we can do it in
10 20 30 minutes and not have to wait
hours for this type of data um we could
collect it something like this um we
could have then instead of just a slice
that is showing the geometry the image
what you typically think of as the
structure in your image um you could
have both the structure and the material
properties and with those material
properties then I can then feed that
data into an additive manufacturing
process or I can 3D print a socket that
is the perfect G geometry it sort of
matches conformally the outside geometry
of the limb but also has the correct
material properties so it's it's
mechanically stiff where it needs to
mesh it's mechanically soft where it
needs to mesh with the mechanical
properties of the limb right so I need
to be able to acquire that data in real
time so I'm not having my patient
sitting there in a long time with the
prosthetic trying to form my my my the
cup that's matching me to my my
prosthetic okay so if we're able to do
something like that real
time then there's many applications but
how do we make it real time how do we
get around how can we use sort of comput
other computational approaches to get
around the fact that fundamentally if we
really want to have that analysis the
mechanical properties be physic
physically grounded the the structure be
physically grounded you know how do we
use machine learning how can we do some
training to maybe think of a faster way
to not solve the inverse problem
um but a a learned way to solve the
inverse problem so when we're doing
classical inversion the way that we're
going to do this is collect our data and
iteratively solve a physics physics
problem but can
we feed the the inverse of that problem
so feed in the the image that we're the
data that we're acquiring and
automatically train a network to kick
out the image that's what machine
learning could provide for us but to do
that we need lots and lots and lots lots
of data
and human data is really hard to acquire
so there's no easy source of of the
massive quantity of data that we'd like
to acquire to teach a network how to
very rapidly solve our inverse problem
the the raw data that we get in and
automatically fast kick out the image
even if it takes a long time to train
the algorithm you know we can imagine
the inverse being that running that
inverse problem being fast so we don't
have a lot of really good easy data to
acquire on humans that would be the the
the training data that we would need for
this but we do have really good physics
models of of the physics of the Imaging
process in this case of ultrasound we
can write down the first principles of
the wave equation dispersive or not in
two dimensions and three dimensions we
can create a a speed of sound map of
some domain we can simulate a transducer
the mechanical properties of the
transducer and how sound propagate
through that so we can create some
really robust synthetic data we can
simulate them
for our Imaging
scenario or the water tank and a
residual limb put into the center of the
water tank we can simulate for all the
as many different sort of physical
virtual physical things that we want to
put into that domain we can simulate and
understand what those ultrasound signals
would be and then we can flip it around
now we have a physics based or a
synthetic way of getting our training
data and the input to a network for
which we want to learn the parameters of
how we map input to Output data the
input would be the raw data that we
receive see if my laser pointer works
here oops the raw data that's not the
laser
pointer we go the raw data that we
receive um going into a network to
automatically kick out the sounds speed
map now machine learning is great for
fitting within the boundaries of the
data that is that it has observed right
it's not going to work very well for
things that it hasn't n observed so just
as an aside one of the nice things about
this type of approach if we can teach a
network to take our raw data in and get
a good estimate of what the actual
domain looks like what the speed of
sound map looks like then we could also
use that as the starting guess to our
conventional or classical physics-based
inversion process that the closer that
we can get our initial guess the initial
condition of that iterative Loop we
don't have to be constrained just having
observations that are uh that that our
network has been trained with but we can
sort of get close and then still allow
the physics to sort of do the things
that are maybe outside of our
observational space okay so this is what
a network looks like um that has allowed
us now to First confirm with our
synthetic data that if on the left we
have these are data that weren't used in
the training of this network there
speeds the sound Maps randomly generated
we trained a network how to do this
Imaging how to create those images
directly from the raw data that we
acquire and you see some of the noisy
images that are generated on the right
now we've been able to do this now to do
realtime Imaging of this of the speed of
sound map so the tomography example that
I showed you previously water tank this
data that's collected over 10 or 20
minutes still takes three hours to
reconstruct to form the speed of sound
map the image on your right was
collected and analyzed in real time 30
frames per second and it was that image
inversion had been is performed by a
network that we've trained with
synthetic data but these are now being
applied on real data so here just to
show um how one of the areas of how
we're using this um if you take muscle
um if you activate muscle meaning you're
loading it or unloading it the speed of
sound in the muscle changes so if you
have the ability to
image the speed of sound of the tissue
in real time you can actually visualize
in real time how your muscles are being
activated and so here we do an
experiment um in the emersion lab over
at MIT Nano where we go through the
squatting exercise standing on your toes
and squatting while we're collecting
real time ultrasound data of a probe
attached to the side of the leg and we
can see through these this this false
coloring the coloring being
corresponding to the speeds of sound in
the muscle the thing that we would
expect to happen in normal healthy
muscle which is when we go from a
standing to a squatting um motion that
the the muscle activation is going to go
from the gastrock to the Solus and then
when going when starting in a squatting
position back up to active it goes
similarly from the soas back up to the
gastrock right now that is true in the
situation where we have healthy muscle
we see this transition the red going
from the bottom the red going to the top
but it it also allowed Us in this very
um small clinical study in N of two two
people we found and um accidentally
discovered and sent this individual off
to get um to to actually see a doctor
where the was later confirmed that this
individual had nerve damage they did not
realize they had nerve damage um but
their muscles had their brain had
learned how to rewire how their muscles
activated and we observed something very
unusual in their muscle activation
process through observing speed of sound
maps from a network that had been
trained with synthetic data coming from
a physics
model okay so um what I want to do today
and so here just sort of with that same
idea for ultrasound scanning um we're
also applying moving from the macro to
the micro and it can be used for doing
things like characterizing of defects
and voids through a package where you
can see both the package and the
internal structures you can see de
delaminations and structures and and
things that you wouldn't see in an x-ray
you can see because you're able to
visualize some of the mechanical
properties that AR that aren't visible
in x-ray um but what I want to do today
is is for this session take this
perspective of well where does
computational Imaging so this
intersection of Imaging physics Imaging
data allow us to impact Metrology so if
we're doing offline
characterization um or sort of online in
real time
characterization and and we'll see when
we conclude with Julie um that one of
the points that came up earlier today
where well how is AI actually allowing
us to physically interact with the world
we have some interesting ways to connect
image acquisition with robotic
manipulation of helping us to discover
and experiment with materials and so
there's there is early work that is
helping us to sort of connect physical
interaction with the world based on
automatic decisions that an AI or an
algorithm is telling us so we're going
to hear today U First from George Barb
stus that'll talk a little bit about
Optical physics and machine learning uh
for inspection and control uh Bill
Freeman will talk a little bit about
visualization of the tiniest little
motions in so looking at how we can
apply those in other domains and then
Julie finally a little bit on on
autonomous exploration of materials uh
again we're not going to take uh
questions at the end we'll take them at
the as after each speaker except for me
um and with that I we turn it over to uh
my good friend uh George um and um we'll
take it away
okay thank you
Brian Okay so so my name is George
barbastathis
um and
um so I'll be talking about something
very related actually so I'm very
grateful to Brian for the for the um for
for the setup I guess um so first of all
let me acknowledge all my my former and
current students especially those in
boldface um and um so I'll pick up from
where Brian left it uh basically our
claim here is that using machine
learning in something like computational
Imaging maybe it's a good idea right so
I'll try to make the case for why it is
a good idea and show you a few examples
of the work we did in our group so I
think you're all familiar with these S
curves it basically tells you that even
if you're willing to pay a lot of
money at some point performance such
rates usually because of some physical
limitation and the technological
innovation is actually to push up the S
curve so you can either pay the same
money and get better performance or
actually pay less money for the same
level of performance that before used to
cost you a lot of money so the way we
figured out how to use um how to how to
shift up the curve in computational
imaging is as Brian very well put it by
a combination of optical physics and and
data and AI and I'll show you a few
cases so so we started working on this
about 8 years ago in
2016 interestingly it came up through a
disagreement I had with a student of
mine Justin Lee who had sort of an
argument and and we decided to do this
kind of work but uh so basically I'm
touting my own horn here but before that
I really want to acknowledge at least
one uh other colleague that is professor
uner at tfl who he started doing this at
about the same time as us and he showed
that it is possible to reduce the dose
of X-ray radiation on a patient by using
AI that was un's accomplishment as far
as back as then so that was very
inspiring for us and um and then of
course we did a lot of work and I'll
tell you a little bit about it one of
them one of these had to do can I go
back yeah okay here we go yes one of
those projects had to do actually with
um integrated
inspection that was founded by an agency
called I arpa where I stands for
intelligence and there's not the
intelligence as in AI That's the
intelligence in the CIA acronym okay so
I have no idea why they wanted to
inspect circuits but they they gave us a
project to do it it's a it's a really
difficult problem circuit inspection
because of course circuit features are
very very small they go down to maybe a
few nanometers these days and also it's
a lot of them uh this calculation
actually I computed about 10 to the 18
voxels that you need of course voxel is
a 3D generalization of a pixel so this
calculation is already conservative I
did this a few I don't know a few years
ago and already the number of degrees of
freedom in this imag system is higher so
it's vast right sort of astronomical
level uh
complexity and this is actually what uh
Drew was What attracted us to this to
this project we we thought AI can help
us do it so we succeeded but it it
actually took us a long time to figure
out what exactly AI can do and actually
it comes down to Time Savings uh we were
able to do an operation that without AI
would take a rather long time we were
able to do it 100 times faster and you
can see one reconstruction here of one
such circuit and also I should
acknowledge the most of these data were
taken at actually not most all of these
data were taken at at argon National
Laboratory uh with a synchrotron a
synchrotron is a kind of a x-ray quasi
laser okay it is a vast instrument it's
diameter is a couple of miles if I'm not
mistaken maybe bigger and they they were
taking the data and
um and uh I think I put yeah maybe I'll
tell you a little bit about how this
works it involves two operations in one
of them you kind of zigzag a beam over
the integrated circuit and collect uh
data this is called tgraph and then the
second step is you rotate the specimen
as as you know with respect to the
incident beam and you repeat you zigzag
and you rotate and you zigzag and you
rotate the rotation is tomography Brian
showed the sound uh equivalent of it
this is of course X-rays and the
combination of those two is called tyo
tomography now why you need both steps
it's a little bit technical so if you
want I can tell you after the talk and
um I'm not joking here actually for a
full integrated circuit uh that you
might use as a CPU or a memory somewhere
it would take a full year I'm really not
joking a full year it would have to sit
in front of the synchroton and be
scanned and all kinds of computations
it's a really moonot kind of problem so
we were able to reduce that by a factor
of 100 which makes it I guess worth a
few days H we did a scal down version um
let me tell you a couple of other things
first so one thing we broke kind of a
record there uh one of the ways to
reduce the time it takes to do this
Imaging operation is obviously to reduce
the exposure kind of like uner had done
but here we do it not because the
circuit Minds the exposure we do it
because we want to do it faster right so
we kind of overdid it we went down to
one Photon per pixel now if you don't
remember how much energy is in a photon
let me tell you that the level of
Illumination here is 10 to the 18 times
less than the light we have in this room
10 to the 18 that's 10 with 18 zeros
following right that's the level of
Illumination that we used and we were
able to you know to actually get good
quality images as you can see in a
series of papers
and then we did the tomography problem
first we did it with a toy problem with
a glass actually not a real AC glass uh
but on the on the glass we patterned
things that look like circuits in fact
we copied a cad file from a real circuit
and that's what I'm showing here and of
course people were making fun of us they
were saying this is ridiculous why do
you do it this is this is not solving a
real problem but actually thanks to this
experiment we we did manage to solve the
real problem that's how we did the
actual integrated circuit basically we
thanks to the what we learned from the
glass Phantom we were able to figure out
how to reduce the number of exposures in
tomography and still recover the same
quality of the Reconstruction on the
integrated circuit so we did a lot of
this analysis and um and um basically
this shows you how the how what is the
limit of image so that of how few
exposures you can do without uh
sacrificing any image quality that is
the purpose of this analysis here and
this is basically what the factor of 100
came
from okay so I'll tell you one more
example this is now in the
pharmaceutical
industry H and uh it is not uh it is not
Imaging um sort of objects like
integrated circuits but imagine powders
which are used in the manufacturing of
PE this turns out to be a very delicate
process and you want to be delicate
because when you take a drug it better
be precisely the dosage that is
prescribed right that's very important
and the FDA has a lot of very stringent
requirements for how these processes
should operate so what you see this
movie there is one of the stages of this
process where they have to dry the
powder and they have to do it carefully
so it does not agglomerate if it aerates
basically the FDA requirement will not
be met and the company will lose a lot
of money so they have people who look
into the reactor and try to discern
visually if the process is agglomerating
so they can take corrective action so we
didn't do that what we did is actually
we simply illuminated with a laser beam
and then um we do not even bother to
image the power we take the back scatter
from the particles from the from the
surface of the particles and then we you
we use a physical law it turns out with
Optical figes you can calculate
something called the autocorrelation of
this scattering um scattered beam and
then you can see in real time we can
characterize the histogram of particle
sizes so this is of course a control
experiment where we know exactly the
particle sizes we can verify that
they're correct and then we did um let
me skip this one and come back to it and
then we did experiments with actual
processes so you can see here the
initial histogram is the red one then
the process begins to agglomerate it
shifts to the right which is blue and
then we pour more solvent it shifts back
to the green near the center and then
finally near the end you get something
called attrition the particles due to
friction they actually begin to crack
and that's why the histogram SES to the
left but you only see four curves here
in fact there is thousands of Curves
here that we obtain at U not quite video
rate but about half the video rate so
it's actually pretty fast and our
colleagues are very excited because this
will allow them
to physically quantify now this very
complicated dry and other processes in
pharmaceutical industry this was funded
by Takeda by the way which is a
pharmaceutical company with offices and
Labs nearby in
Cambridge I want to go back and show
this because this shows that our neural
network has learned physics it turns out
I don't not have time to go into the
details but the formula we derived
predicts that the information about
particle sizes is in the rings that you
see around this this looks like a comet
of some kind it's not a comet it's this
autocorrelation function and the
information is in the rings that
surround it and then you see these flame
like shapes these are actually the
activation patterns of the neural
network that we use used to solve this
problem and you can see depending of
course on the physical object that we
put to test the the algorithm you can
see that the Rings kind of change sh
sorry the neural network activation
change shape to accommodate the rings
that it thinks corresponds to the
particles so we're very happy in my
opinion actually this is a highlight of
this work it shows that the neural
network is is um uh it has been sort of
built in a way that is weaving with the
physics that govern this
problem the last thing since this is a
nano Center and Bill is coming after me
to talk about
visualizing uh minuscule motions I
thought I'll show you something that we
haven't published yet and that's all
right this now has to do with
nanomechanical motion it is also a
synchroton experiment with a different
group this is one at Brook Haven and you
can see the names here my friends from
Northwestern and Stonybrook and we try
to characterize motion of nanomechanical
devices these are used in a number of
applications including Quantum Computing
and and and Quantum um basically quasm
microscopic behavior of quantum systems
very interesting devices but we don't do
that horio Espinosa at the Northwestern
does it we just help him characterize
the Dynamics of these
devices and this looks like an easy
problem but it isn't because we want to
do it very very fast and also the
problem is very under sampled so if you
had plenty of then you would get the
signals that you see on the left but
again I'm not kidding you what you do
get is this very very highly under
sampled pattern that you see on the
right that's our signal this blinking
dots that's what you that's the only
thing we can rely on okay how we can
pull it off that that sounds that's that
sounds really really awful but actually
once again we know physics and in this
case is not just Optical physics it does
come in but also classical Dynamics
because this Nome mechanical oscillator
is sort of Shifting according to
something that we call well the harmonic
oscillator or maybe not so harmonic but
we can correct for that then we can set
up an optimization procedure that will
actually approximate the motion of the
mechanical oscillator even though the
measurement is terrible right and what
you see here is a movie that shows the
evolution of this approximation process
as we acquire a few time frames doesn't
take too many time frames I forget how
many but I mean a few I mean a few
hundreds right but not not exceedingly
High anyway so that's another thing that
was sort of just started playing with uh
this is a MRI project funded by the Air
Force office of scientific research and
we're very excited because uh because um
not only it allows us to characterize
complex Dynamics but also again I'm
going to steal some of what Brian was
saying it will also in the in principle
allow us to control these processes
right both in the matical case and in
this um Nano Dynamics it is possible to
to use the what we produce to use it for
feedback control we haven't done it yet
but it's in the works okay I think I'm
going to stop here I'm going to put up
all the movies and happy to take your
questions thank you very
much so just a question George um how do
you see so there's the physics that you
can generate synthetic data with and so
of use it to hear but there's been a lot
of talk as well about how do you embed
physics into the into the network maybe
you could opine about that yeah I mean
that's exactly what we did in this uh
actually in both cases this is one
evidence as I was arguing before um in
the nanomechanical oscillator um
basically the way this works again I'm
going to borrow something that Brian
said what this is trying to do is he
trying to
guess given this horrible data it is
trying to guess what is the best match
of an object that is likely to have
produced this horrible jumping dots the
difference is that um here it is not
only considering a static object but it
is actually taken into account the
sequence of the frames that come as the
oscillator is moving right sorry I keep
saying oscillator I should say the
canver right as the can liver is moving
it is taken into account so so basically
what you have here Brian is you have a
differential a set of differential
equations which are built in the neural
network I don't know how else I can say
it without so in equations here and I
don't want to spill equations into your
nice afternoon but but um but yes there
is a way to write differential equations
that you may remember with nightmares
from your college days or whatever it
there's a way to weave differential
equations with the kernels that deep
learning uses to operate this is what we
have done here and and um and it is
actually some of our colleagues at MIT
Alan Edelman and Chris raaas who
pioneered this kind of idea what we've
done here is basically similar to to
theirs but we've added Optical physics
right we basically added the the
observation uh model if you wish to to
solve this very difficult problem so so
I think this is actually where the
future is because uh because physical
system
are very often involve complex processes
complex Dynamics uh mixing uh
complicated movements and not
necessarily robotics I mean this nanome
mechanical actuator is just as
complicated as a robot actually if you
want to look at it in detail and uh yeah
I think there's are opportunities there
to get quantitative models where
previously we couldn't so is I think
it's very
exciting thank you
okay so uh next up uh Bill Freeman um
and sort of you know seeing motions big
and small and hopefully at all
scales thank you and thanks for the
invitation to be here so this is uh work
that's been we've done over many years
uh involving many people but the primary
contributors uh in addition to me uh are
there on the bottom Mickey Rubenstein
Neil wadwa and Professor Fred Durand at
MIT so
um science progresses in many ways by
having Imaging techniques that let us
see things that we can't see otherwise
uh of course telescopes and microscopes
have uh let us understand the world in
ways that we couldn't without
them and what we wanted to do is
introduce a an analogous thing uh
instead of amplifying the size of an
image we want to amplify the motion of
an image and I want to show you uh
examples of that so here's an input
video of a baby and often parents of
perfectly healthy newborn babies ask is
the baby breathing and so now we can we
can see whether or not the baby's
breathing with this motion magnification
technique um and it works not only for
uh small people but also for large
structures um so here's a crane and you
know that thing's you know blowing in
the wind but you can't really see it and
but if you motion magnify it then you
can see those motions so how does it
benefit us to look at these tiny motions
and amplify them well one thing is I
have this sort of Mantra that um big
catastrophic motions are often preceded
by tiny almost invisible motions so if
you can image these tiny motions ahead
of time that's going to be useful and
also you can learn things about the
structure of the deorations by seeing it
that you might not
be able to otherwise um so okay these
next slides are just to persuade you
that this would be something that's easy
to do you could do it in real time on
lowcost Hardware uh and just to tell you
how we do it there are a number of ways
to do it but here's one simple way if
you take the image and instead of
represented by pixels represented as uh
s and cosine phase little wavelets like
are shown here um so you would take a
that that phase plate at the top left
and you'd represent it by the the um
filter responses shown at the bottom um
you you'd have these s and cosine phase
wavelets at oh I have laser pointer here
how about I don't
sorry the bottom button ah yes says
laser okay you have these uh s and
cosine uh s and cosine phase filters uh
at all different orientations and all
different scales and so here's four
different orientations here's the
different scales and you measure sign
and cosine response a tiny motion just
changes the phase the relative phase of
the S filter and the cosine filter just
by a tiny amount but you can measure
that and amplify it and um
sorry using this architecture you can
then uh have a very simple real-time
system that takes an input video and
gives you a modified output video with
the Motions
Amplified uh I should say as an aside
you can also amplify colors in a kind of
analogous way here's on the left is
someone uh just staring at us and on the
right is a video uh of with the the
small color change is Amplified again
showing the benefits of visualizing uh
things in a video so I got to say this
was one of the most funnest most
enjoyable research projects I've had
because I get to kind of look around the
world and ask where might there be tiny
motions that would look interesting if
we amplifi them and so I just want to
show you a number of examples this is
okay the rest of talk is just a number
of examples okay and what I'm hoping
you'll do is think you know how might I
use this in my own work and uh you know
feel free to get in touch with me I'd
love to um expand our set of examples to
new things and um you know there could
be a useful collaboration to come out of
this so um it's useful in physics uh so
here is a highspeed
video there that it's a PVC pipe viewed
end on it's a highspeed video that
little Hammer comes down and hits it
that's the input video now you know from
your high school physics classes what
really happens when you uh hit the thing
it kind of rings like a bell and there
these normal modes that are excited and
we can see those just from that input
video if we filter temporarily to um
amplify motions at a very narrow band of
frequencies that correspond to these
normal modes and you can search for the
normal modes and find them then you can
get these produce these output videos
that came all from that input video on
the far left um and you can you know see
that the uh okay the the the amplitudes
of the normal modes and how they what
their shapes are um and I'm told that if
there's a fracture in the pipe it
changes the normal mode structure and
you could perhaps identify
that um so again you know asking
physicist friends where are there small
things in the world that that uh are
useful so the transition to turbulence
involves small oscillations that become
bigger oscillations there's something
called a tling sliting wave which is a
streamwise instability and laminer flow
so here's some incense you visualize in
video um there it is it's easier to see
what's going on if you freeze a frame so
on the left is a frozen frame of the
input video on the right is a frozen
frame of the motion magnified video and
there you can see this again streamwise
instability uh sinusoid that gets bigger
and bigger and then finally
um goes unstable in the uh transition to
turbulence um okay
engineering so this is
um a the inverted the uh inverted
pendulum problem so this is from RR lab
uh they had a a control it's it's the
pole balancing problem but even made
even harder because it's got two joints
to it and this poor little controller at
the
bottom has to uh move this thing around
so doesn't fall over the evil graduate
students in the one on the right they
loosen the bolts so it's not the system
that the controller is expecting to see
and in the slow ordinary slow motion
video you really can't see much of a
difference between these two conditions
but in the if you take those input
videos we just saw and motion magnify
them uh then you can see that the one on
the right with the Loos and bolts is
kind of struggling to to control this
thing because it's not behaving the way
it expects it to behave because it's a
different um system than it was trained
on okay here's one that's fun this is
the bridge um in Portsmouth New
Hampshire from New Hampshire to Maine
it's got this uh structure that comes
down it's like a draw bridge but it's
horizontal and parallel and when it
comes down it gives a the the bridge a
kind of a kick so then we went up there
and and just ordinary frame ordinary
Speed video we filmed
the bridge
um after the thing came down and gave it
a kick nothing nothing to worry about
everything's fine uh but if you motion
magnify it and select the frequency of
the torsional mode you can actually
visualize what's going on with the
bridge after that thing comes down and
gives a little kick and you know there's
tiny motions on the bridge that that um
I think you don't even feel if you're on
the
bridge um and again maybe these small
motions will useful to uh catch
instabilities before they become big uh
instabilities and then it's fun to look
at people
too so here's my daughter and um I asked
her just to stay still so the top left
picture is the input video of a person
just staying still then we motion
magnify different temporal frequency
components of that top left video so the
top right video is low fre quen is
Amplified and what can you identify
there well to me it looks like uh the
breathing is Amplified and we can now
see the the
breathing um the bottom left is kind of
midband frequencies one to two Hertz
Amplified and there you see these little
uh micro expressions and then people
often ask can you tell what she's
thinking uh from those and you know we
have no idea I really don't know if
those imperceptible facial Chang changes
have anything to do with what she's
thinking but you could look into that
and then the bottom right is high
frequency Amplified and you can kind of
see the isod a little bit and you can
also see that we're starting to amplify
uh noise in the background cabinets just
from the uh
sensor and you know the beauty of the
web is you can post the code online and
people use it so there a graphic design
student in Yale made this uh composite
of on the left side is the input videos
on the right side or motion magnified
videos I thought that was a nice
design um and here's another one this is
also a pole balancing problem uh a a
ballet dancer stands on one foot and you
know that there's all sorts of control
going on to keep her from falling over
but now we can actually see it uh
Amplified so on the left is the input
video you know she's she's perfectly
motionless it seems and on the right we
can see all the control that she's
having to do to keep from falling
over
um here's one again that was uh
contributed by the public uh someone
posted this using our software uh you
can visualize uh motions of a baby in
[Music]
uo um the eye moves so here's again left
is input right is output and you can see
these micro
cads and it looks like a you know know
bowl of jelly underwater which I think
is probably close to what it really is
um Jello underwater
um and this one's fun this is Mickey
Rubenstein one of the primary graduate
students who did this work um here it's
high speed so the video we amplifi can
be ordinary speed or it can be high
speed here it's highp Speed video and
he's going to sing for
us uh
okay and then we record the sound and we
record the uh frequency response from
the audio you can see that at the far
right so let's grab the base the
fundamental frequency there and mo
motion
amplify only only oscillations in the
input video which are at that temporal
frequency and again this is
straightforward to do you just filter
each of those coefficient pairs narrow
band filter for that frequency and and
reveal what's going on in the throat so
that's on the right now you can see the
the the vibrations from the outside of
the vocal cords as he makes that
sound um you can go and grab the first
harmonic so this is twice as fast and
you can see the little nonlinearities in
the mechanical system uh they're ulating
at twice the fundamental
frequency um as a control we Amplified a
non harmonically related frequency and
you don't see anything special which is
good um okay and then so finally this
one relates to Nano but all these so I
guess the point is you can do this with
telescope data you can do it with
photographic data you can do it with
microscope data all you need is input a
video and it can be an ordinary frame
rate video it can be a highspeed frame
rate
video and maybe there are useful things
going on in your microscope images that
you could usefully ampli amplify the
Motions of and see something that you
see some structure there that you
weren't able to see before so here's an
example of that this is from uh Denny
Freeman's lab no relation to me uh but
we work together and uh he is interested
in um acoustic waves across a particular
membrane in the inner ear um and so uh
there it is you know there's the top is
the input video and what he had done
before we started working together on
this he would he could measure the the
amplitude of oscillation of the membrane
you can do that but but somehow
visualizing it really bring at home and
let's you see the form of it and they
use that for their talks when they
describe it even though we're not adding
new data we're just adding a
visualization of
this um let me just sorry go back to
there um and
um oh yeah and then one last thing
uh sorry let me okay here's a a
cup it's not a wine glass so it's not
quite quite out the resonance that a
wine glass would have but but
um you can hear it ping so you know it's
oscillating but have you ever seen it
oscillate no why not there's two reasons
why you haven't seen it oscillate and
when say what they are or what one of
them
is so one reason you haven't seen wine
glass oscillate is because the
oscillation is too small so we'll take
care of that with motion magnification a
second reason you haven't seen oscillate
is the frequency is too high it's like
you know 500 Herz or something we can't
see that and so what we're going to do
is we use a special camera here that
just grabs 1 Mill second of exposure
each frame and so we're going to Alias
down or beat down the the this high
frequency of oscillation down to a a
frequency band that we can see visually
and and that gives us a live demo that
I'm showing you a video of that lets you
visualize a wine glass oscillating and
then this this beep that you heard uh we
we have set up a speaker next to it and
and uh um play it at the glass and then
you can it allows you then to watch the
thing oscillate in real
time so now you can see a a wine glass
oscillating in response to a
sound um and again the the the special
camera took care of putting it into a
band that you can see visually and and
then the motion magnification took care
of it amplifying it so you could see it
also um so
I I um really think that this is going
to be useful for internal diagnostic
medical imaging you know the the the
canonical picture of a doctor is someone
with a stethoscope around their neck
what's a stethoscope well it takes audio
and amplifies it that's motion
magnification but at the audio bands
surely it it's going to be useful I
think without without any basis uh
surely it might be useful to amplify
motions in in diagnostic video Imaging
as well and maybe there'll be diagnostic
value to amplifying small motions inside
the body so we're exploring that in
collaboration with Brian and his team um
and I think there's a lot to be done
there so that's the story um this is a
tool I think it has a lot of uses I'd
love to hear your
applications and that's it thanks very
much
[Applause]
so let you pick the uh which which which
question you'd like to
sorry um what are the stability I'll
just
go uh there's two tied for one what are
the stability requirements from The
Source video ah yes can uh so yes it can
be implemented with microscope images
and videos thank you um augmentation
bias or SEL itive you have to so there's
two restrictions I didn't quite have
time to go into one is every one of
these things was on a tripod because you
um you want to separate out the camera
motion from the motion of the thing
you're amplifying the Motions of the
subject motion so it's easiest if you
just have the camera Frozen and then you
uh amplify the signal so that's happens
kind of naturally with a microscope
application it happens naturally with
telescope applications but with handheld
cameras you have to put it on a tripod
um and then for all these cases also so
we we uh we're actively selected what
frequencies to amplify and that matters
um it could be of interest to explore an
automatic selection but we haven't done
that
yet and then the second one could motion
magnification be coupled with FAA
structural model deflection to predict
failure points um finite element
analysis right
um
um so okay yes is the answer sorry I'm
just thinking through right now is all
pixel-based but yes you could uh
presumably do it in a finite element
representation as well and I I think um
that might be value um again you know
we're not giving you measurements that
you didn't have but we're letting you
see them in a kind of intuitive and
understandable way um for the can the
motion amplification be done if the
video is acquired with a sparse array of
receiver uh see so there was no acoustic
image that I showed um we had one where
we recorded things with a single
microphone um but we did it was a 2d uh
highspeed video of the
throat um yes you can well it might be
uh for this question you might be
challenged if you to make an image from
the sparer ray of receivers uh so in
many sense I think requires really an
image coming in so maybe the answer is
no on that one so Bill thank you very
much thanks
[Applause]
okay Julie come on up and we'll we'll
impact the physical with the with the
algorithms as
well well uh great to be here uh so
initially I saw this uh Symposium is on
modeling uh at atomic scale so actually
we do have some work on fitting the
entire periodic table uh we're able to
do uh simulations with Quantum
simulation accuracy but much faster but
then I found out this is really uh uh
about Optical Imaging computer vision so
we do actually have uh quite a bit of
generative AI from um mining the
literature data to come up with uh newer
molecular designs for for example
batteries and here you see mixing
several flu together electrolytes for
Batteries there still human that sort of
operating on these kind of
workflows and uh recently uh with ton PC
we have been discussing you know what
kind of pitfall we have in this kind of
autonomous experiments and it's turns
out that uh a lot of irreproducibility
issues you would think that with robots
they wouldn't uh make mistakes but it
turns out that there's still a lot of
like cognitive issues uh even when you
use robots and sometimes uh you also can
find that by changing the hypothesis uh
even So-Cal failed experiment for
example the discovery penicillin is
really come out of a failed bacterial
growth experiment so by just changing
the hypothesis because there is really
no wrong experiment it's really wrong uh
mind models if you change the Mind model
then you can turn a failed experiment to
a successful experiment so uh in my lab
we've been looking at this multim
metallic uh Nano catalyst so here we're
mixing a few uh salt precursors and then
we drop them on carbon paper uh and then
later is fast forward we heat it up and
then we cut into electrodes we do this
test in uh three electrode experiments
and we're using active learning to
change recipe on the fly and uh you know
we do hundreds of experiments uh in in a
campaign to sort of uh do optimization
in a in a multicomponent uh alloy space
and uh it's kind of uh surprising that
uh it took actually more than a year for
us to get consistent results meaning
that uh if we do these different recipes
on the bottom nominally same uh a mon in
between we can get roughly similar
results uh so what other kind of problem
we have for example uh here I'm just
showing this liquid drop a pad
experiment and you will notice that the
droplet size uh is not actually the same
so the speed at which it gets wetted
into carbon strip is is different and
initially we thought okay that's maybe
because of the supplier didn't not give
us a uniform material uh that's actually
one uh possible reason but later we
found that uh just like Bill mentioned
uh very small uh perturbations actually
we because we shock the carbon strip uh
sometimes they're not fully flat uh and
so we have this curvature so you know at
some point uh we have this uh uh uh U
you know bigger drop plate sometime it
doesn't even drop at all so it's only
through kind of a computer vision that
we can actually find that and then uh we
got this kind of garbage data because um
many different problems one is for
example after a while the copper holder
got corroded and uh the solution is we
bought a few hundred dollars of gold and
that solved that problem so we actually
identified uh a lot of different problem
the most sort of uh embarrassing problem
is is this one because this hit sort of
right beneath our eyes so I can really
appreciate what build it's sort of right
we we we see it uh but we didn't catch
it so what happened was we're trying to
mix multiple liquids and this is what
should happen we're mixing two fluids uh
two different kind of salts and uh we're
doing this aspiration up and down uh in
a bit uh and that homogenized the fluid
that's what should happen uh but what
actually happened for more than a year
half a year is uh we use a smaller pipet
and we thought it's homogenized but
because this plate is actually beneath
us so we're looking at from top down and
sort of just hiding in plain sight and
really give us a lot of garbage data
because what we think we made was not
what we actually made and drop on the
carbon paper uh so we cause these uh
seral killers in the AI City uh so we
have uh cable Monsters uh so if you buy
the cheap cables from Amazon they
somehow don't work uh we have these uh
uh temperature in homogeneities uh we
have this coffee ring Monster uh this uh
U you know we have a magnetic stirer uh
in in this uh Beaker and sometime it
just drops for whatever reason so uh we
actually made this kind of uh things uh
just to uh sort of as as examples of
future AI may be able to sort of
diagnose these
issues uh but uh what we come to realize
that we probably can use AI itself uh to
diagnose uh these problems uh it's uh uh
very important that you know experiment
is very different from a program because
in programs uh you can uh always
reproduce the same error but what we
found is very often for example uh even
if an experimentalist is did everything
correct but so you know his labmate did
something wrong in the glove box that
messed his whole experiment up and I
have a situation where I had a postto
who uh you know had a beaker which
looked like this versus a beaker like
this for battery Castle give different
results also I had a Korean postar who
is leaving and I had two students just
follow him from day to the evening
follow an a synthesis experiment and
they took good notes and they did
everything but when The postto Returned
they just couldn't repeat uh the result
so all kinds of issues uh so what we
think uh we can do is is really to uh
use large multimodal models and language
to assist the debugging of experimental
processes so here uh would have S this
is my pH student J he's now doing a
startup company so using the laser
cutting ma to cut plywood for making a
sample stage I set the laser cutting
parameters assistant across the sample
stage but apparently I got a failure
piece could you analyze this
phenomenon hey meta take a
picture the image analysis reveals two
main anomalies non-uniform cut depths
and some charring these could be due to
inconsistent material density or
variations in the plywood's thickness
resulting in uneven Cuts despite uniform
settings another possibility is that the
Laser's focal point or distance may have
shifted during The Cutting process
causing inconsistency in cutting depths
and potential
Charing so so what's interesting is this
is zero shot learning meaning all juu
did was to ask that question and then
send an image uh and it seems that the
uh CH GPT is is able to uh give
reasonable hypothesis on on why uh you
know that happened so what we try to do
is to prevent uh cross contamination
between two different drop plate so we
made actually this holder to isolate the
drop but then during the laser we
eventually had a stainless steel uh this
a holder but when we use wood to do the
initial prototype you know it kind of
called fire but then you know what what
what happened is the AI wasn't trained
specifically on laser cutting wood but
apparently it have seen maybe something
about lasers and something about
carpentry and is able to come up with
reasonable actual hypothesis on what
happened so now uh we're having this log
agents where uh the uh the student just
have this camcorder and uh it's just
capturing all the things and you don't
need to even write logs anymore uh so we
are using it to just capture uh what
happens in the lab and this enables the
searching but more importantly uh allows
us to ask questions on on what might
happen what might cause some kind of
irreproducibility in the system and
another very interesting thing is uh now
we have a script driven sem so uh this
is uh fully automatic you just use
software to move the microscope around
but then uh we now ask GPT to maybe for
the first time to control this sem uh
and identify Marite versus uh austinite
so this is a piece of Steel sample they
just lying somewhere in the
lab and we have this Crest system CR
please take a picture of the boundary
between the austinite and maride with
field width of 80 microns yeah initially
see it's a merchandise not Mar side but
later he recognized it's it's a material
science problem so change it to Martin
[Music]
side so no h control at all we just give
it a goal and then it's sort of Auto GPT
but in the physical world it it use a
script to move the semm uh image uh
Center and then Zoom uh and then there's
another thing which is segment M so only
three
operations uh
and I should say that this is a
successful example uh the success rate
initially is pretty low it's like 20%
it's like a kit that sort of stumbling
around uh but eventually in this
particular case is able to uh use these
three functions and uh eventually
identify a a uh region of mar side
that's uh yeah you're going to hear
[Music]
uh so it has found it now
the Imaging session has been completed
and we have successfully captured a
picture of the boundary between
austinite and Martin site with a field
width of 80 microns the process involved
adjusting the initial field width
locating the region of interest and
fine-tuning the settings to achieve the
desired image the final image accurately
represents the boundary as requested
well it sounds pretty confident but
actually uh initially uh the the
accuracy is pretty pretty low but
recently we done something which we we
form a committee of of these AI so we
allow gini and cloud and have them like
two rounds of debates and uh it's kind
of interesting that these agents for
example GPT is very assertive verus
Gemini seem to be very very submissive
whatever GPD says it says yes yes uh but
then we sort of modulate their
discussion we they have to respect each
other and then through good modulation
actually uh after two rounds uh they
actually improve their accuracy through
this committee
approach and uh we're able to uh use
this uh to search for Catalyst in the
direct format few cells so usually human
are pretty hesitant to go above four or
five elements because people generally
lose intuition when the varying
parameters are more than three actually
uh but with uh uh Active Learning and
and AI we're able to uh find the
Catalyst that beats the previously uh
human discovered best Catalyst in this
eight dimensional Catalyst space and and
this actually got uh a uh best student
paper award in the so-called real ml uh
real workshop on Active Learning uh
active experiment design and active
learning in the real world uh award so
uh my sort of uh
uh last slide is on on in addition to
this kind of uh physical world uh
hypothesis and and cognitive issues we
also tested that GPT have reasonable
understanding of Science and is actually
able to make more abstract hypothesis so
it's actually kind of mysterious how
human inspiration right human scientist
right some people are taking a hot bath
and then suddenly you know come up with
you know some you know Eureka moment
right so uh we we think that uh GPT is
have read many more books than any
individual human have done and one very
basic sort of hypothesis we think the
meaning of words are different in
different fields and so maybe uh in this
kind of meaning space it can do random
perturbations and somehow that can lead
to kind of mutations of of meaning of of
sentences that maybe one way you can
think about just like radiation either
give you cancer or give you you know
mutation which Drive Evolution but that
of course a very low efficiency way to
get creativity there might be some other
things if you connect with uh you know
uh higher levels logic symbolic
regression and so forth so generally we
think uh what needs to happen is this
kind of loop where you can have
hypothesis making by AI but then also
the key is what's the simplest what's
the most cost effective experiment that
can give you effective information and
then also you know if I have something
uh in my lab uh but is it really really
reproducible let's say in uh uh uh uh
Vladimir's lab so I need to have you
know some way to send the liquid or
powder samples to Vladimir even in MIT
right so and then also uh actually if
you do this collaboration between
institutions you need ways to do
material transfer agreement which is
actually a very big hassle it's a very
big friction in collaboration so maybe
some way to also sort of have IP
agreements sort of packaging in addition
to standardized ways of of sending
sample so I think in the future by just
like sort of doing this kind of
iterative loop uh we may have uh really
high stut in uh new materials Discovery
for uh uh energy and and other fields so
uh with that I like to thank you for
attention if you're interested in this
uh feel free to contact Chu who did all
this
[Applause]
work thanks I don't see if there's a
pigeon hole question up but but
please so just a a a probing question uh
from the audience but um so where do you
see the sort of the problems with sort
of connecting to the the physical
experimentation like you know physical
Hardware has control systems and sort of
user interfaces you what is that what's
the connective piece like how you
actually get the machine to then move
the the robotic system to to do what you
want so in our experience is like a
really uh multispectral
and the multi-dimensional sensor is
really the key uh is if we do have
cameras you know at low level at
different angles and not just like the
invisible spectrum and if we do have
acoustic sensors I I do think those
those information including builds small
motions those those do have lots of
information in there and then we need to
have this logic engine to analyze all
this sensor data is is I really think
that uh with AGI you you really can get
a lot more from your your sensors and
vision see if we have a no no pigeon
holes okay so I think with that um thank
our colleagues here and um that
concludes that session so thank you