the MIT energy initiative presents power
to the people Mighty spin-off yaia
energy helps countries work toward
universal access to electricity written
by Deborah
halber when MIT electrical engineer
raaza amantia phd12 arrived in Rwanda in
2015 she was whisked off to a village
she saw that diesel generators provided
power to the local Health Center bank
and shops but like most of rural Rwanda
ki's 200 homes did not have electricity
am Mata knew the hilly terrain would
make it challenging to connect the
village to high voltage lines from the
capital kagali 50 km away while many
consider electricity a basic human right
there are places where people have never
flipped a light switch among the United
Nations sustainable development goals is
global access to Affordable reliable and
sustainable energy by 2030 recently the
UN reported that progress in global
electrification had slowed due to the
challenge of reaching those hardest to
reach researchers from the MIT energy
initiative Mighty and Camila pfal
University in Madrid created W energy
Inc a cambridge-based startup
commercializing MIT developed planning
and analysis software to help
governments determine the most
cost-effective ways to provide
electricity to all their citizens the
researchers 2015 trip to Rwanda marked
the beginning of four years of phone
calls Zoom meetings and international
travel to help the East African country
still still reeling from the 1994
genocide that killed more than a million
people develop a national
electrification strategy and extend its
power infrastructure am MAA W president
and one of five W co-founders knew that
electrifying kambi and the rest of the
country would provide new opportunities
for work education and connections and
the ability to charge cell phones often
an expensive and inconvenient
undertaking to date W with funding from
the Asian development Bank the African
Development Bank the interamerican
Development Bank for Latin America and
the World Bank has helped governments
develop electrification plans in 22
countries on almost every continent
including in refugee camps in subsaharan
Africa sahil and Chad regions where
violence has led to 3 million internally
displaced people with a modeling and
visualization tool like ours we are able
to look at the entire spectrum of need
and demand and say okay what might be
the most optimized solution amatus says
more than 15 graduate students and
researchers from MIT and camillis
contributed to the development of w
software under the supervision of Robert
Stoner the interim director of Mighty
and Osio Perez Ariaga a visiting
professor at the MIT Sloan School of
Management from camillis Perez Ariaga
looks at how changing electricity use
patterns have forced utilities worldwide
to rethink Antiquated business models
the team's reference electrification
model RM software pulls information from
population density Maps satellite images
infrastructure data and geospatial
points of interest to determine where
extending the grid will be most cost-
effective and where other solutions
would be more practical I always say we
are agnostic to the technology amacha
says traditionally the only way to
provide long-term reliable access was
through the grid but that's changing in
many developing countries there are many
more challenges for utilities to provide
reliable
Service off-grid
Solutions why a co-founder found ER
Stoner who is also the founding director
of the MIT Tata center for technology
and design recognized early on that
connecting homes to existing
infrastructure was not always
economically feasible what's more
billions of people with great
connections had unreliable access due to
uneven regulation and challenging
terrain with W co-founders Andreas
Gonzalez gcia a mighty affiliate
researcher and Professor Fernando de
quadri Garcia of Camis Perez araga and
Stoner led a team that developed a set
of principles to guide Universal
Regional
electrification their approach which
they dubbed the integrated distribution
framework incorporates elements of
optimal planning as well as novel
business models and regulation getting
all three right is necessary Stoner says
if you want a viable long-term outcome
amach says initially we designed ourem
to understand what the level of demand
is in these countries with very rural
and poor populations and what the system
should look like to serve it we took a
lot of that input into developing the
model in 2019 W was created to
commercialize the software and add
Consulting to the package of services
the team provides now in addition to
advising governments and Regulators on
how to expand existing grids y proposes
options such as a mini grid powered by
Renewables like wind hydropower or solar
to serve single Villages or large- scale
minigrid solutions for larger areas in
some cases an even more localized
scalable solution is a mesh grid which
might consist of a single solar pannel
for a few houses that over time can be
expanded and ultimately connected to the
main grid the RM software has been used
to design off-grid systems for remote
and mountainous regions in Uganda Peru
Nigeria Cambodia Indonesia India and
elsewhere when tasa power India's
largest integrated power company saw how
well minig grids would serve parts of
East India the company created a mini-
grid division called Tata Renewables
amantia notes that the RM software
enables her to come up with an entire
National electrification plan from her
workspace in Cambridge Massachusetts but
site visits and on the ground partners
are critical in helping the ya team
understand existing systems engage with
clients to assess demand and identify
stakeholders in Haiti an energy
consultant reported that the existing
grid had typically been operational only
six out of every 24 hours in kambi
University of Rwanda students surveyed
The Village's 200 families and helped
lead a CommunityWide meeting why
connects with on thegr Experts and
agencies who can engage directly with
the government and other stakeholders
because many times those are the doors
that we knock on am montis says local
energy Ministries utilities and
Regulators have to be open to regulatory
change they have to be open to working
with financial institutions and new
technology the goals of regulators
energy providers funding agencies and
government officials must align in real
time to provide reliable access to
energy for a billion people she
says moving past
challenges growing up in kmu amata used
to travel to remote villages with her
father an electrical engineer who
designed Cable Systems for land lines
for Nepal Telecom she remembers being
fascinated by the high voltage lines
crisscrossing Nepal on these trips now
she points out utility polls to her
children and explains how the
distribution lines carry power from
local substations to customers after
majoring and engineering science and
physics at Smith college amanta
completed her pH in electrical
engineering at MIT in 2012 within 2
years she was traveling to off-grade
communities in India as a research
scientist exploring potential
Technologies for providing access there
were unexpected challenges at the time
digitized geospatial data didn't exist
for many regions in India in 2013 the
team used phones to take pictures of
paper maps spread out on tables team
members now scour Digital Data available
through Facebook Google Microsoft and
other sources for useful G geographical
information it's one thing to create a
plan Amatea says but how it gets
utilized and implemented becomes a big
question with all the players involved
funding agencies elected officials
utilities private companies and
Regulators within the countries
themselves it's sometimes hard to know
who's responsible for next steps besides
providing technical expertise our team
engages with governments to let's say
develop a financial plan or an
implementation plan she says ideally W
hopes to stay involved with each project
long enough to ensure that its proposal
becomes the national electrification
strategy of the country that's no small
feat given the multiple players the
opaque nature of government and the need
to enact a regulatory framework where
none may have existed for Rwanda W
identified areas without service
estimated future demand and proposed the
most cost-effective ways to meet that
Demand with a mix of grid and off-grid
solutions based on the electrification
plan developed by the W team officials
have said they hope to have the entire
country electrified by 2024 in 2017 by
the time the team submitted its master
plan which included an off-grid solution
for kambi amantia was surprised to learn
that electrification in the village had
already occurred an example she says of
the challenging nature of local planning
perhaps because of W's focus and
Outreach efforts kambi had become a
priority however it happened amantia is
happy that kabi's 200 families finally
have access to electricity