hi everybody I'm Blair dwit uh founder
of Lunar Station we're based here in
Cambridge and we're an MIT startup uh we
organized in
2016 and at the time of organizing what
we wanted to do for the Aerospace Market
was to solve the data problem of the
Moon uh what we quickly heard from
industry was that there was plenty of
data but there wasn't a lot of
insights and so when we thought about it
like okay
this is the data structure in NASA's
planetary data system it's a pi Le
architecture and we quickly understood
why aerospace companies were having
trouble just accessing the volume of
data about the moon that's already
existed so we set about to create
systems that could go into the planetary
data system in all the various nodes
extract and ingest that data fuse it and
produce
insights and that's how Moon hacker came
into existence with moon hacker we have
a way of characterizing the Moon in new
ways and we can help our customers with
site selection surface uh Transit
Mobility Solutions minerology and
minerology heat mapping we also get into
the astrodynamics where's the Sun going
to be where's Earth that affects your
power and comms we also get into
environmentals what are The Thermals
what are the rain es of those thermals
what are the meteorite interactions with
the surface and your area of operation
going to be and then finally radiation
how much exposure are you going to have
because you're farther away from all the
shielding and another Discovery was that
clients had a lot of radiation questions
and understanding that radiation testing
is critical because you get to figure
out how your survive what's your
availability of the equipment uh
establishes costs can you buy CS rad
hard equipment or do you have to build
your own and also a side note for anyone
working on government contracts it is
required for your PDR and
CDR the problem with this is that the
national rad lab infrastructure is
challenged uh we were on the phone with
a DOD Branch uh talking last week about
an 18-month delay now the workforce is
aging it's not being replenished fast
enough and there's a backlog so we had a
client who's ready to launch but they
haven't gotten their rad lab uh
certified so we were able to put their
system in our
simulator and move them along in the
process so that they can actually meet
their launch
window and the way we go about doing our
radiation simulator is first we create a
digital
twin the dimensions the material
the
shielding and from there where you going
to go cuz this is not exclusive to the
surface of the Moon orbiting the Moon it
is anywhere in space so our client being
an Advan propulsion system here in the
Boston area it was all over the place
because they're actually an engine that
will take you from uh any kind of cargo
or uh payload from one place in space to
another so there was a lot of different
places they needed to make sure they
could operate without any critical
failure once we know where your place in
space is we said about in the
bombardment this bombardment can be ours
but we've had clients ask us for two
decades worth of bombardment and this
bombardments uh influenced and modeled
after Advanced particle research
facilities like CERN firery and here at
MIT once the bombardment is done we can
then tabulate all those results
looking at dosage
exposures CES or single event upsets but
ultimately what the client really wants
to know is what's a lifetime expectancy
and are there any critical parts that
will take my system
down and then we can make modifications
to the digital twin as Corrections are
made and run it through again without
leaning on any challenged infrastructure
in the nation for physical red lab a
funny thing also happened along the way
when we were were characterizing the
moon we saw symmetry in how underwater
domain is also developing a lot of
autonomy a lot of data generation not a
lot of
intelligence um so what's interesting is
is that the moon actually is better
mapped than the ocean the moon has
better resolution if you could believe
it and more thoroughly uh photographed
so there's a lot of opportunities for
algorithms to interplay between the two
domains
so what we're looking for and what we
want to partner with are organizations
that need to get to space need to get to
space
timely and let us help you with your
radiation testing again I'm Blair dwit
and come see us at our table across the
hall thank you