[Music]
okay so now you have an understanding of
the experiment that was performed for
the data science Challenge and now we're
going to move into the last section
which is what does that data look like
and how do we work with it so uh you're
going to be able to load the data into
the python environment using these
packages scan pi and and data and so
scan Pi is a python package that's
commonly used in the Single Cell
analysis community and it's very
streamlined and hopefully easy to use
for you and within scan Pi there's
another package called and data which uh
allows us to load in the data and
organize it in a very sensible uh way so
scanpy and and data uh are going to be
the main tools that you can use to at
least get the data into your hands and
start to work with it and so I'll give
you a few lines of code that might help
you along the way so you know when we uh
are going to load the data we're going
to import scan pi and when you import
scan P that will bring along and data
and then other useful packages could be
numpy or pandas okay so and data is
short for annotated data and it's a way
to structure the data and the two pieces
of and data that we're going to care
about the most are what are called X and
OBS or observation so X is going to be
where the gene expression Matrix is
stored so if your and data object that
you load up is called a a data then the
gene expression Matrix will be loaded by
just typing a.x and similarly uh for
every single cell in the gene expression
Matrix we're also going to have metadata
and that's going to be stored in the OBS
or observation uh data frame which is a
pandas data frame and OBS will have for
every single cell what perturbation that
cell received as well as what cell State
we assigned uh that uh T Cell to so
we've already gone through an analyze
this data and assign t- cell states to
every single cell in the data that we're
going to give you now to load up the
data uh that we're going to give you an
object that's an H5 ad file and you can
load it up using the read H5 ad function
and that will give you your and data
object which we're just going to call a
data in these slides and that object you
can just look and it has a a gene
expression Matrix in it as well as an
observation data frame so let's look at
these individual pieces separately so
the gene expression Matrix is stored in
a.x and this is a sparse Matrix uh and
it's a sparse Matrix because to remind
you single cell RNA sequencing data the
gene expression matrixes have a lot of
zeros so you can actually Store The
Matrix in sparse format and uh the
Matrix has Dimensions observations by
variables so the observations are the
number of cells that were profiled
31,000 here and the number of variables
or features the number of genes were
measured 15,000 now this number 30,000
cells is different from the number I
told you earlier and that's because
we've done quality control to the data
and we'll talk a little bit about the
steps that were done in the quality
control but this is the final number of
cells you're going to be given now to
look at some of the uh values in that
expression Matrix we can just convert to
an array and now you can see the
expression values and again you can see
lots of these zeros which is why we
store it in spar format finally we can
load up uh the names of the cells and
the names of the genes so we have ob's
names and VAR names so OBS names um you
know you see these very long strings
that are describing the cells and you'll
see the string of atcs and G's and that
comes from the DNA barcode that was
introduced to label the different
transcripts from every single cell and
this goes back to lecture two where we
introduce the Single Cell isolation
techniques using micr
so the names are not super important but
just so you're not wondering what these
atcs and G's are and then we also have
the G names which are very interpretable
and Within These set of gen names there
will be genes we've introduced in the
lecture like tcf7 or
pdcd1 so that's the and data uhx uh
Matrix and then we also have the a dat.
OBS which is this pandas data frame
which has for each cell different
metadata describing that cell and the
two main columns that we care about are
the genetic perturbation the cell
received so for instance this cell
received a non-targeting perturbation
meaning that's a perturbation that
doesn't affect the cell shouldn't affect
the the t- cell and then this cell
received a perturbation the tox 2 and
tpt1 and so forth and then we also have
the t- cell state that we assigned after
doing analysis of this data and remember
there are four functional t- cell States
in this challenge the progenitor t-
cells the affector t- cells the
exhausted T cells and the cycling t-
cells and you'll find all of those in
this
metadata okay so um one of the things
that we're going to be really focused on
is for each genetic perturbation what
are the proportions of t- cell States we
find for that perturbation so here's
some code to Simply calculate uh for
every single genetic perturbation What
proportion of cells are in each t- cell
state so for instance this is
perturbation one and we find that 28% of
the cells for perturbation one are in
the terminally exhausted state and 26%
of cells are in the progenitor State and
then we can look at the last
perturbation perturbation 63 and we find
that 50% of the cells are in the
progenitor t- cell State and 28% are in
the cycling t- cell state so this is
just a simple code to calculate the
proportions of t- cell States for each
genetic
perturbation now I'll just show you some
of the raw data so here what we're
looking at are all the genetic
perturbations that were applied in
Mark's experiment and the y- axis is the
number of cells in which that genetic
perturbation was detected and the
perturbations are ordered by number of
cells in which they were detected and
this is a log scale and what you can see
is that most cells have more than aund
most perturbations are detected in more
than 100 cells and um we want the
perturbation to be detected in multiple
cells because um increased sample size
for a perturbation is going to give us
uh a better sense of the effect of that
perturbation uh single cell RNA quencing
data is very noisy uh so the more
measurements we can make of the same
perturbation across multiple cells the
more confident will be in inferring that
perturbations effect on gene expression
so fortunately most perturbations are
detected in many many cells but this is
something to keep in mind that the
number of cells we look at kind of
affects like how confident we are for
inferring any perturbations
effect so next I just want to tell you
what quality control and normalization
was done on this data so um I want to
remind you that when we introduce these
perturbations into the te- cells I
describe this as each t- cell gets one
genetic perturbation now that's a little
bit of a simplification so ideally you
know we would like a t- cell to just get
one perturbation and not zero
perturbations or many perturbations but
actually the number of perturbations
that get introduced into a cell when
doing this process of introducing
perturbations using crisper cast 9 the
number of perturbations that get
introduced into a cell follows a Pon
distribution meaning that most cells
only receive one perturbation but some
fraction of the cells receive two or
more perturbations and some fraction of
the cells receive no perturbations so we
do quality control to remove cells that
receive two or more perturbations
because we are not powered to infer the
effects of combinations of perturbations
in this data that would take looking at
hundreds of millions of cells so we
remove these cell here we also remove
cells that receive no genetic
perturbation and you might ask why do we
do that well part of the reason is that
um cells that receive no genetic
perturbation they might have not
received a perturbation but there might
also be a technical reason that we
weren't able to detect the perturbation
and we would like to model what
unperturbed cells look like but the
experiment is designed such that we can
use the non-targeting controls uh to
model that distribution so we really
need these cells we can actually just
use the non-targeting control uh uh
perturbations to infer what the t- cell
State distributions look like in an
unperturbed State and then finally we
remove cells where perturbations have
very low counts because those are
technically probably lowquality cells so
that's the quality control and then what
we end up doing is for every cell we
normalize the total gene expression so
now the total gene expression is just
going to sum to one and then what we do
is we multiply all of that by 10,000 so
now this total expression sums to 10,000
we add one and take the logarithm okay
so once we've done um this uh cell
quality and normalization we carry out
the rest of the Single Cell sequencing
analysis where we do feature selection
dimensionality reduction using principal
components analysis and then graph-based
clustering okay so here we have the
results from the experiment that Mark
performed where he did perturb seek in
t- cells and so here we're showing a
embedding a umap embedding of the 30,000
t- cells that pass quality control and
to remind you the umap embedding is
calculated from the cell's principal
component scores and the idea is that
it's preserving uh the similarity
between cells that exists in high
dimension and it's projecting that down
into two Dimensions so two cells are
similar to one another if they have
similar gene expression profiles in high
dimension and then if they are similar
we want them to be close to one in two
Dimensions so here these two cells are
are similar to one another and have
similar gene expression profiles and
here these two cells are close to one
another have similar gene expression
profiles so we calculate the umap
embedding for all the 30,000 t- cells
that pass the final quality control and
then we color them by uh their cluster
identity that we derived in the previous
uh slides so starting with regenor cells
we can ask um what genes are more highly
expressed in this cluster relative to
all the other clusters one gene that
will come up is tcf7 which we know marks
the progenitor T Cell State uh we can
also look at the terminal exhausted
cells and one gene that is more highly
expressed than those relative to all the
other clusters is pdcd1 and that helps
us Mark the terminal exhausted state so
we can do this for all the Clusters and
this allows us to identify the four main
t- cell States we see in cancer namely
the progenitor State the affector state
the terminal exhausted State and the
cycling State okay so now we get to the
really fun part of the uh data which is
we can link the gene expr we see in
single cells in the cell state to the
perturbation that that cell received and
we can ask how do the perturbations
affect the proportions of t- cell States
we see so first let's just calculate the
overall t- cell State proportions in all
the data so we see that there are 10% of
T cells are in the progenitor State uh
30% are in the affector state 20% are in
the terminally exhausted State 30% are
in the cycling State and 10% are what we
call other now let's look at what
happens when we do a genetic
perturbation and I'm going to leave
these perturbations label but we're
going to perturb you know a single Gene
and ask for all the cells that receive
that genetic perturbation what's the
resulting proportion of T Cell States
and what we see is that the uh
progenitor t- cell State proportion went
up it's 40% now and the uh exhaust the
terminally exhausted t- cell State
decreased and this could be a really uh
beneficial thing for cancer
immunotherapy because as we discussed
before we think progenitor States and
affector states are more effective when
responding to cancer now in stark
contrast to this we can look at a
different perturbation perturbation 2
and here we're just showing all the
cells that receive perturbation 2 and
what you see is there's this big drop in
the progenitor t- cell State and a big
increase in the terminally exhausted t-
cell State here and so this you could
think would be really bad in cancer
because these terminally exhausted te-
cells are unable to really respond and
control cancer and then finally we have
these really clever negative controls
where these cells all received a
non-targeting control perturbation and
we can look at the proportion of t- cell
states there and we can compare that to
the genetic perturbations that actually
affect a specific Gene and so we can
always just do these comparisons between
the negative control and the actual
genetic perturbation to infer how a
genetic perturbation affected the
overall t- cell State
proportions okay so now hopefully you're
starting to see uh how all these
challenges fit together so the first
challenge task is to predict the t- cell
State dist distribution so remember Mark
measured 70 genes in his experiment he
made 70 genetic perturbations we're only
giving you 63 of those perturbations in
the training set and we're going to ask
you to predict the effect of the seven
other genetic perturbations that are in
the test set and so these perturbations
might increase or decrease the different
states so one perturbation as we saw
here increase the progenitor t- cell
State and another perturbation that we
saw here increas the terminal exhaust of
t- cell state so we'll ask you to
predict the effects of these
perturbations on the t- cell State
proportions then in the Second Challenge
we're going to turn this problem on its
head a bit and we're going to ask you
know given that we want to maximize some
te- cell killing objective what are
genetic perturbations we could make to
get there so let's define both sides of
that so first what do I mean when I say
maximize t- cell killing objectives so
uh one thing that we think would improve
immunotherapy is if we had a higher
proportion of t- cell states in the
progenitor State and the affector state
and a lower proportion of t- cell states
in the terminally exhausted state so
that's an objective that we want to
maximize and we think that's going to
make uh te- cells better at killing
tumor cells we think that's going to
make car T cells less exhausted and we
think that's going to have benefit to
checkpoint blockade therapies so that's
the objective function and what we're
going to ask you to do is think about
all 20,000 genes that are out there and
choose the best three genes that are
going to maximize that objective so what
are the three genetic perturbations that
could really give you more t- cell
killing so one perturbation that seems
like it's going in the right direction
is maybe this perturbation one where we
have more progenitor te cells and a
perturbation that seems like it's going
in the wrong direction is this
perturbation where we have more terminal
exhaust te-
cells and then finally the last
challenge will be to propose a
quantitative metric to rank the efficacy
of the different proposed uh
perturbations and so now we've reached
the end of our introductory lectures and
we've gone through the biology behind
this data science challenge the tech
technology that's enabling us to do
these experiments the experiment itself
that Mark did to do perturb seek and
melanoma and how you can work with the
data yourself and really get into the
challenge and so uh we're really excited
about this and we hope you are too we
can't think of anything more important
to work on than making cancer
immunotherapy better so we thank you for
your participation and hard work in this
and I just want to wish you good luck
and have fun with this thanks
[Music]