All right, I guess we'll get started.
Um, let's see. I wanted to just uh
finish up some discussion of topics from
linear algebra that um we didn't get to
the last math lecture. And um to begin
with, I think we did cover this topic of
igen values and igen vectors. Um these
uh linear algebra concepts turn out to
be very very useful in a number of
different uh applications. But um when
we have an igen value and igen vector uh
pair then for a matrix A that has an
igen vector V then
the matrix vector product is simply a
rescaling of that same vector. So matrix
multiplication when we use igen or
matrix vector multiplication when we use
igen vectors is very simple. We're just
rescaling the input. Um and in order to
solve for igen values and igen vectors
one can solve this equation where the
two are equal.
And
when we solve this equation um we want
the roots of the sort of determinant
equation to equal zero. Um this means
that um these are the igen values which
make this matrix factor a minus i lambda
uh non-invertible.
So with a matrix
if that matrix has a determinant that is
in or has is if that matrix is
invertible then uh the determinant of
the matrix is non zero and the inverse
is actually functions of different
determinant co-actors. Um so in order
for V to not be zero
which would be the case if this matrix
were invertible uh we must have the
lambda satisfying this equation. And
this system of equations um is a
polomial
in lambda or at least the determinant
equaling zero corresponds to a polomial
in lambda equaling zero. So these things
can be solved very directly. Uh actually
in R you can actually compute the roots
of any polomial very easily. And then
once we've solved for
a root lambda then we can solve the
equations for what the V vector is that
satisfies that. Now let me put this in
here.
Um
okay it turns out that um if we have
independent igen vectors
then we can linearly independent igen
vectors. Um then we can comprise those
as columns of a matrix S
and the matrix A multiplied by this S
matrix will simply be the matrix of
multiples of the igen vector. So s
lambda lambda is a diagonal matrix and
the inverse matrix of s will exist so
long as we have independent igen
vectors.
And so this equation here can be used to
obtain a is s lambda s inverse.
Alternatively s inverse a s is equal to
lambda. So these igen vectors
uh when comprising a matrix uh allow us
to uh diagonalize
a uh matrix A.
Now um
let's see
all right so IGEN values vectors can
come into play when we have equations
for common filters. Um if our matrix A
uh is transforming states at time t
minus one into states at time t and this
the dynamics of this process uh proceed
regularly over time increments given by
t. Then we simply have the teeth
transition from state zero is given by
the teeth power of a. Um and uh we can
actually get explicit solutions then
which end up
giving us um let's see at least if our
igen vectors v1 through vn are linearly
independent
then if we have an initial condition u
not we can express that initial
condition as a linear combination of the
igen vector vectors
and then we can represent the transition
over t periods to have this form and it
ends up just being a sum of multiples of
the igen vectors
uh with the coefficients being powers of
the igen values. So in looking at this
mathematically
one can see that if the igen values
lambda 1 to lambda n
are smaller than one in magnitude
then
this sort of limiting state transition
goes to a zero vector.
If
the one of the igen values is equal to
one,
then this term here won't change with
each transition. And so we'll have a
limiting value of the state that
corresponds to a multiple of the first
igen vector. And so um what's
interesting to anticipate is that there
will be different kinds of problems we
work with where the igen values may
actually uh be such that the largest
igen value is equal to one and uh the
other igen values are smaller than one
in magnitude and so we can get nice uh
analytic representations for the
transition of the states.
All right. Well, um,
from linear algebra courses, you
probably remember that if we have a
symmetric real matrix, so if this matrix
here is n byn and it's symmetric
and it's real, uh, then
all of the igen values of this matrix
are real as well.
And
if we have two distinct igen values
then the igen vectors corresponding to
those two
values are orthogonal to each other. So
if we have a v1 equals lambda 1 v1 and a
v2 is equal to lambda 2 v2
um then it turns out that v1
do v2
is equal to zero. Um and uh you know
this
is
useful at least if we're with linear
algebra we often want to uh represent
multi-dimensional vectors in terms of
some basis.
And so um if we think of
our matrix A equaling
a vector A1 A2 up to A N.
Um if the matrix A has full rank,
then these columns of A are linearly
independent.
And we could use these column vectors as
a basis for the n-dimensional space. So,
so if the rank of a
is equal to n, then um the collection of
a j's j equaling one to n forms a basis.
And if we have a matrix A
that maybe is symmetric
but has en values that are all distinct,
then we actually could have so if A
is symmetric
and all the EEN values are distinct
Then
the collection of igen vectors VJ J
equaling 1 to uh N.
This would correspond to an orthogonal
basis.
And so when representing
n vectors,
it's convenient to represent them in a
coordinate system that has sort of
orthogonal axes in it.
Um now what's interesting is that
um when a is symmetric and real um the
uh all the igen values are real. It
turns out that there exists
an
orthogonal
set of igen vectors in that general
case. So um so that can be very useful.
Um all right. Well uh a very important
linear algebra
result is the singular value
decomposition.
And let me just ask how many people here
have covered singular value
decompositions?
Just about everybody. Okay. So who would
like to explain to me uh what or explain
to the class what a singular value
decomposition is?
So let me write this
maybe as the singular value
decomposition in my notation.
So who
would like to explain what this is?
Anybody?
>> Yes. expresses the matrix A as a sum of
orthogonal run one matrices.
>> So um
U is such that U transpose
U is equal to say the identity it has
orthogonal columns. Um V is the same
thing
and D is a diagonal.
And so um what's important is that any
matrix
can be expressed as the factor of
a V
transpose which is an orthogonal matrix
that will sort of transform coordinate
axes to new axes that are orthogonal in
the same space. And then D is a diagonal
matrix
down to D
well I'll write D R
where um the uh we basically are
stretching and squeezing axes and then u
is simply has columns that define a new
basis or a new vector space and we're
taking sums of those. So, so it's
interesting to represent any matrix
as this
um
operator which will sort of or do an
orthogonal transformation of axes
stretch and squeeze in that transformed
space and then use those to uh multiply
uh new coordinate vectors u. Now to um
if if we take
sort of any uh let's say here an M byN
matrix
A
um
and it's often the case that we have
maybe m cases in a data set and n
variables
and so this corresponds to a data matrix
for
an analysis of some data. Um if we take
a transpose a then this is a symmetric
real matrix
and so this actually um can be
diagonalized to v
d^2 vtranspose
where I'm representing the igen values
as they're the squared d values and the
uh igen vectors as columns of v. And so
one can sort of construct this do the
igen value igen vector decomposition
here and then we can take the matrix A
premultiply by V and um
or not premultiply post multiply by V
and post multiply by D inverse
and this will basically be our U matrix.
Now all of this is a bit casual with my
notation. Um
the number of sort of nonzero
diagonal entries here can be limited to
the rank count of the matrix A. And so
um you know that's the way it uh can
play out. So we basically have nonzero
values of aranspose a there will be are
the rank nonzero values.
um we can define the orthogonal
orthonormal igen vectors corresponding
to those and then if we want to sort of
expand the orthonormal basis of the
first rig vectors to be an n-dimensional
uh basis um although they essentially
aren't used um and uh so that gives us
our uh singular decomposition.
And it turns out that in dealing with um
data
in a matrix, um the singular value
decomposition allows us to reduce
dimensionality. Perhaps there's
variation in the data values that is
limited to a subspace
of rank two or three.
And so we can identify and specify that
uh subspace easily with the singular
value decompositions.
All right. Um
let's see.
Okay. So in these notes I refer to a
reduced SVD. Um what's rather
interesting as a decomposition of the
matrix A is that it's a sum
of R terms where R is the rank of the
matrix. And those R terms are the
products of
the column vectors of U times the column
vector transpose of V
respectively um with the singular value
sigma 1 through sigma R. So it's um
provides a nice way of uh thinking of a
matrix. It's simply a sum of rank one
terms.
Okay. Um let's see these lecture notes
on linear algebra finishes with the
coron uh frobinius theorem and this
theorem relates to matrices
that are square
with positive strictly positive
elements. And so with such matrices
the theorem states that there is
an igen value a real value lambda kn
that is bigger than any in magnitude
than any other
igen values
and corresponding to this igen value
lambda kn
we can define an igen vector v
which
has elements that are all positive as
well.
And uh this lambda knot
value the largest one
is
alone in terms of all other values are
smaller in magnitude
and this result turns out to be uh very
useful um in working with positive
matrices.
The notes here go through the proof of
that. Um I guess they're included here
if we wanted to sort of get into
technical proofs of uh linear algebra.
Um and I don't want to do that. Uh let's
see. I finished the these notes with
just some mention of different news
sources that you should consider uh
exploring with uh in finance and uh with
well there's Yahoo Finance which is
where we can easily collect price data.
Um but you should know that the Wall
Street Journal is um there are you can
get a free subscription with that
through uh your Keraros password or ID
rather. So so that's very useful and
then there are a number of other sites
that uh you may may find useful. Now um
let's see when uh
let's see in our very first lecture
um let's see I indicated
um how we could use our studio to
collect data plot time series of
different stocks or other assets. And in
this lecture two, I distributed
um this uh workspace which has uh our
scripts
um and output for
looking at uh portfolios of stocks and
considering sort of equal weighted
portfolios with different uh components
in the equal weights. And so with uh
let's see if you go to uh the rcloud
uh
our studio cloud project. Um so with R
Studio cloud
um or maybe it's cloud R studio um one
can
um upload different u our programs in
this uh in this project and so I don't
has anyone in class yet used our our
Studio Cloud for any of the examples. I
I'd like some I'd like everyone to at
least be capable of doing that and uh
I'd like sort of proof that it actually
works with students doing it. So um it
would be great for some of you to uh to
consider that. What's what's nice about
this um environment is that I can give
you an R program and it should run just
by saying run. you don't have to install
anything. And uh let's see with this
output um let's see there's one program
called script SP500
and there's a table of contents for this
R script which says it loads libraries
then collects stock prices and then
saves the workspace.
So the commands are all very simple in
here. Um and uh and then
let's see with the equal weighted
portfolios
script it actually loads libraries
and loads the data set of stock prices
that was just downloaded in the other
program and it uh loads the data in.
Then in processing the data um
I uh let's see consider investing
a portfolio by equally weighting uh
allocations to different stocks in the
S&P 500 index. And so if one does this,
these simple R commands create the uh
value of such a portfolio
where in fact
um as indicated here it's investing
$1,000
at the beginning of uh 2019.
And as an alternative to just equally
waiting across the S&P 500 stocks, um I
looked at the Amazon, Apple, uh Nvidia
or no, Netflix and Google. These were
actually they're really hot stocks about
four or five years ago and uh basically
look at equal waiting of all these. And
so here's how uh the investment
equal weighted at the beginning of the
period resulted towards the end. So so
there are some interesting features uh
one can see if one happened to
be good at identifying stocks to invest
in. You can do much better than sort of
the average S&P 500. um there can be
greater risk
by investing in a smaller number of
stocks because you're not so
diversified.
And so you can see how the red uh the
red uh graph of values sort of decreases
rather dramatically at some points in in
the time period. And
if one looks at sort of what happened to
the $250 invested in each of those uh
four stocks, this is what happened over
this uh whatever fiveyear period or
almost fiveyear period. And this this
raises some interesting issues for us,
which is when considering portfolio
construction,
um
maybe equally weighting allocations
across some assets is a good thing to
start with. But what happens
over time?
Well, in this case, um, Apple
outgrew the other allocations
substantially and so the degree of
diversification in the portfolio is
getting lower because we have a greater
concentration in that one stock. So what
we'd like to do perhaps is to balance
rebalance the portfolio
and um different approaches to
rebalancing portfolios can be uh
considered. Now, um, if we were to
consider
sort of rebalancing every day
the investments in these four stocks,
then
would you think that's a really good way
to rebalance to do it very very
frequently? And why or why not?
>> Yes. Well, if you do it too frequently,
then like variances like in 2022 might
like affect it, but it won't be very
like good for the big picture.
>> Yeah. I mean, it's uh if you rebalance
too quickly, then you're taking
funds away from winners and giving those
to losers.
And so you're sort of equalizing
allocations in a way that doesn't
benefit from
short-term trends or strengths in
different assets.
So uh so that extreme is is uh probably
not something you want to do. Um, one
thing that's rather interesting is just
how if you do not do any rebalancing
then the portfolios
become rather uh uh undiversified
and so the risk level is actually
probably increasing um over time here.
So if you know one way of rebalancing
portfolios is trying to maintain a
certain risk level for the portfolio and
uh such an objective would require
periodic rebalancing.
Okay. Um
well let's
move on then to
the uh
topic of probability theory. And so what
I want to do in this note is to just
give you a quick overview
basically a review of uh probability
concepts that you probably are very
familiar with. Um and so uh with
probability theory um it's customary to
distinguish between discrete valued
random variables and or and continuous
ones. And so with discrete valued random
variables, you know, those can be just
events occurring or not like a default
of a counterparty or um maybe the
federal uh open market committee
deciding on a Fed funds rate. Um the uh
let's see in thinking of individual
uh stocks and their dynamics uh intraday
one can think of different orders for a
stock to buy or sell coming in uh at
random and wondering what side those
would be on. Also perhaps the share size
of uh the next market order. Um it you
now the now it used to be that these
were always discreet sort of outcomes
like share size. It turns out you can
actually now invest fractionally
fractional shares in different stocks.
So the markets become uh more uh rich in
that way. Um but importantly we do want
to distinguish between discrete outcomes
that have probabilities
uh with respective outcomes versus
continuous random variables where we're
thinking of uh values that could take on
any value in some interval or range. And
so
in thinking about the values of assets,
we can think of the value being in a in
a continuous range. Also,
timing of events is a uh an important um
random variable that is continuous as
well. So um one might consider what is
the waiting time to the next market
order for uh Apple stock. Um
mixed variables uh can arise where we
think of a stock having some value
where it's generally a positive value
but it could go bankrupt in which case
um there would perhaps be some discrete
probability of bankruptcy for a stock.
Um now with probability models we use
probability mass functions for discrete
variables and probability densities for
continuous and so we use calculus to
calculate continuous probabilities
in different intervals. Um and
importantly uh the cumulative
distribution function
is a very important
uh tool.
So if we write fubx of let me write c is
equal to probability that the random
variable x is less than or equal to c as
a function of c. Um this
value is going to be no
at no smaller than zero and no larger
than one
and it will be monotone increasing
in C.
um and
distributions will be uniquely specified
by specifying their uh cumulative
distribution function. So these are uh
very simple concepts. Um
let's see there are expectations in
moments. Um
let's see one just uh I'll just call
this an anecdote.
Um
if X is continuous
random variable
um and we define Y equal to F of X.
So we consider the probability integral
transform
of the random variable X.
What is the distribution of Y?
Okay.
>> Unable.
>> Yeah, it's uniform
zero. It's uniform on zero.
So what's really neat is that sort of a
monotone transform of the random
variable X whatever X is so long as we
know what the distribution is transforms
that to a uniform. And so this is true
regardless of what f is so long as f is
continuous.
And uh that property can be turn out to
be very very useful. Um
one issue could be oh suppose you have a
random sample of data from some
distribution or you think it's from some
distribution.
Is the sample consistent with that
distribution or not? Well, if you did
this probability integral transform,
it should lead to a uniform distribution
which may or may not be realized. So
anyway, that's turns out to be quite
quite uh useful. Now, uh we have
expectations and moments of random
variables.
Um basically the mean of a random
variable is the probability weighted
outcome. We can generalize the mean to
looking at which is the first moment to
consider the probability weighted
average of the kith power where k is an
integer. And um the variance of random
variables is a useful measure of
uncertainty about the mean value. And uh
there's a nice formula for the variance
which is the squared distance from the
mean in terms of the average squared
minus the square of the average. So
these are useful
uh formulas that may come in be useful
at certain times. Now um in terms of
measuring uncertainty
about outcomes
instead of the variance
taking the square root of the variance
is useful because its scale is the same
as the original units. Most people don't
think in terms of squared units with any
problem. Um, and so instead of dealing
with the variance directly, we'll
commonly take the square root of that to
have the same units as our original
variable x. Now, with the uh with
skewess
and curtosis, we're looking at measures
of sort of the shape of the
distribution.
And with skewess, as you might
anticipate,
that detects a symmetry in a
distribution. And so something that's
nice to think about is um if we have a
random variable X where um the expected
value of X is equal to mu and the square
root of the variance
is sigma. Um
if we take Z
= X - mu over sigma. This is a
standardization of the random variable.
um the expected value of Z will equal
zero and the variance of Z will equal
one
as will the square root of the variance
and for the skewess
which I use I guess it's a gamma
gamma is equal to the expected value of
Z cubed and the curtosis
is equal to the expected value of Z to
the 4th.
So
the skewess and curtosis parameters of a
distribution
can measure asymmetry at least if the
cubed value has more weight on the
positive end than the negative end. Um
it'll be skewed to the right. And um
with the kappa uh we're looking at Z to
the 4th. So we're looking at basically
how heavy are the tails
and um the uh let's see for a Gaussian
distribution
kappa is equal to three or normal 01
or any normal um and uh
gamma is equal to zero. So anyway, so
these other parameters are useful for
characterizing distributions that are
not Gaussian and non-gaussian terms of
perhaps skewess or heavier tails. Um
all right well let's uh just review
Gaussian distributions.
Um
I hope this formula for the density of a
Gaussian is very familiar to everyone
here. Um we basically have the uh
density function
is uh
equal to 1 / 2 pi
sigma e minus a half x - mu over sigma^
2.
And so um
the mean is mu, the variance is sigma
squared and uh the density function is
symmetrical with a maximum at the mean
mu and the points of inflection are
actually at plus and minus sigma. So if
we think of just trying to draw a normal
density function
then
the peak is at the mean and the point of
inflection
where the second derivative
is zero. It goes from
negative second derivative to a positive
second derivative. that distance is is
sigma
symmetrically. Um
so uh all right so let's take a look at
the normal bell curve. Um
68% lies within one standard deviation.
So this is you know the whatever you
know AP statistics you learn these
facts. Um if we go to two standard
deviations from the mean that's 95%
and three standard deviations is 99.7%.
So um so these models are um normal
models have have these sort of
properties of how likely different
variations are in standard deviation
units. Um
well in finance we'd like to
exploit perhaps Gaussian distributions
for modeling prices.
Um and uh
with a normal density curve it actually
um applies to x values that can be
arbitrarily large negative or positive.
It's an unbounded
distribution in terms of potential
outcomes. And so one way of dealing with
that with say prices
um is to consider taking the log of
prices and thinking of that being a
normal distribution.
And so that con construction corresponds
to a lognormal uh distribution.
And so if we have a random variable X
that's normal and then we take the
exponential of that normal then we say
that the Y variable is logn normal with
the parameters mu and sigma squar
corresponding to the log scale. Now um
what
will be very interesting
in subsequent lectures is when we talk
about uh stochcastic processes
that can be um applied in uh financial
markets. There's an important
stochcastic process called brownie in
motion
which um many of you probably have some
familiarity with. And with a brownie in
motion process, the increments
of the process
over time periods
has a distribution
that's normally distributed.
And as the length of the increment of
time increases
both the mean and variance of the
outcome
changes. And so this Brownian motion
process is a very very interesting
process that is um intimately related to
Gaussian distribution. So so we'll get
we'll get there um in a few lectures.
Now um one of the useful tools we have
in probability theory is being able to
derive
uh the distributions of transformations
of random variables. So with the log
normal we have a normal distribution.
We maybe take the exponential of that
normal outcome and we'd like to be able
to write down the density of that
distribution and compute different
features. Well, um we can think of say a
random variable X being transformed to Y
with a function G.
And then we can consider the function h
which is the inverse function of g.
And
as examples, if g is e to the x, then h
is the log um function.
And with change of variables, if we have
the CDF of X,
um, then the CDF of Y
is equal to the CDF of X evaluated at
the inverse of Y on the X scale. So this
equation here is
a simple sort of logical statement
that's everyone here I think would agree
is valid. And so if this function
relating the distribution functions is
true. If we take the derivative
of the CDF function
of Y, we get the density.
And then we just have to apply the chain
rule on the right hand side,
the density of X evaluated at H of Y.
But then we also need to have the chain
rule for H in there. So with this
formula um
right it's
all sort of familiar but if we have um f
of um x is equal to the integral minus
infinity to x of f ofx f of t dt rather
then the derivative
of f evaluated at x turns out to be
equal to f of t evaluated at t = x.
So the cumulative integral has a
derivative equal to the argument of the
integral. So this is easy and we can use
this to get the density function for a
logn normal distribution.
And
here's the density of the
log normal distribution. It has the same
form as the Gaussian density plugging in
log y instead of e for x. But then we
need to multiply that by the uh chain
rule sort of derivative of uh h with
respect to y which is 1 over y. Okay.
Okay, so here's the logn normal
distribution
and as an example I chose a mean log
value of 0.2
and a SD on the log scale of 0.4 four
and as you work with different
distributions um you may have uh
let's see suggest or not suggestions but
you may find it useful to consider
specific parameter values here I'm
thinking that if one has a
um if we think of say x of zero equaling
one and x of one being distributed as a
log normal
with mu equal to 2 and sigma equal to 04
then
this uh logn normal distribution can
correspond to sort of a one-year
period
where on the log scale we expect a mean
change on the log scale to be 0.2
and with standard deviation of 04. So
this would potentially be relevant for
an asset
and looking at its sort of percentage
change on the log scale over one year
with an annualized return of about 20%
and annualized standard deviation of
0.4.
Well, if we draw vertical lines in this
distribution
space or sample space of the log normal,
um, here I've just drawn symmetrical
percentiles of 25th and 75th percentiles
and then the fifth and 95th percentiles
in red. And it's obvious that it's
asymmetrical.
And uh
what's uh
in what's useful actually with um
different distributions is being able to
calculate
quantities of interest in finance. And
so here's a nice example of uh a
financial um computation
uh where we consider a call option to
buy an asset at some terminal time
capital T and the strike price is going
to be at price K. And so um if we think
of X being the random variable of what
the time t price is, then the payoff is
going to be equal to
X minus K the value minus the strike
price if that's positive or it won't be
worth anything. So um if we have at time
t um let's say if we were to draw here
as a function p subt or sorry x I guess
and there's a strike price here then we
would have the zero value up to k and
then we'd have
um x minus k
be giving this option payoff. off. Now,
you'll hear
Vasili and Jake talk about the hockey
stick payoff function of options. And
so, this is what that
comes from. Now what's interesting to
know is this theorem here says that if
we have a density function little f with
cdf capital f for the outcome at time
capital t. Then the expected value of
this payoff
is equal to this integral from the
strike to infinity of 1 - f ofx.
And the proof of this is done by
considering a finite upper limit m
capital m and then integrating by parts
and getting a formula here. So it's an
interesting result that
if we know the terminal time t
random price
uh of a random of of an asset then a
call option on that uh terminal value uh
will have this expected value.
So, um let's see. Those of you who
actually have some advanced probability
coursework may notice that um when you
uh are looking at sort of um the
expected value of a positive random
variable, you can sometimes express that
as an integral of the sort of
complimementaryary probability of
exceeding that value and so that's that
sort of result ends up being applicable
here in a very nice way. Um now with a
normal with distribution for X we get
this formula coming out for that call
option and if we have a log normal we
get this different
distribu this different result. So
knowing the distribution uh affects what
the option price is. Um now in
probability theory uh we make use of
moment generating functions which I
guess when I first learned of these I
thought well nice tool but I don't
really care at least you know it's a
highly technical tool to use. However,
um it turns out these are incredibly uh
useful moment generating functions and
the definition of the moment generating
function is
given by
looking at just the expected value of e
to the tx.
And
we can sort of expand this argument in a
tailaylor series
which is done
on the first line there and take the
expectation.
Now
something that we should be
questioning perhaps is do moment
generating functions always exist?
And by that I mean do we get a finite
valued function mx of t for all random
variables.
>> Okay.
>> Hello
Sorry. Sorry.
>> That's right. No, no, that's fine.
That's right.
>> Sorry to my head and then I have to go.
>> Yeah, that's
the moment generating function doesn't
have to exist.
Um, and the moment generating function
won't exist if this exponential function
is has too much weight. So that integral
is infinite.
And an example where it is infinite is a
Koshy distribution.
And if you're a Koshy distribution
doesn't have finite mean or variance. Um
but what's interesting is that
um this is called the moment generating
function.
There's a uh
a characteristic function
characteristic function
that turns out to be equal to e to the
tx
where i here is the square root of -1.
Um and if you uh know a little bit about
complex numbers,
this turns out to be equal to the cosine
of tx
plus i * the s of tx.
And it turns out that these
characteristic functions always exist
and can be used almost the same way a
moment generating function can be used
when it exists. So the fact that it
doesn't always exist shouldn't worry us
because we can generalize to
characteristic functions. But what's
what's important is that
um if we have two random variables that
have identical moment generating
functions,
then those distributions
are equal for the two random variables.
So we have identical distributions if
their moment generating functions are
equal. And if we consider a sequence of
random variables
and the moment generating functions
that can be thought of as a sequence
converges to
a function that's a moment generating
function of some distribution. then we
have that the sequence of random
variables x's converges to that
distribution as well.
So, so these are nice properties that
allow us to understand uh limits of
random variables and what the
distributions are of limits.
Now with moment generating functions um
the uh
this
slide here discusses
um well it introduces you to the moment
generating function for the normal
distribution with mean mu and variance
sigma squared and with the special case
of mu equals zero and sigma equaling
one.
Let's see. For a normal 01,
if we look at the expected value of e to
the tx,
okay, it's equal to the integral of e to
the tx
time e to the - one2 x^2
over 2 pi
dx.
So this is simply the formula for
e to the t z I guess. Okay. Um well if
we look at this
exponential here we can write this as e
to the - one2
um x minus
uh
let's see
xus
uh t / 2
squared
That gives us x^2
minus
oh no just x - t ^2
is this right?
Let's see. Okay. I basically want to
take 12 x^
squared
uh
minus
or sorry plus TX
and write this as min - one2 of uh
X - T squared
minus
T ^2 over two.
Is that right? All right. I want a plus
right there.
So, so this exponent
of the exponential here can be rewritten
as this exponent times that. So this so
this is equal to um
so this is equal to the integral from
minus infinity to infinity 1 over 2
pi e - 12 x - t^2
and then plus t ^2 / 2 dx.
And so this exponential factor with t^
squ
um can be taken out and this integral
here is simply going to equal one.
So we are able to find the moment
generating function for the standard
normal very easily
is equal to e to the half t ^2. Now if
we think about transforming a random
variable such as
X
with a linear function basically rescale
X by sigma and add a mu
then the moment generating function of
that transformation of X to Y can be
written out and it's equal to the
exponential of T mu times the moment
generating function of x evaluated at t
sigma instead. So knowing what
the x moment generating function is we
basically get this function coming out
for the u moment generating function of
a normal. Now this uh moment generating
function
is in fact the moment the the expected
value of a logn normal random variable.
Um at least if we set t equal to one
it's the expected value of a logn
normal. And if we take t equal to two,
it's equal to the square
of a logn normal distribution. So we can
use the moments generating function for
the normal to calculate moments of a
logn normal distribution and that'll be
an exercise in the next homework.
Um okay.
All right. So linear transformations.
Um
basically linear transformations
don't change uh the sort of skewess of
distributions.
Um and the curtosis
um can
uh well it might affect the curtosis.
All right. Well, let's move on to
considerations of more than one random
variable and the concept of two random
variables being independent.
In probability theory, we say two random
variables are independent if the joint
probability
of
the random variables
a set
X lying in a set A and Y lying in a set
B. if that joint probability of both
occurring is equal to just the product
of each occurring alone.
And so we have
for uh densities or probability mass
functions we have this property of the
joint density function factoring into
the product of the marginal densities of
each of the random variables.
And it works for continuous or uh
discrete distributions as well. So
independence
means that uh basically knowing one
variable doesn't give us any insight on
the value of the other variable. Now uh
we can compute co-variances between two
random variables
and correlations.
And so um with a co-variance
uh
with a co-variance between two random
variables.
Um this is a generalization of the
variance for one variable. But this is
the probability weighted average of x
minus I'll write here mux
time y - muy
and
the correlation statistic
corresponds to dividing
dividing this co-variance
by the product of sigma x and sigma y
the square root of the variances.
And um it turns out that this is also
can be written as sort of x - mux over
sigma x times y - muy
over sigma y.
And so the standardization of the random
variables to have mean zero and standard
deviation one
can be
made and then the expected product of
those standardized values is the
correlation statistic or the correlation
parameter. Um,
importantly,
zero correlation doesn't imply
independence,
but zero correlation uh does mean that
there's uh that that the dependence
um does suggest that there's no linear
dependence uh between the two variables.
Now when we consider generalizing from
two random variables to many then we can
think of working with random vectors
and with say little n being the count of
different random variables. Um we can
have notation of mu.j for the means or
expectations of each and sigma j
corresponding to the co-variance between
x i and xj for sigma j.
And we can then represent sort of the
expected vector
of x values is equal to a mu vector. And
we can represent the co-variances
between elements in terms of an n byn
matrix sigma.
And so what's important to realize here
is that if we have
um an x vector
and a mu vector. So x is equal to x1
down to xn
and mu is equal to mu1
down to mu n.
Then
we define the co-variance matrix of X
to be the expected value of
sort of X minus the mu vector times X
minus the mu vector transpose. And so
this is an N by one this is a 1 by N
transpose. And so we get an n byn
matrix where we take expectations
element by element in that array.
So um so this is a nice way of
representing the coariance matrix.
And
what's useful in particular is well if
we think of X's maybe representing
returns on different assets
with means meu and the covariance matrix
tells us how much variability there is
in each of the xis but also the
correlation structure across the n uh
x's. Then um if we consider say a linear
combination of the x's given by a vector
a of constants
then this linear combination of the x's
can actually represent maybe a portfolio
of holdings across different assets
given by the x size. And what we'd like
to be able to do is model the mean
value of Y and its variance. The mean
value is very simply the linear
combination of the component means times
the A coefficients. And when we go to
calculate the variance of Y, if you go
through each step here and each equation
here is doing something slightly
important. um you know we're basically
substituting in a transpose x for y at
the beginning and arpose mu for the
expected value. Then we are able to pull
out the constant vector a transpose in
the front of the expectation and
actually in the back of the expectation.
So these coefficient vectors are
constants and can be pulled out of the
expectation computations. And then this
middle term here is simply the coariance
matrix of x. So we have that the
variance of y is simply the sum
double sum over all pairs of
coefficients a i a j multiplied by the
covariance terms between i and j. So
this is the formula for the variance of
y.
um something that's
let's see I'm not sure if we go into
this in the next slide but um
if the co-variance of x i and xj is
equal to zero so if this is equal to
zero for all i not equal to j then this
variance expression simplifies a
And um if say a I ji
um is equal to a j is equal to 1 / n
then
um
the uh sum of the ais
is equal to one
and the sum of the ai
squares
is equal to
what?
No, no. This this is not this this is
not equal to one. It's going to be less
than one.
>> One over n, right? It's it's n
* 1 / n.
So it's sorry n * 1 / n^2.
So the variance of sort of an equal
weighted
average of the x's
will have variance that's 1 / n times
the variance of each of the x's. So this
is where sort of diversification
can be useful in terms of reducing
variability
and uh in the very special case where we
have say zero correlated assets
um and uh
I guess equal weighted variances of the
ass of the x's um then we can reduce the
uh variability
by
the factor n one or multiplying by the
factor 1 / n.
Okay. Um well this leads us to uh
introducing you to principal components
analysis.
Um and
with principal components analysis
um
let's see
we
consider
sort of an mv variant vector x
um
so we consider an x vector that's m by
one which has an expected value
equal to
an alpha vector
and a covariance matrix
which is M by M equal to sigma
matrix
and
this coariance matrix is a real matrix.
that is symmetric.
Therefore, it's going to have real
values
and
it's also going to have
non- negative igen values
because
the coariance matrix is positive
semidefinite.
And so um so sigma
is positive
semidefinite.
The definition of positive semidefinite
is that for all a vectors
um a transpose sigma a is greater than
or equal to zero.
And
this is actually the variance of a
transpose X.
This
product of the coarience matrix times
the transpose of an A vector that. So,
so the fact that the variance
of the linear combination of
the x's is strictly non- negative gives
us this result here which means that the
sigma matrix is positive semidefinite
and uh
we um let's see we can basically list
the ien values to be lambda one through
lambda to m those could be all
different. Um some of them will be non
zero so long as there's no uh so long as
the coariance matrix is uh um sort of
has some positive rank. And so with this
framework where we have um the
co-variance matrix sigma having values
lambda i and corresponding igen vectors
gamma subi. Um
we can
well we can normalize the igen vectors
gamma i to be
of unit length.
So gamma transpose gamma i is equal to
one and we can also define the gamas to
be uh orthogonal to each other.
Then uh principal components
defines new variables
by saying
um we take our vector x
we transpose it to x minus alpha. So
we're looking at deviations from the
mean values component by component and
then we
take each of those and
we
multiply them
or look at the dotproduct of gamma i dox
minus alpha
and we call this um
the coefficient
of the E principal component variables.
And these principal component variables
are very neat because
their average or mean value is equal to
zero.
But the covariance matrix between the PS
is um
it's time to finish the lecture here.
Um
the uh covariance matrix is the diagonal
uh matrix lambda. So we basically have
transformed our original X vector
into
new coordinates which have mean zero
are uncorrelated with each other and
have variability that
decreases basically with I. If we rank
the the principal components uh en
vectors lambda one to be bigger than or
basically to be ordered from lambda one
to lambda m. So we have uh an orthogonal
basis for our data in this case. And um
let's see. I guess we'll finish there
for today, but on Thursday we'll finish
these notes up. And uh what you'll be
able to see is how we can try to
represent
an x vector
as a sum of terms. and maybe the sum of
terms corresponds to using just a small
number of the principal component
variables. So when we have
multi-dimensional vectors that have
variability that is limited to a smaller
number of dimensions, we can
characterize those smaller number of
dimensions nicely with principal
components and obtain uh useful models.
And these kinds of models underly
multiffactor models often in doing uh uh
modeling asset returns and financial
markets. So we'll finish there for today
and uh thank you.