okay so today we are going to cover a
topic which is quite unusual for 14 to
71 uh nonetheless it's quite important
it's about the views that people about
that people have about the morality of
markets um 271 is about antitrust mainly
and of course antitrust is about
market and if people don't believe in
markets um then that raises issues about
what we are doing in the first place
furthermore there are lot of development
nowadays actually it's broader than of
the trust about what independent agency
should be doing so that has started with
central banks um their mission of En
large is no longer just inflation
targeting and financial
stability but you know it goes Way
Beyond and now everybody talks about
green central banks and there is issue
about whether fighting the climate
change should be the responsibility of
the central bank or it should be the
responsibility of
Ministries um with antitrust it's a
little bit the same because there are
more and more discussions in particular
in Europe but you know all over the
world about whether the consumer
standard is the right way to proceed so
the consumer standard is basically that
the antitrust mission is to defend the
consumer maybe not the short-term
consumer maybe an intertemporal consumer
uh because sometimes you have tradeoffs
between today and tomorrow but you know
by and large the mission of of anti
trust authorities everywhere in the
world is to defend the consumer it's
it's pry clear
it's difficult in practice but you know
on paper it's simple you you just just
stand as an advocate for the for the
consumer but now people say no no no
maybe we should relax on the trust um
first for example when we choose
cases so if there is a caviar cartel and
a mil cartel then if you have limited
resources you first go after the the mil
cartel and the cavier cartel you just
say okay
this is not that important so we we
should take into account redistribution
we should take into account climate
change so if we have a cartel which
actually promotes the fight against
climate change maybe we should tolerate
the cartel and so on and so forth there
are lots lots of
discussions uh about that actually next
week I'm going to a conference
organizing by Margaret vager I'm giving
a Peyote there and you know the panel
just after me is exactly about this
topic with people like Tom philippo and
others it's it's really about this topic
so I would know more in a week from now
that's not going to help very much for
for today but uh you know that's really
important because in the end that's that
the mission in my own view i' I've I've
worked on Mission and advocacy with
Mattias and my own view is that it's not
always a good idea to have missions
Mission creep and if the issues are real
so inequality is real climate change is
real of course uh maybe it's
not say to the antitrust authority to
tackle them but actually more political
bodies should be doing that as opposed
to but that's my own view on on those on
those issues um but there's a broader
thing about whether we we like markets
and there's this bizarre thing um that
um almost every economy in the world is
a market economy and nonetheless nobody
likes market so here it's kind of
paradox somehow
um and
that's yeah I will come back to our to
to the big picture about how we think
about the organization of society but
you know it's it's kind of strange so
what I'm going to do is to have a brief
introduction about this and then switch
to a paper that I'm finishing the
revision I'm finishing with Mattias
the uh on the morality of markets but I
just want to have a broad picture first
I will go relatively fast because it's
developed in some detail in in economics
for the common good if you have seen
economics for the common good the book
um but you know you
you feel free to ask question actually
try to ask more question than you did on
Monday okay that's your mission um the
there there are two kinds of attacks
against
Market the first is that a number of
markets are what's called
repugnant so you know we we are we don't
feel very much at tease with those
markets and almost every well-known
philosopher has a book on that um you
know I put here de braat and Michael SLE
but there are many other well-known
philosophers who also have books on on
EX with rough the same title not the
same content because if you compare
those two books for example they they
they start from the same point of view
but you know they they have very
different
analysis um you know the the most
well-known one I mean this was a huge
best seller of Michael sandal uh you
know talks about all those markets that
make us uneasy you we do we have markets
for babies or you know whatever all
those things as are actually creating
some uh some conflicts in our brain
about whether we should have those
markets
now
um this this is more specific it's not
the market in general it's specific
markets that we don't quite like but you
know the the frontier is unclear so
number of people think for example that
uh tradeable emission permits Market you
know the ETS systems for carbon are
immoral they are immoral because you can
pay for the right to pollute or carbon
tax is the same you pay the carbon tax
and you pay for to pollute of course you
can ask you is that more more to not
have toay to pollute but and then then
there's a big silence in front but you
know lots of people in my experience the
last 30 years is that when you talk
about a carbon price it always sense but
it's IM M you talk to a minister and you
and but yeah you're right but it's IM
more and at a point of time you say okay
you prefer people polluting for free uh
is that more M but you know I don't know
and I think you know we are Economist
and we have to realize that in Civil
Society oh these are kind of strange
views as strange to some extent
um and the ideas are are really about
Market incentive it's true that much of
the work we have done in the last 30 or
40 years how about basically when those
markets don't work and when the
incentives don't work uh so you know
they there's a huge number of papers on
why low power incentive scheme might be
desirable because you know you have no
easy performance measurement teamwork
which is a special case and think of
about Banks paper collusion with monitor
my work with my work on on capture
repeating interaction
multitasking uh asymmetric
information and so on and so forth so we
there's a huge number of of pieces of
theory which basically says you know low
power incentive scheme can be good
sometimes in specific
circumstances and same thing that number
of papers about the fact that incentive
can crowd out intrinsic motivation
okay so the the the two papers with Babu
are along those lines the first line is
basically that you know if I give you an
incentive I may reveal something about
you or the trust have in you or about
the task and that may actually
backfires because it conveys information
to you that discourages you um the
second one which is more familiar from
psychology is the idea of uh uh that you
know if I pay pay you to do something
like giving your blood uh then people
don't know whether you're giving your
blood because you are generous or
because you are greedy you want the
money so that kind of stuff so that
those the two papers uh I had with h
about that so but you know I could go on
and on so you know much of our work is
actually about cases in which markets
don't work in which incentives don't
work but nonetheless it is a case that
you know
we we are still more pro market and pro
incentive than the average person in the
population right and you know same thing
for the empirical work there is a lot of
empirical work showing that actually
incentives may be needed um and that's
something that is not very
well
received you can ask why why is that the
case I me part of the thing is that we
are the bearer of bad news okay because
when we say
we need
incentives we implicitly say people are
not as nice as we would like them to be
right that's exactly the point which is
we would like people to be nice but they
are not that nice they keep on polluting
etc
um and you know that that triggers
reaction in France every time you talk
about a carbon price people say you know
the environment should not be per
protecting the environment should not be
punitive you know it's it's always the
same thing um you don't trust people I
mean sure I mean I don't I don't trust
people I mean over the last 30 years
nothing has happened in the fight
against climate change come on but you
know still people they still say oh no
no people will do what it takes and come
on I mean you know the answer is no it's
not going to happen we're the planet is
going to burn um so I don't know I mean
is like
U um but so still despite all the
caveats we've been working on for for
decades it's still the case that we are
pro market and pro incentive on on on
the all right compared to the population
okay um H you know and then the
psychologist I already talk about
the those ones but uh the legal scholar
actually have have another line of
attack which is which is interesting is
about the
expressive uh content of the law so
basically the idea is the law is not an
just an incentive scheme I mean we tend
to see the law as an incentive scheme
you know you have to pay a fine you go
to jail I mean that's that's going to
incentivize you to behave well um legal
Scholars they go beyond that they say oh
but no but the law also sends a signal
to society about the norm in society
about the views what is acceptable or
not so it it goes goes beyond that okay
and then philosophers I
mentioned so they they're unhappy with
markets okay now I'm not going to go
into that but um in economics common
good I spent a fair amount of time
trying to explain that a number of
repugnant
markets are
actually markets with externalities with
internalities with whatever asymmetric
information they can be explained in the
framework of Economics you know there is
no contradiction between economics and
the repugnant Market I me just take
babies for adoption I mean you know we
will not want to be we will not want the
babies for adoption to be sold to the I
beer okay well I mean there you might
say well after all if someone is willing
to pay a lot for the baby that maybe
that person is is going to benefit more
for the baby but you know there's a
third
party who is not part of the contract
that it's a baby right you know you have
a huge anxiety on the baby you have no
guarantee that actually the the I beer
is going to be the best father or mother
right um but you know it goes beyond
that also something which is interesting
which is image ex is so that I discussed
U sometimes you know you could have two
parties who are actually part of a
contract but their contract actually may
shed bad light on the rest of the
population and you image externalities
is thing then there are all kinds of
internalities but internalities
you know like like present bias for
example is just an exet on yourself on
your future self so it's the same thing
so we we don't we don't like um you know
people who sell
drugs or
opioids or things like that um and of
course we are against involuntary
slavery because of that's huge exality
but we are against even against
voluntary slavery and say we not
voluntary slavery if everybody agrees
why not to a contract but you know of
course there are there are present
biases which uh which could play a big
role in those
markets asymmetric
information and sandal for example say w
those Economist will say okay just pay
to get friends I mean but if you pay to
get to get a friend and how do you know
this person is your friend you it's just
start symmetric information it makes no
sense right um so there is there's at at
least a number of those things that can
be it's just a consequence of standard
economics you know so so but the thing I
want to insist
on is more postures I don't like more
postures I mean that's my own bias um
which is they can be useful as a warning
signal so you know I see something I I
get some emotion and that might suggest
that something might be wrong okay so
it's a warning signal it's actually can
be useful but I don't like people who
who just stay with the emotion and say I
don't like
it and you know this is immoral without
explaining why and and that's something
because you know if you say you know in
the old time you know for example
life insurance was immoral everybody
thought life insurance was immoral now
why I mean so they would say oh yeah it
has to do with life sure I mean come on
uh you know same thing you know in many
countries today and most countries
yesterday you know having sex among
people of the same sex or different
races for example was sort of as immoral
by a majority of people and that was
just a way of actually infringing on the
freedom of people
so you know those moral postures are
more always very nervous and you know
when I hear philosophers telling me Oh
this is IM moral period I just I just
don't don't like it again the warning s
signal is is pretty fine I our emotions
actually can reveal real issues but you
know you have to go the next step and
say let's think a little bit more about
this is is there an exality is somebody
is someone and so on and so forth right
so that's just my own view on this okay
questions
yes how sort of could we differ or think
about the sort of difference from you
know someone sort of having a sort of
moral cost of you know taking some
action or consuming some thing um and
then someone having a sort of blockage
where there's a cut off after which they
they just stop um even considering that
you know
considerations that a possible thing
that we could do for instance so there's
this thing that the very very Act of
thinking about
something um actually Reveals All
stuff there is this movie I don't
remember the T I was not such a good
movie but there was this movie in which
a millionaire was offering there was a
young
couple very good uh uh United couple
and then the millionaire comes and but
they they are poor and the millionaire
comes in and say you know I pay 1
million to sleep with your wife and then
they start entertaining the S and I
actually don't remember what happens in
the end but you know they start
entertaining their s and that that
destroys their even entertaining their s
destroys their couple right uh not doing
it just just just thinking about it and
same thing you know if if if you tell a
Catholic you have to uh to think about
you know whether Mary could be a virgin
or whatever you just that that just
starting to question things may actually
already is a signal is that what you had
in mind or yeah
and and
sometimes we economists actually are
guilty of that in a sense so you know
you may
remember last summer talking
about taking uh you know polluting stuff
to less developed
countries because they they're willing
to get less money in order to to take
care of the stuff and that was that was
a big Scandal I don't remember if he was
recommending it which is a different
thing uh just thinking about it was just
already thought of as
being very
strange um and you know that's we often
actually when do we do research we often
think about various other things which
may be S as as not as not right and I
would say it's part of the freedom of
the researcher now when we go public
it's a different different ball game
right uh so I will try to distinguish my
between my life as a researcher where I
want to enjoy maximum freedom of thought
and then you maybe when I go public I
may offend some people and so on and
that's that's a different thing
um but of course there's always a same
line between the
two um now if you think about our
society's organizer and you know all of
that but I just want to to give you the
framework um you know I I will say it's
Adam Smith plus
pigu okay um it's Adam Smith Plus pigu
so the very bizarre thing uh is that by
and large we have for-profit
corporations so for-profit corporations
are entities in which uh the decision
making obeys the
shoulders the shoulders
decide um of course you know it's not
quite true you have agency issues with
with the managers and we have worked on
all those things but basically it's the
shoulders to decide now we know why it's
the case because that makes that where
the shoulders make sure they get their
money back otherwise they might not get
their money back or investors more
Journey but still raises the issue that
shareholders of course are interested in
the decision they want their money back
but what about workers and suppliers and
customers and so there are many
stakeholders ERS in were actually
left left aside in this decision Prime
right so we have this this situation
where one of the stakeholders takes a
decision those are the investors and the
others are basically
left uh their decision
experties so that that speaks to the co
corporate social responsibility
right um fredman at this uh famous
column in which he said the
responsibility of business is actually
to maximize profit not to take into
account the stakeholders
welfare and his colleague at Chicago
actually said well if you want to
protect shoulders this is Ronald
Co okay you the first one was Milton
Freeman so I realize your generation may
never have seen a picture of Milton fman
or Ronald Co but uh So Co basically said
well let's have contracts to protect
shoulders and to some extent that's
that's being done so the contracts with
which insulate the most the workers or
the debt holders and so on against the
decisions of
shoulders um are say for example the
worker is a fixed wage plus some sance
pay if they are lead
off um same thing if you look at uh Deb
holders they get often some fixed debt
repayment uh plus some collateral
pledging in case uh The Firm goes
bankrupt and you could also have exit
options and the like okay so basically
the idea okay shoulders this side that's
onal cause in a sense shoulders this
side but you protect the stakeholders
through
Contracting now the next step is oh yeah
where but what about the quality of
Contracting of course uh imperfect
contracts Collective action Prime and
the environment and competition policy
are good example you have millions of
people who are affected by the decision
of the firm and of course it's very hard
for them to contract with the firms and
so on um and there are many other issues
with
cause okay so in a sense what we have
converge to is some kind of mixture
of you know which one was with Miss and
we speak good right um the uh to to mix
um to to mix basically a market the
invisible end of the market together
with together with with
Recreation so in a
sense the other way you can protect
stakeholders is to have a
regulation you have an environmental
agency you have a competition policy you
have banking regulator you have someone
govern is going to protect the
stakeholders okay so that's the
thing now in this world where you have
the market which which is pretty
efficient but has lots of market
failures then the government corrects
the market failure it's simple
World okay we are Market fixers in a
sense um why should there be any
corporate social responsibility or a
social responsibility as an
investor um and the answer is there is
none if the government does the job you
don't have to do the
job the problem is that in practice
there is a twin failure
between so there is a market failure
plus a government failure and the carbon
Cas is is is a is a typical example the
market
failure the firms and the IND du can
emit carbon they have no incentive not
to and the government doesn't want to
have a carbon tax pay it so you have a
twin failure now we we can ask why is
that the government fails and there are
many reasons for that but you know so
then given that the market fails the
government fails what is left civil
society and that's where we have a
social responsibility
right I told you a little bit about the
repugnant Market which is only a subset
of markets which are attacked uh but
there is a broader condemnation of
markets in a sense all
markets um on the basis that the social
value of activities May differ from
Pride gain that's something that
economists worked on all the time um in
a sense we you know we know about eties
and the like and something I'm going to
to disc discuss in the I discuss in the
work with Matias the report is the IDE
which is more subtle that
market can actually frame ethical
choices so the idea is
that the
managers confronted with this twin
Market plus government failure the mates
actually could substitute and say okay
I'm going to behave
morly
okay um
no there's there's the issue about
whether they will be allowed by
shoulders to do that but same thing the
shoulders could behave morly right if
they are if they are socially
responsible they could behave
morly
um so but still the market might be
creating issues with be Mor Behavior
especially if you're are a
consequentialist which I hope you
are uh
I don't know I'm not going to impose
values on you that doesn't make sense
but consequentialist means you know you
care about consequences of of things um
so and actually this is I think the most
poent uh criticism of of
consequentialism but um so the issue
about the replacement logic is basically
okay I don't like to pollute but if I
don't pollute somebody else
will I don't like to sell weapons to a
dictator that's not
nice but what the hell if I if I if I
don't do it somebody will sell weapons
to that dictator which is correct right
um okay I don't like to bribe official
it's not very
Mor but you know if I don't bribe I
don't get the contract and someone who
bribes is going to get it so in the end
and the outcome is the same so I might
as well do it myself because I make
money out of it um the doctors who over
prescribe Ops were saying that saying I
don't like to over prescribe Ops but you
know if I if I don't if I don't do it
um some other doctor will prescribe
op the same thing happens with sick
leave so in France you go to any doctor
you want to
be you you want to seek leave for for
for two weeks doctor SS uh even so
you're in perfect health but you know
the story is that the the of course if
if the doctor doesn't do that another do
next Doctor will do it anyway um the and
there are many other examples I mean
athletes for example you know you know
many cyclists don't like to take those
drugs or many food ball player and so on
they don't like to take those tracks but
you know they say you know it's the only
way I can I can actually
compete uh and so
on so you see the the idea in all those
example there's a common idea is that
competitive pressure is going to make it
hard to actually
um uh to actually compete so the
conclusion in quotes is that you should
relax competition and therefore that has
deep implication for
271 okay um so that's something we are
going to
discuss now I already mentioned that um
that might have implication for
competition policy which are being
discussed right now the promotion of
open platform ecosystem for competitive
procurement uh for trade and so on uh
and and that might also have there also
discussion about where whether you
should
actually um either favor or just
completely allocate a market
to know firms which are not for
profit um so that that the kind of thing
so uh should we for example
make there was in France there was a
scandal this year ago but retirement B
you know they they they charge a lot of
money and and provided a very low
quality at least some of them um same
thing has happened with hospital and so
on I mean should they all be not for
profit should universities be be not for
profit actually most of them
are
uh well me they're not not for not for
profit for everyone but but you know the
um should they they be subsidized and so
on so um those are important issues
right and I mean in the last decades
nobody was talking about that that much
but now it's
resurfacing okay
just last caveat before I I go into more
technical
stuff
um I'm not going to invent anything on
morality I mean people have been
discussing this for Millennia so I'm not
going to say any any anything
interesting on morality but I just want
to to say you know we economists have a
view of
morality which tend to be in a sense no
externality or kind of you know some uh
basically you know if I stab you then
you you'll find it's not very nice it's
not quite
Mor um the avoidance of of harm okay um
and I would say this kind of conception
of M is the more stable across culture
and across time um but it's
restrictive PE many people have a much
broader view of morality so if you look
at Jonathan Height's books for example
you get lots of examples of immoral
Behavior
without victims in a sense okay so one
of his you know anything that violates a
convention or taboo or general disgust
or something you know his f one of his
favorite example if you haven't read the
book is about you know your favorite
dog uh runs out of the house and is run
over by a car the dog the dog is dead
it's your favorite dog so you are very
sad you take the dog you cook the dog
and you eat the dog
okay
now you might say there's no harm the
dog is dead right why don't you eat
it now many people view will view that
as being totally
disgusting okay and that that the kind
of thing and and many many things about
you know the more serious example are
things like U
Duty Authority loyalty to the in group
and so on which are deep value for many
people now an economists will not think
of those as being de values they might
might think of that as being an
instrument so sure loyalty may be
important but that's an instrument to
sustain cooporation for example or same
thing Authority might be an efficiency
enhancing stuff but we would not value
Authority per se right as an economist
but many people do you know and that the
kind of thing that U you know and that
raises the more the more J issue about
what what do we mean by
harm so you know and that's something
which is very important now in
universities you know if I tell you
something you don't like am I is that an
AG is that
aggressive
right so of course if it's an insult
something racist or something like of
course it is but if it's an opinion
which is not your
opinion okay is that is that aggressive
so that that's really that's really
that's really big thing and you know and
you know huge debate now on on exactly
those those those
things um so let me I mean we could talk
for hours about that but uh uh
do you have do you have
any any views on that or any
[Music]
questional how much is I'm sorry how
much how much is by Society how much is
by some inate
nature I guess it's pretty unknown I
mean
um I mean Society plays a big role of
course because of social norms and as as
we see from some of these example they
flu toate a lot across time for example
or across
culture so the social Norm are very
important
um
now it's it's hard to say of course we
learn that actually punching the other
child is not a nice thing to do
right um
now is is that innate or is that Society
right um we would probably would have
learned it by yourself anyway but you
know just but I I don't
know
I we we still are a social species and a
Cooperative species right by and
large uh
so how much do we learn through a
genetics I I don't know I mean anyone
knows
here I guess that kind of CH is how you
think of the um
intervention it is
in yeah it becomes more more
difficult but I I would guess much of it
is not in it because you see the
difference across culture and across
time that actually the
what is being considered more in one
Society may not be in another
society and you know that's why I was
saying Do no harm are more kind of
universal you know everybody think that
um that committing a crime for example
is not M right
um I mean even
pollution you know some nobody will say
it's great to pollute
even those who don't care you know they
will not claim the immoral High ground
and say it's wonderful to pollute no no
this is you
know those are relatively consensual
issues in a sense we we may disagree
about the importance but the sign is is
clear
okay yes yeah so going back to the point
on competition so is there a sense in
which having more compe can actually be
a bad thing the result is that's what we
that's what we're going to study now uh
because that's a claim is that
competition basically take the morality
out out of people right so the managers
or the shoulders they will behave better
if they were in a non-compete world but
that doesn't exclude the possibility
that if there was no competition that
you know firms would still do imortal
things just to purely seek profit that's
that that would be a possibility so we
are going to look at an environment
where people have moral preferences so
they care about their money but they
also care about other things which I
think we all are like that to some
extent we you know we to different
extents of course but you know we care
about the money but we also care about
doing the right thing with different
intensities of course
right um so what we're going to see is
that um the nature of competition
affects Market maret in many ways so
it's going to depend on the intensity of
competition so Market structure the
number of firms their sub ability which
are standard IO thing but uh it's going
to depend also whether on whether prices
are are flexible or fixed you're going
to tell me price is always flexible well
not quite because sometimes your price
is fixed so if you are a doctor in many
countries or or notary or whatever you
get some fixed amount of money right or
taxi
or you you don't have a you don't have
price
flexibility um in franchising
environment you know the your price may
be determined by the franchiser anyway
so they sometimes the prices are are
fixed but the normal thing is flexible
prices then we'll see it's important to
know whether cutting a SLE Corner lowest
cost or boost demand we are going to by
the way we are going to look at at a
situation where all stakeholders can
have more preferences they can be zero
but they can be also positive so the
stakeholders are of course you have the
managers but you also have the consumer
the investors the
workers okay so here is a picture you
will have an oligopoly with end firms
uh those firms will set a price so you
know except if the prices are
regulated and they will choose a
morality of their morality technology if
you want so they can choose something
that pollutes a lot or pollutes little
they may be nice with their workers they
may uh misrepresent their product they
may you know all kinds of issues which
create externality on people and raises
a moral issue
okay um they will sell to the
consumers and they they are input
suppliers like workers and investors
they bring labor and capital to the firm
okay now those are
stakeholders so they may care actually
about the more more action of the AAL
action which are chosen by the firms so
the consumer for example might want to
buy Fair Trade coffee or whatever might
actually want to have more production
for their
consumptions same thing the workers make
care they may want to work for I firm
they are you know by the way you know if
you look at um there's a premium
actually which is paid to workers
working say in the tobacco
industry so you know if if you work in
an industry which is considered as a
mall you have a higher wage or Casino or
whatever um same thing for investors
investors might want to engage in
socially responsible
investment okay
now the key question as we're going to
see is whether unethical Behavior raises
or lowers
demand because if social responsibility
as we're going to see go through the
cost
structure um then it's not going to have
any competition is not going to have
impact because competition is going to
operate through the demand curve not on
the cost
side
uh okay so we are going to see that's
going to be this pretty unclear at this
stage so the model is is the following
um IOP end firms so unit demand consumer
say um The Firm chooses a price firm I
choose a price
pi and and a s action
AI um so think of AI equal zero as the
most immoral action so you pollute
maximally um for
example and that
um you you sell to any
dictator uh you sell weapons to any
dictator and that creates some that has
a welfare impact think of that as been
an
externality um welfare impact W of AI
per unit of so you might think for
example that might be the pollution
damage from emitting
carbon okay it might be the the Damage
Done by the dictator with the weapons or
that kind of thing and it's increasing
AI so I will be a more more
action um and just by it's just a
normalization AI will belong to some
interval okay uh with zero being the
lower
bound and the welfare impact will be so
it will be increasing and it will be
concave
okay
um the more action may actually also
affect the unit cost so the unit cost of
production which will be
constant will be CI of
AI
now you can consider two cases one in
which this unit cost is increasing or
decreasing with a more action
so if you think about the mor action is
not using child
labor not using fossile
fuel then it's
expensive I mean people use children
they use carbon they they use call
because it's cheap otherwise they would
not be doing it right they use it
because it's cheap so in that case if
you behave more Morely your unit cost
goes up but there are also cases in
which when you behave Morely your unit
cost goes
down uh so that the case coming back to
the previous slide if you have
responsible input supplier so basically
workers or investor with social
preferences then they're willing to
actually have a lower weight or low
lower return on their capital in order
to be associated with a firm which be
small okay
so in that case if you behave more
morally your input supplier actually
offer you
discount okay because have social
preferences so in practice you you
really have both so we are going to be
agnostic at this stage about whether the
M action actually increases or decrease
the cost that depends on the
situation is that is that
clear now a key concept for what's going
to follow is the net price consumer care
about the price and they consider about
the call uh Behavior so they they also
would
have social preferences I'm going to
come to that that in a minute so
everything for them will be as
if um they care about the real price Pi
the nominal price and then they will
have some preferences over over the
action the morality of the action now
this F can be also increasing or
decreasing with the morality of the
action
so usually consumers that prefer more
more
you they are socially responsible
consumers they want Fair Trade coffee
and they want workers right to
be to be respected and so on um but
there also Cas so in that case f is
decreasing in
AI okay because that's as if the price
were going down but in the other example
I gave you of bribing a foreign official
selling weapons to a dictator
giving more opioids and so on um there
basically more fi is increasing in AI
because if you choose a more more
actions that means you are reluctant to
sell uh weapons to the dictator you are
more reant to to give opioids and that's
going to reduce
demand okay so same thing the more
action can actually increase the amount
of reduce demand but not in the same
circumstances so for Fair Trade coffee
more action is going to increase demand
for um for the example I gave you with a
replacement logic actually a moral
action is going to reduce
demand okay and that's going to be
completely crucial for what's going to
happen there will be an outside option
so the consumer choose between one of
the the firms and the outside option the
outside option will
have um an a z and a p 0 and P0 is often
zero so if you don't consume it it might
be zero but but still if your option is
actually to reopen a call
mins then P0 is small but a z is also
very small
okay
um you have Vector of uh
of net prices and those net prices are
going to determine the demand so the
demand for fari will depend the net
price of firi and the net prices of of
of the rivals there are substitute
Goods
okay so basically my
demand uh increasing with your price and
decreases with my price the standard
assumption
so you can you can think about a discret
model in which uh basically there are
there are valuations which are drawn
including for the outside option by the
way um and you choose which option you
prefer and that's one way of of
generating such a
demand
okay so we are going to call E the
elasticity of demand
for firi so it's DDI over DPI or DPI add
the
same um because P at is equal to Pi + 5
I so that's a standard of demand we make
the standard assumption that when price
prices go
up the elive demand
decreases okay it's almost the same
assumption uh as saying
the goods are strategic strategic
complement okay so it's strategic
complimentarity assumption
basically so you assume that for higher
prices the elasticity are lower which is
stand standard but it's also standard
just to assume that basically the goods
are strategic complements
okay so I make the Assumption I make a
so what's going to play a big role is
this uh I'm going to say that demand
demand when demand increases with with
the morality of the action that means
the consumer are socially
responsible when demand decreases with
the moral
action then consumer are socially
irresponsible so all the example I gave
you on the first slide were examples
with socially responsible consumer the
dictator the consumer of the
opioids yeah the the official who gets
bribed the athletes who actually wants a
drug and performance ening rug and so on
so basically so socially irr responsible
consumer F Prime is negative so
responsible consumer means that firei
Prime is positive so for example one of
the things that might happen is that you
internalize and this this going to be a
first example of social preferences you
internalize um the welfare impact of
Your Action so think about that as being
the cost of pollution for
example then you you put a weight Alpha
C on the cost of your
pollution which in all will be less than
one because you don't never fully
internalize the impact on others but uh
okay
now you have this strange case in which
I mean they look like homoeconomicus of
course in which consumers don't care
about the moral action or I should say
rather they may not observe the moral
action because also cases in which you
don't observe the moral action of the of
the firm in in that case their demand
doesn't react to a moral action because
they don't observe it and they are kind
of socially
neutral do you
have do you have
questions about the framework yes sure
um how restrictive at all is it to have
um the morality term entering through
the price like that yeah so the the the
additivity property yeah yeah so so the
idea is that in a sense there is no
income effect so you pay a price and
then you get some benefit or some cost
of uh
um uh of of the moral
action okay so if it's true if if this
this particular purchase were re big
compared to the income of the person
that might not all for
example um so think about a bribe for
example for an
official so if the official gets lots of
small bribes that's that's not an issue
uh
but if that was a huge rbe which then
that might there might be some income
effect
which you know because then you know
that means the marginal utility of
income and therefore the price in a
sense the impact of the price will not
be the
same um but it's pretty reasonable I
would say in
general um
that's a good
question okay the cost side impact of
ethical
behavior um
so we're we're going to assume it's more
General than that actually but we're
just going to assume that people have
social preferences so they
internalize then internaly wi to some
extent so uh imagine just to normalize
imagine that an in you need one unit of
capital and one unit of Labor to produce
one unit of
good um and in Imagine That investor are
willing to forgo Alpha I for investor wi
AI in their return if okay and same
thing for the workers with a different
weight so they're willing to work for
lower weight which if you are more M
okay
um then basically your modin
cost you know the the way it changes
with the action depends
on the cost of doing business so here
you might have the impact of child labor
or pollutions if you use a polluting a
cheap but polluting uh input but then on
the other side you might also have the
fact that workers and and investors are
willing to actually
um get a lower weight lower return on
their capital
okay so I already said that in a sense
uh demand impact of supply and M choice
you have irresponsible consumers now in
the paper in the appendic we have some
foundation for the immen side benefit of
cutting AAL color could
be an anxiety that's the case of those
example it could be an internet like an
opioid it could also be all kinds of
shrouded attributes also that could also
be the case um and then responsible cons
consumers right um I'm coming to the
firm subjective function because that's
so they two have social preferences so
they care about the profit the profit is
price minus unit cost times demand
that's nothing new here but the
difference with a standard firm is that
they would have social preferences so
they care about the
welfare now we can discuss that what is
welfare now in the paper we have a
general we have General consequentialist
preferences and I'm just going to give
you one example of
that okay which can be criticized but
it's much broader than that okay so I'm
going
to assume for for the sake of of the
argument that you internalize basically
the
industry pollution or the industry
amount of opioids or something like that
so you take into account the sum so
basically firm J will get demand DJ a
fraction of consum DJ will go to firm
J the welfare consequence of a firm J is
WJ of AJ and you sum of our old firms
and also the outside option
possibly of those welfare consequences
so you care say about the total
pollution in the industry or the total
amount of the opes that are sold in
Industry
okay there are the class of
consequential preferences is much
broader so you might internalize for
example just your own
wi di so your own pollution in
sense which is harder to defend right
Morely because you have to take into
account also that if you sell one more
if you get one more consumer that's
consumer would have purchased elsewhere
so Morely you will say no no just
looking at that your own pollution makes
no sense morally but that's okay for the
theory you can allow it um and there are
other other social consequences that you
want you might want to to consider the
important thing is that they are
proportional to
quantity and that's that's something
which also can be debated so if you are
consequentialist you say if I kill one
bird is if I kill 1,000 bird it's 1,000
times the cost of killing one bird for
example right if it's not an adventerous
species right if you might say if I kill
1,000 Birds the damage is 1,000 times
killing one Bird Okay uh some people
don't think in those ways actually you
know people would try to measure say the
damage uh incurred when there's an oil
spill for
example you you see that people are
willing to sometimes people are willing
to pay almost as much for one to save
one bird and to save 20 birds or 50
Birds which morly makes no sense but is
a reality right I mean we could discuss
why it's the case actually why do people
react in those ways so you can criticize
but I'm I'm just going to assume that
people are
consequentialist okay
so this is an important slide you do you
have any
question okay so social preferences so
the key assumption you know and we might
add your your comment on separability
but the key assumption is
consequentialism so all players the
suppliers the consumer the workers
investors perception of social impact of
their trade is proportional to the side
of
trade so if you pull it twice as much
it's twice as
bad okay
um the second assumption which is going
to be crucial and read that carefully
what is a flexible price so I will say
the prices are locally flexible at eum
configuration
Pat um by saying that if I change my eal
Behavior Delta AI a little
bit then I can compensate through a
price change whatever sign it has I can
compensate through a price change Delta
Pi which has to be of course minus 5
Prime of a d so I has to keep the net
price
constant so if I change the mity of of
my action I can have an upsetting effect
in the price so that overall I don't
change the attractiveness of my
offering um and therefore demand remains
constant in that
case okay and there will be two
important counter examples the first is
a case where Pi is regulated of course
because then you cannot do that the
second which is more interesting in a
sense is the case
where the more you have limited
liability so you see if if you have this
train which is burning so if your price
is equal to your marginal cost then you
you in the limited liability
region and if you say for example you
increase your the morality of Your
Action that cost you more money for
example um then you have to
you you have to raise your price
accordingly
um right and that may not actually be
neutral with respect to demand care so
there's a link here that intr a direct
link between the price and the mor
action and same thing if you are not for
profit basically you have to obey pi
equal CI of AI and again you don't have
flexible
prices okay otherwise you do okay and
finally we are going to assume constant
returns a scale of a certain kind so I'm
going to assume that the cost function I
already did that is basically I mean you
could have decreasing or increasing
return to scale but at least with
respect to the m action that has to be
basically have constant return to
scale
okay um actually there are a bunch of
cases where you can generalize so it's
this assumption is not as strong as it
looks but
uh okay those are the assumptions
um the first thing is
that if you fix prices which will be the
case when prices are regulated if you
fix prices then the ethical choices are
strategic
complements under weak conditions so
that's going to be true if consumers are
socially
irresponsible that mean their demand
decreases with a marity of the action
that's always going to be true if the
econom is symmetrical so if you're a
symmetric economy and
you
or if the social preferences are not too
not too
strong um I mean you you have a first
factor for strategic complementarity in
strategic which is that we we have
assume strategic complementarity in the
first place on prices but since prices
are like ethical choices you see that
translate into into um strategic
complimentarity for so that that that
tells you
that you
know you may easily have multiple a or
multiple social norms inal Behavior if
prices are fixed exogenously if they are
regulated which is not that's going to
make things interesting which is not
going to be the case at all if prices
are flexible actually we are going to
see that they're always uniquely
determin if prices are
flexible so if prices are fixed you can
have multiple social norms about Mo
Behavior but when they are flexible
we'll see there is only one possible
n okay now here is the first condition
with respect to AI
actually I don't know if you have seen
that you may not remember but you you
have seen that many
times if you have you know standard
oligopolist with Alpha equals zero so
there is no more preferences which is
what you study in 271
usually then you have learner index
equals to one over L of Demand right
where the learner index is Pius C pi the
price cost
margin that's true for monopolies but
that's true also for anopolis of course
the LC is not the same L of demand is
not the same for for neopies and for the
monopolies but this formula is always
true that's just the first all condition
with respect to
price now I for the moment I'm not
maximizing this with respect to price
and maximizing respect to uh the the
action um just do the computation you
know from the objective
function and what is that so the left
hand side so the the right hand side is
something which is pretty well known
product of the larner index times um it
except we are going to see the larner
index is a bit
different and this is basically when you
change AI
you have this
internalization of your own actions
impact w i of a prime minus your
marginal
cost um and this fi Prime is just a
normalization is that that transform Mo
action into
money okay that's the marginal rate of
substitution between the mo action and
money for the
consumer okay so that's the that's the
equation but an interesting thing is the
expression of of the learner index so as
I mentioned the learner index is always
price Minus cost of a price if you have
social
preferences the
cost is a modified cost which includes
your social
responsibility multiply by Alpha I which
is your internalization of social
welfare
and the social responsibility index in a
sense is as a very simple expression
which
reflects um what happens when you change
your Mor action or you change your
price here I forgot to say that W is
equal W of AI and WJ is equal to wjf a
right so and sigma
I is basically
the the displacement so for example if
I acquires one consumer the question is
where does this consumer come from it
can come from
either uh firm J or from the outside
option because this consumer was not
consuming before that's why we have J
greater than zero to include the
adoption and what matters is a
difference in terms of welfare
consequences between I and J and sum of
Sigma is equal to
one okay so it's a
weighted you look at you ask it's it's
really about the replacement effect you
look at if I acquire one more
consumer I am I going to increase
pollution or reduce pollution well that
depends where where I get this uh
consumer from right so if I I get it
from someone who was produ producing
using coal that's a good thing even if I
use
gas but if I get this consumer from
someone who has actually using
Renewables that's a bad thing if I'm
using gas okay so so basically you look
at the
impact on welfare but for that you have
to
know you know whom are you you stealing
consumers
from
okay okay so so that's why in your
course you also take into account your
social responsibility which means that
if you are highly
polluting actually your social
responsibility is actually to
leave the activity to other firms if you
are highly ethical your social
responsibility is to take Market to
increase your market share okay which
which kind of makes sense
right now if you have a symmetric
eum okay if you have a symmetric eum
then wi is equal top WJ let's assume
that the market is covered so the
outside option is not nobody chooses the
outside option everybody needs a
doctor um and basically then W is equal
to WJ and then
your social responsibility is zero
because you're all the
same um in that case the larner index is
a standard learner index if you have a
symmetric equum okay but the basic point
is that under pretty weak
assumption um then you get multiple for
given prices you get often multiple
ethical Norms in AUM that's easy to get
because of those strategy complement
ities okay whereas when you look at
flexible prices you get a very different
picture um which is that if you have
flexible
prices your moral behavior is never
going to depend on the demand
curve so it's going to be the same for a
monopolist or for an
oligopolist it's the same for an
oligopolist an oropo and a cartel
uh the demand care whether they're
highly substable or not doesn't matter
so if prices are
flexible
actually then competitive pressure
doesn't matter which is important
because it tells you just go ahead with
competition policy those are two s
things more Behavior will depend on how
more the stakeholders are but will not
depend on demand curve so will not
depend on the intensity of
competition okay so actually in that
case I
mean
so so put
differently if you have a price
optimization you know that you're going
to get
this price will be equal to the index
perhaps Modified by the social
responsibility but it's always the case
that if you if you have price
competition the learner index is equal
to the inverse vity of demand so that
will be equal to one and basically this
entity will be equal to to one as well
okay and basically your M Behavior
indexed by a dagger will be given by C
equation which means that it's
completely independent of the demand
curve
okay
so whenever prices are
flexible the intensity of competition is
completely
irrelevant and then therefore there is
no
point not doing antitrust because you
want to increase morality because you're
not going to increase morality
anyway it's going to remain
constant okay what is intuition
let me give you two two intuition for
whatever they are
worth the
first is to understand there are two
offsetting
effects
so take a particular case so we're going
to take a par case which is a worry of
many people uh the fact the replacement
effect so you know the idea that I might
want to bribe a an official because
otherwise I will Lo the market so
irresponsible
consumers so with irresponsible consumer
if I cut ethical corner so if I reduce
my
morality I gain market share because
that's exactly what the corrupt official
the dictator or the up consumer
wants okay so if I behave less mly I
again market
share
okay now
if you change theity of demand so you
increase theity of Demand by having more
competition then that means
that um I will get more market share for
you know I will get a bigger increase in
market share if I behave more less
morly okay so that seems to confirm the
conventional wisdom that actually with
ir responsible consumer markets will
lead to immoral Behavior because then
you by by cutting AAL corner you
actually gain a lot of market share but
the same time if you
have more competition you also have
lower
markups right and if you have lower
markups that means you gain Less in
terms of money whenever you acquire
market
share and that makes you know you have a
trade-off between behaving morly and
making money
okay but when you behave immorally you
make less money per unit on more units
in a sense and and those two effects
actually perfectly offset that that of
course I'm not showing you I'm just
showing you there are two of two effects
which go in the opposite directions
right I mean if everybody made zero at
the margin nobody will have incentive to
behave immorally right
if you if you if you don't make any
money from
misbehaving then you'll behave Mor if
you have any social preferences even
weak
ones right and competition is going to
reduce the stake in a sense so it's
going to push toward more Mor Behavior
so you have two effects and and they
offet the other way to see is some kind
of cost
minimization so
and that explain why they perfectly
offset in a sense so when you look at
your cost as a function of AI is C AI
but
then you you also have to add fire of AI
because fire of AI is basically the
perceived price increase due to
AI uh for the consumer so you have if
you want to keep your demon concern you
have to reduce your price by fire of
AI okay
and then there is your social
responsibility which I Rew wrote here so
reing my
J is the fraction of consumers that you
steal from firm J whenever you acquire
new
consumers um and then I rewrote slightly
differently the objective function so I
have to take into account the difference
between uh the welfare that I offer and
the welfare which is offered by my
competitors okay and when you look at
this you know you given that some of
Sigma is equal to one you
can you can rewrite it this way in a
part which as a part which depends on on
on my own
action and another part which depends on
on the prices the net prices but also on
the action of the rivals including the
outside option and it's completely
separable so that means that okay that I
cannot do anything
about um you know when I for given net
prices I can just minimize cost and that
gives me the formula which is within the
previous page okay
uh so um
that's
proof now how how robust is this
conclusion of
irrelevance uh it's not fully robust but
it's actually pretty
robust uh more than we would have
thought
so for example the irrelevance of again
the irrelevance is that the intensity of
competition has no impact on the choice
of moral morality if prices are
flexible um you can use Coro in that
case you don't choose a price you choose
a
quantity but that's still the case that
works you can use a search model it also
works um if you have imperfect consumer
information that works um if you
have um different internalization I give
you a specific internalization you can
generalize to nonlinear pricing so I've
assume you need demands but you could
multi-unit demands that will also work
and so on as non-constant return to
scale is important for the result but
you know you can relax it somewhat so
for
example if
uh if A6 impact only the demand side but
not the cost side doesn't matter you
could have decreasing or increasing
return to scale and so on so it's pretty
robust um
where things are
different and I probably I would stop
here because you
is if you
have if you if you don't have flexible
prices then see it's a different ball
game so I actually it suggest lots of
ampirical
tests um they actually a couple of
experiments which have been run which
fit relatively well with this Theory but
you know it's only two experiments we
need more experiments and we need also
someone pay Cod work in general to to
check all those things but
um
so what we do is okay let's assume first
you have regulated
price okay if you have a regulated price
you have no reduced markup effects of
intense
competition okay competition reduces the
markup and therefore reduces the stakes
in Behaving IM
morly whereas if you have fixed prices
that's not going to happen competition
is not going to reduce the
price um in that case the critiques of
markets are right which is if you have
irresponsible
consumers then more competition is going
to reduce more Behavior that's
correct so if you make the Assumption to
a unique equum you can show that
actually more Behavior decreases with
more competition so there's a grain of
Truth in the criticism it's not like
it's completely wrong there's a grain of
truth but you have to qualify it
substantially not only because of the
irrelevance result but even when the
prices are fixed then um you also get
the reverse conclusion when you have
responsible
consumer it's pretty clear what happens
is that if you have responsible consumer
so we all want Fair Trade
coffee then actually more competition is
going to
force um the firms actually to buy Fair
Trade coffee you know because they want
to please a customer so it's going to be
exactly the reverse so if you have
responsible consumers then competition
is good for marity so if you had those
those things which is the relevance
result plus this slide
you see that first it's not the case
that everything goes um you have
prediction but there are context
specific is the price flexible or not
are the consumers irresponsible or
responsible those are not the same
applications and you get a picture which
you say okay we we we cannot conclude
and you're just modifying antitrust and
all those things just on the basis of
morality it doesn't seem like the right
thing to do now if the if the policy
makers use a final analysis maybe that's
that's the right thing to do but you
cannot just say we don't want markets
right that's not that's not the right
stance now last thing we do in the paper
I think is to look at what happens when
you
introduce either heterogenity in in
Social
preferences okay
imagine one of the competitors is Mo
terasa right um what happens well she
might ear a limited liability
constrain right because you know at some
point she will run out of cash or if you
have for profit and you know that then
it it it becomes more interesting and
there might be an argument in some
Industries actually to protect the not
for profit from the competition of for
profit because what we show is that when
you have very intense competition you
tend to have
mimicking the behavior or mimic between
for-profit and not for-profit the
distinction
disappears basically the the for-profit
to compete with the not for-profit have
to choose prices close to marginal cost
but the the not for profit have to
behave unethically to keep consumers if
consumers are
irresponsible and you see that you know
you lose a little bit the the
distinction between not for profit and
and for profit in that case and that
raises the issue about whether you want
to reserve the hospital Market or the
education Market to not where where
moral issues can be very important to uh
to not for-profit and we don't solve
this issue but it's actually a very
interesting issue to study