thank you very much for having me it's
uh great to be here with you uh today
just out of curiosity how many of you
are interested in the business
applications of
AI and how many of you are interested in
more technical aspects of
AI perfect so now I know how to tune my
uh
presentations so um I want to talk to
you about a new paradigm in AI that I
call it perspective with where Ai and I
want to tell you how I came up with that
with my team I spent a lot of my career
especially during my Graduate Studies to
build these next Generation ubiquitous
Computing applications you know from
coffee machines that could sense the
stress of the colleagues in an office
and adjusted the espresso intensity to
about 10 years ago to a sensory Paradigm
that generated a comic strip about
people's daily life this is way before
uh the Advent of the language models
figuring out tabletops augmented reality
and many applications like that but what
I became interested in was that well the
Paradigm in which you build these
applications are very mechanical there
is no design pattern there's no process
everyone came up with a new way of
Designing these and they cannot scale at
the same time we were watching in our
team that things were moving from human
computer interaction which is about the
interaction of a person versus a cold
silicon to AI systems that can really go
into the background and enabling us to
communicate with each other more
effectively so that really became the
focus area of our research group and
some of the things that we spawn off
later on as technology so what I want to
talk to you about today is that how AI
is helping us to move Beyond
personalization I'm sure you all heard
about this term putting a lot of data in
one location process it and push things
to people and maybe receive some
analytics and data back into a model
that a user can cocreate with the
machine and really develop things
collectively in a in a symbiogenetic way
and also information can have
perspectives one thing that is important
to me when I'm at home as a father is
different than when I'm at school
teaching so how can you use AI to
understand those
perspectives so the goal of our group
instead of building applications is to
really enable and Empower others to have
access to easy to ous intuitive tools to
bring their creativity and build things
themselves not everyone can be Patty ma
it's very difficult because you really
need to have a very cross-disciplinary
view on things but what if we get to a
point that we provide tools similar to
what we did in the early internet days
that first you had to code your HTML
pages and you had to be an engineer to a
model that you can now WordPress say oh
I want a wedding website and a birthday
website and put everything together
using two-dimensional content what if we
can do that with AI for everyone that's
what I want to talk to you about
today while we were working with our
group we were basically realizing things
were changing and things were not
necessarily changing on the interface
layer but things were changing when it
comes to our relationship with data my
dad in the 70s used to work for a
company called Control Data Corporation
how many of you heard about that company
it was a Mainframe company it's very
interesting that the term Control Data
is becoming more and more relevant these
days we are seeing that data is becoming
more decentralized coming from Cobalt
systems CRM systems file systems object
systems and our literacy is growing so
we want more transparency around data we
want to understand when we feed data
into algorithmics what happens to them
we want to teach our kids about the
privacy of their data that when they
post something on Tik Tok or Instagram
what happens to it how do models work
and we are also seeing the importance of
audit it many of us are interested in
generative AI using Foundation models
many of the foundation models that we
use these days are black boxes there's
no Providence there's no audit Trail and
naturally there is a lot of garbage in
garbage out you have used Reddit it's
great we can continue to go from
billions of parameters to trillion
parameters but that's not going to solve
the problem how do we use AI as a
decision support system rather than a
decision Mak taking system really
putting a person in the middle so we can
co-create with
AI I want to share some examples with
you before I go through some of the
technicalities the goal of our team in
perspective of R AI is allowing people
to wear each other lenses and view the
world through their view we have used it
in space so when you send astronauts to
uh on on the um on the inter
International Space Station they have
different cultural views and how they
behave what if they can really see that
space to each other's point of view um
you may look at a menu at a restaurant
and you want to see what your
nutritional coach would eat when you
look at that menu how do you develop
these decentralized perspective aware
systems our very first project tried to
do that with an interface that you're
very familiar with map-based interfaces
so imagine that instead of you following
cartisian coordinates on a Google map
you can go to a city and say I want to
wear a lens of a celebrity or a friend
and I want to walk the streets of Paris
through their point of view where they
went what they ate what music they
listened to so this is the
decentralization of knowledge while you
really have benefit from the
centralization of computing power
allowing you to generate these types of
experiences
so a lot of our work in our team is to
work on these multimodal AI systems that
you can process images cat files text of
course turn them into vectors and turn
them into graphs so the core uh research
Focus we have is on this notion of
Reason ready AI using graphs we
published papers around that but now we
are demonstrating that these reason
Readiness is very important in the
future of AI In classical computer
science departments people who worked on
neural networks really didn't like the
people who were working on ontologies
and semantics the great thing about the
media lab is that we are very
cross-disciplinary we're bringing all of
that together and simplifying it for
people to use so we introduced these
Concepts called Chronicles Chronicle is
a graph that represents your behavior
and as you go about your daily life it
gets better and better I highlight these
are not data these are causalities and
relationships on behavioral patterns so
everyone will use these ontologies we
generate these graphs about them the
colar codes represent different
attributes of social ontologies for
example how do I behave as a professor
in school how do I behave as a father at
home what do I do when I play tennis all
of those will be recorded in these
graphs using structures that are
queriable and identifiable so that has
been a lot focus in our research group
now let me show you some
examples we created a language with our
team called I generate you have used
Twitter now X I'm assuming it has a
syntax you have handles and hashtags we
now know how to use it so we have
created a syntax called I generate I
generate a fine-tune model from a base
model that I have and I want to map it
or put it as a lens on a different type
of an information to filter in
information accordingly so let me give
you an an example I want to generate an
experience of going to Paris in Winter I
put it in a parenthesis instead of a
hashtag I will get the available
Chronicles that I have access to these
are people that I know people who have
been to Paris through my trusted Social
Network I generated a graph I do scene
generation and when I go to that City
instead of relying on Central Iz
recommendation systems like Google
Places and Trip Advisor I can now walk
the streets of Paris through the lands
of my friend now what is the
technicality behind it we partner with a
very large credit card company that
allow people to share their
transactional information with each
other on the St level and on the
category level really building a
peer-to-peer Learning Network for
tourism and then we applied our
technology to demonstrate what these
navigational tools for cities can look
like we then applied this to the work
environment uh I'm not a big fan of uh
work from home sorry to say that I don't
I know there are lots of people who
disagree with me but sometimes you don't
have a choice so with our team we
decided to create a digital twin of our
startup the video you see on the left is
our office and the video that you see on
the right hand side is the digital twin
version of that that we have done with
gausson splatting and liar so we now
have techniques that you can map a space
very quickly is a tool that we created
in our group called open Dome I don't
want to call it a metaverse it's a dome
of pixels connected to open data and
then we retrieved information about
colleagues who wanted to share that
payroll tax project management sales you
know uh tickets for it and map that into
the office so now when someone comes
into the office whether they use a
headset or they use a web interface
using webgl they can just say I want to
look at the office through the lens of
maybe the CEO today what does the CEO
think about today what are the
priorities so now you can navigate the
space and retrieve information in a
decentralized way through project
management systems file systems tax
systems to really have a different
perspective in the office and now I can
switch my lens from this CEO to let's
say the ESG specialist how are we doing
in terms of energy consumption we just
partnered with a major company that they
are now using this for onboarding their
new Talent their interns their co-ops so
when you start you get a much better
onboarding and understanding of your
colleagues and you're measuring as part
of a research paper how quickly we can
activate that
onboarding um a number of my students
Master students are apply this to
nutrition they are very interested in
the intersection of spatial Computing
and uh gen so this is a case in which
you retrieve an information from online
they are all athletes they are working
with a US Triathlon gold medalist who's
an expert in recovery and as you viewing
that article online you can activate
friends and then ask them what do you
think about this particular subject in
this case recovery and very quick l
through information retrieval and using
some of the protocols that that we
created you gain their perspective about
that subject so instead of AI making the
decision for me I am now Consulting with
people through their available knowledge
graphs to me which is privacy preserved
and I can develop a less biased opinion
and if it's a we actually want an award
from Stanford Stanford democracy
challenge award by applying this to us
politics we actually demonstrated that
the two ends of the spectrum can
understand each other more
effectively now everything that I have
shown you up until now are what my
colleagues say at the media lab screen
ai ai that generates pixel on a
two-dimensional screen this can also go
beyond that screen so I'll give you an
example this was my co project I had a
lot of extra time that's my younger
daughter Sierra which is interacting
with a robot this robot is relatively
old but it's a powerful robot so you
could inject these Chronicles into the
robot allowing the kid to interact with
the robot through some type of a value
system that you incorporate in those
Chronicles and it's multimodal so she
was showing a a a a painting uh talking
about it and using the multimodal
systems that I talked about the
chronicle got updated and a paper that
we wrote about this is that in some
cases the kid is more comfortable
sharing and conversing with the robot
than their parents so we are basically
measuring what are those context
elements in which a robot in this case
will be more
useful one of the big grants that we
recently secured is using this to
demonstrate the future of work the graph
on the right hand side is very familiar
to all of you in an organization project
comes in all right based on budget
availability calendar let's bring people
together and let's develop that uh that
project and deliver it what we are
proving in this model is can actually
our Chronicles work with each other in
an organization to develop the first
part of that task so we can all go to
work but instead of doing kind of basic
incremental work we now incorporate that
knowledge in our Chronicles so this is
where auditability contracts which data
is available to whom that's a lot of our
work at the human dynamics group becomes
very important because AI in this is not
replacing our job is basically allowing
us to go about our daily life and learn
and meet with people but our Chronicle
gets better and better and better and we
are demonstrating that things let's say
in a creative agency or in a project
that requires some templatized
now I want to spend a bit of on that and
I want to talk about our ecosystem
approach at the media lab which is very
very
unique in our group we separate the
channel or the interface from the
infrastructure and the algorithmics the
interface can be a conversational
interface could be a web page could be a
prompt-based interface all the way to
what we call synthetic characters these
synthetic characters are becoming more
and more advanced if you're from Germany
this is a very famous uh reporter from
De he came to our lab we mapped his face
we used all of the things that he has
done in Germany into a Knowledge Graph
FedEd into uh the synthetic character
and part of a documentary that you can
watch it's called My Avatar and me I
could basically converse with the
synthetic character instead of uh the
reporter now there are lots of these
things available many of them to be
honest are gimmicks like why would I
want to use this so one of our key focus
is that what is the business application
of these things could it be a professor
could it be someone that people really
want to talk to but they don't have
access imagine you go on the media lab
website even now you see the pictures of
luminaries doing great work what if
instead of a JPEG pixel and a bio you
can actually talk to that professor and
prompt information with control and
governance that could be the future of
digital channels think about a800 number
oh you know wait 10 minutes and someone
picks up activate a character and talk
to them that character already knows a
lot about you through multimodal uh
interfaces so we are building this in
our lab uh we are working this is
another grant that we got to build this
capture systems in our uh in our lab you
can walk into it so we are building
these Pathways you walk into this within
10 minutes we create your digital
version depending on what you want to do
what your company want to do or
individually you can feed your graphs
into your synthetic characters and then
you can um create graphs so I don't want
to take you through a lot of details but
you can use patents you can use
interviews so um this is an example of
someone who came to our lab gave me
access to some of her family uh albums
and things so that we could create her
synthetic characters and then um you
know any information can be fed into
these systems to create these knowledge
graphs we do embeddings and
vectorization from them and there are
papers on this that are published that I
can share with you but to keep you on
time um I'm going to share some examples
with
you there were some very good questions
that were asked in the previous panel
well where is the bias how do I trust
this right how do I know that what this
character is telling me is actually
accurate so this is actually a platform
that we built that you can now ask a
prompt essentially ask a question from
an individual I hope I have audio if not
we'll see what
happens um you prompt and you can
activate different characters and ask
them the same question to see what they
talk about uh my audio is not connected
but this the person is actually
talking based on the prompt the relevant
nodes of the graphs are being captured
that actually our core IP and the
algorithmics that our team uh created
but look at that reliability dashboard
that is basically giving you the score
that although I'm giving you a response
my confidence level on this answer is
low it's up to you if you want to
believe it or not but that's basically
the these are all AI techniques that
give you confidence lift yield those are
techniques that we can use to see do I
have Providence is it open is it being
validated how many people used it so and
then we are mapping these based on
fine-tune expressions of an individual
so in this particular case you could not
hear the audio on areas of research
interest that I have when that comes up
my face becomes happier or sad so think
about where the future of digital
channels uh can go this is a famous
reporter that I'm working on so she's
very big in female empowerment we
created a whole set of uh uh um social
graphs from her and people can talk to
her about different elements of the
business and instead of going and
reading a lot of blogs you now have a
much better more intuitive interactions
uh with her and the interesting thing
about this which surprised us this is my
PhD student originally from Germany a
fantastic student he actually was the
VFX director of Harry
Potter we grafted all of his papers but
for some reason the AI picked you could
not hear the audio the AI picked his
German accent so the synthetic voice
that is coming out actually has a German
accent we did not incorporate that as a
magic number or a magic attribute the AI
picked it so now you need to create more
dashboards for people not to block
things people say biases are bad in AI
biases are actually good we have a case
with the Mount Sinai Hospital in Toronto
that a doctor can consult three other
doctors about a medical dosier we need
their biases there we just need to tell
them why this individual thinks like
that so those are some of the techniques
that we are building in our tool we have
a there is a documentary you can watch
on HBO uh I did it with deac Chopra and
a famous uh movie director an Shin we
mapped a lot of their data we created an
avatar but then the lady brought her
kids in front of the mom's
Avatar and you know what it didn't work
out because the technology was amazing
you could impress people and say this is
a gimmicky cool things but the kids
hated it the kids really didn't like it
and that was an aha moment for our team
because this was not a technology
problem we needed to study empathy we
need to really turn this into
storytelling machines rather than into
Interventional systems and then we are
doing a paper that we are looking at all
the state-of-the-art models and they
perform terribly in terms of identifying
emotion and empathy and others on these
research papers so that's basically
driving our focus and I'm now working
with others like religion experts uh
Divinity experts to get their knowledge
and applying it into our model fine tune
accordingly so hopefully some of those
things go away I don't have a lot of
time to talk about these but I want to
talk a little bit about the media lab
before um I
wrap the unique thing about the media
lab is that you can be all of these
things in one person like you can really
look at it through the business angle
core research angle scale angle and one
thing that we really believe in is that
we need to run this as an ecology and an
ecosystem we need to bring students from
design and systems and mechanical
engineering and fashion all
collaborating uh with each other so I
will wrap by saying this this is the
Paradigm that many of us follow in in
our group if you are bringing AI into a
company you can follow these five AI is
no longer going to be a business a an IT
strategy it's going to be a horizontal
enabler in your organization that even
the boards of directors should be
involved you really need to double down
on the AI literacy imperative from from
K12 all the way to the boards of
directors and tune so when my colleagues
talked about the expro educational
program that is a great step but you
need a lot of that and tune it and
personalize it for different people the
data
imperative the mindset of the industry
right now is a mindset of a graduate
student when it comes to data Professor
give me the data and I'll do my work
that thing does not exist in the
industry you should not give up your
data you should really double down on
the portability privacy audit mechanics
of moving the data around and the last
thing I say that Patty mentioned design
design design in the old days you could
basically bring focus groups and design
low Fidelity and High Fidelity and
launch a channel you're talking about a
time that you're throwing terabytes of
data and channels especially if you're a
regulated industry or emission critical
industry say oh show something useful
you really need to change your uh design
patterns so with that uh I want to wrap
I know I'm time I would love to stay in
touch with you I know some of you may be
visiting the lab it's a very special
place uh I'm happy to staying in touch
and uh thank you for joining thank you
very much