go ahead and uh turn turn to your
neighbor and start. Uh one thing you
could do is pull out the main reading
that we did about situated learning
because we'll do kind of a close read of
that today. So, um, pull that up on
something and then, um, in the minutes
that we have, we usually start 105, but
in the minutes that we have, uh, turn to
your, uh, turn to your neighbor and
start thinking about why why babies
would give, uh, cognitive load theorist
conions.
All right. as a just just as one level
setting thing in case you haven't hung
out with babies in a while. Like in
their first few years of life, how would
you characterize the amount and rate of
learning that babies do? Insane. Insane.
It is bonkers how much babies learn. I
mean, a very strong feeling I had when I
was first father was like like I I do
not improve at all in a week or in a
month or really most years. I'm really
like not that much better than I was the
beginning of the year. And you're just
watching these infants who are totally
transformed because they are learning
things at an amazing rate that you can
see daily, weekly, monthly, you know,
incredibly accelerated learning. Um so
let's use we'll just use that to level
set. Um let's let's let's take it as a
given that babies learn an amazing
amount in their early years. Um why now
keep talking why would that prove to be
such why would that give cognitive load
theorist such a
conipion and and you can think about um
how it connects to some of the stuff
that you've been reading about situated
load theory keep talking
all right good what are some what are
some observations that people made
what are what are baby babies are babies
are significant so what are what are
what are some of the observations that
that you
made. What were you guys talking about
in the
back? What was your group talking about,
Gloria? Um, I was saying that if like
cognitive load theory was true, then
that would say that babies probably
can't learn like anything because
everything is extraneous knowledge to
them and they don't have any long-term
memory. They haven't formed any skills
yet. All right. Yep. So, they're so
they're not drawing in they don't have a
lot of long-term memory to draw on.
They, you know, they are like the
canonical us looking at Sanskrit letters
where like everything is its own sort of
discrete part like um so you would think
they're working memory. I mean, you
know, this video I think is sort of
helpful for that. Like everything on
this screen is brand new to them.
There's nothing that they've ever seen
before and it's filled like there's a
slide and a dad and that other thing
back there and all this stuff on the
ground and people are talking and the
sun is out and all these things are
happening at once. Good. What else did
people talk about?
Um it's also like the the speed with
which they learn doesn't really connect
with like the bottleneck theory and like
um the theory of like it takes a while
for you to like compile all of this
information but it almost seems like a
baby sees it one time and is like able
to retain it. Yeah. babies seem to do
exactly the thing that Sweller said um
people should not be able to do, which
is to be um I mean, would you gen like
this baby learning stuff, would you
generally characterize their experience
as sort of open-ended problem solving or
like being carefully walked through a
series of worked
examples? How would you describe it?
Open. Yeah, this I mean like I'm just
like going on the slide and going down,
you know? It's not like dad's like, you
know, I mean, I think I think you'd find
more structure and stuff like that, but
there's a lot of just like, wow, I'm a
baby. I'm out there. I'm doing my thing.
Um, you know, and and the worked example
effect and the expert reversal effect
suggests that that should not be very
effective. You know, the most effective
way to teach babies should be, you know,
through like careful, you know,
devolving scaffolding of language and
things like that. And that's not what we
do. We just like throw babies in with
people all the time. Um and they uh and
they learn language, they learn
movement, they learn a few other things
at sort of an extraordinary rate. Um so
for how do how does how does what
connections do you see between this set
of ideas and situated
learning? There's a lot of like trial
and error in it. Like we were talking
about like hey when they they see a
block they want to go get they start to
figure out the different ways that they
can go get that block. Like but through
trial and error trying to stand up,
trying to crawl, trying to drag
themselves. Yeah. all that kind of
stuff. Kadus, come on in. Sit with me.
No, no, delighted to have you. Um, yeah.
Um, yeah. I mean, this this certainly
looks a lot more like situated learning
than it does look like a sort of
carefully sculpted classroom. Um, and
uh, so for situated learning people, and
you know, we'll we'll I think we'll see
this more in some stuff that we read.
Um, the experience of babies seems like
something that's pretty important to
draw from. Um, how would you how would
you how would you
characterize like the feelings that
babies have as they learn language? Like
are they happy? Are they sad? Are they
angry? Are they frustrated? Are they
joyful? Are they playful? Like what kind
of feelings do babies seem to have as
they're learning words?
What were you going to say, Jared? I was
going to say like they seem kind of
fearless and like there there's no like
social pressure to like try and
pronounce this word correctly. They'll
just say the word be like, "Oh, good
job. make noises come out of our mouths
whenever. Yeah. Do you want to grab
another chair? There's no It doesn't
seem like there's there's a lot of fear
behind trying to practice what they're
learning. Uhhuh. Um but I think like in
addition to that, there can be like a
lot of frustration as well. The
consequences of like not knowing how to
say a specific thing. Yeah. Or or you
watch babies when they're you know I
mean they cry when they can't articulate
the thing that they want to be able to
say or Yeah. And in addition to
frustration, I think there's a bit of
like happiness when they actually
achieve what they're trying to create
and then they feel understood. I think
there's some some sort of some sort of
pride in that. What were you going to
say, Courtney? Um, same kind. I wonder
my my daughter, we used to uh we used to
just my I guess it was my younger one,
we used to just list vegetables and list
things you get at the supermarket and
she thought that was the funniest thing
ever. you you would just be like
pears in the back of the car just like
saying stuff and she's giggling the
whole time. Um you know I I mean if you
watch a video like this like this is
clearly a delightful um you know there's
there's not a lot that Sweller and
colleagues have to say about like being
delighted. Um you know I I I think if
you were to if you were to situate like
the kind of like moral ethic of work
around learning in cognitive load
theory, it's very like learning is hard.
we persevere through a hard thing. Um,
and we control the hardness of it so
that we can scaffold it for people. Um,
and for situated learning people, these
these aren't really I wouldn't even
these aren't like arguments. And
sometimes they're explicit arguments.
Sometimes they're just tones that you
find in the way people talk about these
things. They'd be like, "Oh, you know,
learning is great. Learning is the thing
that we do and get better at stuff. It's
like nice and natural and things like
that." Um, can anybody think of a thing
that you've learned in which you like
got better at the thing and it was just
like playful, enjoyable, natural to get
better at it? Anybody can shout out one
or two things that was like that for
you?
When I first learned how to use like a
power drill. Awesome. Great. Learning
how to use power drill like very
satisfying immediate feedback things
like that. Yeah. Other things that
people really enjoyed learning? Um, I
think similarly like like tactical
things like learning how to do pottery.
Oh, great. Yep. Pottery seems like a
good one. Learning how to swim. Learning
how to swim was all right. We're saying
a lot of physical things. Good. Video
games. Video video games. Video games
are a there is a whole science. Um
there's a there we won't read it.
There's a guy named James G um who wrote
a great book about learning in video
games. It's a little bit like Toqueville
coming to America if that's a reference
that you know. Um, but Toqueville was
this European who came to America. Um,
and he saw America incredibly intimately
in a way that sort of only an outsider
could by in part by becoming an insider.
Um, James G is an old guy who was like,
"Why do my kids like video games so
much?" And he starts playing them a
bunch. He's like, "These are amazing
learning experiences." Um, think like
think about someone learning a really
hard game like Civilization 6 or
Stellaris or put in whatever game you've
been playing recently that just has like
incredibly complicated systems in them.
There aren't a lot of people who are
like, you know,
Minecraft like redstone building in
Minecraft, stuff like that. There aren't
people who are like, "God, it was such a
drag that I had to take all those
classes on redstone to be able to, you
know, um these games have have systems
built within them. They're sort of canot
almost all them canonically situated
kinds of things. Um where you're just
immersed in the environment, you're
encouraged to play. There are some peer
structures around to help you learn and
stuff like that. But it's extremely
pleasant. um you know even even when um
you know people might find it
frustrating or things like that. I think
a lot of in families cooking is
something that learning how to cook
which has both tactile and kind of
scientific ma you know measurement
mathematical language components um that
people often find quite pleasurable. Uh
and this connects a lot to like the
material I'm learning in CMS 587 about
assessments. We're learning like the
different theories of intelligence and
how um if you believe that your
intelligence isn't fixed and like it can
expand then you can learn a lot more.
And that's kind of like young children
or babies because they're not really
afraid of failure and like they just
like they're very resilient. So yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. They don't they don't care
what's going on. They're just trying to
figure things out. Um how many of you
have have had uh experiences that you're
really happy with where learning was
hard where you like persevered through
sort of a challenging set of learning
experiences and got better at it and you
were like, "Yeah, that's great. I'm
super glad I did that." What what things
come to mind for that for you? I think
for me learning to code was a bit like
that. I think differently from some
people in the room like I didn't learn
to code in middle school. I learned it
in university. So there were like
degrees associated with it and things
like that. Yeah. Yeah. You watched a
bunch of lectures and did pet sets and
turn them in and but I remember like the
first very complex pet that I completed
and like my program worked perfectly and
I was like it's amazing feeling. It felt
it felt very satisfying even though some
of the learning experience of doing
that. Yeah. Yeah. So that that kind of
that you know I think there's sort of a
moral story that emerges around a lot of
instructionist learning which is like it
was hard we put our nose to the
grindstoneone we sacrificed but after
that sacrifice we had this great feeling
of relief and I think most of us have
some kind of learning experience that
goes like that and then situated
learning people have more of this story
of like we just naturally found
ourselves in this space surrounded by
opportunities to learn and it was
playful and it felt easy and natural and
that's what we're trying to sort of
restore So actually the cognitive load
theorists have to me what I think is
sort of a funny way of dealing with
this. Um there was just a guy who
proposed that there's two categories of
things that are learned called
biologically primary and biologically
secondary kinds of things. Um and uh
we're evolutionarily wired to naturally
learn biologically primary kinds of
things and everything else is
biologically secondary and is much
harder. So that you're sort of naturally
wired to learn how to walk, how to eat,
some basic parts of socializing,
recognizing faces. Language ends up
being a real problem for this because
it's like are you biologically primed to
learn your first language to learn
multiple languages? Why would you be
biologic? Like why was it easy for me to
learn English when I was young, but not
Spanish was really hard when I was
older? Like my brain changed? Did
evolution? Like anyway, um I actually
find this theory totally unsatisfying.
Um do do you are familiar with the idea
of epicycles? Um like before the
capernican revolution uh we uh everybody
thought orbits were circles not you know
uh ovals or or whatever it is that
they're what is it? What's the shape of
them? Ellipses. Um and so there was a
period of time when they realized like
oh circle measurements don't work. And
so they added circles to the circles. Um
there they like believed that there had
to be sort of perfect circles making the
orbits. And so they believed that
somehow there were like orbits within
the orbits. um you know and then I think
it was capergus who came around was like
actually it's just like this and that
works a lot better but to me sort of
biologically primary and biologically
secondary thing sort of operate that
like that seems a little bit like an
epicycle to me like we haven't quite
figured out um what's going on there but
that is how um canonically the the
cognitive load theory people just wave
all this away and say ah but babies
whatever biologically primary we don't
have to worry about them um everything
after you're four years old or something
like that is uh cognitive load theory
works um But for the situated learning
people, you know, not not exactly, but
in a lot of ways, they're trying to sort
of recapture the learning experiences
that we have when we're very young. Um,
where where learning is natural,
playful, not always happy, but often
sort of socially satisfying. Um, and
extremely effective. I mean, what babies
learn in a short period of time is just
bonkers. Um, it's one of the most fun
things about being a parent or an auntie
or a uncle or all the other ways you get
to spend a lot of time with kids. Okay.
Um, let's just get oriented
here. So, again, we're in foundations.
Um, we're trying to get a hand of these
two sort of contemporary learning
theories. Cognitive load theory,
situated learning. Um, that these two
ideas about how people learn are
ancient. Um, that you can find people
like Plutarch for the mind does not
require filling like a bottle, but
rather like wood. It only requires
kindling to create in it an impulse to
think independently and an ardent desire
for truth. That's the sort of like this
is Plutarch making a case for situated
learning and against cognitive load
theory, though he wouldn't have known
those terms because they didn't show up
for another 2,000 years. Um, but you can
hear the resonance of the debate in his
mind. Here's a little chunk from a 2017
New Yorker article. For nearly a
century, public education in America has
been influenced by two opposing
pedagogical approaches. Traditionalism
and progressivism. The thing that you
got to catch is that there are these two
ideas that have like each of them has
8,000 different names. But anytime you
sort of notice this dichconomy, broadly
speaking, in the traditional approach to
education, a teacher imparts knowledge
to students through direct instruction
and embodies a disciplinary culture in
which obedience is both prized and
rewarded. That's a that's a nice both
like so like she frames it here's a
pedagogical piece. Knowledge is imparted
through direct instruction and embodies
a disciplinary culture in which
obedience is prized and rewarded. like
obedience was not prized and rewarded
amongst the baby on the playground. What
was rewarded was screwing around. Um the
purpose of the classroom is to equip all
students to meet measurable academic
standards. At progressive institutions,
a teacher develops a curriculum but
urges students to treat it as a staging
ground for their own intellectual
discoveries, often through hands-on
activity and group work. Allowances are
made for differences in the way
individual students learn. Progressivism
was inspired in large part by the work
of John Dwey, the American philosopher
and education theorist. Um maybe I'll
say that last name. For Dwey, the
classroom was not simply a place for
acquiring academic credentials. It was
also a venue in which students learned
crucial values about being citizens in a
democracy. So maybe maybe these things
are laden not just with pedagogical
ideas, beliefs about human architecture,
um cultural sort of values, but even
maybe the outcomes of education. Maybe
we believe differently about that,
though not necessarily. Um the person
who's probably the best counterpoint to
John Dwey is this guy Ed Thorndikeke. um
who is a very early educational
psychologist. I often think of him as
the guy who is like no no no pale
filling is great. Um like a particularly
great thing about pale filling is that
we can measure pale filling. You can
measure like the rate at which you bore
things into people and the rate at which
it falls out and how leaky people are um
and some of those kinds of things. So he
was very involved in testing. Um he
actually um played a really important
role in developing ideas that
educational progressives uh hold dearly.
He's one of the things he studied which
we'll talk about the course goes on is
this idea of transfer. Um so uh uh you
know in the 18th 19th century people in
America Europe believed that a great
thing about learning Latin and Greek was
it sort of strengthened these kind of
like generic thinking muscles. Like if
you got really good at learning Latin
and Greek you would just be a good
thinker. And he was like that's dumb. Um
if you learn Latin and Greek you're good
at Latin and Greek but you're not
actually good at anything else. um like
the brain is not general purpose like
that but that kind of thinking that kind
of thinking if I learn this thing it'll
help me like generically with these
other things shows up all the time. Um
the most contemporary uh version of this
is have any of you ever encountered the
idea of computational thinking. What
people mean by computational thinking
almost all the time is like we're going
to teach you computer programming and if
you learn about computer programming
you're going to learn how to like break
ideas down into smaller parts and you're
going to learn how to think
algorithmically and do all these other
sort of and it's like no you're going to
be good at programming computers. Um you
know if you want to be able to break
ideas down in poetry learning computer
programming will not help you do that
anymore. I mean it will help you about
as much as learning Latin and Greek will
help you do that which is to say like
not that much. um that a frustrating
thing about teaching is the things we
learn um tend to only help us in like
very near cognate areas. Um so these are
sort of the two kind of you know again
I'm trying to give you the sense that
like these two big ideas are millennia
old. They have a scientific basis that's
at least a century old. Um and you're
getting what I think are some of the
best most recent contemporary uh
formulations. Um like the work of John
Sweller and some of these other folks
like the little piece you read from
Mitch Resnik for today. Um and then
maybe just to give you like a broader
overview like overwhelmingly Thorndikeke
is one. Um if you were to walk through a
typical American school in a typical
American day, you would see very little
education is life itself and you would
see a lot of direct instruction. Um like
the the canonical experience of students
in schools is very organized around
direct instruction. However, if you were
to ask teachers who their favorite um
educational philosopher is, you would
get a lot of answers that are Dewey and
you would not get a lot of answers that
were Thorndikeke. Um so the um Dewey is
beloved in a way that Thorndikeke is
not. But Thorndikeke is like actually
the person who uh inspires more of our
ideas. All right, let's do just a little
bit of close reading together, which is
mostly me telling you about some things
that you should read closely. This is
what we looked at yesterday. Here's um
one thing that's fun about the um
cognitive load theory people is that
they have they're really good at stating
clearly what their models of human
cognitive architecture are. I think the
situated learning people have cognates.
I think they have things that they
believe are central about the brain, how
learning works. Um but they would draw a
different model like this is not what
they were draw and and but and they're
less explicit about it which makes our
job a little bit harder but a thing that
you can be thinking about now um is like
what would be you know what is the what
is the situated learning cognate of this
like what would be the pieces that they
would put in the model that would be
most important um for their
developmental learning. We'll play with
that as we go along a little bit. Okay.
Um how many of you ever use the logo
programming language?
Oh good. More than there. How many of
you use Scratch? Okay, there we got
everybody. Um, so Scratch is a
descendant of Logo. Um, Logo is a
programming language that was uh
developed by Seymour Papert um in the
media lab. Uh, one of the first efforts
to bring computer programming to um kids
in schools when I was in the fourth
grade at a monastery school in South NIC
not far from here. We had a little
computer lab and logo was the language
that I learned to do a little bit of
programming anyway with um you'll see
that a lot of it um is about shapes and
geometry. Um but what I really loved
about it was uh choose your own
adventures. Um so you could essentially
like like write a program or function
whatever it is in which uh someone types
a word and that triggers the the display
of a set of text. Um, and so it wasn't
that hard to make choose your own
adventures, you know, you know, like
you're you're you're at the front of the
house. Do you want to walk up to the,
you know, type porch if you want to walk
into porch? Um, type, uh, knock if you
want to knock on the door. And then
knock is a program that releases another
set of text and you can make choose your
own adventure that way. How important is
that for you to know? I don't know. Here
um is a few minutes of Seymour Papert
um who was a student of Jean PG who's
another kind of major social
constructivist sort of thinker. Here's
um what uh logo was supposed to look
like in the classroom in the 1980s about
when I was a kid.
The idea is quite
simple. Let learn mathematics by
speaking in mathematics about things
that really matter to him. So at MIT,
we've given computers the power to turn
motors, to make sounds, to draw
pictures, and we've found ways of giving
children the power to control the
computer. So the child can make the
computer do anything that he can
describe in a suitable mathematical
language by typing on a keyboard like
this.
That's what um P1 sounds like.
[Music]
P2. That's P2 and P3.
A computer controlled turtle is made to
draw and dance by programs so simple
that all children invent them in the
first days of the course. Thus, the
child acquires a taste of math power
that grows and grows as his projects
become more original, more complex, and
more varied. So, you have like the um
first one, then the second one, then the
third one, then the first one again for
the ending. Okay. Now they'll put their
little tunes together to
[Music]
make now. I'm telling it to do it.
I know.
Sometimes I get into bugs like this and
it'll
um when it was doing it in his mind, the
little turtle, it's the little triangle
thing um was on an angle. So it drew the
picture on on an angle. So now I'll go
back and have it draw it in its mind
again while it's in the right position.
And so the child doesn't have to be told
by a teacher whether he's right or
wrong. He can see for himself whether it
works. That's what science and knowledge
is about. Super procedure is named
fancy. And then you have an input which
means you can vary the size. I'm going
to make it
100. Right now it's doing a procedure
called
top. And each one of those little fins
is called fin. And that's another sub
procedure in top. Now it's doing inside.
They are identifiable techniques for
working on a problem. One of these is
known by these children as writing
procedures as subrocedures. Inside and
top are the two main
subprocedures and the other one the tail
is made out of odds and ends. just put
just put together the techniques really
well known. Subdivide the problem. Split
the
difficulties. Make a procedure out of
subprocedures. Make a whole I'll just
tell you one second about this little
robot which again is like iconic my
childhood. I I had a commercialized
version of this. Um but it it t it it
takes the same commands and uses the
same language as the turtle that's on
the screen. So you can tell it like
forward 10 and there's some equivalent
to forward 10 that also shows up on the
screen. It has a pen that's mounted in
it that's controlled with pen up and pen
down. Um, so you can like make varying
kinds of shapes using that. And then if
you see the cable that the person is
walking around with, that was a serial
cable which is the primary thing we used
to use to connect computers to
peripherals. So that like before
wireless or before you know USB or other
things like that that was the cable that
they were using to move things around
procedure out of sub procedures, make a
hold out of parts. Understand each
separately. Everybody knows that, but
they don't do it. Now, it's moving
across the screen the way I um told you
it did it before, but this time, this is
like the way I taught myself to get it
across the screen. It's the first time I
had done it. And so, the way I have the
little one to go is every time it moves
up a little, it subtracts a number, a
little bit of a number, and then until
it it's a small number. And when it's a
certain number, I tell it that it should
stop.
Martha's getting mathematical knowledge
in a meaningful context for use. Now,
it just told me I can't move off the
screen. When I was at school, they told
me to learn long division because I
would need it when I grew up. And I
think I knew it was a
lie. It was to make me despise the
teachers a little more. Now it's drawing
the
gill a
subrocedure. Now the bottom of the fish
Steven is using the ideas of angle of
subrocedure of arc and of circle in a
confident purposeful way. The tail the
triangle part is made out of a procedure
called try one. First you got to do
right 60, then forward 50, back 50, left
60, forward 50, back 50, left 60,
forward 50, back 50, and so on.
Now it's doing a
firm. That's a radius of 300 and a um
arc of 90. I made a big radius. And then
I went sector left which will go right
over it and bring it back. Then I made a
smaller radius of the same arc and then
it would do that again. Then it's even
smaller one. It will do that again. And
that's how I got the
fern. There we are. There's the finished
picture.
I made a big song and I used that for
part of it and then I made an
accompanying with it with the drum and
that's um
[Music]
The kids told me that's a spiral. I
think there was a new mathematical word
that was born there that's going to
stick. I'd call that real discovery.
[Music]
Good. Don't spend time with this. Um,
turn the people next to you. Talk to
them a little bit. What are what are the
things that you saw in there that coher
with ideas that you read about from
other communities of situated learning?
What are some things that you saw in
there that cohered with cognitive load
theory? Do you see sort of evidence of
direct instruction that was in there
anywhere? Um and then what kind of
learning environments have you been like
um where you learned in this kind of way
that was pleasurable? And have people
been in learning environments where
you've sort of learned in this way that
you found very unpleasurable and
unlikable? Then discuss that for a
couple minutes. Ready? Go.
Every good. What are what are what are
some connections that people made? What
are some things that uh where you saw
examples of uh situated learning or
cognitive load theory or things that
seem pleasurable or or frustrating? What
did you talk about in your groups? We
were talking about learning like
programming in general or it seems like
you always need some base level of
whether it's the instructions or knowing
whatever commands there are in logo and
that most likely comes from more of an
instructional place but then you can get
into these situations like we saw in the
video where it becomes open world but it
still seems like you need some base
level where CLT needs to come in. All
right. Yeah. Or or some kind of direct
instruction. Where where did where what
what evidence of direct instruction did
people um did people see? Like where
were you like h that kid didn't figure
that out on their own? I mean just the
terminology they figured out like
procedure subrocedure all of these
things are a kid a kid wouldn't just
figure these out. Yeah. Yeah. It doesn't
seem like Steven came up with the term
procedure and subrocedure. Like pretty
sure somebody taught him you know sat
down and said this is you know here are
a couple of useful definitions that will
allow us communicate with us more
clearly. Um also we were talking about
like when the two girls were talking to
each other it was like one at the
beginning was like instruct instructing
the other. Yeah.
So, I guess that's kind of like Oh, very
direct instruction. Yeah. Instruction
within like a situated learning
environment. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, it's
it's Yeah. Yeah. It's a it's a kind of
worked example like, oh, I'm going to
show you how I you know, I made a thing
like I'm going to, you know, we're going
to make this thing together right now by
first of all, play each of the pieces.
Now, we're going to play all the pieces
together. I've already learned how to do
that. you know what makes it a kind of
peer learning uh uh situated learning
kind of thing is it's one young person
teaching it to another person but does
seem to be you know direct instruction
for sure. Um that kind of led us into a
conversation about how like within
situated learning like that there's like
kind of two ways that it can be seen as
like you have someone who's like an
old-timer like the the other girl like
explaining to the other the like the
other girl about um the situation that
they were working with. But then there's
also the instances when it was just like
the student and the computer and that
like you kind of lost that like social
aspect that you have of like learning
from another person. Um and then we like
went into like an interesting
conversation about whether like maybe
the student was like having a social
interaction from themsel and like
learning with the computer as a tool or
maybe they were having a social
interaction with the computer itself and
like they were learning from the
computer and the computer was like
learning what like they really wanted
the outcome to be. So yeah. Yeah, good.
Yeah, that's definitely something we'll
think about more as we go along. Like
what kind of agent is the machine? What
kind of relationship do we have uh to
the machines? How does the machine
motivate? How does the machine explain?
The thing that seems pretty rad here
that that seem more pepper is the
machine gives some great feedback.
Although lots of other things do. Um uh
hand drills give great feedback. You
know, when you like go through the wall,
you know it. And when you like, you
know, hit something metal or something
like that, you know it and you get that
kind of instant feedback. Um there are
other things that we teach people where
it's just hard to imagine where that
instant feedback might come from. Um
writing is often that way especially
like writing other people. There's
nothing that a sort of screen right we
haven't built things very well where a
machine can tell you like oh that's a
compelling way of expressing that idea
um in the same way that I can be like oh
my swan is on its side. Um so sort of
different you know different
technologies or and different in you
know different things that we study have
have different capacity to give us
immediate feedback about what we're
doing. Um good other has anybody ever
been in an environment like this where
you're like oh my gosh this is the worst
do students have experience in this kind
of like open-ended learning where you're
like this is terrible. Yeah, I remember
this like one or I guess the some more
recent MIT experience where basically
one of the classes like final project
was very like open-ended and they were
like, "Oh, like just like design this
game." And I was like, "Wow, like it
would be nice to get some kind of Yeah,
will you please show me how to design
this game? Like I don't like someone has
figured this out before. Like I don't I
don't want to explore this space
forever." I've definitely have people
who who have taken this class and they
watch this video and they're like, "Give
me a break." Like just show me how to
use the turtle. them. Um I would say in
high school um a lot of the AP computer
science classes are like very into like
this kind of situated learning. But then
if you have certain classrooms where
like in my instance it was like just
overloaded with people who just need an
elective and they were like you have to
take this class then it becomes that um
like peer-to-peer interaction becomes an
issue where it's like okay you have
three people who are trying to teach
like 30 other people how to do a
specific thing because you're in the
same like group and they have to pass
and they don't really care anyway. Good.
people have different motivations or I
mean a huge problem that computer
science education has is that people
unlike other subjects people come to it
with very different levels of background
experience. Um so like none of you
probably ever took a geology class where
like a third of the kids were like man I
just love geology like I do I do geology
all the time in my spare time. I'm way
ahead of you guys. But that is
essentially what just about every
computer science class we teach is like
where a chunk of people are like way
into it know a bunch more already. Um,
and in fact, those open-ended
environments can be can be really great
for those folks who have that extra
expertise, and they can be a real bummer
for people who like can't jump in as
naturally. Harmon, what was you going to
say? Uh, I think what this made me think
of is how CLT and situated learning
cannot be really separated from each
other. Sometimes you need CLT to give
framework for students and then from
that I guess you can fire the wood and
the situated. Yeah. Good. Good. I like
it. I like it. Yeah. Yeah. What are the
I think that's a great question to ask.
What are the different sort of
combination and permutations like the
reason why these ideas have existed that
we can find evidence of them for 2,000
years is that like they both seem pretty
good. Um they both seem useful in
different ways. You know, here you know
here is here you know um Seymour Papard
is once talking about like his teachers
lying to them and despising schools. But
you can also find sort of school things
like we're going to need some
definitions that I teach you um that are
kind of woven even in this sort of
extreme example. Um let me give you a
few pieces from the thing that you read
u from a guy named Jean Le um who with
another person named Eddiad Winganger um
really advanced some of these ideas. Um
and I want you to like be thinking about
like so how is the like what are the
methods that this person uses to study?
What are the kind of arguments they
make? What are the implications for
pedagogy? what's their framework about
um human beings and how they learn and
where do these things lap and overlap
you know some like it can often seem
like when you're writing about you know
if you read a bunch of stuff on
cognitive load theory it seems like
they're just talking about instruction
and they mostly are but they're ways at
talking about instruction that evoke
their beliefs about culture that evoke
their beliefs about values that evoke
their beliefs around methods and
outcomes even if they don't talk about
those things as much in this chapter I
propose to consider learning not as a
process process of socially shared
cognition that results in the end in the
internalization of knowledge by
individuals but as a process of becoming
a member of a sustained community of
practice. Um so anytime you read
anything a thing that you're almost all
probably trained to do is try to figure
out like what is the person's core
argument like what is the thing they're
arguing for. An equally useful thing to
do almost anytime you read anything is
to try to figure out what is this person
arguing against. Um, and people are
often not that explicit. Um, you know,
he's not sort of saying like these jerks
who are really like big on schools and
direct instruction have totally missed
this stuff. But there's that's kind of
what he's he's getting at in here. And
it's and it's a radical statement.
Learning is not the internalization of
knowledge. You know, last week I told
you that for some of these kind of
educational psychology people, memory is
the residue of thought. Like the entire
end point of cognitive load theory is to
store memories facts as memories in our
long-term memory. Um not as the
internalization of knowledge as
individuals but as a process of becoming
a member of a sustained community of
practice developing an identity as a
member of a community and becoming
knowledgeably skillful are part of the
same process. You cannot separate
storing things in long-term memory from
building relationships with other
people. Um with the former motivating
one of the key things that we remember
our colleague Michael Pashan you know
not a theory of everything where is the
motivation with the former motivating
shaping and giving meaning to the latter
which it subsumes it is difficult to
move from peripheral to full
participation in today's world including
workplaces and schools thereby
developing knowledgeably skilled
identities. This is because the
processes by which we divide and sell
labor, which are ubiquitous in our way
of producing goods and services,
including knowledge, truncate both the
movement from peripheral to full
participation in the scope of
knowledgeable skill. Taken to an
extreme, these processes separate
identity from intended forms of
knowledgeable practice. This view
implies that learning and failure to
learn are aspects of the same social
historical processes and points to
relationships between knowledgeability
and identity as important focus for
research. These jerks, these education
psychologists keep trying to convince
you that what learning is is just
shoving stuff in your brain. It's not.
There are always people around when
we're learning. Even when we're learning
by ourselves, reading books and stuff
like that, there are people in our minds
or communities that we see ourselves
being part of. Um try, you know, trying
to understand how learning happens in
schools or any other learning
environment without thinking about the
social environment that people learn is
bonkers, is nuts. Um, it just it it it
denies a crucial part of our humanity.
Um, here's a a blog post that you can
look at later if you sort of follow
this. It's by a wonderful math educator
named Dan Meyer. Um, who has been trying
to explain to people why he thinks AI
chat bots are a stupid idea and will not
work. Um, and and uh and the you know
his core issue is like nobody wants to
talk to a computer. Like maybe the
computer can provide a sort of perfect
direct instructional sequence, but like
the kids who are in my eighth grade
algebra classroom, they don't want to be
there. They're not interested in
algebra. Um I love this framing. He's,
you know, he a students attend school to
answer two questions. Who am I? And how
do I do this? Those are the two things
they're thinking about all the time. Who
am I? And how do I do this? A chatbot
cannot help you at all with the first
question. Um but the other thing I want
to bring up here and you can disagree
with that and we'll talk about more when
we talk about chatbots but um who am I
and how do I do this? This is exactly
what Jean La was discussing that
identity cannot be separated from the
acquisition of knowledge. Um and I think
most of you probably if you think of
your own classroom exper you know think
of your own school experience like I
spent a lot of time in middle school and
high school thinking to myself in one
form or another who am I? Um what do
people think of me? What kinds of
relationships do I have? Why am I here?
What am I supposed to be doing?
Um uh Jordan has carried out extensive
field research in the Yakatan Maya wavel
whose apprenticeship is quite different
more effective and less exploitative
than the butchers of marshall study. The
apprentices are peripheral participants
legitimate peripherence and legitimate
peripheral to the practice of midy. What
did you all take away from what you
think like what is legitimate peripheral
practice or periphery? Like what does
that mean sort of in your own words?
What do you think Dana? Like they're
doing work that like matters, but
they're not like doing the main work.
Like they're doing side tasks that are
like helping them understand the main
process, but like they themselves are
not like giving birth to the child.
Good. Good. And and there's a space
there. A space is held for those people.
It is expected that there are going to
be some folks who are hanging around
midwives who are not quite midwives yet.
And that's normal. They're supposed to
be there. Um, it's not a classroom of 20
people all lined up who are supposed to
be doing the same thing all the time.
There's supposed to be some people in
the middle and there's supposed to be
some people on the outside. I want to
pose a question too to think of the
relationship between what uh Gene Le was
talking about the midwives and the
butchers in the thinking. What's the
difference between peripheral
participants and legitimately peripheral
participants? Do folks remember what
they described about the butchers? Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Was that the butchers even
though like they were doing peripheral
work, they were separated in space from
the like
the experts. So they didn't they
wouldn't really pick up on things as
opposed to midwives who still observe
what the legitimate the expert was
doing. Yeah. So what does that mean in
terms of being a part of that community
and then shaping the learning that
they're able to
acquire? If I'm a butcher and I'm I'm
part of the community, if I'm standing
over here cutting my meat, using my
tool, that's all I get to do. And then
Justin's over there, you know, hanging
out with the pig or whatever it is,
right? What am I losing then? The social
aspect. The social aspect, right? Am I
able to observe him? Can I see what he's
doing when he leaves? Can I pick it up
from watching? Totally miss that. But
then what about the midwife? How's that
different?
How do they describe the midwife
relationship? Justin, I hope this is
okay. I love this book. So, yeah. Go
ahead. Um, so I think the one of the
main differences is beyond the fact that
it wasn't supposed to be more efficient.
So there was no capitalist aspect to it.
There was a lot of culture embedded in
it. So like the daughter of a midwife
would become midwife, meaning that at 5
years old, they would already kind of be
present in that situation and start like
picking up on what was going on and then
progressively have a more like
protagonist role to that experience. So
yeah. So like although both could be
argued as peripheral, right? We're we're
in the same space. We're hanging out.
Like who's welcome in the community and
then what type of knowledge are you able
to gain from that type of peripheral
participation? It's kind of cool. It's
subtle, right? Yeah. All right. That's
all I got. I have Can I make Okay.
um the the previous paragraph I had a
lot of reflection about it and I don't
nec like kind of that in some aspects
I'm not sure how you feel about it but
like I really like the point that he
makes about like learning kind of makes
forms your identity as part of this
social group right and I think that
really applies to kids for example kind
of like they come from this per
peripheral existence and develop their
own identities and become like a
committed like functioning part of
society. But then it really made me
think like oh how do we think about it
like from an abbleist um perspective
right where people cannot acquire
certain knowledges or certain abilities
and does that mean they have less of an
identity like I really thought about
that for a while and at the same time
there's like a criticism in the book
about like commoditization of knowledge
because before like with midwives etc
like okay it was this really specific
group of people teaching this very kind
of like expertise u whereas today we
have universities and we have schools or
you can kind of get to whatever class
and learn things, but it's not
necessarily all bad, right? Because that
would imply that if you're the daughter
of the midwife, you don't really have a
lot of say into becoming or not a
midwife, right? Like the way that
society was structured back then likely
you would kind of become one because
that's what expected of you. Whereas
like when you kind of can choose that
you have some sort of agency and power
even if you won't have that exposure as
a peripheral participant since a since
you were a kid. So like it really made
me think of many things. Great. Good.
Good. And and none of them have to be
resolved either. Um you know that that
uh um probably probably some important
things to take away are like how Jean
assigns values to these different kinds
of institutions. like he thinks it's a
big problem, you know, a big problem
with schools and university is sort of
ripping knowledge away from these
broader social contexts. Um that you go
and take a physics class and in the vast
majority of physics 101 classes, no one
is trying to get you to be a physicist.
They're not trying to get you to develop
the identity of a physicist. They're
just trying to teach you the physics.
And what is lost sort of in that? Of
course, what's pretty rad about like
walking into a campus full of people who
will be like, "Yeah, I'll teach you any
of these atomized little things for you
to learn." like that seems kind of cool
too. Um it is worth noting that it would
be difficult to find evidence that
teaching is the mode of knowledge
transmission amongst the midwives. Um he
makes this claim that like you wouldn't
find direct instruction amongst the
midwives. Um I mean Jordan did the fil
work and not me. That seems totally
laughable to me. I've spent time with
lots of people of lots of ages, learns
lots of kinds of things and people are
always transmitting and explaining
stuff. It's always sort of nested in
there. Um but there's a kind of politics
of John Lave like we don't even need to
explain these things. We don't even need
to teach these people. We can learn it
just like babies learn it sort of in
their natural environment. You just you
know just like you have to surround
babies with language and they'll learn
language. You surround young girls with
birth and pregnancy and they learn
midwiffery. Um
uh apprenticeship happens as a way in
the course of daily life. It may not be
recognized as teaching effort at all.
Again sort of doubling down like there's
no instruction here. If there
instruction, the people are lying to you
and you should despise them. Um, a Maya
girl who eventually became a midwife
most likely as a mother, a grandmother
as a midwife. Girls in such families
without being identified as apprentice
midwives absorb the effence of midwife
practice as well as specific knowledge
about many procedures simply in the
process of growing up. They know what
the life of a midwife is like, what
kinds of stories the women and men who
come to consult her tell, what kind of
herbs and other remedies might be needed
to collected. As young children, they
might be sitting quietly in their
corner. As their minister mother
administers a prenatal massage, they
would hear stories of difficult cases of
miraculous outcomes and the like. As
they grow older, they may be passing
messages, running errands, getting
needed supplies. A young girl might be
present as her mother stops for a
postpartum visit after the daily
shopping trip to the market. Eventually,
after she has a child herself, she might
come along to her birth, perhaps because
her alien grandmother needs someone to
walk with, and thus finds herself doing
for the woman in labor what other women
had done for her when she gave birth.
That is, she may take a turn at
supporting the laboring woman.
Eventually, she may even administer
prenatal massages to the selected
clients. At some point, she may decide
she actually wants to do this kind of
work. She then pays more attention, but
only rarely does she ask questions. Her
mentor sees their association, primarily
one that is of some use to her. Rosa
already knows how to do a massage, so I
can send her if I'm too busy. Um, that
is just a beautiful description of kind
of legitimate peripheral participation,
moving from the periphery to the center.
You just watch this thing for a while
and then your mom's hands are a little
sore and so you do the massage this time
and you know how to move the massage cuz
it happened to you. You've seen it a
zillion times. Are any of you part of
sort of clubs or groups at MIT that have
learning that feels like this?
I guess like technically a lot of
theater clubs are similar where people
are just doing this like how do you
become a stage manager? I don't know.
Look at what the stage hand. Oh, and and
the other thing is like you start as a
stage hand like Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Come,
you know, you watch some theater. Yeah.
You know, just stand there and like
you're like between the second and third
act like hand this prop to that person.
Um and you're probably never going to
take stage manager class. You're just
going to hand that prop once and then
you're the prop master and then the
stage manager gets sick and you do it
for the night and then you're the stage
manager. Yeah, I think theater has a ton
of stuff like this. That's a great
example. What are you going to say,
Omar? In the tech and technique, we have
what's called like shadowing. So, when
we go out for photo assignments where
there's a studio photography assignment
or something out in the field, um we can
always have like a someone shadowing us
and they can also be taking photos with
their own camera and sometimes we will
use their work as well. So, they can
also do legitimate periphery work. I
love it. and you have intentionally sort
of held space for that. You've kind of
designed like, oh yeah, come, you know,
come along, hang out with us. Um, and
you probably have parties and other
kinds of things like that where it's
like, oh, you know, where like some of
you are just goofing around, but some of
it you're like, ah, the story that we
gota d, you know, I'm sure like them
telling the stories of of difficult
cases and miraculous outcomes. I'm sure
the tech has other similar kinds of
difficult cases and miraculous outcomes.
I was going to say like on sports teams
like when people become captains like
not often is the coach sitting them down
and being like this is how you be a
captain, this is how you lead people.
It's more like they just like naturally
have this like personality of doing that
of like maybe they grew up and like
their their mom was like a girl boss or
like they like just grew up seeing stuff
like that. So then like you kind of have
like that natural progression into like
just learning by doing. Good. Yeah.
Yeah. Pretty. What were you going to
say, Sabrina? Okay, this is kind of a
dumb example, but I like I'm really bad
at Smash, so I always get placed with
the best Smash player, and then we're on
a team against two other people who are
also really good, but this person is so
good that like they carry they carry,
but I'm kind of learning along with
them. Um, and like I kind of like hold
off onto the side where I just kind of
like try to like hold lives while they
like destroy the other people. Um, and I
think that's kind of periphery. Oh yeah,
yeah, yeah, yeah. I mean in and in that
particular community it's a space of
legitimate peripheral participation
which somewhat exists because of this
like fairness balancing kinds of things
and so you know like every learning
environment like the substance of uh
Super Smash Brothers determines like
where the legitimate you know and it
determines spaces for peripheral
partition that's different than
journalism that different than sports
that different but this theory is giving
us commonality where we can talk about
really different things that might arise
in different circumstances be like I I
think that's actually kind of the same
thing and it's kind of spaces that I'm
finding for learning.
Um, in short, when official channels
offer only a possibility to participate
in institutionally mandated forms of
commoditized activity, genuine
participation, membership, and
legitimate access to ongoing practice of
a practice considered worthy to the name
are rare. Practice is not to be found in
schools and workplaces. At the same
time, schools and school-like workplace
educational enterprises accord knowledge
skill a reified existed turning it from
into something to be acquired and its
transmission into an institutional
motive. This process generates pressures
towards the trivializing decomposing of
forms or activity. The result is a
widespread generation of negative
identities of misrecognized or
institutionally disapproved insistential
communities of practice. um that some of
the things that might feel most academic
might feel less or least identity
oriented to you. Um because there's not,
you know, think about like what like
what degrees here would be like I'm not
sure there's a way to be a legitimate
peripheral participant there. Like
there's a way to learn the stuff.
There's a way to be taught the discreet
parts of this course or subject or
major, but I I like I'm not learning how
to be a part of this community. Um
uh okay.
Um, here are three things that I'll have
you do together um for five or 10
minutes, which might involve some
drawing. Um,
uh, so grab grab some paper or some
board space. Um, what see if you could
draw sort of the equivalent of human
cognitive architecture. Um, see if you
could draw like just just like just like
you drew these diagrams for um, uh,
cognitive load theory. What is the
diagram you would draw for um situated
learning? Um what is um based on that
cognitive architecture? Um what is the
pedagogy that follows? So based on like
the sort of key fundamental principles
of of situated learning, cognitive load
theory said like here's a model of human
cognitive architecture. Here are series
of like clearly defined effects. The
situated learning people are not as good
as like enumerating in bullet points all
of their pieces, but it's all in there.
um what are some of the what are some of
the like instructional practices that
follow from this model? Um think about
those two things and then also see if
you can sort of recreate some of your
ven diagrams um of what are the
categories of things that seem separate
from um cognitive learning and situated
learning and what are the things that
they seem to be quite similar on um or
quite together on. Um take 10 minutes to
again grab one person or two other
people do some drawing, do some
composing. Feel free to pull up your
notes from your learning journal where
you should have done some of this uh
things. And if any of these questions,
you don't have to you don't have to
spend equal time on all three questions.
If you dive in on one, that's fine. But
those three should keep you busy for
eight minutes or something like that.
Make sense? Ready? You go.
So, one one thing I love about almost
all of these drawings is it's kind of
impossible to draw these models without
drawing other people. Um, that when you
all developed a kind of human cognitive
architecture in cognitive load theory,
you were sort of drawing like one brain.
And actually like actually most of your
drawings you didn't even really
represent the rest of the world. But in
this model it's impossible not to
represent the rest of the world and in
particular other people um because
learning fundamentally is social and
your identity is fundamentally
reflective of your connections with uh
with other people. So these are good. Um
you read a little piece of um give P's a
chance. So four P's from Mitch Resnik
about projects passion uh play and
peers. Hopefully, you can now start
mapping some of these ideas to what we
talked about the reason, you know,
projects, kind of open-ended
explorations, making music, making uh
funny shape, having a robot draw funny
shape somewhere. Um, those are spaces
for open-ended exploration, for doing
multiple kinds of things. Um, projects
have more space for peripheral
participation, like multiple people can
be making music, even if someone's a
little bit better at making music than
the other person. um that they are um
that that learning environments here are
are driven by interests. Um you know
there's very little reference in
cognitive load theory to things like
well yeah and sometimes the kids don't
like learning math so they just don't.
Um although that's very real. Um some
some of the young w some of the
daughters and midwives wanted to become
midwives and some didn't. Um and for the
ones who did want to become midwives
they followed that interest and those
who didn't went and did other things.
Um, and in these kinds of models of
learning, that's actually okay and
really important. We're not supposed to
make everyone better at everything.
We're supposed to let people follow
their interests and get good at the
things that they want to get good at. um
that in environments in which there is a
kind of lightness to the environment
where uh you know lightness play creates
space for multiple forms of
participation like like things don't
have to be optimized
um to to get to the the you know fastest
best trajectory for all people. There
can be like room to to play and mess
around and try other things. And then
you know doing it with other people is
essential as you can see in kind of all
of these kinds of things you know and
part of what uh um you know in some ways
the real genius Jean Leave was a woman I
misrepresented her as a man before and
Aaron hopefully corrected me. Um Eddie
Wanger her partner is a co-writer as a
guy. Um is is it's not it's not just
like people hanging out with each other.
we can describe repeated patterns we see
of legitimate peripheral participation
um of old-timers and newcomers um of uh
there's lots in Le's work that you
probably read that was about trying to
trying to find new language to get away
from the experts and noviceses because
it's not ju that's part of it but it's
not just that um it's our time in its
community it's our space in community
those kinds of things so there's some so
just like in cognitive load theory you
could say here's a human cognitive
architecture here's a set of pedagogical
principles that follow from that. Um,
Jean Leave can describe these social
interactions. We can as you can abstract
from them some models of uh of human
cognitive architecture and say well okay
from those models there are some
instructional principles that follow. Um
if I were to draw one of these I think a
thing that I would pay a bunch of
attention to is that um you know the
thing in in both learning models like
you learn what you attend to. Um seeing
is really important. Um, a key insight
of of uh situated learning is that we
attend to things that interest us and
motivate us and where where we find our
identity and care about like how you
know if looking at something is
essential to get people to learn about
it then we ought to think very carefully
about what motivates us to look at a
thing. Um, uh, T-ball for me is a,
um, a a a canonical example of a kind of
activity which it would be almost
impossible to teach primarily through
cognitive load theory. Um, like it's
really hard to imagine teaching kids
baseball where you're like, "All right,
sit down everyone. Like we're all going
to watch a worked example of how you,
you know, hit a ball or like like we
have to learn the rule book of
baseball." Like the way we teach kids
baseball is we're like, "What is the
fastest way we can get young people with
limited coordination and no knowledge of
the rules to play something like
baseball? How do we get them baseballing
as soon as we possibly can?" And some
genius was like, "Don't do the pitching.
Like, get rid of the pitching. Just put
the ball on the stick and they can just
hit the ball." Um, it h it it it has
some kind of cognitive relationship to
sort of part whole practice um to
devolving scaffolding and things like
that. There's a there's a researcher at
Harvard uh who wrote a book called
Making Learning Whole. Um where he said
that that one of the things we can often
do in curriculum that we underestimate
is get people playing the whole game as
early as possible. Um you could we'll
talk about this more, but think about
like what subjects have you taken in MIT
that let you start playing the whole
game as soon as possible and what
require you to sort of build up lots of
elementary pieces before you can do the
thing that that whole discipline does.
Um but ba baseball instruction in the
United States like very difficult to
imagine in a cognitive load theory
framework. Um like very pleasant for
millions of young people in a more
experiential situated kind of way. All
right. You did this a little bit. Um
which is good. Here is one thing that I
would like to have in the center of your
ven diagrams of things that are similar.
Um this I this is a misconception that
my students have had over the years that
I want to correct.
um
they're the cognitive loads theorists
and the situated learning people agree
on what expertise looks like. They agree
on what high quality practice looks
like. I don't think you'd find these
people. They would not disagree about
what a great body player or a great
carpenter or a great surgeon or a great
lawyer looks like. Um they would believe
that sometimes people think that the
cognitive load theorists want people who
are experts to be really like rigid and
disciplined and pattern repeating and
that is not the case. That is not what
they want as the end point. You know
they they want your cancer surgeon to be
dynamic and flexible when they cut open
your belly um and find cancerous tumors
and are pulling them out of there. Um
they want poets to be creative and
imaginative. They just think that the
way that you develop the knowledge base
that lets you be creative and flexible
and dynamic and strategic is through
really disciplined instruction. Um
because if you don't go through a
process of really disciplined
instruction, um it's hard to get good at
things because no one no one has showed
you how to do fundamental pieces um in
clear ways. Um I have a couple
colleagues, Jal Meta and Sarah Fine. Um
J still at Harvard. uh s was there for a
while in his uh was it high-tech high
graduate school of education for a while
who said who studied schools a lot
studied very different schools with very
different pedagogical philosophies and
found that across all of them they
tended to believe that expertise
consisted of mastery identity and
creativity that you knew a bunch of
stuff in a domain um that you developed
an identity in that domain and that you
were able to do flexible creative work
um you know a bunch of physics equations
and when to apply them you feel like
you're kind of a physicist and a
scientist and when you need to do
something novel like build a bridge um
or launch a rocket or something like
that, you're not just following steps,
but you're doing things that are that
are creative um and expressive. One one
way that I would um I think the
cognitive load theorists and situated
learning people tend to imagine
different pathways at getting at these
goals. Um, so the cognitive load
theorists tend to think that mastery is
like the starting point. If you know the
stuff, if you can do the pieces, then a
we often most enjoy things that we're
good at. So like get you good at doing
things. There's, you know, there's there
there's there's lots of debates in the
country right now, we'll talk about them
some, about teaching kids to read. Um,
and there's some folks who say like we
just have to let kids explore books and
find what they're interested in. And
there other folks are like, you know
what's fun about reading is actually
being able to read. So like teach them a
bunch of phonics and explain to them the
basics of how to construct words. And
that's what makes reading enjoyable.
That would make people feel like
readers, you know, not when they have
like a beautiful library of things to
choose from, whatever they want, but
when they can actually make sense of
what's in there. There's some sense in
that. Um, you develop some kind of
identity and then you get then you have
the opportunity to do creative practice
that builds that mastery. There are
other people who say start with things
like creativity. Start by getting people
to play around in the space as much as
possible so that they're motivated. Um
so that they say, "Man, like I am a I am
a this. I want, you know, I'm a I'm a
baseball player. Like I, you know, I
swung on a ball on a stick a few times."
Um but now I am a baseball player. Um,
and because I'm a baseball player, like
in my heart, um, I'll memorize all the
statistics and learn the rules and go to
practice, you know, and eventually do
like really boring learning kinds of
things. Um, the sort of masteryoriented
discipline kinds of things, but because
I know how fun it is to play around in
this space. Um, what what do you think
at MIT are the are the subjects or
courses that you would take that would
be more canonically sort of mastery
first oriented?
What are what are the subjects you would
take that you would like start with the
smallest pieces or or by contrast if
it's easier? What are the ones that seem
to be more creativity first?
I think more like bioheavy classes would
definitely be like mastery first because
if you don't understand like the basic
of cells like you're not getting
anywhere like you can't go like chapter
2 without understanding like good. So it
seems to be, you know, so eventually you
can do some like pretty rad
computational biology, biological
engineering here, but there's not a lot
in bio 101 where they're like, "Yeah,
let's like have cells start generating
novel proteins or things like that." I
would say most of the general
requirements like especially like the
chemistry requirements and the biology
requirements are like with the hopes
that hey if you learn a little bit about
this maybe then you become interested
and want to go further and want that to
be your major. But yeah, so so which
which ones do that through like giving
you a bunch of facts and which ones do
that by letting you sort of play the
whole
game? I mean my understanding is that a
number of the engineering departments
like in mechanical engineering you'd be
more likely earlier in your career to be
like we're going to build a robot. Um
and like do you know how to build a
robot? No. Are you going to be good at
building a robot? No. You're going to
build a lousy robot. We're going to let
you build a crummy robot. and some TA is
going to put their arm around your
shoulder and be like, "That robot's
okay. That robot's only okay because you
don't know anything about control
systems." But guess what? Guess what?
One of our junior classes is control
systems. You're like, "Ah, I can't wait
to take control system. It's going to be
boring. It's going to be like a bunch of
equations and other pets and things like
that." But there's a robot that you want
to drive. Um, the neat program I think
at MIT is really about trying to create
a bunch of these like experiential
experiences. I mean, historically, if
you were to look at our curriculum
across MIT, many more things would be
much more like this. I mean, like our
math curriculum, I think, is very much
this way. Like, you're just going to do
math that other people have figured out
for years and years, and maybe by the
time you get to the end of MIT, but you
might have to wait till graduate school
that you can do some new math that
someone else has never done before. Um,
my uh my wife teaches the material
science department. Um, and uh some of
the stuff with like the Breaker Lab that
they just developed and things like
that. um where like they did an early
exercise in one of our classes which is
build products from the worst possible
materials. Um so like phone cases that
were made of sponges and absorbed water
or um locks that were made of clear
plastic where you could see all the
tumblers and things like basically like
play around with materials, do stuff
with materials and then you're going to
take like some super boring really hard
classes but you're motivated to take
those things. So I think you can look
across environments um and see how they
choose different pathways um through
these uh these different if you look at
reading instruction in the United States
there's a huge debate right now about do
you start with mastery and facts and
pieces and build up to readers um or do
you start by exposing people to books
and letters and words and the things
they love and and lots of time um you
know and almost no course of study is
the answer only one of those things like
nobody believes you should just do
creativity I think almost all of our
subjects like have classes which are
like okay time to buckle down and learn
this thing. But we can often think about
like how we order these things
differently to produce more motivation
or develop identity or other kinds of
things like that. Um but again the like
across different pedagogical
philosophies is almost always the case
that people have a very shared idea
about what expertise is. Um so I think
even people who you know um are situated
learning folks um you know they like
they they they don't want you to like
invent midwiffery a new like they want
the babies consistently delivered in
safe healthy ways. Um uh so that so it's
that it's different beliefs about how
you get there. Um there are efforts to
reconcile these things which I didn't
make you read but if you wanted to
explore a little bit more I'll give you
an introduction to one of them um in the
rabbit hole for this week. Ken Kadinger
has a a couple of things you can look
at. The the lecture he gives is actually
the easiest way of getting it. There's a
video in there. It's quite good. Um the
knowledge learning instruction framework
and he says one useful way to think
about this um is that there are um uh
more complex and less complex knowledge
components in the things we learn. So
there are things like um you know
Chinese characters and there are things
like you know um anthropological
principles about how society are
organized um and there different levels
of complexity. There's also um sort of
learning processes and there's things
like flashc cards um and then you know
which is just for memorizing stuff um
and then there's things like um talk and
explaining and sense making and stuff
like that um and he has a theory that
basically um you know you should be
matching instructional components to how
complex um the knowledge component
learning processes to how complex the
knowledge components are. Um he has a
nice uh sort of this is kind of like a
giant science which is in process where
here are a bunch of things that people
were trying to learn. Chinese vocab,
French articles, chem models, pressure
concept. Here are a bunch of uh
instructional strategies, optimal
scheduling, feedback, worked examples,
accountable talk, collaboration and you
find that like the you know these are
less complex to more complex teaching.
this is less complex to more complex um
uh uh knowledge components and that like
basically where you get uh studies with
statistically significant effects on
learning is when you kind of move
through the middle of this space when
you map the right knowledge component to
the right learning process. I don't know
that Ken Kinger and his colleagues have
totally figured this out either. Um but
it's one way to start sort of
reconciling some of these ideas. Okay.
Um the the most important thing for
Wednesday is that we're meeting at the
MIT Museum. Please try to be at the MIT
Museum. Like if you could if you can get
there by 1 and get checked in and put
your bag in the locker, then we can
start class at 105. So make every effort
to get there as soon as you can. There's
a few pieces of reading. Um the Steven
Wolf thing is totally worth your time
and it will require a little attention.
Like you'll have to sort of move your
way through it, but he does just a
beautiful job explaining the
fundamentals of generative pre-trained
models. um a little bit about neural
networks and things like that. And then
there's a bunch of other readings that
are in there. Some of which are about
the mu the exhibits you'll see at the
museum and some are some other
educational things that me and some
other folks at MIT have written about uh
GPT. Um and then be sure you refresh
yourself and you start thinking about
working on the assignment because you
now have two of the crucial building
blocks that you'll need for the
assignment. Um which is some sense of
direct instruction, cognitive load
theory, and some sense of
constructionism, situated learning, um
progressive learning kinds of things.
And you'll need both of those ideas to
do assignment number one. And we'll talk
a little bit about uh how we want to do
assignment number one on Wednesday. Stay
safe in the snow. Have a wonderful uh
next couple days. And I'll see you at
the museum on Wednesday.