thank you Tim and kg all right so I know
this is somewhat cliche to say but I'm
standing between you and standing the
bathroom and drinking
food um but I think it's important to to
do this right in formally I'd like to
take a moment to extend my sincere
thanks to our startup companies to our
MIT faculty and to the team that
organized this event it made that made
it possible without their tireless
efforts we wouldn't have be here today
so shinomi Quan yui Rebecca Nang jwan
Mickey and kg I'd also like to thank the
kiden run for welcoming us to this
lovely
space uh due to the diversity of
Industries represented within our
Japanese ILP member base we tend not to
have themed events but if I must give
this conference a theme I'd say it was
centered around addressing Global
challenges through various discussions
on advanc materials energy Innovation
and healthc Care
Technologies in a world that is
constantly evolving this theme could not
be
timely whether you are here to explore
new trends exchange ideas or collaborate
with fellow professionals our
conversations today will shape the world
in a positive way
I'd like to highlight a couple of key
themes
here so we both the US and Japan are
living in a time of Rapid change where
the following are all
increasing aging populations declining
birth
rates labor shortages economic
stagnation climate change geopolitical
tensions rapid digital
transformation and a need to Foster
creativity and critical thinking among
our employees and our youth over the
course of the day we explored some of
these challenges and
opportunities aiming to build innovative
solutions and build lasting
Partnerships the goal of the event was
simple yet powerful to inspire new
thinking spark meaningful
collaborations and provide actionable
insights we wanted to equip you with the
tools knowledge and connections to drive
progress in your respective companies
and
organizations some of the topics we
touched upon were Global Environmental
challenges sustainable energy
systems engineering materials from
architected materials with novel
properties to bioinspired
Services machine learning AI photonic
Computing and bioengineering
enhancing efficiencies productivity and
scalability in fields such as energy
health care and
Manufacturing developing Innovative biom
materials and Technologies for
biomanufacturing medical devices and
Drug
delivery you heard about improving
efficiencies in various industrial and
technological
processes as well as ensuring that
Innovations can be scaled up for
widespread
use whether it's in manufacturing energy
storing or biomanufacturing
we explore the integration of these
biological systems in engineered
technology such as robotic systems
bioactive materials for medical devices
soft biological materials synthetic
Technologies for Health Care safety and
The Human
Experience several talks discussed
Innovations and
Manufacturing adoption of new
technologies and Workforce practices
that drive competitive
advantages many of the talks emphasized
circular economy principles designing
systems that produce products that
minimize waste and maximize the ReUse of
resources this includes closed loop
systems in energy manufacturing and
chemical
production as well as technologies that
enhance supply chain resiliency and
reduce environmental
impact but most importantly we recognize
each one of you here
today as a vital part of this community
whether you're a seasoned professional
or just starting your career your
knowledge and perspectives are what
makes this conference truly
special once again thank you this is a
time to learn grow and more most
importantly connect with each other I'm
excited to for what's ahead and
confident that we will create these
symbiotic Innovation ecosystems thank
you very much