yeah great uh we're going to get started
in just a second um thanks for coming so
uh I just want to introduce roit uh
who's going to give a talk on pricing
for preservation uh designing network
based incentives for sustainable
for thanks thanks Aaron uh so this is
basically joint work with my Pi
Professor sa hamim here in litz uh so
let me begin with some motivation so the
conversion of tropical forests into
agricultural plantations especially when
done unsustainably is responsible for
massive greenhouse gas emissions right
uh especially over the recent years this
has happened but this is the
Environmental side of the story and
there is also an economic angle to it it
has been found that uh by reducing the
prices of forest Commodities it is
possible to reduce the forest loss as
measured in the number of hectares of
forest lost to uh cons to agricultural
plantations it is able we are able to
reduce this Forest loss by reducing the
prices of forest Commodities so that is
good news but if you go on reducing the
prices of agricultural Commodities then
that is bound to hurt the livelihoods of
the producers of these Commodities right
so that takes us to the key challenge as
identified by the center for
international Forest research which is
to uh reduce the total output of carbon
emissions and greenhouse gas emissions
in a manner that does not compromise on
the economic well-being or stability of
the deforesting entities which are the
producers of these Forest Commodities
basically so basically it seeks to
balance an environmental objective with
an economic objective and there are many
policies that have already attempted to
address this challenge in many ways but
they all have a common shortcoming which
is that they do not account for
interactions between the producers of
these Forest Commodities or what we call
synergistic interactions which are
basically interactions that take take
the form of uh knowledge sharing sharing
common Transportation routs uh exchange
of farming equipment and so on and they
are aimed at enhancing the agricultural
yield of the of the uh plantation owners
and the cultivators but in the process
they also end up increasing the
prevalence of deforestation right when
the cultivators get together and uh make
their agricultural activities more
effective then it versin deforestation
so uh the effects of these interactions
on the deforestation rates are not taken
into account by existing policies which
is something that we tried to address
through this work
so basically we need policies that
balance environmental and economic goals
while explicitly accounting for these
interactions between
cultivators so uh we model the problem
as follows we have a network of n agents
Each of which is a cultivator right uh
and the network is represented by a
Sorry by a by an undirected graph which
is uh a graph with an adjacency Matrix G
which is non- negative and uh what this
graph means is that if two or more
agents are adjacent to each other in the
in the network then it means that those
two agents do collaborate with each
other to enhance their agricultural
yield and the the structure of this
strategic interaction Network depends on
both the geography of the plantations uh
of the Agricultural plantations that
they manage as well as the ownership
structure of these plantations
then uh the agents engage in a
combination of two possible activities
activity a is called sustainable
agriculture which is basically the set
of all the forest commodity production
activities that uh do not encroach on
protected forests and they also do not
involve unsustainable practices like
clearing pet swamps and U activities
that send out a lot of carbon into the
atmosphere those are not done in
activity a where whereas activity B is
what we call unsustainable Agriculture
and it refers to the collection of all
tasks agricultural tasks that encroach
upon protected forest or result in a lot
of carbon emissions basically then uh
the agent's goal is to perform the
activities in such a way that it
maximizes their profits their individual
profits okay and I'm going to talk more
about the payoffs in uh more detail in
the coming slides I'll describe the
utility structure in detail and our
contribution here is that we design
price shaping policies or policies that
alter the prices of sustainable Goods
which are a result of activity a and
unsustainable Goods which are a result
of activity B so that uh we can shape
the incentives of the agents to maximize
what we call welfare which is the sum
total of all the agents payoffs uh which
is a total measure of well-being in the
network while limiting the total
unsustainable effort right while making
sure that the aggregate unsustainable
effort is below a certain upper bound
which I will explain and these policies
take the form of premiums and penalties
premiums are basically monetary rewards
for sustainable production and you can
think of Premium as a quantity that gets
added to the prices of sustainable
products and penalties are the opposite
they are uh quantities or their amounts
of money that uh get effectively they
get subtracted from the prices of
unsustainable products right so
penalties for unsustainable production
and premiums for sustainable production
and an example comes from European
Union's deforestation regulation which
basically uses these pre premiums and
penalties to effectively uh make sure
that no uh no unsustainable product get
gets traded from tropical countries into
the European
Union uh and before I make the problem
more precise I should mention that this
work of ours is related to three bodies
of literature one of which focuses uh
primarily on uh modeling interactions
between cultivators in the in the
context of forest management which is
the top set of works there's not a lot
of those then there is a set of works
that focuses heavily on sustainable
Forest management but does not really uh
focus on the interaction between the
cultivators right so it does not use any
tools from Game Theory and there is then
a body of work works that focuses on U
the problem of intervention design or
policy design in a broad sense in
Network games so it's more of game
theory and network analysis literature
uh but does not really necessarily
concern Forest management so our work is
the first to lie at this intersection
because we we uh propose a network game
model uh using which we develop some uh
policies uh meaning premiums and
penalties or their combinations for
sustainable Forest management so in some
sense our work combines all the three
and it also shows how tools from Game
Theory and optimization and also network
analysis can be used to evolve such uh
policies in an effective
manner uh so now let me give you some
more details about the utility structure
and the coupling between the two
activities a which is sustainable
agriculture and activity B which is the
bad activity which is unsustainable
agriculture basically uh but yeah please
feel free to stop me if you have any
questions at any point
uh so when you think of rewards the
first thing that comes to your mind is
the profits obtained on selling uh the
the products right whether they are
sustainable or unsustainable it doesn't
matter the first component of the
utility is the uh monetary payoff And We
additionally also incorporate U the the
aspect of diminishing returns which
means uh if the if the cultivators overe
exploit their labor and resources then
it is bound to cause uh uh cause a
reduction in the rate at which the
reward increases in the effort which we
call diminishing returns so these two U
aspects are incorporated into two terms
very specifically in this utility
function uh which is describing the
utility of agent I or cultivator I
through activity a which is sustainable
agriculture right so this is the payoff
of a agent I if the agent uh only
produces sustainable goods and not
unsustainable Goods similarly uh if the
agent were to produce only unsustainable
Goods then their payoff would be uib
right it has the same structure as UIA
then you might imagine that an agent
that produces both sustainable and
unsustainable goods for whatever reason
gets a total payoff that is just the sum
of their individual payoffs where uh
yeah sorry uh I think I I should mention
here that P stands for prices and X
stands for the volume of the produce
right so Pia stands for the uh per unit
price of uh the quantity of sustainable
goods and uh xia is the volume or the
number of units of sustainable Goods
similarly pib is the price per unit of
unsustainable goods and xib is the
number of units of unsustainable Goods
produced yeah so when you add
sorry when you per when when you
consider an agent that performs both
activities A and B then you might
imagine their total utility to be just
the sum of the individual utilities but
that is not true because there is a
coupling between the two activities okay
so this particular term is what we call
substitutability it basically uh
quantifies the extent to which one
activity substitutes for the other and
this happens when the agent uh divides
their effort e and labor between the two
activities invariably causing some of
the effort to be transferred from one
activity to another right because if the
agent is really trying hard to perform
both the activities it's not possible
because the agent has bounded a limited
amount of Labor and resources so some of
the uh labor is bound uh to be
transferred from one activity to another
and that the loss in uh the the loss of
utility from this division of effort and
labor is what we call substitutability
and this by the way is not a game
because so far this agent has not
started interacting with others so now
let us incorporate the effects of
interactions of the agents over a
network okay so the first two uh terms
are basically uh terms that capture the
effects of within activity or intra
activity interactions so interactions
between the agents that are both
involved either in activity a or agents
that are both involved in activity B but
not uh this does not account for
interactions across the two activities
so how do we do that we uh incorporate
two additional terms that take into
account the uh utilities resulting from
the utility gains resulting from the
interactions of the agents across the
two activities so you can think of this
as uh some
cultivator uh using their Plantation to
mainly produce sustainable goods and a
neighboring cultivator mainly producing
unsustainable goods and the two agents
if they interact with each other by
sharing farming equipment or using
common Transportation routes then their
payoffs will increase by these amounts
okay I'm not going into too much details
since we don't have much time so the
effect of the intra activity
interactions on the utility is what we
call interactivity Network effect and
it's basically Quantified by this
parameter Delta you know this is like
the essence of both the terms of there
and the effect of the Cross activity
interactions on the utility which is the
utility gain on interacting with people
who are not like you who are in the
opposite activity that's called the
cross activity Network effect now uh the
question is how do we exploit this
complex utility structure to design
policies that uh reduce the incentive
for unsustainable production because our
ultimate goal is to improve the
well-being without uh while you know
without letting the total amount of
unsustainable production in the network
exceed a certain upper bound which we
are going to Define so how do we make
sure to disincentivize activity P one
way to do that would be to Simply raise
the prices of sustainable Goods right
but that is not guaranteed to work
because there is a transfer of incentive
that takes place from the good activity
to the bad activity right from activity
a to activity B through the cross
activity Network effect so it's possible
that increasing the prices of
sustainable Goods is also going to uh
increase the total incentive for
unsustainable production which is not
something we want right uh in particular
it can be found that on raising the
prices of sustainable Goods so Pi
basically stands for prices of
sustainable Goods the interactivity and
cross activity interactions will have an
opposing effect on the unsustainable
effort levels and uh whether the
unsustainable effort levels go down or
go or the increase right whether they
decrease or increase totally will depend
on which of these two opposing effects
uh dominates the other and the answer to
that question comes from our first main
result so this result says that uh if
the cross activity effect parameter is
weaker than is less than the product of
the substitutability and the intra
activity effect parameter which
effectively means that uh the cross
activity interactions are dominated by
the interactivity interaction which
means they're quite weak in that case we
uh we can say that our intuition Works
which means that the total amount of
unsustainable effort or production in
the network will decrease with the
sustainable good prices regardless of
the structure of the network so no
matter how the network looks in this
case we can uh blindly increase the
prices of sustainable Goods if we want
to Simply decrease the total level of
unsustainable activity in the network
workor however if the cross activity
effect parameter is violating this
inequality and uh in particular if it is
uh very strong uh as Quantified by this
inequality which essentially means that
the cross activity interactions are
dominating the interactivity
interactions as shown in this figure
then in this case the total amount of
unsustainable effort or production will
actually increase rather than decrease
with the prices of sustainable Goods
meaning if you uh give sustain if you
offer sustainability
premiums uh to raise the prices of
sustainable Goods then that will not
only increase the incentive for
sustainable production but it will also
increase the incentive for unsustainable
production and our premiums will
backfire they will make the situation
worse from an environmental Viewpoint
and this will happen regardless of the
structure of the network no matter how
what the network looks like or no matter
what the adjacency Matrix looks like
this will happen then there is an
intermediate case when the cross
activity effect is uh neither here nor
there and we cannot really compare it
very well with the interactivity effect
and in this case we cannot say much but
we can still say that there will exist
one particular topology or connectivity
pattern of the Strategic interaction
Network for which uh giving premiums or
increasing the prices of sustainable
Goods is going to again backfire it's
going to increase the total
unsustainable effort right so the
takeaway here is that to suppress the
total amount of unsustainable production
in the network it is not only sufficient
but it is also necessary to eliminate or
at least limit the cross activity
interactions the covert interactions
that take place between sustainable and
unsustainable plantations now in reality
what happens is the sustainable
plantations typically belong to U listed
companies and well reputed companies
that have uh obtained sustainability
certification from um auditing
organizations like the round table on
sustainable palm oil whereas
unsustainable plantations typically
belong to Shadow companies or companies
that are not listed anywhere and they
operate illegally and covertly under the
protection of listed companies so it is
absolutely essential to detect and
thwart the illegal and C operations of
the Shadow companies in order to make
sure that sustainability premiums are
actually helping rather than hurting the
cause of the environment so uh yeah
please please let me know if you have
any questions because I think uh at this
point I should answer any
questions uh that you may have and how
much time do we have 5 minutes oh well
actually about 8 minutes okay cool so
moving on uh
we are going to design policies that
will involve a combination of premiums
and penalties but premiums which means
raises to the prices of sustainable
Goods these are going to be an important
part of our policies and to make sure
that these sustainability premiums work
in our policies we are going to assume
that cross activity interactions may
exist but they are weak enough they are
dominated by interactivity interactions
right so that's the uh so in other words
we are assuming that these inter actions
between the uh listed companies and
Shadow companies are already being
detected and
suppressed so now with that background
let us uh introduce the intervention
design problem which is basically the
policy design problem so like I said our
goal is to maximize the total well-being
of the network which we call welfare at
the Nash equilibrium of the game which
we can prove to be unique but that's not
really the focus of this talk so
basically maximizing equilibrium welfare
while keeping a cap on the total amount
of unsustainable production in the
network right so here for for this uh
for the uh purpose of this slide let us
Focus only on premiums and let's not
focus on penalties we'll introduce
penalties later so if we are focusing
only on premiums which this means that
we are not changing the prices of
unsustainable Goods because we are not
imposing any penalties all we are doing
is we are making the decision VAR ables
the prices of sustainable Goods right we
are only increasing the prices of
sustainable Goods not changing
unsustainable good prices so the
objective function is the sum of all the
agents equilibrium utilities which is
the total
welfare the the first constraint is the
tolerance constraint on the total
unsustainable production right it says
that the sum total of all the agents
unsustainable effort levels at
equilibrium should be no more uh than a
certain predefined quantity uh and I
should I mean just to put things into
symbols the welfare expression is the
sum of all utilities which depends on a
lot of different quantities and the
tolerance constraint looks like that
because it's the left hand side is a sum
of all unsustainable effort levels now
the next constraint is just saying that
the prices of sustainable Goods after
your policy is implemented should be
greater not less than the uh prices
before your policy was implemented right
because it does not make sense to reduce
the incentive for sustainable production
so in other words this is a non-
negative premiums constraint the
sustainability premium should be non-
negative and in symbols it looks like
that where PA is basically the prices of
sustainable Goods so remember that a
stands for sustainable production and
zero here just stands for the
pre-intervention scenario which means
the scenario before the policy was
implemented initial case then uh the
last constraint is just saying that you
cannot go on uh increasing the prices of
sustainable Goods arbitrarily there will
be a finite budget uh and this budget is
coming from what we call maximum
feasible prices so basically this last
constraint is just a budget constraint
and in symbols it looks like that where
pmax is the upper bound on the prices of
sustainable Goods now uh at this point I
I should mention that this intervention
this optimization problem that we have
formulated is not restricted to the
context of forest management u in any
economic context where we would like to
suppress a harmful activity and uh you
know promote a desirable activity uh in
a manner that does not really hurt the
well-being of the stakeholders that are
involved in the activities uh even if
the stakeholders are interacting over a
network we we can use this optimization
setup for example in the context of uh
social media platforms that generate a
lot of content some of which can be true
genuine news or um you know fact checked
information the other the bad activity
can be the production of fake news or
misinformation the good activity can
also be the uh production of consumable
content that is safe you know in terms
of its non- extremism and the bad
activity can be the production of very
sensitive and extremist content we could
also think of u a context uh involving
the Pharma industry where the good
activity can be thought of as uh produ
the production of acceptable and drugs
that are safe to consume whereas the bad
activity becomes the production of
adulterated medicines and in all these
cases the uh the stakeholders can be
interacting with each other in the case
of uh platforms the content generators
might interact with each other and in
the case of Pharma companies we know
that these companies often collaborate
with each other to produce drugs so
Network interactions are present and
this optimization problem is of value
now the technical challenges here are
that this game is not super modular
which uh which basically means that the
utilities are not necessarily increasing
in the effort levels in a loose sense in
every agent's effort levels I mean then
the effort levels have to be non-
negative which means that non- interior
equilibria are possible I'm just rushing
through this part because I want to
focus on the main results uh and the
problem most important the problem is a
non-convex optimization problem it is a
problem in which the objective function
is a concave function not a convex
function so uh the main Insight that we
use here is that the welfare which is
our objective function it is increasing
in two quantities it is increasing in
the sum of the prices of sustainable and
unsustainable Goods taken per unit and
it's also increasing the in the
magnitude of the difference between the
two prices now the sum of the two prices
is the total incentive for production
and it makes sense that if the total
incentive for production goes up then
the total reward that is earned by the
agents for the same level of effort will
go up and that's why it makes sense for
welfare to be increasing in the total
incentive right the greater the total
incentive the better but the incentive
skew also matters why because the
greater the difference between the two
prices the prices of sustainable goods
and those of unsustainable Goods the
more uh the more strongly in lined the
agents will be towards one of the two
activities right and uh then their
division of effort and labor will be
minimal they'll concentrate their effort
on one activity and the uh utility loss
due to substitutability will go down
right so so so the welfare also turns
out to be increasing in the incentive
skew and uh then U yeah I think uh for
lack of time I I'm just going to go to
the main result so suppose we are trying
to solve the problem that described when
we do not have enough budget when uh
there is no room or very little room for
increasing the prices of sustainable
Goods then what do we do we basically
impose penalties for unsustainable
production and convert those penalties
into premiums for sustainable production
right so by penalties what I mean is
reducing the prices of unsustainable
Goods by a quantity row which is the
penalty and adding that row to the price
prices of sustainable Goods so
essentially we are just talking about a
transfer of incentives from activity B
the bad activity to the good activity
right so this obviously should preserve
the total incentive for production right
because there's only a transfer of
incentive that we are doing over here we
are not reducing the incentive and uh
does it the now the question is does it
increase the second important quantity
which is incentive Q does it do that or
not so it turns out that if we uh
transfer enough from B to a which means
if our penalty is large enough and uh if
our budget that we pour into the system
externally which uh which you know
contributes to the incentive for
activity a if that is also large enough
which precisely means that if the sum of
the penalty and half the budget is large
enough to satisfy a certain inequality
then it means that the penalties and
budget are jointly sufficient to
increase the incentive skew and the
result here is that if this inequality
holds then uh the the budget and the
penalty are together sufficient enough
to make sure that the most extreme
policy or the policy that imposes the
maximum feasible penalty and also uh
Awards the maximum feasible premium for
sustainable production that is the
policy that Max maximizes welfare and
also reduces all the agents individual
unsustainable effort levels while
preserving individual utility so this is
something uh so there are three things
that we are talking about here the first
thing is that uh we have a policy that
is maximizing our objective function
which is welfare which is the well-being
of the network which is what we wanted
then the second thing is that every
agent's individual unsustainable effort
levels are going down right uh they are
being minimized which is is also
something that we wanted because we
wanted the total unsustainable effort to
remain remain below uh predefined
tolerance and it is giving us something
more than we asked for which is that it
is preserving every preserving or
increasing every agent's individual
utility so remember that the welfare is
the sum of all the agents utilities
right it is the sum it is not any one
agent utility so it is possible for the
sum of all the utilities to increase at
the expense of a few agents individual
utilities right it is in the in theory
it is possible but this result is saying
that that won't happen no agent will
lose out in terms of their individual
payoffs so basically we are able to
increase the total well-being of the
network without hurting any individual
agent that's the takeaway so I think uh
I should quickly summarize uh what what
is the time uh a little bit over time so
uh yeah I think I'll just wrap up in one
minute so basically we uh have we have
some empirical results that we uh uh
that we obtained on validating our
theory on some real data sets obtained
from the plantation networks of
Indonesia as well as the price data
associated with certified sustainable
palm oil and crude palm oil which are
which basically correspond to
sustainable products and unsustainable
products in our context and uh we we
observe an improvement in both the
welfare the predicted welfare I should
say and the predicted reduction in
unsustainable effort uh as predicted by
uh our model so the the empirical
results in some sense validate our
Theory and the conclusion is uh and then
we have our policy recommendations which
basically discriminate on the basis of
whether the budget and the penalty are
together enough or not and uh if so if
they are together jointly sufficient
then basically we need to go for a
certain kind of policies if they are
together jointly insufficient then we
need to go for a different kind of
policies and the conclusion is that the
first result was that we absolutely need
to suppress the covert interactions
between sustainable plantations and
unsustainable plantations otherwise our
sustainability premiums will backfire
and the second uh point is that the
redistribution of prices which is
basically the imposing penalties and
converting those penalties into premiums
that improves welfare and reduces
unsustainable efforts without hurting
any agent individually even if the
external budget for price increases is
zero right even if we are not pouring
any external money from outside into the
system so this has implications for uh
Partnerships in other economic context
as well wherever we need to uh promote
sustainability without hurting the
overall well-being of the participants
this uh optimization framework should be
of value so thank you very
[Applause]
much uh um we're a bit over time so if
anyone has to leave that's fine but
otherwise feel free to ask
questions has any
questions yes please how do you come up
with in your Indonesia example with the
values of the of the interaction
coefficients and thanks yeah that's
that's actually a good question so yeah
so these interaction coefficients you
are absolutely right that uh we do not
yet have a very rigorous method of
coming up with these values but we
tested these uh I mean you we basically
ran our empirical analysis with a range
of values and over here we are just
displaying the results corresponding to
a particular choice of values uh just to
you know clearly show all the
qualitative results but uh but the
results are the you know qualitatively
the results are not really dependent on
the values of those quantities they
continue to hold for a range of values
meaning our policies will promise a
certain level of welfare Improvement and
a certain reduction in total
unsustainable effort regardless of the
value of those
parameters
yeah you you have a question or yeah
yeah sure um so is there uh literature I
me prior literature on incentive design
on networks with synergistic interaction
so I guess um yeah there is uh quite a
bit of literature on Intervention design
uh in Network games with synergistic
interactions such as the paper by core
and zo which is basically Ryan core and
junji Zoo it was published in games and
economic behavior uh just 2 years ago
but this is the first time that uh
anyone has done inter intervention
design on coupled activity Network game
so all the previous Works focus on the
case of just one activity and uh well
actually uh just just a minute yeah
sorry uh cor andu is uh the the first
work that focuses on coupled activi
games but it treats both the activities
in the same way in the sense that either
both the activities are desirable or
both are undesirable it does not really
discriminate between the two activities
so their problem formulation is somewhat
symmetric and easier in some sense to
handle whereas ours is a little
asymmetric over here yeah yeah but
that's a good
question yes please but assuming you
know the T the interaction coefficient
like wouldn't it make sense to have um
penalties and and and premiums that also
depend on interaction coefficient as in
you know I am sustainable but I I I keep
interacting with other guys that are not
sustainable so why do I get the same
premium as others that like stick to to
to collaborations with other sustainable
guys uh yeah that's a valard point so
what happens is uh when the when your
interactions with unsustainable guys so
suppose you are a sustainable agent and
your
interaction with those who are too much
into unsustainable production if the
interaction is very high then it means
that the cross activity interactions are
very high and then premiums no longer
work you absolutely have to impose
penalties right but but uh like I said
we are focusing primarily on the case in
which the cross activity interactions or
you know the interactions between
sustainable producers and unsustainable
producers are being uh suppressed to a
level where the problem becomes more
manageable so let me show you that yeah
basically we are we are assuming that
the inactivity interactions are much
stronger than the cross activated
interactions for all our results but
you're right that in general the
solution could depend on the interaction
parameters
absolutely
yes yes please you that individual
not
down oh how did we ensure yeah uh
so the reason is basically U so you're
talking I think you're talking about
this
uh you're talking about this part really
right uh yeah so yeah it's a good
question we we basically uh trade these
incentive skes and so so I should just
briefly go back to the previous slide
and remind you that U that the welfare
is increasing in these two quantities
right now these two quantities are
actually vectors they are not scalars
and the length of these vectors is equal
to the number of Agents so basically
every agent has a total incentive for
production and a total um not total but
a skew or a bias uh in incentive towards
one of the two activ so basically we we
were able to prove that uh if this if
this budget penalty condition holds then
uh the total incentive of every agent
will be preserved and the incentive skew
of every agent goes up so so that's how
we were able to show that no agent
individual utility goes down so it's
more of a scalar analysis at that point
but uh but yeah it also involves a lot
of Matrix analysis and up to a certain
point in the in the proof but basically
Bally the incentive skewes and the total
incentives do not change across all the
agents they either decrease sorry they
either increase or remain the same uh
and this statement is true for every
agent individually that's how it works
yeah yeah but that's a good
point very well if there are no other
questions let's thank our speaker again
yes thank you so much thanks a lot thank
you thanks
thanks for your
help yeah
the thanks for the questions