Yeah, thank you. Thank you for the
introduction, Dvara, and thank you for
having me here and thanks to everyone
for coming to my talk. Um, so today,
yeah, I would like to talk to you about
this uh local to global approach we
developed uh for uh designing policies
for decision- making problems in large
case networks. Um so this talk is based
on a sequence of papers we wrote uh
during the past two or three years uh
mainly led by my PhD student Eigger at
CMU and in collaboration with uh Xang
who is like undergraduate student from
Chinua and our collaborators Xiaomi and
Yud from Wic. Okay. Um so I'm quite
excited about like what we were able to
achieve uh through this framework. Um so
we were able to design policies that are
are different from like the traditional
class of policies and which leads to the
removal of a long-standing barrier and
also like our approach is quite
generalizable. It can handle like a
strong heterogeneity in the system which
which is usually a challenge for
traditional methods. Okay. Um so uh so
yeah let me get started. Um so uh yeah
feel free to ask questions any any time
and um if you don't ask questions I may
ask you questions instead okay so be
prepared okay um so large networks or
large stoastic systems um they arise
from a lot of uh applications in
practice um so because we are living in
this era of unprecedented scale uh
everything is large scale for example if
you think about communication systems um
is larger than ever because of the
increasing number of smart devices,
personal devices and so on. And modern
computing systems are massive because
they need to uh support the um
staggering need from computation
especially in AI and machine learning
applications and uh um everyone almost
everyone is on uh a social network and
uh also like uh service platforms like
rice sharing systems um provide like um
a lot of service like for example I
think uh for the right sharing service
in Austin every day they provide more
than 100,000 rice. Okay. Um so those all
of those are pretty large systems and
the scale makes it tricky uh to uh
understand the dynamics in those systems
and design uh policies for decision
decision making in those systems. Um
however fortunately most of those like
practical problems are not like that
adversarial. they usually have certain
structure that can help break the curse
of dimensionality. Um so for example low
rank structures are uh explored a lot or
like uh sometimes like uh uh when you
model those as a queueing problem with
many cues there are like state
aggregation so you can use like
techniques like a mean field analysis or
diffusion approximation and so on. Okay.
Um so in our work uh we would like to
advocate this perspective that you
should make use of the independent
structure in those systems. So um this
is like this is like a common idea like
that shows up in many problems, many
approaches, many areas. Um but we just
found it like this the following view
very informative and it forms the basis
of our approach. So basically it's a
very simple principle. If you have like
a system that has n components but if
they were totally completely independent
then you can just like separate them and
then it becomes in separate problems you
can solve them individually and you are
not subject to like any complexity
exponential or anything. Okay. Um of
course like all those problems things
are not completely independent. um but
still there's certain independence going
on which still allows like the
decomposition in some form. Okay. So let
me give you some examples about this
independent structure. Um so the first
example comes from scheduling for uh
computing systems. So you have like a
lot of servers and nowadays the like the
jobs come in and each job you can think
of it as a virtual machine or it's
called a container job. So basically it
requires a certain amount of uh
resources like from different types. Uh
so for simplicity I'm just illustrating
like maybe onedimensional uh
requirement. You can think of it as the
number of CPU cores for example and then
you look at all the servers you decide
where you want to schedule this job.
Okay. Um so for this problem um like
yeah then the servers has this capacity
and they have jobs have resource
requirement and then um you need to be
subject to the resource capacity
constraint. Um so for this problem it
has like uh the compon each component
here is a server um and it has many
servers. So for each component the state
is like the kind of jobs is running um
so like the resource usage from
different jobs. Okay. And this state
could change, right? Like the user who
submits this uh uh job could change the
way they use this like virtual machine
like maybe they go from like intensive
usage to like like lower intensive like
uh usage. So the state could change.
Okay. And then like if you think about
the state transitions here, if you know
the states of all the servers and uh
before the next job comes in then the
transitions from different servers are
independent because like the jobs like
running on one server the their their
behavior is determined by the users and
they are kind of just separate from the
jobs on another server. Okay. So then
like the station the transitions here
are independent from each other. Okay.
Um is that like reasonable like Okay.
Yeah. You it you look like you have a
questionual
coupling happening in terms of how job
allocation is done.
>> Yes. Yes.
>> And then there is a sort of servicing of
each of the queue that's happening.
>> So yeah. So here there's no queue. It's
just like the job like you hosted the
job on the server. The job disappear or
job remain dead?
>> Job could disappear. The job could
remain there and change like maybe at
this moment I need one CPU core but the
next moment I need two CPU cores. It
could change state.
>> What do you want us to agree right now
on this slide?
>> The transitions given the job states
before the next arrival happening are
independent from each other for across
servers. That's what I'm trying to like
convey. And and there is it's it's
basically you're saying that's a
physics.
>> Yeah, that's physics. Yeah, that's just
because they're separate. Yeah. Yeah.
It's reason to model it that way. Yeah.
Okay.
Okay. Cool. Um so yeah. So let let's
look at the next example that comes from
this right sharing application. Um so
here you can think of each car as a
component and then like if you look at
the state it's basically where it is
right now and uh whether it's serving
like a customer or not and where this
customer is going. Okay. So then like
given their current states before like
you make any other like decisions then
each car's behavior is kind of
independent from another car right they
just go on their different route and
assume there's like no strong contection
or anything. So it's reasonable to
assume they're uh they're independent
from each other
>> and with the assumption that they are
not the primary reasons why contections
are happening in the system.
>> Yes. Yeah. Let's assume that. Yeah.
Maybe one way to think about where where
this would break down would be if I
think of the state as also capturing the
location of different drivers and I
incentivize some drivers to be
positioned somewhere else but other
drivers I don't incentivize to
>> and then um that no longer
>> that actually doesn't break this because
like I'm deliberately saying the
transitions are independent given their
current state and before you or like
given the decisions you've already made
like you could look at all the cars and
decide okay yeah so yeah in that way
yeah so in that way you can see that
like there's evolutions are definitely
not independent because whenever you
make a decision you look at all the car
states ideally and then like you make
the decision so that like couples the
state dynamics together but I'm the only
thing I'm pointing out here is like the
transitions are independent from each
other given the state given the current
decisions. Okay. Okay. So I I'll make
this more precise. Uh but this is like a
high level like where the independence
could arise and then like um based on
this kind of independence this like a
partial independence structure. Um we
were able to like uh think about like
come up with this approach that we call
local to global. Um so here is just a a
high level description of it. Um so our
goal is to design a decision making
policy that like optimizes certain
performance and then like it basically
has three steps. First we want to
decompose the system and um we cannot
decompose the original version of the
system because like it's not totally
independent but we may come up with some
average version of it that's
decomposible. Okay. Um uh then like next
one is like after we decompose it we
have separate problems we solve each one
we have like individual policy and then
like uh in the last step we try to piece
together all those policies to form a
valid policy for the overall problem
with the performance guarantee. Okay. So
it's very abstract right now but I'm
going to go through some concrete
problems. Okay. Okay. So um so uh yeah
this is just like u a list of the
problems we have uh worked out using
this approach. Uh first one is this like
beam packing problem uh like described
in earlier slide and with this approach
we were able to uh capture the resource
like usage fluctuation uh uh through uh
across time and this was like a main
reason for a low utilization of
scheduling in some of the uh computing
systems and we were able to capture that
and work out like optimal asympto
optimal policy that maximizes
utilization of servers and then like we
have this sequence of work on the
so-called resistant problem and uh this
is one I'm going to focus on uh in the
next part okay and u then like there's a
generalization of the resided problem um
uh it's called a weekly coupled MDP and
I'm going to also briefly mention this
so I'm going to focus on this and I'm
going to briefly mention this Okay.
Okay. So maybe yeah. Now let me get into
this resist bandit problem and things
will become more concrete. Okay. So this
is a very classical problem and uh uh
but uh first a little bit of disclaimer
here because many people are more
familiar with the stas multiarm vended
problem. So in this problem you have n
arms. Each arm doesn't have any state or
anything. It's just you pull it. gives
you a reward coming from an unknown
reward distribution. And then your goal
is to try to kind of try different
rewards, learn their uh uh expected
reward, try different arms, learn their
expected reward, and try to pull the
best arm as much as possible. So for
this problem, it's more like a learning
problem. There's this trade-off between
exploration and exploitation. Okay. Uh
so the restless bendy problem is a
little bit different. There's some
connection, but I'm not going into that.
Uh so it's also called a marovian
multi-armmed dependent problem. So for
each arm here it c it has a state and uh
um when you pull it it will have a state
transition following certain transition
probabilities and if you don't pull it
it can still transit and following maybe
a different set of probability
distributions. Okay. And we assume so
the state could be something like I'm
just using numbers to indicate the state
and we assume that we know like the
transition kernels and the reward
parameters. Oh by the way each arm
generates a reward depending on its
current state and whether you pull it or
not. Okay. And then your goal is still
to like try to maximize reward but under
known like problem parameters. So this
is at least like oh another difference
is like you can usually pull a fraction
of the arms rather than just one arm.
Okay. So let's say like alpha is a
fraction. Okay. Uh so for this problem
as at least so far it is a planning
algorithm like a planning problem or
like a computational problem. You are
given all the parameters. They're just
just trying to compute like a policy uh
near optimal policy
>> here like there where it's a reward is
you keep pulling the same arm over and
over again ideally if you figure it out.
>> Mhm. Yeah.
>> You're sort of depending on what you
pull transition would happen and that
transition would lead to different
future reward. So now you're worried
about immediate reward or some kind of a
discounted.
>> Yeah. Right. So yeah I'm going to make
it clearer. Okay. we are actually going
to use the average reward criteria.
Okay. Yeah. But right like this is the
thing you are trying to figure out.
Okay. Um okay. So um yeah so for this
problem like I said like uh oh yeah let
me make it more precise. So for each arm
you can think of each arm itself as a
mark of decision process. It has a state
space uh which let's assume is finite
and then like the action space is binary
because you either pull it or not pull
it. Okay. Uh so the active means
pulling, passive means not pulling and
then we have like a two sets of
transition probabilities based on the
action. Okay, it's called restless
because even if you don't pull it, it
could still have like a uh state
transitions. Okay, and then there's a
reward function uh of state and action.
And then like our goal is to maximize
the long-term average total reward
reward from all the arms. Okay.
>> So for all the arms it's the same
transition problem.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Thank you. Yeah. Let's right
now they all have the share the same set
of parameters. Okay. It's a homogeneous
ARM problem. Okay. Yeah.
>> Does the theory depend on like the
decoupling of the mark kernels? So like
if your state depends on the states of
the other arms, does that affect things?
>> Oh yeah. Uh sorry I forgot to mention
like the state transitions are
independent across the different arms.
So given the current state and current
action the state transitions are
independent. Yeah. Okay. But when you
make this decision you would look at
like all the arm states your policy is
basically mapping that comes from that
that maps like a joint state of all the
arms to like which arms you want to
pull. Okay.
>> Yeah. Uh how do you initialize the
states?
>> Um it doesn't matter much here like
>> kind of distribution right or is a face
>> it does yeah it could either way it
doesn't matter that much.
>> How do policy consider stoastic in the
policy? Um so theoretically speaking you
could have you like if you just think
about the set of marovian policies it
could contain the optimal policy
marovian and the stationary policy but
we will see that like what our policy
looks like okay
>> so effectively you got n independent at
some level MVPs.
>> Mhm.
>> Uh and then sort of thing that couples
here is what fraction of things that you
can activate at any given point.
>> Yes. Exactly.
>> Make that as a function of sort of
depending on what state spaces.
>> Right. Right. Yeah. I'm going to give an
example here. Okay. So to put to make
this more concrete for everybody. Okay.
So Oh yeah. Alpha N is called the
budget. Okay. Uh so I'm going to give a
concrete example. Okay. For everybody to
think about. Um so for this problem for
every every arm it has like eight
states. Okay. So if you are a professor,
you can think of each arm as one of your
PhD students. Okay? [laughter] And if
you're a student, just pretend you are
the professor and think about all your
students. Okay? And this zero to seven
like they're like their academic
maturity or something. Okay? And then
like your job is to move students from
zero to seven basically. And then like
if they go to seven then like uh they
can graduate and that's when you get a
reward and then like you hire a new
student you start over. Okay. So that's
the only time you are going to receive a
reward. Okay. So this is just how the
the example is and then like let's see
how your action could affect that. So
your action could be like the active
action is like I'm going to meet with
this student today. Okay. the inact the
passive one is like I'm not going to
meet with them. Okay. So then like yeah
um so the students are like you can
think of those students with the levels
01 to three as more junior students. So
for them if you meet with them they tend
to like go to the right they tend to
progress. Okay. If you don't meet with
them they tend to like go back. Okay.
However if you look at the senior
students the senior students have like
very very different mindset. um if you
dare to meet with them they are going to
go back okay they don't want like
meetings okay so and uh if you leave
them alone they make good progress and
then like they kind of just graduate
okay and then like your the problem you
are facing every day is like I have
those students there in those days who I
should meet with today okay suppose you
can pick for four out of eight okay so
then like there are many reasonable like
answers like does anyone want to try to
see like what would be a reasonable
answer here just for this given state
like who do you want to pick to meet
with today
I do have three options for you actually
so
>> zero and three ones yeah
>> which ones did you pick
>> zero and three ones
>> zero yeah that's a reasonable answer
okay yeah that makes sense right like it
seems like junior students want more
meetings and there's another answer
which is like this okay uh which means
better because zero cannot go on the
left.
>> Yeah, zero cannot get worse. So you may
want to prioritize one and two. Okay.
And then there's another answer that
looks like this which is a little bit
hard to see where it comes from. Okay.
But it actually comes from our policy.
Okay. Okay. So we'll see like which one
makes more sense later on. Of course
like what you decide to do like at one
moment doesn't matter that much. What
matters more is your policy, right?
Okay. Uh okay. So yeah. So this is like
the example you can keep in your head.
And then for this problem if you think
about the all the end arms together they
form like a giant MDP. This space is the
joint state of all the arms and uh um
yeah so the action space is like also
like alpha n out of n ones. Okay. Um so
uh if you write it out uh just a little
bit notation here. This is like
basically you want to find the policy
pi. This is the state of arm I at time t
under policy pi and this is the action
you take and this is the reward and then
you sum over all the rewards from all
the arms and then you normalize it by n.
So we are looking at a reward per arm.
Okay. And then this this is a time
average notion. So we are looking at the
average reward problem here. Okay. And
the constraint is every moment of time
you can only pull off any of them. Okay.
Okay. So hopefully this makes like the
setting really clear. Okay. And uh um
then like this problem if you just uh uh
solve it like a straightforwardly then
it's going to be pretty complicated
because of the size of the C space and
action space. Um so what we are going
for is this um this refined goal here
where we want to efficiently compute a
policy that is asymptoically optimal. So
here like uh RNA is the optimal reward
when you have in arms. R&I is like the
reward under your policy. We want the
gap to be to go to zero as you have more
and more arms. Okay. So this gap here is
called optimality gap. Okay. So is the
goal clear to everyone?
Okay. Cool. So then like um let's review
some of the existing approaches and
those approaches are mainly uh um based
on index policies or priority policies
which makes intuitive sense. So what
they do is like basically you assign the
states a priority order and uh this
might be implicitly what you were
thinking when you look at the problem.
So for example, if you come up with a
priority order like this, then like when
you in go to the inarm system, you start
with like all the arms with the high
like whose states are in the highest
priority. For example, here is the state
one. So you pull those arms and then you
get to the next priority and so on until
you use like your off uh budget. So in
this case, the next priority is two. you
pull one of them and uh you don't have
any budget to pull the other one but you
just stop there. Okay. So this is like a
reasonable answer B like in the previous
slide. Okay. Um so yeah so then like if
you look at those kind of policies um
this one goes back to all the way to uh
this policy called the WTO index which
is one of those like index policies and
people prove that this it is like indeed
asotically optimal uh but with some
assumptions. So here I'm going to
highlight this gap assumption which is
called global attractor property. Okay.
Um so you will see that like for other
policies they require a similar
condition and then like people can also
show that uh the optimality gap can even
be very small uh if you assume more
assumptions but also like a stronger
version of the gap assumption. Okay. So
here I'm only listing like just a couple
of work here but restly spend it has
like a a huge like body of work and um
um just for the flow of the talk I
haven't listed those. Okay. People from
MIT have done foundational work here.
Okay. Okay. So, so for so then the for
if you look at here um then like you can
see that um everyone like all those like
uh guarantees are subject to this gap or
u gap condition. Um so what this
condition is is basically if n is large
then you can use the mean field analysis
that approximates the stoastic system
using a deterministic system that works
like a work uh differential equation in
this case is just discrete time. Okay.
And then like for that like uh
difference equation um you need the
system dynamical system to have a unique
global attractor and that has to be like
a a solution like some like a um uh
optimal distribution okay so that you
need to assume that okay uh so basic but
I wanted to point out that this is a
condition that's a little bit hard to
certify it's kind of hard to verify uh
whether it is satisfied ified like if
you are given the instance okay you can
certify that is not satisfied but it's
hard to certify satisfied okay yeah no
>> maybe a classification so why we care
about the gap with respect to n so n is
the number of the states right
>> oh sorry n is the number of arms
>> yes for example like if I'm a professor
[laughter and clears throat]
>> student is kind of like a fixed for me
when I I'm sorry I just want to know
what's the kind of vacation what I what
I really care is that if I have a small
budget then how much I will do or if the
budget is really large then actually I
can do individually optimization for
each one so that independent what I care
is about if I have a for example if I
have a small kind of budget what is the
gap right
>> so yes so here the setting the
background is like I mentioned at the
beginning you do have a large scale
system. So for example, when you think
about the computing system, you have
like a large number of servers there and
uh uh that is the n here and in the car
routing example each car like uh the
number of cars is the number of like
arms here and uh uh like even like when
n is large your budget is although it's
proportional to n it's kind of big but
still like the alpha there is a limiting
factor that can like uh that is a budget
constraint. So you you don't really like
you cannot afford to use like to pull
all the arms at the same time.
>> For example, like here the C is it the C
depend on alpha or
>> Oh yeah, it could depend on alpha and
even the state space size. Yeah. But
alpha is considered a constant. Yeah.
Okay. So alpha n is the budget. Okay.
Okay. So then like I'm going to also
show you one example like uh to to show
you what happens if this like condition
is not satisfied. Okay. Um so this is a
numerical experiment. The x-axis is the
is the time time horizon and then like
the y or each row here corresponds to
like one state. Okay. Uh so like this is
the previous example where we have eight
states. Okay. And then like the uh
intensity here means like how many AR
what's the fraction of arms in that
state like this is the simulation with
um I've got a lot of arms okay and then
like uh you watch like how so for
example at each time step if you look at
this slice then you'll see like the
distribution uh uh the state
distribution okay and then like you can
look at how it evolves over time and you
may observe that like here like it kind
of just it gets stuck in this same
distribution maybe after like 200
something time slots. Okay. And this
distribution this particular
distribution let me draw it here to to
make it even a little bit clearer. It's
like a a distribution that concentrates
uh just on three states. Okay. And this
is like a bad distribution because
remember we only have reward if you go
from seven to zero. If you don't have
anything uh on seven then you won't be
able to have any reward. Okay. So this
is a um so this shows a case where the
distribution is trapped in this like uh
this distribution under the previous
policy and this is like where the this
one this distribution itself is another
attractor of the problem. Okay. Um and
uh it doesn't satisfy the gap condition.
Okay. Yeah.
>> Question on whether it matters where you
start. Is that is there an
interpretation of that here? So um uh so
yeah I guess and so for this one uh
actually even if you change the star
state it would still like get stuck
there. Uh so we we tried and uh uh
actually here like if you look at here
it's a uniform that is like the optimal
attractor but it's unstable for this
example. Even if you get there you could
like just get out of it. So for this
particular example it doesn't matter.
for some examples it may matter if you
use this policy. Okay.
Okay. So um so yeah so this is the
example and uh uh so then like in our
work uh we basically we have like a
sequence of work. Uh so first we kind of
like uh remove this gap assumption but
we replace it with another assumption
and that assumption is easier to verify
and the previous example you saw
satisfies our assumption but not like
the gap assumption. Okay but then like
later on we actually like totally
removed it. Okay. Um yeah there's like
this small font like
thing here everyone assumes a certain
epiotic and uniting assumption. Okay.
Okay. And then like later on we were
able to make the optimatic gap even
smaller under additional assumptions but
still no gap assumption. Okay. Okay. And
uh here I'm going to focus on basically
this work. U we have a class of policies
here that we designed. Okay. Okay. So
let me uh get started with our approach.
So uh like I described early on uh it
has three steps. The first step is this
decomposition step. If you look at this
is this is the original problem within
arms and what we are going to do is we
are going to relax this condition to a
time average like time average
constraint. Okay. So once we do that
like we can kind of decouple the arms
and basically it becomes like n copies
of the same single armed problem and the
single arm problem you you just have one
arm you have this reward function. The
constraint is like over time you only
pull it for alpha fraction of time.
Okay.
Okay. So this one this problem now like
you have like you decompose this into n
identical copies of this problem and
then like for this problem um next step
is to solve it. It's very easily
solvable. Notice that like there's no n
anywhere. So the complexity doesn't
depend on the number of arms. And then
like you can after you solve oh this is
solvable through a linear program for
example and then like after you solve it
you get a policy for single arm it's
like if I look at the state of single
arm what action should I take okay and
you can prove that this like optimal
value is upper bound on the original
problem. So if you want to upper bound
the optimatic gap you can instead upper
bound like uh this thing with the
optimal reward replaced by like this
upper bound. Okay.
Okay. So now like we have done the local
solution. Uh everything is easy so far.
Uh and that LP is like that's linear
program I mentioned is the same thing
used uh by other policy designs too.
Okay. But the things the thing we do
differently here is we really think
about it as a singlear armed MDP problem
and we have the optimal solution for
that MDP and then like we are going to
use that local solution to construct a
global solution.
>> For example, in your specific example
you gave if alpha is half
>> effectively I sort of in some single arm
01 23. Yeah, I'm going to show you.
>> Yeah, I'm going to show you how it
works. And it's like a something like
what you said. Okay, so we have we have
we call this policy ID policy is one of
the policies in the class of policies we
designed. So we have this single arm
policy and then like for every arm here
we're going to sample action using this
policy. So in this particular example,
this is the previous example. Then like
uh we figured out the optimal single arm
policy. We sampled those actions but
then like they may not be subject to the
they may not satisfy the budget
constraint the hard budget constraint.
Okay. So then what we are going to do is
we want to take the actual actions that
are very close to those ideal actions
but we need a way like to uh to for this
procedure and the particular way we do
this is that we prioritize smaller ARM
ids. So here arm ids are nothing but
those numbers you assign to them
beforehand. Okay, it's kind of arbitrary
but you need to fix them. And once you
fix them, you start from the smallest
ID. You follow this ideal action. Next
one also, next one also here is okay.
Our budget is four. So then we are here.
We are here. And now like we have four
activives like we hit our budget then we
have to set like the rest to be passive.
>> So choosing your choosing IDs rather
than doing at random because you did
consistent randomization across entire
horizon. Yes. Yes. So if you use like a
a complete random like uh type breaking
it won't work. We have like a numerical
uh uh experiments showing that. Okay.
Yeah. Like you said it's because the uh
arms are not consistently like following
this ideal policy. Okay. Okay. Yeah. So
this is uh Yeah. So it's a very it's a
very simple policy here. It just like it
just works like that. Okay. So now like
uh and the guarantee we have is this
like one over square root of an
optimatic gap that I showed you before.
Okay. So now I want to give you a little
bit of intuition on why it works.
>> Rar so this is deviation.
So I could sort of run the policy
individually and now with this
constraint the implementation for each
arm would deviate a little.
>> And the point is this deviation is
small.
>> Yes. Yes. Yes. And uh you you see how
exactly it goes here. Okay. And it's not
kind of per arm deviation. Okay. So uh
so what happens is like this. Okay. So
let's think about this example and our
budget is half. So we can pull four
arms. Okay. So now like if you think
about the first half of the arms. Okay.
So what do you think will happen to them
if we use our policy? We prioritize the
smaller IDs like what do you think those
arms can do.
So
>> they'll do what of your individual
policy.
>> Yeah. They will just follow the
individual policies. Exactly. Because
there's like nothing constraining them
here, right? So they will just follow
their ideal actions. They follow those
policies and they're like um state
distribution would converge to the
optimal distribution and then like if
they can converge to the optimal
distribution. So let's let's call this
like the good subset. Okay. And then
like if they converge then like by our
design each arm is only consuming half
of the budget um on average. Okay. So
then let's just take that literally if
everyone consumes half then like they
together consume one quarter of n. Okay.
And then like uh you can look at the
next one fraction of the arms. Now like
the the budget left over is a quarter of
n and then again nothing is constraining
them. So they can follow their ideal
actions and then like we expand this
good subset to like one to three/4ers of
n. Okay. And then like this goes on and
on until like you can kind of keep
expanding it but due to the randomness
in the problem there's like a square
root of n fluctuation there and then
that leads to the square root of an
optimatic gap. Okay. So back to what you
uh commented like the first several arms
like they actually don't deviate only
the bottom arms will deviate from like
the ideal policies.
>> You're in worst case so this is fine.
Yeah.
>> Yeah. Okay.
Okay. So um yeah so uh this is like a
basic
>> you see what an end deviation or it's
smaller deviation. Um it's you mean like
the gap or
>> is the square root of n deviation is the
optimal one or is that sort of
>> Yeah. For the policy it's probably it.
Yeah. For our policy is probably just
like really square root of it. Yeah.
Okay.
>> So this kind of crucially depends on the
number of arms you all scaling linearly
with the number of total arms.
>> Yeah. That depends on that
>> number.
>> So yeah. So the thing is like if your
budget is a constant number of arms then
like you there's not much you can do and
then like uh uh roughly speaking your
optimality gap would be on the constant
order because you're only allowed to
pull a constant number of arms then your
like optimization space is like small
okay
>> in principle you decomposed into units
of arms and thing I could say well maybe
I'll decompose them into login bit
pieces Yeah, that's it.
>> Each each problem I'll solve separately.
>> Yes. Yes. Yeah, you can do that. And I
think for like for now for this for our
particular policy like it it kind of
works out to be the same optimality
order like optimatic gap. Yeah. Uh but
we do see that phenomenon in the another
problem where we do need to group them.
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay. So yeah. So basically the
algorithmic idea here is to just like
drive a smaller set of arms optimatic
first and then like try to like expand
this set. Okay. So um I think maybe I
will skip the proof because of time.
Okay. And because I do want to talk
about like the generalization um but
it's based on this drift method for the
upnown functions and it's very closely
related like this intuition. Okay. So um
so I'm going to skip those and um our
construction of the leopno functions. Uh
so sorry I'm going to just skip them. Uh
okay uh I'm happy to talk offline. Okay.
Uh and um so quick summary we designed
this new class of policies and uh um so
it's not a priority or index based
policy and it does use like ARM ids. Um
so if you don't like the way it makes
use of ARM ids which seems arbitrary, we
do have another design which is not
based on ARM ids but rather like another
way of constructing what we call focus
set basically a smaller set where the
arms could follow the ideal actions and
then try to expand it over time. We
explicitly maintains the set like in the
algorithm. Okay. Okay. So um then like I
do want to go to um a generalization of
this. Okay. Uh so for the rest
restlessly spended problem uh one like
limitation is that you only have binary
actions for each arm and you can think
that yeah so like there's a quick review
here. So the action space is binary but
you can imagine that in many
applications you may want to take like a
multiple actions like when you meet with
student it could be one hour, two hours
or 10 minutes and so on. Okay. Um so uh
yeah so this is the one limitation there
and correspondingly like the constraint
is kind of goes with this kind of action
space. Um so we coupled MDP is a
framework that tries to generalize this.
So basically here the the action space
could be like a arbitrary finite space
uh finite set. Okay. And then like uh
you still have the transition
probabilities. Now it depends on action
which is non-binary now and then like
you have still have the independent
transitions have reward functions
depends on both. So those are similar to
before but here when you look at the
constraints you could define like a cost
function that depends on both the state
and action and you could have like
multiple types of costs and you could
have a budget for each. Okay. So um so
then like like this is a uh so-called
weakly coupled MTP and the goal is the
same. You find the policy and uh it's
hard when it's big. So you want to uh
efficiently compute the policy that has
a diminishing optimality gap. Okay.
>> So it's the same as before you got
multiple NMES. Now they're the same
their own evolution,
>> right?
>> They're homogeneous.
>> Yeah, that's the thing I'm getting to
next. Yeah. So but yeah. Yeah, they're
homogeneous now.
>> And then the they're constrained or
they're coupled together through a
constraint like
>> yeah through a set of constraints like
this for every moment of time. Okay. And
um yeah uh we assume there's a action
that like makes the cost always zero
otherwise sometimes it's not
satisfiable. Okay. Okay. Um yeah. So
this is this setting and um the next
limitation I want to bring up which is
even uh more important in my opinion is
this like homogeneous assumption. Okay.
So we assume like all the arms share the
same set of parameters even here. Okay.
Um but like you can imagine like um uh
in practice it could be like arms are
heterogeneous. Okay. So then like here
we actually kind of um like we actually
consider the fully heterogeneous setting
where each arm has its own transition
kernel reward function and like a cost
function. Okay. So this is a place where
uh traditional method would really
struggle like mean field based analysis
like would find it very challenging if
everything is different from each other.
Okay. Um okay so this is this setting
and uh if you look at previous results
uh for the homogeneous setting of weekly
coupled MDPS we have like a papers uh
achieving uh diminishing optimatic gap
um but with no specific order there and
then like there's this type the
heterogeneous setting which says the
arms can be divided into a finite number
of classes which doesn't make it very
different from the homogeneous setting.
Okay. So then like uh and uh um those
papers assume like there's only one
constraint and uh that's why like they
can still define certain index policies.
Okay. Okay. And then like you what we
considered is this fully heterogeneous
setting and the general constraints and
we were able to achieve a one over
square root of an optimatic gap. Okay.
Yeah.
>> Could you clarify again the difference
between the type and a small right?
>> Yeah. So the type heterogeneity is like
you have n arms they are divided into
let's say three types and when you
increase n like the proportion of each
type of arms is fixed like I have oneird
of type one one third of type two one
third of type three okay so then like
it's heterogeneous because you have
different types but if you look at each
type is still like a very large system
so that's why I'm saying it's not too
different from the homogeneous setting
okay
>> fully what happens
>> so the fully header setting every arm
could be different and when we increase
n as long as like we have a condition as
long as that condition is satisfied uh
then like we we kind of we can just keep
adding arms to it. Okay.
Okay. Okay. So uh for uh yeah so then
let's see like our um solution. So we
can first go back to this like restless
bandit setting where we decompose the
problem into single armed mdps and uh uh
as I mentioned they could be solved
through a linear program. This linear
program is basically just the state
action long-term state action frequency
uh for this single armed mdp problem.
That's a fraction of time you are in
state S using action A. Okay. And then
like you can solve this LP you get the
optimal solution which can be converted
to this like optimal single armed
policy. That's what we actually used.
Okay. Um so now like we we are going to
the um we coupled MDPS heterogeneous
setting. Um but we can still first relax
the constraints in the same way. So
basically we replace it with the time
average constraint. Okay. And then like
although it see it looks like the arms
seem to be still like coupled but they
are not like really coupled because if
you write out the linear program form it
shows it more clearly like now we have a
set of action frequency for each arm I
okay because I like it they could each
arm is different okay and then like this
constraint is basically just a linear
constraint on those yi of SAS Okay. So
then you can solve this LP. Now it
depends on N but it depends like in uh
like a polomial way you have N * S * A
like variables and your constraints are
also like polomial in those parameters.
Okay. So you can still solve this and
then like you get those optimal
solutions. What you can cons you can
still prove this is like upper bound for
the original problem and then like what
you get is like in different optimal
single armed policies. Okay just based
on this solution okay so yeah so this is
a local step and then like actually we
use the same like local to global step
here. Okay. So what we do is like now we
call it ID policy. we need one
additional step um which is like not uh
it can be done in many ways it's a
pre-processing we cannot use arbitrary
ids we need ID assignment to satisfy
certain smoothness kind of condition but
it can always be satisfied and we have a
particular way to do this okay and there
may be other ways to do it too okay but
once we fix the IDs it's very similar to
before each arm samples the ideal action
so here the actions could be like I'm
just making up numbers here okay
representing different actions and then
you try to follow those actions starting
from smaller arm ids but remember
there's a cost constraint here and there
are multiple cost constraints here so
you you start from the smallest arm ID
you keep following this until you hit
one of the budget okay then you will
stop as long as one of the budget is
going to be violated you're going to
stop okay so for this particular example
So I think I decided this is the point
like where you hit the budget then you
set like the rest actions to the
non-cost action which is called action
zero here. Okay. Okay. So yeah so this
is pretty much like a very
straightforward generalization of our uh
previous policy and with this we can we
can prove uh the optimatic gap under the
following assumption. So for each like
arm uh after we figure out the optimal
policy we can look it becomes the mark
of chain if you follow that policy. Then
P is the transition probability matrix
and we assume it's a periodic unit chain
and we need to assume that the mixing
time of that arm is upper bounded by a
constant. Okay. So this like if we
increase the number of arms we we need
to make sure this is still satisfied.
Okay.
The number of states are right. So it's
a micro chain on states.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Under on the uh Yeah. Just
like we simply share the same state
space.
>> Yeah. And state space is finite.
>> And so for you to have a uniformly
bounded mixing time in some sense you
want the right sets of uh maybe the
transition kernel with right lower
bounds or something like that, right?
>> Yeah. If it has a lower bound, it can
guarantee this. Yeah. dependence of
[clears throat] of course since it's
independent of n
>> this will always remain true
>> um you mean if there's a gap if there's
like a lower bound on the transition
probabilities yes yes
>> and then [clears throat] the reason only
reason sort of the i would change
because your linear program would change
when you add n and that's why sort of
you want to sort of make sure that that
that's the case
>> yeah right like yeah it kind of needs to
be when you add things this kind needs
to be still uniformly upper bounded by
the same thing Yeah. So for example, if
you are thinking about the typed
heterogeneous case that automatically
satisfies this because no matter how
many you add is like the same upper
bound. Okay.
Okay. Okay. So then like um we have this
um result um and uh uh something I
didn't mention is like if you really
look into the constant here it actually
depends on the uh mixing time u but it
depends on the space size only through
the mixing time. Okay. Okay. So I think
um in the rest um maybe I still have a
couple of minutes or yeah so I actually
yeah maybe let me like talk a little bit
about the proofs and uh uh both proof
follow the same uh uh uh framework and
uh so this framework is like based on
leapno function analysis and uh the
basic idea is is this like you want to
construct a leapno function um that is
first needs to satisfy certain drift
condition. Um so this drift condition
here is basically or the expected value
of the leopno function in the next time
step given the current state needs to
kind of like shrink like it needs to
become smaller. Okay, it needs to have a
negative drift and here we allow some
like slack there. Okay, another way to
write it is like this. Then you can see
theta is like smaller than one. So this
is like a shrinking or roughly like a
contraction over time. Okay. Um so um I
guess yeah so I didn't put it on this
slide. It's it was on the previous slide
but I'm going to just talk through this.
So if you have a drift condition like
this that means you have the upper bound
on the expected value of the the optimal
function in steady state because you can
set you can take expectation on both
sides and then left hand side becomes
zero because it's stationary and then
like right hand side is larger than zero
so you move this to the left then you
have upper bound of the leapno function.
Okay and then like the second condition
is particular to our problem. Um so this
problem because we are trying to upper
bound this optimatic gap. If we can uh
make the leop function be upper bound of
the optimatic gap then like from the
drift condition we have upper bound on
this term which then becomes the upper
bound on the optimality gap. Okay. So
then the key thing here is to come up
with the rightly upn function. Once you
identify the rightly upnote function
then like you have proved the result.
Okay. So in the uh previous um so yeah
this might be a little bit hard to not
have the slide but maybe yeah let me
just show you this. So in the
homogeneous setting we already need like
um a kind of specific construction of
the leopno function. Um this is because
um so if you think about the problem in
the homogeneous setting in the restless
bended setting a natural leapno function
is like you look at the uh state
distribution the empirical distribution
across the arms and you measure how far
away that is from the optimal
distribution. Okay, the optimal
distribution can be obtained through the
single arm the problem. So that's the mu
star here. But if you do that, if you
look at all the arms, this distance may
not shrink over time. Okay, because many
arms may not be able to follow the ideal
actions. So that may not shrink. Okay.
So what we do there is to come up with
this so-called focus set which is a
state like you in the ID policy. It's
computable from all the ARM states.
Okay. Uh but this is a subset of arms
that can really follow the ideal action.
So then like we really we only measure
the distance between the empirical state
distribution and this optimal
distribution within this set. Okay. And
then we add on the size of the uh
non-focus set. Okay. The the the uh size
of the arms outside of this DT set.
Okay. So that's what we did there for
the homogeneous setting. Yeah.
>> Is it okay if I ask question?
>> Sure. Yeah. So st is basically the
vector of length n of which things are
>> right
>> dt is
>> is a subset of arms and
>> which let's say in that example there's
a top top set of arms
>> right and uh it's a stochastic it's yeah
it's determined by the states
>> okay and then of x is
>> yeah x is the like uh you count uh the
number of arms in dt that is in each
state and then you divide it by n like
let's say number of arms in state zero
divide by n number of arms in state one
divided by n
>> and then mu is someh somehow sort of the
corresponding version of that but under
stationary distribution
>> yeah that's like the op stationary
distribution of the optimal single armed
problem
and yeah and shrink it like to match the
size okay so that's for the homogeneous
setting we use this but if you think
about the heterogeneous setting then
this is like no longer doable because
you can no longer just count how many
arms are in each state like arms are
different there's no reason to aggregate
them okay but we still want to capture
this distance to optimality and uh um um
I'm not really not expecting you to read
into this but I just want to show you
the general form of the leavo function
uh so we kind of for each arm we measure
the distance to it optimal distribution
and we measure it to see like kind of
how fast it converges to that
distribution. And then like we kind of
need to project it uh like convert it
into either like distance in re
difference in reward or difference in
costs and u yeah and we take a max or
like it. Yeah. So basically we need to
project the distance into uh translate
that into either cost or reward to be
able to tell the difference. Okay. Okay.
So um yeah. So okay. So then like this
is my last slide uh and uh instead of
doing a conclusion I just want to uh
kind of uh uh advocate this like
approach and I want to encourage you to
find this kind of independent structure
in your problem and see like and try
this local to global approach and see if
it works for you. Okay, with that I'll
just stop here.
[applause]