let me introduce our first keynote
speaker Professor Simon Johnson for many
of you I'm sure you know him he's so uh
well known across the world but I still
want to follow the pattern follow the
procedure to make a brief
introduction Professor Sim Simon Johnson
is Ronald Co professor of
Entrepreneurship and professor of global
economics and the management in s School
of Management here Salon is the head of
the global
economics and Management
Group he co-chaired the
CFA Institute Sy systemic risk Council
and served as
IMF Chief econom Economist Economist in
2007 to
2008 among many other duties titles and
achievements he also
cheer uh MIT shaping the future of work
initiative um I also want to mention his
recent book called power and
progress which is highly recommended by
McKenzie for corporate
Executives now let's welcome Professor
uh
[Applause]
[Music]
Johnson uh thank thanks very much for
those uh kind words of introduction um
welcome to MIT H it's a great pleasure
to have you here I I I first um set foot
on the MIT campus 39 years ago I came to
get my my PhD I was 10 let's be very
clear about
that and and and I've um been away and
done various other things as gray
mentioned including being Chief
Economist of the IMF but I'm always
pulled back to MIT to the campus to all
of the invention that takes place here
I'm not an engineer I'm not a scientist
I'm an economist and I want to talk to
you today about what we know and a lot
about what we don't know about the
potential economic and management uh
impact of the latest wave of Technology
which we're putting Under The Heading of
of generative AI um I have written a
book grae was kind enough to mention uh
Power and progress our 1,000 year
struggle over technology and prosperity
it's it's a great read and and it's
really good for thumping the podium and
it'll shut people up at Thanksgiving if
you want to quiet down those relatives
give them this but uh you you can also
uh read the free summaries on our
website at the shape in the future of
work initiative where we have policy
papers and we have various other
presentations of it um
the the key points uh that I that I want
to address or or or or or land with you
today are on my first slide which has
already been up for a couple of minutes
so you've taken photographs of it
perhaps some of you already these slides
will all be available um to everybody
subsequently and uh you know I think
people like you legitimately and and
should want to know the bottom line how
how big an impact are we talking about
and and of course A lot of the things
that you going to see today and a lot of
things we see around us are still fairly
small scale um sometimes people or
perhaps at a moment where there was a
lot of enthusiasm some people are saying
well a lot of this stuff looks
relatively trivial let's remember that
the internet uh when we first started to
to see it emerge in the early 1990s also
seemed relatively small scale and now
we're uh we use digital as our password
passcode on asking questions and do
please put your questions through um
pigeon hole as as greme suggested and
we'll we'll I have at least 10 minutes
at the end to talk about those so what
what you hear what look what I hear and
probably what you hear is is a range of
views about the impact of AI including
some people who are extremely optimistic
and and there are certainly very
credible well- financed brilliant people
who say congratulations humans will soon
never have to work again that view is
out there there's other views of course
which you also hear and these are also
very smart people uh in the technology
space also um who say that we're going
to get mass unemployment that will lose
jobs and and we won't actually boost
marginal productivity which is the the
Cornerstone of of what determines how
much I get paid how much you get paid
how much everyone gets paid so that may
not actually we may not actually benefit
that much and we we could end up with
either very polarized Society or just
um a lot of benefits in the hands of
very few people which is an extreme form
of polarization uh if you only want to
read one book after I speak today you
should read power and progress It's a
great read but if you want to read two
books Kurt vet's play a piano which was
written in the late 1940s I think it was
published actually in the early 1950s
his first novel is really interesting
because he picked up a lot of the ideas
that were swirling around um Automation
in in that period as computers obviously
were just beginning to emerge um and
what was Norbert weiner who's a
professor in it called cybernetics which
is a forerunner of today's AI people
were worried about some of the exact
same
issues so uh our Baseline scenario then
this is myself and my colleagues I'll
mention their names again in a moment on
the next slide our Baseline scenario and
so looking at let's say 10 to 20 years
which is a stretch honestly and it's
beyond the The Horizon that that many
people would be comfortable making
forecasts when technology is changing
this much but at least based on what we
see currently and I'll go through uh
many of the Salient details in in a
moment the US Progressive growth will
remain as it is as as we've seen it as
it as it has been so it's not a big jump
up in productivity growth it's not a
deceleration in productivity growth also
which is helpful given other things
happening in our society we do think
there'll be more polarization of the job
market and I will try to pass that out
for you in in various ways so it means
some people win and some people don't
win from the way this technology will be
deployed um and and there's also
dimensions of of global inequality that
I will flag for you extremely early days
to be making statements about that but I
I think that's a little bit of an
important context and that will tie into
some of the speakers you hear later this
afternoon but here's the key point and
this is what I emphasize with you and
and with audiences all across the US and
actually the world who want to talk
about this there is absolutely nothing
in any technological Revolution
including this one that is pre-ordained
or happens necessarily or it just
happens to be this way technology is not
that technology is a tool technology is
malleable technology is subject to
social choices now where are those
choices made a lot of those choices are
made in the United States because at the
Forefront of inventing lot of those
choices are made around technical
universities like MIT because that's
where people at the Forefront but a lot
of those choices frankly made by you
because you are in business and you are
deciding where to deploy Capital how to
move labor who should get trained who
needs to be let go and so on so these
are major choices that we're making I
mean pretty much on a daily basis in
this Society at this moment a and I
think it's quite fair and reasonable and
not at all anti-technology I can't be
anti-technology I've worked at MIT for
40 years it's in my title the team is
technology right I'm not actually
technology I'm saying we can shape
technology we can choose technological
paths we have chosen better paths in in
the past we've also chosen some paths
that were not so advantageous for more
people and I'll go through that so those
are the questions I want to put to you
today and and and that's what we
continue to Grapple with in in our
initiative this is um joint work uh with
donon asoglu who's a professor Institute
professor at MIT an economist uh and a
specialist on economic growth and and
political economy and David orter who's
one of the country's most famous labor
economists we have an initiative called
shaping the future of work and um we
have a website where you can see a lot
more about our work and we have the book
that I already mentioned the the tagline
and and and I you know this is a very
memorable conversation I had with a
leading entrepreneur in this space so I
won't name um when when I asked this
person what will be the job market
consequences of this technology in the
full deployment mode this person said we
will all be gods and he meant it
somewhat literally as in you will have
the tools necessary to manipulate the
universe around you which which is a
pretty extraordinary and extreme claim
and and I think we can talk about that
if you want this talk and our focus is
much more on who gets a good job and who
doesn't because our view based on a lot
of history and and what we see around us
is that it's that um
employment decision it's the matching of
people and Technology it's the way in
which jobs change that's what drives
both aggregate Prosperity as well as who
wins and who loses in these
technological
Transformations and and I think it's
very important to to say at the
beginning something that's probably
fairly obvious to you but it's still
important to to establish which is
nothing happens in a vacuum every
technological Revolution happens in a
place it happens in a society it happens
with a system of incentives and I and I
think it's very important to ask
ourselves where are we today um and and
what have we experienced particularly
over the past 40 years I'll do more
longer term American history in a few
moments but what's really striking about
the the US economy since 1980 is that
we've continued to innovate obviously we
were coming into the 1970s and into the
1980s with a remarkably successful a
broad-based economic well some people
call it Miracle it was certainly uh uh a
very impressive and somewhat or even
substantially surprising economic
performance in the three decades after
World War II the US exceeded
expectations and and the fears of Kurt
vona in the late 1940s did not
materialize we did not have a more
polarized Society in 1980 than we'd had
in 1949 for example um but since the
1940s this has changed and and I don't
want to suggest that any particular
person or company or even set of ideas
was to blame for this I think this is
something that just happened in the
society around us the consequence of all
those social decisions I was mentioning
earlier but we shifted from a view of
workers as a resource to be cultivated
and enhanced and improved I'll talk
about the history of that to to a to a
view that wages are a cost to be
minimized in an increasingly globalized
economy we can use technology to
automate and to cut labor costs and that
has driven it's not the only driver but
it's a major driver perhaps the major
driver of the picture that you see at
the top which is what's happened to real
work weekly earnings I've got men at the
top women at the bottom the pattern is
similar for women but less dramatic um
which is you see from um the 1960s that
men with graduate degrees and Bachelor
degrees which I'm guessing is most
people in in this room have done
relatively well um in real terms people
who only finished high school barely
improved and people who um dropped out
of high school have not experienced
improved improved earnings so we've had
a what economists like to call skill
biased Technologies just means that the
technology is more advantageous to
people who have more formal education in
this in this context and it's quite
likely
but not necessarily the case that AI
will continue these relatively
polarizing trends when when I asked um
one CEO
about who could be replaced with AI the
CEO used a term and it's not my term
it's his term um but he said he thought
it was people who had what he called cut
and paste jobs it means jobs that have
some repetitive element in them not
entirely repetitious otherwise they
would would already have been automated
but um if you you look at um the wage
distribution of people who are present
on active on LinkedIn for example it's
between the 20th and 30th percentile
it's people who have um what's sometimes
regarded as pretty good white collar
jobs but they have this
repetitious um Dimension to them they
are absolutely in the line of fire for
this um grahe mentioned McKenzie a
moment ago I helped um McKenzie Paris
office do a report just now came out a
few months ago comparing the US and
Europe in terms of Labor Market
Transitions and what is required in
terms of the change of jobs and people
being retrained or retraining themselves
to new positions at least in the
Mackenzie analysis which I commend you
to look at the US has a lot of work to
do but would have the same sort of
turnover of the labor market that we
experienced um in the decades in the
decade at least before covid the problem
for Europe is actually um more substan
anal Europe will need to people to
change jobs and find new jobs and
acquire new skills at roughly the rate
they did during covid so it happened but
that was a very intense Sprint on the
part of the European economy and that's
a major adjustment if they're able to Su
for them to sustain that over the next
let's say uh 10 years in addition that
there are obviously risks that are that
we talk about we work on in our
initiative but it's not the main main
focus today about what happens to the um
what's the impact of AI on
misinformation on social media and on
democracy and our our ability to make
reasonable decisions I I I attended a a
a briefing um I was a I was a witness a
panelist at at a briefing for a a a
congressional panel earlier this year
that Congressional panel was held behind
closed doors there was no cameras there
was no publicity it was an extremely
sensible reasonable bipartisan
discussion with a lot of different views
on different sides of the aisle you
would have been quite impressed if you'd
been there but you weren't there because
it was Private en closed and it was out
of the public light and I think that's a
little bit of a problem is that once
when when we're in this public space
where the view views can get magnified
exaggerated or distorted um we are not
doing so
well now there's a couple more technical
pieces here that I'm not going to dwell
on um but they're in the slides and you
can look at
them one thing that economists care a
lot about and look at and we have pretty
good data on this over long periods of
time is how much of GDP how much of the
income that we earn in the country
obviously we track GDP on on a weekly
basis that's our news headlines but how
much of that goes to labor versus
capital and and one dramatic striking
thing about the US is we used to have a
lot of GDP earned by labor so that's
wages um it declined and you can see
it's bumpy there's some ups and there
some some downs and there's a big up in
in um in the in in the late 1990s which
is when we had the it boom um but you
can see that it's declined fairly
steadily we do however still have quite
a high labor share of GDP relative to
other countries so there's no sense in
which we've somehow bottomed out or it
couldn't get any lower than this or it
couldn't be the case that Capital wins
uh more than labor actually I think
Capital will win more than labor from
from
this and and let me just PL plant a flag
in in in the question about what happens
to Global in inequality among the many
important speakers you're going to hear
this afternoon John Hart who's the uh
chair of the mechanical engineering
department will talk to you about Ai and
Manufacturing and um he and I and some
other colleagues have projects looking
at this and and I didn't talk to Jon the
last couple of days so we'll see if I
mean it's not surprising is it happens
at MIT that people make dramatic
progress but last um conversations we'
had suggested that this is still in the
pipeline and not
yet transforming economies but I think
when AI comes to factories and when it
affects manufactur facturing it's going
to have a really profound implication
it's already affecting the um allocation
of Labor across white colar jobs it
Outsourcing in some ways we'll see what
the net effect is on the Indian economy
what it does for
manufacturing um in countries like China
and others that have used manufacturing
and the export of manufacturing to power
their economies that remains to be seen
and and I think this is this is a major
additional well concern that that needs
to be on your
radar now that that all might sound a
little bit negative or a little bit
downbeat at least and we're in a
technology conference and we're talking
about the future and you know I think
it's conventional to be inspirational
and and there is an enormous amount of
American history with regard to
technology that is inspirational and and
to to just put that in a little bit of
context in
1851 the British held the first great
exhibition this is the great exhibition
of Crystal Palace where they wanted they
invited the world to come and show their
industrial Wares their new technology
1851 the industrial revolution had
really was really uh well established in
Britain they wanted it was catching hold
in other places they wanted people to
show up and and and and and they were
really interested in what was going on
around the world the Americans sent an
exhibit they showed up with um some guns
and some animals they they' shot with
those guns those were the two primary
initial American exhibits and they got a
little bit of stick for that I have to
say from the British
press for 40 years later the United
States was the greatest manufacturing
power in the world by a long way and
just getting going and you can see that
in this chart so how did this happen
what was the transformation uh what was
that transformation about well the the
core piece of that was what we and many
others have called worker augmentation
and in a in in and there's a a term for
it actually in economic
history the they call it the American
system of manufacturing and and if you
think about it makes a lot of sense so
who was coming to America in the in the
early mid 19th century quite a lot of
immigrants from different parts of
Europe in particular without much skill
the US was attracting and continued to
attract throughout the 19th century a
lot of relatively unskilled uneducated
immigrants highly skilled people stayed
behind in Europe because they had good
jobs they had good incomes they didn't
want to leave coming to the UN was a US
was a risky
proposition um so what did people like
you do your exactly people like you 170
years ago they found ways to use
machines to boost the productivity of
workers including workers who didn't
have much formal education uh and the
key balance that any economy needs to
strike with regard to any technology
certainly the kinds of Technologies
we're talking about in the 19th century
and again today is you're replacing
workers with machines there's some
automation there but you're also
creating new tasks for the workers by
deploying those machines so what V saw
in 1949 in play a piano was automation
replacing workers and what vut didn't
see and I'm not blaming him because it
was hard to see or hard it's hard to see
this in the moment was that those
machines in that social context created
a lot of new tasks for workers that
required new skills that encourag people
to get more education and this
technology um this American Technology
you can see it in sewing machines you
can see it in farm equipment you can see
it in automobiles this spread around the
world this had massive positive effects
on lots of other economies and higher
wages um for those workers were made
possible by higher marginal productivity
although I have to also give a big shout
out to trade
unions um who played a role in making
sure that this High productivity
high-profit firms actually did pay their
workers more money that's an important
part of American History so the
um managerial story there is that we
created again globally but the US was in
the Forefront of this um a new class of
engineer managers who came out of um
skilled Crafts People Artisans I'm from
Sheffield in the north of England and
when I go when I trace my family history
back as far as I can um it is uh
carpenters and it's people who bashed
metal and my family made screws for a
hundred years and I would appreciate no
jokes about that in the Q&A uh but that
that on on my birth certificate it says
father's occup patient screw
manufacturer that was a family business
for a long time so that that those small
businesses aggregated up changed um or
brought to us many new technologies the
one that I would flag in terms of
changing mindsets and possibilities and
many Technologies upstream and
downstream is the the locomotive and
Railway systems and then there's a
picture of the original George
Stevenson's rocket from 1829 and and by
the 1880s the the the British and and
the Americans even more so we're running
these incredibly impressive and
efficient um highspeed for the day uh
Railway systems the key thing is they
were you needed a lot of skill you could
acquire the skill on the job um the
railway companies wanted their workers
to show up they wanted to be diligent
they wanted them to be um good with
customers and they paid them good money
uh to to match that and and Chang the
economy Henry Ford transformed uh the US
economy and well Auto automobile
production but much more broadly in two
ways Henry Ford is not I'm not
recommending Henry Ford's personal views
they're not at all Pleasant um but Henry
for without question did two things he
brought um car assembly onto a moving
production line and he brought
electricity to that production
line when Ford started in Detroit around
1900 uh the US made 20,000 cars with
about 20,000 workers uh in 1929
the US made well GM and Ford combined
made 3 million cars and the industry
employed 400,000 workers so Ford
automated production he autom he used
machines to replace workers assembling
cars but the way in which that happened
generated so many new tasks Upstream
Downstream complimentary to production
that there was a a big boom in in in
employment in the Auto industry a
massive boom obviously in cars and what
you could do with cars and
again let's not forget that the trade
unions played a role and it was a very
difficult time and and a lot of um a lot
of anger and a lot of protest behind
demanding higher wages to match their
higher productivity because they had
become a lot more
productive now if you look at what
happened to American wages and these are
there's a very interesting data set that
we have on wages around the world which
is focused on low-skilled workers and
you can look at the data set to see how
that's defined but we're looking here at
those production line type workers and
we're looking at people who are um as I
said potentially vulnerable to effect of
AI and and so on and and you can see two
I think quite dramatic things in this
picture the first is and and I'm looking
at nominal wages here so I'll show you
real wages in in a in a few moments but
um there is definitely an increase in
nominal and real wages adjusting for
inflation in the US after World War II
and and it continues to increase into
into the 19 uh into the 1980s um the
real picture unfortunately after the
1980s I said is is not so positive for
these people I would also note um that a
couple other countries on here I've got
um India China and Japan I'll come back
to India and China but look at the
success of Japan this is what economic
development is supposed to deliver this
is what people wanted to see and hoped
to see in that post-war period which is
a country like Japan um which had some
strong technology previously but really
integrated itself into the global
economy figured out how to export
obviously sold very good cars um
vehicles and and and and other equipment
to the world and and their wages in
nominal US dollar terms you see rising
up towards us levels that is success in
the global economy for our partners and
of course we hope and and we believe
that as people become wealthier they'll
buy goods from us as well as us buying
goods from
them so what about AI
where do we where where do we stand or
what do we think AI could do now well
it's obviously going to automate there's
no question about that it's going to
you're replacing workers with algorithms
um that does not necessarily boost the
marginal productivity of workers it does
not necessarily raise wages in the early
brtish Industrial
Revolution I say 1780 1840 there was an
enormous amount of Automation in the
cotton industry and the production of
cotton goods and very little increase in
in wages uh for most people in fact for
people who' worked in traditional
handmade cotton Goods it was a problem
their real wages went down quite a lot
but if you can create new tasks with
this AI then you can have the kind of
economic Miracle or boom that we had in
the US after World War II so David arter
again as I mentioned one of my
colleagues um has figured out that more
than 60% of the jobs we have or had in
the US in 2018 did not exist in
1940 so that's the good news right
that's what we want we want to create
entirely new categories of jobs that
you've never heard of and when your kids
come to you and say Mom and Dad I want
to create I want my careator be this and
you say what the heck is that cut them
some slack okay because that's the
future new task creation and that new
task creation has to be fast enough to
match or exceed the pace of job loss
through
automation right so it was fast enough
1940 1980 that's good that means we we
had a rising tide that lifted all boats
after 1980 the new task creation did not
keep up uh with Automation and that's
what's behind that that increased
dispersion now there there is some there
are some microeconomic studies specific
looking at how chat GPT and and now
other um generative AI Technologies can
be used in the workplace and we do know
that in in some context you can use it
to complete writing tasks um based on
what my students turn in I would say you
need to be a look careful with some of
those tasks uh it has improved grades in
some cases so you can use it as a
learning tool um and it may lessen grade
inequality so there are very encouraging
signs here and let's say uh a real
potential for individuals to become more
productive which is as I said the the
what you need for as the basis for for
for wage increases um it also seems that
in some cases for example in the
customer service um been studed by Eric
Bolson
my former colleague here and Danielle
Lee who's in the business school slone
school with me um people using the AI
may actually become um more job
satisfied with their job as well as the
people who they're helping they may able
to give them better advice
however that category of jobs my my
colleagues feel is highly vulnerable to
full automation so in this interim stage
people may feel empowered that's great
but if we're heading towards more
complete automation there's still a
question of what what else are those
people going to
do there are also skill gaps and
mismatches um
and Graham standing up but I have 3
minutes and 45 seconds gram I've got it
okay uh that's before I go before I go
for yeah don't worry before I go for Q&A
um so um this is in the McKenzie report
that that I mentioned um and um and and
a couple other references there's an
Amazon report that that there the bottom
here
so even even in the best case where
we're going to create new tasks we still
have to redeploy people from their
previous jobs that are being automated
away into those new tasks now we did a
hug this is um economists call this
labor market transitions or labor market
labor turnover we did a huge amount of
this during covid so one one thing that
happened in Co that was a big
surprise and somewhat positive in an
economic sense although I understand Co
itself was a disaster for many people
was that people um left jobs that they
weren't very happy with and weren't very
productive in because those jobs didn't
exist or they weren't getting good money
and a lot of them went onto new
positions that they found more
satisfying they got better money and
actually at the lower end of the labor
market David otter has shown that people
have ended up with better outcomes more
money now what you need in AI is with
the as AI rolls out is a version of the
same thing but not a Sprint it's a
sustained transition over well you tell
me 5 to 10 years let's say um making
that transition requires people to
understand what they're what what's
going on to be able to see what kind of
skills they need to have um leadership
from people like yourself in terms of
this is where our labor force is going
this is what you need and oh I just
changed our mind because AI is do
something different so let's pivot over
here I mean to the extent that that's
something that business can deliver I
think you will uh find a lot of people
pleased and and gratified and
loyal um and then if we're worried about
skill mismatches which we are worried we
can break it down and say okay who is
more likely to be impacted who is going
to be less able to make the change and
you
know I I don't we're not doing this to
disparage anyone or to discourage anyone
we're doing it to try and um you know
shed a little bit of light on what may
happen and then track it over time so
that we can help people like my bipers
and friends on Capitol Hill um think
about are there government programs are
there ways government can government can
encourage business is this entirely a
private sector or Italian individual
decision which is honestly what we tend
to default to in the United States um
but you can you can see um that there
are
some concerns from Specialists that
women for example may be more negatively
impacted on net um and it may be some
younger people also who who have more um
trouble gaining that initial foothold in
the labor market including um or or
specifically because of the what what
what generative AI is able to do now
there are some very optimistic
macroeconomic forecasts um I think that
those are a little bit exaggerated donon
asoglu my colleague has a very uh well
regarded paper uh that suggests that
would be some productivity gains but
they're all pretty small the the quote
that I like here is emphasizes the one
from John Williams who's the president
of the New York fed New York fed uh
president is the uh Vice chair of the
federal OpenMarket committee that sets
interest rates in the United States and
and John says and I've talked about this
directly and I think it's a Well found
of view that AI will come AI will have
impact but it's going to be generating
about the same productivity growth as
we've seen in the US of late which is
between 1 and 1.5% so it's good it's
positive on the productivity front it's
a concern on the polarization front um
and it's
it's stories of economic Miracles seem
to have been somewhat
exaggerated now um if we had more time
I'd talk about uh China and and the
pressures from China and Global
competition but Graham definitely wants
me to go to questions just point out
here that Chinese productivity has
increased Chinese wages have increased
nowhere near as much as Japanese wages
and that's a very important pressure on
our economy and on other high wage
economies and there are many ways in
which we could choose and push for
policies and we do recommend these um
that would give you a more worker
friendly version of AI a version that
would actually boost productivity and
and more likely to turn into higher
wages um and that is the book power and
progress so I'm going to turn now to two
questions which are going to appear
miraculously on my on on my confidence
monitor here with your votes or
something you
question yeah you can give me a round of
applause that's good I like that oh
that's that's
important and and now and now we have
about 10 minutes for me to answer
questions are there any
questions uh I will start the first okay
gram gets the first question yeah yeah
um I know you're running you you're
leading this uh MIT initiative which
is uh about the shaping the future of
work and I've heard from many companies
they they they're facing challenges how
they can uh strategically reshape or
upgrade or retrain their proes can you
make some
comments related to your research in
this initiative sure and and I and I can
fold that in with this um first question
here why do you think women and younger
jobs are anticipated to be more impacted
by AI so the the the the field of study
that has taken off uh existed before but
is really getting a lot of attention now
is is um the the technical term is Task
exposure so um and David otter is a
pioneer of this in we we we think of
ourselves is having jobs and the job has
various element and you can break those
elements down into tasks what is exactly
you do on a certain day or a certain
week what is it that people um who work
for you do and and if you look at those
tasks you can attempt to determine how
much of that task is at all repetitive
it's similar this week you do pretty
much the same as you did uh last week
and when you look at task exposure more
repetitive is more likely to be
automated this is in the white collar
space at the moment um by by generative
AI so it's women hold more of those
kinds of jobs with that task exposure in
the studies that I cited and you can go
look at the papers and younger people
you know I think the the concern for um
I have two College age children and and
and the the issue is always like okay
how do I break into a space what's the
first thing I'm going to do and as you
know a lot of times straight out of
college or straight out of graduate
school you might get relatively routine
tasks learn the process you know have a
bit of an apprenticeship uh for a couple
of years but if you don't need that kind
of work in your Law Firm or in your
chemistry lab or in your uh
environmental science firm why should
you employ those young people there
going to be additional cost let somebody
else train them and you'll hire them
when they've got five years experience I
think that's the that's the pressure
point that we're worried about and and
that we're flagging and so greme I think
the issue for companies that's very fair
is to say you know I is this your
problem or is it a social problem that
someone else should solve and I
understand that you know it's very to
say the government should solve this our
government has not been particularly
good at helping people retrain and move
on acquire those new skills and become
more productive over the past 40 years
now maybe we can come up with some
better programs I like public private
Partnerships I that's a core part
obviously what we do at MIT um but I
think we're talking about a much broader
range of skills and jobs than we cover
at MIT and and I think that's um that
that's a that's a that's a problem okay
next question is about it seems related
uh what changes will need to happen to
the US and Global education system to
help put uh people workers at the center
of this AI
Revolution
so some sometimes I like to say my my my
audiences um the the question before us
is which Neil Stevenson novel we will
live in there are some very apocalyptic
negative ones I think snow crash will be
in that category but there's another
Neil Stevenson novel called The Diamond
age in which he imagines I mean this guy
is amazing because he imagines things a
long time before the rest of us get the
memo but he imagined in the late 1990s
that you could have individual personal
devices that would help young people
learn skills and become productive and
and and and full members of society um
in a way that was um decoupled from the
formal education system he actually
focused on young women in China in that
particular story but I I think that the
the interesting thing here or the
possibility is to
empower families young people
uh whether you want to put more digital
devices in the hands of children is of
course a very fra issue but um enabling
people to lowering barriers to to the
acquisition of knowledge and enabling
those access to that knowledge to become
skills that you would recognize and that
you would say yes this person has
learned these things this person is
useful to me I will hire
them and we could do that through our
K12 existing systems we can do it
through
universities I think we have struggled
with it I know we've struggled with this
over the last 40 years and I think we
are
um hoping for and recommending and and
Advising much more profound
transformation at least of um vocational
education and skills acquisition for
people who don't have a lot of formal
education to to bridge those gaps and
and to become more productive with uh
with AI tools all right next question
can you show me the list
again
uh why do you need McKenzie when you've
got chat GPT uh 17 votes uh yeah you
should take that up with MacKenzie
absolutely yeah I ask them that I ask
that all the
time I think seriously seriously that
the um why do you need any why do you
need any analytical um capability or any
analytical people why do you need any
management if you got chat GPT why why
don't we just you know put a bot in
place and have it run a business model
and tell it to maximize profits and hope
it doesn't destroy the world uh and and
I think that uh you know based on our
current understanding obviously you're
going to have a very deep dive on this
today so you may have a different view
at the end of the day but based on what
I see and and and understand from the
technologist um and from how the
technology works is
that uh the the form of AI we have right
now
is good at aggregating the sum of human
knowledge or the way humans have
answered certain kinds of emails or
whatever you want to say that if you're
looking for something different
something humans have never
imagined it's less clear yes there are
some specific
um uh processes and I think chemistry
and Material Science is coming up this
morning because they've led the way on
this yes there happen some specific
instances uh like the folding of
proteins where uh AI is done remarkable
things but once you get Beyond those
well specified problems it's harder to
imagine and and if you go back and look
at you know how do humans invent things
it's not usually the high status people
the people at the very top of the ladder
the people who've built their careers
with one view of the world who come up
with a new view of the world and change
science or engineering or practice It's
usually the scrappy people The Outsiders
the people who are you know the the the
sand and the oyster that that's where we
get a lot of our human creativity that's
what we encourage at MIT and that is
what has served us really well over the
past 100 150 years so McKenzie may need
to reposition MIT may need to reposition
absolutely um I I don't think this is
the end I don't think chat GPT and its
successes will will deliver to you what
you're hoping for in terms of of
creativity and and new
thinking
uh okay do do you think AI progress
implementation will be hindered more by
governmental and business regulations or
our ability to develop and utilize the
technology successfully in an accepted
way look the
um the overwhelming sentiment in
Washington and I spend quite a lot of
time there and I talk to people about
this technology and other Technologies
the prevailing view among officials you
hear this in public but it's very
strongly articulated perhaps more in
private is that they do not want to get
in the way of
innovation the us as I said from the
19th century has led the world in terms
of innovation it's Innovation that
Propel propelled us to a world um
leading production role and and in
1940 Vana Bush who was a former dean of
engineering um at MIT went in to see
President Roosevelt in the White House
and said you know big global war 1940
the US was not in the
war bush veva bush
said big glob war is coming we need to
tie we need to figure out how to use our
engineering and science knowledge to
defend the United States
in to to enhance our national security
in modern language and um FDR famously
wrote okay on this memo and out of this
came a big push in the US to do exactly
that apply science to Military and and
production needs and after World War II
was was an
enormous conceptual and political
breakthrough to to further develop
science in the interest of the economy
in the interest of shared prosperity in
the interest of National Security now we
haven't always done a good job on that
we
um could do better I have another book
that came out a few years ago called
jump starting America where we talk
about exactly that but I think basically
nobody in a position of power wants to
stop Innovation or prevent Innovation
from developing now they may regret
things later there's a lot of discussion
about could we what can we do about
social media today but even if you wind
the clock back and say okay what's the
moment in which you would have said no
to social media before you saw the
effect
I I mean maybe with hindsight you can
imagine that I don't think the
politicians would have gone for it at at
the time so the US bottom line here is
we are going to innovate We Can't Stop
ourselves we can guide it we can push it
in certain directions but as far as the
US is concerned in political economy and
and I think leading business it's it's
always Full Speed Ahead on Innovation
and that will include generative AI
thank you very much