Please join me in welcoming our first
speaker, Jonathan Rosenfeld. Jonathan is
the leader of the fundamental AI group
at MIT Future Tech. Take it away,
Jonathan.
>> Good morning everyone. Let's try and
make a sense at it all. So what we want
to try to do is to answer the question
of the life, universe, and everything,
right? We're talking about AI in the
context of data centers, its progress,
what's driving it, and what I'll attempt
to do is hopefully sort it all out in
terms of what are the driving forces,
how can we when we how can we answer
basic questions like imagine tell me
before you invest to the tune of tens of
billions of dollars, what will be the
end result and how performant it would
be, what's going on today and how are
economics fitting into
So I've set here an agenda that I hope
to cover in 30 minutes. Starting from
where we are today. I assume this will
be very very familiar. Try to tease out
a bit of the hype and what's actually
going on and then how we got here. What
is the role of actually answering
quantitatively
this idea of predictive power of our
performance
and how all the components of that fit
together? What are they with decisional
technical laws the equivalent of Moore's
law that we are seeing and what are
their limits
and how they interact briefly with
market dynamics putting it all together
in terms of how do we actually measure
the things that we care about
and then hopefully I'll I'll make it in
time to have a unified view of that and
if we have time we'll talk a bit about
what is happening from the edge in the
data center and what we can say about
the edge from the data set. Okay, so we
have a packed agenda.
Let's start with where we are, right? So
instead of talking about today, let's go
exactly almost to the day, a year back,
right? So a year back at Google, roughly
a quarter of the code was generated,
note generated. This doesn't say how
good it was. This doesn't say how useful
it is. So generated and then reviewed.
If that is the case, we can ask okay in
the software domain
that was the case a year ago. What has h
been happening across industry? And this
is data from the US Bureau of Census.
What you're seeing in orange is the
actual reported usage. Again, not
productivity, but actual usage and the
prediction at the same moment in time
shifted such that we can see how well do
people actually predict. So this started
at 4% around 2023 mid year. We're now
predicting in half a year 14% and this
is industrywide. This is general. So
this was anecdotal usage in a Google. So
you know a very very narrow this is
industrywide. Okay. So so we have the
view. Now we can ask the question of hey
okay this is being used how much
productivity is it driving? Okay. So
again in the narrow view of software so
you can see it's definitely saving time
in generating code but it's creating
many other categories of work
in the sense of the tasks that need to
be done by using this and today we are
still at the you know working this out
in terms of the net effect but we are
definitely progressing and you can ask
the same question this is very very
recent a couple of days ago from open
AAI where they released 44 four tasks
and evaluated a question of
for a different models. How do those
models fare in their answers relative to
a industry expert as judged by experts?
And we're making different progress
across broad areas there. Okay, let's
talk about money a bit, right? And the
numbers may seem detached or may seem
very very
logical depending on understanding what
they are driving. Right? So this is a
rough timeline to give you a sense
of the scale. Right? So 65 billion
dollars already this year commitment of
hundreds of billion more. And this is
driven by the voracious appetite of
compute. You know, a single training run
even without accounting uh to uh the
overhead in organizing the data easily
scaled from the hundreds of millions to
the billion scale already.
Okay. How did we get here?
And how do we have this confidence of
saying okay we're going to invest this
and this will be a worthwhile investment
right building data centers to the tune
of you know things that are approaching
the trillions of dollars in expected
spending.
So this might be the most important
moment here. There were many but one of
them was this idea of tell me again
before you build something before you
train these models before you you deploy
a model what would be its performance as
a function of the amount of capital
amount of compute to invest and please
do so before you train the model and to
the tune of billions of dollars okay so
if that sounds like a big ask in 2019
here at MIT we answered that for the
first time in a constructive fashion
what you're seeing on the left side is
the expected versus the actual loss of
models as extrapolated
100x into the future as it were into
larger compute. So this these red dots
here are models that were predicted to
to have a certain performance before
trained and uh indeed they had in both
language domain and vision. This was
scaled massively then by industry.
If this was 2019 here at MIT, then by
2023 extrapolation
was done four orders of magnitude into
the future
and I won't go into all the details but
this has been progressing very very
quickly. So if in 2019 we had the first
scaling laws for training and then they
were expanded throughout the industry at
very large scale. um by 2023 we're at
the inference scaling regime. At 2024
we're talking about data exhaustion.
Today we are inching into
the maturation or early inroads of
agents but more quintessentially this
idea of experiential or systems that
learn through interaction with the real
world and not necessarily by collecting
the entirety of the internet or to the
universe.
What is a scaling law? What do we scale?
There's the amount of data or
experience. There's the size of the
model. Together, they determine the
error. And there is an optimal curve
which is defines the amount of compute
that we need. If you take that optimal C
curve and you ask what how quickly does
that
actually reduce the loss what you're
seeing here are different training runs
smaller models with data you get this
power law okay so that allows us to
predict now this has been shown again
and again to hold across different
domains but different domains have very
very different characteristics if in
language you need to the tune of a
million x in order to have the the loss
in other domains it's less
and not everything actually scales so
nicely some things saturate before okay
so from laws of the physics of what
determines loss again I don't really
care about loss right you can ask your
latest
AI assistant what is your loss and that
might not be a very useful answer we
want to talk about the underlying ing
technical laws that are governing this
industry. So think the equivalent of
Moore's law but now in our context. So
what I'm showing here is a top envelope
in Nvidia
GPUs from 2009 to
2023.
And what we have is actually an
exponential increase in
compute.
And you see that's for a different
precision. Well, I'll show in a second
what that means. But also of the energy
consumption, the price to an extent, but
computer actually grows much much faster
than everything else. Right? So with a a
a very high clip and that is explained
here. We can take a different look by a
composite effect of both the actual um
performance
for a certain type of computation a
floatingoint operation and then an
advancement of what an operation
operation actually means as we move to
uh quantization methods and others.
Okay, if that was the device, what is
happening at the data center level? So
what you're seeing here is training
intensity. Okay, so think of this as the
operations per second, right? So we have
here
over time and I'm showing two
views of the same thing of the models
and how much
operations did they require in their
training and correspondently how much
energy
did they sorry what was the peak power
consumption corresponding to that and
these handsomely fit on exponential
curves and this gap between them is a
efficiency gap or if you will a increase
in efficiency over time okay so both
energy is scaled as we well
Right. This is at the watt. So here
we're talking about
many many megawws and the compute per
watt also increases exponentially. Now
you could ask okay if that is the inputs
in terms of energy and then the useful
computation relative to that energy what
happens in terms of what we call
algorithmic efficiency. How quickly does
computation actually translate to a to a
a performance improvement? So you can
for example if we hold over in time the
performance constant and ask how much
compute did this require we discover
that the required computation
is also exponentially dropping. Okay. So
both things are happening at the same
time. both we have more energy with
exponentially more compute per energy
and exponentially decreasing compute
needed for a given performance level. So
this is a a dance of exponents. What
happens as you increase the models? We
move from loss to actual things that we
care about here on different benchmarks
in terms of completeness of tasks. You
see that
it takes a short while for the same
level of benchmark. each one of these
scenaries is a certain difficulty level
within a benchmark to be solved by a
smaller and smaller models. Okay, so
over time this is the different view but
now in the things that we care about
demonstrating that smaller models become
capable at solving what a moment ago was
solved by larger models.
Okay, so this is technical what is
happening on the market side. We have a
Pareto where we can trade off the
performance versus a cost per token and
we can ask for a given benchmark across
all benchmarks or tasks. What would be
the
win rate of a model relative to a
different model? So if we compare two
models of the same size at the same
moment in time, win rate will be by
definition 50. If we take a model which
is 10 times as large as its neighbor at
the same time then win rate goes to 90
79%. If we go all the way to 100x then
we're at 94%. Not 100 but 94. That's in
a moment in time. Does this mean that
from a market perspective you can hold
market share? Well, the answer is no
because things become very very quickly
abs obsolete.
If you took the model today and compared
it with a model of the same size in one
year, you'd already be losing 90% of the
time. Two years in, 7% of the time. Even
if you compare a model today which is
100x larger than a model in to in a year
or two, you very very quickly lose
market share.
Okay.
So what's actually explaining the final
piece? The final piece is we talked in
so so this might sound very familiar.
There are benchmarks but we actually
care about useful tasks and we want to
quantify that. So imagine for a second
the most simplistic
explanation to what is governing the
performance evolution of models. There
are tasks in the world and let's uh for
a second define a task by the
the number of steps that it takes to
complete it. and assume for a second the
simplest version of the world where the
probability of failure of a model or an
AI system I should say at every given
step or every unit interval is constant
there's a failure rate that means that
if it's a 5% failure rate if there's one
step then the probability of success
would be 95% if it involves two steps or
two durations that compounds right we're
already at 90% at three steps steps or
at 86. This falls very very quickly
and you can actually measure that if you
take tasks and you annotate them by this
is an amazing work by quiet takes real
real tasks. this isn't the software
domain and you bin them by the length it
of time it would take a human to perform
that task and then you ask for different
models how well do they perform on
different tasks length right and you get
this uh very rapid decline with the task
length
which agrees quite well with our
simplistic model before and then you can
ask okay so for different models as they
were released what Is this median?
What is Let's say that we take the 50%
success rate. What would be the how
would this 50% success rate or the 90%
choose a point here? Let's choose the
the 80%. How does this evolve over time?
Because that's the thing that we really
care about. How long of a task and at
what success rate can these systems
actually solve? you find that that too
amazingly
grows exponentially. Again to explain
the x-axis is time in years and we're
looking at the 50%
success rate and we ask what was the
length of task for which a model
succeeded half of the time that grows
with a doubling time of roughly 7
months. Okay, that means that if you
have a model succeeding at 90% today for
a task that takes half an hour in just
over half a year it will be cap as
capable in tasks which are twice as
long. Okay, so that's what's empirically
going on. And you can actually
show that for it's a bit faint here, but
for the 80% empirical success rate and
you can ask how long does it take me to
move from 90% to 99 to 99.19
and at the current rate it's roughly uh
two years
and correspondingly also doubling the
lengthing performance of the task that
it can complete. This is very very quick
and this is again the thing that we
actually care about. Okay, I have 12
minutes and I expect this will generate
a lot of questions. So I'm going to try
to put it all together. This is what we
talked about up until now very very
quantitatively. Okay, we know that for a
given class category, right? We know
that in different domains we have
different learning efficiencies. We saw
you know ranges between 40x to 100 to a
million x in compute across domains. But
in a domain we know
this number. We know we just sh looked
at the software doubling time and it was
doubling every seven months.
We also know what the algorithmic
efficiency is because we can measure how
quickly
the same model sorry the same
performance can be uh generated as a
function of compute. We covered that
power efficiency at the device and at
the uh data center uh level. We know
this and we control how much we build
and currently we are building at an
exponential rate. Okay. But this is a
matter of choice. So we know all of
these. This is a domain specific thing.
We basically have everything that we
need in order to put everything in the
equivalent of a road map of how to
navigate and make choices in this
industry or in the data center. And it
looks something like this. Okay. So on
the
y-axis we have the amount of compute.
Okay. Um on the
x-axis we have again time
here is shown again the compute buildout
for the models up to a bit earlier this
year. Okay. So we're seeing the compute
versus time with the actual uh models at
the end here. I think is
this is gro 3 probably uh in terms just
to calibrate on the uh time. Okay. So
this is actual compute buildout. Now we
said two things are happening at the
same time. We have an exponential
increase in efficiency per watt. Okay.
So if this is the ISO power contour
meaning this is a buildout to the tune
of 10 megaww then over time efficiency
will drive the amount of computation on
that uh energy contour. Okay. And at the
same time we have the algorithmic
efficiency which is four different task
horizons. So this is 3.6 seconds. This
is times 10, right? 36 seconds, 6
minutes. So each one of these is a
successful completion at a given rate of
a task which takes 10 times as long.
That too is dropping at an exponential
rate. Meaning that if we hold everything
constant, we will be able to that's the
seven months doubling time that we saw
before. Meaning that this is our design.
If we want to say okay I want to know
what my performance will be blue curve
if I invest this amount of energy over
for this horizon assuming that energy
efficiency we will land here. Now the
the slopes are pretty wild. You can look
this is up to 20 35
and these are two orders of magnitude
between ISO power. Okay. So this is a
single device level to
100 of those to 10,000 terminal. So this
is the gigawatt level
and time is closing by virtue of the
intersection of algorithmic efficiency
and energy efficiency these gaps very
quickly and you can say okay I I want to
to win this and move over here and
actually drive algorithmic efficiency
with a buildout because I'll be able to
make tasks
with my systems that are much at much
higher success rate and durations.
Now there are limits to this thing and
there are two fundamental limits. One is
well you can't continue
to get more computation out of the per
watt at the infinitum right at some
point there's a limit and the second one
is well algorithmic efficiency also has
a fundamental limit at some point I
cannot complete the same task or task
duration with a with less computation
okay and it is the product of these two
that determines or to try and
show how to tackle just one of these. So
let's talk a bit about the efficiency
limits in the energetic domain. Okay, so
again we're talking about here we have
operations per second versus the power.
Okay, so this is the idea of how many
operations can we get per watt
per second, right? Operations per second
per watt or computations per unit
energy. And what you're seeing here is
the same data that we had before. So
these are GPUs from 2008
colored by time
from 2000 uh sorry 2010 to 2025.
And what you're seeing is these paral
frontiers as we're adv advancing we can
do more operations right this is a
logarithmic again these are large large
jumps every 100x per per octave here
per grid line.
So you're seeing this perro frontier
where you can have very little
operations at low energy, very many at
high energy, but the efficiency is
actually progressing through time. And
these curves here are the fit of the
of the of these frontiers. So this is up
until where we are now. Now we can talk
about the limit. There's a fundamental
limit, a physical limit.
You could question where it whether it
is possible in principle or not. But uh
somewhere over here there are different
guesses of to how to account for human
brain or other mleian brain operations
per watt. I won't get into it. It's not
my area of expertise. I chose here one
such and I'll show error bars in a
moment. But you see that assuming the
current rate we have
roughly. So if the last 15 years hold to
the next 10 will close a a gap that
might bring us comparable to some of the
estimates of what our human brains are
actually doing. And we're still very
very far from the fundamental physical
limit. So let's tie it together what we
saw. Okay. By now this is very familiar.
We're all singing it in our sleep
hopefully. And now let's put the limits
on it. So this is that limit for the 1
kilowatt
contour. Okay. So roughly at the scale
of a single device. You can see here the
single device scaling which has added
some more power and that's why it's
going over the efficient the net energy
efficiency contour. You see that by
roughly a decade from now we'll be at
the vicinity of estimates of human brain
efficiency and still several orders of
magnitude from what is physically
possible. So we have a ways to go.
So there's room here significant room on
the one side.
I want to give a just a preview to I
know that I promised five minutes. I'm
at four for questions. I'll maybe just
give a a short preview of how all this
interacts between the data center and
the edge because this is actually more
nuanced than one might think. For
example, if you think of we didn't talk
about it, but the it's also the case
that compute relative to bandwidth is is
exploding. Now that might sound like a
very big big challenge known as the the
data wall, the communication wall, the
memory wall in the data center. But you
could ask a okay what actually happens
when we have that to what extent
algorithmic efficiency can drive task
completion with less bandwidth between
nodes. At the extreme this is what is
happening at the at the edge. I have a
single node with very very measly
bandwidth to the rest of the world and I
need to cope right
so how does that look so one so there
are two things to understand one let's
take the let's extend our graph here to
the 10 watt efficiency uh contour and in
practice uh at the edge things have been
moving slower uh in terms of the rate of
exponential
growth still exponential but that entire
thing
changes timelines somewhat but less than
what one might think again because what
we are interested in now is the
intersection with algorithmic efficiency
and the energetic efficiency again we
can play this game and say okay if I
want to have what would take on a
gigawatt scale to reach performance in
seven All right.
When will that reach the 10 watt scale
for the same level of performance?
Okay. And we're talking things are
progressing currently. If you
if if what held for the last 15 years
and accelerated actually lately would
hold for the next
five then we'll be at the 100 kilowatt
or 10. will be at the uh 10 watt scale
and at that point the difference in
terms of energetic efficiency at the
edge matters a lot but less again than
what you may think so that's point one I
wanted to make and the other one is okay
this dynamic of having very capable
nodes we call them the edge you can
think of what happens in the data center
once you reach those levels of
performance per node okay and I left one
minute and 30 seconds for questions Any
questions?
>> You mentioned uh model obsolescence, but
any comment on hardware obsolescence and
what kind of horizons you see in terms
of like what's the useful life of a
typical GPU or
>> Yeah. So there's actually a very nice
graph of a a
you know generation over time in
buildout
and you could imagine to so so the short
answer is in order to enjoy these energy
efficiencies you actually need to drive
them with novel architectures. That's a
lot of what is happening there and the
the clip is roughly
is roughly doubling every 16 months at
the aggregate uh when you include
movement of floating pointer operations
etc. So that gives you a sense of the
the cycle time right call it a year and
something and then the hardware
efficiencies
are at the scale of doubling every two
or so years. So that gives you a sense
of sort of technological node. Okay.
However, if you look at buildout and I
don't have it here, you actually see
this titration. You have a you have sort
of a the a
an exponentially larger buildout with
the new nodes, but still the nodes
previously lingering on and making
useful work. And that should not come as
a surprise because again algorithmic
efficiency is actually allowing us to
get much more. Your phone currently can
do things that you didn't imagine that
it can would have been able to do a mere
two years ago and you haven't switched
it.
>> All right, one more quick question.
>> Hi. Um I find the uh benchmarking of the
human brain uh against AI pretty
interesting because there are things
that a human brain can do that AI cannot
and vice versa. So in a way my pocket
calculator is smarter than the human
brain in in terms of you know big number
of multiplications or whatever. So so
how do you quantify that comparison?
>> That's a fantastic question and
it's incredibly insightful. We are you
know we are very very specialized
hardware so comparing is very difficult
I'm not claiming to I'm giving a a
rough comparison which tries to bin or
account for operations per second
relative to power usage. Okay. And there
there's a a lot of literature out there
of how to do that bin counting.
You're welcome to argue with it.
But there is the the the takeaway is
this
basic idea of if a task is governed for
a given architecture and we know that
the by the amount of computation which
in turn is governed by the amount of of
energy per per operation or the power
for that total uh instantaneous number
of computations.
then that itself is progressing
exponentially for the class of problems
that these things can solve. Okay,
clearly our calculator are better at
things. You know, models we build can
read the genome. You know, I can't,
maybe you can. So, it can do a lot of
things that we can't, but there's no
reason to think that fundamentally,
maybe that's the thing you're alluding
to. There's there are there's a class of
things that we can do that we will not
be able to reach. So that's the short
answer is this is just bin counting as
of operation
per second per watt.
Okay, let's hear it for Jonathan.