PROFESSOR: So have you guys
seen the elephant toothpaste
reaction before?
So we're going to react hydrogen
peroxide with potassium iodide,
in this case, and
I'm going to pour out
about 10 milliliters of
this and then dilute it
so that our new
concentration is about 7%.
So what's happening in there?
It's bubbling.
All right, so it's
taking its time.
So while that is going,
we can set up another one.
We said that concentration
effects rate, right?
So if that was 7%
hydrogen peroxide,
what do we think is going
to happen if we use 30%?
Let's find out.
[AUDIENCE EXCLAIMING]
AUDIENCE: Whoa.
PROFESSOR: So hydrogen peroxide
naturally decomposes over time,
so this reaction is
always happening.
So you can be
thinking about that
when you are thinking
about what happens
in the cells of your body,
because you are forming
these superoxide radicals
and hydrogen peroxide
all the time in your cells.
And the reaction
that you just saw
is happening this
many times faster
in the cells of your body.