so while while we're doing this I'll so
explain the reason I have an Emmy is I
developed a system for CBS broadcast of
the PGA Tour um and if you want to have
a disaster of of broadcast trying try
being the director in in sort of
broadcasting live golf you have the
director screaming profanities over the
airwav trying to get shots across the
playing field which is the entire golf
course so spent a lot of time sort of
crawling around golf courses doing that
so that's not what I'm going to talk
about today um today I'll talk about
smart factories data analytics and and
sort of try to frame a couple different
machine learning AI tools through the
lens of manufacturing so the exciting
opportunity being a mechanical engineer
computer scientist is to look at at our
Factories at our supply chains as data
sources they we make product there's raw
material in hopefully product out
there's data in and data out and how do
we leverage those data with content
right so to be really dangerous and
really powerful in this AI smart
industry for whatever you want to call
it it's actually having some data
science knowledge and the contextual
knowledge with which to apply simple
tools so the key idea is smart digital
it's not new right our ability to
leverage data and high computational
knowledge with sort of context domain
knowledge is quite critical for us to be
successful right so we need to bring
these two worlds together so
realizations what's not changed sort of
think the world varies uh there's we
need to control sort of for M raw
material variation people variation
machine Weare um we need to have models
you know where those models come from
physics we need to understand some have
some physical intuition for why the way
why things work in a particular way and
use models to predict what's going to
happen to sort of compare against what
actually does happen um so why smart now
so cost and ubiquity of tools the
ability to sort of I left my cell phone
over there but so the ability to get
data from point A to point B without
wires certainly the the AI tools that
we're deploying now have been around for
decades we've reached the point now
where we have somebody else's computer
the cloud and we have some Innovations
and how we train these models that have
and the access to data that is allowing
us to be a lot more
powerful but it's building on the
context of what we're trying to do as
manufacturers so in your industry you
you need that context
you understand well how to machines
operate what what's the sort of the
point of the what you're trying to make
having the intuition for the types of
questions to ask and then you need to
have the data science folks either
embodied in one team or embodied in one
person to know well here are the types
of algorithms that you can use some that
are are interpretable which means a
person can look at them and understand
what they're doing by opening up the
hood or or not um and sort of understand
well how do I bring these two things
together the data science and the
manufacturing
okay so if you want to think about how
we approach a smart ear in data tensive
system take your system take your
machine take your oil field take
whatever it is what is the sort of the
physical intuition what's your sort of
mental model the engineering model for
how that thing operates and what do the
sensors give us this this world of data
the data comes from a sensor from
someplace so you should be your best
practice you should be good using good
analog filtering you should be doing
good instrumentation you should be
satisfying nwis and collecting your data
fast enough and as an aside I spend a
lot of time working with companies that
are asking hey we saw this wonderful
paper that you put out on deep
reinforcement learning applied to
process control and we'll get to that as
the last topic but six months into
working with a company say yeah actually
you know what this data that you told us
had been collected at 1 second interval
uniformly yeah sometimes it's acquired
every 1.5 seconds sometimes every 0.5
seconds and just the basics of
understanding what's the time what what
is time associated with your data if you
don't do that you can't do some of the
basics like understand the frequency
content of your data use the thing
called the 4A transform which is the
underpinning of all of signal processing
and it's what allows you to do fast
convolutions so some of the basics are
some of the things that
are just the housekeeping that needs to
be put in place to be able to take
advantage of the advanced tools so what
do we want to visualize how do you
visualize it and bring these two things
together um so do your
data give you consistent Insight with
what you expect physically and if not if
you see patterns and things that you
don't understand do I need to do some
additional experiments there's my mental
model for what the operation is actually
wrong design experiments and iterate in
this sort of simultaneous physical model
and digital and data model so this is my
digital twin you know the the the clean
clean shaven version of it I'm winner
Rising I will be bleached in at the end
of the week I'll be Santa Claus by the
end of the year um and then I'll Dy it
red for New Year's anybody want to
Define what a digital twin
is I don't really like the term digital
twin I don't like giving new names to
things that have existed for a long time
so a digital twin is a model and the
subtle difference that I'll sort of all
accept where what we call a digital twin
versus a model is a digital twin
presumptively is something that is a
model that you're dating it's a model
that with some regularity you're getting
additional data and improving the model
in some way but you're using this twin
you're using this model to predict to as
an engineer as a designer as an operator
to predict what's going to happen when
you don't get what you expect to try to
improve the
model and go on and so models digital
twins models that have some kind of at
some time scale real time digital update
and there can be models twins of of of
process of product of factory of supply
chain so my if you put um create a into
a dolly your chat GPT create a a graphic
that represents that that's this is what
you get sort of the brain sort of
ingesting sort of the data that with
some physical model of the real world
and doing some type of analytics off of
that okay so
models can come from to oversimplify
purely data or purely physics or
someplace in between and I would argue
that the place where we can be really
and where we have to be most focused in
manufacturing and in operations is is
really that gray box area meaning that
we have some Physics we don't have all
the physics we may be able to run
computational fluid dynamics models we
may be able to run bite element models
um but we can augment that with
additional data as opposed to well let's
try to capture everything in the physics
that's going to take you a long time and
Flying Blind by just using your data in
a black model doesn't really make any
sense right because you don't you need
to understand the context and sort of
relate it to the things that you care
about on the factory floor in the
field so a way that I'd like to explain
smart digital industry for
digitalization it's really applied
instrumentation and we we acquire data
we try to interpret the data we try to
develop models from that data and it's
not a lot more complex than that and I
would argue that we do that now and a
lot of what I spend time working with
companies about is like listen you're
already doing AI machine learning you
may not call it that you may call it
things like real-time process control
you may call it statistical process
control and that's often a good place to
start in demystifying within your
organization bringing people along on
the journey say listen AI is not this
phenomenal new thing that is something
we haven't been doing we do real time
feedback control with Fe feedback
control often you'll have a model a twin
of a process and you're measuring
temperature time your rate heat and
you're trying to maintain a certain
temperature over time or or rate of
deposition over time and I have a
controller typically a PID a
proportional integral derivative
controller that monitors that process
and tells the Machinery go faster put
more current into that motor to go
faster or increase the amount of heat
drill faster to try to Main main a set
point and then typically after we do
that real time control shown on the left
there is this
divide where we say okay great after
things are using a real-time controller
to deal with arguably deterministic
sources of variation we then ask the
question well is the process in control
from a statistical perspective and what
does it mean to be within control from a
statistical perspective that means that
the variation that remains after you
you've done this after you've used the
best physics models and you have a
real-time controller trying to maintain
a rate a temperature it's like okay well
now what is the normal VAR we're never
going to get rid of all variation
variation is going to happen but what it
means to be in control from a
statistical perspective is like is the
mean value sort of stable is the
variance stable is it drifting off over
time is the mean shifting and if either
of those two questions are yes then
you're not in control from a statistical
perspective and then somebody crosses
this line back over here and figures out
well deterministic source of error what
is it is it is it raw material variation
is it operator variation and we sort of
ping-pong back and forth generally now
in sort of these two ways of thinking
about control so this is we we are this
is Big Data the statistical process
control it's big data where we assume
the world is normal we assume the world
is a bell curve and we're looking for
deviations from that bell curve and the
things that we're doing here we're using
models we're using digital twins to
predict so one of the opportunities not
the only opportunity one of the
opportunities in how you can accelerate
the rate of awareness and appreciation
for what machine learning is it is
contextualizing it within your
organization say hey we do realtime
feedback control we do statistical
process control one of the opportunities
is to sort of do these better and one of
the opportunities is to break down the
wall between these two things and and
allow the big data that we're collecting
over long-term Trend to actually
automatically cross this divide instead
of having a person try to go tweak and
adjust a model have automatic knowledge
that's propagating back over here to the
models that we're using to control our
process so I want to use some three case
studies with increasing complexity a I'm
going to give you a test or a couple
different tests see how well you
understand your machine learning tools
um and and try again to say listen you
can do a lot with some very simple tools
so first case example and this is a
project that we did with
tetrapack um making packaging material
your milk containers what have you um a
virtual wear sensor and sort of this is
in this opportunity exposing the iot
meaning exposing the real-time data that
we have to do something a little bit
different before I do that and see I'm
as I don't have my slides in front of me
I have to figure
out this is the Machinery that we're
going to talk about before I get there I
want to go and talk about a very simple
example to motivate something that's
called a decision tree anybody heard of
a decision tree okay anybody be able to
explain to your direct reports or to
your supervisor how a decision tree
works you know some some okay maybe okay
but a decision tree is is is basically
it's a bunch of questions right decision
tree is looking at our data and in some
way looking at our data and figuring out
well where what are the information Rich
questions that we can ask of our data
and that's a key key point so the the
the sort of the Insight with this thing
called a decision tree is it's trained
by quantifying the information content
how if I if I look at something that
happens very rarely and I get that event
I'm surprised if I if I tell you that
the sun is going to come up tomorrow
you're not very surpised Ur I didn't
give you much information but if I tell
you with 100% certainty that I know the
sun's not coming up tomorrow a you
wouldn't believe me but if it were true
that's that you're really surprised
there's a lot of information that I've
conveyed to you and telling you that
that answer to the question you didn't
ask but if you ask me the sun came up
and I said no okay you're surprised so I
want to quantify that notion of
surprise so here pretend to sort of
frame this pretend that these 10 data
points are big data so it's it's 10 data
point data but it's big data or it's a
data set and the other problem the other
opportunity SL challenge in
manufacturing is often you don't have
big data sometimes you really just do
have small data and sort of context is
important to sort of make best use of
that small data but here let's just
pretend it's big data or big enough data
and this is data that comes from a a um
a printing operation printing a flexible
circuit board and we have two different
types of machines machine H and machine
a three different bat sizes the machine
can be autof fed or not
it can be lined in different ways
different speeds and we as the
manufacturing experts have decided that
we'd like one of these observations we
like a configuration where we get 95%
yield or higher so we say hey we're
going to flag this thing our our
human supervised learning our human
information is telling us like okay we
we're going to label these data good bad
past fail based on what we want to
achieve in terms of a 95% yield on the
configuration of this machine so we have
some of these configurations that have
over 95% yield as a pass and some not
and a very reasonable thing to do is
like well given this past given this
history we've designed a new product and
the designers of said product would like
to use this configuration a very
reasonable question to ask is well given
this configuration what is our
expectation of success meaning do we
expect that we're going to get 95% yield
or higher or not now this particular
thing this particular configuration does
not sit in our big data it it may and it
may you may have multiple observations
but pretend again this is a sort of a a
toy problem to motivate a
tool that's a question that we would
like to ask put in the X Vector the
machine bat size autof fed no Center
alignment fast and say does our model
tell us does it model predict they're
going to get 95% yield or higher so here
in one slide I'm just going to
explain what r or mat lab or python
would do for you if you gave it this
data and said hey give me this
interpretable AI tool give me a decision
tree that's going to help me make a
classifier that predicts passor fail
based on my historical data and it
hinges at the bottom on this idea that
I'm I'm sorting my data in Excel just to
show you show you what's going on but
I'm sorting this data based on the idea
that I can quantify information
and just happens mathematically and
there's a lot of theory around sort of
why this sort of mathematical expression
of the amount of information in a
question is negative log base 2 of the
probability of an answer right what that
means is if it's a very surprising
answer the amount of information is high
if it's not a surprising answer the
amount of information is low and the way
that we can
determine the probability of something
is well let's look at all the data we
collected look at the statistics of the
data look at the statistics of well how
much did batch size matter how much did
auto feed matter and so here let's see
if they get the laser pointer here we go
here I've sorted the data at the top and
I apologize as an ey chart but I've
sorted my data on batch size and why is
that an information Rich question well
here you'll notice that every single
time it's only three times but it's big
data pretend every single time that it's
500 or 900 it fails do that tell tells
me a lot say hey if it's 500 or
900 yeah it's not going to work and if
it's 700 well sometimes it passes
sometimes it fails so a very information
Rich question to ask and answer is let's
first ask a question about batch size
I'm G to ask a question about batch size
if it's 500 900 my series of questions
are right off the bat going to tell me
500 900 it's a fail and if it's 700 it's
a little more nuanced than that I need
to ask another question so there on the
next table of pulled out just the 700
data and I've sorted it now on machine
every time that it's machine a it passes
every time that it's machine H well
sometimes it passes sometimes it
fails and we go on so this now a
decision Tre as a tool is often the very
first thing if you know no other tool to
use it's the first out of the boox thing
hey let's try it because I can
understand say hey it's a series of
questions this sort of this complex set
of data I I quantify information in this
way but the result is a series of
questions it's like paying playing 20
questions with your kid and you want to
guess the thing that's on your head um
you want to ask information Rich
questions to be able to figure it out
with the fewest number of questions that
you can and so this is now an easy to
understand easy to interpret thing it
has limitations right but it's a great
way to get started say is there some
signal in the data can I sort of get a
first Baseline prediction of the thing
that I want to know which is in this
case is well am I going to get over 95%
yield or not so now that is all I'm
going to tell you about a decision Tree
in practice you'll actually not just use
a tree but you'll use a forest what's a
forest a forest is a bunch of trees
trained in slightly randomized ways to
make it more use an on Ensemble which is
he just a bunch of different trees
working together we'd like adding all
these new complex words to things that
are just quite intuitive um so here's
the tool now
now we're going to turn our our
engineering and our sort of production
hats on for a bit so we want to apply
that tool to this case where now we have
a packaging
system and this packaging system takes
as input on a conveyor belt bottles in
six packs 12 packs nine packs and wraps
them with a piece of plastic cuts the
plastic shrink wraps the plastic and
pushes the bottle
along and the question on the table is
like well okay we have
all of these data that is the real-time
Control Data coming from every package
that goes through so this data is the
torque versus time of the blade of the
of the um motor that's controlling the
the knife edge that's cutting the Saran
Wrap we have positions oops we have
positions and accelerations of the Saran
of the plastic wrap of the blade of the
material and this is for one package
going through this is time series data
for one package as it passes through
through so we have the time series data
and then over here we have just the
histogram of that time series
data and the question is well I would
like to I know any mechanical system
whether it be a rotating piece of
Machinery or not wears over time we lose
lubrication bearings wear things wear
mechanical things wear and I'd like to
say I'd like to take these data without
adding an additional sensor without
adding anything any additional cost from
a hardware perspective I would like to
say
using these data can I also predict the
health of the machine like these are
these are data that I'm getting that are
just from the the operation of the the
system the doing its job wrapping this
plastic wrap but I would like to also
take better use of this data to do some
predictive maintenance are there
signatures in this data that are going
to start to tell me when the machine is
changing right so what is a what is a
real-time controller doing a real-time
controller is compensating for the
things that it can compens for if if
material varies maybe I need to do
something different if it's if if the
material is off axis I need to shift it
over a little bit so it's it's moving
things around trying to compensate for
the variation that naturally occurs so
now if I have a system I want to take
both my physics View and my data view so
what your physics view this is the first
question first test what's your physics
view do I I have these data these types
of data for hundreds and thousands of
packages that go through through this
production
line is there
information about the health of the
machine about that's narrow it down
about the the health of the blade that's
cutting the plastic wrap is there
something in this data that would tell
me about the health of that
blade I see some heads nodding yes what
wh why why is are those head nods yes
what's your physical intuition that
tells you that this data that's coming
from the automatic operation of moving
things around cutting a piece of plastic
wrap heating it why is there something
physical about the machine embedded in
these data anybody want to venture a
brave
answer so the controller is
responding the torque okay so why why
the torque
okay so if I gave you a scissors and I
asked you to cut a piece of
paper if I give you a dull scissors
versus a sharp scissors I'm going to
need a lot less torque a lot less Force
to cut the same thing with the sharp
scissors so indeed if the blade that's
attached to a motor is sharp and I apply
a torque it's going to be less torque
required and it may take a little bit
longer but at least from sort of a
baseline physical like domain expertise
I expect some information about the
machine to be embedded in this so that's
sort of the starting point like yeah
okay great I have a tool that can I can
use as a regressor as a classifier I'm
going to use this thing called a
decision tree but don't even bother
applying it unless you have some insight
some contextual knowledge that says yeah
I expect some type of success and here's
where I expect some of the information
to be embedded and indeed there's
information embedded in everything here
because it's it's a control system and
everything's interconnected but at
minimum you know the amount of torque
should be revealing so now that being
said great I can actually just take
these data and there's a whole bunch of
other stuff that you'll need to do it's
like well what is my what's my input
data what's my output prediction my
input data could be like here are these
all these time series data package 23
comes through package 24 package 3,000
comes through do I pass into my machine
learning tool um all of these time
series
data maybe you could that's that would
be a naive approach maybe I can do some
feat engineering to give another fancy
term to it I can do some pre-processing
of my data and I can say well actually
let's first just try for each package
worth of data let's extract the mean and
the standard deviation of all these time
series or or maybe do a frequency
analysis and say well where is most
where is more of the energy in different
frequency bands and do some of that
feature engineering that pre-processing
that us as the experts say hey let's
help the machine learning tool to
extract the things that we care about
now if we do all that then we can indeed
we can say hey I'm going to dump these
data Maybe with some feature engineering
dump it into python mat lab or R and I
can indeed develop a set of questions
they're going to take as input the
speeds positions torque and tell me
level of where and it would look
something like this the the deals are
not that important and if I were then to
compare if I had split my data into
training and validation you know sort of
take my data like let's train on some of
it and use some of it to see how well
that our model is is working and we
plotted the the residuals the errors on
the things that we didn't use for our
training a perfect model would say well
the the error between what we predict
and what we actually measured for the
data that we didn't train on should be
zero a perfect model says the level of
of where in this case we're using a
surrogate for where we're using the age
of the blade but a perfect model would
be the residuals the errors would be
zeros we've developed a model that looks
really really really bad potentially
like we have there's a lot of zeros
where the model is actually predicting
what the reality is but we have
situations where we're predicting the
blade is actually 8 months older or 8
months younger than it actually is do we
care so here the axis the these this is
sort of package
number now this is a noisy sensor and
what do you do with a noisy
sensor you may filter it you may average
I don't care for each package that comes
through I don't need to predict well
what's the apparent age of the blade for
package number 24 package number 25
package number 26 I care about a larger
time scale is look at the like the last
100 packages and I can sort of filter
this data and from a physical
perspective that makes sense you know my
model can be really really really noisy
for any one observation but when I
filter it and average it over time at a
time scale that makes sense for my
context I can get down to sort of a a 2%
error rate that I can predict within
plus or minus a month how old this blade
how much wear is apparent on this blade
and use this now as a very simple
without with minimal cost with just a
little bit of physical insight and a
machine learning tool that's painfully
easy to use and painfully easy to train
and get significant added value now in
being able to do predictive and
preventive maintenance and so this is
sort of one project that is an example
of some of the things you can do with
just a little bit of that sort of you
know not using a complex tool but with a
little physical knowledge so now let's
up the complexity a little bit um this
is a project that we're working on with
Nissan um and ultimately what they would
like to do is improve the ability of
their quality control of a new variable
compression rate engine manufacturing
these new engines they an internal
combustion engine with a bunch of
additional mechanical part parts to
allow mechanical changing of the
compression ratio and this is an example
of we're sort of we're we're moving
beyond sort of assuming the world is
normal noral uh and sort of my my
opportunities here um so
first before I do that okay so a couple
of you nodded your heads yes with
explaining thinking that you could
explain to your direct reports or to
your supervisor to your family a
decision tree who would like to explain
to my seven-year-old how a neural net
Works anybody want to try how would you
explain a neural net
works like a brain okay and I'm not sure
my my seven-year-old doesn't understand
that how how do what is what is a neural
net what is it doing and I would argue
that a great way to demystify a neural
net is neural Nets and a lot of machine
learning looks just like line fitting if
you oversimplify a lot of supervised
learning you we either going to classify
something meaning past fail good bad
which is what we did with the packaging
or we're going to try to predict a
continuous parameter not dissimilar from
this toy data so what have I done here I
have a bunch of data points the red
things and I fit a digital twin okay
maybe it's not a twin because I'm not
continuously updating it but it's a
model and I looked at this data say hey
a line looks like the right thing maybe
this data is coming from a spring and so
I know there's a linear op relationship
between stiffness and and Forest for
example but I've decided as having the
context domain knowledge that a a
straight
line is a reasonable model to use and I
could go to Excel and I can say fit a
line so I've done a couple really
powerful things a I picked the model I I
picked the mathematical structure I said
hey for whatever reason whe whether it's
I visualized the data or I had some good
contextualized knowledge about it's a
spring that I'm characterizing I picked
something that is the right physical
structure that mathematically can be
described anybody remember the equation
for
yal MX plus b and that's it can be
described by a slope and an intercept so
the act of learning when I take this
data and I fit it to the line like I
picked the mathematical structure the
learning activity is finding what is the
optimal slope and what's the optimal
intercept some notion of optimality to
put this line through the data and it
you know the human eye looks at this and
say yeah that seems like a reasonable
thing I didn't draw a line that went up
like this I didn't draw a line that went
like this I didn't draw one that sort of
went this way either I picked in some
way this
line so I
can here we go uh and I have these
clouds here not to represent anything
other than don't really pay attention to
the details you can if you want it's
here for completeness but I can write
down first principles I can write down
analytically given a bunch of data given
my X and Y data points and given the
thing that I want to determine which a
slope in the intercept and given that
okay I'm going to choose this a notion
of
optimality meaning I have the prediction
for for some model that I haven't
determined yet it's going to predict an
output I'm going to compare that output
to my measured output and I'm going to
square those and I'm going to add them
all up and I want to minimize that thing
I'm going to say my my measure of
optimality is I want to drive that sum
of square error to zero as or get it as
low as possible once I done that I'm
going to go through calculus I'm going
to set first derivatives equal to zero
that you think back to calculus it's
back there someplace right set you want
to find you know what's the peak what's
the valley of something find where the
the derivatives are equal to zero
confirm the second derivative is either
a peak or a valley um but I can sort of
go through a little bit of mathematics
really relying on calculus and say well
given my model that has that can be
described by an A and A B given my data
I can just write down what the optimal a
and what the optimal B are
based on my data my data are given
they're fixed I'm trying to find the
slope of the intercept and I can just
tell you what they are given that this
is my error metric so that's exactly
what we do with a neuron
net with a line we're trying to find for
the mathematical structure described by
a line and I can write it down easily Y
is equal MX plus b I can find these
parameters in a neural net it's a little
bit more complex so a neural net
has for
example here's three neurons on the
input layer here's one neuron on the
output layer and what I'm doing
graphically and typically a neuron net
is just described by a bunch of circles
with connections but what actually the
mathematics under that is well I have in
this situation an input Vector that has
an X1 X2 and X3 so three
parameters and it's I'm trying to
predict some output y
and this neuron what what does this
neuron do this neuron takes parameter 1
2 and three multiplies it by a weight
weight one weight 2 weight three adds a
a a a bias to it and then passes it
through this thing that we call an
activation function which is just a a
function for which we have the
mathematical equation and I do that for
these three neurons I do that for this
neuron and so for this neuron net I've
picked a mathematical structure that I
can write down I can't write it down as
cleanly as = MX plus b but each thing
here is like I have well this neuron has
three parameters of Weights a bias I
multiply my X by a weight X2 by a weight
X3 by a weight and I do that for each
neuron and so it's exactly like line
fitting because now after I've done this
all I'm going to do is I'm going to
Define an error metric some a square
error and I'm going to go through some
calculus now the calculus I can't write
down analytically anymore so I need to
go to an optimization algorithm a
training algorithm that's going to
iteratively using something called
gradient descent which really just means
I'm going to iteratively apply calculus
to figure out how to change my weights
and biases iteratively slowly over time
until I get to a point where I found
weights and biases that are the best
possible to make this mathematical
structure the best that it can be in
mapping my input to my output that I the
data that I have but it's just like line
fitting I can't write it down analytic
anymore I need a and I have maybe a lot
more data so I can't load all my data
into memory but it's just like line
fitting so given that now okay that's
all you need to know today so hopefully
you can explain to my seven-year-old
that it's hey you can do it in Excel my
seven-year-old can actually use Excel so
maybe not every seven-year-old can
Google Sheets actually um but you know
so you can do neural Nets are just like
lines so now given that now let's put
this into the context of how we can use
this tool now the wonderful sidebar
interesting thing about neural Nets is
that there's a very nice elegant sort of
notion that a neural net neural Nets as
a structure can be used to represent any
function now the the sort of The
iterative Secret Sauce the art of neural
Nets saying yeah that particular neural
net I picked three neurons here a neuron
there I don't know how many neurons I
need and what the activation functions
are but a neuronet can be used to
represent any mathematical function
that's sort of the the power of them um
so now okay what's the problem this the
what's the manufacturing problem so here
we have this variable compression rate
engine and in this engine you know we
won't I won't play the video now but it
it mechanically sort of Alters the
compression ratio um and in the
manufacturer of this engine it goes
through multiple
stations and at each station a different
mechanical member is bolted together uh
it goes from station to one station
two they may um take some Dimensions
from the gaps of between a a part one
and part two after it's been bolted
together at each station so there a lot
of data that comes from each station and
we want to use this data want to
describe I'll describe the data a little
bit more we want to take the data that
we have from assembly and given that
this is a relatively new engine Nissan
does a functional test of every engine
and that functional test is very
timeconsuming very costly and and very
we'd like to get to a point where
instead of doing all of the assembly
operations which are never going to go
away assembly is never going to go away
can we start to reduce the amount of
physical testing that we need to do to
prevent a bad engine from exiting the
factory so the question is can we
develop a a
model relying we're going to use a
neural net to gave that away and we're
going to use some physical intuition to
sort of gather like do we expect success
um can we develop a model that will map
all these data that we're going to
collect from assembly to some notion of
the assem assembly or I'm sorry to some
notion of the physical functional test
so the data is on assembly we have the
dimensions of all the parts we have all
the torque versus time curves through
all the 100 plus bolts that are used to
assemble all these these parts together
and then once the engine is assembled we
then put the engine on a Shaker table
and we put an accelerometer on the
engine we shake the engine and we say
well we just record the data like how
much is the engine shaken shaking
for the this while sitting on the table
and we also will pressurize the engine
and we'll ask the question we'll measure
the amount of torque that's required to
BL break static friction and then how
much torque is required to keep the
shaft moving after you've broken static
friction and so the question is well do
we
expect if our data that we have on
assembly is all these torqus versus time
dimensions of all components dimensions
of the gaps between a assembled
components can we take all this assembly
data and predict something about the
functional test meaning how's the engine
shake how does it vibrate when I shake
it and how much torque does it withstand
when it's been pressurized what's the
physical do I have I know this is a
little bit more complex than cutting a
piece of plastic but is do I have a
physical intuition for why I might
expect success in being able to develop
a
model data pure at the moment that Maps
as input all of the assembly data that I
have to the functional
test and now it's the end of the
day well what happens if I don't bolt
the engine very
tightly it's going to shake a lot it's
going to shake a lot differently than if
I bolted it together well and what's
going to happen if I have a big gap
between the piston and the Piston wall
it's not going to pressure it's not
going to hold very much pressure and so
it's not going to take much torque to
break static friction and it's not going
to take much torque to keep it moving
right so at at base yeah hey if I if I
have big gaps in things it's not going
to pressurize if I don't bolt things
down very well how it shakes is going to
change so I I have some physical
intuition and so indeed if I do that I
can then with indeed some iteration
terms of the structure of the neural net
but it's a neural net Bunches of neurons
connected together and each neural n is
just a bunch of weights and biases and I
can take my data do line fitting and
find out what those weights and biases
are and indeed I can take all that data
from thousands of engines learn in your
own net learn the weights the slope and
The Intercept equivalent so I can map
assembly to test functional test and
here there are hundreds of dimensions in
this but here we're just showing for
example assembly generic assembly
parameter 1 generic assembly parameter 2
that predicts
the the colorful surface here is the
surface that the neural net mathematics
gives us after it's been trained
compared to the real data points in
blue and so the takeaway here is like
yeah indeed okay there is a Surface a
structure where this curve has gone
through my data in some appropriate way
so indeed I can take these data feed
them into a neural net and and develop
this mapping now if you're if you're
Nissan you don't yet trust the fact that
okay this is a relatively new technique
a relatively new approach and we're not
yet going to go from testing every
engine to testing no engines and we're
actually we're just going to still fully
test every single engine and so what
we're going to do is we're going to
indeed use our trained model take our
assembly data for a new engine predict
what the functional test would be
compare that functional test to the real
test that we still do and now we
actually have a quality signal that
we've been able to use to bin the
engines every engine passes but we're
able to we've demonstrated be able to
predict like these really good these
engines are good enough to pass but we
can now use these in a in a creative way
to help us get some additional Insight
um in terms of the quality of the
engines okay so um I'm assuming the
timer started when I actually started
talking as opposed to given all the the
sort of the rig roll that we went
through to get slides going but the the
last thing that I want to share with you
just to complete the
story is okay case one very simple easy
to understand easy to interpret tool
decision tree hey I can see what the
questions are neural net it's a little
harder to understand I don't know what
the weights and biases mean I just know
that they are what they are to give me a
result and I need to iteratively explore
them so here I I'll show just
briefly um a paper that has led to sort
of a lot of interesting conversations
with companies and a lot of interesting
research and a lot of interesting
deployments we first use this um a full
melding if you will of real time control
and statistical process
control in this thing that we give a new
name deep reinforcement learning so deep
reinforcement learning
is I'll skip to this slide right there
so this is a graphical representation of
the mathematics of this thing called
Deep reinforcement learning but I guess
the point that I want to make here is
through the lens of manufacturing if I
sort of break down this thing that is
simultaneously trying to control the
process of in this case fiber
Extrusion um and figure out how to do
the realtime adjustments to get 125
extruded Micron fiber which is the
backbone of our wireless communication
Network Glass fiber that's embedded
under the ground under the ocean every
place um and I want to
simultaneously do realtime control and
collect the historical data of what I'm
doing and passes through this thing
called an actor critic Network that's
not important what I'm really doing is
this is realtime control and this is
statistical process control in one
mathematical structure and so instead of
saying there's a wall between realtime
control and statistical process control
my mathematical structure is at
different time scales doing real-time
control here seeing what the long-term
trends are and based on those long-term
trends slowly updating the models that
we use for our field our real-time
control um so just showing that you know
that that piece looks like realtime
control that looks like a realtime
controller and all this other pieces
just the memory the thing that the
long-term data where we don't and we no
longer assume that it looks like normal
distribution and we no longer have a
somebody that needs to hey well we see
that our run charts are going off let's
figure out what was the deterministic
source of error that stuff happens
automatically now in all
honesty companies have been coming to me
say hey we saw this paper we'd like to
apply this to Coffee Roasting which
we've done we've applied this to
packaging but I'd say there have been 20
companies that have come to us and said
hey we think this is going to solve our
problem and six months to a year into
the Endeavor I say actually you know
what you don't need this you just need
to do better PID controllers you just
need actually your your your your your
sensor over here was not grounded uh the
data that we found the data that we're
using so like we of if if for no other
reason the advanced tools are driving
putting into place what best practice
should be with current tools that's a
plus that's a huge win right ignoring
sort of all the advanced things but the
advanced things AI still can be cast as
real-time control and statistical
process control um and I'll skip over
these in the in in the interest of time
I do want to end I'm going to skip over
that that we talked about data security
for a moment um I want to end with this
with a sort of a a a a please reach out
to me
um couple weeks ago um we talked a
little bit I think um Liz talked a
little bit about the manufacturing
institutes um there's things like aim
photonics NEX Flex uh MDX that are these
these fronhofer leg organizations in the
US that are intended to bridge the gap
between manufacturing innovations that
are happening both in universities and
companies in sort of the the at scale
Department of Commerce has been
competing two one the the semiconductor
digital twin one has been announced this
proposal is due in the end of January in
MIT there are three teams that I'm aware
of Nationwide and as a company you
should engage with I would love for you
to engage with our team but you should
engage with every team because one
team's going to win and everybody's
going to work with that team because
it's a national resource but the idea is
that these this will be an Institute
that has some some funds from the
government um to accelerate sort of
commercial use of said funds to try to
help to accelerate how we deploy AI in
small companies and big companies and
having both sort of pillars within how
we use AI in design in operations and
supply chain and then taking a
significant lead as well and well how do
we actually figure out the best ways to
train the workforce both the the
entrenched worker and the sort of upand
cominging worker and we're looking for
um partners with which to Pilot
companies that have data that would
they' be willing to share companies that
would be openly willing to engage in
co-investment to get this uh Institute
going forward so I'd love to if anybody
has an interest in learning more please
do reach out um we're feverishly as the
days been going by I've been feverishly
communicating with the team of multiple
universities multiple companies that are
putting this proposal together um so
it's an exciting opportunity um to sort
of bring together both Federal
investment uh and and Company investment
do really try to accelerate how we use
and teach and understand the use of AI
um in manufacturing