Welcome to the 2025
Gardener Lecture.
I'm Julie Shah.
I'm the department
head here at AeroAstro.
And this is a very exciting
event that we hold each year.
And so thank you so much for all
coming out to be a part of it.
The Gardner Lecture is
made possible by a bequest
of the late Major Lester D.
Gardner, a member of the MIT
class of 1898, to sponsor
annual presentations
on aeronautical history.
He was an air officer
in World War One.
And he was the recipient of
numerous aeronautical awards,
including the Daniel
Guggenheim Medal in 1947,
given for the citation for
Outstanding Achievement
in Advancing Aeronautics.
He had a long and
storied career.
He established a
publishing group
that's responsible for a number
of major aeronautical trade
publications, including the
predecessor to Aviation Week.
And he was also the
founder of the Institute
for Aeronautical
Sciences, which eventually
evolved to become our AIAA.
Major Gardner's interest
in MIT and our department
continued throughout his life.
And it lives on not only in
this Gardner Lecture, which
is a big, important event
for us in the department,
but also in the
Hunsaker professorship,
which he helped to establish.
And in his honor, we
continue the tradition
of hosting the Gardner
Lecture to celebrate
our history and our field,
and to keep looking ahead
by looking up.
And so over the years,
our Gardner Lectures
have included Grover Loening;
Igor Sikorsky; Yvonne Brill;
Neil Armstrong; Robert
Seamans, Jr.; John Langford;
Pam Melroy, just to name a few.
And so with that incredible
history under our belts,
it's my great pleasure
to welcome and introduce
this year's Gardner
speaker, Dave Limp.
Dave is CEO of Blue Origin,
a private space company
founded by Jeff Bezos, with a
vision of millions of people
living and working in space
for the benefit of Earth.
And as you all know, the company
builds reusable rocket engines,
launch vehicles and space
systems and lunar landers.
So Dave joined Blue
Origin as CEO in 2023.
And he also serves as the board
chair for Blue Origin's Club
for the Future, which is a
nonprofit organization dedicated
to inspiring and mobilizing
future generations
to pursue careers in STEM.
Dave has previously been
at Amazon, since 2010,
where he oversaw the
development, retail sales,
and operational aspects of
Amazon's consumer electronics
devices and the
services behind them.
So, including Alexa,
Echo, Kindle, Fire TV,
Ring, just to name a few, as
well as other initiatives,
such as Project Kuiper.
And many MIT alumni have gone
on to work at Blue Origin.
And we've also had quite
a few research payloads
launch on Blue Origin's
New Shepard rockets.
So now, with Dave at
the helm, Blue Origin
is exploring increasingly
ever more exciting
missions and aerospace
engineering challenges
that are truly at the
cutting edge of spaceflight.
And he's here today to
tell us all about it.
So please join me
in welcoming Dave.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
Thank you, Professor Shah.
I hear the previous
speakers on this
and the quote from Wayne's
World pops up in my head,
that I'm not worthy.
So I'm going to do my best
to give you little words.
Hopefully, they inspire
you in some ways.
This lecture series
goes back to 1959.
And it's just an amazing
honor to be here.
I want to talk
today about how we
as a collective species,
and specifically this class
and you all, given your
focus on aerospace,
can help build a road to space.
This is a big, really
important mission in our mind
and one that's going to
take multigenerations to do.
But it is critically important.
And so to plant
that seed, I'm going
to start with a quick video.
And then we can
talk about something
that is seemingly small.
But is the seed that plants
this very, very large vision.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- Holy cats, weightlessness.
Oh, Jesus.
[LAUGHTER]
Oh, my God.
Oh, wow.
I can't believe this.
Everybody in the world
needs to see this.
- Stand by, touchdown.
Stand by, touchdown.
- There is Mother
Earth and comfort.
But what you see is black.
Oh, my God.
I hope I never
recover from this.
I hope that I can
maintain what I feel now.
I don't want to lose it.
[LAUGHTER]
What you have given me is
the most profound experience
I can imagine.
I'm so filled with emotion
about what just happened.
Jesus.
Oh, my God.
It was unbelievable.
Oh, I'm telling you--
[END PLAYBACK]
You saw Bill there.
And there's been
over 700 people that
have gone above the Karman line
and had their version of this.
I've been super lucky to
meet a number of astronauts,
a pretty significant number.
And Julie and I have
seen a few of them
in some of the same conferences.
And to a T--
I haven't met them
all-- but to a T,
they all have a similar story
to what you just saw Bill have.
There's actually a name for it.
It's the overview effect.
And everybody comes
back from space
changed in many different ways.
But one common thread
is this overview effect.
And it's the sense that as soon
as you leave the atmosphere,
you see how thin of a
line there is protecting
this great planet, Earth.
And then you look up and you
see the deep darkness of space
and see how vast it is.
And you come back with a
feeling that Earth is small,
Earth is fragile, and
Earth should be protected.
And we've sent-- with lots of
people in this room's help--
probes to all the moons--
most of the moons-- all the
planetary bodies we've crossed.
And rest assured, the
Earth is the good planet
if you want to live.
And we know that now.
And so our purpose
is to figure out
how to think about
that in that context
and preserve that
which is the Earth.
And to do that, we have
to think about what
has happened over the
past couple hundred years.
If you go back a
couple hundred years,
and you think about almost every
metric that we would measure
prosperity by, life expectancy
is up from 40 to 75 years,
infant mortality is decreased
from 175 deaths per 1,000
to less than 28.
Global literacy is
at an all time high,
highly correlated to prosperity.
Poverty rates are below 10%.
Hunger is at an all-time low.
I could go on and
on and on again.
And you would find reasons why
our lives are incredibly better
than they were.
There's one notable
difference, though.
That notable
difference is, I can't
go down to the Charles
River, ladle up
a good scoop of that
water and drink it.
We've paid the price
of all this prosperity
by using some of the
natural resources that
are on this Earth.
By any dimension,
it's more polluted.
We could argue how
much warmer it is.
But the fact of the matter is,
it's still the great planet.
And our job is to try to
figure out how to preserve it.
And this is the foundation of
our mission statement, which
is, in a simplified way, we want
to take the polluting industries
and move them to space.
And then we can rezone this
great planet of ours, Earth,
to parks, recreation, maybe
a little light industry,
roller coasters, you name it.
But it's going to
be a place that you
can come back and visit.
Some people still live here.
And we'll be prosperous
in space and preserve
that which is the thing
we love about Earth.
So for the next 20,
25 minutes or so,
I'm going to try to paint a
blueprint of the infrastructure,
the key pieces.
And they're not all of them.
They're not all-inclusive.
But some of the key
pieces that we think
are critical to invent, to
make this a reality as we
move forward.
So the first thing I would say
is that to get this to happen,
space needs fundamental
infrastructure.
And if you think about the
building blocks of any step
function change, as
you think about how
to get to a big
vision like this,
it is the infrastructure that
you actually think about.
I have a front row seat to this
because I've spent a lot of time
with Jeff.
And Jeff tells the story of
this in the context of Amazon.
So let me tell you that
story about Amazon.
Jeff started Amazon in
a garage in Seattle.
It's just him, a
couple other people.
And yet now you look ahead
and it is your new normal.
What would you do without it?
How would you get
packages delivered to you?
How would you do this?
But how does one or two or three
people do this in a garage?
It's because they
had infrastructure
that they could rely on.
They were standing on
the shoulders of giants.
They didn't have to build an
entire transportation network.
There was UPS, there was FedEx,
there was the postal system.
They didn't have to build
new payment systems.
There were credit
card companies--
Visa, Mastercard,
American Express.
All those existed.
So you didn't have
to go build that.
You didn't have to build
that which was the internet.
That was on the backs
of DARPA and Xerox PARC
and a lot of other
research institutions
that had built
this infrastructure
to be able to move bits around.
And so the young entrepreneur
that was Jeff at that time
could focus on building
the application layer,
knowing that all that
infrastructure existed for him.
And we want to do the
same thing for space,
build that infrastructure such
that when your kids' kids--
it's likely a multi-generation
thing-- wake up and decide,
gosh, I want to do X in space,
they can take it for granted
that all the hard,
heavy lifting is there
and focus on the
application layer of what
they want to bring to market.
So what do we want to do?
I'm going to give you a couple
different infrastructure
pieces, selfishly that
Blue is working on.
But there's lots of other
people working on this as well.
The first is we have
to dramatically reduce
the cost of launch,
specifically, dramatically
reduce the cost of a
kilogram of payload
to the orbit of your choice.
One of the hardest
things here is, in fact,
getting payload to space
in an affordable manner.
Now, we've done this.
You can go all the way
back to the Apollo program.
And we got a lot of mass
all the way to the Moon.
It came in an incredible cost.
At the peak Apollo,
it was spending--
there's different estimates on
this-- but spending about 2.5%
of GDP per year.
That is an unfathomable
amount of money.
Give me 2.5% of GDP, I will
give you fusion in 10 years.
But it's not going to happen.
And even at the end of
Apollo, the American people
got fed up with it.
It was too much of a
drag on the economy.
And it had to be slowed
down and eventually
shut down because it's
unsustainable at those rates.
But you can do amazing
things in space
if you have the
ability to do this.
So our job as this industry,
and certainly at Blue,
is how to take the amount
of price of that kilogram
to orbit and bring it down?
And you can start
seeing this on a curve.
It's a logarithmic curve--
dollars on one axis and
then years on the other.
And you can start seeing where
the knee in the curve happened.
And specifically, where
that started happening,
is when you started to
see the introduction
of reusable rockets.
When you get in your car and you
drive from point A to point B,
you don't throw away
your car into the ocean
at the end of the trip.
Similarly, when you get
on a Southwest Airlines
and you fly point A to point
B, they don't scrap the plane.
Yet, for the last 50 years,
except for the last 10,
that is how we treated rockets.
We just got rid of them.
They were disposable.
And so reusability is a key.
And Professor Shah
mentioned that you've
seen some of this in
some of your classwork
because we have a
suborbital reusable vehicle.
And it's incredibly profound
that things like this
are our new normal.
Just 10 years ago,
this was the thing
that science fiction
was made up of,
that the idea that we would
be landing rockets literally
every other day,
or every third day
right now, orbital,
suborbital, is just
an amazing and profound change.
And this reuse is
completely new.
And on the booster
side, it dramatically
changes the formula.
And as we start thinking
about reusing second stages,
it furthers that formula.
And you can see us
continuing to climb down
that curve that I showed you.
I know this is something
that you, in Course 16,
have been studying a lot.
And you've put payloads on this.
So it shouldn't be new to you.
But it's dramatic in its ability
to help us down that cost curve.
The second part of
the cost curve--
anybody know what this is?
No.
Rocket formula.
There you go, OK.
Extra credit for you.
I have no grades to
give, but you get it.
So this is--
Tsiolkovsky is often
credited with this.
I think there's some controversy
that it might have been Moore.
But anyway, this is a
very famous formula that
tells us a lot about delta-v.
But one of the most incredible
things that it says is--
it's a function of wet
mass over dry mass.
And it leads you to a lot
of different conclusions.
The one I'll focus on here
today is that it leads you--
that rockets want to be bigger.
As rockets get bigger,
that mass fraction changes.
And every extra amount
that fraction gives you,
we can move to payload, assuming
we're maxing out on payload.
You could argue that some
payload is volume out.
And so we want to
be able to do that.
And that is where the
industry is moving.
We're moving to
ever larger rockets.
It's another place-- it's kind
of amazing how much the Apollo
engineers had right.
I'll talk some more
about that later.
But large rockets have
incredibly good mass fractions.
And you can start seeing that in
the percentage of the propellant
that goes over the payload.
And our rocket, which is New
Glenn, our big rocket-- which
we launched earlier
this year, got to orbit.
Haven't landed it yet.
But just hang on to your hats.
Coming soon-- is an incredibly
large rocket by any measure
that we would have been talking
about just five or 10 years ago.
It's 320 feet tall.
It can throw 45 metric
tons to LEO orbit,
which is 13 metric tons to a
high energy orbit like GEO.
So this is an
incredible workhorse.
But more important
than that, it also
has a completely
reusable first stage.
We launch from the Cape.
We land out on a barge about
300 nautical miles offshore.
We barge it back in.
We refurbish it for
a couple of days.
And then we go ahead
and try to fly again.
And it also has--
I talked about that
mass is important,
but increasingly
the amount of volume
that you can put up as well.
It gives you more flexibility
to design the payloads.
So our fairing size is 7 meters.
So to give you a sense of
the size of that fairing,
New Shepard, which I
showed you land earlier,
with the nose cone on it, can
fit into the payload fairing
of New Glenn, to give
you a perspective
on the size of this vehicle.
And it's powered by
seven BE-4 engines that
are methalox engines and
optimized for the atmosphere.
And then the upper
stage is powered
by BE-3 engines, which are very
high efficient and optimized
for non-atmospheric work.
So these are incredibly
powerful vehicles.
And when you get to
this size again start
seeing the cost per kilogram
of payload come down.
I would be remiss to
talk about New Glenn
without at least
showing you a launch.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- There we go.
- [CHANTING]
- I think it's a big
day for a lot of us.
A lot of us worked
many, many years,
putting a lot of blood, sweat,
and tears to get to this point.
And it's a very,
very awesome day.
- I'm very excited
for the world to see
what Blue Origin is capable of.
- I'm most looking forward to
seeing us safely reach orbit.
And I'm excited to celebrate it
with my team and with my wife.
- [INAUDIBLE] set the fire
switch to launch function.
Liftoff.
- All seven engines
have full throttle.
- [INAUDIBLE] continues
to perform well.
Now, passes through
max q, [INAUDIBLE].
- We have ignition
and [INAUDIBLE].
Chamber pressure is good.
- GS-2 is now orbital.
- As soon as we saw liftoff, we
were like, oh my God, we did it.
We got to orbit.
What an incredible rumble
from the diesel engine.
[END PLAYBACK]
Yeah.
[APPLAUSE]
Never gets old.
You just got to do it
over and over again.
I also love-- the thing about
that video I love is the BE-4
team is like--
they see Miko.
And they're just like,
we're done, we're out.
Meanwhile, the BE-3, the Blue
team, the upper stage team,
is just like-- just sweating
bullets trying to get to orbit.
It's OK, though.
So what have you
done for me lately?
It's great.
[LAUGHTER]
So we talked about
reducing the cost of mass.
That's the first critical
infrastructure thing
that we have to think about.
The second critical
infrastructure thing
I would postulate is how do we
build a hydrogen space economy?
So why do we want hydrogen?
Well, there's a lot of reasons,
but some have come very true
to fruition in the
very recent time,
which is with the
latest exploration--
that's just again all come
about in the last decade or so--
is now we have very
high confidence
that water is on many parts
of the Moon and also on Mars.
And this means you
can just crack H2O.
And we can get both the
fuel and the oxidizer
from hydrogen. And being able
to get that, if you just go back
to the rocket equation, the
mass fraction would tell you--
for all the things that
make this Earth great,
the atmosphere is pretty good.
I like it.
Gravity, 1 G-- kind
of like 1 G, too.
But it's pesky for rockets.
So every time we have to
bring fuel up or oxidizer up,
it's just mass, that if we
could build it in space,
it's so much better.
And so knowing that
we now have water
on Earth-- on the Moon and
Mars and likely elsewhere,
gives us high confidence that
hydrogen was the right choice.
But again, I go back
to the Apollo era.
And they had it right again.
It's amazing how a bunch
of folks using slide rules
had so many design decisions.
But this is another
example of it,
which is that you
really do like to have
a carbon-based first stage
engine-- in our case,
we're using liquid natural gas.
But back in the Apollo days,
it was a different propellant--
because you have such
good density from it.
So you can pack a lot
more in your tanks.
And while you're fighting that
atmospheric and gravitational
drag, you can go ahead
and get through that.
However, when you start
getting to upper stages
and you're not
fighting those forces,
you want to try to
get something that's
much, much more efficient.
And when you think
about ISP in an engine,
the actual specific
impulse of the engine,
there's really
almost nothing that
beats the ability to put
hydrogen and oxygen together.
And it just makes sense.
And so we have chosen
that for those reasons.
Now, there's obviously
downsides to this.
I can make a lot of
arguments about why
you wouldn't want
to do this, not
the least of which is they're
entirely different engines,
with entirely different cycles.
So the logical choice, if
you're running a business,
is to just say, OK, I'm going
to take my atmospheric engine
and I am just going to
optimize a vacuum version of it
and I'm going to call it a day.
It's less test stands,
less infrastructure,
less ability to have
things go wrong.
But the right answer
architecturally,
to create a hydrogen
economy, is to have
optimized hydrogen engines.
And we do it not only
in what you see here,
which is-- this is the BE-3U.
That was the upper stage
engines you saw on the video.
And there's two of those
on the New Glenn vehicle.
But we also have a secondary
hydrogen-oxygen engine.
Different cycle, smaller,
10,000 pounds thrust engine,
that we're developing, called
BE-7, that is available--
think of it as the
inter-solar system engine,
to get you around.
So it'll fly our
transporter to the Moon.
It'll power our lander
to land on the Moon.
And it also uses hydrogen
for all the same reasons,
that it's readily available
and incredibly good
in terms of performance.
So what's the other downside of
going to hydrogen and oxygen?
Well, they're stored
at cryo temperatures.
And cryo temperatures
have this pesky thing.
They want to boil off.
And we can insulate them.
We do and we can.
But for longer duration missions
in space, traversed to the Moon,
starting to think about
traverses to Mars, that boiloff
as a percentage of--
you can see the numbers
here-- as a percentage
of where you are starts
to add up pretty quickly.
And so you want to figure
out how are there ways
that you can mitigate this?
Again, insulation helps,
but in itself is not enough.
And so, again,
thinking about what
do you have to build to
do this hydrogen economy,
it comes back to what
do you have to invent.
And so in this case, you
want to invent a cryocooler.
And so zero boiloff
cryocoolers-- by the way,
cryocoolers are not
anything that's brand new.
If you ever see somebody
with heat vision goggles--
they have a version
of these kinds
of things in miniature Stirling
engines and things like that,
inside of them.
But when you want
to do this in space,
it's just never really
been done before.
And you're talking about
liquid hydrogen, liquid oxygen.
And you need to store them at
very, very low temperatures
and in a vacuum.
This is one of those
things where I say,
when I got to Blue 18
months ago, I was actually--
I was worried about
this invention.
It had never been demonstrated.
But we hit our NASA
milestone about two months
ago or so, on Earth.
So we still haven't
done it in space.
But it was in vacuum on Earth.
We demonstrated that we
were able to, in vacuum,
keep at 20k and 90k.
Those are the
stable temperatures
that we need to
keep liquid hydrogen
and oxygen from boiling off.
And so it's a huge
milestone change.
Again, hard problem--
but if we can knock down
these hard problems,
we can actually
get the incredible foundation
of this hydrogen ecosystem
in space.
So we talked about reducing the
cost of space at least to orbit.
We've talked about building
a hydrogen economy.
Third, I would
postulate that the Moon
is our strategic gateway.
And this may not be the
common wisdom across all space
companies, but it is ours.
And I don't know where you all
fall down on the Fermi paradox.
But if you're in
the simulation camp,
the Moon would be a cheat code.
I mean, who would possibly
put this body three days away
from Earth, no atmosphere, with
asteroids and meteorites hitting
it for millions of
years, guaranteed
to have every element
known to personkind on it.
You would never have
guessed something
like this could
possibly have happened.
But, indeed, it is there.
And I don't think
we're in a simulation.
So we're going to use it.
[LAUGHTER]
And it's our mine, our resource
depot, three days away.
And it's incredibly
rich in resources.
And it's something
that we really want.
We want to do.
So a lot of what we're
doing is thinking
about going back to the Moon.
But it's not just about
going back to the Moon.
In fact, our lunar team
is not called Lunar.
It's called Lunar Permanence.
We've been to the Moon.
We've been there and back
a few times, a dozen times.
But we didn't stick.
And that was an
amazing accomplishment,
by the way-- probably
fast-forwarded
the Moon 20 years, the
Apollo program, if not more.
But now you want to
go there to stay.
And you want to go
there and be able to use
the resources that are up there
in clever and innovative ways.
So how are we doing that?
Well, we're going to
do it in two steps.
This is the original
Apollo lunar
module, the LEM on top of it.
Our first vehicle, that you see
here, is our Mark 1 vehicle.
It is in final
assembly right now.
It's just about to go off to
vacuum test in a little bit.
And it is a cargo lander.
And we'll go to the Moon, first
quarter of next year probably,
in that range.
And it will be the
biggest vehicle
to have ever landed on the Moon.
We're not going to make it easy.
We're going to do a
triple Lindy here.
We're going to land it on near
the south pole of the Moon.
So it's a big
effort for the team.
But just to put
that in comparison,
then contrast it to
what we call Mark 2--
by the way, Mark 1--
we just won a NASA contract
to take Viper to the Moon.
So it'll be serial
number 2 of Mark 1
will take Viper to the Moon.
And then next to it is the
human-rated Mark 2 vehicle.
We're also doing a
cargo version of that.
But to give you a sense
of the scale of that,
it's 15 meters tall--
30 metric tons to
the lunar surface.
So this is the
semi-truck that is
going to be able to
pull lots of cargo
down to the Moon to allow
us to get that permanence
and begin to plant the
seeds for a permanent base
there, that we can then-- again,
manufacturing, mine the Moon,
and begin to build the
infrastructure there to hop
off to the rest.
And so you can see an incredible
amount of difference in mass
from where the Apollo
missions were up until--
that might be a typo.
I think it's 30 metric
tons, but I could be wrong.
So what do we have to
do to make the Moon more
interesting in terms
of infrastructure--
back to the same things.
Actually, this is going to
seem very duplicative to some
of the students
that presented to me
earlier on your
own class project,
or I guess NASA project,
for being able to navigate
autonomously on the Moon.
We're going to have
to build vehicles
that can traverse the Moon.
Some are going to
do mining, some
are going to be
to do exploration,
some are going to be transport.
And the first stages
of this are how
do we build a rover that
can be able to do this?
And I know you guys--
the Maple team, which
I saw present earlier
today, it was just
great to see the
progress you made.
Second place is a huge
achievement in this.
And I was sitting
there biting my tongue
because I know how hard the
problem is, because I meet
with this team every
two weeks and I
get a sense of what's going on.
So our effort here is to start
taking payloads up to the Moon.
Our first one will be on
Firefly's next lander.
Our honeybee team
is doing the rover.
And it will be a
traditional rover
in every sense of the word.
It's lower cost.
But it will be teleoperated
and be able to be teleoperated.
But we're, in
parallel with that,
going to put a complete
autonomous package on it,
so that we, in parallel, can
run experiments about what does
autonomy look like on the Moon?
So that vehicles after
that and after that
will get steadily more
advanced as we move through.
And I think, again, it was
one of those things that
was shown in very, very
good detail earlier today.
But having worked on
autonomous vehicles
for a lot of the last
10 years of my life--
Zoox was in my team at Amazon--
much of the problem of
getting autonomy working
is a data problem.
That's why when you go
around San Francisco,
you see lots of Waymo
cars with a driver in it,
with sensors on it or Zoox cars.
They are training
up the road systems
and getting data
and understanding
what are the anomalous things
that happen in traffic.
Last time I checked, we
don't have those on the Moon.
And, in fact, you could say,
oh, but wasn't Apollo up there
with a rover?
Yes-- but the
cameras, not so good.
They were running.
I think there's seven
hours of true video.
But when you back
it off, it ends up
being about an hour
because it was running
at 12 frames per second.
It only took a snapshot
every so often.
And so we do have that data.
But it is not
representative of what
you're going to see, especially
at different parts of the Moon.
As you get to the poles,
obviously, the lighting
conditions change dramatically.
And you can be in night
for a long period of time.
You can be in sunlight
And so the navigation challenge
becomes incredibly complicated.
And so what we're able to
do through simulation--
this is actually a game engine
running our lunar terrain
scenarios internally.
And we can then do a digital
twin of what a rover looks like.
And we can try different
sensor packages
and say, huh, I wonder if it'd
be better with stereo optics
or it'd be better with LiDAR?
Would it be better if we
had a really good IMU?
Or should we figure out
a way that the lander has
really, really
interesting beacons
and use trigonometry to
figure the problem out.
There's lots of different
ways you can solve this.
But it turns out to be a
pretty tractable problem.
And we are very
excited about where
we're going to get to here.
The other thing about the Moon--
I talked about how
resource-rich it is--
is that you don't
have to go very far.
I was implying
that you could dig
and you'd find platinum
here and gold there
and unobtainium there.
That's true.
I'm very big an
optimist on that.
But the regolith itself is
incredibly rich in resources.
So we have a whole different
team called Blue Alchemist.
Again, infrastructure--
figuring out
how to build reactors that
can be powered on the Moon,
but that you can just put in one
side of this robotic reactor,
throw the regolith in it, and
literally out the other end
is going to come a
silicon solar panel.
And this has been proven in our
labs already in the piece parts.
And we're now in the
formulation stage
of putting that all together.
And in our labs, in California,
we're getting purities
of silicon at more than,
I guess, three or four--
five 9s at this point, 99.999%.
So this is incredibly optimistic
to be able to now create
power on the Moon.
And once we crack
silica and that,
the refining process
actually works across a lot
of different types of things.
So the more we find out
about regolith and what's
there and one layer below,
the more this on premise, on
lunar ability to be able
to get rich resources
is really going to
be game changing
in a sense of infrastructure.
Again, it's just
less payload you
have to bring from other Earth.
The final thing I want
to talk about in terms
of infrastructure-- we've
talked about lowering the cost,
hydrogen economy, use this cheat
code of the moon as a stepping
stone--
is building comms
infrastructure.
If there's anything
we've learned on Earth,
is that comms communications
infrastructure
is incredibly important.
The amount of just exponential
growth in both free speech
and the ability to
understand what's going on,
because we have open comms
systems and effectively
unlimited bandwidth in
lots of parts of the Earth,
has changed how we think
about our social life.
It certainly thinks about how
we change about our work life.
It changes productivity.
There's no reason to believe
that that's not going
to be true in space as well.
And if you look at the
infrastructure in space today--
again, not taking anything away
from the amazing engineers that
put the infrastructure
that's there--
it's aging.
The infrastructure around Mars
should have died many years ago.
What's around cislunar is aging.
Even in the upper parts of Earth
orbit is aging in many ways.
And so we believe that
you have to think about
how do we build the
internet of space,
how do we lay that
infrastructure?
So again, that entrepreneur,
that's coming in the future,
just knows comms is
free or so inexpensive.
It rounds to free.
And so one of the things
that we're thinking about
to start this is building--
we have a satellite
platform that
can be used for lots of
different esoteric orbits.
It can be in GEO.
This example I'm
showing you here
is for the Mars
Communication Orbiter or MCO.
So we would take a-- this is
a 20 kilowatt satellite bus.
It has an incredible delta-v--
4,000 meters of delta-v through
both chemical and electrical
propulsion.
And we would send this to Mars.
It would sit in Mars orbit.
Then you can see it shed off a
bunch of little baby satellites,
because it has a lot of payload.
That would circle Mars.
Think of them as the Kuiper
constellation around Mars.
And they would then
call back to this hub,
which is highly powered.
And it would use laser
communications and RF
communications to get back
to something in LEO orbit
on Earth or a ground station,
depending on what we do.
And then you can
then stamp these out.
You can do a few
around cislunar.
You can do one out in GEO.
You can communicate down
to these proliferated LEO
constellations, like
Starlink or Kuiper.
And you begin to start
seeing an architecture where
you, as an entrepreneur, have
this amazing comms capability,
just like you have if you plug
in to your Wi-Fi that's kind
of right around the corner.
This is a sense of the
kind of data bandwidth
that we'll be able to change.
And i it's an order of
magnitude at least--
I think we'll actually
do a little bit better
than this-- as when you can
start thinking about this.
And the first
advantages here is not
going to be that
young entrepreneur.
Like I said, that's multiple
build generations away.
But it's going to be science.
And we're going to
learn more about Mars.
So much is throttled today
about what we can put down
on the surface of
Mars for payloads
or on the surface of the Moon.
And more bandwidth we have, the
more science that can be done,
the more we'll understand
about these bodies
as we look through this.
So I'll just finish
just summarizing
a few of these things.
That if you're going
to go and build
a place where millions of people
can live and work in space,
you have to start somewhere.
Somebody asked me this question
earlier today at lunch.
They said, well,
where do you start?
And I would postulate, what
we talked about here today is
where you start.
Start with the LEGO building
blocks that are infrastructure.
And if you start there
and you do it well and get
other companies to do
it well, then generation
after this or the generation
after that will help a lot.
My team would kill me
if I just stopped there.
So I'm going to give a
unbelievable pitch for MIT.
Despite not going
to this university,
I'm still going to give a pitch.
We have incredible people.
I know a number of you
have done internships.
Thank you for that.
If you haven't
done an internship
and you want to do an
internship, please,
that would be great, too.
But some of the faces
that you see here--
Jordan is the
first one up there.
He runs all of New Glenn
and he is an MIT graduate.
Henry, who runs the entire
second stage and reusable
and fairing program,
MIT graduate.
And his son just was one of
the 10 most recent invitees
to be astronauts for NASA.
So that's kind of cool, too.
And I would just
say that I'm biased.
I'll be the first
person to say that.
But I love this company.
It is so missionary.
I told Jeff I would do
this for free for him.
Luckily, he didn't
take me up on that.
[LAUGHTER]
But every little bit
of it, I go to work
with a smile on because I
really do think WHAT we're doing
is helpful for the planet
and it's very cool.
And so often, having worked
in and around technology
for 30 years, you don't
often find the Venn diagrams
that intersect there, where
it's awesome, cool technology.
And you just have
a ball doing it.
Sometimes it's laborious
or sometimes you
trade those various
different things.
So I want to thank you for that.
And before I go
to Q&A, I did want
to ask Professor Shah
to come up as well.
We've been thinking about
this relationship from MIT
for a long time, so
much so that every
once in a while on New Shepard,
we fly a pennant to space.
And this one went up
on our first flight.
And so there's not
many from that flight.
But we wanted to present
it to MIT as a thank you
for the partnership.
OK.
Yeah, thank you.
That's awesome.
Thank you so much.
I appreciate that.
[APPLAUSE]