[Music]
From the MIT Energy Initiative, this is
What If It Works, looking at the energy
solutions for climate change. I'm Cara
Miller. And I'm Rob Stoner.
[Music]
And today we're joined by Munji Buendi.
He's a professor of chemistry at MIT who
has thought a lot about creative ways to
reimagine clean energy technologies. He
also recently received the Nobel Prize.
He's a co-winner of the 2023 prize in
chemistry. But Wendy's early research
led to more energyefficient lighting and
televisions, but also to lots of work on
creating more efficient solar cells. As
a post-doal student, he worked in the
famed Bell Labs, a place where he says
he learned a lot about chemistry in part
because there just weren't that many
people around to help him out. It was an
amazing place because it was populated
with extremely talented, ambitious
scientists that were giving a lot of
trust and a lot of free reign. It was a
place that had a lot of equipment, but
not many hands. As a result, you had to
build a community if you wanted to get
anything done. So, everybody was happy
to talk to anybody else. In fact, it was
part of the job to to talk to everybody.
There was no army of graduate students.
It was each scientist with a technician
and maybe a postoc and that was pretty
much it. What that meant, Boendi says,
is that he learned a ton. Now, by
contrast, he does a lot of paperwork in
order to have the funds to keep his lab
running and to support his doctoral and
post-doal students. At Bell Labs, he
spent a great deal of his time just
thinking about science. What I didn't
know much about or really much at all
about was synthetic chemistry, making
things. You know, I was a measurement
person. But at Bell Labs, in the
atmosphere of Bell Labs, you were you
were allowed and encouraged to learn new
things and to try new things. And I
worked in Mike Stigerwal's group lab
rather, who was a organic metallic
chemist makes molecules and he taught me
everything I know about chemistry, how
to make molecules, you know, using
inorganic chemistry. And then from uh
from Bill Wilson who's now uh at Harvard
who was a a laser expert you know I
learned everything about visible lasers
from from him and from Lewis I learned
how to think through Bruce he was you
know was sort of the the chief thinker.
It was at Bell Labs that Bo Wendy
started working on something that would
eventually be called quantum dots. Here
he is explaining what a quantum dot is.
The quantum part of quantum dot is
because the electron that you put in the
quantum dot no longer acts like a little
particle moving in in a wire. It's
behaves like a wave. That's the quantum.
That's the magical part of quantum
mechanics. That's when you get to really
small scales. Things that you think of
as particles are now described by waves.
Okay. So, now that you're trying to get
your head around the idea that tiny,
tiny particles are, in some sense,
waves, think back for a minute to your
junior high school band and the various
instruments in that band. Why did they
sound the way they did? So, if you look
at a flute or a piccolo, you know that
the sound of a flute or piccolo are
really different. The flute is lower
pitched than a piccolo. And why is that?
Because the soundwave in a flute has a
bigger cavity than a piccolo. And for
organ pipes, it's the same thing. So a
little tiny organ pipe sounds much
higher pitched than a big organ pipe.
And so you can think of the electron in
the quantum dot in the same way. The
wave of the electron is has a different
pitch depending on the size of the dot.
Okay, just like for the organ pipe. And
what does pitch mean for an electron?
It's the energy. So the energy in a
small of an electron in a small box is
higher than the energy of an electron in
a big box. But Wendy says that when the
electron releases its energy, it turns
into a wave, a light wave. High energy
colors tend to be blue and low energy
colors tend to be red. You got your
rainbow. So the higher energy electron
gives rise to bluer light coming out and
the lower energy. So there's there's
your size effect right there, right?
from small to large just like in an
organ pipe. So if you think of the sound
as being colors then the high-pitched
little organ pipe is blue and the low
pitched big organ pipe is red. The work
on quantum dots was part of a quest to
make better quality materials for
communication because Bell Labs was
after all part of a telephone company.
But it would be a while before Bowendi
realized that the work he was doing
might have implications for clean
energy. When he first had a sense that
it could, he was collaborating with a
chemical engineer who had friends at the
tech company Huelet Packard. And so he
had a supply of these brand new labbased
gallium nitride dodes. The first thing
that we tried, I mixed the quantum dots
in polymer and put them on top of a blue
diode to change the color because there
was a big push to create uh more
efficient uh lighting, white light. So
by mixing different colors of dots
together and pumping them with this very
efficient blue light source, we could
make white light. And that was really
the beginning of me thinking about the
dots in the energy world. And that was
the late 90s. And we wrote a paper I
think around 2000 or 2002 on that.
Quantum dots are now used widely in
televisions. And as they've made us more
energy efficient, the irony is our
appetite for them has grown, especially
in outdoor in a bright room. Uh so
there's room for expansion in the in the
screen business to make more and more
screens bigger and bigger and brighter
and brighter. The quantum dots are used
in the screens again as a way of color
shifting. So you use a source of blue
light either gallium nitride dodes or
blue OLEDs in the newer televisions and
use the quantum dots to create all the
other colors in a very energyefficient
manner because you only create the
colors that you need as opposed to the
previous generations of televisions
where you created white and then you
filtered out the colors you didn't need.
So you you wasted a lot of energy in all
these colors that you just threw out. Um
and so now we have, you know, much more
energy efficient, much nicer colors,
better colors. And what happened is that
the televisions just get bigger and
bigger. They just use the same energy,
maybe a little even a little less, but
they just get bigger and brighter. And
now you can use them in a sunny day and
and in your room. It reminds me a little
bit of when the manufacturing of clothes
got mechanized, people went from maybe
having three outfits to having like 50
outfits, right? Because like and and so
humans find a way. Exactly. So, it's
interesting that, you know, just because
you can make lights or televisions more
efficient, then we say, "Okay, great.
Then we're going to double that screen
size because why not? Who doesn't want a
bigger television?" So that's emission
where we're we're making light using
these things or shifting light into
range of colors that we want. But you've
also used quantum dots in solar cells to
capture light and make electricity.
Right. Sure. So um I think I started
going into that soon after probably the
mid
2000s and the idea first was to make
photo detectors because you could then
really tune the sweet spot of that photo
detector to to particular wavelengths.
What is a photo detector? Something that
turns light into electricity. Okay.
Light in, electricity out. And that then
morphed into solar because you know
light into electricity and and our our
first foray and I was doing this with u
a colleague and Vladimir Bulovich whom
I've had a long-standing collaboration
starting from 2000 basically uh the
quantum dot said because you can tune
their what they absorb in terms of color
you can tune them so that they are in
the sweet spot for the solar spectrum
for converting
as much of the solar spectrum as you can
and solar is actually a very slow moving
field because you've got an established
material silicon that works really
really well and the cost of silicon you
know follows a law called Swanson's law
which is that the cost goes down by 20%
for every doubling in production that's
been going on for 70 years it's the
solar of Moore's law I was going to say
I know Moore's law but Swanson's law I'm
going to have to add to it okay anytime
you have a mature technology there's
this kind of law associated with it it's
basically a scaling law the more you
make the cheaper it is basically so that
that scaling is largely taking place in
China right now it's taking place in
China right and so the whole US industry
where silicon photovoltaics began has
moved away and and does using quantum
dots to create different sorts of panels
offer the possibility of reshoring that
to some extent so what we've learned
from the quantum docs is that using them
as the functional material to replace
silicon is probably not going to be cost
effective because silicon is so cheap.
So the cost of anything depends on the
number of steps you need to make it. The
more steps the more expensive it is.
Silicon you process the silicon and you
make it pretty much in one step. You
know you crystallize the silicon and you
cut it in pieces. The dots you have to
make the dots first. then you have to
process them and so you got a few steps
in there and some of the components of
making the dots uh may not be very
cheap. So everything in solar needs to
be really really inexpensive
and the quantum dots as a functional
material I don't think are going to be
inexpensive enough to replace silicon
but they can add to it for instance
silicon doesn't absorb very well in the
UV or the blue but the quantum dots can
and they can remit light that silicon
can absorb really well. So you can
combine them not as a functional
material but as this downshifting
material
um where you so you're going out and
getting more light that you can bring
into the range that that the silicon can
absorb better. So you'd have both of
them existing like if you were talking
about a solar panel that went on a
building or something or in a field or
whatever they would both exist both the
silicon and the top one would enhance
the other. So they're directly on top of
those cells or the bottom. Uhhuh. that
those are called tandem cells if I
understand right so the bottom would be
are called birectional or bfacial cells
facial bfacial cells yeah and they're
making those now right bfacial cells are
are existing yes they're they're
becoming they're going online yeah so
traditionally you think of a silicon
panel as absorbing light from above you
know directly from the sun but there's
all this light that's being reflected
from the ground that comes back up from
the ground so if you can capture some of
that light you can increase the amount
of electricity I see. So when you say
bfacial, you're really talking about
like this is a double-sided solar cell,
right? Instead of Exactly. is what we
think of as like we see them on a house,
the thing that goes up towards the sun
is the thing that matters. You're saying
like, no, you can make the thing that's
on the underside matter, too. Yeah. And
then you can use dots on either side to
help you catch more of the light that
you need in order to increase the
efficiency of the panel. And if you
increase the efficiency of a silicon
panel from let's say 21% to 22% that's
real money. You know it's sounds like a
5% change but if you go from 21% to 23%
you say that's 2% change but actually
that's actually a 10% change in the
amount of electricity that comes out.
That's real, right? When are these
things coming? when I when can I go out
to
alti you know like I said solar is is
slow moving because silicon works so
well not only does it work so well it's
extremely stable so any thing that we
add to silicon has to last as long as
the silicon panel right which is 30
years or even
more and so that's where you get the
problem that's a challenge so you have
to end up engineering protective layers
and and and that costs money. It get
just gets harder. I see. Right. So there
all these ideas that are extremely
interesting ideas from a science or
technology perspective, but then when
you add the layer of the
commercialization, the business part of
it, then you have to realize, you know,
some things are just not going to be
worth it cuz they're never going to be
cost effective and others they could
become cost effective, but it's going to
take some work.
[Music]
You know, there's another application
which is an interesting application that
there's a small company out of um
Arizona that's pursuing. It's not a new
application, but they're really pushing
it forward. It's for um
agriculture.
So, when plants grow, you know, they
like light, photosynthesis, right? But
they don't like a lot of UV light or
blue light because it burns the plants.
So you can actually have better yield of
your crops if you take some of that blue
light or UV light and turn it into red
light. So they're coming out with these
very inexpensive products that are
basically films plastic with quantum
dots embedded in them that you throw
inside a wear a greenhouse. They will
take some of the blue light remitted as
red light and increase the yield of crop
production by 20% to 25%. It's just
amazing. So this is if I like owned a
greenhouse and I was going to get this.
This is just some sort of film or
something that you put you've got your
windows in your greenhouse and you put
it there so that when the light comes in
from the sun, there's like a little bit
of fiddling with it from the quantum
dots and then the plants are happier and
grow better. Exactly. Yeah. They just
see a brighter light in the spectrum
spectral range that they want that they
like. Yeah. Yeah. I mean that in some
ways that also contributes a lot to
energy efficiency because if you can
grow fewer plants, right, fertilize less
and you get a better yield. Just you
didn't really have to do anything too
fancy. Absolutely. And initially the
application in green houses was okay, so
we're going to filter out some of the
blue lights that the plants don't like.
take some of that red emitted light and
make electricity out of it and then
power fans. So that improves the
economics of the which would improve the
improve the economics. Mhm. But it's not
clear that that's the best way of the
DOSs either because you know okay so you
power fans with light that you filtered
out but maybe you know all you need is a
little tiny silicon PV that you put to
the side of the greenhouse you get the
same result and then you filter out the
light with something cheaper. So the
economics of combining the two together,
you know, trying to make something do
two things at
once may not be quite right. And that's
how they got to the idea, well, you
know, the plants like red light. We've
got these films that were created. It's
much easier to make a film that doesn't
wave guide, that just remits
than to try to make it turn into
electricity, which then you can use
maybe to power red LEDs to make more red
light. So, let's just make a product
that makes one thing really well.
Instead of making a a film, coating a
film with quantum dots, could you make a
spray that actually coats the plant? Say
the corn. Are they too expensive or
coats the window? Could you spray the
coat the window? Yeah. Yeah. Coating the
windows is another way or or integrating
the dots directly into the window. So,
the next thing is going to be to to make
the windows directly so you don't have
to buy a film, you know, you make the
windows with dots in them. Uh-huh. Are
people doing this in their green houses
yet or is this not in commercialization
land yet? It's um it's in the testing
phase. Okay. So, you know, there are
contracts from the government, from
NASA, from other places. There are
collaborations between large companies
and these startups to do that. And it's
in the um a phase where they're
demonstrating the the possibilities. And
then, you know, whether it's going to be
adopted
is is always it's in the marketplace.
We've talked about different companies
doing different things with quantum
dots. Are there just give me a sense?
Obviously, this is something that you
did initially, but now it's like way
beyond you. It's sort of out there in
the in the public domain. Are there just
like are there hundreds of companies
that are working on things related to
quantum dots in all different realms or
do you have a sense or Yeah, I would say
they're probably hundreds of companies.
Okay. Yeah. All over the world. And what
large and small and what are the big
like if we were to look at a you know
pie chart of what they were doing what
are the big you know chunks of thing
like the main things that those
companies are doing with the quantum
dots the biggest thing is uh screens
display screens for like television for
televisions for laptops for displays of
all sorts you know automotive whatever
okay uh that's the biggest so they're
made in in the dots are made in in huge
factories and on on a huge scale for
that. How much how much do quantum dots
add to the cost of a computer screen? Is
it is it a big fraction? It's tiny. I
would say probably there are two huge
manufacturers of dots right now that
that provide essentially all the dots
that are in the marketplace. And one of
them is Samsung, okay, or Hansel
Chemicals, which is part of the Samsung
um business and and then there's a
Japanese company uh Show Chemicals and
they provide and then there are all
these little startups that are trying
to to work in that field. But it's
interesting because you said the cost
may make it really difficult to compete
with like the incumbent solar panels
that they're like people know how to do
them. It's cheap. It's fine. But then if
they're so widely used in computer
screens and television screens, why is
that cost effective? But like solar
panels, like maybe that won't work out.
The kind of dots that are made for the
screens are made to emit light really
efficiently. If you want to make dots
for solar panels, they also have to
conduct electricity really efficiently.
The amount of dots you need to make
light in a screen is pretty small.
Um the same thing for the aggro business
because really all you need to absorb is
a little bit of blue light, some of the
blue light in the solar panel. You want
to absorb all of the
colors, the whole solar spectrum. You
need a lot more material and then you're
competing with the silicon and you're
competing with the stability of silicon.
The stability of the dots in the in the
TVs is actually incredibly good. Um
meaning they'll last for a long time.
They're going to last forever. Mhm. In a
solar environment, you need to create
electrons. Whenever you have electrons
around, you can do chemistry with those
electrons. And that's the part that
really hard with the dots to make them
last 30 years in presence of all these
electrons. Now, you've also used quantum
dots in number of biological
applications as well. Talk about that a
little bit. That actually was the first
commercial application of quantum dots,
which is a little backwards when you
think about it because it's a really
hard application. much. You know, the
TVs is really easy in comparison because
we make the dots in organic solvents,
meaning not in water. Then you have to
work really hard to get the dots into
water into a biological environment and
protect them. You could inject them into
somebody and they would go to some place
where you would image them for example.
Yeah. So the first application was with
cell imaging. You target different parts
of a cell and you see it in in the
emission in the light that comes out and
you can map out a cell very similar to
what had already been happening with die
molecules and we use die molecules for
this all the time and now people
there's the first company was started in
98 I know I helped start that company
quantum dot corporation and now the the
dots are part of thermopisher can just
buy the dots from thermopfisher for
biological applications and so there's
still a market for them. And we've used
them also for invivo imaging with animal
models of cancer, you know, to
understand the micro environment of of a
tumor, to understand blood flow in
tumors with collaborations with folks at
the at MGH at Harvard Medical School. So
you're like dying these little things so
that people then can track right what's
happening in these cells or is that
right? Yeah. You can you can peek into
the microscopic details of what's
happening in a tumor. What we learned in
the animal experiments with the quantum
dots really fed into the design of what
we used in what we used in humans.
So it's good to remember that the time
scale from discovery to an application
is really long, you know, decades. The
average
um gap between the discovery, the
invention and the awarding of the Nobel
Prize on average is 30
years. It just takes time for the impact
to be seen. There's so much work that
goes from the initial idea and the
discovery to getting something that's
actually working well that society can
use, you know, dayto-day. So when you
think down the road about the work that
you've done and you think about clean
energy and energy efficiency, which is I
know very important to you, where do you
think like that biggest impact of your
work will ultimately be felt even if it
isn't felt yet?
I mean there are two answers to that.
One of them is I have no idea.
Good answer. So humans are pretty good
at looking three years ahead. They're
really terrible at looking 20 years
ahead. We just have no idea what's the
world be like technologically 20 years
from now. If you look back, you know, 20
years ago,
we were just wrong about most
everything. Right. Right.
So it's really hard to know for sure. So
but I can tell you in the next 3 to 5
years I think this
downshifting business maybe in
agriculture or in increasing the
efficiency of solar maybe in 5 to 10
years maybe that will have an impact. So
the one the sort of films of in a
greenhouse of filtering out the light
that the plants don't like and so
increasing yields that way. Increasing
yields that way and then and then maybe
in a few years that there will be a real
impact on the efficiency of solar. Yes.
It sounds like I mean I I don't have a
good sense Rob. I'm sure you've seen a
million efforts to do solar. You were
talking about like it being 20%
efficient and maybe quantum dots taking
it to 22 or something. I know this is a
silly question, but what where's like
the 50% or the come on?
I think there's like a long way between
20 and 100, but I'm not sure. Yeah. No,
but people are working on that. Those
are those would be tendon cells where
you have multiple PV cells that absorb
different parts of the spectrum. Okay.
And then you can raise that to the 40%
range, which would be just, you know,
incredible, right? That isn't
necessarily quantum dots. Not
necessarily quantum dots. Offsky. That's
that's part of my research actually you
know taking silicon and adding on top of
silicon a thin film of these materials
called perovsky thin film solar
which is what um these are thin films of
this um material that you can make
essentially in one step with earth
abundant materials near room
temperature. So it's really inexpensive
and easy to make. You can add on
principle on top of a silicon cell and
raise it from 20% to 30%. It's been
demonstrated above 33% now and there's
no reason why it couldn't be in the 40%
range theoretically. These are also sort
of tunable materials in the sense that
you can you can modify their properties
in order to capture a particular part of
the solar spectrum. Yeah. So that's part
that's why I don't work on quantum dots
for solar in that business anymore
because the sparovski have taken over.
They're much cheaper, much easier to
make from a cost perspective. They're
just as
tunable and they could be maybe in 10
years you could start seeing real tandem
cells that would be in utility grade
applications. you know solar fields
where you're getting 28% 30% power
converting efficiency real real increase
seems like a game changer I 50% increase
in that would be a game changer yes so
the issue with those materials is the
stability how long do you need it to be
because if it's inexpensive enough maybe
you can just replace that part every 10
years and keep the silicon under it but
that replacement is going to require
labor so that's going to be a cost. So
the economics of it are not completely
clear. I mean it would be best if they
could last 30 years and so the whole
thing lasts 30 years and the big company
the big solar companies are all working
on this because they see they think that
this could be really important for the
future. Got it. And so they're putting
in hundreds of millions of dollars into
that
space and they may at some point start
gobbling up the startups for their
technology which is a good thing. Which
is absolutely a good thing. Absolutely a
good thing. So what if it works? I mean
solar panels get what? Cheaper maybe for
for every watt of electricity they
produce. Yeah, they maybe get smaller.
Smaller or cheaper? It depends on the
application. I think for perovskite I
think the solar fields is the right
application for them. You know people
talk about
flexible PVs that are ubiquitous etc.
I'm not sure that peroskites are going
to be able to do that for the one reason
is that they contain lead and that's
going to be a lead. Lead. Yeah, that's a
non-starter I think for anything that's
um consumer related. Okay. But for solar
fields, there was plenty of lead in
silicon big silicon panels out there and
cadmium tally is a big material for
solar fields and it's contained and it's
recycled and it's not going anywhere and
it's not a problem. It's kind of like
you have a differentiated marketplace in
in vehicles, right? Just because you
might put a certain kind of fuel in like
a big rig doesn't mean that's what you
put in your little car. I mean, it
sounds like, you know, the solar panels
you might put on your house on the side
that faces the sun is not necessarily
what you would have in like a huge
industrial solar field. Yeah. Yeah.
So when you think about your own views
about clean energy, where are you in
terms of optimism, pessimism, how you
think about our journey towards clean
energy? Oh, in terms of the technology,
I'm quite optimistic. Yeah. For two
reasons. One of them, we already have
the tools today. Silicon works
incredibly well. Wind power works
incredibly well. They scale up. You look
at the cost. I mean Swanson's law again,
you know, 20% lower cost every double of
production. You just follow the line
down and it crossed fossil fuel in most
part of the worlds already and you keep
falling down and there's really no real
reason why suddenly it should saturate
and say stop falling down. It's just
such a mature technology. So just from
that perspective, it's incredibly
optimistic. And then all these add-ons,
all these other technologies that are
coming on board, we don't need all of
them to work. We just need a fraction of
them to
succeed. In the end, it's policy. You
know, are we going to use the
technologies we have or that we create
or are we just going to it becomes
policy? It becomes politics. The problem
is that um in terms of basic science
when we are at the beginning of
discovery the support for that has been
less and less over the last 30 years
independent of what field it is. Um just
this is just the NSF doesn't get as much
money as it should. Is that the
situation or Yeah. The budget of the NSF
has not followed inflation by any means
over the last 30 years. You know what
could fund research from an NSF grant
when I started
is what we get now is about a quarter of
what we used to get in terms of real
dollars. Wow. It's really I mean I
talked to my colleagues all over the US
and we think that you know we could do
what we could do before but now we're at
a it's really critical now. It's not
sustainable and that's was the beauty of
Bell Labs. It allowed people to really
explore with with little accountability,
right? It was trust. Trust that, you
know, you guys are really smart. You
think of really hard problems. We trust
you that you're going to come up with
something interesting. I think in the
early 60s, the government spent like 2%
of the budget on science and research. I
mean, this was like part a lot of it was
to get to the moon. You know, when you
talk about the heyday, that all sorts of
ripple effects out. And I don't think
it's anything close to No. Right. Yeah.
A couple percentage points now. And if
you think that it takes 20 or 30 years
to reap the benefits of that
investment, you know, 1960 plus 30 is
1990. And yeah, we're not feeling the
pain. We're not we're not we're not
replenishing our pipeline of basic
discoveries are going to change the
world, right? Do you think it can shift
to the private sector? I mean, a lot of
the work That's an argument that I've
heard. Yeah, I've heard that argument
and maybe in biotech there's a lot of
research going on today that is more
basic than is you know there's a lot of
money in biotech and they're doing
really amazing things. I don't think the
private sector has the timeline that is
needed for basic research. It's just not
in the cards. Bell Labs was an anomaly.
Bell Labs was anomal because it was
funded by AT&T which had a monopoly on
the long-distance network and was just
making money right and left and uh and
had the ability to do that to really do
that. And when the monopoly was broken,
Bell Labs disappeared. The other big
monopoly around that time was IBM's
monopoly in the large computer business.
Exactly. Pieces and the Yorktown Heights
was was an example of the amount of
research that came out. It's just
amazing. Yeah. And it's also, you know,
faded away.
Yeah, it's pretty much all gone. And
when the big oil companies, you know,
really were making a lot of money like
um
Exxon, Exxon had a research lab where
they studied the fluid dynamics and all
sorts of things. Very really active
place that's pretty much disappeared as
well. Yeah. Yeah. And yeah, you know,
the the the oil and gas companies still
do fund a lot of university research. I
mean it's not necessarily um received
graciously or gratefully um in some
quarters but you know I'm just recalling
that they have funded a great deal of
solar research at MIT
very active in um plasma science and in
fusion research and other areas I think
they see I mean they they are used to
looking at long time scales when you
develop an oil field it takes decades
from the initial fine to developing.
You're talking about 30 years, right?
And so they're used to really long time
scales and they see their business 40
years from now. What is it going to look
like? It's going to be really different.
So they know they have to switch. Yeah.
And there parts of them are funding
things that could allow them to switch.
Munchupendi is professor of chemistry at
MIT. He's also the winner of the 2023
Nobel Prize in Chemistry. Thanks so
much. This really fun conversation. My
pleasure. Thanks, Muji.
What if it works is a production of the
MIT Energy Initiative. If you like the
show, please leave us a review or invite
a friend to listen. And remember to
subscribe on Apple Podcast, Spotify, or
wherever you get your
podcasts. You can find an archive of
every episode, all of our show notes,
and a lot more at energy.mmit.ed.
edu/mpodcast. And you can learn more
about the work of the energy initiative
and the energy transition at
energy.mmit.edu. Our original podcast
artwork is by Zitler Design. Special
thanks to all the people at Mighty and
MIT who make this show possible. I'm
Cara Miller. And I'm Rob Silver. Thanks
for listening.
[Music]