so the last speaker of this session is
Professor caros Spa he's a assistant
professor at MIT Department of
mechanical
engineering uh he talk about his
research a 3D micro or Nano architected
material to achieve a significant
enhancement of the properties his title
is uh 99% air very interesting title
so all right thank you very much for
that nice introduction Mickey and thank
you all for being here and uh hopefully
I'll get to uh energize you a little bit
right before our coffee break and where
we get to network a little bit more so
today really the goal one is to describe
the research that we're doing in my
group and second I want you to take some
some messages out of this and hopefully
learn a little bit more about
architector materials and in particular
the message is that I hope I can
convince you that we can really engineer
the materials of the future materials
that do not exist yet if we start by
designing them at the Nano scale and go
upwards so let me start off by looking
at this case study let's imagine that we
have a slab of a mystery material in
front of us and this material is
actually going to resists some load we
try to bend it it actually resists that
it's kind of hard to break it but then
I'll tell you that what's special about
this material is that it's about 99% air
so then the next question that you're
going to ask is if 99% is air this 1% of
solid where is it distributed and that's
a very hard question to answer and I'll
tell you it's easier to say what the
wrong answer is and we know that the
wrong answer really is that the material
is not going to be just localized along
one corner or or just the edges right so
this is the question that we're trying
to answer in our field of architect and
materials the question is how do we take
a little amount of material and do the
most with it by Distributing it in a
very interesting manner so this leads to
the first question that I want to answer
which is what do we mean by this term
architected materials the good thing is
that all of you brought samples of
architected materials with you so human
bone is the best example to us it feels
like a homogeneous material but we know
that if we look at the micr structure of
bone we get this very nice ligament
based architecture which leads to very
interesting properties such as a
highight toughness and also the high
strength of bone right and bones are not
the only architector material out there
in nature for instance the SE sponges
are an example of an architector
material in this case they are
hierarchical and what I mean by that is
that if you start zooming in at
different length scales you're going to
start picking up different structural
features each that serve a mechanical
purpose now this concept of architecture
really it is not new to us um and it is
epitomized in structure such as the
Eiffel Tower but the point I'd like to
make is that the Eiffel Tower is not an
architected material so why is this well
if we look at the leg of the Eiffel
Tower and I'm going to try to pick out
one of the struts that makes up the leg
and I say it has some length L but then
I compare that to the effective width of
the leg that it makes up we see that L
and W are about the same right they're
on the order of tens of meters and
that's an issue because we don't achieve
what I call separation of scales what
this means is that no matter how far
away you are from the Eiffel Tower you
can always tell that this is a
heterogeneous structure you can always
poke holes through it so the opposite
would be some architect material where
we indeed have some overall Dimension W
and some intrinsic micr structural
length L that is significantly smaller
than w at that point we can call this an
architected material so I can try to
categorize a broadly just three broad
examples of architector materials that
we readily use one type is a stochastic
architector material where we need to go
no further than our kitchen a kitchen
sponge here is where we architect the
pore sizes just to give us a certain uh
property um if we take fibers carbon
fibers as an example well composits are
one of the most efficient architecture
materials out there and this is you know
heavily used in the Aerospace industry
and the third example is one where we
take material and we distribute it in a
periodic Manner and we call what I what
I what I describe as lattice architected
materials and an example here are these
honeycomb panels that are used
extensively in the airspace industry
basically all the floors and airplanes
and most of the walls are made of these
very lightweight honeycomb
panels so that's the first question the
next question is why do we bother with
architecting materials and I'll try to
answer this question by giving you three
answers the first one it's kind of
obvious and I already alluded to it is
this idea that because a large
percentage of these materials is air
naturally you're going to get a very
lightweight material and if we want to
keep sending probes to different planets
we need to make sure that we continue to
do so with materials that are very
lightweight but also very mechanically
robust the second question as to why
this is
worthwhile is that if you architect
materials at the right length scale and
here I'm talking about the Nano scale
you're going to endow these materials
with properties that you never would
have imagined an example are ceramics at
the macro scale let's think of our
coffee mug if you were to drop this
coffee mug it's going to shatter in a
million pieces well if you take ceramics
at the nanoc scale there's going to
they're going to behave in a very
different manner more like a rubber so
this is an example where you have we
have a hollow architecture that's made
up of a camic and it has been shown that
you can deform these to about 50% of
their original height and then upon
removing the load they're basically
going to fully almost fully recover so
extrapolating this to larger Dimensions
really would change the way we think
about Ceramics
altogether now the third point is that
if we want to absorb a lot of energy for
instance for protective applications uh
we can design the micr structure of
materials such as Foams but in a more
careful manner to maximize how much
energy we can dissipate an example here
is a material that has two stable
configurations it has an uncollapsed
configuration and a collapsed
configuration and it takes energy to go
from one to the other and that energy
can be used to prevent an egg from
breaking right if you put the egg on top
of the structure and the impact makes
the material collapse that's energy that
did not go into breaking the shell so we
can think of using this concept to
design structural components that can
absorb energy and in some cases they
don't have to be permanently damaged but
you could potentially just pop them back
into its original configuration and go
ahead and use it over and over
again so at this
point we we can step back and look at
architect of materials and and try to
answer the question okay where if
they're so interesting where do they
land compared to all other materials
that we already use so what I'm showing
here is called an ashb plot all I'm
showing is basically every single
material that we know of the x- axxis is
the weight or the density of this
material and then in the y- axis I have
some mechanical property here I'm
talking about the effective stiffness of
these materials
and what I hope you're realizing here
and the takeaway of this plot is that
there is this white space where no
existing materials really currently uh
land right so this space right here well
that's exactly where architector
materials land architector materials
have allowed us to make very lightweight
materials but uh uh with very high
mechanical properties but what I'm
showing you here really is an idea that
is about a decade old in the sense that
you know our this field that has uh
really evolved over the last decade
started by looking just at stiffness but
nowadays the fron interior of
architector materials is is looking at
more interesting properties such as
thermal conductivity uh energy
absorption and and any other uh types of
of of interesting properties that you
want not just the
stiffness so okay I think we defined
architector materials I hope I convince
you that they're worthwhile studying
them and we know where they land from an
engineering perspective the next
question is how do we go about
fabricating these materials and I'll
describe the two ways that we fabricate
them my lab we do this extensively at
the micro to Nano scale and uh we can
make these solid out of some polymer or
we can also make them Hollow as I
described earlier where we basically can
use a polymer or a ceramic uh uh or
sorry a metal or a ceramic to to make
this coating the way we do this is
basically by using 30d printing but it's
a special type of 30d printing it's the
highest resolution 30d printing
technique that currently exists uh it's
basically a light based 3D printing it
uses a ftoc layer that is focused very
tightly inside of a drop of a
photosensitive resin and we're going to
trace we trace this focal point that's
about 200 nomers Big we trace it in
three dimensions and it's going to
locally solidify the material wherever
it passes after we trace it in any
complex arbitrary paths then we end up
with our polymeric nanom microl luses or
whatever complex geometry you
designed so then how we how do we go
about making these Hollow well we start
off with these polymeric ones as a
template and then we go through a
conformal coding process what I'm
showing here is a process called Atomic
layer deposition it's basically a way to
get fully conformal Coatings and we do
this one layer of atoms at a time and it
allows us to really have high resolution
uh and and very very thin Coatings so at
this point now we have a core shell
composite we have a polymer in the
inside and then we have a ceramic or
whatever you chose to do the coating
with but ultimately I told you I want to
make these Hollow so then we go ahead
and cut some AC ficial beams because we
want to expose the polymer and then we
put this inside of an oxygen plasma
chamber to remove the polymer so that
the ultimate product is this Holo
ceramic architecture so this is at the
micro micro scale but we also can
fabricate architecture materials at the
macros scale as long as we achieve
separation of of scales and here we're
using nothing fancy really is just 3D
printing it's another form of light
based 3D printing uh we it's called
Digital Light processing 3D printing it
basically uses UV light uh and IT
projects a 2d pattern of light inside of
of a resin pool and as you increase the
number of layers that you add you
basically emerge with a
three-dimensional uh
part so now the next question is how do
we once we make these materials how do
we test them how do we get mechanical
properties out of them so I'll start by
describing this at the macros scale well
we can make a cube of this material
which has some overall height L some
cross-sectional area a and when we apply
some force with a loading frame we get
uh what we call their engineering stress
it's just the force that you applied
divided by the area of this material and
upon some deformation that we'll call
Delta then we get some Metric of
deformation which is just our strain
engineering strain so what we get out of
this are these so-called St stress
strain plots which have a lot of
information I'll just describe briefly a
couple of things that we generally
extract we try to extract the effective
stiffness of these materials we're also
generally are interested in in knowing
when they start failing in other words
we Define the strength the yield
strength of these materials we can also
extract things like the energy
absorption in these materials so this is
at the macro scale but as I told you we
fabricate a lot of these at the micro
scale and this is where things get both
hard but also a lot of fun um the way
you know these materials are are
extremely small so we basically have to
work with scanning electron microscopes
we cannot see the materials with with
our eyes so we have to be inside of a
microscope
and we have to use a specialized tool to
be able to get the mechanical test so
let me let me zoom in here so you can
see what I'm talking about this is a
nanoindentor this is how we push the
material and measure loads but we still
can't see the sample quite yet so we
have to keep zooming in so just to give
you a sense of scale so this is a flat
punch Diamond tip that is going to push
on the sample we have a load cell here
on the left and just to give you a sense
of scale if my hair would have fallen
inside of the scanning electr
microscope's chamber this is
approximately how it would look compared
compared to these samples right so we
don't need a lot of material to be able
to extract all of these properties if we
work at this
microscale so but things are very hard
right and we have to work with the
microscope so I hope the next question
you ask is Carlos if it's so easy to
make them at the macroscale and you're
getting effectively some same properties
why why do you bother with doing these
hard experiments I also have three
answers for you the first one we already
discussed it right if we want nanoscale
size effects there's no way around it we
need to make sure that you can fabricate
at the right resolution and get these
nanoscale features the second aspect is
that it really depends on the
application that you're looking for for
instance if you're interested in making
these These are called acoustic meta
materials because they can uh manipulate
the way the way sound propagates through
them if you're interested in
manipulating them in the kilohertz
regime in the audible regime then it
suffices for you to have just a
millimeter length scale in your unit
cells right the repeating building block
can be in the millimeters that's totally
fine however if you're interested in
something like medical ultrasound which
is now in the megahertz regime there's
no way around it you need to make sure
that your unit cells are now in the
order of tens or hundreds of
microns and lastly the third aspect
which I'm I'm very excited about is this
idea that materials characterization
doesn't have to be a slow process if you
do it at the micro scale in particular
we can do high throughput fabrication
and validation of materials in a
substrate that's just as big as a
fingernail you could put hundreds of
samples and then in a matter of an
afternoon you can get all the data you
need and you can really accelerate the
way you do materials Discovery and
characterization so with that I I'll
I'll Briefly summarize the last two
decades of research in architector
materials and architecture materials
really for the last two decades has been
playing this game of looking at
different micr structures and trying to
link this to the mechanical properties
that we get so you see that there's a
lot of interesting lates things that
look like fibers which we'll describe in
a bit in a bit also things that look
like Foams I'll mention that in a second
and as you might have expected they all
delivered on the promise and what were
these promises so a reminder they were
all lightweight materials indeed there's
a lot of air in there um they also were
good at absorbing energy and some of
them depending on how they were
fabricated indeed were able to tap into
these size effects the issue though is
that over the last decade plus we've
been limited to very very small samples
again very comparable to about a 100
microns
so this leads us to to the goal and and
the vision that I have for the research
that we're doing and I'll try to portray
this by plotting this work that we've
done over the last couple of decades in
the y axis we have the effective length
scale associated with these materials
that have been made and tested and then
the x-axis is the deformation rate under
which we understand them intestin so all
of these have been quasistatic
conditions basically very small
deformation upon which uh we we report
mechanical properties so one of the
issues is that we cannot scale up these
materials or we have not been able to do
this so one of the ways that we've been
able to do this and I'll mention here in
a second I'll start populating the
x-axis as to how we're understanding
these materials under higher deformation
rates but the first step is trying to
scale up the fabrication of these
materials and there the answer is in my
opinion the quickest solution is
actually to bypass 3D printing
altogether and in a sense we're using
natural self assembly processes to
create these materials and and and we're
forgetting about 30d printing for a
little
bit to understand them under higher
rates higher deformation rates we're
interested in knowing how uh vibrations
or mechanical waves propagate through
these materials and this includes sound
uh ultrasound and then now in the more
extreme regime we're also looking at how
these materials dissipate energy under
very extreme conditions such as impact
mitigation so we have a technique that
does supersonic impact on these
materials so the goal for today and I
want I want to convince you is that
really the objective is that we want to
enable the potential of these
architector materials Beyond laboratory
settings I think over the last decade
we've done enough fundamental research
to know that they're worthwhile but we
need to really translate that to real
applications and there's three hurdles
that we're trying to work towards to
make sure that we can do this first one
as I mentioned is scalability the second
one is being able to understand these
materials to employ them under extreme
conditions and lastly is that we want
these materials to be resilient we we
want to make sure that we can use them
we can use them and abuse them and not
necessarily uh have them fail
prematurely so let me start off by
describing this aspect of scalability so
I already spoiled the surprise which is
that let's forget about 3D printing
altogether so what if we use a process
that is very familiar to us if we use
water and oil and we mix them vigorously
we're going to form an Emulsion but if
we wait long enough we know that oil and
water is going to separate again right
this is a process called spinodal
decomposition so we're basically
leveraging that concept except not using
oil and water we're using two types of
polymers and upon creating this Emulsion
before they fully separate we actually
stop this process because one of the two
polymers is going to polymerize and
solidify which means that then we're
going to form these very nice porous
structures because we can remove one of
the two polymers and then the solid one
that that polymerized is going to remain
and what's remarkable is that we can do
this in a matter of minutes and get
these sizes of these samples again this
is now at the cubic Center scale if I
would have tried to print something like
this it would have taken a couple of
weeks with the printer that we have so
this is what this micro structure looks
like under the sem you'll see it has its
highly porous these pores are in the
order of about 10 microns this is a
little red blood cell for to give you a
sense of scale but again these materials
are not what I care about I want to make
sure that these are very lightweight and
efficient so this is where I take these
as a template and I coat them with these
nanoscale Ceramics and ultimately I want
to remove the polymer so we end up with
these very nice lightweight uh ceramic
based architectures and this is what
these samples actually look like so
basically the best way to describe it
think of this as an interc connetic
network of X shells that are very
efficient mechanically uh and because of
these nice curvatures lead to very
interesting properties but I want you to
actually believe it by seeing these
experiments as a demonstration that
these properties are quite unique so
what I'm showing you here is one of the
classical examples that we do in the lab
except these material is about 99.9% air
and then the rest is this ceramic
basically the same ceramic that makes up
a coffee MOG the thing with this ceramic
though is that it's extremely thin so
what you see are these shells that are
about 30 atoms thick just 11 nanometers
and we can do this experiment and try to
do the compression and observe what
happens on these samples so let me go
ahead and play this video so the ceramic
started actually wrinkling unbuckling
and not
shattering and eventually it actually
even
recovered and we can go ahead and
continue doing this compression and we
see no indications of big cracks
propagating through these material to
the point that we can do this over and
over again again this is the magic of
nanoscale features in materials the
ceramic really should not be doing any
of this but it is because it is so
thin so but I started on this Direction
with this promise that these materials
should be scalable so that's exactly the
research that's ongoing in the lab uh so
we know that we can make these in large
volumes but what we've been missing to
until now has been really understanding
what are the the the micr structures
that we're getting not just looking at
them on in a 2d picture of an sem so
we're using nanoscale resolution x-ray
tomography which allows us to then
perform these scans which then
ultimately give us a full 3d
reconstruction of the micr structure of
these materials and this is important
because I can take this uh
reconstruction and go ahead and and plug
it into my finite element codes and be
able to now start predicting the
mechanical properties even before I I
need to go to the lab to do an
experiment but this is the real promise
of these materials so we're developing
the process we're really understanding
the structure and we're also measuring
and predicting the properties But
ultimately we want to enable inverse
design of these materials so the user
should be able to determine what
properties they want basically what if
you want this material to have different
stiffness along different directions and
then it should tell us we should be able
to then inform you what does the process
need to look like so that you can get
those properties and then the structure
really is just what links these two
things
together so let me shift gears now and
start talking about these extreme
condition uh applications so to
understand these materials under extreme
conditions uh the first step really is
to go to the established methods to
characterize nanoscale materials at
extreme
conditions well that's the
issue there are no techniques that
allowed us to do this so upon realizing
this we went back to the drawing board
with my team and started really coming
up with a wish list of what would this
technique actually look like so we said
okay we want to do highr
characterization because we don't want
to waste our time in slow experiments
and we don't want to destroy every
single sample that we test right we want
more than one data point out of each
sample and what if we can get all these
mechanical measurements without ever
touching these samples at this point I
think you might be saying Carlos you're
crazy this is impossible but I'm happy
to report that this is no longer a
non-existing method so let me describe
what it actually looks
like the way to do this is actually
using lasers and we use one laser to
excite materials to vibrate them by
basically using a very high power short
Pauls laser uh doesn't destroy them it
basically makes them ring just like a
bell and then we use a different laser
to serve as our probe to measure these
vibrations so again I'll use the analogy
of a bell often because this is
virtually all we're doing is metam
materials that are just Bells because we
can dictate the height of these samples
we can basically dictate the wavelength
at which these samples are going to
vibrate and this is the mode that we
effectively excite and just as in a bell
what do we care about when we hit a bell
we care about the frequency that that
comes out and that's what we measure
with our ears well basically our laser
is our ears our green laser which allows
us to now obtain a measurement of this
frequency and as I mentioned the
wavelength is something that we
determined based on how we made the
samples so what this means is that now I
have a speed of sound measurement with
if I know these two properties I know
the speed of sound in this material and
this is important because if I know the
speed of sound I now have many
properties including the effective
stiffness of these materials and I did
this again without ever touching these
materials so this is a schematic of what
this technique looks like so as I
mentioned in a substrate that's just as
big as a fingernail we can go ahead and
have hundreds of these samples and then
if I put my pump laser on top of these
samples and and stay there anywhere from
1 to three minutes and as well with our
prob laser we're getting about 10,000
measurements over and over again because
this is a non-destructive method so
we're really increasing the signal to
noise ratio in our experiments and this
technique is what we call the leras
technique for laser induced resonant
acoustic spectr roscopy so we went ahead
and took leras and we demonstrated it on
on a variety of metamaterial architected
material architectures but the main
point also was that this really is
agnostic of the type of material that
you have so we demonstrated that this is
also good for testing any material at
the microscale including polymers metals
or
Ceramics and the signals as you might
expect you know this is what you would
expect out of something a bell that is
vibrating right you start with some
oscillations but then they're going to D
out naturally uh because there is some
damping in the material and from there
we're getting all these properties that
I mentioned we know the speed of sound
and we can also get acoustic properties
so why am I so excited about this
technique well our Dream really is to be
able to create these broad library of
architect materials with a variety of
different properties including different
acoustic impedance different speed of
sound and why we want to use them is
basically two main applications one is
this ability to perform vibration
control one of the demonstrations that
we've shown is that we can use These
acoustic materials basically just like a
lens in an optical sense we can go ahead
and then Focus ultrasound into one spot
and then as you saw earlier from from
the talk from my colleague Professor
Shan haa um there's a demand for
materials that are able to couple these
very Advanced probes for ultrasound to
soft materials such as the skin and for
that we need to make sure we have the
right acoustic impedance mismatch or or
match between transducers and skin and
this is what meta materials architector
materials will allow us to
do with that let me shift gears into an
even more extreme condition of
deformation Beyond just simple
vibrations and there's one aspect that I
didn't tell you is that we can also make
materials architecture materials that
are made out of carbon so on the left
what you're seeing is how we can make
them at the nanoc scale and here's a red
blood Sul for scale so these are
extremely extremely high resolution
materials and we can also make them at
the macro scale these are two different
fabrication techniques different
applications and today I want to focus
on these nanoscale
materials so this idea of using lates to
as for protective applications think of
of a foreign object of a projectile
trying to hit something um is really has
been it's an all idea and we've been
wanting to actually uh uh use these
materials for protective applications
the issue is that these really are not
architect materials right you agree with
me that there is no separation of scales
here so it's not an architector material
it's just a structure nowadays of course
there because of advances in Native
manufacturing there's a lot of these uh
actual architector materials that have
been shown to be very very efficient at
Dynamic uh compaction however the
problem that we've are interested in is
a little bit different it's that of
micrometeoroid impact so if you're
familiar with this basically in space
there's unwanted debris flying around in
some cases it can be just a a Fleck of
paint that is traveling at velocity of
up to 10 km/s the issue is that even
though they have very small Mass because
of these high velocities they have so
much kinetic energy they can be very
dangerous and damage a lot of very
expensive equipment that's up in
orbit currently the best solution is
something that looks like this this is
what we call a Whipple Shield it's
basically a multi-layered material that
is designed to basically spread out the
kinetic energy instead of letting these
particles go through all the way so we
wanted to design something that could be
more efficient than this so the way we
went about this was again we go to our
uh two phonography technique to be able
to fabricate these precursor polymer
architectures that then we convert it to
carbon basically by do burning them in a
controll manner by using pyrolysis we
can burn them in vacuum up to 900
Degrees celsus this is the precursor
polymer and this is what we get after we
pyy it so you can see that we retain the
shape and the geometry we started off
with unit sellers or building blocks of
about 10 microns and then we end up with
something that's about 2 microns s with
struts or features that are about on the
couple hundred nanometer in size and
this is again a red blood cell for for
scale so what we did next again we want
to test them under extreme impact so
this is where we use a technique that
was invented at MIT called the laser
induced particle impact test so what
you'll see here is a video of these
effectively think of them as as grains
of sand basically glass spheres that are
about 14 microns in diameter we can
shoot to velocities of about 1 kilometer
per second and then using a high-speed
camera we can then image this process
this impact process taking place so what
you'll see is this projectile coming
from the top and impacting these samples
so I'll go ahead and play the video now
so when we're shooting these at about
230 m/ second we were seeing this kind
of response where the particles were
going in damaging the material and then
rebounding this is what we call this
particle rejection regime because then
we can look at the the samples and we're
able to to see the crater that was uh
actually carved out uh from from these
impact events if we were tested we
started testing these materials upon
higher velocities and this is about
approaching twice the speed of
sound we started seeing a very different
response in particular we saw that these
projectiles came in damaged the material
clearly but then we never saw the
particle come out and upon inspection
afterwards we saw that we were entering
this capture dominated regime so these
materials were now really being really
efficient at not only dissipating the
full energy of this impact and
protecting what was under but really
just also capturing these projectiles
that were trying to damage it so this
was very interesting and we had a lot of
fun doing these experiments but this
really begs for a comparison to to
materials that we're more familiar with
so the way we'd go about this is by
calculating how much energy gets
dissipated by looking at comparing the
kinetic energy of the projectile and we
normalize it by the amount of mass that
went into dissipating that energy and
then we can come up with these metrics
for other materials which we find in
literature such as stainless steel
aluminum or polymers like pmma and what
you see is that they all lie on this
trend line basically meaning that all
the energy from these projectiles is
basically going into deforming the
material that the projectiles see right
under them so the opposite would be when
we have more interesting materials such
as Kevlar which is one of the the
standards for impact mitigation uh which
is now adds a new an added complexity to
the material meaning that it allows you
to delocalize
the damage of of these impacts and you
start seeing that for the same amount of
mass they're actually much more
efficient than these monolithic solid
materials and this is not only to for
Kevlar other nanoscale materials such as
graphine can also do this and also
nanoscale polystyrene films can do this
so where do our materials land on this
plot well I'm happy to say that they
were also able to show that there is a a
significant improvement over monolithic
materials in this case because there's a
lot of energy that can get dissipated
from compacting uh these very intricate
architectures plus the nanoscale size
effects uh that we have in our samples
with that I have a couple of minutes
I'll try to describe this resilience
aspect uh very
quickly so I wanted to make sure that we
didn't forget about materials that have
to be soft and extensible and this is
something that this community of
architector materials has forgotten for
over a decade they've been in this
search for a very stiff very strong
materials not something that is
compliant and extensible and we went
basically on this search and we didn't
need to look too far we just looked at
textile materials or woven like
architectures where the building block
really is just a fiber that is
intricately coiled or curved and we took
this as our building block to to build
now periodic architectures in three
dimensions that then we could
potentially print and get some
interesting properties so this is what
an effective strut looked like it's
basically three heles that that are
interwoven along these struts but what's
most important is that the nodes these
Junctions are actually just an
entanglement of these fibers which meant
that these materials were actually very
very deformable even though the polymer
this polymer that I'm showing you here
is actually quite brittle because we
architected it in this way now the
effective material is very deformable
and it doesn't break uh very easily this
is just one of the designs that we
worked with now we've in the process of
of publishing very soon this uh
computation design framework where
basically we Define a lattice we Define
where we want this node of entanglement
to happen and then we Define the
features that Define each of these
struts these helices which allows us to
now design arbitrary unit
cells not only that we can Define
different topologies and we can build
broader large volumes of these materials
uh using this designed
framework as you can see this is just
one of the examples that why do we care
about designing different architectures
well we can embed information in
something that looks like a very intri
intricately designed fibric material so
I hope you can see there's going to be a
message embedded in
here and I think it's becoming
clear there you go this is just one of
these examples that we can embed uh
information in these materials the other
aspect really we've we've been inspired
by other materials uh such as hydrogels
which in some cases you can find these
double Network hydrogels at the
molecular scale they have two polymer
net networks one that's stiff one that's
very compliant uh that leads to these
hydrogels being as as Professor Shon hij
was showing very hard to tear uh and at
the same time in some cases quite stiff
so we went ahead and designed an
analogous material system in an
architected sense so we basically have
these materials be uh have a monolithic
lattice serving as the rigid framework
and then we have the woven lattice
serving as the compliant
framework and we fabricated these with
two Photon lithography and to our
surpris actually works surprisingly well
we can make both networks and they don't
actually fuse together even at these
small scales and we test them under
tension by printing a a tensile gripper
on top of the samples and then going in
with our nanoindentor and going ahead
and doing the experiment so this is an
example of these experiments what you're
seeing here is just a monolithic Network
just a woven Network and then this
double Network the remarkable thing is
that this double network is
significantly stiffer than the other two
but because it has the the woven
component as well it's quite extensible
and it doesn't fail immediately uh fully
uh when you do this this type of tension
just as an example again this is the
extreme case of the most extensible
material that we've made extremely hard
to
break and it dissipates a lot of energy
in the process of trying to do this so
we're in the process of characterizing
basically to answer the question how
hard would it be to tear these materials
this is basically a fracture mechanic
question so we're doing these types of
experiments where we have a notch so
basically a notch that we intentionally
create on these materials and then we're
going to pull on them and see how this
fracture starts propagating throughout
as you can see the monolithic network
not surprising it just fails and just
goes away whereas the woven network is
actually able to have a lot of uh
toughening mechanisms uh making it
extremely hard for us to actually be
able to tear these
materials okay this leads to the end of
the story but I hope I was able to
convince you that architecture materials
have a a huge potential especially if we
start designing them at the at the
nanometer scale but ultimately we need
to apply them by being able to fabricate
them at the centimeter scale and we need
to do this in a close loop fashion as
you saw in my group we do computation we
do the fabrication but we also need to
do the testing and and and work
harmoniously so that make to make sure
that we're not uh just focusing on one
of these features what I described
really is just examples of the four
directions that were working on in my
lab one of them is of course scalability
of these materials U working on the
multifunctionality and I describ the
acoustic properties as one of these um
looking at the extreme impact mitigation
properties and then ultimately how can
we make these materials also be quite
compliant and extensible and not fail uh
in a brittle
manner so the takeaway message hopefully
architected
materials land into a spot where no
other materials
can also we need need to leverage these
nanoscale features and hopefully next
time I see you I can share a sample a
nanoscale sample that you can hold in
our hands and also that we need to
understand these materials under real
world conditions it doesn't suffice for
us to just do slow deformation because
these materials eventually will be
dropped so we need to make sure that we
can full fully understand how they
respond across
scales with that I want to thank uh the
group The postto the students that are
the ones who are doing the hard work and
the funding agencies that have made this
possible and I'll leave you with this QR
code which is actually an augmented
reality model of these materials which
you can play with you can actually drop
it in front of you and your phone uh and
play with it and then hopefully I'll
show you what I think is the world
record for the smallest MIT Dome ever
made there we go with that thank you
very much for your attention I'm happy
to answer any questions
[Applause]
okay first
question at the nanoscale a conventional
FM framework works okay to predict the
mechanical behavior of the structure
great question
um yes and no in a sense yes so okay
what what is what is happening at the at
the nanoc scale when we have a ceramic
shell that is extremely thin that means
that there's so few atoms that we have
also a very small probability of having
defects inside of this shell what that
means is that this ceramic shell can
reach theoretical strengths of ceramics
that is impossible to find in a in a
bulk ceramic because a bulk ceramic is
going to have a lot of defects and how
many defects you have will determine how
strong the ceramic is so the way that we
use FM to model nanoscale uh Frameworks
is by being able to correct properties
such as the effective yield strength by
increasing that to the actual properties
of an experiment at that scale um
there's ways of modeling you know every
single atom using methods such as
molecular Dynamics um that would be the
the the more rigorous way if you really
want to understand everything that goes
on in these very thin shells the issue
is that we're Limited in volume as to
how much you can model so there's no way
that we could fit a full lattice inside
of those computational Frameworks so so
the short answer is yes it works um as
long as we understand the the the
constitutive properties of the material
that we're
modeling second question is how do we
predict the cost competitiveness of
architected materials for industrial
applications compared to traditional
Composite Materials that's a great
question so it depends on which of the
material systems we're talking about um
I'll give you the best example I have in
terms of the cost aspect which is that
of the self assembled architector
materials there I believe you know we're
talking about cents per gram of cost or
or I guess let's talk about volume cents
per cubic uh centimeter of these
materials um so they're very cheap to
make U compared to ones that we need to
3D print um so in that realm it's it's
it's very easy I will say 3D printing so
if we talk about nanoscale 3D printing
those at the moment uh really come with
a with a hefty uh uh price tag
uh it doesn't mean that it's not
applicable it just depends on what
application can can go ahead and and and
and justify that cost for the the
applications or the the properties that
you're getting however I'll give an
example um in terms of 30 printing being
an industrial uh step in in in a
manufacturing process for instance I
don't know if you're familiar with these
Adidas shoes actually should buy a pair
so I can show it at presentations um
that are made up of a midsole that is a
lattice architecture so these are solely
3D printed and you know you can buy
these I think they're on the order of
maybe
$130 uh so so to the point that it is
competitive um of course with an added
maybe performance metric so short answer
is depending on the architect
architector material the cost will vary
but I think there are some applications
that that really could use uh some 3D
printing at a reasonable
cost the next question
is so is this
carbon is it 100% carbon or does it
contain poers uh great question so
depends on how much we burn it um the
ones that we've that I showed and tested
are 100% carbon um because this thermal
process that we go through you know it
goes up to temperatures where any other
Organics or volatile components are
going to to to leave the sample um the
caveat is that the carbon
I guess it's not part of the question
but is it a good carbon or is it B bad
carbon and what I mean by that um it's
it's really not graphitic carbon like
what you see in in a fiber uh for a
composite um this would require much
higher temperatures for processing and
maybe different polymers to start with
um but it is 100% carbon but it's a dis
disordered micr structure of
carbon okay are there any studies that
aim for good physical properties by
optimizing both the molecular level
structure and the macro level
structure yes and and that's actually
the current point of where architector
materials Community is now we first
started by saying I'm just going to take
you know any polymer and go ahead and
print the 3D structure but now we're at
the point that we could potentially make
more interesting resins that at the
molecular level give us very different
mechanical property
and then if we combine that with the
right morphological design at the 3D
level gives us improved mechanical
property so so the answer is yes we're
this is really kind of the ongoing
research in our community not not just
looking at the architecture but also
looking at how are we designing the
material that we're printing
with okay thank you
[Applause]