Okay. So, today we're going to be
talking about
um
error correcting codes.
So, on Thursday, Professor Mitra told
you about um Shannon's noisy coding
theorem. And I don't know if he drew
this picture or not. It's not in the
notes. So um and it's a picture
everybody draws when they talk about
Shannon's noisy coding theorem. So you
have some message
message
drawn from M
which is some set of messages.
And now
you encode it.
And now you have a noisy channel
and
you get C tilda
or you get the received code word which
maybe I should call it
C tilda. And now you decode
and you get something which I'll call M
tilda
and
Shannon
if
the noise
um
at the rate
which I want to A is
um
log K over.
Okay. What is the rate? It's K over N,
right?
K over N. So these messages are k bits
and this code is n bits
is less than the channel capacity.
There exists a code
such that
as n goes to infinity and k / n remains
the same
the probability that
m tilda equals m goes to one.
So in the limit of long block lengths
I don't know how much coding theory
terminology
um anchor used but
n is called the block length.
Then
the
error rate goes to zero.
So that is the noisy channel coding
therm. So did um professor mo put this
diagram on the board?
Okay. Oh well.
And
Shannon used
random codes to prove his theorem.
And these are totally impractical for
large N.
Because what you have is you have a list
of code words which is
exponential inn
and you get a receive word and you want
to find which of these code words it's
closest to and we don't know any way of
doing this that is substantially better
than going through the entire list of
code words computing the distance and um
finding the shortest one and in fact you
can show that this is uh np P hard
problem which means that there probably
isn't such a way.
So what you need is you need
to find
specific codes
with
practical decoding algorithms.
And
today and Thursday I will tell you about
two of these codes and um
they will basically
you know stand in for the whole class of
linear codes.
So,
so Shannon found, you know, Shannon
proved his theorem in 1948
and two years later,
Hamming found the first
um error correcting code
having
found actually found a whole class of
Eric reckoning codes but the first part
of the talk I'll just talk about the
simplest one in this class
um can
encode
four bits
into
seven bits
and correct one error.
So if you have
I don't know a million bits that you
want to send and their rate is their
error rate is one in a 100 then um this
is not going to work because you can
break the million bits into blocks of
seven of blocks of four and transmit
each of them in seven bits. But chances
are very high that in these million bits
you will find one block of four which
has two errors in it which means it will
not be corrected.
So what you really would like is you
would like a way of encoding say a
th00and bits into 1500 bits that correct
10 errors.
And we will get to something like that
with
um
read Solomon codes which we'll talk
about on Thursday. But what is the
Hammond code?
So I'm going to give you a first a very
simple description of the Hammond code
and then a more complicated one.
And a simple description.
We're going to start with a vin diagram
with
um
four
bits. Well, with three
um
regions and these regions are actually
going to be correspond to specific bits
of this code.
Okay,
now
let me see if I can do this. Um
I want to do this. So let's take the
four bits to be bit A, bit B, bit C and
bit D.
So these are the message bits.
And now what we're going to do is add
three parody check bits.
And these, you know, 4 + 3 is seven,
which is why we're encoding four bits
into seven bits. And these bits are
going to give you
the error correction ability. So let's
say this is
a + b. This is um a + b + d.
This is b + c + d.
And this is a + c plus d
where the plus is exclusive r. So binary
addition
example
let's take
um
one
011 to be the message.
And now
Okay. So, one 0 one one. Oh, I'm sorry.
One 0 one one.
Okay. So now we want to compute the
parity check bits. So what we do is we
put a bit in here so that the sum of the
bits in this circle is even. So that
would be zero because 1 + 1 is zero.
And similarly this is zero because 1
plus 1 is zero. And this is one because
1 plus 1 + 1 is one. And we know to add
a one to make it zero.
Okay.
So our
code
is 1 0 1 1
and now 0 0 1.
Okay. Now let's send it through the
channel and we will change one of the
bits. Does anybody have a suggestion for
which bit we want to change?
Who wants to change the second bit?
Okay, we'll do that. So it's 1 one 1 0 0
1. Okay. So what we do now is we
compute
uh let's call these A b C D E F G and
this was
A B C D E F G I believe.
Yeah. So now we compute a + d + c + g. a
+ c + d + g.
Um
that is
zero. So this circle is
correct.
Now we compute a plus e plus b + d. a +
c + b + d. That's one. So this circle is
incorrect.
And B + C plus D plus F B plus C plus D
plus F that
B C D F that's also equal to one. So
this circle is also incorrect. And so
now we know the incorrect bit is not in
this region but is in the intersection
of this region and this region.
And that means it is B.
So the received um
word is that
incorrect
bit is B.
And now we change B. So we get one zero
one one zero zero one
right
and
well you might have noticed that the
message was the first four bits. So this
is the message.
Okay.
Okay. So now I'm going to tell you about
general linear codes and then
general Hamming codes.
Uh linear code
over
a field
f
is a collection
of
length n
strings enough.
So
if C1 C2 are in the code,
I should probably call this a code C,
then
C1 plus C2 is in the code.
And if
C1 is in the code and alpha is in F,
alpha * C1 is in the code.
So any linear combination of code words
is also a code word.
And it's fairly easy to see that this
holds for this um
you know this Hamming code because
if you add two
if you have a set of bits that satisfies
this. So the sum of these sum of these
and sum of these is all zero. And you
have another set of bits that satisfies
this. Then when you take the sum of
these sets of bits,
the sum of things within the circle is
the sum of the things from the first
code word in this circle plus the sum of
things and the second code word in this
circle and 0 + 0 equals 0. So it's also
a code.
Okay, so we have this is a linear code.
by
linear algebra.
Every
code
C has a generating matrix
G
such that
um
C is
the row sums
of G.
So now I'm going to write down the
Hamling code in a different way and
actually you're not going to get quite
the same.
Well, I mean,
I'm going to write down the Hamming code
in a different way. And let's see. We
have
um 1 0 0 0.
And now the first
So this is the first bit. So now the
first two bits of the parody check
matrix are both one here.
So 1 0 0 0 1 1 0.
So when you put that when you put these
bits in the vin diagram
they will be um
assuming I've done this right they will
satisfy the parody checks and then
there's 0 1 0 0 and that's just one 0
one one and 0 0 1 0 and this is going to
be 1 0 1
and 0 0 0 1 1
because this fourth bit is the center
region of the vend diagram and that
means all three parody checks need to be
one for the
for them to satisfy that. sub g is equal
to this
and
there are 16 code words in C
in C
and um
what do I want to
and they're the rose terms
of G and 000000
is in C. And actually the all zeros
vector is a
is a code word of every linear code
because
we know that
um if C1 is in C and alpha is an F then
alpha C1 is in C and if alpha is zero
then alpha C1 is the all zeros vector.
So every linear code has the all zeros
vector in it.
Okay.
Correct.
Oh,
okay.
We need some more um we need some more
definitions
before I can continue.
The Hamming weight
of a vector
Okay.
And let me see if I can find what
W of V
is the
number
of non
Wait,
I I did this wrong. The having weight
w of v of a vector v
is a number of nonzeros
v contains.
Let v equ=
0 1 3 2 0 4 1. Say
the Hamming weight
is the number of nonzeros. It's 1 2 3 4
5 is equal to five.
The hamming distance
of D and W
as a number of places where V and W
differ.
So let's pick an easier example. 013
and
Okay.
Okay. I I want to I want to use the same
notation for Hamming distances in the
notes and
Okay.
So this is d subh of vw
and 1 2
is
well how many places do they differ
anybody?
Two.
So call this C1
and C2.
So the hamming distance between C1 C2 is
equal to 2. And it's easy to see that
the Hamming weight of C1 minus C2 is
equal to the Hamming distance between C1
and C2
because
if two bits are the same then their
difference is zero and if two bits are
different then their difference is non
zero.
So here C1 minus C2 is equal to
-1
0 1
has handling weight
2.
So theorem
a code can correct
um
let
D
of a code
B
minimum over C1 C2 in the code C1 not
equal to C2 the Hamming distance between
C1 and C2
so it's the smallest Hamming distance
between two non-equal
vectors
Then
the code
can correct.
T is equal to
um
DH of
C over two floor errors.
What's the proof?
Well, let's assume.
Ah, I'm sorry.
I wrote this formula down wrong. dus one
over two errors.
Suppose
it cannot
then there is uh well there's a received
word
uh
received word
C
tilda
such that
two code words could have
well the two code words could have
resulted in B tilda.
So
I mean this is just saying that if you
can correct every code word to its
unique every if you can correct every
word with errors to a unique code word
assuming there are fewer than T errors
then
the code can correct T errors. So what
they cannot correct here is there must
be some word c tilda so that there are
two code words which are in dist in that
are in a hamming distance
t
of c tilda.
So t is equal to
c tilda
or actually t is greater than or equal
to
the hamming distance between c tilda and
c1
and
t is greater than equal to the hamming
distance
between c tilda
and C2.
Then
the distance between
C1 and C2
must be less than or equal to
the distance from
C1 to C tilda
plus
the distance
between
C tilda and C2.
And this is just because Hamming
distance is a metric. Which means if the
distance between C1 and C tilda is say T
and distance between C tilda and C2 is
T, then the distance between C1 and C2
is at most 2T.
But this is equal to less than or equal
to
2 t
by this these um inequalities.
And that is less than or equal to
I guess the Hamming distance for the
code.
But we know by the definition of a
hamming distance from the code that it's
the minimum
distance between two code words.
So this is a contradiction.
I should say less than here
because t was one less than the distance
of code divided by two.
Okay.
for a linear code.
Let
D equal the minimum
over all code words in the code
of the Hamming distance or Hamming
weight.
Um
what did we use for Hamming weight? Um
W. Okay, so W of C
and we have to specify that C is not
equal to zero here. So the minimum
weight of any nonzero code word
then
C can correct
um
D -1 / 2 errors
proof.
Well, we're going to use this theorem.
Might as well call this a theorem, too.
Proof.
Um
so the minimum
over C1 C2
2 in C of the distance between the two
code words is equal to
the minimum um
C and C the weight of C
because
well why because the weight of
C1 minus C2 is equal to the Hamming
distance between C1 and C2.
So for a linear code C, you want C to be
able to correct
D minus one over two errors.
Okay.
So the generating G for Hammond code
was G equal
one 1 0 0 1 1 0 0 1 0 0
1 0 1 1 0 0 1 0 1 0 1 and 0 0 1 one one
okay I want to claim you can define a
Hamming code with block length 2 to the
k minus on.
Okay.
I
n = 2 to the k
um 2 to the n minus k minus one.
So here for this hamming code K which is
the number of
bits it encodes
is four
and the block length is 7 which is 2 7 -
4 that's 8 - 1 is 7. And how do we do
that?
Okay. Well, we're going to do the same
thing as we did before. one one one
um
one one.
So that you see is
And then okay so we put the identity
matrix here and now we're going to put
all
all binary strings
length K
length um
s
with
at most two
with at least two ones.
So 1 1 0 0 1 0 1 0 1 0 0 1 0 1 1 0 1 0 1
0 0 1 1
So I guess there's six here then four
1 one
one
so this is 11
and this is 15.
So here k= 11
n= 15
um k equals
well there are two to the s strings of
left s total and if we remove the ones
with one one and the ones with zero ones
you get 2 s - s - one
and n has s more rows or s more columns
than
I mean so this identity matrix has an
equal number of rows and columns. So we
have s more
um
columns
than k. So that's
k + s = 2 s -1.
So this is the 1511 hamming code.
Okay.
And now we have to explain why does it
correct.
Why does
it correct
one error?
need to show
all row sums
minimum
weight three
are all nonzero row sums have minimum
weight three.
So let's start start with easy case.
All rows
have minimum
weight three or rather all rows have
weight at least three. Why is that?
Well, let's pick any row.
Let's say this one.
The um
the identity matrix has one
bit in it
and the parity check bits have at least
two bits in them.
One bit
parody check bits
two bits.
Okay.
any sum of two rows.
Well, let's
um
take
two rows and look at their sum. There
are two different
um ones in the identity matrix part. So
we need at least one one in the parody
check bits. But we arranged these parody
check bits so that they were all
different. And when you take two non-
different strings and you sum them mod
two you don't get zero you get at least
one.
So here the addended matrix part
has two bits
on the parity check
at least one bit.
I should have said at least two bits
there.
And any sum of three rows
or more,
the um
identity part
has at least three bits.
Okay.
So, the last thing I want to do today is
tell you how to correct
errors in
um linear codes
because
um
>> I have a question.
>> Yeah. Why is that k 23 - 5?
>> Okay, so we're looking at all binary
strings of length s with at least two
ones.
So how many binary strings of length s
are there? There are two to the s binary
strings of length s. And now we have to
subtract out the ones that have one one
or zero ones. There are s1's with one
one because the one can be in any of the
s positions and there's one string with
zero ones which is the all zero strings.
So the number of binary strings with at
least two ones is 2 to the s minus s
minus one.
And then to and that's the number of
rows in this matrix. To get the number
of columns in this matrix, well, we just
take the number of rows because the
identity matrix has an equal number of
rows and columns and add s and that's
2 to the s minus one.
So this is a this is the class of
Hamming codes and
um
okay I should I should say something
about them later but let me first tell
you how to correct errors in
um
linear codes.
Okay.
Oh, wait. I want to pull this down.
Well,
to work with a code
need
to
encode a age.
Identify
positions with error.
And once you've identified the positions
with the errors, you can fix them and
then decode.
And
we
defined generator matrices.
generator
matrix for code
G equals
code
is
set of all row sums.
to encode
use
C= M * G. So M is the message,
C is the code code word and G is a
generator matrix.
So
if m = 1 0 01,
mg
is the sum
of the first row and the last row
because this is this is the first one
and the last one. So it's 1 0 0 1 0 0 1.
So encoding is easy
to decode. We need the parity check
matrix.
H is defined
as
well.
We want GH equals zero
and we want H to have maximum rank. So
that GH
H maximum rank
with
this condition.
Okay.
Um,
let's leave this up
and I will say something.
for all codes, all linear codes,
we can find
a generator matrix G
of the form
one one one one.
So this is the identity matrix and some
matrix here S.
So you see
here here
the second part is S and this first part
is the identity.
and by general linear algebra
configurations.
Proof
proof is really Gaussian elimination.
You take the code and you do Gaussian
elimination on it and then you rearrange
the order of the coordinates to get this
identity.
And
you know, I'm not going to go into
further details because they're not that
important for this. And the um
and they're not in the um notes either.
And I want to claim that here h is equal
to
minus s i
where you have a minus s here and an i
of the right form.
So,
h is equal to -1 -1 0.
I feel stupid putting these minus1's on
because minus1 equals one in the um
there's another row here. -1 -1 - one 1
because min -1 equals 1 in binary. So
this really could be simplified to
this but for non-binary codes you really
need the minus s.
And you can see that.
Oh
well, I will explain
and G equals I S. And note this I is a
different size identity matrix than this
I. But anyway, G H is equal to
um I S
minus S I.
And when you do matrix multiplication
here, you get I * - S plus S * I equals
I * - S
+ S * I equals zero.
So G is
um
so GH is zero which was our condition
for
um
parody check matrix. And you can also
see that H is a maximum
rank matrix such as GH equals Z because
um well that's linear algebra 2. Um
H.
Um
I mean I'm going to say H gener um
yeah
H transpose generates
the um perpendicular space
space
2 G
and the dimension of H transpose plus
the dimension of G is equal to N, the
dimension of the entire space.
And this is true for any
spaces over
for any linear spaces
even those over finite fields
even though
g intersect hrpose
might be non-mpt.
So um I mean you you guys are used to
thinking of linear algebra over the
reals and then you have a space s and a
perpendicular space surp and s intersect
sp is just zero. This isn't true here.
Um
let's see.
look at the last row in G. It's
perpendicular to itself. So the last row
in G is also in
H
in the row space of H transpose because
everything that's perpendicular to
um all the guys in G
is an H transpose and you can see that
the last row is per all the other rows
in G.
So there's some linear combination of
rows in H which gives you this and you
can see that it's or some linear
combination of columns in H that gives
you that and you can see it's the sum of
all three columns because you need one
one one
and the last three entries in the column
and then the
sum of the first three is
is
the sum of these four columns is 0001.
So
a space and its perpendicular space can
intersect but that doesn't matter. So
this is the parody check matrix.
And now
suppose we have
uh
linear code
with
G and H are the generators matrix and
the
um parody check matrix.
End code
we get mg
error.
We have mg
+ e.
And the next step is compute
the syndrome
of C tilda. And that's c t k t k t k t k
t k t k t k t k t k t kilda * h.
This is mg + e
* h is equal to
mg h + eh
which is just eh
because remember g * h was zero
and this is called syndrome.
And it's called the syndrome because
it's what you use to diagnosed the
error.
So
syndrome
depends
only on the error and not on the encoded
code word.
not on the message.
Okay.
How do you go
from
S to E?
Well,
it's not easy.
Depends
on the code.
There's no
efficient algorithm for taking a
syndrome for an arbitrary code and
computing the error. You have to do
something that is code dependent. And
we're not going to um
I mean there could be lots and lots of
different ways going from the syndrome
to the error depending on the code and
some of them can be quite complicated
some of them are easy for Hammond codes
it's very easy
code.
Assume
error
has
one bit
our Hamming weight one.
So one bit equal one and all the others
are zero.
0 0 1 0 0.
Let's make this the K bit.
times the Hamming matrix
is kith
not Hamming matrix times the um
parody check matrix. So the if you have
a one if you have a vector with one and
you multiply it by the matrix you just
get the kith row of the matrix
So because the Hamming code can only
correct one bit errors, we only need to
worry about the case where
the
error E has one bit in it and that case
is easy to decode. So let's do an
example.
Because I think we have just enough.
Well, we pro probably have more than
enough time for an example, but
we should do an example.
End code
1 1 0. Oh gosh. One one zero in
our seven bit Hammond code.
So there's our seven bit hamming code up
there. We sum the first three rows
because one one we have the first three
entries of our message are one.
M= 111. So that's um well it's 1 one 1 0
um
0 0
add error
and you get Let's say E equals 0 0 0
1 0. We get 1 1 1
0 0
1 0.
So now we have mg
plus e * h.
So that's the first sum the first three
rows of h
and that's uh zeros. and then add the
fifth row of h that's uh 0 1 0
equals 0 1 0. And this is a syndrome
0 1 0 is
um
the sixth row of h.
Oh, this I I think I said fifth when
here, but I meant sixth. The sixth row
of H.
error in position six
0 0 0
1 0
and um
this was C tilda. So C tilda plus E is
equal to
1 1 1 0 0 0.
And this first bit is the message.
Okay.
Now, there's one more piece of
one more section in the notes about
Hamming codes. I don't want to get to
read Solomon codes this time because I
want to do them all next time. And
that's about perfect codes.
Oh my.
Oh, perfect code
as one.
All of whose
syndromes
correspond
to an error of
an error
of
T bits
or fewer.
If it's a T error correcting perfect
code, all its syndromes correspond. So
the binary
the Hammond codes are perfect codes.
So how many syndromes do they have?
Well,
they have um
their syndromes are length
espits.
So there's 2 to the s syndromes
and the code has 2 to the sus1 bits.
So I want to say first the zero syndrome
corresponds to no error and every other
one of these syndromes corresponds to
exactly one bit. So there's exactly as
many syndromes as bits.
Okay.
And you can ask,
are there any perfect other perfect
codes?
Okay.
So to have a perfect code,
you need um
you need
sum
all the possible errors. So um
let's say L equals 0 through T.
And how many errors are there with how
many
ways are there of getting an error of
exactly L bits? It's n choose L
is equal to 2 to the
something
to the number of bits in the syndrome.
So this is a condition that you need for
perfect codes.
and it's satisfied
or this is a solution you need for
binary perfect codes
for Hammond codes
and it's also satisfied if I'm
remembering these numbers right n= 23 3
and t = 3.
So there's exactly one solution other
than the one you get for Hamming pots.
And remarkably,
maybe it's remarkably,
this is
something called the gole code.
And I should have looked this up before
um
before coming to class, but I didn't get
around to it. This was discovered by
Gole
um sometime after Hamming's um paper.
But
the construction had already been found
by
uh football, although you should call
that soccer enthusiastic enthusiast who
I think was finished and coming up with
a betting system for soccer games,
football games I should say.
But um so
this is actually a remarkable
mathematical construction which is
related to finite simple groups but um I
don't have time to I mean
we don't have the mathematics to go into
that and I certainly don't have time to
go into that but this is the one
other binary very perfect code. There's
also a code over Z sub3 called the
turnary goalie code where
um you have a three to the S here and um
I guess uh
and a three to the something on this one
as well. Three to the L I think. But
anyway,
this is
if you want to use perfect code. I mean,
so at first, you know, after discovering
the Hamming code, you would say, well,
perfect codes are exactly what we want
to use, but there aren't enough of them.