okay good
morning
so we are still here in
studying uh cross
effects that
emerge from
the on Sager theory
of know equilibrium near
equilibrium as a result of linear
relations between forces and
flaxes just as a
reminder in this slide we uh got these
uh Expressions that
summarize uh the relation between
U energy
flux and entropy flux and constituents
flux
including Uh current electrical charge
flux uh and these
are diffusive flues so they are relative
to uh
the if you if we have a motion like in a
fluid they relative to the body center
of the fluid
parcels and this other slide
also which we have reviewed the last
time allowed us to
write the this term uh uh in the uh
expression for the rate of entropy
production in terms of independent
fluxes
or actually in terms of this ji JS these
are differences between um fluxes of
pairs of uh constituents that are
present in our system
and they go together so the conjugated
Force to this U diffusive relative
fluxes are uh we could call them
diffusive relative forces and they are
uh given by the difference in the
gradients of the chemical potentials of
the same two
uh kinds of
particles notice that
these by definition are
anti-symmetric so you change you swap
the IND indexes you change the sign of
course
because it's obvious from here and um
therefore you see here we have one half
of the summation over i j and you're
supposed to sum over all the I and all
the JS and that will pick
um
uh each of these elements uh
twice uh
so the the one half will go away and so
for example if you have just one
pair you will have uh J12 plus
j21 and uh they will uh end up this sum
will end up being just one term J12 *
X12
you also should remember that uh we have
to use the Gibs do relation which
relates the gradient in pressure to the
gradi in chemical potentials for example
for a pure
substance so there's only one uh
constituent this also holds and it says
that the gradient in pressure is equal
to the concentration of the substance
times the gradient in the chemical
potential uh at constant temperature of
that substance we will use this today in
one of the
examples so here uh I've
included up
there here there still the full
expression but now I'm I want to focus
only
on on the vectorial uh fluxes and
forces so the fluxes of extensive
properties that are U that are of
vectorial of yeah vectorial character so
we exclude the scalars chemical
reactions we exclude the tensorial uh
flues so we exclude the citation
function you see here that we have
many uh different
terms and then
the let's suppose we have
only three kinds of particles in our
system that summation over the i i and
JS uh ends up
contributing only uh three of these uh
products of forces and fluxes
only three of them are non zero and
independent so this will be the inter
diffusion of particle one with respect
to two of particle one with respect to
three of particle two with respect to
three and then we
have um the diffusion of of electrical
charge related to a change in
electrostatic POS potential gradient in
electrostatic
potential of course heat is in the
gradient of one / T and then there is
also this term with the
pressure which gives you uh flux of
particles um driven by a gradient in the
pressure so we have six
terms six
different uh extensive properties that
can be transported in our
system and six
different degrees of dise equilibrium
which uh uh control and uh Drive the
system back towards equilibrium this is
also related to the chatelier brown
principle and
you
remember um the
more see each one of these uh degrees of
this equilibrium is related to a
a condition necessary condition for
Mutual equilibrium so if you have no
gradient in temperature you have a
quality of temperature that so from that
point of view uh uh you have uh you you
are okay for equilibrium but that's not
the only condition you also need no
gradient in pressure that's pressure
equality if the systems can exchange
volume
um this is part of the chemical
potential but it's the electrical
electrostatic so if
you so you have a you're at equilibrium
at least from that point of view from
the electrostatics if you have no
gradient in the electrostatic potential
and here also you you have
the equality of chemical potentials of
the various pairs if they are all equal
to zero then we are at
equilibrium uh the more you have of them
that are different from zero the farther
you are from equilibrium the more degree
they add up to the degrees of of
equilibrium and therefore like chat
Brown says uh you uh your system will
have a stronger tendency to uh uh return
to
equilibrium and the way they uh the
system returns to equilibrium is is uh
described by this big
Matrix in
fact I didn't put the the tensor signs
but these are each each of them is a
tensor because the most General relation
between a vector and another Vector is
through even if linear it's through a
tensor so you see how uh
Rich the variety of
phenomena uh that we can uh encounter
and that
we we can model uh is so of course
uh if you want to uh include all of them
you need the computer uh computer
program to to do it this is done in
simulations but um even though uh
nowadays uh we have computers and we
have uh softwares that are
very they're able to com to to to to
model very complex uh
phenomena in
fluids and not only fluids because of
course I'm talking fluids but also in
solids we have the
same
ideas
um very
seldom they are implemented to include
all these off diagonal
terms most of the times you just uh keep
the diagonal
ones for example here I've
already uh sort of shaded out these off
diagonal ones because most of the times
you assume that um uh each
pair so the relative Flux Of pair one
two is driven by the relative
um uh difference in gradient of
[Music]
the chemical potentials of that
pair and not the other ones but these
are possible cross effects and these
possible cross effects may
result in for
example
uh the possibility
that concentration
gradients uh you have two two different
different so you you could have a flow
uh upward the concentration gradient of
one constituent driven by the the flow
downward of of two other constituents
and part of it could be captured by
these
but I think that if you want the most
General description of that you you
would need to include also these off
diagonal
terms okay now we have have
uh already done thermoelectric effects
and from this point of view the
thermoelectric
effects
uh cover these degrees of the
equilibrium so a material in which you
have gradient in temperature and a
gradient in electrostatic
field and so our system becomes just 2
by two two
quantities extensive quantities
transported and two degrees of this
equilibrium
and since we are at it uh I think I
should uh there was something wrong in
the The View graphs that uh in the slide
where I did this calculation last time
so I corrected it
now because I was using the wrong
expression for uh the work the work
triple work so here uh I've have taken a
slightly different approach to correct
that uh first of all I write what the
reversible work is and you remember in
the situation like we have
done uh in when we did the heat transfer
so we had here uh this is
X here is T and here is T Plus uh
DT and then we put in an
engine that
receives a heat
flux and like a Carno Engine with the
Carno efficiency because it's a
reversible engine
produces a W
uh let's call it U th for thermal uh
reversible which is given by that
minus Q gradient in t over
T now here we also have a a a gradient
in the electrostatic
potential so you we can use that by
extracting with an electric motor for
example some uh work also this
way and that will
add a an electrical work
reversible which is given by uh since uh
the effect that the the gradient in U uh
in the electrostatic potential is is
driven by the the um CC
effect this is given by minus
I
times uh the gradient in
v and that's minus
I
time
Epsilon uh gradient in t
or maybe sorry there is no minus
here uh I drive a current
down from high potential to low
potential and the power of the engine is
uh current per per voltage the power is
a current per voltage and so there's no
I here the minus sign comes from the
relation for the uh CC effect
so
that's what I've done
here and next I say
well the actual if I put
uh my uh thermoelectric
generator and it does have uh some
entropy produced by
irreversibility and that entropy
produced by irreversibility
is given by the
Fier term and the Jewel effect
term of course the actual work of the
generator will be uh less it will be the
reversible minus t *
Sigma and since I was I was there I was
just I just decided to keep also all the
tensors that I know complicates the
story but uh since I I haven't seen it
done
uh anywhere not that I looked everywhere
but uh so I said well why not working it
out and I hope I did the right thing
um so
[Music]
you using that expression and
substituting the
thermoelectric electric relations these
ones you find an expression for
the actual electrical work you can
maximize it so you find at which current
density it has the maximum
power so maximum power doesn't mean that
the engine is
reversible uh it's a particular
particular point of operation of the
engine and uh or generator
and so if you if you compute this
current if you substitute this
maximum current density at maximum power
into the expression for the work you get
this expression
here where there begins to appear now I
highlight this parameter
Z which forign an isotropic material
takes this form and it's what is called
the U the
the yeah the parameter of Merit the
figure of Merit for the electro for the
thermoelectric
material and there are some materials
that have have that parameter of the
order of one but uh there are also some
Nano structured materials that go well
above one maybe I think even two or even
three um
and this is why the fact that you can
achieve and that
nowadays you
um you are actually uh engineering
materials by
layering exactly like we did uh for for
the non-isotropic heat transfer example
here you can cook
up um layers layered materials that have
uh properties alternate properties with
high conductivity or or low
um I mean um yeah High um uh CC
coefficient and uh low conductivity
thermal
conductivity and uh depending on how you
structure them you may
obtain uh good aspects of this tensor
which of course relates to the
properties uh of how how much it I mean
in the direct if the the directions come
in see see the gradient in temperature
dotted into the tensor means that the
directions are important the relative
direction of your material and uh the
direction in which you put the the
gradient okay then you once you have
this you can also substitute all the
rest in all the rest and compute also
the second low efficiency second low
efficiency is the I
between
the work at maximum power and the
reversible work that you could
get with that current that you have at
the maximum
power and this is
the generalized expression for that
efficiency which for the isotropic
material becomes this one the figure of
Merit divided by 1 plus 2 Z and if you
if you look at this
function uh um I mean z and what is it Z
ided by 1 + 2 Z well it's a function
that of course is zero at
zero uh and then it goes
up and
eventually it could reach one
does it reach
one or does it
reach2 uh it's a good question H yeah it
looks one half
yeah
okay all right so this fixes that um
error that I made a while ago but it's I
mean errors are instructive and uh
stimulating so that you try to correct
them so that's
good here is
another example somewhat similar to that
one
uh think of having instead of the
electrostatic potential having the
pressure so you have two reservoirs one
at T and P and the other at t plus DT
and P plus
DP so here you could uh since you have
suppose this is a
fluid uh well then you could use in
addition to the termal work you you you
in in um you could use the difference in
pressure to drive a
flow through a hydraulic
turbine and the work of the hydraulic
turbine is given by the difference in
pressure times the volumetric fluide
like in a pump no uh so that uh is sort
of uh very analogous to the
thermoelectric effect
and so with this pair of degrees of dise
equilibrium o sorry here no yeah okay so
um you treat exact you you take those
two elements that survive in the
expression for the entropy
production you assume linear
relations and now the flows are Heat and
instead of charge here now you have just
particles and if
you divide the uh flow of particles by
the concentration you get a volumetric
fluide so this is cubic meters per
second per square meter uh
flowing so you can rewrite because
usually what we do is rewrite
these Expressions were
uh we have been careful in using the
entropic uh degrees of dise equilibrium
so
that that we know that that's where the
onager reciprocity applies and so I can
uh safely say that these coefficients
lqp is equal to
lpq here Q Q stands for heat and P
stands for pressure of course and so now
at this level I can apply on
sagger but then we like to work with
more familiar variables which in this
case are the volumetric flow rate and
the gradient in pressure is already
there and the gradient in temperature
instead of the inverse temperature so we
introduce
parameters
like the normal
conductivity uh or on the other uh the
other diagonal element is usually
written as K Over new where new is the
viscosity the sheer viscosity of your
fluid and K is
the Dy uh permeability because if you
had only these um
uh diagonal term here uh this is simply
Theo of flow in like in a capillary or
in a porous medium driven by the
gradient in uh in pressure which is what
you would use for example to describe uh
the flow in a porous material or a semi
or a permeable
membrane like here
or in a in a capillary tube or in a
micro fluidic device or things like
that but the off diagonal terms are
also there and they give rise to U two
cross phenomena that are related to one
another that sometimes are go under the
name of thermoosmotic effect or
mechanocaloric
effect so the thir
osmotic is is this
one uh no I'm sorry Theros motic is this
one you have a flow of
material in the
absence of uh gradient in in in in
pressure driven by a gradient in
temperature we could
actually have this
flow uh go uh if the gradient in
pressure is is small but opposite to
what it would what the Dilo would drive
the flow you could uh go against that um
pressure gradient by uh using a thermal
gradient appropriate thermal gradient so
that is one way in which you could
U somehow uh drive your material in uh a
capillary uh or mic microfluidic device
with a gradient in
temperature
against Grine pressure and the the
opposite or the
um yeah cross the conjugated the cross
effect is this one where you would
without a gradient in
temperature you could have a gradient in
pressure that drives a heat
flux but also here you could have uh if
if depending on the relative diff
differences you could have a gradient in
pressure Drive
Heat against uh up a temperature
gradient so in the opposite direction of
what you would
expect if you just had for you
okay so now let's move into the realm of
uh diffusion of
particles the
simplest is when we have two uh
constituents like a pair of particles so
we have inter diffusion of one into the
other and uh so this is a sort of a
direct uh low
case which you which gives rise to fix
law of
diffusion or
also since we're talking about a pair uh
it it it is belongs to instead of fi
it's called Stefan Maxwell Stefan um law
of of
diffusion and here is uh the story
actually uh see on the left hand side
here uh it's just repeated all the
various steps that took us
to uh the relation I just said so uh
let's just look at uh what we have here
on the right hand side which is the new
aspect so we assume a linear Force flux
law and as we've seen in the previous is
just a direct
effect the of this equilibrium X12
drives the flu the relative
flux J12
through a a coefficient that yeah on the
previous slide we call it l1212 here
just sort of drop the double one
two okay you
usually there are a couple of ways of in
which this is typically
Rewritten so there is no single uh
familiar way of writing of rewriting
this uh we like to rewrite it in terms
of diffusion
coefficients which are the things that
we measure in the
laboratory or we measure
also of nowadays with Monte Carlo
molecular dynamic simulations
uh and so we rewrite we call this l12
this way identify so these are the
concentrations of the
two constituents and of course they are
related to one another not because the
mole fraction is of SEC of the second
species is one minus the mole fraction
of the other one so uh also between the
concentrations you have a
similar
relation because uh all right and
so the other aspect is that you uh
somewhere yeah here you yeah here you
you you notice that you can prove that
the
X12 can also be written by virtue of the
um relation of
the Gibs DM
relation uh can be written also in terms
of either just
one uh gradient X1 is just the gradient
in in chemical potential of uh substance
one so it's just is this one like min-1
/ ttimes gradient of
mu1 and that's uh X1 but you could also
Define an X2 and these are all related
to X12 so by substituting and expressing
these uh in terms of the flux of
particles
one as proportional to the gradient in
chemical potential of that particle
you can rewrite it this way and then the
gradient in chemical potential of
particle one can be related if you do
properly the various derivatives since
the chemical
potential uh is a function of the
concentrations so you remember our
uh
usual expression here
for uh
for example for an ideal uh
mixture uh for an ideal mixture you can
U write this and therefore the gradient
in in the chemical potential done
because here we temperature fixed
temperature and pressure so this doesn't
enter into the gradient and so that so
then you get that gradient in mu is
RT times uh the
gradient of the logarithm so
that's
that's the gradient over over
Y and of course since the the con the
the mole fraction are related to the
concentration you can also rewrite it in
terms of
concentration so uh that
is I mean this expression is for the
ideal if you have a more General
situation uh you would have to do the
the partial derivative of U with respect
to to to n which is written here and
that's that's what appears
here so if you include all these then
you have a relation between the flux of
particle
one and the con the the con
concentration of particle one times the
gradient in the mole
fraction and then you can call this
group The F diffusion
coefficient which you see is related to
the Maxwell St and diff Fusion
coefficient and so it all depends
on giving names to these diffusion
coefficients the
um typically people measure F diffusion
coefficients notice also that you can
uh you can also Define
a self
diffusion uh
case this is done for example
U suppose you have just water in your in
your box
and but suppose that some of the oxygens
some of the water molecules some
percentage of of water molecules are U
doped well actually they're made with
isotopes of oxygen so instead of using
oxygen 16 you use oxygen 18 so you have
water
molecules that have a a an isotope for
the for the for the oxy
oygen that doesn't the isotop doesn't
change the chemical
properties uh but that allows you to uh
with
proper uh detection to follow the
diffusion of the sort of a heavy uh it's
not really heavy water because the heavy
water is with the arterium not with the
oxygen 18 but uh that in this case it's
a heavier water than uh than the other
one so you can see the inter diffusion
and and of course this diffusion is
related to the brunian motion the random
motion uh generated by collisions and
the kinetic energy that the particles
always have at finite temperatures so in
that case you
measure the self diffusion of uh
water uh which is which is a which is an
interesting uh case and subase of this
one now if in addition to having
gradients in concentrations you have
also gradient in
temperature this opens
up uh to diffusion or Thermo diffusion
effects
and so the transport THM of for Asis
means remember foris means transport so
uh it's
you you
generate Flux Of of um
particles with a gradient in temperature
even if you don't
have the driving force of the gradient
of the chemical potential so even if you
don't have gradients in concentrations
just the GR in temperature drives
particles so that so that
is this is
the written explicitly X12 which is
minus one / T times the gradient mu1
minus mu2
uh we can write it also in terms like
I've said here with the partial
derivative starting from the chemical
potentials you can write it this
way in terms of the
concentration uh yeah sorry this should
be a C1 over C1 not I I'll correct that
yeah okay so this is the setup up so
that's the usual formula for the entropy
production from which you infer what are
the entropic degrees of thise
equilibrium which are the ones that
enter in the linear Force flux
relations and
um
so the
the force flux relations are are this
you therefore put in Matrix of
coefficients and the Matrix has to be
symmetric so we will have that L
q12 is equal to l12
q and we rewrite it
in so-called familiar variables or the
traditional ways so as to single out the
gradients in concentrations instead of
the gradient in canical
potentials however when you do
that your system of
equation loses the
apparent
symmetry so you see this of diagonal
terms are not uh
identical
H but I have
used in order to uh to put this DT here
you see DT is called the thero thermod
diffusive
coefficient and
uh whereas
D12 is the FI so this is the F diffusion
coefficient is the direct effect
between so it's it's you drive a flow
flux of particles a diffusion of
particles by the concentration grade
of one of
them and uh whereas this
drives the flow of
particles the flux of particles the
diffusive flux of particles with the
gradient in
temperature and you can enter these
equations in many different
ways for example if you you assume uh no
uh gradient in
concentration then you have the heat
flux that is simply given by Fier
F or if you choose to work at zero
gradient in
temperature the second equation gives
you fix law
you could
also uh consider though that when you
work at no gradient in in concentration
you don't have only the first equation
you also have the second equation and
that uh gives you a a flux of particles
driven by just the GR in temperature
that is the S effect
effect this is the effect
whereby for
example uh you have
U dust particles in the
air that
collect uh like I you may have noticed
or you probably know uh that uh in your
house you often find dust near the cold
walls is S effect
because
me from the mechanistic point of
view suppose this is a a dust particle
so it's a large particle with respect to
the molecules of air and let's say these
are molecules of oxygen nitrogen and so
suppose you have um a gradient in
temperature this
way so you get cold
here and and hotter there
okay so the idea is simply that the
particles on this side have a a higher
kinetic
energy and when they bounce on the
particle of course they uh exchange that
they exert the force on one
side that is
slightly
less than the one exerted by the
collisions with the particles that come
from the cold side which are a bit
slower so this
pushes
Your Dust particle towards the
cold
uh notice also
yeah and the opposite effect the
the the conjugate effect is is the duur
effect so when I have a thi
law at no gradient in temperature so I
have a flux of particles driven by
concentration but I also have a heat
flux driven by the by the the
concentration
okay so it's it's like the the the flux
of of of particles that carries with it
also a heat
flux and that's the duur
effect these effects were were
discovered separately then only later
they were linked by the onager theory of
reciprocity also it's interesting uh to
note this that um for example suppose
you have
a suppose you you you have no U flux of
particles so you set this equal to
zero okay so if you set that equal to
zero you see that there comes a relation
between a gradient in concentration and
a gradient in temperature so if you
suppose you impose a gradient in
temperature
then and there is no way
that
the you don't allow this flux of
particles then the gradient in
temperature builds up a gradient
gradient in concentration and that
gradient concentration has a play in the
first equation up
here and it um
reduces the effective
conductivity so the the conductivity the
the thermal conductivity at no
concentration is higher than the thermal
conductivity at
no uh diffusive
flux okay
now that simple picture that I have uh
shown here on the
Blackboard
is is one uh possibility and it's
uh
uh one mechanistic possibility that
explains the s effect or the term of
orasis so the transport of dust
particles of to towards the cold
side in part that is due to the size of
the particles and so it belongs this
this nice article
that
summarizes
thermophoretic
mechanisms shows that there are many
other mechanisms that uh um Drive
The Sur effect that control the Sur
effect so typically the the heavy
particles like to get moved to the cold
side uh or the the skew uh particles for
the large particles but then there are
also more
sophisticated um actions including
some double layer effects on the surface
of particles that have some charge on on
their surface so there is a whole realm
of
uh
possibilities uh with which you can use
S effect to drive
things uh towards the hot or towards the
cold depending on how you engineer your
materials and or how you or the
properties of your materials
this is um another paper that shows how
you can use um gradient in
temperature to move
particles against uh friction force in a
small pipe this is the carbon nanot tube
in which you have water
molecules and uh and so you manage with
a gradient in temperature to win the
friction forces because one of the
problems in moving stuff in small pipes
is that you have you would need huge
pressure drops if you wanted to do it
with a pump and and that will the device
will break because of the high pressures
whereas thermophoresis or electroforesis
are more effective and uh more more
doable
and this is also in a
thermofluidic device the
idea that the gradient in temperature so
you have
a like a hot flow which keeps a hot side
and the cold Flo which keeps a cold fly
side and then you have your uh actual
device with with particles in it and you
want to separate the particles and
that's what what happens by S effect the
let's say the big the particles go to
the cold side and so you reach
separation in your
device now it is also
uh important to realize that U what we
have covered here is only
very uh
minor aspect of the phenomenologic
phenomenology that goes with diffusing
particles and uh so what I'm doing with
these slides is I don't pretend I want I
can describe what happens but I want
just to
suggest that the variety of phenomena
that needs to be discussed uh if we have
um let's say another course but also by
another teacher because I'm not prepared
on this topic
uh but maybe the next teacher of this
course will be uh and um and so there
are for example we talked about the nsen
number uh the relative
uh size of the um mean mean free path
relative to
the dimension of your
device so if the nuton number is very
small then your
particles let's say that uh if they make
um at least 100 collisions before uh
traveling a distance of the order of
magnitude of your device which the so it
could be the diameter of your
pipe then we are safe and we are in the
in the you can make the Continuum
assumption that we have made uh in what
we've
done but if the nuton number becomes
larger
um and you may uh you may reach the
Other Extreme which is the
ballistic extreme in which a particle
May travel all the way from one side to
the other of your device without even
having a
collision so this is not uh dominated by
collisions between particles but it's
dominated by collisions between
particles and the walls of your
device plus there are surface
effects and
so uh you see there is a variety of
things that uh need to
be
considered now thermop
foris can also be is
also used as a way
[Music]
to uh move particles
around this is called self propelling uh
particles
for example here we have
a
um a PhD thesis and an
article that talks
about using a phenomenon that we have
discussed which is spinodal
decomposition
uh in order to move move around
particles and there are two kinds of
particles uh this one which has a double
phas it's called Janos particles because
Janos is the god with two faces Greek
god with two faces so this is so this
particle is goldplated on one side and
not on the other side and the gold uh
surface layer uh guarantees a since it
has a high conduct AC ity guarantees a
uniform temperature uh and so then what
what what they do is to um shine some
laser light to heat up that
particle and that
therefore um a temperature
profile uh builds
up
and and then they found they find a a
solution so the particle is in a
solution solution which is which
is non non missible at high temperatures
so we have we have studied spinodal
decomposition in in substances that have
an upper critical
point remember and this is the uh
spinodal curve this is the unstable and
this is the metastable region
okay so you could do that phenomenon
that that thing if you could cool down
the particle but it's easier to heat up
than cool so they found it easier to U
develop a mixtures that work the other
way
around uh from what I remember also
water and nicotine uh as a lower bound
as a lower critical point like this uh I
don't know exactly what substances they
use here water and 2.6 looted in
okay whatever that is uh in any case uh
the idea is that you start I mean the
blue uh mixture which is on the
surrounding the particle is at this
point so it's fully
mixed and
then since you heat up the surface of
the particle in this uh layer say
boundary layer around it the temperature
goes up and you enter into
the uh
unstable region and the unstable
region uh
creates
uh the let's say the freeze the free
energy uh and that free energy if
properly directed can be used to propel
the
particles in two ways you need
asymmetries so for the Ginos particles
the asymmetry is on the fact that uh you
have more heating on one side on the
other and therefore uh you get you
generate a concentration gradient from
this side to the other side and that Mo
that movement of particle in One
Direction uh
uh propels the the the big particle in
the other direction and so you get the
particle move or
here they have a still a goldplated
particle but all around so it's not
Janos but but it's not uh completely
it's not completely spherical so non non
sperical particle and the the non
sperical aspect here makes it so so that
the gradient in the concentration and
the gradient in temperature
cross so that Crossing means that the
these two gradients are not directed in
the same so there is a
component of the gradient
in uh in in
concentration uh that
goes orthogonal to the gradient in
temperature and that will cause the
movement of particles that will push
your
U your big particle
uh I think
downward okay so you can play also you
can play people are playing because you
see this recent uh this is recent work
there's a lot that people are doing
using these uh
methods
or another way
to exploit uh or Deploy on equilibrium
is
um what they are called molecular
Motors essentially
are
Nano particles that develop motion at
the expense of
um chemical
reactions and here for example the the
particle it simply has a Catal a Catal
Catalyst or an enzy enzimatic site which
catalyzes the chemical reaction so it
lowers U the activat the venous
activation energy only uh locally here
so it promotes chemical reactions uh in
this side of the particles of course the
chemical reactions change the
composition the change in
composition creates a gradient in
concentration and that and that's how
you get you get Flux Of of
particles in
fact we
said that uh the
um um KU symmetry
principle uh prevents in an isotropic
medium uh two couple chemical reactions
which are scalar uh um transport with
with with with with vectorial transports
but on the other hand uh the fusion
is sometimes the limiting aspect in
chemically reacting system because it is
by diffusion that particles go to the
proper place and then where they used up
for uh reacting with with the other
reactants so indirectly uh the fusion
processes are are very important in in
in controlling chemical uh reactions so
they are effectively not coupled in the
way of the onager kind but but they are
coupled overall in order to feed the
chemic the chemical reactions with the
reactants where they need to be
and then if you have uh
simultaneously a
diffusion uh so many uh constituents and
also the electro static
field the the charges play a role they
may play a role just locally like these
kind of double layers around
particles um that have charges inside
that can move to the
surface and these effects are things
that happen for example at electrodes in
in in in a fuel cell
[Music]
or or an electrolytic
um
device or simply you have like a
thermoelectric effect coupled to
diffusion
so this is
a what you so electrochemical systems
belong to this kind of class and these
are the kind of equations that you need
to
consider if you model an electrochemical
system with say three different part and
three different particles is very common
because you may have like the solvent
and you have two solutes but often you
have many more and these solutes could
be the ions that travel in your
electrolytic
solution uh the typical models are done
this way with this inter diffusion uh
taking up only the diagonal ones and
often
uh forgetting these other
more complicated or second order maybe U
cross
effects uh but if you are interested in
doing Electro chem modeling
electrochemical systems
then these are the references that you
should not uh um
overlook this book
non equilibrium thermodynamics for
heterogeneous systems by KR and
bed um is an excellent starting
point for doing properly things the way
we've
done and also for realizing that uh so
you can compute distributions in in the
Heat this they call they call they use
the the the gr and mazour notation so
what we call called The Q double Prime
they call measurable heat flux but other
than that
uh they essentially
use the
same notation that we've
done
uh and
um also a very important aspect here is
the the interfaces
at the
electrodes and uh so where you have you
you have sort of um jumps from one
substance to the
other and uh yes you
could Define um continuous or diffuse
interface theories which is another
aspects that that need to be covered
uh but
um they do it with sharp
interfaces which is the Gibbs uh
traditional
method uh but the reason why I urge you
to go to their work is that they do it
correctly and carefully and in
particular Also regarding this
um role of
interfaces and then on equilibrium
thermodynamics at surfaces there is this
paper by GED by one of them dick bed in
1986 which is really wonderful and uh
you should uh uh study that paper if you
are in this
business now of course um we are at the
end of the course so not covering
anything more of
but I want to mention that
um there are many other directions in
which you could go in the field of
thermodynamics which
is related to the general principles
that we have
developed but perhaps not the detailed
models
so of course the the Queen is
statistical
mechanics which is behind we've used
also some of it when we did the single
particle in the
Box
um but then you have also uh kinetic
theory of to deal with rarified gas
Dynamics if you if your notes and number
is not very
small and in fact
uh to cover that the phenomenology of
essentially the the entire fluid
mechanics redone at the uh at
the
non
nen very small nsen
number people have redeveloped uh
there's been
a couple of Decades of very active work
on small scale
hydrodynamics still still
ongoing then on the side of
um
um on the side of developing
uh the foundation so even for
Continuum uh we have this uh issue
remember that of the local
equilibrium where we assume that we are
at this state but we're actually there
and so there is this difference in
entropy uh that we are
neglecting if you do local
equilibrium and uh
which is not neglected in these other
theories like rational extended
thermodynamics or
uh other non-e equilibrium
thermodynamics theories and there are
not only papers but books about these
approaches and you've seen that we by
using this we' we've seen one example
the katano heat transfer equation well
in that same uh idea you can develop and
you should develop also uh all all the
things that we've done even include
including what we've done
today so there is a lot to be done also
in that
Direction there is
also okay then there is quantum aspects
we talked already about that and uh
there is
also this diffuse interface uh uh
methods that again if you have two
phases you could consider them as sharp
like uh for example liquid and Vapor you
could have uh uh this is the density of
the of the
vapor and this is the density of the
liquid let say
yeah you could consider it sharp but if
you enlarge this
region uh it's
actually something like this
okay and by assuming the fundamental
relation for your States uh for example
by assuming that
s is not just the function of U
um v
n but it's also a function function
of the gradients in
concentration and actually since you
need scolar it's you can take uh the
square of the
gradient and you put in it in in as a as
an additional variable which determines
equilibrium and now we're talking about
equilibrium because that's a stable
equilibrium state for
equilibrium that term
which was uh present also in um in the
paper by vand der
vals and that which actually is a very
nice paper has been trans translated by
rimson later on and I suggest that you
go and see that paper if you are
studying this well this Theory here has
been developed by land it has
this is now become known as can and
helard models or diffuse interface uh
methods with that thing uh you can
predict the exact shape of this curve at
equilibrium uh and actually there is a
paper very nice paper in the physical
review by an antovski that
uh I suggest that you read if you are
interested in in that kind of
development all right so plus of course
you have a a list of an infinite list
of other
approaches from uh statistical to
numerical simulations so the bolman
equation um approximations of the M
bolman equation this is the famous one
which allows you to compute the
hydrodynamic quantities like heat
flux but Al so the fluxes of particles
but also the like momentum and and
diffusive uh as moments of the balsman
distribution uh uh of equilibrium so we
talking about models that can cover
also non equilibrium and far non
equilibrium uh another approximation is
one
which
derives the equivalent of the N talks
equations but more complicated with more
moments then fer plank
stochastic
um equations these are equations that
have some
random noise terms in in
it and then you're certainly familiar
with molecular Dynamics Monte Carlo and
various types of molecular
Dynamics various flavors of the
molecular dynamics that have been
developed over the years to overcome
some of the
limitations Okay so
yeah so with this I I think I like to
end the course remembering that uh we
have celebrated
carnot's um 20 200 birthday
with and uh I also yes I want to remind
you of the progin prize so if you ever
end
up uh with a PhD thesis in the field of
Dynamics all aspects of thermodynamics
from applied to experimental to very
theoretical don't forget to uh apply for
this uh
price it uh it is done every two years
the next deadline is February 1st next
year and for this call it will Co it
will cover uh PhD defended between
January 1st of last year
2023 and December 31 of this
year uh it's a pretty International uh
uh price it in the last eight8 editions
we had one 134 uh candidates from 28
different
countries you can click here for um all
the
details and it is sponsored by um a
series of conference it's called a joint
European thermodynamics conference but
this has become an international
one uh and the next one will be in
Belgrade in in
Serbia next year in May or
June the day the date is not being
decided yet as soon as it will be out
I'll I'll provide I'll put in a link
here uh so that you can
you can see what it is
about all right so I'd like to conclude
and i' like to thank you for attending
the lectures which I dedicate to my
mentors and um but
also I thank you very much for the
quality of your video homeworks because
they have been um stimulating me for um
uh at least um there
a giving me some feedback that uh some
of the messages I wanted to pass have
been passed so thank you very much