I'm a London -based neuropsychologist and
former professional ballerina. I came across
MIT Open Learning back in 2022 whilst
looking for new things to learn about the
world and myself. My highlights remain
Professor Adams' course in quantum mechanics
and late Professor Winston's lectures
on AI. I am now enrolled in the Computer
Science and Programming in Python course
offered by MIT, quite an adventure. I am a
multilingual and I find learning how to
code similar to learning a new language, a
fascinating challenge, along with perhaps
finally learning how to cycle this year. And
yes, I do have my debugging rubber ducky.
Thank you MIT Open Learning for making
knowledge accessible and for encouraging
curious minds to share and apply knowledge,
hopefully for the greater good. It is
perhaps the only way for us humans to move
forward. And that comes from me, the
greatest Terminator fan. Thank you.