So, a very warm welcome to BT's
headquarters.
Um, and an especially warm welcome to
our guests from MIT who are hosting the
MIT London Symposium today. My name is
Ed Staintton and I lead the public
sector business here within BT which
gives me a fascinating vantage point
because in my role I'm at the
intersection of politics,
technology,
society and business. And as I look
around um the UK and some of the
challenges that we are facing into in
this ever changing world, being
absolutely at the forefront of
technological innovation is key to how a
business like BT has ma remained
relevant for over 180 years. In fact,
next year is our 180th birthday.
Um, and the reason we've been able to
keep relevant is we've always been at
the forefront of innovation from
essentially forming the internet
um through to today where we keep ahead
of the threats that we're all familiar
with uh from cyber security to
protecting our networks against the next
wave of technological evolution. Um, for
example, quantum encryption is a key
area of research for us.
Um, but at the heart of research and
innovation is collaboration.
And that's why I'm so proud that at BT
we are part of the MIT's industrial
liaison program and it's actually run
out and hosted by um our public sector
business because we see the read across
between uh the vital research that comes
out of arguably the most important uh
research innovator academically globally
um and how we then bring that back into
the UK and help um support our
government and public sector partners
and in fact if you look at the
industrial strategy for the UK that's
just recently been published by the UK
government at the heart of that is
actually um innovation and research
around advanced telecommunications which
is vital to keep the UK and society on
the front foot when it comes to um you
know evolution of our economy bearing in
mind that um techn um telecommunications
is very much at the heart of
underpinning many of the areas we're
going to hear about today, be it kind
of, you know, AI and other advanced
technologies.
Um, one thing I'll be reflecting on
today as I listen to the the various
amazing speakers we have coming up and
and sharing their insights with us is
the societal impact of technology.
Um, as a kid, I always daydreamed what
the future would be like. And I had a
vision of hoverboards, flying cars, and
this amazing, exciting, friendly world
where technology
has resulted perhaps in some dystopian
outcomes
um that that we see on the battlefield,
that we see in cyerspace. Um, and it
also has potential to completely reshape
society.
um especially with the phenomenal
advances we're seeing in AI shaping
society around jobs around culture
around societal interconnection.
Um so while technology is is a
fascinating area and we're going to be
certainly hearing about a lot of that
today. Um those societal impacts are one
thing that I will certainly be thinking
over. Um, so all I'm here to do really
this morning is to offer you a very warm
welcome before we bring up onto stage um
our guests from MIT.
Thank you for the welcoming remarks. Uh
I'm Gatri Shrini Vasan. I head corporate
relations. I'm the executive director at
MIT corporate relations.
Um with that you know at MIT we define
innovation as a process of taking ideas
to uh impact right as uh here we have uh
shown the nanoarchchitected carbon that
can withstand ultrasonic impacts
basically materials that laugh on the
face of physics. Um we are working on
commercial plasma fusion and clean
energy because why not solve the energy
crisis while we are at it. um and paper
thin solar cells. Um I mean that's uh
that's what we think of thin margins. Um
I think um and then of course you have
Bob Langanger um who's one of our
institute professors who's basically a
patent factory walking down the halls of
MIT uh professor Munji Bendi uh who won
the Nobel Prize uh for quantum dots uh
which by the way are now in your TVs and
helping you with Netflix binging which
which works for me as well and make uh
things look better than ever on TV. Uh
and by the way, we've also sent a few
people to outer space because these MIT
alums who uh decided that earth was just
not challenging enough. Um and then last
year we had Darren Asimoglu and uh Simon
Johnson who won the Nobel Prize for
economics. So yeah, we are covering
everything from atoms to astronauts to
economic systems. Um and of course you
saw this uh the video before so that
itself was um uh very inspiring but just
showing you um these uh exam examples
also help. Um speaking of impact here
are just a few of the companies that
were started by MIT folks and when I say
a few I mean all these and there's
Campbell soup. So your chicken noodle
soup has MIT DNA in it. The point is
MITers don't just start companies, they
start industries. So that's the point
I'm trying to make by showing this.
And these are just numbers. The Nobel
laureates, the MacArthur Genius Fellows,
all that. But beyond that, I didn't want
to focus on 362 patents, which is one
patent a day pretty much a year. Uh
which three days vacation. So I guess we
give people vacation. Um there's 700
companies that we collaborate with. Uh
593 invention disclosures. So a lot is
happening. So you may ask like what is
MIT doing now, right? What are we
focused on? And so that's a great
question. But um President uh Conluth's
priorities are um to double down on
these specific areas. uh climate where
we are marshalling our expertise to lead
on technological, behavioral and policy
solutions because someone has to. Um and
we've got all the kinds of solutions
including the rocket scientists uh that
can help solve these problems, right? Um
then we have health and life sciences
bringing together worldclass expertise
catalyze discovery and innovation for
human health. Um you saw Mona and that
was that helped solve our COVID uh
vaccination uh and you know uh uh
immunity for us. Um human insights
elevating human- centered um research.
We are engineers but we also remember
that humans are the ones who are using
all the technology. So we need to bring
that uh insight into existence as well.
um artificial intelligence uh providing
leadership as uh society navigates AI's
implications
um education um designing curricula that
is going to be um meaningful for the
digital and AI age uh manufacturing
defining future of manufacturing with
higher productivity lower carbon uh
footprint better jobs greater resilience
resilience um trying to make things
better than what it is right Now um
quantum amplifying quantum research and
driving innovation because regular
comput computation is not good enough.
It's just boring. Um but uh beyond that
um jokes aside um so what do we have in
the water here? What is special about
MIT? Um and uh it's not the weather. Um
it's it's you know four things that I've
highlighted here. One is uh we ask what
the problem is. um then we figure out
how to pay for it and um uh work on the
problems. Second, we encourage highly
encourage risk takingaking and uh
focusing on hard problems. We uh expect
failure on the way to success. Uh we
don't just tolerate failure, we actually
celebrate it towards the journey towards
uh uh as a learning opportunity. Um and
that is hard in a corporate environment
but in an academic setting it becomes
easier.
Um third we have well staffed uh offices
um that's our office which helps with um
putting industry in the room um
understanding the problem where and we
are literally here to make the
connections happen. Um and last but not
least all key ecosystem stakeholders are
within walking distance. We have the
entrepreneurs, government, corporate,
risk capital or venture capital um uh
firms, uh MIT researchers all in the
same neighborhood. Um we can't have
serendipitous conversations
uh or coffee meetings when everybody's
in a different time zone. Uh it just
makes it easier when everybody's in the
same place. And uh again uh it's not
about MIT being um the solution or
problem solver in isolation. is about
MIT being the catalyst to bring everyone
together. Um, and we are like the yeast
in the innovation bread. I hope that
sounded good.
Um, uh, but anyway, we we help uh uh
leaven and rise the bread and so I guess
rise innovation. Uh, but uh let me tell
you about uh two programs uh which our
office runs with. One is the industrial
leazison program and the second one is
the MIT startup exchange. The industrial
leazison program is the comprehensive uh
portal to MIT. Uh we have 200 plus
members who use this as the front door
to uh to everything that MIT has to
offer. Um the MIT startup exchange um is
a program through which we promote
collaboration between um industry and
MIT connected startups. uh we've got
over 800 uh startups in uh that we work
with and that's a lot of disruption
that's waiting to happen.
So um you might wonder um
what do you actually do once once you
become an ILP member right um what you
actually get is the opportunity to
connect with MIT around research
innovation students and education I call
it rise because it's easier to remember
all the four pieces but the idea is you
can connect around all those four pieces
through our conferences like this uh
leading edge webinars um inperson in
events ac across the globe, customized
events that meet your specific needs. Uh
meeting faculty, executive briefings,
learning journeys, uh with researchers
and experts in the field, uh meet with
and network with um students, the
startups and other peer uh organizations
that are part of the program. Um in
addition it helps uh you get upskilling,
reskilling and new skilling also
possible through our uh professional
education, exec education and uh open
learning.
Industry all industry now have to be uh
focused on innovation. So if you are
innovating come and talk to us we would
love to collaborate with you. And I also
wanted to uh let you know is that you
know um we are not talking about only
one industry or one area or a couple
areas. When we think about uh impact we
talking about all kinds of areas of
impact and you can see aerospace,
defense, automotive, um life sciences,
equipment, all kinds of areas where MIT
can help um you with your um innovation.
Um and this is not a Boston thing. I did
talk about you know serendipitous coffee
meetings on campus but this is a global
thing. So the 200 plus members that we
have are across the globe and this is a
representation of where they exist.
These are a few success stories of
companies that have worked around
specific projects. Um these are all
member companies and you know uh the way
to think about it is um these are kinds
of breakthroughs that are waiting to
happen when you bring brilliant minds in
your organization to work with brilliant
minds at MIT to solve uh tough problems.
These are a few representations of uh
startup success stories. Um these are
companies that started with an idea uh
some MIT knowhow uh and a healthy dose
of audacity and now they are changing
the world and these are all companies
that they're working with uh that are
member companies
and with that I thank you for sitting
through my presentation but I did want
to emphasize that MIT is not just about
producing great research we we do do
that uh and it's not about uh creating
great startups which is also something
that we do but it's about building this
ecosystem of collaborators across the
globe solving real problems and with
that um if you want to know more about
ILP how to work with MIT please uh reach
out to us I have a few colleagues uh
from my team that are here um can you
please stand up um that's Steve Palmer
that's Steve Whitaker um and of course
there are lots of MIT folks that you
will see today. You can of course ask
them about ILP as well. With that, thank
you. Um I don't know whether there's
time for questions, but if you have a
question, I'm happy to answer.