and let's welcome um Nicolas stransky um
the corporate VP of data science um of
serice Life Sciences um Nico the floor
is yours I know that there is a slight
change on the titles of the slide so
I'll leave it to you to introduce the
title thank you all right so I'm going
to take us in a slightly different
direction today than uh the first couple
talks um and uh the reason for that is
because drug Discovery spans really a
lot of topics especially in Industry
where in drug Discovery first we need to
understand what the biology of the
disease is what potential targets could
be all the way down to identifying a
patient population so who are we going
to treat how are we going to find those
patients uh how can we predict whether
they're going to respond or not to a
particular drug um and of course drug
Discovery also includes like coming up
with the the drug or identifying the the
the relevant Targets in the the the
structure of those targets and so what I
want to focus on today is aspects that
relate to our use of genomics and
Diagnostics and molecular data to better
understand uh patient populations and
predict uh drug response and
outcomes so uh my name is Nikos trky I
lead the data science at Caris Life
Sciences which is a cancer diagnostic
company based in Texas and Phoenix
Arizona and also here in Cambridge where
as a data science team that that I
lead so um to to start with a little bit
of additional context U 30 years ago um
the the first targeted therapy was was
invented IM matb against Abel which is a
kyes that drives acute maloid leukemia
and following that and that revolution
in the care of that disease there was an
enormous effort to identify more of
these targets
uh more more kindnesses and other kinds
of targets that could be uh treated
directly with a with a drug in a
targeted fashion meaning precisely
inhibiting what's causing the the
disease and shortly following that uh
that Revolution there was the rise of
the what we called Next Generation
sequencing uh with driven by multiple
companies who really revolutionized the
space not with that exact sequencer in
the 2000s but but still uh there was an
enormous revolution in the the
generation of genomic data which led to
multiple improvements in the field one
much better molecular characterization
of diseases cancer and other
diseases uh that led to better Target
identification but also gave us the
tools and the data to identify those
patient
populations and then because of that
enormous rise in the amount of data that
was generated genomic data we needed
better tools to analyze those data and
tease out what could be driving disease
what could be specific targets and what
could be uh uh subsets of the the the
patients that might respond to a drug
and and AI or ml or or extremely useful
for that and that's what I want to to
talk about
today so um following that rise of of
the use of sequencing we went from a
symptomatic diagnosis uh there's a mass
there's a different uh uh there's
different appearance of of a a certain
condition to really profiling
molecularly cancer and other diseases to
understand what genes are involved what
what mutations any kind of other
alterations are involved so that we can
very effectively match a drug in a
patient uh when when it comes to either
the response or or the um the
outcomes the um the the the the the drug
space or the treatment space in in
cancer uh comprises a lot of drugs that
are associated with a particular
diagnostic so the so-called companion
diagnostic which require that we
identify the precise molecular
alterations that would allow the doctor
to prescribe a drug to treat the disease
and in this uh slide are the depicted
multiple of these these targeted
Inhibitors so they're mostly uh uh small
molecule Inhibitors on those slide
together with the kind of molecular
alterations that need to be detected in
order to prescribe the drug so that's
really a combination of the the
availability of the drug and the ability
of the the Physicians to identify those
patients and that's why the field of of
Diagnostics uh is is so important
because there's a there's these are not
drugs that can be prescribed to all
patients for a particular cancer these
are drugs that need to be prescribed to
a patient when they have the particular
alteration and that's uh this the then
the enormous challenge of identifying
those patients because it requires very
Advanced uh uh profiling techniques very
costly profiling techniques for those
cancers uh that span multiple
Technologies and the reason why um I'm
having um the reason why I have this uh
this U diagram in the middle is because
we're spanning DNA sequencing RNA
sequencing uh protein profiling through
imunohistochemistry and other
Technologies and all of these need to be
done most of the time all on the same
sample to identify which uh drugs might
be prescribed to to a
patient so with that context uh Caris is
diagnostic company were uh a a mostly a
sequencing company generating an
enormous amount of sequencing every day
24/7 uh probably the the biggest
sequencing company uh there's
50 actually many more uh 50 Nova 6 uh U
Down in in Arizona to perform all the
sequencing 50,000 uh cancer samples per
month uh that's tissue samples there is
also liquid profiling from blood
biopsies uh and uh he hematological
malignancies profiling soon as I said
there's labs in Arizona in in Texas and
data science in Cambridge so the the the
the kinds of diagnostic the kind of
diagnostic that need to be performed
employ uh these various data types that
I mentioned before DNA sequencing RNA
sequencing which allows us to identify
certain fusions or certain gene
expression DNA of course allows us to
identify point mutations also fusions
and and uh copy number operations and
and other kinds of operations that are
important for the prescription of drugs
uh and then of course through protein we
can identify certain markers that would
be overexpressed or present and allow us
to to prescribe certain drugs so all of
that is very important for Diagnostics
but it's also very important for drug
Discovery and it enables our R&D
identifying new targets identifying new
patient
populations and the the nous amount of
data that's available to to us at Caris
and elsewhere enables these such
activities at the beginning of drug
Discovery so that's what I want to to
focus on today so let's start with an
example of one such diagnostic that has
existed for for 20 years on type DX it's
a diagnostic that's used in certain
breast cancers and predicts the
likelihood of
recurrence uh after after treatment with
a certain certain therapy it's based on
the gene expression of of multiple genes
uh that are profiled through rtpcr so
it's an old technology it's robust but
it's it's been around for for decades
and then there's a very simple score
that that's uh calculated that uh gives
a numerical number that allows to to um
uh uh determine the the next course of
treatment and there are multiple such
signatures of scores that exist in the
industry and this one seems um pretty
pretty simplistic although this
discovery was not but uh there's
probably better tools that we can employ
today through the enormous availability
of of data that's generated every day by
by many companies and through the use of
of machine learning and other techniques
to come up with better signatures
so with that
uh we need better signatures we need
better signatures because uh the the the
um we because we have the the POS the
the we have the the means of doing so
through better data and better
techniques but also because the current
ones don't work that well and there's
not perfect matching between drugs and
patients and I want to start with a
quote that seems a little Grim but but
is is true most drugs fail most patients
most of the time most drugs are not
going to work on on on on a particular
disease uh most patients are not going
to respond to a part particular drug and
when they do they're actually sadly
going to often times recur and and U
progress in their disease and that's
even true for the the the recent
generations of of therapy So-Cal Target
therapy that are much more tailored to
an individual's tumor so we need better
signatures because we need to match much
better the drugs and the
patients on top of that drug resistance
which is a phenomenon that either occurs
uh uh right when a patient is given the
drug or that that cancer evolves to to
um to to have it not respond to the drug
anymore drug resistance is not due to uh
to any one mechanism is due to a
multitude of mechanisms and it that
sadly that means that just profiling one
gene or or one part of the genome is not
going to tell us whether there is
resistance or not we need to look
everywhere uh to to identify or
understand drug resistance and that
that's uh also a necessity of of um
employing larger and larger data sets
methods that are going to maximize our
chances of of understanding uh drug
response drug uh U uh or or targets uh
are are most likely to be helpful that
use the methods that use both genomics
transcriptomics pathology images other
kinds of clinical information so using
as much information as possible is going
to teach us more about what's happening
in the disease and and which patients we
we want to identify and finally of
course machine learning is highly suited
for these kinds of all these kinds of
questions so with that jumping into the
the first uh principle of what I want to
talk about how do we use machine
learning to establish a robust data set
to enable R&D and by that I mean
identifying better targets
identifying
uh uh cancer drivers and identifying
patients
so 10 years ago this paper was published
uh here at the broad actually uh and
made uh certain predictions about what
kind of data are necessary to better
understand multiple kinds of cancers uh
down to the percentage of uh uh you know
down to three to 1% of prevalence of
certain mutation and so what it did is
uh depending on the the mutation
frequency across a a variety of cancers
that are depicted at the bottom it made
predictions of how how many of these
cancers need to be sequenced in order to
identify a mutation with a prevalence of
10 5 three two and one 1% and as you can
read on the this y AIS this is these are
staggering numbers they were completely
improbable numbers 10 years ago because
by that time uh we were uh or a lot of
people were in the middle of of the the
analysis of already a very large project
for cancer sequencing the cancer genom
Atlas or tcga and the the the number of
cancers that were sequenced in the tcga
was Al together between 10 and 15
thousands across all of these cancers
and so thinking that we would need one
day several thousands of to see we would
need one day to sequence several
thousands of samples for one particular
cancer was was uh not not imaginable at
the time of course we knew that with the
progress of of SE quencing that would
come one
day and that's now we're now at the CP
of achieving that scale to understand uh
and discover new cancer variants um
because we're starting to have the
numbers of course there's a one
important uh aspect here which is that
we need to uh focus on somatic mutations
somatic mutations are those mutations
that occur specifically in the in the
tumor and and that that are not
polymorphisms meaning that they don't
they're not part of our normal U genome
so sematic mutations they they can be
discovered when we're comparing a tumor
genome with a normal genome but in the
course of the data that we generate at
Caris we're only sequencing the tumor
and that's for for multiple reasons one
is for cost reasons it would cost twice
more to to sequence both the normal
genome and the tumor genome but also
because logistically it's much more
complicated to deal with with two kinds
of samples one liquid sample from from
blood and one uh sample from one one
solid sample from the the the solid
tumor of course it's possible to to to
sequence both tumor and normal but it's
it's more costly and impr practical so
then we're left with a question which is
how do we constitute a data set for
discovery that
uh is purely composed of sematic
mutations so the first quick example I
want to talk about is is a a technique
that we devised that we called Som alone
to identify the somatic mutations in uh
in tumor so tumor it's tumor only
sematic germline
classification um we the goal was to
apply it to the collection of a half
million cancer cases that we have that
I'm going to talk more in a couple of
slides uh but we used to to to devise
and train this method we we used a a
smaller data set of matched t uh uh
cancer tissue and normal blood
sequencing of a size of about 300
samples and that gave us the ground
truth of what sematic mutations versus
germine uh look like uh and long story
short this algorithm is using uh two
main source of of information one the
frequency of Norm of polymorphisms the
normal human population and the little
fraction of those mutations in the tumor
that was that was sequenced so in in all
our cells there's multiple polymorphisms
about one per thousand bases uh and in
case of heterozygous germine mutations
they're present in about 50% a little
fraction so the the polymorphism is
about half the reads in the in the
sequencing data and that's in all our
cells and in tumors there's or in tumor
samples there's a a mixture of both
normal cells and and and and tumor cells
normal cells are the the blood blood
vessels and fibroblasts and uh and
immune cells or infiltrate the the the
tumor so there's always a mixture of
normal cells and cancer cells in the
cancer sample that we're sequencing
which actually works to our advantage uh
because when then we we look at the
mutations that are present in cancer
cells they're going to come at an AIC
fraction or a be a little frequency that
is lower than that of the the normal
cells so we're going to use that kind of
information to uh potentially uh um
detect which which mutations come from
the tumor and which come from the normal
cells and so to illustrate this um what
what I'm depicting here is chromosome
one so so these are the genomic
coordinates of one chromosome on the the
x-axis and on the y axis are all the
mutations that we can find in the tumor
sample
so all the dots are are the mutation
with their be frequency meaning like how
how frequent is that mutation in the
sequencing data uh and that's for one of
the samples that was in the ground truth
data set so so there's match normal
which allows us to identify which of
these mutations are semetic in red
because they're not present in Blood and
which ones are a germ line in Gray
because they are present in Blood and
the the principle that I just uh uh
talked about one slide ago that tumor
mutations are going to be preferentially
at a lower BL frequency than the the
germline mutations is generally true the
the the red dots are are most of the
time lower than the the the gray dots
and that's that's information it's it's
imperfect and incomplete but it already
gives us uh information so when we uh
make a model to use that kind of
information to predict whether the the
mutations are
germine or sematic there is a a
relatively poor performance of of uh in
that exercise which is which is expected
but it's still important so
second uh there are actually really
really good databases of germline events
uh that that exist and and one is Nomad
that's also a project from the from the
broad and multiple other um centers that
cataloges all the the that that attempts
to catalog all all the the polymorphisms
in the human population for that they're
using a data set of
800,000 uh exomes and genomes and look
at the the frequency of every single um
every single
um mutation in that data set and and uh
um that allows to make this this
database of of polymorphisms together
with their frequencies and that's
extremely useful for for research so
using that we we can uh compare all the
events that we find in tumors with with
that database of of uh of Journal
mutations and and estimate based on the
frequency in the population whether
that's going to be likely a germine
event meaning present in normal cells or
a sematic event and and if if if
mutations are are frequent in in the the
population and we find it in tumor it's
likely germline uh if they are not
present in tumors sorry in the general
population or at a very low frequency
it's likely sematic so that's a second
source of information that we can use
and and that gives us better uh better
performance in predicting from tumor
alone whether we have a German or
sematic event uh but still still not
perfect and combining both uh we can
achieve better um uh uh better
performance in predicting whether we
have sematic or or or germline events uh
and it can actually get really either a
good Precision or a good recall and and
uh what this allows us to do then go
back to the entirety of a half million
exomes from tumor only and sort all the
mutations and focus precisely on on
sematic events so why is that important
it's important because then we can go
back to the question that was that was
uh identified 10 years ago of of how
many samples are needed to identify
driver mutations in a series of of
cancers depending on their mutation
frequency and now we have the numbers
and we have the sematic mutations in
those those tumors and these are numbers
from the the uh collection of of of data
that we have assembled or assembled or
are assembling at at Caris through
diagnostic testing and there's 12,000
melanomas more than 70,000 lung cancers
and were like well into the numbers of
tumors that are needed to
uh better understand those U those those
those tumor types and and uh now focus
on um identifying new cancer
drivers uh and that's work that is
happening right now so so so I don't
have the second part of this story but
at least we uh we we are able to analyze
those data of an extremely large scale
to constitute better data sets for for
R&D and Drug Discovery so next I want to
talk about the second aspect of of the
use of of machine learning or or
actually there's there's not a ton of
machine learning in that that short
section but it's really perfecting the
data set that is going to be used for
for R&D uh in this example I want to
talk about an effort from uh last month
actually where we reprocessed close to
400,000 RNA samples so like I described
at the beginning for for every single
tissue sample that that comes through
the door at U at Caris we're generating
a whole exom sequencing and a whole
transcriptome sequencing and and also a
lot of U IHC uh and H so a lot of
digital pathology images and to uh to we
needed to uh uh go back to the entire
data set for RNA to to improve certain
aspects for the for the for the purpose
of R&D and went back to Raw data and
reprocessed 400,000 samples in a matter
of a couple days and that was really a
notable effort um that was a a both
scientific and also engineering feed to
to to generate that amount of data in
such a short time and for those who are
interested in the the the stack employed
here I'm writing it here but basically
in AWS we build up an infrastructure to
to uh deal with that amount of data and
it's important to to do so and go back
to to Raw data
because in a diagnostic test there's
Evolutions every day of of how we can uh
improve improve the the the workflows
how we can generate better data and so
year after year the data change a little
bit morph a little bit and and uh when
we want to go back to all the data we
need to take steps to to harmonize and
make sure that we we don't have these
effects and and drifts in the data so
that they can be uh
analyzable and uh the the the the the
advantage of that is maybe to go back to
one of P that's point at the in the
intro what is needed for for ML is data
and the data is there it it needs to be
put in a in a shape and a form where
that is usable then for for drug
Discovery and the kinds of analyses and
and machine learning want to do with
those um so briefly uh the RNA data
generate expression data so the
expression of all the the genes in the
genome those expression data can be used
to compare various tumor types and and
there's a lot that can be done with
those that's also um uh something that
is that is starting back in the days of
tcga we were using 10,000 samples uh
across 10 to 15,000 samples across all
tumor types here there's close to
400,000 there's there's even more in the
collection uh this can be represented so
all these transcriptomes meaning gene
expression can be represented in this
this Disney plot which is typical for
folks who work with single cell data uh
with single cell data It's Not Unusual
to see a quarter million and half
million or a million cells across a few
samples here we're not talking about
cells each dot is one sample and there's
there's a close to 400,000 samples
depicted here across variety of of solid
tumor types uh very as we would expect
sample types the samples cluster by by
cancer type due to the expression
differences between uh between these uh
these samples uh
I forgot to do so earlier but there this
this work and then the previous work
that I showed on some alone is the the
work of multiple members of the team uh
NOP Laura Richards mukun Varma Christian
fresh Greg Demaris Brady Gil and and and
others in the data science
team um I'm I'm only going to to uh
barely scratch the surface of what can
be done with these kinds of expression
data here but I want to give an idea of
of why that's important for drug
Discovery and what kind of features we
can
distinguish in in those kinds of
expression data so here's colorl cancer
um there's close to 50,000 coloral
cancers in in this data set that are
that uh uh are depicted here in Brown in
this this Disney plot and uh we can
start distinguishing some features that
tell us about the biology of of those
those uh cancer samples so so everything
in brown here is called actal cancer
including this little island here and
this little island there and when we
color the data set now by where the
specimen was was U uh sampled so where
it was coming from in the body so either
the liver in the case of a liver
metastasis or the lung in the case of a
lung metastasis we can see that those
those uh this has the the site of the
the the biopsy has an influence on the
transcriptome of those Cancers and so
that's why they they belong to this
slightly different islands in the in
this Disney plot so anyway that's that's
really just the surface of of those data
as as you saw saw this uh this massive
data set was just generated last month
and so this is very new but now
constitutes the kind of data set that
can be used for R&D both for uh both
from from mutations but also transcript
home data and uh and and we we need to
dive in not just us but Al partners of
of Caris that are working on this
data so next I want to talk about the
application of machine learning to
improve treatment decisions uh that's
one where we we as I said we need to do
better with signatures we need to do
better identifying patients and
identifying their their uh the the
disease
characteristics that are going to train
guide treatment decisions and for that
I'm going to focus on on this uh aspect
of the diagnostic test that is um um
available to patients who who are uh uh
profiled at Caris where we can use the
variety of data that are generated
through the diagnostic test so the whole
exome sequencing the the transcriptome
sequencing in the IHC U through through
a model that identifies the exact tumor
type uh of of the the uh of the tumor
that was that was um profiled and that's
where work from Anthony Hemstead and and
Hass ghani in the and the in the team
so the purpose of this mainly is to
identify the primary tumor for the case
of cancers of unknown primary which are
a kind of cancer where the
doctor the doctors cannot identify which
cancer type they are dealing with and
it's very important because the the the
outcome for cancers of a non primary is
very poor about a year less than a year
because the doctors cannot determine
which drugs would be best suited for
treating that
cancer uh so they revert to sequencing
to learn more about the cancer uh which
can tell what kind of mutations exist in
those tumors but mutations alone does do
not drive treatment decisions yet it's
PR important to to under understand what
kind of disease we with so that they can
follow standard of care and for that
reason identifying or being able to
identify the the the the primary origin
of these these cancers is very important
and that's the goal of this this GPS
Test that's performing the data
generated uh very briefly it's multiple
models that are using the the whole exom
data that go down the tree here and and
classify every time which which branch
of the tree to to go through and go
through additional levels of uh of um
granularity through the the the enor Tre
uh at the end there's a prediction for
which cancer type out of 90 cancer types
can be uh uh is is predicted to
be uh that the cancer of origin has been
trained on uh about half of the
available data at Caris and then tested
on on more cancers of unknown primary
and uh and and and with known primary
origin and validate on prospective cases
and and that's the aspect of validation
just as a brief aside validation of
diagnostic testing is an extremely
complicated task where the the bar is
extremely high to to submit those kinds
of U of uh of of of tests and
performances to to the FDA so that
there's really the certainty that the
results can be actionable by the by the
doctors and the the by by by by
physicians so every time we're talking
about these kinds of prediction
and machine learning or not uh from from
uh diagnostic data we also have to
understand that there's there's a very
very high burden of proof of can that be
applied to to a patient would would I
use that test and Trust the result for
for for for my
patient
uh to close the the the loop a little
bit and uh this test test has been
applied to the tcga data that I talked
about earlier so like I said there there
was a this here only 8,000 of the the 10
to 15,000 tumors in tcga but uh we could
validate it with a very high performance
on this those dcga data which of course
have known uh tumors of origin but with
with masking the the the tumor of origin
and applying GPS onto this data we could
we could repr predict what the the tumor
types were and that was a very good
validation of the the performance of
that test and robustness to the source
of of the data which is really
important uh it's very robust to to the
SES of metastasis as we discussed the
transcripton data is going to be
slightly different whether we have a
primary tumor or a metastasis depending
on which organ so those are aspects that
are going to be really important when uh
when when applying this this test so
that we're we're making false false
calls but it's robust to that so with
that I want to give a a brief patient
highlight because this was really
notable and and we actually have many
many many examples of how that kind of
of test applied to cancers of unknown
primary is really helping treating uh uh
patients so in this instance I'm talking
about a a male specimen submitted as a
renal cell carcinoma so like cancer in
the kidney arising in a transplanted
kidney
and so first uh first uh thought is
probably kidney cancer but GPS favored
the gynecological origin with 99%
probability and and uh histology of
serus carcinoma which of course is a
female cancer but uh uh so that raised
questions from from the beginning when
comparing the snip profile of the tumor
and that of the benign kidney around the
tumor uh it showed that there was a
negligible chromosome y copy number
which raised additional questions but
also that the the tumor matched the
transplanted transplanted kidney and in
fact uh of course you guessed but this
this was not Rosell carcinoma this was a
a um uh ovarian cancer that was already
present in the transplanted kidney at
the time of the the transplant and the
oncologist was was uh updated and
oncologist was was made aware and they
updated the therapy accordingly and and
that led to much better treatment for
that person which otherwise would have
been treated for for kidney cancer and
probably would have not received the
right treatment that's the kind of
treatment decisions that can be informed
by the use ML on this this diagnostic
data so next I want to talk about the
use of ml for predicting biomarkers and
and patient
outcomes um
and that's where we're going to go in a
slightly different direction here with
using the digital pathology data at at
Caris so there's two kinds of pathology
data that we're generating for every
single case that comes through the door
one is h& so hemox and eosin and the
other one is uh IHC so
imunohistochemistry where we're staining
the slides for a particular protein that
uh binds an
antibody this is used to confirm
diagnosis so uh the the the Pathologists
are are looking at these slides and
identifying the the shape of the cells
and the histology to confirm that we're
deal in in fact dealing with the the
cancer type that we that we thought it's
also used to determine the percentum or
nuclei so the the purity of the sample
and and where the tumor areas in the
slide are because we're micro dissecting
every single uh sample that need needs
to before
sequencing what that means is when when
when sequencing samples they first the
the block the ffp block so the paraffin
embedded block of the tissue is scut in
thin slides those are put on a
microscopic slide a pathologist is
looking at the tumor identifying where
most of the the tumor cells are and then
micro dissecting that area to go to the
the sequencing essay and what what this
U the consequence of that is that it
creates much better data for Diagnostic
because we're not sequencing a bunch of
normal cells we're focusing the
sequencing on the tumor cells when
needed if the tumor is already pure it
just goes straight to to sequencing so
that's great for Diagnostic but it's
also great because these images are all
digitized and there's a ton of
information in them that we can use
machine learning to to to leverage very
briefly uh as I said all the images are
digitized and so so that's use of robots
that are picking the slides putting them
in the scanner that's all uploaded to to
cloud and various uh various tools that
allow the Pathologists to to look at
them uh there's automated scanning and
everything so so so that's there's
really a massive scale here as you
remember there's more than 15 between 15
and 20,000 tumors per month that are
going through the labs all this data go
to uh uh uh the the the our cloud
storage and and can then be used for
various efforts uh of course at the
beginning we go we need to go from a a
scanned image that contains some labels
some pen marks some some that has
various sizes and and and and shapes and
and everything and detect all the the
areas that we would want to focus on in
a in a computational fashion so where's
the foreground which areas are in Focus
or out of focus are there artifacts are
there labels we need to to remove and
and finally uh dealing with the the the
the images that's going to be
interesting for our data There is close
to 4 million images uh both from uh h&
and IHC that represent 350,000 cases and
and we're digitizing everything that
comes through the door today but there's
millions and millions of images that are
uh that have not been images in years
that have not been digitized in years
prior that are also being digitized so
this is a growing a set a massive scale
already so like I said there's a ton of
information in these
images uh here two examples of breast
cancer one uh with the cdh1
mutation uh and the other one with a
fusion Gene so so a translocation that
leads to the overe expression of this
this uh Gene and track and they look
massively different and that's that's
obvious to the to the eye that's obvious
to a pathologist but in some instances
is the differences are not obvious to
anyone and and neither the untrained or
the trained eye and that's where we want
to use computer vision to help us make
those distinctions uh we can employ a
bunch of models I'm going to give two
examples all for the purpose of uh
modeling modeling tumor types or drug
response or or various aspects of tumor
biology so first use case uh let's say
we we have a a clinical iCal trial
against U for kise inhibitor Ross one
against Ross one and you want to
identify a 100 patients that have a
fusion in this Ross one gene the problem
here is that the prevalence of that
Fusion is about 1% of lung cancer and if
we want to recruit those patients uh and
identify uh those that Harbor that that
Fusion we need to sequence the genomes
uh of 100 patients to find one and so if
we want to identify 100 patients we need
to sequence 10,000 and that has a St
staggering cost um if it's several th000
uh dollars to sequence one sample you
can imagine the cost of sequencing a 100
so how can we use uh ml
to uh train a model that
enriches the the the cohort so that we
don't have to sequence so many so that's
what we did uh we we um briefly used a
CNN to train a model on a lot of our
data uh to identify these Ross One cases
and here you can see that the enrichment
that we're able to to achieve so so uh
then running it on unseen cases if we
instead of naively sequencing 10,000 if
we run the model on on
25,000 h& slides we can identify a short
list of a thousand cases to sequence
already a decrease in 10,000 uh a
tenfold decrease in the in the cost of
the the sequencing and further if we run
it on 30,000 h& cases we only see need
to sequence 300 cases to find 100 that
would be enrolled in the in the trial
and so it's that kind of of uh machine
learning that can help drug Discovery
because it's going to help the clinical
trials for a particular drug and uh and
definitely benefit the the the patients
that's work by Tommy Boucher mukun
varman Ming Chang and others in the in
the
team uh briefly because I think I'm
close on
time okay a couple more minutes the the
um some learnings we need to account for
the various sizes of the the the data
and its hogin there's class imbalance so
we need to account for that when we're
training the data like Ross one fusions
were 1% of 1% prevalence so it's really
hard to train data at 1% prevalence we
need to to take that into account uh and
and then make sure we're not overfitting
and uh then um uh we're dealing with
data that have multiple resolutions so
so like a microscope we can either uh
look like a large field of view or or
very narrow and we can actually employ
multiple magnifications at the same time
to train better models to see the
overall structure or really the the
cellular structure the next the next uh
example which I will it's it's several
slides but I'm going to to abstract uh
abstract from it so we we wanted to
provide a an alter we're working on
providing an alternative to the the test
I talked at the beginning on type DX
which is an rtpcr test based on roughly
20 genes gene expression uh that's
that's uh that's cost due to generate
and and uh given all the data that exist
today we can probably do better and to
decrease the cost one aspect of doing
better is to start from uh h& slides so
digital pathology slides instead of
expression data for that we're using
data from a clinical trial where uh
simply put there was um a breast cancer
diagnosis Then followed by five years of
treatment with a of treatment with
endocrine therapy and at the end of the
5 years some patients were put on a
placebo and some other patients were put
on additional endocrine therapy for five
more years and then there's a readout
for the the the for for for 10 years so
really we're looking at 15 years from
diagnostic to the end of the the the
followup and we're going to use data
from day Zero so at the time of
diagnosis to predict whether there's
going to be recurrence 10 to 15 years
down the line and whether those patients
would benefit or not from additional
treatment with the endocrine
therapy uh computer vision model we're
extracting features from from the slide
cut into two tiles uh like so so number
of features using a Transformer
predicting a score whether there's high
risk of recurrence or low risk of
recurrence and it works so like between
the predicted low risk and high risk we
can see that there's a a large
difference in this the survival curve uh
when looking at at all patients so I'm
not even focusing on whether they used
additional endocrine therapy or no
that's done from the images only so no
other information or incorporating some
of the clinical data into the model such
as type of the tumor whether they
received surgery and other things like
this now where this becomes interesting
is where where we look at where we bend
the data uh whether the the sample the
the patients received additional
endocrine therapy uh or received Placebo
and in the low risk group very very low
risk of recurrence in the high risk
group we see a difference between
between those two groups but what this
tells us is that these patients here
probably don't need to be treated it
doesn't provide an advantage and that's
a very very important information to not
overtreat patients this can be compared
to the the results of uh the these other
T tests so so another test that that
does the same is the breast cancer index
um where where achieving very good if
not better performance and that's really
the basis of proposing better diagnostic
cheaper diagnostic with modern
techniques and that are going to help
patients so with that I would like to
thank you all for your attention and
take any
[Applause]
questions we are a little overtime but I
would be happy to take at Le one
question for Nicholas
if no question from the audience I have
one question for un nio
um as as you have been working in this
field of data science and in cancer you
you talked about rnac data pathology
data what would be one data type that
you wish we had more and need to produce
more which will help developing machine
learning proteomics large scale
proteomics that's very very important uh
right to today it's really hard to
generate large scale data for the
expression of a variety of of proteins
there are techniques that exist based on
on antibodies that can Multiplex the
detection of say 5,000 proteins it's
very costly it's not high throughput but
there's so much more that we can learn
from promic uh than than we do today and
especially large scale promic and that
goes beyond cancer so with cancer most
of the aberration are are based in DNA
cancer is the disease of the DNA uh
there so we can detect mutations and and
other kinds of events that occur in in
DNA mutations epigenetic modifications
Etc all of that occurs in DNA we can see
that with sequencing uh both DNA
sequencing and RNA sequencing but we
don't have a ton of information on
proteins and in cancer this is going to
help but it's also going to help in
other
diseases great please go ahead I really
liked your question actually but my
question was in the case um cases where
the GPS AI model is not correct what are
the things that are driving the
misclassifications oh that's that's
that's that's hard uh what's driving the
M classifications is so sometimes the
the the quality of the data so when
we're dealing with extremely small
tumors uh there's there's so much so
little material that it's that it's hard
to to generate sufficient sequencing
data to to generate
uh the the proper calls so so some of
those misclassifications we actually
know from the beginning that sadly
there's there's there's not enough
there's also some um uh some some of the
misclassifications in the cases where we
have mixtures of multiple cell types due
to the location of the tumor so I showed
some of the confusion that could exist
for for primary samples that are that
that have metastasized to another organ
that can generate some some confusion so
that could be that could be some of the
the misclassification a thank you all
right so we'll take a short break now
but do come back at 11: for our next
talk
[Applause]