[Music]
I'm Cara Miller. And I'm Rob Stoner. And
from the MIT Energy Initiative, this is
What If It Works, a podcast looking at
the energy solutions for climate
[Music]
change. Today, we're going to examine an
energy source with huge potential to
shape the future, but one that's not
without some complications. Hydrogen.
And let's start with a little story
about hydrogen and how its power can
kind of creep up on you. The story takes
place in the late 1980s in Mali in West
Africa. Okay, so the Molly story is
really an interesting one. This well
that was being done to find water and
they got down to about 100 meters. They
didn't find water, but they noticed that
there was wind blowing out of the well.
That's Brad Hager, a professor of Earth,
atmospheric, and planetary sciences at
MIT. He's also the associate director of
the Earth Resources Lab. So, as usual,
they uh sat down for a break to ponder
the situation. The crew member lit up a
cigarette and kaboom uh this big blue
flame shoots out. He was burned.
Fortunately, he he recovered and it
continued to burn in this bright blue
flame for several weeks. So, they had to
figure out how to cap the well. And, you
know, capping wells is is a little bit
tricky. And especially in Mali, they
didn't have the expertise to do it, but
it burned for several weeks and finally
they capped it. So what was the
importance of this big blue flame? Well,
no one explored it for a while. Hager
says the well just sat there for 15
years. And a local entrepreneur decided
that he would invest in a lot of parts
of the Molly economy. And he he invested
in a Loudcat oil and gas company. And so
they decided they'd find out what was in
the well. They took a sample and they
found out it was 98% pure hydrogen. Now,
this was a pretty amazing find, but
Hager says there just wasn't the
infrastructure to transport the
hydrogen. The only thing they could
figure out to do with it was to run it a
generator. So, they got an old Ford uh
motor and hooked it up to a generator.
They now produce electricity uh for the
local village because they can't go
anywhere. You know, this is very
exciting. The equivalent amount of
energy that's produced in this well is
uh about three barrels of oil equivalent
each day, which is about 120 gallons of
of gasoline. So, you can think 120
gallons a day, you can run a pretty big
generator for a village, but but that's
about all you can do. Plus, Molly is
politically unstable. There have been
three coups since 2012 when they did
this. So, no big company's going to go
in there and try to produce this. But
the find points to hydrogen is a clean
energy source of the future. So let's
say we could get a lot more hydrogen out
of the ground. How would that change
things? It would be huge. So right now
we are producing about 100 million tons
of hydrogen annually to use primarily
for fertilizer manufacture. So you want
to make ammonium, you want to feed the
world, you use fertilizer made
substantially out of hydrogen. But going
into the future, using hydrogen to make
steel, for example, instead of using
coke would take away a tremendous amount
of the CO2. But here's the catch. You
don't find such concentrated sources of
hydrogen in very many places. So we do
now understand why it's there in Molly.
And it's a very special circumstance.
There is a uh a trap very much like the
traps that hold natural gas
accumulations. And in this case, the the
trap is made out of a layer of
solidified magma. Underneath that magma,
there is a layer of limestone that has a
lot of pore space in it. And then deep
in the earth, maybe one or two
kilometers below that, there are some
very old rocks over a billion years old,
that are full of iron. And there is a
small amount of water that percolates
through this ironrich rock. And there's
a chemical reaction that goes on that
converts some of the minerals in this
rock to a kind of rock called
serpentanite which is the same as
asbestous. In doing that it takes the
water and strips off the oxygen and uses
that to essentially rust the iron that's
in the rock and leaves behind the
hydrogen. So over some period of time,
we don't know how long, that hydrogen
has been moving up towards the surface
and accumulating in this reservoir below
this cap rock. Brad, there's a lot of
iron down there in the Earth's crust and
a lot of water that circulates beneath
it as well. Uh that would imply that if
this reaction is going on between those
two things, there's an awful lot of
hydrogen potentially available to us.
Yeah, that uh that sounds great. But uh
so first of all uh the iron rich rocks
that sounds great but okay now the other
shoes going to drop go right ahead. Okay
so first of all the iron rich rocks uh
are not that common in the earth's
crust. Most of it we think about you
know silica and and other rocks but in
the crust there's not much iron.
Underneath Molly there is a formation
which is over a billion years old called
a greenstone belt. It's a place where
two continents smashed together and and
left the kind of a scar that's full of
iron rich rocks. The place where there
really a lot of iron rich rocks that are
coming up near the earth's surface are
at the extending plate boundaries at at
mid ocean ridges. In terms of water, we
have a lot of water at the surface, but
at great depth, although there's often
water, it's not often circulating very
much. And so, in order to run this
reaction, we need a continuous supply of
water. So, what's special about Molly is
that they're right at the same place uh
where there's this greenstone belt.
There are also some old fractures that
apparently are open a little bit and
there's water circulating through it.
So, there's a local source uh in Molly,
but we don't know how much is being
produced there. Uh all we know is that
it's at least some of it is being
trapped by this cap rock. So, let me
compare this to oil, which you know
people kind of have a sense of. I didn't
you say it's like three barrels of oil a
day coming up, right? So, if hydrogen is
an excellent energy source is like sort
of one of the things that's going to
happen or maybe already happened that
people are going to look around just
sort of they like they realize that
there was stuff in Texas but there's
also oil in the Dakotas but there's also
oil in the Peran basin. Are they going
to look around and be like so where's
the hydrogen like you know can we go to
Kansas and find it? So that's the
process that's just beginning and it's
very much like oil was in the 1800s.
People are beginning to look around and
there's a lot of effort in doing this.
The United States Geological Survey has
a big program to try to identify
hydrogen systems that are comparable to
petroleum systems. So what you need is
you need some source rock. In this case
it's uh water percolating through iron
rich rocks. You need some cap rock. In
Mali it's basalt most places it's shale
and you need a reservoir rock where the
hydrogen will accumulate. So right now
what people are doing is focusing on
where these potential source rocks might
be. So for example in the United States
there's an old continental rift scar
extending from Nebraska, Kansas, Iowa,
Minnesota, Michigan. There's a structure
called the mid-continental rift and
people right now are targeting that to
see if they can find hydrogen there. So,
are you saying like that in, you know,
like the upper
Midwest, we're looking potentially at
the kind
of I guess not gold rush exactly, but I
mean there there have been times where
people got really excited about
different sorts of energy all around the
country and obviously the world. Is is
that going to happen? And people are
going to like go there and be like, we
can get hydrogen out of the ground. It's
it's clean. It's a great source of
energy. See if we can make a bunch of
money here. That's exactly what people
are doing and uh both because they want
to make a lot of money and because they
want to save the world. So there is a
huge amount of interest right now in the
venture capital community. There's a guy
named Bill Gates who you might have
heard of who has dumped a substantial
amount of money in in into a startup
company called Breakthrough Energy which
is uh going big into into hydrogen. And
just to quote Gates, uh, it could be
gigantic or it could be a bust. But if
it's really there, wow. Well, also we're
hearing like people are estimating the
cost if they're going to produce it like
they produce natural gas by drilling
into a deposit and sort of extracting
it. And I'm hearing numbers like less
than a dollar a kilogram. Yeah, that's
right. So people are anticipating even
50 cents a kilogram uh for these
pre-existing hydrogen uh deposits. And I
think that's an order of magnitude less
than than what it costs to produce it by
hydrarolysis. So that's wild though. I
mean it's what a situation. Here we are
trying to make hydrogen through all
these complicated energy intensive means
and it might be beneath our feet at a
cost we'll probably never achieve or may
may never achieve with these other
techniques. That's right. It's uh it
might be really cheap and would be a big
help in the uh energy transition. So
there are a lot of as I said venture
capital companies going after this.
There are some startups. There's one
right up the street here in Somerville,
a startup called Eden Geopower. Uh it
was founded by two graduates of our
department. But the notable thing is
that there are no major hydrocarbon
companies investing in this. They are
all sitting on the sidelines with a wait
andsee attitude. And what they're
worried about is that yes, there'll be
some anecdotal fines, but there won't be
enough there to justify the costs of the
infrastructure to produce it. and to
really make a big impact. So, they're
playing wait and see. That's very
interesting that that you've got the big
I mean obviously like Bill Gates is
plenty rich enough to figure to saying
like as you say like it could be big or
it could be nothing but whatever he's
got the money to bet on it but big
companies would also have money to bet
but it sounds like no they don't they
have not only money but they have data
and and considerable knowledge about
what's underground what's down there I
mean these companies have been drilling
holes some of them for hundred years or
more and gathering all kinds of seismic
data doesn't that give them a big
advantage spread. Well, one would think
with all these holes they're drilling in
the ground, but uh the issue is they're
drilling those holes to find oil and gas
and they're finding very little hydrogen
in the holes that they've analyzed. So,
that points to a problem and that is
that it is difficult to accumulate
hydrogen in the earth for two reasons.
One, you alluded to it being a very
small and slippery element. So, it tends
to escape. But the other thing is that
microbes, I'll call them bugs for my
geohysical terminology, bugs love to eat
methane. So the big methane seeps on the
earth are at mid ocean ridges where the
plates are spreading apart and they're
bringing hot rock up to the surface.
Those rocks are fractured. Sea water is
circulating through them and there is a
lot of hydrogen being produced. And if
there any any of these microbes around,
they will eat it pretty fast.
Do people in I mean I think it's like
Michigan and Minnesota and Iowa under
Lake Superior where some of this stuff
is. Do people know that this gold like
that they are you know like Texas part
two. Do they know this is happening?
Something good's going to happen in
Michigan. Well, it was realized in 2012
that we could get hydrogen from the
ground. in 2018 about these venture
capital companies began to be put
together and they began running around
scooping up leases in places like Iowa
and Kansas. Anyway, around 2 years ago
there was a great outpouring of
publicity in um journals like Science
and Nature talking about the potentials
of hydrogen. So, it's being picked up
broadly in the press now and everybody's
excited about it. So there's a gold rush
going on kind of getting going of a gold
rush and and it's not just in the United
States. I mean I'm hearing about big
discoveries in Eastern Europe, Africa
for sure, maybe South America,
Australia. Yep. It's all over the place.
Is that what's going to happen? We're
going to find this stuff and start
producing it like natural gas. Well, I
think that we will find some of it.
Australia is is pretty far ahead and you
know, new finds keep coming up. Albania,
the Pyrenees of of Spain. I mean, there
there are a lot of these places. As you
mentioned, Bill Gates has a lot of
money. He can bet on this. I don't have
enough money to bet, but I can bet my
time. Uh, would you say you have so
little money that you have to bet? I I
have
so Yes. Uh, I I I I desperately want to
make a contribution to saving the
climate. Earth scientists have this
saying, we have multiple working
hypotheses. And my working hypothesis is
that in the very near future we are
going to run out of the hydrogen that is
naturally accumulated analogous to
natural gas accumulations because even
if there's a high generation rate it's
it's leaking out all much faster than
natural gas would bugs are eating it.
Bugs are eating it and groundwater flow
in continental interiors is is pretty
slow. So I don't think we're going to be
able to keep up using this analog of the
you know kind of conventional natural
gas system. So I think what we what
would be the real breakthrough and I
think it's the breakthrough that we
should you know bet on here at MIT is
answering the question can we actively
produce hydrogen in the same way that
it's being actively produced at these
mid ocean ridge systems where water is
circulating through hot ironrich rocks
and reacting in real time and at high
rates with uh you know the water and the
rocks are reacting hydrogen is being
generated and and it's coming up to the
surface rapidly enough that there's more
of it than the bugs can eat and that it
could be produced. So, it's being
produced in kind of real time. This is
not like old deposits, right? Kind of
like there's deep water drilling like
you're down there in the water capturing
it in real time. Yes. As it's being
produced kind of. Yeah. So, not
capturing it from the water but actually
going down into the rocks themselves and
capturing it. Okay. This process
actually is going on right now in
Iceland. So in Iceland is on a plate
boundary where the European and the
North American plates are pulling apart.
Hot rocks are coming up to the surface.
That's why we have these volcanic
eruptions and the rocks are all cracked
up from the tectonics of stretching the
crust. There's water circulating through
there. Icelanders are using this hot
water to produce geothermal heat.
They've also been looking at the water
and realize there's a fair amount of
hydrogen in it and they are actually
extracting the hydrogen which is being
actively produced uh at the mid-Atlantic
ridge. So you mean you're you're going
to pipe away the water so to speak or so
so the water comes up they separate out
the hydrogen and then they like soda pop
like like it's like soda pop. They just
you know it it's it's also got some
carbon dioxide in it but they separate
it out separate out the hydrogen and
then there it is. It's it's collected.
So, if you got hydrogen in Iceland, what
are you going to do with it? Well, they
have a very clever solution. Iceland is
where a huge amount of oxide is smelted
into aluminum because they have cheap
electricity there. And what they've
discovered is that they can let the
hydrogen be absorbed in the aluminum
ingots. And if you heat the ingots, the
hydrogen comes out. So, they have a
perfect serendipity where they've got
heat, hydrogen, aluminum, and a
transportation mode. So, it all works
together. like many other things works
for Iceland might not work elsewhere but
so so moving it around is a problem
though I mean if if you gather it up I
was saying earlier you mean it doesn't
it's not a liquid at room temperature or
anywhere close to it you you have to
compress it enormously in order to get
enough energy into a volume that's
transportable can we move it around or
does that that create a huge problem uh
as you know it's it's expensive to move
around it is being moved around right
now primarily in the form of fertilizer
ammonia ammonia Yeah, the optimal thing
would be to uh produce fertilizer
locally. So you you pull it out of the
ground and then you think what did we
want to use this thing for? Let's have a
plant right here that makes fertilizer
so that we don't like lose half of it in
transport or this or that. It's just
another thing that works great in
Iceland too because they could generate
electricity from geothermal and use, you
know, the hobbos process to to convert
it into ammonia and ship ammonia instead
of aluminum or maybe along with you.
They could do that. Yeah. You know,
Brad, I as you know, I think a lot about
developing countries, countries that are
economically poor, but in many cases
also, and perhaps this is why they're
economically poor, also resource poor.
The possibility that they have
these hydrogen producing rocks right on
their doorsteps, right beneath them, is
is exciting to me. What about places,
for example, in Southeast Asia and and
in Africa? Is is what's the resource
opportunity there? Yeah, that um that's
great. And it's something I've I've
thought a lot about. So let's start with
Southeast Asia. India has a very large
deposit of flood bassults when the
dinosaurs were killed 65 million years
ago. At the same time, there was a huge
volcanic eruption going on over the
continent of India. And many people
thought that that's what killed the
dinosaurs. Anyway, so there's all this
65 million year old ironrich solidified
lava overlying a large portion of India
called the Dean traps and that is full
of iron. Uh this is basalt. It's basalt.
Yeah. And it's uh a lot of it is right
next to the ocean. So there's a a ready
source of water nearby. So that's you
know potential that you know I would
imagine could be lowhanging fruit for
the Indians. And then also in India when
India smacked against Asia to form the
Tibetan plateau and the Himalayan
mountains it trapped some very ironrich
rocks in between India and Tibet. So
that's another potential source of very
iron rich rocks that the Indians might
be able to tap. What about the rest of
Africa? I mean ancient
rockratons I think they're called. Yeah.
Yeah. So Molly is is in one of these
ancient cratons where these uh ironrich
rocks are called greenstone belts from
you know some of the fossil plate
boundaries back billions of years ago.
And also in East Africa you have the
East African rift where you know the
crust is pulling apart bringing iron
rich rocks you know closer to the
surface. There are volcanoes erupting
there. So that would be another
potential uh you know area where you
might find hydrogen.
[Music]
Let me just go back to the Midwest for a
second. It sounds like you feel like the
venture capitalists maybe they won't
make the kind of money they think
they're going to make or is that wrong?
I don't know if they'll make the kind of
money that they think that they will
make. There may well be return on
investment for the first wave of venture
capitalists. Okay. But whether this is
something which is going to sustain us
till 2080 for example, right? Will they
quickly run through? Will they run
through and and you know they'll make a
killing on their initial investment but
is it sustainable? Is it scalable? And
then another question is when you talk
about this the thing I think of is like
fracking. Um not very far from the kinds
of places that you're talking about. A
lot of people who live around fracking
sites would tell you it's not so great
and there have been a lot of problems.
So are a whole new set of people about
to come in for the same kinds of
problems that the people near the
fracking sites have? Right. So that's a
very good question and I think that's
one of the potential obstacles for
actively producing hydrogen. I I I want
to be clear. It's not going to be a
problem in Kansas where they're just
drilling in the same way that we would
for natural gas. But if you move to say
Southern California, there's a a a
spreading plate boundary that comes
right up into the salt and trough area
of of Southern California. There's
geothermal produce there. In many ways,
it's an analog to Iceland. It could well
be a place where we would produce
hydrogen and use it to make fertilizer,
etc. You know, I think you're you're
going to run into people who are very
worried about some of the same problems
that uh that fracking produces because
in order to reach these hot rocks, most
places you're going to have to uh drill
down and fracture the rocks to establish
permeability. Are you worried? and and
what do you think could happen um to
like ordinary people? Right. So there
are a lot of issues uh with fracking.
One of the main issues of fracking is
that a large amount of water has to be
injected into the ground and then once
the pumping starts the fractures close
and the water comes out uh the surface
this dirty water has to be disposed of
and that that's a problem. Okay. uh
stimulation of hydrogen uh that is not
likely to be an issue uh because
actually what happens is quite a bit of
water is absorbed by the rocks in the
process of getting of of forming the
hydrogen and so you put the water down
and it does not come back out. So that's
one advantage that it's got over uh
fracking for natural gas. You're going
to have to have an infrastructure to do
that. that infrastructure you can be
messy and there will be environmental
effects associated with it. Uh probably
the major environmental effect is that
when you inject water into rock and
change the composition of the rock, the
rock that's down there expands by a
substantial fraction. It expands by
about 30%. So, if you're have a a zone
of rock that you're producing at a depth
of a kilometer, it's going to cause
uplift at the surface. If you're tilting
the uh aqueduct and irrigation ditches
in Southern California, people are not
going to appreciate that. So, you're
going to have to be very careful to do
this in areas where you're not affecting
uh infrastructure. What about water
consumption itself? I mean if we're
producing something like well let's see
today's total consumption of hydrogen is
something like a 100 megat tons globally
right if we really go big time and find
other applications for it maybe we have
a gigaton right of hydrogen well okay so
you think about H2O O has a mass of 16
hydrogen's got two so that's eight times
as much mass of water so 8 gigatons of
water that's a lot of water or how is
that not a problem if we're producing in
the interior of a continent for example
Yeah. So, so the uh the problem is
actually worse than that. Uh because
your your uh your rock to hydrogen ratio
is not 1 one, but it's more like 70 to1.
So, you have to react an awful lot of
rock and an awful lot of water to
produce some some hydrogen. So, this is
being like injected. So, you're
injecting huge amounts of water. So, it
sounds like an awful lot of water in an
area, you know, like like Superior Lake
Michigan where you have all these rivers
flowing into it. It would not be a
problem. It would be a problem in
Nevada, for example. you know, if that
if that were were there. So, so so a ton
of water is just a cubic meter. So,
we're talking about 80 billion cubic
meters of water a year, which is a 80
billion sounds like a lot, too. But when
you figure out how, you know, how
fraction of Lake Ontario, it's it's it's
not that much water. But one great thing
about this is it does not require
particularly clean water. So, you don't
have to use potable water to do it. You
could use water from the sea. You could
use water from saline aquafers. So you
can use cruddy water to do it. So at
what point are we going to be drawing a
lot of hydrogen off out of the ground
and it's really going to be changing the
game in terms of like our energy
consumption? Yeah, you used the word
will a second ago. That's intriguing.
Well, maybe I should have used wood, but
uh um yeah, so I'm I'm I'm optimistic
about this. So right now there are
people who were trying to do this kind
of stimulation in Oman. Okay, so Oman is
a country in the Middle East. It's right
at the uh the mouth of the Persian Gulf
where all the oil tankers have to go in
and out. And they have a very special
geology there. Uh it was an old plate
boundary where some iron rich rocks got
thrust up to the surface of the earth
and they're actually exposed. And you
can go and look at the outcrops and you
can see this transformation of iron rich
rocks into serpentite. And you can see
that happening, you know, in the in the
outcrop. And there are actually projects
which are beginning right now. If those
work out, I think that one could begin
producing hydrogen in a place like Oman
within the next, you know, certainly
within the next decade. And once a lot
of hydrogen starts coming out, are
people going to immediately know what to
do with it? are they then gonna have
that secondary problem of thinking,
well, we don't really have a fertilizer
plant right next door and we don't
really know how to transport this. So,
yeah. So, that's that's already a
problem that that that's being worked on
in the Mid East. They realize the future
of natural gas you know with the carbon
footprint may be limited and they're
already you know investing in things
like you know fertilizer plants
exporting hydrogen from the mid east to
Japan for example using using
fertilizers so people are aware very
much aware of that and these companies
are carrying out reasonable
technoeconomic analyses to see how to do
this so yeah they're not going into this
blind so it sounds like in terms of
years We're looking at very soon. It's
wild, right? I mean, like in five years,
we could see a significant amount of
hydrogen being produced. That that's my
hope. You know, once it happens, I think
people will jump on and and you'll get
the investments and the technology that
you need to really then scale this up to
the to the size that we need. You you
mentioned that Breakthrough Energy is
investing in some of these companies and
there the Bill Gates company. Yeah.
Well, Bill Gates and others who are
putting money into Yeah. And also
philanthropists are going the Grand
Foundation has invested in this local
company up in uh in Somerville. Exactly.
Look, breaking rocks. Yeah. In Oman. In
Oman. Breaking rocks in Oman. Yeah. So,
this is kind of crazy that we've got
these philanthropic organizations doing
all of the exploration work and Exxon
and Chevron are sitting on the sidelines
twiddling their thumbs. I mean, what do
we have to do to get them off the
sidelines? When does that change? How
sure a bet does it have to be you're
willing to invest your meager savings?
Yeah. So, um I think the uh the oil
companies uh although they don't want to
redirect their research labs to do this,
I I I'm more optimistic than you are
perhaps because I less know less about
it than you do
as in your role in the energy
initiative, but I think the oil
companies should be investing in the
small projects it will take to actually
demonstrate the feasibility of this. So,
you don't feel like there's some sort of
herculean demonstration that has to be
made for them to begin to believe it's
inertia. I mean, this has only been out,
you know, for a few years. You know,
it's one thing to have these venture
capitalists running around, but if you
get, you know, the the gravitas of a
place like MIT saying, "We've got this
group of a dozen faculty. They really
think this is great." And I suppose
that's the other thing is that this is a
very multidisciplinary problem, right?
You've got to have geologists who know
where the rocks are. You have people
understand mechanics, understand rock
fracture, how to transport hydrogen
through the brines up to the surface
that how to stimulate the reactions on
the surfaces that are broken. So it's my
hope uh is that you know by seeing a
place like MIT invested in this and you
know these serious scientists uh who
have many problems they could work on
saying hey this is this is the one let's
do it.
Oil and gas companies are riskaverse in
many ways. They're making large capital
investments. They want them to pay off,
but they're also very sensitive to
public's reaction to what they're doing.
We were talking about environmental
concerns a minute ago. If we're going to
really be producing hydrogen beneath the
surface by pumping water down there and
fracturing rocks and so on, what sorts
of risks do do they need to be mindful
of? What what bad stuff could happen?
Yeah, I think that that that's a good
point and that's something uh you know
that we really need to take headon uh
before we run into a situation like it
happened with the fracking methane and
so forth. So just starting in uh in an
analogy with that. So hydrogen there
will be a certain amount of leakage of
hydrogen into the atmosphere. Okay? I
mean that's just unavoidable when you're
when you're handling this gas. We've
seen the problems that that happen with
the methane emissions associated with
natural gas. So people are right now
looking at the implications of
additional hydrogen in the atmosphere
and what that will do as a greenhouse
gas. What will it do? Nobody talks about
I mean I don't hear people talk about
hydrogen as a greenhouse gas. I don't
think it's a new thing. But first of all
I'll say we have hydrogen leaking out
all the time right so it's already
there. So the question is you know how
much are we going to be leaking compared
to the natural flux? But hydrogen by
itself is not a greenhouse gas. But
there are indirect effects and I think
you know probably one significant effect
which is easy to understand when we emit
methane into the atmosphere it decays
with a half-life of about 10 years and
that's because it's reacting with uh you
know oxygen containing radicals in the
atmosphere. And so if you put hydrogen
there it's going to compete with methane
and so the methane will last longer in
the atmosphere. It won't decay as fast.
It won't decay as fast. So, another
problem I mentioned previously was just
this surface deformation. It's something
that happens slowly, gently. You want to
make sure your pipes are not altered by
it, but it's it's it's not a showstopper
in in my opinion, as long as you avoid
critical infrastructure. Your pipes,
what it's a what's a pipe in and you
mean in your house? Well, in in let's
say uh if if you chilled with Boston, it
would change greatly the flow of sewers
into the sewage treatment plant. So,
that would be a bad idea. Yes. Well, and
I mean you see in California these like
amazing pictures of how the ground is
shifted because the aquifers have been
so depleted that people may have a field
of rice that's 7 ft lower than it was
when their grandfather had that field. I
mean like really shockingly different
and you can see it in, you know, sticks
that stick out of the ground or
comparisons of pictures from now and and
70 years ago or something. Yeah, there's
an amazing picture that the United
States Geological Survey puts out for
the the Great Valley of California where
there's a telephone pole and they have
ground level marked on the telephone
pole and it's down like 80 feet from
where it's a whole telephone pole from
where it is right now. So, uh that's
just from Pump Hill aquifers. That's
pumping the aquifers. Yeah. But but now
we're going to be going the other
direction. Now we can jack them up. But
you have to do it in the same places. We
can jack up Boston and Harvard so we
don't have to worry about MIT being
flooded by by Oh my gosh, we've solved
so many problems. solve a lot of
problems by selective uplift around the
edges of of continent. Brooklyn, we
could make Brooklyn a little higher. We
could sell Yeah. I mean, are we going to
really be producing enough uplift to to
be noticeable if we do this? Oh,
absolutely. Yeah. Because the amount of
rock that's consumed, you know, as I as
I said, you know, you consume like 70
times as much rock as you produce
hydrogen. And so, yes, you're you're
creating a lot of uplift. Probably we
won't be doing this in like Brooklyn and
Shanghai and stuff, but it seems like a
good place to do it. Yeah. But under the
great valley is, you know, is plausible.
There are iron rich rocks under the
great valley. So, so what reassuring
words can you give us to prevent the
legislators of the United States from
immediately going out and banning
hydrogen production? You know, I think
the most fertile place for largecale
long-term hydrogen production is is just
on the offshore. So, when North America
and Europe Europe split apart, the crust
got very thin, not very far offshore
here. And so we could do this under the
water. We know how to do subsurface
under oceans. So that's probably where
we're we're really the big hydrogen
production. So nearshore meaning we
still have to build pipelines, but
they're not long intercontinental sorts
of things. So we're just getting it to
shore. Getting it to shore. How far
offshore is that? Uh it's about 100
kilometers offshore. Okay. So it's like
offshore wind almost. Yeah, a little bit
further than offshore wind because it
it's in the somewhat deeper water. But
you know, I think another real serious
problem uh could be the uh seismicity
that's triggered by all this fracturing
of of rock, meaning earthquakes. You
just go too far, it lets go. It seems
like a real problem. Huge amount of
deformation. But I believe that that can
be managed. And one of the most
interesting things about this this
chemical reaction when you take these
kind of hard brittle rocks and react
them with water and you form uh rocks
like asbestous which are very kind of
soft and squishy these rocks do not
deform in a brittle way. They tend to
deform like silly putty you know very
very in a ductal way. So there's a place
along the San Andreas fault in
California which has almost no
earthquakes and the earthquakes it has
is is very tiny and it's a region you
know one or 200 km long that breaks the
San Andreas into a northern section
where the San Francisco magnitude 8
earthquake happened and the southern
section where magnitude 8 earthquake
happened near Los Angeles and in between
the plates are just slipping beside each
other just you know like they're greased
and huge amounts of deformation larger
deformation than than we would see
associated with production of of
hydrogen just happening without
seismicity because so the ground is
getting all changed and looks different.
So the plates are moving. You can you
can go to central California and you'll
go to a curb that crosses the San
Andreas fault. Put a paint stripe across
the curb. Come back in a year and you
can see that the curve has been offset.
Wow. No earthquakes in that time. It's
just slowly moving along, you know. So
the big one might never come to it will
never come to central California. People
are very confident that the big one will
never come to central California. So do
do you not worry then that this is
potentially induced seismicity is going
to be a a a break on the development of
of terrestrial hydrogen? I do worry
about that. I because my reasons for
believing that it will not be are
theoretical and based on analogy to the
San Andreas fault and and I think you
know this needs to be demonstrated uh in
the field and that there again that's
where this project in Oman could be very
uh very important because uh you know
there actually be breaking rocks there
injecting and and and so we'll be able
to if they uh monitor that adequately we
ought to get a much better understanding
of the earthquake generation associated
with this. So when you just think about
like right now in terms of your own
career, um does this feel like a very
exciting time and does it feel like uh
like a pivot point to you? I just wonder
in terms of like the you know the
research you do and the work you follow.
This is a pivotable point as I mentioned
before this is really an
interdisciplinary problem and you know
that's something I can do. I can I I
understand, you know, kind of the
boundaries between geology and geoysics
and fluid mechanics and stuff. So for
me, it's this uh new like play pen, you
know, that just came just at the right
time for me that I can, you know, think
I can uh you know, maybe do one more
thing before, you know, and and it could
be important, you know, if I can if I
can make a difference in uh you know,
the transition to a lowcarbon economy,
that would be very gratifying.
Brad Hager is professor of earth,
atmospheric, and planetary sciences at
MIT. Brad, thanks for being here.
Thanks. It's been a pleasure. Thanks,
Brad.
What if it works is a production of the
MIT Energy Initiative. If you like the
show, please leave us a review or invite
a friend to listen. And remember to
subscribe on Apple Podcast, Spotify, or
wherever you get your podcasts.
You can find an archive of every
episode, all of our show notes, and a
lot more at
energy.mmit.edu/mpodcasts. And you can
learn more about the work of the energy
initiative and the energy transition at
energy.mmit.edu. Our original podcast
artwork is by Zitler Design. Special
thanks to all the people at Mighty and
MIT who make this show possible. I'm
Cara Miller. And I'm Rob Ster. Thanks
for listening.
[Music]