technology uh is closely related to
economics uh decarbonization is really
we are uh uh considering the externality
of of of our past the impact of the past
150 or more years of
industrialization so I personally I know
that a lot of the decarbonization
Technologies uh are not economically
viable today without uh orbon price or
that is the government policy so that's
why we have our second speaker Dr
Jennifer
Morris and uh she will talk about this
important subject uh and Jennifer is is
a principal research scientist at the uh
uh mighty MIT uh energy initiatives and
the uh joint program on the science of
global change as well and she's expert
on energy Transitions and uh econom
economical development Pathways so is
that uh Jennifer
please thank you sorry I lost my mute
button there for a second all right
thank you so much for the introduction
um yeah I'm happy to follow up on the
great talk that Emory gave um and I'm
going to focus on decarbonization and
carbon credits and uh I'm going to start
with a little bit of uh the context
which I'm sure you're all well aware of
but just to make sure we're all on the
same page um here's a historical view of
CO2 emissions by world's region and here
is the type of decarbonization that
we're talking about um this is an
example of a global Net Zero by 2050 um
policy and the dramatic decline in
emissions that it would require and as
emry showed as well we know that the
bulk of those emissions are coming from
the energy sector and so to achieve
these types of emission targets we need
a dramatically different Energy System
and to look at the long-term trend for
um Global Energy Mix um here by energy
by type we see that current ly uh fossil
fuel generation uh natural gas oil coal
are accounting for about 75% of um
energy and the type of transition we're
talking about again an example Net Zero
Global Net Zero by 2050 policy would
require shrinking those fossil fuels to
only about 25% of the energy mix so a
couple key points about this um is that
this the scale of the energy transition
that we're talking about is dramatic if
we want to meet these long-term climate
goals and another key point is that this
scenario that I'm showing this Net Zero
by 2050 is just one scenario and there
are countless others and I can't tell
you how many times I interact with
people who see for example the iea the
International Energy agency's Net Zero
scenario and think that is a
prescriptive um scenario what we need to
do to achieve the target but it's not
it's one possible Pathway to get there
and there are many different Pathways to
get there and it's really critical that
we explore different Alternatives um
because they have different implications
for things we care about cost land and
water infrastructure biodiversity human
well-being and so it's really essential
to think about alternative scenarios and
Pathways which is one of the things we
um do very well within the MIT energy
initiative um other key points are that
we can't rely on Technologies alone to
drive the transition we need policies
and as we just heard from Emory it's
important to keep in mind that energy is
a lot more than just electricity um it's
Transportation fuels it's heat for
industry it's it's a broader concept um
so we need to go beyond just thinking
about electricity
decarbonization and so to to further
this point that there are many Pathways
to to achieve Net Zero um we know that
Net Zero means that any released
emissions need to equal any negative
emissions but within that very simple
equation there's still a lot of
questions that arise um first of all
what are we talking about Net Zero what
um often times targets that are declared
aren't even clear if they're talking
about just CO2 or fossil energy CO2 or
industrial CO2 what about land use
change CO2 um or are we talking about
all greenhouse
gases another question is the timing of
Net Zero um
often we hear about Net Zero by 2050 but
I think it's very important to note that
that's not actually a requirement for
achieving a
1.5c um temperature
stabilization um that stabilization will
require total greenhouse gas gas
emissions to eventually decline to Net
Zero but the the choice of 2050
specifically is really a political
Choice um and the science um has shown
if we look at for example the IPC
Special Report on 1.5 um there's 90
scenarios that achieve 1.5c and only 18
of those have net zero emissions um and
only CO2 and Industrial emissions in
2050 and if we look at the mo the latest
um uh ipcc assessment report we see that
while all of the 1.5c scenarios that
achieve that Target with a 50% chance
achieve Net Zero CO2 emissions the
timing varies um from 2035 to 2070
there's nothing magical about 2050 and
only half of those Pathways in the
report achieve Net Zero greenhouse gas
emissions at any point during the 21st
century and so so really the the the
commitment to the 2050 Target is more of
a a a political choice and maybe a
recognition of the need for climate
leadership and I wanted to highlight um
a paper that we worked on that compared
a global net zero Pathway to an
alternative pathway that achieves 1.5c
temperature stabilization with a 50%
probability that's the difference
between the orange line and the blue
line here and so while the the orange
line is specifically designed to achieve
that 1.5c Target at the end of the
century with a 50% chance um the Blue
Line based on our climate model
simulations is expected to achieve about
1.2 degrees by the end of the century
virtually guaranteeing the achievement
of the 1.5c target however that comes at
a substantial cost and so if you look at
the lower left here um you can see a
dramatic increase in the the global um
change in consumption or change in
GDP between these two emission Pathways
with the global net zero Target costing
significantly more especially around
mid-century where it's extremely
difficult to achieve that net zero
emissions um so these are this is a
trade-off right are we willing to pay
more to guarantee achievement of the
1.5c Target or
not um other questions relate to the
pathway to Net Zero um even if we have a
Target we say 2050 often it's not um
thought through exactly how to get there
maybe a straight line is drawn from
present to 2050 um but there's obviously
different ways you can get to the end
point and they will have different
implications for things like the
Technologies involved the cost of
meeting the Target and even the climate
um because it will involve different
amounts of cumulative emissions along
the way
and then an important question is really
about the amount of released emissions
versus the amount of negative emissions
that are involved in the net zero and
this question is important not only for
Net Zero but also for stringent targets
like a a 2C or 1.5c
pathway and as we we heard from
Emery the whole there are difficult to
eliminate emissions in the economy and
that's the whole reason we're even
talking about Net Zero um there are some
activities for which there are currently
no good Alternatives or very very
expensive Alternatives um and that means
that some emissions are likely to
persist in the economy and we're going
to need negative emissions to offset
them and so this question of of how to
balance the negative emissions and the
released emissions is an important one
and one strategy is to reduce emissions
as much as possible and offset the
remaining difficults to eliminate
emissions with negative emissions and
this is commonly what is assumed will
happen however there is an alternative
strategy in which we continue to release
and then offset any emissions with a
marginal abatement cost that is greater
than the cost per ton of negative
emissions
this means if you can buy offsets for a
lower cost than it would cost you to
Abate your emissions you'll do that and
so this is a very different picture and
both of these strategies and ones in
between can achieve the exact same net
emissions pathway but they will have
extremely different implications for the
Technologies involved the cost of
meeting the Target and other things we
care about such as land use Health
biodiversity Etc
so um what would drive us to one
strategy or another um there could be
specific policy uh around the amount of
negative emissions that might be used or
um if there's not in in the absence of
that there an important driver will be
the cost of
Technologies and so we know that there's
generally two categories of of
Technologies there's low carbon
Technologies where the goal is to lower
released emiss
um some of the key ones are shown here
and then there's a category of negative
emission Technologies where the goal is
to offset released emissions um some of
the big players in that category are
bioenergy with carbon capture and
storage direct air capture and
nature-based solutions such as
aforestation and while there are many
options with within each of these
categories they have different costs
they have different technology Readiness
levels they have different emissions
implication and public perceptions so
there's pros and cons to each which
suggests as emry said there's it's very
unlikely for there to be any Silver
Bullet that going to solve this problem
um but at a very basic level there's a
there's a trade-off between these two G
categories in which the more low carbon
Technologies we employ the fewer
negative emission Technologies we need
and vice
versa and research that we've conducted
here at MIT has suggested that there's a
a significant potential role for
negative emissions in that global net
zero greenhouse gas by 2050 scenario
that we've run for example um our
modeling optimizes meeting that Target
by deploying a significant amount of
negative emissions you can see on the
far left there's a lot of Becks in
particular bio energy with
ccs and that deployment en enables the
continued
emissions from fossil energy and non-co2
greenhouse gases um and you can see in
the energy mix in the middle a a
significant deployment of
bioenergy and a continuation of fossil
energy now if you look all the way to
the right um the blue and the gray
hashed marks are colon gas with ccs so a
lot of the coal and gas that continue in
that scenario are accompanied by CCS
however the orange in the middle plot is
oil and so the negative emissions from
the beex um deployment is really being
used to offset the continued use of
oil now if we did have more cost
competitive technology options for ating
emissions for example in energy
intensive Industries or commercial
transportation that could Rel reduce the
Reliance on negative emissions
um let's see research has also suggested
better economic outcomes with the more
deployment of negative emissions in this
study that we conducted we looked at 2C
and
1.5c um temperature stabilization
scenarios without bio energy with ccs
those are in purple versus with bio
energy with ccs those are in in green
and what we found is that the
availability of the beex essentially
caps the carbon
price while significantly reducing the
policy cost um resulting in policy costs
more like four to 5% of global um
consumption compared to 13 to 19% while
having a limited impact on food prices
so this is a this is a very appealing
economic
outcome now
importantly we need to think about what
is a realistic scale of carbon dioxide
removal
deployment and this is really going to
depend on the assumed climate policy
regime and this is because the most
coste effective CDR options are
geographically concentrated and would be
inaccessible to Global markets without
trade and in turn the level of
trading um is likely to depend on how
article six of the Paris agreement is
implemented article six is the article
that
allows different nations to cooperate in
their achiev M of their emission targets
and trade
emissions and another important point is
trading across Regional Net Zero or near
zero targets is is predicated on the
availability of negative emissions in
some regions in order to offset the
remaining positive emissions and others
or else there is nothing to
trade um so we wanted to dig into this
question and we have a recent paper that
just came out that focuses on this
interplay between land intensive carbon
dioxide removal options and
international trade in greenhouse gas
emissions permits in order to assess the
the deployment of these
Technologies so to do that we use a a
different tool than the tool emry was
talking about it's called the MIT
economic projection and policy analysis
or EPA model and this is a multi sector
multi-region model of the world economy
that we use for energy economic and
emission
projections and it tries to make use of
the highly detailed and Tech
technological detail of work such as em
is doing um but putting it into a
context that is covering um all sectors
of the economy and all regions of the
world and interactions across those
markets so um capturing feedbacks across
regions and sectors um interindustry
linkages um um ex uh endogenous price
effects and GDP effects um so um there's
a lot going on in this model I won't
spend too much time talking about it um
but it's it's well recognized and
commonly used for this type of um
analysis however for the work that we
wanted to focus on that involved this
landbased carbon dioxide removal
Technologies we needed to make sure we
had were well representing some key
features related to land um such as its
availability and competition um the
representation of different dedicated
biomass crops the cost of these
Technologies um representation of
aforestation and reforestation land
conversion cost um direct and indirect
land use change emissions International
Trade of Agriculture and food
commodities and different
decarbonization policies and their their
impacts so all of those features are
included in this model model um which we
then use to run a set of
scenarios and so the scenarios that we
are looking at are all 2 Dee temperature
stabilization scenarios with a 66%
probability I should mention that our
economic model the EPA model that I just
mentioned is linked to the MIT Earth
system um model and so we can pass it
our resulting emissions and run the
Earth System model to project future
climate change um so we've done that
here and we're running scenarios
consistent with a 2C um temperature
Target um importantly the we have
regionally differentiated emissions
limits um and those are based on
existing commitments as well as
proportional historical contributions to
greenhouse gas
concentrations and then we're looking at
this set of scenarios that are exploring
different combinations of the availab
ility of international emissions trading
and carbon dioxide removal specifically
aforestation reforestation and be so you
can see the four um scenarios here in
this grid um going from neither trading
or CDR to be being available or both
being
available and so what we find first
looking at the results for the
deployment of CDR um is that first A4
station is pursued it's the lowest cost
negative emission option um we find um
but then it's followed by the a
significant deployment of Becks and look
focusing on the left side when trading
of emissions is allowed it opens up more
opportunities for CDR in countries that
have competitive advantages for those
Technologies and on the right without
International emissions trading we find
significantly less CDR is deployed about
60% less and this suggests that in the
world on the left there's a significant
amount of the CDR that's being produced
for sale
abroad and in that case we can see the
majority of this CDR is coming from a
few regions those that have comp um
comparative advantage for those
Technologies especially land
availability or high crop yields um or
other factors that would would make
those Technologies competitive and the
regions that that they're deploying are
not surprising um Latin America Africa
Brazil Russia are some of the key
players and importantly not all of these
negative emissions are being sold as
offsets to other countries some are
being used to meet internal um emission
targets but the majority about 2/3 by
the end of the century are
being produced to be sold
abroad and we see um that when we can
trade um when we're looking at the the
emission the scale of emissions
trading when we have CDR available it
significantly increases the the scale of
global emissions trading in the long run
um without those CDR options there's
very little wiggle room for
international emissions trading when
most countries in the world are nearing
near zero emission
targets and
so thinking about who is buying the
offsets um we can see that here and
there are many regions but the biggest
players in terms of being the buyers are
China India us and Europe and again we
saw who the producers were um but there
are if you focus on the gray bar at the
top there are uh a number of emerging
economies that are also becoming buyers
of offsets in in this
case um next looking at the carbon price
um carbon prices depend on the
availability of CDR and international
emissions trading and here I'm showing
um carbon prices indexed or or
normalized to the the best case or the
lowest carbon prices which include both
CDR and
trading and we find that when you don't
have CDR or trading we have
significantly higher carbon prices and
that's the gray dash line and that's
because in that scenario each region is
forced to to meet its cap domestically
without the use of negative emissions
and that can be extremely expensive for
some regions and so with global trading
and CDR the optimal strategy for many
regions is to emit above their cap and
to purchase offsets from the
international
market and that
strategy results in the highest GDP
growth for all regions of the world um
all of the count do best in terms of
their economic outcomes when both um CDR
and international emissions trading are
available um but an important finding of
this work um is that the availability of
CDR without trading actually results in
higher GDP growth than the availability
of trading without
CDR and it's long been known in economic
literature that emissions trading um
lowers the cost of achieving a policy so
we expect for emissions trading to lower
cost but it was a a new finding that c
the availability of CDR can lower cost
even more than emissions trading and in
all of the regions the worst economic
outcomes are when neither CDR or trading
are
available and we also took a look at the
scale of transfers in involved in in
these scenarios and under the different
settings the scale of emissions traded
and the scale of CDR both move in
opposite directions of carbon prices so
when you have more trading or more CDR
you have lower prices and vice versa and
so as a result the total amount of
resources spent on International offsets
is similar both with and without CDR
that's what I'm showing on the left and
that total amount spent reaches over $7
trillion in
2100 and a growing portion of that
spending is coming from emerging
economies um which is an important um
result as well and then if you look on
the right we similarly find that the
total revenue received by producers of
these offsets is similar both with and
without emissions trading and it reaches
over 9 trillion by
2100 um and with trading the vast
majority of the CDR revenue is acre in
emerging economies so emerging economies
there's a subset that are receiving
massive amounts of transfers through the
sale of offsets but there's also a set
of emerging economies who
are paying an increasing amount for
offsets um so this is important
political economy dynamics of cost and
benefits to different groups of emerging
economies um importantly while the scale
of
the um resource transfers involved are
similar regardless of the scenario the
efficiency of that implied spending
differs significantly
and that's what we saw in the GDP
results um spending is most efficient
when both CDR and Emissions trading are
unconstrained um so you can get a lot
more bang for your spending if you can
trade and have
CDR um so to to provide a a summary of
these findings
um we we are finding that emissions
trading and CDR are mutually reinforcing
in deep decarbonization scenarios um
that International emissions trading
unlocks geographically distributed CDR
potential and that trading in a net zero
world really requires negative emissions
um without them there would be nothing
to
trade um however most of the
literature um ignores this relationship
because scenarios are commonly assumed
to have the most optim optimistic
settings um if you look at um long-term
2C or 1.5c scenarios in the literature
they overwhelmingly assume both um
International emissions trading and um
carbon dioxide removal availability
which may not be the case and so we need
to be thinking about these alternative
scenarios that may not have those um
available um this work also um speaks to
the importance of Po design as it
relates to trading as it relates to CDR
Technologies and offset markets offset
markets are currently um extremely
immature they're basically voluntary
offset markets or what it currently
exist um and there are a lot of things
that would need to be flushed out for um
the type of CDR and offset um trading
that I showed in these scenario arios um
thinking about things about the
longevity of the negative emissions are
there differences in um the permanence
of the negative emissions that come from
aforestation reforestation compared to
beex compared to direct air capture um
if there are differences um do we value
the offsets differently and how so how
to how do we speak to um small
individual landh holders versus versus
large landholders in terms of things
like aforestation and
reforestation and what about things like
wildfires um forest fires that
potentially um wipe out your aforest
station emission syns um what happens
then so there's a lot of things that
would need to be flushed out in terms of
offset markets to make these types of um
uh offset trading a reality
um we also as I mentioned find that CDR
matters more for um GDP than
International emissions
trading we find rules for both beex and
aforestation
reforestation um in this work we did not
include um direct air capture as an
option however we have previous work
that has um included direct air capture
and we also have um uh my colleagues and
I have recently
um published a commentary on the topic
and our consensus is that direct air
capture is just too expensive um it's a
lot more expensive than um most studies
in the literature that are site numbers
of100 to $200 per ton of CO2 removed uh
we believe it's more like in the range
of $600 to $1,000 per ton of CO2 removal
um and therefore not economically
competitive with beex or aforestation
reforestation at least least not um
under current projected costs that we
find um importantly the buyers and
sellers of permits are going to depend
on comparative advantages in um CDR
Technologies as well as in the assumed
decarbonization trajectories for each
region um depending on how different
countries
um set their emission targets that will
change
um
their willingness or ability to trade
participate in emissions
trading um finally well the scale of
resources is not strongly does not VAR
strongly depending on the scenario but
it's more efficient when we have both
trading and
cddr um and the final important point
about the resource transfers these are
potentially extremely large transfers of
resources if we're talking about
emissions trading um and using CDR
offsets and most of it ends up in a very
limited set of regions and we find
emerging economies spending an
increasing amount on offsets over time
um and this is probably a different um
distributional outcome in terms of
resource transfers um than is being
advocated on the international scene in
terms of um the conference of the
parties the cop um under the UN um and
the Paris agreement process there's long
been discussions about um resource
transfers to developing and emerging
economies to help meet decarbonization
targets um and if you want to have
specific um distributional outcomes um
you can achieve them but you would need
to have more purposeful design of
emissions Caps or transfer mechanisms if
you just rely on the sale of carbon
offsets and and emission permit credits
um you would likely not see the
distributional outcome in terms of
resource transfers that um is being
demanded on the international stage um
so with that I am happy to um end and
look forward to some discussion and
questions thank you hey thanks thanks
Jennifer uh it's great great analysis uh
uh big picture uh issues we all need to
understand between
countries uh uh a few questions uh uh Al
studies that um go beyond the energy
sector but also including the U uh
Agriculture and the farm
industry uh yes and um apologies for not
making it clear but the the study I just
talked about covers all sectors of the
economy including Agriculture and
farming and so we are capturing not only
the emissions of the Agricultural
activities themselves but also emissions
related to changes in how we use land um
so those are in there as well as
um energy emissions from um the service
sector from um Aviation and shipping um
any all of the emissions in the economy
are covered under our um the study I was
just describing which is imposing an
economy-wide limit on greenhouse gas
emissions okay thank you uh next
question uh do you see the CDR emissions
trading occurring through the uh
International emissions trading
Association or or have you look into the
the mature maturity of compliance and
the verification services to validate
the CDR claims a long question but sure
yeah um yeah no it's a great question I
think this is one of the big question
marks um potentially through the
international missions trading
Association potentially through um
bilateral or multilateral agreements
across Nations um potentially a broader
um Global mechanism like set up through
article six of the Paris agreement um
there's a lot of questions and a lot of
possibilities about how this could um
play out and the compliance and
verification is an extremely important
question mark in when it comes to
offsets overall um as I mentioned offset
markets so far are are voluntary and
there are services that try to um
validate or credit them but there's not
an a L accepted or agreed upon um system
for doing that there are different ways
to think about offsets especially as
they relate to land and it really
matters what you are assuming is your
your Baseline and on the international
um policy scene you will see differences
for example um Brazil has a lot of
forest and
they would argue that they should
receive credits for not further
deforesting the Amazon if if other parts
of the world want Brazil to protect the
Amazon instead of cutting it down to
further their Economic Development they
should receive credits for
that other people would argue that you
should only receive credits for
additions that you're making to the
current state
and so there's different accounting
systems and schemes that
can uh get at very different results of
what counts as an offset or not and so
that's an area of international debate
um and that's an area that adds
complexity to the question of of what
counts as a credit um and then the
verification and monitoring is extremely
important and something that also needs
um further attention and exactly how to
make it
work okay thanks uh uh what are some of
the proposed methods for determine what
the carbon caps should
be um
so
there are the carbon caps
for are going to vary depending on the
scale of which you're talking
um so in terms of global greenhouse gas
emissions
um we can give you as scientist a range
of global emissions that we are are
confident could
achieve a given temperature Target um
for example the pathway I showed that
could achieve a 1.5 emissions Target
with a a 50% probability we can
calculate the those types of global
emissions that are more or less
consistent with a a temperature Target
with some some probability because
there's always uncertainty in how
emissions get translated into
temperature change in the earth system
um how then those global emissions get
distributed across nations of the world
is an important question um so far we've
left the process in the Paris agreement
for countries to um put forth their own
targets um and we have seen
growing pressure to increasingly move
towards Net Zero by midcentury more or
less um I I showed the figure there of
if if everybody actually did Net Zero by
2050 would overachieve a 1.5c Target um
but we can do different things as
economists one of the things we do is we
set we can set a use our modeling tools
and set a global a emissions um app and
then let everybody trade in our model
and find the cost optimal allocation of
emission reductions by region um whether
or not countries will listen to that
type of um analysis is a different
question and may not align with the
political uh economy scene um so some
thoughts there yeah sure more questions
uh do you think trading of offsets will
take take hold uh what major efforts are
being taken for advocating for offsets
and the
tradings um so
there the the role of carbon dioxide
removal Technologies in these deep
decarbonization scenarios um has proven
to be increasingly important in the
literature we we are consistently
finding um a a strong potential role for
CDR um if we're going to be using
CDR um the value of that right is we
could
potentially um produce negative
emissions in a way that's cheaper than
some of our abatement options and these
really hard to Abate sectors so that's
going to let us achieve targets in a
more cost-effective way um whether or
not we're going to allow trading across
regions of these Miss negative emission
offsets it is a question and I think a
lot of attention is currently being
given to that question of how could we
realistically make that work and there's
a lot of attention to that question
because it has such a large potential to
lower the cost of Glo of meeting
policies across the globe so there's um
desire to make it work and I think
attention to how re how we could
realistically do that is growing um I
think a key example or a key push for
that reality is coming from the aviation
industry um which currently is the
largest purchaser of voluntary offsets
um because Aviation is so hard and
expensive to decarbonize and so um
there's a a a real interest in that
industry to make these offset markets
work and I think kind of having a
industry leader pushing this helps um in
the real world to try to get these
markets up and
running okay Jen one more question uh
when you have those tradings among
different countries uh uh how are the
carbon price uh set is that based on the
cost of Technology of uh uh abating the
CO2 emission in the buying side and the
cost of avoid emission in the producing
side yeah it's and it's a good question
and um it will depend on the design of
the policy the specifics in the in the
scenarios that I showed we put them all
under the same
policy so in a a permit from a baiting
was equal to a permit from a negative
emission and so there's just one carbon
price um and as long as there's trading
that carbon price would be the same with
any um trading
partners um however there are other
strategies out there um and I think
maybe the UK is an example or in the EU
they're thinking about having um
distinct targets for abatement and
carbon dioxide removal and therefore
they would not be within the same market
and you might be talking about then
having um one price for your abatement
in your cap and trade system and a
different price for offsets um but you
could bring those offsets into your cap
to cover your achievement of your your
target um so it really would depend on
how the policy is set up there's
examples in avenues for both
ways okay uh now how do you inovation
the the um credit producing countries or
regions uh obtain those um reductions
by uh carbon negative emissions or by
not
DeForest te like as you mentioned in
Brazil
case how does it generate those credit
so that the the the price is low enough
that the other side of will buy
it yeah and so a lot of the the regions
that we see with the the biggest
potential for
um um carbon dioxide removal for the
production of international offsets um
is it Latin America and Africa um some
other regions as well but those are the
key players there and if they um for
those
regions to get the the most um I guess
bang for their Buck they would have to
Abate themselves within their countries
um and deploy the CDR because if they if
they didn't do their own abatement um
they would have to use up all of their
CDR to offset their emissions to meet
their own targets so if you want to be
able to have enough to actually sell to
so while also meeting your target you
have to Abate too um and so the in our
analyses um beex bioenergy with ccs is a
is a real um winner in terms of the
economics um and for a lot of places at
least initially in the near-term um
aforestation and reforestation which
would mean in our World's new addition
to Forest rather than promising not to
Deforest what is currently there um is
aforestation really coste effective um
with the caveat of the challenges of of
permanence um how long are we promising
to keep those new forests there and can
we even make that promise um given
natural disasters Etc um so a lot of
question marks um but again a lot of
interest and potential to
really mitigate well mitigate the cost
of
mitigation um so yes yeah uh you
mentioned the DAC the direct air capture
is was one of the uh carbon netive
technology options uh you know lots of
talking about that you know in your
models
uh I guess that option must be very
expensive at this point because some
dynamically it's just uh uh pretty hard
to uh uh capture CO2 from 400 PPM
air uh any comments there uh whether I
they will become a real impactful
Technology Solutions um yes um I would
encourage everyone if you go to today's
um homepage for the MIT energy initia
itive um on the homepage is an article
um describing our recent commentary
about um getting real on direct air
capture um which reflects the opinion of
myself and um Howard Herzog who's a
world-renowned expert in CCS
Technologies um as well as um Sergey
pulv and Angelo gel and our our main
message that we wanted to portray in
that piece is that
the physics behind direct air capture
prevent
some serious challenges that make some
of these lowcost estimates extremely
unrealistic and if we account for those
challenges such as the extremely diluted
concentration in the atmosphere the high
amount of energy that's needed to run
these processes um the scale of the size
of the infrastructure that would be
needed um then if we really account for
those the more realistic cost of these
of direct air capture is more in the
range of$ 600 to $1,000 per ton CO2
which is just not competitive and while
there may be some room for improvement
and lower cost there's always going to
be those challenges of the laws of
thermodynamics that are going to prevent
you from getting too low um so that's at
least our our our projection until maybe
we have some techn technology Revolution
um in the area but for now um the the
even with a multiple variations of
direct air caption capture options um we
see it as as expensive yeah okay thanks
Jennifer uh obviously uh a lots of good
questions and good answers