Yeah, you're going to hear about some
cool tech today and that's not
surprising. I mean, this is the
Massachusetts Institute of Technology,
but uh I want to take a broader look at
the theme of connection, connectivity,
and in order to do that, I'm going to go
back a little ways to go forward. So,
I'm going to talk about some history,
but with luck, this will also give us
some insights about the future. So,
yeah, I started in 1975.
I've been here a long time.
Uh that was a couple of years after uh
Vince Surf and Bob Khan proposed what
the internet might be and they convened
a group the network working group.
We had to figure out how to actually
build it. We wrote code. I chaired that
group in the 1980s.
Um in the 1990s I worked on well I'll
tell you about the 1990s when I get
there. But since this is about
connectivity um what were we connecting
in the 1970s? We thought we were hooking
up time sharing mainframes, huge
machines. They filled a room right now.
We sort of knew about personal
computers. Xerox Park had the Alto and
we saw Ethernet out there, but we
where's that? What's going to happen?
Um,
in the 1980s, it was clear we were
hooking up everything. The IBM PC
happened and we realized everybody was
going to own one and all of a sudden we
weren't hooking up hundreds of thousands
of machines. We were hooking up hundreds
of millions of machines. So basically
the 1980s was a scale up decade. We had
to scale up routing. We had to scale up
addressing. Um in fact it was 1991 we
had a big workshop where we realized we
had to have a bigger address base. And
so that's what got us to IPv6 which
we're still working on 40 years later.
No, no, no, no, no. But but we could see
the trajectory of connectivity and and
the important insight that you should
have in this case, which I would say is
that applications always stalk capacity.
I have to remind you we were doing voice
over the internet in the 1970s.
Okay. Now, we had to really compress it
down to [laughter] like two kilobits
because the backbone of the arponet at
the time was a 50 kilobit circuit,
right? Nobody said, "Did you say
megabits?" No, no, I said kilobits,
right? Um, oh, the first generation of
the NSF nut showed up. My god, it was a
megabit and a half. Oh, we did video
teleconferencing.
worked really well, but you could only
do it to a campus because that's the
only place you had that capacity. And so
we we basically got up to the point in
the early 90s where all of a sudden a
whole bunch of things became clear and I
might describe them as sort of negative
epiphies. Um
I I will tell you a couple of stories
which are sort of wonderful. Um,
everybody saw we needed more capacity to
the home.
Dialup modems 9.6 kilobits. No, no, no,
no, no, no, no. We needed more capacity.
And there was an National Research
Council study called Realizing the
Information Future. I wrote a fair
amount of it and it was written in 1994.
And then we do some industry briefings.
We get a room like this.
the telephone people would not be in a
room with the cable people. He said,
"They're disgusting."
So, we briefed the telephone people one
day and we briefed the cable people the
next day. Now, in fact, there've been
both telephone and cable people on the
committee. They managed to [snorts] get
them to talk to each other, stay in the
same room. And it was really interesting
to listen to those two people because we
talked to the telephone people and these
were sort of the regional carriers, you
know, and they said, "We don't no, we're
not going to do broadband to the home.
It's not in our business interest.
We don't think we can make money.
The only way you'll get it done is if
the regulators tell us we have to." I
said, "Oh, that's right. You still think
you're in a regulated industry where the
government's going to tell you what to
do? Oh, yeah. Right. Next day, we get
the cable guys in there and they're
cowboys. They're entrepreneurs.
And they said, "Oh, we have a 10-year
plan.
Don't tell the telephone company.
They think we're clowns. They wouldn't
even be in the same room with us. Here's
a here's a cable company joke. How can
you How do you become the vice president
of engineering in a cable company?
you stay sober enough so you don't fall
off the pole. Um
that's that you know lawyers tell lawyer
jokes, cable guys tell cable jokes. Um
but they say here's the 10-year plan.
We're going to start selling internet
because we have broadband because we
have enough capacity in the cable to do
it. And yeah, it may not be completely
stable in the sense that you'd like your
phone system to be stable. We're
upgrading our engineering. We're
upgrading everything. And we'll get the
consumer accustomed to the idea that
they can get multiple services over
cable. And then when we get the system
stable and our engineering up, then
we're going to start selling telefan
over the cable and they'll never see us
coming and we're going to take them from
behind and kill them.
And they did.
But they saw the business opportunity.
And and I said, "Oh,
it's all about money, isn't it? And the
tech follows where the money goes."
There was a visionary at Xerox Park. You
know, they did the Xerox Alto and all
this kind of thing. Allan K and he said
the best way to predict the future is to
invent it.
Allan
best way to predict the future is to
figure out who's investing in it. I I
had an economist conversation in about
1995.
Uh guy who knew a lot about the
economics of the internet and he said,
"David,
the internet is about money routing.
packet routing is a side effect and you
screwed up the money routing protocols.
That wasn't the word he used. And and I
said, I didn't design any money routing
protocols. And he said, that's what I
said.
So I hired an economist.
And I sort of was trying to understand
how to think about this
the the centrality of money.
Yeah, we were government funded guys
building something in the 1980s and
yeah, we knew it was going to get
commercialized. We had no idea how to
think about it.
But but the next interesting phase here
was about it was about this was in the
19 about the year 2000. Intel had a
negative epiphany.
Intel figured out that in order to keep
selling chips,
the computers had to get bigger and
faster and cooler and more fun.
And that wasn't happening in business
because people were just running.
[laughter] They were running, you know,
you know, Excel.
It was the gamers that were buying the
high and they were in the home. So they
needed broadband to the home so they
could sell more chips so they didn't go
out of business. I said, "Okay." And
they actually came to Washington. This
is Intel hates regulation. Came to
Washington to see if maybe they could
get the government to push for the
deployment of broadband to the home. so
they could sell more chips. Okay.
And at the time the cable guys were
executing their plan and there were at
that point there were all these little
tiny
dialup
uh modem people. You know you get dialup
service from your guy has a modem bank
in his garage. There was a industry
representative and he she said to me
there 8,000 of these little companies.
How are you going to protect them? I
said protect them. They're all going to
go out of business
because it's all going to be facilities.
It's going to be the cable guys against
the telephone companies. If you don't
own the wires to the home, you're out of
business. And they said, "What?" They
thought that was unfair. Okay.
But there was still a business problem.
Uh the cable guys actually had an
infrastructure that was really good for
connectivity because you could invest
incrementally and get incrementally
better service. With copper pairs, they
just suck. So you have to overbuild
yourself from scratch with fiber. So
it's this massive investment and I was
talking to guy in Verizon early on in
the in the 2000s and he they decided to
do FiOS you know fiber of the home and I
said what's the business model he said I
have no idea
but I'll tell you the business model if
I don't do it in five years we're out of
business so we're gambling I said huh
okay so I I sort of said okay it's
really it's really if you want to
understand connectivity you got to
understand money.
Okay, that's fine. I already hired an
economist. So,
I'm actually a bit of an optimist about
connectivity in the to the home.
Actually, I'll tell you, uh we're going
through a gigantic investment phase now
where we are putting fiber in
everywhere, but fiber will last a long
time once we put it in. And I'll tell
you a little bit of an experience I had.
I'm on a on the board of an organization
called the Massachusetts Broadband
Institute, which was set up. It's a
public private corporation set up to get
connectivity into western Massachusetts,
which is very rural. It's not like
Montana, but it's very rural.
And we now have broadband in I think all
but two towns. Uh those towns are
particularly stubborn, and I don't know
what to do about them. But
is it a tech problem? No, it's not a
tech problem. We know exactly how to do
it. Okay.
Is it a cost problem? Well, broadband in
rural areas is going to cost more than
it is in downtown Boston. And I was
talking to guy out in western
Massachusetts. He said, "Grumbble,
grumble, grumble. Broadband cost more.
Grumble grumble grumble." And I said,
"When you drive into town to go to the
grocery store, how much does it cost you
to park?" And he said, "Cost?"
I said, "I go into Boston, it cost me
$40 a day to park." And he said, "Huh?
I said, "Two days I've bought your
broadband.
There's some things that are cheaper
like parking and there's some things
that are more expensive like broadband.
What's the problem?" Actually, the
problem is rural poverty. It's not cost.
So, what is the problem? Well, the
United States went down a connectivity.
We made an article of faith that we
didn't have to regulate
broadband connectivity because we had
competition between two companies, cable
companies and phone companies. Okay? In
the rural area, there is no facilities
competition. Nobody can afford to do it
more than once. So, all of a sudden,
we're going to have a dominant incumbent
and we've forgotten how to regulate
them.
Now, there's a town out there,
Stannisfield. I spent quite a bit of
time out there.
They want to build out broadband in
their town. 1,600 people and it's big
enough. They have two fire stations.
They don't have a regulator who can
regulate price regulate their internet
provider. Who's going to do this? We had
to solve the money problem, the
regulatory problem, and all the rest
comes. Okay. And by the way, let me tell
you how to screw up in rural
connectivity, which is you lose you. I
don't know how to do price regulation. I
don't know how to. So they say, we're
going to we're going to let out a
contract to let somebody come in and
build the area. And what we're going to
do is we're going to ask them to tell us
what the retail product is going to
cost. And the person that says they can
give the retail product for the lowest
cost, we'll get the bid. And so
everybody tries to low bid it. So, they
get in and then they get in there and
they say, "Oh, I'm not quite making any
money. I didn't qu That bid was a little
too low." And they come back and say, "I
need to raise that price." No, you can't
raise the price. If you raise the price,
the other guy might have won. You have
to. And then they go out of business.
That's called the world's stupidest way
to do price regulation. The price, the
price, the regulator has to be able to
change the price. And I said, "Okay,
it's about money, isn't it? It's not
about the tech." I was uh up in Maine.
There's a little a little
place on the coast we rent for a week
and a year ago I was in there and I did
a speed test and it was 3 megabits in
each direction. That's crappy DSL from
the local phone company. I went in and
just for the fun of it I did a speed
test and my god it was 120 megabits
birectional.
I couldn't believe what happened. I went
running outside to look at the back of
the house because there was fiber on the
house. There's a small company that's
running fiber into rural Maine. This
part of rural Maine around Bath. It's
not terribly rural. And they have fiber
to the home half mile off the road. Many
poles.
Okay. I don't know what the business
deal was, but the point is that's where
we are now. And once we've done it'll be
there for 30, 40, 50 years. So, so I'm
uh I'm actually somewhat optimistic
about connectivity at that level. And
we're seeing it overseas. Although when
you go into other parts of the world,
obviously they're behind the curve. But
I will say, by the way,
is wireless the great white hope? No,
not in western Massachusetts because the
terrain goes like this. So you put the
tower up there, you can't get down here,
you put the tower down here, you can't
get anywhere. Towns that went for
wireless discovered they got like 70%
coverage and the company went out of
business. So just spend the money. By
the way, notice all kinds of federal
subsidies now for building out
connectivity in rural areas, but they're
only paying for the initial capital
expenditure. You got to cover the
operating expense.
And wireless has a much higher opex
because you have to continue to refresh
the tech. So, let's actually switch for
a minute. Oh, and by the way, low Earth
orbit satellites are really cool,
but only use them when nothing else
works because otherwise they don't have
enough capacity. But that guy at the end
of the five mile driveway out in rural
Massachusetts, just yeah, give him a
satellite dish. You know, don't run
fibers five miles up his driveway unless
he wants to pay $25,000.
Actually, no, it's not that. It's about
20,000 a mile to construct fibers. So,
five mile driveway. Well, I was joking
about the five mile driveway, but that'd
be $100,000. So, don't do that. Okay?
Give him a satellite dish. Um um let me
let me switch topics for a minute and I
do want to talk about wireless because
what's happened in the cellular space is
something we did not anticipate at all.
This this is truly amazing. Okay,
everybody's carrying one. Yeah, look on
the subway. Every single person is just
sitting there staring at us like this.
But but this is a transformative device.
And what's interesting since we're all
talking about money here is almost every
innovation comes with its own hype
bubble. You know, we're in the middle of
the AI hype bubble now and and we're
waiting to see when it bursts and yeah,
I'm an optimist about AI, but the curve
always goes like this. But there wasn't
even a bubble, but it just happened. But
the wireless industry and the buildout
in the wireless industry is quite
amazing. But there's an interesting
question. Why all those G's,
3G, 4G, 5G, and now we have 5G? They're
talking about 6G. And I was talking to a
cellular guy and he said,
"Unprintable, unprintable, unprintable."
And he said, "The G's are a conspiracy
by the equipment makers to make sure
that every 10 years we have to replace
all our equipment because you got to
have the new G." And I said, "Is 6G
going to be better than 5G?" I don't
know, but I'm going to have to pay for
it and they're going to sell it to me
and they're cramming it down my throat.
So cut out the with the G's, please. You
know, 5G is good enough. Oh, oh, future
blah blah blah. Just cool it, man. Cool
it. And you know, this is actually true.
Um,
I said that apps stock capacity. And we
knew we could do video over the
internet. We knew it in the 1980s. We
did audio over the internet in the
1970s. We're just waiting for the
capacity to get up.
So, here's an interesting policy
question. It's not about connectivity in
the sense you do, you don't have it. How
much is enough?
100 megabits,
500 megabits, a gigabit, 10 gigabits.
Okay, who said 10 gigabits? Um, you
don't need it. Now when we fantasized
about the applications we saw well
audio
spoken audio has a certain you want to
do music it's got to be high fidelity
it's got to be bigger you have v video
it gets bigger
if there's an application that is
driving that is waiting for capacity
what's beyond video well one answer is
one multi-person immersive augmented
reality or virtual reality and you can
say okay How much bandwidth do we need
for that? Well, maybe it needs 700
megabits.
So, why is Comcast pushing a gigabit
right now, even 3 gigabits? Because
their marketing department told them
that people are so stupid the only
number they can understand is speed and
more is better. That's a quote. And the
engineers in Comcast hate it because
they say, "We're having to build out
capacity we don't need in order to sell
a product the customer doesn't need
because that's what our market people
told us." Okay. Okay. Okay. Okay.
Um, it's important to ask where will the
apps go next. And if you're trying to
figure out where the apps go. Well, look
in the lab. Look at MIT. See what's
going on. What's the what's the answer
of the day? Blah blah blah AI blah blah
blah. Okay. And now people are telling
me we need a new internet for AI.
You do?
Uh, we didn't need a new internet for
video.
What about AI needs new capacity? Please
tell me that. I'm just waiting for
somebody to answer that question. And I
love I think AI is cool. I think it's a
bubble. All of those statement can be
true at the same time. But you know,
people said, "Oh, we have wireless. We
need a new internet for wireless." We
could have done a better job of
designing the internet for wireless.
It's too late now. We got what we have.
But it's good enough. It works. So what
what's the problem here? Um, I'm still
waiting for somebody to say useful,
something useful to me about the role of
the internet in the age of a
we're all going to be talking to our
agents. Okay,
maybe we have AI generated imagery. We
already have that. We have we have
synthesized AI video, some of which is
quite appalling and disgusting.
Um, but I'll come back to that. Still
just video. Okay. So what's actually
going on on the internet? If you ask
about the connectivity that we're
deploying today,
we're getting actually beyond speed and
we're beginning to look at second order
parameters that make a difference like
variation in latency. This is a very
technical problem. It's called jitter.
You know, if I'm sending packets to you
and one of them's late, is that a
problem? I'd love to be able to sell
that product because Comcast knows how
to sell it. It's a premium for gamers.
Okay, I'm trying to get the marketing
department to understand how to sell it.
Now, um this, by the way, these
questions are relevant to the deployment
of broadband in the rural area because
people are doing federal asking for
federal subsidies. So, the federal
government asked, "How much is enough?"
Well, of course, everybody had a
self-serving answer to that question.
Okay, but we're getting over it. So, you
know, other kinds of connectivity I
could have talked about. Well, somebody
a minute ago said internet of things.
That was a little fad. You know, we
thought, oh, this is going to be we need
a new internet for things. Actually, we
do because things are so stupid.
Okay. They're so feeble they can barely
breathe. Okay. So, what do we have?
Well, sometimes in the home we have
little proprietary networks. I have a
little proprietary network that connects
my light switch to my lights. in a few
places. Doesn't have to be on the
internet, but there's actually a box in
my house that's a gateway. The system
can send me an email if something goes
wrong. Okay. So, you know, there's sort
of a shootout there between things in
the house that are working over Wi-Fi,
which is an open standard, and things
that are working over proprietary
standards, but I don't think the
consumer is being screwed at the moment.
Um, I don't know whether somebody's
going to talk about data centers today.
What's going on in data centers is
amazing.
It's all about AI, right? Because we got
these incredibly high-capacity chips and
you got to get high-capacity networking
into them. That's a technical problem.
That's not a money problem because it's
been internalized by the firm. And
that's some really cool stuff and I
don't I don't do that. I'm still
concerned with connectivity of the
internet at the global level. So, so
where's my research gone? My research
has gone up the layers. Um,
what were we hooking up? I we we thought
we were hooking up computers, right? And
we made some unrealistic and I'd say
simplistic assumptions about where the
apps would come from. But okay,
users don't hum normal people don't send
packets, right? They run apps. It's the
app that defines the internet
experience. I built the packet carriage
under layer. Yeah, I send packets just
to measure the internet, but I'm I'm
weird. Okay, you who who wants to send
packets? You just send you want the app
to run. What we didn't understand was
where is the app coming from? We had
this simple idea. Well, you know, you've
got a computer and you put some software
on your computer and that person puts
some software in their computer and
they'll talk to each other and all be
great.
Um,
no,
we're actually hooking up people. And
the problem is
people don't write code.
And so we didn't understand where the
apps were going to come from until the
big apps started showing up. The obvious
example that we're all alarmed about
today is social media, social networking
apps like Facebook, where everybody
says, "Oh, yeah, it's actually
wonderful, but it's also full of
disinformation and it's going to cause
the end of democracy and and we can't
stop using it because we're addicted to
it." And where'd that come from and why?
Well,
the internet started out as a
decentralized infrastructure. There's
75,000 ISPs connected together to make
the internet. The web is a decentralized
infrastructure. Anybody can run a web
server. Anybody can run a browser. You
can have anything. The domain name
system, which is a fairly technical
thing, but it's very decentralized.
Okay. And by the way, I don't have time.
But why is the domain name system
successful as a decentralized system?
because it's got a defined money routing
protocol
and I didn't even see it was about to
happen. Okay. But the centralized
solution like Facebook, okay, is it more
nimble? Yeah, they can make decisions
quicker. You don't spend five years
debating something in a standards body.
But what's really powerful about a
centralized solution? All the money
routing has been internalized to the
firm.
And
this is where I didn't understand how to
think about hooking up people because
people don't have the power to shape
their online experience. They have to
use the code they're given. And the
question was where is that code going to
come from? And of course the other
problem is when we look at the way
people behave given things like social
media and so forth, some of their
behavior is what word can I use? Stupid.
irrational. Why the hell did you do
that? Okay, so the mantra of the
internet when we designed it was
permissionless innovation was a general
platform
and part of what we were concerned about
was making sure that the ISPs could not
manipulate the experience you had
because they can see all your packets go
by. So maybe they shoot that packet and
amplify this one. And we were worried of
course that's that's network neutrality.
Okay. But while we were busy worrying
about that, what we notice is that at
the application layer because the
internet all the intelligence is at the
edge. It's in your computer. But at the
application layer, all the intelligence
is moved back to the center. It's inside
Mr. Facebook or inside Mr. Google or
inside Mr. X. That's just like the phone
system where all the intelligence is in
the center. And so they could control
exactly what you did. We were worried
about the wrong villain. We thought the
ISPs were going to be the villain. No,
it's big tech. Okay. So, what did I do?
I'm currently, as I said, in 1990s, I
hired an economist. I'm currently
collaborating with a behavioral
psychologist
to try to understand what happens when
you hook people up because they're so
weird. Okay? They're much more
complicated than packets.
And and and by the way, I would say if
you come to MIT and you want to see
innovation, that's cool. Cool stuff.
If you want to come to MI, if you want
to come to a place that really has a lot
of experience in the subtleties of human
interaction,
geeks aren't necessarily the best person
people to be talking to about that kind
of thing. So, um I would say there's an
interesting and painful dynamic going on
right now in this space, which is I
would like to see decentralized systems
be more viable. Okay, the web was
decentralized. Why can't we have a
decentralized social networking
experience?
Because we didn't design a money routing
protocol.
And if money can't flow among the actors
in a decentralized ecosystem, it'll die
and the centralized solution will take
over. We needed to design money routing
protocols. And that's what we're
connecting up. We're not connecting
computers. We're not connecting people.
we're hooking, we're connecting up the
money flows. And I I I couldn't say that
sentence in in 1995. I couldn't say that
sentence in the year 2005, but now I
understand it. So, as I say, I still
have an economist. But what I would like
to do is some research on decentralized
systems. And here's an interesting
question. Okay, obviously
federal money's gone to hell. I can't go
to NSF and ask for anything. You know
this, you know, let's not talk about it.
What's our lab doing?
We looking for industry money.
What does industry want? Solutions they
can monetize. Those are centralized
solutions. Why would big tech pay me to
design an architecture such that it
blows them into little pieces?
So, I can't get any funding for
research. Okay. But I do have an
behavioral economist that I'm working
with and I am an optimist. But the point
is
the ex the thing that's going to define
the future of the internet is not new
tech.
It's going to be the user experience and
we're waiting to see how AI changes the
user experience. Um it's possible that
there will be something happens there
that is so completely out of the blue.
We just didn't see it. But the buzzword
today is blah blah blah agentic AI which
is to say um we all have agents. So
I will close with a dystopian story
because I think sometimes you need a
ounce of
counter optimism. Okay. And MIT is a
place of optimism. We're all techno
optimists but and we were techno
optimists about the internet. But what
we were optimistic about was not the
tech. We were optimistic about how it
would be used, which is to say we're
being optimistic about people. Oh,
I was having trouble being optimistic
about people.
What's happening today?
People are being offered AI companions,
AI
pseudo people that you can talk to. I
don't have any slides,
so I can't show you a picture.
of the female companion that ex Mr. Musk
has created.
the system, his system is called Grock
and the the female companion is called
Annie Aani and she looks like a cross
between a uh a sort of a
Japanese
anime Lolita character
uh sexy as hell and she flirts with you
and she's easy to talk to. She doesn't
have all the social pathologies of real
people. She doesn't have bad days. So,
what's happening? We're raising a
generation of guys that are sitting in
the basement talking to artificial
entities and they don't know how to talk
to people anymore. We're raising a
generation of people that can't talk to
each other. All they can do is talk to
simplified AI simulations. That's my
pessimistic story.
Um, the more I learn about what
motivates people, the more I learn how
tricky it is to connect them up. And MIT
is a great place. It's as it uses
Institute of Technology, but the
problems I'm dealing with here are not
technology problems.
Oh, do I do we do questions? What are we
doing here? I've lost track. Are we
doing questions or am I out of here now?
>> We can do some live questions if there's
any.
>> Okay, I've lost track of the timing
here. The clock went to zero. I saw that
and so I stopped. But
>> couple questions.
>> Couple of questions that person said.
Anybody? Okay, sir.
>> Um, great presentation. Um, I know you
were instrumental in building kind of
like that early stages of the internet.
I'm wondering how you see the
introduction of agents also interacting
with internet. Do you think there's
going to be kind of like this new
protocol layer where agentic systems
kind of like interact autonomously? Do
you think um we're going to keep it a
lot as it is? Do you think it's going to
be centralized in one player? Do you
think it's going to stay decentralized?
>> Um, there's a lot of issues there and
the crystal ball is cloudy at the
moment. We have competing providers of
AI systems.
There are people who are trying to come
up with standards for interoperable data
that would allow you to move context
from one place to another. So, uh when
you when you do an AI query, if you're
doing sophisticated stuff, you can not
only put your prompted, but you can put
in some context. Okay? And there's a
protocol called model context protocol
MCP and it's supposed to be an open
protocol and we're trying to make sure
that people can use it. So that would
mean that you could move your
interaction with an AI agent from one
LLM to another LLM and I hope it will
play out that way. I know there are
people that are trying to facilitate
that. It's not decentralized. We're not
trying to get them to talk to each
other. We're trying to make it, we're
trying to empower the user by giving
them the power to exit so that they
could, you know, if they get bored with
Grock, please do. Um, you can go
someplace else. Um, and you can take
your history with you, too.
[clears throat] The history of your
interactions, your prompts, and the
responses. Um, I don't think it takes
any special kind of internet for agents
to talk to each other. Agents need to be
named so we can find them. We may need a
new directory architecture. And there
are people at MIT trying to design a new
directory architecture for agents the
project called Nanda so that uh there
would be just like we have DNS for
looking up hosts we might have a
directory system for looking up agents.
So I think people are trying to figure
out what's new and what's different. Um
but it's not going to require a whole
new protocol suite. You know I can I can
I can talk to an agent over the existing
protocols just fine. It's around the
edges where you're going to find these
new things that may actually affect the
industry structure like model context
protocol.
Thank you. David
>> stunned. Okay, good.
>> [applause]