CLAUDIA URREA: Welcome.
It feels so wonderful
to be here, right?
As we officially launch
this portion of the agenda,
I want to recognize
and a warm thank you
to all of the students, all
of the MIT community members,
and our collaborators for
sharing their insightful work
during the showcases.
So thank you so much.
[APPLAUSE]
I want to share a little
bit of my journey.
I began climate-related
work at MIT
as I began my PhD in '98, with
Seymour Papert at the Media Lab.
And part of the work
that we were doing
was developing curriculum,
toolkits, technologies,
running professional
development,
and more importantly, running
innovative camps for high school
students around the world.
The most insightful
part was not only
what we learned
from those people,
but some of the work that
was transformational for me
came from Peter Senge and
from Linda Booth Sweeney.
And that work came from Sloan.
And it had to do with system
thinking and the relationship
that it has to learning, and
learning about the real world,
and what it matters and how
it matters for world learning,
for problem solving.
So I kept some of
those insights.
And that has been really
transformational for my career.
And just to quote Peter,
"Systems thinking is
a discipline for seeing
the whole rather than just
the parts, and for understanding
how things fit together
and change over time."
So understanding the
interconnectedness
of the work and the actions
that bring us together,
the power of collecting
efforts really
brings us hope today and brings
us together at this event.
As I prepare for this event
and talking to Peter this week,
he reminded us
that climate change
offers a unique
opportunity, because it's
the first time in human
history that all nations face
a common problem.
And that's not always seen.
We have very little opportunity
to experience something
like that.
Leading this climate
work, Day of Climate
has been an honor this year.
We take this work
seriously, so I
want to acknowledge all
of the members of my team
that have been in support
of this work this year.
We come together to
acknowledge the urgency
of the current challenges
the world is facing.
We recognize the collective
work that many individuals
that I just mentioned,
in organizations
that represent them, are doing.
And I emphasize "recognize,"
because I feel like it's hard
to think about celebrating
when we need to recognize all
the work that is ahead of us.
I encourage everyone to
listen to our speakers.
They're here to inspire us.
They're here to ignite
our collective actions
towards a better future.
And they're here to
elevate the leaders
of tomorrow, you, young people.
Before I introduce
our first speaker,
there is an important
emotional dimension
that I want to highlight, and
it's the importance of love--
falling in love with
knowledge, falling in love
with learning, with action, and
with the people you work with.
So welcome, everyone.
[APPLAUSE]
ANNOUNCER: Please welcome
Chris Knittel, Associate Dean
for Climate and Sustainability,
professor of Applied Economics,
and faculty director of Day
of Climate and MIT CATE.
Woo.
[APPLAUSE]
CHRIS KNITTEL: Great.
Thank you very much.
One more round of
applause for Claudia
and the team for
pulling this off.
An amazing job
and amazing venue.
As was mentioned, my
name is Chris Knittel.
My main job here at MIT is I'm
a professor of Applied Economics
in the Sloan School
of Management,
but I'm here to represent
four groups around campus
that came together a few years
ago to develop a high school
curriculum on climate change.
So the first is, as I mentioned,
I'm a Sloan faculty member.
And it occurred to
me a few years ago
that we, at MIT, have a
lot of resources available,
not just to MIT students, but
to K through 12, more generally.
And that got me really excited
about potentially developing
a high school curriculum that
was based on MIT resources
and based on MIT research.
And that came together with some
other organizations on campus
that I'm involved with.
The first is the
Center for Energy
and Environmental Policy
Research that has been around
for almost 50
years, does research
on trying to understand the
costs associated with pollution,
the costs associated
with climate,
but more importantly,
what we can do to address
environmental concerns.
I'm also faculty
director of what's
a new center on campus, known as
the MIT Climate Policy Center.
And that's working hand
in hand with policymakers
at the state level,
the national level
and the international
level, to actually do
something about climate.
And then finally,
two years ago, about,
our president, Sally Kornbluth,
announced the Climate Project.
The Climate Project,
in her own words,
is an all of MIT
Climate Project that's
going to bring together all
the schools around campus, all
the disciplines to actually
have a meaningful impact
on the trajectory of climate
change over the next 10 years.
So I want you to keep
an eye on what we
do under the Climate Project.
But that all came
together to what
we call CATE, so Climate
Action Through Education.
It's a interdisciplinary
high school curriculum
that's science-based,
standards-based, and modular.
And most importantly, it's free.
And rest assured,
us, faculty at MIT,
did not develop the curriculum.
It would have been impenetrable
and certainly not be effective.
I had this vision of
a one week curriculum,
where every school just spends
an entire week across all
the disciplines on climate.
We met with some teachers.
And they said, well,
that would be great,
but nobody would ever use that.
So at that point, I
said, we got to actually
go to the professionals here.
We have hired five
fabulous curriculum
developers that are current
Massachusetts high school
teachers.
If you go to the
CATE website, you'll
see 30 lesson plans that
are free to download.
Each lesson plan has
background material
for the teacher, background
material for the student,
some lab or assessment,
and more importantly,
a sheet of standards
that curriculum meets.
I wasn't going to say
this, but it really
speaks to the importance
of an event like this.
The actual reason why I wanted
to develop that curriculum is,
two years prior to that, my
dad, who was a high school math
teacher, got, in his mailbox,
a high school climate
change curriculum.
And he gave it to me
to look at, and it
was all climate misinformation.
So it just points to the
importance of us coming together
to share actual science-based
facts on the importance
of addressing
climate change, how
we can address it,
and more importantly,
understand its impacts
across society.
So it's days like
this, a day of climate,
that is just a small
stepping stone in actually
solving this worldwide dilemma.
And I look at all you,
kids, because unfortunately,
the old guys like me are not
going to be able to do it.
But I trust that you
will be able to do it.
So let's end by giving
yourselves a round of applause
for addressing climate change.
[APPLAUSE]
ANNOUNCER: Please welcome Pete
Bouchard, chief meteorologist
at NBC Boston.
[APPLAUSE]
PETE BOUCHARD: Hi, everybody.
That's an old
picture of me, right?
Yeah.
Am I good?
Oh, I changed the slides.
Wonderful.
Thank you, everybody.
Wonderful to be here today.
It's a little drab out there,
a little cool, a little chilly.
Is it?
[INAUDIBLE]
Should I just turn this one off?
Nobody likes feedback.
So I've been on a little
bit of a time kick recently.
I think it's a little bit
because I'm middle aged now,
and I've got a lot
more years behind me
than I did have ahead of me.
I'll just shut this off.
I'll just take it out.
So in the shallow surface that
I'm scratching here of time,
I learned that time is a little
bit of an illusion, right?
When we look ahead
into other galaxies,
when we look ahead to,
like with the James Webb
telescope, for
instance, or the Hubble,
you go look millions
of years in distance,
really, it's millions of
millions of light years away.
And you see those galaxies and
those objects as they once were.
MAN: Facing the
speaker a little bit.
PETE BOUCHARD: For the
purposes of this meeting,
I'm only going 15 minutes.
So even though time
is an illusion,
we still have a stick on it.
So back to the discussion.
And this is a little
deep too for some people.
But if you think about it, that
is the past you're looking at.
And it's hard to conceptualize
that because if you thought
about maybe a civilization
sending you a selfie,
it would take millions of
years for you to get it.
So you saw that selfie
as that civilization
appeared millions of years ago.
And when it comes
to you at that time,
it's millions of years old.
And the same thing if
you look into the future.
If we could travel
the speed of light,
we would go the speed of light,
and you'd go into the future,
in a sense, because
time would stop for you.
You'd come back, and maybe
a decade or two decades
would have passed
for you on Earth.
And you would have
aged on Earth,
but for you, it would
have been a blip of time.
And then we think of time
in the sense of the now.
There is only the now.
When we think of time and what
they conceptualize as time
is only now.
You can't go back to the past.
The future is undecided.
And when I think about that,
I think about climate change
and how the now is probably the
most important part of where
we are.
Right?
Because we can't
change the past.
We're living on what
happened in the past.
And in the future,
it's still undecided.
We still don't know
what's going to happen.
But if we plan for the now,
if we plan for the future
and everything that we can do
to stem the tide of emissions,
do the work that
you're doing, we
can actually make a difference.
But we're at the precipice.
Time is short.
There's not a lot of it left.
We live in a bubble, right?
We are in a greenhouse.
Closed system.
You don't have a lot of
venting in that system.
The only way you can get rid
of carbon and greenhouse gases
is to consume them.
And they take hundreds
of years, maybe even
thousands of years in
the case of carbon,
before it actually
is whittled away.
So that's the problem
we have going forward.
So the time to act is now.
WOMAN: [INAUDIBLE]
PETE BOUCHARD: Oh, sorry.
My bad.
It would help.
[LAUGHTER]
So when we think about it,
now is the future in the sense
that if we don't do
something about it now,
the future is predecided.
And again, in my limited
knowledge of the human psyche,
I've gone into a little bit
of research on this too.
I took a course in Climate
Communication at Bentley
a few years ago, with a
great professor, by the way.
And shifting baseline
is one of the things
that the human mind goes
right to immediately.
Our grandparents' climate
is not our climate and not
the climate of the future too.
So when we actually
engage with people,
you have to take
that into account.
Climate change is something that
they perceive, but it's changed.
And right here at MIT, they
did research many years ago.
And it takes about five years,
in general, before temperatures
become unremarkable.
So you hit 78 in Christmas.
Big deal.
Becomes normal after a
period of five years.
It's normalized, unfortunately.
Climate change is also a
cultural cognition thing.
Unconscious process,
which causes
people to shape their beliefs
to dispute on disputed matters
of fact, based on their values.
So there's obviously, the
hype with the fake news.
The planet is warming
at an alarming rate,
not seen in thousands of years,
perhaps, millions of years.
And everybody's an
expert on this too.
And there's another part
of it that I won't go into.
It's attribute substitution,
which is essentially,
if it's 90 degrees today, of
course, the climate is changing.
It's very warm.
But if it's 20 below tomorrow--
are you insane?
That's crazy.
Of course, it's not.
Politicians would have
you think that there
are two Americas-- a blue
and a red America, right?
But in essence, there
are six Americas when
we talk about climate change.
There are the people that are
alarmed, that are concerned,
that are cautious.
And then there are a few that
are disengaged, agnostic.
They don't know.
The doubtful ones, too,
and the dismissive ones.
So when you add those up,
that's 27% of the population,
but they get all
of the talk, all
of the chatter on social media.
They're the ones that
always troll, right?
are always in your face.
They want you to disengage.
They want you to back away.
They don't want you to be
a part of the conversation.
They want to be
front and center.
But the vast majority of
people have your back,
when you think about it.
This is the latest research, by
the way, from Yale University.
This just came
out last December.
So this is very topical.
And when you think
about the people who
are interested in knowing
more with news stories,
and they want to know whether
it's happening or not,
74% of the population, when
you look at the country,
it's not blue and red,
it's not polarized.
It seems like a vast
majority of people,
even in states that don't have
a lot of knowledge about climate
change or maybe dismissive about
the idea of climate change,
they are engaged here.
They want to know.
And when you think about what
stories they want to hear about,
[CHUCKLES] it is
interesting at the bottom--
candidates for president.
And it's interesting,
at the very bottom.
Presidential candidates' plan
in response to global warming.
76% of the population wants
to know more about that?
I find that intriguing, too.
But generally, again,
the minority of people
are not at all interested, 20%.
And that's across the board
in news about climate change.
Katharine Hayhoe, a very
famous climate scientist,
had a great quote.
I mean, she balances what?
Life, and career, and faith,
which is involved in science,
and that cross, that is very
difficult to actually balance.
She had a quote.
She said, "The biggest
problem we have is not
the people who willfully
decide to reject
200 years of basic science.
The bigger problem is the number
of people who say it's real,
but don't do anything about
it and don't think it matters
to them."
That's a vast, vast gap
that we have to close.
And that's the issue,
going forward, too.
So our issue is obviously
tapping into that.
But we live in a bubble.
We come to these conferences,
and we talk about it,
and then we leave, and we
go, oh, that felt good,
because we're with our tribe.
We're very tribal.
We're with our people.
We have backup.
We have common interests.
But obviously, there's 72%,
73% of the population that
still wants to know something
about climate change.
When you look at it in
a statewide perspective,
it comes down to the
blue and the orange here.
And you can see, some states
are dismissive of the idea.
And then here's the
tribalism involved.
Then you go down to the county
level and the little fiefdoms
in there.
And everybody just
squirrels away.
So it's about just homogenizing
the whole conversation
and bringing it out
there, and also making
it accessible to people
who really want to know.
And I think, by
staying in our groups
and staying within our
own like-minded people,
that we miss that
opportunity, I think.
And then the estimated
people, the adults
who think global
warming is happening,
wow, that's also pretty
enlightening too.
Again, in the 70%
change, in the 70%.
So that is the
challenge, going forward.
And obviously, it can be
a very difficult thing
too, when you're talking about
trying to change someone's mind.
There are people you will
never change their mind,
and I've run into those.
And so it's a waste of time
to engage in that sense too.
So there's a limit to
what we can tolerate,
anybody can tolerate.
It's a crazy thing
too, because some
of those that you
don't reach again
will want to come
after you, especially
if you're in the media.
But I find it interesting too
as the next generation moving up
is not really fazed by that.
They're still formulating
their opinions,
they're still with the idea
of what they believe in.
And what they believe in
is, the planet is warming.
We're going to do
something about it.
My generation wasn't
really like that,
and I feel weird about that.
But also, it does mean
that there's a lot of work
ahead, right?
And to quote another famous
professor, Professor Dumbledore,
for those who like Harry Potter,
"Dark times lie ahead of us.
There will be a time when we
must choose between what is
right and what is easy."
Obviously, it's
not an easy task.
There's a lot of work ahead,
and there's a lot of dark times.
And that can be a little bit
more on the anxiety level.
And that is a big thing too.
Doomism is a thing
in climate change.
If you go, and you
doomscroll, as they say,
the climate discussions,
the job is overwhelming.
You can fall into
a spiral, and there
can be no coming out of that.
Climate anxiety
isn't dismissive,
and it shouldn't be
dismissed, it's apparent.
And it, honestly, can fall on
the lines of race and gender
too.
This graphic too, also
from Yale University,
shows that Latinos
are mostly affected
by this, 17% of those who
think it's an overall issue.
And some of that is severe, some
of it is moderate, some of it
is mild.
Gen Z, there you are, and the
millennials, male versus female.
Gen X, honestly, do throw
the weight of my generation
upon my shoulders.
It does feel like, we
saw the train coming.
We heard the sirens,
the gate went down,
and we didn't do much about it.
It feels like we didn't
really get engaged.
Not to defend it, but some of it
might have been the fact that we
didn't have a lot of
information in the '90s.
I remember going to conferences,
and it was just like,
we sat around and were
like, we're pretty certain,
it's warming, but our
models weren't great.
They didn't simulate the
atmosphere as well as
they do now, which is
all the more reason
to believe the data, right?
And it is funny too,
because I saw the program,
and I saw, it said, Pete
Bouchard, climate activist.
And I'm like, I had
to pause for a second.
I thought, am I really?
Have I really done enough?
I mean, I go to conferences,
I speak about it a lot.
But it is something
that you think back,
and there's always
something you could do more.
You can always really
take up the cause.
And again, it's your
generation inspiring
mine and inspiring me to
come to these conferences
and talk to you about it too.
But anxiety, and climate,
psychological distress
is also something, I think, that
is playing a role in what we're
seeing now with
social media and how
we perceive how we're
going to go forward,
how we're going to attack
this whole subject matter.
And it is necessary
for you to find help
if it really does bother you.
And it's OK to step back, right?
I do woodworking on the side.
And sometimes, I get
really tangled up
in some of the geometry or
the joinery that I'm doing.
And I actually have
to step away from it.
And I come back to it.
And I go, wow, what
was I thinking?
Right?
Because that can be something
that can be regenerating to you.
And fall back on your peers too.
That tribalism,
that's your core.
When you go out
there in the open,
and you're expanding
your horizons,
and you're confronting these
people, it's OK to fall back
and say, hang on,
I need a second.
So if the planet
could speak to us,
what do you think it
would say these days?
Right?
If we personified the
planet, it probably
would say, what are you doing?
And also, does it feel a
little warm in here to you?
Right?
Those are the things
that you can think about.
But also, it might
be saying, thank you.
For the people who are
doing the work out there,
stay hopeful, and
don't give up hope.
Thanks.
[APPLAUSE]
Again.
ANNOUNCER: Please
welcome our panel,
moderated by Margaret
Wang-Aghania, executive director
and cofounder of
Subject to Climate.
[APPLAUSE]
MARGARET WANG-AGHANIA:
I hope that works.
OK.
Great.
Well, Thank you
all for being here.
And today symbolizes
a lot of great things.
It symbolizes the day of
climate resources launching,
which is fantastic.
But I also think it
symbolizes how we
democratize climate knowledge.
And in the place where I
think makes the most sense
in the classroom.
And also, what it symbolizes is
not only upcoming Earth Day, not
only Earth month, but I think
it shows that this is something
that we need to be
teaching every day,
needs to be integrated across
all grade levels and subjects,
because our students, and
our learners, and our kids
deserve to learn about
the world around them
and what's happening.
And it's not something
we leave it just
for them to solve on their own.
It's something that we all work
intergenerationally together.
And the classroom is
a great way to start.
So I used to be a teacher.
I used to be a social
studies teacher.
And I saw how it
activated my students.
And now, I run a nonprofit,
called Subject to Climate,
where we help educators
integrate climate into all grade
levels and subjects.
So I'm very excited
about this panel,
because studies show that
if you teach about climate,
it'll lead to immediate
carbon reductions.
And then also, students
change their parents' minds,
and it'll also affect
their communities
because they'll take action.
So I'd love to hear directly
from learners, students,
and educators.
So if we can welcome them with
an applause, and we'll get
started.
[APPLAUSE]
So first off, I would love for
you all to introduce yourself,
what you do, and what inspired
you to get involved in climate.
Was there an aha moment or
something that happened?
And we can start
with you, Naima.
NAIMA SAIT: Yup.
Hello, everyone.
Thank you for being here.
My name is Naima Sait.
And I'm a former high
school French teacher.
And yeah, so on
the personal level,
I am originally from
North Africa, Algeria.
And in 2018, just watching the
region from a lot of villages
burned to the ground
due to forest fires.
So that was very devastating.
And then in the classroom,
as a French teacher,
I had a lot of English learners.
And then coming
to the realization
that a lot of those students
did not have access to one class
that the high school offers,
environmental science class,
but they were fluent in French.
So I took advantage of that
and started teaching fact
about climate change in the
classroom in all levels.
And then realizing
during that journey
that a lot of those students
were also part of a youth hub,
Sunrise in Somerville.
And they had their
little community.
And yeah, from there, it was
a long journey of figuring out
in the classroom what we can
learn about climate action
at the local level, but also
how they can take that and do
more local climate advocacy.
Yeah.
And I will talk more
about that later.
So it's all these
different things.
MARGARET WANG-AGHANIA:
That's amazing.
And you can learn it in French
class as well, which I love.
And then love to hear from
your perspective, Laelia.
What about you?
LAELIA MAYNOR: So hi,
my name is Laelia.
I'm here with the Center
for Systems Awareness, which
is a compassion-based
education reform nonprofit.
I'm a product of
public institutions.
I went to public school my
entire life in a very small town
in Northern California.
And for me, the pull
towards climate change
wasn't necessarily
an aha moment.
I was raised in a
spiritual practice that
values the environment
and protecting it.
And alongside growing up
in the redwoods, which
are the tallest living things
on planet Earth, they're trees.
And I feel a great
amount of respect
and very humbled by them.
So for me, protecting
the environment
and going towards climate
education wasn't a moment.
It was more of a
moral imperative.
MARGARET WANG-AGHANIA:
That's very powerful.
Thank you, Laelia.
And Sophie, you represent
another student perspective.
So what about you?
SOPHIE SHEN: Hi, everyone.
My name is Sophie.
I use she/her pronouns.
I'm so excited to see so
many young faces here today.
I'm a student at
Arlington High School.
I'm a senior,
graduating this year.
And I run the Slash the Trash
team, which I cofounded,
which basically,
we do a lot of work
about diverting our lunchroom
waste into composting,
recycling, trash.
And we also do a lot
of education work.
So we do environmental
justice presentations
for high schoolers.
And we also do
work about learning
about how policies
impact our environment
for elementary schoolers.
I guess, for me, the reason why
I'm so excited to be here today
is because I've had so many
great educators in my life, who
have taught me a lot
about the climate.
I remember, all the way
back to elementary school,
my green team at Dallin
Elementary, shout out--
MARGARET WANG-AGHANIA:
[CHUCKLES]
SOPHIE SHEN: --Rachel Oliveri.
She's our school
sustainability coordinator.
And she helped out
with the green teams.
I remember this one very
memorable experience
where we learned about milkweed
and how monarch butterflies
thrive off of milkweed.
And so I'm really excited
to talk to you all today.
MARGARET WANG-AGHANIA:
Wonderful.
And speaking of
sustainability coordinators
and admin level,
Dave, what about you?
DAVE KRAMER: That's what I do.
My name is Dave Kramer.
I am the director of Green
Programs at a school called
Boston Green Academy.
Shout out to my colleague, Dina,
right there in front of me.
She's from Boston
Green Academy as well.
At the school, they
call me Big Green Dave.
I don't know if I earned that,
especially with other guests
here today.
But I think I became passionate
about climate and sustainability
education as a result
of a gradual process.
I grew up in Florida, which,
clearly, now is very vulnerable,
went to college in New
Hampshire and really fell
in love with the outdoors,
and mountains, and whatnot.
But the main catalyst
for me was moving
into the country of Colombia,
and teaching there right
out of college.
It opened a whole
new world to me.
And I saw ecosystems at
every different altitude,
all these different
areas in the country,
different cultures that
really sparked my curiosity
and interest.
So I tried to bring that
back to students every day
and try to work to
help young people care.
I think, a lot most people
care, and just to highlight it
in their day to day.
And also to spark
curiosity, wonder, and awe.
I'm really honored to be here
today, so thanks for being here.
MARGARET WANG-AGHANIA:
It's amazing.
And so we hear a
lot of themes of
lived experiences,
connection to nature.
A lot of times, that's
what sparks climate action
and interest in climate.
So I want to start off with,
we have two educators here.
So I want to learn more about,
how have you integrated climate?
Or how have you seen other
educators integrate climate
in the classroom?
And what are the effects
that you've seen on students?
And we can start this
time with you, Dave.
DAVE KRAMER: OK.
Go right back down.
At Boston Green Academy, anyway,
I think we do a lot of work
to integrate climate,
and sustainability,
and environmental justice across
different classes and Susan
curriculum.
For example, we have a tradition
called green exhibitions
at the end of the school year,
where teachers may complain
in the planning process.
It's a lot of work,
but they basically
let go of their regular classes
for two or three weeks, some,
even longer, and have an
interdisciplinary approach
to looking at everything from
food justice and food systems
to intersectional issues
related to climate and justice.
And our youngest
students look at,
what does it mean to
be a green school?
And how can we make it better?
And I invite them to
bring suggestions.
I think, also, just one
example of a teacher that does
an awesome job in our school is
our 12th grade Green Engineering
and Physics teacher,
very project-based.
And we actually
have a student who
is starting an internship
at the Zero Waste Program
in the city of Boston, who
told her just a couple of days
ago, this school pushes
sustainability and climate all
the time down our throats.
But you know what?
This project, where I had
to use upcycling and do
a shark tank-style
presentation really
taught me that this matters,
and it was really enriching,
and I'm looking forward
to my internship.
So that right there
was just proof
that kids may complain
along the way,
but a lot is seeping in
through teachers and others who
are trying to weave
climate sustainability
across every subject,
including French.
MARGARET WANG-AGHANIA: Great.
And I had the privilege of
visiting the Green Exhibitions
in Boston Green Academy.
And if people are
interested, they
will talk to you
afterwards and invite you.
It is really great to see those
different interdisciplinary
projects.
And also, visiting Boston
Green Academy is great too.
There's the hydroponic
freight farms as well.
DAVE KRAMER: We're in
Brighton, I forgot to mention.
But yeah, we have
a freight farm,
which is a retrofitted shipping
container for growing vegetables
all year long, and finally,
serving that in our cafeteria,
too.
MARGARET WANG-AGHANIA: Yeah.
Who wouldn't want that in
their classroom, right?
That's a real skills like that.
They're learning.
And so, Naima, what about you?
I know that you
were in Somerville.
NAIMA SAIT: Yes.
So as I said, I was a
classroom French teacher.
And at first, they just started
teaching about climate change
in all the levels.
And then my students started
asking for specific things.
They started to
feel very powerless
in terms of what we can do.
So they asked that we focus
on what we can do locally.
They really took ownership
of their learning.
And I will just mention a
few things that they've done.
They hosted the Climate Panel.
And they invited educators.
They invited student
climate activists.
They invited city staff from
the Office of Sustainability
and also some climate
activists in the community.
And we're asking them questions
about all sorts of things,
like, how many trees
are we planting?
What can we do to create
more sustainable modes
of transportation?
And green roofs.
They even had an
elected official,
so they asked about ordinances.
And what we can do
at the city level.
So that was really
inspiring because they
invited the whole school.
And they were also trying
to recruit more students
to join the climate hub that
they created in the community.
And outside of the classroom,
they did a lot of things.
One, they decided to put a
questionnaire together and make
endorsements during elections.
So they put climate
platform together,
endorsed candidates for
mayor, for city council,
and had them commit
to certain things,
that they will do everything
to offer free blue bike
passes for staff, for
students, that they
would be more funding for parks
and a lot of other things, even
green roofs, which
is part of zoning.
So it was very inspiring
to watch them do that.
And also, they worked with the
teachers, we'll get to that part
later.
I was part of a teachers union.
And they worked
with their teachers
to push the district
of Somerville
to start a path towards
mandating climate change
education in all
subjects and grades.
Actually, that was negotiated
during a teacher contract
negotiation, and
it passed, making
some of the first city in
Massachusetts to have done that.
So we're still at the very
initial phase and still figuring
out how to do that, but--
[APPLAUSE]
This was a collaboration
between teachers and students.
And that was very,
very powerful.
MARGARET WANG-AGHANIA:
All right.
And I remember, that's
when we met Naima,
when I found out about
Somerville public schools
having climate change
be a requirement.
And this really gets
us back to, this
is an intergenerational,
collaborative effort.
And oftentimes, we
walk into this problem,
saying, oh, my gosh, there's
so much we don't have,
but I'm here to show
you that we need to look
at an asset-based approach.
Look at how much we
do have right now.
These are just two
amazing teachers,
educators with their stories.
And I want to now turn it over
to our learners, our students.
And so for students,
what about you?
How has learning about climate
impacted you and influenced you?
So we'll start with you, Sophie.
SOPHIE SHEN: Yeah.
So growing up, I've never
really known a time,
where climate change hasn't
been an existential threat
to our globe.
And so I think that that has
formed a lot of the career path
that I've decided
to take in life.
I see a lot of,
as we were talking
about like interdisciplinary
connections between government,
literature, and the
climate, and so I'm
really interested in town
government, like Naima is.
I interned at our
Department of Public Works.
And I'm now an elected official,
as town meeting representative.
Oh, thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
And I think, learning
about climate change
has inspired me to
take action on a wider
systemic level in that sense.
MARGARET WANG-AGHANIA:
That's amazing.
And just you're seeing like
it's not just a science problem,
there's so many layers.
And Sophie has really
been able to leverage
what she's learned in
social studies, for example.
And Laelia, what about you?
LAELIA MAYNOR: For me,
it seems paradoxical,
but I actually
gained a lot of hope
through my climate education.
The climate education program
that my organization puts on
goes deeply into the
social and emotional aspect
of the climate crisis.
I know, like Sophie,
I've struggled
a lot with climate anxiety,
and depression, and doomism
of my public life.
Public officials
aren't doing anything.
The companies aren't
doing anything.
How are we ever
going to change this?
And being able to critically
reflect on my own thought
processes and feelings have
allowed me to show up more
presently in these
climate spaces,
alongside learning about
the amazing initiatives
that students, and teachers,
and just people across the world
have done that have deeply
changed their local ecosystems.
It's very inspiring.
And I would say,
just the ability
to stay present in
the work I do has
been the greatest skill I've
gained through my climate
education.
MARGARET WANG-AGHANIA:
That's amazing.
And that's a important thing.
I know Pete talked
about climate anxiety.
And one thing is that,
when you teach about it,
you can also teach
about the solutions.
Because also quoting Katharine
Hayhoe, which Pete did,
is that Katharine
Hayhoe talks about,
it feels like you're
pushing a boulder,
but when you're
doing a little bit,
you feel like you're
making progress.
But when you see other people
joining you, you're not alone.
And that can be the difference
from anxiety to hope.
And so, again, we
hear all these stories
from educators and students, and
they're doing amazing things.
And so we need more
of this in classrooms.
So in your all's
perspective, what
is needed to accelerate this?
Like, bring climate
change education
to schools and communities.
And we can start with
Sophie this time.
SOPHIE SHEN: Yeah.
I guess, maybe to
touch a little bit more
on what I was saying earlier
about multidisciplinary
and interdisciplinary
learning, I guess,
I want to give a quick shout
out to the CATE program that
was also presenting today.
I'll see a lot of
the ways in which we
can talk about climate
through different angles,
and that makes it
more approachable
for different students who
have different aptitudes.
And so, for example,
in literature classes,
we can talk about romanticism
and environmental preservation.
We can talk about
how infrastructure
bills in our government are
impacting our environment.
And so I think it's
really important
to lower that barrier to entry
by engaging students with topics
that they are already familiar
with, already passionate about.
And I think that's a
great way to introduce it.
MARGARET WANG-AGHANIA:
What about you, Dave?
DAVE KRAMER: Yeah, I think
I would agree with that.
I think that fundamentally,
climate change education is not
a STEM, science and math, issue.
I think I've had people
talk to me and think
that I must be a
science educator.
I was an English major
and an education minor,
then an environmental
policy in grad school.
I think that it takes
all the angles Sophie
mentioned to tackle this.
And different people
get hooked into it
by different personalities
in their classrooms
and different subjects.
I also think that teachers are
very unlikely to incorporate
without standards like
Somerville's or the state
of New York or
New Jersey, right?
I think, if anyone here wants
to advocate at the state
level in Massachusetts,
I know Margaret
would be willing
to help you, but I
think we really need to mandate
climate change as standards
across the board in education.
And that will make it a
lot easier for teachers
to be able to do it.
Even though it adds more
work, it's just something
that they have to do.
MARGARET WANG-AGHANIA: Right.
And again, this idea of, there's
just so many requirements of,
how can we bake it in
into what they're already
going to have to teach in?
Standards are what they
already have to teach.
And Laelia, what about
your perspectives on this?
LAELIA MAYNOR: I
went to a school
in a very small rural
town in California.
My community has the highest
rate of childhood trauma
and an above average
rate of poverty.
So kids show up to school, and
they're not ready to learn,
they're not ready to be engaged.
So I see, the intro to
climate solutions in schools
is to radically invest
in students' well-being
and academic needs.
So showing up with
food security,
housing security,
and a community that
is focused on creativity
and a passion for learning.
Communities in the US that are
most affected by climate change
are Black, and brown,
and poor communities.
These are the
students that we need
to invest in to
make sure that they
are ready to show up and
engage in the content
that we are giving them.
MARGARET WANG-AGHANIA:
That's amazing.
NAIMA SAIT: Yeah.
So what would be some of the
things that were already said?
Because it's important
to, yeah, say it again,
mandating climate education
in all subjects and grades.
And what it means is, you
need funding for that.
So one, at the state level,
the adults in the room
reach out to your
state representative.
There's a bill at the state
level for exactly that.
So if that bill is
passed, district
would be able to get that
funding from the state.
So that's one thing.
At the local level, get to
know your school committee
representatives as well,
because in Somerville, again, we
started that
journey, but it does
require a lot of
funding to train
teachers to buy curriculum.
So making sure that
every year, there
is a budget that's
dedicated to that.
And teachers are being
paid for this work.
So these are few things that
we can do at the local level.
And I think we've gotten a lot
of different advice on-- these
are things that can
help accelerate.
And so maybe you're thinking,
OK, this is amazing.
What's my next steps?
What do I do next?
So in closing, I'd love to
ask our panelists to share
just a lightning round.
What's your call to action?
What's your advice for
people listening here,
who are like, OK, I understand
that this is what is needed,
but what can be
my very next step?
And yeah, to start with.
DAVE KRAMER: I'm happy to go.
And we'll just go down
the line, I guess.
I would say, honestly, come
visit schools, go to schools,
come to Boston Green Academy,
go to other schools that
are doing this kind of work.
I don't think you can
advocate for change
without knowing what it's like.
Some days are really
heavy in schools.
And everyone needs to understand
that and match the energy
with what you can recommend.
But you're welcome to come.
And as Margaret
said, if anyone wants
to talk to me about end of the
year events, we have a lot.
And they're fun.
SOPHIE SHEN: I guess, just
to call back to something
that Mr. Bouchard
was saying earlier,
there's a lot of
misinformation in the world.
So teachers, keep
doing your job.
And students, be willing to
engage with that material.
And there are so many
ways to get involved.
That could be starting
a community garden.
They can be great community
hubs, great learning spaces.
That could include advocating
to your local or your state
government.
They're super accessible,
a lot of times.
And that's a really great
way to get your voice heard.
MARGARET WANG-AGHANIA: Great.
LAELIA MAYNOR: For
individuals, I really recommend
checking out on-road simulator.
It's what the UN uses to
predict climate change.
It was developed here at MIT.
And for schools
and organizations,
I highly recommend collaborating
with your local Indigenous
community.
The tribes have been the
stewards of these lands
for so long.
And they have an
intergenerational relationships
within their community.
They really know how to
work with your community
and what your community needs.
So set up a meeting with
your tribe, tell the stories,
and learn how they
take care of the land.
NAIMA SAIT: Yeah.
For students.
I will say, try to find
community within your school
and also within your city.
Work with your teachers.
We have done it in
Somerville, and it worked.
So yeah, just other things
is join a local climate
hub, the Sunrise.
That's just an example, but
there's a lot of other ones.
Yeah.
MARGARET WANG-AGHANIA:
And I think,
one thing that I'll
ask everybody to do
is, after this, I think the
first step is talk about it.
Somebody who's
not in this event,
share some of their stories,
talk about what you learned.
Some of the flyers that
you gotten of resources,
bring it up to your
friends, your teachers.
And that's where we start
when if we talk about it.
So thank you, all,
so much for this.
And I hope that
you learned a lot
and walked away with
some action items
on how you can help be part
of this movement of climate
education, and therefore,
climate action.
DAVE KRAMER: Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
ANNOUNCER: Please
welcome Aladdibe Joroff,
deputy climate chief at the
Governor's Office of Climate
Innovation and Resilience.
ALADDINE JOROFF: Hi.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
Hi.
Wonderful to see so
many people here.
And thank you for inviting
me to join you tonight.
It's a hard panel to follow.
But I will say,
what was inspiring,
as many people
often ask, how do I
get involved in climate change?
How can I make a difference?
We just heard a lot
of inspiring ways.
Showing up at an event
like this is one as well.
Learning about climate
change is what's
going to help give us all,
as individuals, the tools
to address climate change,
whether it's reducing emissions,
so that we lessen the
impacts of climate change,
or dealing with
the impacts that we
know are already going to see.
So some of you may remember
when recycling started.
A large part of the
reason that got going
was students, like in
elementary and middle school,
we're taught about recycling.
They went home.
And every time their parents
put a can in the garbage can,
they would go and take it out,
and put it in a recycling bag.
Same thing with
turning off water when
you're brushing your teeth.
Some of these things start
with the youngest generations
teaching everybody else and
making it a habit in our lives.
And as individuals, our actions
around climate change matter.
And it can be as inspiring as
becoming an elected official
and joining causes,
but it can be
things we do in our daily
lives individually as well.
And I say this because climate
change can feel overwhelming,
right?
It is a very large global issue.
But if we think about
just a few examples.
So in the energy sector, we
know the most cost effective way
of reducing emissions
is to use less energy,
so turning off the light
when you're not in a room.
In the transportation sector,
if there's public transportation
available, taking a bus or a
train instead of a car ride,
that can reduce emissions.
And you may feel when
you're doing that like,
is that so significant?
But when you look
on the bus, and you
see the 20 other passengers,
you think, oh, that's 20 people.
And there are 20 other
buses going around my town.
And there's 20 other towns
in my state with bus systems.
And there's 50 other states.
It's collective that our
individual action matters.
And I'll just reference, there
was a study, it was in 2009.
So the data may be a
little out of date,
but the principle is the same.
And it studied what they
call the behavioral wedge
from household activities.
And it said, things
that we, as individuals,
can do in our homes, not
high technology lifts.
We're not talking about
adding heat pumps.
Things we can do in our
behavior can collectively reduce
approximately 7 and
1/2% of US emissions.
So that's just things
we can do at home.
And then on the
resilience side, when
we think about
increasing storm events,
heavier rains, if you
walk around streets
and see the storm drains on
the ground, those grates,
they're designed so
the water flows through
during a storm event.
Well, particularly
like in the fall,
when the leaves are falling,
if those get clogged up,
the rain doesn't go down.
It pulls back onto the street.
And when it gets really bad,
it goes into people's houses.
It can flood streets, homes.
So if you're walking by, you can
just use the side of your foot,
clear it off from the sidewalk
side, not the street side,
be safe.
But there are
studies about this,
where there was a village
in England that had a really
significant flood event.
And they did an analysis
afterwards and said,
if we clear off this
system of storm drains,
we think that would
solve the problem.
And the next time they had
a same size weather event,
they didn't have any flooding
because they proactively
had volunteers going out and
clearing out these grates.
And you don't need special
equipment or anything.
So there's a lot we
can do individually.
And as we already
heard, we are all
or will become consumers,
voters, officials.
We are peers.
We talk to our
friends and families.
There's a lot of ways
to engage and influence.
And I'll say first, people
who are still studying,
no matter what classes you're
taking or career you go into,
you are going to have some
interaction with climate change.
Our prior speakers
were just talking
about the really
interdisciplinary nature
of studying climate change.
It's true when you're
working as well, right?
You may be working on
priorities like housing
or economic development,
biodiversity, equity.
They are all affected
by climate change,
and climate change
can affect them.
So we really need this
integrated approach,
where we look for synergies and
how we maximize our cobenefits.
If we're going to
take an action,
how do we do it in a way
that's good for climate change
and improves affordability,
and public health, and equity?
Why not go for lots of
good things at once?
But let's keep climate
change in the mix,
because it's always going
to be there and have a role.
And this is part of the
reason Governor Healey created
the Office of Climate
Resilience and Innovation
was to integrate a whole
of government approach
to climate change, to make
sure we do not accidentally
silo these issues and
really think about how
our actions interweave.
And you'll see in the
title, "innovation"
is part of the title.
That's because climate
change is a challenge.
It also presents opportunities.
And one of those is innovation.
Massachusetts has been
a leader in innovation,
and MIT is obviously
a large part of that.
Innovation is at
the heart of MIT.
So we want to look for
those opportunities.
We don't just need
to take action.
Let's make things
better at the same time.
If we're going to have
to do a lot of work,
what more can we get from it?
Let's be really creative
in what we're doing.
And again, an underlying
piece of all of this
goes back to, I
think, why we're here.
Having climate change in our DNA
of analysis and decision making
requires a lot of education,
a lot of knowledge.
And I'll just say,
on a personal level,
when I grew up in
the area, so I took
some of the middle school
and high school classes
that MIT offered before
I came to school here.
So I will add my personal
thanks to all the volunteers,
and staff, and faculty
who make these courses
and these programs possible.
It's really important.
And I really appreciate
the work everyone's doing.
And I hope, everyone
in this room
keeps moving forward
as climate activists.
So thank you, all, so much.
[APPLAUSE]
ANNOUNCER: Please
welcome Yashasvi Raj, PhD
candidate at the Center for
Climate Repair at the University
of Cambridge.
[APPLAUSE]
YASHASVI RAJ: Hi, everyone.
Hope you can hear me all right.
I want to start off
with my PhD research
by showing you this
really iconic photograph.
I'm sure, a lot of you have
already recognized this photo.
This photo is called Earthrise.
And it was taken in 1968 during
the Apollo 8 lunar mission,
by Astronaut William Anders.
And this was a really
impactful photo at the time,
because it showed our
vast and powerful Earth
as actually just a small, and
delicate, and finite planet.
And this helped realize that
we really need to protect it.
And it helped catalyze the
modern environmental movement.
At the same time
in 1968, this is
what the map of global
temperature anomalies
looked like.
And back then, our warming
was relatively moderate.
But as we fast forward
to the present day,
I'd like you to pay
attention to the redder
areas, the areas of higher
temperature anomalies.
And you can see, right at
the northern hemisphere,
especially towards the
Arctic, it's much redder.
And that's because the Arctic
is warming four times faster.
And this warming has had a
significant effect on ice cover
as well.
This is two images,
showing simulated ice
cover between 1984 and 2016.
And within about
three decades, we've
already lost about
60% of ice cover.
And not only that, I want you to
take a look at these two images
and see the shift in color.
On the left side, it's much
wider, but on the right side,
it's actually quite darker.
And if you've been outside in
the summer on the black asphalt,
you know that dark
surfaces absorb heat.
And so what's happening now
is, as the surfaces get darker,
they're absorbing
more heat, which
means that there's is more
ice melting, which means
that there's darker surfaces.
And this self-destructive
cycle is something
called arctic amplification.
And this accelerated
warming means
that we might have an ice-free
summer as soon as 2035.
And this could have
global consequences,
like sea-level rise and
extreme weather conditions.
So what can we do?
Well, already by
attending this, you're
being a more educated citizen,
a more educated voter,
leading to better
sustainability policies.
And that has curbed
our emissions.
However, in terms of the
Arctic, emissions reductions
might not be enough.
And carbon capture
and storage, these
are very important things
for the fight against climate
change, but unfortunately,
these technologies are still not
scaling fast enough.
So this is when we ask ourselves
an unconventional question--
what if we could reflect
sunlight back into to space,
as a temporary measure
to help cool the Arctic,
while solutions like
decarbonization and carbon
capture ramp up?
And this idea is called
Solar Radiation Management.
This umbrella term includes
several different techniques,
from injecting aerosols
into the stratosphere
to mimic the cooling
effect of volcanoes,
to even wackier ideas
like giant space mirrors.
But for the purposes
of this talk,
I'm going to concentrate
on this one right here,
which is based off of my PhD,
called Marine Cloud Brightening.
Now, marine cloud brightening,
the idea behind that
is, what if we could increase
the albedo or the reflectivity
of clouds?
And this could potentially
reflect sunlight back
into space as a
regional cooling.
Well, how does that work?
Well, so here, we
have a white cloud.
It reflects sunlight.
In contrast, a darker cloud
reflects less sunlight.
And the difference
between these two
is just the droplet size
within those clouds.
A white cloud is comprised
of smaller droplets,
whereas a rainy
cloud, the dark cloud
is comprised of large droplets.
And each of these droplets,
they grow on a seed.
And that seed is called a
cloud condensation nucleus.
The idea behind marine
cloud brightening
is-- what if we
could add more seeds
into existing clouds in the
form of sea salt crystals?
And we could do that
with a little ship
that sprays droplets
into an existing cloud?
And the idea is that
potentially, this
could brighten or
whiten the cloud,
increasing the solar
radiation reflection,
thus calling a local cooling.
And interestingly enough,
we've actually accidentally
been doing this already.
This is a photo of the
North Atlantic trade
routes for cargo ships.
And these white streaks
here that you see
are clouds that were formed
on tiny sulfur particles
in the exhaust of cargo ships.
So it had a cooling effect while
also increasing air pollution,
not great.
But the idea is, what if we
could do this deliberately
without the use of pollutants?
And this is where
the science comes in.
So our research has
seen that we need
the following
technology requirements,
specifically, the first two.
We need tiny, tiny particles,
30 to 500 nanometers in size.
And we need a lot of them,
10 to the 15 to 10 to the 17
of these particles per second.
Also, for scaling,
we need to make sure
that it doesn't actually
take too much power.
It needs to be robust against
environmental conditions,
because seawater is actually
quite corrosive to work with.
And also, it needs to be
scalable for potential
continental sized deployment.
So on the right
here, there's a photo
of these droplet cannons by
our collaborators in Australia
at Southern Cross University.
However, the size of droplets
that they're generating
and the rate at which
they're generating them at
is still too low.
And that's why we
need innovation.
And this is where I come in.
When I started my PhD, I
remembered what my dad actually
taught me, which was that, when
you come towards a problem,
you want to see how
nature did it first.
And nature makes sea spray as
it's the most abundant aerosol
produced in the world.
And the way it works
is that, as waves
crash over the
surface of the ocean,
it traps air, forming bubbles.
These bubbles then
burst, and they release
a wide spray of tiny droplets.
Now, these droplets
then, some large ones
will fall back to the surface,
but some of the other ones
will waft up into the
cloud layer to form clouds.
But how can we do
this deliberately?
How can we control this process?
So this is a video of
my experimental setup
at the University of Cambridge.
And what I'm able to do is use
a small rubber tubing that I
poked a bunch of holes in.
And I pass a low
compressed air through it.
And you can see in
this bottom left corner
that it's making
a lot of bubbles.
And these bubbles
are being generated
and burst right at the surface.
And this process creates a
really fine mist of droplets.
And my preliminary
research has seen that,
when testing with 3 and 1/2%
salinity or salty water,
which is roughly, the
salinity of the ocean,
I'm able to generate 10 to
the 10 particles per second,
of which, 70% of them are within
the MCB range that I described
previously.
So it's really exciting.
The one thing that
I need to work on
is improving the energy
efficiency of this.
An exciting way to do that
is actually integrating it
into an existing system called
a bubble drag reduction system.
And that's actually being
researched here at MIT,
where if you can inject
a layer of bubbles
right underneath
the helm of a ship,
you can actually reduce the
drag and reduce the fuel
costs for a cargo ship.
And this could
potentially then leave
a raft of bubbles that could
burst to brighten clouds,
or just leave it there as a
white reflective streak when
there aren't clouds to brighten.
Now, to end my talk,
I'd like to first remind
people that to be
absolutely clear,
marine cloud brightening is
not a cure to climate change.
It's not a replacement
for cutting
emissions, or decarbonization,
or ramping up clean energy.
But what it might be able
to do is buy us time,
time to scale these solutions
and slow down arctic sea level
loss.
And this is a very small part
of the larger climate action
picture.
It's controversial.
It's not perfect, but
it's a conversation
that we need to have
responsibly, ethically,
and inclusively.
And that's where
you all come in,
not just as future scientists,
but as educators and activists,
policymakers, engineers,
and informed citizens,
because climate action
isn't just about technology,
it's about collaboration
and community.
So I also want to take this
moment to congratulate all
of you for whether this is your
first step or your 100th step
in the climate space,
for attending this event
and choosing to care,
and to learn, and to act.
So as we close, I ask you
today to just carry these ideas
forward with a creativity,
and integrity, and hope.
And maybe, we'll be able
to brighten some clouds.
But more importantly,
I hope that we can
brighten the future together.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
ANNOUNCER: Please
welcome Jaylen Brown
of the Boston Celtics and
Media Lab Director's fellow.
[APPLAUSE]
JAYLEN BROWN: This work?
Does this work?
Can you hear me?
Good evening, everyone.
Today, we're here to
talk about something that
affects us all, climate change.
Today marks a very
pivotal moment in time.
The decisions that we
make now have an impact
on future generations.
Climate change isn't just
an environmentalism issue,
it's a social justice issue,
it's an economic issue,
and it's also a
moral imperative.
As someone who prides himself
on influence and responsibility,
what an honor it is to be
here to talk about this topic.
MIT, thank you for having me.
[APPLAUSE]
Today, we're going to talk about
the crossover and intersection
between environmentalism,
social justice, and education,
in combination with raising
awareness, leveraging
your platform and influence,
and investing in the sustainable
future.
But let me be clear.
I think we're in a
little bit of a crisis.
This isn't just fiction,
this is reality.
This isn't TikTok.
And some of these things
are happening on our watch.
I was taught that the justice
of all human well-being
is all encompassing.
My grandmother taught me
the importance of education.
She also taught me the
importance of recycling.
She would get upset
if I threw my water
bottles in the wrong trash.
And she also made me pick up
trash on our walks to the park.
As a seven-year-old,
I would question her,
but this had an
impact on my journey.
She also had a garden,
where metaphorically, I
learned to plant seeds
and nourish the soil.
This also had an impact
on my journey, which
led me to communities and
organizations such as habitat
for humanity, where I
was joined by a bunch
of other young
people, just like you
all, who had a passion
for climate change.
And now, I'm here at the
Day of Climate event at MIT,
speaking about the effects
of environmentalism.
And I hope, I'm making
my grandmother proud.
Thank you.
I'm all for it.
[APPLAUSE]
One of the more concerning
effects of climate change
is the weather patterns--
floods, droughts, heat waves are
all examples of these events.
These events put pressure on the
infrastructure of our community,
the infrastructure
of our society,
the infrastructure of our
economic and health systems.
And they make vulnerable
populations a little bit more
vulnerable, who necessarily
don't have the chance
to defend themselves.
This is inequity.
This is a call to action for
all of us and a major concern.
I believe that
environmentalism and climate
change isn't just something
that we should think about.
It's also an evolution
of our thought process,
from serving our ecosystems
to helping our ecosystems,
from the understanding of
footprint to the embracing
of your soul print, the
concerns, the consequences
of greed and capitalism.
From the products
we use to the rivers
we poison, my
question is, globally,
is it clean energy if we
leave dirty footprints?
Education and awareness is key.
A lot of people have a hard time
seeing that climate change is
affecting our day to day lives.
They see it as
something distant.
But the reality is that climate
change is already here--
our air, our oceans, our forests
are already being compromised.
These aren't just
social media events.
We've already seen the fires
in California to the Hurricanes
in the Caribbean.
Education and
preparation is key.
The disruption of ecosystems
and environments are imminent.
And as a society,
because of the awareness,
I believe that we
are ill-prepared.
But I'm optimistic,
because education
has the power to transform
societies, it always has.
It's no coincidence
that the solutions
to environmental
problems and challenges
come from places like this.
And young people and young
minds like you all here today.
This year, I had the pleasure of
meeting one of my heroes, Bill
Nye, the Science Guy.
[LAUGHTER]
[APPLAUSE]
Shout out to Bill.
Bill made science accessible and
exciting through his platform.
Through my platform,
I aim to do the same.
He inspired a generation
to care about science,
and environmentalism,
and physics,
all while indulging
in dad jokes.
[LAUGHTER]
I think this generation
needs more of that-- more
learning, more inspiration,
more action, more desire, more
solution-based thinking.
As an athlete, I've
been able to travel all
over the world, meeting
people of all walks of life,
experiencing the
beauty of our planet.
And I've already seen,
through my travels,
the evidence that our
changing world is here.
The science is real--
human activity,
the burning of fossil
fuels, deforestation,
the greenhouse gases that
affect our atmosphere,
leading to a warmer planet.
Has anybody ever had a fever?
What happens when
you have a fever?
The body heats up.
What does that tell you?
What does that mean
when the body heats up?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
JAYLEN BROWN: It's
trying to heal.
Now, Earth is heating up.
It releases water.
It receives storms, floods,
rising tides, unseasonal rains,
all examples of the
Earth responding,
trying to cool itself
down, attempting to heal,
no different.
I take responsibility
on the court.
I believe, we all should
take responsibility
of our environment, through
strategy, through teamwork,
through sacrifice.
I think this is essential.
I want everybody
to close your eyes.
Imagine that we're all on
the same team, same arena,
same jerseys, and the
game is on the line.
Now, think about this.
We're not just
playing for ourselves,
we're playing for
the next generation.
Open your eyes.
Who is willing to do
what it takes to win?
To invest is not just monetary.
Investing is time, effort,
energy, and resources.
We need to invest in
sustainable communities.
We need to invest
in clean technology.
We also need to invest
in education that fosters
environmental stewardship.
To invest in our
environment is an investment
in us, to young people, to young
minds who may be listening.
When you dream about
your future, dream
about a future that brings
harmony and balance with Earth,
to the jobs you choose, to the
foods you eat, to the energy
you invest.
Think about how you can
bring harmony to our planet
rather than taking or
extracting from it.
Our Earth is at risk.
She is slowly being
taken advantage of.
And the people
responsible have names,
have companies, have
incentives, have egos.
This is the city of champions.
Right?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
[APPLAUSE]
JAYLEN BROWN: So I
think we should all
take responsibility and
carry a championship
mindset in our environment.
It starts with us.
And we can start a global
movement in the future.
Nicholas Negroponte, a
name that some of you guys
will be familiar with here at
MIT, his vision with the MIT
Media Lab was to create
an environment, where
a bunch of collective minds
and subjects can work together.
Change doesn't
come from one plan,
one person, one initiative.
It comes from a host of people,
all working together in unison.
So when I look into the crowd,
that's what I see here today.
If you haven't gotten
involved in your community
and your environment,
this speech is your cue.
I want to see a movement
for climate action.
It's not about just
us, it's about securing
a safe and livable future
for the next generation.
We have the power.
We have the resources.
We have the intelligence.
Do we have the willpower?
Do we have the desire?
Do we have the
foresight in order
to secure a livable future
for the next generation?
In closing, the fight
for climate change
is a response for justice.
It is a urgency for
the next generation.
It is a preparation
for communities
who are ill-prepared.
And it is an insistence
for us and our values
that we hold as human beings.
Let's stand together,
united in our purpose,
with unwavering commitment.
The time to act is now.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Please welcome Cynthia Breazeal,
dean of Digital Learning,
and professor of Media,
Arts, and Sciences.
[APPLAUSE]
CYNTHIA BREAZEAL: All right.
What an amazing day.
What an amazing event.
I am Cynthia Breazeal.
I am the final speaker in
this part of the program.
And it is my privilege and my
honor to help bring us together
as a community to really
express our gratitude
and appreciation for everyone
who was involved in making
this event possible today,
through your participation,
and all the people who do
the work behind the scenes
to make the day of
climate program possible.
So whereas everybody,
you've been
such an awesome, quiet,
attentive audience,
in my remarks, I want you
to make a lot of noise.
[CHEERING AND APPLAUSE]
All right.
So, I mean, first,
we really have
to give Claudia Urrea, the
pK-12 team, and Open Learning
a huge round of applause for
the tremendous amount of work
that they've done.
And our faculty advisors--
Eric Klopfer, Peter
Senge, and Pawan Sinha
for their advice and
guidance through the creation
and the execution
of this program.
I want to thank the Climate
Action Through Education,
the CATE team, and
the Boston Earth Day
team, who also contributed to
the organization of today's
event.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
A huge thank you to Michael
John Gorman and the MIT Museum.
What a perfect venue
for this event.
Beautiful space.
Thank you so much
for hosting us.
[APPLAUSE]
And I want to express our
deep, warm appreciation
for the generous support from
Dirk and Charlene Kabcenell
as well for helping to create
the Day of Climate program.
[APPLAUSE]
All right.
So some of you may know,
some of you may not know,
but MIT is actually quite
passionate about K-12 education.
So when we have this concept
of the Day of Climate Program,
we wanted to get
curriculum, as we've
said from Chris
Knittel, world class,
innovative, free curriculum.
We ran what's called an RFP or
Request For Proposal process.
We basically sent out to the
whole MIT community, saying,
hey, we want to start to
create terrific curriculum
that teachers can teach
in K-12 classrooms,
to students from elementary to
middle school or high school.
Would you like to
contribute materials?
And MIT answered the
call across all of MIT.
And so I just want to give you
a sense of just the breadth
and the range of curriculum
that MIT did just this year
for this program.
OK.
So just to put this
into perspective.
CATE contributed
curriculum on topics
such as industrial
revolution and climate
change for middle school,
climate and renewable
energy, and the impact of
population growth on climate,
the MIT App Inventor team
contributed curriculum
for elementary school students,
and upwards on water ecosystems
and climate change.
The MIT Edgerton
Center contributed
to curriculum for
middle school students
on coastal climate science.
The School of Architecture
contributed curriculum
on the impact of construction
on carbon emissions
and climate-resilient
future buildings.
The MIT Environmental
Solutions Initiative
developed a curriculum on urban
heat islands, climate justice,
geothermal energy networks,
and curriculum for high school.
The day of AI
contributed curriculum
on data science AI and climate.
And our Cambridge Public School
collaborators and the PLIX team
contributed curriculum
on cube satellites
for exploring outer space
environment and urban ecology
for elementary students and up.
So just an amazing
range of curriculum.
So again, let's put
our hands together.
[APPLAUSE]
In one year, and we're
just getting started,
world class, free,
innovative curriculum.
So we had an amazing
lineup of speakers.
So again, let's just thank Chris
Knittel, Pete Bouchard, Yashasvi
Raj, and Jaylen Brown, and
Aladdine Joroff, who just shared
phenomenal presentations.
Thank you all so much.
[APPLAUSE]
I want to thank those
who participated
in our grantee showcase.
And we had this terrific
learners and educators
panel led by Margaret Wang.
Thank you, Margaret,
for leading that panel.
[APPLAUSE]
And of course, we heard
for our true stars,
who are our K-12 students and
educators, who presented really
exciting projects here as well.
You are the stars, and
you are the future,
so we really want to
celebrate and honor
your contributions for today.
So thank you for all the
students and teachers
who are here,
presenting their work,
their ideas, their passion.
Really phenomenal.
Really, really phenomenal.
You're really showing us how you
can make such a big difference
from these high-quality
educational content,
combined with the passion of
K-12 educators and our students.
And it's just been truly
inspiring to witness
how our whole community came
together today and demonstrated
the power of
collaboration and advocacy
in driving meaningful change.
So as we conclude, let's just
remember the significance
of empowering K-12
learners and educators,
with the tools and knowledge
to tackle climate change,
the connections and insights
gained here today are really
just the beginning.
We encourage everyone to
continue their efforts
in their communities, leveraging
what we've learned today
to make a positive impact.
So please stay engaged
with Day of Climate at MIT.
And explore further
opportunities
for collaboration and learning.
And together, we really
have the collective power
to create a sustainable
and resilient future.
So thank you so much.
[APPLAUSE]
So the Day of Climate at MIT
was put forth by the larger MIT
pK-12 initiative.
It's a brand new
initiative at MIT.
I think you're
going to be hearing
a lot of exciting work
being done by this group.
And we're going to have some
really exciting workshops next.
So I'll invite Claudia to
tell you a little bit more
about them.
Again, Thank you all.
[APPLAUSE]
CLAUDIA URREA: Awesome.
Thank you so much, Cynthia.
I want to invite the
speakers also to the front.
We have a little gift for you.
But we have three workshops that
are going to happen from 6:30
to 7:00.
We also have appetizers,
and drinks, and social.
So I welcome you to that.
We have inroads in this space.
We have map works IN one of
the workshops in the beginning.
And then we do have a
climate change in solar,
no, IN wind turbines, right?
So wind turbines.
So one of the
educators from CATE
is going to run, also,
a workshop for us.
So don't miss the
opportunity to work
with those educators
in this 30 minutes,
and continue this
excitement work.
[APPLAUSE]
Speakers.