warm welcome to Bangkok and the
opportunity to speak with you today and
tell you about our company which is a
novel application of AI in the in the
realm of financial
technology um my name is unus Sim I'm
the CTO and co-founder of almond fintech
at almond we are developing the the new
standard for how money moves
globally what started that MIT SL years
ago um turned into a team of 30 diverse
and highly motivated
people we are driven by solving one big
problem that is the global funds
transfer system is broken on average it
takes 6% in fees to move money A to B
that means if you send $100 the
recipient only receives
94 furthermore due to the the banking
holidays and the business hours it often
takes one or two business days for your
money to reach its recipient this is not
only a problem for the individuals but
also for millions of companies that rely
on paying their overseas suppliers or
partners and the the counterparty and
foreign exchange risks that are
prevalent in these transactions are
often baked in to the economics so the
costs are even
higher this is how the the traditional
uh crossb Finance flow currently works
when you send money from one country to
another let's say from the US to
Thailand your money hops through
multiple financial institutions
including one or more intermediaries
along the way each hop adds cost and
delays as well as uh unreliability into
the
system in comparison this is the novel
almond uh transfer protocol that we have
developed instead of using intermediary
manag institutions we route each
transfer through a series of uh crypto
exchanges this network of crypto
exchanges is monitored and analyzed by
almond and we identify the best route
through a series of exchanges and
cryptocurrencies to optimize the route
in order to reduce the cost and the
delay for each individual
transfer looking under the hood our
system ingests a lot lot of data um
mainly the the volatilities of the
crypto and the Fiat currencies that we
use as well as the forecasted rates and
fees we also take into account the
demand projections from our partners we
use AI algorithms to uh process this
data and in return get an optimized
route and the optimized time for each
individual transfer across the 100 plus
cryptocurrencies that we work with and
the 12 crypto exchanges each individual
transfer takes the optimal route from A
to B in order to reduce the cost and the
delay and we pass on those benefits to
our
partners so that's enough Theory let's
look at a real example I just pulled
this data yesterday this is uh January
20th um if you were to send money from
the US to Thailand yesterday and went to
wise or Bank of America the rates you
would see would be
34.2 um and 32 3 3.2 um
respectively if you were to do the same
operation through almond
yesterday the rate you would see is
36.99 almost
37 this corresponds to over a 6%
improvement over the rate of our closest
competitors if you were to send $100,000
this results in over 200,000 um bot in
savings these are the savings that
almond shares with its
customers I must admit yesterday was a
spectacular day on average uh across the
last 30 days our price Advantage is
close to 2% over our closest comparator
and again if you were to send $100,000
each time your savings come up to around
75,000
BT in addition to our rate Advantage um
our value proposition also includes 24 7
availability um this is because
blockchain is fast faster than
traditional Financial rails and also our
crypto exchanges unlike Banks don't have
banking hours they don't sleep they
don't have holidays so we can send money
any day of the year any time of the year
uh in near real time and by making the
settlements just in time and limiting
the delays as much as possible we thus
reduce the foreign exchange and the
counterparty risk associated with
traditional
finance a quick case study we are
working with a global um credit card
payment company um on a pilot between
the US and Brazil over the last quarter
we moved
$800,000 in the same Corridor uh and
over overall we saved on average eight
basis points net to our partner and each
transfer vast majority of our transfers
took less than five
minutes um taking a step back uh this is
our Global traction last year we have
moved $8.8 million across 10 countries
our Network includes 12 exchanges and 19
customers uh we offer rates across 30 30
uh Fiat Pairs and over 100
cryptocurrency
exchanges and finally most importantly
uh Thailand is Thailand poses a very
significant opportunity for us we are
already in talks with B's regulator
sandbox program we are working with bitb
uh as one of our exchanges in our
Network we have demonstrated transfers
between Singapore and Thailand as well
as the US and Thailand and we are
looking for Partnerships with
International companies for funds
transfers between Thailand aan and
Americas if you're interested in working
together or just want to learn more I
will be happy to talk to you outside
over email thank you for this
opportunity thank you
[Music]