Awesome. Thank you all uh and thanks for
the introduction. So I'm really uh
excited to be able to talk to you all
about some of the work that's happening
in my group uh in visualization at
CESAL. And this is uh work that that a
lot of different folks in my group have
contributed to over the years um as well
as a project that the CIRC seed grant
helped support. So I want to start by
sort of casting our minds back to the
pandemic era, right? Um we might
remember being inundated with
visualizations, right? The flatten the
curve chart went viral. Ironically, not
actually a visualization. It was not
showing any data, but nevertheless, uh,
you know, really bolstered a bunch of
change at a societal level we'd never
seen before. I think many of us were
sort of frantically checking these kinds
of dashboards, right? the John's Hopkins
one or uh you know our local state
government websites and then the front
pages of most major news publications
were plastered with sort of wall-to-wall
coverage of charts uh tracking a variety
of different metrics from you know case
rates to death rates to vaccination
rates when we had those um and these
visualizations became such a part of the
mainstream that they were even me right
so here obviously is the reason that
some countries did better with the
pandemic than others, right? Like how
much bubble tea were we drinking as a
society? And so as a result of sort of
this outpouring of visualizations, you
know, lots of folks thought that this
was data visualizations breakthrough
moment, right? Uh the folks who were
producing some of these charts um you
know, were interviewed in in
high-profile publications like here is
John Burns Murdoch um an incredible
graphics editor at the Financial Times.
Um, you might remember, you know, these
charts with an orange background that I
feel like were at least everywhere on my
social media feed. Uh, but sort of in
parallel to this glowing coverage was,
uh, you know, a set of experiences that
people were having that is really well
encapsulated by this tweet from Chanse
Fleet who is a, uh, blind technologist,
uh, and researcher um, uh, who works at
the New York Public Library. So Chansy
writes that today she uh you know read
the alternative text for a chart on a
local news site. Um and that all text
suggested that in New York City the
COVID case count had been steadily
declining since April 20 uh the April
26th. Um and that that trend was
continuing. And she thought well that
can't be right. Um and so what Chanse
did was emboss the graphic and confirmed
that actually you know the alt text was
wrong. And the reason that the alt text
was wrong was you know in this case um
the person who had written the article
had just sort of copied and pasted some
boilerplate uh text to describe the
chart um not necessarily double-checking
the facts. Um and and Chanse was not
necessarily alone in this experience,
right? Uh there are by by some estimates
from from the National Federation for
the Blind and and this is pretty dated.
This is from 2016. There are about seven
million people in the United States. So
about 2% of our population that has some
form of visual disability. And and
according to these estimates at least,
visual disabilities refer to folks who
either experience total vision loss or
some pretty serious form of vision loss
such that even wearing glasses or
contact lenses, you know, doesn't fully
correct them to 2020 vision. Um, and
this is also a good moment to just sort
of like pause and and think about, you
know, how we actually think about
disability more generally. So, typically
scholars think uh, you know, there are
essentially two models of disability.
The first is what what people refer to
as the medical model of disability. The
idea that, you know, being disabled
suggests that there's something wrong
with your mind or your body. Um and and
the critique of this approach is that it
often focuses on designing technologies
and interventions that are focused at
the level of the individual person,
right? Where often the goal is kind of
implicitly to fix the thing that is
wrong with um the person's body. And I
you know I really like this description
of what those sorts of technological
interventions uh produce. So Liz Jackson
is an disability rights activist and she
calls these sort of interventions
disability dongles, right? Um I don't
necessarily have a very positive
affinity with my dongles. I think all of
us who have Macs, uh you know, probably
have a whole tray of different dongles
that we have to kind of juggle, right?
Um it's a well-intended, um elegant
even, yet nevertheless useless solution
to a problem that disabled people never
even knew that they had. And so in
contrast to the medical model um you
know there's a social model of
disability that considers people to be
rendered disabled because of choices um
and decisions that society has made. In
essence, you know, people who with
disabilities are not having their needs
met. And so this this approach
recognizes that essentially all
technology is assistive in some way,
right? So, I particularly like this
chart from uh Microsoft's inclusive
design toolkit because it not only sort
of surveys all the different senses
along which um you know someone might be
disabled but notes that disability
doesn't have to be a permanent sort of
uh state, right? It can be temporary or
even situational as in the case of a new
parent or a distracted driver. And so,
as a result, the social model tries to
make interventions at the level of
infrastructure rather than the
individual. Right? So what do I mean by
infrastructure? Well, a very commonly
used piece of infrastructure
particularly by people who are blind or
have low vision is something called a
screen reader. So screen readers are
built into most modern operating
systems. It's on Mac OS, iOS, um most
modern browsers even have uh plugins for
them. And essentially like the name
suggests a screen reader narrates
oncreen content. So I want to show you a
quick demo um from my postoc Jonathan
Zong who's been leading uh all of this
work in my group for a few years about
how a screen reader works. A screen
reader is an assisted technology that
narrates oncreen elements as speech. The
software provides a cursor which is
shown visually on the screen as a black
rectangle and a user can use keyboard
shortcuts to move that cursor and
highlight different elements to be read
out. I'll demonstrate that with my
keyboard now. Visited link heading level
one. Hi, we're the MIT visualization
group. Visited link home space visited
link publications space visit visited
visited link image CSI logo heading
level one rich screen reader experiences
for accessible data visualization.
So you'll notice that the narration was
actually pretty fast, right? Um but what
I what what Jonathan did there was
actually slow the speed of the narration
way way down because we imagine that
most folks in this room aren't um you
know used to to uh uh this kind of
technology. that actually proficient
screen meter users have that speed, you
know, sped all the way up. Um, and so
what does it look like when a screen
meter user experiences a visualization?
Let's take a look.
Joe Biden image 306. Joe Biden Camala
Harris Donald Trump image 232. Donald
Trump, Mike Pence. One votes. One votes.
20 votes. Four votes. Two votes. 11
votes. 10 votes. 10 votes. 16 votes. Six
votes. 14 votes. Four votes. Five votes.
29 votes. Four votes. Seven votes. 20
votes. Three votes. 13 votes. 12 votes.
10 votes. 11 votes. Nine votes. 55
votes. Seven votes. Three votes. 16
votes. Three votes. 29 votes. Six votes.
Nine votes. Three votes. Three votes.
Five votes. Six votes. 38 votes. 11
votes. Three votes. Nine votes. 18
votes. Seven votes. Three votes. 15
votes. Two votes. Three votes. 10 votes.
Six votes. Eight votes. Eight votes. 11
votes. Six votes. Six votes. Four votes.
One votes. One votes. One votes.
81,283,495 votes.
581,283,495 votes. 51.4%. Group. 270
needed to win.
74,223,755 votes, 46.9%.
So notice that, you know, it read out
that whole string of essentially
nonsense, right? Um but the person who
made this video, Sarah Fosheim, she
wasn't actually tabbing around, right?
Her cursor was actually on the same node
for that entire, you know, minute and a
half long video. Um and here, you know,
this is actually a pretty good
experience if you can imagine that. Here
is often what happens with most
visualizations.
Image image image
image image one face image logo other
image image logo other image. And so we
kind of get the point, right? But I
often like to let these videos play
through because I want us to have a
really visceral experience of how
frustrating
the experience of using the internet
with a screen reader can be for folks,
right? I think for us it's kind of
amusing because this is just a cute one
minute video and a talk, but imagine if
the internet was a series of images just
being narrated out to you like this,
right? incredibly incredibly not just
frustrating, but you're locked out of a
pretty key information modality, right?
How many of us were making decisions
about whether we should go out or not in
the pandemic and you would be locked out
of that modality entirely and just hear
image image image. And so the challenge
with uh you know uh v uh representing
visualizations in this way is that as
you're noticing right the pattern of of
reading things out has to be linearized
for a visualization but all of us
probably read visualizations in lots of
different ways. Some of us might look at
the title first maybe look at some other
textual annotations. Others of us might
look at the trend that um uh the
visualization is is trying to convey.
And so part of the challenge uh with
with visualizations currently is that
the current best practices don't
represent that diversity very well. Um
at most, you know, you might get a piece
of alternative text like this that tries
to summarize the chart um and then gives
you a link to a data table uh for
further sort of analysis. And when we
talked to to blind people about this,
you know, they they talked about how
they felt like they were at the mercy of
the all text writers who made
assumptions about what sorts of intra uh
data they would be interested in. You
know, another person said that I would
like to have time and space to interpret
the numbers for themselves. Right? Blind
people want a sense of agency um and to
feel like they're in control of their
experiences. On the other hand, you
know, I'm sure none of us would want to
actually page through a whole data table
to understand who won the election,
right? There's 393 rows. I would never
scroll through all of it. Um, and
because everything is being read out
linearly, you have to sort of hold all
of this information in your head to have
any sort of ability to to sort of make
some insightful observation. And so
instead of this very linear structure,
my students and I, you know, have been
thinking about a much more hierarchical
textoriented way of depicting uh
visualiza, you know, visualized data um
to screen readers. And the way to think
about this hierarchy is at the the sort
of topmost level, you get some sort of
summary of the chart, right? So a
scatter plot with some data along the
x-axis, some other data along the y-
axis. And then with the down arrow key,
you can essentially descend into
different levels of these hierarchies
based on visual properties like the
x-axis, the y-axis, so on and so forth.
And you can keep drilling down into this
chart again, continuing to make use of
visual affordances like the major axis
ticks, the minor access ticks, and so on
and so forth. So let's take a a look at
an example of what this looks like.
Let's say I'm using a screen reader and
I encounter the scatter plot on a page
with Ali. At first I'll hear an overall
description of what the scatter plot is.
A scatter plot with axi slipper length
mm and body mass g. Let's say I want
more detail about the scatter plot. So I
can press the down arrow key and expand
this structure to the next level where I
can get information about the different
axes and legends of the chart. X-axis
titled flipper length. mm for a
quantitative scale with values from 172
to 231. And once I'm on this level, I
can press the left and right arrow keys
to cycle through the other elements on
this level. Y-axis titled body mass G
for legend titled species for let's say
that I'm interested in getting more
detail about the X-axis. So I can
navigate back over to the X-axis with
the left arrow key and then press down
again to descend into a further level of
detail. Yaxis titled Xaxis. and down
arrow to expand. One of seven flipper
length mm is between 172 and 180. Seven
values. Press t to open table. And on
this level I get information about the
intervals along each axis. Two of seven
flipper length mm is between 180 and
190. Three of seven. Flip four of seven.
Five of seven. Six of seven. Seven of
seven. I'm going to demonstrate here an
alternate navigation technique that
we're calling spatial navigation. So I'm
going to use the WD keys to move along
the grid of the scatter plot. Five data
values in the interval body mass g 2500
300 flipper length mm
180,190 60 data values in the interval
body mass g 79 data values in the in 10
data values in the interval 25 data
values in the in 32 data values in zero
data three data values in the 23 data
values in the interval body map 30 data
values in the inter body so here by
moving around the grid I'm able to build
more of a mental picture of how the data
values are distributed spatially and so
you can see you know we've taken that
idea of alternative text and made it a
much more sort of dynamic experience
Right? Folks can drill down into
different levels of detail. They can
move around a scatter plot almost like
they would with their fingers on sort of
a tactile graphic. But one of the things
you might notice is all the textual
descriptions right now, they're kind of
bog standard, right? There's not a lot
of richness or or particularly
insightful things. And you couldn't
expect any human visualization designer
to sit there and enumerate, you know,
every sort of interesting thing in this
huge sort of space. So this is sort of
almost a perfect opportunity to
intervene with some generative AI to
think about, you know, what richer
textual descriptions of visualizations
might look like. So here I'll I'll turn
things over to Isabella Padraza Pieros
who's been exploring this um work as
part of her master's
thesis. In this version of Ali, we've
added something called data highlights.
And if I navigate into the data
highlights by pressing the down arrow
key, it's going to show us semantically
meaningful groupings of data that we've
generated through calls to chat.
GPT data highlights for highlights. One
of four efficient foragers. This group
combines midsized flipper lengths with a
healthy body mass, indicating penguins
that have adapted well to a range of
environments, being able to swiftly
navigate open waters while also capable
of agility. A combination suited for
efficient foraging. Flipper length mm is
between 191 and 210 in body mass G is
between 3,3001 and 4385 values. Press T
to open table. Select. So in that
description, we heard about a grouping
called efficient foragers. And the
system provided some reasoning about how
certain values of flipper length and
body mass might indicate that certain
penguins are part of this group. And if
you look over at the
visualization, you can actually see the
visual representation of this efficient
foragers grouping that we've highlighted
to draw an analyst's attention to this
grouping of data. We can also explore to
find more about other data highlights.
Two of four, three of four. Antarctic
marathoners. Long flipper lengths paired
with a robust or athletic body mass may
indicate penguins that are specialized
for endurance swimming in Antarctic
conditions capable of long-distance
hunting in open waters. Flipper length
mm is between 211 and 235 and body mass
G is between 43001 and 6,400 96 values.
Press T to open table.
I mean I love the the titles that you
know Chachi PT is giving to these
different kinds of penguins, right?
Antarctic marathoners. Um and turns out
so did uh user you know participants in
our user studies. So, you know, one
person said that they really appreciated
being able to drill up and down these
different layers in the grid because it
gave them a really different way of
thinking about, you know, data and
visualization. Some of our participants,
you know, all of whom were blind. Um,
some of them said that, you know, with
our system, this was the first time they
actually understood what a scatter plot
was showing. Um, you know, they never
really understood what a scatter plot
was. And that was kind of a really
special moment. Um, you know, another
person told us that they were able to
think much more in spatial terms, right?
Um, I'm moving up and through the grid.
I'm I'm drilling down just to that
square to get some particular
information. Um, you know, another
person mentioned how things like the
data highlights gave, you know, it
boosted their sense of confidence,
right? Their their ability to actually
think in terms of the data. Um, and a
final person, you know, said that it
made them even much more interested in
exploring the data. that open their
minds to particular kinds of insights or
trends that could be unlocked through
the data. Um, and so we've released uh
this toolkit um you know as an open
source project uh called Ali. Um these
LLM extensions will be coming soon. Uh
and with that I'm I'm very happy to take
all your questions. Thanks very much.
[Applause]
Thank you very much. Servin questions.
Hi, thank you so much for this talk.
Absolutely. Um I was wondering uh
because these uh large language models
are prone to for example
hallucinations where they uh create
false data or maybe describe things in a
way that is not intended. if there was
any sort of metrics or ways in which you
decided to go about that or to combat
against that. Yeah, absolutely. So, one
of the ways that you know we produce
those statements uh with chatgpt is we
give it the context of the data that
it's looking at. Um so we're not we're
not sort of you know prompting it with
with no guidance whatsoever. Uh the fact
that you know we provide that data often
kind of constrains its generation. Yeah.
That's not to say, you know, there's no
chance of it hallucinating. Um, but at
least that that captures sort of a broad
bucket of them. Yeah.
Okay. Further questions.
Oh, right here.
Um, thank you so much for your talk. I
was also just wondering expanding on
like metrics for accuracy. Are you doing
any validation to assess how accurate
the model is or like um prevent any
hallucinations from happening? Yeah,
absolutely. So, um we haven't yet, but
it's certainly something on our uh on
our agenda. And so right now, one of the
things we're sort of curious about is,
you know, when do like how should the
text be worded to prompt the user to
actually consider verifying or
validating? Um, so are there different
ways that that a particular description
could be worded to, you know, encourage
someone to verify or validate it? Um,
when, you know, do they want that sort
of verification, validation, um, things
like that. Yeah. Thank you.
Um just thinking uh one can imagine
giving the user the ability to instruct
um with verbal instructions that are
somewhat flexible. Have you considered
that as well? Yeah. So, that's a really
great question because um you know, one
of the interesting things about
visualization is often we use it to ask
questions we don't even know we have,
right? Um and so a lot of the use of
visualization is often more for
discovery and sort of serendipity and
and things like that where you almost
don't know what it is you're looking
for. So, you wouldn't know how to sort
of formulate the question. Um, and so
that's why we focused on these sorts of
of use cases where we're trying to use
generative AI to sort of, you know,
accelerate that that knowledge discovery
process. You could certainly imagine,
you know, augmenting this interface
with, you know, some sort of Q&A panel
or something like that. Certainly. Yeah.
I was wondering what's the main
demographic that's testing
uh because I feel like that would affect
the way they perceive things. Yeah.
Yeah. So, the main demographic we we've
been testing with are are sort of
full-time screen meter users. Um, so
they're folks who, you know, use screen
meters day in and day out because they
have some form of fairly serious visual
disability. Um, most of our folks were
were fully blind. Um, but some fair
portion of them have some kind of low
vision. So, they use, you know, screen
magnification alongside a screen reader
or things like that. Yeah.
kind of coming off of that question,
um did you look at like like their maybe
like their the various the people's like
education levels and ability to
interpret like just since it's about
interpreting data like are they I feel
like that has a lot to do that can vary.
Absolutely. So we we had a pretty
diverse range of sort of familiarity and
experience with data. um we had a you
know a handful of folks who do
professional data work um as well as you
know folks who don't use it at all um
and so I think those final two quotes
were from folks who had you know much
more minimal experience and familiarity
with data um so that's why you know it
gave them a a boost in confidence it
increased their interest in engaging
with data because they're the set of
folks who would not be sort of thrilled
to just have a link to you know the raw
CSV and and sort of like move through
the table, right? Um, but on on the flip
side, they also aren't satisfied just
being told like here's the alt text,
like here's what the the summary of the
chart is, right? So, it's it's trying to
meet those people where they are in
terms of their data needs as well. Yeah.