Hello everyone. My name is Jack Louu and
I'm the CPO and co-founder of
Tristarai. So my co-founder, he grew up
spending a lot of time at his dad's
plastic manufacturing plant. He he
distinctly remembers the noise, the
smell of melting resin, and more
importantly, his dad constantly running
around trying to solve issues with his
production. His dad was able to solve
this through instinct, through
experience, and honestly just good
old-fashioned hustle.
But he always thought and he always told
Seem, my co-founder, that if there was a
way for him to see what was happening on
his production floor in real time
instead of trying to solve problems
after, that would be a game changer. And
that's what stuck with us and
um how we based our company on. So um as
we found out as we went to the industry
um he wasn't the only problem with this
uh only only person with this problem
right and after years at MIT and at auto
manufacturing plants we saw that this uh
most people still operate on making
decisions on a bad or incomplete
feedback cycle and just lack of
information and um and this gap in
information is kind of what cost these
companies billions s in lost uh
production in scrap and just general
inefficiencies and uh that's what we aim
to
tackle. So uh basically uh the idea is
that we try to fill this gap of
information by understanding the the uh
lack the biggest lack which is the human
element of any production cycle. uh
there's no real good in a way to get
that information other than
self-reporting which is just inherently
unreliable and what drives these uh gaps
of
misinformation. Uh at the end of the day
um we come in uh we install our vision
system and we put we use that to inspect
the production line. We understand that
the entire production process um and if
any of the operators kind of go outside
of the standard operating procedure,
we're able to flag that uh give the
instant alert to the operator and that
gives the opportunity to fix that in
real time instead of trying to go back
and resolve it after.
Um and so the the underlaying technology
behind this uh this monitoring system is
that we essentially have these action
building blocks. Um and in a way you can
think of it as Legos where we understand
these complex motions through basic
movement and being able to restitch that
in a different combination to detect
other complex actions. And that's how
we're able to map it directly over to
their production process and the
production cycle.
Um and um and because of this like
uh mix of smaller or more basic movement
blocks that we can assemble it into uh
fit it to any uh application uh in uh
any kind of environment.
Um, so in in one of our plastic plants,
as you can imagine, that's where we
started, uh, based on my co-founder's
dad, uh, we we found that we were able
to reduce the, uh, defective and scrap
rate by over 60% in over just a month
by, uh, allowing them to react in real
time instead of going back and fixing
things. And uh in another one of our
customers that makes uh auto radiators,
they're essentially every time we catch
a defect as it's happening, they're
saving tens of thousands in lost
production in scrap. And not only that,
you're saving them essentially over 10
hours of rework. As you can imagine,
anything that you build incorrectly, you
have to unbuild and then rebuild. So
that basically triples your production
time for each of those parts.
Um, and more importantly, I I think more
than just that, we're helping the
engineers and the operators have more
visibility. They don't feel like they're
flying blind when they're uh doing their
shifts day day in day out. And it gives
them a tool that makes their lives a lot
easier because it's a second pair of
eyes and it allows them to resolve
things without feeling the effects of
incorrectly doing something later on.
Um, at the end of the day, I I think
like our
fundamental drive for what we're
building is that we're trying to build
something that I think our co-founders
would have loved to have. You know,
these people, they don't care about
computer vision. They don't care about
cameras. They don't care about
algorithms. What they want is ability to
react in real time and full visibility
in what's happening on their plan 4. And
at the end of the day, it's it's just
about making manufacturing smarter,
leaner, and uh more agile and resilient
to, you know, everything that's going on
in the world. And uh so all I ask of you
is if you think this application or this
technology can improve uh things at your
company, please come and speak to us and
we'll love to have a conversation. Thank
you very much.