the gex portal provides an API for
accessing gex data this tutorial will
demonstrate how to use the gex API to
retrieve gene expression Data before
using the gex API you should think about
your use case and carefully consider
whether the GX API is suitable for your
application the gex API is not meant for
high 3w applications for example if if
you need to perform a computation for
all 56,000 genes you might be better
served by downloading the needed data
files from the gex portal and either
Computing on those files directly or
loading the data from those files into
your own local database performing
56,000 round trips to our API server
would probably not be
performant the gex API is called via a
URL which returns data in Json format
you can query the gex web services by
submitting your url via a browser or a
scripting language of your choice any
scripting language can directly parse
Json formatted
data we can think of the URL as having
two main
portions the base URL which identifies
the web service and then the
parameters in the G Tex portal most of
the web services take query
parameters which have two parts the the
query parameter name and then the query
parameter
value the delimiter in front of the
first query parameter is a question mark
the delimiter for subsequent query
parameters is an
aent let's use the GX API to retrieve
gene expression data
you can find a link to the API
documentation on the gex portal select
documentation API for data access and
then the link for the gex API
V2 as you can see the documentation for
the web services are separated into
groups we want to retrieve gene
expression data so we will Ex we will
select expression data endpoints
get gene
expression if we look in the upper right
corner of the page we can see the base
URL for the endpoint so we will copy
that and in the center pane we can see
the documentation for the query
parameters for the gene expression web
service we can see that the Gen code ID
is a required
parameter so let's construct the UR Ur
L we'll open up a new
tab we'll paste in the base
URL and all of these URLs will be down
uh in the
description and let's just send the base
URL without the required parameter and
see what
happens as you can see we get an error
message which is not
surprising so let's add the query
parameter we start with the question
mark delimiter and then
gen code ID which is the query parameter
name an equal sign and now we will paste
in a gen code
ID and as you can see we received
results this
time the resulting data for the web
service is returned in Json format any
scripting language can directly parse
Json data
as you can see the result has two
attributes data and paging
info GX web services are paginated so if
your query results in large amounts of
data then you'll have to retrieve the
results one page at a time just like a
Google
search if we expand the paging info you
can see there's just a single page of
data for this query so we've got all the
data that we need
if we expand data you'll see that this
has 54 entries that's one entry per
tissue GX has 54 tissue
types we can expand the first
result and see
that this contains data for the tissue
thyroid and within the tissue thyroid
there's another data attribute which
contains the actual expression values
now you probably don't know the Gen code
identifier for your Gene of interest but
instead you probably have an hgnc Gene
symbol if we go back to the gene
expression web service documentation you
can see that it does not accept an hgnc
G symol so how can we retrieve the Gen
code ID for a particular Gene
symbol let's go back over to the
groups and select the reference genome
endpoints and then we will select the
get genes web
service once again we'll look in the
upper right hand corner to get the base
URL and copy
that and we'll see here in the center
pane that this takes a gene ID as a
query parameter so let's construct URL
will'll paste in the base
URL add the question mark then a gene
ID equals and let's search for
egfr and as you can see there's a single
batch so now we have the Gen code ID for
egfr we can then use that gen code ID to
query the gene expression web service as
we demonstrated prev
iously now what if we want to retrieve
expression data for the gene egfr but
only for a particular tissue say lung
let's go back to the documentation for
the get gene expression web service and
you can see that it takes a query
parameter called tissue site detail
ID and if we select the details for this
query parameter we can see the allowed
values for tissue site detail
ID so let's construct the URL we
will
again copy the base
URL open a new
tab add the Gen code ID
and now you remember that uh after the
first qu parameter the delimeter changes
to an Amper sand so now we will add
tissue
site detail ID equal
long and as you can see
now we only return returned the web
service only returned data for the
single tissue