Thank you so much. Thank you Sherry. Uh
it's been great to be here and uh I'm
very inspired by this uh day of talks
meeting with you all and uh thank you to
Sarah as well. Thank you to the lids
organizers. Thanks to everyone for uh
making this so smooth. So yeah, this is
called Mo Earth. Now we just rebranded a
couple couple months ago. And so um
Earth is the name of this new foundation
model and platform that I'll be uh
telling you guys about. We we launched
this as Sher said uh just um just last
week actually. So I said in the abstract
Earth AI is surging in popularity and I
uh I got feedback on this abstract from
my wife which I always do and she said
uh hey you know really love what you're
doing but also it might be a bit of a
stretch to say this is surging. And so I
looked it up to prove to her that this
was in fact the case and here's the
interest over time. And I think it's
rightfully that that inflection point is
somewhere around uh mid this year. And
so she believed me. But then to put it
in context, of course, the LLM space has
been uh rather dominant in the AI world
of late. So in the end, we're both right
and our marriage is still strong. Um but
in in in in uh in more serious terms,
like I think in general, AGI is
receiving a ton of press, right? It's
like basically constant. And I think
it's
maybe not the thing we need to be
talking about. We we may or may not
build AGI and you know different people
will give you a different uh timeline
for when that's going to occur. I don't
think necessarily that just because we
build AGI if we do in fact build it and
we can talk about what the real
definition is if we want. But even if we
get there it's not going to magically
solve all of our problems. And here are
two papers, one from Microsoft and one
from Anthropic about uh or maybe it's
open AI about kind of what it would mean
and and you know what would happen once
we have AGI and perhaps we have sparks
of AGI at this point. I think these are
basically not the thing we should be
focused on. I think we should be
focusing on steering artificial
intelligence towards our highest ideals
towards what we think really matters um
from the outset. So I'm from AI2 as Sher
mentioned the Allen Institute of
Artificial Intelligence. This is a
nonprofit AI research institute that was
founded about 10 years ago by uh the
late Paul Allen uh Microsoft co-founder
Paul Allen and our mission is to build
AI for some of the world's big
challenges and we build AI I would say a
little bit differently from um perhaps
from uh from the norm. So we first of
all center the user from the outset of
R&D and in our case that means literally
speaking to users from the very
beginning of the project from before we
even start the model research and
development talk project we're talking
with the users who are going to be the
recipients of that technology so we can
ensure that whatever we're building is
closely aligned with their interests and
that might be an agriculture and food
security or wildfire resilience or uh
deforestation cause mapping in the
Amazon. So we talk to those folks
literally from the very beginning before
we do any before we write any code to
make sure that we understand what it is
that we're trying to build and what
success would look like from their
perspective. Another big principle of
AI2 and and uh that underlies our work
is openness. So we strive for open
artificial intelligence research and
development and that means open code,
open data, open training and evaluation.
Uh all of our libraries are open. The
the both pre and post training code are
open. and we open the um these these
libraries are on GitHub right now. You
can look at all this stuff if you want
to. You can inspect exactly what we did.
Uh the models are of course available on
hugging face the weights I should say
and the training data that we use to to
to build those models. So you can
replicate exactly what we did. You can
extend it. You can um critique it. You
can find flaws uh and um and let us know
and and uh we we take that very
seriously and and and we care a lot
about that. We also open source our
production inference services. So a lot
of the models I'm going to be talking to
you about today, especially the
applications are literally run. They're
running right now in production. The
exact same code that we're running in
production right now is available to
you. You can look at it. And then the
final big difference I would say is that
rather than just a model, we really want
to support the full ML life cycle. And
we see this as central to kind of
putting the user at the center of
development. So we are uh in this case
uh I'll be talking to you about a
platform that open that is the entire
life cycle of machine learning uh
research and development all the way
from like raw data acquisition through
training or through annotation training
and so on. So we really strive for
endto-end solutions which we think are
um again really critical for our users
and also these these three principles
really are uh self-reinforcing. Um
openness is really not a crutch it's
it's an advantage. Um and and here are
some examples of the applications that
we've built on the AI for the planet
team. So some of these you may have
heard of. This talk is going to be
focused on the earth but I want to give
you guys a little bit of a a kind of
motivation or like how we got to uh
building wanting to build this like big
open platform. So these are a bunch of
programs that have been around for um in
some cases many years um started at uh
at AI2 and uh Skylight I want to talk a
little bit about in detail because it
offers some examples of kind of building
these uh computer vision these
artificial intelligence models at global
scale for real-time applications for a
bunch of users. Um and it was kind of a
key motivating uh factor behind the
creation of Omo Earth. So Paul Allen uh
and and this is the AI for the planet
team uh and
I just wanted to recognize them. So this
is it's I'm uh there's a large team
that's uh built all this technology and
um I'm just one person. So uh Paul Allen
he uh he envisioned a future where so
skylight was started about seven maybe
eight years ago and Paul Allen thought
that you know eventually artificial
intelligence would get to a point and
eventually there would be sufficient
satellites uh in both frequency and
revisit and everything that we would be
able to basically constantly monitor the
oceans like remote like high high seas
basically with uh computer vision and
this would enable uh maritime
transparency um protection of uh marine
protected areas and basically have have
eyes on the water and and this
transparency is of course critical to
sustainability. So I'll talk to I'm
going to talk a little bit about the
models that we built um that enable
this. So one side of the models are
satellite imagery based detection. So
this is like literally vessel detection
on the high seas from a bunch of
different satellites. Um satellites are
constantly orbiting the earth of course
and we and many of these sources prov
are are public data. So we can take them
and and do uh uh detection with them.
And then the other side is is GPS
sequence modeling which I I'll briefly
touch on. This is just a quick primer. A
lot of people in this room are probably
very familiar with uh how this generally
works. So I just want to walk through
very quickly. Um so we have activity on
in the remote areas somewhere on the
high seas. We get an image from an
orbiting satellite that's down linked to
a ground station. Uh eventually copied
to our servers. We run a model against
that and then we serve this up via some
API or GUI. In the case of Skylight, uh
it's both. And this is serving currently
a couple hundred or 300 or so
organizations across like 60 countries.
And this whole process uh occurs in like
a matter of uh hours in the case of a
satellite that I'm about to show in just
90 minutes. So we need to make these
models extremely accurate, extremely
reliable because people depend on them
and people are literally making
decisions with very limited resources
on, you know, on the basis of this
information. So if you have a, you know,
$50,000 fuel budget and we're saying,
you know, we we see some activity out
here and, you know, in this marine
protected area, for example, uh we
better be right. And we care a lot about
being right and and false negatives and
false positives both uh cause big
problems. So here's one example just in
more concrete terms like what exactly we
built and why. So you probably know
different satellites have different
strengths and weaknesses. Uh Vers is a
satellite that can see through uh see at
night. So it's sensitive to light. Um
it's actually exquisitly sensitive to
night uh to to to light. You can pick
out literally street lights on highways
on the across the whole world. And if
you have Earth at night on your phone or
on an iPhone or whatever, this is the
data that that's coming from. So the
pretty pictures, it's called Black
Marble comes from from this data. And
there's a couple there's several
satellites now that are public publicly
available and support this uh this
particular sensor. So couple great
things about this satellite. It's uh the
the it's we're getting real-time
coverage or near real-time coverage, I
should say. It's about 90 minutes from
everywhere on Earth, and that's really
quite good, especially for satellites.
It's global. It's providing global
coverage. So that's excellent. literally
everywhere, high seas, land, everything.
Uh there's a roughly a 3x uh three times
a day revisit rate, which is really
good. So you can see kind of successive
snapshot successive pictures of the same
uh vessel, but the spatial resolution is
quite poor uh relatively speaking. So
especially if you're doing something
like object detection or vessel
detection, 750 m is really not good. But
you can see lights and if you're doing
bad things uh uh you can probably turn
off your GPS transponder for example but
you can't turn off your lights or it's
much more difficult to do so. Uh so we
leverage the satellite for detection but
it wasn't built for detection. It was
built for clouds and for for detecting
clouds for uh basically for atmospheric
modeling for atmospheric purposes
definitely not for vessel detection the
way we've repurposed it here. So we've
had to do some things to make it uh work
and uh and this is roughly what that
model looks like. So we have vessel
detection which in this case this is a
super simple model. It's literally a 2D
CNN like ve very very uh very fast very
efficient kernel with a bunch of other
detectors for various uh sources of
false positive that occur when you
actually uh try to operationalize this
kind of model. um when we first uh got
this model. So our initial version of
this was literally just vessel detection
and we shipped that put it into the
service looked at the outputs and it was
it was terrible. It was absolutely
unusable and um we realized that we were
detecting all these other things which
are sources of of false positives. So we
decided we needed to build detectors for
all of those. Um so over the course of
building this model we built detectors
for uh gas flares uh like oil platforms
um lightning. Actually, this this uh
this model is really good at detecting
lightning if you need that. Uh aurora um
aurora is a huge source of false
positives and um the aurora move. You
may have seen them uh uh last week. They
were really far south. Uh so all these
are sources of false positives. So you
have to control for all those. We built
a model. It's a it's a 2D CNN with these
channels, moonlight, land, sea, clouds,
uh and the nanowatts which is the signal
itself. So this model is tiny. It's like
40,000 parameters. it can be run as part
of CI/CD and it's very effective. Um I
want to just briefly comment on the fact
that you know in general when we do
offline training we see extremely high
quality data and it's fairly easy to
make a really good model. When we ship
that model when we actually get into a
production it typically doesn't work
very well and um and most models uh
generally don't see production and so
users are not going to see see practical
benefit. And so we think about this a
lot and one of the way to address one of
the ways to address this is to make it
extremely easy to get feedback from
users. So I'm showing here a skylight
platform that's on the bottom. And
notice how simple this is. This is
literally as simple as it gets, right?
You you do not need a sophisticated
detector to detect that that's uh um
that this is a vessel here. Um it's not
always that simple. I'm showing a very
simple example. um gets a little bit
harder than that but in general we just
show users hey this is what the model
saw uh and and this is what it sees in
the case of veers and then uh just tell
us if it's right or wrong right you you
know these our experts are generally
they will know and they'll be able to
tell us oh that looks like a cloud or
false positive or something like that or
we know it's a gas flare there oh it's a
new platform oh it's a new wind turbine
whatever so we just make it super easy
to get feedback the model that we were
uh not I'm not going to use the word
competing But the another model in the
space that people were asking us to
compare ourselves to um was uh basically
this is how they provided feedback. It's
the upper up upper row here. And and you
know it's very difficult to interpret
this even if you know you know about
signal processing and know how this
model was trained. It's pretty difficult
to immediately interpolate oh okay that
model was right or wrong. Right? It's
much easier to just look at the output.
Um and we do this via feedback and it's
very effective. So we've done this for a
bunch of satellites now and we have
computer vision. This is all operating
right now at global scale in real time
serving uh about 70 countries and uh
we're covering these satellites viewers.
So that's the one I just showed you. And
then Sentinel 1 which is radar that's
synthetic aperture radar. Sentinel 2
which is optical imagery and and LANCAT
8 N9 which is also optical imagery. So
all these satellites again they have
different strengths and weaknesses. We
use them all uh at at the same time and
users rely on these signals for
different so synthetic aperture radar
you can see through clouds ve at night
as I said um optical is of course very
useful and uh so these models generally
kind of work in tandem with one another
and users uh rely on all of them they're
um quite performant at this point we've
been iterating for a while they're right
around say like 90 F1 uh they're very
reliable they're literally always on um
and and a bunch of users depend on them.
They run at reasonably low latency, so
90 minutes for vehic it's it's hours or
so for for the others. Um, and these run
on T4s. These are super light models and
they are T4 is like, you know, basically
the cheapest GPU. I don't know. Google's
probably going to turn them off soon at
this point because they're so um
uncommon, but uh we get we get great uh
utility out of them and they're um uh
they're uh uh they they work they work
for these models. So everything here has
been open sourced both the models and
the APIs as I mentioned. Uh and um and
we provide this for free. You can go to
this link actually if you want to see
this. Uh this is a public version of
this uh of we have a public version of
these maps uh or of the kind of the the
the outputs um dynamic and and you can
look and actually I show I'm going to
show a few examples because I just think
it's cool. Computer vision is fun. Um so
this is some kind of uh fishing vessel
with maybe a person or something like
that. Um here's a vessel that we
discovered. This was underwater. So uh
in this case we found like this
shipwreck basically. Um here I'm showing
this is uh just outside of Boston. I
just came up. This is what I found last
night on on the plane over here. And
here I'm just showing you that like
synthetic aperture radar. This is
actually like quite hard to do this
really well at scale. The signal is
fairly faint. Um but we've and we've
trained this model on something like
50,000 uh expertly labeled annotations.
This took years just to be clear like
this this and and and and um one of the
reasons I'm showing you all this is that
I think there's a ton of value here but
it's really hard to extract. Um so
anyway so this is synthetic aperture
radar and and here you're just so this
is not optical. This is not what a human
eye sees. This is what radar sees. Um
and uh in this case uh you know this was
positive a positive detection. Um and
and radar sees through clouds. So that's
very useful. Um, we've also done uh
global real-time modeling for the same
platform, for the Skylight platform with
GPS data. And I'm just showing you a
quick example here of of what that looks
like. So, GPS data, I think, is
generally another pretty rich source of
information that is comparatively
undervalued. Um GPS is usually
transponded by every vessel on the ocean
unless you're like really a bad actor
and then you're probably going to turn
off your um you're probably not going to
constantly broadcast your location, but
it's generally used by most uh most
vessels. And we can model GPS data
really similar to how we model uh uh
language data. The difference here is of
course we have kind of this geoloccation
lat long plus a sock but we can just
trans transform this into uh um tokens
in a way that transformers understand uh
do the standard thing and language model
training. Here's the custom model that
we built on top and then we can get
really high precision high accuracy
classification of all these GPS
sequences at every moment in time on the
whole world um in real time. So we're
processing right now right now as we
speak in skylight uh about 5 million uh
GPS uh it's called AIS automatic
identification system GPS's messages per
day. This is all running again on T4s.
These models are pretty small. This
model I think is on the order of
I think it's about a million or so
parameters. It's super super efficient,
fast to run. And here we're providing uh
basically we're just telling all of our
users what the vessels are doing at any
moment in time so they can go and
intercept as needed if a vessel is doing
something nefarious um or just knowledge
of exactly what's going on. So this is
happening or this these models are
running in real time everywhere um and
they're producing literally
instantaneous classifications of the
entire uh of the entire planet um with
with with these uh with these models.
This is outside of Boston. And this is
showing you in the last like I think
it's couple weeks or so maybe month um
just literally every single GPS message
that was broadcasted from all the
vessels that were in and around the
Boston uh sea area and and what they
were doing. Um we can use these same
models to forecast human wildlife
conflict. So uh we haven't uh uh
produced this model yet but we believe
we can take uh earth observation data
for land cover mapping combine that with
GPS data combine that again with weather
data to to get a sense of what um what
animals are going to do in especially
around national parks where there's
concerns for human wildlife conflict.
Human wildlife conflict for elephants
for example is the leading cause of
death now uh for elephants. And so we
believe we can do something similar
here. take the Atlas models uh and um
and basically forecast where there's
going to be a conflict. Um this is just
a pretty picture that I wanted to show
you. This is uh basically all GPS data
in the world um in the last this was I
think 2020
2024. Um this is roughly 5 terabytes of
data and it was just to force me to
pause and think carefully but yeah this
is just a pretty picture. Um so the the
net for us was that earth scale modeling
is generally pretty hard. Um it all
these models took years to make and to
build and to ship. Um each one was like
very different. We had to kind of do
slightly different things. Build the
machinery to both train and then also to
productionize and deploy them. And it
was it was just very hard each time. It
was fairly resource intensive. Uh and we
get asked to make tons of models. Um
it's very difficult to do this at scale
or for many different tasks. So you need
expert labelers, you need machine
learning research teams. This really is
not a solved problem. You generally
can't take off-the-shelf models and just
like make them work for this kind of uh
use case. You need training
infrastructure, thousands or maybe
millions of GPU GPU hours to train the
base foundation models that do all these
things. You need dedicated inference
systems and and of course you need to
maintain these things if they're going
to be productionized. So basically this
is out of scope for many nonprofits and
NOS's [snorts] and we said well what if
we can do this you know for the world
and make this a public good and really
just kind of build it once foundational
infrastructure one time and then give it
away and let people kind of leverage the
same technology that we've been uh using
for uh to to to build our uh models and
and that's what the earth project is
about that's what we just launched as
Sher mentioned and so the idea here is
we have massive global scale realtime
data coming from all different kinds of
sensors, not just the satellites, but
also there's ground sensors, there's
buoys, there's there's uh there's
weather balloons, there's all kinds of
different sensors. Let's take all these
data that's let's train a large
foundation model with all these sources.
Then let's integrate it into a full
platform that enables actually
leveraging this technology. And I'll
show uh you what that means in a second.
So we can empower many different comp
you know many different organizations
many different NOS's many different uh
users who who want this technology but
don't have the resources to get it and
we really think that this is the the
right time to do so. We think that
artificial intelligence is about where
it needs to be. The data is where it
needs to be. Um, we get asked literally
by hundreds of organizations to build
various models and we just we we kept
saying no honestly and it was a bit
heartbreaking because these
organizations have extremely important
missions that we want to be able to help
and that really is kind of aligned with
our mission about building you know
artificial intelligence for for good and
and and for these challenges and we
didn't want to keep saying no and so we
said let's build this this platform and
that's called earth. So, OMO Earth is
this new uh very very new platform that
we just uh released a couple weeks ago
uh la last week and it's a it's a set of
um it's a set of uh models that we also
built new foundation models uh that are
state-of-the-art a platform that enables
leveraging these models and then and
then fine-tuning them for various
downstream applications like ecosystem
extent, biodiversity, uh conservation,
sustainability um forest deforestation
uh in the Amazon, forest risk uh
assessments, uh all kinds of different
applications that our users have come to
us and asked, hey, can you build this
model for us? And we said, hey, uh just
give us a little time and then we'll
have a platform that hopefully will
enable you to build whatever you want.
And so that's that's what we did and
that's what we've been uh building for
uh the last year or so. So the idea here
is we'll have a a a model a foundation
model that I'll describe in a second and
it's a foundation model that can do um
many different tasks really really well
uh across classification segmentation
change detection time series non-time
series that kind of thing and then a
platform that enables fine-tuning these
models and deploying them. So the the
entire uh ML life cycle here all the way
from you know again raw data annotate
that data deploy API now you have a
serviceable endpoint whatever it is that
you want maybe you want to download the
maps maybe you want to email the maps to
a colleague maybe you're the UN and you
just need this kind of more from a
policy perspective we want to do all
those things simultaneously um so that
users can take action so maybe it's a
real-time use case where users just want
to know like exactly what's going on
right here right now and we have some
applications that I'll describe that do
exactly that. So Earth as I mentioned
this is a new foundation model that we
built. So it's it's a very multimodal so
it combines many different satellites,
many different sensors plus uh some
derived maps. It's multi-mporal
multi-mporal because we need to model
changes over time. The earth is
obviously extremely dynamic. It's
flexible uh so it can run on whatever
you have whatever users have. Users
typically don't have every imaginable
modality. they may have one or none or
whatever. And so you just want to be
flexible for them. Um it can uh it can
run even when you have missing data,
missing time steps. It's no problem. And
that's actually common because in
production settings, satellites go down
all the time, right? They go dark, they
whatever. So we need to be able to uh we
need to account for that. We also
importantly want this model to be
extensible. So in general, this was like
a first step. We're trying to build a
foundation, one that can be extended to
many different modalities, many
different sensors, basically whatever
users have. Uh we want to be able to
meet them where they are. Uh we want the
model to be fine-tunable, fine-tunable
for many different tasks. So
fine-tunable for uh basically whatever
the user needs and and of course we need
this model to be open. We want the data
to be open. We want the model to be
fully open. You can reproduce this
model. You can extend it. You can do
whatever you want with it. Um
[clears throat]
what does the data look like? So in
general the data is we consider it uh
quite multimotal. So you have visual
infrared, you have microwave, you have
radar. Um you also have like elevation
data and land cover and you have many
derived maps produced by many different
organizations. Open street map uh uh
European space agency world cover um
world serial uh the US has has produced
a bunch of crop land data masks and we
can put all these into the model. Um in
general it's variable spatial
resolution. So um this can vary quite
dramatically. uh and um we need to
account for that. Our current data sets
right now, the ones I'll share with you
in a second, they're training on fairly
modest data about 10 terabytes across uh
these uh these sensors. Um we have maps
for world cover, cropland data, world
serial, open street map, and several
others that I'll show you in a second.
So this is what the pre-training data
set looks like. So we have a bunch of
satellite observations. We have these
are all uh geo reference, so lat long
and timestamps. And then we have a bunch
of high quality maps and we're putting
these into a model. This is just the
pre-training data that we're going to
feed into the model. And then we have
this covering about 300,000 locations.
So uh you can see here the sampling is
not uniform. It's uh it's it's obviously
biased and it's biased towards area
where you have more data. uh and we
certainly want to strive for even more
data and especially in the areas that
are uh underrepresented here. Um and
that's um that's a
that's a major future effort. Um here's
approximately what the training recipe
looks like. So I'm not going to cover
this in detail, but uh we've uh
published the paper a couple weeks ago
uh and you can look at that for details.
But in general, what we're doing is
we're pre-training via uh latent mass
image modeling and then we're doing kind
of a um uh a fast version of that for
high qual for the for the map data. So
we're kind of combining self-s
supervision and supervision uh in this
uh in this setup so that we can leverage
the uh the data from both um and that
ends up being quite effective. So OMO
Earth we've shown is state-of-the-art
for a huge variety of EOT tasks. We
evaluated more earth this this new
foundation model against uh industry
standard benchmarks of course uh
research benchmarks that people have
been using for for a while. We also
evaluated this model against our partner
data um real world tasks that
organizations have given us asked us to
uh do for them crop crop uh crop type
mapping for example or deforestation
cause mapping or um wildfire risk
assessments and we've tuned these models
for uh or we've I should say we've uh
we've massively benefited from those
collaborations because it's enabled us
to make sure that our models do really
really well not just on the research
benchmarks which are of course quite
important but also against these uh kind
of maybe a little bit messier real world
tasks and so we've been optimizing for
both and we now have a model that
performs really well on both. So on the
on the left you're looking at uh this
earth is now paro front for uh
computational efficiency and and
performance across this is showing the
average on 13 uh 13 different tasks via
KN&N and and linear probing. So here
we're taking just the embeddings
from the model. So no fine-tuning and
we're just saying you know how do we
compare to other major models in the in
the field and uh we're doing um not bad.
We're also doing not bad even for really
small models. So you'll notice here that
the vit tiny and the vit uh uh nano are
actually quite good and they're better
than some much larger models. And that's
significant because if you have a small
model, you can retrain it faster, you
can uh iterate faster, you can um it's
inference is much cheaper of course,
etc., etc. On the your on the right,
you're seeing fine-tuning. So
fine-tuning is a bit different, right?
There's a lot of variations in
fine-tuning and here we're doing uh
relatively full fine-tuning and excuse
me one second.
What you're seeing here is average model
rank. So earth is on top and actually
the vit tiny is also quite good. It's
it's second best on these. Uh this is 18
tasks. So this is 18 fine-tuning tasks
covering a whole bunch of different uh
segmentation, change detection,
classification,
etc., etc.
Okay, I'm not going to ask you to look
at this really closely. This is just to
emphasize that we evaluated this fairly
extensively on dozens of tasks and then
we also evaluated every other major
model against those same tasks. So this
is in the paper. The point of this is
not to have you stare at the numbers. So
forgive me if that's what you're trying
to do right now. It's rather just to
show you we've really done quite
thorough evaluation. Top is KN&N, bottom
is SFT. We evaluated this model
extensively and performance of these
these models this family of models. So
earth nano tiny base large is very good.
It's uh generally the best or near the
best and um and that's a good thing
because that means that our users can
you know leverage this model for many
different tasks. The source code is
available on GitHub. The weights are on
hugging face as I mentioned. Um but you
can also access this model within the
north platform. Um and I just put an
asterisk here. We we recommend using the
base model. For most tasks, large is
generally better, but consult this table
uh if you're unsure and and um and if
you have the spare compute. Um this was
just super super brief uh and just a
taste. The ablations and results are in
the technical report which I'll provide
a
um well, if you go to earth.allenai.org,
you can see it there. Um apologies, you
can't you can't see the URL here. And
then uh hugging face and GitHub, of
course. And I just want to shout out our
infra team. uh Beaker which uh does all
the experimental management at AI2. So
this is fairly hard to run all these
experiments and they've been awesome and
the language modeling team that's the
open language modeling team Almo um
they've we've we've basically based this
these libraries off their core uh
training code which sped us up by a huge
amount. Um I'll briefly comment here on
comparisons to Alpha Earth. So, Alpha
Foundations, you might have heard about
generated huge buzz and is probably
largely responsible for that massive
uptick we saw um in the in the beginning
in Google trends. Uh so, Google came out
with this model earlier this year, I
think in June, something like June or
July, and it generated a ton of interest
and that's a really great thing. And I
want to emphasize that you know in
general we are thrilled that so many uh
uh talented teams are contributing
models to this space. It's a great thing
for the world when uh people work on
this kind of technology. Um we're
thrilled to see Google work on this. Um
there's been a lot of activity recently
and it's generally just a great thing
and we really don't see it as a
competition at all. That's not um how we
look at the space. Um we see it more as
like what can we learn from this? this
is a a great uh contribution to the
world and alpha earth and our model
earth they're quite similar in some
respects so they draw on similar data
sources uh if you've read the alpha
earth paper um quite similar data
sources and they support similar
downstream tasks um the big difference
is that Google released annualized
embeddings uh and I showed you that
performance of KN&N LP uh earlier and
I'll show you again sort of how we
compare to to Google in a second but the
they released annualized embeddings uh
rather than the model itself. AEF
embeddings are free uh to an extent.
There's also a request for pace bucket
if you need better scale. Um we have not
released embeddings yet. Uh we're
thinking about it and we may but we
haven't yet done so. We've released a
model and a platform that supports kind
of more customization, greater
customization of these models. Why did
we not just release embeddings? Uh we we
we certainly could. We think our
embeddings are generally pretty high
quality as you've seen from the CANNLP
chart. Full fine-tuning, we we've we've
found that full fine-tuning can
significantly outperform frozen
embeddings. And in our case, that means
uh our users are going to get just
better performance from uh doing
fine-tuning. Fine-tuning is of course
not trivial. The the reason folks are
excited about embeddings in the first
place is that it's kind of this cached
artifact that is easily sharable and you
know, I can just give you embeddings and
then you're off to the races. and
fine-tuning is uh not exactly like that.
It it requires a little bit more uh
in-depth work with the model. There is a
argument that embeddings are a lot
cheaper than fine-tuning. And in
general, I think that can be true. But
when you think about the cost of of of
of these kinds of projects, when you're
building an application that's dependent
on this kind of technology, you're
generally making a pretty significant
investment. And it's it can be in many
cases like months to years of effort and
that's like of FTE time and and and
significant resources well beyond just
like the model. So I think that in
general from from our perspective the
the the cost of embeddings and
fine-tuning uh may be you know similar
maybe embeddings are a little bit
cheaper may maybe not um but both are
somewhat insignificant when you compare
to the cost of real world application
development. So fine-tuning for example
for the models that I'm going to show
you in a second with our applications
are on the order of like 24 hours of
H100 time. So uh you know not that
expensive and especially when you or I
shouldn't say not that expensive
relatively inexpensive compared to the
cost of full application development and
that really is what I think matters most
at least to our users and that's why
we've uh chosen this route. Um here's
some performance. This is a table from
our paper just comparing AEF and uh
Helio. Uh this is Helios. This is an old
name but Helios directly. So uh AEF is
Alfred Foundations. KN&N is uh K nearest
neighbors. So this is just embeddings uh
just vanilla embeddings. Whatever you
get out of the box. So you can download
these right now from Google. They made
them all free um covering the entire
world. These five applications here are
from our partners. This is data that
they've given to us and then we've
evaluated our models against uh their
data. We've trained and evaluated models
against their data. So NANDI is a crop
type mapping in Kenya. AWF is a land use
land cover classification from the
African wildlife foundation. This is
also we have ecosystem classification
here. Uh live fuel moisture content.
This is a measurement of wildfire risk
and then solar farm detection. So a
fairly wide spread of applications here
and covering kind of various things you
would do with geospatial foundation
models. And we've evaluated this in a
few different ways. Here I'm showing
KN&N a frozen decoder setup and then
full fine-tuning. Obviously you can't do
fine tuning with AEF because we just
have access to the to the embedding. So
we're only showing you those results for
uh for OM Earth. Just try to ignore
Helios here and just think about OM
Earth as an old name. Uh and um what I
want you to kind of take home or take
away from this is that yes embedding
performance can be really good. If we
look at AWF for example, the performance
the accuracy is is in the 80s and that's
great and that's out of the box
performance with embeddings. But we see
fairly significant improvement from uh
from from full fine-tuning. And on the
left here, I'll draw your attention to
Nandy. So this is crop type
classification again. So this is a
fairly hard problem within uh within EO
tasks. Crop type classification is
extremely important. It matters like
what we're growing. We we need to plan
for the future. we need to figure out
how climate change is going to affect uh
growing and so on. And so we want to do
this really really well. We find that
fine-tuning which again in this case I
think it was something like 12 12 hours
of of H100 time can generate a pretty
dramatic improvement in performance and
this could very well be the difference
between uh you know shipping and not
shipping this model.
We also measured the environmental
impact so which we think is important uh
to to contextualize here. So here I'm
just showing you the numbers uh ho how
many H100 hours it it took to uh to
train these models for both pre-training
and then for fine-tuning. Finetuning was
a mix of hardware. And so I'm not
showing it was it was variance of uh a
H100 and A100. And so we're just showing
you the GP hours here, the energy, the
carbon and the water. Uh we have a
cluster uh or we we do pre-training on
our own cluster at AI2 uh which is
fairly energy efficient and it's also
very water efficient. it's closed loop.
Um, and so, uh, uh, it's it's it's
fairly water efficient in that regard.
Um, but we're obviously using energy.
And here, just to contextualize these
numbers, this is about what it would
cost, uh, across all these models, the
the energy was what it would co or what
it would take to power an average US
house for 5 months or an economy ticket
to or the and the carbon emissions are
are equivalent to an economy ticket on a
flight from Seattle to Portugal. So this
is the Omar team. This is the the
incredible team that built these models.
And I just want to shout out uh all
these uh these very special people that
that built this applications. So want to
talk a little bit about applications.
But before I do, I just want to say that
the reason we even have applications is
that we have a ton of partners that
we've been collaborating with from the
beginning of this project. And these are
some of them. Um so in wildfire we
collaborated with or and for forest
management we collabor collaborated with
ACA the Amazon conservation association
uh and NASA JPL. Um we've also been
collaborating with uh uh the
international food policy research
institute um as well as the uh uh CGI
and more recently the United Nations uh
food and agriculture organization um and
very recently with with NASA harvest.
And these organizations, these
collaborations are were integral to the
work that we did throughout this
project. They literally are um really
centering and anchoring our work. Um so
let me show you a few examples of of of
wildfire and forest health. And I'm also
going to ask Sher how I'm doing on time.
It's 450. I don't know when you want me
to stop.
>> I think you can take five minutes.
>> Five minutes.
>> Okay, I'll speed. I'm gonna go faster.
Um,
just kidding. I'll just focus a few
examples. So, Wildfire and Forsell. So,
uh, so I'm going to skip this. So, we
can take these models, these base
foundation models. We can fine-tune them
on a bunch of, uh, of ground truth
reference data from, uh, DNR uh, uh, um,
uh, forest uh, uh, DNR employees who go
out into the forest and and collect
collect wood samples, take them back to
the lab. uh dehydrate them and then
weigh them and that's a measurement of
of moisture. You can imagine that that
process that I just mentioned doesn't
scale super well. Uh we discovered that
we can take these models that we built,
fine-tune on those expert samples and
then produce wall-to-wall coverage. So
entire Pacific Northwest or entire
United States at like literally the cost
of a few cents. Uh it's just a little
bit of H100 time. And so we've done this
in a few areas uh before and after fires
to see if they work. And the net here is
that it's it's about a million times
cheaper. You still need that reference
data. You cannot do this without
reference data. Uh you need the experts
going out into the field to collect this
data, but enables you to scale in a way
that is just otherwise impractical. Um
we've also looked at deforestation in
the Amazon. I mentioned this earlier. So
uh on the right you're seeing a map that
we've produced of Amazon conserv with
Amazon Conservation Association. So
we're producing deforestation maps
specifically what the cause of
deforestation was. Was it farming? Was
it a landslide? That kind of thing. So,
these are time series models. Omar was
trained, fine-tuned with expert data
from from the experts from Amazon
Conservation Conservation Association,
and we're yielding uh roughly a three
order of magnitude over what uh the 10
km norm was before. Um
we've done uh work with the global
mangrove watch with these same models
and we've been partnering with the
global mangrove watch from the
beginning. Actually in this case uh they
gave us um or we worked with them on
training a new model anomal earth model
uh so base foundation model again
fine-tuned on expert uh GMW data and we
can get about roughly similar
performance that they were getting um
with their you know five and 5.8 8
million training points with uh like
literally 10k samples and that enables
them to spend more time uh doing the
important work that they're doing less
time hopefully on the things that you
know on say data annotation um so they
can do their work uh we can accelerate
their work
um
okay one more example Sher and then I'll
wrap up um I want to highlight one more
example and this was with the
international food policy research
institute so we we need to map crops at
scale we need to do this really really
well um for a whole bunch of reasons for
policy for farmers for planning for
climate change for many different
reasons and currently this is like an
unsolved problem in the space and we
think you can do a pretty good job and
we're not the only group to do this just
to be clear in fact Sherry is is is one
of the labs that uh has done this really
well but we are generally trying to do
this well at scale with very few samples
um it's a really hard problem so uh we
were approached by the international
food policy re research institute they
say hey we all this data, can you train
your model on our data and see if you
can get good results? And we got pretty
good results. So on the left uh table
here, you're seeing a random forces from
iffree. On the right, you're seeing
literally first pass from Omo Earth. Uh
and the results were were quite good.
And now I'm going to go
lightning speed, Sherry. So Earth is
designed to close this gap from
foundation models to to our users. And
we've built a whole platform that
enables everything that I just said to
give people access to this technology.
So all the foundation models uh
applications for uh we built all of this
and we've uh made it available uh all
the way from you know data acquisition
through annotation labeling deployment
serving and we have a web app uh and
this has this is now available. So we
and we're making this all free. Uh we
think this should be a public good as I
mentioned. Um and we think we'll do
better by by working together. Um so
this is approximately what it looks
like. Um and I'm going to skip now to
the last slide
like I even said otherwise skip time
permitting.
Um there was a lot of interesting stuff
in there that will be for another time.
So this is kind of what I want to end or
or leave you with is that I think this
was a step in in uh a step towards open
accessible and you know more holistic
modeling of the earth. I think we have a
quite a long ways to go clearly and I I
think you know our approach here is to
build open artificial intelligence
really in close collaboration with
partners. Uh we of course welcome new
partnerships across uh research,
engineering, obviously fieldwork,
policy. Um and in general I would just
uh end with the the the idea that you
know we have a responsibility to steer
artificial intelligence you know for the
benefit of all humanity. So thank you so
much for your time.
[applause]