okay so now that we've seen that gene
expression programs are important in
health and disease and can tell us a lot
about what's going on in the tissue
let's talk about how we actually measure
the genes in the tissues so we're going
to use a technology called spatial
transcriptomics to measure a gene
expression in a tissue using Imaging so
in spatial transcriptomics we are
measuring the expression of every Gene
inside every cell in a tissue so here
I've taken a piece of colon tissue in
the h& stain and I have outlined the
border of every single cell in that
tissue and this is called segmentation
and inside these cells I would like to
say what genes are expressed and what
genes are not expressed and to do this
we're going to use one of the many
Technologies out there to do spatial
transcriptomics we're going to use uh
the zenium instrument made by the
company 10x genomics and we are going to
use this to measure gene expression in
the colon
tissues so here on the left we have have
an h& stain of the colon mucosa and the
sub mucosa we have the epithelial layer
the muscle layer that separates mucosa
and sub mucosa and uh we're going to run
the zenium spatial transcriptomics
instrument and measure the expression of
genes inside cells so here's an example
of that measurement where we have
measured the gene epcam which is
normally expressed in epithelial cells
and what we're showing here is every
single dot is a single uh epcam Gene
transcript so the epcam gene was
transcribed and an RNA molecule was made
and each of these dots is one of those
RNA molecules or transcripts and what
you can see is that the location of the
RNA molecules for epcam perfectly
overlap with where the epithelium is as
judged by the h& image so that's really
beautiful uh we can measure another Gene
Desmond desmin is normally expressed in
muscle cells and we can see that the
Desmond Gene is showing up in this
muscle layer and again we can compare it
to the h& image and these the h& image
and the zenium spal transcriptomic
measur they have the same coordinate
system because these measurements are
made from the exact same piece of colon
tissue then finally we can look at this
other Gene dearin which is more spread
out but it's normally found expressed in
the sub mucosa so the bottom of the h&
image and now we can keep doing this
over and over and over and we can
measure many many genes and here I've
superimposed into one image all Gene
transcripts that we measured during our
during our spatial transcriptomic
experiment and there are 480 genes whose
expression we were able to measure in
the colon tissue so you can think of
this as a 480 Channel image and you can
compare that to the h& image which is
really a three Channel image it has red
green and blue so you're getting a lot
of information here uh from these
spatial transcriptomic
measurements so now I'd like to just
walk you through how a spatial
transcriptomics experiment works this is
a bit technical so don't worry if um you
don't understand every single detail but
we wanted to walk you through this
because it's such cool technology so it
starts with us placing a tissue on a
zenium slide zenium is the spatial
transcriptomic instrument we're using
and then once the tisue is placed on the
slide we add DNA probes that are going
to bind to every Gene transcript in a
specific manner based on complimentary D
DNA Bas pairing now these probes also
have an optical barcode that's encoded
in in the DNA sequence and there is a
unique Optical barcode for every Gene we
would like to measure so epcam has one
Optical barcode and Desmond has a
different Optical barcode now how do we
read out these Optical bar codes and
identify the gene uh that we have uh
have the prob bind to and that's just
really elegant scheme where we're going
to read the sequence of the optical
barcode using rounds of microscopic
Imaging so this is kind of similar to um
you know how you would use your phone to
scan a QR code so you might go to a
restaurant and you scan a QR code and
it's for the McDonald's menu and then
you go to another restaurant you scan
the QR code and it's for the Burger King
menu so those are two different QR codes
the link to two different menus in the
same way we're going to be reading out
these Optical barcodes and they are
going to be linking to different genes
that are being uh expressed inside that
cell so here's how that works where
we're going to have rounds of Imaging
where every single round of Imaging we
read out one character of the optical
barcode and the optical barcode is
encoded uh or decoded using fluorescent
molecules so here we have a cartoon of
the cell with the nucleus at the center
and we have different transcripts that
we're reading out and every time we do a
round of Imaging we read out one
character of that Optical barcode so
here in RNA molecule one the first uh
character is orange in an RNA molecule 2
the first character is purple in an RNA
molecule 3 the first character is red
and then we do another round of Imaging
and another round of Imaging and as we
do this we build out an entire Optical
barcode sequence where again every
single barcode is preassigned and unique
to a specific Gene so for instance this
first barcode which goes um orange blue
green yellow that encodes the Gene epcam
and a different barcode encodes cd3d and
so on so this is a really elegant scheme
by which we can measure all the
transcripts for for the cells in that
tissue and again this is just done by
rounds of Imaging on a
microscope so once we've identified all
the genes in the cells and the tissue we
still have to say uh which cell each
transcript belongs to so how we do that
is first we need to identify the cells
in the tissue and what we do is we apply
a special stain called dappy and when
applied to the tissue this stains the
nucleus of the cell sort of the center
of the cell blue and then at the same
time uh we have the location of the
transcripts here and we need to assign
them to the nearest nuclei essentially
and so what we do is we carry out a
segmentation process where we draw
polygons around the cells that are going
to separate each individual cell and
this is often done using a deep learning
algorithm to detect the boundary of the
nucleus and the boundaries and then once
these boundaries have been made and the
cells have been segmented now we can say
this transcript belongs to the green
cell here and this other transcript
belongs to the purple cell here so at
this point we have identified the gene
transcripts and assigned them to
individual cells so let's review what
the ultimate data that you'll receive
looks like so here we're showing uh the
h& image and we're showing one uh Gene
epcam and it's being expressed in these
little purple sorry cyan dots uh this is
where it's being expressed and we can
see again that it's really in the
epithelium in these colonic Crypts and
that's what we expect to see um we can
look at another Gene uh mki67 this is a
gene that's expressed in epithelial stem
cells it's involved in making more cells
um and these stem cells tend to reside
at the base of these colonic Crypts and
you can kind of see that they have this
specific localization at the base and
the third Gene I'll show you is des
which you've seen before and it's really
showing up in the muscle cells so you
have this really nice alignment between
the h& image and Gene transcripts that
Mark different cell types and states in
the cells in the
tissue let's look at another example
here we're in the submucosa now and
we're looking at a gene plvap that marks
endothelial cells endothelial cells line
your blood vessels and so the plvap is
sort of forming this circular tube and
then inside you actually see this mass
of red and those are red blood cells
that are carrying oxygen uh they're
bringing oxygen into the
tissue another Gene I want to show is
snap 25 this is a gene that's expressed
in neurons it's involved in your neurons
making synapses and the neurons are here
and here in this myeric plexus or nerve
fiber that's in between the circular
muscle and the longitudinal muscle so
again the spatial transcriptomic is
really highlighting to us specific genes
that Mark cell types and states that we
know are important in the tissue and
then finally I'll show you one last
example which is this lymphoid aggregate
which is a collection of immune cells
that aggregate in the mucosa and you see
in the h& stain this sort of heavy
patterning of a blue nuclei so immune
cells are often quite small and they're
mostly just these small blue nuclei
under an H stain and in this lymphoid
aggregate we have two different cell
types um T cells and B cells in addition
in addition to other cells but but the T
cells are marked by CD3 Delta and that's
shown in yellow and the B cells are
marked by cd79 Alpha and shown in green
here and so again we're able to really
pick out these really fine structures of
the colon tissue using spatial
transcriptomics so this is you know in a
sense what your data is going to look
like that you're working with across
these three crunches you're going to be
receiving h& images of colon tissue and
uler of citis tissue and you're going to
be having paired zenium spatial
transcriptomic measurements where all
genes 480 genes have been measured and
here again they're just shown as uh
little dots for where each dot is a
location of a transcript and then we'll
also provide you with a segmentation
which is going to tell you uh what cell
each transcript is being expressed
in so this is a lot to take in but maybe
one of the things you might have noticed
me say is that we're measuring a about
480 genes and what you recall from the
beginning of this uh lecture is that
there actually 20,000 genes in the human
genome so what about the remaining
19520 genes that we didn't measure like
what can we say about those genes so in
the last part of this lecture I will
explain to you how we can measure those
genes as well