Hi everyone, welcome back to another
interview with an amazing Sloan
professor. Today I am joined by
professor VC Barayas and he's going to
tell us about his journey here to MIT.
Would you like to introduce yourself to
the audience and tell us about your path
as a professor here?
>> Yeah, so it's great great to be uh you
know being a part of this. I've been at
MIT for 18 coming up actually I'm in my
18th year over here. I started here in
2007. Uh I'm a professor in the
operations group. Um and uh I'm also
associated with the O center. Uh you
know more recently MIT started something
called uh our Genai impact consortium.
>> It's a you know center of MIT's geni
work around campus. Uh and I'm one of
the faculty co-directors for that. The
other faculty co-directors in CELL
>> uh which is the computer science and AI
lab. I think I've always enjoyed uh
learning new things and I've always
enjoyed like tinkering and like building
things
>> uh you know and stuff like that. I
worked actually a bit while I was in in
graduate school. Uh and so you know
through the lens of that work that's
kind of what I thought I' I'd continue
doing. Uh but weirdly enough the the
content of that work it got me exposed
to
>> you know the academic career because it
turns out there's lots of academics
involved in in that world. Did you study
um data science in undergrad? What was
your
>> Not really. So
>> yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So um again like I I
never really knew what I wanted to do.
So So here's the funny thing. So when I
applied to graduate school,
>> uh just to give you a sense of my sort
of indecision. Uh so when I applied to
graduate school, I applied to programs
in applied physics, in applied math, in
electrical engineering, in operations
research, like all over the place,
>> right? And I ended up I ended up doing
electrical engineering, you know, I
picked up all these research projects to
work on, like things that like caught my
fancy. Um and in kind of working on
these things I you know I found my path
in in fact actually like you know what I
ended up doing in graduate school in
graduate school I ended up working on um
uh reinforcement learning that so all my
research was and it continues to be in
that on that on that topic right and how
did I get involved in reinforcement
learning and how did I get involved in
doing this so I'm not like necessarily a
mathematical person or anything like
this so and I'm going to date myself
here you know there used to be this
thing called uh RoboCop,
>> not COP, C cup, right? And it was like
robotic soccer.
>> And um you know, so so I wanted to get
involved in Robo Cup.
>> And uh as I sort of started getting
involved in Robo Cup, I realized that a
lot of the the stuff that one needed to
do over there
>> pertained to planning, right? Like like
you're you're like if you play soccer,
you're you're you're not thinking about
the first domino that falls. You're
thinking about the the hundth domino
that falls. Ideally, if you're good,
right? And uh you know that that got me
like you know down this path and I very
quickly realized there were so many
things I didn't know. It's a very
tenuous
process. Uh but like ultimately I think
it boiled down to just doing what I like
to that was kind of it.
>> That's so cool. I I never knew that.
From electrical engineering to Robocup
to
>> the Robocup was before electrical
engineering actually. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah.
>> To uh genai at MIT. Tell us about some
of the research that you're doing with
your PhD students. So a few of the areas
I'm particularly interested in so I
spoke about reinforcement learning right
and one of the things I'm very
interested in with respect to
reinforcement learning uh today is kind
of thinking about um how and so there's
a broad there's this broad problem
called alignment okay which is how do
you take large language models which
chat GPT is a large language model right
how do I take large language models and
align those models with uh you know our
preferences as human beings so this
problem is called the alignment problem.
>> And uh you know as LLMs and agentic AI
and things like that get like more
common
>> this alignment is going to get more and
more and more and more important.
>> Okay. Like why? Like imagine right like
imagine you have your own agent that's
making decisions on your behalf. Well
>> you you wanted to behave like you.
>> Yes.
>> Right. And uh so so these tasks are
non-trivial and you know when faced with
training data from lots of different
individuals uh from a diversity of
individuals how do you kind of weight
this how do you think about this these
are non-trivial questions so this is an
important research area for me there
also more foundational things that I'm
I'm very interested in and these range
from uh problems of continual learning
this is the problem of how do you kind
of just train a neural network forever
>> right like and you can imagine that
that's not a crazy thing to ask right
like I build a model, I want to
continuously feed it data over time.
Well, what happens when you do this?
Turns out lots of crazy things. Another
problem I've been thinking quite a bit
about again relating to sort of
generative AI. If you think about like
running generative AI, right? You're
running a large language model
inferencing as they call it a large
language model. Uh this is a process
that's fundamentally sequential.
>> So I generate like you can colloquially
think of it as I generate a word then
having generated that word I generate
the next word and then having generated
I generate the third word and so on and
so forth. Yeah.
>> So this is fundamentally a sequential
process. It takes a lot of time,
>> takes a lot of energy, blah blah blah.
Can we make this faster?
>> Are there fundamental limits to making
this faster?
>> Right? Um and this is like there so many
attacks at this problem, right? Like I
can try think about making this faster
by building clever hardware,
>> right? I can think about making this
faster by building um clever models. And
in fact, people are thinking about this
like do we need really need LLMs the way
they are or can you know diffusion
models be used? There's so many
different approaches out there. I'm kind
of focused more on with that problem I
view it as being so fundamental. I'm
curious about the limits
>> of what we can do on
>> right. So so yes, we'll eventually build
algorithms and approaches and so on and
so forth, but I think what what what's
merited over here is an understanding of
like the fundamental information
theoretic limits of doing this.
>> Wow. And if a student out there would
like to do research with you, how would
they go to go about um becoming part of
your research group?
>> Uh one is to talk with me or write me an
email or something like that, right? Uh
but no, so so for instance, you know,
for for the masters in analytic, the MAN
program,
>> um I've been very proud uh to be
associated with over the years
>> on average I think three or four
students every year. U so I didn't
really talk about this but there's a
large sort of applied element to kind of
everything uh you know we work on right
um and the applied element actually
allows for an easier ingress point
>> uh you know for students there's
something for them to do they get
momentum they're not stuck on something
super hard and they can make progress
>> and so all of these things are
associated with like very often I have
like a ton of like very real very
applied projects I'll give you an
example of a real project right like so
one one thing we're working on right now
is with this large consumer goods
company
>> uh they're trying to kind of understand
whether they can do a better job of
understanding how their consumers
respond
>> to various things they may do
>> but doing this using generative AI okay
so using generative AI maybe to make a
guess at this
>> a fascinating problem
>> okay it's very applied it's something
that's like you know very natural for a
stu for you know a master student that
that you know to to get involved in the
only sort Honestly, the only
prerequisites for doing this are one
just being intellectually curious,
>> right? You have to be super
intellectually curious. Uh and then the
other is like, you know, a willing like
like how bring something to the table,
right? Like so for instance, maybe like
some of the algorithm design scares you
>> uh but uh you know you're a great hacker
>> or conversely maybe you're not a great
hacker but like you know you're a great
al so right like so bring something to
the table and be intellectually curious.
That's really typically what's needed.
And could you talk about this um
certificate that you launched as well,
the product management certificate?
>> So, I enjoy teaching.
>> Yeah.
>> I've been involved in teaching a lot of
things, you know, um starting this
coming year, I'll teach a you know, I'
I've been teaching this class called
hands-on deep learning. The idea is to
kind of get you up and running and and
and and proficient uh with uh you know,
building complex generative models from
the ground up. And that's a class that I
co-developed with a colleague of mine,
uh, you know, Rama Rama Krishnan. Um,
and we we started on this class in like
like like a long time ago. Okay, we
started in 2020
>> and uh, right like we're like we're
nerds. We're kind of very excited about
the space. Uh, but yeah, that's grown
tremendously in popularity. I've enjoyed
doing this. I continue to do it. Uh,
right now outside of these classes,
there are other classes I taught and
teach at MIT. So uh you know about uh
it's about eight years ago now I sort of
saw a sense a trend where you know
students from the business school as
opposed to thinking about careers in
finance or in consulting they were
increasingly thinking about building
their own companies going into careers
in tech.
>> Yeah.
>> And um you know it sort of became
important to understand okay well
>> what is the core education for a career
in tech.
>> So we created this like product
management uh curriculum. Okay, starting
with a class and actually that that was
you know the first class right that has
grown into a full-on curriculum and an
associated certificate. It's called the
product management certificate
>> uh where you take u you know a class
there's u you know over you work closely
as sort of being shadowing a product
manager at a company and this and that
uh so it's been very exciting uh you
know um just given the the limits on my
physical abilities in terms of teaching
I handed that class so I could focus on
hands-on deep learning I handed that
class over to another colleague of mine
uh you know a couple years ago uh
Charlie Fine and so now Charlie Fine uh
you know manages is that it's very
successful. It's very exciting. And of
course, you know, I'm in the operations
group over here. I teach the core
operations manager. I used to teach the
core operations management class, but
still teach it uh over the summer to our
Sloan fellows. These are folks that have
>> kind of been in industry for a while.
They're coming back.
>> Well, great. Well, I hope you stay at
MIT for another 18 minimum years. And
>> Oh, yeah. Minimum.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> And uh thank you so much for your time
today. We learned so much from you.
>> Thanks, Michelle. And thank you all.
>> Hi everyone. Thank you for watching. If
you like this video, check out our other
videos in the series where I interview
influential professors at MIT Sloan. If
you would like to learn more about the
Master Business Analytics program, we
also have a playlist where you can see
more videos about the admissions
process, student life, and the program
overall.