the MIT energy initiative presents
policies to cut carbon emissions
designing an equitable option written by
Nancy W
stoffer the growing urgency of today's
climate challenge is intensifying
discussions of policy measures that
could enable the United States to
achieve Net Zero carbon emissions by
2050 leading Economist support policies
that Tex carbon emissions as the
approach that will bring the needed
change most quickly and at lowest cost
but there are serious questions about
the possible inequity of that approach
all policies lead to unintended
consequences including transferring
money from one household to another if a
carbon tax is imposed will certain
groups bear more of the burden than
others the burden imposed will depend
directly or indirectly on the level of
carbon emitting goods and services that
various groups consume the first step in
addressing the equity question is
therefore to establish the carbon
footprint of households across the
country the ideal would be to know the
carbon footprint of every household in
the United States but that's not
feasible says Christopher kidle the
George P Schultz professor of energy
economics at the mit's loan School of
Management deputy director for policy at
the MIT energy initiative and director
of the MIT Center for Energy and
environmental policy
research Instead kidle at Thomas Green
sm20 now a fellow at the US Department
of energy set their sites on determining
the the carbon footprint down to the
level of a census tract there are more
than 74,000 census tracks in the United
States each including about 4,000
households the researcher's goal was to
calculate the average carbon footprint
of the 4,000 households in each census
track no data are available on the
consumption of electricity natural gas
gasoline or other sources of carbon
emissions at the sensus trct level but
we do have such data for a
representative sample of Americans along
Ong with their age income a variety of
other demographics and maybe what state
they live in says kle that's where the
machine learning comes
in by analyzing those data a machine
learning model that the team developed
determines the relationship between the
variables about those people and their
consumption of for example
electricity once that relationship is
known the model can apply it to data on
age income and other variables for a
given census tract and estimate average
electricity consumption then we do that
for all the things that produce carbon
and add it all up for that census tract
explains kidle now we have the average
carbon footprint for all households at
the census trct level ultimately canid
and green were able to estimate average
household carbon footprints for 72,0
538 of the
74,4 census tracks in the United
States with the carbon Footprints tell
us kidle finds the carbon footprint
striking there are three broad lessons
that we learned from the carbon
Footprints he says emphasizing that all
three should be taken into account
during the policym process the first
Brad lesson is that carbon Footprints
increase with income in other words
wealthy people produce more carbon the
second is that carbon Footprints are
higher in the middle of the continental
United States and lower on the west
coast and along the mid to South
Atlantic Coast the third is that carbon
Footprints are lower in cities than in
Rural and suburban area
to convey those findings canid and green
use maps with colors that represent
average household carbon Footprints at
the census trct level carbon Footprints
are measured in tons of carbon dioxide
equivalents a measure that puts
emissions of all greenhouse gases on a
common scale the colors they use range
from purple and red the highest carbon
Footprints through yellow green and
finally blue the lowest carbon footprint
on a map of the continental United
States the colors provide Visual
Evidence of the second broad lesson much
of the middle of the country appears red
indicating that carbon Footprints are
high in that region as they are in
certain areas of the Northeast due to
cold Winters and high consumption of
heating oil the west coast and lower
Atlantic Seaboard are among the areas
dominated by Green which indicates low
carbon Footprints colored Maps focusing
on specific cities mostly demonstrate
the third broad lesson the carbon
Footprints are lower in urban areas than
in the suburbs Chicago and Kansas City
are good examples they are green in the
center and become more yellow and then
red moving outward Los Angeles appears
green but small sections in the city
center are blue indicating the very
lowest carbon footprints on the scale
another analysis provides a quantitative
look at both the impact of wealth and
carbon Footprints the first broad lesson
and how that impact changes depending on
how Urban or rural an area is the third
broad lesson the researchers divide the
total households in the United States
into five income groups or quintiles of
equal size an approach often used in
economic analysis as an example if there
are 100 households they could be ordered
based on income and then placed into
five income quintiles with 20 households
in each one they then divide each
quintile into urban suburban and rural
areas analysis of those data show that
as households become wealthier their
carbon Footprints increase in addition
for a given income group carbon
Footprints are generally higher for
households in Suburban areas than in
urban areas and still higher for
households in rural
areas that change serves to quantify the
researchers third broad lesson that
people in more rural areas have higher
carbon Footprints than those in cities
we find that any policy supporting
decarbonization is likely to be tougher
on the middle of the US and tougher on
Rural and Suburban areas says canid
that's not usually a recipe for success
in Washington
DC how Equitable are carbon tax policies
armed with estimates of average
household carbon Footprints across the
United States kidle and green were ready
to model various versions of a carbon
tax policy to estimate the annual cost
and benefit for the average household at
the census tract level the policy that's
most often discussed is a tax and
dividend plan that taxes carbon collects
the revenues and redistributes the
collected money equally across
households so every household receives
the same check in light of the
researchers broad lessons concerning
carbon footprints they asked is that
system fair for everyone the fact that
wealthy people consume more carbon is
good for the equity of the plan because
it means that wealthier households would
pay
more indeed the researchers found that
on average low-income households would
actually receive a larger dividend check
than what they would pay in increased
prices due to carbon
taxes thus the policy is not regressive
but rather Progressive it benefits
people with lower
incomes however the other two broad
lessons lead to inequitable outcom comes
from the simple tax and dividend plan
the researchers say with carbon
Footprints generally higher in Middle
America and lower on the coast the
former regions would pay more than the
latter in essence there would be a
transfer of money from Middle America to
the coasts and with carbon Footprints
higher in Rural and Suburban areas than
in cities there would be a transfer of
money from rural and Suburban households
to Urban
households both of those outcomes mean
that the simple carbon tax and dividend
plan is inequitable households in Middle
America America and in Rural and to some
extent Suburban areas would carry more
of the overall burden of the tax than
others but there's a way to design a tax
and dividend policy to keep those two
negative outcomes from occurring send
different dividend checks to different
households using their model the
researchers examine the impacts of
carbon tax and dividend policies with
the same per ton carbon fee but with
differing dividends based on geographic
location in the country or in urban
Suburban or rural
locations the the results showed that a
small adjustment in the dividend checks
as little as 8% would solve the inequity
problem inequity and other proposed
policies for canid a final takeaway from
the study is that alternativ to a carbon
tax don't look great at all for example
both clean energy standards and
renewable portfolio standards common
policies designed to reduce emissions
focus on decarbonizing the electric grid
the latter excludes nuclear power but
the middle of the United States relies
on a particularly dirty grid so those
policies will again be more costly for
people in the middle of the country than
for those on the coasts fuel economy
standards focus on vehicles and people
in the middle of the country in rural
areas tend to drive more miles and have
less fuel efficient cars so such
policies will place them at an economic
disadvantage but perhaps the biggest
drawback of such regulations is that
unlike a carbon tax they don't generate
Revenue so there's no way to undo the
negative impact says kidle
unless policy makers can find another
source of Revenue they have no
flexibility to protect certain
groups practical
implications what is the message for
policy makers a policy that taxes carbon
emissions is more efficient and less
costly overall than other frequently
proposed
policies but it's critical to design any
carbon tax and dividend policy carefully
and intelligently to avoid some of the
inequities that may arise and the
political pitfalls that can result since
n in terms of how to design the refund
checks he has a suggestion there are 10
census divisions in the United States
and he proposes sending different checks
to households based on those divisions
with bigger checks going to those in the
middle of the United States and to Rural
and Suburban areas but he stresses that
the decision is out to policy makers my
goal is to give policy makers data with
which they can make informed decisions
in the interest of their constituents he
says and his analytical techniques are
available to help decision makers assess
the implications of specific policies
being
considered as an example he describes an
experience in December
2021 at that time there was considerable
discussion about a federal budget
reconciliation package and for a while a
carbon tax seemed to be on the table
including a version that Exempted
gasoline from such attacks I began
receiving requests from policy makers
and staffers in DC to generate new maps
for them so they could see what
different carbon tax proposals would
look like he recalls did he and his team
do so his response of course we did we
were generating multiple maps on a daily
basis as the debate unfolded policy
makers could see in detail the impacts
of specific climate motivated policies
on different populations including their
own constituents the researchers
conclude that done well a carbon tax and
dividend policy could serve as a good
bipartisan win-win option that would
benefit constituents in Progressive and
conservative districts
alike this resarch was funded by the
Emerson Collective through the Roosevelt
project under the MIT Center for Energy
and environmental policy research the
goal of the Roosevelt project is to
provide an analytical basis for charting
a path to a low carbon economy in a way
that promotes highquality job growth
minimizes worker and Community
dislocation and harnesses the benefits
of Energy Technologies for regional
Economic Development