Hi, my name is Ava. I'm a junior at MIT
and my project along with my supervisor
Robert is called Climate Change Happens
Below Water and it's all about using
sensors to collect data about the waters
around us. Water has a memory. It
remembers some of the harms that come to
it. One way that you can show how carbon
dioxide affects regular water is to get
a simple straw. It becomes more acidic
because it's creating carbonic acid. The
plant life is counteracting that effect.
There actually are global changes that
are impacting the level of compounds
dissolving into the water around us.
When it's snowy out, a lot of people
like to put salt down on the roads.
Fertilizer and pesticides, all of these
things have to go somewhere and they can
also end up running off into the water
source, which again can impact the
quality of the water and can be measured
by the total dissolved solids
measurement kit that we have for
students to use. For more MIT moments
from MIT Open Learning, like, subscribe,
or