okay so good
morning we're back to
243 so let me just very briefly review
what we've done uh the last
sign we are in part one
and we riew some of the basic
definitions up to the statement on the
second law and we have to pick it up
from there
uh just quick reminder we said what we
mean by the word system and we explain
that the word system is loaded with
meaning it's not just uh that anything
can be assisted it has to
qualify uh in particular there is a
constraint on how the external uh forces
should be uh mounted in your model they
must not depend on coordinates of
external constituents of your
system later on we'll see that we there
is also another uh constraint reg
relating to
correlations also
uh this means that your this your system
should not um depend uh on
uh be cooperative with some other system
if if it is you have to consider also
the other uh system in order for it to
call to be called a system uh in our uh
in our little
business in our little uh
um
the then we design the property uh as
being
physical observable so something that
you would
um obtain by PR your system in some way
according to some recipes some
measurement procedure and measurement
procedures are what define those
properties and we gave uh the
measurement procedure for a for
example we talked about what we mean by
the word State it's the list of numbers
that
uh give the values of the properties at
one instant of of
time and the time
evolution is described by equation of
motion in a detailed
um
model but it can also be uh described by
just an initial State the final State
and uh um a description of the effects
that occurred outside of your system um
during that time
interval in either
way we have a few things to check in
particular important business obser
Dynamics is that uh it has to you have
to check two things one the consisten
the first
law which would be a
theorem in the framework in which you
start from the equation of motion
theorem of the equation of
motion and you also have to check the
second law which would be another
theorem of the uh dynamical
equation the idea of process I already
said um it's three things initial State
final State and effects on the
environment of the system and uh how do
we account for effects in the
environment well uh the most we can say
is how it
State uh
changes then by defining uh the weight
process namely one in which the only
external effect is the uh highly lifting
or lowering of the weight in a gravity
field which is a prototype of the
mechanical
effects we could introduce the statement
of the first
law it is an ingredient of that
statement it says that you take any
system and any pick any two states of
that
system they can always be interconnected
by means of a weight
process you not always you can do it in
uh either the direction you want but if
you cannot do it in One Direction you
can do it in the
other and then gives grounds for the
definition of uh of support for the
measurement procedure uh that we
introduce to define the property en
without the first law you
couldn't assert that by making this
procedure you
get property valuable
property so essentially this is the main
uh uh the most important consequence of
the first law is the existence of
property energy which yes then it is
addied it can be exchanged between
systems and uh its
concern and that gives rise to the
energy imbalance uh
equation with this
symbol which you have applied in your
undergrad courses or previous
uh we every every time we we perform a
model we we perform an energy balance to
account for to check that the difference
between the final and initial value of
property
energy is equal to the energy that uh
the net energy that is being received by
the system during that time
interval so that's a statement of uh
conservation of that so some people call
this I write the first law but I prefer
to say I write the energy balance
then we headed towards the second law by
introducing this idea of
um classification of States based on how
they change in time and why they change
in time particular we focused on
equilibrium for the moment but later on
we will focus on non
equilibrium and there is equilibrium an
equilibrium and we Define what we need
by stable equilibrium and meta
equilibrium the Sable equilibrium States
is most important because it enters the
statement of the second law and uh it is
defined as a
state uh an equilibrium state so that
means it doesn't move doesn't change in
time it doesn't move in in state space
so it doesn't uh change with
time
and and you cannot change it
without uh uh paying a cost uh without
having some net external effects you
need to uh spend something in order to
change a stable equ you cannot do it
uh for
free so to
speak and here is the statement of the
second law it is also made up of two
assertions uh let's start first with the
uh we focus first on
uh certain
wine it responds to the question uh how
many stable equilibrium states do a
system hand in a way that is apparently
contradicting the what we know from
mechanics uh because it says that uh if
you fix for your system the amounts of
constituents so that means the number of
particles of each kind and the Val of
the parameters that is all the like the
volume of the system or the other things
that describe uh
the external force or the things that
you can control from the external so you
fix
this then for each value of the
energy there is one and only one stable
equum state that is the statement uh
introduced by uh
I think by George atopos when he was uh
collaborating with Jo Kenan uh in the
60s uh in this
department and we'll talk about this the
second session in a
moment and we will see also um as we go
on that in fact there is no
contradiction as long as we
understand and and we convince ourselves
that thermodynamics considers a set of
states that is broader than the set of
States considered in mechanics So within
the set of mechanics there's only one
stable eum state which is the lowest
energy State for the given values of N
and beta uh but uh in the more broader
uh set considered by
thermodynamics there is one equum state
state mistake for
um every value of the
AG and these has consequences
important consquences that we will uh uh
uh
beuss
today yeah so one would uh ask well
why I mean we we already have statements
of the second law why do you accept this
other one well that's because it is more
General uh and it implies as cuses as
theorems the most famous statements of
the second law which are the Cy plank
statement called also a possibility of a
perpetual motion machine of the second
kind we this is the only thing we will
prove today uh in some I mean some
fashion because it's
easy is a direct consequence of the
first assertion of the second
law and later
on uh not
today uh probably next time uh we prove
the other statement of the second law
which is
Claus
statement the one that says that uh uh
heat does not go from uh from cold to
Haw from D Vice
vers that requires that we introduce
Define what we mean by heat what we mean
by temperature uh it
takes a while not long but another
lecture but the beauty of this
construction is that you you get to that
result as as a theorem of of uh combined
first and second
law there is also another important
statement by karate aing which is more
mathematical though which can also be
proved but we will not do it in this
course okay so what is the Perpetual so
now I want to talk about kin plank U say
what um is a perpetual motion machine of
the second
kind all right is any
device essentially a system in our uh
language that would start from a stable
equilibrium
State remember a state that cannot be
changed without uh leing some net
external
effects and and in another state a
different
state why in a weight process in which
uh the um the weight goes
so in which you have transferred some
energy out of your system and into
lifting the weight okay if you manage to
do that it's a perpetual motion machine
of the second
kind it's funny
because uh it has been very long since I
have not received any um emils from
these uh crazy inventors
but perhaps because I I mentioned it or
maybe Google listens or maybe that's
because I'm at MIT but uh on Wednesday I
receive one I would be happy to show it
to you very fun somebody who wants to
put a container in the sea and it's yeah
it's a it's not even Perpetual machine
of second kind it's of the first kind I
would say and I think the guy needs to
learn some mechanics but
um in the old days it was a continuous
flow of applications for patents uh in
uh
violating this uh the impossibility of
the
same until in the 60s or the 70s I
forget the patent office uh uh US patent
office decided that anything that
violates uh uh the law of the or the
principle of this principle of
impossibility ofm to uh is rejected
immediately without going to uh
referee that's
because as I may have told you I forget
the last time but uh I remember when I
was a student with Professor gpos he
would uh be so well um um educated that
to uh reply
in written and in full length to any
letter that he would receive which is a
principle that I still have uh uh but he
would spend like 20 pages to explain
line by line why you wrong and what and
U often these crazy inventors make very
complicated uh and uh convoluted
reasoning that uh makes it very hard to
dismantle and uh and uh and reject but
he was doing that uh
consistently uh whether you whether it
was it was asked by the patent office or
by the inventor
direct fortunately we don't have that uh
sort of spam any longer so how do we
prove this well one way uh one simple
way is uh to prove it that if I if F
system can be divided into two parts so
let's uh
reason this so that we see also what
kind of proofs uh logical proofs
are we're talking about and it is
a a proof of ABS also that means we
assume that the emm2 is possible and
show that leads to a
contradiction so let's assume that our
system which can be divided in two parts
that an addition of assumtion can be
removed but it makes things more
complicated assume that it does ser from
a stable equilibrium State and it does
end in a different state
A1 with as external effect the lifting
of
way all right if that's true if that's
happened then you can take the energy of
the weight
back and use it to take one from the
system and accelerate into some veloc
give it in form of kinetic energy take
the potential energy of the wave and
give as kinetic energy of the second
part of the
system so what did we
achieve so look at this St and the initi
should
State why why is this not possible
because the final state is different
from the initial one and the initial
one was a stable equilibrium
State and there are no external effects
because the wave went up but then it
also we down so the net external effect
is zero yet we manage to start from a
stable State and change it to an
entirely to a different
set that contradicts
the definition of stable
equilibrium
okay all right so this is the proof of
plus of the
second now in order to go uh on the
second aspect of this second or second
assertion we we left behind one of the
definitions that are peculiar of
thermodynamics and it's the uh that of
reversible process what we mean by
reversible
process okay the definition is a solor
you you have a process first of all so
it means you have the initial and final
say and you have an external
effect B1 goes to
V2 the state of the environment changes
so
much okay the process is we call it
reversible if it is possible not
necessarily retracing back uh backwards
exactly the same forward path of your
initial uh process but in any other way
if you find a way to bring the state of
your system back to its
initial and also the stake of the
environment back to its initial
State then and only then we call the
process
reversible okay so that means you have
to try have all possibilities this a
very
abstract definition but it's also very
precise so I usually I'm not going to do
it because the I want to make dust but I
usually take a piece of chalk and throw
it to the wall it breaks and asked
you is that process was that process
reversible or not what would you
say it's
not
fine
but how did you decide I know it's
in I mean I'm making something that
might sound wa SAR about all that other
dis better you can G back
that good okay so you use your physical
intuition that's because that's because
you have a background youve already see
the idea of reversibility and
irreversibility but in our game if you
accept the rules of our
game
uh what should you have done to to
decide you should have tried to
reconstruct the state of the piece of
Choke to see if it is possible to place
that and then also whatever it did to
the environment must be
undone and you have to try all possible
ways so how could you be so quick in
answering okay it's a correct answer but
uh you didn't apply our rules this is to
just uh underline this is a very
abstract concept and impossible in
practice it doesn't correspond to a a
procedure so that you can verify if a
process irreversible or not but it's a
con and soon we will find a a method and
of course as soon as we have defined
atopy that will be the method to compute
to calculate entropy measure entropy and
see how it changes and from that from
the entropy the balance equation we can
decide whether a process is symol or not
so we develop a practical method to uh
measure this very abstract uh
concept so why is uh uh reversible the
concept of reversible process important
in the second law because uh the second
statement uh second assertion it
says you start from any state of your
system
and you you can always
go to a stable equilibrium
state to bring your system from that
state to a stable equilibrium
State and in a wave
process which is
reversed so it's lot L all our concept
together that's why we find them before
uh now we put them all the all together
there but if you go slowly and you
Mumble about it uh um that's what it
says uh redefine all the terms start
from initial State you can always uh get
your system to a saying say uh maybe so
way processed a reversible way processed
okay now it turns
out that if you try other
ways
to change your state to a stable
equilibrium
State other ways that are not
reversible you would uh lift the weight
less than when it is
reversal so that means this is a
theor and uh uh yeah it's proved in the
the usual book and uh the theorem says
that the
maximum uh lift that you can give to a
weight in a weight
process with your system starting in any
state is
obtain when your system ends in a stable
equilibrium State and when the process
is
reversing and that final stable
equilibrium
state is uniquely fixed by your initial
state only one stable equilibrium state
that can be reached in a reversible
weight process uh uh from State
A1 so this is enough to say that the
amount of energy that you transferred to
the weight in these conditions is a
property depends only on state A1 so
that is only on time
T1 because the final state is a function
of A1 so it po defend on T1
on the state
at1 and we call this property atic
availability of the system in state
A1 it's the
maximal I don't want to call it but we
could also call it work because
eventually that's a work interaction so
it's a maximum work you can extract from
your
system in the given state
and if you are an
engineer and you're trying
to make devices to uh exploit
um
um natural resources like uh
energy resources like coal natural gas
uh nuclear whatever
solar you you the main question that
then Dynamics was set for 200 years ago
by carau is well what's the most I can
do out of this
situation and diabetic
availability is an
answer of course it gives an answer
under certain conditions you change the
conditions you get different answers as
we will see we will have more
availabilities it depends on the
condition here the condition is in a
wave process so if I have my system and
I confine myself to just a wave
process that's the amount of the maximum
amount of energy I can extract from my
system the most I can do out of
it if it weren't for
um an important uh uh detail uh we we
would be satisfied that thetic
availability is all that we need in
order to describe our engineering
applications the detail is that this
property is not
additive and therefore it's not very
practical
because um when you
have a a system made out of two
subsystems and you measure the availab
the adamatic availability of system a
and then the adamatic availability of
system B uh well if you want to consider
the combin system you have to make
another measurement to measure the
adamatic availability of the system
C the the the simplest example that I
can think of as suppose you have a glass
of
water which is H
hot and a glass of water which is uh
cold so you measure thetic availability
of this
one and if it is hot but in a stable
equilibrium
State how much is thetic
availability it's zero because otherwise
it would be a
pmn2
no I mean if you could uh if you started
from a sa equum State you cannot leave
the we so a system in a sa equum state
is zero diabatic availability so the
thetic availability of uh we use a
letter s so of uh this glass of water is
zero P of that glass of water is
zero but if I
consider the composite system of course
we all know
that for example with a Carno
engine you can extract work out of this
situation so you see that 0 plus 0 uh
does not make number different from Z so
we lack additivity of this proper and
this is why it takes uh the next half
hour to build up um another property it
will be
entropy which will contain features so
that we can compute the TIC availability
and it will be addied we have to build
additivity on around atic availability
there is
also this other
theorem that I'm not proving but I'm
pointing you at this U proof uh it's on
page 76 of of the book um again so since
I'm not doing it I'm not uh
uh asking that you study it but uh if
you're curious just go and
look
and it
says that if you consider a weight
process so now we confine ourselves to a
weight
process between any two
SES
okay so
um clearly if you since our thetic
availability is a property now you can
measure it for sayate any1
you could also measure it for State
A2 like uh energy the property so you
can measure it for A1 you can me it for
A2 so you give me two states of system
a and I can measure for each s its
energy and its arotic
availability so it turns out that this
theorem says that if uh
you have a a necessary and sufficient
condition
for the process to be
reversed
if the difference between energy and
arotic availability so you could
interpret that as the energy that is not
adiabatically
available at the
end is equal to the energy not
adiabatically available at the beginning
so uh in a reversible process the energy
not diabatically available is
concerned
whereas in an irreversible
process it
increases very similar in fact also
entropy will play the same will will
will play in a similar way
so this uh energy not adiabatically
available is a weakness of
uh reversibility it's the basis for uh
measuring uh in practice whether a
process isible or not all you need to do
is according to if you trust this
theorem is measure energy measure
adiabatic availability with the tools we
developed and then check this
inequality if you is an equality the
process is reversible the reverse sorry
the weight processing is reversible if
it is uh an
inequality uh like like this one the
process is
irreversible if it's the other way
around it's impossible it may something
wrong so it is
impossible to
decrease uh the amount of energy that is
not at vacally
um
a okay so this is a precursor of the
principle that we will call of entropy
non decree we could call it the
principle of non decrees of the energy
nonat thetically non
available of okay so now
we try to
make or build up this
property that has
um that builds a additivity
into diotic availability so we are
heading towards a
eight in order to do that we introduce
some other Concepts the first one is the
concept of mutual stable equum for
Mutual
equilibrium between two
systems so two systems are in mutual
equilibrium like the hot and
cold they these are not a mutual
equilibrium
because because the composite
system is not in a stable equili State
the fact that it has diabetic
availability because that's an if and
only if theorem so the fact that it has
nonzero diabatic
availability uh is equivalent to not
mean a stable equum
state so these
two they are individually in stable
equilibrium but the composite is not in
a stable equilibrium state so they are
not in mutual stable
equilibrium in another situation in
which
instead they are individually and also
the composite system has zero diabetic
availability so that means the
um the uh the composite is in stable
equilibrium then you say that the uh two
systems are in mutual equilibrium that's
the
concept the other
concept is that of thermal
Reservoir a thermal Reservoir is a
particular system I would uh say a
limiting
system there has this feature that I
will describe with a practical system
making any
L you take the substance like water in a
fixed volume
container and you
produce
uh a Poss a combination that we call
triple point so a situation in which you
have the
coexistence in stable
equilibrium of ice liquid water and
water
vapor right here ice liquid water and
VAP
okay then you find another
system let's call it
C that is in neutal equilibrium with it
for for example it could be another copy
of another uh piece of water at the
triple
point but not
necessarily the important thing that
defines a reservoir a thermal Reservoir
is that if you uh change the
energy of this particular system for
example I I consider a state with more
energy so it will have lesser
eyes uh maybe a little more water or or
less liing water in any case so the
proportions of the three phases
change so the these are two different
stes with different energies
but they are both in neutral equilibrium
with this systen C
all why did I choose triple point water
that's because H it
is easy to prepare in any uh
blood and as you
know we haven't defined yet what the
temperature is in a moment we'll do
it but just because you know what
temperature is uh uh triple point uh
is at a low pressure
like6
kilopascal and at a temperature of
273.16 so it's
.01
celsus
okay so now that we have the
reservoir we apply again the second
assertion of the second
law which says we can always start from
a system in any
state and
reach a stable equilibrium state in a
reversible way
process this is an important load
statement that it it it allows it I mean
how do I know that it always
exists okay it's very
abstract but is very similar to the
statement that says in the first law the
second assertion that says yeah you can
always interconnect the two weight
process that in the two states by mean a
weight process but uh uh no matter what
weight process you choose it's always
the same energy that you transfer out to
the weight how do you know that by
because I can invent uh many different
ways to to to do their job and how how
do I know that they will all get the
same outcome okay that also is a very
abstract idea but it works because
energy as after all has been very
successful in describing stuff in in
physics and we believe that it so much
to be one of those great conservation
principle that we talked about last time
and here is the same thing we have a
very abstract idea about the existence
of something it guarantees that now we
Define a measurement procedure based on
this if we didn't have this statement we
couldn't uh um trust our measurement
procedure and the measurement
procedure is based on this ingredient
which I repeat uh here um with a little
more detail so I take a system and the
resare and they are some initial States
a one and in the r
one the res starts in a stable
equilibrium State like water at the
triple
point then I do a reverse Symon weight
process for this combination for this
combined system composite
system uh which has is only a teral
effect the lifting of the weight
and it's maximal lifting because uh the
process is
revers because it's the weight process
is revers so that's the maximum we are
applying essentially the theorem of
adiabatic availability here but to the
composite
system
uh a uh n r all right if this L thing is
uh
Massimo and
I think I jumped a little bit but maybe
I I I could I could say that if the F if
the finance say order to apply the
theorem of adiabatic
availability the final state would have
to be a stable equilibrium say for the
for the composite system
now and by our definition of mutual
equilibrium it would mean that uh since
the composite is in stable equilibrium
the two parts are in mutual equilibrium
so it means that the final in the final
State
A2 the system a is
in here I want to do it a little more
General and
uh you see I'm applying that theorem
twice because I'm going you know in
order to go from A1 to
A2 I could uh in which uh my reservoir
is an R1 and here is an R uh
two so now I
do consider the
composite of the two systems
uh the theorem of adiabatic availability
says that uh if I
go let's say
R let's call it R um r r okay so if I go
from here to here and this one is a
stable equilibrium State for the
composite then I have extracted as much
as I
could uh also I can do it starting from
state two
so here I would extract the adiabatic
availability let's call it c one one of
system of the composite system
a and here I would have
extracted the adiabatic availability of
this uh of the system uh in this other
state to
to
okayy but since in doing this extraction
I'm using reversible weight
processes I can
also
um reverse the arrow so I can go this
way and of course I
undo the effect on the
weight so as I go from here I so that
means I can go from here to there by
means of that reversing we process and
the amount of energy I transfer to the
weight is uh s 1 minus S
okay however in this the ingredient uh
yes so we we know how much energy we
transfer to the weight in that process
on on the on the
slide but for the measurement procedures
that we are going to introduce in a
moment uh was was um important is
uh the changing energy of the
res how much did the energy of the
reservoir change during this
process because that's something that we
can measure so measure you do that
process you give me
a uh choosing two states A1 and A2 the
second low guarantee is that you can do
this process with any
Reservoir and then once you've done it
you can measure energy because you we
Define property energy and so measure it
for the reservoir and make the
difference of the final energy of the
reservoir and its initial
energy now this Syle here is complicated
because
uh uh no because I want to
emphasize
that yes we are measuring an energy
difference for a for the
reservoir but it's more than that it you
we have to do it in those particular
conditions so it it says that system a
starts like this and so on that the
process is a weight process and that uh
it is reg you do it under under other
conditions it's another St okay all
right
so this is the
ingredient okay with that
ingredient here is the measurement
procedure that defines a property that
we will call um temperature of the
res and that will turn out to be a uh
the constant for the given resware so
equal for all of it uh stable
equilibrium
States we already know for we already
know that for U for the triple point
water it's
2736 K or
0.01
Celsius
and if
after it
is for as long as you in the Box you
have all three phases you can you can
put in energy take the energy out and so
on as long as um you have at least some
ice some water and some water vapor um
that temperature doesn't
change so it's equal for all the states
of that
system okay but how do we measure it
okay so now for this meas measurement
procedure the object of measurement is
the res you come to my lab with you
Reservoir and I am supposed to
measure this property for your reservo
so here's
the
object in order to do the measurement I
take an auxiliary
system so I choose whatever system I
want and any arbitrary two states for
that
system and I
do my my reversible weight
process for the
combination that will list the weight by
somehow some some El and I measure how
much your changes in energy and I put
that in the
numerator in the
denominator I put the result of the
similar measurement that I have done
once and for all
for a reference Reservoir we I happen to
like to choose the triple point
water of
course when I did this measurement I use
the same system a and the same two
states A1 and
A2
okay and I measured how much energy
changes the this res were reference res
and I take this
so this ratio is a measurement by
comparison it's exactly like when you
say well uh uh how long is this uh thing
okay you compare it with the meter or
the inch uh okay and the meter is
another object U that is maybe in some
Museum in Paris but and you see how how
many times this thing stays so take the
ratio of the this length to the length
of the meter you get a dimensionless
number it's exactly like here it'sing
this L there and as you know when you
have measurements like that you can
introduce a unit of measure you call the
meter one meter but you could have
called it uh
uh I don't know how many
each is s a meter but you could call it
like
40 something uh
H
okay it
say we take the
ratio we
multiply we take this unit not
one Gibbs or one at what we call it
since Kelvin was the first we call it uh
and he didn't put one but he put
273.16 all right so that's our uh basis
but we put here this
number and the
result so you multiply by that number
this dimensionless ratio and you
get this property temperature in Kelvin
of course there is a an important
theorem again proved there that uh says
first of all that this ratio is
positive that it is
independent of the initial states of the
reservoirs that it is
independent of your choice of auxiliary
system and once you've chosen that
system independent of the initial and
final a States A1 and A2 of that
system and also that it is equal for all
states stable equum states of the of the
res so that is a
property add a constant volume we call
it the temperature of the res notice we
Define just the temperature of a res we
haven't defined yet the temperature of a
stable equili state of the general
system not
yet but this is enough for our
purposes also notice that the by the way
we Define the property to this formula
you can rewrite that formula by taking
the things with the subst r on the left
uh hand side and subst R zero on the
right hand side you get
this
uh other
equality from this equality you can
infer what that uh if I measure this
ratio for Reservoir R it's the same as
for the reference Reservoir it's the
same for all
reservoirs so it's independent of the
res
so this ratio although we use the
reservoir to measure it is independent
of the res so what does it depend on it
depends only on the system a the
auxiliary system that you have used and
the two
states this is why this is very
important because essentially this leads
us to the
definition of
entropy that ration
we call it the entropy
difference between two states A1 and
A2 of our
system if you want to put it in another
way what's the measurement procedure for
entropy okay so now you come to my lab
and uh bring your system and bring the
system in a given State on which you're
interested in measuring the
entropy again I tell you look I just can
measure entropy differences so it
pick reference uh State a zero Give It
Whatever value you want for the enthropy
of that one I measure only the
difference and how do I measure the
difference well I
run I find a reversible wave
process for your
system and my Reser for example I could
choose water at the triple
point but not
necessarily and
measure the energy change of the res
using this
process and put it at the
numerator in the denominator I put the
temperature of the reservoir that I have
previously measured with that other
measurement
procedure and this ratio we just proved
is independent of the res I I chose
here so I
add this ratio
to so this ratio essentially is the
answer that's difference in
entropy between these two
states all right so we have an explicit
uh measurement
procedure that gives us
anything and the advantage of this
property with respect to diabatic
availability is that it is
UND you do it for a system a you do it
for a system
B and then you do it for a system
composite AB where the the entropy is
the
same entropy differences are
added in a moment we will see also
um a practical engineering meaning of of
ENT but let me also
Define this other property which we
essentially already did here when you
have a system in combination with a
reservoir like here system and a
reservoir they start in some initial
States the Reser in a stable equilibrium
State system a in any state of the
equilibrium on equilibrium doesn't
matter I can apply the theorem of
adiabatic availability to the composite
system and find that the
maximum uh weight list that I can obtain
from this composite system in those
initial
States uh is thetic availability is uh
is obtained when
we make the reversible Pro the weight
process
reverse and it
also ends in a stable equilibrium for
the composite system so when the two
when a are are in mutual te
so here system a ends in a state that I
call a subr just uh to remind us that it
is the state in which system a is in
mutual equili with the
res and the final state of the uh
Reservoir is also
uniquely fixed by the initial states of
a and r
okay this is a new property you can view
it if you fix the reservoir or with
respect to a given Reservoir this is
another property for
system it is another availability
another U maximum worth in other
conditions when the system can also
interact or as an a reservoir available
with which to
interact we call it available energy
with respect to the reservoir
R we can make uh so so we call Omega
Omega is the energy that goes through
the
weight we can make you can write an
energy balance for that uh
process because now we know how to
compute the energy so we can compute the
energy
difference for system
a it
goes uh from A1 to a
r so the the energy that goes out of
system a is E1 minus
E the energy that goes out of the
reservoir is e the energy of R State
S1 minus the energy of R in this fin
state
and since any is conserved these are the
things that go out they they sum up to
what uh uh is received by the weight so
this is
theb but now if you remember how we we
defined the the entropy of syst a just
previous SL
it's the
ratio of the energy change of the
reservoir so it's this
Bunch the change is actually final minus
initial so it's minus this much divided
by the temperature so that's the eny so
this ratio Which con could substitute
this part using this equation and make
an expression for the available energy a
terms of the in
I to see
the the algebra
here so this is the working uh equation
for U Computing available energy of a
given
system all you need to to know available
energy with respect to to the reservo r
you need to know the initial energy the
final the initial entropy E1 and S1 you
need to know
the energy and that the entropy that the
system has once it gets into mutual the
reservoir and you need to know the
temperature of that
res and this is a
combination if you uh we call it
available energy respect the ter
reservoir
uh later on when we give it say a few
words about ARG I this one form of
ex ex is a war that was invented in the
70s so maybe
uh uh earlier Kenan called it
availability in 1941 so this concept is
around for been a while around for a
while U but
exergy the X means like it's like the
essential part of of energy because
exergy is the answer to the question
what's the maximum I can do for from a
given situation so there are many
exergies and we already have seen a
couple a diabatic availability is an
energy that applies when the system
under goes just a weight
process uh here we have available energy
it's another energy that applies when a
system uh also is available a uh a
reservoir it is the combination of the
system and the the reservoir with I'm
going to go away
first so this is the formula so let's
play again here let's play a bit with
the formula and rewrite it in this way
putting in evidence the entropy of State
one of the
system yeah before I before I do that
notice that um
except for the temperature on the
res this formula doesn't have any other
um properties s so doesn't have the the
difference
in has disappear because we wrote that
in terms of the entropy change for the
for the
system okay so we put in evidence the
entrop of system a state
A1 any we notice
that except for some things that are
constant fixed
by The Chosen
Reservoir the entropy is
proportional to the difference between
energy and available energy so again it
is the energy that is not available
with respect to the
res divided by the temperature of the
res so the entropy is proportional to
the proportional to the non available
ener with respect
to so the higher the entropy the lesser
the energy that can be transformed to uh
lifting a away which is the Prototype of
a useful effect mechanical
effect so that's why I C engineering me
of lot of mechanical engineering Energy
Engineering is related to trying to
exploit as much as possible the
availability of systems in other words
to uh um an entropy Place
against let entropy increased you lose
ability to do useful effects so that's
why in engineering we have to working at
trying to improve the efficiency of
stuff of machinery and so on uh with the
purpose of
reducing the spontaneous generation of
an because that will
kill the available
energy okay uh we said already said that
thop is additive and it can be proved
that is
additive and
uh the the theum on the criteria for
reversibility we already see the first
line here expressed in terms of thetic
availability of the system you can
express the saying that theorem uh
translates also for uh available
energy so
the the difference between energy and
available energy in respect to any
Reservoir any given reservoir uh remains
constant in a reversible process so the
unavailable energy remains constant in a
reversible
process while it increases in an
irreversible
process and it cannot
decrease and since we just saw that this
these are available energies
proportional to to uh the entropy we can
write this
as s
remains
constant in a reversible way
process energy I'm sorry entropy
increases if the process is
everal entropy cannot decrease in a
weight
process but careful here about the
conditions that we make this statement
in uh
because it would be wrong to say ah
energy I mean the entropy cannot
increase the entropy decreases all the
times whenever you take a can of Coke
and put it in your refrigerator the
entropy of that kind of coke decreases
because you're cooling it down that is
not a weight process what we're saying
here that the entropy cannot decrease in
a wave process if the only external
effect is only uh the
changing I mean the lifting or or
lowering of the of the weight then you
cannot decrease the
anop but you can decrease the anop of
your system by simply taking making it
flow out on your system because
entropy is actually uh
transferable we prove that in the same
way as we for the transferability or
exchangeability of energy consider a
composite system you apply uh
um if I do it for a reversible processor
then enthropy remains constant so it's a
con principle entropy conservation in a
weight a reversible wave
process you combine it with additivity
you find that uh the entropy
cannot
disappear if it goes out of system a it
means that you find it somewhere else in
system
b in a reversible wave
process so in the same way as we uh
decided to give a symbol to this amount
of entropy that is transferred from one
system to the other we use a symbol that
a simil so s for entropy
transferred from B to a in the direction
of the our Arrow so it's it's a positive
number if the slow is in the direction
of the arrow otherwise it's a
negative and so we can write this as a
balance
equation a balance
equation uh for a reversible process you
wouldn't have this part would simply
say that if there is a change in
enthropy of your system it is due to the
amount that it has of entropy that has
been
transferred with this
environment but then entropy is not
really
always conserved it's conserved only in
a reversible process in an irreversible
process it's not
conserved and if the process is a way
process it can only increase so that
means
that the entropy change of my
system can be greater than the amount it
received but cannot be
lower so essentially we are writing an
an inbalance equation and a balance
equation if you
want uh it becomes a balance equation if
you put in the balance also um
the imbalance by calling it
enop generated or produced by uh
aab and this brings us to the uh en
balance
equation I assume that you have um play
with
this in solving problems uh in undergrad
thermodynamics and your applications in
energy or exergy analysis uh any uh
technological uh uh
problem to
do with uh energy transformation of
energy various Force requires you to
make not only an energy balance but also
an entropy balance and the and the
combination of the two is what allows
you to determine uh things like uh how
good am I doing uh what's the efficiency
of what I'm
doing so these balance equations as we
see more
explicitly are the fundamentals to
Define efficiencies of U um Power blands
and uh any
lies that does transformation of edge
okay this is also um the version of the
entropy
balance a r version of the entropy
balance if you have the kind of
description in which you can follow as a
function of time the state of the system
therefore you can measure as a function
of time the entropy and also how much
entropy is we exchange
them as in the right of the entropy
exchange and remember that in an entropy
balance there are three very distinct
elements there are three parts of the
equation the left hand side says how
much the property changes from the final
to the initial
State the transfer term says how much
the system the net uh entropy that has
been received by your system or
exchanged if it is negative it's given
out by a
system due to interactions it's a flow
of ENT going in and out of your
system the last term
inste
is the
generation it occurs internally to your
system it's the
dissipation it's the waste and the curse
if you let thing
uh
uh move around for example you take
um Irish coffee no uh it's very nice if
you until it is separate first time you
see it you were
excited if you stir it you lose you lose
the the beauty no and by Sting it you
have uh mixed up things you have
produced uh
generated you
lost I mean the beauty because you are
sort of big trunk and so that's
but this gives the idea of the fact that
stirring um is something
that happens uh
spontaneously uh if you help it by
stiring it it help it it goes
faster and it's something that you
cannot
undo I mean the Irish thing will not uh
separ maybe to but
uh not in not not in sure talking about
um energy
applications so the if you're not
uh careful enough and things get stirred
up you lose opportunities to convert the
energy and to extract energy out of your
source and you've lost it
forever
okay luckily
um I don't think this time this I don't
think today but
the next time we will be able to
introduce
a a graphical representation of all that
we have said that is very useful to
remember and to reason uh
um uh the various consequences and also
to set
up problem solving and answering
additional questions it will be the
energy versus entropy uh di down
uh but we're still building up uh
material so that we can use the diagram
to summarize what we have seen so
far and one of these ingredients that we
still need is um another theorem that is
called the maximum entropy principle
which says that um among all the states
of a of a given system once you fix the
value the values of the amounts of
constituents and the parameters the
external
forces and uh you
consider of course you remember that uh
if I fix the amounts of constituents
let's call
them n of
T let's forget the t
n n
beta this doesn't uh fix the state
because the state
is these numbers plus the values of all
the conceivable
properties most of the times this list
is an infinite number of
numbers okay so fixing just this two
leaves you again with an Infinity of
States now suppose I I fix also the
value of the N
energy okay so I fix this
much still I have a lot of stat they
will differ in the values of all these
other properties but they have the same
energy okay so if I consider all these
states that have the same energy amounts
of constituents and uh parameters of the
exteral
forces it's a set in this set the second
law first assertion says there is a
unique Saum
State this theorem
says that state is also the highest
value for the
an and it's a strict uh uh
inequality it's it's the only state that
has that value all other states with the
same energy and so on uh
have lesser
entropy the stable State among these
ones is the one that
achieves the maximum value is and it is
the only one that achieves their far
this is called the maximum entopic
Bri there is also a dual uh principle uh
that it's called the minimum and energy
fre similar to this one except that here
you put
s so if I consider all the states of a
system that have same given same values
of n beta and the same
entropy then among all these
states there is one St stable
equilibrium state
only and and it is the lowest
energy when you fix the value of s to
zero that corresponds to the the domain
of
mechanics and that minimum energy stable
equilibrium state is the only one and so
then we recover the minimum energy fre
for of mechanics
but thermodynamics is about states that
have also entropies difference from
zero and so we have a more General
minimum yes in that we basically saying
that
um yes if you start from um the low
estable eum
State
um like this one is a stable equum
state if you spend some
work so if I go this direction and I
spend some work I can obtain any other
state any other state but
only those that have the same entropy as
I started with if the process is
reversible I the entropy will remain
constant so I can I can go from my
minimum energy stable equilibrium state
to any other state Which is higher
energy because I put in some work
but it um if it is um reversible it has
the same U entropy if it is irreversible
it would have higher entropy so I can go
only let's say if I'm here with energy I
can go up and then this is entropy so
this will okay so I start with certain
value of the entropy say s uh
R I can go
up in a reversible process to values of
the
energy higher than I started with so
this is
e or I can also go to the right
because I put in
energy but if the process is
irreversible I generate some entropy so
the entropy adds and I go to the left to
the to the
right so so yes thanks because this
anticipates essentially this energy
versus entropy diagram and which is
useful because as you know a picture is
worth a thousand words and uh uh this is
the picture that allows you to answer
this uh kind of
questions uh the last ingredient we need
in order to go to that graphical
representation is called the state
principle again it is a consequence very
directly from the first assertion of the
second
law which says You Fix N and
beta fix and in beta
you fix the
energy and once these are fixed there is
a
unique there exists a unique stable
equilibrium
State
T all right the last s means
stay so yes it's a state which is stable
equilibrium so what does mean state
state means the values of all the
properties so that means that this thing
fixes the values of all the
properties of course we're talking about
overstable equili
could
stake
so we so
mathematically that's exactly what we
mean by a function the properties it
means that this properties any property
is a function of these numbers if these
numbers fix the value that's what we
mean by value of a such so we can write
a
property of stable ium at
Saum as a function of the amounts the
parameters and the
energy and since among the various
properties we Define and entropy we can
also write that for the entropy so we
can say that for the St equum States the
entropy the value of the a of be six
like call
Properties by the amount of constituents
the parameters of the forces and the end
this expression this formula this
function is called the foundamental
relation for the Saum States in some
oldfashioned books of
thermodynamics this function is page one
you take the book by colen Ken was a PhD
from MIT
also uh very nice contributions
but in his times uh thermodynamics was
only about sa
St and so that's the starting point and
U since I'm I'm I'm e it why not say and
reminding you that instead we've seen a
definition of
entropy uh
today in which you may or may have not
noticed but I will stress it anyway
that we never said anything about how
many particles the part the system
should
have in our game so far we could have a
system with one particle or 10 to the
23 it could be just water in a box or a
nuclear power
plant complex or
SLE small or large plus we didn't make
any assumption about the kind of
state
fact uh most interesting
states are those that are not savable
equilibrium at least from the point of
view of making a weight
process because in a stable equilibrium
State we just we just have seen that the
perpetual motion machine of the second
kind is impossible you cannot extract uh
work so not very useful from from an
engineering point of
view and that's why uh consider the
ocean the ocean is a as a thermal
Reservoir not the waves that's a
different story but there a thermal
Reservoir and if you forget also the
fact that the inside there are
temperature gradients and also salinity
radi so on but if you fake Co it as a
huge uh system so it has a huge amount
of energy but that energy is essentially
useless the thermal energy is
useless because it's in a equum
state
whereas if I have a a system in a non-e
equilibrium
State uh and I'm quick enough to extract
its adiabatic availability I can do
something useful
for example we will do uh later on
uh in the second part we will do like
chical Rea you think of uh what happens
inside your internal combustion engine
got the Piston you got a mixture of air
and and
gasoline and uh you like the
SP at that moment you produce an on
state which very quickly in matter of
micros and milliseconds will uh uh
interest the entire combustion
chamber pressure will go up and so
on the internal combustion engine is an
incredible incredible uh device that uh
has been there for a century now maybe
longer uh and it's still uh powering our
cars and uh
because it's a smart way to extract the
availability it doesn't do the entire
job though
because it loses the opportunity that
you have from when you uh light the
spark to when uh uh the flame is uh
engal the entire combustion
chamber that is a very irreversible
uh process and that's where you lose uh
the about um what is it 60% of uh of
your uh availability no because internal
combustion engine is 40% efficient so
that means that I lost 60%
somewhere and that's where I lost
it
uh
so no equilibrium
States and so we Define entropy uh also
for non equilibrium states which is most
important for the more modern
applications of thermodynamics and
that's why we're
here actually uh I was um very happy
just yesterday to receive um any an may
I think it was sent to the entire
Community not very special but uh I
didn't email from the MIT president
announcing this initiative about
climat
okay uh a
lot of the applications that will U come
out of that uh project in in the
future uh will have to do with energy
and the best use of
energy okay not only
CO2 segregation or greenhouse gases but
all the crazy ideas that people are
talking about in uh trying to control uh
uh for example the the amount of uh uh
heating that that comes uh uh to the sun
there was an article the other day in
the New York Times talking about people
that uh want to build a shieldy Spades
no to to um reflect away some of the
power some of the photons that come from
from from the Sun so that you could
control temperature of course you need
you need a surface to I think it was
like uh the surface of the entire um
Argentina which is essentially half of
South
America there somewhere put in a in a
place which they call it the lrange
place or lrange
SP where it would say because the
gravitational force on the sun is on the
earth is the same all right so uh yes
crazy ideas but one one tool with which
you have to evaluate these ideas and see
if they are feasible or
not is precisely what we are doing here
for any energy technology or for any
technology you have to see uh that
you're transforming forms of energy of
you're you're spending energy to rec to
recover another effect you have to
Define efficiency feasibility and
efficiency are very important now
because if you if the amount of energy
you consuming for a certain task is more
than the
the the the work minimum work to do that
task uh it's worthless you better not do
it we can do it in another way okay
so uh what I'm saying is that uh somehow
by learning
these tools and ways to understand the
equilibrium and non equilibrium for
small and for large and small
systems uh you are in good position to
go and contribute to this uh very bold
uh MIT project for might uh Enterprise
for the next 10
years so that brings me
to yeah one one more thing and then uh
just we have three minutes once I had a
function like this function
here then I can apply all the tools of
mathematics for example if I in looking
how the function behaves in the
neighborhood of uh the given point so
here's the function and I'm here and I
want to see uh how it behaves in the
neighborhood by changing one of the
variables for example the
energy right I can
uh write a series expansion on the
function I take derivatives first second
order if the function is uh um Regular
enough so that it's going to take at
least two the first two Thea to Che all
the variables you in good
shape and in
practice in most of the models the the
the function is analytic so it there's
all
der some of these partial derivatives
will turn out to
be uh
useful and to be um important uh in
determining um necessary conditions for
Mutual equilibrium between
systems and it turns out that all the
first derivatives the first partial
derivatives of this function
here play a role uh in deter meaning
those uh
mutually uh conditions and that's why we
give
names for example the derivative of s
with respect to
e is the inverse of what we will call
the
temperature of the stable equilibrium
state of the
system yeah that's because I I I write
it also this way
is a derivative of s of e with respect
to
S uh because once you have a function
and if it is U uh well behaved enough so
that all the derivatives are not neither
zero or infinite you can invert the
faction okay there are mathematical
theorems for inting faction so if I add
this function of s and the function of E
I can also most of the times write it as
a e is a function of
s if I can do that not for all systems
we'll see you can do that but if you can
do that P then you have another version
of the fundamental relation which is the
energy form because it makes energy
explicit and entropy becomes a dependent
independent
variable and you can also take
derivatives of this one so the partial
derivative of B with respect to S is
going to be what we call the temperature
of the stable equilibrium State the
partial of e with respect to n is going
to be the total potential or chemical
potential depending on
situations and uh if one of the
parameters is the volume the the partial
of the energy in respect to the volume
is what we will call the pressure with
the negative in front signning front
so this
um partial derivatives are related to
conditions for Mutual equilibrium and
are also therefore related to
instruments with which you measure
them by exploiting the mutual
equilibrium condition so you have the
thermometer the
monometer and
the uh again u a manometer that allows
you to measure partial pressures so that
you can compete mechanical
poten all right so we are out of time
and uh we stop here so next time we go
to the energy versus
entropy diagrams to summarize all that
we have seen and go further