Now we will continue with the different
startups. We have five startups under
the same dynamic.
10 minutes for each representative
of the startups that have been created
under MIT. Let's start with the first
one. Welcome
to the scenario. Brendan Smith,
representative of Citration.
We have 15 full-time team members and
growing all the time, hiring more great
people uh to bring on the team. What we
think about primarily at citration as
you can see here in our title is
developing a new process for what we
call the ultraefficient extraction and
recovery of copper and other precious
metals and minerals largely in the
mining sector. looking at primary mining
streams like leeches but also from
mining waste streams like tailings and
acid mine drainage. So we'll talk a bit
more about this in the next 10 minutes.
And so really importantly the reason why
we're doing this at citration is we feel
so so strongly that the global energy
transition is going to require a
critical minerals and a critical mineral
metals revolution. And what do we mean
by revolution? That can mean a lot of
different things. to citration. It means
we need to develop and implement new and
innovative solutions. What we think of
as full value mining and that may have
different definitions for different
people. When we think about full value
mining, we mean getting the the full
value not just out of the primary ore
that we're digging out of the ground,
but also extracting and recovering the
full value from the waste streams, the
tailings, the acid mine drainage as
well, while at the same time recycling
chemicals and recycling water back into
the mining process. So we don't have to
just throw that out into the waste and
desalinate more water or pipe more water
from the ocean for example. And so
copper is a great example of this. I
think actually the most important global
example with recent news and it's great
to be here in the heart of the you know
the copper producing nation of the world
in Chile. What we see as as I think all
of you today know is a steadily
increasing demand for copper through
2050 and beyond. And copper is special
because it's one of the most diversified
commodity metals in that it's needed for
not only the grid, the grid technology
and expansion, but also energy
generation and storage of course,
construction, and a whole plethora of
other different industrial applications
with which you're all very familiar. But
in the face of this almost inevitably
growing demand, I think we all agree
that it's going to happen and it is
happening today. We have several
challenges and and what we think of as
headwinds that we have to push through
to be able to meet this demand of
course. And so we have as we all know
declining or quality that was mentioned
this morning by Anagasta CEO. Uh we know
that over the last 40 years we've seen
about a 50% decline in copper or grades
which is a pretty staggering decline and
one that's not going to slow down and
reverse course as far as we know. We
also know that we're losing a lot of
value into the waist stream as I
mentioned before. So chiefly not really
with copper, but a whole plethora of
other critical minerals and metals that
are also essential for the energy
transition are largely flowing into the
waste and maybe dilute concentrations
that can't be economically or
sustainably recovered so far today. And
finally is the negative impact. And so
we all know that mining has an impact.
It's a very necessary impact uh to be
able to achieve this progress that we
need to achieve. But really importantly,
as we try to get more resources out of
the exact same amount of rocks that
we're already mining today, but needing
to be more productive and more
efficient, we need to mitigate that
waste production of solid and liquid
waste and tailings, uh, consumption of
energy and water in that process as
well. And so I think some of these
headwinds are actually driving the
opposite trend in what's predicted in
mining production of copper, which is
going the other way in a negative
direction for all those reasons I just
mentioned. And so we're we're seeing
projections of a shortfall of 40 to 50%
already by 2040. And so what are some of
the key pieces that could actually help
to close this gap as we really need to
do. When we look at the the market and
the industry and the sector today, what
we see is an incredibly complex process.
And in a lot of cases, we're using
hydromeergical and parameergical
uh processes or methods that were
developed in the 20th century up to 100
years ago. And of course we have
incremental innovation throughout that
hundred years or century but not
necessarily a lot of new technologies or
approaches because it's very difficult
to do. And so these things are complex,
10 or 15 steps to get one, you know,
critical metal target, for example.
They're high cost, takes a lot of
resources, energy, water, and chemical
coming into the process and going out
into the waste, not being reused. And of
course, then harmful to the local and
global environment. And as I mentioned
before, leaving a lot of those more
dilute longtail resources that are very
high value and very critical for our
future in the waist stream unreovered.
And so finally, this is where citration
comes in. We're working to enable a
paradigm shift in the mining sector and
other adjacent sectors and metals and
minerals by deploying a fully
electrified solution with no chemical
usage to extract these minerals,
concentrate them and recycle other
resources in the process in a very
streamlined way. At the core of this
system is two chief technical pillars
that Citration has developed, scaled up,
deployed and patented. The first is a
siliconbased filtration membrane. So
many of you are familiar with
filtration. The difference with our
membrane is it's uniquely durable. And
so we can utilize this with streams
directly of pH0, pH1, very high TDS,
very high solids loading, and pull out
clean water or clean acid for recycling
in the process. At the same time, we can
also up concentrate by say a factor of
10 to 15 times those dilute highly
valuable things like rare earth elements
or precious metals in that tailings
water for example. The second piece of
technology we've developed and are
deploying today, it's a siliconbased
electro extraction module. You can tell
we really like silicon at citration.
It's actually in our name. You probably
noticed. Um, and it's a silicon based
electro extraction module. It gives us
the same durability as the filtration
membrane, but the application here is
very different. It's very much similar
to electroinning that you're probably
all quite familiar with where we're
pulling out things like copper, cobalt,
nickel, and other precious metals like
gold and silver in a single step with no
chemical directly from those complex and
challenging streams.
And so when we talk to our global mining
partners including Antifagasta who we're
very thrilled to be working with today
about the advantages here we see several
really key important advantages. So the
chemical free nature of what we're doing
extremely important in terms of the
operating cost the sustainability we can
as I mentioned get to that really long
tale of dilute profitable byproducts
that typically aren't really leveraged
in most assets and we can do this while
really importantly reusing water and
acids that are going into the process in
terms of lxivians. At the same time,
it's a very modular, low capex, low opex
system. And so we can scale up or down
with on-site process requirements of a
specific asset. And then really
importantly, the durability speaks to
this a little bit, but we're highly
adaptable to very diverse. So you can
think about biolleaching or the um the
chloride leech that we've been talking
about at these uh at these sessions. And
we're compatible with all those things
in the exact same way we would deal with
a sulfuric acid leech, for example.
So a few examples for you with more
specificity and um in a quantitative
way. I mentioned we're dealing primarily
with PLS or primary leech and also
wastewater like tailings or acid mine
drainage. And from either of these feed
streams in that single step with no
chemicals, we're able to pull out 49's
purity copper which is extremely
important of course as a standard for
the industry. We can do this with a very
flexible form factor either with high
purity copper powder which you see here
on the slide in that single step. We can
also do a a highly dense cathodic copper
sheet like you would find in a standard
electing process for example. Really
importantly energy consumption has to
stay low that drives the operating cost
and so we can achieve well below 3 kwatt
hours per kilogram of copper which is
approaching on par with commercial
electroinning today. The yield can also
be very high. So we can achieve upwards
of 97% even approaching 99 or 99.9%
depending on the application. As I
mentioned, high compatibility with
diverse including chlorides and of
course sulfuric acid as well.
And so we're not just stopping at
copper. Uh it is our number one focus of
course unsurprisingly to all those in
the room. But with the exact same
hardware, the exact same process, we can
actually pull out diverse critical
metals and minerals um from very harsh
conditions. So think about hydrochloric
acid streams of pH negative1. We can
directly pull out gold that looks like
this from a stream like that. also
addressing platinum group metals,
platinum, platium, uh precious metals
like silver. I mentioned the base metals
and other really critical minerals like
lithium, manganese, and aridium to name
a few others that we're doing uh with
partners today. So, I want to really
emphasize that we're not just a
streamlined copper producer with high
efficiency, but also really importantly
unlocking this multi- metallic value of
an asset both in the primary process and
the the uh waist stream as well.
So, where we are today, we're still
relatively early, but we're scaling up
quickly. We took our uh demonstration or
a picture of this to a to Sentinel
yesterday and I think some people found
it kind of funny because it's so small.
Uh but we are really importantly looking
to scale up very quickly with partners
around the world. So today we're
deploying a thousand liter per day a
10,000 liter per day system on the site
with Riotinto in the United States
primarily to pull out copper from a
waist stream being acid mine drainage.
So that's being deployed this summer and
we're looking to bring something similar
very soon to Chile as well. But
importantly the scaleup potential is
very high. So we expect to do a 10x
scale up uh to 100,000 liters per day by
the second half of 2026 and then going
up much more much more quickly from
there. And so one of these great
partners today is of course Antifagasta.
We are down here to discuss you know
potential next steps with with you as
well and we're looking at different
applications in raphnate pls and
possibly on the way side. Then Riointo I
mentioned we're pulling out copper from
that acid mine drainage stream today on
a site in the United States. So I just
want to close by saying we're extremely
excited about Chile. We're really
appreciative of event Fagasta inviting
us down here. We're very excited for the
next steps and to continue working
together and scaling up the technology
and process. The reason we're so excited
about Chile is not just because it's the
copper capital of the world in in terms
of proven reserves, of course, which it
is. It's more about the attitude of of
doing this doing the scale up while also
generating all the clean energy
production that you're generating and
these state-of-the-art water management
systems that we feel overlap completely
with Citration's mission. So, not only
are we also trying to be very energy
efficient, very much streamline the
copper extraction process, but we're
also looking at reusing the water and
chemical on site to really advance the
sustainability aspect of what we're
doing and what our mining partners are
doing. So, that I'll finish up. Looks
like right on time. I would love to
contact all of you in the future if you
have interest in learning more. You can
find my uh email down at the bottom of
the slide there. And I really appreciate
your time and attention. Thank you.