it's our last class which is happy
because we get to go on break but
there's so much more I want to tell you
guys so but you know that's all we have
time for uh there are cookies here for
to make our last class sweet so please
come and get some if you want they're
very small so you can take to uh or you
know if you didn't want to commit a
large cookie you don't need
to so uh okay so today uh finally we're
going to actually construct the snars
that we've been after that was kind of
the goal uh is to uh construct uh snars
s interactive arguments and like this
entire course was a buildup to construct
uh these snars and today we're going to
see how to construct them uh they
cookies
guys cookies if you want from flower
really good ones so feel free to take
some um okay so uh what we're going to
do today is show how to construct these
snarks uh and uh we're gonna last class
Jen Jang uh uh showed you is a really
beautiful work on constructing bargs
which are batch
argument and you know on their own you
can say uh why do we care about B
argument I'm going to recall the
definition but the I mean it's
interesting on its own but what makes it
super interesting is that we can use it
in a pretty straightforward manner to
construct snars so that's what we're
going to see today we're going to see
how to use these bars that I'm going to
recall the definition in a second and
also how to use I think Jen Jong called
it a somewhere statistically binding
hash functions it's also known in the
literature as somewh extractable hash
functions both are used so I'm just
going to use the other just so familiar
with both uh a uh formulations uh both
names uh so what we're going to see
today is how to use these bars with with
these hash functions to get
snars that's kind of uh the plan for
today uh so let me first recall what a
barg is really uh fast so a bar you want
to kind of prove that many instances
belong to an NP language so about Mark
for an NP language L consists of three
algorithm gen uh takes as input a
security parameter the number of
instances you want to batch maybe I'll
close thank you can you close the door
thanks uh K which is the number of
instances you want to batch and N with
which is the length of each instance and
then
output uh some
CRS note Lambda is given in unary
because we want them to run in time poly
Lambda but K and N are given in binary
so because it's polinomial time
algorithm it runs in time poog in K poog
in N the instant size okay and then the
Prov algorithm takes as input uh the
CRS and then X1 up to xn uh XK sorry so
K elements with
Witnesses and outputs
uh proof
Pi but importantly this proof should be
small so this Pi is of
size uh poly log or poly in security
parameter but log K that's
important okay we want it to depend only
Poly arthic on on K that's kind of our
goal okay okay and then maybe ideally
also log n but the point is we want it
to be succinct okay otherwise it's
trivial you just output the witnesses
and the
verifier takes his input CRS the
instances and a proof and it output
01 accept or reject okay and this but
when I say the size of the proof is this
actually you can make it bigger smaller
but we want it to be SU
okay that's oh sorry I uh sorry I
didn't we wanted to depend only
logarithmically and K so on
but we allow it to depend uh L polom and
one in one witness okay so I can put it
here a single witness one not many
ideally we want to be as exing as
possible but what we can get is a as a
bar that depends grows with one instance
one witness as opposed to K
instances okay so uh so this is kind of
the the algorithms uh then we want
completeness and soundness completeness
is the usual thing that just says if P
has valid Witnesses and he generates a
bar this bar is going to be accepting
with probability one over kind of the
CRS generation so that's the standard
completeness and then uh the soundness
property
that uh that we have ideally you would
want to say that uh so in soundless
computational soundness we have adaptive
soundness and nonadaptive soundness and
we want to we want to say that the a
cheating prover cannot convince you of a
false statement so he cannot generate he
cannot give you X's that are not all in
the language with a valid proof that
soundless okay there's an issue is when
does the cheating Pro gets to choose
these X's is it before he sees the CRS
or after he sees the CRS if he needs to
decide them before he sees the CRS then
it's non adaptive if you get to decide
it after then it's
adaptive ideally we want to say it's
secure for all like very uh all as big
classes provs as possible and thus we
would like to have sounds against
adaptive provs to say even if a cheating
prover chooses this X1 of XC
adaptably after seeing the CRS if one of
them is false he cannot generate a proof
that's what we would like to say what we
can say is what's called a semi adaptive
something in between okay so let me just
write it here so semi-adaptive sound
is just says the adversary needs to tell
you which in so he's going to give you K
instances he can choose them adaptively
but he needs to choose the ion which is
going to cheat so he's a cheater so one
of that eyes is not in the
language which ey which location I the
XI is going to be not in the language
that should not depend on the CRS okay
so so it says that for any poly
size P star and for for every I which of
course may depend on on Lambda because
for any Lambda you have an i because the
I is between one and K and K grows with
can grow with Lambda so for any I you
want to say the probability that P star
given a
CRS outputs X1 up to XK and
Pi such that x i is not in the language
and Pi is accepted is negligible so XI
one of them is the XI one is not in the
language and the I was chosen before he
saw the CRS okay so for any P star he
tells you I'm going to cheat on location
I now he's given a CRS the probability
that he gives you an accepting proof for
X on of dek that he chose adaptively
after seeing the CRS the probability
that it's accepting so
CRS uh X1 up to XK and Pi is
one and X is not in the language x i is
not is
negligible this equals
negligible okay so again for any
cheating prover he needs to ahead of
time I'm going to choose my xon XK
adaptively after I see the CRS but I'm
going to I'm going to cheat on location
I the probability that he succeeds in
cheating in location
I in an accepting way is
negligible that's the semi-adaptive
soundness okay so and uh last class
jenong kind of showed you the high level
of how you construct such a like the
construction of such a
bar okay any questions yes uh is piz
required like the indices other than I
are those required to be act like in the
language or no no we don't care so yeah
good question so the P star can choose
the rest of the X's however he wants in
the language outside the language
however he
wants okay but he wins if the XI is not
in the language and the pi is
accepting and he wins with probability
yes transforming this into fully
adaptive will imply
guessing
yeah okay uh good so the question is can
why like can we transform this into a
fully adaptive snar so ah converting it
into a fully adaptive
snar is um non-trial and I'll tell you
why you can you can guess I you can
guess I and you'll guess it correctly
with probability one over k
in
general but here is so you you can do
the you can do it but here is the issue
I'll tell you what what um complication
is in the analysis so I I don't want to
recall too much the construction but the
high level idea of how these bars are
analyzed even without kind of knowing
the construction uh the way they're
analyzed in this CRS so in the proof in
the analysis we say Suppose there exists
some cheating
prover that Che on some
ey in the
CRS I'm going to I'm going to change the
CRS now I'm going to tell the cheating
Pro here's a new CRS and in this new CRS
I'm going to kind of hardwire I I'm
going to put some information about I in
a way that's
unnoticeable okay and when we'll see I'm
going to call the somewh extractable
hash or what J called SSB hash some more
statistically binding and then you I'll
remind you a little bit how we where we
stick the the index ey but in analysis
we say you know let me change the CRS to
a CRS a different CRS it has a very
different distribution but it's
indistinguishable it looks the like the
original CRS so P star can't distinguish
between the two so he'll still give me a
valid bar okay and now I'm going to say
in this new CRS actually there's no way
he can cheat on location I there's no
way he can cheat okay what is the issue
so now you're saying why why do we need
why can't we do fully
adaptive the the issue is it may be the
case that once we switch the CRS it
switches where he's cheating so here's
an here's an alternative way let's say
the approver tells you here you know I'm
going to cheat in location I but I can
be adaptive chosen based on the
CRS so now in the analysis I'm going to
say I'm GNA guess where he cheated I'm
GNA say let's guess he cheated location
seven I'm GNA hardwire kind of the CRS
to depend on this location and then the
cheatting pro doesn't cheat on seven it
cheat on something else he can kind of
evade me now you're saying oh if he
cheat something else I can tell I can
tell the difference so like I shouldn't
be able to tell but the thing is you
don't know what's in the language it's
not what's not in the language so the
the problem is whether XI is in the
language or not in the language can be
very hard to tell it may
take and that's why kind of getting
adaptive like just guessing is
not is not uh good enough because he
needs to the the issue is if you could
tell efficiently whether exi is in the
language or not in the language then yes
but because it can be very
hard that's where things become tricky
so that's so you can guess but it's not
good enough is is uh the
answer okay any yeah
even huh even if he commits to
do will that
be well he can com what do you mean he
commits the so you're saying let's
change the scheme kind of and have him
add commitment
or I guess not be
that I I guess the issue is look when
he's cheating we don't know whether like
he gives you X1 of to XK and and approve
Pi now he cheats if one of them is not
in the language that's when he cheats
it's hard to know whether one of them is
in the language are not in the language
and the concern is he can say I he can
say whatever he wants he's going to
cheat so nothing he says we we we
believe right and the concern is that
maybe when we switch the CRS to kind of
depend on I all the exite becomes in the
language and then what do you do and now
you can say you can't tell the
difference because exide in the language
and outside the language they look the
same so that's why kind of guessing is
is in some sense not good enough like
it's not helpful
okay so this is uh any other
questions okay so this is one ingredient
that we're going to use to construct our
snar the other ingredient is uh what's
what uh the some extractable hash or SSB
has so let me write it out I'm going to
write it here uh so we'll keep it on the
board so that's so let me just recall
the
definition uh somewhere extractable hash
family uh
consists of uh many several PPT
algorithm let me start writing so so the
first one is uh
gen gen so now we're constructing a hash
okay so gen takes a security
parameter the length how many bits we're
going to Hash so let's say n Bits we're
going to hash and how many and okay so
let's say in the location I this is
going to be I and N this is where we're
going to be binding on or where want to
be extractable on and it
outputs a hash key and a trap door this
trapid door is going to be we're going
to use it to kind of extract from the
hash the I location of what we hashed
okay so there's a hash key and a trapo I
know when Jen Jen taught it then he just
said hash key and he put kind of the
trapo at the end so I'm I'm going to
write it with a
trapdoor okay so Jen outputs a hash key
and a trapo and then you have eval
algorithm it just takes the hash key uh
uh input X and 01 to the
n and then output a hash value
V uh and then you have
open where you take a hash key the X and
some index J that you want to open
to and it outputs an opening row or row
J
and this should be in 01 to the Lambda
or poly Lambda similar here this should
be small 01 to the Lambda or poly
Lambda and then there's ver that
verifies so ver takes a hash key a value
and now you you let's say you want to
say I'm going to open location J here's
my B that opens and here's the
opening and he checks is it valid
opening or not so it
outputs zero or
one and finally so consist of
five vpt
algorithms so first you generate a hash
key with a trapo then uh there's an eval
algorithm that given nbit string outputs
the hash value v short succinct then
there's open that you can open given uh
that you can generate an opening for
specific index J so you generate row J
which is an opening and anybody can
verify the opening using only the
succinct hash value okay so given a hash
key the succinct hash value the index
the bit you can verify the opening and
finally that's the extract algorithm
and it takes the
trapo and the value and it outputs a
bit and this bit should be
XI okay so let me say the the uh
properties
so the first property is completeness
that's kind of usually the a
straightforward
property which essentially says look if
everybody's honest you get what you
expect which means one the verifier
would accept the opening and B the
extract will output the I bit so it says
that the probability okay so for every X
for every Lambda for
every uh n which is at most two to the
Lambda we always restrict the length of
what we're we're hashing to be at most 2
to the
Lambda and for every
I we say that the
probability that
a open sorry that
there an hash key generated from gen V
which is
theal ah and for every
J J row
generated by
open it always outputs one it outputs on
probability one and
extract I'll just denote by okay extract
let me denote by just X for Simplicity
uh given trap door and V output x i and
this hold with probability one where the
probability is over what hash key and
trapo are in gen so essentially I won't
write it but the hash key is generated
by this V is generated by this eval row
or I'll call row J is
generated by
open and this just says if if everything
was done correctly the ver always
accepts and the extract indeed will
extract the correct bit
so this is just if everybody follows the
protocol everything should be as you
expect okay uh the soundness or
binding or the statistical binding I
should say somewh or I can call the SSB
somewh statistically binding condition
says that on
location oh before I go to SSB uh
there's another property which is index
hiding index hiding
means that the hash key hides the index
okay if you see just hash key you have
no idea what I is okay so it just says
that for every I and
J if you look at hash key generated by
and I'll call it I or hash key generated
by J
they're
indistinguishable okay this is just a
notation to say hash key generated where
here I have I and this is just a
notation saying this is Hash key
generated by uh giving J to gen okay so
this the the hashy HIDs the index for
any
inj uh the hashy generated with I the
has generate J they look the
same okay so that's the index hiding and
finally is The Binding
condition and The Binding condition says
that so the SSB the somewhere
statistical binding says that for the
location
I that we that we're binding on even an
all powerful adversary that is given
hash key cannot generate V and and two
different openings to location I an
opening to zero and opening to one on
location I so on location I you're
really information theoretically bounded
okay so again even in all powerful
adversary that is given hash key with
respect to a i on location I cannot open
both to zero and to one except with Neal
probability Okay so ah I hoped to put
everything on that but I I'll I'll add
one here so I'll put here The Binding
condition so the SSB
binding The summ Binding says that for
every all
powerful adversary a the probability
that a and hash key where hash key is
generated
from
gen 1 Lambda n and I the probability
that he outputs any value
V and row zero and Row
one such that there would accept both so
that for every B both zero and
one there on hash key v i b Robby
outputs one this is
negligible okay so
on on index I the one that we're the
hatch came from that we're binding on he
cannot open to both zero and open to one
uh in an accepting way with uh accept
probability yeah does have to be
generated from eval here or no good good
good good great question V malicious
there's no a can be so the adversary
he's not following any guidelines he's
completely malicious he generates V
according to his own will generating row
zero and Row one however he wants he's
still and he's all powerful he's still
cannot uh generate two accepting
openings for location
I yeah just to follow up on that that's
the only reason that we don't get this
free from extraction right exactly good
good good very good so let me just uh uh
uh repeat what s said look in extraction
we said that we're binding completely
binding because guess what from V we can
actually uh we can actually learn the
the bit XI so XI is sitting there so
yeah if you're honest XI is sitting
there but if you're malicious you know
you can do whatever you want and maybe
if for malicious V maybe there's no you
can't extract anything from
it
yeah right good good good very good yes
yes yes this is the same as saying that
there exists a
v row zero for any H okay for almost all
hash Keys the probability that there
exists v r z and R1 is is is uh zero
they don't exist for almost all hash
keys this triplet that satisfies this
does not exist yes yeah very
good any any other
questions okay so the plan for today is
to show how to use these two building
blocks to get a snar but before I do
that I want to say a few more to first I
want to give you time to digest and ask
questions uh also I want to say a few
more things about these two Primitives
any questions before
I okay so one thing I want to mention is
even though the binding condition was
only an I I said only on the specific
eye I promise you you can't open two
different ways now say what about the
other eye what about J Jay can an ADV
open two different
ways and the answer is no actually he
can't and we don't need to state that
explicitly from from the SSB and the
index hiding I want to argue already we
can
conclude that a poliz
adversary cannot open a poze not all
powerful but a poliz
adversary cannot generate V any index
J and two
openings that will be accepted except NE
probability
okay so in other words I'm saying
binding holes this local binding holes
for every J not against all powerful but
for any PPT or poly sizing we get this
binding condition for every
J
why so because of the index hiding
property where we cannot distinguish
like index I or something else precisely
so the reason is this a he doesn't know
if hash key came from index I or index J
they're they're indistinguishable so now
if he can generate it for index
J then he should be able to generate
also for index so let's replace this
with an J he can't distinguish so he'll
fall in the same J again at some point
and that that'll be a
contradiction okay so because he has no
idea what's sitting here the fact that
he cannot do it for that index I even
information theoretically means he can't
do it for for any other
index yeah so this indexing really
statistical no this index hiding is
computational
actually oh good good good good so the
corollary
is for any poly
size the cor say is that for only any
poly size a the
probability that a on hash key let's say
from I same hash key outputs V or v j
row zero and Row
one such that the same thing here holds
namely for every B he generates
accepting answers for both zero and one
is
negligible because if there exist some J
that he does that for non- Negal
probability then let's replate replace
HK with hash key generating like that's
binding on this that actually
statistically binding on this J A can
distinguish so we'll still do this for
that J with some prob non- negligent
probability and that he cannot do even
information
theoretically so that's why we get like
because index hiding actually just
getting statistically binding on one of
them is good enough it will imply
computational binding and all the
rest okay another thing I want to
mention and this we'll use actually in
our construction
today I said that the hash is binding on
one location and XI we can get it
binding actually on L locations not just
one how do I get it binding on L
locations I'm going to just generate hk1
hk2 up to hkl where the first L is Bing
on the first I'm just going to
generate L
hashes I'm going to ask to generate the
AAL on all these hashes so the hash
value now is going to be V1 up to VL
where the honest uh evalid is going to
take X you want to hash and do eval hk1
of X eval hk2 of X so just hash the same
x with all L keys so now the hatch value
is Grows by a factor of L and then when
you open a certain bit a certain
location you'll generate all the
openings so just do the same thing kind
of all times just repeat it all times
and now what do we have from that if you
by repeating our time so let me uh write
it
so uh let me erase the quary so I'll
have
room
so uh no
remark by repeating
L
times we
get uh somewhere extractable hash that's
extractable on L
locations and moreover another property
that's we're going to need even if I
let's say gave you the trapo
corresponding to some of the alloc not
all the allocations let's say gave you
trap door one trap door two and trap
door
three still what's in the location
hidden in hq4 you have no idea what it
is so even if I reveal some of the trap
doors the other IND indic sees remain
hidden okay and we're going to use this
property okay so again if we repeat all
times we're binding an L location
but even if I destroy I kind of reveal
the trapo corresponding to I don't know
location to a couple
locations the rest of the so of course
if I give you the trapo then all bets
are off you learn everything you learn
the eye you learn everything that's
that's the trapo our trap doors are such
that once I give you the trap door you
learn the index you learn
everything but the other indices that
are not in the not corresponding to the
trap doors that I give that I gave are
still completely hidden CU I did them
completely in
independent and this is something we're
going to use when we're going to
construct our
snars okay so that's one thing we're
going to use a I I want to mention a
little I want to talk a little bit about
the construction because I think maybe
in Jen jang's uh lecture last time this
was missed a little because he said it I
think a little too fast so I want to say
a few words about the construction but
before I talk about the construction I
want to say one more property about the
bar that we're going to also use so what
we're going to use about the bar so we
said that these gen p and v are
polinomial time algorithm probabilistic
polinomial time algorithms in particular
V I want to talk about v v is a
polinomial Time algorithm but V's input
is really large it has X1 up to XK so
poom time means it runs at least in time
poly K it needs to read its
input ever turns out that the bars we
have this is what J called bar for index
languages if there exists a suing
description of these X1 of to XK the
verifier only needs to run in time that
depends on the description in other
words we can replace so uh
if I didn't bring
my okay I forgot to bring my colorful uh
chalk so uh sorry but at least you have
cookies I mean what would you prefer
colorful chalks or
cookies so if a if you can generate
these X1 up to XK if there's kind of
succinct
description then the verify runs in
polinomial time in the description okay
so if let's say there exists some
machine
M such
that for every I
XI is just kind of the train
machine on on input I so this kind of
machine you can you should think this
algorithm you should think of has kind
of a succinct description of all the X
on up to x k and you give him I you get
it it gives you the X I if this is the
case
then V the runtime
or I say
time of v it grows with with the size of
M as opposed to
K okay so the
grows with M and does not grow with K so
of course if you give him xon to XK he
need to read his input his run times
grow K but if you can kind of generate
in succinct way then he doesn't need to
grow grow with
K okay so the you should another way to
think about it you can think of x i as
like M comma
I and the instance just says if you run
M on i x i then XI in the language and
that's why it's called index language
because it's like there's an index yeah
so this means that there still like a
depend in these R time right yeah yeah
yeah there is a lock dependence 100%
sorry yeah yeah it just means yeah
exactly that runs into time uh log K
actually yeah you have I here which is
log K so there is a log K dependence
yeah the CRS is sublinear in K as well
is that true the length of the CRS in
general you want it to be sublinear in K
in the snar construction it's po okay
but yes but when we'll talk about snar
so yeah in the the in the bar the bar
construction we have the
CRS MO most of our construction the SS
is of size
pology uh the one under lwe that Jing
Jang showed is is of size
poly so I know that if we have a bar
that size these properties and function
I guess you can always kind of like like
add the property that you want here
being able to extract a witness from the
group itself is there a world like do we
have any bars without the assumptions
that we need for
function you're asking is there a bar
for which we we we don't know how to
extract is that what you're asking okay
okay so okay so let me you're asking a
great question let me kind of uh
uh okay so when we said when I when the
soundness condition just says that a
cheating prover cannot uh you know cheat
cannot generate X1 up to XK that one of
them the I is not in the language and
yet convinced
often time also in our snar in our snar
construction we want something stronger
what we want is that I can actually
extract a
witness from from this cheating prover
so I want to say this cheating prover I
can't extract all the
witnesses but for some ey I can generate
a CRS that looks like just standard CRS
but I can kind of change the
distribution a CRS to be such that using
some trapo about the CRS I can actually
extract from P star a witness for XI and
once I extract a witness of course it
has to be in the language I I argue not
only it's in the language I can even
find you know get a witness from him so
that's called somewhere this is like
somewh extractable bar now what Li was
saying is that the bar that Jen Jong uh
showed you last time was extra had the
somewh extractable property okay was
extractable actually let me tell you we
also will need bar that are somewhere
extractable I didn't write that here why
didn't I write it here and this is where
the exactly the answer is any bar we can
make it somewhere extractable by just
adding a hash so we can kind of up we
don't need to worry about summer
extractability of a bar because what we
can always do is add put a hash of all
the witnesses a some if you have some
extractable hash if you have a somewh
extractable hash you can tell the
verifier put a somewh extractable hash
of all your Witnesses so take witness
one witness two witness three up to
witness K hash them and in the analysis
just jumping ahead we're going to be
extractable on all the locations
corresponding to witness I and now we're
going to tell him we're going to say
give me a bar the bar is not for the
original language L the bar says
the bar that X eyes in the language now
says there is an opening for the hash
value that in the locations conf find to
Wi if you opened you would get a valid
witness bar that language so instead of
barging the original language bark a
little bit kind of upgraded language
that again says there's a so the
verifier will give you a hash of all the
witnesses and he will prove for every
eye he won't won't prove just XIs in the
language he's going to prove for every
eye I have openings corresponding to
witness eye so that the a the openings
are valid and B wi is in the is in the
language L that's the bar he's going to
give you and now the fact that you're in
the
language means that it must be that if
you take the trap door and look into it
it must be by by
soundless must be that's what's sitting
there because you're binding if if
you're going to be binding on that part
you know that what's sitting there must
be the correct
witness so that's uh that's kind of uh
why why actually we don't need to
construct bars with with extractability
we can always attach uh uh some
constructible hash to them yeah I guess
actually Wonder something assumptions do
we have any constructions of bars from
assumptions weaker than those needed to
construct which would make it I guess
interesting I see what you're saying I
see uh um I don't think not that I yeah
I don't think so I don't think
so yeah I don't know how to construct a
bar from an assumption for which I don't
know how to construct a some
constructible hash
yeah okay a any other
questions okay so I want to get to the
bar to the construction of the snar but
before I do so I I I do want to spend a
little more time on the summer
extractable hash and say a little bit
about the way we construct it because
I'm just want to make sure that a
a that you you you you didn't miss a
part from last lecture that I think was
a bit said too succinctly so the high
level idea of how you construct a Sumer
extractable hash is using uh fully
homomorphic encryption okay so I don't
want to get into uh uh I don't want to
recall too much the definition but I'll
I'll give you a high level so the basic
idea which doesn't work okay let me
first tell you the idea that doesn't
work because that's very natural and I
think maybe that's what you got from
last lecture so the basic idea that
doesn't work is to say that
gen will just output
encryption so it'll give you a public
key an encryption of I with this public
key and the trap door that's going to be
the hash
key and the trap door is going to be the
secret
key okay so I'm just the hash key is
going to be an encryption of of the
index
now I want X1 to X n Let Me Assume for
Simplicity that n
suppose N is a power of two otherwise
you know pad okay so let's say big n is
a power of two so it's some two to the
small n now here's what I'm going to do
let me so when I say encryption of I
let's think of it as bid by bit
encryption so it's
encryption of
i1 up to encryption
of I
in okay and now the idea
is what we'll do is for for each like
pair so I'm going to do kind of a Merkle
hash and for each pair I'm going to
encrypt so I'm going to do this Merle
hash where for each node I'm going to
associate a cipher text and the output
is going to be the cipher text of the
root that's my hash value the hash Val
is give be a cipher text of the root and
this Cypher text going be a cyppher text
it's encryption of
XI okay how do I asso so of course I can
comp encryption of x i this is a
homomorphic encryption given X an
encryption of I I can do computation
under the hood so I can compute
encryption of xabi okay so because this
is a a fully homomorphic
encryption
given X and encryption of I
I can compute encryption of
xabi of course there's public keys I'm
omitting them for sness of
rotation okay this is because I can
compute under the
hood the value of the root is going to
be encryption of
XI but what kind of encryption it's not
any ENC so let me tell you how exactly
how I compute this encryption so the
idea would be so and and not only that
how do I open
okay I want to do local opening so the
the way I'm going to do it is as follows
for each for each pair I'm going to
encrypt only one of them I'm going to
either put here encryption of X1 or
encryption of X2 which one depending on
i1 so let's start with i1 if i1 is zero
I'm gonna so I'm I'm GNA let's say
choose X1 if i1 is one I'm going to
choose X2 it's I'm gonna choose even
other so that the output will be the
correct one uh okay so I'm gonna the the
i1 depending on encryption of i1 that's
going to tell me which one to put here
zero I put all the
left like the left children or one I put
the right
children and then I do the exact same
thing given
these whether I choose the left or right
depends on encryption of I2 if I2 is
zero I choose the left if I2 is one I
choose the right and so on so forth
that's the idea
it's it's like an OT it's really like an
OT exactly exact I didn't Define what OT
is but it's exactly like an
OT okay this does not
work okay it it almost works but it does
not work so let me tell you why it seems
like it should work and then I just want
to mention the uh the um the the a the
subtlety here so the reason it you so
okay so first how do you generate local
opening well you check so if you want to
open XI I I'll tell you okay give me X1
and X2 so I can check that this is
corrected and then give me the hash the
cipher text here and I can check that
this is correct because each each Cipher
text is some f valuation that depends on
the two children and on the the hash key
which is encryption so in in layer J it
depends on the two children and
encryption of
IG okay each time the the the the
node the the cipher text corresponding
to some node is a deterministic function
of the cipher text corresponding to the
children and the hash key corresponding
to that level so encryption of let's say
JJ okay cu because remember if if I'm
let's say in level two I have here
Cipher text I don't know one and Cipher
text two then I do
U the way I compute the the parent uh
Cipher text is just a homomorphic
evaluation that takes if I uh if I to is
zero it it takes cyppher text two if I
two is one it takes sorry c one
otherwise t i verx 2 okay so this is
really just a deterministic homomorphic
evaluation and so that's how I open I
just open all the relevant CER Tex and
the verifier will check that the
homomorphic evaluation was done
correctly so you can local opening you
can do local opening but it's not
binding or I don't know how to prove
that it's binding is the problem okay
and probably you can find a weird FHA
for which it's not binding I don't know
maybe for natural constructions it is
binding I don't know I don't know how to
prove it
but there's a problem with binding and
the problem with binding is that a
cheating so it seems like it should be
binding because look here is sitting
encryption of
XI but the thing is the reason why it's
not binding is because a
malicious
ah a malicious
adversary he may give Cipher Texs that
are are garbage are completely garbage
they don't actually they're not legal
Cipher texts and and he if he gives
Cypher Texs that are garbage I don't
know
why why would there be binding so I mean
maybe extract doesn't work okay here's
me I'm a malicious person I nothing ex
no you can't extract anything I just
want to ruin the binding my whole goal
is
to kind of Ruin binding here okay I'm
going to give you V that doesn't encrypt
anything it's a junk V and I'm going to
open it in two different ways Maybe
maybe I can generate a v like it's I
call it Cypher text but it's just a
bunch of bits that have no meaning
cannot be decrypted at all and maybe I
can somehow generate valid
openings so and I we don't know how to
argue that you cannot do that so in
order to actually get soundness I need
to make sure that the things are well
formed that these are actually valid
Cipher text or what I open to is a valid
Cipher text
and the way we get this is by making
this a little more
cumbersome so the way we get this is we
actually don't use one public key we use
small n public keys so for each layer
we'll use a different public key and
what we encrypt so what okay so what we
do is we
have public key
j for J goes from one to n okay so we
have n public keys and with public key
j we encrypt i j but also so the you one
I has I want up to i n we encrypt i j
but we also
encrypt skj minus one we I want to have
the decryption it's important me to have
the decryption
key now okay so the the the bit the
important bit is that homomorphic
evaluation I'm doing here I need to know
the secret key because I'm not just
gonna say before I said what's going on
underneath under the hood I'm saying
look I have I one I have two Cipher
texts give me one of them no no no no
what I want to do is to say the
following under the hood decrypt
this decrypt this
and give me only the relevant one so
that even if this does not
decrypt so okay so here's the point
let's say I want to open to
X2 okay so okay he gives me X1 these are
valid so this is valid good but
now Cypher Tex 2 can be completely not
valid cuz when he opens he gives me
Cypher Tex one with these two so I know
this was valid because this is
computation and then they give me Cypher
Tex 2 and I do this evaluation then they
G me so the The Sibling Cipher Tex that
he gives me they may not be valid I want
to Ure even if they're not valid even if
they're not valid this is going to be
valid the openings are going to be valid
kind of the on the path things are going
to be valid even though the siblings
that are given in order to just kind of
do the verify the opening even if
they're not valid the opening path will
be kind of valid Cipher texts so why are
they going to be valid because the way
that what is so now let's what is the
deterministic computation that's
happening here the deter or the
evaluation the the evaluated Cipher Tech
the way we do the evaluation is the
following I decrypt this and I decrypt
this and then I take the decrypted value
and I encrypted with the next public key
so the point is even if this didn't
decrypt maybe this didn't decrypt I
don't
care I'm this is still going to be
valid okay so the point is even if the
The Sibling Cipher texts that are given
only for verifying the opening even if
these sibling Cipher text are malale
formed if you give me the open openings
in the entire path I get the guarantee
that on the path not on the siblings on
the path things are well formed and I
mean well formed cyer these are Cipher
Texs that decrypt
correctly and that's what I need for for
the soundness so it's important to do
the decryption this is really uh crucial
okay you doing each I follow okay again
what what am I doing on each note good
good good so here's what I'm doing on
each Noe H the evaluation function takes
kind of i j
secret key j minus one and two Cipher
Tex Cipher Tex zero and Cipher Tex
one and what it does is the following
decrypt cyppher Tex zero so it
decrypts with SK J minus one uh cyppher
Tex Z cyppher text B for every B get get
some uh bit I don't know a a alpha
B and then it
outputs one of them I know Alpha B Star
Alpha
i j so so it gets to bits and he he he
chooses one of them which one depending
on the IG you want so what you will get
the point is what you will get is really
an encryption so the point is let's
say I do it under the hood this isn't a
computation that is done under the hood
yes so this is going to be encrypted in
and in in a box but what I'm going to do
Under the box is to say so these I have
so sorry these two are i j and skj minus
one are in a box and the computation
that I'm doing inside the box as I'm
saying I have these in a box I have
these in the clear Inside the Box what I
do is the following I say I have the
secret key j minus one and these two
Cipher texts let me decrypt both of them
I'm going to get two bits Alpha zero and
Alpha One now maybe one of them is bad
so but so maybe one of them doesn't
decrypt so the one that doesn't decrypt
I'll put
bot and then the output will be the
relevant one that according if if it's
zero I'm going to Output Alpha zero if
it's one I'm going to Output Alpha One
and now what I can argue is on the path
itself everything has to be well formed
so I'm actually going to get the the
correct Cipher text and I can argue that
by induction Okay so
here of course this is well form because
I this is just a deterministic
computation that's done locally now the
point is so let's say like I I want to
Output I want to I'm binding an X1 this
is X1 is what I want to open Okay so
this must be well formed and now the
point is even if this is not well
formed what will I do under the hood I'm
going to open this and open this this is
going to be the correct value this is
not going to be maybe the correct this
may be bot but this is the one I choose
and then I encrypt it so I have it here
and then again this may be bad I'm going
to decrypt it it may be bot but this is
going to be good and this is the one I
choose so one can argue kind of by
induction that this is going to be inp x
one this is going be inp everything in
of X1 until the end so there's no way
you can open two different ways you have
to open to
X1 and the verifier is also going to do
the same computation to check exactly
the verifier does the exact same
computation to check yes
yeah
only right this is not opening a general
good so this exactly this shows that the
specific uh so this
[Music]
um
uh okay this shows that the specific eye
that's encrypted here so there's one the
hash key is binding on one eye on
specific eye the the eye on which you're
binding you can only open in one way uh
statistically and then by the index
hiding it means that you can only for
any J you can only open one way
computationally because you can
distinguish yeah you avoid this chain of
keys if you happy to
ENC good very good good good yes so you
can avoid uh you can avoid avoid using
many public Keys you can just use one
public key encrypt the secret key and
and rely on what's called circular
security that's another option if you
wish s doesn't want to do
that but yes
exactly exactly
yeah you see get
resistance you okay so yeah so you're
asking will you get uh Collision like
Collision resistance and the answer is
yes
because for the specific eye that you
for the specific ey that kind of you en
encrypted in the hash key you get uh
binding kind of statistically okay
there's no way you can open two
different
ways
and what you have at the end is just the
encryption of that Index right right so
you're asking about a different J oh
sorry no that you you have two x's that
have the same uh
index have the same that index and then
but the are
different you get a different outut of
the if you take those two different X
good good good okay so if you take two
different X's for which let's say they
have the same X1 and let's say the hash
key is binding on location
one the value would get if you if you
hash them honestly will be actually very
different
but because you use different X's but so
you'll get different values but if you
decrypt these values correspond to a
cyppher text as values they're going to
look very different but if you decrypt
you will get the same bit which is
X1 yeah good okay so anyway if you if
you didn't follow the exact construction
it doesn't really matter I just wanted
to make sure that uh uh you know this it
was clear that you really needed to do
this decryption uh yeah the reason you
don't need circular security as it is
for this F is that each of these
computations is simple enough that you
don't need to like the bo strap is that
the reason Okay the reason I don't need
uh uh um circular security is I'm I'm
never
encrypting a secret key under its
publicy so sorry asking why the you're
using not need to be
unbounded oh oh oh okay okay okay you're
saying okay sorry sorry you're you're
asking okay got it you're saying well in
general if we want arbitrary FHA we need
to assume circular secure LW inside it
kind of and you're asking do we not need
to assum like you're kind of going into
the you're saying do we actually need
fully fully fully homomorphic encryption
because if we do then actually we need
to rely on like a circle security
assumption inside too the answer is we
we because the computation is very
specific and very small depth you don't
need to there's no you don't need like
full full FH you need FH for very
bounded depth
computations yeah great thank you a any
any other
questions okay so let's
snar well let me just make sure I
covered everything I wanted
[Music]
to okay after three months we SN we snar
okay the last kind of two hours in class
last we're going to
snar okay
so okay so now the snar is really simple
it's like as simple as one can like you
essentially can do it done we're done
okay so how do we we can go home uh okay
so anybody want a cookie before we
snar I feel like these grandmothers that
kind of you know constantly feed
you okay so here's the idea the idea is
very simple take any so
snar okay so let me first say kind of
the high level idea the high level idea
is the following here's what the prover
will do the so the prover wants to
convince that X is in the language
there's some verification circuit so you
have X let's start with let's take X in
the language
or there is some for any X you know it
doesn't matter for any
X you have a circuit C
subx and C subx takes a
witness and now put 0 one like it's a
verification circuit you can also think
of it if you want
c as taking X and a witness and I'll put
zero if it's a not valid witness and one
if it's a valid Witness if it's a
deterministic computation there's no
witness just say x and output zero or
one that's the
computation okay so when when I talk
about snarky you can think of snar of
non- deterministic snar of deterministic
any language L I don't even want to go
to specific okay but when I have a
language L you know what how what does
it mean a language well there's some
circuit it takes the instance maybe with
a witness and the circuit kind of does
some checks to decide if it's valid or
not valid
okay now I want to convince you I have
an X I want to give you a snar that this
C an X outputs one either that there's a
witness say that outputs one or maybe
it's DET terministic so just C of X Out
outputs one here's what I'm going to do
what I'm going to do I'm going to
compute all the wires of this circuit
I'm all the wires and I'm going to give
you a hash of all the wires now there's
a lot of wires so it's going to be a
shrinking
hash I'm gonna actually use a somewh
extractable
hash
so let's say we agreed on a hash key for
somewhere extractable hash I the prover
I'm going to compute all the wires of
this verification
circuit and I'm going to give you the
hash the hash of the the values of all
the
wires okay hash what are you going to do
with that so the other thing I'm going
to give you is I'm going to give you a
bar a proof a bar of what the bark I'm
going to give you is that every gate
here is satisfied so I committed to all
the wires I can commit to anything I I
mean I hashed all the wires now I'm
going to prove to you that for any gate
if you look at kind of the
two the in the two input wires to the
gate and the output wire of the gate
they satisfy the gate so for any for all
every gate in the circuit I'm going to
prove to you that there exists an
opening to this wire and an opening to
this wire and to this wire such that
these openings are valid and that the
values that I opened accept the the kind
of respect the
gate and I'm going to prove to you that
the
output that so I I I I said that I I
hashed all the wires I'm going to argue
I'm going to open the output wire so you
see the end output is one so again what
am I going to do I want to I want to
convince you that the output here is
one I'm going to Hash all the wires the
value of all the wires in the
circuit I'm going to prove that every
gate is kind of satisfied I have an
opening that's kind of respects each and
every gate and the output wire is
one that's my SN yeah how's this
different from gkr okay how is this
different from gkr uh G okay so gkr is
uh is very different in many ways first
of all it's a interactive protocol now
you can apply F to it but essentially in
gkr you kind of take the circuit you
compute all the wires in the circuit but
actually I don't bar say look all the
wires are satisfied instead I'm going to
kind of we're doing an interactive
process saying oh I'm going to I argue
the output wies one and then we do kind
of a little sum check or some inve
process to reduce checking that value to
checking a value in one layer below and
then we do an instructive process to say
Okay if that was false you know then the
layer below needs to be false until we
reach the the leaves and then you can
apply F chamir to that to kind of make
it a
snar here we're doing something very
differently we're starting with a bar
now it's true that the construction you
saw for bar uses F also but some
constructions don't use f actually for
bar there are various constructions of
bargs you saw one of them but there are
others so we say take any
bar and there's no interaction here like
besides maybe they're inside the bark
but maybe the bark doesn't have any F or
anything to it and we're saying just
hash all the wires of the circuit and
prove that everything is consistent
that's
it that's really what we're
doing so let me write this down so it
will be so that my ingredients that I
have for my snar is uh so okay so
ingredients maybe I'll write it
here so my
ingredients is a
bar and Sumer extractable
hash these are my ingredients and I'm
going to show you my snar okay so snar
has uh three algorithms we have a gen
algorithm and here's what my gen
algorithm is going to
do it's going to let's say the Gen also
has an input
length ah we don't need it
okay here's what it's going to okay
let's say it has an input
length so this says you know you're
going to prove to me statements of
length that the input X is of length n
okay so here's what we're going to do
first thing we do is we're going to
generate a hash
key for Gen of the Sumer extractable
hash so generate a hash key
corresponding to the summer extractable
hash this is going to be with security
parameter n is going to
be this is going to be number of
wires in the circuit C this is the
circuit that takes X of length n
possibly a witness and output zero or
one okay so this is going to be the
number of wires and take any I I don't
know whatever I equals 1 take any I in
between one to n it doesn't matter
choose it arbitrarily your favorite
number okay so that's first thing and
then you also generate a CRS for the bar
so you
generate a CRS for
bar this is for the
bar and this will be with input one to
the with the sc one to the Lambda K the
number of statements is like the number
of gates in the circuit so K is going to
be number of
gates in C because we're going to
remember we're going to say we're going
to prove that for every gate is
satisfied so usually K and N are very
similar it's like essentially the same
number but you know uh let me just be
clear that this is we're going to have
the number of gates and the length n
there and let me call it n Prime we'll
see what it is it's a we'll see what
this n Prime is in a in a minute so the
we're going to Bar statements not of
length n but of a different length n
Prime we're going to see what that is
but the output is just
a uh let me call this CRS bar so you
output CRS which is equal to Hash key
and CRS
bar okay so that's how you generate so
the key generation the CRS has a CRS for
the bar and a hash
key now we're going going
to
a uh what does the prover do so the
prover gets his input X maybe a witness
if it's an
NP maybe there's no witness let me say
generally with a witness but uh actually
the bar we're going to construct today
is going to be for deterministic
languages but let me write it also for
because I'm going to show you kind of a
general
framework so p is going to get a CRS
X and maybe a witness if it's an
NP and he needs to generate a snar so
what does he what does it do
compute all the wires in the circuit so
X is fixed let's think of X is like
that's not part of the wires because
it's fixed but let's compute all the
like
W1 up to w a n which is the wires of the
circuit you can think of the first m has
kind of the actual witness let's say the
if you have a witness and it's of length
M W1 w m is the witness but then the
rest are the wires so I'm thinking the
wires include kind of the witness and
everything above and if there's no
witness then it doesn't include a
witness so I compute these are all the
wires in
C except
X except the input Y is corresponding
the input Y is corresponding to X cuz
that's kind of we know what it is the
verifier knows
it okay so you compute all the wires and
then you
compute hash of the you compute V which
is a hash the
eval with hash key of W1 up to
WN so you hash all these wires together
okay so the verifier computed all the
wires of the
circuit hashed all the
wires oh uh okay actually let me just
say
sorry when you generate a key I said you
know use a a a su constructible hash yes
exactly but let's you don't need to just
use one index okay so let's use it with
few index i l now you can ask what is
L we'll see you know you can think of it
as a few L's you can think of poly log l
the bigger the is the less extinct the
snar is going to be so the snar is going
to grow with L because the hash key
grows with L it's like L hash Keys
essentially because we're
repeating so here I'm going to be
binding on L
locations the hash value grow with L
because you're like you're Computing
essentially L hash values so the more
the bigger L is in some sense the more
secure we're going to we're going to get
we'll see but the more non succinct it's
going to be so L now is going to be a
parameter and when we talk about then
Elis we'll see which L we want yeah is
there any hope for getting like
sublinear dependence in L like any other
construction instead of a direct product
construction so okay in V there's no way
to get sublinear and L because you need
to extract it's like a there's must have
information so in V there's no way to
have to have in the Hat key on the other
hand
um okay if the I I want up to I L can be
shrunk somehow if there's a sucin
description of i1 to I for example in
the case of a witness you know I'm I
want to be extractable and witness I
these are consecutive locations so I
don't need to write location I I plus
one I plus you can just say I and go
from I to n there's a very suin
description in the case where there's Su
description
you can hope to get the hash key
smaller and we do know how to get the
hash key smaller but in general uh for
the Val value there's no way information
theoretically great great
question okay so a okay so you compute
the the hash value of all the wires and
then you add a Barb so the last thing
you do is you
compute uh the P bar like you take the a
bar
prover and here's our bar prover you
give it CRS of
bar and you have axes and Witnesses now
what are the axes and the witnesses okay
I want to use I want to argue I'm going
to generate a bunch of axes and
Witnesses and generate a proof so what
is it that I'm what are so I'm going to
give you X1 star x k star and W1 star
I'll tell you what these are in a second
w k star so this is going to be Pi this
is going to be
compute Pi
Bar so you bar case statements but what
are these statements so so let me just
tell you what these and these
are
so
X star J
is essentially it's going to it's going
to be hash
key value and
J okay that's X that so what I'm going
to prove that for each gate
J I have an opening to the input wires
of the gate and the out wire of the gate
with respect I have an opening with
respect to V that satisfi the gate okay
so the XJ is going to be well I have the
hash ke I have the hash value and gate J
and the witness for gate J is going to
be opening so I'm going to have a like
bit uh like a left child right child
output
child not child I'll put the
parent uh so left child right right
child and parent of the
gate opening row of left child row of
right child row of the
output that's going to be a witness and
it's a valid witness
if b0 row zero are valid opening of the
left
child of
GJ B1 Row one are a valid opening of the
right child of gate J B out and row out
are valid openings of the output wire of
gate J
and these satisfy the gate so if it's a
end gate this and this is
this okay that's gonna that's what
that's G to that's so a valid witness is
a six tupo like this that all these
openings are accepted and these bits
satisfy the gate
and are valid opening with respect to
which wires the wires that are defined
by the gate so think of that you know we
have this circuit C the gates are kind
of uh numbered and for any Gates J we
know there's we know the number of the
input an output wire okay because it's
this is uniform everything the circuit
is uniform so for every gate J we
corresponds to you know I know I yre I
yre J and yre K yeah and so these
openings should be with respect to y i y
j and y k the same hash key for same
hash key for all of them yeah because I
used one hash key I mean it's one hash
key that's binding and and allocations
but I'm uh now I'm thinking just just
one hash key that's binding how I
construct it
will abstract that for now but yeah I
have one hash key that's binding on a
location I hash all the values of the
the W the values of all the wires to
this specific hash key and then add a
bar for any uh gate J that I have an
opening for the input the two input
children the output output uh um wire of
gate J that satisfy the gate yeah only
differ index itself so it's like one of
the
index yeah yeah yeah yeah good so you're
saying where's J here where's
J is that you're saying no more like
like J star and XJ the only difference
is J okay so this is an index kind of
language yeah this note this is kind of
it's that X1 X1 star X2 star are the
same hash KV K one two 3 four up to K so
it's kind of an index language we're
going to get back to it when uh because
we want the efficiency of V so we'll
talk about that but
yes any question about the the prover
here
okay so now the verifier what the
verifier
does is uh okay so now let's write the
somewhere oh that's sad I want to keep
this okay if you don't mind we'll write
the verifier
here okay so what does the verifier do V
takes his input a CRS which
is hash key and CRS
bar that's the CRS and it takes an
instance X and a proof what is the proof
a proof is a
value and um a
bar a hash value and a bar okay so the
verifier he gets the CRS which is of
this form he gets an input X and he gets
snar a snar is oh did I say what did
output sorry okay sorry compute
output V and P
bar so now he takes the The Snug which
is a
hash and uh and a bar
and it just outputs
one and
output the output of V bar he accepts if
and only if the bar is accepting what do
I mean the bar V bar takes CRS
bar and X1 star up to XK star which are
essentially an index language
corresponding to
HK V
and
J so it
accepts if and only if the bar is
accepted that's the
snar one thing I so again you a the
again what is the snar in the CRS
generated generation you generate a hash
key for the sum extractable hash and you
generate a CRS for the barg the
prover computes the values of all the
wires in the circuits hashes it using
the hash key to generate a value a hash
value V and then he proves he gives a
bar that all the gates are satisfied
namely for every gate he has an opening
valid that's satisfi that respects the
gate gate and that the upper gate is one
that's another thing you also prove that
in the B you also prove that the upper
gate is one so for the upper gate you
prove it respects namely you prove it's
one
um good so that's and and how do you
verify you just verify the
bar now here's one important thing to
note this V bar takes his input the bar
of length k k is like the number of
wires in the circuit we do not want want
the verifier to run in time K that would
be the the size of the circuit no we
want the verifier to be very
efficient but that's but that's okay
because he actually doesn't need to run
in time K because actually it's an in
it's what's called an index language
namely X1 up to XK
star essentially it's like an index on
an Hash k and V so the the you can
generate them kind of you can um Express
them very
succinctly right the you can you can
express them by hash key V and all the
index between one and K that's it so
because they have a succinct
representation the RM of the verifier
only grows with hash key and V PO with
hash and V he does not need to grow with
K that's kind of the um efficiency
property of index languages and that's
very important without it we can't use
it for the bar for the
snar so the so in terms of efficiency if
the bar has good efficiency and let's
say the the dependence is poly log on K
then the V is going to be so what what
is the what's the the snar grows with v
and with a bar proof the bar proof is
very if it grows with poly
logarithmically with K it's like poly
log the circuit sign very
efficient V grows with the number of
indices we're binding on so it grows
with L so okay grows with L we'll try to
minimize L we ideally want L to be poly
log K okay so that's what we want we'll
see what we get but ideally this should
be polylog K and the runtime of the
verifier because it's an index language
is also going to be poog K assuming uh
a sorry uh and he needs to to um to
uh he does run in time x because he also
needs to check to check this Pi Bar is
Pi Bar comma of X because when you check
the validity of the of that each gate is
satisfied the the gates in layer one
depend on the on X so to the gates in
layer one the input wires are x x i XJ
so the bug needs to know X the verifier
of course needs to know X but but uh
that's it so he doesn't need to run in
time linear in X but the bar itself s is
very short so the The Snug is very short
the verify of course run needs to run
time x he needs to read the input but
that's
it okay so any
questions okay so let's take a break a
cookie break a fun break and let's start
again like 10 minutes and then we'll
talk about the analysis and when but
this is all that's done we're done with
the construction this is your snar okay
and we built up to it here it is and
then we'll analyze it uh after the break