hi everyone uh my name is Hara Hara
podima I'm um an assistant professor of
operations research as statistics at
Sloan I'm fairly new this is my uh
second year being here um my background
is from theoretical computer science um
I did my PhD at Harvard then I did a
post hook at Berkeley uh and now I'm
super happy to be among the faculty here
uh at SLO so my research focuses on
everything that has to do with the human
facing algorithmic decision making and
specifically about how human behavior um
affects the results of algorithms that
we use to make um real life decisions
for people to give you some uh better
idea of the pipeline of problems that I
consider um so all of us know that you
know there are many algorithmic
decision-making systems nowadays that
can classify us and um give give
decisions give us like loan approvals or
whatnot so the pipeline of uh the
interaction there is as follows uh
humans submit uh applications that that
contain all of their features for
example their features include their
demographics their credit history if we
talk about the loan approval
situation um any loans that they already
have and so on so forth and um the
output of this inter action is a
decision so this decision is whether the
person was approved for a loan whether
the person that submitted an application
will be invited for a on-site interview
or even whether uh the person will be
given some benefits or some
recommendations according to um what
their preferences or what their
consumption profiles were in the
previous rounds now because of how
consequential these decisions are for
people's everyday lives um we have
started seeing that um the way that
algorithms make decisions for humans
directly impacts in the downstream way
society and because people have realized
how consequential these decisions are
they have started being documented to
quote unquote misbehave when it comes to
how they submit their applications
through all these algorithmic
decision-making systems um some of the
ways uh of misbehaving that my research
is considering uh is what happens when
agents are myop agents or humans we call
them agents interchangeably are
myopically strategic uh what does it
mean to be myopically strategic it means
that when you are applying let's say for
a loan and you send your application to
the system you're trying to uh
strategize with the features that you
submit in order to maximize the
probability that you will be given the
loan so uh a very concrete example of
strategize that actually many websites
uh advocate for and suggest that you do
um is that before you apply for a loan
you have to uh increase the number of
credit cards that you have so that uh
you are shown to the system as more
credit worthy other types of misbehavior
uh include individuals that are
sometimes completely unpredictable or uh
make take actions that can be described
as
irrational um but also sometimes people
are um like not just myopic so they try
to strategize uh thinking almost like 10
steps ahead in the future now um of
course there are many ways that the
algorithms themselves can stop
strategize but another component that my
research considers is what are the
inputs from policy and regulation that
can help uh algorithms make good
decisions in spite of the fact that
individuals are misbehaving when they
supplying their data as input to these
algorithms so the three pillars of my
research are the following pillar number
one how are the decisions that
algorithmic decision-making systems are
affected when uh the users the agents
are misbehaving pillar number
two how can we quantify the downstream
effects of
strategizes uh to society as a whole uh
pillar number three what is the correct
approach approach that we should be
taking when it comes to policy and
regulation when we know that uh
algorithmic decision making systems are
going to be interacting with humans that
have you know different incentives that
what uh systems may have thought about
already um I want to highlight a very
quick uh research project uh that was
very fun to do about the disperate
effects of strategic recommendation so
I'm sure all of you know here uh that
recommendation systems nowadays exist
and create a certain type of feedback
loop what is this feedback loop on the
one hand we have the user who goes on
the recommendation system and for the
purposes of this example let's just
consider Tik Tok uh but again like these
results generalized to any type of
recommendation system you can have in
mind so let's assume that our user uh is
interacting with the recommendation
system of uh Tik
Tok now the user consumes content uh
based on the recommendations that the
recommendation system or Tik Tok itself
gives to the user so the system gives a
slate uh of options to the user and the
user can decide what to consume and for
how long to consume it but note that the
Slate of recommendations that Tik Tok
chooses to present to the user crucially
depends on what the user consumed uh in
the previous round
so um this is uh this is a very
well-known phenomenon in um
recommendation systems and it's the
whole purpose behind personalization of
these recommendation systems uh and
because of the fact that every one of us
can personalize the experience that we
have in recommendation systems you may
hear in popular press that uh curation
nowadays uh has become a form of
Creation in the content that people
consuming recommendation
systems uh and of course you don't have
to think about the recommendation system
as just Tik Tok um your favorite
recommendation systems Netflix YouTube
Instagram Spotify they all satisfy the
same core
property so what are some main questions
uh that I'm interested in in this area
um question number one is are people
that are not researchers uh at MIT aware
of these feedback Loop um in some sense
I want to understand whether Society
knows that you know whatever they
consume is based on recommendations that
they themselves are based on past
patterns of
consumption uh and sub question number
two is if they are aware of this
feedback loop how do they act in
response and I want to give you an
example here of uh something from my
personal experience so I have a maintain
two Instagram accounts uh for one of my
Instagram accounts which is my personal
Instagram account I have all my personal
interests except for dogs then I have an
Instagram account specifically for my
dog where I only consume dog related
content um so I was wondering when I
started this project is this something
that other people do are they
specifically trying to strategize with
what they consume in order to steer the
system one way or the other and then if
they do are there any harms to users if
the recommendation system does not adapt
to this type of curation or strategize
and are there any
interventions so some of the things that
we proved in this work well first of all
before uh starting to prove concrete
results uh my research uh thinks a lot
about the problem from of um
identifying like what are the realistic
human behaviors that we encounter in
practice and the way that I uh identify
that in my work is I run uh surveys on
user consumption patterns so we surveyed
a population of 200 individuals that
have no relationship with a university
um that basically they told us how they
are interacting with uh platforms like
Tik Tok then my resarch introduced a
theoretical model uh about recommending
uh content to different types of users
and we show that if you have a
population a total population that is
split into two big chunks a majorities
of population and the minorities of
population if the system the
recommendation platform does not adapt
to the type of
strategize that the users are doing it
may end up being the case that the
minority population becomes even more
secluded uh from the general uh
subpopulation the mainstream content
that the uh majority population consumes
this means that another explanation for
filter bubbles another another
explanation for polarization can be the
fact that the um the system does not
understand that users are strategizing
in order to uh curate the content um in
a more aggressive uh active way compared
to what we thought before now I have uh
roughly 3 to four minutes I had two
sample research projects to discuss with
you um that I have done uh with MBA and
uh Ras one is about uh one is more
traditional operations research uh land
where we tried to improve the operations
of uh breaking ground which is a
nonprofit in New York City that helps uh
match uh unhoused individuals to um
housing uh to some like temporary and
then hopefully permanent housing but for
the purposes of uh
being concise and being on time I want
to highlight the uh current uh project
that uh me and Alex shakya who is one of
the uh panelists that is going to talk
to you later today are doing with uh two
MBA and uh student arrays uh at a very
high level we are trying to build a
canvas GPT um this is like an automated
uh assistant or an automated bot for all
uh MIT loan classes so let me just parse
uh what that means um so MIT Sloan uses
canvas which is a website uh for this is
a learning management system that helps
us manage class
information now the problem here is that
um all of the classes have a lot of
information that is really really hard
to navigate at times just to give you a
very uh quick example here I hope that
you can see my screen but this is like a
sample of uh the information that a
student in our MBA program gets um when
they take my class which is one of the
core classes data models and decisions
so this is um a lot of information that
the students need to remember and pay
attention to at all times so our project
is dat is to build a custom GPT a custom
um assistant to answer questions about
class material that is uploaded on
canvas uh the question questions can be
um what time is Professor hara's office
hours uh what did we learn in class 13
uh when did I when did we learn about
linear regression and how can I find the
specific content so it has to do with um
mostly administrative questions and
questions that pertain to um you know
the syllabus of the
class and uh at a second at a second
phase which is not the thing that we're
currently focused on at the second phase
we would like to build uh an automated
tutor that can help students uh learn so
what would be a tutor uh in our example
well a tutor would be some like pot that
explains to the students um how linear
aggression actually works given the
material that we have been taught in
class uh and also can hopefully uh help
uh professors create homework for their
classes