okay uh can people hear me in the back
we good okay nice let's uh let's get
started so uh last week uh last week yes
last week uh we started talking about uh
our number Theory unit and in particular
Vis visibility uh and we saw a very
exciting uh you know application of of
divisibility saving New York City uh
today we're going to look at an even
more exciting example um modular
arithmetic uh so
recall so uh we saw bit's identity and
uh the
pulverizer so I'll just write that up
here so for all
integers
uh a
B uh there exists s and
t whoops such
that uh that's a little bit confusing
sorry uh
gcd of a comma b equals a s + b t okay
and uh moreover we can compute these uh
efficiently using the uh the pulverizer
the extended ukan algorithm
uh then the other useful fact that we're
going to make use of
today
uh every
number
uh can be
written as an
ilc of A and B if and only
if it is divisible by their gcd
okay so we are going
to make use of these two facts so do not
forget
okay oh sorry
okay so let's start talking about
modular arithmetic then um I expect that
at least in some form it is something
that's you know fairly familiar to all
of you uh so presumably you learned back
in grade school like what what is the
sum of an even integer and an odd
integer what what do you know about
it did people not learn this oh yeah
yeah it's odd okay so first example even
plus odd is
odd even plus
odd is
odd okay uh what is the last digit of uh
say
357 by
994 yeah eight yeah so ends in eight
okay why is
that yeah you can you can basically
ignore everything except the uh the last
two digits uh you multiply those
together you get 28 that ends in an
eight so this is also going to end in an
eight okay uh it's currently 2:39 p.m.
what time will it be in 49
hours 330 yeah about
339 in 49 hours and why is
that yeah uh is that an
answer how how are we getting to that
yeah yeah so 49 hours is one hour more
than two full days we can kind of forget
about those two days and just add an
hour onto the current time okay uh what
day of the week will it be 100 days from
now Thursday yeah 100 days is uh two
days more than uh 14 weeks right so we
can forget about those 14 weeks add
those two days and we get Thursday okay
so these are all you know fairly
familiar examples to to most of you
hopefully of uh modular arithmetic and
the the theme is kind of that when
you're when you're working modulo n uh
you're just ignoring all multiples of N
and only focusing on remainders okay so
even and odd this is the remainder when
dividing by two days of the week we
divide by seven look at the remainder uh
last digit this is you know remainder
when we divide by 10 uh our remainder
when we divide by 12 or 24 depending on
whether you care about AM or
PM uh and so we often call Modular
arithmetic clock arithmetic for for this
reason uh because it's something that
people are are familiar within that
context
okay so let's define what we mean
actually why don't we use a new board
for
this so we're going to say that a is
congruent n to B so this can be uh that
this will usually be pronounced uh a is
congruent to b modulo
n uh if and only
if uh n divides a minus B
okay so you might also see this written
as uh a congruent to
B mod n who has seen this notation
before okay many who has seen this
notation uh couple not quite as many
okay so uh for the purposes of this
class um we're going to you know
generally be using this notation we're
going to try not to use the the right
one
right yes right um and I will explain
why in in a few minutes uh the the right
one even for people who think they're
familiar it uh often leads to some uh
some confusion okay so let's let's try
and stick with this one until you like
really know what you're doing okay but
uh you know for future reference if you
see the the right one it means the same
thing
okay so basically we would like to
consider a and b to be you know the same
like you can think of this roughly
speaking as
equals uh if n divides their
difference okay so for example if we're
working modulo 5 there are only you know
five different kind of distinct values
okay
so we're going to notate them like
this so uh that this is uh the
congruence class of of Z modu of 5 so
everything that's congruent to to zero
okay so this is going to be 0 plus orus
5 plus or minus 10
Etc okay so that's you know one set of
of values that are the
same got a second one represented by one
okay and this is going to be you know 1
6 11 uh - 4 - 9
okay so everything that's equivalent to
one modu
5 and then we've
got three more okay defined
analogously okay and so for a general K
which of these five groups is it going
to belong to like how how would we
figure it
out yeah
yeah so uh the answer was we're going to
divide it by the the modulus five and
look at the remainder okay
[Music]
so a general K is going to be an element
of the remainder when we divide K by
five okay does that make sense to
everybody okay so in particular if we
write uh you
know K = 5 q + r where R is
between
zero and five then K is going to be an
element
of this set
okay so that makes sense to
everybody Rec simply happy with
this okay
so more generally recall the division
theorem okay so the division theorem
says uh for all pairs um n comma D
with d greater than
zero there exists a unique pair of
integers
uh q and
R with uh zero less than or equal to R
less than
d uh such
that uh n equals QD + r
okay uh and we say that Q here is the
quotient
and we sometimes denote this as uh div n
comma D or sometimes we might write this
in infix notation and
div D okay and R is the remainder so
this is going to be uh
REM n comma
D or sometimes we also write this as n
REM
D okay
[Music]
yeah
sorry oh uh the exclamation after the
exists this means there exists a unique
pair uh so not only does there exist
some pair but there's only one of them
okay so when working modulo n uh a
number is always going to be equivalent
to its remainder sometimes we'll also
call this its its residue
okay and you know just as we saw up here
uh these residue
classes uh form a partition of all of
the uh of all of the integers okay so oh
sorry so the the numbers zero up through
n minus
one uh these represent you know all of
the possible groupings uh modulo n okay
does that make sense to
everybody
okay so the following
theorem is quite
useful
so A and B are congruent modulo n
if and only
if remainder of a comma
n is equal to the remainder when you
divide B by
n
okay so how might we prove this
rigorously any ideas
somebody volunteers
yeah
okay yeah so we're we're going to use
the division theorem right the if if we
apply the division theorem to to both A
and B we're going to get the same R okay
I'm going to back up a step first uh at
a very high level what do we need to do
in order to prove a statement like
this we're trying to prove an if and
only if we have to prove implications in
both directions okay so first
direction if uh REM a comma n equals REM
B comma
n then
uh a is congruent mod n to B
okay so we're going to
assume that these are equal right so
then the the r that we get from the
division theorem is the same in both
cases so a = q n + r b = q Prime n +
r
okay now what happens when we subtract
them well then we get a minus b = n * Q
- Q
prime plus r - R and this is
zero
okay so now the difference is a multiple
of n so by our definition A and A and B
are
congruent okay does that make sense to
everybody
yeah uh oh so some examples of a n and B
okay uh so for example uh 17 is
congruent mod 5 to
12 okay because five divides the
difference right if you subtract them
you get five uh five is a multiple of
five so they're congruent okay uh
17 is also congruent to say
32 right if you subtract these you get5
same deal it's not
congruent to
33 okay if you subtract those you get -6
which is not a multiple of of
five
okay any other questions
yeah okay so well this is only half the
proof right we're we're proving One
Direction so we are assuming that uh the
two remainders are the same okay and
we're trying to prove
this right so if the two remainders are
the same right that's you know from the
division theorem we've got the same R in
both
cases so uh we're going to write them
we're going to write both numbers in
that form okay so a is qn plus r
r b is QPR n plus r Prime but you know
we established that R is equal to R
Prime okay so we're just writing that as
Q Prime n uh plus r okay and now in
order to show that A and B are
equivalent we have to subtract and and
see whether the difference is a multiple
of
n so in this case when we subtract them
right the RS
cancel uh the N factors out and we get
uh n * Q - Q Prime
okay so that is indeed a multiple of N
and so uh you know n divides the
difference so they're
equivalent
congruent okay
yeah uh how we say this a is congruent
to B mod n or a is congruent mod n to B
uh there are you know several different
ways of of saying it
okay okay what about going in the other
direction
suppose a is congruent mod n to
B now we want to prove that the
remainders uh when you divide by n are
the same how do we do
that
y
okay okay
okay yeah so the the last step here is
now to use the division theorem again
okay so if we apply the division theorem
I guess to B is probably going to be the
most useful right we can write b equals
let's do the same form that we had there
Q Prime n +
r
okay now a is B plus k
n so that's going to be Q prime plus
K * n plus
r okay and now the division theorem says
that this Q prime plus K and R those are
unique okay so that Q prime plus K is
the the Q that we need and the the r is
the same
okay so both of them have the same
remainder okay do does this make sense
to everybody
yeah uh a congruent to B mod
n uh so what we're trying to prove an if
and only if here right so for One
Direction we're assuming one side and
trying to prove the other and for the
other direction like we did the
opposite right so this is One Direction
we're
assuming that the remainders are the
same and we want to prove that they're
equivalent they're congruent for the
other direction we assume that they're
congruent and then we want to prove that
the remainders are the same okay so kind
of two separate proofs
any other
questions okay so yeah in in some sense
we can consider you know the the N
different numbers like 0 through n minus
one to be you know the only numbers we
care about when when working mod n okay
everything else is going to be
equivalent to one of those it's going to
be equivalent to its
remainder
okay uh so I'm going to take a moment
here to talk about
notation
okay uh so the remainder which we've
called uh REM a comma
n uh so
our convention right is that uh you know
even if n is negative this remainder
should always be positive okay not
everybody uses this convention uh so
particular in in particular when you're
dealing with uh programming languages um
most have you know some operation that
looks like
this uh it may be denoted uh differently
in different languages um like sometimes
it's a percent sign sometimes it's
actually you know rem or mod or
something like that and uh sometimes
it'll behave the same as as you know how
we def it sometimes it'll be allowed to
be negative so like if n is negative the
remainder might be negative or something
like that okay and uh some languages
have
both uh usually with different names
like uh you know mod versus double
mod uh in this class whenever we write
uh RAM m a comma n we always mean the
the positive uh or the the non- negative
remainder so this is always going to be
you know between
zero and uh n
okay um and perhaps even more
confusing uh sometimes this would be
written
as mod of a comma n or even worse an
infix not a uh a
mod n okay so this is why we don't like
to use uh the word mod when talking
about modular uh
congruences
um because if you see something like uh
say AAL B mod n what does that mean
who can tell me what that
means
MH yeah do do do you have a uh a
guess okay and what why is that
yeah the answer was that's just the
definition um yeah so the the the
important distinction here is between
these two things
right right these are very different
statements okay the mod here is kind of
attached to this uh equivalence uh
sign and uh so this is you know talking
about a relation between A and B okay
this is a function written in infix
notation okay so that this is saying
that you know a is actually equal to the
one value uh that you get when you you
know divide B by n and take the
remainder okay so these mean different
things it is going to be much less
confusing if you use uh you know a
equals B
REM n or you know in prefix notation REM
B comma n
uh for the left one and a congruent mod
n to B for the right one okay so it's
hopefully much more obvious what the
distinction is between you know these
two things than between these two things
so please use the ones on the bottom
until you are you know very comfortable
with with modular arithmetic
okay okay so let's go uh let's go back
to the actual content now
so as I promised before we're actually
going to be talking about arithmetic so
let's let's start on that okay so the
the simple statement that we wrote up
there on the on the left even plus odd
equals uh equals odd in some sense
that's saying something kind of profound
right like you know no matter which
uh even number and which odd number you
pick if you add them together you're
always going to get an odd number
okay uh and you know more generally if
we take you know any a congruent to
let's say 3 mod 5 and any B congruent
mod 5 to say
four right if you add
them what do you know about it
what do you know about their
sum
yeah
mhm so their sum is always going to be
congruent to two module of five okay or
perhaps uh an
easier thing to
see is it's always going to be
equivalent to s
which is in turn you know congruent to
two
Okay so adding A and B module of 5 like
you you get the same result as if you
you know add these two equivalent
remainders
okay so we have a
theorem suppose
that uh
A and B are equivalent mod
n then for all C we have the
following uh I have space here so a +
C is congruent to B+
C uh a minus C is congruent to B minus C
uh C minus a is congruent to C minus
b and a *
C is congruent to B *
C
okay so as you might expect you know if
you want to add subtract or or multiply
modulo n you're kind of allowed to
replace things wherever you want with uh
something it's equivalent to
okay so at any point during this
computation you can you know replace uh
oh sorry different A and B uh that this
this is not relevant for the theorem
statement like if if a and b are
equivalent then you can you know replace
A's with B's wherever you want and
you'll get the same
result okay do does that make sense
uh okay so
question what
about a to the C and B to the C
so let's assume that uh you know C is
positive for
now can I say anything about
exponentiation modu
n okay if we assume that uh A and B are
congruent modu n can we say anything
about a to the C versus B to the
c yeah
yeah so uh let let me rephrase that
slightly I you can prove it more
formally by induction
okay right so you can repeatedly
multiply every multiplication is going
to give you you know congruent values
okay so by the time you get to to a
power of C there's still going to be
congruent okay so yes this is true and
proof by
induction on C okay so our base
case is going to be when C equals 1 okay
in this case you know our assumption is
that a is congruent to
B right so a to the 1 is congruent to a
well it's equal to a b to the 1 is equal
to B so this is
fine uh our inductive
step so
assume that a to the cus one is
congruent mod n to B to the
cus1 okay now what happens when we uh
when we increment our exponent
what is a to the
C
yeah
mhm okay so we can uh you know strip off
a a a factor of
a now we can replace each of these
factors
individually
okay so by our theorem up there this is
congruent to B the cus one * a okay we
can replace this
factor and now by our uh theorem
assumption right we can replace this
Factor as well
okay does that make sense to
everybody okay what
about C to the
A and C to the B
so we just saw that when we're working
modu n we're allowed to you know replace
uh the base of exponents as we like can
we do the same thing with the with the
uh exponents
themselves show pounds for
yes show pounds for
no okay no it seems like it's winning
out by popular vote but not by much
there are a lot of extensions
uh can anybody give me a reason why or
why
not
yeah uh 2^2 is not congruent mod 5 to
what 2
cubed
uh okay that is a true statement um does
that uh does
that yeah so you you are correct that we
only need one counter example um is this
a counter
example so let's see so the the the
claim right is that if a is congruent to
B mod n then C to the a is congruent to
C to the B right we haven't satisfied
our precondition here two is not
congruent to three Mod Five okay so you
you are you have the uh the right idea
we do want to find a single counter
example that will suffice to disprove
this uh we're going to need a different
counter example if we want this to
work okay does anybody else have an idea
for a counter example or failing that
does any have a
proof
yeah okay uh what are the smaller
components like factors of of C
yeah okay
uh
so what do you want to do with those
factors of
C I suppose we could you know strip off
you know say a is smaller than b we
could strip off a of
them okay so you want to divide out a
bunch of factors of uh C and until we
get something like
this
okay
um how do you divide modern
okay let's look at a concrete
example so let's uh keep trying to to
look at
five let's say B minus a is also
five is this a true statement
sorry did did somebody
um is this true for all
C so I I claim that minus one is not
going to work
here right yeah
yeah so anything to the zeroth power is
is one that's that's fine uh the the
problem is uh you know we're
subtracting a from both of these
exponents
right so if say you have b equal 5 plus
a right you're going to end up with five
on on the the right hand
side
right so counter example right is going
to be you
know maybe we could have something like
you know C to the one and C to the 6 and
in particular we're going to want C to
be minus
one okay
uh n was five that's
right
okay so this is our counter example
right we've exhibited a specific a B and
N where our you know uh purported
theorem statement
fails okay it is not the case that minus
1 1 is congruent mod 5 to min-1 6 right
the left hand side isus one the right
right hand side is positive
one okay so when exponentiating we have
to be careful we are allowed to replace
the bases of exponents we're not allowed
to replace the exponents
themselves
okay so we will see in a little while
how we can uh you know get around this
to some degree we can do something with
the exponents it's just not
this
okay
uh why don't we take a look at an
example
first
so suppose X is 1
1335 to the
11111 uh multiplied by 6 +
7799 to the 5
okay uh how might we
compute remainder of X after we divide
by
100 okay how can we use the uh two
theorems that we did prove to compute
that efficiently
what might our first step
be uh okay so the answer was distribute
this uh across this
addition um I claim that that's going to
make our lives harder not easier
so what what was the theme of the two
theorems that we just
proved if we want to do computations
modul
n we can replace things by you know
other numbers that are easier to work
with uh and which are congruent
okay so Computing the remainder when we
divide by 100 right
that's looking for a computation modul
100 okay so we can replace these values
modul 100 and make them easier to work
with
Okay are any of these values that I've
written down uh congruent to anything
nice modu 100
anyone
yeah
yeah yeah so we can just get rid of
these right that's congruent to
35 what else can we
do yeah
uh so we're we're Computing modul 100
right we're looking for the remainder
when we divide by
100 uh so we know that uh one whoops
1335 is congruent to 35 modul
okay yeah so we're we're getting rid of
the the first three digits and only
looking at the remainder after we divide
by 100
okay so basically the the idea is that
we can do this division you know at
intermediate
steps we we can you know take remainders
uh in the middle of our computation okay
that's that's what these two theorems
are are telling
us okay anything else that we can
simplify no does somebody want to do
that computation by
hand no nobody yeah okay
okay
okay okay yeah we can do the same thing
here turn that into just
um I claim that we can take that a step
further 99 is not particularly easy to
work with I claim that there's something
else it's equivalent to that
is
yeah uh not zero negative one yeah
so we can replace the 7799 with negative
Okay negative 1 is easy to work
with
Okay so now what
happens yeah
yeah okay so let's exponentiate this
negative
1 so we end up with 6 + 1 which is
7 now what do we do about 35 to the uh
11,111 uh we don't really know how to do
anything with with exponents
right so let's kind of just try to start
exponentiating it and see what
happens
okay
so what's 35
squ that's going to be uh well if we
actually compute it it'll be 1225 right
I
think is that right 1175
1225 okay so that's going to be
congruent to
okay 35
cubed well it's going to be 25 *
35 okay so that's 875 so that's that's
going to be congruent to 75
okay 35 to
4th uh 35 to 4th is going to be 35 squar
squared again so 25
squ okay 25 squ is 625 that also has a
remainder of
25 so what's going to happen after this
point
what happens is we continue multiplying
by
35 yeah the answer was it'll alternate
between 75 and 25 right whenever we have
an odd power as long as it's greater
than one right uh when we exponentiate
uh 35 it's going to be 75 whenever we
have an even power it's going to be
25 okay you can you know prove that
formally by
induction not going to do that here but
the point is 35 we've got an odd
exponent here so we can replace
this with
okay and now 75 *
7 is going to have a remainder of
25 okay
okay so does that make sense to
everybody we perform the computation but
instead of just like doing it over the
integers and then reducing mod 100 right
we're reducing mod 100 you know whenever
we can we're we're always trying to
replace intermediate values with things
that are easier to work with okay and
that simplifies our computation
considerably yeah
uh you can perform the computation uh 25
by 21 is possibly an easier one to
do
okay okay uh any other
questions yeah
yes uh so uh we had six plus -1 to the
5K okay uh so we are you know
exponentiating this this negative 1 over
the integers right negative 1 to uh any
even power is going to be
one okay so
we
sorry oh sorry uh 5K 5,000
sorry it's it's not actually
um yeah my
bad this this kind of
K
okay sorry that's that's that's my bad
any other
questions
yeah pardon
like oh okay so the the question was is
there always going to be a pattern like
this uh so this is kind of touching on
um stuff that we will see later but yes
there will always be some pattern it may
not be this easy to
find right but you know the basic idea
right is that there are only 100
different values that it that it could
take you know modul
100 right so if you have you know more
than 100
Powers right something's going to have
to collide okay and you know at that
point it'll start
repeating uh here it you know it it
happened to be quite nice it started
repeating you know very quickly in the
the period is only two uh that may not
always be the case though okay but we we
will see in a moment how to uh uh you
know something more about uh about what
we can say about that okay
okay so we we've seen how to add
subtract multiply how to change the
bases of exponents what about
division okay are we allowed to divide
modulo n so suppose we
have 3x is
congruent uh to 3 modul 6
okay so if we had this over the integers
say or over the reals right uh I guess
reals are a better example if we just
had you know 3x = 3 how would we solve
this for
X it's it's not a trick question I
promise yeah yeah you just divide both
sides by three right you you can cancel
off this three and you just just get xal
1 okay so now the actual question is can
we do that you know modu n can we do
that modu of 6 are we allowed to just
cancel these threes and
conclude that uh oops X is congruent to
one modul
yeah okay uh so the answer is yes
because it's the same as multiplying by
1/3 okay uh so remember that 1/3 is not
really uh something that we can like it
it doesn't really make sense modulo
modul
n okay or at least not modul 6 you know
sometimes it might make sense sometimes
it might not we'll see more about that
in a
moment um but like what is a third right
we're talking about
integers
yeah so
sorry so other way around multiply
instead of
dividing okay uh so the suggestion was
instead of dividing by three let's try
multiplying by something so that we get
one
here okay so let's you know try to
multiply this like you know multiply
both sides by some
a and this should end up being one if we
choose our a
appropriately
okay what a do we
choose does there exist such an
a yeah
yeah okay so the original claim is
false uh the counter example right is
that we could take X's three here right
3 * 3 is is 9 that is congruent to
three right but X is not congruent to
one
okay
so the answer I guess to the to the
follow-up question is that no there is
there's no such a right we cannot divide
by three or you know multiply by
something to to uh get one
okay and this is you know basically the
same thing that we were doing last week
right we're looking for a solution to
you know 3 a is congruent to 1 modul
6 right if we unpack what this uh
actually
means 6 divides 3 a -
okay is there a solution to
this
no
okay so basically that's asking if we
can uh write one as a linear combination
of six and three okay
but one is not a multiple of their gcd
so we
cannot okay does that make sense to
everybody so we cannot always
divide are there circumstances under
which we can divide
yeah uh oh okay so the idea was divide
to divide the six as well um yeah I
suppose he could do that um but we are
looking you know we are specifically
trying to do arithmetic modul 6 so that
may or may not make sense right um
but I mean yeah I suppose you could say
you know six divides uh 3x - 3 a and so
you could you know factor out a three
and say that you know X is at least
all and in fact that that does
characterize the solutions to the uh to
the original problem it's just that may
or may not you know that may or may not
be what you're actually looking for okay
okay so under what circumstances are we
allowed to
divide so you know we just saw that we
can't divide here because you know
there's no uh solution
to this equation okay what if there is a
solution like what if instead of uh
modulo 6 we
had uh modulo
okay would we be allowed to divide
here if we have 3 X's congruent to 3
modul 5 can we then
include x is congruent to one module of
5 seeing some nods
why well basically exactly the same
reason right this exactly
characterizes when what we described
will work okay
if
uh the the modulus and the uh Co
efficient we're trying to divide by our
co-prime right if their G gcd is
one then we'll be able to
divide
okay
uh so more formally let's write out what
we
mean so let's start with a
definition so we'll say that uh a
multiplicative inverse
of let's call it x uh
modulo
n uh which we will denote uh x to the ne
1 is a
number uh which as you might expect
satisfies the following uh
congruence okay so just as we have
multiplicative inverses over the reals
right so x * X inverse should be equal
to one in that case we are defining
something analogous uh when we're
working mod n
okay so does that definition make sense
to people
so as an example
right uh one
inverse uh you know so one is a is a
multiplicative inverse of one maybe I
should write it like that
you know
anything
okay two is a multiplicative
inverse of
three Mod Five okay because 2 * 3 is six
six is congruent to one modul
5 okay so two and three are modul
inverse modular inverses of each other
modu of five
the the last part yeah so
um what this is saying right is that uh
2 * 3 is congruent to one modulo whoops
I should write it like
this
okay uh so 2 * three is is six right six
is congruent to one module of 5 right
so that means that two and three are
multiplicative inverses of each other
module of five okay because when you
multiply them you get
one okay does that make
sense okay so when do multiplicative
inverses exist
can anybody uh finish this theorem
statement can anybody characterize
this when is a invertible modul n
yeah yeah when the
gcd of A and N is one
okay and why is that
okay yeah so that's uh that's good
intuition if the gcd were not one like
say the the gcd is two right so both A
and N are even right multiplying a by
anything is going to give you an even
number right that's never going to be
congruent to one modul another even
number
okay so more
formally so a has an
inverse mod n if and only
if uh there exists a b so this is just
the the definition
such that a is congruent mod n to
one
okay now how do we characterize when
this is
true well let's unpack this definition
here okay so this means that n divides
their
difference so Oops why don't I write
this
as AB minus
one
okay right so we're saying that n
divides a minus one we're looking at
what that uh division actually looks
like what the uh what the factor of n is
okay so there's some Q such that qn is a
minus one
okay now we can rewrite
this so 1 equal a minus q
n okay so we're saying there exist B and
Q such that 1 equal
AB uh plus minus Q * n okay so this is
just saying that one is an ilc of a
Ann okay
okay and as we saw before this happens
if and only if the gcd is
one okay
so does that make sense to
everybody so if two numbers have a gcd
of one then we can divide by uh by one
when working module of the
other
okay uh
so if we have say 7x is congruent mod
30 to
okay then we are allowed to divide by
both sides because the gcd of 7 and 30
is one so we're allowed to divide both
sides by
seven okay so we are allowed to conclude
that X is congruent mod 30 to
two Okay I suppose more formally we'd
want to find a multiplicative inverse of
seven okay uh and I think 13 is such an
inverse 7 by 13 91 yeah so if we
multiply both sides by 13 right we'll
get a coefficient of one over here and
we'll get we'll get two uh on the right
hand
side
okay so sometimes you can divide but not
always
okay so let's use that now to figure out
what more we can say about
exponentiation okay so the following is
a
theorem which is attributed to FMA as
many things are it's often known as
fma's little theorem not to be confused
with fma's Last Theorem which
FMA I I feel like that one should not be
attributed to him at all um because he
didn't prove it or I think he thought he
knew a proof and was like a complete
up but you know whatever uh f
little theorem is a different story it
is uh you know much more Elementary he
did actually prove it um it states the
following uh so if p is
Prime and a is not a multiple of P so a
not congruent mod P to
zero okay
then a to the P minus one is congruent
mod P2
one okay
[Music]
so if you think about what this is
saying a little bit right um it's
similar to what we were trying to do
with with exponents
earlier but instead of getting rid of uh
you know multiples of of p in an
exponent when working working mod P
we're instead going to get rid of
multiples of P minus
one okay so so basically we can always
factor out an a to the P minus
one without you know changing uh the end
result
yeah
sorry thank you Zach I promise I'm
awake yeah if if a is congruent to zero
then um clearly this theorem is false uh
yeah a a should not be congruent to zero
if if a is congruent to zero then a to
the pus one is also
zero
okay uh so how could we prove this any
ideas it's a bit of a weird proof idea
let's consider the following
Set uh so
a 2 a 3 a
all the way up to P minus
one *
a
okay
now what can we say about this set if we
reduce everything in it modu P
MH yeah so the answer was that you know
this is basically equivalent to this is
abusing notation a
bit
okay the claim is that all of these are
distinct modul p and none of them are
zero okay why is that
now first probably the easier part why
is none of these
zero that's basically saying why is none
of them a multiple of
P well all of the coefficients on a are
less than P so P doesn't divide any of
those P also doesn't divide a by
assumption and P is prime so doesn't
divide any of these
products okay so none of these is
zero why are they all dis in
modul yeah
okay um let me try and rephrase
that uh so if you look at two different
values
right like two different coefficients
you
said so suppose for
contradiction a * I equals a * J right
so where we're actually going to use a
instead of n
okay or sorry this should be
P okay what is this telling
us
yeah that's right
yes yes so the answer was uh p is prime
so A and P are co-prime right so a has
an inverse we can consol
it so this tells us that I is equivalent
mod P to
J right the two coefficients are
equivalent the two coefficients are
coming from the set 1 to P minus
one so if they're congruent mod P
they're actually equal okay
so that means that all of these values
are going to be distinct modul
P none of them are zero so they're you
know these particular
values okay what happens when we
multiply everything in s together
well if we multiply everything in this
set what do we
get
yeah yes uh P minus one factorial that's
what it's
called
so if we take the product of both sides
we have you know the product of this or
sorry the product of this one
is going to be equal to P minus one
factorial
okay what about the other
one well the other one is going to be
the same except we've got a bunch of
factors of a right how many factors of
a yeah
yeah and so this will be a p
minus1 * P
minus1
factorial
okay so P minus one factorial
is equivalent to P minus1 factorial time
a p minus
one what does that tell
us
yeah okay so the answer was that because
p is prime
none of these
numbers right are a multiple of P so
their product is not a multiple of P so
P minus one factorial is not a multiple
of P so it has an
inverse so that means that we can cancel
it from both
sides and we end up with one is
congruent to a to the P minus
one
okay so we have uh P minus one factorial
conent mod P pus1 factorial time a
pus1 these
canel and we have one is congruent to a
to the P minus
one
okay and that's the uh result that we
were looking
for okay so if we're working mod n we
cannot generally reduce exponents
n but if n is prime we can instead
reduce mod uh nus
one okay do does that uh does that make
sense to
everybody
so as an
example so if we wanted to say find
uh the remainder of seven to the say uh
95 uh
modulo let's say
13 okay how might we do that
well 13 is
prime so instead of computing 7 to the
95 let's reduce that Mod 13 minus 1 so
modul
12 okay so this is going to be the same
as 7 to the what is it
11 13
okay now what can we
do what is 7 to the
12 H
sorry did did somebody give an answer I
I
no one yes okay so 7 12 is
1 right 7 11 * 7 is 7 to the 12 so this
is the modular inverse of 7 modular
13 okay what can you multiply seven by
to get one Mod 13 yeah two
okay so that's all we have time for
today um I will see you on Thursday and
if you have any questions you know feel
free to come up and ask