hello everybody and congratulations on
on getting problem set seven in this is
Michael cubert and I'm going to unlock a
new set of features on chords for you
now that you have successfully
implemented some of them yourself so I'm
going to go ahead and um import the
chord module from music 21 and we
remember that within the chord module is
the capital c chord class so we'll say c
um major equals chord. chord and we'll
say C4 E4 G4 um by the way when creating
a chord we can do um we can create it a
couple different ways uh you can put it
as um a list of strings we can make it a
single space separated string or if we
really want to do this um if we want to
be painful for ourselves but sometimes
that's how we'll do it we'll create um
four equals pitch p. pitch
C4 E4 is pitch. pitch E4
and the next one G4S pitch up Pitch G4
and then we can make C major
equals
um a list of those already created pitch
objects and depending on what context
you're doing one of these will be easier
than others um we could also do it with
a list of no objects but not going to
demonstrate that now in any case we have
C major and we have this chord going on
and that's all nice and fun okay do that
so in within this chord um one of the
things we can do is we can get the root
of it and takes a little bit of time so
I've made it a function call a method
call on that um so that seems to work
and get the base of the same chord and
that's the same thing here because the
inversion is
oops the inversion is zero great now
let's do um C major 6 um not in the
chord symol sense but in the Roman
numeral figured base six as in first
inversion we'll create chord. chord
think through it before you copy down
what I'm going to write great E4 C5 oh
let's let's go and put in open position
C major
6 root it's still C base it's still an e
but now oh is now an e uh because the
inversion is one great we can set the
inversion
here
and see that everything has moved up
above the G and um moved all the way up
it's pretty far up there so maybe we'll
do six.
transpose in place oops transpose down
let's say down two octaves and place
equals true and now we're here and uh
I'm just realizing that this inversion
thing should have returned a new chord
or something like that so I'll put in
Tod do let see make
inversion not return uh
not in place
and just in case you're watching this
video later and you're inversion to
something else that's I fix that problem
okay so these are some of the things
that we can do here um notice let's go
back to create our original first
inversion chord um great
and some of the other things we can do
those notes are pretty far apart so we
can say um C Mage 6 closed equals c
major 6 in
closed
position and now we see see s in closed
position keep still keeps that e in the
base um but figured out that hey that c
that g could move all the way down to
octave 4 because C4 would be below E4 C5
only gets left there so these are some
of the things that we can be doing with
uh with the kinds of things that we're
doing with chords in
our most recent problem
set here's an a a little interesting
thing with roots that I'd hoped to get
to in class but now we can talk about
it's one of these strange moments in
music so one of the things that came up
in our discussion was of course finding
the root and when you were working on
finding the rout you know on something
like uh C major
Triad okay that's pretty easy then um
you end up with a little bit harder is C
major tried an open position and maybe
even harder is you know let's do it an
open position and an inversion and all
of these of course the route is going to
be C but how did we do
this I haven't had chance to go through
everybody's um everybody's assignments
yet but there's different possibilities
some of which are more efficient some of
which are less efficient but basically
whichever route you chose it ends up
usually trying to find some way to
permute each of the U Notes so maybe we
we rewrite them all to be in the same
octave
so and then we try various permutations
maybe we rotate below so we take uh the
top note and move it down so um down to
here and we have some sort of a template
in mind and that template says that when
you have stacked
thirds then the lowest note is the root
so here we don't have stack thirds what
do we have we have a fourth and then a
third above it we would say 64 in
figured base but you think of it this
way and here we don't have it we have a
third and a fourth above it we call 63
position and we don't have it so we go
one more time and here we have
um this which we know is um 33 or 53 and
this is our perfect solution and yay
we're super happy and the cool thing is
that this kind of work works just as
well with um with seventh chords so
let's say we're doing
um here we're going to use some of the
same notes but we'll be a dominant
seventh
type um position in F major something
like that and we can again start moving
things into the same
octave I always make little noises when
I make chords and um we can see nope
what do we have here we have third third
second so that's doesn't work we'll take
the top note bring it down an octave
oops just AAL enough that I want all my
notes to be in blue so today so we can
do something like this and voila we have
what do we have third third third and
we're all happy and so the route is C
again
but what Happ happens if we have um a
knife well I won't make it a knif chord
you can again put it into this
particular position and voila we have
C9 whatever inversion it's in and so on
uh but let's take a second and listen to
a piece of music that going to challenge
some of our assumptions about what does
a root mean maybe go beyond what we've
seen in our Theory classes but the type
of things we have to consider as
computational music analysis analysts
whatever we
are the piece we're going to discuss is
by Benjamin Britain it's his Opera Peter
Grimes from
1945 and we're going to be looking at
one of the last scenes of the Opera
where the main character Peter Grimes uh
has become deranged and lost his mind
and believes the accusations that have
been made against him that he has been
killing his assistants when uh really
the most recent one has just died in a
tragic mishap and uh the music that
we're going to be listening to there's
no singing It's the music that
accompanies him going out to sea to
drown himself so it's a very somber
moment I want you to listen particularly
though to the arpeggiated chord played
by the harp
[Music]
let's look at that chord from the harp
in detail
it's starts in the base cluff with uh f
a c contining up e g b d and then coming
back down
and when we put it into treble cluff and
stack everything up we see that fa d g
Etc we basically have a whole bunch of
Stack thirds going all the way up and so
that's an f13 chord so we know the rout
because we see all of the stack thirds
but now let's take the root and we'll
move to the top so we'll start on a c e
g b d f and hey that's also stack third
so our original chord could be an a a
13th chord um in first inversion I don't
know what the figured Bas symbol is for
that but then we can also Take the A and
put it to the top and see that hey c e
GB d f a that's also a stack of thirds
so this is a C3 chord in second
inversion okay let's see what happens in
music 21 when we try to do something
with this so we'll um import everything
oh Le we just need cord this case and um
let's create an f11
chord and so we'll do it the same way as
the
um as we're doing with the Peter Grim so
F3 A3 C4 E4 G4 B flat 4 uh we're leaving
out that high D for now and when we look
at
f11 root is the F3 it's in
version We gu in root position great
let's take that B flat 4 down um to the
lowest part we'll put it in B flat
2 and now something like
that and will we find the root of this
it's still an f and it's in the
inversion where the 11th is in the base
which we all learned in no didn't uh is
fifth
oops is fifth in inversion here okay so
that's going along pretty well now let's
create the f13 chord in
inversion and we'll put same that B flat
2 F3 A3 C4 E4 G4 and we'll add that D5
at the top and what used to happen when
you called root in this point is it
would crash until you couldn't find the
root this chord eventually I found that
to be kind of annoying that you had to
code around a special case that you
could have a 13th chord or something
would uh crash so I've just decided that
um the root of a 13th chord is always
whatever note is in the base so this
case
um now I put the BF in the base so now
that's the now that's the root and the
inversion is always in root position
which is kind of uh you know that's also
maybe a problematic thing that you can
take the same notes rearrange them and
put them in a different place and uh the
inversion stays the same but the root
changes so that's just a little thing on
how 13th chords are a little bit
different than every other chord and why
computational musicology computational
music music theory is so much fun thanks
everybody