Good morning everyone. Thank you so much
for joining us. My name is Alexis
Marcus. I'm part of the admissions team
here at MIT Sloan and I am joined by a
number of my colleagues today on the
back end of this Zoom webinar who are
here to answer your questions about the
MBA application um which we're so
excited is now open for this next
admission cycle. So for entry in fall of
um we're really excited that the
application is live. You can you can
start your application, you can submit
your application, but we'll go through
all of those um details today and then
answer any questions that you might have
about the application itself. Let's get
started. So, the first thing I want to
talk about is the mission of MIT Sloan.
And the reason why I think this is
important is because it really is
ingrained into everything that we do at
MIT Sloan and really is at the heart of
our application. We at MIT Sloan um are
trying to develop principled innovative
leader to improve the world and generate
ideas that advance management practice.
And within our application, we're
looking for different components that
will indicate that you will become one
of these leaders in the future. And
we'll talk about that in just a minute.
So there are a number of programs at MIT
Sloan. And as I mentioned today, we're
really focusing in on the 2-year
full-time MBA. So, our MBA program, as I
mentioned, it's two years. You have the
summer off in between the two years.
You'll have um you'll start at the end
of August for an orientation, and then
classes begin at the beginning of
September. They run through May. Again,
you have that summer off, and then you
repeat for your second year. Um it is a
full-time program. It's all on campus in
Cambridge. There's no hybrid option.
There's no online option. So, it all is
in person on campus. And then, as you
can see here, we have that portfolio of
programs. So there's a number of other
programs at MIT Sloan and as part of
your MBA experience, you will be taking
elective classes with folks from all of
these other programs. So it's really an
exciting opportunity. Those that are
interested in the MBA program do have
the opportunity to do some dual degree
programs. Um so there are three dual or
joint degree programs. The first is our
LJGO leaders in global operations. As
you can see, that's a full 24month
program. So that actually starts in June
and goes for a full 24 months. Um you
get both an MBA at Sloan as well as an
SM in one of the nine engineering
disciplines at the engineering school um
within MIT. That does have a separate
deadline which we'll talk about but um
there are some additional application
components for that program. We also
have a dual degree program with DUP,
which is the Department of Urban Studies
and Planning, as well as a dual degree
with the Harvard Kennedy School for an
MPP or an MPA. Both of those programs,
you do need to apply concurrently to DUP
or HKS and you must submit your
application for Sloan in round two,
which isn't going to be in January.
We'll talk about the deadlines coming up
soon. So, just a little FYI there.
Something to think about if you're
planning out your year and when you're
going to be applying and if you're
interested in those dual degree
programs.
So, here's a quick snapshot of the MBA
class of 2026. So, these are the rising
second years, not the folks that are
coming into the class this year. Our
class profile for the class of 2027,
which are the folks that will be joining
us in just a few short weeks, um will be
available probably in late September on
the website. Um, but many of the things
will stay relatively the same. So, you
know, when you're looking at this, just
kind of giving you a snapshot of, hey,
do I fall into what Sloan is looking
for. Um, I think the most important
thing to remember is that we are not
looking for a specific type of student
or someone from a specific background.
We certainly have people coming to the
MBA program from, you know, specific
undergraduate majors, specific
industries. Um, however, there is a
place for everyone here at MIT. You can
see we have people from the social
sciences, from the humanities studies,
um we have people from law uh industry
coming into the MBA program. So, there
really is a spot for everyone. And then
you can also see just some of the
academics, what we're looking for
typically um for an average or median um
GPA from your undergraduate institution
as well as any median scores for your
GMAT or GRE. Um, one thing to keep in
mind, I know that this is representing
the 10th edition GMAT. We hopefully will
be reporting out for this coming uh for
the incoming class this year on that
GMAT focus. So, you can understand
really where our median look or median
or average looks for the GMAT focus. So,
that information should be coming in
September.
So, a couple reasons that you might want
to pursue an M um an MBA at MIT Sloan.
It's really a unique opportunity because
we sit at that intersection of business
and technology. We are MIT's business
school and for that reason you have
access to everything at the greater
institute. Within the program itself,
you'll be developing your leadership
skills. Whether you're looking to
advance your career in whatever industry
you're staying in or if you're looking
to pivot, you absolutely have the
opportunity to develop those skills to
learn something new while you're at
Sloan. um and you'll build, you know, a
lifelong lifelong uh network within your
community. Here at MIT Sloan, we have a
ton of academic offerings really
focusing in on hands-on learning through
our action learning labs, our study
tours and tracks. Um and then we also
have that one semester core which is
your first semester at MIT Sloan and
then after that you have full
flexibility to take whatever classes you
want including taking up to three
electives across the greater institute
or at Harvard.
So want to quickly talk about the
application timeline um for this cycle
because that's really what we're here to
talk about today. So the deadline for
round one is going to be September 29th
this year. Um, and then on the 30th, we
will get started on reading right away.
So on the 29th, you will want to get
everything submitted no later than 300
p.m. Eastern time. So 3 p.m. in
Cambridge. On the 29th, we will start
kind of going through those applications
shortly thereafter and then reading all
of those applications on the 30th. We'll
read for a few weeks as you'll see here,
and then you'll get a um interview um an
interview invite or a final decision.
Um, so you could potentially get
weightlisted without an interview. You
could potentially get invited for an
interview or you could be um rejected by
the 27th of October. And then if you are
invited to interview, you will be um
invited to schedule a Zoom interview
during the month of November through the
first week of December. And then a final
decision will be rendered u by December
11th um of this calendar year. So, you
will have the opportunity um you know,
you you can see kind of here what the
schedule will look like between
September when you submit the
application all the way to December. A
couple things to note. We do not look at
applications on a rolling basis. So, we
do not look at them when you submit. So,
if you submit it on September 2nd, no
one is reviewing that application until
September 30th. Um but we will start
looking at those applications on
September 30th, including all of the
components. So, you want to make sure
everything is submitted on time.
So, in terms of the evaluation process,
here's a quick snapshot of how many
applications we receive year-over-year,
how many are reviewed by the admissions
committee, and then ultimately how many
are admitted. So, you can see we roughly
get about 5,000 MBAon applications every
year. Every single application that
comes in the door is reviewed by a
member of the admissions committee. um
we read every single file that comes in
and then from that um pool of of
applicants we invite about 25% every
single round to interview and then
ultimately we admit about 16% of the
overall pool to um to join our class.
So what are we evaluating during the
admissions process? So there's kind of
two buckets that MIT Sloan um MBA
program is really falling into here. Um,
in true, you know, MIT fashion, we do
plot it on an XY axis, which I'll show
you in just a minute. But we're looking
for kind of two categories. One is this
demonstrated success, and the other are
certain personal attributes, including
your leadership skills or leadership um,
abilities. So, we're really curious on
the demonstrated success side on your
academics. You know, how have you done
in your undergraduate, if you do have a
a graduate degree, how have you done in
your graduate degree studies? So, we'll
be looking at your transcripts for that.
We'll also be looking at your um
standardized testing scores. And then
also in demonstrated success, we're
looking at your um impact within your
professional career. So, as a reminder,
our MBA program folks have on average
five years of full-time work experience
before joining the MBA program. So, they
do have that span of about two to seven
years is pretty common um where we see
those MBA uh students joining the
program. And so we want to understand
throughout your application how are you
having impact within your professional
career and how have you had that growth.
Similarly on the other axis we're
looking again at those personal
attributes. How well do you work in
teams? How are you solving problems? How
do you communicate with other people on
your teams? How do you communicate up
and how do you communicate down? How do
you adapt to change? So all of those are
the kinds of things that we're looking
for specific examples throughout the
entire application to understand a
little bit more.
So here's a just a sample of that XYaxis
and how we kind of score um applicants
and then ultimately who moves forward
within the process. So you can see, you
know, the dots here represent where you
scored, where applicants scored within
their written application. And then in
the upper right quadrant, those are the
folks that ultimately move forward, the
25% that move forward and get invited to
interview with MIT Sloan.
This is similarly repeated after the
interview. You will be, you know, um
scored again on the same competencies
because there'll be more additional data
and information. and then those folks in
the upper right quadrant will be moved
forward for admission.
So, let's get into the checklist and how
are you going to be showcasing all of
these things that I just mentioned,
right? So, first and foremost,
deadlines. We already talked about it.
Round one is September 29th and then we
have two other rounds, January 13th and
April 6th. As I mentioned at the
beginning, if you're interested in that
dual degree with the engine with an
engineering um department, that's the
LJGO application, and you do need to
specifically do that LJGO application um
and apply by November 5th. Anyone that
applies to LJGO is automatically
considered for MBA. So, if you are not
successful in getting into the LJGO
program or not successful and um getting
in getting into the engineering side,
Sloan is still looking at you and will
still consider you just for the MBA.
So, talking specifically about the MBAon
application, here are all of the
components and we're going to go through
each and every one of them um together
and answer answer any questions that you
might have and hopefully I'll give you
some tips along the way. So, each of
these components are things that you're
going to need to submit in order to have
a complete application to MIT Sloan MBA
program. Um, and we'll go through those
right now. One thing that I want to talk
about is which deadline should you
apply? And that's always a question that
we get is is one deadline better than
the other. The best deadline is the
deadline that you are ready for? Because
many of you are here today. You are a
couple months away in in anticipation of
going um of submitting this application.
So hopefully you'll be getting it in in
round one. It's really just a simple
math problem, right? When you think
about it, we obviously are admitting
people in round one. Those seats get
taken when they commit to the program.
So seats get taken up in round one. So
that there the most seats are available
if you apply in round one. However, that
being said, we do get a number of
applications in round two and that is
also a really large large round for us.
So the balance for you as an applicant
is to find when your application is
ready. So you don't want to rush things.
You don't want to um submit an
unfinished application. If you need that
extra time, you can take it. Um, but you
know, if you're planning in advance, I
would shoot for the earliest round. That
also gives you more opportunities to get
in front of the admissions committee.
So, the reason I say that is because we
talked about um if you are weightlisted
without an interview, you will be then
reconsidered in the following subsequent
round for an interview. So, you'll be
looked at more frequently than someone
that says say applies in round two or
round three. They only have that one
chance. So, round three, I would
definitely not be planning for it. is
quite small and there are not that many
seats available at that point. But
certainly focusing in on round one or
round two is a smart plan. All right, so
let's jump into each of the different
components. So first the first component
that we want to talk about is the cover
letter. So MIT Sloan's application as
general rule is relatively lean and we
make it that way on purpose. We really
want you to be thoughtful about how
you're kind of portraying your impact
and your successes in both your academic
and professional careers. And for that
reason, we don't really have those
traditional essays that you might see in
other business school applications. So,
the cover letter is a 300word cover
letter. It doesn't include the address
or salutation. Um, and it's your
opportunity to really sell yourself and
also sell you sell us on why MIT Sloan
is the right place for you. One of the
unique things about the cover letter is
that we're asking you to seek a place in
the MIT um MBA class and also highlight
what those successes have been in your
professional career. Um one of the
things that we're not asking are why do
you want to go to business school and
what are your goals? Certainly you are
welcome to submit that as part of your
application, but we're not asking it and
we're actually do that on purpose. We
encourage you to explore different
opportunities. um pivot within your
career or see what is interesting to you
when you get here um and you know we're
not holding you to a certain industry or
a certain uh function postmbba and so
for that reason you know you might not
want to talk about what your goals are
because you're not sure yet and that is
completely okay so within the cover
letter you really want to be
highlighting some of the examples from
your work that um highlight some of the
attributes that we were talking about
before how you're working in teams what
have you done that has been really
successful full within your professional
career. Um, and again, you don't need to
focus on those future goals. We're
really looking um at your past
performance as an indicator of your
future success.
So, the second part of the application
is the resume. So, the resumeé is
limited to a onepage resumeé. Um, and we
look for a really standard kind of
format. So, you don't need to go crazy
with making it, you know, a different
format. you know, just the standard CV
resume that you're you you've used
you're you're used to seeing, excuse me,
um is perfectly fine. Some normal Times
New Roman font, size 10 is what we these
are just suggestions for the formatting.
Um certainly not required, but something
very simple and easy to read. We don't
want to be taking too much time trying
to just figure out where the information
is. you know, really kind of
understanding um you know, the the
format and being able to quickly have a
snapshot of what you're what you have
done to date. Um we really want to see
sections on your education, your work
experience, and then any additional
information. You can certainly showcase
your volunteer experience or
extracurriculars, any certificates that
you have, um leadership positions, or um
any interests. I always love a little
line at the bottom that tells you some
of the interests that you might not find
elsewhere in the application about uh
the applicant. The most important thing
to take away from the resume is that all
of the bullets within your professional
um educ or excuse me within your work
experience section of your resume should
be impact related bullets. So
quantifiable
um successes within your career. So, you
really want to focus in on um what have
you done really well and what where have
you had those kind of highlights within
those the different roles that you've
held. We don't need your daily
activities. Um we really want to see,
you know, those specific highlights. And
then within your resume or within your
cover letter or within your video, which
we'll talk about in a minute, you might
be highlighting those more some of those
examples a little bit more and
elaborating a little bit more on those
examples. But you do want to make sure
that you're talking specifically about
the impact that EP had.
So, next component is the video
statement. Definitely a favorite for the
admissions committee. This is an
opportunity for you to record a
60-second video. We ask that you do it
in one take. Um, so no editing. There
should not be any subtitles. There
should not be any background noises. Um,
really being aware of your surroundings
is very important. um no music, anything
like that. So, it really is just you in
front of a camera. Um and you're
answering the question of introducing
yourself to your future classmates. Um
so, we really do want you to do exactly
that. Even though only the admissions
committee will see the video, we want to
hear how you would give your introduce
yourself when you walked into a Sloan
classroom in a year. Um you want to use
your best judgment here, right? So,
while only the admissions committee is
seeing it and you're quote unquote
introducing yourself to classmates, you
want to be professional and um as well.
So, you want to kind of keep that in
mind. Keep it simple. Don't do anything
that you feel uncomfortable doing. Some
people shoot these videos outside or
while they're doing one of their um you
know, favorite pastimes or hobbies. You
absolutely can do that, but don't feel
pressured to do that. We also have
really fantastic videos where people are
just sitting in front of a camera like I
am right now and answering the question
um and introducing themselves. The video
really should be an opportunity for you
to share a little bit about who you are,
why you're at MIT Sloan, right? Because
you're introducing yourself to those
future classmates. Um and you know what
brings you there, right? So it's kind of
like your elevator fit, excuse me, your
elevator pitch to your future friends is
a good way to kind of think about it. um
you want to tell a little bit more about
what else is not in your application
already. So this isn't a time to kind of
go through your resume um or talk about
things that are you know not
particularly good in your application or
things that areas of concern. We there's
plenty of um space for that within the
written application but the video
statement is a really great time for you
to show us your communication skills.
Speaking of communication skills, we
have a second video question now. Uh
this was introduced in the MBA
application last year. It is required
for all applicants to submit. This video
question two appears when in the
application on the left hand side you
will see that it will appear after
you've finished about 80% of the
application. Um and what happens is
you'll have some you know testing to
make sure all of your camera and your
microphones are working. Um but after
you do that you'll have a a randomly
generated question will appear on the
screen. um you'll have 10 seconds to
think about an answer and then the
camera will automatically turn on. So
unlike video, the video statement where
you're recording it and uploading it.
This is part of the application and once
you hit start, that's it. There's no
re-recording it. Um you can't go back
and redo it afterwards. So, you know,
this is really something that you want
to make sure that you're sitting at your
computer and you're ready to go. So, the
questions are very open-ended. They
don't require any prior preparation. Um,
an example of a question might be, tell
us about a time that you were
disappointed by a teammate or tell us
about a time that you disagreed with
someone. Um, and we're really just
looking for for you to communicate the
answer. It doesn't have to be the
perfect answer. So, I don't want you to
go to bed that night and think, "Oh my
goodness, I had a better example that I
should have shared in video question
two." That is not our intent here. The
intent is really for us to understand
how you communicate those um those
thoughts on kind of you know a a quick a
quick turnaround.
So we're assessing those competencies
that we talked about in the
communication skill. There's no right or
wrong answer to video question two
recommendation letter. You're required
to submit only one letter of
recommendation for the MBA application.
So you need to think very carefully
about who you want to ask for that
letter of recommendation. On the right
hand side here in the blue box, light
blue box, you'll see the questions that
we specifically ask the recommener to
respond to within their letter. Um so
think about who can answer these most
effectively and most favorably for you.
Um and ask that person. Make sure you're
asking them early. the letter of
recommendation is due in as part of your
application by the deadline date. And so
for that reason, you want to make sure
that they're getting it submitted and
that if they have any issues with
getting it uploaded to our system, we
can help them out with that. Um, in
order to get your recommenders
information, get their letter, you have
to go into the application, you input
their information into the application,
and we will send them a unique link
where they can upload their letter
directly. So, you should not be writing
their letter for them. you should not be
involved in the upload of that letter
whatsoever. Um, all of that will happen
directly through the application.
And if you have additional people that
want to write you letters of
recommendation, you do have the
opportunity to include them uh their
name and contact information as two of
your professional references. Those
professional references you are people
that we may contact during the
admissions process um to ask additional
questions similar to what's written
here. um but we will not be asking them
for a formal letter. So again, it's just
one letter of recommendation. Um and we
do ask that you kind of abide by that
because that is what we ask all
applicants for. So in fairness, one
letter of recommendation is considered
for everyone.
And here's the information about the
additional references. Um we may contact
them, we may not. So if we do contact
them, we will find a mutually convenient
time. We'll send them an email and see
if there's a time that we can schedule
um a call with them.
All right, the organizational chart. The
organizational chart is really a a
visual snapshot for the admissions
committee of where you fall within your
current organization. So, we want a
one-page visual. So, this is intended
for you to create. It is not intended
for you to go on the HR website and
print out, you know, the team um org
chart. We're really looking for you to
create a visual for us. We want to
understand within your unit, within your
department, within your organization,
depending on how big it is, you know,
where do you fall, who are you reporting
to, who are your peers, who reports into
you, if anyone, do you have a dotted
line to anyone? Does anyone have a
dotted line to you? These are all great
examples of things that you might want
to showcase within the within the org
chart. The idea is that, you know, we're
seeing who you're working with on a
daily basis. We do have some really
great examples that are available on our
website in the FAQ section. I believe
they're also linked within the
application so you can see what those
look like. Um, we would like that you
circle yourself in red so we can easily
identify where you are on the
organizational chart. Um, you can also
if you have any of your recommener your
recommener or any of your references
fall within the org chart, you can
identify them in a certain way. We've
seen some really creative org charts
that have been very helpful to give us
that visual and really understand how uh
the reporting structure within your job
works. It is not intended to count up
direct reports by any means. You are not
required to be a manager. You are not
required to have any direct reports to
apply to the MBA program. So it is
definitely not that. Um it is really
just an understanding of where you are
visually. With regards to folks that are
in the consulting field, we often get
this question. Um, if you're in
consulting, you can give us a
organizational chart of a more recent
project that you've worked on. Um, and
you can showcase people from the client
or people from your firm, whatever makes
sense um, based on that. And then
similarly with anyone um, that might be
a a military veteran, if you've held a
civilian job, you are welcome to submit
that as well um, as for your
organizational chart. completely depends
on you know what your preference is. Um
other thing to note we al often get the
question of what about confidential
information do I need to put people's
names titles etc on the org chart? No
you can absolutely redact confidential
information. You don't need to include
people's names maybe just include
people's titles. It really is up to you
on you know your comfort level as well
as your company's comfort level on what
information you'd be sharing there on
the ORC chart.
All right, test scores. So, the GMAT,
either the focus edition, which is the
current GMAT that you can take now, or
the 10th edition that you could have
taken a couple years back, but the
scores are still valid, or a GRE score
is required for all applicants applying
to the MBA program. Um, we accept all
formats of all of the exams. So, you
could have taken it online, you could
have taken it in person. Um, whichever
test you take, what whichever format you
take is completely fine with us and we
have no preference. Um, I know we're
going to get questions about this, so I
will just address it now. We will not be
having a test waiver for this year. Uh,
we did have that during COVID and we've
h held on to it for a few years, but we
are seeing more and more people having
access to that test and having access to
getting um, a GMAT or a GRE, especially
online over the last few cycles. And for
that reason, every applicant will be
required to submit a test score as part
of their application this year.
So the next thing that we will be
considering when we think about that
demonstrated success that I was talking
about are your academic records and your
relevant coursework. So we need you to
submit all of your transcripts from your
prior institution. So, for undergrad, if
you studied abroad or if you had
transfer credits, you need transcripts
from all of those sources to be uploaded
to your application. Um, so we will ask
for them if they are missing. So, just
keep that in mind. Um, sometimes it can
be hard or take a little bit of time to
get some of those applications, so you
just want to start doing the leg work uh
now if needed. If you're currently in a
graduate program or you're currently
pursuing some other degree, upload your
most recent transcript. Transcripts do
not need to be official at this point.
You can upload unofficial transcripts to
the application. Just make sure that we
can read them. So, when you upload them
to the to your application, open that
PDF and make sure it's legible. If you
can't read it, I can assure you we
cannot read it. So, it's really really
important um that you check that. And
then you also have the opportunity to
tell us about any coursework that you've
taken, any professional certificates. So
if you've taken um any Corsera courses
or if you've taken MBA math um or any
Python classes, I'm just giving some
examples of things that I've recently
seen or you know if you um you did your
CPA, you could put all of that
information in there. We're really
curious and understanding you know what
you what is interesting to you and also
what you have pursued post undergrad.
So we have a short answer question um in
the application and it's called the
world that shaped you and within this
question we are asking you how is the
world that you come from shaped who you
are today. So curiously, we want to know
um you know, did your culture, your
family, your community, what about you
shaped the aspects of your identity? And
tell us a little bit more. We really
love this short answer question because
it's an opportunity to get to know you
as an applicant more than other parts of
your application that are really focused
on your academics and professionals,
professional successes. And this is
about you specifically. So it is limited
just to words. We do not want any links
or videos part as part of this. It's I
believe it's 250 words that you will be
typing in um and responding to this
question but it's a really great
opportunity for you to share something
that we cannot find elsewhere in the
application.
So those are all the components and now
I just I'm going to briefly talk about
the interview. So as I indicated at the
beginning if you are invited for an
interview you will get an email to
schedule that zoom interview. It will be
a 30 minute Zoom interview with a member
of the admissions committee. Before the
interview, you will get um prompted to
respond to two additional short answer
questions which we'll share at that time
and you must have those submitted um at
least 24 hours before the uh scheduled
interview. During the interview, we'll
be asking you a series of questions and
we're looking for really specific
examples on how you've handled
situations in your professional career.
So, as you're putting together your
application, you could kind of think
about what have my successes been, where
are things that I want to highlight to
show them. How am I a problem solver?
How do I work with others? Like, what
are those um attributes that you really
want to make sure that you're showcasing
throughout the application? And, you
know, putting together those a list of
examples that you could put that you
could use both within your written
application as well as your interview
because you don't want to be duplicative
in both of those things. So, kind of
being mindful about putting together
both um your written application and
then potentially your future um
interview will be really helpful so that
you have additional material to share
during the interview.
So, a couple additional tips before we
open it up to questions. Um applying
early, I talked about earlier, you know,
applying when you're ready, um is really
important, but if you're if you're
ready, submit your application. If it's
if it's good to go, you've checked it.
you feel really confident, it's okay to
hit submit. Um, making sure that you
follow the directions. This team that's
all on in the background today have read
this application. We've developed it. We
have really been thoughtful about how
the uh instructions are written and why
they are written the way they're
written. So, make sure you read them
carefully and follow them. Um, within
the application, we really want you to
be yourself. We are not looking for
something specific within the
application to, you know, there's no
secret sauce, right? So, we're looking
for reasons to admit you. And so, we're
looking for you to advocate for
yourself, help us gather the data that
we need. And because our application is
lean, my best piece of advice is don't
think about it as one each individual
component. You really want to think
about it as a whole. So once you've put
together all of the materials, look at
it and say, "Hey, is there any, you
know, holes here?" Like, am I not
explaining something or am I not
showcasing one of those competencies
that I was hoping to showcase? Um, and
then you can kind of go back and rework
it. Maybe it makes sense to include it
in your resume. Maybe it makes sense to
include it in your cover letter. Um, you
really need to think about all of those
components together and how they're
showcasing you as an applicant. Um, but
we're really excited to consider you for
admission and um, you know, hopefully
putting together a really thoughtful and
meaningful application will showcase all
of that to the admissions committee.
So, at this time, I'm happy to take any
questions that have come in. I think
Katherine from our team is going to pop
on and I know they've been answering
questions in the background. So, any big
areas that people have lots of questions
about?
>> Yeah. Um, we've had a few questions
around folks who have maybe recently
transitioned in their role or gone to a
new company. What are your
recommendations for, you know, choosing
their recommener, submitting an org
chart, things like that?
>> Yeah, great questions. So, when we're
thinking about recommenders, we are
always looking for professional letters
of recommendation. Um, that being said,
whether you've just changed
organizations or whether you just aren't
telling your employer that you're going
to apply to business school are all
valid reasons that you might not want to
ask your current boss um for a letter of
recommendation and that is completely
fine. We we see that all the time and we
completely understand it. So, I would
say asking someone um from your prior
job that could speak to your skill set
is completely acceptable and we will
understand that. With regards to your
org chart, you should be submitting the
visual or excuse me that yeah, the
visual representation of the org that
you are currently in at the time of your
um application. So, if you started a new
job on September 1, uh, and you're
applying on September 28th for the 29th
deadline, I want to see your new
organization because by the time we get
to the interview, you will have been
there for a number of months and we'll
we want that visual of where you've been
so that we can understand a little bit
more about, you know, what that new role
has looked like. So, hopefully, did I
get the all of the questions, Katherine?
I
>> think so. Thank you.
>> Okay.
>> Um, another question for the relevant
courses section. And if someone has a a
wide variety of STEM courses and that
fit, should they list them all or how
would they choose?
>> Yeah, so you should limit it. I believe
there's you can only upload three, maybe
four um per subject matter. Um but
really, you know, focus in on the ones
that are like like 100% of that class
was focused on that subject matter. If
you touched upon um you know, economics
for 5% of the class, it's okay to not
list that. Um, we are going to be
looking at your transcripts as well. So,
it's not one or the other, right? So,
the the relevant coursework is really
just kind of a quick snapshot for us,
but then we will be getting and digging
into every class that you take within
your transcripts.
>> Thank you. Um, another question, um,
what are the common mistakes that you
see applicants make? And I know you went
over this a little bit, but in the cover
letter and then also in their videos.
>> Yeah. Um, common mistakes are being
duplicative. Certainly, I feel like
people aren't using the real estate on
the application to their best of their
abilities. So, certainly, you know,
repeating your resume or repeating the
example that you already had in your
cover letter within that video
statement, you have 60 seconds to tell
us more to give us more information
about who you are as an individual. Um,
and that's really kind of a downfall
when people don't don't take advantage
of that. With regards to the resume, I
will say the formatting issue that I
kind of highlighted earlier is the
biggest one for me. Um, not being able
to find information I think can be a
struggle for the admissions committee
when we're kind of there's a lot of um,
visual clutter if you will. So like
colors and pictures and we can't find
the information quickly that we're
looking for. So really trying to avoid
that and focusing on just like a
standard format.
>> Great. Thank you. And then a number of
questions around is there any
disadvantage in applying in later rounds
or do you have a suggestion?
>> Um so there's no disadvantage to
applying in later rounds aside from what
I was saying with just simple math,
right? CL like there have seats have
been committed um by round two and round
three. That being said, round two and
round one are pretty equal in terms of
the size of of applicants as well as
admins. Round three is significantly
smaller. Um so I certainly encourage you
to apply in rounds one or round two. Um
and certainly for international admits I
would say you know definitely not round
three because by then we if you do need
to get a visa appointment to come um to
the United States you want to be
starting that as soon as possible once
you've committed to the program. Um we
also have admit days for round one and
round two. So, it's a really great
opportunity to come and visit us and
learn a little bit more about the
program and and who we are at Sloan. Um,
the other thing that I can just add is,
you know, uh the weight listing process.
So, if you are weight listed either
without an interview or after an
interview, you will continue to be
assessed in this in subsequent rounds.
So, the earlier round that you apply in,
the more you're going to be looked at um
by the admissions committee.
>> Great. Thank you. Um, another question
and then we get this a lot from
consultants. Um, who should they use and
how should they approach the
organizational chart?
>> Okay. I think I just talked about this
but I can I'll talk about it again. Um,
if you are a consultant you can talk
about a recent project that you did
within your organizational chart. So you
don't want to do like you know if you
work at McKenzie you don't need to do an
organizational chart of McKenzie. Do a
recent project that you worked on. So
who did you work with at the client? who
you know was your counterpart were did
you have other um analysts or associates
that were working with you from
Mackenzie I'm just using Mackenzie as an
example you can be at any consulting
firm but um really just kind of
showcasing that within your
organizational chart is completely
sufficient in what we commonly see
>> and quick easy question are folks
allowed to self-report their test scores
>> yes that is a great question and thank
you for bringing it up yes you can
self-report your test scores so if you
took the test the day before uh the
deadline, you can absolutely just put
those right in there. Um, keep in mind,
we are not going to be asking for those
official scores to be reported to us
until you're admitted and then we would
do the verification process down the
line. So, you can self-report um and
we're happy to take it that way. They
would just of of course need to match uh
down the line. One other thing I want to
note is you are not to supercore any
tests. So, you can submit as many test
scores as you want, but you cannot pick
and choose like you can't cherrypick
like a high quant score from here and a
high verbal score from here. But you can
give us your all of those scores um in
in a list and we will we will see what
those highest scores were for your quant
section or your verbal section.
>> Perfect. Thanks. Um another question and
you may have touched on this a little
bit. I know you did. Um but could you
expand more on the short answer question
on the the world that shaped you?
>> Sure. So, this was a um optional
question a few years ago and then we
made it required as of last year for all
of our applications for MIT Sloan. Um
and we've found that it's a really just
great way to learn more about applicants
above and beyond their academics and
their professional successes. Um you
know, which is what the rest of the
application is focused on. So, um it's a
little bit more to get to know who you
are um as an individual and share a
little bit more about what makes you,
you know, um who you are and why you're
kind of pursuing um an MBA. I mean,
everyone shares something different. It
really depends on, you know, what your
your situation is or who you are. Again,
the world that shaped you. So, if it's
unique to everyone, we're not looking
for anything specific. We're just hoping
to get to know you a little bit better.
>> Thanks. And I know we've answered a lot
of questions, so just
looking through the list. Um I guess I
I've seen it a couple of times. I I know
um could you touch on if we have a
number of years that we're looking for
for years of work experience or if you
have a little bit lower, you know, how
that impacts you as an applicant?
>> Yeah, that's a good question. So on
average, we have of our MBA program has
five years of full-time work experience
coming in. It ranges from about two to
three years all the way up to like seven
or eight years. Um but again, those are
averages. So, there are people that fall
without outside of those averages.
Sometimes there are people with nine or
10 years of experience coming into the
2-year MBA program. Sometimes there are
people at that 2-year mark coming into
the MBA program. Um, we are not really
seeing anyone below the 2-year mark. So,
that's just not as common. Um, we are
looking for people that have had, you
know, enough significant work experience
to be able to contribute in the
classroom. And we have seen time over
time with anyone with lower years of
work experience that you know they don't
get as much of uh as much out of the MBA
experience than those with the with the
experience the professional experience
before joining.
>> Thank you. Um and I know you probably
touched on this as well but a couple of
questions around the professional
experience section of the application
and the CV. What are you looking for if
anything differently in those?
>> Yeah, so they actually should be mirrors
of one another. one another. So, within
the employment widget, which is the the
kind of the popup window that comes up
in the application, you want to be
putting in um your main job there first.
And there's a but a button that you can
click that says primary or you know main
employer. So, if you are on an
internship, externship, secondment, you
want to be putting who your main
employer is, who you're going to be
going back to. And then as the second
thing you can put your secundment or for
your second one your prior roles and
things like that. I think you can list
up to three employers there. We want to
see that match the dates and the
timelines from your resume. Certainly
you might have more on your resume. Um
but certainly you know you want to be
filling out that widget in that area of
your application to give us a little bit
more detail that might not be in the the
resume. It also is your opportunity to
explain the company or explain your
function within the company, your role
within the company that you don't
necessarily do on the onepage resume
where you're focusing in more on impact.
So on the, you know, employment section,
we're really able to see what does this
company do, what do you do, how many
people like work within the company, uh
just more information like that, whereas
the real estate on your onepage resume
is really focused in on your successes.
>> Thank you. I think we have time for
maybe one more question and I've seen
this come up a bit. So, um, and when
we're reviewing applications, do we
distinguish at all between someone who's
an international applicant versus
someone who's a domestic applicant?
>> Absolutely not. Um, everyone is
considered exactly the same. So, that's
the same with regards to your prembba
industry, with regards to your
undergraduate studies, with regards to
your citizenship, all of that. Everyone
is considered exactly the same. And we
are so excited to build um a really
diverse and thought you know in thought
and experience and perspective um class
for the MBA cohort. I