hello everybody one of the great things
about making these videos is that we can
introduce small Concepts that otherwise
might fall through the cracks so I want
to introduce the concept of ties and how
we represent them in music 21 and how
you might represent them in your own
project so let's go ahead and import
from music 21 note stream and the new
tii module and we can go ahead and
create a stream of a measure we'll call
M and let's create two
notes and let's doesn't really matter
when you make them just make sure that
they're
um that they're at the same pitch
because otherwise we can't tie them
that's pretty good and uh we'll say
We'll create a time signature
it's why I usually eventually will
import Star
but
uh
to4 and let's put
m. append time signature m. append Note
One actually we could just put more than
one thing in and we'll show these two
notes
and now while it's doing that we'll go
ahead and get n1's tie will be a new
tie. TI object and it will be a start
and two tie will be a tie. TI object and
it will be stop and now where we
show The Measure we have what we should
have written as a half note right but we
can go ahead and let's create another
measure and here's a course um where we
would be more likely to do this at make
a quarter rest that's the default but
just to show it and so we can by the way
put um objects in more than one stream
and so this is something that's going to
happen
um sometimes we'll put the first note
in and now we'll create M3 is a stream.
measure and M three
dots
append and two o you know I really do
care about having uh all our measures
sort of appear and P is a stream. part
we go ahead and put inside the
stream
M2 and pend
M3 and let's go ahead and show
that great so this shows kind of how
ties might work now here's the thing if
we do forn in um well p. recurse do
notes and we try to figure
out how many notes there
are well looks like there's three of
them but if we listen to this piece
obviously we're just going to hear two
notes so what can we do well we can
create a new part we'll say P2 equals
part. trip
ties and now if we do forn in well
actually let's show this and we'll show
it as a text file we'll see here that uh
we only have two notes now but in this
next measure this note the C only begins
one quarter note
in so we've reduced what we've done is
we've taken this these two e there tied
and we can replace them with one half
note in fact we can look at
this that's our note
and duration it's a half
note when we strip ties we create things
sometimes that don't really musically
exists we have a measure that has a tie
signature of 24 has a quarter rest and
then it has a half note in it that
really can't work so you can't really do
P2 do show and expect something that
that looks right because that that just
wouldn't work but instead in terms of
iterating for n inp2 do recurse we'll
say notes and rests we buers that let's
print NS offset and and and we can see
that
um and we could even do measure number
ha this would totally have saved you
time on problems at three wouldn't have
um oops uh we'll go back and do call
these number equals one measures are
auton
numbered and now when we go back here we
can see the rest is in measure
one then the not e is in measure one at
offset one in fact let's
print
it's we should see that e's in measure
one at offset one is a half note and the
C is in measure two at offset one is a
coordin I'd make this longer but that's
basically all there is to do with ties
thanks fisting