Hi everyone. Um, thank you all so much
for coming to MIA today. Uh, we have two
great speakers from UMass that'll be
speaking with us. Um, I won't say too
much just to let them have time to talk,
but um, thank you guys so much for
coming.
>> Um, thank you. Thank you very much for
having me. This was um, super cool. I
had actually no idea this was a thing
and now I have u a lot of YouTube to
catch up on. So, I'm sure my I'm sure my
my wife is going to be thrilled. Um, but
I'm going to give you, you know, um, you
know, kind of an overview more on, you
know, what I've been working on really
within the past year. Uh, working on the
interpretable, uh, interpretation side
of deep learning and what we can, um,
learn from these trained neural networks
on regulatory genomic data. Um, so my
name is Greg. I am a bionformmatician in
the lab of Japing Wang at UMasschan
Medical School in genomics and
computational biology. Um my only
disclosure is that in my free time I
even do more biioinformatics. So um I
definitely need more hobbies I would
say. Okay. So um I think we all have
seen something like this before. Um
that's why we're here. But our work
we're particularly interested in the
non-coding genome that constitutes 98
and a half% of our three billion base
pairs. And in particular, we're
interested in um these regulatory
elements, enhancers, promoters that
regulate the 1% and specifically in a
cell type tissue spec cell type tissue
type specific manner and in particular
when this goes ary and its implications
on human health and disease.
So my work in particular I study uh or
I'm focused on transcription factors and
specifically the about 1,600
transcription factors that bind DNA in a
sequence specific fashion and for our
purposes I don't know why my computer's
decided to not work but um as part of my
work um you know I've curated I think
you know over at this point 30,000
chipsseek data sets or transcription
factor chipsseek data sets from publicly
available repositories
And we're up to about se total of 75% of
these transcription factors have at
least one uh TF chipsseek assay
available across any of these uh four
repositories
and specifically um you know but the
coverage is uneven. So if we look you
know surprise that we have about 3,000
data sets for CTCF. CDCF has pretty much
been uh chipped at this point in every
cellar tissue type you can imagine. But
as you um you know I just took the top
60 transcription factors in terms of the
number of data sets or publicly
available data sets and you can see that
the coverage um is quite sparse. So the
focus of my work is can we fill this
matrix in and if you actually zoom out
on this entire matrix and you look
across all 1600 transcription factors
and about 1100 cell types that have at
least one transcription factor chipsseek
assay it's about 1% sparse. So um as
much work as we've done in we have done
in assaying these transcription factors
in specific cell type contexts there's a
lot more information um that we could
learn or has still yet to be found. And
then you can actually think that this
matrix is actually infinite when you
think about each cell or tissue has uh
treatments conditions time points that
could be assayed or studied.
So um you know deep learning has
transformed you know I'm sure you know
given where I am I'm sure deep learning
has come up once or twice but deep
learning has kind of transformed the way
not only our everyday lives but kind of
the way we study regulatory genomics in
the human genome but for our purposes we
can think of a neural network as just
taking DNA sequence and um you know
learns uh features in in the DNA um in
the sequence itself and transforms via
neurons that sequence information into
any form of output or prediction,
whether it be a classification or
regression task. Um, but unfortunately,
the downside of neural networks is
they're often thought of as black boxes.
So, we don't often um it's not easy to
or it's not often um readily available
or known what these neural networks
learn in uh taking your input and making
a prediction or arriving at a given
output. And that's kind of the focus on
my work. My focus on my work is kind of
opening up this black box. Um so if you
think you know if you just take you just
train a simple convolution neural
network. So convolution neural networks
excel excel at learning features in
images. Well the DN a DNA sequence one
hot encoded is just an image in and of
itself and you just take a simple one
kernel single output CNN and you train
it on a CDCF chipsseek data set. You see
that you know and this occurs within a
matter of seconds. You see that the
convolution filter if you just cast the
values of the filter to nucleotides you
see that it begins to look like a CTCF
motif. And then we can use some you know
um very simple matrix operations um very
similar to what was done in some of the
earliest of work in deep learning and
regulatory genomics. So that being deep
bind and study studying transcription
factor binding Basset in studying um
chromatin accessibility. we can convert
that convolution filter into a CDCF
motif that everybody um knows,
recognizes, is familiar with. So, we've
leveraged this. We've used the fact that
CNN's excel at motif discovery. Um we've
shown that they outperform you um you
know both classical and other uh deep
learning approaches um in uh motif
discovery. And then um we were lucky
lucky enough to partner with Eleanor
Carlson here at the Broad um as part of
the Zenomia consortium. So, we're very
thankful for her for inviting us for
being a part of that. Um, and we used,
you know, deep learning to essentially
annotate transcription factor binding
sites for 367 transcription factors. And
then we're able to project um all of
these transcription factor binding sites
into 2D space via UMAP. And what we were
actually able to learn is we were
actually able to learn when specific
transcription factor binding sites so
these specific regions of the genomes
that um uh transcription factors bind
we're actually able to see where they
entered into the primate lineage. So
that was really cool. So that was
largely a focus of my um dissertation
work. And then we used that we showed
that you know not only does CNN's excel
at uh learning motifs in TF chipsseek
data but we showed that this phen that
we can do this for any other kind of
technology for assaying transcription
factor binding. are showing here. Uh we
can do this for HCL. So uh in in vitro
high throughput method for assaying
transcription factor binding and then
you know as I am here as a
representative of the wang lab our lab
um in the brilliant software engineers
in our lab um have built our factor book
database you can just go to
factorbook.org
um and you can explore kind of all the
data that we put together. Um forgot
that that was two slides. And then um we
continued to kind of refine our the way
that we use um neural networks to
ascertain motifs um in in this case a
host of uh different technologies. And
we, you know, we continue to refine this
method and we're able to essent um to
win the IBIS challenge which was a um
kind of worldwide data science think
like a Kaggle like competition but
specific to um biology and we're able to
um you know uh develop a method
combining both CNN's and uh expectation
maximization. So kind of old school
bioinformatics method. It's crazy to say
old school bionirmatics. you know,
bionatics is a field that's only 20
years old itself, but that's how kind of
quick this field is moving and how
evergreen this field is. Um, so that's
really cool. I think that's just
wrapping up. Um, and then we've used
this to um Oh, yeah, absolutely.
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah, yeah, absolutely. Uh,
no, I have this one I'm wearing, right?
I think [laughter]
>> that's all the problems. Um,
>> could you
>> Yeah. Hey, no, thanks for stopping me. I
I don't think I have enough slides to
fill an entire however long we have. So,
yeah. Can you comment a little bit on
like the experimental approaches to
define transcription factor binding
sites and like what's what would you be
cons I mean I see some of them up there
but like there was there were I guess
recent papers about like quote lower
affinity transcription factor binding
sites and contributions from like I
guess flanking kind of nucleotides and
>> um like is it getting more complicated
ated our understanding of like what's
actually going on. Can you just like
comment like on how you would
[clears throat] actually define a
transcription factor binding site
experimentally?
>> Yeah. So for us so okay so if we're
looking at say transcription factor
chipsseek um transcription factor
chipsseek data you know you take your
reads align them you call peaks now you
have your you know essentially you have
your enriched genomic regions that are
bound by the transcription factor. But
you know if you you know ever worked
with you know especially um you know uh
chipsseek or you know even um DNA or
attack peaks right they tend to be about
200 300 base pairs long but we know
specifically with a transcription factor
they only bind a a specific six to 20
base pair um nucleotide sequence and
that's what I refer um you know when I
say transcription factor binding site
that's specifically what I'm referring
to essentially the sequence within these
peaks that the transcription factor is
actually binding and that's what I've
used deep learning to essentially
annotate these sites for any
transcription factor that we have a data
set for. But you're absolutely right in
terms of so if you look if you were to
say there is some degree of correlation
and it differs between from factor to
factor. But if you essentially take the
the the the peaks in a CDCF data set
that have the highest signal, you'll
find that those are your highest
affinity sites. They're the ones where
if you take the in the transcription
factor binding site that specific 19
base pair recognition sequence that CDCF
actually recognizes it has the best
match or the strongest match to the
canonical motif. Now what you're in
terms of now these you know these low
affinity sites they're they're super
important right because you know what's
the prevailing theory that these low
affinity sites are the ones that can be
easily tuned or they can be the sites
where maybe it's a CDCF site but maybe
it's also an SP1 site. So maybe it's a
site where two TFs actually come
together and that's they're those are
really difficult, right? They're really
difficult for us to annotate. They're
really difficult for us to define
because what are they, right? We don't
have we don't have like a a curated
motif for a CTCF SP1 hybrid. So it's
it's a really challenging and ongoing
problem. And I would say for me and then
the work that I'm going to discuss
coming forward you know it's difficult
that poses a problem because it's
difficult to tell whether oh you have
this kind of you know you know hybrid
motif but is it noise or is it truly a
hybrid so how would we how would we
properly annotate them but then how
would we also properly validate them so
it's a really hard ongoing problem
especially because these as I was saying
before these these hybrid motifs tend to
be lower affinity sites So they're the
ones that, you know, maybe they have a p
value slightly greater than 0.05. So
when you call peaks, you don't even see
them. So yeah, certainly, you know, it's
something that we're aware of, um, and,
you know, we think about, but it's
definitely hard to pinpoint. Yeah, great
question.
>> There was a question on the chat.
>> How do I see that? It's pretty
impressive for a bionatician. I'm
actually very computer dumb. So, how do
I see or can someone read the question
on this this
>> uh so the question is uh can you detail
how you transform the DNA sequences into
images that can be ingested into a CNN?
>> Sure. So um what we do is we actually if
I if you allow me to go back actually
this slide has it. Yeah. So what we can
do is so here's your here's my kind of
you know um toy uh nucleotide sequence I
created and actually in this case I kind
of inserted a a gata motif right so gota
is a transcription factor so named
because it recognizes gata. So, but what
you can see is what we do is we actually
take this string and we actually cast it
to an Lx4
array and when you stack them together
it becomes a tensor. But what we can do
is numerically we can convert the DNA
string into essentially what becomes uh
a matrix or array that is of length L by
in this case four. But you can imagine
it's just by however many um nucleotides
you have or uh letters you have in your
alphabet. So if you're looking at amino
acids it'd be L by 20. If you're looking
at DNA or RNA it'd be L by4. So
essentially we just convert it to a we
call a one hot encoded array of ones and
zeros where one is um that nucleotide is
present zero being that nucleotide is
absent.
>> So you you do 1D convention basically
just move the uh
>> Exactly. Exactly. And this is a great
toy example you essentially. So you have
your convolution kernel here. This is
what the DNA sequence actually you know
uh this is what the convolution kernel
you know that's what's actually
learning. So it's in this case it's
learning the motif you know as um as
training progresses. And that's what I'm
showing you know if I go one slide back
that's what we're showing here. We're
essentially here is your actually um
here is your filter. These are your one
two three four nucleotides. Here's your
what we would say is W is your motif
width that you set in your neural
network. You know, typically you set it
to say like 32, something that's
computer scientists, we love our uh
powers of two. It's, you know, most
computationally efficient. But for our
purposes, we know that motifs are
between six and 20 base pairs. Um, so
you can see that this convolution kernel
as as the model learns, you can see the
model learns it, you know, the accuracy
of the network, you know, is approaching
90%. You can see that you know that
convolution filter that's randomly uh um
initiated you know learns some
biologically meaningful information.
Yeah,
it depends on um depends. Yeah, I got
it. Yeah, I got it. She was loud enough.
Um it it depends on uh what you're
looking at. If if we're training in this
case, this is trained on transcription
factor chipsseek. So essentially
anything that comes from a peak is
assigned a label of one. You know you
can use um you know just randomly pull
genomic regions and assign them zero as
long as they don't intersect a peak in
this case or you can just you know
usually what we just do ducleotide
shuffling. So preserving ducleotide
content in any any other region is
assigned a zero.
>> Yeah.
So I'm wondering for the chipsick data
used for the training of the models. So
does the chipsick consist of diverse
tissues or very tissue specific data
sets?
>> So you can um you can train in both uh
what so if you say train on a single
data set we would call that single class
learning or single class or single task
classification. You can absolutely do
that. You can do it in a as you were
saying a multitask fashion where
essentially okay well given all of the
TF chipsseek data set um all of the
transcription factor chipsseek
experiments in a given bio sample cell
or tissue you train on all of them at
once and that's actually um I'm not
showing it here that was actually part
of my uh part of my dissertation was
essentially looking at what happens when
you train these neural networks in a
single task versus multitask
classification um scheme because you
could what happens is sure you can train
um a a model to predict transcription
factor binding for all transcription
factors at once in a cell type. But you
what happens is that model learns cell
type specific regulatory
um patterns, but those aren't then
generalizable to an unseen cell type. Um
the best example I can think of, and I'm
sorry I don't have the slides to show,
but essentially take the transcription
factor rest, right? REST is responsible
for um silencing neuronal genes and
non-neuronal cell types. REST actually
plays or plays um you know plays or is a
co-actor with um different transcription
factors depending on the cell type. So
if you take a rest data set that's
trained in say HEPG2, but you train on
all of the TFS at once, it performs very
poorly when you try to um make
predictions on an unseen cell type. So I
guess the long story short is yes you
can technically you can train on one
label you can train on on many labels as
you want but you run into difficulty and
this isn't you know this isn't
bionirmatics or computational biology
specific you run into difficulties when
you try to make inferences in unseen
cell types and you know we call this
essentially a lack of generalization
cool this is good this is good because I
definitely didn't have enough slides
All right.
And like I said, my computer is just
like, I'm don't want to work today.
That's fine. Me neither. Oh, this is
working now. So, we've used this as part
of our factor book project to um learn
and annotate alternative binding sites.
So, this is essentially going back to
the question of what we can see really
well is when two transcription factors
um uh they like to uh cooperate together
within fixed proximity. So we see that
really well and the benefit of neural
networks over uh classical
uh motif discovery approaches is there's
no need to essentially mask learned
motifs. So if you've ever used like a
like the meme suite to learn motifs in
your data set, you essentially have to
you learn a motif, you then mask those
instances and then you learn another
motif. So you wouldn't see these uh homo
and heterodimeic motifs because you
would learn the monomer first, mask it,
then you wouldn't see the two together.
So that's kind of the advantage of deep
learning is we can learn these
alternative hetereroimeic motifs because
of the um there's no need to mask uh
instances in the input sequences
and then so so sorry give people a
headache. So, so to kind of uh increase
the complexity so we you know we we can
we can learn use very simple neural
network CNN's to learn motifs and
transcription factor chipsseek but we
can taking this kind of a step further
um we can change you know we're not
going to change our input we're still
going to use DNA sequence as input but
what if instead we said okay can I learn
the single base pair resolution
um attack seek or DNA seek signal so um
our collaborators uh at Stanford. Anel
Kutaj has in his lab have developed
Chrome BPnet um short for you know
chromatin accessibility base pair
resolution network and what chrome bpnet
does is it actually consists of two
neural networks. One neural network
actually learns the intrinsic bias
component of the assay. Right? So what
happens is you train a neural network
first on um non- peak regions to
essentially learn the intrinsic enzyme
bias whether it be TN5 in the case of
attackseek or DNA one in the case of DNA
seek and then you use that you freeze
that model and then you train a larger
neural network to learn the individual
um uh biascorrected
chromatin accessibility profile and all
we're showing here is that here it's you
know And if you essentially take the
number of predicted cut sites versus the
number of actual cut sites in peaks, it
does a pretty good job when looking in
this case across chromosomes. So the d
the the neural network hasn't seen uh
that data in that held out chromosome.
Um what we can do is we can actually um
so rather than just interpreting
interpreting the filters as motifs,
which is kind of the easiest way, we can
run these networks in reverse. And when
you run these networks in reverse, these
attribution based approaches for um you
know sequence interpretation, we can
actually learn what individual base
pairs in a the DNA sequence contributed
to making that prediction. So we do that
and I'm showing you here just kind of a
I actually don't even know what locus it
is. It just looked nice. We take this um
so this locus has a DNA seek peak here.
you can see that the, you know, the it's
not this nice uh smooth peak we're
accustomed to seeing um from chromatin
accessibility data because all we're
actually doing is we're just taking the
five prime cut sites of the read. So
we're actually DNA one made the cleavage
or cleaved the DNA and what you see is
there's actually this bowl that's left
behind and then we can actually if um I
chose a good color you would actually
see that we can accurately predict with
chrome bpnet the chromatin accessibility
profile at that region but most
importantly is we can use these
attribution based methods to calculate
nucleotide importance and you'll see
that the attributions sit perfectly
right in the middle of that bowl that
divot that's left behind. Because when a
transcription factor binds DNA, TN5 DNA
one can't get in there to cleave the
DNA. And you zoom in on this locus and
you essentially cast these attribution
scores to nucleotides, you know, using
the corresponding genomic sequence and
you see that they actually resemble
transcription factor binding sites. And
again, if I used a good color down here,
you would actually see that the
predicted chromatin accessibility
profile has this really nice bowl where
otherwise in the observed signal, it's
kind of it's kind of more sparse. So
what the the network is doing is the
network is able to essentially learn
properly learn the underlying intrinsic
enzyme bias and then predict separate
that and predict the true chromatin
accessibility profile. And if you're
interested in all this, they have a
preprint and bioarchchive that um it's
really nice. I think I referenced it on
the last slide. And then here you can
see better because I chose a better
color. You can actually see this works
for a taxi as well. And then same thing,
you see the nice bowl where the
transcription factor sits. Um and then
same thing, you have the the bowl that's
left behind in the observed signal. We
can accurately predict it and those
contributions or attribution scores fall
right in the middle of that footprint
where that transcription factor is
indeed bound. Um, so what we can do is
we can actually scan these contribution
tracks. So I kind of relate this to um,
if you've ever used like a FIMO find
instances of motif occurrences um, you
know, it's kind of part of our normal
workflow for whether it be bulk attack,
DNA seek um, or single cell attack seek.
We we we essentially want to look for
what sequence features are enriched in,
you know, those peaks or those regions.
So we always kind of scan, we use a a
library of motifs and we scan the
genomic sequence. Well, that's kind of
the old school way. Well, now what if we
essentially weighted the nucleotide
sequence by how important that
nucleotide sequence, how important each
individual nucleotide is to making that
prediction. Well, now we can kind of
scan genomic sequences, but in a cell
type specific context. And what we see
is when this happens the peaks whether
they be DNA or a taxi peaks um we
observe this kind of biodal biodality
where you have um you know your set of
chro open chromatin regions that do not
possess a transcription factor binding
site for a given TF and those that do
and what this looks like in uh the real
world um is it looks like this. So what
happens is we have these transcription
factors exhibit this biodality in the
cell types in which they are active or
expressed. So, um, kind of cherrypicked
three TFs here, CDCF, SP1, and NRF1. Uh,
showing you here the gene expression.
Just pulled the gene expression from,
uh, Node. You can see that those three
TFs are about evenly expressed across
these, uh, three cells. We're looking at
HEP G2, so a liver cell line, GM12878, a
white blood cell line, and then K562, a
red blood cell line. And then you see
for CDCF, you see that indeed CDCF, we
see this biodal distribution. And then
what we're also doing here is we can
actually use this biodal distribution to
derive a threshold for essentially
whether or not we see an instance of
that motif or not. And if you've ever
used like a FIMO to scan your genomic
sequences before, there's always this
problem of what Pvalue threshold do I
set, you tend to find that different p
values um are better for different
length motifs, different motifs of
information content. This kind of takes
care of that problem for us. And then
what you see is if you take all of the
transcription factor binding sites, so
the individual six to 20 base pair
nucleotides corresponding to the
underlying transcription factor, and you
aggregate both the observed and the bias
corrected signal. In this case, I think
it's DNA. So you see that indeed you
have a bowl for all of these
transcription factors. So not only can
we pluck them out, we can observe their
footprinting. So you can also think
about it as another means of a
footprinting method. But like I said, we
see this in a this is um you know, we
see this in a cell type specific context
just like my uh clicker likes to work in
specific contexts.
Um so we see that um in HEPG2 HNF4A only
um exhibits this biodality uh HFA I'm
sorry only exhibits this biodality in
HEPG2 or herpatic or liver cells where
otherwise it does not. Same thing for
NFCappa B. We see that it only exhibits
this biodal
um this biodal pattern in white blood
cells but not in the liver cells or the
red blood cells. And then lastly, you
can see where we're going with this.
Again, you know, H&FR only expressed in
the liver, NFCAPPA B1 expressed only in
the white blood cells and then uh got
one only expressed in the red blood
cells and it's only biodal um in those
uh red blood cells.
So just kind of going in a little
further, we can look at CTCF here. So
what we actually have is we actually
have 1500 of these trained models
corresponding calculated attribution
scores um for 1500 combined DNA and
attackseek data set um from the encode
consortium and this work is you know
essentially will is part of kind of
phase four of the encode project and if
we essentially just take the difference
in the two means of the populations just
using a two component Gaussian mixture
model um some questions I always get is
you know two component Gaussian mixture
model um doesn't seem to fit great. This
actually ties into the question before
about um you know essentially these
composite motifs motifs that resemble
both you know more than one
transcription factor that tends to be
what this middle regime is. So if you
actually convert this into a three
component Gaussian mixture model you'd
see one here and then one there
essentially you would see that kind of
that murky population but for our
purposes and moving forward two works
fine. But you essentially see that if
you calculate the difference in the two
means of the two populations you see
that CDCF a ubiquitously expressed
transcription factor that mean that
difference in those two means is always
great right we express CDCF is active in
every cell line master regulator Swiss
army knife of the human genome um to be
corny but if you look at H&F again our
our liver specific or herpatic specific
transcription factor we see this
biodality so if you take the difference
of the two me means we use that as like
a surrogate for biodality right
obviously we we do statistical test as
well but um we can see that it's HF only
exhibits this by modality in you know
liver and related tissue so intestine
large intestine um liver etc so um so
well to this point in the or you know up
to this point you know we've only
presumed that the given transcription
factor is bound at these TFBS's that
we've plucked out from these open
chromatin regions but if you then
essentially you go back and you
intersect these TFBS's against all the
chipsseek data sets that we've curated,
you actually find that even in the best
instance, you know, say CTCF and REST
are bound about 80% of the time to these
sites that we've plucked out. And this
is mostly also due to the fact that um
you know, these transcription factor
binding sites don't often perfectly
match. They they look like one, but it
you know, kind of a threat could still
be a thresholding issue. Um, and then
this is just to highlight the fact that,
you know, you know, we understand the
kind of the limitations of this work is
the fact that you can really only do
this at a transcription factor family
level, right? We know that we know that
CDCF and CDCL have for the most part
indistinguishable transcription factor
motifs. Now, we can we can use the fact
that CDCF is expressed everywhere. CDCFL
is only, you know, um, expressed in the
germ line. So you know we can
essentially we can use other lines or
orthogonal lines of evidence to
essentially you know oh we we know that
most likely it's this transcription
factor member of this family and not the
other. So essentially just showing you
here that as part of this work we've
essentially taken 60 620
um TF motifs derived from chipsseek data
and we've clustered them into it's about
350 unique clusters based on their
binding specificity. Um but here just
highlighting again it's more likely if
that transcription factor exhibits this
biodality it's more than you know more
than likely going to be bound. But can
we make a more accurate prediction about
whether or not that transcription factor
binds this TFBS that we've plucked out?
Well, what we can do is we can take all
of these um you know chrome bpnet
associated track. So we can take our
observed signal profile, our predicted
signal profile, the bias corrected
profile
um and then these contribution scores as
well as evolutionary conservation
because why not? It's just another you
know tacking on another uh vector. And
we can use that one hot encoded DNA
sequence at these essentially puditive
TFBS's or transcription factor binding
sites. we can pass them through just a
very small neural network um and we can
actually make inferences or accurately
predict that a transcription factor is
bound at that location or TFBS that
we've plucked out and more specifically
if a transcription factor exhibits this
biodality in both the training and the
testing cell type we can accurately make
inferences across cell type and this
goes back to um we talked about in a
previous question we talked about you
know um the lack of generalization or
neuronet networks, one of their
downfalls is their inability to
generalize across cell type. And that's
really the focus of my work is to be
able to make make accurate predictions
across cell type and know specifically
when we are confident in making those
predictions. So highlighting here that
essentially okay well you take um DNA in
K562 and you train and then we're also
training cross cell type and cross
chromosome. So um if you ever done this
work before, you essentially I train on
all chromosomes but chromosome 1. I
leave chromosome one out. And then when
I make my inferences, I make my
inferences across cell type but also
cross chromosome. So if if there are any
sort of patterns that are specific to a
chromosome with respect to transcription
factor binding, the model will never see
it. So we can accurately make inferences
you know within DNA in K562 cross cell
type cross chromosome. We can do that.
We can also same thing we can do the
same thing for attack given attack seek
in K562 we can accurately predict
transcription factor binding in HEPG2
and then the coolest part is um again
really cool that my clicker started to
decided to not work right there we can
actually if you have a model or that's
trained on DNA you can actually use that
model to make inferences not only cross
cell type cross chromosome but also
cross assay if you have a taxseek data
so this is actually really because the
you know the encode consortium has um
dozens if not hundreds of very deeply
sequenced DNA seek data but for the most
part due to costs the number of cells
required at this point most people just
do attack seek so but we can leverage
all that information that we have as
part of the encode consortium to make
inferences cross cell type cross assay
in essentially unseen attack seek data.
Now what can we do with this? And so
what we can do is well okay so now we we
know which TFs we can accurately
annotate and predict they are bound in a
given cell type. We can construct this
matrix of say we can take cy regulatory
elements from encode. So promoters,
enhancers, insulators, silencers from
the encode consortium and we can
annotate how many times this is just a
toy example chatbt gave me on the train
today. And you can essentially say okay
well we can calculate the number of
times that a given cy regulatory element
harbors a transcription factor of
interest. Again the ones that we know we
can accurately pluck out. And then what
we can do is we can embed this matrix of
integers again into 2D space using um
and you actually see that in this case
about 100,000 cy regulatory elements
that are open active in HEPG2 they
actually form many distinct clusters
based on cy regulatory syntax. So
essentially which transcription factors
they harbor transcription factor binding
sites for. And here I'm just
highlighting again highlighting that if
you um just plucking out this specific
cluster three here that this cluster
three are your HEPG2 specific cis
regulatory elements open chromatin
regions again promoters and these are
enhancers in this case they're they're
all um enhancer like they're all distal
um from a TSS but they're all the ones
that harbor transcription factor binding
sites for H&F1A and HNF1B. So we can use
this to begin to essentially you know um
interrogate these cyst regulatory
elements in terms of you know not only
are they active but why are they active
who's contributing to their activity in
the sense of who's binding there.
So then lastly what we can do is well we
just looked at one cell line and we said
okay well in HEPG2 we're able to
annotate which um you know which
transcription factors are binding to
which cis regulatory elements but if you
look at one cyregulatory element across
a host of um cells and tissue types and
here I'm just um essentially showing you
across I think this is actually um it's
combined um bulk attack data with also
single cell um single cell brain data up
here you actually see that you see
different transcription factor usage
across different cell lines and we refer
to these these regions as polyntactic.
So they're open across several cells and
tissue or tissue types but they do so or
they're leveraging or using different
transcription factors and different
transcription factor binding sites in
their activity. So this is kind of part
of my work is you know how often you
know obviously I just kind of I can just
generate a bunch of PGs and I can just
pick out the which one looks best but
essentially you know part of our work is
essentially can we calculate or can we
quantify how often cis regulatory
elements exhibit this polyntactic
behavior. So that's kind of like kind of
an offshoot of this project that I'm
working on. Um and I think I think
that's it. Yeah. So, um, you know, I
just like to say, you know, thank you,
you know, very much for having me. This
is, um, you know, a really great
opportunity to highlight all the the
great work, um, of the Wang lab and more
lab. We're essentially one, uh, giant,
uh, conglomerate or entity at UMass Chan
Medical School. Um, but would just like
to thank, you know, all of the lab
members, all of our, um, HPC admins
that, you know, um, anytime I break
something, they fix it for me, which is
quite often. Um so yeah and with that I
will take uh be happy to take any and
all questions.
>> Thank you. Great presentation um for
your last slide where you showed
basically like in different cell types
or cell lines that these different
regions um can be active due to
different transcription factors. How
much does that correlate with like the
expression of that transcription factor
in those cell types? Like would you be
able to just infer that based on like
what transcription factors are active?
>> Exactly. Exactly. And it it comes down
to at the end of the day those
transcription factors do end up being
the ones that are expressed. Um but we
just don't know how often this is
occurring. Um we don't know say this I
know for a fact this is like an enhancer
region. Is this enhancer regulating the
same gene in one cell type as it is
another? So questions like that as well.
But yeah, absolutely. You can you can
trace this back to the gene expression
just like I did like a couple slides
ago.
>> Thank you.
>> Hi.
Um
I wanted to ask about the if you can go
back to the biodality.
Um
like
in the next example I guess H HNF4 was
it that you have a more zoomed in uh oh
like yeah this one. So here
>> um like I wouldn't have said that this
is biodal. So no matter what you try
always to fit a bimodel distribution
like how do you evaluate after like for
something that is less known you say
okay let's assume that this is by model
you fit the distribution and then you
see some scores do you rely on
literature information how do you know
that that is not like just because
you're going to always divide something
you're going to get something
>> yeah exactly exactly and actually in
talking with you know Jacob's been a
huge help on this project too and that's
exactly something the first thing he
brought up is how [clears throat] do you
know you're just not artificially,
>> you know, fitting two means where you
should really only have one, right? Um,
and so right now we just use the
difference in the two means as our
surrogate for biodality. Now I've also
you know incorporated more statistically
rigorous methods like Hardigan's dip
test to you know essentially assign a p
value for how much the distribution
deviates from you know uni modality I
guess for lack of a better term. Um but
that actually you know wouldn't actually
catch this case. So it's definitely it's
a it's a technical certainly a technical
problem that we have to that we have to
push through because what happens is you
actually see you know there's like
there's a you can imagine a mode there
like you could fit as many Gaussians as
you want into this right so essentially
you see like there's like a Gaussian
here and what happens is it actually
turns out to you know these are the
sequences that perfectly match the CA a
in the motif but then you see the
population here is the ones that only
slightly deviate from the consensus and
the problem is because you know motifs
are a different length you know they you
know they don't just it's not a picture
perfect biodal unimodal pattern so yeah
it's definitely an ongoing technical
problem that we have to solve because of
the biological implications
>> and kind of related to that and I
remember because I remember you showed
me this a long time ago but for how you
presented you rely a lot of course on
the motif like chromi pinet usually uses
modisco after like you know because yeah
the sequence attribution score
>> per se can still be yeah I don't know
what I'm looking at right so you either
>> so in your case you're relying on the
motif but I remember you in some
instances you improve the motif right
>> like you are able so I I guess what I'm
asking is how good does a motif need to
be for you to catch it basically how
robust it is and uh and also through
this method can you actually improve
just per database and
>> yeah so that's part of this as well so
essentially what I've done is for for
this every every TF that went into this
heat map is a TF motif that I have hand
curated so
and again it's kind of you know
unfortunately circular in the fact that
I'm the one who curates the database and
then I'm the one doing so like you know
it is a bit circular in that sense but
I'm essentially hand curating using the
most informationrich
motifs to do this essentially scanning
process because you know you sound
familiar with TF modiscoco and using
secret based methods to do denovo motis
discovery from contribution scores and
sometimes those motifs don't if you say
like run tomtom against those discovered
motifs against the literature aren't
fantastic matches right so that's why I
use the handcurated ones from chipsseek
um you know using like this just the
very simple kernel scanning method which
I find gives better motifs than the
attribution based methods.
>> And so what how many are you left with
from 1,500?
>> So 620.
>> 620.
>> 620. So they're the only 620 that I am
confident in from the chipsseek. Um
>> Yeah. Yeah. No, that's fine.
>> Yeah.
Nobody has asked it though.
>> This is for this is for the future.
>> Yeah. I there's been I think someone in
the lab did it but there are um other
papers that show that that of course a
lot of these motifs are more um
sensitive to others to genotype
variation. They show a little frequenc a
specific binding. So
have you thought are it's in your future
interest to try to incorporate genetics
and try to characterize them more in
like go to the basically to the clinical
like look up variations and try to
annotate
which one are more uh
oh yeah uh which one are
more likely to respond to a snip
variation more causal or something and
intersecting with G was this kind of
things.
>> Exactly. And that's like the that will
be essentially the hopefully the you
know tying this all together will be
exactly that intersecting all of these
essentially we'll use the the 1500
endode experiments DNA synagic
experiments to essentially call an atlas
of these transcription factor binding
sites and then that'll be one of the
first things we do is essentially
intersecting them with all the G-W was
and all these snips to do exactly that.
Right.
>> So this is going to be just posterior
like
>> Exactly. Yeah. So in in the case that
you said no that's not hasn't been using
like looking specifically at a specific
binding. No that's not not in the
immediate future.
>> Someone did
right or at least what was available at
the time
>> and did an alo specific study on that.
>> Yes.
>> Unfortunately that unfortunately that's
still sitting on um
>> this is the publish. Oh, publish.
>> I think someone did it.
>> Okay.
>> I double check.
>> Yeah. Yeah, show me. Yeah, show me.
Uh so for in your last slide um again
bringing in the genetics here I don't
know if you you mentioned for example
that you don't necessarily know if this
different um uh elements through the
different through binding to different
TFS will even regulate the same gene in
the in different tissues etc. So I was
wondering if you have already a few
examples or if you plan to have some in
the future of specific genes and how
that or maybe take uh this elements this
regulatory elements that we know what
gene they regulate at least in some
tissues because for example it's been um
proposed that more essential gene for
for example they have more complex
regulatory landscapes. So that might
actually be very interesting for someone
to see that the same gene has different
um is being regulated by a different
enhancer or a different pattern in the
same enhancer in different cell types.
So I think that would be very
interesting. Um yeah starting from from
genes that we know the enhancer gene
link.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. And we hope to
that's what part of what we hope to do
especially leveraging all of the um 3D
chrom chromatin interaction data we have
from encode is ab absolutely do that.
Yeah. my to-do my to-do list just keeps
getting longer and longer as I'm sure
all of ours does.
>> One more question if we um yeah I think
you briefly touched upon that. I wanted
to ask if there is uh anything more you
can comment on uh like the uh
cooperative or synergistic effects of
the different TFS or if if you have any
way of pursuing this further. Um yeah
like they bind they both have or yeah
let's say pairs for now they both have
to bind to like uh how does that factor
in in how how uh much more complicated
would it be to systematically
um
>> so it's easy no I don't mean e but it's
easier sorry as I give everyone a
headache here I don't remember where
do I have it here yeah I do so it's
easier when you're looking at
essentially two TFs that bind we know
bind at a distance. So we know that um f
uh foss and te cooperate together and we
actually know specifically they
cooperate together um in a lot of uh
cancerous cell types and we actually
know that actually not only do they
prefer but we actually know that they
prefer to be separated specifically by
six base pairs and you can do the
analysis you can actually you can you
can take these two motifs and you can
slide them across one another and you
can see the changes in the predictions
of the binding or chromatin
accessibility. you see it actually, you
know, spikes at that six base pairs. So,
when it's two motifs that um, you know,
are separated by a specific fixed
distance, we can see that really well.
When it's more murky and it's
essentially the two sites overlap one
another and, you know, you kind of
squint and it looks like one motif and
you then squint and, you know, look the
other way and it looks like the other.
That's very difficult and that's
something that's very hard. Do you have
any sense as to how often these two
motifs appear together versus separately
in the whole genome or like is is this a
trend that you see uh in the entire
genome or uh I don't know very local?
>> Yeah. Yeah. So in this I can tell you
specifically in this specific instance
of the essentially um fos ted dimer
there are thousands of these um and
specifically they're enriched if you
look if you were to pull um if you were
to run motif discovery on um like MCF7
cells A549 cells a lot of these these
cancerous cell lines you'll see an
enrichment for these and it occurs in
the thousands. Now in terms of like when
one versus the like when when they occur
exactly at six base pairs verse not I I
don't have that exact number but that
specific this this specific instance is
I don't know I don't know if it's in the
literature that it prefers to be six
base pairs. I know that it's that they
prefer it's they're always together but
yeah that analysis is sort that that
like field is still in its infancy.
>> Thank you. Yes.
>> Well, thank you so much, Greg, for
speaking. That was a great talk. I think
we'll do like a five to 10 minute break
um before we begin the next talk. We're
now gonna moving on to the next talk of
programming for MIA today. So, we'll be
hearing from Jacob Shriber, who actually
just began his lab at UMass Chan in
Worcester. Um and we're very excited to
hear about his work. Um so,
Well, thank you. As Laura mentioned, I
just started my group at UMass Chen
Medical School. And so, it's kind of
fortunate timing that I get to come here
and introduce to you a little bit about
what I've been doing over the course of
the last uh over the course of the last
few years. But before we talk about
that, let's take a little bit of a step
back. Over 20 years ago now, the first
draft of a human reference genome came
out and a little snippet of it looks
something like this. In the words of a
familiar face, Dr. Eric Lander, genome
bought the book hard to read.
Even though it is challenging for us
mere mortals to understand these long
sequences of AEC's, G's and T's, having
this map provided the basis for the next
generation of biochemical assays to be
developed. Here we can see four such
experiments, each measuring the binding
of an individual transcription factor.
Just by looking at these readouts, we
can see how informative these sorts of
experiments are. At this enhancer,
there's the binding of Oct 4, SOCK 2,
and Nanog, but not necessarily the
binding of KF. However, relying solely
on the readouts from these experiments
is kind of reminiscent of the blind men
trying to describe an elephant based on
what they felt. Just because we
understand what is happening and where
in the genome doesn't mean that we
understand why it is happening there.
And so enter sequencebased machine
learning models. Greg gave a great
introduction to the sorts of models that
I'm talking about here. But at a high
level there are many different internal
computational units that these sorts of
models can have. Convolutions,
transformers, etc. And there are many
different precise formulations of the
tasks that the models try to solve.
However, broadly speaking,
sequence-based machine learning models
are those that take in nucleotide
sequence and make predictions for the
outputs from these sorts of biochemical
assays. But the predictions from these
models, in my view, are kind of some of
the least interesting aspects of them.
Most of the assays that we deal with
provide us with genomewide readouts.
There is no more like secret genome that
we need to go and make predictions for.
Rather, in my view, one of the strengths
of these machine learning models is
being able to run them backwards to be
able to get them to explain why they
made the predictions that they did. And
if we look at this example here, we can
see that the reason why this model
predicted the binding of Oct 4 here is
because there's an octetic
binding site there. So over the course
of the last year, I've been working on
basically trying to take this mechanism
and repurpose it for design, but
specifically the design of edits to
biological sequences with a uh or edits
to biological sequences. The way that
this works is basically as follows. Just
like before, you have some sequence that
you're working with. You have your
machine learning model, but now you have
a new component, the desired output from
the model. Maybe you want to design a
region where proteins really bind very
strongly. Maybe you want to design a
region where the protein doesn't bind at
all or one that's a site that's
accessible, a site that's transcribed,
etc. Anything that can be the target of
machine learning prediction. The way
that this works is that you take your
sequence,
you run it through the model, and you
get what the [clears throat] actual
output from the model is. Now you take
the actual output, you compare it with
the desired output, and now you run this
difference backwards through the model.
Rather than being able to highlight the
nucleotides that are driving model
predictions like we did before,
we are now highlighting the nucleotides
that need to change in order to achieve
your target objective. But we encounter
a problem here. This design of edits
problem is discreet. We have to choose
which positions we want to edit and what
characters we want at that position. But
the values that we saw before were quite
continuous where the height of the
character basically corresponded to how
important it was to the model. So the
main technical challenge that we had to
overcome with our method was recasting
this discrete optimization problem as a
continuous optimization problem that
could be solved quite simply.
So the way that we did this was we
introduced this method called lidi that
ends up under uh learning an underlying
continuous weight matrix. Let's uh take
a look at what's happening midway
through this design process. We have our
initial sequence that we're trying to
edit. At this point in the design
process doesn't really care what it is.
Maybe has a slight preference for C. And
what we end up doing is sampling the
original character, the G, at that
position.
Then at the next position, uh, it's
originally an A, but Lydia thinks that
quite strongly it should be a T here.
And so we end up drawing a T, an edit to
that sequence. We can go down the entire
sequence mostly keeping with the
original sequence, but at some points
making edits to the sequence and we end
up with a new edited discrete sequence.
We can run that through the model, get
our actual output, compare it to the
desired output, run the difference
backwards through the model as before.
But when we encounter the edited
sequence, we can just go straight
through it and end up optimizing this
underlying continuous weight matrix. In
this manner, we have recasted the
discrete optimization problem of
choosing which edits to make as a
continuous optimization problem that can
be solved using just off-the-shelf
optimizers and really just a few lines
of code.
What's a little bit more complicated
though is the exact loss that Lid is
optimizing. It's comprised of two terms.
The first is the output loss term that
most design methods have. Are you
achieving your desired objective? Does
this sequence make the predictions that
you would like it to? The second is this
novel input loss term. It's basically
just counting the number of edits that
were made in that sequence. And so in
this manner, we are explicitly trying to
minimize the number of edits necessary
in order to achieve our target
objective.
Then of course because there are two
terms you have to have a mixture weight
there that controls uh the balance
between the two and the rough intuition
here is basically uh you set it to
however many units of the output loss
you want each edit to be able to reduce
by. So it takes a little bit of tweaking
but it's actually usually quite robust
to this. Then the first question is does
this sort of formulation work? And so we
paired it with a a situation I initially
thought was going to be quite simple but
ended up being quite interesting
afterward. This was the design of gata 2
binding sites. Uh Greg introduced in the
earlier talk that gatter is quite a
simple motif. It binds basically to the
motif gata and that's where I expected
it to land. And so we took some sites
that initially were not predicted by a
bpet model to uh have data binding the
dark uh the black line there. And we
wanted them to be edited to become a
site that gata bound quite strongly. And
after running our process we end up with
sequences over there. they don't quite
end up on the cyan line because remember
we have a mixture of two terms and that
if we got closer to the cyan line that
would cost too many edits to do but
basically we're still able to design
sequences that had strong data binding.
Yeah.
Oh sorry I need the microphone for the
people online
about the loss term uh because then you
say the number of edits that's the
discrete thing. So it's like the your
sampling it's like the pro you're
penalizing the probability difference
like can you just talk a bit about what
that
>> it's quite literally the the discrete
number of edits and so it's it ends up
being an integer loss and you can work
this into a differentiable loss in the
same way that you'd work an L1 loss in
uh in the sense that it's uh
>> we can talk a little bit more about it
afterwards but it's not that
complicated.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. So uh yeah, can you uh say a
little bit more about the leidi matrix
itself? I was going to ask it's uh if
every row does it sum to one like is it
a probability of finding each
nucleotide?
>> Yes, that's a great question.
>> Is it parameterized somehow? How you
know how yeah it's dimension?
>> It's a really good question. Sometimes I
skip over the technical aspects here
because depending on the audience they
don't care. Uh but it's nice to
encounter an audience that does care.
The gist is basically that this weight
matrix is initialized to all zeros,
though you could potentially initialize
it to very small random values depending
on if you want to run this multiple
times and get something different. It's
initialized to all zeros. And what you
end up doing is you interpret the values
of these weights as uh logic. And so
it's not that you sample from the lid
weight matrix, it's that you sample from
the addition of the initial sequence and
the lid weight matrix. And so what you
end up doing is slightly preferencing
that probability distribution towards
the initial sequence but still allowing
the weight matrix to say absolutely not
if it thinks so so strongly. Does that
make sense that that's the reason
there's the plus sign there that you are
sampling from the addition of the
initial sequence and this weight matrix.
But another little detail here is that
that's not just the one hot encoded
initial sequence. It's basically the log
of the initial sequence plus a small
epsilon term where when the value is
like a g there that's a zero and for the
non-G positions it's like minus 4 or so
in principle that's another
hyperparameter but usually I found that
it it doesn't really make that much of a
difference that it just controls the
dynamic range of the final values
>> okay
Thanks.
>> Thanks. Um, on the next slide, could you
just reexplain like what's the starting
sequence you use before you start making
these edits to get the data to? Like is
it a random sequence or do you
>> and does it depend where you start in
terms of what you get?
>> That's a great question. We're going to
um hopefully talk about that exact
second question about differences in how
you start uh a little bit later in the
talk. This is entirely a toy example
meant to just show that lidi works in
principle. So here we took regions that
were not gata peaks. I didn't do
anything particularly clever here. So I
just took real genomic regions that GAT
did not bind to and I set it to a very
high value and I wanted to see whether
or not LBD could create edits that uh
caused you to have gata binding.
>> This is such a biologist question. I'm
sorry I feel a bit like a fish out of
water in this seminar, but how big is
the region? You know, we think about
transcription factor binding a lot and
how big is the region compared to like
nucleosome binding or
>> Yeah. Um, I'm going to remake this point
a little bit later, which is that the DD
is a design algorithm, which means that
it can be paired with any machine
learning model. And so the receptive
field you are doing the edits on depends
on the model that you're using. Here,
this is a BPET model whose input window
is intuitively 2,114 base pairs. Uh, and
so that's the size of the edits. Uh, the
window being edited.
Cool. Okay.
So, uh if we look at the losses, oh,
another question.
>> So, how do you actually optimize the
loss here? Do you use gradient descent
or some sort of like sampling like
genetic algorithm or something like
that?
>> Yeah, that's a great question. I just
use the atom optimizer. I use Atom
because everybody uses Atom and
specifically I use the Atom uh
implementation which has a bug in it and
not the Atom W implementation which has
fixed the bug because everybody uses the
Atom implementation or maybe not bug but
it misses a technical detail that from
the but that's what I use. You can use
any optimizer that you would like. uh
really just if you're using PyTorch
which you should uh it's the optimizer
that you use is completely decoupled
from the design process.
>> Yep. Thanks.
>> Okay. Uh so if you look at the if you
look at the losses during the design
process, you see that there are
basically three regimes. In this first
one, the input loss rapidly increases.
Basically, edits are being proposed
rapidly in order to try to meet our
desired objective.
In the second regime, these obviously
unhelpful edits kind of like edits which
are in LD if you think about it from a
computational perspective with the ones
that are actually valuable end up being
discarded because we're trying to
explicitly minimize the number of edits
that are being proposed. And then
there's this third long regime which is
a long tail. Basically that we are
slowly merging sets of slightly helpful
edits into smaller sets of moderately
helpful edits. Basically trying to see
whether or not um we can condense the
size even more. And if you look very
carefully there you can see that roughly
you're reducing the size number of edits
by 33% over the course of you know that
150 uh steps there.
So what edits are actually being
proposed? If we look at the gata site,
you might be unsurprised to see that
adding in gata binding takes five
nucleotides when the gata motif is gata.
But if you look at the exact positioning
of where these edits are happening, you
see something really interesting. Only
one edit, that really big a is happening
in the core gata site.
Three edits are being made in the
surrounding flanking regions, which is
another point that Greg alluded to in
his talk, which is that the flanking
context of these motifs can matter a
great deal. One edit is kind of out far
there. You may initially want to
discount what's going on there, but what
it's doing is it's adding in a towel
binding site. Towel is a co-actor of
GATA, which greatly enhances its
binding. And so what's happening here is
that not only are we making GAT the GATA
site nice and easy for GATA to bind to,
we are adding in a co-actor site. And so
Leidi is specifically targeting a site
which was almost gata almost a strong
gata site and specifically making the
nucleotide changes there as opposed to
just plopping in a motif somewhere
random in sequence.
If we uh use a simple pruning algorithm,
we can actually get this down to two
edits and still preserve 98% of the
predicted binding. So maybe you're still
not impressed. Maybe you think GAT is
quite a small motif. It's still not
surprising that five edits adds in gata.
This was quite pervasive. If we look at
CTCF, you can see that with just four
edits or three edits after pruning, we
were able to go from no CTCF binding to
strong predicted CTCF binding by
targeting a site in the genome that was
almost CTCF.
I have a kind of evolutionary hypothesis
about this which I'm as a computational
person I'm not particularly well
equipped to handle even super formalize
which is basically goes like this that
our genomes are a graveyard of past
viral infections transposon activity all
sorts of other things that used to do
stuff which was bad and our genome
evolved out that function in part by
disrupting key binding sites and so we
can use lidi to bring back these binding
sites um in a ways that you might not
intuitively expect. So I think about the
genome as being much more kind of
continuous than you might normally
expect. That there are so many sites
that are almost motifs, much more than
you would normally expect.
Um just for time reasons to make sure I
get to everything, I'm going to skip
this. An important point here is that
because the DD is gradient based, uh it
involves running these values backwards,
it ends up being quite faster than other
approaches that are out there. If we try
a simple approach where we take around
17 motifs that are relevant for the
design task that we care about and we
try plopping them in at every position
in the sequence and do our design that
way in this method which is called motif
implantation. It takes a few hundred
seconds to do the design task using this
model called say.
If we try greedy substitution which is
uh sometimes it's called directed
evolution where you make one nucleotide
edit at a time until you achieve your
desired objective. It takes around 200
seconds to achieve your target goal. If
you use lidi it can be over an order of
magnitude faster. And the reason for
this is because you can imagine that
greedy substitution is basically just
going through and saying does this edit
help? Does this edit help? Does this
edit help? for every possible edit that
one could make, kind of like a petulant
child. In contrast, Leidi potentially
can make multiple edits at the same
time. By using the gradient, it can even
add in entire motifs. And so each step,
even though it takes slightly longer
because you have to go forward and
backwards as opposed forward, adds in
more information to design task. You
take bigger steps towards your goal.
Um I'm going to skip this also for
reasons. So
um like the point I was making before,
Lidi is a design method. Sometimes when
people publish papers talking about how
they have a new design method, what they
really mean is they have a really cool
new machine learning model that they
have then applied standard design
methods to and those machine learning
models are cool and the ultimate designs
they get out of them are cool, but they
haven't actually proposed a new design
method. Because it is a design method,
Leidi can be paired with any model
that's out there. Any model you've
already trained in your lab or have on a
collaborator, any model that's already
public and out there. And so in order to
demonstrate this, we tried to apply
Leidi broadly just using out of the box
settings. Here's a different version of
our gata friend from before where we
take a region that exhibited median
activity in the genome. not particularly
high, not you know, not an anomalously
low region, but a region where gata
didn't bind. And we wanted to turn into
a really strong region where gata does
bind. And we're able to achieve that,
like we showed before. But then we
considered four different transcription
factors across two different models. Out
of the box, we were able to design edits
that achieved our target goal quite
simply.
Then we looked at four different models
of chromatin accessibility and again saw
that we were able to achieve our desired
goal uh without changing the settings at
all.
Then we looked at transcription
transcription initiation.
We looked at MP activity.
We looked at starsek data. And in each
one of these settings, Leidi was simply
able to design edits using the model in
order to achieve our target goal. So
Leidi is a generalpurpose designer of
edits.
All right. Sometimes this term
overfitting comes in when people talk
about training machine learning models.
They're worried that the model has
overfitit to the training set and is not
actually generalizable in practice.
Here it's important to keep in mind that
the same concepts can apply to design
that potentially the designs that you
create can overfit to the parameters of
the model. Maybe the model has learned
something wacky which doesn't actually
hold. Maybe you're able to push the
model out of distribution in some wacky
way. If you think about computer vision,
there are a series of papers that came
out that showed that if you had an
image, you could change one pixel value
in an imperceptible way to get it to
predict any class that you wanted. It's
not quite as easy to do with DNA models
because you just have discrete
characters, but that sort of idea is
potentially valid. And so a question
that we had is are the edits that we're
proposing actually generalizable or do
they you know are they just pushing the
model off distribution and so what we
did is we took edits that were designed
using BPN models each group here is for
a different transcription factor and
each color is a different external model
and we wanted to verify if we design
edits using BPAT
do external models also predict higher
you know binding we were considering
mostly just higher binding here. Do
these external models also cons give us
higher binding? And even more
indirectly, if we consider models of
chromatin accessibility, if we design
edits that say add in CTCF binding, do
models of chromatin accessibility
predict higher accessibility? And so in
each one of these cases, we saw that we
uh were able to that the models that
that the edits that we designed were
generalizable across models and we're
able to valid Yeah.
If if all the models predict that pixel
doesn't make the pixel biologically
relevant.
>> Like just because they agree that that
pixel is important doesn't make the
pixel relevant. Like you said, you can
still predict every class. They just
agree on.
>> So yeah. So here the the the idea is
that we're trying to not overfit to the
eccentricities of any specific model.
It's unlikely that very different models
trained on very in very different ways
on different processed forms of the
readouts even different forms of
biochemical assay would have the same
eccentricities
or like I think in the case where you
take a pixel and you are able to modify
it slightly to get any prediction that
you want that if you then fed that into
a second model you would not get the
same response that it's just an
eccentricity of the specific model
you're working with.
>> I see. And when you when you write led
plus pruning, is that the pruning is
post or is something that just happens?
>> Oh yeah, that's uh that's an optional
post-processing step afterward
>> like that like the you do
or
>> there's built-in functionality builtin
function. What we have is I mean you can
do whatever sort of pruding you want but
we do a greedy approach where you go
through every edit and you see what
happens when you revert it and if
reverting it doesn't bring you uh you
know there's a tolerance for how far
away from your desired objective you can
go during the pruning thing and if the
edits are within that tolerance then you
undo them
>> because I was just think seeing that
that you go to just a couple of bases I
would been curious to see from BPET for
example attribution scores like if
you're peing the top two most important
from from BPnet.
Um
like in a certain kind of way and trying
to understand the the like how you use
it and uh and
>> so are you saying for the pruning step?
Uh yeah, in general because right you
have you cannot make that many edits
like like you showed at the first output
>> and so and but in the end after you
prune you get just two bases
>> and maybe it was just a case but like if
those two bases are the one that Pineta
gives a very low attribution score
meaning that if they're not there
there's not accessibility. If you pick
just the top two,
the model will tell you that now there
is accessibility but maybe biologically
will not work. No, like I think this is
an interesting conversation that we
should talk about later. I think that
ultimately you're right that there are
many sorts of post-processing strategies
that one could use. I generally try to
avoid getting into this because there
are so many heristics that one could
consider. I was more just trying to make
the point that we were so close to a
data site and you might not have known
it if you had only looked at
attributions or if you you know had only
looked at predictions from the model.
>> Are you going to talk more about
experimental validation or is
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
>> Um yeah quick question about the
baseline. So um yeah, what do you mean
by same edit composite because it I'm
trying to understand whether this is a
result about the consistency of these
models or about your approach to find
something that is
>> consistent. So the same edit baseline is
that if we take the same number of edits
of each type like a to transitions etc
and we apply them randomly a hundred
times in that sequence what do the model
predictions look like? Okay. But there's
different ways to think about what same
is is going to be in that sense. So for
example, as you're saying, it's like the
frequency of one to other, but then
you've also got for example like do they
align match up with the attribution
uh the the bases that are contributing
to the like do you do you include that
information? So it's like
>> remember that these are sequences that
do not exhibit the activity normally. If
you look at the attributions, there's
going to be nothing because the models
are not predicting that there's binding.
So you can't really use the attributions
in order to guide where you want to make
edits.
>> Right. Okay. I see what you're saying.
But I mean you could take the gradient
or something to in in this particular
direction like try and control for I
mean if you start talking about you
taking the gradient in a certain
direction then you come up with lidi
right because that's what lidi does. It
uses the gradient.
>> Okay. But then just in general, do you
think this is saying something about
lidi or about the consistency of what's
driving these models?
>> I mean, I think ultimately it's both,
right? That if one model fails to pick
up on a motif that actually is
biologically plausible and a second
model is picked up on, like you're not
going to see as strong a like there's a
reason here that CTCF gives us the
cleanest signal, right? in terms of if
you design a CTCF binding site that
informer really agrees that that's a
CTCF site because CTCF is so simple.
These other ones have more complicated
binding modes and so there may be more
disagreement about what exactly is the
strongest version of each motif amongst
them. Uh so I mean I do think that it's
both. I think that
uh it can be a way of seeing how much
models agree with each other, but also
that it is a way of making sure that you
haven't done something absolutely wacky
with one model that nothing else agrees
is reasonable.
>> So a general principle would be like
you'd expect some signal in all of the
models, but then just the overall like
maximum.
>> Yeah, thanks.
I'm just curious if there's a biological
reason for why or the model design
reason for why that outlier exists with
informer and CTCF. Um is it something
specific to CTSCF binding sites?
I think that
>> so I think part of part of it is that
CTCF is a very conserved somewhat simp I
mean it's not super simple but it's like
it is more simple than some of the other
ones in terms of the what the motif is
and how strong the CTCF binds to all
instances of CTCF as for why informer
and not the other ones have such a
strong response I would say that that
just is because bpnet and informer here
seem to agree more on the exact um the
exact composition,
right? I think I have to keep going if I
want to get to some of what I think is
the most interesting aspect of this.
So, because of the DVD speed, we can use
multiple models simultaneously in the
design process. Sometimes the way that
research goes is that you design a
model, you train a model specifically
for the targets that you want to make
designs for, even if that's multiple
things. Because the DD is very fast, you
can use multiple models. Maybe you want
to use an informer model, but one of the
heads happens to be bad. So you train
your own specialized model for that one
head. Maybe you have an internal
experimental track that you want to
train a model for, but you want to
combine it with models that your
collaborators used, etc. And so, Leidi
is able to use these multiple models
simultaneously to really precisely
control multiple characteristics of the
design. So, the question becomes which
multiple models should we use? Well, I
spent the last year in Vienna at the
research institute of molecular
pathology sitting next to Alex Stark.
And so, given that I was contractually
obligated to use his starsek models and
so we use those in order to design cell
type specific enhancers in Drosophila.
So here we use two deep store models.
One of which was from a previous
published paper that we didn't touch at
all. The OSC model had to be retrained
for uh for this work but was not
originally proposed in this work. And we
but each one of them only models a
single cell line. This isn't a multitask
um setting. This is two distinct models
and we wanted to try to design enhancers
that were active in only one cell line.
But like I said before, one of the
aspects of Leidi is that it is designing
edits to an initial template sequence.
And so our natural question is what
should those template sequences be? The
simplest such set of template sequences
is regions that are never enhancers.
Regions that are non-enhancers in other
cell line and we want to turn them on in
one cell line, turn them on in the other
cell line.
And when we do that, we can see that
computationally we are able to designers
that are quite specific. On the top we
have the designs which are S2 specific
and the burgundy shows the predictions
for those sequences. The green shows the
predictions for OSC and we can see that
those are quite low even a little
negative and we see a little bit of the
reverse. These are this is in silica. So
these are predictions from the model but
we can consider other template pools as
well. We can take regions which were
initially enhancers in S2, regions which
are initially enhancers in OSC, ones
that are enhancers in both and then just
uniformly randomly generated DNA. So not
endogenous at all, just uniformly
randomly sampled. And in each one of
those cases, it seems like
computationally we were able to design
cell type specific enhancers. But the
question arose earlier, what about
experimental validation for these? So we
then went and uh Franciscoca in the
Alex's lab went and ran an actual
starsek experiment. And so this is
actual real starseek data. The dots
correspond to the target cell line that
we are trying to design activity in. And
what you can see is that the margin
between the two is quite large. Uh for
the OSE activity, the ones in green, we
can see that the activity in OS is quite
large and the activity in S2 is quite
restrained. The ones in Burgundy are a
little bit more of a complex story.
Ultimately, we use this loss which was
trying to maximize the gap between the
two as opposed to necessarily keeping
the offtarget cell line low. And so
that's why we get the results that we
see here where some of them seem that
quite a few seem to have activity in OSC
as well but stronger activity in S2.
It's just like across all these
different settings we were able to
design cells uh enhancers.
We then considered a more complex
setting what we're calling an affinity
catalog where not only are we trying to
control the cell type specificity of the
region we're also trying to control the
dosids in the onarget cell line. And so
we set specific targets here where where
we want to design weak enhancers,
mid-strength enhancers, strong
enhancers, and unnaturally strong
regions which are more strong than any
indogenous enhancer uh from previously
characterized starseek experiments. We
also wanted to see if we could design
enhancers which are active in both cell
lines from each one of these pools. And
so this was kind of a comprehensive
experiment. One of the benefits of
Starseek is that it's super high
throughput and so we're able to easily
do thousands of such candidate
sequences.
U
this is what the data looks like there
that it seems much more cell type
specific here because we are explicitly
trying to keep the offtarget cell line
off but we see a gradient of activity in
the ontarget cell line where there's a
bit of overlap there between the weak S2
enhancers and the weak o enhancers some
of them kind of dropped out but that
otherwise it's forming this sort of L
shape when we consider the enhancers
which are supposed to be active in both
they kind of follow the diagonal where
the regions that are they're getting
stronger and stronger cell lines.
So,
uh was kind of surprising here is how
few edits we were able to do this in
these uh sequences were 249 base pairs
long because that's the input window of
the deep store models. But that we were
able to design um cell type specific
enhancers that were of strong activity
in fewer than 20 edits. So by editing
less than 10% of the sequence uh we
could induce you know kind of strong
activity. The mining gap ones are a
little bit of a outlier there because
they are I can talk about that later but
basically they are a little bit of an
outlier due to the way that the
objective is formulated. But it was
quite surprising how few edits one was
able to uh one was able to use here. But
this brings up a natural question of
well okay so what are the edits that are
being made here? And so I want to share
two stories here uh that I thought were
really interesting.
The first was when we took a region
which was initially an S2 enhancer and
we wanted to edit it to become an
enhancer in OSC. You can imagine that
this involves two components. The first
is we have to turn off activity in S2
and then we have to turn on activity in
OSA.
And so when we look at the attributions
from the deep star models, you can see
that the reason that these models think
that this region is S2 specific
initially is because of the presence of
these two gata motives. Scatter is a S2
specific uh is a S2 specific factor
here. When we want to design enhancers
which have weak OSC specific activity,
you can see a few things are going on.
The first is that we make an edit on the
left hand side to knock out that data
binding site. We make two edits on the
right hand side to knock out the second
GAT binding site and then we make a few
edits that the model is a little bit
confused as to what exactly is going on
there. But we'll see in a second. With
10 total edits, we are able to convert
this from being a strong S2 specific
enhancer to a weak OS specific enhancer
where the experimental data verifies
that. I'm not showing the experimental
data, but it verifies that.
When we want to create a mid-strength OS
enhancer, you can see we're basically
doing the same thing. where we're
knocking out the gata binding sites on
either side but with one targeted edit
in the middle we have induced a traffic
jam motif now called traffic jam because
you know how drosopha people can be
sometimes
so what was interesting here is that
with one targeted edit just adding in
that C we were able to get a mid
strength OSE enhancer here but it took
us two edits before in order to get a
weak OSE enhancer and the reason is
because that C site there was critical
for getting the traffic jam motif at
all. And then you had to make a
subsequent edit to make it a weak
affinity version of that motif. So
sometimes activity in the genome when
you're doing editing isn't necessarily
linear with expectation. So it's not
exactly linear with the number of edits
needed for the amount of activity that
you want. It takes 10 total edits to get
uh to either direction and then 17 total
edits to make it a very strong version
of this OSE specific enhancer. Basically
what we end up doing is adding in a
second copy of this traffic jam motif
sort of on the dead body of the gata
motif that we had on the left hand side
there.
So then the second one that I wanted to
share with you was where we took a
region which was initially an OSC
specific enhancer and we wanted to make
it active in both cell lines. And so
this involves adding in activity as
opposed to you know swapping which uh
which cell line is activating
here. uh you can probably figure out
which one of the figures is being
included in the paper and which one was
made just for the uh slideshow. But here
we can see the attributions for the S2
cell line in the bottom and for the OSC
cell line on the top. The reason that
this wasn't an OS specific enhancer is
because of the presence of the traffic
jam motif with a little bit of other
stuff going on on the right hand side
there right next to it.
When we want to try making this weak in
both cell lines, we can see that not
much is really going on. There's some
stuff going on offscreen here.
When we want to make this a mid strength
enhancer in both cell lines is when we
start to see something really
interesting. By making these edits,
adding in a C and an A, we create a
traffic jam dur. This is a very strong
OSE specific signal there. But by
positioning the two traffic jam motifs
at that distance, what you end up doing
is implicitly creating an AP1 motif
within them. AP1 is specific to S2 as
well. And so this is something which I'm
describing as basically like Mario uh
motifs that these are motifs that are
that are explicitly within each other.
By being cell type specific for
different cell lines, you can now make
them active in multiple very distinct
cell lines. This only happens because
Leidi is trying to minimize the number
of edits that are being made. You could
imagine that there's no constraint. You
could just put the AP1 motif wherever.
You wouldn't have to think about this.
But it saw that by making these two
edits, you could add in activity in both
these cell lines at the same time. So I
think this is really interesting.
Sometimes we think about motifs as just
like, oh, there's a there's a blah motif
here and there's a blah motif over here.
But I've been trying to push for a while
now that the genome is much more
continuous than that. So here we have
different we have totally different
motifs that are overlapping each other.
Different proteins are binding to the
exact same nucleotides in different cell
lines.
And then we start to see stronger
activity in both when we want these to
be strong. And then we want them to be
unnaturally strong. Today uh we see
another version of the same phenomena
with the TJ Dmer and the APY motive on
the left hand side. So this is kind of a
reproducible sort of phenomena.
All right. Um I'm going to just skim
over a few things just some food for
thought for people. One of the other
inso experiments that we did is that we
paired together a chrome bpnet model
which made predictions for accessibility
with a bpnet model that made predictions
for the binding of an individual
protein. And by doing this, we're able
to design regions that were accessible
and control why they were accessible.
Instead of just using a panel of
different, you know, motifs depending
on, you know, what happened to be
available, we were able to create sites
which were uniformly accessible but
control which exact transcription
factors were binding and causing that
access or were binding in that in those
accessible sites. We don't have
experimental data for this yet, but
these uh incilico data looks uh quite
nice.
We can also turn this concept on its
head. We've been talking so much about
uh uh we've been talking so far about
using models that make predictions for
different sorts of things and being able
to control different parts of biology
with them. But what happens if you use
multiple models that make predictions
for the same thing? This can be used for
a more robust design setting that if you
make edits that all of the models have
to agree are helpful for a particular
task like the binding of a particular
protein or accessibility, you're much
much less likely to overfit to the
eccentricities of any specific model.
This is a little bit uh difficult to
interpret. who are reworking the figure.
But the gist is basically that when you
use even one other model, when you pair
together two models that make
predictions for the same things, you get
designs which are much more robust and
much better validated by external models
than if you use any individual model.
Okay. Uh
this last part is a little bit uh
complicated. So I think that I'm just
gonna wrap it up at this point and
I think I was gonna wrap it up at this
point and thank all of my colle
and summarize it. Uh so basically leidi
is a design method which means that it
can be paired with any machine learning
model or a collection of machine
learning model to design edits to an
initial template sequence that can
control very precisely the
characteristics of that sequence.
Um we have introduced this idea of an
affinity catalog where instead of just
designing for a single target which is
pretty common right now trying to design
very strongly cell type specific
activity you try to make designs for
many different steps along a path
because this can be quite useful not
only in practice but also for
understanding the biology of sequences.
So
um I think that the
in general the development of these
sorts of models these sorts of methods
which make use of the train models are
important for the field. We've been
spending a lot of time trying to
optimize the predictive performance of
the models that we train. We have
competitions that try to you know
encourage development in this but we
don't really know what to do with these
mo maybe not don't know what to do but
much less focus has been paid to what
exactly we do with these models after
they have been trained and so design I
think is a really promising area for how
we can use these models that actually
make a real world impact. So I'd like to
thank all my collaborators over the
years that have helped with this project
and many other collaborations and thank
you for taking the time to listen to me.
Thank you.
Um thank you for the great talk. I think
this is related to Orura's question a
little bit actually. Um a lot of these
sequence of function models are trained
on the reference genome, right?
>> Yeah. And um
in the past the reference genome the the
reference al didn't necessarily need to
be the most frequent one observed in the
population because I don't think we've
had sequenced that many. Um I read that
the newest like the most recent version
updated some of the reference alals to
um the more frequent um alals. Anyway,
so I think some of the models are maybe
trained may may have been I don't
actually know trained on an older
reference genome. Some of them may be
trained on a newer reference genome and
I'm assuming your initial sequence is
the reference genome. Um how much does
can you comment on whether
the consistency between the models with
respect to the you know base sequence
used in training matters.
>> Yeah.
>> Um yeah
>> this is a great question. Something you
may also be interested in is that I
think that autoboot had a paper a few
years ago showing that the HG19
reference genome had the markers of type
1 diabetes in it. And so for anyone who
was studying diabetes using that
reference genome, it may have given a
incorrect impression of the genetic
landscape there, which is weird because
the way he phrased it at least, and I
don't know if this is true, it just
seemed like nobody had looked before to
see whether or not these sorts of
disease markers were present in
reference genomes as to whether or not
this affects machine learning models. I
think the field is kind of split. The
intuition makes sense as you clear the
presented that if you train on the
reference genome but the reference
genome is not correct how could the
machine learning models be correct
but when people go and they try to train
on either corrected versions or
personalized versions or using a variety
of genome it doesn't actually seem to
increase predictive performance that
much so I think it's still an open
question of whether or not we haven't
yet found the best ways of improving
predictive performance given the
variation that we're able to incorporate
whether or not we haven't actually
gotten that much data that really
incorporates personal variance or if
there's just something else that we're
missing because it is true conceptually
that any limitations in the data will
become present in the models. But this
is also
it's unclear whether or not if you're
averaging over tens of thousands of
protein binding sites whether or not the
variation at any particular or like even
a dozen sites really matters that much.
>> Thanks for the great talk. Um so I guess
uh my question is related to
uh whether you've done experimental
validation on other models which have
you know more nonlinearities added. So I
guess for lidi you know the benefit is
you know you have a pre-trained model
and you have you're basically optimizing
a given sequence using that. So and you
know it's speedy you can plug in
different models as well. Uh but have
you compared performance on experimental
data with you know maybe you have a
generator network for example and then
you have your pre-trained predictor.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh and you know have you compared that
and you see any uh improvements or
Yeah. I'm just curious if you run those
comparisons.
>> Yeah. I think the the short answer is
that no we don't have experimental data
for these sorts of generative models. Um
there are some practical reasons. The
first being I don't have a wet lab. Um
but there are other just intuitively I
am sometimes skeptical about this idea
of these generative models um because
what you have to do is train a whole
separate model for your design task
against the Oracle model that Lidi is
using and so it's basically like
stacking spinning plates on top of each
other. I already don't trust the machine
learning model that I'm using the DD on.
And now this idea of having to train and
quality control a whole second model
before I can even do design even if it
was successful. It seems to me that it
would be a huge investment of time that
isn't necessary because ultimately you
can just use a method like the DD in
order to get designs as well.
Uh this is probably a bit of a silly
question but you uh talked about how
that it is a design algorithm and you
can pair it with any machine learning. I
was wondering how exactly do you plug
this machine learning model like how how
is it is it for the user to do that for
example what kind of integration does it
actually entail
>> or to talk about the implementation
details that if you have the model as a
pietorch object you just drop it and the
initial sequence into the lid function
as well as what you want the output from
the model to be and you're done. So all
you need is the pietorch object. Uh if
you want to use multiple models
simultaneously,
you you basically just can create a
wrapper class, we have one provided for
you where you just put put in a list of
models and then what the corresponding
output would be, you end up like
concatenating or whatever the um it's
not always straightforward because if
you want to have one model that makes
predictions for a profile and another
model that makes predictions for a
single scaler, you can't just
concatenate those. But you can do it
with lyidity if you follow the
guidelines.
>> Thank you. And the second question uh on
this uh on the like um final part of
your presentation where you talked about
combining models like uh chrome bpnet
and bpnet for example and um combining
where are the chromodin accessible and
why it is accessible. I'm guessing what
you find is a subset of the two um a
small one I'm guessing or I don't know
how small um like you have open
chromatin but only for a subset of that
you can actually figure out why
something if actually something is
binding there and why uh I was wondering
if you have um or thinking about any
examples where you can do some
biological validation why this is
interesting or if there is any way of um
pursuing this. Well, in terms of why
it's interesting that most of what this
boils down to is the design of
constructs for say AAVs or other sorts
of uh other sorts of probes. basically
that if you want to design something
which say glows uh you know you want to
design something which expresses GFP in
proportion to the concentration of
particular protein then you want you
know a particular transcription factor
then you want that transcription factor
to bind and through its binding increase
the expression of GFP and so if you are
designing a promoter site you want to
make sure that there are not secretly
maybe not secretly but that there just
aren't other sorts of binding sites
there so that the signal is convoluted
by the binding of other proteins and so
this very specific sort of um targeting
of a TF has quite a few practical
applications when you want to design
these sorts of reporters.
>> So uh so there is lot of reg as you said
like you know designing this is for like
in this whole cell experiment or in in
in vivo experiments uh so there is also
regulation a lot of regulation inside is
like a lot of things affect each other
right?
>> Yeah. So since we are only like two like
one uh step down I think you have showed
like okay we can have a promoter far end
of the protein and uh far out of
sequence and which the promoter can bind
and therefore increase the activity but
there are multiple steps cascades of
steps under down this initial thing. So
how like uh what could be like have you
done what could be done to sort of get
to that type of simulate?
>> Yes. So that's a great question.
Basically the gist is that predicting
transcription factor predict binding
accessibility transcription initiation
that's nice but that's not the whole
story when it comes to gene expression
and if we want to very specifically
target gene expression patterns we need
to do more than just these sorts of
models. So the nice thing about lyidity
is that you could any sort of model
that's differentiable and takes in
sequence context you could use and so if
we were able to model the how uh
changing protein binding patterns
influence accessibility and stack on top
of that a model that looks at how
changes in that predicted gene
expression might change global patterns.
You could stack all that together and
use that uh with lidi as long as it
becomes a single differentable unit. Uh
the gist is basically that this is a
weakness on the predictive modeling side
that lidi itself can't solve but when
one of us does solve it uh you can
immediately plug in lid to do designs.
>> Thanks. I wanted to follow up on the um
question of practical um applications. I
think this is perhaps more of like a a
suggestion than a question, but um the
reporter design is obviously really
really helpful, but in real world
applications um there are times when we
do want to create different enhancers in
um engineered cells. The the big one is
carti cells. So Alex Marson and Luke
Gilbert I think just had this really
nice paper where they did joint genetic
to make the cart tea and then epigenetic
to reduce T- cell exhaustion. But of
course the epigenetic you know a pro of
it is that it's not um very durable but
a a con is that it's not very durable.
So um in that case editing an endogenous
enhancer
in in a you know a targeted way to make
it more active to activate a given gene
expression program is very desirable.
And so I think my questions suggestion
is how many places in the human
non-coding genome in human enhancers
could you predict that maybe one or two
base changes because that's probably
what's practical, right? Is possible to
create to go from a weak enhancer to a
strong enhancer or to toggle an enhancer
based on your like you know minimum
maximum um effects because that would be
super interesting to know. That's a
really good question. That's something
we haven't uh quite looked at yet
because we weren't sure what to do with
the results once we had them. You know,
it's nice to publish a list of such
edits, but it presumably require
experimental validation in order to
reach its full impact, which uh I don't
yet have a collaborator in that space.
It's a really good idea though.
Uh so that was really interesting. Thank
you. You mostly talked about recruiting
activatory factors to enhance
expression. Have you tried to design
repressor elements?
>> That's a good question. Uh we have not
tried to design repressor elements yet
in part because it's challenging to know
whether or not you've designed a
repressor or you just haven't designed
an activator.
And so that would require careful
design where you have something which is
slightly active and you need to make
sure that you also haven't encountered
dropout just of the signal. Right? Uh
this is something I talked with Alex
about when we were trying to design the
experiments and ultimately we decided
that because of all these caveats when
it comes to repression that it may be
more challenging than an initial paper
would but it's super interesting.
Cool. Well, if there aren't any other
questions, I'll just mention that
because I'm a new faculty member, I'm
always looking for new grad students and
postocs. So, if anyone's interested or
knows someone who might be interested,
happy to chat.
[applause]