So, welcome again. This is MIT Startup
Exchange Demo Day. We're excited to have
you whether this is the first time
joining us or you've been with us before
and you're back.
So, you're going to uh soon hear from
eight exciting startups. They're all
members of Startup Exchange. But first,
I will give a brief introduction of our
program.
So MIT startup exchange was created to
support MIT connected startups as they
grow, expand and help solve some of the
world's greatest challenges. And we do
this by fostering partnerships and
collaborations between the startups and
industry primarily members of the
industrial leazison program or ILP which
are represented by so many of you
joining us today and also the MIT
innovation ecosystem and beyond.
The MIT um startups in our program have
a strong connection to the institute and
they may be based on MIT licensed
technology or founded by MIT faculty,
staff or alumni. They've also may be
vetted by some of our MIT peers
including the engine start nano or CEL
startup connect plus.
We have around a thousand startups in
the program and they usually join at
pilot stage or beyond and they can
represent any sector and any geography
and here you can see the breath of
solutions some of the trending
technologies of MIT startups and I've
noted in bold those that are represented
by the startups here today of course we
start with AI and ML big data and
analytics sustainability robotics and
sensing and healthcare and life science
among others
And so when it comes to value,
everything that we do at Startup
Exchange is about exposing the startups
and making connections with industry for
possible partnerships and
collaborations. And we do this in a
variety of ways
and um in a very customized approach. So
I hope that everyone is taking advantage
of these benefits. For example, we
launch calls for startups and we call
these opportunities and they're based on
a corporate's uh priorities and internal
challenges. And so as a startup, you can
apply on our website and if selected,
you can work with a an IP member um to
help them solve a problem that they may
be facing in the industry. We also host
one-on-one meetings, demo days like
today, conferences, other webinars and
um different events have a um lightning
talk for startups and and an exhibit and
we also host sometimes workshops and
trainings sometimes in conjunction with
our MIT peers.
And so what is demo day? It's a virtual
event that we host on a quarterly basis.
It's a forum that is pretty interactive
and dynamic. So I hope it will be that
today as well. And we help facilitate
corporate interactions with the industry
ready startups in our program. And the
goal is that this can happen sooner
rather than later. It's a short and
sweet format where you can meet a lot of
the startups and see if there's
potential to work together.
The format today will consist of eight
startups. They will present for uh four
minutes and we'll follow up with a
couple of minutes of Q&A and then we'll
go right into breakout room so that
there can be more engagement. So please
stay and join us for that. For the Q&A
part, I ask that you use the Q&A tab at
the bottom of your screen, indicate
which startup the question is for and
you can also upvote questions which is
always fun. And then always engage via
the chat with the startups so you can um
stay connected, exchange information,
learn more about the technology, etc.
And as always, reach out to us if you
need help connecting with the startups
anytime.
Um, so a couple of reminders. The
recordings of the startups are being um
recorded and um also there's going to be
a pop-up video um survey at the end of
the event on your screen if you could
please help us with feedback about the
event.