we have come to the end of our day and I
would just want to thank you Houston for
sharing it with us at MIT we wanted to
bring you some interesting ideas and
things that we're working on you heard
from Liz
Reynolds brought us some insights on
policy and things that she was doing at
the White House and things that she's
thinking about on Workforce and the
workforce of the future initiative that
she ran then Ben Armstrong actually
figuratively and literally he took over
her job when she went to the White House
and then on stage he talked a lot about
how transformative Technologies are
impacting the workforce and shared a
number of research studies that he's
doing on that uh then we heard from our
fantastic startups so you know uh we saw
oh is Shi gone oh I loved the uh the
flexible solar we heard about uh new
ways to do
learning uh and how AI is transforming
manufacturing and
safety uh and then we had our afternoon
which I think should be freshen up in
Your Mind Brian Anthony and car
Pearson uh and then this great panel so
what I'd love to hear from the audience
in just our last two minutes on a lot of
you took some good notes what what's a
key takeaway that you had my table my
guys here what did you what did you
learn what is stuck with you what are
you bringing back to the
office thoughts ideas these guys over
here you got one
go I think they importance of bridging
Academia with corporations and the fact
that uh you know like the MIT labs and
other universities where they have
funding and they have actually uh
students and uh and mentors and teachers
studying emerging Technologies and uh
embellishing other things in there that
you're Bridging the the Gap with the
actual real world and making sure
there's connections that you don't wait
till they graduate and then them go on
their own and look for jobs and then uh
connecting them with startups as well I
think I think that that Trifecta is uh
is crucial yeah and so you heard from
Olivier who said that
91% of MIT students are engaged in
research right they're not just sitting
in lecture Halls listening they're
actually rolling up their sleeves and
getting their hand dirty and that's why
MIT is actually ranked number one uh
on preparing students for the workforce
we're number one on that and I think
that's that's probably the one of the
stats I'm most proud of because I think
that as I call myself a pracademic
that's the most important thing that we
need to be doing anyone
else yeah the takeway that Brian had um
I also agree with him I hate that
digital twin and a on all these buzzword
have complicated matters because a lot
of this stuff has been around for a long
time and you're not going to convince
any people that your regular average
person to adopt this if they're scared
of it or if to give them something
they're familiar with is probably going
to be more helpful to them to adopt it
so totally agree with that and it was
validating to hear that today so
awesome right one more over here there
yeah I I do Innovation at scale and uh
one of the topics about the maturity
model for the um cyber security uh the
level five I was thinking okay wow I can
see how our Innovation management
process would be a perfect fit
to basically engage the entire Workforce
in coming up with uh or understanding
new ways that uh that cyber impacts are
happening so that was my kind of
takeaway good
horrific what I learned was like uh it's
not like the everybody has like a
specific problem right like I see like
some commonality like AC across the
board like know what people are having
the problem and you guys are researching
and bringing in like some kind of a
solutioning right like you know how to
solve this problem right across the
board that's really good for me like
know working for a startup and then like
know trying to do that stuff I'm
learning like know and and I also know
like who to reach out to right like know
if I need more right that's number one
number two regarding like AI right like
there is a lot of misconception like you
know in the industry learning like you
know how to communicate like those
misconception being a technologist I
know what they are but how to
communicate them to like you know inside
the company right that's very important
right um like our cyber security expert
talked about right like you know how to
make cyber security important like as
part of your like you know company life
right like the great point is like talk
about like you know I did that like
locally in my meetings but uh what she
said is like you know tell your like you
know leadership team to talk about
regular safety like know before the
meeting but also talk about cyber
security take like one incident and then
like talk about it as like a safety
incident right so like be authentic and
be attending yeah so that is very
important to communicate and evangelize
like no cyber security as like a uh what
do you call part of like know your
company not like something Fringe like
no sitting on with the IT department
right right good all right you guys
ready for beer thank you ready to go all
right so I I want to thank thank Quan
and Liz for doing an awesome job in
putting this
[Applause]
together and arena for really
architecting this thing thank you so
much everybody one thing I learned is
that we need to have these conversations
because train is moving at full speed
and we don't have Solutions so we need
to share each other's opin opinions and
and learnings to to save ourselves from
so many difficult issues that we're
running into thank you so much for
coming that was a great event thank you
to all of my colleagues to Kathleen to
Jim to Olivia Dave uh all the faculty
who came here all the startups thank you
to all of you and we're going to have
some beer yes I don't know what's
outside food and beer thank you