hi I'm Richard rabbat I want everybody
to take a second close your eyes no no
cheating close your eyes and think about
your last week and think about like all
the stuff that you decided to accomplish
versus what you actually
accomplished now open all your
eyes
and and think about like what you could
have accomplished if there was a
companion an AI companion that could
help you that could be your Chief of
Staff your admin and that could help you
achieve more for yourself I'm Richard
Rabat I'm a PhD from MIT I was most
recently VP off product at Twitter
rebuilt to whole data in ml
platform when you look at AI most of the
systems that you look at CLA or chat GPT
all these systems they've been trained
all a lot of data that's available
publicly so they can like give you a lot
of information we've seen like some
amazing startups that are like you know
helping you like retrieve information
but like a lot of these systems are
actually not aware of like how you work
how your how your company organizes
itself what workflows actually work
meanwhile everybody is under pressure to
adopt AI because there's an IM immediate
need for bringing more productivity into
the
workplace so Li is an agentic AI so
basically it's something it's an AI that
does things and what it does is it
builds a we we build an Enterprise
specific
llm that can help you with all tasks
including onboarding planning coaching
scheduling task assignments tracking
your
okrs and we also do it in a personalized
way so that the AI actually like speaks
the language that you want and they you
know Converses with you in a way that
like you know makes you feel comfortable
here's an example of uh the AI basically
like helping you with scheduling a t
that actually take end ends up taking a
lot of interruptions of of your time
each of these interruptions typically
takes you about 20 minutes to like you
it takes you about 20 minutes to G coup
from that interruption in this case
basically ly just takes over the
conversation negotiates on your behalf
available time and then sets it up on
your calendar and it's
all basically powered by a knowledge
craft that captures you your relations
with other people and like the work that
you're doing and the the next thing that
happens is when when you do this when
the other person like you know is you
know gets the calendar entry done they
actually have a conversation they've
actually created the relationship with
the AI so it has a viral viral uh impact
as well here's your daily planner
typically you go into a me you know you
go into your day and you're like oh my
goodness like I had like a bunch of
meetings that I should have moved around
but like you know it's too late and here
like you know by liy like you know
coming and like giving you like the
information ahead of time you can say
I'm just going to cancel you use like
natural language and like Li will just
do
it and
then at the end of the day all of us are
missing that capability that coaching
capability that we used to have in some
cases you're assigned an executive coach
you know you find your own mentors but
liy here like basically like looks at
like what you're spending time on and
like helps you reorganize against like
the goals and objectives that you said
in this case I said that I want to spend
more time on deep work and like Lighty
like gives me recommendations but by
looking at what my calendar looks like
and giving me uh insights into what is
what I should do so basically like
spending you know blocking more time to
do deep work canceling some meetings
that are too tactical
Etc and then finally like when you look
at like the uh you know every meeting
that you get get into but when you leave
when you leave that meeting some people
have taken notes they've they remember
some action items liy is much more
comprehensive it make sure that like all
the action items that were spoken about
are actually captured and then there's
follow follow through to the to you know
on on these action items and uh there's
typically a you know a bias when
somebody's taking notes because they
they just care about the things that are
that matter to them light is more
comprehensive it like picks on all the
pieces and make sure that they get
assigned and people like you know
progress on these tasks uh we're also
doing a production deployment with a
platform partner so it will be available
to hundreds of thousands of companies in
that case
uh we have a number of Pilots that we
that we've established and we would like
to work more with companies that want to
really improve how their teams work and
how they collaborate to be able to like
deliver more for themselves for their
teams and for their organization thank
you we're outside and we'll you know
we'll uh we'd love to connect with you
Mikey our CEO and myself will be there
thank you