Hello. Can people hear me?
Hello?
Getting some thumbs up.
Okay, why don't we get started? Um,
hello everybody. I'm Brenmore. Uh, if
you've been coming to lecture, you've
already met, uh, Eric and Zach. I'm the
third instructor for this course. Uh,
today we are going to switch gears a
little bit. So, we're going to move on
from uh, state machines and we're going
to start a new unit on uh, algorithmic
analysis. Uh so we'll be looking at that
until the end of uh until the end of
next week. Uh this lecture is going to
be about sums. Okay. So sums are quite
useful uh as I hinted out a moment ago.
They're good for algorithmic analysis.
You'll use uh you know everything in
this unit uh quite a bit if you take uh
61210 or any other algorithms course. Uh
they're also useful for things like you
know probability uh counting uh machine
learning everything's useful for machine
learning nowadays uh recurrences and you
know bunch of other things. Okay so
let's start with uh let's start with an
example. Okay has anybody here ever won
the lottery?
Hands. Nobody really Oh come on guys.
Okay. Uh well does anybody know how it
works?
So, if you if you win a million dollars
in the lottery, uh it it turns out you
don't actually get a check for a million
dollars in the mail. Or you do, but it
won't it won't cash. Uh it actually
comes in installments. Okay? So, imagine
you get, you know, $50,000 now and, you
know, $50,000 next year and so on for
the next 20 years. Okay? So, you know,
in total it ends up being a million
dollars in some sense, right?
Uh, but does it have the same value? Who
would who would prefer to have a million
dollars right now?
Lots of hands. Who would prefer to have
the uh the installments? 50,000 per year
for 20 years. Oh, a few hands. Uh, can I
get some reasons?
Oh, you don't waste it all at once.
Oh, that's an excellent reason.
Suppose maybe anybody else. A reason
either way. Yeah.
Sorry.
Yeah. Okay. So, that's that's an
argument for uh getting the million
dollars right now, right? Uh the the
$50,000 you get in 20 years, right? Like
if uh if you know a gallon of milk
costs, you know, four $4 today and like
$10 in in 20 years, like that $50,000
isn't going to go so far, right?
Uh so you know at least in terms of the
actual you know buying power of the
money you'd really prefer to have that
$1 million right now. Uh cuz you know
money now is more valuable than money in
the future. Inflation or relatedly you
can invest this money and it'll end up
being more worth more in in uh in 20
years. Okay.
So this is you know exactly how a loan
works right? you uh you know you get a
lump sum of money now and you pay it
back in installments uh and you know you
account for interest. Uh so this is
what's known as an annuity.
Okay.
Uh so for an annuity we're going to make
some you know fairly simplified
assumptions. We're going to assume a
fixed interest rate
uh let's call it P. Okay. So as an
example the uh Federal Reserve says that
uh you know interest rate right now is
about 5.33%.
So let's just take that as a working
example
or at least that's what it was at the
beginning of the week. I haven't checked
it today.
Uh, okay. And we're going to get m
dollars
every year
for
n years.
Okay.
So, in the example that we were just
looking at, uh, m is 50k, n is 20 years,
and you know, we've got this interest
rate p 5.33%.
Okay, so what does this mean about the
value of money over time?
Well, $1 now.
If we get this $1 now, you know, it's
going to be worth or it's, you know,
equivalent to getting 1 plus P dollar
one year from now.
Does that make sense to everybody?
Right? Like if I take my my $1 now and I
invest it, I'll end up with like $15
uh in a year. Okay? Or in two years
it'll be 1 plus p^ squ or you know in k
years it'll be 1 plus p to the k. Okay.
Uh conversely what if I get that dollar
in you know 10 years how much is that
worth in today's money?
Anybody
hunt?
No.
Are we still asleep too early in the
morning? Okay. Well, you know,
conversely, if uh uh if I get my dollar
in 10 years, it's going to be worth 1 /
1 plus b to the 10th. Okay. Does that
make sense to everybody?
Yes. No. Kind of. Thumbs up. Few thumbs
up. Okay. Good. Good. I'll I'll take it.
Okay.
So, basically what's going on is we're
getting M dollars now
M dollars in one year
M dollars in two years. Okay. Dot dot
dot up to n years.
And we'd like to kind of figure out what
the equivalent value is today. Okay. So
this M dollars now you know this is
worth M dollars today.
Okay. Uh this M dollars in one year is
going to be worth
uh oops m * 1 + pus
1. Okay. This ms in two years is going
to be m * 1 + p the minus 2 etc.
And the ms that we get in n years is
going to be m * 1 + p
to the minus n. I guess this is uh n
minus one, right? Yeah, we're starting
at zero years.
Okay,
does that make sense to everybody?
So, what is the total value the total
equivalent value in in today's money?
Okay,
we we'd like this in a closed form.
Okay, so right now we've kind of got
we're trying to sum all of this up,
right? But it's not a very nice
expression. Okay. We we'd like a closed
form. Something that you can, you know,
put into one of those oldfashioned
calculators if you've ever seen it. You
know, those things that you hold in your
hand and push the buttons on it. No. Oh,
yeah. Okay. There there are some old
souls in the audience. Okay. Uh but
yeah, we don't want any like uh ellipses
like this or, you know, sigma notation
or anything like that. We just want a
nice clean expression that you can put
into a calculator. So, how could we go
about computing it? Any ideas?
What if what if we were to replace this
uh 1 plus p with an x? Would would that
make it any any easier? So we've got uh
m + m x + m x^2
plus
mx to the n minus one.
Are people happier with this expression?
Getting getting some nods. Okay. Uh what
is it?
Anybody remember?
Yeah.
Yeah. It's a geometric series. Okay. So,
this is going to be m * uh
1 - x
uh oops
n over 1 - x.
Okay.
Uh, so you know, we knew this expression
already. How could we check it?
Or how how did you check it? I believe
you already have.
Yeah.
Uh,
oh,
thank you.
Uh
yeah.
Yeah, you're right. Thank you. So, um
how could you prove this? Or how how
would I have failed to prove it if I
tried to do it just now?
Yeah. Yeah.
Okay,
so this is what we call the uh the guess
and check method. Okay, so if we've got
a sum
like this and we know or we can
reasonably guess a nice closed form for
it, right? Then you know we can prove it
by induction, right? That's that's
fairly straightforward. The hard part is
figuring out what that uh closed form
should be. Okay.
Uh and you know in this case the
inductive step you know it reduces to
you know some fairly simple algebra as
you already saw I think in I think in
recitation. Is that right? Recoach.
Okay. Even if you don't remember Zach
does.
Okay.
So, uh, how might we discover this this
closed form if we didn't already know
it, though? Any ideas?
Yeah.
Yeah. Exactly.
Okay. So this is what we call the
perturbation method.
So the answer was you know if we
multiply this entire thing by x and uh
you know subtract it then things will
cancel. Okay. Uh so this is uh one
example of what we call the perturbation
method. Um this is something that uh
does anybody know the story of um Gaus
in the kindergarten or first grade when
uh he was given a massive sum to
evaluate by his teacher and uh you know
3 seconds he uh gave the teacher his
answer and the teacher's like what the
hell no go back to your seat. Okay.
Yeah. So perturbation method in action.
So Gaus was asked to evaluate you know 1
+ 2 plus
I think the story was 100 not actually
sure and G observed that if you you know
take this series and perturb it a little
bit so in this case flip it around
and then add them together you end up
with something very nice Okay.
Okay.
So he's got you know two copies of this
sum
right? So 2s is equal to this thing
which means that s should be equal to
that.
Okay so fairly straightforward. We can
do the same thing with this geometric
series here.
[Applause]
So for simplicity, I'm going to drop the
m. So if instead we have s = 1 + x + x^2
+ x nus1
and uh your your colleague said that we
should multiply this by x. So xs equals
I'm going to shift everything over so
it's a little bit easier to see what's
going on.
Okay.
And now this time instead of adding them
we're going to want to subtract.
This one doesn't have anything uh to
subtract.
Uh, and now here we've got, you know,
plus x - x plus x^2 - x^2. So everything
is going to cancel
until we get to the end. And here we've
got - x n.
Okay, so now we've got s - x s is equal
to 1 - x to the n, which means that s is
1 - x n over 1 - x.
Okay,
so if we, you know, didn't know the the
formula for a geometric series off the
top of our heads, which, you know, I
clearly didn't, we could derive it like
this and then we can check it by
induction. Okay, does that make sense to
everybody?
So if we go back to our annuity example,
we had uh so m was
50k, n is 20 years.
uh P was
uh 0533
which means that our X here was uh was
it 1 over 1 - P
1 over one uh 1 + P.
Okay. So if we plug this in, it turns
out that uh the value of our annuity is
actually about
638,000.
Okay,
so
you know, it's it's not just less than
the $1 million that we were promised.
It's like substantially less, right?
Okay.
And uh
you know what what if we uh what if we
took an even more extreme example like
suppose instead of uh 50,000 per year
for 20 years we got $1 per year for a
million years. You know for simplicity
let's just say it's forever. Okay. So
suppose we got $1 forever like every
year forever. How much is that worth?
Half a million.
100,000. Yeah.
Yeah, it's about 20 bucks. Uh so this uh
this x to the n just goes to zero. Turns
out that if we have uh m = 1, n is
infinity. Same p as we had before,
it's about 20. Okay. So, you know, it
might be a little bit counterintuitive
that uh you know, getting money like
forever, it's still has finite value,
right? Um but
yeah, I don't know. Maybe if you think
about it, it it uh it kind of makes
sense, right? Um like that that money
that you're getting like n years from
now, like you know, who cares? Like
you're you're not even going to be alive
to use it, right? So maybe it maybe it
also kind of makes sense that it uh that
it doesn't it's not worth very much.
Uh and you know in the real world there
are actually you know perpetual
annuities like this. They they do exist.
Um I believe there is a surviving one uh
issued by a Dutch water company in the
17th century. Uh I think they issued
five that are still around today. And
one was acquired by Yale in uh let's see
maybe 30 odd years ago I think uh for
$24,000 and it gets them about $12
annually. So uh only worth it for the uh
historical value. The uh the money is is
a complete wash.
Okay.
So, are people reasonably happy with the
uh perturbation method?
Yeah, some thumbs up.
Okay, so let's move on to a slightly
different method for evaluating, you
know, other sums.
Uh
so this is what's called the MSAT
method.
I'm spelling this correctly. I hope so.
uh or if you don't like German I think
it is uh you could also just call it the
educated guess method. Okay.
So suppose we have the following sum
sum from k = 1
to n of k^ squ.
Okay.
So first does does anybody already know
the answer? What what does this sum
evaluate to?
Oh nobody. Okay, in that case uh next
question is open to everyone. Uh does
anybody have any idea like what vaguely
the solution might look like?
Like yeah.
Yeah, it should it should be some sort
of cubic, right? Like we're we're
summing up a bunch of squares. Well, n
squares. Um, a bunch of them are, you
know, about n^2. And so we should get
something that's about n cubed. Okay. So
guess
uh s is you know approximately
n cubed. Okay. Now it won't do us too
much good to uh you know put that into
our guess and check method. Yeah.
Uh intuition basically. Um
but uh so what one way you could think
about it is uh so half of these terms
are going to be larger than n /2
right? So that's 1/4 of n^2. Uh you've
got n /2 of those. So you should have
something that's at least 1/8 of n
cubed. Does that make sense?
Uh and then for an upper bound, right,
you've got n terms which are all at most
n^2. And so it's going to be, you know,
something between 1/8 n cubed and n
cubed itself.
Does that kind of make sense?
or hinting at something else that we'll
do uh a little bit later. Uh if you
squint really hard, a sum kind of looks
like an integral.
So if you integrate that, you're going
to get something that looks like nubed.
Okay. Uh another question.
Yeah. Uh we could do that if you like.
So we've got, you know, 1 + uh 2^ 2 + 3^
2 +
uh n / 2
squared
plus all the way up to n^2,
right? So these terms, you know, plus or
minus one term if it's, you know, even
or odd. So these are all greater than or
equal to uh
n /2 squared and we've got n over2 of
them or n /2 + 1 or whatever. Okay, so
the sum is going to be at least
n /2
* n /2
is 1/8 n cubed. Okay.
Yeah. Question.
Yeah.
[Music]
Ah, okay. So, uh, we're getting a a more
refined guess. Um, though actually I
would argue that n cubed is already good
enough uh for for what we're doing
anyway. Um,
and here's why. So, we we as as we said
like we it's not very precise, right?
like we don't know uh like you said the
leading coefficient should probably be a
third. Um but we're just going to start
from you know guessing that it's a cubic
of some sort. Okay, we don't know
anything about the coefficients
but you know it seems like a reasonable
guess.
Okay,
so we're going to say that s is equal to
a * n cubed + b n^ 2 + cn
plus d.
Okay, we're just going to take that on
faith, assume it, and see where it leads
us.
Okay,
so if we assume that, what can we
deduce?
Any ideas?
How might we go about figuring out what
A, B, C, and D should be?
Well, what if we look at you know small
n?
So if we have say n equals 0,
what happens if we put in n equals 0?
Exactly.
Okay. So then we have uh a * 0 cubed + b
* 0 2 + c * 0 + d = what?
What is the value of our sum at zero?
Zero. Yeah, we've just got the empty
sum.
Okay.
What else can we do?
Yeah, n equals 1. That seems like
another decent choice.
And so this time we'll end up with a + b
+ c + d equals what?
What's the value of our sum there?
1.
And if we continue like this,
we get uh 8 a + 4 b + 2 c + d = 5. So 1
+ 4. Uh question.
Uh no, we're trying to figure those out.
So we're just taking it on faith that S
has this form. Okay.
Mhm. So we already know that because S
was defined as the sum of squares. Okay.
So if we sum up all of the squares up to
n equals 1, we get one. If we sum them
up to n equals 2, we get five. etc.
Okay,
is this enough?
Yeah, we need one more. So, let's put in
n equals 3.
Here we've got 27 a + 9 b + 3 c + d
= uh 14.
Can I arithmetic at least?
I think I can arithmetic. 1 plus 4 + 9.
That sounds like 14.
Okay,
so now we've got a system of uh four
equations and four variables. So we
should be able to solve it. Okay.
Um has anybody figured out what the
solution is yet?
Well, d equals 0. That's an easy one. Uh
I think it turns out to be a =3
b = 12 c = 16. Is that right?
And uh yeah, d equ= 0 because we've got
a bunch of zeros here.
Okay.
So are we done?
Have we found our solution?
Yeah.
Yeah. So, we we've maybe found our
solution, but you know, we we don't
know. We just pulled this out of a hat
and assumed it. Okay. So, we should
actually prove that this is correct. So
now we're going to take uh you know s=
1/3 n cubed + uh 12 n^2 + 16 n and use
that as our guess and go back to the
guess and check method and prove this by
induction. Okay. And uh
we're actually going to want strong
induction. These are our base cases.
We've already proven that essentially
like that's what we use to derive ABC
and D. Okay? And our inductive step is
just going to be a bunch of algebra. So
I'm I'm not going to go into that right
now, but uh yeah, if you're interested,
feel free to prove it.
Okay.
Uh yeah, and uh if it works, we'll, you
know, we'll have a proof that our uh
that our formula was correct. And if it
doesn't, you know, we go back to the
drawing board. we uh we know that this
form was wrong and so maybe we try and
figure out you know a different form
that that our answer might take. Okay.
Uh does that make sense? Are people
happy with that?
Any questions? Maybe I should phrase it
the other way.
What's your name?
Oh, I'm Bmore.
Uh, like the Pennsylvania College. Same
word spelled differently.
Uh, I saw another hand over here. Was
that was that a question or
Yeah. So that that's if you if you solve
this system of equations uh like that's
that's what comes out like you you could
do Gaussian elimination or you know
invert the matrix or whatever.
on your notes.
Oh, no. I'm I'm not that good.
Oh, I mean, no, I totally don't have it
on my notes. Um,
yeah. Yeah. Question.
Yeah. Uh so as as we were discussing you
know before we we dove into it right uh
we think that it's probably going to
look something like n cubed um we don't
know exactly you know how close it is to
that but it's kind of reasonable to
assume that it's a polinomial like a
cubic polinomial
um so you know maybe we could have
started with uh you know something like
this instead head
like maybe it's some constant time n
cubed plus you know quadratic term and
then you know the onsance method would
have failed we would have uh uh we would
have ended up with you know suspicious
looking guess we would have tried to
prove it by induction and it wouldn't
have worked
um but yeah as it turns out uh
this is a reasonable
Yeah.
How do we know that means it's wrong?
What if we just didn't figure out the
right way?
Ah, so the the question is if we have a
bad guess and we can't prove it by
induction, how do we know that the guess
is actually wrong and not that uh you
know we're doing something suspicious
with the proof? Uh so that's a good
question. Um,
so maybe I should digress here a little
bit. Uh, if you're trying to, you know,
figure out a proof or a disproof
disproof for a statement that you're not
quite sure whether it's true or not, uh,
often the thing that you'll want to do
is attempt to prove it, see where your
proof seems to be breaking, like if you
if you find a block, like something that
you can't figure out, and then try and
use that to to generate disproof.
uh and then you know you can iterate on
that and uh you know if your if your
disproof gets stuck somewhere like maybe
you try and use that uh that block to
try and come up with a different proof.
Okay. Um and you know eventually
hopefully you'll be able to come up with
one or the other. Uh so in this case um
there's a a you know fairly uh clear uh
path towards a disproof you know put in
more numbers right so
we could try you know n= 4
right
uh then we'd have 64 a + 16 b + 4 c + D
should be equal to what is it? 30.
Okay, so that's a decent sanity check,
right? Like if that doesn't work, then
you know we know that we've uh we've
screwed something up. Okay, does that
make sense to everybody? Yeah. Question.
Uh so that's because we have uh four
variables here. We've got a b c and d.
So we needed four uh equations like four
constraints.
Yeah. Like we could equally well have
chosen like n= 1, n= 2, n= 5 and n= 100.
Uh it would have given us the correct
answer. It just would have taken more uh
complicated computation.
Yeah.
Uh
oh. Here you mean?
Oh, okay. So the the the squared term is
right because you know each of these
terms here is at least n over2 squ. Uh
the last term is because there are n
over2 of them and we're trying to
evaluate the sum.
So we're summing up n over2 things that
are all at least n over2.
They're at least zero. We don't care.
Yeah.
Okay. Are people reasonably happy with
this?
Yeah. Okay. So, let's move on to a third
technique.
Okay, so sometimes we're going to end up
with uh you know sums of sums, right? Uh
nested summations which we call double
sums. So for instance, what if we had
the following? So i = 1 to n of the sum
from j = 1
to i of j.
Okay.
So now you know before we had uh the
thing inside our sum
was this nice simple expression k^ squ
right now our sum and is itself a
summation.
Okay what can we do about that? How
would we evaluate things like this?
Mhm.
Yeah. So the answer was to evaluate the
inner sum first right figure out a
closed form as a function of I right and
then we can evaluate the outer sum okay
so in this case what do we end up with
what happens when we evaluate this inner
sum
I claim that this is something that we
already know how to do something that
we've seen for
yeah exactly
so this is the sum from i = 1 to n of i
* i + 1 all divided by 2
okay
now how could we evaluate this sum this
this expression is a little bit more
complicated than the ones that we had
before Right.
Is there a way that we can simplify it?
Yeah.
Mhm.
Yeah. So, let's uh distribute this i and
then break the sum up. Okay. So,
uh if we distribute this, we end up with
i^ 2 + i
/ 2. Okay.
And now we've got a sum of you know a
sum uh so we can split it into two
different summations
i = 1 to n
i^2 plus
sum of i.
Okay,
so I've taken each of these terms and
split it into its own sum and also
pulled this factor of 1/2 out in front.
Okay,
so this is now something that we know
how to evaluate. We just evaluated it.
Uh this is also something we know how to
evaluate like also we just evaluated it.
Uh
so this comes out to
the answer that we had there. So
16 n cubed
+
1/4 n^2
+ 112n
uh plus
14 * n * n + 1. Okay.
Does that make sense to everybody?
Suppose instead
we had something similar but slightly
different.
So sum from i + 1 to n
sum from j = i to n of j.
Oops.
Okay. So our inner sum now instead of
going from uh one to i, it's going from
i to n.
Okay.
Now, we could evaluate this in the same
way as as we just did,
but it turns out that there's a slightly
easier way. Okay, we can exchange the
order of summation.
Okay. And what I mean by that is that we
want the outer sum to be in terms of J
and the inner sum to be in terms of I.
Okay.
So
what are the possible values of J?
So uh yes.
Yeah.
Yeah. Oh.
Okay, so if I equals 1 here, J equals I,
J equals 1. Okay, so that's the smallest
value of J.
And you know, J can clearly go up to N.
Okay.
What are the bounds of summation on our
inner sum?
How would we compute this?
What constraints do we have on i and J
originally?
And we know that 1 is less than or equal
to i less than or equal to n. i less
than or equal to j less than or equal to
n.
Okay.
So we could you know phrase this as 1
less than or equal to i less than or
equal to j less than or equal to n.
Okay. And now we've got bounds on i in
terms of j.
Does that make sense to everybody?
So, we still want the sum over the same
set of pairs I and J. We're just
expressing it differently.
And now our sumand is the same.
Okay. Does it does it make sense to
everybody how we got this?
Yeah.
Uh so this right
just came from the bounds on our inner
sum.
Okay. We're saying that J should range
from I up to N.
Okay.
And so then we just, you know, stick
this pair of inequalities in here.
Okay. Does that make sense to everybody?
You reasonably happy with this?
Okay.
So now we've exchanged the order of
summation.
We've got uh J for our outer sum, I for
inner sum,
and now we've got a much simpler sum
here that we can easily evaluate. Okay.
What is our inner sum?
Mhm.
Yeah.
Okay.
The sumand has no dependence on the uh
index of summation.
Right. So we've just got J terms. All of
them are J. So it's J squ.
Okay.
And now this is just the sum that we had
before.
Does that make sense to everybody?
Yeah.
Mhm.
Uh this one
here.
Uh so that's that's just uh an
expression that you've already seen,
right? We we've already seen how to
evaluate the sum from J= 1 to I of of J.
Uh so that's just you know plugging in
that closed formula uh for that inner
sum.
Okay. Are people reasonably happy with
this?
Yeah.
Uh did we
uh
oh yeah here is
I mean here it's the you know particular
example where where n equals 100 but
yeah
okay so why don't we move on to The uh
last topic for today.
[Applause]
So what happens
if we have the following sum?
Any
idea how we might come up with a closed
form for this?
Does anybody already know a closed form?
Nobody really.
That's good because it's an open
problem. Um,
well, I suppose that doesn't make it
good. If you have a closed form, you
could write a paper about it. That would
be pretty exciting.
Uh okay. So it turns out that you know
there isn't any nice close form for this
as far as we know. Uh so does that mean
we should just you know hands in the air
give up?
Getting some getting some nods. Yeah. I
mean I suppose that's a that's a
question of philosophy. Um but you know
we can still say something about it
right? like maybe we don't need to know
exactly what this sum is. Uh but you
know, as long as we figure out something
that's close enough, maybe we're still
happy. Okay, so maybe we want to
approximate it.
Okay.
So, can anybody give me
a guess as to an approximation for this
sum?
Mhm.
So the answer was, you know, again, if
we squint really hard and pretend that
this is an integral, maybe s is
approximately equal to the integral of
rootx
dx uh say from 1 to n, which is going to
be
about
2/3 uh n to the is it three halves? Is
that about right?
I swear I've done calculus before. Um,
it's been a while. Uh, okay.
So, the question then becomes,
how close is that approximation?
Do we think we're, you know, within a
factor of two? Do you think we're off
by, you know, n by root n off by one?
Maybe
it's not entirely clear. Okay.
So,
in order to figure this out, we're going
to use what we call the integral method.
So,
give me a moment to draw this.
And you know,
Redux looks a little bit like that if
you squint really hard.
Okay.
Um
so suppose we have a weekly increasing
function of x.
So rootx is indeed weakly increasing. So
that that'll work.
Um
now recall remon sums from uh from
integral calculus. Okay.
No no post-traumatic stress. Are we are
we okay? Okay. Uh so how could we how
could we approximate
uh the integral of f ofx
yeah
yeah so if we've got one 2 3 4 dot dot
dot
we can draw a bunch of rectangles like
this.
Okay. And this step function here.
Actually, maybe I should get a different
color.
Okay,
for completeness maybe I should do that.
so this this step function here that
I've drawn is uh f of the floor of x,
right? f is weekly increasing.
So that means
you know floor of x is an under
approximation for x. So f of floor of x
is an under approximation
for f ofx.
Okay.
Now what happens if we integrate the
step function?
What is the integral
from 1 to n
of f of floor of x? Yeah,
sorry.
uh almost.
So in in this case it actually does it
turn out to be s
uh
yeah exactly we're we're missing a term
here.
Okay,
so we can break this into n minus one
integrals,
right? We've got a an interval of width
n minus one.
Uh this is constant on each of those uh
width one uh sub intervals, right? So we
can break it break it apart into a whole
bunch of rectangles.
So this is going to be the sum from i =
1 to n minus one
of
f of i.
Does that make sense to everybody?
So we've got intervals of width one. Uh
our function is constant on each of
those intervals, right? And it's equal
to, you know, the left hand uh the left
hand side of that interval.
Okay, does that make sense to everybody?
And this is just going to be s minus
uh f of n.
Okay.
Yeah.
Sorry.
Uh so the question is why are we using n
minus one as the bound here? Okay, so
that's because the width of this
interval is n minus one. We're splitting
into n minus one intervals of width one.
Okay, so for instance, if we uh you know
went up to say n= 5.
Okay.
So if we were trying to sum f of one, f
of two, f of three, f of four, f of
five, uh we would then want to compare
to this integral here.
So the integral from 1 to 5, right? And
this gives us four rectangles,
right? We've got the interval from 1 to
2, from 2 to 3, 3 to 4, 4 to 5.
Okay. And the uh the interval say from 2
to three has width 1 and height f of
two.
Okay. So you know maybe we could phrase
this as you know 1 * f of i. Does that
make sense?
Okay.
So now we've you know we've got uh
so we've got an under approximation for
our integral now. So uh I haven't
actually written the the integral.
So let's let
I equal the integral from 1 to n
fx dx. Okay,
so
we said that this function here under
approximates f, right? So this integral
under approximates i.
So that tells us that i
is greater than or equal to s minus
f of n.
Okay.
Now, equivalently, we could phrase this
as a bound on S in terms of I, right?
Because S was what we originally wanted
to figure out. Okay? So, instead, we
could write this as S is less than or
equal to I plus
F of N. Does that make sense?
Okay.
Now
what if instead
we over approximated?
Okay,
so now we've got f of the ceiling of x.
Sorry.
So the new step function that I've just
drawn in green is f of ceiling of x
which is an over approximation for f
ofx.
Okay. So if we integrate it, the
integral from 1 to n
of f
of ceiling of x
dx
should be greater than or equal to i.
Okay.
Now doing exactly the same thing as we
had before.
What is this integral?
Yeah.
So sum from i = 2 to n of f of i
say times 1,
right?
And this is just sus f of one.
Okay.
So s minus f of one is at least i.
Once again we can rephrase this as a
bound on i or sorry a bound on s in
terms of i.
So I uh sorry S
is greater than or equal to
I + F of 1.
Okay, does that make sense to everybody?
So putting these together now
we have
I + f of 1
less than or equal to s less than or
equal to i + f of n.
Okay.
So this is what we call the integral
bound for increasing functions.
Are people reasonably happy with this?
Okay. So if we go back to our original
question, you know, where f ofx equals
rootx, right? What are the bounds we
get?
What is i first?
wasn't quite what I wrote down before.
Yeah,
it is from 1 to n. Remember what I wrote
originally was uh 2/3 n^ 3 which is I
believe the integral from 0 to n.
So
what we actually have here is
I = the integral from 1 to n of x^ 12 dx
which is
equal to 2/3
x^ 3s evaluated
at one and n which is going to be 2/3 *
n^ 3
- 1.
Okay, so almost what we had before.
So our lower bound then is this value
plus f of one, right? f of one is just
root one. it's one
and our upper bound is I plus roo
n. Okay,
so it turns out that 2/3 n^ 3 halves is
a pretty good approximation,
right? It's uh you know it's going to be
a little bit larger than that but not
much, right? we're going to be within an
additive root n.
Okay. And you know given that our
approximation is you know a cube of that
that's actually pretty good.
Okay. Does that make sense to everybody?
Are we reasonably happy with that?
Okay.
What if instead we had you know s equals
sum from i = 1 to n of say 1 / i.
Can we apply our integral bound to this?
It thinks yes.
Who thinks no?
Okay. Can anybody explain why in either
direction?
Yeah.
Uh okay. So the answer was uh you know
after one uh it's going to converge.
Uh I would dispute that.
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay. Fair enough.
So even if we could apply the integral
bound, it may not get us very far.
Uh I think there's a bigger problem
here. Yeah,
that's right. So
remember that our assumption, right, was
that f should be weekly increasing.
One over i is not or 1 /x is not. Yeah.
Yeah.
Okay.
So the observation here is that if we
take f ofx
= 1 /x this is weekly decreasing.
So we can do something similar.
Okay, what exactly are we going to do?
Well, let's take g of x
to be equal to f of n + 1 - x.
Okay.
Now, what do we know about g?
So basically what we've done here,
right, we are essentially negating the
argument. So we're kind of flipping it
horizontally,
right? We started with a weekly
decreasing function.
So when we flip it like this, we're
going to end up with a weekly increasing
function.
Okay. Yeah.
Ah. Uh, so are you worried about the n
plus one as opposed to the n?
Yeah.
Okay. So basically we are mapping uh one
to n and vice versa
and then everything in between should
just you know interpolate linearly.
Okay. So if we put you know one into
here we end up with f of n. If we put n
into here we end up with f of one. Does
that make sense? So the question is why
do we have the uh n plus one there
instead of just an n or a minus x or
something like that?
which you know kind of gets into the the
next question. What is S in terms of G?
So maybe it would be better to write it
using ellipses instead of sigma
notation.
So we defined it as f of 1 plus f of 2
plus dot dot dot plus f of n.
Okay.
Now how can we rewrite this in terms of
g?
Yeah.
Okay, so this is actually equal to the
sum of G of I same balance.
Okay.
So now what can we do?
Mhm.
Yeah, G satisfies all of the uh
requirements that we needed for our
integral bound. Okay, so we can apply
the integral bound now to G instead of
to our original F.
Okay.
So now
uh we know that
I + g of 1
less than or equal to s less than or
equal to i + g of n.
Okay.
So the integral is exactly the same,
right? We are, you know, we've just
flipped it, right? But the area under it
is is going to be the same.
And what is this g of one? Well, this g
of one is just f of n.
g of n is just f of one.
Okay,
so this is the integral bound for weekly
decreasing.
F.
Okay. Does that make sense to everybody?
Yeah.
Uh,
strictly speaking,
uh,
Um
so you end up with a uh a slightly
different problem if you uh if you just
negate it. Um
which is
well I'll hint at it in a moment. Okay.
Uh what happens if you take limits as n
goes to infinity?
Pardon?
Yeah. So you kind of have to um like you
you can do that but you you'd have to
kind of adjust for it and it doesn't
work quite as nicely with the with
limits. Uh so the answer is strictly
speaking yes. You could negate it if you
want to.
uh but uh you know flipping it and you
know
I personally find it easier to think
about but
yeah
so that that that was the idea to to
negate f instead of x.
Okay.
But uh yeah, segue into the uh the last
thing. We've got a couple of minutes or
eight minutes. Oh, nice. Um
so what about s=
sum from i = 1 to infinity of let's say
because as somebody pointed out we do
not want to be working with logs.
So let's say 1 over i^2.
Okay.
So how could we evaluate this infinite
sum?
Well, we can basically do what we were
just doing, right?
So,
well, does does anybody remember how we
actually define what an infinite sum is?
It's just going to be a limit of partial
sums.
Okay.
Now all of these
we know how to evaluate.
Okay.
So each of these if we take you know i
subn to be equal to the integral from 1
to n of 1 i^2 oh sorry 1x^2
dx
okay what is this integral
Anybody
want to evaluate that? No. We don't like
calculus.
Me too. That's why I'm asking for help.
Yeah.
Yeah. 1 - 1 / n. Okay.
Why are you laughing at me? That's so
rude. Ah, come on guys. Okay, so we know
what these partial sums are or you know
we have approximations for these partial
sums. Okay, so the partial sum s subn is
going to be bounded on one side by
uh okay
oops why don't I write it like this?
So I subn plus f of n less than or equal
to s subn less than or equal to i subn
plus f of 1.
Okay.
Now what happens when we take limits?
So weak inequalities are preserved by
limits. Right? So the limit of
I subn plus f of n
is going to be less than or equal to s
less than or equal to limit
of i subn plus f of 1.
Okay.
Now, what does the limit do?
Well, we can separate these. What's the
limit of I of subn?
Yep.
Mhm.
uh 1 - 1 / infinity basically, right? So
as n goes to infinity, this 1 / n term
disappears.
Okay, so
this part is just going to be one.
What's the limit of f of n?
Yeah,
also infinity. Uh
also
yeah zero
less than or equal to s less than or
equal to we just established that this
is one.
What's f of one?
One.
Okay.
So we have an approximation.
Is it a good one?
I'm seeing some people like, "Yeah, good
enough. Let's just go home." Some people
like, "What the hell? We're off by a
factor of two." Uh, yeah, it's between
one and two. Like,
not so great. Any ideas how we could
make it better?
How could we make our bones more
precise?
Maybe if we go back to the picture,
it'll be a little bit uh easier to see.
Okay.
So
this lack of precision is coming from
the fact that like you know we're kind
of looking at the difference between
these two step functions, right? So the
farther apart they are the the worse our
our approximation is going to be. Okay.
So if we kind of just forget about the
first few terms, compute those exactly,
and then just approximate the rest,
we're going to end up with a more
precise bound.
Okay?
So if instead we say you know s =
uh 1 + 14 + 1 9th
plus the sum from i = 1 to infinity
of
1 /
i + 3^ 2.
Sorry, it's a bit crowded. Okay.
Now, what happens if we approximate this
sum?
How close are we going to get?
Well, our error term remember
was just
the first term in our series.
Okay, we are going to be between
the integral and the integral plus the
first term.
Okay, here the first term is much
smaller.
Okay, so this time we've got uh what is
it? 1 16.
So instead of being, you know, between i
and i + 1, we're now between i and i + 1
over 16 for a different eye.
Same I, no, different eye.
Yeah.
Okay. Does that make sense to everybody?
So if you want a better approximation,
just, you know, strip some terms off the
front and approximate
the tail of the sum instead of the
entire thing.
So that's all we have time for today. Uh
let's see. I'm not sure who will see you
next week. Um somebody will see you next
week. Zach will see you next week. Uh
feel free to come up if you have any
questions. Yeah. started. Uh your role