this is a short video following up on
the unlocking of pitches where we will
unlock duration and note objects in
music 21 go ahead and start up your
Jupiter notebook and let's get
programming start with durations um so
go ahead and from music 21 import
duration and um that thing we've just
imported duration is it um put a thumbs
up if it's an object put a thumbs down
if you think it's a
module okay so in this case it is a
module there if you didn't get it right
no worries because there's no way you
can actually tell just from that except
for by convention python by convention
we write our modules in lowercase we can
see that it's a module by um taking it
type Yay good i'' be terrible if I
didn't within um the module there is uh
usually an object with the same name as
it I hit Tab and I get oh there is a
duration object so we'll create one
assign it to D and I'm going to create a
duration of
3.0 what I want you to do is open up the
chat and don't um don't yet hit iner on
it but if you could put what you think
3.0 might
represent yep so we have a lot of um a
lot of Beats going on um some I like
qualification with some standard of how
long a beat is um and we also have
dotted half and things like that nobody
seems to like our favorite uh thing
milliseconds maybe if I had had
purposely made my thing um
3,000 than than people would have
thought that um you know but it is a
float it could be seconds or something
uh in this case we'll figure it out um
well okay that doesn't tell us much of
anything and um what we can do is we can
get the full name of this and see it is
a dotted half so um it could be beat
still I'll just go ahead and say in
music 21 I made the decision to have um
the number represent the number of
quarter notes uh I may over time I have
sometimes regretted that decision um but
it had to be something and one of the
reasons I decided not to go with half uh
with Beats is that um the length the
representation of a note in terms of
Beats is dependent on something external
and that is the ti signature right so 22
has a different number of Beats from 68
has a different number uh has a
different type of beat from 68 which has
a different type of beat from 44 so
that's um that's one of the reasons uh
going with this so every um every
duration object has a full name it also
has a
type half and uh has a dots it's great
um it also a something called quarter
length which in this case um is yeah the
number of quarters and that's not so bad
but maybe uh I mean that's something you
already knew how to do but maybe we do
we can create a duration in a different
way we'll say type equals whole and dots
equals 4 and suddenly the quarter
length of this is a little bit harder to
compute anybody on off the top of their
head right you're all too shy to say
7.75 okay good well I don't I don't know
that number okay so here are some of the
things that that we can um that we can
do can we um can we create a a triplet
let's try
that one onethird of a note so what kind
of a triplet is that somebody shout it
out an e triplet let's let's see type
yay triplet so we can create trip blits
um notice we'll go back to D here um
notice that some durations are expressed
in floats some are expressed in rational
fractions and that tells you whether or
not um you're going to safely be able to
add them up and get an exact number uh
anything that's a multiple of a power of
two in binary will be exactly
representable anything that isn't will
be here so great so trip type is
eth so it doesn't tell me anything about
it its dots I hope are zero there's no
dots there great um so there is
something
called tuplets which a tuplet is a type
of U like a quadruplet a quintuplet
triplet is the one we most know great
what I want you to do is take a second
and put in the chat what kind of object
was just returned from um
tuplets okay have um a couple different
uh different answers but most people say
it's a tuple right a tle of tuplets
which you Tred not to say that she many
times fast and you know it's a tupple um
because it has this comma at the end so
um it's an immutable a list of it and
that means there you can have more than
one tolet so you might have a triplet
within a triplet and so on so those are
some things we can do um
the top so we can get at that darn tolet
object I'm just trying to pull it out
pull it out uh oh right it's not a
graphical environment so um we'll get
the first one we'll call it
t and we'll see that the tuplet itself
is also a complex object we can dir it
and we can see it has certain things
like tuplet multiplier which I happen to
know is a meth
and so we can see that when you throw
this tuplet onto a note that note
becomes 2/3 of its previous here are
just some of the things you can do you
will learn this in um in music in um the
music 21 users guide two and three which
we'll get through in a bit um some of
the things you might see are
um duration
that obviously four is a whole people
who like these things eight is a dotted
a double whole note also called a brieve
um which means short because there used
to be longer notes and they're still
somewhere and that's the longest
possible note U which no longer exists
except that somebody used a double the
longest possible note but then at a
certain point you can't do it similarly
on the small side you can go
um and let's get the type of
that notice that the type of an eighth
note is e i g h t the type of a 16th
note um I misspelled 16th too many times
so I decided U We Go From Here uh I
don't think I know my fractions below
that so we'll just keep going like that
you can go down pretty far let's skip a
bit oops or
16 and you can go down to 14 20 1 24
notes theoretically notes go on forever
but
um music 21 at a certain point says yeah
this isn't representation music great I
want to do um one more little exercise
and this is a this is a trick question
so just put um put your head what you
think I'm going to sing something to you
and you tell me how many notes I sang
yes I sang a eighth note tied to a 32nd
note was slightly longer than half of a
beat in my head so how do we deal with
things like that well let's make it a
whole note tied to a quarter note let's
say the duration was fast so I'll call
that an odd uh thing and by the way
thank you one thank everybody for saying
one and not saying seven because of you
warbles too much but um let's take that
uh eighth note tied to a 30 second note
uh what is that
125 so we can see that you can create
things and this says it's complex it is
a duration that has multiple what I call
components um which that there's an
eighth and um an eighth and the 32nd
that are put together and so what we
mean by the length of a note will depend
on where a note splits will depend on
the context that we want to use it so if
we're thinking about um hey he just
saying that note in a sound context in a
recording context obviously that's one
note there's there's no other way around
it but if we're thinking about it in a
notation context and you're writing
something that has to draw notes on a
page you're going to want to put say
that well that's actually two notes
because there's no way to represent the
duration that we heard with just one
note so some of the things we're going
to be working on this class is how do we
move from different represent one
representation to another so that um
we're always using the
representation that is most appropriate
for the situation and so we'll spend a
lot of time in this class um working on
translations among
representations okay remember you can
always um take the directory of um of a
music 21 or any python object to get
some more things about it um but you can
also uh in Jupiter you can put in
question mark afterwards and get some
docs or look at the Docks so now you
have unlocked pitches and you have
unlocked
durations let's um move on to the last
thing that we want that we're going to
unlock today and that is those are
notes
so there are a million ways we could
have called something a note um we could
say um you know a note is the same thing
as a pitch some people say that whatever
but here's how I have chosen um and with
my uh advisors and stuff how to
represent a note a note takes in sort of
a string just like a pitch just like we
saw the pitch video um it's called a
note it doesn't print the octave for
some reason but and it has a name just
like uh just like a pitch does but it
also all those things are in a stored
pitch object so a note has a pitch
object and so you could change that and.
pitch. octave equals 4
see all that um but a note also has a
duration and so in this case the default
all notes start off with the duration of
one quarter note I don't know why I'm
privileging quarter notes but somehow I
have um we can change the quarter length
of that
3.5 and
then well has a full name so we can look
at this be flat in octave 4 Double
dotted half note okay so that's all
there um hopefully this is working one
cool thing that you can do that you
can't do with a pitch or duration really
is you can show a note it's weird that
the first time it always takes longer
and then later so here we go we have a
particular note it figures out some kind
of context for it has a couple other
things we can do we can change the note
head to be an X we can change the note
to be no red I'm slightly color blind so
I can't really see the difference but
you can tell me that
works yep and um we can also make it
into a complex note so I think we
learned
6.25 couldn't be represented normally
but we can see that um music 21 will
figure out how many notes are necessary
to represent it on the staff
there's other miscellaneous
things you can give it a
lyric and so on so uh again everything
there is in the during it and you'll see
there's a lot of stuff and we're going
to get through um a good chunk of
looking these things
later no you will not be ever quizzed on
okay what does purge orphans mean on a
note so it's not that kind of class but
but we want you to um I want you to feel
free play around with this play with
anything except just like with pitch
anything that begins with transpose is
off limits um only because uh it'll make
the problem set where we uh do a lot of
things with intervals a lot less fun
because you're not using anyhow uh this
is the end of the locking for topic one