All right, good morning and good
afternoon for those of us who are
joining from overseas. Um, and even good
evening as well. I'm Trisha Dinkl and
I'm with the MIT Startup Exchange which
is an integrated program resource within
MIT ILP and it's an honor to be here
this morning and to introduce the MIT
Startup presentations. Today you'll be
hearing from two startup companies, Muan
Vision and Fieldstone Bio. And both of
the presenting startups are part of the
MIT Startup Exchange and are developing
critical technologies and services that
address both the challenges and the
emerging innovations for mining and
resource recovery. So with this
selection of startups, we want to give
you an idea of the technologies that are
emerging from MIT that are advancing the
mining industry. Each startup
presentation will be followed by its own
brief audience Q&A. So I encourage you
to ask your questions into the Q&A
field. uh throughout the respective
presentations. If you'd like to connect
with either of the startup presenters
following the webinar, you can reach out
to me directly. I'll put my contact
information into the chat field or you
can ask your ILP program director
because that's what we do at Startup
Exchange and ILP. MIT Startup Exchange
brings together MIT connected startups
and ILP corporate members to foster this
collaboration and partnerships between
them. The startups that we support all
have a strong connection with the
institute. This connection can come
through the founding team or the
technology. In other cases, startups who
don't have an origin at MIT, but because
they're vetted and supported by MIT
peers, we assess them for MIT startup
exchange. So, examples of MIT peers
could be Cale Connect Plus, Start.no,
The Engine, and their respective startup
portfolios. Today, we have a network of
over 800 startups virtually working in
any sector. And we are also
geographically agnostic engaging with
MIT uh MIT connected startups
headquartered anywhere in the world.
Everything MIT startup exchange does is
to expose and connect startups and ILP
industry members in a highly curated
way. So this includes launching calls
for startups on corporate's own
challenges and priority or facilitating
one-on-one meetings between both
parties, hosting virtual demo days and
other events and learning opportunities
where we can typically co-organize them
with our MIT peers such as the Martin
Center, Martin Trust Center, E14 or
venture mentoring service. right here
just a very small brief snapshot of the
success cases we've had to date that
includes proof proof of concepts uh
pilots joint development acquisitions
and it's the intent with every event
every meeting every introduction to
produce the valuable connections that
will ultimately lead to its own success
case so now on to the startup
presentations each company will be
presenting for seven minutes followed by
a threeminut Q&A so be sure to ask your
questions