I'm uh you know it's a pleasure to be
here today to to talk to all of you uh
about some of the work that I've done in
the Boyer lab um on you know fluoresence
microscopy so I want to start out with
uh a pretty simple claim that microscopy
is a very important tool in cell biology
in particular there are two things that
I think microscopy does really well um
the first is it gives us information
about morphology of cells and organel
I'm showing you here a couple of um
there's two screens a couple of uh
cardom myosite nuclei that tend to have
pretty interesting morphologies and I'll
uh I'll get back to that a little bit
later and then I'm showing you um some
other work on the on the right that
we're working on in the Boer lab um we
work with a a putative mitochondrial
protein and using microscopy we were
able to show that it has some some sort
of unique spatial relationships with
with mitochondria and so that's really
the other thing um is is spatial
relationships or something that we can
get really nice information about with
microscopy now if we look at the
microscopy Market landscape it's it's
really diverged into high content uh
machines um like the the Perkin Elmer um
Opera Phoenix that I use um and and
other sort of super resolution machines
that are developed by uh a bunch of
companies and I want to take a second to
um try and espouse the value of super
resolution microscopy to you guys so I'm
showing you here a couple of cells that
are staying for a structural protein
called alpat tub ul and in a in a high
content High throughput microscopy
system um this is about the resolution
that you can get um and and when we
apply super resolution to this image we
can really start to pick apart the
individual fibers in these cells in a
way that can allow us to ask pretty
interesting questions so we think that
that you know higher resolution
microscopy is really important in cell
biology and I don't think I need to um
convince this audience that high content
or high throughput microscopy is also
super important so in the bo we kind of
asked if we could come up with a
compromise between these two
camps and in thinking about that we came
across a technology that was developed
in Ed boyden's lab in 2015 called
expansion microscopy if you're not
familiar expansion microscopy is a a
super resolution microscopy technique
that works by um uh having doing
something on the sample rather than
changing the microscope and so to be a
little bit more specific we'll do the
the standard fixation and uh imuno
stating protocol and then we'll um add
an anchor molecule into the cells that's
going to uh coent bind to proteins we'll
peruse in uh a mono uh sorry
uh um uh a monomer solution that uh we
can then polymerize to form a hydrogel
that sort of incorporates the anchored
proteins in the sample after we digest
the the cells we can add water and the
the gel will essentially swell
um and it'll bring the fluorescent
molecules with it and and the the
outcome of that is essentially larger
cells a larger sample that we can image
at effectively a higher resolution and
so you can see this process happening on
some cells that are staying for that
that structural protein off a tubulin
here and you can see they're kind of
expanding up to the right um in this
little
video uh
so we this this technology was developed
like I said in 2015 um and it's been
used since then in hundreds of papers by
uh a large number of of labs across the
world um but the implementation has
pretty much always been uh sort of
handheld very meticulous sample by
sample so we wanted to take this core
technology and adapt it to 96 well
plates in a manner that would be
conducive to high content Imaging and
what we came up with was this this
device we call the high XM device it's a
simple plastic wellplate insert that
works by essentially collecting small
volumes of the hydrogel solution and
depositing them into the well plates in
a in a manner that's conducive to uh the
expansion microscopy and so in this
first step we're collecting small
volumes of the gel basically just by
dipping the device into a
reservoir this this collection process
is mediated by uh geometry on the
surface of these tips after which we can
take the loaded device insert it into
the wells of the well plate where the
gels will be
deposited uh on the cell culture surface
where we have our fixed and stained
cells um we then polymerize with
ultraviolet light and we have this gel
that has U sort of a doughnut shape uh
which means that we can add our digest
out our water to the well while the
device is still there um the gel will
swell and it will effectively remove
itself from the device after which we
can remove the device from the well
plate and go to image without ripping
the gels out of the well
plate um and so we're able to use this
device and
form uh you know these these gels in
these Wells and mass in 96 well plates
and we can take those samples and bring
them to a high content Imaging system we
use um the Opera Phoenix uh one of the
oper phoenixes at the broad
Institute um and we can generate you
know essentially terabytes of data from
uh super resolution samples quote
unquote um without really too much
effort um and I want to take a moment to
uh uh kind of address one of the most
common questions that we get about
Manion microscopy particularly in this
context which is how do you know after
the thing is blown up that it's a
faithful recapitulation of what the cell
originally was um and and in order to
answer that question um we had to do a
ton of validation work that basically
involves taking images of the same cells
before and after expanding them finding
those images where you have the exact
same cell and then putting those images
into register and doing some relatively
complicated math to to come up with a a
deformation Vector field and I'll spare
you on the details of that except to say
that the the data that we produced from
that was on par with uh previous
expansion microscopy uh Publications so
that was kind of what we were looking
for so so you know having kind of shown
you the technology that we've developed
we think that this this High exm device
is potentially widely applicable in the
academic pharmaceutical and biotech
sectors but to give you uh a couple of
examples um I'm going to show you two
quick stories of things that we've used
this technology for in the Boer
lab um so the main focus of the Boyer
lab is the heart um and in the context
of drug trials cardiotoxicity is one of
the leading causes of toxicity related
drug failure and there are a ton of
systems in cardiio my sites which are
the heart cells um that can be affected
by a drug um so we elected to study do
rubison which is a known cardox
chemotherapeutic um and it's its sort of
main mechanism of action is thought to
be uh through DNA damage through the
inhibition of a protein called topal
isomerase 2B um and we know that DNA
damage has pretty um systemic
consequences in the nucleus for one we
know that it affects um the lamin
structure which is the proteins on the
inner surface of the nucleus and we know
that it can cause DNA uh chromatin
condensation um in in in the case of
apoptosis
um so what I'm showing you here are
images of cardium myosite nuclei before
and after expansion before being on the
top and and and after being on the
bottom and just to note that these are
not the exact same nuclei so they
haven't majorly restructured
um
and uh uh different concentrations of of
Doc rubison um increasing as you go to
the to the right um now in typical
cardiy you know inv vitro dox rubus and
toxicity assays uh people use
concentrations of of of this drug in the
microl range and so we wanted to see if
we could use the additional resolution
that we get with hxm to detect subtle
changes or subtle effects of docon on
these cells and and with the added
resolution we were able to observe um an
apparent increase in uh chromatin or DNA
compaction at the edge of the
nucleus and so we set out to quantify
that
using um a custom analysis pipeline that
I'll sort of demonstrate here what
you're going to see is as this red ring
uh goes in toward the center of the
nucleus the curve on the right is going
to track the average signal intensity
along that ring so what we can see here
is there's there's essentially um a
spike in Signal intensity and and this
is um a hoook stain by the way which is
it's like dappy it's sort of the
non-specific DNA stain um we can see
that there's a a spike of signal
intensity right at the edge of the
nucleus that sort of gradually falls off
as we get toward the center so we can
take these curves from hundreds of of
nuclei from hundreds of of different
cells and aggregate them to get
population averages for the different uh
uh dox rubison
concentrations and when we do that what
we see is is first of all when we
compare you know pre-expansion standard
resolution and postexpansion um we don't
really even observe this sort of signal
intensity Peak at the edge of the
nucleus unless we we apply the
additional resolution
and what's more when we look at these
peaks of signal intensity um what we see
is that they change in what appears to
be a a doc concentration dependent
manner the the peak sort of tighten um
which in math uh is the curvature of the
peak so we can calculate the curvature
by um taking the the minimum of the
second derivative the curves which is
not really important um and what we what
we get are
data that look like this which which
basically show us that we can see
statistically significant uh effects of
dox rubison um on these cells at
concentrations as low as 10 nanom which
is orders of magnitude lower than
typical um invitro toxicity assays will
sort of look at at this
drug um so I want to take a sort of a
moment to pause here and say that if
there's one kind of take-home message
that I hope you take from this this talk
it's that uh increasing resolution in in
imaging um is is really adding
information to your images um and and we
sort of demonstrated that here by
showing that this added resolution um
sort of unlocked an observation that we
were able to quantify but I want to show
you another example of a way that
increasing resolution can give us more
information about
images um and sort of in line with with
the the last talk actually um another
thing that we're working in the blower
lab excuse me is uh studying the
intracellular fates of nanom
medicines um and these are drugs that
have to be endocytosed they have to be
engulfed in order to get into the cell
where they're sort of trafficked through
um a a diverse population of different
types of endosomal organel and when
we're studying this process uh
understanding the type of organel in
which these drugs reside can give us
important information about the
trafficking behavior of the drug and
ultimately it's fate in the cell um so
in fluoresence microscopy we can study
this type of system by staining
different uh subsets of these organel uh
as as well as the drug and then reading
out differential
colocalization and that image might look
something like this so I'm showing you
here uh a stain of early endosomes with
a protein called ea1 uh late endosomes
and lomes in cyan with a protein called
Lamp one and then the drug in yellow
which in this case is an antibody drug
conjugate that gets taken up into the
cell and and from these insets what I
hope you can appreciate is that we can't
really tell which compartment this this
um this drug is in uh and so this is
kind of where the added resolution
shines because if we if we you know add
that resolution to this image we can
pretty clearly see that this this drug
is interacting with the the early
compartment and not not really with the
late
compartment um so so particularly for
colocalization analyses um we think that
adding resolution is is you know really
valuable especially when you have you're
studying an organel that uh tends to be
very packed inside the
cell um but there's other information
that's baked into the uh the the images
with additional resolution that we can
use um so if we go back to
this
um sort of model of cell staining that I
talked about earlier um what we're doing
here is we're using antibodies to Mark
surface proteins that exist on these
organel that that are thought to be
canonical markers of different types of
of um endosomal organel but in reality
um you know a given protein is going to
localize to a broad swath of
functionally distinct or unique uh
endocytic organel and there's there's
value in making that distinction more
granular um and and one of the ways that
we can do that is through understanding
the morphologies of these organel um and
so in in earlier transmission electron
microscopy studies of of these types of
organel the main way that was actually
used to uh sort of understand the
identities of of these organal was
through their
morphologies um and in particular uh the
tubulation on these organal is is really
important in sorting and uh the Pres of
these these uh intraluminal vesicles is
an indication of uh maturity basically
and although the resolution that we get
is not nearly as as high as you can get
with transmission electron microscopy um
we still get enough resolution to
um uh sort of get at some of these
morphological features that are really
important so then the question becomes
how do we take the sort of subjective
observations of the human eye and turn
them into an unbiased imag analysis
pipeline that can you know be used on
hundreds of thousands of these images um
and the first step is of course to take
our full fields of view and convert them
into individual uh organel images that
can be independently analyzed and so you
know at the moment we use a combination
of adaptive thresholding and Watershed
segmentation to do that at this point
there are much more sophisticated um
methods for doing that that can um that
can do a little bit of a better job
excuse me and then the question becomes
um how do we you know how do we sort of
understand these organal better and um
you know where we have the human eye to
to kind of pick up features we can
substitute that for deep learning um and
we're we're actively pursuing a number
of different methods um uh supervised
and unsupervised to try and meet this
need but you know as an example one
could imagine taking um
a yeah taking a a an autoencoder model
which sort of takes your images and and
encodes them into a A reduced latent
space that you can then plot on a
two-dimensional plot like this and use
clustering to sort of classify different
types of
organal um but I think what's what's
really important to note here is that
these types of machine learning
applications require uh tons and tons of
of data and the more data you have the
more successful your general going to be
and so the ability to generate these uh
sort of really high resolution images in
Mass puts us in a pretty unique position
to combine um uh super resolution
imaging and machine learning in kind of
a unique
way um so in summary I hope I've
convinced you that there's some value in
Striking a balance between image
resolution and throughput um I've shown
you some earlier work that we did in the
vein of of uh sort of trying to show
that the extra resolution that we can
get gives us additional information that
we can turn into a a quantification of a
a
new um yeah a phenotype and then um I
showed you some some more recent work
that we've started working on um in the
vein of trying to think about endosomal
organal in a bit of a a new
way um and I'll just take this time to
thank my adviser Lori Boer and our lab
we're here at MIT I'm a biological
engineering student um Lori is in the
biology
Department
um and are yeah sources of funding and
i'' be happy to take some
[Applause]
questions thank you John any questions
from the audience
thank you amazing talk so how about if
we extend the high expansion microscope
into spal biology so we can St Sal
Communications
yeah um that's I mean it's definitely
possible I I mean so like the you know
to on a high level the limitations that
you have with expansion microscopy are
essentially you can't do live Imaging uh
because you have to you know blow the
cells up um and
well yeah I mean so certainly you know
looking at things like um like CAD like
the connections between cells and and
and that kind of thing is is definitely
possible things like paracrine signaling
where you have you know um an exchange
of factors through the medium would be
more difficult um but yeah I mean
definitely would be able to uh to do
that thank you yeah
hey uh great talk I had a question about
the um have you been able to or uh has
anyone tried to apply this to like um
some of the more in each of these Wells
what is the extent of the like high
content Imaging you could do like with
for example the panels of O conjugated
antibodies for like the sort of um
morphological readout of something like
an arrayed crispas screen like I guess
I'm interested in understanding the
throughput limitations of of of this and
like whether you've uh applied it to
something like PAB view or something
like that yeah the the throughput is
something that I forgot to mention but
um I to put some numbers to it if you
we're Imaging the 60 inner Wells of a 96
well plate um if we're getting 20 fields
of view per well which in expansion
microscopy since the thing that you know
sample is getting bigger um the field of
view is effectively getting smaller by
the same um
Factor uh and then if we have like four
channels um the the amount of time that
it would take to image that whole set of
Wells is about 60 hours so it's um you
know like I said it's a compromise
between resolution and throughput um
depending on you know the the the
specific uh parameters that you want to
use you can you know go down on the time
by uh you know a lot um but
we Chris screens was one of the earliest
ideas that we were thinking about but we
didn't end up going in that direction um
so hopefully that an your
question hi thank you for your talk um I
wanted to ask you you show some example
in 2D would it be possible to do the
same but in 3D when the cells are
embedded in a gel absolutely yeah yeah
um in our in the the do rubison
cardiotoxicity study
um we we use two-dimensional Optical
sections of the nuclei
um uh
because that's sort of the easiest way
to really get out the the edge of the
nucleus um and it it turns out that the
I think the main reason why the standard
resolution doesn't really work is
because uh for one Optical section
you're getting too much depth of the
nucleus so if you imagine like the the
edge of the nucleus in in the Z
Direction um if you're Imaging where
it's kind of at an angle the the the
microscope doesn't do a great job at
picking up just that uh section of the
of the object and so you have some extra
signal from the sort of the uh the above
and below and it ends up making the
um the the analysis do does not really
work but um yeah I mean the so the the
cell the sample expands isotropically in
all directions so you you know as a
result of that you get uh you know 3D
information that's definitely useful and
and it's possible to expand the say if
they are embedded in a gel like really
like in 3D if there is a micro oh I see
that's a good question it's definitely
possible um there is a limitation in our
technique for the volume of the sample
that you're trying to expand because the
the expansion gel itself is about 250
nanoliters and if you if your sample is
on that order of volume then you end up
um lowering the concentration of the
monomers and and the gel doesn't really
form correctly but we've we've done um
like cell clusters that that are fairly
substantial without much of a problem we
haven't tried really like fully embedded
cells other than um cells that are
cultured on kind of like a coating but
it's definitely you know possible thank
you
[Music]
any other questions what we have
John can you comment the possibility to
bridge the stor with expansion scope
yeah yeah yeah um there are Labs that
that combine expansion with storm um
there's one in Australia that I can
think of I forget the Pi's name but um
you know I've never use a storm
microscope so I don't know if you can
put a 996 well plate on a storm
microscope it's not something that we
really thought about because storm
itself puts a limitation on the
throughput and you know we're really
interested in extending the throughput
as far as it can go for expansion
microscopy um but yeah I mean I think
with with a combination of storm and
expansion you can get resolution as low
as like 10 nmet without much trouble
thank you