okay I only have five minutes but I
first want to very sincerely thank the
organizers and to the audience this is
the best meeting of the year and I
really just love being here and the
engagement from everyone so thank you
for that my name is Brian Chamberlain
I'm a medicinal chemist at tanmai we are
a drug Discovery Services Company a cro
that is dedicated to addressing
bottlenecks and Drug Discovery by
combining a state-of-the-art wet lab
with Advanced computational Techniques
be they physics based or AI we get very
excited when we can combine physic space
and AI approaches to accelerate and
overcome these
bottlenecks last year I showed a poster
in which we showed our implementation of
using Active Learning and rbfe to
optimize our groups very efficiently we
and others in the field are doing this
and if you're not doing this you're
missing out on opportunity to be very
efficient and comprehensive in driving
the potency of your R groups in that
case you're able to enumerate large
libraries of reasonable compounds using
reaction-based um framework very simple
you know your Chemistry you have a
building block a building block library
of hundreds of thousands of compounds
and you know you're going to be able to
to execute on those
synthetically predicting the potency of
those compounds is also amenable to the
current methods you're able to tweak the
state-of-the-art for predicting potency
rbfe in certain ways to make it even
more computationally efficient and then
you're able to drive that in an active
learning cycle again the synthesis is
already baked into how you have set up
that experiment and you're able to
execute on those very easily often times
in a plate based
format core hopping is an essential
activity in drug Discovery I don't think
I've worked on a single program in my
career where we haven't tried to do a
core hop whether to address a known
liability protect against an unknown
liability protect RP or quite frankly
fast follow on someone else's IP here
all of
the here the challenges to this vers our
group enumeration are that it's very
difficult to enumer at large reasonable
libraries of cor Hops and then
calculating the potency of those is is
quite challenging um rbfe needs
congeneric molecules with small changes
to be effective so probably the most
important scientific advance in my
poster is our implementation of Fe which
we call
CBF I won't get into the details now um
but it allows you to calculate the
potency of compounds in a relativistic
framework um purely arbitrary changes um
so these compounds you would not be able
to calculate using rbfe this is a brd4
data set and we show very nice
correlation here unlike an abfe
simulation you never have to sample the
apostate we apply this method in a Soup
To Nuts um prospective case study on SAU
one inhibitor mrtx 0902 and for me as a
medicinal chemist the most interesting
aspect of this work is the enumeration
We compare multiple enumeration methods
sort of the most common ones in the
field um link invent both the prior
model and reinforcement learning on
basic objective endpoints creme and
recore um we did a lot of work to get
those libraries for those methods if
you're aware of them to work on a corop
and give us meaningful number of
compounds and we compare and contrast
those um we also have a human medicinal
chemist designed the compounds as a
human medicinal chemist would by looking
at the crystal structure and thinking
about what type YP of reactions
are expected to perform
well a lot I can say about the
enumeration of all those different
modules but the two things I'd like to
highlight is that generative AI is the
most important computational approach to
generating cor hop libraries simply
because of its ability to generate very
large libraries which you will not be
able to access with Library based
methods very interestingly to me if you
compare um the compounds enumerated from
the generative AI approach and look for
the human design compound you can't find
it um even if you were to run link inv
vent with reinforcement learning onto a
very narrow molecular weight around
which the molecular we're looking for
you would have to enumerate maybe a 100
million compounds to maybe enumerate the
compound that a medicinal chemist came
up with so I think that's really
important um we have to combine and take
the best features of all of these
different enumeration techniques to
achieve our goal
we then dock all these compounds using a
few algorithms to make sure whatever
we're observing is not just strictly
related to Vena or R do or whatever and
I have trends that I can show you um
probably the most interesting one uh for
the next 15 seconds is that the library
based methods are really really perform
well at reproducing the rmsd POS of the
reference Li and that's super important
to being able to deploy the physics
based methods so I take it all the way
um we run the CBF I have the real data
on how that performed um so you can
assess for yourself if you think it's
interesting or if you would want to use
that tool and then I show the actual
ic50s uh I don't have time now but I can
kind of philosophize um how these
techniques are impacting me as a
medicinal chemist of course none of this
really was existed or if it existed it
wasn't easy to use or someone like
someone like me to access and and deploy
um without really a lot of special
computational help
so 5 minutes exactly thank you