All right. Thank you all uh for coming
here and listening to these exciting set
of talks. I've been like super enthused
since morning. Um and thank you Dmitri
for setting the stage for organ
transplantation. And um this talk is
about some new types of organs that are
being discovered at this very moment in
the last couple of years. And uh so I'm
going to talk about the impact of
cryopreservation and xenographed organs
on the already complex organ
transplantation pipeline. And I want to
say a huge thank to the circ seed grants
for helping us jumpst start this
collaboration. Our uh team here has some
fantastic students Thomas and Meline.
Meline is actually in the crowd there.
And we have master students uh Jesse and
Praik. And our collaborators uh Dr.
called IEN uh Heidi Mahmed Toner and
David Cron have actually been involved
in successfully transplanting a first uh
pig edited gene organ uh into a human
and they're actually looking at clinical
trials uh uh starting in 2025 uh for
this technology. They've also
successfully shown uh
cryopreservation uh for um uh pig and
human kidney partial freezing. So in
that context uh let me give you some
numbers again. So each day 18 Americans
die waiting for an organ transplant.
Thousands never make it to a transplant
list. Out of these endstage organ
failure alone accounts for around 7
30,000 deaths in the US and it's
estimated that 30% of these can be saved
with an organ replacement. So with these
staggering numbers when we preview these
exciting technologies uh that are about
to uh you know that are already starting
and uh rapidly rising in growth of
cryopreservation and xenor grafting we
have an opportunity. So with these
breakthroughs the opportunity is that
you know we can we have a chance to
reshape the organ transplantation the
future of organ transplantation. But the
question isn't just can we do that, it's
where and how should we target these new
technologies uh to have a positive
impact on the existing organ
transplantation pipeline. How should we
assess that? Because look, these
technologies are currently being uh uh
passed through clinical trials. So
there's not enough data. So we have to
rely on the data that already exists in
the current system with the current
practices and find opportunities where
these should be uh these should enter
the market in some sense right so as
Dimmitri already mentioned organ
transplantation is actually a very
complex process it's uh beyond the organ
transplantation policies there are
various factors on what is the kidney
quality so these are donor factors what
are the recipient factors things like
HLA compatibility things like
sensitization, things like you know what
is the age of the recipient and how how
sick and how urgently they need that
organ. There are human factors on you
know what is the surgeon's estimate of
the benefit and the risk of doing an
organ transplantation with a particular
kidney that becomes available. There are
uh logistics and timing which include
geographic distance, the time to offer
acceptance which might already uh you
know deem that organ unviable but
perhaps we could save that using
cryopreservation. Cryopreservation is
this uh you know you freeze an organ to
very low temperatures so that you can
extend its viability not just for 24
hours but for days and that creates
massive opportunity because you could
preserve high uh even mediocre quality
organs and make them available across uh
the US and across uh the world even. And
there are institutional and policy
factors that not just impact that not
just come from national policies but
there might be local and regional
policies that impact organ offer
acceptance, right? And so what we want
to do is we want to look at all of this
data that already exists and we want to
use AI to help us understand where are
the gaps in supply and demand, where are
the opportunities for xeno and cryo uh
organs. But this is a hugely complex uh
medical uh decision-m space and what we
would like is for that AI to know also
where it is uncertain. We don't want a
system that can only predict and
prescribe but we want a system that is
very transparent about its errors.
Right? So our goal is not to automate
the process. It is the augmentation of
decision- making using prescriptive AI
which is transparent about the errors
that it makes.
And that is a a big open question.
There's a lot of research that's
currently happening in trying to
calibrate AI models and think about what
are the errors in different instance
spaces that they make. And so we are
going to try and bring that thought
process into the space of organ
transplantation. So our first question
is when uh is xenographing most useful?
So which types of organs are more in
demand but there's not enough supply and
if we could actually create these tailor
gene edited pig organs if we could all
if we could target specific profiles
then could we actually close that supply
demand gap could we actually provide
better kidneys uh to patients who really
need them and so uh here is a
perspective from a patient's uh uh you
know from a patient's perspective what
happens when they're made kidney offers
or what might they expect in an organ
transplantation pipeline. So here is a
patient or you can think of it as a pool
of patients that are looking for an
organ that is a good fit to them. In the
uh pipeline there'll be many organs that
will be offered to patients with similar
profiles. These organs can have a higher
quality and they can have lower quality.
And so this is measured by something
that is called the KDPI which measure
measures is a measure of uh organ
quality for kidneys how useful how how
beneficial these kidneys are going to
be. And once a patient is offered all of
this portfolio of organs over a period
of time and I'm thinking about a patient
cohort but simplifying on this slide. If
I typically match patients of this sort
with an organ of a high quality relative
to the offers that they've gotten, I
say, well, there's enough supply of such
organs, you know, accounting for time
effects, for weight list effects, for
placement effects and so on. There's
enough supply of good organs and they
can be matched to an organ with
relatively high KDPI. But on the other
hand, we see cases where there are
patient groups that are despite an organ
the distribution of organs or the types
of organs that are offered to them have
higher KDPIs, they often end up getting
lower uh uh quality kidneys. So they end
up getting not the high quality kidneys
that would have appeared in an offer to
them in the system but they end up
getting lowquality kidneys. And so for
various reasons um we call that a supply
demand gap. So we say that you know if
something like this happens that's an
opportunity for xenor grafted organs
because I've identified a patient
population that for various reasons in
this complex pipeline are actually not
making use of the or high quality organs
that are get uh getting offered to
them. And so our question here is that
let's look at all of the ptr data. So we
have uh this is the matchr run algorithm
which makes offers to patients uh
through policies that uh Dimmitri
discussed in his talk and so we have
around 25 million records here and we
want to use AI to automatically find
sets of patients with various recipient
characteristics where then they do don't
have access to high quality kidneys in
that system. Right? Okay. So we can uh
uh create metrics. These are uh
statistical metrics. They are just a
single number that we evaluate for every
patient and we evaluate it for a cohort
of patients. And we can create these uh
models that tell us where the nodes are
redder in color, that's where there's
excess supply. Where the nodes are
lighter in color, that's where we are
kind of closing that supply demand gap.
If the nodes are white, that's where the
demand is much higher than the supply,
right? And so let's let's unpack that a
little bit. So this is in one of the
regions. So in this talk, I'm going to
consider three regions. There are three
um big cities with a lot of
transplantation centers. They're uh
demographically very diverse and so but
uh uh we are going to offiscate the
names but just call these regions one,
two, and three. In region one, we see
this node with a very red color. Which
means that if I look into that node, the
patients are have been offered kidneys
of quality that look like that. So
that's worse kidney quality. These are
the offers, the blue histogram. And the
acceptances are skewed towards the
right. Uh which means that this is
higher uh relatively higher uh uh
quality kidneys were accepted more
frequently than the lowquality kidneys.
And so that tells me there is no supply
demand gap. In fact, supply is enough
and there is uh enough uh there is not
uh demand that we cannot meet with the
current availability of organs in the
system. Let me show you another example.
This is a supply demand gap in region
two. And here we see a node which has a
negative value. And what that negative
value means mathematically is that there
is more demand than potential supply.
when I unpack the offers that patients
with these characteristics have gotten.
So these patients are the ones that are
not blood typo and where a particular
alil B162 is present. For these patients
the mean quality of kidney that was
offered to them is better than what was
uh actually accepted. And so the offers
tend to be uh towards lower kidney
quality rather than higher kidney
quality as in the previous example. So
this automatically helps us uh this
system automatically helps us go through
millions of patient uh uh uh organ
offers and automatically detect areas
where xenor grafting can be very useful.
Next up, I want to think about
cryopreservation. And cryopreservation,
as I said, is this uh uh scientific
technology of kind of uh uh decreasing
the temperatures and freezing the organs
to such a low amount that you can
preserve the organ for a much longer
time beyond 24 hours of kidney
viability, but also you can do it in a
way you can slowly increase the
temperature in a way that the organ
still remains viable. And uh our
question is that you know there is a lot
of kidneys lot of organs that are
actually unused in the system. They're
non-utilized and can we actually utilize
them potentially by
cryopreservation. So some statistics
again. So here we are looking at disease
donor organs in this space and the
kidney non-use in 2023 and this is a
slide from SRTR uh shows that there were
5,000 donors with at from whom at least
one of the kidney was not used. There
are approximately there were 85,000
8,500 kidneys that were non-used from
these 5,000 donors and there were 26
million offers that were made for these
kidneys that were ultimately not used.
So imagine an organ becomes available,
it is getting matched and offered to
patients by their uh priority on the
weight list. By the time somebody could
even accept that offer, that kidney is
already not viable anymore. Right? And
so there is a lot of uh uh you know it's
over 28% of the kidneys recovered from
disease donors were actually not used in
2023 and that's a huge uh uh opportunity
to use cryopreservation. It's also a
huge opportunity to automatically
understand if a kidney is not likely to
be used by the first 500 patients, why
not bypass and create an expedited offer
that can place that kidney faster and
potentially somebody can benefit from
it. So with that in mind, we thought
about you know what are the uh what are
the organs that are viable for
cryopreservation. There are definitely
factors that uh you know correspond to
high creatinin levels, low filtration
rates, uh old kidneys from very old
donors that make them not very viable
for use. But what about kidneys that are
kind of in that mediocre range that
could still be useful if they were just
transplanted early enough or
cryopreserved and transplanted later in
the system. So that's our next question
that we considered on how can we use AI
to predict how different regions in the
US so we've just done it for three
regions so far how different regions in
the US will respond to an offered
non-utilized organ in the system by
learning from past
decisions. So we are taking the current
system the current organ transplantation
pipeline which does not have an estimate
of the risk. It does not uh have
cryopreserved organs in the pipeline but
we are trying to learn from that data
and again we're going to keep our eye
towards uh uncertainties in that
pipeline and errors in these
predictions. So we took all of this data
uh we went very happily uh you know we
developed our machine learning models we
did some feature selection we got input
from doctors uh because of the policy
changes we incorporated years we had low
and high KDPI kind of variables uh we
had uh you know regional models that
predicted uh what is the maximum uh you
know predicted acceptance of organs
across the three regions and there these
models are different reflecting regional
practices
And then using all of this, we wanted to
predict accept or reject. But of course,
this is a system that's using all of
this data that exists and the system can
make mistakes. So let's look at the
accuracy of this. The accuracy that we
got was fantastic. We were very happy
when we saw that, right? But an accuracy
of 98% 99% from accepted from uh the PTR
match run data has to be taken with a
pinch of salt. Why? Because most of
these organs are actually rejected. Most
of these offers in the system are
rejects, right? So even if I predicted a
reject for every organ, I would get an
accuracy of
98%. So accuracy has to be taken with a
pinch of salt and instead we can look at
precision accept. What is precision
accept saying for offers that were
actually uh labeled as accept? How many
were actually accepted in the data? So
for organs where I actually predicted
and accept how many of these were
actually accepted by the doctors that's
when a system can be really useful right
and so across these three areas we
actually saw that region one had a 65
precision accept region two had 94 which
is fantastic and region three had 85%.
All right. So, we thought to ourselves,
you know, is our uh AI making mistakes
or uh is the data bad or is the
decisions of the doctors very noisy?
Like what is going on here? Why don't we
have the same precision accept across?
And a little bit of insight into that is
that indeed region one has much sparer
data than region two. So there is that
effect of not having enough data across.
And we trained national models and they
didn't help us. So we said you know can
we create can we understand what are
these regions based on organ quality
where I will have more fidelity in my
prediction versus where I know that my
prediction is uncertain and I should not
make a decision. And so in that uh uh in
that vein so with that thought process
we looked at what is the performance of
these models across the three different
regions. And as you can see the
performance is not uniform. So as the
kidney quality changes for very low
kidney quality. So that's very uh that's
the end of the bar chart here. Uh a lot
of kidneys are rejected and so the
decisions are much easier for very high
quality kidneys. A lot of kidneys are
accepted and decisions are easier. But
you will see a dip when the decisions
kind of become in that gray zone. Right?
And so our thought process here and let
me skip through these slides was that
you know we want to be able to navigate
these predictions with the amount of
uncertainty in my AI model. And here is
the kind of tradeoff that we would like
to make visible uh to our team uh and
and and to the uh transplantation
system. So in region one the expected
number of placements for the set of
kidneys between 0.5 and 6 kdpi. So this
is mediocre range was around 23 to
57%. That's kind of our our range of how
uncert uncertain we think the model is
and the precision accept of that model
is 43. So every time I'm giving you in
some sense a range of what I think the
benefit can be from placing this organ
into region one, region two or region
three. And I'm also combining that with
the precision accept across uh for these
kinds of organs. So this is a simplified
slide to tell you that there is a
trade-off, right? I can go with a very
certain model in region three that has
that almost saves no kidneys or I can go
with a model in region one that is uh
much less certainty and saves uh organs
amongst in that range. And so one might
think that you know if I want to have a
trade-off I might go with a more a
region two which has a 0 65 precision
accept. So with all of this we are very
excited to understand the trade-offs
develop more machine learning models uh
kind of open up that back uh that black
box for uh physicians and decision
makers in the system and uh we are
developing currently web tools to bridge
this to practice. So for any organ that
becomes available in the system, we have
a web tool that's not online yet but
will be very soon. Um where you can ask
for the predictive models for different
transplantation centers in the regions
that we've considered for the organ. We
can show you that you know this organ
looks like uh very similar to all of
these organs that were actually
rejected. you can explore what organs in
the systems which past offers were
rejected which were similar to these or
if there is a possibility of placing
that organ in that uh center. So that
will help us create these expedited
offers that can help with the use of
cryopreservation decrease
non-utilization of kidneys. So with that
um thank you all for listening and I'm
very happy to take questions.
questions.
Are you using the region's data to train
the regions model? We are. Yes. Or
you're not cross you're not using it
across the three regions. We tried
training a model across the three
regions and fine-tuning for the regions
data and that ended up uh not having a
higher predictive power as we can see on
the test data for the regional models
themselves. Sometimes we also find that
the variables that are being selected so
we have a staggering number of 800
variables that go into uh prediction for
every offer and uh the variables that
are selected that are most predictive
are often different for the different
regions. So some of the key variables
are the same but uh you know you see
insurance pop up in one of the regions
and so that's uh you know that's a
potential you know there's some
correlation there that we would like to
explore.
Great further
questions. Thank you so much for this
presentation. I have some questions
about the AI techniques you use. So you
use XG boost. Did you also consider
using like transformers or CNN or any
other models? If so, what were the
difficulties when trying? Right. So uh
we used um LLMs.
So uh we uh actually uh we followed up
on a very nice uh recent work from
Dimitri's group actually on tap tech
creates uh which takes a tabular data
creates that into text data creates an
embedding from that and augments the XG
boost model and we found that you know
for some regions it had a slight benefit
but for others we've not seen the
benefit yet so there's more exploration
to be done there. Yeah.
But perhaps some of these uh uh uh you
know uh transformer augmented models
could help create more context. But I
think what what we are seeing is that
there's enough noise in the system that
you know you're kind of reaching the
limits of what can be predicted here.
Awesome. Any further questions for
Swy? Yes.
Hi. Um, is it possible that the machine
learning actually is learning the wrong
things and emphasizing the wrong things
continually?
So, we we are trying to make sure that
that doesn't happen. So, using all of
our various analysis. So we've done like
SHAP analysis. We've tried to understand
you know what are the different factors
that go into that decision-m we've
talked to the doctors. We've kind of you
know it's it's that uh we've kind of
tried to check at every step with the
domain experts in this area to see if
things are uh aligned with you know what
they would
expect. So and and sometimes we've been
able to see uh examples. And so for
example, we have a model that predicts
non-utilization in the current system.
Uh is this organ going to be
non-utilized or not? And we do see when
we predict non-utilization, we see areas
of high creatinin and high age donors
that pop up as very certain non-utilized
in the system. Right? So every time we
train a model, we try to back up and
then stress test that on okay, what are
the distributions? Where are the errors?
What is it saying? Is it saying
something that we believe is true or
not? And this uh space is very complex.
So I I feel like we're peeling an onion.
Every time you peel a layer, that's
there's another layer to peel. Great.
And final question. Um how are you
planning to prevent model drifts in the
future?
So uh one way that uh we are kind of
thinking about this is incorporating
year and kind of time trends uh in the
model specifically with respect to
policy changes. You know, as policy
changes, there is a a lot of change in
the system. And so, you have to in some
sense stay current, but also incorporate
like some of the resistance. Like in one
of the analysis we did, we thought uh we
found some evidence that you know
centers that have that have that are
more reputed and that you know they they
just have a higher friction in kind of
changing their policy across the years.
So they change the policies much slower
and centers that are much smaller they
are more actively changing the policies.
So there's there's a lot to be done in
that space and I I think we are only
scratching the surface.
Thank you so much.