[MUSIC PLAYING]
We think there's something
special about flying machines.
They're just so
difficult to build.
They have to be lightweight.
They have to be safe.
And they get us to places that
we couldn't otherwise get to.
You have to be able
to think big and not
get intimidated by your ideas.
Maybe it is crazy to
put someone on the moon.
But hey, we did that.
I'm working on sending
something to Mars
to pave the way for
humans to go to Mars.
I study multi-agent
reinforcement learning -
getting robots to work with
humans in the real world.
I'm researching entry
descent and landing
for planetary vehicles.
A neural network-based
visual crater detector.
We'll be using these
craters as landmarks
as we build up a map
internally on the spacecraft
as it figures out where it is.
My research focus
has been on aviation
and its environmental impacts.
When your research helps
inform public policy,
it's a big motivator.
When they're
finishing their PhD,
they know more
about their problem
than anybody else in the world.
It's really great to be able to
have so much control over what
you're learning and where you
take your research direction.
What's occurring right now in
aerospace is a Renaissance,
the amount of entrepreneurial
energy and excitement
is just palpable.
Graduate students pretty much
drive most of the research
into the department.
We get some results and
then we say, all right,
let's go fly it on some drones.
If you're really into
entrepreneurship,
MIT has a lot of resources
for starting your own company.
If you want work at NASA, all
the recruiters come to MIT.
The faculty here are
extremely well connected
to what's going on in
the aerospace field,
both in the companies and
within the government.
If you're even at all
slightly concerned about,
I have no idea what
I want to study.
I think I want to
do propulsion, but I
might care about robotics.
Or I want to do sustainability,
but I care about business.
Guess what?
All of those things
we do in AeroAstro.
You don't leave the
department to do that.
I'm interested in the
big science questions
like, where do we come from?
Where are we going?
What else is out there?
I'm very interested in
building spacecraft that work
on interplanetary missions.
I want to learn as much as I
can now about human spaceflight
and Mars and space
engineering so that I can help
push humans to Mars.
I work with people who
come from all backgrounds,
all disciplines.
My lab is very diverse.
There's a really great
sense of community.
And I think that the department
leadership puts a lot of effort
into you supporting
the student groups.
We have a group called AeroAfro.
That's just a group of the
black graduate students
within the department.
They're not just
brilliant engineers
or aspiring astronauts
or amazing scientists.
They also care so much about
taking care of each other.
Every Friday, we get a
group together and go down
to the pub, talk, and destress.
I mean, you just have to
come here and find out
how special of a
place MIT really is.
If you really want to
be at the forefront
and have impact
on real missions,
this is the right
place to do it.
We push the boundaries
of the possible here.
Where else can you say we
look ahead by looking up?
[MUSIC PLAYING]