So we've heard amazing talks about
models, foundation models and
non-foundational models and wormholes
and many many other things. Um it's
wormholes plugging the wormholes, right?
Um so
um eventually children do ask their
parents where do data come
from? And so this session is to address
that question. All of these models
depended on data. But where do data come
from? Where did like large data come
from? Well, somebody thinks up a method.
Well, first somebody thinks up what data
do I wish I had and then figures out
ways to get it and there's of course a
happy interaction with the analysis end.
These of course talk to each other but
the data getting and the data organizing
and the data cleaning and the data all
sorts of things is an amazing wonderful
thing. So I think it's wonderful that
today we have a panel devoted entirely
to novel largecale data creation colon
genomes cells tissues and organisms.
We are going to do it in that order
except we're well we're going to start
really with the cells I guess and then
work our way to the tissues and then
work our way to the
organisms because um we're going to
first hear about about cells and cell
imaging. We're going to hear about then
tissue imaging and more tissue imaging
and two wonderful talks on that. And
then to just show how much this is this
is an oraoros that follows its own tail.
Mark daily is both genomes and organisms
because he's looking at the genome of
the organism just as you can start
wherever you want to and go around like
that. They're going to be great talks.
You're now awake you're seated and we're
going to first start with Shantanu Singh
who's senior group leader in the imaging
platform at the broad. He leads a data
science group that develops
computational and statistical methods to
create fingerprints of genes and
chemicals and diseases from microscopic
images of cells. Shantine, all yours.
Thank
you. Am I audible at the back? It's
good. Thanks, Eric. I have 12 minutes,
so I'll I'll jump right into it. U
with with the slide. This um you know
our lab believes that that images of
cells that look like this are uh
incredibly and uncannily informative of
cell state and that if we use computer
vision methods to to extract uh to to
identify every cell in this image and
extract features from them uh that's a
really effective way of of of capturing
that information. And that if we can do
this for cheap, we can do this at scale.
And and that scale matters when u
anytime you're doing biology, when
you're doing a whole bunch of
experiments, thousands of experiments in
parallel, for example, knocking out a
whole genome worth of genes or or
screening a compound library with
millions of compounds in it. Okay. So,
so the things in the lab that that we
care about are first how do we make
images of cells like this richer in
information uh so that we can get more
out of it but but keep it cheap. All
right. How do we then extract
information from these images to create
profiles? How do we uh then then use
those profiles to solve problems in drug
discovery and and functional genomics
for example? And then importantly and
very relevant to this discussion today,
how do we then produce a lot of data
that will help us make these discoveries
but then also um train AI models to help
us make those discoveries. So the way
we've approached it in the lab I'll just
go in order of this you know making
these information uh these images richer
in information. We invented the the cell
painting assay here at the broad along
with the tribal lab and goal was to pack
in as many stains as we could into a
single imaging assay to mark all these
organels the this confederacy of
subcellular uh structures as Jennifer
told us morning. going to use that term
uh going forward. And and uh
importantly, we we kept this protocol
open and we kept it cheap and we made it
easy to use so that it's now been widely
adopted uh by by the pharma industry and
a lot of academic labs uh that routinely
use it for for phenotyping. Many labs
have uh adapted it when the biology
demands to to suit their needs. uh many
broadies here have uh adapted it to
study heart cells and and brain cells
and and fat cells um and and adapted it
uh as as it's been been relevant to
those to those cell types. So, so given
these images, uh, given these rich
images, uh, how do you then extract
information from them? The the so-called
image based profiling workflow is fairly
straightforward. Uh, you you start with
you start with a pool of cells and then
you perturb them in some way and uh, let
them grow for a bit. You fix them, you
stain them with dyes and uh, image them
under a high throughput microscope and
then use image analysis software uh,
typically to identify each cell. uh you
don't always have to do that as we saw
earlier this morning and then extract a
whole bunch of features from them.
Thousands of features. The fact that
it's thousands is going to be relevant.
We'll probably chat about that a little
later during our discussion today. But
uh you know take all those measurements
and then uh summarize them them in some
way. Typically just average them. It's a
great way of summarizing things and then
those individual those those profiles as
we call it those imagebased profiles are
now representing the population of cells
that we that we started studying. So we
have now these um image based profiles
for the millions or thousands hundreds
of thousands of perturbations that you
might have started with right uh and and
then we do a whole bunch of downstream
tasks with them and I'll talk about them
about a few of those obviously with any
uh such bionformatics workflow comes
with its own complications and we've
built a bunch of tools to to help us
along the way with that okay so we've
got these uh now we have these
imagebased profiles we have these
imagebased profiles uh what do we do
with them how do we how do we use them
to solve problems in drug discovery and
functional genomics and uh there are
many examples I have time for just two
of them today that I thought would would
be most relevant to to what we're going
to chat about um so we may ask for
example can we identify signatures of
disease and then and then screen for
drugs that that reverse that disease to
find potential therapeutics so I'll
focus here on this on this um
collaboration with Miko Taipali's lab in
the University of Toronto uh who are
interested in studying the impact of of
coding variation on the localization of
proteins to see where they to see to see
where they lie and how that changes. So
for example, take this example of this
protein LZTR1. That's what it looks like
in a cell. That's how it it localizes.
Uh but if you consider a if you consider
a variant of it that has uh that is
positive believe of Nunan syndrome um
the localization is significantly
different and consistently different and
importantly then what that gives you is
a screenable phenotype which is to say
that now you can go and screen for
compounds that might revert the
phenotype to look back like a reference
type like like a sort of healthy
reference al right Um and and Miko's lab
had has had studied about 3,500 more
than 3,500 uh disease associated
variants together with their wild type
together with their reference
counterparts uh and found screenable
phenotypes for about 200 of them which
is a uh which is a small fraction uh but
a huge number especially when you think
about the fact that you probably want to
do drug screens for each of these. uh we
are now scaling this up together with a
with a bunch of friends across many
different labs and uh scaling this up
20fold or so um and screening many more
uh disease associated variants and now
we're faced with a new bottleneck which
is how do we do uh 200 drug screens and
maybe 4,000 drug screens once this large
data set is
created. So, so for that we we turn to a
technology uh developed um by JT Neil
and Paul Blay's lab here at the Broad.
Um uh and the idea is fairly
straightforward when I describe it like
this, which is to say that you just take
these 24 well plates uh and then you
pull you you you you plate each each
well with uh with the same with cells
coming from the same pool uh each cell
uh which is is uh is overexpressing one
of the 400 or so alals that we are
studying uh in this experiment which is
a mix of the uh disease caring causing
variance and the corresponding reference
alles. uh we then treat each well with
uh with a compound and then we look for
cases where the compound is rescuing is
reverting uh the signature of the
disease associated al back to looking
like a reference type right and that's
it that that's really what we're trying
to do here and of course there's a big
there's a big question as to how do you
how do you
um how do you deconvolute the pool to
figure out which cell got which which
protein and we we we took the same this
the we took a fair took the same
approach here which is that we first
stain the cells to mark the um to mark
the localization and to see whether
where the protein localizes and also
cell morphology using cell painting. We
wash those dyes off and then use a
technology you're all familiar with in
C2 sequencing to read out the barcode uh
that will help you identify uh which um
which protein was overexpressed in in in
which cell and that's about it.
Obviously a lot more to the protocol uh
than I described but essentially
technology a technology like this can uh
dramatically scale up um drug screens
and we have a pilot uh experiment
underway to to test this out. All right.
Uh I'll give a very quickly another
example as to whether we can use um you
know image based profiling to identify
gene function by grouping similar genes
and alals. And here uh in a large
collaboration including calico, we
knocked out every gene in in the human
genome uh by crisper and then used the
same pool bar coding technology and cell
painting um uh to to profile them. And
this allowed us to visualize the
phenotypic landscape of the several
thousands of genes that had a detectable
phenotype. we we saw meaningful clusters
emerge with neighborhoods of related
genes clustering together. There are
many more such examples of of using
imagebased profiling in this way and
these slides are available for download.
So you can look them up and especially
that that recent review article uh that
reviews the progress in this field over
the last decade would be a good way to
catch up on what's going on here. But I
will uh I will switch to now just
talking about about the data creation.
How do we now scale all this up? How do
we produce massive amounts of data so
that we can enable these discoveries but
then also train machine learning models
to help us make those discoveries? And
the approach that we took, we're we're a
small but mighty lab. So the the
approach that we took is is to create a
community uh throughout pharma around
this technology. We launched the uh the
jump cell painting consortium in 2019
uh through uh which comprised 10 pharma
companies and and several academic labs
u led by us and together uh across all
these labs we produced the world's
largest cell painting data set
comprising 136,000
u pertibbations uh spanning about
three-folds of the human genome either
overexpressed or knocked out and over
100,000 compounds um in it all this data
and and a lot of single cells that that
that is indeed a billion single 100 1.6
billion single cells. So all of this
data is publicly available on AWS um
thanks to their thanks to their
generosity. We don't pay the $50,000 it
takes to host it every month and uh you
can uh you can download that. We have
built tools to we built tools to explore
it. Um others have built tools to
explore it as well. You can check all
this out. uh and the the there's very
quick adoption of this in in uh in the
field. These are papers that just came
out within the first several months of
the of the data being released. Um this
encouraged us to launch another
consortium recently, the Oasis
consortium uh that is uh with many more
pharma companies and agrochemicals and
companies and and uh and academic groups
focused on a much narrower problem of uh
of predicting or being able to predict
liver toxicity of drugs uh in in humans
using uh cell painting uh data but then
also transcrytoics and other such omix
data to solve this very important
problem that JP referred to this morning
of uh the fact that 90% of drugs fail
and a lot of those a lot of that 90% is
actually toxicity. If we can do this
just using uh data like this using im
using imaging and other such
technologies that would be great. So
this data is also going to be coming out
and maybe I can chat a little bit about
that during our discussion. Uh all of
this data now allows us to solve a lot
of problems uh in biio medicine uh as
machine learning problems. Once you have
all this data, the problem of for
example learning representations of life
is you know needs needs a lot of data
and data that we generate through
consortia like this allow us allow us to
do that. uh we've been doing our own bit
in um creating benchmarks and data sets
for the machine learning community and
putting that out and also doing our own
uh bit in creating
um methods and and baselines for
representation learning because that's
something that we care about deeply uh
in this field. Um I am at the 20 second
mark so I am going to just stop there
and take the rest for our discussion and
thank our lab and all our collaborators
who have helped us along the way with
all of this.
Well, thank you Shantu for a fabulous
kickoff to the panel and for keeping it
on time because after we get each of the
four speakers talking for give or take
about 12 minutes. Um we're going to have
a general panel discussion where we'll
go deeper into all of these things. So
we shall immediately go to Shia Jwang
the David B. the Arnold Jr. Professor of
Science
um in the department of chemistry and
chemical biology at Harvard. Uh she is
an HHMI investigator and she is a
pioneer in developing me methods to look
at cells and beyond. So shall we thank
you very much for being here.
[Applause]
All right. So, uh
Oops. All right. Thank thank you Eric
for uh for moderating this exciting
panel and uh uh thank you uh Carolyn for
the for the uh kind invitation and uh
for 12 minutes I'll just I'm going to
talk about spatial genomics and
functional genomics and then usually I
give some introduction and so on and for
12 minutes I'm just going to skip all
that and then go directly to the uh uh
uh Murphish platform that We developed
that uh for spatial genomics and
functional genomics and then of course
you are aware of other spatial genomics
and functional genomics platforms and uh
you you've heard of Shatnu talking about
functional genomics already and Fchan
will talk more about spatial genomics.
So uh for Murfish let me just be uh very
brief without going into really the
details of what the method uh details of
the protocol but just to say the
capability. It is a genome scale imaging
approach that allow us to image uh
thousands or tens of thousands of genes
or genomic loi. And with these concepts
of uh uh aerobust barcoding uh
combinatorial labeling and sequential
imaging and with a combinatorial
approach it allow us to u image the
number of genes that grows exponentially
with the number of bits hence the number
of rounds. That's what allow us to scale
to thousands or or more more than 10,000
genes. And then of course with each uh
gene identified by multi-bit signal then
every bit the error accumulates over
multiple bits. Then the we uh develop
this error detection and correction
approach. So with that we can have
simultaneously high scalability and high
uh accuracy. And then this is a murfish
image of more than 10,000 genes. And
then uh I talk about cells too. So you
can see the cells individual dots are
RNAs that are colorcoded by their
genetic identity. So the ability to uh
do gene expression uh profiling unlike
single RNA sequencing in an imaging
approach we do it in situ without
destroying the spatial context. So with
that then we can identify through the
gene expression profile these cell types
in situ and then look into their uh
spatial organization which is critical
for tissue function and the cell cell
interactions and uh that has in my lab
we primarily use that for the brain and
uh many other labs have used it for a
variety of other uh tissues and organs
uh from model organisms to human. So,
uh, what I'm going to show you here is
just one such example that we did for
the whole mouse brain where we imaged
more than 1,000 genes in the about 10
million cells and then built the whole
cell al the cell atlas of the whole
mouse brain. We also integrated our
murfish data with the uh uh singles RNA
sequencing data taken by
our collaborator uh Alan Institute the
Hungu Jen's team uh in the same
consortium in parallel and then we uh
then even get the genomewide not only
identify the cell types in situ but also
can do a imputation to get the
genomewide expression profile of every
imaged genes.
And with that we can identify an
extraordinary diversity of cells diff
you know hundreds of different major
cell types and thousands of
transcriptionally distinct clusters and
their complex spatial organization. And
this is a scanning from the anterior to
posterior. Every dot every dot is a
cell. They're colored by their cell
type. And then you can query in an
interactive way uh of where different
types of cells are there in the
different uh brain area. And then uh
through their uh gene expression
profiles and uh uh spatial proximity we
can also infer cell interactions and
also the ligan receptor basis and
functional implications of these cell
cell
interactions. And uh you know speaking
of data being very useful for model we
also make our data very uh you know
publicly available in an interactive way
through this uh you know really
wonderful uh portal that Allen Institute
put together. So and then we also uh
extended murfish to do epigenomic
uh imaging and that's by using uh uh
antibbody recognizing epigenetic marks
and then fused to TM5 that cut the uh
epig genetic element into fragments and
then uh tag them and then image was
smurfish and then this labeling approach
is inspired by the cut and tac approach
uh pioneered Steven Hanukov and then we
can actually not only image the RNAs but
also image the epigenetic elements and
then study their correlation in terms of
how epigenomics connects to gene
expression and as you've heard from a
number of talks in the morning that the
3D genome organization is also an
important gene expression regulation
mechanism. We also extended murfish to
uh 3D genome imaging and in this case we
use murfish to identify genomic lossi
thousands of them and then
uh identify them and localize them so
that we can trace the 3D genome
confirmation and we can do it in
multimodal manner together with RNA so
that we can study the relationship
between gene expression 3D genome
organization all in a native tissue
context where we also label the uh
nuclear structures. So with the protein
marks such as nuclear oli and nuclear
lamina and the nuclear speckle and so
on. So that we can query that connection
between 3D genome organization and uh uh
transcription all in the native nucleus
context also directly in tissue in a
cell type specific manner by combining
RNA and DNA then we can see how
different cell types have different uh
3D genome organization. So uh and then
uh the I'm saving most of my time for
this last topic is functional genomics
and uh so from this kind of a genome
scale imaging measurements or other kind
of a genome scale imaging measurements
imaging or sequencing you know it's
really uh a wonderful way of collecting
a lot of data to describe the cell
states with a very high dimensionality.
So you learn a lot uh but that's still a
description. So if you want to know the
causality to say you know which gene
performs which function you know the
causality building the most powerful
approach is through genetic perturbation
such as crisper you know perturbation
and so on. So you delete the gene and
then see what kind of a function get
lost. So uh well after we developed
Murfish one of the first applications
that we thought is indeed using Murfish
to do imaging based pulled screening and
the pulled screening is very powerful
again as Shnu has already talked about
because you can query many many
perturbivations or the loss of many many
genes simultaneously in one sample and
each cell gets a different pertivation
and then you can try to measure their
phenotype difference. So then you can
build genotype phen phenotype maps in a
very high throughput manner. And then uh
if you do that by the traditional
approach such as fact sorting or cell
survival and so on the phenotype that
you can query is relatively simple. But
a lot of the cellular phenotypes are
really best measured by high resolution
imaging such as subcellular structures
dynamics and then also the imaging give
you the the the cell interaction the
spatial information even at the tissue
level so that you can see non- cell
autonomous effect one perturbed cell how
it affects neighboring cells and so on.
Now one of the challenges in terms of uh
this kind of imaging based to pull
genetic screening is after you image the
phenotype you got to see say hey which
cell got which perturbivation and then
with murfish then we thought of that
naturally because we could then link the
pertivation guide RNA and so on or even
a mutation of a protein base type of
mutation of a protein to a barcode and
then we can use the murfish to read out
the barcode and then this way. So uh so
we've published these couple of early on
papers both in terms of uh actually
screening out protein mutations and
screening out to crisper guide RNA in in
vitro system and then recently in
collaboration with Jonathan Weissman lab
we extended this to a multimodal invivo
p screening approach by actually uh
combining both murfish for imaging based
screening and perturb seek for sequence.
ing based screening all in tissue so
that we can we developed a lot of uh you
know protocols that allow us to both get
high resolution let me actually show you
the images protein images with
morphology preserved and then yet still
can measure many RNAs hundreds to
thousands of RNAs for transcriptional
profiling but in the same fixed tissue
sample we can do a perturb seek so that
we can get the transcripttonwide
uh phenotype so then as a demonst
Demonstration of that we actually
applied to the liver and then perturbed
hundreds of genes and read out the
phenotypes through both RNA and dozens
of morphology meaning protein imaging
and single cell perturb seek for uh
transcriptto while wide uh phenotype
imaging uh phenotype measurement with
this then it becomes a very high
throughput approach that allow us to
determine gene function and how genes
control cell and tissue function
directly in organ in vivo. So uh rather
than going details into these findings
uh but I do want to mention some of them
to show you that it is a very rich and
high throughput discovery approach. For
example, uh we actually find that uh for
those of you who know liver, you know
that liver has this beautiful zonation
pattern of the hpatocytes where cells
near the central vein and the
parapodoral region are uh quite
different in terms of their gene
expression profiles and functions for
hpatocytes. And then uh we actually
found a number of different previously
unknown genetic regulators that can
institute through transiffiation
actually change the zonation identity of
hpatocy. And uh also you can look into
really uh integral uh essential cell
stress pathways and ask the question of
uh hey whether these pathways can be
adapted for a organ specific or tissue
specific function. And one very
interesting thing that we found is that
such a highly conserved cell stress
pathway unfolded protein response
pathway in the liver has a specific
function and that it is to degrade the
uh plasma proteins that are secreted
such as elbooming a huge amount that are
secreted and then uh with unfolded
protein response we uh uh it actually
reduce you know substantially the mRNA
level of these plasma proteins so that
it reduce the folding burden of the ER
machinery. And then this final example
uh I see I'm
uh running out of time but let me say
this one is actually my favorite example
that really shows the power of combining
imaging and sequencing transcriptto wide
phenotype to see that we looked into
this phenotype which is very interesting
and very important p uh disease-wise.
It's the lipid accumulation or stosis.
And we found multiple different
pertivations can all induce this
physiological phenotype of stosis. But
they actually by doing the uh sequencing
uh genomewide sequencing to see which
genes gets upregulated down reggulated.
We found that this convergent fe
physiological phenotype or pathological
phenotype actually can go through
multiple different pathways. So whether
it's a lipid bio things as upregulation
or stress pathway upregulation and
others and so on. So with this uh let me
just uh end by saying that you know in
the uh th those of you who love
foundation model building or other
things for virtual cells and so on one
of the major missing thing the sparse
data is on the perturbation side. So
this functional genomics data will be
very helpful. So I'm sorry for not
having time to uh acknowledge the people
who have done the work and so uh so let
me just say that the last bit I do want
to because I spent time on it. It was a
very wonderful collaboration with
Jonathan Weissman and the uh my uh
former postto who's also independent
Harvard junior fellow will Allen now a
uh taking independent position at
Stanford and the Jonathan's graduate
student Ruben Saunders.
Fantastic.
Fantastic talk and also well compressed
into almost 12 minutes but well done.
Well done. Next up we have Fay Chen. Fay
is a core institute member at the Broad
and assistant professor in scrub the
department of stem cell and regenerative
biology at Harvard and he is building
tools that bridge single cell genomics
with space and time. So Fay, all
yours. Oh, and he was previously a
Schmidt fellow at the Broad.
All right. Does this work? Okay, great.
Uh I'm very impressed by how much
Shallow can manage to compress into our
12-minute talk. Uh and again, I usually
have introductory slides which I will
skip. uh because actually today's uh
sessions have really illuminated that
the fact that you know people are
thinking about spatial data all the time
uh and the interaction between spatial
and single cell data and I think
fundamentally a lot of us are interested
in this question of how are cells
organized and influenced by their
environment and how you can think about
that is that you might have cell types
and they might have transcriptional
changes you might call them cell states
but somehow in tissues in vivo that's
affected by what this thinking of you
know where does the cell live what it's
or cells what is the organization of
cell types around it what cells is it
interacting with and often times what is
it communicating with and then
ultimately how does this feed back to
shape a cell's identity and for a long
time we've really only been able to
study this uh in dissociated context and
I I won't belabor the point but I think
there's been new technologies that have
enabled us to start studying this uh in
taking genome omic measurements and
making them directly in the tissue
context and it's becoming extremely
scalable and I just added this just some
food for thought or maybe questions to
the parents that Eric mentioned what are
we going to talk about in this talk well
what can we learn from spatial data
maybe some what are some outstanding
modeling questions and then what about
uh the future for data collection not
the data for data collection okay and um
our lab uh has built some tools in the
past couple years uh on to measure the
transcriptto, the genome, as well as
other types of genomic features directly
in tissues. And a lot of this has been
focused on being able to capture the
mRNA, spatially barcode the mRNA onto
these arrays which allow you uh to
capture the XY location of sequences of
mRNA and DNA directly from your tissues.
And um this has been commercialized and
and there's a 10X also offers this
Vizium which is very similar. But
recently we've developed this technology
called slide tags which we believe is a
universal approach to jointly measure
single cells and then know where those
cells come from. And I'm just going to
take one minute to talk about the
technology before really talking about
what can we learn from this sort of
data. Um because the you know the data
modality is generally generalized across
all spatial data and and the concept
behind psychics is quite simple just
like perform your SQL cell sequencing
and know where your cells are from the
tissue. And so how this works is that
you can put a tissue onto an array of
barcoded beads and these beads encode
their XY location in a sequence barcode
and when these beads are also photo
cleavieable. So they get when you
photocle cleave them they actually
release this barcode into the cells and
then when you sequence the cells you get
for each cell a collection of barcodes
that barcodes where that cell came from
in XY. It's like GPS for the cell. And
so at the end of the day, you can just
perform single cell sequencing and you
know the XY location of the cell as well
as the gene expression across the
transcriptto at the single cell
resolution. You can also do single cell
for epigenomes etc. And so so there are
some advantages. It's true single cell
resolution is really high molecular
sensitivity and genomic and epigenomic
measurements. But for the purposes of
this talk, I I want to take a step back
and just talk ask what can we learn
about from spatial data because you know
at the end of the day you get this gene
expression matrix with XY coordinates.
So how are we going to think about or we
want to take away? Well, one idea that I
want to want the audience to take away
from this this talk is that you know um
changes in spatial context within a
tissue are often times you can almost
think of them as natural pertabbational
experiments where the pertibbation is
maybe your cell is experiencing a
different spatial context or a signal
different signaling environment and um
and then you can use that to maybe learn
something about what that pertubation
does to the cell or how does that change
the cell state. And you know, this h
probably happens in many different
contexts, but in particular, it probably
happens a lot in the immune system and
it probably happens a lot in in in the
cancer micro environment in the immune
system. And this this idea I think is
kind of cool because you can allow it
allows you to measure these sorts of
perturbational effects in human samples
where perturbations are often not
feasible. Um I think maybe this you know
for that interest of time there's just
many types of cells in the tumor micro
environment and they might assume
different states and they have different
interactions and importantly probably
the functions of these cells and their
interactions are directly maybe
therapeutically relevant. We have many
therapies that take advantage of um
check such as checkpoint blockcade or T-
cell therapies that take advantage of
interactions of cells or the states of
cells. Um and so I'll just give you an
example in uh melanoma about how we
think about one how tissue organization
is related to the state of cells and
then I'll talk to you about something
about how we might use these natural
perturbational experiments. So here we
just applied some slide tags data to um
you know just a takeaway from this is
that we applied some tags data to
melanoma specimens. We can reconstruct
single cell data directly into the
spatial context and you find that there
are different here are the tumor cells
and you find that the tumor cells
exhibit transcriptional variability and
that this transcriptional variability
maps directly into different spatial
contexts and not only are they
transcriptionally variable they also
arise from different genomic clones. So
there's some evolutionary process that's
driving the transcriptional variability
as as well as the spatial localization.
And one question then you have is that
you know um is this is this spatial
variability related to uh the intera
like does the does the transcriptional
variability at all related to its
environment? And so uh you know just
using some simple cell type
compositional analysis. We've talked a
lot about niches but you know one the
base analysis is just looking at the
relative composition of nearby cells. We
can find that one of these states is
very enriched in T- cells and another
state is very depleted in T- cells. So
there's these two regions and they have
different environments. They also are
enriched and depleted in a lot of other
stromal cells. And this this this
enrichment in CD8 T cells in particular
piqu our interest. And when you sequence
the TCRs, you can see that there's this
part particular TCR clone. So these are
the TCRs are like the sequences for the
T- cell receptors and that's what they
use to recognize the antigens. And
there's this particular clone which is
associated with one tumor clone. This is
like kind of a very surprising result.
Nobody has been able to sequence TCRs
and uh in space. And so um so here you
can see the purple dots represent one
this particular clone and the gray dots
represent the TCRs for all the other
clones. Um and so this is actually one
of the first times we can observe
directly T- cell clonality linked to a
specific genetic tumor clone. Now the
question is is this linked to the
antigen? Is this linked to the state?
We're not exactly sure, but what we're
doing is we're systematically collecting
lots and lots of uh melanoma specimens
and we're we're discovering uh it with
the spatial data and we're discovering
just as a highlight that there's a
direct coupling between micro
environmental niches and the tumor cell
states. So there I showed you one
example of there these two tumor clones
and they're associated with different
environments. We find that over this is
30 different tumors that here are
different tumor cell states or
transcriptional programs and these
include genetic clones but also just
environment like transcript true
transcriptional programs such as
interferon response or this
differentiation trajectory and they're
associated with particular niches. For
example, there's this particular
immunosuppressive niche that we're
finding quite interesting that's
associated with this differentiation and
this transitory neuropressant type which
is actually related to this T- cell
enrichment uh that you saw in the
previous sample. So that's this idea
that you know you can go and uncover uh
transcriptional lineage heterogeneity in
cancer cells and you know you get to ask
this question of like what what actually
dominates um these cellular communities.
Is it cell intrinsic states and lineages
that are shaping uh these interactions
or cell intrinsic environments? And I
just want to you know highlight one
initial example for for this idea that
local communication pathways are are
perturbations and that's this example um
actually in in a different cancer but
this idea that um well the sustained
growth factor is actually signaling is a
hallmark of cancer. from some cancers
instead of needing to mutate the
pathways uh that drive growth factor
signaling they co-opt their micro
environment to get them to supply these
signals in particular in Hodkkins
lymphoma only one to 2% of the cells are
tumor cells and they're surrounded by a
unique micro environment and you know
perhaps you can use this idea of this
intrinsic perturbation experiment to
identify what micro environmental
factors are are actually causing the
survival in this in these rare cancer
cells and that's What we did, we
performed it on very few samples. But I
think the key is that the intrinsic
variability gives you a lot of power and
we did a simple analysis. We just looked
at the enrichment of lians next to tumor
cells. And these lians that are enriched
next to these tumor cells, we postulated
might be ones that are responsible for
uh paracquin signaling actions
interactions that cause survival. And
when you do that you find um a list of
uh you find a list of immunosuppressive
and growth factors enriched as
paracqurine signals in particular 13 and
I 13 alpha uh alpha and we we have a
bunch of other supporting evidence but
importantly there are therapeutic
antibodies that have already been
approved that we then can test and see
that when you block I3 signaling you can
uh basically suppress tumor growth. Um,
and so this is kind of cool. So we we
leverage the intrinsic heterogeneity in
the sample in very few samples to
identify paracqurine growth sample
signals that support uh the growth of
these tumor cells and then it generated
this testable therapeutic hypothesis. So
like can we do this more more
systematically? Like can we just like
leverage this idea of changes in spatial
context, neighborhoods, interactions and
s signaling as natural
probab the samples uh the this data um
we today we really talked about and and
these are problems that we're all
working on. We need to think about how
we define the organization of tissues uh
including you know how we assign cell
types and segmentation and these base
level analyses but also how do we like
think about what an environment is if
we're thinking about the environment as
a perturbation we have to be able to
define these environments and we have to
be able to compare them between samples
although I just said that you know
comparing them within a sample is better
but you might also want to compare them
between samples right and we might want
to then have really strong statistical
frameworks
uh to look at uh differential expression
and these signaling
interactions. Okay, so this is modeling.
I won't talk we're working on these but
I won't talk about them because it's
been talked about a lot today. And then
I think we need to also collect
different types of data like one area of
data that we're excited about you know
to collect is how does like mutations
and somatic variation affect uh tissue
organization function. This is another
axis of intrinsic variation and I won't
get go into the details but we're
starting to collect true like single
cell genome sequencing and transcryto
sequencing directly in space. The other
thing I think we need to do is we need
to really scale the amount and the type
of data. I like really do believe that
we need true sequencing true single cell
sequencing data and I think single cell
sequencing has been scaling
exponentially and so we need to develop
new technologies to really exponentially
scale the measurement of spatial data
and uh we've been doing that in some
ways to make it extremely extremely
cheap and then lastly I think we need
systematic approaches for manipulating
cellular communities in vibo which shall
we talked about but we're also excited
about awesome
[Applause]
Fantastic. And thank you for the
homework list. Uh so clearly stated
there. Um we have one more talk and then
we're going to have a panel. Um and
we're going to start with a panelists
asking each other questions, but then we
will turn to the audience to jump into
the conversation as well. So you should
begin thinking about the questions you
want to be asking during the
conversation. But I have the
extraordinary happiness to introduce
Mark Daly with whom I have been working
for nearly 40 years. That's a terrifying
thought, but a very happy thought
because it's been a very fun nearly 40
years. Um Mark is an institute member at
the Broad Institute. He's the
co-director of the program in medical
and population genetics. Um he's the
founding uh chief of the analytical and
translational genetics unit at MGH and
uh for a number of years he was living
in Helsinki
um while still having at least one foot
here in Boston as the uh director of the
Institute of Molecular Medicine in
Finland which I'm sure will become clear
that Mark is is deeply deeply thoughtful
about populations all over the world. So
tell us about organisms and their
genomes. I will. So I have the privilege
of being at the start and the end of the
cycle if you will. Um the earliest stage
which we focus on for my entire career
anyway. Um because of the unique causal
arrow that can be drawn between the
human genome variation that you're born
with and your disease outcomes over your
life course. Um it has been demonstrated
but we won't go into details about it um
with systematic analysis or if you
prefer with notable examples that the
discovery of genetic variance even
through population studies such as I'll
describe is a valid and strong entry
point that enriches for ultimate
clinical success. Um, the last 20 years
of many of our lives have been spent
getting a little bit older as you can
probably see from that uh slide, but
have been spent in compiling massive
data sets of human genome variation and
through population studies and
phenotypes linking those to diseases.
And I'll go into a few examples. Um, but
that's not where I want to focus your
attention because the genetic links
between variation and disease outcome is
largely an intellectually solved problem
over the last 20 years from constructing
the foundations of the first G-W was
studies when the broad was first opening
its doors. Um there has been dramatic
discoveries of tens of thousands of
variants associated to rare and
mandelian disease, common protein,
common protein coding variants
associated to common diseases and tens
of thousands of cancer driver mutations.
And in addition, we've still barely
scratched the surface in how we
interpret the many of those findings
that are in non-coding regions of the
genome. So with that in mind, I think
finding the genes is not the problem.
The problem is really this is really
challenging to read and interpret and
what is its impact on patients
ultimately and it hasn't been that
great. As I said, there are good handful
of examples, but there's clearly a huge
gap in our ability to learn from this
data. So, briefly, the progress that
we've been making in human genetics, I
just exemplify it with some results from
inflammatory bowel disease. We're not
going to go into um you heard some
studies earlier about that. Um over the
course of the last 20 years of
genomewide association studies, these
have been almost uniquely successful in
inflammatory bowel disease. And then
over the last 10 years, we've added on
top of that the genome exo sequence of
nearly a 100,000 inflammatory bowel
disease patients, which is quite an
accomplishment for a disease that's not
that common in the human population. Um,
with this, of course, there are dozens
and dozens of low frequency coding
variants conclusively linked to disease.
And we've done this not just in IBD,
we've done it in schizophrenia. We can
compare and contrast the results. each
of them produce quite plentiful results
at this level. But while individual
pinpoints on these graphs might be
informative and allow you to um begin a
drug targeting activity, it's hard to
put the whole story together and to make
sense of it in a way that would really
describe that we are understanding
disease. Um I won't go into natural
selection as a factor but you find lots
of things whether there's natural
selection or not acting against it. Um
so we moved on to over the last decade
to focus on bioanks because and the text
at the bottom would say it seemed to us
to be the time to move from looking at
one disease at a time to looking at all
diseases simultaneously sort of
everywhere all at once or what have you.
Um, I moved to Finland, um,
particularly, most notably because of a
tremendously favorable and progressive
legal structure that would allow you to
do a nationwide project with really no
barriers whatsoever, as you can see
here. So, this is what Arno Pelote and I
built. And what it allows you to do is
consent a person to join this study and
you immediately have a vast array of
lifelong phenotypic data from all of the
medical contacts that this person has
ever had. What this looks like in
reality is some of these data sources
that are mandated by law and have been
for more than 50 years to be collected
and entered into a single national
database. Although there are many
different databases depending on the
type of data. This is all available for
data for research um use. And to take
one example, the last 10 years, you know
how you have a patient portal? Well, you
can go to your patient portal and see
your lab values. We can essentially go
to 500,000 people's patient portal and
see all of their clinical lab values
over the last 10 years. And so what this
creates for us is a data resource that
we've added genomes to, but is primarily
powered by the fact that we have nearly
on a on the order of 1,000 clinical
medical data points per individual,
including all of their prescription
medications that have ever been filled,
all of their procedures, um, primary
care, tertiary care, etc.
Um, on top of the discoveries in human
genetics, you might ask, what's the
value addition to if we already found a
500 genes for IBD and 500 genes for
schizophrenia, what's the value add?
There's the longitudinal aspect. As I
said, this data goes back 50 years. and
human genetics approaches have really
not been concerned with what are really
the primary drivers of interest in the
pharmaceutical industry which is
stopping disease over time after it
already starts not simply not predicting
it in
advance. There are a huge number of
undeser underserved diseases and
populations that need great attention.
And as you can imagine, those that have
not been funded are generally in
underserved populations or having to do
with women's and reproductive health and
many other topics that just haven't been
popular for funding. Um, but there's
many more opportunities and needs for
the follow-up work after discovery that
I think bioanks can serve. But the one
that I wanted to point out that I think
is a great opportunity for AI and ML
approaches is exemplified on this
picture. Each dot here represents a
clinical data point, a diagnosis, a
prescription medication, a procedure.
And these are two men, both alive today,
both age 80. And we can see visually
here what is a definition of healthy
aging. And this is I think when people
talk about studying aging and studying
you know healthy aging and so forth what
they have in mind is the person on the
far side of the screen who has up until
about age 75 had no medical procedures
or any contact with the medicali system
outside of getting prescribed
antibiotics a few times as opposed to
the individual on the right. And so our
studies of aging and longevity can and
must go much further than simply
assessing how long did everybody
live. So where do we go from here? I
want to highlight a few exciting things
that might help us begin to fill the
huge gap between massive discovery of
thousands or tens of thousands of
variants and very few new therapeutic
concepts that come through.
Basically, cut a long story short,
discovery of genetic variants is pretty
straightforward compared to interpreting
what those tell us about the biology of
disease and how we might reverse it. So,
we'd like to be able to move
systematically from point A to point B.
But how do we do it? And so the first
step is I've told you that you know
we've essentially solved genetic
discovery that there are literally tens
of thousands of gene variants associated
to disease. So step one you might ask
where do I go to tap into all this
wonderful data and the problem is you
reach quickly reach the conclusion that
it's massively siloed and that actually
nobody has put together the data from
all of these diverse sources of insights
all of which could be valuably deployed.
um and and assessed with
AI. So such a catalog could be in
principle incredibly powerful. We could
learn from protein structure. We could
learn from the plyotropy across many
diseases of where there are variants
that are shared. And I'll give you a few
examples of those. But that just really
begins to scratch the surface into what
we could do if we really computationally
apply ourselves to everything that's
been discovered thus far. Um, one way to
do that is to tap into the unique
opportunity that happens over and over
in the genome where distinct single
genetic variants influence multiple
diseases and many of them group together
to influence multiple diseases. And that
gives us a little bit of an insight when
you think about it into
um the potential for exposing and
understanding potentials. the shared
mechanisms between diseases and grouping
distinct mechanisms within a disease. So
study of gestational diabetes, we
realized when we were building the finen
resource that all of a sudden somebody
woke up one day and said we have a data
set to study gestational diabetes that's
twice as large as the world's largest
publication to date. So they did that um
and discovered with you know simple good
oldfashioned basian statistics that
there were actually two distinct um
modes of genetic variant associations to
type 2 diabetes in the general
population and gestational diabetes
separately. One of them that was
predominantly or uniquely affecting
gestational diabetes.
different example. Um when we started
looking into um as we often do
autoimmune and inflammatory diseases, we
stumbled across the observation that
autoimmune hypothyroidism and skin
cancer shared an enormous number of
associations. Almost 10% of the variants
associated to hypothyroidism were
associated to skin cancer, but nearly
all of them in the opposite direction.
So what was causing risk for
autoimmunity was protecting against skin
cancer. And as it turns out, what was
being uncovered here was simply the
signature of what at at a low level in
the population of what
um the immune immunotherapies in cancers
are actually doing. And in fact, the
same genes are at play in this
signature. And you can strongly see that
genetics, if we didn't already know it
from the success of imunotherapies,
support strongly the idea that increased
levels of immune surveillance put you at
risk of autoimmunity but protect you
from cancer.
So quickly in the last you know few
examples um we have another challenge
and just shifting gears for a moment
that's in a you know I think a pretty
interesting area um that we haven't
really gotten much out of the rare
genetic variants that we've been
identifying in all these sequencing
studies um because every time you might
encounter one variant that causes a
disease there are many many around it
that are rare and simply neutral in the
background and so What Hillary Finane
and Share Gerggas and others in
Hillary's group have taken on is the
idea that we might map our case control
data onto protein structure and get much
further with identifying not only what
the genes are relevant to rare diseases
but also importantly figuring out what
mechanisms might be at play. They did
this in the case of one particular
plasma membrane calcium transporter in
schizophrenia that had a relatively
interesting but not convincing
association with 66 rare variants in
cases and 191 seen in
controls. However, when structurally
mapping these variants, you could see
highly significant evidence that they
cluster in one or two neighborhoods in
the gene. in fact pointing directly to
the location where the calcium ion binds
in the transporting process.
So finally just in closing the main
challenge we really then look forward to
is how do we move beyond simply
discovery but inferring mechanism from
experimental work and just to highlight
the last place where I think there's
huge opportunity in integration of data
across these modalities um cell atlases
and especially disease relevant cell
atlases and I'm sure you're aware of
some of these exciting papers that have
been published in recent I think create
a great opportunity and so we've been
expanding on this concept to link not
only you know these cell atlases you
know do them at a at a higher scale but
also do them in individuals that are
from the finen resource and have full
profiling available to them and so in
doing this Masakana in Romnik Xavier's
lab has developed a resource not only
that has on the order of a 100,000 and
eqls in PBMC's and 100,000 um chromatin
accessibility QTLs but can connect these
also to the life history and clinical
history and those thousand data points
per person in each of those individuals.
So I will close there and just leave a
few thoughts where I think large data
sets are being developed in the space of
the human organism and the DNA that
definitely can be benefit from and are
seriously undermined right now with
respect to what could be obtained
through AI and ML approaches.
[Applause]
Thank you Mark. Um yeah, amazing what
what uh one can do from turning the
uh the whole health care system into a
learning system. Um someday we'll do
this in the United States as well. Would
that be cool?
Ye of little
faith. All right. Can I invite our
speakers up to the table
and I'm going to ask them first
to ask questions of each other and then
you all will jump in and I might ask
questions occasionally. You never know.
Um okay. Pick any
order. So, what do you want to
know? What do you want to say?
Does this work? Does it work? Testing.
Say, does it work? Maybe just start. Um,
can you hear him? Can I Can you hear us
at the back all the way? Yeah, you got
to talk like right into the microphone.
Right into it. Okay. I'll I'll I'll try
to be like Eric. All right. Uh I will u
I'll probably start with um just asking
you all as to and Mark you you alluded
to this towards the end but I couldn't
capture it all as as to what problem in
your fields do you think are at the
brink of being solved and you have the
data for it uh but what it needs is
probably AI methods to solve it. I I use
AI very grudgingly because I I don't
like that term but you know things that
are complicated too late now. Yeah. Um
so that that's a broad question.
That is a broad question. Um you know I
think what we're trying to do is you
know
identify you know the mechanisms of
disease so that we can ultimately
reverse them. I think you know the the
potential integration across OMIX
modalities with the DNA and with the
health history offers us a great
opportunity for that but we are not
close to the computational approaches
that would need
to really learn from that. So what do
you need
a lot of smart people to you know
aggregate all the data and then start
working on it. I think I mean the data
is you know falling into place
don't see that as such a limitation
right now right so you're aggregating
the data even you know slowly wrangling
all this stuff and so computational
methods what do we need so can I ask
follow question a bit AI gets used in in
different ways there's
is foundational models that are, you
know, throw everything in and stir and
do an excellent job of predicting
something. And then there's I'm
caricatururing, guys. I'm just
caricaturing, forgive me. And then
there's kind of like building up
particular mechanistic things. How much
do we need of each of those for getting
this into medicine?
I'm not sure. I Well, I mean, basically,
so we need a lot more of the latter.
Which was the latter?
Building up mechanisms. So, you want
things that build up mechanisms rather
than make predictions. Yeah. And the and
the assertion that I would make is that
we have glimpses of that when we look
across diseases. We have glimpses of
that when we look across, you know,
associations in the single cell data.
And we have glimpses of it in a couple
of other of these dimensions, but
nothing that's putting together the full
picture in a way that's internally
consistent and that would convince you
that this and this and this are actually
mechanisms of disease.
Good. Keep asking each other questions.
I was really I I was telling Hillary
also that I'm just so impressed by
um oh I I I'm just so impressed by we
are impressed Hillary by um you know
this idea of enriching the rare
misssense varants onto the structure of
of
proteins and actually I'm just impressed
by how much information there is in
these language model protein language
model embeddings and so so I'm just
curious about you know How do you think
we'll be able to get
um do you think we need to collect more
rare variant data where it's not even
associated necessarily with disease
phenotypes in that way like you know
Shant um Shantu showed like these
imaging phenotypes of varants like can
we use that sort of thing to discover
the functions of prote mechanisms of
proteins more systematically in a way um
that's not just about I mean I I don't
want to say that's not just about G-W
was but you know in a way that's more
generalizable.
I'm afraid that's a human genetics
question.
So I think I think and so if we look at
the human population and we ask where do
rare varants occur or not occur and we
had I don't know 100 million people how
far would we go? So you think about
things like the Nomad database. Tell us
you know what can we learn by looking?
So yeah we're we have you know on the
order of a million to a few million
genomes sequenced and I think we can do
a lot of that already. I think when we,
you know, what we get to with those
analyses are, you know, identification
of
specific domains, specific structural
elements where mutation is not
tolerated.
That's not the be all end all of human
disease because you know obviously
there's a great many diseases that don't
really have that delletterious a effect
on reproductive fitness and we're
interested in those just as well. So,
but you can certainly learn a lot from
that. I think where we can also is just
by looking at these patterns of limited
variation whether it's structure based
or or what have you across proteins with
similar structures and that's going to
help us you know further zero in on the
particular functional elements that are
right. So you actually you think you can
aggregate misssense mut you think you
can aggregate misssense
mutations around proteins with similar
structures? We know we can done this you
know ago with you know simple examples
like sodium channels and calcium
channels and so forth.
Right. Right. So human genetics is the
kind of mutational screens you want to
do because it's it's off doing it
anyway. Can I ask you guys about the
tissues projecting forward 10 years from
now? Where are we going to
be? You know, you can talk either
methodologically, you could talk about
the reach of it, you can talk about its
uses in clinical medicine. Where are we
going to be?
Actually all of those are uh I think
very interesting directions but I was
going I I want to pivot this a little
bit to to to my observation today
towards predictive uh models and so on
that I see today. You know you can and
identify a missing you know a a gap. So
you see a lot of this foundation model
or deep learning models that helped so
much in towards the structural
prediction of protein and so on. And
then you see the foundation models in
terms of describing cell states and so
on. But then when describing the cell
states it's more of like a a molecule
list of the cell right you know a vector
of pro profiling and so on. But the cell
is not just a list of things of which
genes expressed or not. It's like a
structure, you know, it's a lot of
interaction networks and so on. And when
it gets to tissue, it's the same. It's a
network. I mean, it's getting to a
little bit of your question. It's a ne
network of cells that interact. At that
level, you see a lot less of this
predictive uh powerful deep learning
model going towards that direction.
Although if you think about it uh you
know at the protein structure level, it
is a structure model. But then at the
cell level and tissue level it's more of
a list model rather than a structure
model and those structure interactions
are very important for you know
understanding eventually the mechanisms.
No, I don't know whether for curing
diseases because sometimes you find out
the mutation and then you can do you
know maybe eventually the gene editing
kind of therapy and so on but for a lot
of us who are uh curiositydriven for
understanding biology deeply we do want
this kind of a level of mechanistic
understanding that has the molecu
molecule interaction the network the
salo interaction network. So how do
computation and AI help on that
direction is something that bothers me
daily now you know when when I keep
thinking about these large predictive
models in that direction.
FA yeah I I just wanted to add that
protein protein interactions are are
something that is you know both bridges
this well maybe we can use misssense
varants actually in human genetics study
protein protein interactions but maybe
we can also use spatial genomics study
protein protein interactions and
something that's actually very
mechanistically powerful and also
missing from our data actually um maybe
I'll just ask answer Eric's question
more directly oh good I was going to
come back to it anyway. So, go for it.
Well, I I I I I think that, you know, a
lot of us believe uh that we're going to
be able to systematically collect the
comprehensive catalog of cellular
programs, which are gene modules that
cells use to define their function and
their states and their types. And how
are we going to do that? Well, we'll
probably actually right now we're trying
to do that in single cell, but I think
we'll probably what we'll do is we'll
learn it completely from spatial data
because you know there's most cell types
in the body you can't dissociate
eased by the interactions of of the
cells and
um and that's going to be I think quite
quite a powerful way to repres represent
biology where you you have your programs
and then you have some way of just
saying like a tissue you know is
composed of cells of these types and
they act have these programs and they
communicate with each other through
these modules and that's how they change
change the programs that they're
undergoing and then that's the base case
for health and then you can start using
that for all of disease so it's just
like I think we're not that far actually
from collecting that data and generating
that sort of analysis.
Um, that's basic research. But I think
there's probably also some a lot of like
clinical translation of of the spatial
data because especially in the
integration with like hisystologology
models because
um it might be really challenging to
collect and I think it will remain
challenging to collect spatial
transcripttoics data in the clinic
because from what you know I visited MGH
pathology and they were like you know
it's been 20 years since we started
collecting fluorescent IHC but we can't
convince the clinicians to routinely
collect it all the time or something and
so I think there's just a lot of
ingrained method methodology but you
know that's a place where ML can really
take these images and transfer the
learnings about like molecules onto
those images and that's something that's
quite exciting and we don't have to
change anything about how clinical
practice is done that's well okay it is
sometimes worth changing clinical
practice practice by the way. Well,
maybe we can do it in 10 years. Maybe 10
years is hard. Although I I note the
resistance of cancer uh specialists in
looking at gene mutations. There was a
time that they were they didn't want to
do any of that sequencing. Then they
felt you should do 20 genes, then a
panel of 300 genes, then okay, a whole
exo, and now whole genomes. And
eventually as we see it's valuable one
can change it but okay so so maybe
they're not going to do it immediately.
Um
still how far can we go from taking
ordinary images collected in the course
of pathology and
reconstructing the entire transcriptto
or proteome or whatever. How sanguin or
say the three of you from the jump
consortium and from the things you do
we'll start with you Shantu
how much is in that image so
amongst gene
expression maybe new gene transcription
chromatin structure and protein levels
can I reconstruct all that by just
looking part.
So I I don't know about those specific
things. I just made this up but I mean
just answer whatever you want but but
but in general uh the way I've been
viewing uh viewing imaging and that's
why I use the term uncanny uh because
you know when you look at those images
it's very hard to believe that you know
those images contain enough information
for you to be able to
recapitulate pathways be able to find
mechanism of action of drugs be able to
predict other readouts and it is still
uncanny to me every time it happens
although I've been doing this for 15
years right so I I don't know it's
possible I think It's I mean especially
the the examples that you gave
specifically are possible but I think in
in general um you know sort of combine
the two questions you asked the one you
asked me and the one you asked Feyen uh
is that I think uh what we will see in
the next 10 years along these lines is
that we will hopefully start doing
things uh we we'll start doing the
things that we doing right now but
cheaper powered by predictive methods.
methods in the sense that we will have a
lot of data that is expensive to collect
and we've been collecting it right now
and then we'll have a lot of data that
is cheap to collect. I'm giving the
example of histologology for example and
and and anything downstream and I think
you'll be able to do increasingly better
job of being able to predict the
expensive stuff and this is really the
benefit of any supervised learning
technique right uh so for example we're
already seeing that in our field of
image based profiling where uh we we
stain you know cell the cell painting
die set is fairly standard now in the
field uh but I don't think it will be
used in five years I I think in five
years we will only need to collect
bright field images and companies is
already doing this and just be able to p
predict those five stains for example
dramatically reduces your cost. Um but
also scales things up allows you to do
live cell imaging and things like that.
Um I'm trying to get back to the the
main question that asked me I I think
you you can predict a lot of complex
things. We there's this whole could get
into it but one sort of direction in
which our field takes this work is is
predicting complex assays. being able to
predict uh the the outcome on a zebra
fish screen using using cell painting
images of cells in a very specific uh
lung abnor cell right who would say
there's any correlation I can't say
there's a correlation by looking at
those cells but given enough data and
careful training we seem to be able to
do that so I'm very optimistic about it
very optimistic about it cautiously so
and which is why I'm sort of looking to
the ML community to tell us you know how
do we do do this uh more in a more
principled way in a more uh in a more
um with with more harnesses um and uh I
I'll stop there probably come back to
this thread but show yeah so I I think
the verdicts is out but there's more and
more data in terms of the joint data in
the same sample that has both
hisystologology and imunofllororesence
and uh sort of a transcriptto kind of a
data and then We've tried a little bit
uh and I mean the kind of data that we
have perhaps is not large enough and
then we did find that for example with
the last bit that I showed that we
weren't able to predict the cell state
with the you know 20 kind of protein
labels and so on but that doesn't mean
ultimately you know with enough of label
you cannot but with a large amount of
label then you also start to wonder is
that a cheaper way because the
transcrytoics imaging is not necessarily
as it keeps scaling not not going to be
cheaper than the protein imaging but
what I like is the connection of them
whether it is a way to predict with a
cheaper approach it is a connection that
at least for understanding biology we
have to build you know between the trans
you know the the molecular programs and
the the morphology and the you know the
protein the dynamics the network and so
on just even for the fundamental
understanding of biology which of course
eventually will lead to benefit in
medicine. So that kind of a connection
is going to sooner or later be built. I
mean that's why we spent so much time
working on imaging you know both
modalities and so on. We should let some
more folks into the conversation. Yes,
I shouldn't throw that.
Yeah, but you could shout. I think
they'll hear you. No, talk to the
microphone. I'm loud enough. generally
loud enough they won't hear you on the
internet. Yeah, it it's a fantastic
conversation. I just
we were talking you I think Mark was
talking about like there's a lot of data
and we can aggregate it now. I think
that's partly true and it's also not
true in really critical ways. So if you
look at where foundation models and
large models have been showing a bit of
promise, it's generally on data that
does aggregate. So sequences for DNA or
for proteins and things like um atomic
distances for structure. when you look
at stuff like expression data, it's a
nightmare to train a model on it doesn't
aggregate well. It's still full of batch
effects, you know. So, um or and what
ends up happening is like Jiao was
saying, you just dumb down the task that
you're asking the model to do to a point
whereby it kind of works, but then it's
not much use for anything. So, like how
do we get to the point? So, a am I
please tell me I'm wrong and b like if
I'm not, what do we do to address that?
Because that to me feels like a major
blocker. We need to have a global effort
to aggregate data that is consistent
enough to train large models and it
doesn't feel like we're doing it yet.
Actually, I don't think you're wrong.
Actually, I think you're right on
target. I mean, whole organism data,
especially human data, is messy. I mean
we're dealing with real world data and
on the clinical side and then even on
the biopecimen and and transcryto side
proteome side there's a huge amount of
variability. The proteome especially is
incredibly sensitive to environments
like 10 times more than it is respon
responsive to what's in your genome. So
it will take you know a considerable
effort I think just to have technical
compatibility across studies around the
world. So not a task to be overlooked. I
think it it's worth noting that sequence
didn't used to look so good either. It
took an awful lot of quality control
before sequence became combinable across
places. All the genome centers in the
human genome project just hated doing
the roundrobin quality controls because
it showed that you had mistakes and you
had other things. It's possible that
what's needed and maybe you should help
drive it is to say that anybody who's
developing new methods should be running
you know data sets that are in parallel
being you can ask can I properly
translate this from method A to method
B. I don't have to do it identically,
but I need a very good translation. And
people should not be allowed to publish
data without the ability to do that. And
that's a lot of computational work to to
sort of validate that this can be
translated from one to another rather
than just later, you know, saying it's
batch effects. We got to have the
internal controls within it that tell
you how to correct inherent in it. So,
make that happen. Yes. Next question. Uh
I I have a comment on on the question.
Oh please. Yes. So I actually think this
aggregation being able to put together
all kinds of data that has batch effect
is a very important computational method
and there are ways that one could
envision to do that. It's not impossible
and it will be very important as a
success. Uh but just be mindful while
doing that. There are technical art you
know batch artifacts and so on but some
of those are also true biological
variations because of the conditional
differences. So when the aggregation
power is too strong in the computational
power it can also cause the loss of some
of those actually important biological
variations. So a balance between that
but I do think it's a uh it's a good
computational problem. Of course, as
experimentalists ourselves, so we will
try to standardize and remove this. But
it is a very interesting and
intellectually uh uh important challenge
to overcome. We have a question over
here. Hi, thank you for your talk. So my
question is related to what have you
have seen the said a few minutes about
the qual the quality of the data and I
am no machine learning scientist. So
everything today was really really new
news for me. But I am a super resolution
microscopy scientist. So I try to see
this the things from from the inside to
the nanoscopic level to the outside. And
there are I have there there are another
ways to try to simulate the biological
data but it requires a lot of curation.
B based on my context, I I see that all
your
methods it looks like you input as a
after after you finalize the the the
analysis. But how about curation before
using that data for
the for the input of the machine
learning methods? Let let me add you two
more things. Um in the case of uh FA
there's a new paper about the antibbody
of transumap the for for can breast
cancer cell about that the way it it
works it's it was it's not about
blocking the receptor but generating a
second uh response. So, so that kind of
things will be
really diff um maybe they can
be I'm very Why don't we give the
question to Fay? Yeah,
you seem to be No, I I I have three. May
I finish my three because I think one
one is mine. I think I think maybe
you're you're saying maybe the data
needs to be curated before it goes into
ML algorithms but I I I think I think
the community actually spends a lot of
time
curating certainly actually all of our
data transcriptto data or imaging data
um you know there's certainly in single
cell you know I think people it's become
more mature although we can still argue
about how much curation is being done uh
as we pull data sets but one nice thing
is is that all of the data in our
community is actually downloadable
whether it's spatial or single cell or
anything. And so um people are
constantly revisiting this task of data
curation and data integration actually
speaking to Lindsay. So so I do think it
is a problem that people are aware of
and we're we're doing it. It's just not
that sexy I guess. So maybe there's
maybe more people should be doing it
than they are
already tools should be doing it or
maybe AI tools should be doing it. Yeah.
So, you know, a lot of the algorithms I
see out there and, you know, um
sometimes guilty as charged is people
say, "Oh, here's something that the
machine learning community, you know,
developed, you know, transformer,
whatever. We're going to plug it as is,
you know, some chat GPT or or whatever
directly on biological data because it
sort of mapped this that to the other."
But actually if we look and everyone you
know uses AlphaFold look the LLM worked
but actually in in Alphafold uh it you
know it wasn't out of the box they
actually took evolutionary conservation
and that was a major thing that allowed
it certainly the earlier versions to
work and I feel that we have that sort
of a little bit missing in in in other
areas. So as you know people who are
closest to the data and all its warts
what type of like biological insights
are missing and could possibly be
encoded into these architectures to make
them better. Um can I I can take that.
So I I really enjoyed your talk, Dana,
because you talked about like that we
should work on algorithms that make
practical biological discoveries versus
algorithms that are super fancy, which I
am resonate with a lot 100% 100%.
And um but but I your question was a
little bit different which is that what
what sorts of information that we know
exist in biology that we can leverage um
I think into the architecture I can just
give I can give an example like Caroline
and I are working on something um
together uh uh there's a EWSC fellow
working on it which you know we did try
to take this is a good example actually
because we took we tried to do what you
said because we were like, oh, we'll
just take the offtheshelf thing and
we'll apply it to the biological data
because, you know, it worked in alpha
fold or it worked in um ESM fold and and
I think what happened was that um it
didn't work actually because there's
there's features about bio the data that
there there there's um uh uh naive like
uh naive solutions that can find about
biology that are not interesting like
just like the local composition of cells
is highly predictive of what you're
going to be. And that's like you can
know that, but it's like not an
interesting thing to learn. And you
know, one thing that we realized was
that if you take into account that
tissues are
hierarchical, right? And if you can
design an architecture that leverages
the hierarchy of the the the tissue, you
actually learn things that are not
trivial. And that was a really cool
result. I mean, we're still seeing how
it plays out, but like it's like an
exact example of what you talked about.
We spent like a year and a half trying
to just like use the the, you know, the
naive thing of just like cramming it in
there. Um, and then we Sorry, I I'll
finish. I I just want to say that this
is a real world example of what you just
said. Great. We're going to take now
lightning questions. You have 17
seconds. Go. Um Um, actually, I have two
questions. Why you No, no, no. You You
have one and you've already used and
you've already used four of your
seconds. Okay. Um so in the past two
years we see so many foundation models
or language models
um doing uh happening in this in this
field. I was just wondering what is
beyond the re beyond the reach of
current foundation models like what
tasks cannot be finished with the
current foundation models. Excellent.
And right on time good job. Many many
many most tasks
Ah, we are are you foundation model
skeptics at the moment? Do you feel like
we don't have the data to make
foundation models? What what did that
all mean? It's a strong reaction. I can
go ahead first if you like. I was just
saying that, you know, although it can
answer some questions, the an the
questions it can answer is far fewer
than the questions that it cannot
answer. I'm not a skepticism of
skepticism of foundation models. I'm
just saying that that that question has
an easy answer. I see I formulated but
but you're only skeptical at the moment
that it's not going to give you what you
want to know. That's good. That's a good
answer. Okay. Very clear. I'm skeptical
about foundation models specifically,
but I feel like the thing that's missing
right now is that we are not leveraging
enough the ability of language models to
do function calling to be able to do
this thing called tool use where
essentially instead of outputting a
result the thing called called function
calling which is that instead of instead
of uh outputting a result instead of
like asking a question getting an answer
you ask it a question and it gives you
uh it gives you a function call it it
basically tells you how to solve the
answer using the tools that you
different type of foundation though.
Yeah, that's right. So basically instead
of trying to solve instead of trying to
say you know in what pathway does this
gene lie instead it should be able to
return to you the parameters of the
function the parameters and the function
you should call to solve it and you have
a complete hold on that. So I think if
we sort of couple foundation models with
tool use in that specific way I think
you can do a lot more in part you can
solve the hallucination problem. I just
want to clarify. I'm not skeptical. You
know, I actually love the approach. I'm
just saying that it's early days. There
are many things that needs to be done.
Okay. Yeah. No, no, we're not saying
what might eventually happen. It's just
does it do what you need today? And
you've said no. Okay. The answer for me,
I I am the answer.
Okay. If their answer is all no, then my
answer is clearly no. because the only
way you go from DNA to the life
phenotype of the organism human is
traversing through from DNA through all
of the other modalities. Okay. So,
nobody is skeptical. That's excellent.
Wonderful. We had a question over here.
Well, I'm skeptical. Very quick
questions and more
actionable question is
that address
to you know interview a wonderful
technology platform you know for decades
and 1995 you know if you go back uh
people discover the you know
DNA 43
uh original was a HIV one suppressor but
later on we have a good
news 2020 we find that theocracy of it
can related to
And I wonder you know why they don't you
know focus all this effort and
technology you know large scale data to
handle this and come up a solution. All
right we'll give that to Mark. Sure. And
I I wouldn't say it's not happening. I
guess it's maybe not happening at the
Broad Institute, but there are certainly
a lot of people who are focused on that
particular question with respect to
TDP43, its molecular consequences and
what the rest of the genome tells us
about where there might be opportunities
to intervene. And I think there are some
that have emerged from the population
genetic studies of ALS.
And you now you want Well, no, no, we're
gonna have to stop here because it it is
Sorry, you guys can talk afterwards,
but I was assigned to keep us on time.
And what we've what we've learned is
there are so many rich questions that
remain and that's going to be the case.
And we should all continue this
conversation with the folks up here on
the panel and with each other. This was
an amazingly stimulating session. Uh
thank you to all the people who make
data make the methods to make data first
and then actually make data and and have
stimulated so much work. You know deep
uh Alphafold would not be here but for
the tremendous amount of protein
structure and sequence that was there
and all the things that are happening we
heard about today are happening because
these new sources of data are just
burgeoning. And so this wonderful
symbiosis between data creation and data
analysis and the fact that we're mostly
doing both of those things together uh
is a great way to end. We have a whole
another day tomorrow of exciting talks.
I looked I peaked. It's a very good
list. But we're going to declare victory
now. And uh we'll be back at what time
tomorrow? 9 a.m. 900 a.m. for yet more.
See you then.
[Applause]