All right. Hi. We're gonna get started.
Um, thank you everyone for coming out on
a rainy day. I know it's kind of gloomy
out today, but we're really excited for
our two speakers today at MIA. Um, the
first of which is Hanchen. Um, Henchin
Wang is a joint posttock at Stanford
with Yuri Leavik um and at Janentech
with Avivv. He works on AI for
scientific discovery and therapeutics
broadly and earned his PhD in computer
science um at the University of
Cambridge with Joan Lassenby. Um some of
his recent work which I'm sure he'll
touch up on a bit today as well um
includes like discrete diffusion, DNA
and protein design. Um and so we're
really really excited to have him here.
Both of our speakers did come from
California. So if you're doing the math,
it's 6:00 am time and so we're really
really appreciative of you guys. Thank
you.
>> Thanks. Um you can hear me right the
micro is on. Um
yeah I don't I don't need more
introduction. So uh the structure of
today's talk will be um as I'm giving
the first talk I will cover like the
basics of the agents like um I like 20
25 minutes um we'll talk about the agent
will be specialized for spatial biology
and we will cover some new recent agents
that are doing massive money on aging
intervention as well as using computers
to analyze cells as well as um doing a
better statistical calibration on the um
different kinds of agents on different
kinds of data sets. Um yeah, so if you
think of the um biomedical discovery,
it's roughly can be divided into like
three stages. You have some observations
can be uh from some previous data, it
can be from the nature or can be from
you know some literature and you
generate some hypothesis. The habos can
be with different forms like whether
there's like a direct relationship or
causal infacts from gene A to a
phenotype B those kinds of formats and
we design some experiments to verify
that to collect more evidence to collect
more the data to help you to refine or
reject or accept your hypothesis. So
it's roughly you can think of it like a
three interconnected and circulating
stages until you find something you
wanted or until you
run out of your budget. Um and we see
that computation helps at like every
single stage of them. And there are some
examples like for instance you can use
some source of autoenccoder alo some
variational measure variations measure
to decide like which genes or which um
um are more informative for your for the
tissues that you are interested or
there's like a different ways that can
use graph you can use the relationship
of the gene coexp expression patterns to
uh help you design um help you predict
and design what would be the next rounds
of experiment term uh uh uh genetic
perturbations.
And speak of the observations um I have
to uh say good words uh to shout loud
for the w collections of different kinds
of efforts um for instance omix data for
instance other types of data as well um
and hypothesis one of my favorite
example is like uh the double helic
structure of DNA um it's um um back then
like 50 oh sorry 70 years ago uh when uh
these two cambridge aluminina developed
they proposed a hypothesis double uh the
the structure of DNA is just based on
some pair wise distance matrix from 2D
um um and it's quite a quite a um I I
would say quite elegant uh example for
positive generations and there are more
examples recently used different kinds
of computations some are agents uh that
help us to verify or generate uh some
better hypothesis Um and the task can go
long and long for every single stages
and there's u there'll be some
computation methods help us to u make
the uh process easier faster um and
better
and uh so what is AI agents um in some
of versions of my slides I usually give
a formal definition of the AI agents but
today let's start with a example so this
is kind of the analysis I've done like
last week so uh when we like back and
forth on a manuscript that is about to
be preprinted very soon. So basically we
done a lot of interventions of the mouse
models and um so our PI is uh commented
in in in in in the documents saying that
you need to find more evidence in the
human data in so in supporting what you
have been found such as a special um
type of u inflam
um fibroblast or inflamary microfasages
that are we know that are critical for
the uh uh cancer therapeutic um
reactions. So you need to find some
evidence like shared does does the same
population happens a lot in the human
single cell RNA seek data as well or
it's uh have the similar dynamics or
similar pathways. So um it's kind of
like a very high level instructions and
that's me I converted to a few sentence
and a plugin to cloud code. So I I I
gave a relative detailed but still very
high level instructions. ask the cloud
code to which is a coding agent you can
think of uh to create a Jupyter notebook
to project the human prostate cancer
fiber blast onto the the mouse cancer
associate fiber blast and transfer the
subtype labels from the mouse to human
also load the uh also uh list the data
path for the two data sets use the top
2k high genes intersections so which
involve like a conversion uh and find
the intersections of the symbols from
the mouse and to the human and then make
some analysis and visualization as well
as see the results. So the car code it's
uh start working the engine is on and
it's generate lots of code first
generate plan and its final solution
which uh only involve like two or three
additional inputs from my end and it
could generate a lots of working
solution which include mapping the mouse
and human uh shared gene space and
project the human data to the mouse
transfer the label use a uh a convention
method uh um that is shared used by lots
of public literatures and uh doing some
visualizations
uh uh the U maps the competence score
the proportion comparations across
different conditions as well as plot the
markers for different subtype annotation
as well as save the results. So this is
all figures that are generated by cloud
code. The top left is a mouse reference
data set. You have different types of
fellow lost and you you project the
human um data uh which is uh from the
cancer progression samples. You project
them onto the same coordinate space as
shared by the mouse and you as well you
have the uh confidence as well as you
have the distributions which is the top
bottom right and we find the evidence we
want which is this specific type of
fablas uh CCL2
enriched uh which we know it's play
inflammatory role and the larger
population is which means the um the
more therapeutic um uh potentials you
will have. So essentially we we we find
the human has even larger pro proportion
for this specific cell type which stress
the findings we find in the original
paper and this entire uh workflow this
entire pipeline um takes uh speak of the
API cost takes less than $3 and the
total uh include a few back and forth uh
from uh between me and the cloud code it
takes like uh less than 20 minutes. So
this is kind of something that is
already uh functioning and uh make at
least make my life easier and uh also um
to use the AI agent to help with better
science specifically on biomedical
discovery. um is also the vision is
shared by lots of industry leaders um
like anthropic saying uh actually the
CEO is also trained by a biologist back
in um by then he was a PhD and postto so
he's saying the the right way to think
of AI is to treat it as a virtual
biologist can perform like a co-pilot to
all the tasks human scientist do so not
only uh you know uh like a forward pass
to do like a protein uh structure
prediction but also to do a complex
chain of action
towards a high level goal as well as
this as well as the simation shared by
by deep mind as as you can see from lots
of their publications as well as openai
and a generic um structure of the AI
agents can be show as a left paradigm so
it's powered by a large language models
and it can take actions usually from two
callings nowadays um and have some
impact on the environment environment
can be uh let's say your local
computation platforms as well as I guess
Kashin will show some example like a
manipul like robotic arms to do um more
uh uh physical interactions with the
work as well you can receive some
feedbacks such as uh from the human such
as from the environment like whether the
code is successful or not whether your
current design is good or not and it
knows when to start as well as when to
stop. This is like a quite high level
but I still like this paradigm. Later on
we will introduce a lot of modules but
which will make the sense more
complicated but essentially it you can
remember it's powered by large language
models. It's kind take actions to
influence the environment and receive
the feedbacks from the environment and
adjust itself as well as know when to
stop have also have the interactions
capability with the human. And if we
dive deeper on the agent roughly saying
there's like a three modules inside of
the agent um you have tools which is the
major things to generate actions to
impact environment and the memory is uh
and the planning you can think of both
of them as as as part of the context. So
the memory store uh for its goal as well
as the progress and the planning um is
like make a concrete plan um to um take
action according to the plan roughly
saying something like that and um
there's many um so for every single uh
module there's many
techniques that helps the agent to make
better planning make better memory as
well as make um more accurate and
uh concrete actions. So for the first
like I think we we all know like but we
cannot aware that so every um if you
look at some um um public um GitHub um
package you will see that a lot of
prompt instructions nowadays still
involve this basic modules. So one of
the module is called chain of salt. It's
very simple and it's uh but it's so
powerful and elegant. So basically um
what is showing that so instead of just
ask the LM um the question you want to
provide example with a few uh chain of
thought process for in the example here
instead of doing a single question on
calculation like a five plus six you
want to uh provide a few short um
examples for the intask learning for the
LM to capture have a better idea like
what would be the uh inference process
looks like and another thing uh which is
I believe all shared by all the agents
currently is called react so it stands
for reflection and action um so it's
also uh have the similar philosophy as a
chain of thought uh so instead of
provide a salting a sync chains it's
provide more like a pardon so ask the
arm to to reflect like what is the
current status what you have information
you have and what's the objective want
to achieve and then to do the actions
and also update its.
So is is this is kind of like a very
generic principles and every
single agent nowadays find they have
some um uh shared statistics in in their
instructions also called prompts
and second next we move to the memory so
the way I think memory is like it's a
it's it's a it's a giant context window
uh it's a intelligent retrieval machine
which allows the agent to to record the
user's behavior as well as the user's
information. So this is like one of the
example we borrowed from MGT. Uh so uh
it the the memory usually have like few
functions. For instance, like first it
will create a memory. For instance, you
have some interactions with your
chatbot. Uh discuss your birthday and
it's the chatbot will if it's the first
time conversation you discuss on this
topic. The the chatbot will create a
memory to to memorize. Okay. Um uh today
is your birthday February 7 February
7th. And uh later on for your follow or
for your future conversations your
chatboard or your agent will have the
caveat to retrieve the memories. Uh it
will know you better. It will have more
tailored for your own uh interactions as
well as update like your break up your
uh with your boyfriend or girlfriend. So
the memory will also change uh uh to
update its u uh knowledge and you can um
and the system design actually is not
that triple. So in in this paper uh is
one of the representative paper to build
a memory system for the agents and
essentially have a lot of um layers and
modules that just help uh the LM to make
a better um use given the budget of its
context window as well to update them
with uh uh with few time latency and you
can easily think of how we can use the
memory in terms of the biomedical
discovery. So it can help to learn the
labs know how I mean even there's like a
100 labs doing perturbation experiments
or analysis there's still different uh
labs you have their different knows and
preference so having inter having a
agents that could memorize the lab know
how the labs taste it will help you
build better workflow and analysis and
it help um uh uh also uh tackle the hard
tasks with long horizons of action.
because you have a good memory system,
you can memorize what's your current
stuff because usually there are for
instance like playing Pokemon or um
doing a large simulations the act the
the the time the runtime of agents can
last for hours or days. So in in that
way you want to your memory system um
not only to uh keep a track on
everything but also intelligent
compressed during the it its progress.
So uh having having having a very good
memory system is also kind of crucial
for building an intelligent uh science
scientific discovery agents and you also
want to avoid your previous failures or
pre failures. Sometimes the larger
language model will make very silly
mistakes. Um you want to avoid that
after you credit it like one or few
times. So memory would help with that
ideally. Um and next we're going to move
on to tools. So the tools I believe is
kind of question you move on
you're outlining these components I'm
curious in practice whether people um to
you know do they fine-tune the models be
like you have the prompt right but do
you also fine-tune the model to be a
good memory system and do you fine-tune
the models to all work together or is it
is it like just just everything is
better specified through the prompt and
um
I actually prefer no fine tune. Many
papers they find tune on let's say llama
and usually with a fixed context window
like 8k or a few a few a few thousand
key um um but if you look at some like a
very maintained open source project like
some let's say it's called open cloud
code it's kind of like open source
solution for cloud code they essentially
write a very detailed prompt or detail
ask the u on it or uh opus itself to
compress the the the contact window
compressor map was kind of that side. So
speak of the compression, speak of the
tracking a single run, I feel like it's
more elegant to just
the past in features. But speak of like
a let's say if you have some interaction
with the uh system last year and you
still want to have it to remember such
information like for uh your today's
conversation. Um I I was feel more safe
to build a very intelligent right
retrieval system instead of um fine tune
a a small uh retriever on um um yeah
>> I see so there's some choices there but
but I guess beyond the memory there's
also as you saying like the planning
stuff and these components are all
interacting so do people fine-tune them
to like interact in terms of how well
they form on the overall task or is it
kind of just okay let's build the best
possible memory system let's build the
best possible planning system let's
build the best possible
tool calling system and then just hope
they work together
um
I mean there's basically like a two
types of fine tune one is provided fine
tune second is reinforcement fine tune
which are like are basic fine tune um
most
on on both side most way I think is more
like two are tool based it's like you
want it to make optimal plan you make
wanted to find the right argument for
calling the tools um I didn't see many
like a like a join tuning include the
memory system um does that answer your
question
>> question thanks
I should repeat the
They're right. We should we should
repeat the question.
Um yeah so the tools tool says um where
you can make a lots of efforts because
it's kind of the sense your the agents
will interact or have uh the impact on
the environment and there's a different
category of tools for inance you can
have the models or have some binformatic
tools like verse um and you have
database you can look up database um to
uh find the information you need find
the relevant data you need software al
can be also treated as a tool So not
only coding based but also computer use
like you have a graphical user
interface. You can move the mouse, you
can click the button, you can drag the
the menu and select the things you want
and adjust the range uh using drag or
using drag or draw. um coding for sure
nowadays I think we all witness like a
by your own experience uh with using
cursor or cloud code or github copilot
you will see you'll have a sense like
how coding uh how how good they're good
at coding nowadays and a a broader view
of tools you can think of like other
agents can be treated as a tools through
more standardized protocol like MCP and
also like our human sciences can be also
like treated tools to provide additional
feedbacks or corrections for the agents
behaviors.
Um so this is like our overview on the
modules of agents. You have memory um
you have the planning and you can take
actions by calling the tools
and this is kind of the shared design
for all the works we've been build like
a perable agent. You have actions also
the memory to remember what action
you've done. You have a pool of actions
which a combination of tools and
databases and you have some oblivations
for uh the uh the impact you made on the
data on the environment as well as biom
I think Christian will share more how we
how we build that uh we spend tons of
time on building the tools
also to universe um it's from here uh
from maras lab so they also uh push the
extreme of a better tool system like you
want to find the best tools, you want to
call them, uh you want to manage them,
you want to retire some of the less
frequent or unqualified tools as well as
to add new tools, you want to combine
them together, you want to uh u u to
optimize it. Uh let's say if it's a
better arguments or it's a better um u
adjust a few lines inside of the tools.
And uh next we're going to talk of some
frontier eye um um of the agents. Um
it's uh it's it's it's I would say it's
um very parallel and I just list all the
topics that come to my head. So it's not
a comprehensive list but I hope it can
give you some um overview of what people
care about uh in the recent
three or six months. Um so first is
multi- aent system. uh I mean there's
already paper published let's say from
James lab which is use a lab of virtual
scientist to help us design a better
antibbody uh sequence for uh covid uh 19
diagnosis um but still I think we're
still waiting or
uh not satisfying like what would be the
best optimal multi-agent system so this
is kind of one of the diagram from uh de
minds co- scientist
So they spend most of their computation
budget on this multi- aent system which
is essentially to create a hypothesis a
useful hypothesis a useful plan
hypothesis and if you think of like the
um and it's more like a role play so
it's using all the same LM but with a
different instance and with different
rules so you can think of the advantage
body system is like it can speed the
context it can speed the tasks because
Sometimes you have a very complex tasks.
It's always easier to accomplish it by
divide and conquer. So having more
agents that tackle different angles of
this problem will help you to uh achieve
the tasks with a higher success rate and
also it's can add some diversity. For
instance, your agent can have the
different access to the tools. Your
agent have the different expertise. Uh
so timeism discuss with each other will
help um um some uh like different angles
for the question you care about. Um and
second is
self involve there there should be a
video here which is like a like a like a
like a uh like a Minecraft like a
character in the Minecraft that is like
involved itself. So this is a paper from
Nvidia actually like two years ago. Um
um yeah preprinted like two years ago
and the the task is very simple. It's uh
ask the targeter to learn to use a
diamond tools in the Minecraft world. So
actually the diamond tools is one of the
very high-end tools in in the micro mic
Minecraft.
And uh to achieve uh using the diamond
tools, you need to first to develop the
wooden tools which allow you to mine the
stones and and you will have the
capability to create the stone tools and
the iron tools and finally diamond tools
and uh uh they create a reinforcement
learning policy models that uh allows
allows which is more like embody agents
in in that simulation work and to to to
try with different policy to explore and
exploit to find the optimal to find a
way to to create the diamond tools and
have a better survival uh status and uh
this is also used by this this kind of
philosophy is also shared by lots of
recent work like Alfa involve and many
other many other um works.
Next frontier is contact engineering. So
this is kind of like a hacker word like
especially two months ago. Um so
everyone is talking about contacting
back then and so compared with the
traditional like prompt engineering
which like a single turn query you have
the system prompt um as well as a user
message uh context engineering is more
like a more comprehensive engineering is
you can think it's a nature natural
progression of permanent engineering. So
the reason we need context engineering
is like uh based on two based on two
observations. First we have very limited
context windows. Second we we cannot fit
all the informations. Second is even we
have infinite budget of the context
window thems performance the agent
performance won't be better if we feed
all the informations actually because
the intrinsic computation complexity the
quadratic complexity uh of the
transformer especially calculating the
cross tension scores uh usually the
shorter information shorter accurate and
diverse information provide within the
contact window the better the agent will
perform. It's like you you think of like
annotating like a cell type or doing
some analysis. It's not always like you
provide all the informations we will
have the best annotations. model provide
the most salient uh useful informative
um information to help the agent perform
better uh um for the tasks that you are
interested
and reinforce learning it's also a very
emerging field and especially in the
past months or past one or two months
everyone is talking about
um agentic aisle um lots of people
inventing wheels for training a better
um agents under different signals. So
roughly saying there's like um two
modules. You have the trainer which is
which is uh which is um which include
the agent as well as some uh uh
framework um as well as base models and
you have a environment you have a
generator which is generating uh use for
training data. You have an inference
agent which involve like a serving
system as well as the agent which is uh
uh you can think of like a large
language models and it will take um um
actions to uh to the environment you
should you receive signals um uh and you
can update your model from um methods
like a GRP or DPO or different kinds of
ways and even uh and this is very um a
complex engineering um And even for a
single tiny bite of them such as analyze
the model's behavior on the different
signal on the different optimization
algorithms um is still there's tons of
papers on that for instance to analyze
how to select the most informative uh
examples the successful traces as well
as the failed traces to uh using the
same algorithm such as GRPO there's at
least you can find like five or 10
papers that just doing this types of
angle analysis. Um
um yeah and it's and it's also worth
mentioning there's two types of RL one
is online one one is offline and and
nowadays the community trend is more
like on online which you can learn and
interact with the environment as well
update model uh update your policy on
the same time and frontier another uh
frontier is computer use um
yeah I feel like it's not playing
because we are I'm not connected to the
internet. But essentially uh uh uh a
current trend one of the current trend
on building agent is ask it to use a
computers ask it to move the mouse to
move the to to drag the window for
instance for like cell profiler for um
lots of other uh uh software such as
from 10x genomics such as from uh such
as you're doing some um
fast q files analysis many of such uh
operations are not actually interact
from common lines. You interact them
from uh the graphical interface. You
want so you so in order to have a larger
action space uh uh a capability for the
agents you wanted to use the computers
such as like the browsers which uh which
triggered quite some noise yesterday. Um
and for sure the last piece of the
frontier is like to build a better
rubric as well as benchmarks and there
are some efforts on building better uh
comparations of the agents uh such as
agent arena as well as to um uh to to
deliver a better uh user satisfied
results by running multiple agents at
the same time and select the best and
return to the users.
And the last piece of the basic is um
some common failures. I think this is
something that not many people
discussed. I mean we are a bit hijacked
by the promise of the agents. But we
also need to have a sense like what are
the common failures when we build the
agents. So when we start to build the
agents I say like one year and a half
ago or two years ago we encounter a lot
of errors especially silly errors such
as hallucination on some tools that are
not existing or some arguments that are
not um uh that are not defined by the
tools um for instance you you import
some gene labels in the alpha fold which
is not expected and the context overflow
back then is on GP4 it's very easy to
exceed the context window as well as it
has very poor performance to handling
some simple errors such as variable
undefined errors. But nowadays this kind
of errors are very less likely happen uh
thanks to the advancements of building a
better large language model from those
um industry leaders but we still have a
lot of few other um common failures. So
first is like stuck in the loop which
which represents the agent will repeat
the same actions for a few more times
even till the end of your budget and no
finish action. It's kind of similar with
stocking. So stuck in loop is one of the
way to uh have no finish actions. Uh but
there are a few others. It's like the
agent will sometimes just happen to stop
itself from delivering some um final
results or delivering some or or reach
its final budget which is the number of
actions we we preset.
Still it's have a lot of hallucinations
especially we move on to very
specialized domain of the science um as
well as shortcut for instance if you
wanted to if you want agents to analyze
like um 100 gigabytes or even larger
files that has like millions of cells or
or other types of information. It's a
it's it's tend to find a shortcut which
is to subsample data or doing lot of
simulations instead of to work on the
actual data as well as trail findings is
like um a lot of a lot of things we find
in today's agents is like either they do
a a lot of hallucination or find some
shortcut
which is something very unrealistic
um or they provide something trail
findings as we all know like a fus exist
in tumor tissues those kind of two
findings. So this is something uh still
exist but despite of this common
features we we uh already observe there
many positive signals in building
agents. So one of the few one of the
example I'm going to share today is we
build for spatial biology. So the reason
we chose spatial biology um because it's
a a very u
a very broad a very vertical field but
it's have high impact. Um for instance
one of the example is like distinguish
cod tumors. Um so the way we design
spatial agent is like we as we shown
before is like it has um um three
modules. You take actions to have impact
to the environment. uh you have the
memory to track your progress and you
can make plans and we choose
representative works from uh every
single stages of the biometical
discovery in the spatial context to
support multiple organs as well as cross
species. Um so uh speak of the time I
will keep the results is in the paper is
like 100 or so pages of manuscript. Um
uh so one of the things we're going to
highlight is that are especially good at
aggregating informations like multiple
layers informations. So here we ask the
LM to look up different database and
select the most informative genes. uh
given it's a few principles such as if
it's if the gene used to name the cell
type which means it's quite important if
the gene you know is included in your
target tissue here is a specific region
in your brain then it's kind of very
important and if it's appear multiple
times it's important so I'm kind doing a
very good job in aggregating different
types of information resource and
ranking them as well as provide reason
in nature languages that are very easy
for us to identify to to justify
Speaking of performance, we compare
mostly with the specialized tools that
people build uh in in this specific
task. It's better uh consistently across
different metrics. We also ask a lots of
human scientists to do the same task
using the same informations. And so
first observation we made is like a
scientist they are so different. So we
ask like um eight or 10 scientists we
summarize their design panel design
workflow and they are quite quite
different. For instance, some scientists
will just use some existing templates uh
that he he or she has in hand or some
scientist they will do a very detailed
track. They will look multiple data sets
of many literatures as well as some
database for pos mark markers to find uh
to add to adjust her his or her design
each um one by one and some just um uh
use some literature as well as a
reference data set. And so what do we
show we compare with special agent and
human scientists we basically can see
that it's performed um the most of the
scientists we the data we collected uh
which are mostly PhD post dog as well as
full-time scientists
and it's kind like 85% of the human
initial designs and also agent plus
human um agent work on the human initial
design is also better than agent alone
so this is what we found uh using GB4 um
nine months ago. uh since might be
different if we switch some more than uh
LMS which we will have in the revised
manuscripts and it's because of the time
and cost it's much cheaper uh compared
with the methods that I use GPUs and
also very for sure you can imagine it's
cheaper for the scientist because uh we
know the scientist time is very precious
annotations have the similar
um
uh flow um as well as similar
um um performance. It has better than
cell typist some GBT based annotations
as well as most of the human scientists
and we use it to doing mostly to analyze
how the cell cell interact with each
other and different context which here
is um a tissue remodeling process and
it's and and as you can imagine lots of
omix based analysis is on comparative
analysis. It's like you have different
conditions, you have different ways of
grouping them and you would just want to
group them and to analyze what changes
and what are the intrinsic reasons and
are quite good at doing this um very
standardized or pattern um finding types
of analysis and there are some similar
works that they published uh preprinted
after our work like cell voyager like
paper to code uh both are from uh Jim
Sto's lab and we do some lab validations
which is another manuscript that we hope
we can f hope hope we can share before
the end of this year because there's a
lot of uh um screening policies we need
to make um
and one thing uh I want to say as the at
the time we build special agent we
already considered its extendabilities
um uh so it's like um uh the user make a
message and the agent will decide
whether uh the uh the user's task has
been encountered has been like baked um
in its previous like a plane templates
or knowhow or SOP uh it's a different
terms but for the same concepts and uh
they if the plane exists and the agent
will make the actions much easier using
the template if it's not the agent will
make the plan on the fly use the tools
it has and
This is kind of the the stages we use
like a nine months ago and uh nowadays
there's like a much more um um uh
comprehensive uh modules for this for
instance like a cloud skills. It's kind
of like you provide a a ripple or
provide a folder and the cloud can learn
what is learn the know-hows, learn the
preference, learn how you do the
analysis, how you make the figures from
from the examples you provided and
updates the memory to update its uh uh
plan um in order to make a better
tailored uh user um uh quests.
uh and we show that okay SP region um
thanks to the coding flexibility can do
simple task such as harmonizing
annotations between two different data
sets but can but it's still failed at
complex task mostly because uh um we
didn't uh grill its coding capability as
well as we didn't add the uh the tools
that are needed.
So next finally I'm going to talk some
recent works we're about to release. So
I'm so excited for them. Uh so uh
there's there's a few works. So each of
them will be covered by a few slides. Um
so first is like a ination with here um
vian school as well as Tony's group by
Stanford. So we basically didn't use a
very complex agents. We basically use a
coding agent to do a massive mining the
aging agent uh the aging interventions
uh uh using the clock system uh from
Omix data. So the reason the motivation
uh uh we we need a gentic system instead
of like a predefined like a python
programs is uh is because um every
single go study they're different
they're in different formats to record
the metadata. So they're so messy and uh
uh you want you might want to try
different statistical tasks um um based
on your grouping based on your sample
size and uh you want to uh aggregate
multiple informations not only on the
statistical measure like a p values um
but also on how the experiments is
designed what are the relevant what are
the relevant literatures so you kind of
want to have this kind of flexibilities
also because of intrinsic complex text
of of the data. You want to have a more
dynamic or flexible system to to write
code for each single geo data set to to
do some analysis.
And what we find is this is as you all
know this is a typical vikino plot and
uh we show so the color represents uh
how the uh different types of
interventions affects the agent clock
changes and we find one of the
interventions which is open um which we
verified in the white lab we show that
it's actually um could increase the
lifespan of the mouse model and the
phenotype uh is basically it's help the
hair to regenerate or regrow from the
mass models. Um
so I so so the so the example here is
basically I want to say uh in order to
to make the use of agent you don't need
to um build a very comprehensive ones
you just to find what you need and you
can uh easily use some very simple
agendic structure to help you to um um
meet your need.
Second project is like we're uh building
playing some statistical games. So uh
it's it it's it we use e statistics
which is a method actually using proper
from pushing and many others which is
like a way to model the um the the
sequential uh statistic the sequential
decision makings. Um so this is like
like one of the example because as we s
as we as as we said agents still make a
lot of silly errors such as you want to
find some uh low side on the chromatin
17 associated with type two diabetes the
agent might sometimes in the middle it's
fine they use a different chromosome
instead of the 17. So, so in that way
you want you you want your jar, you want
your verifier to um identify that uh and
uh it has some additional advantages
such as you want to uh early terminate
your agent and start a new run or you
want to to save your budget or you want
to provide a measure that the current
agent running is not ideal most likely
to provide a field results. So we use we
we call our method called EV E evaluator
which is like a a the sequential
estimation on how the agent will
successfully achieve its tasks and we
show that we find uh with a few serum
proving showing that the the method we
design will have controllable error
rates as well as optimum power and we
show that compared with raw LMS as a
charge we compare with some before
roy test as well as some empirical um
baselines. And we show that our method
is compare can achieve like a ideal
empirical type to one arrow estimation
as well as to have a better power um
which means you require less samples to
do robust estimations and we show that
it's can generalize across different
data sets for different agentic
architectures. So here is like a from
future house and GSM AK which is a mass
data set and this octo tools another one
from James O lab and um uh on the
medical uh uh data sets we show that the
same our pros method have the same um um
good performance compared with all the
baselines and the last project I want to
share very briefly uh is
I mean we're is a agent that can not
only coding but also use computers. So
um we are still designing the name it's
whether called coco but or co um um but
essentially uh you'll get a sense of the
data. So it's it's it's it's
a multi- aent system and you have two
agents. One is just doing manipulation
do operations on the graphical user
interface. You can have a lot of
interactions with let's say cell
profilers or Q pass or napari or
different types of uh softwares that
work on let's say cell images and
another is like a software engineering
agents that can mostly uh run a lot of
code and can robust recover from
different error messages as well as for
a long horizon task and these two agent
can communicate um with each other and
collaborate to to achieve a very complex
task especially uh complex if we think
of another layer of modality for cell
images and we compare some baselines uh
this baseline so for this type of so the
right is like a two example one is
generated from the agent when is
generated from the tutorial where is
downloaded from the tutorial on cell
profiler which we treated as a ground
tru and we show that this complex task
it cannot be achieved by a single lm um
because it doesn't have access to to to
to us provider to doing some data
analysis on on on your image and u we
compare with a few baselines we encrypt
the bomin because it's original design
for coding but I know there um uh uh
there um yeah so we we compare with the
coding versions of bom mini equipped
with a cell profiler we also doing two
types of version of our own method. One
is just on coding, one is use both
coding as well as the computers and we
show that um um it has a very
um
good better performance than most of the
methods. uh not only on the in-domain
test which is like a trend test split on
the subprofiler which are like 20
different samples data as well as uh
different tasks but also for the out of
domain task which is we download the
most hard challenges from the online
forums that is not encountered or uh
included in the self profiler official
tutorial and many of them have open
solutions
and speak and we also analyze when the
computer use is necessary. So
essentially you can think of you can see
that our system essentially use tons of
computer um use softwares such as to
validate to ver to verify your results
as well as to adjust the parameters such
as the um the range in the threshold to
to to to color your cells to to dye your
cells. um um as well as to just build
from scratch which is like move the
button from beginning to drag the data
file into serif window and drag the
manual to find the corresponding
functions and doing some analysis.
So to recap so we um share the vision u
many of you shared as well like the
agent as a scientist co-pilot and we
talk about the basics of agents uh we
talk about it modules uh um and we talk
about the frontiers topics as well we um
share uh some common failures why we
build these agents and we introduce some
specialized agent we build for spatial
biology uh we build it uh uh in the
light of to compare most of the
specialized domain tools. We didn't
compare with other agent but more we
want to show the agents can offer some
um performance gains across some like a
previous computation method like whether
it's a transformer or incoder or some
statistical based methods um uh and we
have some manuscript to do lots of wet
lab verifications and uh I share some
works that is soon be released uh um
master mining agent interventions
validations using sequial hypothesis
testing framework as well as doing
coding and computer use at the same
time. Um so finally I want to sh my
mentors this is because there are so
many authors I um I I kind of lazy
didn't list all the um people's
essentially this is one of slide I
borrow from uh one of my previous uh um
presentations. I want to thank my
mentors and the cortium special agent as
well as um a portable agent vi many uh
agents and many works mentors and
mentees and uh thanks for listening.
>> You have questions let me know.
Hi. Um I I was wondering if you think
that for example you could have an agent
but without the LLM component because I
know that the LLM component is providing
a lot of the underlying reasoning for a
lot of these uh agentic workflows but
it's also providing the knowledge source
as well where like you know if you ask
it to run a single cell pipeline you
know the agent probably is drawing from
a lot of that pre-trained data that's
been mined from the literature. So I was
just wondering how you differentiate,
you know, agents as a whole versus the
LLM field as a whole or there sounds
like they're inherently intertwined.
M
>> um
yeah actually so as you know the agent
concept is developed better or proposed
earlier than the LM um for in this paper
they didn't use large anchorage model
for I mean they use some visual models
for instance on the very early stages
like um from deep mind they developed
some firmware called hide and seek so
basically the you know that in that way
it's It's not agent more as in it's not
LM power agent more used to analyze the
reinforce learning how the emerging
behavior happens in the multi- reinforce
learning um um policy uh powered agents
um I think um for now it's like for sure
um mostly agent we're talk about today
or talk about by the committee is
powered by large models and it's
avoidable that is has some bias
inherited from its training data. Um
so so first it's getting better and
better for base models. Um uh yeah uh
there there are some uh people are
showing that for some data set like GPQA
or graduate level science you the agent
are already have better performance than
the average PhD. Second it's um our
human self is also have bias right I
mean you can read 10 different cells
papers they have their own bias to do
the analysis to do the figures to tell
the story as well so um one of the way
to uh to alleviate the amount bias from
the LM and to bake your own bias we
think is like uh for instance like I
think cloud skills or some memories or
um
like a more better context engineering
could help that.
Yeah, I'm not sure does it answer your
question.
Uh very nice work. I have a question
just out of curiosity. Do you guys
observe any two usage preference for the
agents? For example, you have multiple
tools doing the same thing. Does the
agent prefer to use one over the other?
I assume like most humans do have their
own preference but not about agents.
Um
yeah so we do have so like uh I would
say cloud 3.7 start from cloud 3.7 it's
tend to use coding itself instead of to
calling like a lot of predefined tools.
It's feel I feel like it's more like
from the training side. It's like I I
feel like it's it's the training of 3.74
4.5 Sonet is um compared with the
product of color code. So they want to
train the model in order to have a very
good coding capabilities. Uh so instead
of you know from the tools we predefined
such as some like scampy or some other
different type of tools. And the
question for that for for your specific
question I feel like um this is
something I didn't I I we realized but I
didn't find an elegant solution. It's
like for a single task you can have
several ways. You can use skumai can use
sat you can use different type of things
to do like a differential expression.
Just let's say differential expression a
simple example. Um for different data
you might want to use a different for
sure parameters for the same package as
well as different packages.
um in building in building of this I'm
I'm not sure about the uh situation of
the two universe but in building of the
operation we're trying to kind of a bit
uh centralize the tools we did we try to
avoid duplication of the tools for the
same purpose but uh ultimately I think
it will be better if someone or or from
our side we can propose something that
agent will try a lot of different
solutions
like different tools, different
arguments and propose. Okay, this one is
optimal in my hand. Currently, it's more
like a one time pass even if you look at
the it's it's kind of like it makes a
plan at the beginning and just make
actions according to the plan maybe
adjust the plane in the middle but
essentially as long as it has a final
result and then it's stopped. It won't
okay I have one version of the result
then I start from the beginning.
Currently we don't have such
thing. Um but I I I believe have such
kind of thing will make a better um
deliverable things. Thanks.
>> Um for people who have done a bunch of
computation in their life but haven't
really jumped into this yet, do you have
like a quick recommendation of where you
would go to try building out one of
these? Let's say you had a computational
task, a machine learning algorithm
you're trying to build or something like
that. This world of like there's lots of
choices out there at this point. Can you
offer some recommendation as to what to
try first and why? Or does do you need
more specifics on the problem? Let's say
it's a pure data science problem. It's a
pure like there's a lot of data and you
just but there's a lot of pieces you
need to connect together to get it to
work.
I
yeah if we think of like a resource uh
like a like something to read I would
have a very heavy bias to read something
from like anthropic I really enjoy
reading their blogs especially engineer
blogs
like a reading like if you start from
something reading to understand the
basic concepts I would start from
reading blogs from anthropic they are
very
aggressive in in pushing the agentic
power for large language models. If you
think of um um a very good open source
packages, I I would recommend Bowin and
Bowin which Kushin will introduce in the
next talk. um as well as some like
existing like a um like a like a like a
project like a sweet agent which is like
push the boundary of the coding cer base
of the agents. uh for your own need, you
might want to first like figure out like
what kind of the tools or functions you
want to have. Um and you find something
that is very easy to extendable such as
biomin to to to add them. Um yeah um I
think personally now is like we spend uh
our time is um saved a lot by using like
a coding um uh assistance such as cursor
and call code and u you could also like
um uh you you find some aentic framework
you want to work with and you download
some tools that or local tools you want
to use and you can just translate the
tools that are in that are be callable
by the your agentic framework just to
use like the cursor or cloud code
provided a few example and some
instructions and this can do a quite
decent job with a few rounds of
interactions
I'm going to move on to the next speaker
just for the sake of time but they will
be sticking around afterwards if you
have more burning questions for him
thank you so much thank you so much for
for being here. Yeah.
>> Heshan recently defended his PhD at
Stanford um in computer science also
with Yuri Laskcock's group. Um his work
also broadly focuses on AI and biio
medicine mainly looking at like
multimodal modeling therapeutics
development. Um GNN's agentic systems
for scientific hypothesis testing which
I'm sure we'll hear a lot more about
today. Um he's a Stanford Biox um SIGF
fellow. Um, and recent projects include
what we just mentioned with Biom, um, an
agent for biomedical sciences, and we're
really excited to hear more about it.
Thank you.
>> Great. Um, thank you.
>> Can you guys hear me?
>> Cool. Um, really excited to hear and
share about some of our recent works.
The title is building a virtual AI
scientist. Um so I will probably give
really really quick introduction because
Henry has already covered a lot of the
motivation of why we're building a kind
of a virtual scientist and then I'll
delve into our methods and also show
some recent work. So as you probably all
know bat discovery super fundamental
impact all kinds of different industries
ranging from drug discovery diagnosis
even like agriculture and so on. But if
we look at the day-to-day life of a
biologist um they're actually a lot of
time they're not doing science they're
doing like this manual complex tasks
right because real real world discovery
is extremely slow messy and complex for
for some examples like some papers on
some databases actually talking talking
some colleagues no one knows everything
um if you're a wab scientist if you want
to run some data analysis you need to
engage with some bathematician or
computer biologist and wait for a few
days and come back with the result and
then design some molecule with some
legacy tools, draft protocols, other
materials and so on so on. In the end
you get some potentially useful sub
results and the best case if take months
if not years uh to get it done. So this
basically motivates us to say okay part
of reason biomeic progress is limited by
you know lack of crazy innovative ideas.
Another reason is just limited by human
bandwidth. there just so much data
generated because of the new sequencing
technology out there. when we talk to a
lot of labs uh PIs they just complain
right they have 80% data just sit there
no one's analyzing it and then there's
also many scientists they have tons of
innovative ideas because of the limits
of bandwidths they can only do like one
test one idea at a time so this
gradually means that as the time goes by
the supply of these biomeatic expertise
just grows very very linearly founded by
the human uh but the demand of it just
grows exponentially so there's a huge
gap and the gap is basically the missing
insights the missing discoveries
So in order to close this gap we need a
new way of scaling this kind of a
expertise
and we're able to see that in AI agents
in other domains it's able to scale this
expertise for example in coding the
cursor right and the legal industry this
hobby and the agent hung already give a
really great great in-depth uh
introduction so I don't need to delve
into it but we're thinking can we extend
this AI agent to bio medicine and we do
believe that future biology is agentic
um one created a virtual AI biologist
automate bi research and there's a lot
of benefits that it can brings right
because for for example like now it can
perform task much much faster but when
I'm seeing many many examples where it
took months of work now it takes minutes
and also it enables uh tackling many
tasks at the same time because
everything happen in silicon so you can
actually have 20,000 agent working for
you at the same time if you want so this
actually remove cost of problem that we
met before for example P4 you because
you can
one gene at a time you you have the gene
selection problem but now if you have
20,000 gene then you can just have
20,000 agent looking at one gene for
each right so there's a lot of problem
can be solved with agent that's kind of
impossible before and also of course it
because of the reasoning ability the
intelligence layer can also suggest and
explore novel hypothesis as well
so we think this is a new way of doing
biome research so in the future it's
hard to imagine there's still still
people spending all this manual complex
It's like this kind of artisan in era in
contrast to uh here right now in the
future biologist will be working with a
class of a team of AI agent just get all
the task done and the impact is like uh
a single biologist now can be have equal
to impact of entire specialist team like
genetic geneticist can actually now
design proteins uh while lab scientists
can now do all the bionformatics tasks
and so on and also this is a great
democratization tool as well like great
education tool Because now if we can
encode all the knowledges from uh here
um and then in into the agent and then
distribute it to anyone uh on earth then
we're dramatically reducing the barrier
and everyone has the same educations and
also it's also the first time where the
every step of the discovery process are
being documented um because agent does
everything right. So you have the very
granular step of okay is you using this
tool and then that that tool. So it it
becoming a a record um so it's also
becoming a system record that can of the
of the discovery process itself. This
this also has a lot of new way uh a lot
of benefits as well. So overall we think
this is kind of new way of doing bal
research. Um so this talk we're
basically trying to uh motivate uh this
is great but also I guess more d into
more technical side which is how do we
build such a a biologist.
So to build such a biologist we also
need to look at how does a bi biology
research being done today. So here I'm
giving extremely high level some uh kind
of overview. Um so as to broadly uh you
need to generate a hypothesis for
example this is a hypothesis and usually
how you generate generate hypothesis
through reasoning through reading some
papers also doing some kind of analysis
as well and then given hypothesis you
need to validate it. So typically for
example bio statistician could look at
these multimodel data sets and then
write some simple scripts to generate p
values or it could be a more targeted
web experiment for example knocking out
the gene and see what's the phenotype
changes but overall you're able to see
that generating hypothesis and eving
hypothesis it involves multiple
individual tasks um and then to to do
this kind of a more high level um high
level kind of a task. So if we summarize
in a nutshell, we have the auto loop
which is the hypo generation and a
validation loop and once it's validated
you can you basically add it to your own
knowledge and then you can generate more
hypothesis. Um so there's auto loop and
within auto loop each step there's
massive number of individual tasks and
the and workflows. So if we model
biomeical research in this way then it
basically naturally gives us a recipe
for building a biologist. Basically we
need a generous biomeic agent that can
perform all kinds of different
individual tasks and then we also have a
genic system when we can just compose
everything together uh and and then to
do the generation and validation of
hyposis.
So this talk I going to focus on the the
on the foundation layer which is the
generous biomeic agent which is called
biom. Uh but we also have some work
which I'll briefly in two slides talk
about as well in generation and
validation as well. uh but I gonna spend
the most time talking about the biom
project.
So yeah so I guess I want to first
acknowledge my co-authors uh biom is a
it's a big project collaborating with
amazing people Serena Henchan here Jerry
and Ma and also with our collaborators
and adviserss as well.
So now we're looking at each individual
tasks. Now if we zoom in uh if you look
at uh how how how is the task get done
it's usually a loop of reasoning and
actions. So you reason about it and then
you think about it and then you perform
some stuff and then you look at the
result from that um kind of actions and
then you you will inform you then make
the next step and then just continues.
So it's like this kind of the loop of
reasoning actions and we know there's
recently there's tons of progress in LM
reasoning um uh but actually the
biometical action space is like
undefined.
So what do we mean? Basically the LM um
is like it's kind of disconnected to the
all the things that a biologist have
access to right. So the machine
predictors what experiments database
mathematics tools so and also so
basically the challenge is that we don't
have an environment um almost like a
scientist just keep thinking without
doing anything just then you can you
cannot do like real real discoveries.
So our motivation is okay so there's no
environment let's just build a one then
the first challenge is like biometic
action space is super super large
complex and scattered so we need we need
a method try to create an action space
at the first place
so we create a a new method uh we we
look at bio archive because in bio
archive there's like 25 subjects and it
covers the biology very broadly and then
in each subject of the bio archive we
retrieve 100 recent publish papers and
then for each paper we ask another agent
which is called our action discovery
agent read through each chunk of the
paper and ask the agent okay what kind
of tool what kind of software what kind
of databases that are necessary to
reproduce the result in that chunk of
the paper if it's if it's rep uh uh so
after screening it for like 2500 papers
you get a collection of tools software
databases and uh if you think about
theoretically speaking if you
implemented everything really really
quite correctly then you can kind of
reproduce all of these recent published
papers in an automatic fashion given the
um reasoning abilities is really good.
So but of course that's seriously
relatively speaking um but but I think
after this step you'll get a a good
snapshot of the possible um action space
out there. This is our kind of northstar
but it's actually not implemented yet.
So then we go ahead and then try to
implement some of it. But because there
were just thousands of kind of thousands
of tool and then databases and students
were scattered. Um so for our the first
version we just picked the most popular
and the most frequent uh subset of it
and we initially also tried to let to
create its own just have like action
generation agent as well. It just does
not perform really well. So here we we
curate like a manually kind of a very
high quality um subset of it which is
called a biome E1. E stands for
environment. So in this environment we
decompose it into three parts. The first
part is the software. So these include
our packages like D62. Um there's also
Python packages like biopython
image and there's also command line
tools like CCTA um um muscle and so on.
So, so, so here we actually we're not
defining predefined functions but just
we just create a single like software
environment that's compatible with all
of these and then the LM because it has
read all the documentation of these
popular softwares you can automatically
generate code to get a task done and
this is much more flexible compared to
predefine some functions uh based on
these softwares
and then there's the databases So for
these databases it includes like nomad
open genetics binding DB by gene regular
DB clean and so on so there's fitting 59
of these and it consists of two parts as
well. The first part is this more
massive web databases like terabytes of
data. So for that uh you can also define
a large number of like predefined
functions to cover this ID to that ID
for example. But we think if I want to
be g general we're actually using a sub
agent uh that takes in a natural
language query and have another LM to
generate the SQL and the kind of graphql
queries to extract the relevant data
sets on on the fly. So this way it's not
it's much more flexible. Of course,
that's the web to large web databases
and there's also the data leaks where
these are like private like like a list
of files uh where there's no API
endpoint uh but it's just like a raw
data data sets with like pandas data
frames and and so on. So the software
and databases are at are the core but we
also know um kind of actually sometimes
cannot generate on on its own because
there's so much private knowledge uh in
in our medicine so much knows and also
there's also involve tools that are
really complex. So here we we include uh
only tools that are very hard for our to
generate on its own. So these are the
specialist tools that's how we define
it. So this include like for example you
want to predict adamat property you need
some proprietary models. If you are
doing some wab cloning pro wab uh
protocols uh so we need to like manually
talk to some lab to grab some protocols
from them. If you are working on some AI
models like UC if dog so these will
tools that we give the LM access to in
our first environment.
Cool. So that's the E1. And next uh we
also build a agent that kind of
customized for this environment um
because this is a the first environment
that's really massive a huge um compared
to the other like environment like for
example it's like 20 tools and a very
simple software environment. So in order
for to accommodate this this this new
environment we develop some customized
modules. But first of all for example
retrieval um because you cannot put
everything into the context of uh like
it's just so much of them also most of
them are actually not relevant for the
question at hand. So for this single
given a question we have a retrieval
step which basically retrieve the most
relevant subset of tools software and
databases that are needed to answer this
question and uh for the retrieval we
also experiment on different kind of
techniques. Um and in the end we
realized that actually retrieval also
requires reasoning ability as well. So
uh we we have we put another sub agent
that does the retrieval as well. So in
the end it will get a subset of of of
relevant resources. So almost like a sub
environment just designed for this task
and after you retrieve it then you can
do reason about it. You you need to
think okay what's the steps uh needed to
utilize this resources to and also the
reasoning abilities to answer the
question at hand. So here in biom we a1
we kind of prompted to create a plan on
the fly. So part of reason is like we
want to be a general purpose agent. We
don't want to be like a a very very
focused agent. Part of reason is like we
know in the day-to-day life of a
scientist there just so much tasks so
much diverse task. Um if you are using
like each point solutions then you're
still kind of a need to switching
different tools. It's kind complic
complicated but if it's like a single
general purpose agent that you can tap
in any question and it give you some
answers just much more convenient. Um
but in order to do that then you will
need you cannot like predefine workflows
or like predefine like a concrete steps
for every task out there because there's
so much task right that's part of reason
we want the LM to generate on on fly uh
the the plans to tackle any any given
questions and we're pretty surprised to
find out is actually has read all the
papers and all the literatures and all
the all the internet so he's able to
generate a pretty reasonable plan um and
of course there's some very very
specialist task and we have some other
approach trying to tackle that but for
the most common popular tasks we're able
to observe that the plan generally by
the LM that's pretty reasonable to give
you answer and also the plan is actually
tracked along the entire process uh
maybe because there's some maybe
sometimes in the middle there's some uh
wrong answers and then you need to
update the plan it will also also
automatically up the plan as well
cool so now you have a plan now you need
to really get a task done right you need
to perform the steps so for each step of
plan uh we use uh coding as a way to to
to solve um to kind of perform the step
so uh I think this [clears throat] kind
of already become almost like a standard
as h mentioned with the call code and
things like that like when we develop it
actually um uh it's actually like one
half years ago so it was still a bit
unclear like coding is the way to do uh
but For us, we are using coding because
it's almost like a necessity because for
our environment, we don't define any
prespecified functions on the softwares.
So it has to use coding to execute these
softwares and also we wanted to interle
the software databases and prescite tool
intelligence. So coding is a basically a
way of general task solving uh that can
interle them and also can do like more
complex logics for example for loop if
and else uh this just gives much more
flexible flexibility compared to this
kind of a direct function calling
approach where it's constrained by the
list of tools available.
So this is a kind of general overview of
our agent. It's actually very simple
kind of it's not like a very complex
architecture. Um part of reason we also
as as I'll also mention later we're
going to train the models as well. So
having a simple agent architecture also
gives the uh the it's much easier uh
when we do the end to end kind of a
agent uh as well. So just give an
overview give a task uh give a question
from the users and you have a retrieve
from uh the relevant tools and you will
reason about it and then you will code
uh and then you have an execution result
and more reasoning and more to use and
so on and until you think okay this is
the answer that can return to the user.
So that's our uh method and then I'll
delve into a tons of evaluation that we
did uh to show that it's actually have
30 signals. So we first used utilize
fusion house lab bench. Uh so we use the
development set from like 45 questions
from these data sets just to tune the
agent to just tune the tools and these
are like database queries and sequence
manipulations as well. And on hold out
test set we're able to see the biom
achieve human level uh performance on on
on these two specific uh tasks and it
also outperforms all the baselines
including RMS react coding agent it's
literature agent coding plus research
agent and also this is the ablation uh
where we instead of using coding where
we use a tool use and yeah but this is
kind of a like more like a sanity check
because we kind of we have the other
side So here on completely no
development set benchmarks on humanity
last exam
our agent is also able to perform uh
pretty well uh on completely zero shot
uh settings
but but actually all of these three
benchmarks are like exam style like
multiple choice questions. They are not
like real world research questions. So
we set out to kind of go ahead and then
create a new class of evals that
correspond to real world uh research. So
this include like GW was collagen
detections. uh for example you have GW
was hit there's a neighborhood there's
many genes which one is the color genes
and then the perturbation screen design
you want to design a screen you want to
select 50 genes uh for like T- cell for
T- cell exhaustion which gene to select
and also single science annotations
microbound text analysis repurposing red
diagnosis and so on and so on this is a
snapshot of uh the thousands of tasks
out there but it's a a snapshot of the
most some of the popular tasks out there
and for all these tasks we're able to
get some proxy of the ground truth from
the users. For example, the collagen
detection, we have some expert annotated
deeply. For the perturbation screen
design, we have uh like for this
specific cell like context of interest,
some people have already done the genome
screen. So, we know whatever 50 genes
you choose, we already know the post
posturb effect. Um and for single sign
annotation, we have the alter annotation
as well. So these are all like some
proxies of the ground shoes and we can
measure how good is the agent align with
this kind of proxy and overall we to
find out also completely zero shot no
development set our agent is able to
have best performance for them
but still we feel like this is still
also some benchmark with some kind of
proxy of the grues I think we really
want to give this tool to the scientists
let them try out and then see if it
really uh kind of useful for them so we
first partnered with a few labs just to
test it out. So for example, we work
with Li Tong's lab. So so Li was doing a
lot of functional genome functional
screen on like crispers genetic
experiments and so on. So one one of his
uh students uh was was doing this
cloning. Um so I have I have a plasma
sequence here. I have to clone a crisper
guy targeting the human B2 gene into
this plasma. I want to generate a plasma
map and a step-by-step guidance. So
instead of human do it it give the task
to the bounty and the bounty just go
ahead and then do the plasma analysis gi
design or design near and so on so on so
so on it takes around after eight
minutes to complete the task
and then b is able to generate a wellap
coning protocols uh in a very in details
for example the the the olo sequence
here the primary sequence here and also
each step by
uh plans and the scientists will
basically need to just need to follow
the protocols and and then perform the
clone experiments and Jerry there here
just really perform the experiment
following the protocol and he's able to
find this successful um and he's happy
so he you know I mean cloning cloning is
not like a it's not the the the craziest
noble kind of task but it's like super
frequent super super kind of a involved
it still takes some time right few hours
and navigating different from different
tools snapping a um to generate one even
one construct but biomic does it on in
10 minutes and they just need a natural
language prompt and just wait there and
after a coffee you'll just get get a get
the result
so later we kind of further want to test
it out uh to like a more rigorous
settings so so Jerry here created 10
more tasks that correspond to this like
day-to-day gene editing experiments and
then We recruited a trainee who is a
Stanford master students um and uh she
has done cloning before and also
recruited expert who has done who's a
postto in this lab and she has done
cloning for the past eight years like a
real world kind of expert
and we asked I also do the LM and biom
and we for all these four entities we
asked them to do this 10 tasks and then
we have another expert just blindly
review all these 10 tasks and rate how
complete is how accurate it is and then
we're able to find that bomi has pretty
similar grade as the expert and it's
much much better than trainees of of
course much much better than LM LM just
kind of hallucinates all the time for
the this kind of very granular protocols
so actually this gap is actually really
interesting because the trainee um like
usually training needs to bug the PH
sing P to get a task done but now
actually you can just need to talk to
Bomi has similar performance you know
biom will never say no to any request.
Yeah.
So, so that's on the web part and then
you also we also able to find that uh
the agent is really really useful for
the dry lab data analysis as well. So
here we partnered with uh micro
standards lab with MTA um basically they
have a lot of wearable sensor data like
glucose monitoring activities and uh
they're like 458 raw style sheets like
super comp like there's a lot of missing
data in there and just a pretty manual
and kind of complex task uh for for
humans. But the more complex it is
actually the most suitable is the agent
right because the agent just feed into
the folders and then it just goes in and
then just iterate over everything. Um so
we give the task to the agent uh it have
um you know the data set pre-processing
some doing doing all of these steps and
after 35 minutes it generate tons of
visualizations and also generates some
interesting conclusions and
interestingly uh Ma when she did the
same analysis um she also has a similar
similar kind of conclusion but the agent
actually did a much more visualization
much more explore much more experiments
as well and uh she it took her like
three weeks and taking working two to
three hours per day to get a task done.
But the the agent was able to complete
it in approximately 35 minutes.
So we are able to see that on this kind
of manual complex data analysis agent is
tremendously helpful.
But actually for this example uh it's
all like Excel sheets. So all this kind
of uh um uh like uh it it does not
require like specialist software
packages to do this unprocessing. So
here we are actually also demonstrated
with a more complex example on this
single single taxi data set this multiom
data set where it involves very complex
softwares and and a choice of databases
and and kind of the steps. So hung here
uh was want wanted to an analyze this
multiomx data sets and then uh it gives
some kind of detail instructions and the
agent just be able to follow the
instruction use pyynic uh jung boost
this target and so on so on and after a
few hours it generate all the
visualizations and also generate um kind
of some interesting findings as well. So
here is the this no TFS um that show
hierarchic activities across the scatter
lineages which is is not reported in the
original author's papers and also the GT
and Pierre who who are the biologists
also manually check the traces and and
find out they actually align with how
they also perform the task as well.
So cool. So these are some like quick
case studies that we demonstrate in
paper and since our the launch of Bomni
we also increasingly realized that you
know we want to basically create an
operating system of B research that just
can defragment all these database
software tools and putting them into the
same roof. Um and uh we we make the the
open source package like really really
easy to integrate this new integrations
and uh we also realize that every new
integration enables new task
capabilities in a compounding way right
because you add a new tool but this tool
can be used by multiple tasks and then I
keep adding this tool you're unlocking
more and more kind of a capabilities.
So here just want to demonstrate a few
of these examples. So we partner with
Siverse uh who kind of host a various
list of softwares in for single cell
spatial and perturbation data analysis
such as porti scampy um and and like svi
and things like that. So here uh after
equipping adding the software to the
bioni uh it's able to do like spatial
data analysis for example. So here we
give an example like given a sick fish
data set uh we ask it to explore it
freely and analyze it and identify
interesting structures and generate some
hypothesis
it so it made a plan and then after like
a few like a few hours I to generate a
few interesting hypothesis and well also
with the post experiments and the
expected outcome as well.
So, so that's on the single side
analysis and then we also partnered with
Tamar Bio who's like a API writers for
this protein design models. Um, so here
we can now do ping design uh with biom u
for example g studing porting sequence
you want to iteratively optimize it
thermal stability. The biom basically
given a sequence it it make the make a
plan to use alpha fold to make a
prediction on the protein sequence and
it use another model thermal mpn to
predict the thermal stabilities and then
it look at different databases
literature'ses and also look at the
predictions and the the structure itself
and propose the mutations to modify the
protein sequence to optimize the thermal
stabilities and it's it and it does it
in like several rounds until it kind of
improve on the on the thermal stability
And so here's the the answer like all
autonomously it's like this is the
optimized sequence and this is the in
each cycle what is the mutation close
and this is also the rational right here
this at the early early 80 uh 80 third
positions the transfer from like Q
mutated to I and the reason is like it
has enhanced hydrophobic co-acking and
so on so and it's also able to see that
the the thermal stability also just uh
uh kind of increases um as the cycle
goes by
and u and also we partner with pallet
robot which is like a u like a python
interface um for all kinds of different
web lab equipments like Hamilton open
and so on because we think in the future
if you really want to build a biologist
that can just automate everything like
from data analysis all the way to well
experiment all the way just to give you
something um you know like a very long
horizon fashion the web part is
definitely a bigger a big bottleneck uh
and I think it's still very early right
now but we partnering with pilot robot
to demonstrate some early capabilities
um so for example right now you can just
use natural language queries to uh
orchestrate like liquid handlers or some
other robotics as well here is a is a
demo so this is really bly in action you
just put it in a natural language query
um and it's able to basically move move
kind of plates from plates um in the
future as pal robot is kind of expanding
to more and more robotics covering kind
of more operations where where we're
we're kind of thinking like you know in
the future it's like another agent
create a prompt uh for the pan robot to
do it and then will also return the
result and then it will inform it to do
the next step and it just continues um
until it has the answers.
Yeah, as you can see it it successfully
move from wheel to world.
Cool. So these are also just kind of
some demonstration because we we it's a
general purpose agent. We can do all
kinds of different u capabilities. So
we're able to try a few things out like
for example you can do varying
interpretations for human analysis and
we can do automatic profiling for J
developers and we could also do some
like manual task like download some
random data sets online which actually
takes some time as well. Um and then
also do like screen designs as I
mentioned also do some real data
diagnosis because often it involves more
than justification phenotypes but also
you give like the VCF files then you
will need to uh basically run some
binformatics pipelines and use reasoning
ability to integrate it with some the
phenotypes and then create a diagnosis
and also dockings annotation and so on.
Yeah. So we open source biom uh you know
to public and uh since then I think a
lot of people are contributing uh new
tool data set and softwares as well. Um
and also we also add like MCP support so
we can expose it to to the I don't know
like other uh like cloud code and things
like that as well.
So we also build a web platform that for
scientists that can quickly just give a
natural language query and it'll get the
task done. Um so here this is the
platform uh interface. So I'm just
giving you an example here. Here for
example this is a s the the the spatial
data analysis example here initially it
makes the plan um and then you write a
lot of code and then this code will be
automatically run in a sandbox with the
result and then you will just keep doing
it and um yeah just going through all
this iterations and uh it generates some
visualization as well like the
spatializations
um yeah and then you will once it gets
it done you will also like black the
step is and then just continue the next
step and then continue until all the
steps in the plan are finished and you
will return to the user with the final
report. Um yeah that you can immediately
use as well.
Cool. Yeah and it's available right now
at biom standard review. Feel free to
try that out as well.
And I think since we launched it we also
able to amazingly find out a lot of try
to scare people like real world like
moving beyond academia right this so
this is a number of user in the first 80
days. also able to amazingly find all
these pharma scientists actually using
it across different use cases ranging
from target discovery um like add meta
property predictions and all the way
even to the clinical side of things
cool so I think that's the you know was
the the first project first phase of
bing project so what's next I'll share
some more recent works on um the things
that are we are very excited about uh so
I think it briefly kind of a it
generally falls into two two categories.
The first one is want to achieve expert
level performance and the second one is
this kind of a when we have the
generalist biometical agent the
foundation layer then we can start
building the agenic system to compose
them and to get more even more kind of
new capabilities. Um so here I will
demonstrate hypos validation and also to
develop some biology new algorithms as
well.
Um so the first task is uh how do we
achieve actual level performance because
biom can get a get a task done and give
you a report no matter what task you
give. But it's also yeah we able to see
that for many tasks it's able to give
like expert level performance but for
also a long tail of many many tasks it's
not there yet. Um so how do we improve
the agent in a systematic way to achieve
accessible level performance for any
tasks? That's kind of the a very
important problems. Um and I was
thinking if there's a scalable way to do
it as well. So as Helen mentioned like
reinforcement learning recently has got
a lot a lot of attention because it's
it's a extremely scalable way. Uh you
just define the data the reward and you
just train agent uh just it will figure
out on its own uh like he climb uh on
its own. Right? So this a so this this
the idea is very appealing also for bio
medicine as well because we can collect
a lot of b data with some reward and
then you train uh end to end and then
just improve it.
Naturally the I is also I think very
interestingly how uh is a kind of enable
potentially a new way of doing things
right because if you think about how how
our current way of doing things is also
scientists follow some like a protocol
some convention like se sequence of
steps and this convention was also
generated through this trials and errors
by a group of researcher maybe like 10
years ago
but it's not necessarily the optimal way
uh because it could be there's optim
more optimal sequence of steps to do it
And I think the IO is a very nice way
because basically ask it to do massive
number of trials and errors and then
given a reward it's able to see okay
this actually this path is actually more
optimal and then maybe it's a more than
it could be a way to learn this kind of
a superhuman level convention a new way
of doing the same task.
So we're inspired by that and we built
the first version of it uh which is
called army R0 uh because it's it's we
think there's so much things to add on.
So that's why we call it R0 instead of
R1. Um but basic basic idea is like we
still use our environment the E1 and
also the A1 which is the agent
architecture. It's like a very simple
agent architecture and then we do like
trajectory like roll out. So you collect
a bunch of trajectory with the answer
from the agent and for we define 10
tasks with a predefined reward and you
can let the OM know okay for for this
kind of trajectory you you're doing
really well and for this kind of
trajectory it's not and then the
during the back propagation is able to
automatically figure out what kind of
steps is important what kind of step is
not and then by aggregation it's able to
generate a new trajectory that is that
is kind of a optimized the the reward.
So this joint work done with led by Ryan
and also collaboration with she ga Yuri
and also with the sky group at Berkeley
and uh for some initial results we're
able to see that even use some open
source models like a billion queen
models after training it's able to get
really good performance on in domain uh
tasks for example here we are able to
have 85% improvement and actually the
performance is actually on par with the
clos models as well and If we use a 32
billion model, it's actually even able
to outperform this closed source models
and uh because the performance is so
sign so significant we're thinking this
is a potentially a very interesting
recipe to um kind of do the here climb
and achieve expert level performance
and we're also able to find that
improvement is also very consistent
across different subtasks. So here this
is the list of 10 tasks we are using um
for now crisper crisper delivery G was
color gene g paralizations and also
patient patient gene detection is also
like design the screen and things like
that and you can see that actually this
agent I think in this 10 task [snorts] I
think our agent is has the best
performance in like seven to eight uh
task as well so it's also very
consistent
yeah so I think after that we're also
thinking a lot about you know is this is
really the way to go. Uh we're still
thinking about it. So we'll be also
curious to hear your thoughts as well.
Um but if you we really look at like
first of all is it like similar to
humans? um because for IIO it actually
require hund hundreds of examples for
same task for the trials and errors as
well but to throw out but for real world
biologist they they don't have the
privilege to do hundreds of trials right
because it's so expensive to run uh on
one task and they just need a few uh and
also the biology domain like I think the
hard one of the hardest challenge that
we face when we do the R0 project
actually the reward function is very uh
hard to define uh there's many the task
there just no reward. Um so because of
because it just biology is intrinsically
low data right so how do you um kind of
define rewards uh in this setting in a
large scale fashion it's also a bit
unclear and recently I think there's
also lots of lots of discussion around
this idea around system prompt learning
where um you just try it once and then
you have another LM to reason okay what
kind of lessons did you learn then put
the lessons into the prompt as kind of
in the memory or something like that so
we also exploring all these kind of
ideas trying to uh achieve expert level
performance in a in a more kind of data
efficient fashion.
So so that's the first category of
[snorts] task we're we're looking at
right now and another task is also
another category is like this multi-
aenting systems. So uh as as ham briefly
mentioned um I think getting a task done
is just one component of this more
global hypothesis validation. So
typically given hypothesis there's
usually multiple different kind of
falsification experiment that you want
to do to really forify a hypothesis. So
here uh in working with uh Ying Ryan
Michael and Emanuel and Yuri we proposed
a new method that actually was based on
biom agent uh that interle multiple of
them and then to have a more rigorous
approach to do hypo validations. I think
the idea is like we have one agent which
is called the experiment design agent
given the hypothesis it will basically
we ask it do some iterations to design a
falsification experiment to falsify the
main hypothesis
uh and then after um it is done we'll
have a experiment execution agent which
is based on biom omni to execute it for
example like writing a lot of code uh
observe it and the result and then just
continue and generate a p val
and then because usually for a main
biology hypothesis there's often usually
all kinds of different subcation
experiments we need some way to
aggregate it in a rigorous fashion to
have some kind of sequential error
control this relates to the E values
that Helen mentioned u to give like more
rigorous error control in a sequential
fashion and so overall we're able to
this genic system able to kind of
control the force discovery rate sorry
control type one error rate and still
improve power by a
So we test it out in the real world. We
recruit like 10 PhD level uh scientists
and then give them the same level a same
kind of hypothesis to validate. So they
uh and we able to find that they have
similar type rate similar power as well
and also it takes much much shorter for
uh but takes and and it generates much
more experiment write more code uh than
humans but interestingly it's able to
also find kind of a they're doing pretty
similar things right they're designing
similar kinds of falsification
experiments like testing the expression
correlation from G from GTA interaction
network from some physical physical from
protein point interaction networks
EQTL data sets um and there's also
proposed some new ones and human have
some new ones as well and also they're
using all kinds of different diverse
statistical tests as well.
So we're able to say like by composing
this agent together we're able to do
like more high level uh tasks uh that
enable like new capabilities for for
scientists
and uh and lastly I also want to
highlight a new work that's in
collaboration which is led by Alistister
uh working with Li and Martin here uh is
basically using agent to also develop
our algorithm. So actually the first few
years of my PhD before the agent stuff I
was also just developing this AI bio
models like just on the biological data
sets and I often find that it often the
best model is often involves uh
embedding this kind of biological
inductive bias right into the model. So
you you need to know both AI and biology
deeply in order to create like a
customized models like alpha flow. Alpha
is a great example like embeds all this
kind of prior knowledges the deep
knowledge about the data and trans and
convert it into the modules in the AI
models and make it really work. So we
think the AI agent is actually maybe the
for the first time the maybe the best
single entity that knows both AI and
biology so deeply. So it can potentially
de develop much much better AI plus biom
models. Uh uh yeah. So here we we
created the first uh versions of it uh
like a like a initial attempt which the
basic idea is like given a task. You
have some uh kind of the uh validation
set as well and then you ask the agent
to collect all these domain knowledges
and then create propose some solutions
and then start iterating on on on this
on these solutions and for this during
the iteration for each step you will
have the validation set performance and
also from the literature we also gather
a lot of instructions on how do you
update uh uh these solutions and there's
a lot of details as well but overall
that's the idea. So you can iteratively
just optimize this algorithm in order to
beat and in order to have like great
validation set performance as well.
So in the in the paper there's much more
in-depth benchmarks. Uh but I think
really interestingly we kind of at least
they really apply it to human genetics
tasks. For example this is SDIS which
was opposed by Martin uh while he was
actually had here. Um so it's like a
disease critical cell population cell
type uh detection algorithms that has
like kind of forces control but I need
to detect as much disease critical cell
types as possible. So the so the tus AI
just takes in the original SDIS and then
just start optimizing it. So also not
notably the T AI can do both auto
optimization from existing algorithms
also just can completely generate from
scratch as well. But for this example,
it's basically generating from some uh
base checkpoints. But it's able to have
like much much better power like 40%
more power. And then it's able to also
have kind of same level of force
discovery rate control as well. And then
it's also able to detect like no cell
types that match with truth and also
detect no cell type when you when we
apply it to some autoimmune diseases.
And interestingly uh it takes 24 hours
and the agent tried like 136 versions
and at a cost of 30 cents. Uh but the
original author take like 10 try 10
versions of it over three months uh to
get it done. So we're we're really
thinking in the future maybe the next
generation of AI plus bio models
actually generated by agent. So we need
to actually train the agent to how do we
generate uh these AI plus biom models.
Cool. So I guess uh that's all for my
talk. Thank you. I want to talk my thank
my co-author again and uh this is also
my contact information.