and uh Juliet, we can't wait to hear
about the model,
maybe.
>> Oh, okay. That goes a little little too
fast. Um, well, hello everyone. My name
is Juliet Simpson. I am a researcher at
ENL. I'm excited to be talking to you
about the modeling work that we've been
doing. I know I've gotten a lot of great
feedins from earlier today. Um I will
just start by noting that uh this is
geared a little bit more towards like
teaching people about generally the
modeling that happens for these systems
and a little bit less towards results.
So if you're interested in that, feel
free to talk to me. And also um I'm
going to be talking about modeling for
these systems within the context of a
model that we've been building out on
the legup project. Um, but just know
that there are a lot of other models out
there. Um, each tailored to kind of do
some slightly different things. Um, and
a lot of great options. And I'm just
doing this kind of within one context.
So to get started, I'm talking
specifically today about technoeconomic
modeling. And that involves two
components if you're not familiar with
it. Um, as you might guess by the name,
the technical model and the economic
model. And this is really important
because it allows us to think about
trade-offs between impacts to technical
design, how that impacts operation and
performance of a system and then looking
at the costs of that, the economic
impact.
Now, why does all of this modeling uh
why is it matter? Why is it important?
This really helps us to answer a lot of
questions without having to go dig holes
in the ground. um we can start to think
a little more critically ahead of time
before the design and before the build.
We can think about what communities does
the geothermal network make sense in. Uh
does it make sense to just go for
geothermal bore holes or should we pull
in some of the other thermal resources
that have been mentioned today? What
kind of monthly payment might be
required from customers or what expected
total costs might there be? There's lots
of questions on that side of the
economics as well. Um, so having
something that can help um, people start
to think about the finance side as well.
And then after you build, what would
happen if you added one more house to
the loop or what would happen if you
wanted to change a little bit the
performance set point for the
temperatures or the operation or the
speeds of the loop. Um, so being able to
work with some sort of um, modeling
option, digital twin, something that
lets you change those parameters before
going out and impacting your customers
in the real world.
Couple of components that I'm then going
to talk through in a minute. um both on
the physical system side, a lot of the
major components that we've already
mentioned today, understanding your
building loads, knowing um when they're
going to need heating and cooling
throughout the year and how much of it.
Understanding your opportunities for
thermal resources in an area. Um
capturing the distribution system
correctly. That could include knowing
whether you want to go for a one pipe
system or two pipes. How big is the pipe
going to be? How much thermal inertia is
there in the water or whatever working
fluid you have moving in that pipe? How
well are your heat pumps going to
perform? What's their coefficient of
performance look like with different
entering temperatures?
And then something we've discussed a
little less today, the economic side.
Um, estimating capital cost, operating
cost, maintenance is all really
difficult. It's something that we we
certainly struggle with, but it's really
important to these systems. And then
also thinking about the finance plan.
what's your cost recovery look like? Um,
who is paying for it? It's probably
going to have a big impact on that. Um,
but that then has an impact at the end
of the day on what customer payments
look like as well.
Now, we've tried to put both halves of
those models into something we're
working on at ENL called heat nets. This
stands for heat and economic analysis
tool for network thermal systems. ENL
has been building out this tool in
collaboration with heat as part of the
legup project. And so we're really
excited to have both halves of it up and
running now. So we have this code that
is written in Python. It's intended to
long-term be open source and we're
working towards having that being a
public GitHub repository. The first half
is the physics-based model. That's a
reduced order model. As Isbel mentioned
earlier, the idea there is that it's a
little bit more uh high level. It really
builds on a lot of other more detailed
models to capture the energy flow around
the network and the use of electricity
over time.
The second model is the economic model
used to calculate uh economic metrics of
the system as well.
So I'm going to give a little bit of
highle information about both of those
models before talking about what kind of
questions we can answer with them. So
first on the reduced order side, this is
for capturing the physics of what's
actually happening on the loop. Where is
heat moving over time? Where is water
moving? Uh how much electricity is being
used for that whole process. The major
components that we're capturing are
shown here in this simple diagram, but
know that this is showing one building
when you might have 50. And these are
just going to be um repeated over time.
The main backbone of this model is the
ambient temperature loop. So, a lot of
the modeling effort here goes into the
effort of capturing how does heat move
physically around this loop. How much
thermal inertia is in there? So if you
dump in some heat, how quickly is it
going to change temperature and how
quickly is that going to then propagate
around the loop and affect all of the
customers?
Then plugging in and exchanging heat
with that we have all of the buildings.
Um so that requires doing some building
modeling, understanding their loads over
time, understanding how the heat pumps
are going to perform given different
entering temperatures um from that main
thermal loop. There's also all of your
thermal sources and syncs. So in this
case we're mostly focused on borehole
fields. Um but there could be other ones
as well. Um this modeling is being done
um like I mentioned at a reduced order
level. So we're relying on collaborators
who are doing some more detailed
modeling including models that we're
getting from Lawrence Berkeley National
Labs um to be able to look at what is
our bore hole bore hole performance look
like over time.
And then finally, having some sort of
central control control station. Um,
being able to model the circulation
pumps to move the fluid around. Um, in
our models right now, we always account
for the option of an auxiliary heating
and cooling system. And that allows us
to really play with our temperature
bounds and um, how many buildings we
have on the loop. And then having a
control decision architecture that
determines how do all of these pieces
run together.
Just as a quick example of some of the
outputs we can get from that. On the
left we're showing one that shows uh
spatial trends. So as you move around
the loop, this is done in a straight
line. We can imagine the end feeds back
into the beginning. Um this relates back
to what Isbel was saying earlier that
you see changes in temperature as you
move around the loop. And then you also
see things happen over time. So the one
on the right hand side is showing uh
every hour throughout a year how is heat
being exchanged with the loop. So in
this case we're showing building loads
and bore hole loads um in blue and green
and those are generally opposites. So in
the wintertime buildings take heat out
of the loop and the borehole field puts
heat in. We see the opposite trend in
the summertime
and then some additional auxiliary heat
in this model. Um, and so you could see
maybe where there's areas uh that you
need um you might need some additional
heat and you can consider trade-offs for
is it worthwhile to have some sort of
electric boiler provide that or to drill
more bore holes. And again, this comes
down to a lot of trade-offs.
The other half of this model is
economic.
Um I will warn you that this is the side
that I spend a little bit less time on
um at work but um this takes in a lot of
inputs from um the physicsbased model.
So the physics based model will tell you
how much electricity are all the
components using over time also what
were the design specs you chose for the
system and then you have to give it some
additional information. So what
financial assumptions are you putting in
um how much of this project uh how much
is financed with debt? How much is
upfront? um what kind of assumptions are
you making on incentives you might
received? That all comes together into a
variety of outputs that we can look at.
One that we're particularly excited
about right now is something we're
calling um LCO X. Um this builds off of
the standard levelized cost of energy
equation, but here we're allowing for
pulling in multiple energy flows. Um so
it's no longer just energy. um our costs
are including both capital cost and the
cost of the electricity to operate the
system and then our thing that we're
producing in this case is heating and
cooling to buildings. Um right now we're
looking at that as just the absolute
values of them. How much total um you
know uh help are you putting into these
buildings to maintain their climate. Um
so heat and cool are equally valued at
the moment.
And we can then get more granular with
those outputs as well. So just an
example of something that you could look
at. Um this is just using
not random numbers but uh example
numbers for some example building. You
could start to look at how much energy
consumption do you expect throughout a
year? How does that then trickle down
into what might that user depending on
um what cost recovery is being used?
What might their monthly bill payment
look like? Things like that. So now we
can start to go all the way from design
decisions down to monthly bills for um
individual homes.
So just kind of to wrap up that this
idea um showing how the data flows all
together. We have first this reduced
order model. This is physics-based. We
have a lot of different inputs that come
into this. It really relies on highle
modeling done elsewhere that all can
come together.
And a major output from that is the time
series electricity consumption.
There's some other inputs that we're
going to need to get to the economic
model. So we start to have to think
about component cost, estimating those,
knowing what our financial assumptions
are, and then eventually feeding that
all into an economic model where we can
get outputs like that LCOX value I was
mentioning, also net pleasant value,
internal rate of return, um, and
something we're calling thermal energy
price.
And then you get to answer the fun
questions. So this is what we're really
here for. We build out all of this
modeling so that we can start to answer
interesting questions. So I have two
quick examples here to wrap up. The
first is what if you change the minimum
loop temperature. Um so in this case
we're assuming with the way our control
system that we've built is set up um you
have to decide uh when do the pumps ramp
up, when does the borehole get used,
when does auxiliary heat turn on in
order to maintain some minimum
temperature.
In this case study that we did, we found
that as you increase that minimum loop
temperature, the cost to the utility
goes up greatly. This makes sense.
They're having to work really hard to
maintain a higher temperature, but the
cost of the consumer goes down slightly
because their heat pump is working more
efficiently now. So, you see this
trade-off here. Well, in this case,
we're talking about annual electricity
costs, not considering capital cost that
goes into that. But um we have to think
about how benefits are shared to all
parties involved in a geothermal
network.
And as one final example, you can also
think about what happens as you change
the number and location of bore holes
around the loop. And here we see that if
you just think about electricity system
costs, electricity usage, um more bore
holes means less energy is used. um in
this case because we're not needing any
sort of auxiliary electric boiler. Uh
but you have to consider that weight
against economic impacts. So how much
did they cost? Was that cost worth it?
What's your trade-off look like there?
So thank you all for listening to me
talk about modeling. I think that
modeling can really help us to answer a
lot of key questions as we move forwards
with building out geothermal networks.
Um, one model that we're excited about
for it is heat nets, which I've talked
through some examples of today. Um, but
again, a lot of great modeling going on
in the space that we're excited for. Um,
but we're looking forward to the
opportunity to think about the um,
analysis of how these design and
operational decisions impact both
performance and economics of these
systems.
Thank you.