Thanks so much. Awesome. Um, well, yeah,
it's a a pleasure to be here. Can
everyone hear me
clearly? Okay. Um, right. So, I come
from two stop two stops away. And, um, I
want to introduce you to a, uh, concept
that has recently kind of completely
reformulated how I think about where and
when we should deploy AI because if I
look at the AI for society seminar, you
know, call, it's about the role of AI in
society. Oh, so um let me start there.
When should we use AI and when shouldn't
we? I think this distinction between
consequentialist thinking and what um
professor Talbot and philosophy calls
dialectical activities is a really
important um compass for us to think
about. So consequentialist thinking is
reasoning when you're reasoning about
actions and it's all about the ends
right. Um a lot of HCI work that's my
home field human computer interaction is
about you know providing new means to
get to the same ends or um uh new means
to get to new ends and uh so you know if
I'm at a hackathon uh maybe I don't care
about the code that is being generated
for me I just care that it has certain
qualities that um you know reflect the
um uh the the new idea that I have and
if I'm dealing with email I hate email
um I care about the relationships that
email supports and I don't want to harm
them but the email itself. You know, if
something could do that for me, that
would be great. Um, whereas with
dialectical activities, they are a
really special subset of activities
where the they are have intrinsic value.
Uh
oh. And um they have intrinsic value
that is revealed through repeated deep
engagement. Right? So um this was my uh
fuzzy rubber duck during my PhD in the
building across the street where I was
uh AI assisted programming didn't exist
back then. So I had to repeatedly deep
deeply engage with the codebase that I
was building for like the key um uh part
of my thesis. And only because I was
repeatedly deeply engaging with it did I
realize that the exercise of
implementing a scheme interpreter and
scheme that we used to have to do
freshman year um was was replaying
itself because I was implementing a
Python interpreter in Python, right?
that that kind of epiphany moment would
not have been uh available to me if an
AI had shortcircuited the process of
engaging deeply with my code. Uh
similarly, you know, um if you're you're
writing a thank you note to a friend or
you're reflecting on the meaning of a
relationship in in a in a eulogy, right?
If an AI uh wrote that for you based on
a bullet list of like uh milestones in
the relationship, um did you really get
the value out of that exercise? um uh
such as honoring a
friend. Um necessary conditions of
learning is a um is a a book about a
particular theory of learning that I
have repeatedly engaged with and it has
revealed new insights to me every single
time. AI cannot read it for me. Um or if
it did, I wouldn't have those insights.
Um um and also, you know, um if it uh
had summarized this paper that
introduced to me this concept at all, I
wouldn't be uh probably have as
influenced. So
um teaching is an example of a
dialectical activity. Uh giving talks I
have learned in the last 48 hours new
things about my work because I was
forced to explain it again in a new way
to a new audience. So for that I am very
grateful already. Um uh even you know
parenting um most people are not
consequentialist about parenting. um
they would not take the offer of uh
exporting their kid to be raised
elsewhere provided that the kid one of
reaching 18 would have sufficiently
comparable you know kind of beliefs uh
uh uh to
you. Okay. So why should we care about
making this distinction? Argue this is a
key distinction for deciding about when
to use AI because
uh when you're working with
consequentialist uh activities AI truly
can help. But if you try to apply AI to
a dialectical activity, people who
already know the value that would be
revealed if they engage with it deeply
will consider your tool useless or
harmful because it would shortcircuit
that value. Or if they've never
repeatedly engaged with it um already,
if they've never, you know, thought
deeply about programming and they are
starting off their um journey as
programmers with AI assistance, um they
may never realize that that value can
come through, right? you're cutting off
their ability to discover the
dialectical nature of the
activity. So, um there's a kind of
preient comment in a uh paper by my
colleague uh Kristoff Guyos and his uh
former PhD student Ken Arnold um at
IUI20 where they um they're looking at
predictive text and how it affects what
people wrote. They said for um well, for
the most most part people wrote more
efficiently with predictive text
systems. This may have come at the cost
of thoughtfulness, right? And this here,
you know, when you are trying to measure
the impact of introducing AI or some
other smart intelligence into your um uh
into your activity, you know, if you
treat people like transcribing machines,
you consider it to be a consequentialist
activity that you are accelerating.
Sure, you can say we made them more
efficient, right? But the the writing
was more predictable predictable that
they produced in that study. It was less
thoughtful, right? And so because you
didn't treat people as thoughtful human
being, you know, human beings that um
might in the process of writing, if
you've heard the phrase writing is
thinking, come up with new ways of um uh
new insights as they engage with the
activity and you're cutting that off. So
um to be meta about it, right? Um as I
mentioned, writing this talk is a
dialectical activity. Um I have to
re-engage with the concept of
dialectical activities, resee my own
work through this lens.
um go uh and and keep going back and
forth with um Howchi Zang's philosophy
paper on this and there's also
non-diical activities, right? So,
searching for sufficiently appropriate
photos for the examples that I've
provided, copying and pasting these
previously made slides and and
rejiggering them um because of this new
lens through which I'm looking at them.
Uh citation lookup, all of these things
I'd love AI help with. it will not
diminish the activity's value. Um, but
the dialectical activities, if I didn't
realize they were dialectical, I might
um mistakenly I think mistakenly design
AI to help with them or accept AI's
help. And we'll um which I would argue
uh in this case would fundamentally
remove some of its dialectical nature.
So first takeaway would be that um if we
were thinking about AI in society, we
should think really carefully about what
components of an activity are
dialectical and then be very careful
about designing systems that affect
those components. I'm not saying that
you can't have AI play some role in
there. Um uh but um if you are not you
know it's it um exactly what you can and
can't do without fundamentally changing
the dialectical activity I think is is
um uh something that we need to consider
in every situation. Okay. So I've
explained the concept of dialectical
activities. Let's look at some of my own
um uh work through this lens. So I
promised two systems. First about AI
writing. Uh I was my attention was drawn
to this um uh blue sky comment. Even
accepting the premise that AI produces
useful writing which no one should um
using AI in education is like using a
forklift at the gym. The weights do not
actually need to be moved from place to
place. That is not the work. The work is
what happens within you. Right? So, you
know,
um,
uh, I'm going to talk about using AI in
the context of writing original research
papers, okay? where you could argue um
maybe AI has no place but I think that
we've developed some strategies that
don't take away the dialectical nature
and um still um make some aspects of
writing I don't want to say less
effortful but um maybe a little more um
enhanced okay so if you're writing a
paper you know good old overleaf I'm
sure many of you have used it uh it's a
dialectical activity and it's also for a
particular audience you're generally I
would argue you not ever writing without
some audience in mind whether that's a
particular conference um or a particular
type of reader. It's effortful and um
and that effective communication
requires reasoning about the receiving
audience's
expectations. So um you know for example
if you break certain rules that can
distract or confuse the reader.
um the information they might want might
be in a place where they don't expect so
they don't know where to find it. Uh if
you've ever heard the phrase know the
rules so you can break them effectively,
right? Um it's it's not that you are
constrained by those rules, you just
need to reason about them as you decide
uh how best to communicate your ideas.
So
um existing AI assisted writing systems
in this class uh or sorry that that that
we were kind of responding to that
pre-existed to the system that we made
they generate they generally generate
text okay um but the risk with this
characteristic is that it might be too
close to an original source document and
you are not resilient to that mistake on
the AI's part right um uh you it's
extraordinarily difficult to detect that
AI choice that could land you in real
hot
water. They also often only show a
couple of examples because the kind of
going thought process is that more than
a couple examples is overwhelming.
Choice overload, people kind of shut
down, right? Why would you do that? Just
carefully choose those few examples.
Problem with that is that you may be
vulnerable to retrieval quality, right?
So the AI that's choosing or or whatever
intelligence is uh choosing those
examples. If it's bad choices, you have
very little recourse and you may anchor
on those one of those choices
unintentionally. And again, you're back
kind of in this plagiarism um place. You
don't really have that sense of that
like uh of the the full diversity um uh
from just a couple
examples. Uh you could I I've not seen
any existing systems except some sort of
fine-tuning, right? Um but even if they
did um even if even if there was writing
system you said I want to write like you
know um you know here's the audience I'm
you know here's some examples of papers
written by the audience I'm trying to
write for even if you had uh chain forge
which is um still publicly available
it's um there's a Kai paper about it uh
last year or uh our uh kind of
rrendering enhancements that are also at
Kai last year that helped you see
variation across compare the outputs of
multiple models right? One may be
fine-tuned, one without the fine-tuning
for a particular audience. Um, it's
still hard to to to in a kind of big
picture view understand whether that
fine-tuning action, you know, what if
any it changed about how the LLM is
generating text for your purpose.
So, we created a system called Corpus
Studio at this year's Kai um which takes
a radically different approach. It
retrieves many examples retrieves and
many being the operative uh words here
from the corpus of papers that informed
your audience's expectations. So other
papers that were um uh uh previously
published at the same conference and um
because it's retrieval, you don't have
to worry about AI introducing plagiarism
you can't detect. Because there's many,
you are not vulnerable to subconsciously
anchoring um or kind of having less of a
um big picture about uh what options you
might have or what people might expect.
And
um and also having many examples you
know um gives you um if you can see
emergent patterns it can help you think
about uh what that implicit norm is and
how you want to either fulfill that norm
or uh break it. And we also compute and
render cross document sorry cross
example relationships so that you can um
you don't have to do all of that thought
process yourself. we kind of try to um
give you a leg up in forming mental
models of how people write in that
community to communicate what they want
to
say. So
um all
right at the document level we apply um
something called positional diction
clustering on the section titles. That
positional diction clustering comes from
um this previous kai paper for LLM
outputs, but in this case it's being run
on the document outlines like the
section titles of all the papers in your
corpus. And this basically just um kind
of align uh similar sorry diction
similar position similar section
titles and um clusters them. Right? So,
uh, you'll still have distinct clusters
of titles even if they're identical, if
they if they commonly occur in different
parts of the document. And then we reify
the size of those clusters uh with a um
a histogram. Right? So, the introduction
maybe in this three document example is
uh present in all three. The background
only was uh in one of them. Related work
was in two. um at the beginning it was
also once at the end which is very
uncommon choice in the communities that
I like to speak to um there was only one
out of the three had a formative study
all of them had system design section
though um we render when there's a
diversity of
um to give you information sent about
the content of a cluster we underline
the tokens within that cluster that are
consistent across all cluster members so
you have some sense of what kind of uh
brings that cluster
together and then um you know the rest
uh the example here are also all in the
three examples. So if you do that for
hundreds or thousands of papers um you
can get this what we call an ordered
distribution um that gives you kind of a
big picture view of having registered
all the paper structures against each
other. Um a critical note is that this
positional diction clustering algorithm
is what you could call a uh structural
mapping engine. This comes this is
language that comes from the structural
mapping or structural alignment theory
of human cognition. Right? In a sense we
all in order to com um to look at a
bunch of things. We start comparing them
to compare them our brain starts kind of
iterating through representations of
them and finding alignments of them so
that you can you know notice their
commonalities but also the differences
within those alignments. Right? So this
is all happening subconsciously and
we're just trying to premputee that so
that you can kind of stand on the
shoulders of the computer rather than
being overwhelmed by a wall of text. So
um this is what I think enables people
to enjoy and leverage the many examples
that were um our alternative to
generating uh text or kind of um more
intelligently choosing a smaller set of
examples.
So
um in order to uh for the sentence level
example retrieval because we not just do
it at the document level but also at the
sentence level we have an editor where
you are uh typing where you can you know
in markdown say write um uh indicate
that you're starting a new section you
know hashtag participants if you're
doing a user study and then
um uh you know you can have some text
but then At some point if you ret click
retrieve right the sentence that you are
currently in and the context around that
sentence the section title um and uh
even its
offset goes through a vector embedding
space and is used to retrieve analogous
sentences in the papers in the corpus.
Right? So um whether you've finished
that sentence and you want to reflect on
it or you're in the process of trying to
write it, we can retrieve we retrieve 25
examples of other sentences that may
have not necessarily similar diction but
similar um position within their
structure and um some uh overlap in
semantics.
So um because let's see now we don't
have a full uh we did not yet find a way
to operationalize a to make a structure
mapping engine for these sentences
because they were a lot more diverse
than the structure u than the uh
document level structures. But um
instead we kind of tried to get
ourselves as close as possible by at
least highlight premputing the
overlapping tokens for example across
these and highlighting them in
colorcoordinated things. So, so maybe
that that that you know the hypothesis
with this might help you your own
structure mapping engine see emergent
structure. Um maybe you're in a part of
the uh document there where the language
is very stereotype. There's written
expectations about what information you
provide. there's a typical order and in
other places maybe there's very little
overlap across the retrieved sentences
because that you know you're you're in a
part of the document where it's the
reader doesn't have strong expectations
and you're free to do whatever you want
um without worrying too much. So um you
can see in the full interface on the
left on the left hand side we have this
ordered distribution that big picture
view
uh and on the right hand side we have
the what others wrote as well as what
others wrote next which is another 25
sentences which were ones that they
immediately came after the retrieved
sentences based on where you currently
were. So this is kind of the miniature
version of the blank page problem,
right? Um uh kind of in uh helping you
see where other people went next. This
is the
um overarching uh kind of the the
markdown editor in the middle that has
this spatial retrieval um to populate
both these lists, right? So um you know
clicking tab um to retrieve uh both
these columns. Okay.
So, I would
argue that this might be an example of a
strategy that is providing AI assistance
to a dialectical activity without
fundamentally changing
um uh the the the you know, it's it's
it's almost orthogonal to the reflection
that people are going through. Um, and
so I would argue that we have not we we
um this is a p I would argue this is a
positive example of AI supporting
dialectical activities without
interfering. But I'm I'm very much open
to uh to push back on that
characterization because we should get
on the same page about, you know, what
is and isn't harming these really
critical
activities. Um,
yes. Yeah. I'm a little unclear about
what the interaction actually is. Is it
you're you're just writing and then it's
it's um like a a complete it tries to
complete a phrase or tries to what's the
interaction actually? So the interaction
is you are writing in that center panel.
Um here let me just go back real quick.
Um so uh uh you're writing the center
panel and as you uh you can be informed
by um interacting with these clusters.
If if you're thinking about how to
structure it, you know, you perhaps you
already kind of structured your paper.
So I'll just mostly the interaction was
mostly with the right hand side with
sentence retrieval where as you write
either a full or partial sentence given
the prior context in your document
including the um uh the the sentence or
sentence fragment and the section title,
it indexes into your corpus and
retrieves sentences that have similar
semantic meaning. Right? So like you're
you're calling it the interaction is I'm
I'm retrieving I'm a little stuck. I
want to know how other people at this
point in their paper what they wrote
about especially what they wrote about
relative to what I you know am writing
about. Okay. I I I I still don't get
that. So I'm typing along in markdown in
that in this since this is a static
screen. So we have you're typing a few
participants mentioned. Yes. And then
maybe I you do that. You see everything
in section C here. I if I if I want to
invoke retrieval at that time because
retrieval is costly. I'm not constantly
refreshing lots of sentences in your
face. Okay. So if I if I say that's what
I'm trying to figure out. Is it the
display dynamic or is it just on demand
or? It's on demand. Okay. And it's and
how do you and you have to hit a special
operation when you get to that mention?
Well I Right. So, I typed a few
participants mentioned and then I hit
tab and that
retrieves 50 sentences
screen. Well, this is probably like not
I mean it's probably the leftovers of
what I last retrieved. I don't think
that they we wiped that away and um um I
believe the students um who built this
did allow this to be collapsed, right?
if you really don't want to see it but
um uh primarily you know we we we had it
visible so that people remembered that
this novel affordance was there right
during the inter the study so in a
certain sense the study wasn't even like
hey this is exactly how you should
design this kind of AI writing assistant
it was more like can we design enough
cognitive support that people can
benefit from these many retrieved
examples to augment their thought
process as they compose
truly unique new writing that you know
an AI could never generate for them
because they're the first person to have
that
thought. Does that make sense? Yeah. Why
don't you just go? Okay. All right. But
you know if you have the question other
people do too. So yes, I have another
question. So you had mentioned that you
um you you know one of the reasons why
people were given these single responses
was because it was overwhelming to get
like a lot of different responses. Well,
it could be if there was no cognitive
support. Okay. But but you did find that
this was not overwhelming in the sense
that like as opposed to saying something
more iterative like was it a conscious
decision to have I guess the right panel
with Yeah. Yes. Right. So in a sense the
the the implicit design challenge that
we gave ourselves was um we know that
many examples can prevent you from
overfitting on a particular couple,
right? It can prevent you from anchoring
and implic, you know, accidentally kind
of plagiarizing. Um, it can give you a
better sense of the expectations of your
readers. There's all these positive
things that come out if I can get these,
you know, if I can help you consume more
than a handful of examples. So, if I can
retrieve them and that they are
semantically tight enough that they are
more likely than not, but not always,
right? Unreliable AI is part of the
title related to what you're you're
typing out. And if I can post-process
them in some way that helps you see and
I realize, you know, here these are not
necessarily showing kind of any emergent
structure, right? So there's like a lot
more variation here. So, you know, in a
certain sense, it's like, well, these
are one-off examples that, you know,
might give you some ideas about what you
want to include in your sentence, but
there isn't some sort of overarching
expectation that the reader has given
this particular prompt. But where there
are kind of expectations in stylized
writing, right? the same way that
there's very particular ways in which pe
papers are structured in a given
community you you might you know that
will um if requested be revealed. So
it's like can we provide people the
cognitive support? Can we shortcut
enough of the cognition
um that they can benefit from the the
schema that emerges? Yes. Did you um did
you compare this against um people who
would use LLM's like Q&A to be like oh
what do the papers say about like so
like that says a few participants
mentioned but what does the what do the
research papers say about um like how
participants would like use this thing
we yes yes I mean that would be a a very
interesting you know contrast
um for these kinds of dialectical
activities ities that require deep
engagement over a non-trivial amount of
time about something they cared about.
Like in this user study that we did,
people brought their own manuscripts.
They continued trying to write their own
manuscripts in this interface. You lose
the ability, I shouldn't say lose,
within an amount of time that people are
willing to spend with you and and um uh
it's harder to kind of swap in different
conditions. And so this paper and papers
since we've stopped kind of including
strict baselines or strict um
alternatives and a certain because um um
while informative the first point the
first question is is this even can cog
people cognitively benefit from this if
yes we move on to that next. So like
this this would be that would be a great
follow-up experiment. Um uh now I will
point out okay I already know one thing
that's going to be a failure mode
potentially. Okay, for having a say a
chat, you know what what other things do
people include when describing an
experimental setup, right? Um, say the
LM hallucinates an extra step, right?
That that step is really common in that
community over there, but I'm not part
of that community, but it's, you know,
got so much training data from over
there, it kind of leaked in, right? Um
because everything else was kind of
similar. And um what if it left out
something that is really uncommon, but
if you saw it, you'd be like, "Oh yeah,
I should be including that too, right?"
Like good practice is often initially an
aberration from the the typical and and
people recognize it as good and it
becomes more and more common, right? So
um if I'm only relying on a chatbot to
summarize these things, I cannot be
resilient to both kind of imputation of
things from adjacent communities or the
missing out of things that are rare but
good. So by scaling up the number of
retrievalss, my hope and also trying to
help people um see any emerging schema,
my hope is that they can notice the
common and uncommon things. If the
uncommon thing is bad, fine, you can
know that it's bad. if it's good, you
have the opportunity to replicate that
good choice, that uncommon good choice
in your own work. And I would argue that
you cannot if you're relying on a chat
with an AI to answer the same
question. So I would I would to to kind
of kill my own, you know, I would call
this an AI more AI resilient interface,
right? I'm more resilient to the choices
that the AI makes on my
behalf. Thanks.
Okay, I'm gonna keep moving unless
another but yes, I um very much
appreciate these questions. Okay, so um
yeah, these were um we had 16
participants. They drafted their
structure, then they drafted pros. Um
took up to 75 minutes. We gave them $25.
They were working on their Kai paper
anyway. I at least one was working on a
Europe's paper. I don't know how they
got in.
All right. So, um what we found was that
um the section title frequency was used
to gauge norms. So, that worked. Um some
adapted section titles from the
distribution while others um just kind
of like took the existing titles that
they already had in a draft and kind of
maybe modified them knowing now what
maybe expectations were of their
readers. People noticed variation within
section title clusters. So, this notion
of kind of trying to reveal what was
consistent or possibly varying within a
cluster seemed to work. Um people found
it help helpful to see uncommon titles.
So this person said the section titles
are more diverse than I thought. There's
things like you know expert interviews
which I've never done. These are um
there were a few others that I found
which were pretty new to me. Definitely
broaders my sort of horizon. Right? So
this is the value of the longtail and if
you can make that long tail cognitively
accessible by precomputing what's common
and letting that kind of those those
differences uh surface. Um some also
opted to deviate from implied norms. So
people didn't feel like they were stuck
um uh to um what was most common on the
sentence level side. People alternate
between iterating pros and engaging with
retrievals. So to your point about you
know we kind of thought well you'd be
writing along and then you're like a
little help tab right and look at the
the stuff but they were actually kind of
because this is an implicit query
whatever you were writing you know the
sentence that you were you were writing
um people would edit the sentence
because they were refining their edit I
mean they're in the process of of
composing but sometimes that that that
editing sometimes seemed to be more
about modifying the retrievalss the
retrieved sentences than it was about
like what the final compos composed
sentence would be. So, they're kind of
blending the two of composition and
querying, but anyway, um it's not
necessarily a bad thing. Uh um they used
retrieved sentences to uh get community
specific terminology, phrasing,
structure, and ideas. They discovered
relevant uh literature for citations. Um
so, it was true that you could save
individual sentences, you know, look at
the kind of local context of that
sentence and what paper occurred in. So
people sometimes when they noticed uh a
sentence that they um piqu their
interest they could uh at a later time a
bookmark for a later time to engage with
that the paper it came from. In terms of
confidence and perception um one
participant said it's great to read what
others wrote because we perform a
similar process but we did not mention
that um in our own writing. So it' be
great if we could add those. So this
notion of of you know maybe this was in
a paper that was in a completely
different superficially different field
but there was some some process some
similarity some analogical sentence that
you would um never have found if you
were searching in a traditional way that
um uh revealed the relationship they
could follow up on. So exposure to
similar work boosted their confidence in
how they were writing. Um but also if
they didn't see a lot of other sentences
like the one they were writing, it
boosted their sense of novelty. Though
you know obviously this was all from one
corpus. So if it's not in the corpus
that doesn't mean it doesn't exist,
right? So you have to be a little
careful about misperceptions we could
give them. And in the sentence rendering
um people did initially find this
overwhelming. And I will just point out
these the these strategies of like
graying out repeated words across
sentences and such. Um it's not based on
a structure mapping engine. We are just
kind of showing s superficial
similarities. And for that reason I
think we both highlighted possible
analogical relationships across them and
and correspondences that had nothing to
do with analogical relationships. And so
it was almost like we were jamming the
same channel with good and bad
information. So I based on that I think
um uh developing structure mapping
engines for new contexts if you want to
employ this is really important you
can't skip it.
Um
so we when they were drafting the
structure they had we did do a little
kind of controlled uh you know baseline
experience where they were either
drafting in like Google Docs with no
assistance or with a view of that right
that uh left-hand side um just because
we felt like you know didn't take that
long and and we felt obligated to have a
baseline because so much work you know
it's kind of hard to say how good
something is if you don't have something
to compare it to and you Sure enough,
people liked drafting their structure in
uh corpus studio better than in the
baseline. Okay, not surprising. But what
more interesting is what um the
questions we tried to ask and answer
without that baseline when they're
drafting pros. Right? So the the two two
questions that I want to highlight here
is um how much they agreed with the
statement. I have a clearer sense of
when it might be appropriate to break
the writing expectations of the target
venue for sentences that I write.
Um this is like um uh not quite as as
positive. Um well, okay, sorry. So
here's the zero, right? So there's more
positive than negative. Um more
agreement with um the statement that
evaluating many sentences from other
previous papers at once. Um sorry uh
gave me a better understanding of the
typical writing expectations of the
target venue.
you know, these these goals that we had
for our users, we at least even without
a baseline can can show we have some
evidence that we achieved those goals um
even if certain aspects of it were
overwhelming. Um okay, so
um again using this language of
resilience to AI, right, or um you know
kind of reliable outcomes despite
unreliable AI, right? Right, we're
arguing here that this alternative
approach of retrieving many examples and
render, you know, uh computationally uh
analyzing them and rendering them with
respect to how you see cross example
relationships makes users more resilient
to the AI's possibility of plagiarizing
if they were if if it was um generating
text, their own plagiarism risks, and um
whatever quality of retrieval that they
have, right? Just less sensitive to it.
Um which I think is a good thing.
Um so
um all right so that is um uh this work
this was a collaboration with um my
colleague Daniel Bushek and his student
high Chelsea and Hi uh were co-first
authors on this um but yeah if we had to
rename it um you know through the lens
of dialectical activity and the the
notion of um supporting cognition and um
uh making people more resilient you
could have just as easily re um retitled
this paper corpus supporting the
dialectical activity of writing with AI
retrieval of unknown and variable
reliability. Okay. So the second paper I
want to talk about little in a little
bit less depth is also going to be
presented next week at KAI and it's um a
collaboration um equal collaboration
with Toby Lee at Notre Dame. It's led um
by his wonderful student Simrat who's
really taken this uh my proposal of
thinking about these theories of uh
human um concept learning like uh the
emergent structure that we see in
examples and using that to think about
uh machine teaching right so I have a
notion in my head how do I communicate
that to the computer so it can more
reliably carry out my desires say um uh
when doing qualitative coding on some
data or
annotating additional data. So I'll just
point out we're very thrilled it was
awarded with a best paper award though
these things are um half random and we
call it mocha um just for short um the
name of the system that instantiates
this. So okay so variation theory is the
one theory we haven't talked about yet
um it's really clear here or necessary
to
discuss basically variation theory is
about the experience of difference and
how that affects your conceptualization
of the what you are trying to describe
for yourself or someone else or
something else right so if I'm
interested in uh uh characterizing a
banana um there's critical dimensions
where you can see difference here these
other along shape right if I'm too far
away from the banana shape I I cease to
be a banana um whereas color is not uh
it's a superficial aspect right you can
have red bananas green bananas right um
and we want um of course there's many
dimensions of variation that can be
either critical or superficial and um
both types are important for a model to
understand which are which so um you
know if I had only had access to uh this
apple um is it some some sort of greens
and watermelon then um I would not have
been able if if I did not carefully
construct these counter examples I still
wouldn't actually have that much or have
communicated that much about what makes
a banana a banana because these vary in
both color and shape right um so so um
providing
um providing examples that leave all
dimen dimensions fixed but one is one
way to kind of communicate to someone or
something what's critical and what's
superficial. Right? So um the question
we asked was how we could generate
counterfactuals say to augment an
existing data set um that variation
theory would predict are helpful.
So um rather than you know revealing
variation that exists in a corpus that
you're kind of you're stuck with
whatever variation exists can we
strategically generate it um to to help
clarify the concept of banana or um so
um yeah um I will point out that um
variation theory only predicts that
these are helpful for human learners.
That's where it comes from. It comes
from learning sciences. Um but uh uh
Simret led um a beautiful paper that's
currently on archive and I believe in
the is in the process of being accepted
at NLP conference um about uh the fact
that you know this variation theory
while evaluated in the context of human
learning is really just describing kind
of an information theory kind of basic
fact right so um we do have evidence
that machine learn you know uh short
fueshot learning of machines is also
benefited from kind of listening to the
design implications of var variation
theory. So um we want the model to know
that these superficial dimensions of
variation are relevant. We want the
model to know where the boundaries of
the concept are along critical
dimensions of variation. That's the
purpose of these counter examples. This
is a lot harder to do um for humans if
it's not fruit but text because text
unlike fruit you know it you have to
it's linearly parsed. We have a large
site vocabulary, right, which allows us
to read things fairly quickly, but we
still um uh you know, without kind of
premputation of relationships across
redundant sentences, you're really just
stuck reading them and mentally
remembering the differences between
them. So um you know and and also I
guess the um the dimensions of variation
that are critical and superficial for a
certain concept like a comment on a Yelp
review about ambiance is a lot harder to
even um give a name to except by
defining of you know in terms of like
positive and negative examples. Um and
there's no ground truth for ambiance
either. It's like that's that's a
concept that you may be refining in your
own head as you review examples whether
they are naturally in the data set or
counterfactual um
generations. Okay. So, Mocha combines
variation theory um and structural
mapping theory in a really interesting
way. So, because we can generate we
strategically generate examples that um
basically are variations of an original
in uh in corpus example. So this says
breakfast was delicious, right? Um and
we have a model predicted um and
probably user confirmed label that this
is uh about kind of the products that
are sold by this restaurant um that the
Yelp review is from. And um we have an
initial guess from whatever earlier um
annotations were provided of this
neurosyolic pattern um that basically
um uh the neurosymbolic pattern is
pretty basic right now. It's just like
um it is uh you you've fulfilled the
pattern that predicts product if there
are uh there is a word that matches a
synonym of delicious or a synonym of
good. Right? So this is basically a um
it's a superficial aspect of the data
that is also quite possibly
overfit. So, um, Mocha then generates um
a bunch of variations that are still
alignable by construction with the top
one, right? They they they share in this
case all breakfast and they all share um
the fact that they fit they match this
pattern, but they've been tweaked in the
smallest possible way to have a
different predicted um category, right?
to cross the conceptual boundary outside
of banana or in this case outside of
product into some other category that um
exists or could exist. And so then um
the human is going to confirm or come
up, you know, kind of um label
themselves these proposed out of concept
examples to clarify those boundaries
along the implied critical dimensions of
variation that are are kind of uh we're
not explicitly labeling them. These are
across many different uh critical
boundaries of v variation that we're not
explicitly naming. But by crossing the c
the the uh concept boundary
um they are going to help us um uh
refine that initially overfit feature
that's picking out something um that
kind of makes that example the category
that it is. Um because we construct them
to be alignable, right? um or we can uh
kind of post-process them and gray out
what's similar and draw your attention
just to the part that is uh different.
And because volume of of counterfactual
examples, the more you can label, the
better you can communicate, both refine
for yourself what it is that you know,
product means to you in a Yelp context.
um uh and um and better communicate more
hopefully to make a more reliable AI
classifier of that same concept. Um you
see three but there are many that the
person can um add. Right. So first
question that we had was um whether or
not Mocha would affect task user
efficiency and cognitive load. Right.
Yes. Yeah. I'm sorry I had the same
question but you know what is the
interaction? Are you writing a review?
What is the So the interaction is um I
have I'm trying to say label um uh I'm
trying to do labeling of uh Yelp data in
terms of what it is uh commenting on. So
that are you trying to classify reviews
that already exist or are you writing?
Yes, I'm classifi I have a data set of
of Yelp reviews. Okay. And um they the
the sentences in the Yelp reviews are
addressing different aspects of the
restaurant and I want to teach the
machine to annotate, you know, to to
parse those Yelp reviews in terms of
what concept about a restaurant they're
commenting on. So you're trying to uh
categorize Yelp reviews that are
pre-existing and then you're but your
category is is not predefined, right?
I'm trying to teach the machine. In
fact, so this is building off of work
I'm that was published previously uh
called BAT which was you know kind of AI
assisted um annotation of short texts
right um and so uh the short texts
people would come up with categories and
then ask the AI this neurosymbolic AI to
um propose other texts in the large
corpus that might get the same label
right and as they additionally labeled
um examples in the corpus the patterns
that detected did you know you know had
the learned patterns became more and
less and less overfitit and more and
more appropriately um uh having higher
and higher accuracy in identifying
additional correct applications of that
label. The problem is is that the
diversity of examples in say that Yel
data set may not be optimal for quickly
communicating the notion of that concept
to the machine or even like really fully
understanding what is and isn't part of
ambiance to the person. Right? So these
counterfactual uh generation is to kind
of amp up the the uh the variation
they're exposed to to prompt early and
early that reflection of what they they
want and communicate that in that in the
in as quickly as possible to the
machine. Okay. So how how would that
relate to things like you know active
learning or basic basic? This is active
learning, right? Okay. Yeah. It's just
so so this is um I mean so the the paper
that I'm not discussing that is like
going off to an LLP because it wasn't
about human interaction was like hey
does variation theory help active
learning happen faster right and the
answer was yes which is cool right
because variation theory even though it
was designed for humans it's just really
just basic information uh you know how
much information is quantified um but
here I was like all right it's better
for the machine can we make it better
for the human too right if if so so um
here let me give you an example example
of um people experienced counter
examples that they had to label that
weren't generated in this strategic way
and weren't ren you know rendered um
with this kind of pre-ferencing. Um we
had them uh another condition the next
one was they were generated
strategically to be this more
informative variation theory inspired
way but we didn't postprocess them in
any way. Okay, so you still had like
this long list of of things you had to
detect the difference with every single
one. And then we had the final condition
like you know we strategically generate
them. We do this post hawk analysis of
where they are similar and different.
And um we we people either experienced
an emotion data set labeling the emotion
expressed in natural language or in the
Yelp for um in this case we didn't allow
them to define their own um we gave them
a name for a concept that they had to
teach the computer. in the previous work
they could define whatever concepts they
they wanted. Um so what we found was
that
um this uh that basically um variation
theory which we already knew from the
previous paper was helping the machine
learn faster. When we when we combine
that with this post-processing, right,
which was enabled by the strategic
generation of these these variations, um
suddenly people got a lot faster at um
generating a batch. They could just
likeup, right? So the machine was
learning faster and they were faster at
clarifying for themselves and the
machine with these counter examples what
it is that they meant. Um and so um you
know the the fact that the there was
higher variability in that in that first
the first uh the time to first
annotation applied speaks to the fact
that people had to get to familiar with
the system, right? um they felt more
skilled over time as they learned how we
were reifying relationships across
counterfactual examples um and and
between the counterfactual examples and
the original incorpass example um to
really kind of benefit from this uh
cognitive
assistance.
Um we also um just focusing on on um the
third research question we asked um how
useful Mocha was in allowing people to
learn about their own evolving
conception of the label. We have uh you
know people did acknowledge um for
example P3 said I think by changing
different parts of of it the original
sentence it highlighted a part of the
sentences that I was not previously
focused on. Right? that difference
allows discernment and and so that did
help my sort of reframe of what I
initially had labeled. Right? So this
notion of um almost close reading that
um and reflection that this uh made
visible to them cog salient
cognitively. So um so that's that work.
We're we're almost out of time. So,
um
I I'll point out that um uh you could
say that um well, you you could say that
uh refining one's understanding of a
concept is also a dialectical activity.
By repeatedly engaging with things, you
may come to understand new ways of
defining what is or isn't um you know,
ambiance, right? It's that sounds better
than saying what is or isn't banana.
That one's pretty clear-cut.
Um but um so both of them to some extent
are AI helping dialectical activities.
So, we've seen from these two examples
that one way for AI to support
dialectical activities is by revealing
existing variation
um in a relevant collection of data
corpus of of papers that um that your
your audience has already read or
generating it strategically, right? as
was done in the um in teaching a machine
about a particular concept to um and
this revealing or um pres presentation
of strategically generated variation
helps deepen the human's cognitive
engagement, right? They they notice
things they wouldn't have discerned in
isolation.
And um so the AI is supporting the
dialectical activity when the um I would
argue
that one guiding way in which we can
design for AI support of these really
important activities is to think about
how we can make the thought processes
that reveal the value happen still
within the user's mind. Right? um that
we cannot if we start to compute the
process that already is happening in the
user's mind or we um we start to
encroach on the value that they might
otherwise get. Right now I realize it's
a little bit of a of a um uh almost
contradicts this notion of like oh I'm
going to premputee these relationships
so that people can keep you know
thinking about the the emergent patterns
from that. Um, so maybe in a sense you
you could say if you're really sure that
you have the right representation and
the right structural mapping engine that
aligns them and and reifies those
alignments, then great, you know, you
you're helping them get where they would
already have gotten. Um, however, if
there's uh many different possible
representations and therefore alignments
over those those representations, by
surfacing one, you might impair their
ability to see the others. So like use
with caution. Um and
um my final thought here is that um
uh you know no matter what the AI does,
I still at the end of the day want to
make sure that the humans are resilient
to AI choices that are objectively wrong
or contextually inappropriate for them
or or just subjectively disliked. And
these choices can often be hidden.
Right? If I um uh uh going blazingly
fast, you know, if I get a generative
summary of um stuff on a um on a search
query about like the probability of
having twins in your late 30s, right?
It's very difficult to detect whether or
not this is right. It sound, you know,
looks good to me, right? Um even though
those those statistics look a little bit
high. Um and and it looks corroborated
by a different feature down the page,
right? Turns out both of those things it
was not hard not easy for me to notice
right that they were actually pointing
to the same original paper sorry uh page
where it had truncated the fact that
younger people had an even higher rate
so that that they left out the the thing
that would have violated my expectations
and then it also left out the context
that these were people using IVF where
doctors often intentionally put multiple
embryos in to maximize the chance of
live birth. Right? It was answering a
completely different question but I was
completely. You cannot blame me for not
recognizing this except for the fact
that that seemed a little higher than
average, right? But um this these this
variation, okay, um can be a great way
to combat this. So, you know, these
deceptive patterns AI can generate these
deceptive patterns. We cannot as
designers
um just throw up our hands, right, and
say, well, we you know, we gave you the
information. We didn't. Um, this is this
is where the variation saved me. I uh
query um full weight daily for pregnancy
and and I'm sure you know that many
pregnant people are looking to the
internet for information on on you just
this kind of of query. I get two
answers. They're off by an order of
magnitude. 400 micrograms or 4,000.
Okay, because I got two bad results.
Okay, they're both wrong. The first one
is telling me how much it was the first
time we ever had recommendations. The
second one is telling me how much I
should take if I'm at high risk for a
neural tube defect. Okay, two bad
answers, but I became more I my outcomes
were better because I revealed both of
them and that um sparked my engagement
um to know that I should look further.
Uh you know this is a mockup of other
ways in which we can supervi um super
provo sorry super oh goodness juxtapose.
I'll go with that. Juxtapose different
narrations of the same event, right? Who
was the actor? If I read any one of
these lead sentences about um this
particular event back in like 2019, I
might have taken for granted that um uh
that the Treasury Department did this,
right? Um but actually, who was the
actor? The the contrast poses the
question implicitly. We have work where
we show this um for large language
models. The last thing that I will um
leave you with is that while I've talked
about how great variation is um it's not
a panacea. The variation that we show
and the variation that we don't show can
actually constrain your imagination
about what that other world is. So if I
go to um uh if I um if I go to you and I
say um you can either get the surgery
now or you can get the surgery uh at an
emergency next week, right? um I've
constrained that the your imagination to
the things that are different between
getting surgery now or later when in
reality there are other you know if I
had said or not get surgery that
dimension of variation is still salient
to you rather than something you have to
cognitively try to remember. Um so our
our choices can be shaped by the
variation we do show and what we hide.
So
um there's there's um I've worked on
this notion of AI resilient interfaces.
I have an AI resilient alternative
summarization that I can talk talk about
um that I've run out of time for. Um I
define there's a a nice working nice I
hope you'll check out my working paper
that uh in which we try to define this
generalization of an AI resilient
interface. Um but I I summarize it as an
interface that increases the safety
usability and utility of AI powered
features by giving people the ability to
notice AI choices, have the context
necessary to judge them and recover with
them from them with ease. It's a high
bar. Maybe nothing will ever perfectly
meet it. Um but I think it's something
that we should be shooting for. Um and
um uh uh it definitely resonates with
the wording of the initial se uh seminar
invitation that I received. So um all
the papers that I talked about today,
you can um take a look at them. Uh
they're linked in this um through this
QR code in a Google document. And I'm
happy to take uh any uh further
questions that you have.
[Applause]