so now let's talk about autoimmune
disease in our gut so inflammatory bowel
disease is an autoimmune disease and the
most common type of inflammatory bowel
disease or IBD is ulcerative colitis
ulcerative colitis occurs in the colon
which is part of your large intestine
the Colon's the longest part of the
large intestine and it's important for
absorbing water uh certain nutrients and
electrolytes and it's also where most of
the bacteria in our bodies live
so during ulcerative colitis there's
inflammation in the colon and the
symptoms of this would be things like
abdominal pain diarrhea and weight loss
on the lower right here we're seeing a
colonoscopy where a doctor can take a
tube with a camera and put it into the
colon and on the left we're seeing
healthy colon and on the right we're
seeing inflamed it looks red and kind of
unhappy and so ulcer of colitis is
really characterized by chronic
inflammation in combination uh withy of
flareups where there's more acute
inflammation and very noticeably bad
symptoms so uh how is aler of cly is
currently treated well uh certain
treatments are steroids which generally
suppress your immune system there are
also biologics which are molecules that
can Target specific parts of the
inflammatory Pathways and finally in
really bad situations there's the
colectomy where either part or the
entire colon is removed from the
ulcerative colitis patient so before we
had these treatments uh the mortality
rate for ulcer of cidus was very high it
was up to 60% so this is a really
terrible chronic
disease so how does ulcerative colitis
arise so here we're looking at a cartoon
of your colon and the colon at its uh
innermost part has a single cell
epithelial cell barrier and this
separates microbes that live in our
colon from us and when this barrier
breaks down due to damage the microbes
can start to get into the epithelial
layer and penetrate in there and when
these microbes get into the epithelial
layer uh this triggers an immune
response so some of the first immune
cells to arrive are neutrophils which
are trying to essentially remove the
bacteria and kill them and when the
neutrophils arrive they bring along a
lot of other friends other immune cells
and this triggers a lot of inflammation
and as you're trying to get rid of these
microbes or these bacteria that have
gone into the colon uh this is also
leading to damage of the colon tissue
itself and that's where you start to get
these symptoms like diarrhea and pain
and so forth and this uh inflammation is
chronic so it can continue for years and
even decades and it requires careful
treatment by a gastroenterologist