So, uh, in the rest of the class, let's
talk a little bit, uh, about, um,
interest rates, uh, and a little bit
about bonds, uh, because that's very,
important for and central for many will
be will be definitely part of many
classes and is generally central for uh
for finance and for life in my opinion.
So what is interest?
Um well let's start with
now
and suppose we have $1 which we uh
invested oh put it in the bank. So what
happens in one year?
Well you expect to get your dollar back
with some interest. And what does it
mean? So you get one plus something I
know 5% nowadays and this r is called
interest rate. So what happens if you
reinvest it what what will you get the
the whole thing? So in two years you
would expect to get
1 + r * 1 plus r right? So 1 plus r 2.
So in n years
you will expect to get
1 plus r to to the power m right
well let's let's make it small and small
not to confuse ourselves. So uh now
let's uh let's make life a little bit
more complicated. What happens if you uh
if you decide to take your money in half
a year,
right? You had one here. So what happens
in h half a year? Well, you get half of
the interest, right? So it will be 1 + r
/ 2 and in one year it will be 1 + r / 2
squared, right? Because re you reinvest
it. So suppose you you keep it in the
bank and in n years it will be 1 + r / 2
but twice n right because there are
twice as many periods.
Okay let's subdivide further let's make
m periods. So in one in the first period
you get one over 1 + r / m
in one year it will be
1 + r / m ^ m and here you'll get 1 + r
/ m
* n.
All right.
What if we take the limit? Let's if we
are able to reinvest every second, every
millisecond, what happens then? So
we'll send this m to the infinity.
So what is who knows what what is that?
>> Well, it is E but
R
>> right has to be there and N this N will
stay there right well yeah if we keep N
here. So in fact interesting historical
fact that's how E was discovered and
defined. It was Berni in his seinal
paper in uh 1683
where he
described this computation and it was
about interest rate uh about uh how
interest is compounding. So maybe this
was the first mathematical finance paper
in in the history.
Uh okay. Now let's change uh the uh game
a little bit. Not a game change the
question a little bit. So suppose we
know that we will receive uh uh we will
receive $1 in one year.
uh how much
should we pay for this right to receive
a dollar in one year? How how much
should should we pay now to receive a
dollar in one year, right? So, and let's
compute it. So, suppose we don't uh we
don't know. Let's let's assume that now
it is act x dollars
and let's consider the the following
strategy. Let's borrow $1. Uh let's
borrow X this amount
now and let's see what happens at the
end. So at the end in one year I mean
we'll receive $1 dollar for sure, right?
And we'll have to repay our debt but
with interest.
So we'll have repay
plus uh x * r uh uh
sorry x
* 1 + r
right
now
what should this be?
Can it be greater than zero this
difference?
Well, if it's greater than zero, why
wouldn't we borrow? Why why wouldn't we
buy a right to receive a billion
dollars? Then we'll have a lot of
profit.
Can it be less than zero? Well, then we
would be stupid to enter this contract
because we'll lose money for sure.
That's that's we know that this will
happen in one year. So for no arbitrage
and we we don't assume that anybody our
counterpart is stupid. We don't think
that we are stupid right? So it has to
be zero.
So and this x
is equal to 1 + divided by 1 plus r
and this is called discounting
meaning that if we know that we'll
receive certain amount in the future and
we know the interest rates pre
prevailing interest rates then we have
to discount the the uh the future value
to today using a discount factor and
this is the discount factor assuming
analyzed compounding. Right? If uh if we
if we assume analyze compounding and uh
receive n dollars in the future uh in
the future n years, right? the value of
n dollars in the future.
It is the value of our n dollars which
which we'll receive in the future n
years but it has to be discounted by n
years right so it it should be
and here it is discounting right if we
assume a continuous discounting
something like this then it will be our
price will be n
*
e to minus
RN right this will be our discount
factor
assuming continuous compounding
so and we already hitting the uh the
problem or not a problem but we are
already hitting a situation uh where uh
some model is needed
so
which brings us to the world of
financial interest is financial
instruments, interest rate related
financial in instruments.
Uh and the simplest financial instrument
is a zero coupon bond. That's exactly
the right to receive certain amount of
uh of notional or notional is quite
often one or 100 in certain amount of
time, right? And that's the value of our
zero coupon bond. More common uh
financial instruments are coupon bonds,
right? Because most people would like to
receive periodic interest
for uh for giving for lending money,
right? And that's effectively lending
money. And uh this is typical b uh
bonds. For example, if you buy
government bonds, that's that's what
will what will happen. You'll give the
government your $100
and government will be repaying you
coupons periodically usually semianually
uh here in US in Europe it's quite often
quarterly and the notional all your $100
at the end right so what what the pri a
pri the price of such a coupon bond
should be well we'll need to take all
the cash flows
and discount them.
And if we assume a constant interest
rate,
we'll have to discount it with our
constant discount factors.
And that's how uh how much and this
assumes well say annual coupons and
annual rate. So that's will be your
sequence with a notional at the end,
right? the the whole big notional at the
end. And can we sum this up?
Well, sure. That's geometric geometric
sequence, right? Everybody can sum up
geometric sequence. And that's
uh that's the value. That's what you
get. Uh so u and that's the value of the
bond.
Now
uh
the bonds are traded on the markets
uh there are prices of the bonds uh and
if you start uh investing into uh into
bonds and not in just in one bond you
should be able to compare two bonds
and comparing the price is not really
convenient
because bonds of different maturities
even with the same interest would will
have different prices, right? Because
there will be different number of cash
flows. Bonds of different coupons will
have different prices. So what turns out
uh to be more convenient measure to
compare bonds and various fixed income
securities is yield. And yield is
such a constant interest rate
which by this discounting gives you
market price. You so you you buy
something at the market price. You know
the market price. So uh you know all the
cash flows. So you back out one flat
interest rate which will give you uh the
price of uh of the bond. Right? That's
called yield of the bond. Obviously
there is uh onetoone relationship
between price and yield. So for our
zero coupon bond yield is pretty simple
right you just invert this uh this
formula and here this is here on the
slide for coupon bonds
yield computation is more complex
because inverting this formula is uh
more involved in in fact it has to be
numerical right but that's uh that's how
fields are computed. Um
here I'll I give you an example
of uh of a few uh of price yield
relationship for a 10-year bond with
different coupons. So what's important
to know here is that the higher the
coupon and that's natural the uh the uh
the higher the the yield is right for
the same bond of the same maturity. Uh
but what is important to know is the
yield and price are in inverse
relationship. The higher yield the low
lower the price right because it's all
about discounting.
It's in denominator. The higher the the
price the lower the yield.
Um
so uh that's that's what it is. Uh and
but real life is
uh is more complicated than that in real
world as if we wanted everything to be
the same simple interest rate and all
bonds have
to be discounted the same. Uh real life
is slightly different. So if you take
market uh uh securities, market bonds
and start baking up their yields, they
uh they will not be constant uh
particularly with maturity.
And this is called the yield curve. And
I gave you uh here I plotted a yield
curve
uh for uh 10-year uh term structure of
10-year yields,
US government yields for a variety of
times and I want to talk just a little
bit about it because it's quite topical.
So that's the the the thickest line is
this. That's uh the yield curve uh for
September 3rd. So two days uh two days
ago right? Um so quite different and
yields here in for a very short dated
securities are quite higher than for
longdated security. This this is still
quite atypical. For example, in 92
around the same September time, yield
curve looked like this.
Uh considered to be more or less
classical curve. And generally speaking,
we expect upward sloping curves because
generally speaking, people would like to
receive more yield for longer term uh
for longer term investments, right?
And that's what uh was the case uh in uh
this is what uh this is
21 uh this is uh 14
uh yeah nice looking curves. The only
difference here is that now they they
are ground if in 92 they were grounded
at 3% and went all the way up to seven.
Uh they those were grounded at zero and
went only to two 3%. Right now
interesting observation here is so where
uh let's look at this inverted curves. A
year ago it was inverted.
Now it is inverted.
It was inverted in 2007. Uh no, this is
20 2019 and this is 2007.
So what do do you have anything
in your mind? What's uh what's common
between 20
21 and 2007?
So
>> the year before recession.
>> Yes. Exactly. Well, 2007 the recession
was the recession, right?
2021 there was a recession in 2020. Even
this this this yield curve is before
COVID. So nothing was and if you look at
the shape of the yield curves and
recession times
uh well it is common analogy and there
there are papers on that uh how
predictive is inverted yield curve for
the recessions.
Generally it is uh assumed to be
predictive. So here we go we have
inverted heel curve. What does it tell
us about the future?
Well, that's all Fed's job to keep it uh
to to keep it to make it a soft landing
and and and for a recession not to
happen. And we'll see maybe it will be
or maybe not. But uh what what I want to
emphasize that there is a lot of
information in yield curves. uh one of
the lectures in the future Andrew Gston
he will be talking mostly about yield
curves and yield curve constructions and
the instruments around that so uh uh
it's very uh important piece
um of knowledge uh and uh yeah I I'll
promise you when I come back later on to
talk about black shs uh I'll I'll bring
this slide back and we'll see what
happens with with the yurf because what
and I can guarantee you it will look
different because the Fed is happening
the Fed meeting is happening in
September. Everybody expects uh uh the
yields to be cut which immediately will
bring the short end down. What happens
with the long end? I wish I knew.
Anyway, u that's about yield curves. Uh
but uh another important thing to
emphasize that no matter what
uh bond prices
are sensitive to uh to yields obviously
right and they are sensitive to yields
in nonlinear fashion. What does it mean?
Well, it means that if you hold bonds on
your hands and yields change and they do
change,
you will your your investment will
change. So it's quite important to
understand the sensitivity of your
investment to uh to interest rates and
yields. So uh and uh and what are
sensitivities? Those are derivatives,
right? So or uh in in finance and fixed
income world they're called durations
because they're usually uh scaled by
price. So uh very important measures are
duration of the bond
which is derivative with respect with
respect to yield u and there for each
different bond and each different
security they will be slightly different
right uh and uh not only the first
derivative is important the second
derivative or convexity
uh is also important so um yeah and
that's what we'll be talking about uh
in in a various classes. Uh we will be
talking about more interesting
uh interest rate objects in the future
in particular forward rates and swaps,
but I'll leave it to Stefan and and
Andrew uh to to talk more about that.
Uh that's probably all for today and any
questions to to any of us?
>> Have you done this? Have you done that
game before?
>> Uh not specifically this format. So we
tried before it was more open-ended. I
was thinking I so I think by fixing the
dates you don't have to make the market
timing decision. We already made it for
you.