good
afternoon welcome everyone um it's my
distinct and special pleasure to welcome
you to our 10th um uh annual rare
disease Day event here at bro Institute
and um I would like to First welcome um
my uh co-chair for this event Belinda
termier to say a few welcoming remarks
thank you all for
coming thank you so hello hello everyone
my name is blinda Tamir and I'm the
president and co-founder of the Tamir
Foundation um it is my honor to welcome
you today to an Era of innovation and to
congratulate the broad on the 10th
anniversary of Hosting this rare disease
Day event I'd like to start by thanking
the Bro Institute for their partnership
on this event specifically Dr Anna grea
and Jillian Shaw the Tamir Foundation is
honored to continue
collaborating so in in ation is at the
center of our work at the foundation I
look around and being surrounded by
exceptional entrepreneurial thinking
leadership is an honor thank you to all
of you of to today's speakers and
everyone in the audience for your
commitment to patience this industry and
the world the Tamir Foundation was
founded to continue the legacy of my
husband Henry Tamir who for many was an
inspirational leader our goal is to
connect life science innovators biotech
entrepreneurs CEOs and Visionaries
because we believe that helping leaders
succeed will ultimately help their
Innovations reach patients we believe in
the work of everyone in this room and
are honored to play a role in amplifying
the voices of rare disease researchers
discoverers and CEOs we recognize how
important it is to Foster community and
collaboration in this space days like
today remind us to pause and come
together with that we are inviting
everyone to join us in Partnership skill
and knowledge sharing towards driving
impact and change in the lives of rare
disease patients and families again
thank you for joining
us thank you Belinda one couldn't ask
for um a better partner and co-chair for
these events our two organizations the
termier foundation um Katherine Smith
who um helps uh run that together with
uh on our side Jullian Shaw and then
also uh Katy liori um and others I'm
sure on the termier foundation side who
I haven't mentioned are uh very much uh
the people behind this event today so I
want to make sure that we don't forget
uh sometimes it happens until the end
but to acknowledge them at the beginning
and say a great thank you for bringing
us all together today uh for this
special event so um my name is Anna grea
I am a professor at Harvard Medical
School I am an uh a Core Institute
member here at the broad Institute and I
have really dedicated uh my scientific
uh career to understanding uh rare
diseases and hopefully building
therapies uh for rare diseases and it is
um actually our 10th anniversary today
uh the 10th event that is being
organized here at Broad which really
coincides with you know a conversation I
had about 10 years ago or 10 and a half
years ago now with um the founding
director of the broad Eric Lander and
then subsequently with the current dor
of the Bro Todd Gob in both cases I sort
of made the case for how can the world's
or one of the world's Premier uh
genetics and genomics Institute not have
a special day for rare diseases and of
course in the typical entrepreneurial
Spirit of the broad they said well why
don't you start one and so here we are
10 years later uh celebrating uh the
10th anniversary of this uh day of
coming together to um talk about rare
diseases to meet with all the
stakeholders in this uh broad Community
it's the uh
the scientists the families the patients
uh the Physicians everyone is welcome
under this big um tent uh and it really
um in in many ways affects all of us in
different parts um of Our Lives as you
know of course uh rare diseases uh there
are you know about 10,000 rare diseases
they disproportionately affect children
of course um and it is you know a big
fight to try to understand them and
develop therapies for as many of these
diseases as quickly as possible and many
of you and many of the people will hear
from today are very very much engaged um
in this fight and you know of course one
has to acknowledge uh at an event like
this that there are some headwinds that
you know we're all facing at this time
um I think it's uh important to uh
mention that you know there have been um
you know uh there was a lot of Hope for
the renewal of the priority voucher
review program for example which many of
our colleagues in biotech and Fara would
have relied on in order to make
investments and make progress in this
space and you know this is uh something
that did not happen um uh in December
and so it's something that we now hope
uh will become part of the conversation
again um and of course we all uh you
know wish to advocate for that program
to be uh reinstituted so that it can
help our patients especially our
pediatric patients uh with rare diseases
and I think this generally compounds an
overall landscape that one again has to
acknowledge in biotech and Pharma where
there has been some uh reluctance in
making investments in this space and
again I think that we all um you know uh
understand this and we all feel it in
different aspects of our lives but as
everyone who knows me knows I am an
optimist and a a glass half full type of
person and so I couldn't be more excited
about what this next uh decade will
bring in terms of our abilities to
address uh rare diseases uh especially
an area that our group here at Broad is
very much interested in rare genetic
diseases um we have launched um an
initiative um that is really focused um
on making progress uh in this space we
call it the ladder secures accelerator
some of you may have been to uh our
symposia we have another one coming up
in May which you're all absolutely
invited to attend um but the whole
concept of the ladder secures
accelerator is to actually uh in simple
terms uh try to harness what we
understand about the biology of rare
diseases uh in a massively parallel
fashion so that we can find nodes
targetable nodes that underly many uh
diseases so that we can potentially
develop treatments for as many of these
diseases as possible the orphan as many
diseases as possible and so you will
hear today from uh some of the speakers
who are involved in the latter secures
accelerator because they have you know
received support uh from uh from our
accelerator to uh push some of the what
we call nodal biology projects forward
and you know you you'll hear about
progress that's happening in that space
you will hear more of that at our annual
Symposium which is happening in May um
but there's also some deep verticals
that we're fighting for uh as part of
this uh uh this project this accelerator
which basically means that we're going
deep into understanding uh noal biology
here at Broad by really uh attacking
simultaneously thousands of rare genetic
diseases modeled in um human cells in
parallel and interrogating them with
modern tools like crisper Technologies
and uh AI driven Imaging approaches that
allow us uh to actually understand about
the underlying biology of thousands of
misspellings in the DNA in a massively
parallel simultaneous fashion
and no one uh could be a better speaker
to represent some of those efforts that
are happening here at Broad than our
keynote speaker for today Dr Anne
Carpenter who is of course my colleague
uh my friend she's an Institute
scientist here at the broad and she's
really a Pioneer in you know what you
hear now more and more like Aid driven
image processing and understanding
images well Anne was doing it way before
this was actually cool or a buzzword
that everyone used all over the all over
the world and I think you will hear
something about about all these
foundational discoveries that she made
possible which now make it possible for
us to potentially understand thousands
of um rare genetic diseases in a
massively parallel fashion so without uh
further Ado I will let um an uh take it
from here thank you so much for coming
thank you so
much I'm so proud to be part of this
celebration today of how far the
community of rare disease research has
come and also um pushing towards what's
in the future so really excited to be
part of this event today thanks for
organizing thank you Belinda as well um
I want to begin with just this visual
that you may have seen before of all the
individual genome regions associated
with disease that have been discovered
you know back when I started my career
there weren't so many um and now it's
just exploded this doesn't even come up
to present day and what this chart tells
me is that while of course it's
wonderful if we could assign a a team of
a thousand researchers to each disorder
out there it's just not going to be
scalable even to keep up with the new
diseases that are discovered every day
through genome sequencing much less to
get to this backlog so we need something
more systematic and of course we always
think well technology should help us
here right and there are some amazing
technologies that have come into play
Computing is one that I'm very excited
about as a machine learning and
computational biology expert um you
might be familiar with this view Mo's
law which is showing on a log scale this
sort of exponential decrease in the cost
of compute over time and it's just a
phenomenal um you know um peak of human
Ingenuity that has allowed us to stay on
this track and allow Computing to be
faster and faster better and better to
accomplish so many things including in
biology and you as you probably well
know sequencing has gotten cheaper and
cheaper it used to cost hundred million
doar to sequence a genome and it um the
the reduced costs of this have even
broken More's law even better than
computing
uh over time and so you think okay well
this is great technology is great let's
do the same for drug Discovery and it at
first looks like an awesome picture but
then you notice wait a second um the
scale is wrong and upside down here
because instead of looking at how many
at the cost of a drug going down and
down over time instead what we're
looking at here is exactly the opposite
that um in the 1940s you could get uh 30
new drugs if you had a billion dollars
even in today's dollars um but now it's
somewhere between1 to6 billion dollar
per drug and this is absolutely not
scalable to um to rare diseases or even
even the the more common ones that we
have so we call this a room's law
because it's More's law backwards and
it's something that really needs to be
fixed and why is it so expensive why
hasn't it why has it gotten more
expensive over time even though we have
all these amazing molecular techniques
cell biological techniques computational
techniques and yet it's getting more
expensive over time um the answer is
first of all there are just a lot of
steps in drug Discovery this um
simplifies it quite dramatically but
there's hundreds of steps along the path
from having an idea of what might cause
a disorder what are the proteins
involved what are the pathways involved
to then finding a small molecule or
another uh type of um fix for the
disorder and then all the testing in
cell systems animal systems and and
ultimately in humans for clinical trials
but I would say really that's the time
element the cost element really comes
down to this that drug fails most of the
time and so even with everybody's best
efforts all of our Ingenuity all of our
hopes and dreams going into drugs that
go into a human clinical trials 90% of
them fail um and just things just don't
work the way we expect because humans
are a very complex system and chemistry
doesn't always work out um for small
molecules um gene therapy doesn't always
work out and so um this is the real
struggle of why it's so so expensive to
um to cure illnesses okay but maybe
robots will come to our rescue um or at
least um Ai and machine learning you may
have seen a lot of um a lot of headlines
about the new advancements and there are
many and they are very exciting I don't
know that they're going to um reverse a
room's law um in the upward Trend but
even if we could just stabilize um we
would be quite delighted and it turns
out that the a lot of these Pharma
companies that have been built from the
ground up with some kind of a a basis of
using large scale data and using uh
computational Tech techniques um they
are are starting to get drugs into
clinical trials it's too EAS too early
to say whether these will be
dramatically different than um and
faster in the pre-clinical stage or
whether the success rates will be
different there's just too few that have
actually gone to human clinical trials
but there's at least some inklings on
the horizon so today what we'll talk
about is not the entire field of AI and
Drug Discovery but rather some very
specific areas where I'm seeing progress
happening in drug discovery where
machine learning together with beautiful
kinds of data and clever new molecular
and and cell biology techniques are
allowing us to make some progress so
that's what we'll talk about today is
and how we use images so you might all
be thinking a lot more if you're in the
rare disease space you might be thinking
a lot about genomics and um molecular um
proteins genes mrnas um but here I'm
talking about images and I'm literally
talking about microscopy images of cells
it seems a little bit of an old school
kind of technique but because
computational methods allow us to
extract information from images and turn
those into numerical data we can then do
a lot of the same kinds of things we do
with molecular data so there's two big
things I'll talk about today the first
is measuring known phenotypes in images
by which I mean measuring things we know
we want to look for in images and then
the second half we'll talk about
profiling to characterize samples so
I'll explain what that means as we as we
go along so first off measuring what we
we know we want to measure when we are
looking at images of of these particular
cells here we're just highlighting the
DNA of the cells so these are nuclei
that we're looking at and you can think
about how to cure cancer in this case um
this type of amkl one way is to kill the
cancer cells great if you can do it um
another approach though when that
doesn't seem to be working out so well
is to just cause the cells to sort of
stabilize just stop proliferating that
that alone would be good enough to to um
solve many types of cancer and so the
researchers we worked with here John
crispino um from Northwestern University
LED this work with a whole team here at
the broad they thought well let's let's
see if we can find some compounds that
push these cells into this polyploid
state where the the DNA has divided but
they've just kind of stabilized they
don't they don't proliferate as quickly
anymore and examples of what this looks
like is shown here on the right and um
we used in this case uh image analysis
software to measure what they knew they
wanted to look for we want nuclei that
are big and have a lot more DNA in them
and so that's what they did in this
experiment very simple kind of readout
from an image analysis perspective but
allows us to screen um tens of thousands
of drugs here at the rooad and identify
that one that was already being used for
other sorts of cancer looked really
promising and they ended up deciding to
test it in a clinical trial for
myofibrosis which was Su which was
successful so this is one of the first
foray here at the bro that that led to a
successful clinical trial and again
we're looking at the images and we're
measuring a thing that we already know
is is a useful outcome for patients and
and it worked well here leukemia is a
nice thing to study because you can take
blood from the patients and do a lot of
experiments with it it's very kind of
native context so that worked out very
well but now let's turn to this second
kind of way to use images which is
profiling so what if we don't know what
we're looking for what if we're working
in a disease area where we don't know
the genes involved we don't understand
them maybe we know the gene but we don't
really understand the mechanism of how
that causes a disorder in the human
whole organism in these cases we've
really found a lot of use in this
strategy called profiling and what I
mean here is instead of measuring just
the one thing that we care about in this
in the images like how much DNA is
present instead we measure everything we
can about the cells and then we use that
numerical data kind of like a barcode or
like a fingerprint of what is happening
to the cell when this disease is present
and this strategy is called image-based
profiling we often use something called
the cell painting assay I won't describe
today but um that's the assay that
labels the cells and um we can think of
an analogy here to human patients so to
many of us we can look at a lot of
little kids and have no clue whether
they might have some kind of underlying
pathology but for pediatricians who
specialize in many of these different
kinds of disorders they have a very
visual very um strong ability to detect
a disorder just based on a picture of a
human face and so it turns out of course
computers are pretty good at that too um
if you give them a training set and
explain that these children have down
syndrome these children have Anglin they
are able to distinguish these just based
on the facial structure features alone
so what we're doing here with
image-based profiling with cells is the
exact same thing just sort of zooming in
quite a bit so of course you know your
um your dermatologists can tell if your
mole is um is uh sketchy looking if you
um if they look at a picture of it um
and your U pathologist can take a slice
of a of a potential cancer and and take
a look at it and see what's going on all
of these are examples where the physical
structure of the thing tells us whether
there's a disease so let's take that
concept and use um cells growing in a
dish which are cheap and easy to acquire
and most importantly we can perturb them
with tens and thousands of uh different
drugs we can knock out all their genes
and see what happens and so on they're
much more manipulated in the in the dish
and yet we can still take pictures and
see what's wrong with these cells when
we knock out this Gene do they look a
little funny and so on so this is the
the field of image-based profiling and
what are some of the things we can do
with it the first example I'll give was
originally an academic project um I take
no credit for this experiment other than
they used our software um in in order to
extract the features that they needed
for this project so what was it um at
the University of Utah they took some
cells and grew them in a dish and
stained them with some stains and then
they knocked out a gene that was known
to cause cerebral cavernous malformation
CCM and when they made that knockout lo
and behold it had an extremely obvious
phenotype you can tell something's wrong
with these cells they're much more green
the red stuff is much more bright and um
what that means is now you can take
cells that are in this unhealthy disease
Associated State and test drugs
systematically can I find a drug that
makes the unhealthy cells look healthy
again and what's lovely about this kind
of a of an experimental setup is uh
these researchers happen to be experts
in CCM but you don't actually have to be
an expert just knock out the gene that
causes the disorder and look at the
cells is there something wrong with them
and you can look at them of course by ey
which they did originally here but you
can also look at them with a computer to
get much more subtle effects if it had
been more subtle maybe you'd need a
computer to detect this now in this case
it was obvious and what they did is they
chose some drugs out of this big screen
after doing this experiment they
examined every pair of images by ey and
they also let the computer pick some um
some of the uh drugs to follow up on it
turns out the ones the computer picked
were actually better than those chosen
by the experts and eventually led to a
drug which is now um in phase two
clinical trials as part of recursion so
they spun off this company and this was
how this whole um company got started
they now have hundreds and hundreds of
these kinds of phenotypes because this
is a very systematic thing you don't
have to study each disease for decades
you just if it's a loss of function kind
of disease where the gene function can
just be perturbed we can just see is
there a phenotype if yes screen a bunch
of drugs to to fix it and that's the the
systematic approach that they're taking
within this company they now have eight
eight clinical trials in
progress okay so back to my lab we
realized this is really powerful to be
able to analyze images in a systematic
way and so about uh five years ago I
helped to organize this large Consortium
consisting of the number of Pharma
partners that you see here as well as a
lot of academic collaborators and and
other um service providers in the
biotech space and what we did is we
created giant data set which is now
available and you can see the the
website and and what we've produced here
but what's really lovely about it was
we've taken cells and we've said let's
just create one Baseline data set that
has lots and lots of genes that have
either been knocked down using crisper
or overexpressed um and also a lot of
different small molecules and we can use
this resource for all kinds of different
things I'll just highlight a couple of
them
today the first is to just learn more
about your learn more about the gene or
the chemical perturbation so um there's
20,000 genes in the human genome and
weirdly enough to me if you had asked me
20 years ago I would have thought by now
we would have a decent idea on the
function of most of them but um many
have zero function annotated some of
them have a function that's been
described but it's not the whole story
and so what's lovely about this data set
is you can um go to the website type in
your Gene of interest and find out about
um about the impact of either over
expressing or knocking down that Gene in
this given cell line what do the cells
look like um are there other genes that
produce similar kinds of phenotypes um
we've used the term nodal biology today
maybe I should Define it before we go
too too much further that um if it's the
case that every single variant um and
every single Gene is completely
different and completely unique and we
have to solve them all one to one
hand-to-hand combat it's going to take a
very long time but what if it's the case
that multiple variants have actually
kind of the same impact on protein
function or multiple genes when they're
perturbed have kind of the same impact
on an overall pathway it turns out there
are certainly many examples where this
does happen and if we can step one um
group all of the variance or the genes
into some categories some nodes and find
some common commonalities amongst them
then we have a better chance of dividing
and conquering and so that's um uh one
of the ideas here is that if you type in
your Gene you find other genes that are
similar to it that might give you some
Clues okay maybe my Gene has no
functional annotation but if it if its
impact on cells is exactly the same as
some other Gene that is annotated it
gives me a bit of a clue on on which way
to go or maybe the morphological
features tell me something ah in this
one the the DNA is is uh has a funny
texture or in that one the mitochondria
are um are located in an unusual
location and so on the other cool thing
we can do when we have a giant database
like this is we can start going hunting
for um drugs and so let's say I have a
gene that I know is associated with a
human disorder and I perturb it and I do
see a phenotype like I described um in
the case of recursion um in the
beginning so once we see that it has a
phenotype I can say in this database of
all of these cell images that I've
created have I ever seen a drug that
produces that same kind of impact or the
opposite kind of impact on cells and by
doing this matching exercise it's a
pretty straightforward computer vision
approach we are able to filter down all
the hundreds of thousands of compounds
or genetic perturbations and look for
matches so we did this in one experiment
where we had 30,000 profiles to match
against and we typically picked um 20 or
30 uh drugs to follow up on that looked
like they would impinge on the gene of
interest and sure enough um it doesn't
work all the time it would be kind of a
miracle if it if it did because this
step usually costs a few Millions to
tens of of millions of dollars to run a
high throughput screen to physically
test compounds to to determine whether
they have some kind of impact that
you're looking for instead we're taking
that one year and10 million and doing a
computational query in an afternoon you
don't expect it to work all the time but
we were shocked to find that it worked
32 to 42% depending how you count
exactly um and you can read the paper
for more details one particular case we
used Yap one as the query Gene because
we knew it was important in a a rare
type of cancer called saroma and and
identified some drugs that looked really
promising for it so promising that we
spun off a little company to get started
and at trying to attack these types of
of cancer and solid
tumors okay so now we're getting really
excited about scaling things up if we
can gather large sets of images we have
the the potential to um to solve lots of
lots of disorders in parallel and so we
see this vision of a future um here at
the road largely led by anag grea of
this um this to function um pathway
where okay sequencing we've got that
down pat and we're very good at it and
it's lot lot cheaper than it used to be
so we can find variants that are
associated with disorders but then how
do we go from there to drugs and one way
is through this kind of profiling I am
excited about profiling with morphology
because it's very inexpensive and very
scalable kind of Technology but we can
also use transcriptomes and proteomes in
order to capture all the information
when this um change in the DNA code is
there what do I see as the impact on the
cell and by doing this we can do two
kinds of things we can immediately gain
phenotypic insights like the DNA looks
funny the mitochondria looks funny the
MRNA levels look odd um but we can also
classify these variants and that's where
we get to the nodal bio biology we can
find the nodes that group a lot of
different variants or different genes
with each other and that allows us to
either um uh find diseases and try to
reverse them with drugs either
computationally like I described or
through physical experiments um or we
can we can kind of go the oldfashioned
way and and really dive into each
disease once we know a little bit more
about its mechanism so I'll my last
project that I'll describe is a very
large one it's called project ver champ
and our goal is to um it it as you can
see a very large group of people are
involved in this project I'll just talk
about a tiny bit of it today which is um
but the big picture is taking 880,000
coding variants um it's not every
coating variant that exists in humans
but it's a lot of them and um and you
can see some of the details here some
are known to be benign some are known to
be pathogenic and some are uncertain and
we're working to get these all cloned
and tested and and what are we going to
do with them once we have them we're
going to measure all the things about
them so when this variant is present
what happens to the cells the there's
other parts of the project that are
working on testing does this variant
cause the protein um in which the
variant exists is it causing that
protein to interact differently with
other proteins um the second one is when
that variant is present does the amount
of the protein change does it knock it
out completely for example um but we'll
talk today about the localization and
morphology since that's what my lab has
been working on directly does this
variant have any impact on the
localization or the morphology of the
cells so here it's a collaboration with
Miko typal who um did a beautiful
experiment with his um graduate student
Jessica lacost and here's one example of
how this works you take a protein that's
known to be associated with a human
disorder you express it in cells and tag
it so you can see it and so here's three
cells three kind of dark oval nuclei are
not shown in the middle and then the
green stuff is around it and then you
just say well um if I introduce this
variant that's associated with Nunan
syndrome does that localization change
and I don't have to know anything about
Nunan syndrome or this protein or its
normal function or even what these dots
are I can see there's a difference and
then all I have to do is test a bunch of
drugs to see if I can find one that
reverses it so in the same way that a a
pediatrician I wouldn't notice that
there's anything unusual about this boy
but a pediatrician specializing in Nunan
syndrome certainly would be able to tell
um I can look at the cell images and see
that there's a difference so that's the
idea of the of the project they tested
3,000 variants in this in this initial
pilot experiment now as I said we're
scaling to 880,000 but not there yet but
in the initial 3000 they found around
250 disease phenotypes that were um
discovered most of them were associated
with pathogenic um phenotypes and here's
some examples of what those um
phenotypes look like and um some are
pretty common Pathways that we notice so
um for example it wasn't very common for
there to be a mislocalization between
tubulin and cytoplasm but it was
extremely common to find mislocalization
between the plasma membrane and the ER
for example you can see a lot of traffic
let's say coming between those two
compartments so here again we're trying
to group these variants into classes
where is it possible we could find a
drug that would that would um treat
every single one of those maybe 30 to 50
that are in that pathway that are
mislocalized between these two
compartments maybe so so let's give it a
shot um how are we going to do this
though because um at at the broad we
certainly can do drug screens and we we
do a number of them each year but they
are expensive and now we have 250
disease phenotypes we can't afford to do
250 diseases times 30,000 or 100,000
drugs so how are we going to break this
bottleneck we'll use technology that was
developed by Paul Blay's lab and then
perfected by JT Neil in order to allow
this kind of localization screening and
here's the basic idea um and which we're
running right now in a pilot experiment
um funded by ladders to cures where in
each well we have a single compound so
one potential drug already FDA approved
if it works well it's like a a really
good candidate so in each well we put
one single drug but we put a mixture of
the 250 or so diseases um and so it's
it's the the normal healthy version of
the Gene and also the um unhealthy
disease Associated version throw them
all in there um but each one has a
barcode so we know which one's which and
that allows us to do this decoding where
the first step is we look at the
localization does it have the healthy or
unhealthy version uh of this
localization and then the second step I
won't describe the details is where we
um do this barcode detection where each
Little Dot of light is call in us either
G A TC and it's flashing over many
cycles to tell us the the identity of
the barcode which tells us which for
this little cluster of cells which Gene
did they get and is it the healthy
version or the diseased version so for
each little island of cells we find out
did this drug make the unhealthy version
of the protein go back to its normal
healthy location and that's the idea of
the project we're just in the pilot
stages of being able to do this drug
screening and so now we're hoping ing
these 80,000 variants lead to many
thousands of these phenotypes which we
can then put into this drug screening um
here we're testing it in a single cell
type but eventually we could test it
over many over
time and so with that I'm very happy to
take questions and looking forward to
the discussion for the rest of the day
thank
you and please come right up to the the
microphone if you don't mind
thank you great talk happy to learn so
many exciting applications of IM based
profiling so my question that can you
comment the possibility using Imaging
based profiling how to design a
combinatorial drug Discovery how to
design combination drug Discovery
combination drug Discovery ah yeah yeah
so everything that I described um you
can put whatever you like in the wells
to treat the cells so if you have
combination therapies if you think maybe
um a two panels of drugs you might like
to combine you can absolutely test them
together and see if they have the impact
that you're looking for it's possible to
use the AI based algorithm to predict
the combination yeah yeah and so there's
a lot of research out there to say okay
if I perturb one gene I get this output
what if I perturb two genes is it sort
of the additive effect of the two is it
the multiplicative effect of the two or
do I expect them to interact in some
weird way so I've seen this often with
genes than with compounds like at least
with genes you have an idea of what
you're perturbing in the in the cell um
but the same principle applies for for
chemicals as well where um you can take
large data sets with individual
perturbations and maybe a small data set
that has the combinations and try to
learn from that to be able to predict
the combinatorial effects how well it
works depends right now there I've only
seen a couple of experiments in this
mostly in the transcriptomic space not
the image based space um but it seems
like like um it's at least promising
let's say um but I I I think it's too
early to say whether it's um going to be
possible to really predict the the
outcomes from scratch like that thank
you yeah thank you for the
question beautiful talk so I'm thinking
about how do you think about going from
cells to patients right the you know
that Discovery in the cells of changing
the phenotypes how do you consider all
the physiology all the pathophysiology
and all of that um what's your process
of thinking through that yeah yeah it's
a it's a very great point so um most of
my research has focused on clearly the
early drug Discovery stage right um You
don't go from a cell experiment to
giving humans um a drug the next day and
so for most um I would expect that for
most projects if you did find an already
FDA approved drug that let's say looks
like it reverses a localization
phenotype in the cell based assay um the
next step in my mind would be to try to
find some animal model of the disorder
to to try to try to see whether you have
the same impact at the whole organism
level
um but it also depends on what the drug
is if it's a very innocuous um not too
scary you know vitamin or neutraceutical
or something like this you might be a
little more inclined to give it a try
whereas if it's a nasty cancer drug you
might be a little more reluctant to
immediately try to give it to patients
um it's beyond my it's my beyond my pay
grade this is where the MD phds should
get involved but well I'm think of even
ways of you're recruiting you know lar
large language models and other things
to be able to inform better mechanism of
saying hey this is more amenable to a a
change right like something in a dish or
something that's in you know a leukemia
that you're describing um those seem
like just better Target so to speak is
there some way of compressing the use
right now of consultants and MD phds and
actually having some more um I don't
know like logical flow that is
programmed to evaluate these compounds
you're generating oh that's it's a it's
a great point so let's say for example
out of an experiment you get either a
list of gen that look like promising
targets or you get a list of compounds
or drugs that look like potentially
useful I absolutely see there's some
potential for large language models that
can synthesize the existing biomedical
literature and just say Okay out of
these 10 you know these maybe make sense
or these might make me a little nervous
because of these side effects or so on
and so kind of interpreting those lists
for clinicians to use their judgment as
they're thinking about it there's
definitely potential there but as
everyone is well aware there's also
hallucinations and so building um these
AI systems that are capable of um
accessing real data providing you the
direct link to the to the underlying
data resource those will be really
important as we're trying to interpret
these these kinds of um
experiments hi um beautiful talk
um as you may remember I'm focused on
ALS I was yesterday at the natural um
ALS Consortium uh to understand patients
um 80% of patients that who develop ALS
have we calling um I guess
non-genetic sporadic yeah at the same
time um when we take um stem cells and
and generate motor neurons from these
patients it's kind of an undiscussed
Topic in the field but they all seem to
have
phenotypes and so for me that says and I
think most people would agree with that
there's probably a genetic component
even in what we don't call genetic ALS
yeah and so there's a lot of variance
obviously in a lot of different genes
and Pathways that could be involved in
development of
disease this is kind of a big bottleneck
for the field at this moment because we
don't understand which patients we
should Target with what type of
therapies do you think because I don't
know how your variants were selected but
do you think your technology would also
be uh able to kind of identify maybe you
know unknown variants and and and the
Rel ship to disease I love this question
because especially at the Brad we're
pretty genome obsessed and but it turns
out DNA is not everything and mRNA is
not everything sometimes there are
disease phenotypes that manifest at
levels sort of beyond that protein and
onward and just morphological
infrastructural phenotypes and so I
think that um profiling Technologies
like Imaging and transcriptomics
proteomics can play a role in this
ideology of like what are these how do
we classify these patients into groups
that make mechanistic sense and might be
treated in the in the same way and so a
whole another um approach I didn't
describe today is to take patient cell
lines and grow cells in a dish we've
done this for a few disorders so far
where we try to identify from the
patient samples are we able to group um
the samples in some kind of meaningful
way that gives us some kind of clue as
to what the shared mechanisms might be
in different classes of patients and I
think that's a real potential here and
have you thought about taking um very
from patients and and introducing those
variants into cells yep and then making
isogenic cell lines it turns out if you
want to make an isogenic cell line by
introducing a mutation um it's a very
clean experiment um from a like a design
perspective it's a little messy when it
turns out because when you clone the
cells they turn into like multiple
independent snowflakes and so if you if
you um if you don't even knock out the
cell but just um knock out the gene but
make 10 copies of a cell line they all
look a little different from each other
so there's if there's strong a phenotype
you will certainly see it in the
isogenic case but it's not quite as as
easy and simple as one might hope so if
phenotypes are weak it's still very
challenging it's yeah still challenging
but the only way to know is to try so
empirically I think it's a really good
thing to try okay thank you yeah yeah
sure hi thank you so much it was a
really wonderful talk um question was
already commented on a little bit but I
was curious about the technology um and
its application and understanding
variance of unknown significance um if
you could look at using the different uh
localization to try and understand those
better and maybe reclassify absolutely
that's that's really the fundamental
goal of of that project is to um is to I
mean for the pathogenic ones to keep
moving along towards drugs but for the
unknown significance ones to group them
do these look more like the pathogenic
or more like the benign so that is
absolutely one use of of this kind of
data and we've seen a number of
different examples sometimes um it's
like pathogenic and benign other times
it's like three different class es of
pathogenic and then benign and and
sometimes you can't tell the difference
at all because it's not a localization
problem it's some kind of other
functional problem so we see across the
board all different things thank you
great thanks
everybody and that was amazing um but uh
following up on our long Now 10e history
um of uh celebrating this uh particular
day we've always been uh very focused on
uh in equal parts celebrating the
science and actually uh the other
members of the community who are just as
important either because they're
scientists themselves or because they're
pushing the science forward and of
course I mean the parents or the family
members The Advocates the people who
really make this community work um I
think and um to paraphrase um Margaret
me me um do not underestimate what a
motivated group of parents can do to
change the world indeed it's the only
thing that ever has and so on that theme
it is my honor to introduce you to two
parents who are doing incredible things
um in this area so aah Leo and Nathan
guo um are uh both here to represent the
zttk sunshine Foundation I think they'll
tell you much more about their work but
I just want to say um for our um ladder
secures accelerator an important uh
collaborators also the Chan Zuckerberg
initiative and they have been successful
in securing funding for their
organization and so um It's a Wonderful
to explore ways in which uh we can all
work together the scientists and the
parents and uh Patient Advocates so I
leave it to you to tell us more about
your work thank you thank you so
[Applause]
much thank you so much to the terier
foundation and the broad Institute for
having us here today to speak to all of
you my name is aah Leo this is my
husband Nathan guo we are parents to our
2-year-old son Lucas whom we call
endearingly luki we're also patient
advocacy group leaders of the zttk
sunshine foundation advocating for luki
and others like him with
ctk syndrome and ultra rare neural
developmental
disorder today it is such an honor to
share our journey to accelerate a cure
for
zttk I will start off by first defining
what is even a cure for us and how
critical it is to integrate patient
Insight in our journey and then my
husband Nathan will walk through the
research road map integrating patient
insight and how some of you can share
your Innovative work as part of our
journey we hope you will walk away today
from our talk with more insights into
how partnering with patient advocacy
groups like ours can increase the impact
in innovation in rare disease
research so first I want to get some
insights from the audience what is
secure how many of you here think you
have a precise definition of what is a
cure by a quick show of
hands great I see a few hands
Now by another quick show of hands how
many of you are quite uncertain about
what is a
cure great I see many hands in the
audience great in fact when we talk to
other patient advocacy groups and even
within our own ctk Community there is no
UniFi definition of what is a cure
so how do Nathan and I think about what
is
secure we would like to borrow a
framework from healthc Care
Professionals this is a framework they
use when administering safe medications
we believe it is also applicable to how
we think about rare disease
research it is giving the right drug at
the right dose at the right route to the
right patient at the right
time while we think dose and Route are
important today we're going to focus on
defining the right drug for the right
patient at the right
time to understand what is the right
drug we have to first understand what is
the disease zttk
syndrome was discovered in 2016 by four
researchers it is an ultra rare
neurodevelopmental disorder it is a
monogenic disease caused by mutation in
the son Gene it is diagnosed primarily
through whole exome or genome
sequencing our community is growing we
have estimated roughly 300 families
around the world we believe many remain
undiagnosed today
our phenotypes and symptoms are are wide
spectrum what we know today is that the
most prevalent symptoms are Global
development delays motor delay speech
delay feeding difficulties and also
intellectual
disability based on a paper published in
2021 we know that from the initial ctk
cohort about
50% of the patients develop seizures
during
childhood there is currently no cures or
treatment so by looking at this one
might think that one important concern
would be to address the seizure
burden we know that some other
neurodevelopmental groups have also
identified seizures as their primary end
point and even have drugs in development
and this is where patient insights are
critical last year we conducted a survey
with our ztk community we asked them
what are the top three symptoms that are
most important for you and your family
to address in your
child
cognition
speech seizures come in low lower than
these other
symptoms we duck a little deeper to
understand why we collected stories
anecdotes from our
families some mention that they
prioritize cognition because they hope
for their child to have Independence one
day some say that they
prioritize speech because they would
like their child to express ex
themselves more freely even if they're
just basic needs and
emotions and this is where we believe
patient voices are so critical for us to
Define what is the right
drug but even when we have what matters
to the entire
Community each family has their own
unique Journey they has their own dreams
and hope for their
children it is up to the individual
patient and family to Define what is the
right drug for
them I can only speak for what matters
to me Nathan and
luki this is our trial son luki he is
sweet
curious and he is clever in his own way
he's also experiencing profound
challenges at two and a half he spent
hours every single day working on the
most basic
skills the first picture of is of him
working on standing and walking he's in
this big equipment called a standard
that he has to be in for at least an
hour a day to help
withstanding initially it would break my
heart to strap him to this big equipment
and he's strong he would fight me
kicking and shouting to get out of the
standard but now we are more used to it
and we even have some fun this is
actually a photo from last year our
photo shoot from where is this
day the second picture shows that he's
still working on fine motor skills how
to point how to pick up a cereal this is
from a 3-week
intensive that we were in last year
where he was in therapies three hours
every day for three weeks otpt speech
therapies just to work on these basic
skills in his picture he's working on
crawling and after the therapy sessions
he was a able to put a ball in the
container and he was so proud of himself
the look on his face was
priceless now luki is desperate to
communicate with us the only word he can
say right now is Mama he says it
constantly he says it to everyone and
everything but I cherish it so much
because I've also heard from other
community members that kids may lose
their speech
the few words that they have acquired
there may be regression over
time the other pictures of him drinking
from a straw Cup every meal he's working
so hard on basic skills to chew to
swallow and this is one of the first
pictures of him being able to drink
water out of a straw Cup today he still
primarily fed by a feeding
tube for Ely he has not had a seizure
yet but it is a fear that is looming
over us every single
day while we don't know when luki will
be able to walk to talk to feed
independently what we do know is that
which each each day that passes his
brain is not developing the way it
should be
we love luki for who he is but we also
want him to
fulfill his potential beyond the
limitations of
zttk the right
drug is a drug that can help him right
now a drug the right drug may not be the
drug that can help him reverse all his
symptoms the right drug may be a drug
that can improve his
cognition his speech even just a little
bit because like some families in our
community we also hope for him to have
Independence one
day when we're no longer around we too
hope that he can express himself freely
maybe one day say Mom Mama and Papa I
love
[Music]
you as we sit here
today discussing groundbreaking research
and
Innovation I want to thank all of you
and encourage you to think beyond the
molecules and
data you are giving an
opportunity to children like
luki and opportunity to rewrite their
future thank you so
much great so before I start to dive in
further into the science of this all I
want to First acknowledge that Aiden and
I are very lucky to be here today drug
development for ultra rare conditions is
largely driven by parents which is very
empowering but they we have to
acknowledge that only parents that have
sufficient resources the ability to
access networks like the bro are able to
really be successful at this and so we
feel a deep obligation to our community
some of whom are just trying to survive
the dayto day many of whom do not have
the resources to be able to to progress
these um treatments and cures so it's
really important to to acknowledge that
first up front so in the next few uh
slides I'll take you through more of the
science of this right when we think
about the right drug for the right
patient of course we need to understand
the underlying biology and then put that
together with the right time what does
that mean so on this slide you'll see a
lot of detail about zttk and the son
Gene biology it's a heterozy mutation
it's a hlin sufficiency and loss of
function we haven't seen any toxic gain
of function almost all of the mutations
we've seen in our community are denovo
um you'll see the to the left side here
um the both the S Gene and the S protein
you might see a very large Exxon 3 you
might see both DNA and RNA binding
motifs you'll see a lot of little
triangles along both the Gene and the
protein these are each triangle
represents one patient documented by our
lead researcher Dr Arin an at the
University of Alabama at Birmingham what
you'll see is that scattered across the
bottom there's a lot of onesz twz
mutations and then there's also one big
spike that spike is actually about a
quarter of the population has the same
four base pair deletion resulting in a
frame shift mutation um we're still
understanding the genotype phenotype
correlations but we're continuing to
learn more about the sanen and its
function you know our understanding
today is that the sanen is quite
important um it's a nuclear speckle
protein it's U believed to be a master
Reg of many Downstream genes actually
many of which also have their own
intellectual disability disorders
attached to them um it's important for
intron excision in prear splicing and
it's also critical to some regulation of
some transcription Pathways and you know
it's highly conserved across species and
it's um expressed ubiquitously in the
body so now that we understand a little
bit more about the disease and the
biology we really want to present kind
of a framework work of how do we
prioritize our zttk drug development
efforts because as a a patient advocacy
group we don't we have limited resources
time and money to be able to pursue um
treatments and cures for our kids so
what I'll uh show on the following page
is a 2 by two both a and I are ex-
Consultants so we think everything can
be solved by a 2 by two um on the bottom
x-axis what you'll see is speed to the
clinic speed to the clinic is really the
time dimension of this are there
existing approved or clinical stage
drugs for CNS ideally even for rare or
ultra rare CNS you know that can
indicate that there are you know real
regulatory Pathways we can leverage
right it's more much more difficult for
us as an ultra rare group to um you know
try totally brand new um Pathways and
then on the y- axis what you'll see is
kind of all the potential therapeutic
impact really the right drug for the
right patient right does it actually
address the patient need that ADA talked
about earlier that the community has
identified that the patients identify as
their primary need what's the mechanism
of action how safe is it um and
ultimately what's the patient experience
uh with that so here is the 2 by two
I'll I'll walk you through the different
pieces really a 3X3 um so as I mentioned
on the x-axis speed to the clinic so on
the far right side that is the fastest
of the clinic things that are much more
uh likely to be proven um on the y- axis
what you'll see is kind of the potential
therapeutic impact and for those of you
who are a suit you'll probably al
already figure out that you ideally want
things in the top right corner right
things that are fast to the clinic and
have high therapeutic impact
unfortunately in our case this one's a
little empty um our uh protein is quite
large it's not able to fit in an A9
Vector also we have not yet identified
any obvious ASO targets so as a result
that remains empty for now as we move
into the blue category these are the
ones that we think have the most promise
um but today what we're doing is really
spreading our bets across these to
understand what might bear fruit and
then finally uh you'll see also um a
number of innovations that have come out
of the broad a lot of advanced
modalities that are you know just
entering the clinic um still in early
translational research but maybe too far
uh in the future future for us to
seriously consider at this point but
obviously hoping that those May
accelerate so a few comments about this
overall framework first um this is
really disease specific and even to some
extent uh mutation specific as well so
for example in our case um it's a four
based parap frame shift mutation that
requires that has different drugs
applicable to it than say an inframe
deletion or a whole Gene deletion so the
context here is really important and you
could really draw a different 3x3 for
every disease and even subclasses within
the disease the other thing to point out
is this is not a static chart what this
is just a view of what we know today and
really the goal of making bets in all of
the blue category here is to identify
are there Pathways that might move that
into the top right corner these
modalities will eventually become actual
hits and then actual leads and that will
be what progresses over time but this is
what we really hope to kind of arm our
own e efforts and other patient advocacy
groups as well so maybe just to take you
through a few examples so um Gene
replacement therapy is a really common
one I mentioned earlier uh av9 single
Vector gene therapy ruled out uh you'll
see in the middle the truncated A9 gene
therapy so a Minon construct or
something like that it today you know
our assumption is it may not have the
full efficacy but we just need to do
more research to understand how much do
we actually need to boost son Gene
function and then you also see dual
Vector gene therapy in the top left um
obviously a lot of experimentation um
but no uh kind of clinical dual Vector
strategies for CNS there's a couple for
op opthalmological diseases but not for
CNS another example is Aso um you know
Exxon skipping Asos kind of out of the
picture you saw that very large Exxon 3
we can't really skip that um and Al
we're but we are looking at Asos to
promote fulllength sa um expression by
kind of inhibiting other um isoforms and
um we'll continue to explore other ASO
Pathways as well U finally you'll also
see for the gene editing Technologies
many of these have come out of the Bro
of course um but in our case crisper
editing and base editing don't quite
work for a frame shift mutation Prime
editing may be a good candidate just
given the
we really just need to knock in for base
pairs or just get it in frame um but
hopefully this gives you a bit of an
understanding of how we might think
about on a disease by disease basis how
to tackle the problem at a systemic um
level and finally I'd say all of these
kind of different modalities are
interdependent and context dependent so
in our case actually as you've seen
we've walked through a few of the other
op options from a genetic medicine's
perspective in our case drug repurposing
may be the most promising route because
some of the other ones have been ruled
out and especially from the speed to the
clinic perspective this may be by far
the fastest option so really I would
encourage the audience to think about
when you're building up the picture of
what how to uh uh leverage Innovation to
really have the impact that we're all
hoping for we really need to think about
the holistic picture of the right drug
and the right patient at the right time
so you know today the way we're
approaching this is we're really
operating a pre-clinical biotech out of
our foundation so just like any other
pre-clinical biotech what we're doing is
understanding the Natural History uh of
the disease which is very limited given
that it was just discovered in 2016 um
our lead researcher Dr Aaron an who I
mentioned earlier um published on the
first ztk Mouse model last year um some
of my colleagues at thermop Fisher
developed the first ztk ipscs um and
we're working on quite a number of
projects to identify both um targets and
hits and also to verify those including
some projects with the bro as well so on
this page you'll see we have a lot of
projects going on uh in this next year
not going to go through all of them but
what I would highlight is you know we
there are projects that we're still
looking for partners to um work with us
on um so specifically
proteomics understand which s isopor
show up in which organs to understand
kind of you know what do we need to
focus on in the CNS versus liver versus
stomach Etc um also trying to better
understand what are the critical
epitopes um to ultimately inform son
antibody and Eliza assay development and
you know after an's fabulous talk
earlier I think we also need to add a
cell morphology project on here as well
um so you know I would really encourage
the audience you and the audience to
think about it uh the framework here
that we've presented the right cure for
the right patient at the right time and
you know I think think for um scientists
at the broad and other research
institutions like this everyone doesn't
no one wants to do Innovation for
Innovation sake people want to do
Innovation to drive real impact and I'd
say that the best way to realize that
impact is to partner with patient
advocacy groups like ours parents like
ourselves who are learning the science
and could use your help and partnership
in accelerating the work um I'd like to
thank um quite a number of people our
support network Dr Aon an our lead
researcher at the University of Alabama
at Birmingham she is also um a board
member of our foundation and was a
co-discoverer of zttk syndrome in 2016
um we have our foundation of course our
scientific and clinical advisory boards
and many many partners who have shared
in-kind resources support all along the
way so if any of you in the audience are
interested in supporting Aden and I on
our journey to cure zdk please feel free
to email us at enuo or Alo at ctk.org
and with that we'll open it up to
questions thank
[Applause]
you I don't need a
microphone I'm surprised you're not
mentioning the one generic approach
which is to enhance splicing of of the
wild type copy of the gene that has
proven very effective in spinal muscular
atrophy there are now clinical trials
for a capo insufficient genetic disorder
of the central nervous system D syndrome
it appears to be a genetic type of
therapy where what one needs to do and
Tim you on your Advisory Board knows how
to do it yeah which is scan aligon
nucleotides to Simply find those that
will enhance splicing of key exons in
the wild type copy of the gene yeah and
that could be a generic therapy for many
Capo insufficient genetic disorders yeah
absolutely um I'm not as deep on the
oligos signs as timu um the the ulab did
um spend quite some time scanning for
kind of obvious ASO targets and
unfortunately they didn't come up with
anything um I know that of course Stoke
Therapeutics is working on the Tango
approach um we've had some initial
conversations with them about it and
unfortunately doesn't seem like it's
applicable at this time but continuing
to look for other options with that
strategy in mind computer is not
necessarily the
best thank you thank you little tick
note
thank you for talk to sharing my
personal M and inspiring stories and the
Strategic road map for drug disent so my
question that of course the cell and the
dream therapy offer a final C promising
for the disease and how do you evaluate
the possibility we are using the
nutritional interventions like a
supplementary forood supplementary is to
intervine the progession of disease and
imediate symptoms of
patients yeah it's a it's a great
question you know I think part of what
we're working on with whenever we're
thinking about Gathering more natural
history is even just what are patients
taking today even just Gathering the
data on what medications what
supplements what diet Etc have patients
been using might unlock hey actually
there's quite a few patients that have
converged on the same kind of Therapies
whether just food or medicine or
otherwise uh those might even evolve
over time it might be different in
childhood versus adulthood Etc so um
it's something we're working on um to
really gather that data actually one of
our partners citizen Health um is really
helpful in aggregating a lot of the EHR
data to be able to just observe at least
historically what are our what is our
community doing but it's a big focus of
ours we're also working on a project
with um combined brain which is another
nonprofit in the neurodevelopmental
space specifically to do metabolomics of
human patients to understand are there
differences we're still trying to
disentangle is are the
neurological um features of the disease
actually being driven potentially by
metabolism itself so uh we're continuing
to investigate that as well thank you
very
much thank you
good afternoon I'm Katherine Smith I'm
the executive director of the trir
foundation I'm apologies I've sort of
lost my voice today so we're gonna we're
going to muck through this it's going to
be short um first of all I just wanted
to say to Nathan and a not sure where
you guys went but thank you for
introducing us to luky I've been
following the progress of the work that
you've been doing and it's tremendous
and impressive and thank you for all
that you're doing
um I'm going to be introducing Richard
Novak can come on up if you'd like um
Richard is one of our 2024 trere fellows
and he is the CEO of unravel and you
would have seen probably their logo up
on the last presentation and Richard's
going to be sharing with us about the um
Partnerships that he's done with
patients and share more about what that
looks like from the first time founder
of first time CEO side of things so
welcome Richard thanks so much I think
I'm miked up
[Applause]
now thank you thank you so much it's a
it's an honor to be here it really is
thank you to the broad to Anna to uh the
trir foundation uh for this wonderful
support um as a relatively newly mted
member of biopharma I'm here to share
both good news and bad news um bad news
biopharma really stinks at making drugs
um we get it done eventually with enough
money I think as Anna uh uh pointed out
but we're really terrible at it um the
good news is we believe there's a really
good solution and that's in in the
patients themselves they are part of the
problem that we're trying to solve but
they are part of the solution and so
what I'm here uh to present today is not
so much the science though we're going
to dive into it a little bit um it's
really um how do we make this
infrastructure work for everybody and so
our uh our strategy at unravel is
Patients First that is the problem that
is the Northstar we are singularly aimed
at that and let's work together to
figure out how we get there um and and
we're doing it through a very heavy
partnering
approach so here is traditional drug
development um in a very abstract sense
uh but you can see that there's a Target
this usually comes out of Academia um
there you know Mouse highlights any sort
of preclinical models cells animal
models Etc and then you get into the
critical question does it work in
patience this is what we've been trying
to do this whole time and um this is
where my earlier bad news comes in we're
terrible at this um it takes years if
it's even going to be successful um on
average a new target has about a 98%
failure rate uh in terms of this
approval process so this doesn't work
and this is for non-rare diseases too uh
but when you get to rare and especially
ultra rare this just doesn't work right
um so what can we do and what you know
kind of digging one layer deeper what's
the problem our is that people are
trying to treat disease when really we
should be thinking about treating
patients all right diseases are not the
same as patients and so um a shout out
to the Cleveland Clinic for these really
helpful uh Graphics but they represent
the generalities they don't represent
individual patients
so again what we say is it's the
patients not the disease that responds
to the treatment um and here's actually
a picture from our office that reminds
us this is why we're we're we're here um
and actually lukia is on there as well
um and so you know this is not a New
Concept I I would love to be able to
take credit for it uh but it actually
goes back to the 19th century with
William oer so the father of modern
medicine U basically the good per good
physician treats the disease the great
physician treats the patient with the
disease and I think we've lost track of
that along the way and so we're trying
to bring that back and part of it is
because the Technologies today enable it
and part of it is because the the
patient advocacy groups are so
freakishly sophisticated and and
motivated that now we can do it right so
so it's this kind of it takes a village
but even more complex concept and so
what we did at unravel is we have this
patient-driven drug development and
there's you know people pay lip service
to patients and you know every Pharma
company has a has a has a page that says
oh you know we're patient Centric that's
great um but have you actually worked
with these groups have you worked with
with the patients right and that that's
sort of the the question and so and why
do we start with patience right and and
to some extent it's obvious but to some
extent there's there's really deep
biology and the scientific problem is a
really big one and I think Anna
mentioned this really nicely in the
beginning we have no clue what half half
of the pathways are doing you have these
these proteins genes that have been
identified that's great no idea what
they do or maybe we know one thing out
of you know 100 um the reality is that
what constitutes a patient right now not
just a human but just a patient
specifically sure genetics in the case
of genetic disorders um the environment
this includes diet medications Etc and
and time and I think uh aah and Nathan
really nicely alluded to it you know
when is a really critical question to
ask not just what and how and who um and
so what we did and we spent out of the
Harvard uh ecosystem uh so just across
the water here um out of the VIS
Institute and there we had this Insight
that these complex biological networks
Drive clinical function and here's
actually a real example um of one of our
networks and the idea is that these
interactions as opposed to any any one
component of this drive patient outcomes
right it's not it's not it's kind of the
sum of all the parts now if you have
tried to drive through Boston um for
example just coming here today um there
was a a malfunctioning traffic light
turns out that backed up the traffic
onto sto which backed up onto i93 which
who knows what what it's doing right so
one traffic light can have these vast
effects that's a network problem that
you encounter every day especially in
Boston um and so let me walk you through
you know how we do this so obviously
this this is teeing up to a computation
example as you might imagine but the
idea is that you have this healthy
Network and again just completely
arbitrary this is actually from a r
syndrome patient I'm going to talk about
later but uh don't worry the yellow
lines are just for for show here you
have some sort of healthy interaction
this is what normally should be
happening um and there's a problem
there's a gene maybe that's mutated
there might be an infection that's
causing something who knows what it is
um in this case it's um actually the
mecp2 gene that's highlighted here
there's some problem there mutated node
and you heard this nodal biology is
really kind of getting that um so great
it causes some disruption it's that
malfunctioning traffic light right so
how do we fix it well you could fix the
traffic light but you can also fix
anything else that rebalances this
network and that's the really great
opportunity in biology it's a mess and
so why focus on just one thing right you
can take any of that mess and and use it
to your advantage as unfortunately every
oncologist knows cancer cells are really
good at at finding these alternative
Pathways so why can't we use that for
for good um and that that's really what
we do at
unravel um and essentially what we do
we're forecasting how patients respond
to therapies again it's about the
patient not the disease so we have
patient RNA signatures from actual
individual patients that we work with on
a daily basis and we have drug RNA
signatures and not unlike what what Anna
showed with with the visual uh visual
signatures these are really
transcriptomic signatures but from the
perspective of these networks and then
we go through this magic um and we ask
will it help this patient right luky for
example
um can we treat all the patients within
a particular disease or however you want
to look at it um the answer may be no
but you can treat some of them in one
way and you have to find something else
for the others are there better
treatments so repurposing might be a
great place to start we agree um but
we're also developing new drugs that are
now tailored to the the mechanisms and
targets that we
discover um and one thing I mention want
to mention is that also looking at the
adverse side of it right so you make all
these mole ules one of the biggest
drivers of costs are all the failures
toxicities lack of efficacy and all that
but toxicities are you know put patients
at risk and are just bad business so
just you know there's no reason to uh to
not avoid that if you can and so we see
all of that um in in in a pretty clear
way so we bring this function first
approach to drug Discovery and we have
these three components one is bav and
it's really this Google Maps for health
um this network biology of human health
coupled with an insilico compound
Library about 40,000 molecules now all
these are purchasable you could say this
is repurposing to us they're Discovery
tools and over time families and
Foundations like the ctdk sunshine
Foundation came to us and ask can we
just use those tools for the ones that
are actually approved for patients the
answer is yeah we're not a repurposing
company but we're trying to probe the
complexities using these molecules um
one thing that we do as an intermediate
step we developed this concept of
squishy wear it's not hard it's not soft
it's squishy these are tadpoles they are
actually very squishy um and we can do
sort of kind computer vision type
analysis like again with with the cells
that you saw earlier but with living
moving tadpoles that are again mutated
with the various genes and we can just
ask does it help that rescue that model
but then really where we're at again
it's patient driven and patient focused
uh drug development are the clinical
studies does it actually work in a
patient and so what we do we use
existing drugs to ask that question
because you could administer those today
not in 10 years right with potential
other toxicities and other things yes
they may not be ideal they may not get
you the 100% of the efficacy you're
after but if you can get 50% one it
proves out your mechanism that you can
now invest the the resources for a New
Drug um and it might help patients today
in the meantime right you don't have to
wait 10 years for the perfect drug and
have nothing you might have an
intermediate step in between and so does
it work well uh yes it works even to our
surprise quite well um we've actually
shown this actually during the lovely
pandemic that we had a few years ago we
showed that we can predict the function
uh of specific statins in this case so
used for cholesterol control um you
predict specific Statin impact on
Survival from covid so these are
patients who are getting statins because
of their hyper lipidemia anyway and we
showed that specific molecules but not
the class as a whole were actually
therapeutic and this was death as an
endpoint so pretty pretty cut and dry in
terms of outcomes and we were
statistically significant um actually um
we had a false negative which is a good
one to have uh but overall much better
than your your 2% success rate we had an
80% success rate in predicting clinical
outcomes and so part of the challenge
here is really this infrastructure and
how do you work with patient groups how
do you partner and I mentioned that
famili started coming to us and so we
actually had to develop a new business
model and we set aside the one that we
started out with you know about four
years ago before spinning out and we
said you know we really need to offer
these Services even though we are not a
service company and we're not a
repurposing company and so we started
the rare shift uh service platform and
really this is just sort of cost based
drug Discovery for nonprofits um it's
ri.org and and there it is drug
repurposing that is the goal that is
that is the message that is the goal for
us it's a stepping stone towards the
novel drug arm essentially provides
clinical Discovery and validation and
then the Partnerships build in the
process and we become a partner to the
foundations or the families um and they
become our partners in the in the
discovery and validation process so it
becomes a win-win um and what we've been
able to do is actually using nasal swab
so again before the pandemic this would
not have been possible uh to collect a
few cells on on a covid test kit
essentially um and use that to extract
RNA run it through our biona platform
and get insights on the brain because
most of what we work on our neurological
diseases and then we can use this AI
platform to figure out how do we uh
potentially fix this patient what's
going on how is patient one different or
or the same as patient 2 and and so on
and what's really exciting we can work
all around the world um so we've
actually sampled patients from the
remote Outback took 5 weeks but we did
it um we can basically ship these kits
all around the world at room temperature
um and so what we have started to do is
see the the evolution of these diseases
into truly what we call Therapeutic
response groups it's not about how you
got there it's how you fix things right
and so that's where these trgs
therapeutic response groups come in and
so this is actually s Gap one is another
one of these neurological
disorders if you take a look at at this
rainbow Matrix um there is no pattern we
tried there's there's nothing really
clear different ages different mutation
sites genotype phenotype doesn't really
exist but what we start seeing in terms
of drug response are three groups and
they actually correlate really
beautifully and those patients are
actually quite different from each other
once you look at them from that
perspective and so now we're trying to
take these really complex populations
and and reduce them to something more
manageable and so just to show what
we've been able to do on the the
biofarma side of our company we work on
red syndrome it's again one of these
neurological neurogenetic disorders one
of the more common ones this is not rare
and there actually there's been one
approved drug on the market um and we
actually use that as a benchmark and we
basically did the same process collect
data from patients and from other
sources uh run it through our platform
here's actually the mutation but we
found a Target somewhere else doesn't
matter what caused it but if you can
engage this target right there right um
how we got there is is is the magic but
we we show that if you can as you engage
that Target right there it fixes the
network and that was the real insight
and so now we actually have a new drug
for this but we're not going to develop
it until we show that this works with an
existing drug because that's how we can
test it today by the way the existing
drug veristat um formulation in in Ravel
one outperforms the one that's currently
on the market dramatically especially in
the later stag of the disease and we're
starting two clinical trials in red
syndrome um and then you might may ask
does it actually work well this is the
beauty of using existing drugs there's
actually a family with a boy with red
syndrome boys are really rare they tend
to not do very well uh with this disease
and um they were you know really looking
for options their clinician was looking
for options and so uh long story short
we identified vernat actually to work
for that patient uh computationally and
the clinician felt that it was
appropriate for her to prescribe it to
the patient and uh sure enough have
extremely low Doses and this is a cancer
drug right so keep in mind this is not a
supplement um the Sleep Quality improved
pretty dramatically normalized blood
metrics is an objective measure of of
improvement um and then improved motor
and cognitive function as assessed by
various uh clinical uh professionals um
and now we're actually um the boy still
on it this is he been for over a year at
this point continues to improve and
we're actually layering additional uh
therapies on top of that um I mean the
clinician is but but uh with our
data and what we're doing now this was
really exciting to us saying look this
really can can help even reverse this
extremely severe case um
we're actually starting two clinical
studies one in red syndrome um in
Colombia so I joke that we're bringing
white powder to Colombia for a change um
and uh it's it's a really fantastic
place we go to where the patients are um
there are 15 patients all being treated
by a single clinician single sight study
really fantastic uh place and they have
never been able to participate in
Cutting Edge research like this and so
this is this is what we're doing doing
we're actually using oral liquid
veristat validating our Target right now
there's a repurposed candidate um we
potentially we have orphan drug
designation for it in the US we will
bring it to the US uh we also continue
with it in Latin America but then we're
actually building Ravel 2 which is this
new optimized drug specifically for rat
syndrome and several other diseases um
but that we ask the critical question
does it work before we commit tens of
millions of dollars to developing a new
drug and it gets even better so the
question is you know there's 15,000 rare
diseases or whatever the number is a
really big number um how do we tackle
not one at a time but how do we paralyze
it and so we've actually identified
these therapeutic response groups to
span diagnosis so there's pit Hopkin
syndrome which is not R syndrome it's a
different Gene different disease uh with
some you know similarities but they're
actually sponsoring clinical study
because we predicted that it would
actually be quite effective predicted
that it would work in mice lo and behold
it worked in mice so now we have to go
to patients that's the only way to
answer that question um and overall we
have about 50 different diseases in our
portfolio
um as you can see um they they usually
start with this bav screen some of them
have tadpole models that get developed
um some don't some have Mouse models
that get developed some don't we work
with Jackson Labs as well um where
people are really headed is is the
clinical part right does it work in
actual patients I mean that's that's the
ultimate question and so all these are
off label I should I should note that we
do not treat patients but we can we
generate research use data that could be
used for clinicians to evaluate as as
they see fit um one thing I want to
announce here today so we actually have
not announced this yet so this is the
first time um we just signed a very key
uh agreement with combined brain so so
Nathan and aah mentioned them um they're
an umbrella organization that really
spans about 120 different different um
patient advocacy groups encompassing um
a little bit more diseases than that
some of them have actually more than one
falling under them um and essentially
what we're doing is taking our uh really
Patient First approach RNA driven
approach and applying it to not just the
50 dis orders that we already work with
but another 120 right so this represents
really a landmark uh partnering in the
space rare disease most of these are
ultra rare diseases Ultra ultra rare I
mean one one group has uh six patients
documented right so these are talk about
a challenge of of scaling to commercial
uh opportunities um and this is the type
of partnering that I think we envisioned
that we thanks to all these fantastic
patient advocacy groups um are are
really trying to change how we how we do
drug development so with that want to
thank you for your your time and um
again drug development driven by
[Applause]
patients thank you wonderful talk so you
mentioned the powerful pipeline biona
for clinical usage so can you comment
the current practice in regulations of
FDA how can you to meet with
da regulations and then you talk about
the clinic Trail in Colombia is a a
possible solution to navigate the RDA
regulations yep y yeah so the the
regulatory aspects are definitely key um
we'll again it's a very right now last
few last month or so has been very
dynamic in that space so we'll see how
it plays out but I'm sure it will I'm
sure it'll it'll you know stabilize um
so that caveat aside um absolutely key
to engage with FDA early and often um we
have we filed a pre in the US before we
went to Columbia we want to make sure
the FDA agreed generally not necessarily
to some of the specific details that are
more country or regulator specific but
would this make sense right before we go
to where it's faster cheaper easier to
do a a trial um the regulation actually
in Columbia is very similar to the US um
but the patients are there the cost of
doing the trials is just a fraction of
that in the US as you might imagine
right um so absolutely uh key to to
engage with FDA bav we have no vision
for that to be a clinical tool to us
it's a discovery tool because the
regulatory challenges dealing with these
networks I don't think are possible to
overcome just given how the FDA
regulates
Diagnostics um that said what comes out
of it is a drug we can regulate the
drugs and and and we can be absolutely
compliant with that and and do so in a
very efficient way that's also where
repurpose drugs are have an advantage
because a lot of the safety the main
safety concerns are addressed now the
question is is it safe in this
population but you sort of know what to
look for is it kidney toxicity liver
toxicity you you have a better idea of
what what to look for so it's it tends
to accelerate the whole process and
reduce costs but the regulator
regulatory aspect is is really key to to
bring in early yeah thank you thank
you I uh I think it's amazing that
you're able to uh actually develop a
therapeutic for so many different
diseases but how do you actually on the
actual biotech company prioritize which
diseases to actually pursue the clinical
trials for
yeah that's a great question um this is
where being in rare actually has its
advantages um so orphan drug designation
gives you priority review it reduces the
time for review it it uh eliminates a
lot of the fees that Pharma typically
has to pay so you have all those
benefits to your your um you know to
advocate for it now which one of these
rare diseases within the rare space um
this is where it's a partnership right
and as with any partnership some are way
more Dynamic and and F fast and others
are are more slow and there are
different priorities that the the
different patient advocacy groups have
that may or may not directly align with
the given trajectory at any one time and
so it's it's a a group decision of like
what what makes the most sense and it
may be that you pick one for example
with ret syndrome um you know I think
we're more likely to get investor
interest for a US trial for R syndrome
versus um one of the subgroups that we
found already has 40 patients Nation
globally probably not a good thing for
investors to for
that said they may be a really good
opportunity for getting um EU approval
for that drug because once the drug is
approved in a given country you can
start selling it and clinicians can
start prescribing it off label right and
so especially for Ravel 2 that new drug
may actually could go through this 40
Patient Group much faster in a five
person study and so like the commercial
and the approval side are are not always
as aligned as they are for large
diseases
iig yeah yeah actually
just to pick up on this theme have you
considered doing basket trials is that
something that would be open to
absolutely um so we like it um talk to
your neighborhood regulator about
it um in fact in Colombia we we propose
that they do not on principle allow
basket trial so we're doing two separate
inds two separate everything even though
it's more copy and paste for for all the
documents um we'll do that if at least
at the beginning hopefully that'll
evolve as as these these um these things
change and this will also be a factor of
the the patient advocacy groups
advocating hey there's no way we can do
our own trial but can we have three
patients in this trial right um so I
think that will be kind of two-way
street there that said in the US um the
US is open to that the US FDA um it has
its own set of challenges uh but
absolutely there's lots of
precedent yeah great thank you thank you
[Applause]
that was remarkable basket trials
remember that because um all of our
efforts in noal biology will ultimately
be served by you know being able to use
the same medication for patients with
multiple different genetic misspellings
that seem to converge on a biological
node that can be targeted that's exactly
what we hope to accomplish so this is an
important uh point that was made so I'm
I'm glad that it was made it's been
successful in cancer and the US FDA is
open to it so we have to all Advocate as
a community for this structure to be
utilized for rare diseases and to also
provide examples where that uh can
happen speaking of the future and um you
know people working uh within the
context of the latter secures
accelerator and the broader broad
Community uh toward that uh incredible
future and um maybe also building on um
Harvey lish's incredible suggestion
about identifying ways in which you can
increase the activity of certain genes
and how you might be able to
systematically do that I'm wildly proud
to to introduce um Arya raal who is an
mdphd student here at Broad working in
the Laboratories of two incredible
physician scientists and colleagues uh p
saetti and Sangita baa and she's going
to tell you about her work uh harnessing
Evolution to try to understand how we
can uh regulate genan so Arya take it
away thank you so much Anna um and it's
great to be here with you all this is
such an amazing community and I'm
fortunate to be a part of it um so thank
you to the Tamir foundation and a big
shout out to Julian for all of her help
uh today and and in general uh I'm
excited today to share with you in
particular my vision for the next
generation of rare disease Therapeutics
and how we can achieve it with insights
from evolutionary
biology Back to Basics our genetic code
is made up of four simple letters a c t
g so with different combinations of
these bases our genomes are able to
execute this huge number of functions
necessary to make our body's work this
is the language that Evolution has used
to sculpt our intricate human physiology
but it turns out that Evolution has a
really narrow
vocabulary the human genome is 300 or
sorry three billion base pairs long and
so if we do the math there are four
possible bases that we can have at each
of those three billion positions which
means this for a genome of our size
there are four to the three billionth
possible
configurations that's more than the
number of atoms in the observable
universe but less than 1% of these have
been explored by Natural Evolution
so what's going on with all of that
missing
code Evolution works with two main
forces mutation and
selection as our cells divide throughout
our lifetimes our genomes are copied
over errors are sometimes made in this
process called mutations mutations that
are beneficial are selected for these
rise to high frequency and then are
passed on from generation to
generation we can imagine Evolution like
a hiker who's going through this big
mountain range
each step that the hiker takes is a
mutation a beneficial mutation is a step
forward closer to the top of the
mountain whereas a harmful mutation is a
step back down the slope here's the
problem though our hiker from where
they're standing in the mountain range
does not know whether the path that
they're on is the path that will take
them to the tallest peak and so it's
easy for them to get stuck on a
suboptimal peak because from where
they're standing they don't know what's
up what's down where to
go it's for this reason Reon that
Evolution has only explored a tiny
portion of our mountain range which
we'll call sequence space but there are
still many many Peaks to be found in the
sequence space that's been
unexplored synthetic DNA DNA that's
explored from this Uncharted Territory
may have useful therapeutic
functionality we can explore the rest of
the Peaks to get
there while I was a medical student on
the Ws at Mass General across the river
I was really fortunate to work directly
with some amazing Ry disease patients uh
and their families and something that
struck me during this process was this
if we were more able to precisely Target
the affected cells in these patients and
the cell types specifically we could
have more effective Therapeutics in
general most of our genomes in fact are
conf composed of regulatory DNA this is
DNA that tells genes where and when to
be
expressed uh CIS regulatory elements or
cres are one type of this DNA uh and
they can act like a genetic dial so if
we tune this dial we can obtain
different Crees that lead to different
levels of gene expression in different
tissues so if we learn the rules of that
regulatory grammar and build around them
we can find the peaks of new mountains
and thereby generate a whole new world
of therapies we could engineer our DNA
for any number of functions things like
Hier gene expression greater cell type
specificity greater tunability and so on
achieving this vision for rare disease
Therapeutics of course requires the
right team and as Anna alluded to I'm
pretty fortunate to have a great one
there are two major elements to
achieving this next generation of rare
disease Therapeutics uh one is designing
the right cres and the second is getting
them to where they need to go delivery
and so in pursuit of these I joined the
cetti lab and the baa lab partisan Anda
are two extremely intelligent and
wonderful and kind mentors I'm very
lucky to work with them paris's
expertise is in computational genomics
and Sangita Works in nanotechnologies
and so these are the two areas that we
need to bring together to make this
happen and so in the cetti lab we've
come up with a way to rise up the
metaphorical mountains I told you about
to design new regulatory elements that
can design in unprecedent that can work
in unprecedented ways we use an
experiment called a massively parallel
reporter assay or an MPR uh to test
hundreds of thousands of CES at once
this allows to describe the genome's
regulatory code and its grammar
empirically and then we can use
computational tools to learn those rules
more precisely and then design new
sequences that work even better than the
old
ones we can dive a little bit more
closely into this approach uh first we
start with the experimental end this
massively parallel reporter essay we
take a starting DNA library of
cres we can tag on a fluorescent
reporter Gene onto these CES and then
transfect that into cell lines
and so the level of expression of our
reporter Gene in each cell line tells us
how effective that CR is in that
context so from these experiments we can
generate numerical activity scores for
different cres in different cell types
in this example I'm showing you we have
liver brain and
blood in the new age of high performance
Computing we can now use those massive
amounts of experimental data that we've
collected to explicitly learn the rules
of regulatory
grammar these models can hone in on what
parts of DNA sequences contribute to CR
reactivity cell type specificity Etc and
so we can begin to answer questions of
why a certain C is more active in one
cell than another and more broadly where
and how we might gain functional
advantages in our cres by modifying
their
sequences so this predictive machine
learning model essentially gives us a
bird's eye view of the mountain range
that we
discussed so this is the understanding
that we use to fuel computational
exploration of the remaining sequence
space with our predictive map in hand we
can guide generative AI models to design
cres with the highest reach possible in
these mountains engineering for many
many desired functions here's how this
works we start with sequences of unknown
activity typically random
sequences these sequences are passed to
our predictive machine learning model
which obtains a baseline measure of
their predicted
activity we can then then use a function
which looks at the whole overall
sequence space finds the Peaks and then
Tunes the sequences as it goes to reach
them and thereby we obtain sequences
with the maximum desired function of
whatever we're looking for and this is
an iterative cycle we can then test
those sequences that we've designed with
MP again and it starts all
over fortunately when we test these
computationally designed cres we see
some really promising results and there
are lots of examples I could go through
but I think this is the most striking uh
this is a neuronal CR that we designed
with this pipeline that we then
expressed in an embryonic Mouse and
early on in development you can see that
there's a little bit of blue expression
in what looks like the brain so a couple
of weeks post natal we did dissection
and see that our enhancer not only
expresses specifically in the brain and
not anywhere else but localizes to the
cortex a specific anatomical region and
as any neurobiologists in the room know
cell types in the brain can be tricky so
we're very fortunate to have these
results and overall we're really excited
that our model is able to build
completely synthetic short regulatory
sequences that can drive really tissue
specific expression but we have a lot of
work ahead of us to extend our models to
additional cell types and most
importantly to therapeutic
applications and so with the support of
the ladder secures initiative we're now
working to extend these findings to
novel cures and rare diseases and
specifically uh in muscle cell types of
skeletal smooth and cardiac muscle uh we
think these cell types are interesting
because they have similar contractile
functionality and similar embryonic
Origins but they function in really
different ways and have so many diseases
that affect them and so this is a one
node that we think we can
Target to close I'll just tell you about
a few of the ways that we're tackling
this in muscle um and the ways that we
think a multi- disease approach uh using
these cres can achieve big outcomes in
rare disease uh the first is in disent
muscular distrophy or DMD DMD is a hot
topic for a rare disease community it's
caused by mutation in the disten gene uh
and it has devastating effects on
muscular tissue which then cause
devastating systemic symptoms Gene
therapies are emerging on the market
right now uh which aim to deliver normal
distri to damage tissues or edit native
genomes directly but one key concern
with all of these is off Target effects
many of which I've put up on the slide
here and so we need to ensure that our
genetic products are only expressed
where they're needed that is offt Target
effects are minimized and so we think
that our cres could prove useful in this
setting and so by combining our muscle
specific cres with muscle specific
delivery vectors or just using our Crees
with a standard delivery Vector uh we
could achieve some pretty interesting
results and the second is thinking more
broadly about what kinds of disease
cases these cres might be useful in um
as I think towards being a physician
scientist I'm always thinking about the
patients first and I really appreciated
Richard's approach to that um one of the
diseases I think would be really
interesting to Target here is hereditary
hemorrhagic t inasia
hht and now hht is a disease that
affects one in 6,000 people um it is
caused by a structural defect in a
protein called endoglin and endoglin
help endoglin helps support our blood
vessels and keeps that structural
Integrity uh these mutations can cause
some really devastating complications uh
by losing structural Integrity of the
blood vessels you can get things like
stroke anemia heart failure Hemorrhage
um and it's utmost important to tr to
try and prevent these but there's no
cure right
now the therapy here is deceptively
simple if we can upregulate endoglin
only in the cells where we need to then
we could prevent these complications uh
and so we're really excited to continue
work towards that
direction and so to finish off I'd like
to bring us back to where we started uh
there is so much to be explored uh in
the sequence space we haven't covered
yet there are so many mountains left to
climb and so if we combine highr
experimentation which the bro so good at
with computational modeling that's being
enabled by all the latest advances in Ai
and machine learning uh we can get to
those next Peaks and achieve this next
generation of rad disease Therapeutics
um and so thank you so much for your
time happy to answer any
[Applause]
questions thank you wonderful talk so
can you comment the pros and cons of the
no world DN sequence targeting cie and
compare with current nucleic acid
medicine sorry uh so to rephrase the
question comparing current cres used in
gene therapies as compared to our new
ones like a current practice using R
medicine or D or P other a lot of
nuclear acid based medicine so can you
compare your methodology with current
practice I think the beauty of this is
that you can do it all together right so
we're generating elements that can
upregulate the expression of DNA or the
expression of genes and so these can be
used in combination with existing Gene
therapies or can be used to drive their
own and so we sort of view this as a
platform as opposed to a competitor here
thank you
yeah Arya do you recall a specific um
experience in the clinic or a patient
who uh inspired you to go into this work
you know I can think of so many but I
think uh one of the ones that really
stuck with me is when I was a first year
medical student I rotated um on the
Pediatric paliative Care awards at
Boston children
uh and there I I was um working with
this one patient who had a a very rare
muscular disease that caused constant
contraction and and that was the moment
where I realized that the work that I
had been doing in the lab which I
actually started prior to my clinical
rotations had a really direct impact um
his family was just so amazing and the
care team uh was so dedicated to the
whole disease process trying to find
cures trying to find options that would
alleviate symptoms and more importantly
emotional emotional well-being and and
so this is sort of the picture that
brought me together and so this is
something I got to work on um so thank
you for the opportunity absolutely thank
you so much question question and how
large are these this is an excellent
question so uh it's of great importance
to make sure that whatever we're
designing can fit into either standard
vectors or new vectors and space is a
hot commodity uh in this setting the
enhancers that we've designed in the
study I showed you here are 100 base
pairs but I'm working on shrinking them
down to 50 uh which is about the size of
the minimal promoters that we use in
standard applications
currently brilliant thank you so much
Arya I think you can all see why I'm so
wildly proud you know if this is our
future then we have a lot to be uh proud
of and look forward to so um as was
evident in the question that I just
asked Arya one of the most fundamental
ways in which we communicate well before
we had uh you know written uh textt for
example to communicate with one another
uh is actually storytelling um and it
turns out that storytelling is what
we've been doing here today scientific
as well as personal family storytelling
uh and it's a really effective way for
humans to motivate one another uh it's a
it's a way for us to motivate our
elected officials for example our
colleagues you know our community
members our neighbors and so uh the next
speaker is actually a master at
storytelling I think that maybe you have
um heard of feie parks and her white
well-known uh podcast series Once Upon a
gene but if you haven't I think she's
here to uh tell us um about um there she
is about this uh uh Journey really that
has been inspired by her son Ford so I
will let her share the rest of the story
with you
eie so hi everyone like Anna said um my
name is eie Parks and I'm so excited for
this 10year anniversary event it's such
an honor to be here with you today um I
always have a little bit of writer's
block before um I do a talk like this
I'm always maybe a little bit down on
myself and I don't have any letters
behind my name I'm Ford's mom and I know
I'm not alone there uh I can stare at a
page a blank page for weeks and sit my
coffee I will call a friend and stare
some more look for ideas and advice and
I just hope for some inspo to shake
me and then it happens the dam opens up
and the ideas that were stuck behind
blank pages and negative selft talk come
flooding out and that happened the other
day for me I was like um wait a minute
I'm about to speak to a group of some of
the most evolved
scientists uh some of the most Brilliant
Minds people who lead experience
experiments
who find patterns who create assays
people who analyze genomes for
breakfast surely these people believe in
maybe the existence of little gray or
green dudes that are light years
away so why were aliens my idea for this
talk that opened the
floodgates it's because like being a row
disease parent is actually like
being on another
planet but let me back up and take you
uh to my story 10 years ago in 2015 I
married the love of my life and I got
pregnant with my first child it was
everything I had dreamed of a family
motherhood uh everything was as bright
as a
supernova we even had a space themed
Nursery because the obvious next step
for my child was
NASA the metaphor really did feel
magical and a perfect child ready to
explore the infinite Universe of
possibility was just
magical but when my son was born it
turned out that he was on a different
Mission and had I listened to the
doctor's
explanation maybe a mission that would
never have even left the LaunchPad
it was certainly one that we did not
expect something was wrong with our son
and we didn't know what we found
ourselves fighting to Simply keep him
alive for the first couple of years
addressing symptoms with hardly a moment
to look up and recognize where we
were and then genetic testing pinpointed
a diagnosis of an ultra rare disorder
called ctnnb1
syndrome at 16 months old it felt like
we had crash landed onto an alien
planet there was no road map no research
no data points just
emptiness there were no humans around us
that spoke this new language and there
were no treatments very few patients and
no one to tell us what was
next in a moment our world had gone from
the INF hope of the night sky to the
vast cold emptiness of
space back then just 10 years ago social
media was not the vast resource for
families like mine like it is
today costs for genetic testing were
Skyhigh doctors were more skeptical and
the pace of research felt painfully slow
and progress impossible day
today we were desperate
alone and searching for a guidepost in
any community that might say hey we're
here in this weird place
too we were not Travelers here my family
and I we were Pioneers set out to
terraform this strange
place and to make it a place that we
could
live and so I realized that if such a
community did exist I better go looking
so I did what any rational person would
do and I started a
podcast and I radioed for
help once upon a jeene became my version
of an Interstellar radio
Beacon broadcasting into the
void hoping
someone
anyone would
respond and they did
suddenly families like mine were on the
same
frequency we were all these little
spaceships floating out there in the
void Pew peing meteors and space
monsters disguised as insurance denials
and feeding
tubes trying to dock compare notes and
find
refuge for many of us it was the first
time that we realized we weren't alone
what started as my voice and the laugh
track of my
son it quickly
multiplied we compared notes we shared
tips we found a new sense of comfort
hope and a new sense of urgency from
each other's
stories in these early days we learned
from
Trailblazers families and Advocates who
had been fighting for decades on behalf
of rare diseases they discover long
before the rest of us showed
up they passed on that knowledge and
that share your homework
mentality with each new org that showed
up these Pioneers they taught us how to
navigate the medical system how to push
for research how to speak up at
conferences like this and how to find
the essential resources we needed simply
at
home and the coolest thing
with each new family on board our
community didn't just grow in numbers it
grew in
power maybe we weren't just a bunch of
Lone stars in the sky and maybe we were
a
constellation we were building momentum
and amplifying each other's
voices and it's incredible to look back
now and see how this turned into a
movement
with parents and caregivers driving
research
forward finding funding studies
partnering with biotech and research and
Industry we might not have lab coats but
we know our children better than anyone
and our Insight is crucial to any
progress a few advances of the last
decade uh once described off as far off
has rapidly become part of our reality
there's still plenty of work ahead but
every year brings new tools new
knowledge and most importantly
hope genetic testing is a diagnostic
tool once was the cost of a mortgage in
my son's case a brand new
car now it's less than a Netflix
membership and you can get it through
tella Health on your couch just like
Netflix this means that families can get
an answer fast and skip the black hole
of being unor
misdiagnosed they can get to work a lot
faster in accelerating Global
collaboration among advocacy and
companies
scientists patients and caregivers know
that we shouldn't have to have our data
locked away in a silo that we cannot
access we know to pool our resources in
orgs like combined
brain and we
innovate tella health and remote care
technology have been a
godsend then we're flying across the
country just to see the one
expert for the last year 40 of our
ctnnb1 patients have been wearing a
device that's been tracking their
movement disorder in preparation for a
clinical
trial these rare
families are more than Mom and Pop
nonprofits they fund grants they found
bio
techs they have matured into
CEOs policy experts and they radiate
love for their children and their
Community like a
son the shift is
happening each year more families
connect and more solutions inch closer
to reality solutions that once sounded
like science
fiction and now there's the Hope
part we didn't cling to Hope because it
sounds
nice hope is Prickly and sharp just as
it is
warm we build hope because it is fuel in
our
rocket the thing that keeps us searching
for
answers every new technology every new
data sharing platform every connection
that we make is a shooting
star and in moving forward to together
how do we keep that momentum going we
collaborate
relentlessly families scientists biotech
Academia healthc care providers and
policy makers all have to work in sync
because progress in rare disease thrives
and can only work in
Synergy not
silos we tell our
stories because personal narratives
don't just Inspire hope they open doors
to funding and research and
understanding and because it turns out
people actually do want to hear
them we question everything since we can
assume any system works until it true
doesn't work until it truly does we push
for new approaches new cures and
clinical trial designs that miror our
real life
experiences and finally we stay hopeful
not not the fluffy blind optimism
kind but the belief backed by
action and maybe a little bit of rare
parent crazy
eyes because at the end of the day
that's how breakthroughs
happen so there you have it my slightly
derailed Journey from storye new mom to
space themed Nursery to crash landing in
an alien world of rare disease
in the end though we realized we weren't
in this galaxy
alone we formed a collective we fostered
community and we turned heartbreak into
Innovation and
hope and that's the kind of Unstoppable
energy that we're here today
celebrating when your world blows up you
adapt you innovate and you share and
together we keep going while Pew peing
all of those evil space monsters
so thank you for letting me beam my
story Into Your orbit
today each of you are so vital to this
unfolding
Mission I'm convinced that together we
can end rare
disease while I have felt like an alien
on another planet these last several
years and I
was I felt like I was forced onto that
planet I am starting to understand that
maybe we were never actually needing to
board ships and rock it off to some
distant Galaxy to find our
people we were all right here on Earth
scattered by isolation and
Circumstance but once we connected and
once we found each other we realized
that this planet has everything we need
to innovate collaborate and make a
difference this isn't about chasing the
Stars this is about bringing the
stranded explorers home
there will be setbacks and failures on
the way to the safe landing that we all
dream of but we cannot accept what we
cannot accept is progress being stalled
by the lack of
collaboration communication and
willingness to work
together I want to hear everyone our
scientific Community academic industry
Partners stepping up and Sharing Hope
and knowledge just just like our rare
disease Community has
done we don't have to separate to A
Whole New World we just have to join
forces to make this one better than we
found
it in all serious thoughness though if
anyone does have Intel on some
extraterrestrial
beings please find me after because I'm
pretty sure I could pitch them um to
join our patient registry or at least
give me a sample for the bio
so beam me up broes I can do this all
day with the analogies I'm thank you I'm
done thank you for
listening if you have a question I'm
happy to answer I know we're running a
little
overtime questions for
feie okay thank you thank you so
much okay so by now you're noticing how
masterfully um Jillian uh has been
weaving in the stories uh this afternoon
so we're doing science and we're doing
uh Advocate and family stories and then
coming back to science and so it's my
great pleasure to uh bring us back to
some really cool um innovative ideas um
around another um uh rare uh disease
Marfan syndrome um our speaker is aany
ragavan uh who is a postto in Patrick
Elanor group she's also a cardiologist
at Mass General um and again one of the
people in the younger generation will W
wildly proud of and you're about to uh
find out why so
Avante um thank you so much for that
introduction and um a huge thank you to
latters to as well as the Tamir
Foundation um for organizing this um
it's a real privilege to speak here
today so um as Dr grea mentioned um I
have dual roles I'm um a cardiologist at
Mass General and then I'm also a
researcher here at the broad and really
the focus of all of my work my clinical
and my research work is thoracic aortic
disease and a few years ago that led me
to a rare disease called Marfan syndrome
which is a melan form of aortic disease
and so for the next 10 minutes or so I
want to tell you about some of the work
we've been doing um to uh accelerate
therapeutic development for this
disorder
so what is Marfan syndrome um like I
mentioned it's a melan u it's a melan
connective tissue disorder and it's
caused by mutations in the fibrin one
gene so fibrin one encodes an
extracellular Matrix protein it's
expressed throughout the body and so as
you can imagine these patients have
multi-stem connected tissue issues and
often they're recognizable because
they're unusually tall and thin but over
the course of their life they develop
many issues including skeletal issues
pulmonary issues ocular issues and then
most importantly the most feared
complication of Marfan syndrome is
aortic disease so what is the aorta it's
the biggest blood vessel in the body so
every year our hearts beat 35 million
times and with each of those heartbeats
our aortas have to expand to accommodate
that entire blood volume under high
pressures and distribute blood to all of
our body's organs and so that takes a
lot of contractile as well as elastic
strength and so in Marfan syndrome
fibrillin mutations lead to aneurysmal
degeneration and weakening of the aortic
wall so over time as early as
adolescence into early adulthood
individuals develop aneurysms or
enlargement of the aorta and this can
predispose to acute complications such
as aortic tears or rupture and this in
fact is the leading cause of death in
Marfan
syndrome so traditionally there have
been been two pillars of treatment for
Maran so the first is surgery you can
have an open heart surgery where the
surgeon goes in and basically cuts out
the disease portion of the aorta and
replaces it with a graft and this may or
may not be Curative for some patients it
is other patients they continue to have
issues over the course of their life
they continue to develop issues
involving parts of their aorta that were
not replaced and so for those patients
we can offer medical therapy and really
we only have two classes of medications
we can offer these patients they're both
blood pressure agents and they show sort
of variable benefit in terms of slowing
aortic growth but the one thing I want
to point out is that both these classes
of medications have been around for
decades and so I think that kind of
speaks to the fact that there really
hasn't been much meaningful therapeutic
advancement in this area for many many
years and so when I you know first
became interested in studying aortic
disease a few years ago um I noticed
that traditionally genomics and a lot of
these high throughput technologies that
we routinely use at the broad had not
ever really been applied to aortic
disease in a meaningful way and so our
kind of overarching goal was to think
about how we could leverage some of the
strengths of the Bro Institute in
genomewide association studies single
cell multiomic studies high content
Imaging and combine them with more
traditional approaches such as Mouse
modeling and molecular biology to
accelerate the pace of therapeutic
Target get identification and
development from our fan syndrome so
over the next 10 minutes I hope to give
you a flavor of some of the efforts that
we've been um we've been doing on
several of these
fronts so one of the first things I
wanted to do is I realized we didn't
have a tissue biobank for Marfan
syndrome and I was extraordinarily lucky
to work with a couple of folks um
Antonio ceso is a cardiac surgeon at MGH
um as well as Ben Landis who's a
Pediatric Cardiologist at Indiana
University and we actually established a
pipeline for collecting aortic tissue
from Marfan syndrome patients um and so
what we do is we chart review and we
consent all eligible patients not only
with Marfan but many other rare genetic
aortopathies um and so we consent them
prior to their elective aortic operation
and then we go to the O and so as soon
as that aortic tissue becomes available
we flash freeze it so it's as fresh and
as fresh as possible and then we Bank it
and just in the past few years alone
we've been lucky that MGH is such a high
volume aortic Center we've collected 16
tissues from Marfan syndrome patients to
date as well as over 30 healthy control
tissues and so in the next few months
and years our goal is to use these
tissues to inform um various techniques
including single cell transcriptomics
and
epigenomics but flash Frozen tissue just
kind of gives you this snapshot of gene
expression um at a certain moment in
time and so what we really wanted is we
wanted a system
that kind of gives you a more Dynamic
readout right so what if we want to
perform a drug screen what if we want to
perform a crisper screen so most of the
pathology in Marfan syndrome really
centers on the smooth muscle cell the
smooth muscle cell um is the most
abundant cell type in the aorta and I
mentioned earlier that the aorta needs a
lot of contractile strength and it's the
smooth muscle cell that gives it that
contractile strength and so it turns out
that if you have a fresh aortic biopsy
you can actually isolate that muscular
layer you can put it into culture and
the smooth muscle cells grow out so you
can establish lines directly from
patients and so we've been doing that
over the past few years we've generated
multiple um Marian syndrome lines from
multiple patients and so then we asked
can we develop some sort of morphologic
profiling technique in order to kind of
understand how these disease cell lines
look and so to do that we took advantage
of of um something that we know about
endstage aneurysm so in endstage
aneurysm um smooth muscle cells lose a
lot of their contractile abilities and
they upregulate a lot of synthetic
markers like collagen and so we stained
a couple of different um couple of
different components of the cell um the
actin cytoskeleton collagen um as well
as smad which is an important signaling
mediator in the TGF beta pathway and we
just looked at our cell lines under the
microscope and so here I have two
different well type lines on top and the
bottom I have a Maran line and if you
look at like the highest seating density
it's I mean the cells are just totally
different which is not surprising so the
wild type lines are green they have lots
of contractile features and then the
Maran lines they're more orange so
they're they have all this collagen and
in fact when you look at these
morphologic features in the disease
lines over a third of those features are
totally different in the in the disease
line and so we're really excited to see
that phenotype um and of course we can
quantify individual phenotypes But
ultimately our goal is to identify
features that are common um across
multiple donor lines and eventually the
goal really is to perform a reversion
screen so to look for small molecules or
to look for um guide rnas that can
actually revert that disease phenotype
right back to a healthy
cell so I've spent some time telling you
about things that we want to do um in
order to accelerate theraputic
development and so for the second part
of this talk I actually want to tell you
a specific story about a Target that
we've already found and that we're super
excited about um and this is a really
special story from our lab a few years
ago um our group did a genome wide
Association study looking at aortic size
and found over 80 loai that were
associated with aortic size and I have a
Manhattan plot from the study showing
all those genetic loai with the P value
on the Y AIS um and I simplified it to
show you just two loai so one of them
was fibral in one so we found fibral in
one which is good that's reassuring um
and then another Gene that jumped out to
us very early on was this one Locus on
chromosome 16 called
wwp2 and and we that kind of made us
raise our eyebrows because we' never
heard of this Gene being connected to
aortic biology before so um what what
was it about this Gene that that made us
excited now when we do a GS of course we
found lots and lots of genes but really
what we're looking for is the Unicorn so
we're looking for that one gene that has
some set of intrinsic qualities that
tells us this Gene is going to be
successful in the Target development
Pipeline and wwp2 just had them all so
what were those features so first of all
when you look at expression of wwp2
across all tissues in the body what
jumps out at you is that wwp2 is highly
enriched in arterial tissues and the
expression is in fact highest in aorta
which tells you that if you were to
employ a wwp2 directed therapy
theoretically it should have the highest
impact in aorta which is what we want
and then the second thing we found was a
very favorable directionality so we
found that the minor Al of the lead snip
at this Locus is associated with less
wwp2 expression in aorta as well as
smaller aortic size so what does that
mean less wwp2 equals smaller aorta
which is good right so that tells you
first that we should focus on developing
a wwp2 inhibitor but and two right it's
easier to develop an inhibitor typically
to a protein product than it is to
develop an activator so for all these
reasons the strong genetic Association
the tissue specificity and this
favorable directionality we felt that
all the stars had aligned and this was
the target Target that we wanted to go
after so how did we do this we used
Mouse model so it turns out that there's
a Marfan syndrome Mouse model it has a
point mutation in fibrin one and it
phenocopies the human disease
beautifully um so these these mice are
long just like Marfan syndrome patients
are tall they have skeletal overgrowth
um and they develop aortic aneurysms
from a really young age and so we took a
um we took um a mouse that had wwp2
inactivated alals and we crossed it onto
the Marfan Cinder background and then we
looked at the size of the aorta using
ultrasound so we actually do this in
humans except Mouse is about 25 times
smaller so we can use ultrasound to look
at the aorta um in mice and I've kind of
colored in the aorta on those um Mouse
images for you and what we found is that
from Wild Type in purple to Marfan and
blue you see an increase in aortic size
which is what you would expect and then
you see that that increase is attenuated
when you go from the Maran to the Marfan
mice that have w P2
inactivated and then when you look at
those aortas under the microscope they
look better so one of the histologic
features of aneurism is you have a lot
of elastin fragmentation we clearly see
that in the Marian mice and that seems
to be attenuated to some degree in the
Marfan mice with the wwp2 in
Activation so wwp2 is an E3 ubiquit and
ligase um it functions um to transfer
ubiquit into a substrate protein and so
in some ongoing work um we're using
different proteomics approaches to
identify um Downstream substrates of
wwp2 that may be responsible for this
effect on aortic
biology so um that kind of brings me to
the end of my talk um and I I covered a
lot of ground today but what I want to
say is that um you know a lot of this
work is early we started um many of
these efforts just a few years ago um
and our long-term goal is really to
integrate functional genomics High
throat B biology as well as Mouse
modeling to identify novel therapeu big
targets for Marfan
syndrome um we've invested a lot of
effort the past few years into resource
development so we're establishing a
biobank for Marfan we're establishing a
lot of primary cell lines from these
patients um and then of course we've
identified a promising Target already
that we're really excited about studying
further so thank you so much for your
attention um a huge thank you to the
Eleanor lab um for making all of this
work possible as well as to our
collaborators thank you
hey um really cool talk just on the
human genetics is there a natural
experiment where you have a Marans
patient who just has a natural mutation
in wwp2 that happens to have a small
aort or something that's protected is
there like a proof of genetics there
yeah so that's a great question um so
when our group did the original gwas we
did look for rare variants this wasn't
in Marfan patients just in in general so
we looked for rare variants in wwp2
unfortunately the burden of rear
variance in wwp2 just wasn't high enough
to understand if potentially there's
some kind of protective effect certainly
in the future I think it would be really
interesting to look at maybe large
cohorts of of patients with Marfan
syndrome um there is a lot of phenotypic
heterogenity and Marfan syndrome so
there are over 3,000 mutations in the
fibrin one Gene and different mutations
are associated with different disease
penetrance and expressivity so it may be
a little bit challenging to sort of
tease apart the effect of the mutation
versus the effec of wwp2 in activation
but it's a really really excellent
question thank you fantastic so in y map
so besides wwp2 there are a lot of top
hits yes so what are those SC and what
do we study those sorry why do you
choose ww
P2 not all other top HS oh why it was
wwp2 so I I think you know wwp2 was just
um of all the 80 something lowside that
we identified that was the one that we
thought just based on a certain set of
qualities just seemed most likely to be
successful in just from a drug
development perspective obviously you
don't know until you model it but I
think we were really excited about the
clear tissue specificity for aorta um as
well as the fact that it seemed like
inhibiting wwp2 was the way to kind of
attenuate aortic disease so that kind of
jumped out just from the genetics data
but I think ultimately our goal is to
look at a lot of these other gai using
some of these using crisper screens and
other screens with our morphologic
profiling platform um to identify other
potential targets for the disease thank
you thank
[Applause]
you our next talk is going to take us
back to the company creation space so
I'm really happy to introduce tanas
chanduka he is a 2024 prier fellow um
he's a physician and serial entrepreneur
every time I talk to him I learn about a
new company that he has spun out from
his work um he's currently the CEO of
tab Therapeutics which focuses in the
cancer space but today he's going to
talk to us about his journey with nandi
um which focuses on cancer Auto
autoimmune and rare disease
welcome thank
you okay no no no no no no you can do it
at the end you can do it at the end to
the end um let's get the device let's
see is this working I'm not screwing it
up great how are you guys
doing are we sounding like people who
are solving for rare diseases or
not can I hear the people at the
back can I get a hell yeah there we go
there we go so over the past two weeks I
have been in multiple cities I've been
in Houston Texas where we're building
some of our exciting uh compan ianes
I've been in Florida in Fort Lauderdale
having a great time with one of my
co-founders working intensively on a
manufacturing problem in China and then
I'm here today why do I do this I would
do nothing else with my life I love
creating companies finding people who
have a mission that they want to um use
biotechnology to solve and empowering
them to do that that is my gift on Earth
is to bring people together and to solve
those problems I'm an mdphd by
background I was a road scholar at
Africa sorry in in in Oxford University
I was born in South Africa my home I
love that place haven't been in 5 years
because I'm so busy doing this stuff but
it lives inside me and it's important
for you to know that because the people
in Africa need these medicines and my
thesis is if I can create medicines that
can translate into something valuable
for all the people in this room then
will cover my continent so that's the
thesis that's the thesis of impact right
there I'm very lucky that um I I I went
through a background of having uh
studied at Oxford and then been involved
in Venture Capital working for Europe's
largest early stage life science fund
called Oxford science Innovation I was
involved in helping to stand up 55 life
science companies out of the company's
100 portfolio companies that equals very
little sleep and you know what I put my
hand up for all the tough things because
that's how you become a good company
Creator and because of that I became
involved in the oxid vaccine now some of
you didn't get
that um but two billion people on the
planet did and it did make a difference
for them and I was very proud to have
been one of two people in our life
science team who put my hand up in
January of 2022 to say which sry 2020
say that we would shut down the company
because the flu vaccine had failed and
at the bottom of everyone's screen was
this this little uh you know pulmonary
infection that's happening in Wuhan in
China it's not a big thing and it turned
out to have been one of the most
important projects I was involved in
through that I was recruited uh by a
gentleman called bobach azamian um or
Bobby aaman to work as Director of
Business Development at his uh
biotechnology company in in California
and that afforded me the opportunity to
work in a public biotech company from 40
employees to to to a much uh bigger
level I I could sit in meetings were
requiring companies I could work on
everyday problems like how are we going
to make this app that reads people's to
launch a drug product but all of these
things have been instrumental in
becoming a company Creator I want to
stop here for a second and highlight uh
the woman who's here she is my sister
and I managed to convince her to leave
her job at meta she's a corporate lawyer
by background m&a lawyer uh trained at
Baker McKenzie multiple IPOs on the uh
London Stock Exchange and New York Stock
Exchange and worked at uh Morgan Stanley
and then later on at meta and she acts
as the executive chair of nandi Life
Sciences and I'll tell you about bit
about n9y today um we're values driven
people every day we're making decisions
in our companies that are yes based on
science yes based on financials but that
are based on integrity and who we are
I'm a doctor first which means I have a
line there are things that I will not do
and I think it's important for everyone
in this room to think about that for a
second sometimes there are medicines we
can develop and sometimes there are
medicines we should not develop and it
comes down to these values and you'll
notice that the first one there is being
relentless because developing drugs like
the family that's here requires you to
give everything of yourself think about
that for a second in terms of what that
means but also to be an advocate to be
impactful to be empathetic and sometimes
to actually take one for the team
because you have to make decisions that
are Guided by integrity and I think all
too often we don't talk about what that
actually means um look at me you know
exactly that I don't sound like I come
from here and you know like I'm in a
country where sometimes things can get a
little bit weird at this moment let's be
honest and um so what did I do I knew
that I wasn't going to raise money here
because I didn't go to Harvard I don't
have the social network let's just be
honest so what did I do I found a group
of crazy people in in in Texas who have
a lot of money and believe in crazy
people like me to build something like
this and what did they do they gave me
healthare benefits a stien to work at
and that's the Texas Medical Center
right so please throw away all your
conceptions of who is capable to
innovate where they live you know just
hustle just do what you need to so I
found my path to being a company Creator
in Houston Texas beautiful place the
world's largest life science Community
actually if you arrive there you'll see
it it's a city they see 10 million
patients a year rare diseases are pretty
common down there and great doctors who
trained here and around the world world
who are there doing great things so
let's just work together so what what do
I do at nandi what we do is we partner
with Scientists with great ideas who
generally may not know someone who has a
lot of money because maybe they didn't
go to college with them or they just
don't know how to communicate it
fluently and what we do is we will spend
months Landscaping a particular disease
area finding um identifying unmet
clinical needs for example um
what if you have a renal kidney disorder
and we've just understood the basic
biology but there are no medicines to
treat that what if a child suffers from
seizures and we've just begun to
understand the biological targets but
it's not a sexy subject that VCS are
investing in right now because it's not
a validated Target those are the
situations that we like to get involved
in where we've understood the basic
biology when we sit down and we do the
financial models over $700 million of
peak sales opportunities places where um
antibody Therapeutics and other protein
Therapeutics could make a difference
this has to do with manufacturing we can
talk about that someday and also where
we know that we have uh IP so freedom to
operate if we you'd be surprised how few
things meet those criterias but if we
can do that and then most importantly if
I can stand in front of you and actually
Define the disease condition we're going
to be treating so many good ideas cannot
translate because what are you heading
to right so often starting off with the
disease area the problem and then
heading Upstream like the family here is
doing helps us to always remember the
patience right that we're going to
develop a drug that doesn't give people
additional adverse effects so what if we
done in the last two and a half years
also very little sleep um we've built
four companies most of them are stal so
I can't tell you exactly what they do
but I'm very excited because three of
them will be announced this year these
companies have raised over 50 million um
largely led by our most advanced company
we've partnered with uh a Boston Venture
Capital fund I I I I wish I could I want
to say thank you to one of the gentlemen
there but when he watches this talk
he'll know it and uh by the summer of
this year it'll be announced um let's
start from the back so we will often
find a concept 6 months to 18 months we
will front the cash to en license the
technology to build the company to find
Consultants to find team members that
means that my family liquidated most of
our assets because I had a crazy dream
and when you start to try and build
something good luck finding someone who
give you money you often have to front
it so when I moved from California to
Texas um a lot of things were lost a lot
of sacrifices were made and so you know
on the back of that my wonderful family
and friends we've been able to find
these Technologies to build them
in-house and take this forward
then when an idea when we decide to pull
the trigger when we understand that um
we even have conversations with farmer
far in advance understanding who will
buy this company and take it to the
world once we are sure that we can meet
those criteria once we know who the
customer is and that I speak to patients
to Physicians and they said yeah if the
drug did even half of that yeah I'll
take it then we really start to go on
the road to find real money and you know
what's more difficult than finding money
great talent that's gonna run it because
you know they actually ask tough
questions they're like so I've got my
great job at sanofi or fisa or something
why should I leave that great job and I
come work with you have you figured out
the science what are the risks walk me
through it nah that's not true go look
at that go look at this so I'm very
excited that for for for our companies
that we build the conversations are very
intensive it's often over dinner but
generally people say yes this is
something they want to get involved in
I've jumped into the Helm of t-map
Therapeutics and oncology company uh a
partnership with MD Anderson as its
co-founder and CEO let's dive deeper
into that as an example of what happens
do do you understand what is happening
here who
knows uh please could you
share canc sorry cancer there we go it's
it's finishing your chemotherapy course
we hope you've beaten it but but it's a
it's a big moment um so the scientist
here Professor Neil sud and jishan an
identified that there were Escape
Pathways to anti vef drugs and anti
drugs are anti-angiogenic agents that
stop blood vessel growth into solid
tumors they can also be used in the eye
but the problem is they haven't
generated overall survival benefit
they've generated progression free
survival benefit which means that VCS
won't fund that because unless if you
can demonstrate that a single drug in a
trial beats everything else and can
demonstrate overall survival benefit
they're just not going to fund it right
CU otherwise it's Russian Roulette and
we can't do that with pension fund money
so these two scientists worked for years
trying to understand how women with
ovarian cancer which is a rare disease
um needed new Therapeutics That Could
That Could demonstrate um overall
survival benefit in that field and
despite the fancy drugs we come up with
some of you in this room were involved
in that par Inhibitors uh that that are
used in 50 % 50% of women with ovarian
cancer eligible for that despite the
great new antibody drug conjugates that
have been developed that only qualify
for 30 30 to 40% of the women who have
recurrent Platinum ovarian cancer we
still have this huge group of women who
have Platinum resistant ovarian cancer
and you know what's common across all
the lines of therapy that not so sexy
drug that doesn't do much what people
say
bab very important drug and when you
speak to the to the Physicians they say
it's a great drug we we use it in some
women for 9 to 18 months we can keep
using it when all the other drugs fail
what can we do about it but I go and
speak to VCS and they say they don't
care about it so last year after these
scientists have been working on this for
15 years they published in nature a
phenomenal publication demonstrating
that the reason why uh ca25 goes up when
patients are now on
bmab um and the their continuation
treatment in recurrent ovarian cancer is
because of these two novel secreted
lians that are over expressed very
similar to vef and they mapped out the
transcriptional pathways that involved
in these being overexpressed and leading
to New Blood vascul growth and immune
cells growing and what we've been doing
as a company um is building
multi-specific antibodies that can
Target anti Pathways while targeting
anti cd5l and anti-fl 6 and stimulating
an immune response um over the next
coming weeks you'll see us more in
Boston there'll be an announcement about
what we're doing but um I I want to say
um thank you to to to our competitors
who have paved the way Summit
Therapeutics in AO have developed a b
specific that's going to transform the
cancer space anti vef plus anti pd1 it's
demonstrating 50% progression free
survival benefit uh versus pism AB which
is just astonishing uh in a phase three
head-to-head trial in China and MD
Anderson is is helping to FastTrack the
approval of that drug in the United
States by running a large phase three so
what do we do we found talented people
heren who headed up antibody engineering
and discovered astroica came out of
retirement his wife is not very happy
with him and he helps us late at night
to engineer or try specific antibodies
Rakesh who's like a mentor and dad to me
um he used to head up uh animal studies
at astroica and oncology and you know he
acts like a mentor he makes sure I don't
do dumb things um and and he's our
fractional Chief scientific officer we
also have a ton of Partners uh who work
with story companies like Johnson
Johnson orenic and genmab I can't tell
you who those are but they're really
good at what they do and yet I still
stress them out because of my demands um
and this is what we're dreaming of We're
Dreaming that of that if we can raise 50
million over the next over the next uh
24 months we'll be able to run uh two
phase one trials at MD Anderson one with
our super avastin drug which combines
cd5l VF and egfl6 in tumors that respond
to anti-f drugs but need an additional
kick of immune activation that's what
cd5l does makes macras start to make
inflammatory cyto kindes recruits tea
cells with our other multi-specific
antibody construct that has a checkpoint
inhibitor component to it we want to
Target cancers that have responded to to
checkpoint inhibitors but you know could
need an additional boost things like
microsatellite stable choral cancer
where we've had a lot of difficulty so
that's it in a nutshell we could apply
to all of these Cancers and this is why
we get the companies to phase one we
start the relationships with farmer and
then we say we can do this as a small
biotech the right thing for patients is
to hand over the technology to Great
teams that can run the trials around the
world and get these drugs to patients as
quickly as POS possible we do do the
numbers this is an example of the peak
sales opportunity uh for a for a um a
trip specific construct that would be uh
looking at nons small cell and cancer
and that said I think what I want to
show you is we're very busy uh we're
building teams for our other portfolio
companies and this is the tough thing if
you want to learn how to build a company
please speak to me happy to be your
friend and maybe one day when you do it
I'll be there cheering you on and uh we
we can work together through this
structure so thank you very much for
your time these are all the wonderful
people who help us and uh all the
partners who've made it possible who
took a bet on our company gave us
massive discounts to get going and
that's the truth that's how these things
start is people take a beted on you so
thank you so much for your time
[Applause]
no questions
good our next talk is going to shift our
lens a little bit so we are going to
hear from Bart who is from the
Netherlands and he's going to talk to us
a bit more about how he uses AI to
facilitate both um care delivery and
Drug development through his work in the
Netherlands so we'll get to see a little
bit about how he thinks about how an
academic Medical Center can fit into all
of the innovations that we've heard
about
today thank you Katherine and what a
what a wonderful program you've
developed I'm so uh proud to be part of
it and a little bit anxious to be
following such great great great
speeches um and when I when I what I
want to present today is really
uh of course AI is a sort of a catalyst
u a catalyst through uh uh which can
enable a Health Care system to adopt all
this great research and all these great
companies and this development into
something that actually uh reaches the
patients at scale so I want to talk
about an enabling ecosystem and um as
mentioned I'm from the Netherland so
it's closest to uh my home to talk about
the Dutch ecosystem uh and U yeah I I'll
elaborate a bit about that um so I'm
currently employed by the University
Medical Center in koning um my main role
there is to develop our corporate AI
strategy which covers both the medical
side but also the research and the
educational
sides uh I'm also the the president of
the Dutch Clinical Research Foundation
and I'll I'll talk a little bit about
that as well because it's an important
step to this enabling uh
ecosystem uh I also want to talk a
little bit about you know more the
European perspective or the larger
European
ecosystem and um yeah finally dive into
a few examples of the applications of AI
in a medical uh system or a medical in a
hospital so first of all the the Dutch
Clinical Research Foundation which I
currently chair um if if you want to
develop new uh agents and bring them
into uh into Healthcare of course
research is a key component and in the
Dutch Clinical Research Foundation we
really align Partners in research uh to
make sure that the process is as
efficient as possible so first of all
there's uh the researchers themselves or
the clinicians themselves the the Dutch
academic hospitals and the larger
hospital system they're all
collaborating uh together in in the dcrf
we also have industry so the Innovative
Pharma uh the C are also part of the the
foundation our Regulators so the the
Central Committee for human bound
research the the Dutch medical ethics
committees and also a a research funding
uh uh
entity and they're part of a a larger
connected ecosystem and that's how we
see the Nelons as well it's a really
condensed small country uh
geographically it inhabits about 18
million people uh but it's really well
connected it's well connected in terms
of data infrastructures it's also well
connected in terms of physical
infrastructures and it's part it's
really Central to uh to Europe we also
house the European medicines agency as
well as the European pent
office so some anxiety exists around
Europe being a really difficult place to
bring your research to especially if you
want to skill because it's of course not
one country it is is uh many different
countries but what is the interesting
thing about that is that in Europe we we
have a habit of collaboration because uh
because of the the fact that we uh we
have many different countries in in one
legal economic entity so on the left you
see that in uh General more and more uh
commercial research is being done in
single countries so one country uh and
and all your eggs in that one basket
let's say
especially with China but also here in
the US it is a more common practice and
over time you see a trend that it it it
becomes more more common whereas in
Europe uh increasingly we are doing
multinational studies especially since
the introduction of the clinical trial
regulation that has been much more the
case and also if you look at you know
the total volume of of of studies uh
continuously the European economic uh
entity area has been uh well U uh
positioned to do multi multicountry
studies and increasingly there are
Advanced Therapies in those studies so
over 15% of these studies are uh using
uh Advanced therapies and I think that's
good news for the rare disease space
because I think nowhere uh else it is
more common that advanced therapies are
used as in the rare disease space and
there's a clear reason why and and this
is a hashtag that was introduced in uh
in Europe a few years ago uh it says 30
million reasons which uh represents to
30 million patients of rare diseases in
the in Europe and um actually some
studies show that it might be as as high
as 36 million and that's twice the
population size of the Netherlands um so
and these patients can't weight so this
is this is something that we uh we
really need to focus on and one of the
great ways to do that in a European
context is through the European
reference networks I don't know if
you've uh heard about these before but
the European reference networks bring
together patients uh healthc care
institutions Academia uh around certain
rare diseases and in the Netherlands
we've been uh really focused on
promoting uh participation in the
European reference Networks so out of
the 24 that were established in
2017 uh seven are actually coordinated
by Dutch uh uh Specialists and we
participate in in nearly all of them and
it's a a really fantastic way of
knowledge sharing and expertise sharing
and it really allows us to quickly U uh
go to a a paneuropean u uh
collaboration on a more Dutch scale we
have also invested in rare andl and rare
andl is a organization that brings
together Academia um Healthcare
professionals but also industry around
rare diseases and Drug repurposing so
this is a a hub really for the
development where uh we we work together
uh from these different
disciplines some of the um work that was
done um
well I I I won't go to into much detail
there sorry so um this Dutch ecosystem
the way it works is we have our
University Medical Centers there are
seven and they this is really a system
of collaboration that we have over
80,000 people are employed in those
institutions about 12 billion turnover
every year uh and U uh yeah most of the
science actually is developed there most
of the rare disease specialists are
there and then there there is also other
infrastructures so for instance health
arai is really about aligning data
infrastructures Across the Nation to
make sure that we have those data that
we need to do uh research and Innovation
and also we have some different uh
organizations such as rnl but also the
Dutch Center for RNA Therapeutics which
you may be familiar with who really
support the work in this uh rare disease
space now some of the examples from a
more clinical
approach and this is not something that
we yet do in rare diseases space but we
are sort of trying to see how especially
generative AI is helping our uh Health
Care system and uh those examples I I
think we we we can later expand into the
the rare disease space so if you look at
AI in a you uh in a single Hospital the
way we approach it when we look at this
technology we think of of different
value streams that we can use this
technology the first one being
efficiency which is quite quite uh easy
to identify so use AI to reduce
administrative burden for instance uh
then AI for Discovery I think a lot of
the work that's being done especially
here in the broad Institute is about AI
for Discovery or you know the machine
learning or the Deep learning that
that's already been uh explored for many
decades but also now with the generative
AI uh then the AI for precision I think
that's where it becomes more interesting
because for instance we uh use a a
project that's called the
pharmacogenetic passport where uh
through uh Gene testing and multimodal
data approaches we can find and identify
unique therapies for individual patients
and AI is really supporting us there and
the last one is AI for augmentation and
there you I think you should really
think about also the patients
perspective in this one so imagine you
being at your physician he or she is
telling you all about you know your
disease your therapy and the things that
are ahead of you and and AI can really
help us by for instance taking that
information and then relaying it to the
patient in a really um understandable
and and U uh easy accessible language
for instance so we're actually doing a
lot of work of on that and I'll skip
this one um so what we've done is we've
really developed a framework in our in
our Healthcare institution uh We've
looked at you know what are the unique
challenges uh that generative AI bring
to us in terms of for instance bias
medication uh we heard hallucinations or
confabulations in in one of the previous
presentations as well but also things
like liability how does it work if such
a system fails or if it makes mistakes
so we've we've generated this framework
we've we've developed a team that that
you know brings together all the key
expertises that we need and based on
that we've we've done a pipeline of
different uh use cases that we've
introduced so that's for instance
helping our doctors getting a a draft
response to the patient's questions uh
but also an AI text assistant that helps
doctors draft patient accessible
language in their discharge notes uh and
some other functionalities so we
currently have eight functionalities in
in clinic
today and then the next uh Frontier for
us is normal typing and that's really
about the ambient listening so listening
into the clinical conversation moving
that into high contextual text and then
into high quality quity data and I think
therefore the rare disease space is
going to really open up because if we
are able to do that go from uh a
discussion in clinic into high
contextual text into high quality data
we can start exploring for new avenues
to identify patients for instance
through uh U uh symptoms that they
describe during those
conversations of course this is all
being done in a context where you know
it's really important that we also
consider the ethical legal and societal
aspects and for that reason we've
established the elza AI lab which you
know focuses on this specific part of of
the introduction of this
technology um and and there we really
want to understand if for instance you
only ask a lawyer whether something can
happen or if you only ask somebody who
is really involved in privacy aspects
then the answer might be too black and
white and if we can do that from a a
more framework perspective on the
ethical legal and societal aspects I
think a lot more can be done with that
data and I think that also opens up the
patients perspective U uh from this
technology and and the reason I I
mentioned that so in in chronia we we
actually have an mosis expertise Center
and um when you look at patients that
come in with this uh destructive disease
which is really rare by the way um the
most one of the very common complaints
is that they have is num feet and there
are so many reasons why you could have
num feet but um if you look at family
history for instance patients with mlo
dosis typically have a strong genetic
predisposition so they will have uh a
lot of history in their family with such
complaints and if that could only help
us to more quickly identify and and
diagnose those patients and ensure that
you know the the damage that is done by
this disease is uh is captured early
then then I think we have a lot to
win so I have one last and I'm looking
at the time one last um example that I
wanted to to uh to
give and that's the uh genome met for
all and um actually this is the work
that's done um a follow-up project that
was done by edart F beers from the the
UT University Medical Center so that's
another uh hospital and what they have
actually been able to do is to to model
through Federated learning through
synthetic data uh something for Cle cell
disease that you know enables them to
identify new patients on a quicker scale
and this is led by the uh Euro blood net
which is one of the erns and I think
that that shows that you know there's
really hope for those patients in those
rare
diseases and um yeah maybe still a last
one last month uh a paper was uh
published in in nature medicine about
solve Rd
um and this is a network where actually
from about 6 and a half thousand
patients that had you know un un diagnos
where diseases uh they bring they
brought together you know pulled
together a lot of data they pulled
together expertise from different uh
European reference networks and then
through this project they re-evaluated
those 6 and a half thousand patients and
were're able to identify over 500
patients U or diagnose over 500 patient
with a rare disease and I think that
goes to show that that that technology
really helps us to U uh move forward in
the rare disase space so to Briefly
summarize and I hope U have been able to
relay my message
properly um I'm not trying to promote
the Nelons here but I think it's good to
look at it from an ecosystem perspective
so how from all that important research
how do we actually bring it to patient
and and that's really through a
collaboration in the ecosystem both in a
national perspective but also uh from a
European
perspective um the the drug repurposing
was mentioned a few times during the
presentations and in the nland we really
feel that that's a really high potential
because it brings to together to the
patient therapies today rather than uh
10 years down the line which I don't
want to make an argument for that we
stop doing that Innovative work but look
at what we already have I think we
should really uh get experience in using
those AI models in healthcare in general
so not just the most advanced models but
also everyday uh applications so for
instance browsing through patient data
to find new patterns um yeah and lastly
and I think this is um something where
the the uh Massachusetts area and the
Nelons have already you know have have a
long-standing relation this model of
collaboration which is really part of
the DNA of this ecosystem and it's also
very much the uh the DNA of our
ecosystem in the Netherlands so leading
by example uh I think is a key work and
with that I I want to thank you for your
[Applause]
attention questions for Bart I have a
question um I'm curious about your
impressions from from your Vantage Point
um as to the uh potential for collab
operation between the EMA and the FDA in
the context of rare diseases what have
you seen what do you see as challenges
or opportunities uh in terms of those uh
interactions yeah thank you for the
question and um
um I I don't know the extent to which
these organizations already collaborate
I know that uh what really helps of
course if uh let's say the ecosystems
themselves collaborate and that The
Regulators could follow uh over the past
years I've seen positive developments in
terms if you look at for instance from
the US side uh the arpage uh initiative
which really Fosters collaboration
between the or transatlantic
collaborations on the EU side the same
has happened right so especially in the
health uh research space there's
opportunities for us counterparts to
collaborate with EU counterparts and I
think if we can you know Foster that
collaboration much more then I think
those Regulators will follow
I don't know whether they are already in
advanced State uh in in the current
discussions okay okay thank
you
so wow what an afternoon I know it's
been long but I think fascinating and I
just want to give again all of the
speakers a a round of applause for just
incredible stories and scientific
discoveries
clearly there's a lot to be hopeful for
and a lot more work of course ahead of
us so I know we had like this whole long
sort of list of questions that we wanted
to discuss but I also want to keep us um
on time so I just wanted to maybe um you
know just have a conversation and just
think about you know whoever you know
feels like sort of jumping in from
everything that we've heard today or
from all the different you know groups
and and and constituencies that you
represent different stakeholders in the
field um what would you point as to a
recent win something that you're really
sort of positive about you know each
from your different Vantage points and
whoever you know wants to jump in first
what what what can we name as a recent
win I have a couple I'm going to start
with CTN mb1 uh the disorder that my son
has two things the CTN mb1 connect and
cure Foundation here in the USA uh
obviously from fundraising from families
and generous donors around the world uh
has funded uh Michelle Jacob labit tffs
who has partnered with the broad and was
awarded the ncats nah Trend program so
they will be working to optimize a lead
compound for the disorder my son has and
second our ctb1 foundation in Slovenia
is um well on their way they've
manufactured our aav9 gene therapy and
hoping to go to clinical trials this
fall and to shout out some amazing rare
Advocates out there uh Terry pakis just
appeared on Kelly Clarkson Sunita P was
at the White House speaking and I just
think it's so profound that these rare
Advocates are showing up and raising
their voice in places that maybe they
don't belong I'm at the road I mean
people are listening to us and it's it's
it's moving and it's really wonderful
and it's and I'm seeing that the these
aren't just diseases anymore to people
and that people are seeing that there's
a community and human beings behind it
so it's I'm hopeful and I think the
future is bright I love it
yes of
course so I talked a lot about patient
insights I want to share one win um for
one of the partners that we're working
with global genes weax they are a
patient registry platform they were
recently awarded a 1.5 million Grand
technology Grant from the Cher
Foundation we're also a grantee from the
zzii grant so we're very happy for both
of them they're essentially using AI to
better understand patient data and that
is so powerful because a lot of times
it's really hard for the patient the
families to fill out pages and hours of
survey they have all the information for
years of history but it's just so
complicated to share all that data with
your clinician with the researchers I'm
really excited to to see AI in general
being a tool to capture more patient
insights data stories um as part of
research fascinating yes I think that's
incredible and there are many
opportunities ahead any more takers
recent wins any any
takes um okay fine we'll kind of uh move
into the next um next uh topic I I was
just um curious about you know we we
talked a lot today I mean there was a
mix of of of uh you know scientific and
sort of more uh you know stories from uh
inspired by your work in advocacy uh
working with family foundations but the
thing that struck me as a common theme
you know has been the tools you know
there's there's a need for tools
sometimes there are scientific tools we
discussed the discovery of some of those
and other times there's other tools so
and then that brings us of course to you
know who has access to these tools and
how do we you know make it better um uh
I know that many of us today talked
about um you know problems with access
is how it's Unique that we can all be
here in Boston together um you know
talking about these topics but you know
um others who are listening to us and
and sort of uh uh thinking about all the
things that we discussed today does it
sound like something that would be
accessible to them so I'm curious about
how you're thinking about this from your
different perspectives and uh maybe you
know what are the tools that you're
focusing on and how you might be uh
securing their uh access to others in
our broader
communities any takers well the one of
the reasons I'm doing my research at the
broad is just this enthusiasm for making
publicly available tools um not just the
software not just um the assays and
molecular techniques but also putting
data into databases and making them
sharable and doing our very best to make
them usable by um by everyone
researchers families clinicians as well
so to me that's a really important part
of being
here maybe another dimension on the
tools question I think obviously the bro
um does a lot of of work in developing
Innovative tools I hope one of the
themes we've heard today is how much
having uh end application a rare disease
or something that you're really working
towards can help Focus your efforts so
that the tool is something that can be
extensible can be applied because I
think you know in my day-to-day work at
thermofisher we do see lots of
innovative tools come in but not all of
them have clear applications that can or
are worth being democratized because
there's only a few people at the road
who could possibly use the tool so part
of it I think is really partnering with
patients with patient advocacy groups or
partnering with the end users of these
tools to really understand kind of how
applicable these are and you know having
some sort of focus really helps drive to
usefulness and ease of
democratization oh sorry go ahead please
please okay I was also going to say that
places like Simon light and combined
brain again are working to gather these
patients and really think about how
where the similarities are more than the
differences and really keeping a pulse
on the extra motivated Advocates out
there yeah just just a layer on what you
both said I think the intentionality is
really critical um so all our contracts
our missioners really provide that
access and we'll figure out how to do it
but let's start with assumption that we
must do that um so for example we share
all the data back immediately for for
research use we don't blind anything we
don't take the the best hits off the top
of everything gets shared back because
we want to advance that research and it
may not be us doing it and that's okay
um and so kind of letting go of that
protective aspect that sometimes has at
least historically been in the space um
that's a decision that we made we're not
going to do that um and we won't get it
right every time but at least having
that kind of guiding principle that you
know we are in this together and we're
going to solve it together let's start
with that and then we can figure out
what we do along the way that's where
all the tools and databases and that
going take place and maybe just one more
thing to add on there since we are in a
more academic setting here you know one
of the things we heard when we first
started this rare disease Journey was
how many rare disease groups have
partnered with Academia to develop
models whether that's Mouse models ipscs
Etc and how many of them had difficulty
just getting the models out of the
University developed assets hits targets
Etc and I think sometimes the the tech
transfer offices the powers that be view
these assets as having substantial value
before they've been moved out of the
institution but the reality that anyone
in biotech will tell you is once you
take it out you still need to plug tens
of millions of dollars into it before it
has any value at all and it may not be
worth anything too so I think there's
this embedded assumption sometimes that
every asset has huge value coming out of
the institution and there's a big
incentive to just not let things out but
that substantially slows progress both
in Innovation both in democratizing
Access and then also for our um patients
ultimately yeah and I want to follow up
on that because I think that's sort of
um a theme for the terier fellows which
I greatly admire in all of you but this
idea of jumping into starting a company
or or or um you know becoming a CEO of a
company where you know there's not a
proven business modeling the classical
sense so would you like to speak a
little bit about that you know yeah so
one of the things that we get dinged on
by VCS is why are you changing so many
things at once why not just one thing
and the whole point is if you want a
substantial change it's probably not
going to be done by any one little
change um and so huge credit to the
terier foundation for uh taking a a
chance at putting me into the the 2024
fellow group um it's been fantastic and
I have to say the mentors are really key
along the way I think Tanashi also
mentioned you know his his mentor
outside of the program where they're
taking a chance on you it's not on your
technology or your business or it's
somebody thinks that you can change
whatever it is that you're proposing and
all the ter mentors for example go in
with that assumption and there's not
this like kneejerk well that's not how
it's done now where if I talk to VCS
it's like every other conversation it's
like that's not how it's done like well
yeah and look at the results um that is
let's try something different it may not
work right it's not guaranteeing that
but the only guarantee of not doing
anything different is you're going to
get the same thing out um and so that's
where that mentorship and all that comes
in and so absolutely that the ecosystem
driving that support for just take that
shot and see if it works I think it's
key and Tanasha said you know this the
greatest challenge is you know finding
people right like-minded people building
those teams so I'm curious about you
know both from well anyone's perspective
here really how hard has it been to find
you know you you told us some elegant
stories about how you know uh your
podcast for example or how you have done
um you have reached out to other
families to try to build community but
how what are the Challen Alles in terms
of finding people either people to work
in your startup or people to work with
your foundation or both you know in some
cases they're intertwined so uh how how
how are those challenges and and how did
you overcome them um yeah I'd say um a
for a and I it was probably a lot easier
than it was for Fe a decade ago um we're
lucky that there's institutions like the
broad institutions like eff's podcast
and you know support from organizations
like ultr genics who have a boot Camp to
bring people together so in a lot of
ways the only reason a and I have been
able to accelerate so quickly is because
of all the groundwork and Foundation
that's been LED now there are still
challenges I think the pre-clinical path
for these uh uh rare diseases and ultra
rare diseases is a lot more clear there
are still a lot of questions to be
solved in the clinical and Commercial
stages obviously um whether that's
manufacturing or trials what have you
many different questions still remain
but at the very least the front end of
it the network hint is there and there's
a more clear road map than you know of
course when you
started I want to add another point that
may not be directly answered in question
but I've been thinking about that for
our community we're still trying to
identify more families more Patients Out
There Our disease was discovered in
2016 we have 300 families identified
since then and they're mostly children
and what we're trying to find are more
families out there and with the use of
um AI um you know mapping uh facial
phenotypes to the disease when I was
listening to your talk I was very
inspired to think that can we use tools
and Technologies to find more families
out there not just in the US but around
the world in an easy way so we can
expand our community and then our
community becomes our our partner in in
this journey so I think there are many
ways we can accelerate even finding uh
families in our community as part of the
equation and maybe just one more Point
building off of that and connecting to
the access point you made earlier you
know uh early last year Aiden and I were
lucky to have uh our story and L's story
on the the front page of the Boston
Globe um through that a mom of another
zttk patient reached out to us they're
the only other zttk family we know of in
the state of Massachusetts they live in
Springfield Massachusetts and they only
got their diagnosis last year their son
is aged 12 so I'd say around access you
know they're only a 2-hour drive from
Boston one of the best you know medical
and scientific centers in the world and
yet their access to these Technologies
is so limited in a lot of ways even in
America someone in a rural or exurb um
area of America may have less access to
whole exom and genome sequencing than
someone in a major city like Istanbul or
something like that so we really need
more um access to these tests you know
there's a lot of um uh research out
there about how uh it's estimated 20% of
cereal poy patients actually have a
genetic disease of some sort like these
are all very obvious lwh hanging fruit
to increase testing and just um help
patients obviously we then to solve the
problem of you know Finding treatments
and cures for them but identifying them
is like the very first problem that
needs to be solved and that will really
highlight the
problem yeah was now I'll pgy back off
both of those comments because what I
was going to say is we need to like look
at the patients who have passed this
there at the hospital and have young
kids and people are worried and
wondering what's wrong but what about
those grown those grown kids those
adults that have autism epilepsy and
cerebral paly who were totally missed
over 35% it's believe believe maybe even
up to 5050 is that especially the
patients with cerebral poy have a
genetic ideology and so how do we get
those genetic tests to those people with
those umbrella
diagnoses I think we'd find a lot of
rare disease
patients makes a lot of good sense and
maybe part of the reason why there
should be efforts that really um you
know health and rare diseases and
pediatric diseases affect every state
you know every constituency all around
the country and of course every country
around the world so um I I hear your
point about sort of AIS and and making
sure that that's um so now for the last
question for each of you um we are
transported we just celebrated 10 years
for this um um Gathering that we do
every year here at Broad uh we've been
doing it for the last three years
successfully with the termier foundation
again very grateful for that now we are
being transported somehow through a
spaceship
perhaps yeah yeah uh to 10 years from
now and I want each of you to tell me
the one thing that you know we have
learned or achieved or like what does it
look like in terms of the when you look
out there in terms of the um uh rare
disease landscape from each of your
different Vantage points you know 10
years from now you don't we don't have
to go in order but if anyone has any any
first uh
takers yes all right I'll say Precision
medicine is what I want to see happen in
our talk we talk a lot about the right
drug for the right patient at the right
time and let's bring back the right dose
at the right route so I really believe
that Precision medicine hopefully is
less than 10 years can really transform
how we think about treating and
supporting each individual based on
their needs because it's not a one size
fits all as we all know so I am really
excited to see where this goes and how
we
can get the data for that one individual
and really tailor the drug to that
specific specific person that's great
any more Visions 10 years from now maybe
another dimension of that more from an
industry perspective and another area
where perhaps Academia can work more
with industry you know there's a lot of
innovative modalities that have been in
in in innovated by the broad and other
institutions the cell therapies the gene
therapies as anyone who spent time in
the space knows one of the biggest
challenges in these spaces is
manufacturing right there's promising
science but we just can't get the
manufacturing right I would like to see
a world where academics work more with
industry further in advance to solve
those challenges along with the science
because those challenges can be just as
important to the success of these
therapies and I'd like to see those
solved much better in the future
absolutely I think it's not unreasonable
within 10 years to imagine just a much
more systematic approach so whenever any
baby is born they're sequenced and any
issue is immediately diagnosed at least
solving the the genetic um component of
this and then if I'm allowed a second a
second wish then as as you want then at
the very least can we get the loow
hanging fruit of matching up the
existing drugs with existing disorders
using some of the kinds of Technologies
we talked about today if we can just do
a first pass of all of those against
each other um we we really would get far
so what you're saying is let's maximize
the drugs that we have already invested
billions in building you know and make
sure that they're used for every last
patient who can benefit from those I
think that makes very good sense over
though hopefully in 10 years we can also
be on our way to some new new treatments
right to to um Aus Point anyone else
vision for 10 years from now I'm yeah so
this has been been addressed but you
know there's concept of the systems
level approach and I think it's a
systems level problem um it's not just a
genetic problem it's also access to
healthcare access to a lot of other
factors you you know we work with some
families in remote South Africa it is a
whole another problem you're dealing
with that right and the patient here
could just go to Boston Children's same
day be seen by the world's top experts
um in this case that's just not possible
so what do you do and the answer is not
nothing it's something but now what is
it right and so I think my my vision is
really that systems approach like We're
All in This Together uh rare isn't rare
it's just fragmented um I think
recognizing that is a is going to be a
very key acknowledgement of the problem
and the sheer scale of the problem that
we're we're facing um and I I you know
it's a system system that we need to
build together um so I hopefully in 10
years you have the same event and we
have 500 successes and then well we
don't really need to do anything more
that's my vision for we're all out of
work 10 years that would be great 10
years we're all out of work that's
that's a great message any more
Visions mine is similar to yours I would
love to see newborn screening and whole
genome sequencing on every baby not just
a baby in the nicku not just a baby with
symptoms to completely eliminate that
diagnostic Odyssey that causes so many
problems for everyone involved um so
that's what I would like to see and I
think that is closer than 10 years but
who knows with bureaucracy so that's my
wish that's great any more anything to
share Nathan or you're you're covered by
that sounds great uh well so I'd like I
think to uh close this out you know with
just uh again a huge thanks to all of
you for coming to all of our speakers uh
for uh excellent talks really in on a
broad array of uh topics uh I want to
thank again uh Katie liori who's been
sort of the logistical organiz organizer
behind all of this and my right-hand
person and Dr Jillian Shaw who was
curated an incredible program so thank
you Jillian uh really I want to thank
all of you
[Applause]
[Music]
big and just to say sort of as as a
closing uh kind of as a closing argument
if you will um I think we've done a lot
of good work over the last 10 years and
of course much longer than that for all
of those who have been in this space for
for a very long time there's clearly a
lot more work to be done um but I think
that today you can see why I'm a glass
half full Optimist I think that there's
a lot to be hopeful for we heard great
science uh promising Technologies also
very interesting approaches and a huge
amount of commitment from all the
stakeholders in this space the patients
the families The Advocates the
scientists the Physicians um the biotech
um and Pharma leaders who are committed
uh to this area so I think there's a lot
um of work ahead uh but there's a lot of
hope uh that there will be uh great
progress uh coming uh our way if we
continue to uh think about this as a
space that we own together as as shared
sort of stakeholders of this space and
so I'd like to end with the idea that it
really it will take each and every one
of us and all of us working together uh
to make progress so thank you again and
please uh enjoy uh networking reception
side um after this thank you again