All right, good morning everybody.
Welcome to the MPG primer. I hope you
had a good two weeks off and enjoyed
ASHG if you attended. I'm really excited
to introduce um Ben Fernander. He is a
fifth year PhD candidate in Chris
Walsh's lab at Boston Children's
Hospital. He studies somatic mutations
and neurop fibromyitosis type one and
prenatal somatic mutations associated
with maternal infection. He is also a
prolific STEM teacher which you'll see
today and mentor throughout the whole
Boston area. And outside of his amazing
research, he also loves to travel and
hike which is great. So Ben, thank you.
Um ask questions throughout and yeah.
>> All right. Good morning everybody.
Thanks for coming to this primer. I'm
really excited to be here. Um, and thank
you for the wonderful introduction. So,
who here studies germline mutations?
Show of hands. Most people, anyone
studies somatic mutations?
What? Okay, I'm excited. I have some
family here. So, today my goal is going
to be to tell you how not just germline
mutations impact human health, but also
somatic mutations. So what I've got up
here is a diagram of how many cells can
be impacted by a sematic mutation
depending on when they happen during
development. So there's two main ways
that we're going to start out talking
about how sematic mutations can have an
impact. And one way is if they happen
really early on in development. So we
start out as a zygote. We have one copy
of the genome. We replicate that DNA
over and over and over and over again.
And we mostly do a very very good job.
But we're not perfect. So if we have a
mistake that happens soon after
fertilization before gastrolation, we
might introduce a sematic mutation
that's present in the brain, in the
lungs, and the hearts. If however it
happens later, maybe around the
formation of the neural tube, then we'll
have a sematic mutation that's just
present in the brain. And as we go on
through the weeks of development, we
might have a sematic mutation that would
only impact one hemisphere or part of
one hemisphere or maybe even just a
focal region of the brain. So what I'm
showing you here is that sematic
mutations during development impact more
cells the earlier they happen. The other
way that sematic mutations can have a
big impact,
but point it this way.
Oh.
Oh, just click it.
Yeah.
Oh, it's not even clicking here either.
>> See if I can click around. If I do that
and then I do this. Here we are. Okay,
we're good. So, I mentioned
developmental sematic mutations. The
more popular example of sematic
mutations is in tumors. And this is
really illustrative of the second way
that sematic mutations can have a really
big impact. So we're familiar with the
idea that we could have a tumor
initiation mutation in a regular cell
that increases its ability to
proliferate quickly. And as that
massively proliferative cell continues
proliferating, it will accumulate
additional mutations, some of which are
also driver mutations that increase its
proliferative capacity further. So what
we're seeing in this graph here is that
over time on the x-axis, the cell
accumulates more mutations and those
mutations that increase its ability to
proliferate form larger clones.
So we have this idea that in development
sematic mutations can have an impact by
happening earlier and we can also have
impactful sematic mutations if they
increase the ability of a cell to
proliferate.
But what about sematic mutations that
don't cause cancer? Right? We're pretty
familiar with this idea that cancer is
bad for our health and that a cell
proliferating out of control is a
concern. But are there other cases where
sematic mutations can impact the
function of our bodily systems? And to
get into how our lab started studying
this question, I'm going to give you a
little quick history lesson of what our
lab has done. So our lab's been around
for a while. This is like ye old recipe
for a paper in the Walsh lab, right?
We're very interested in how the brain
is formed and also malf forations. So
what we classically will do is we'll
identify patients who have a specific
brain malf for and then we'll look in
the DNA by looking at blood consented to
be used from that patient and we'll look
for a mutation that's suspicious put
that mutation either into cells or into
a mouse or even a ferret if we need a
folded brain to study it and we'll try
to create a mechanistic model. So we've
been doing this for a long time and I'm
going to give you just one example to
illustrate our point here on a paper
that I was actually able to contribute
to. So this is poly micro gyria. If we
know our Latin roots, we can figure out
that this means many small folds. So
there's supposed to be a bunch of folds
in our brain to increase surface area
and contact between the neurons. But
what happens in these individuals is
there are too many folds. And because
there's so many of them, they're all
very small. And these individuals have
reduced intellectual capacity along with
other cognitive symptoms.
So we did what we said we would do and
we looked in these individuals. We
looked in their blood and we found some
suspicious variants in a gene called
TM161B.
So you look at the family tree, you look
at the pedigree, you see who has
polyicrogya,
who has these mutations, you see it all
is concordant with this idea that
variance in this gene might be causing
this disease. And then we go and put
this mutation into a mouse and we look
at the brain to see if there's anything
suspicious. And to skip to the punch
line, we found something very
interesting.
So this is what the apical surface of
the developing mouse brain might look
like if you take a serial electron
microraph. And you see these antennaike
structures sticking out out of all of
these cells. And they look like antennas
because they pretty much are antennas.
These are primary psyia and their job is
to detect morphagens that tell the cell
what to develop into. So if there's some
kind of gradient, for example, Sonic
Hedgehog, this organel is going to
detect that. [clears throat] And when we
mutate T-M161B,
those cellular antenna are all kinds of
messed up. They're blebed out here.
There's lots of debris floating around.
And this is consistent with the idea
that this gene and mutations in it are
important for how the brain develops.
So this is just one example of an
example we found of a brain malf for a
patient variant and a mechanistic model.
We've done this many many times across
many different classes of genes. We've
looked at genes that regulate neural
stem cell proliferation, neuronal
migration, differentiation, and even
neuronal function. And all using this
same pipeline of looking at a brain malf
for sequencing the DNA found in the
blood and then modeling it in the
appropriate system. And you could
probably guess that it did not always go
so smoothly. And that's when the focus
of our lab started to evolve a little
bit. We thought we could do the same
thing with another brain malf for hemi
megalen.
And we can play with the Latin roots
again and see that what we're talking
about here is half of the brain is too
big. You see on the right side here we
have our nice cortical folds. On the
left side it's all bulging out. It's
pressing up against the skull. This is
hemgal and sephilate.
And we did the normal thing. We went
into the blood of some patients and we
sequenced looking for exonic mutations
that might be suspicious and we didn't
find any,
at least not in the blood. And we're
geneticists, so we understand that
genetics are indeed the cause of
absolutely everything. So this doesn't
make any sense, right? This has to be
some kind of genetic cause. So we dug a
little bit deeper and instead of looking
at the blood in the and the DNA in the
blood I should say we looked at the DNA
in the brain and that's when we started
to see something interesting.
So this is a very old style plot. This
is a Sanger sequencing plot of the part
of the gene AKT3 which is in the mtor
pathway where we found something
suspicious. So we see these peaks here
indicating that the sequence of this
gene is what we expect it to be. But in
this particular location, we don't see
one peak in this site. We see two
indicating that in the brain there are
some cells with the mutation. This
adinine residue is not what we expect to
see in the sequence of this gene.
So if we look at the blood, this is
where we look first. We don't see this
mutation. It's just the guanine residue.
And in the brain, we have two different
clones. 17% of the clones have this
adinine residue. The rest of them have
the correct guanine residue.
So now we have some evidence that it's
not a germline mutation associated with
hemalincense.
It's a sematic mutation just impacting
part of the brain.
And this makes sense if you think about
this image again, right? When we see
hemiggal and sephille, we don't see the
whole brain affected. We just see part
of it. So in this case, we have a
mutation that probably occurred sometime
around here during cortical neurogenesis
and ended up impacting just parts of the
brain. It's now understood that
hemalincense is a disease whereas you
have a larger mutational load. you have
a larger part of the re of the brain in
um affected I should say. So we have a
later mutation the mutational load is
going to be low the amount of the brain
affected is going to be low and then as
you get earlier and earlier mutations in
genes like AKT3 you have a larger
portion of the brain affected
and it's not just hemgalencil
that's like this. This is called
Proteius syndrome. It's literally a one
ina- million disease. It's very
difficult to diagnose because it's so
rare. But it is also a disease caused by
sematic mutation E17K specifically also
in an AKT gene in the mTor pathway. So
you could see here that this individual
unfortunately had some of these sematic
mutations in some bone and we see a
massive overgrowth of the jaw and even
the nose area. But depending on where
this mutation happens, these might be in
the feet, these might be in the hands,
it could be anywhere in the body. But in
general, we see that this pattern of
sematic mutations impacting health when
they happen during development is
consistent across a few different
examples.
So one question you might have is, okay,
if I made it all the way through the
process of development, right, I am a
fully grown adult now. I'm done building
my brain. and all those neurons are
ready to go. Am I safe? The answer is
no. So, it's not just cancer either, but
there are also sematic mutations that
can build up in proliferative cells in
the body. So, what I'm going to tell you
about now is clonal hematopoesis of
indeterminate potential or chip
mutations.
So when we're talking about clonal, what
we're saying is that these mutations
ultimately become part of a larger group
of cells that all harbor the mutation
because they're proliferative. We're
talking about hematopoesis, so we're
talking about blood stem cells. And then
indeterminate potential is the key word
here. So these mutations do have an
effect on growth, but they're not
immediately causing cancer. their
potential for proliferation is
indeterminate.
Right? So we have blood stem cells. We
have a nice pool of blood stem cells to
regenerate all the blood cells that we
need for our body. As aging progresses,
we may have the formation of a chip
mutation shown in purple here, right? Or
a non-chip mutation shown in brown. And
then those cells with the chip mutation
will become a larger proportion of the
cells as time goes on. They have an
increased ability to proliferate. They
start to out compete. So this makes
sense in a theoretical context. But how
important is this, right? How many
people have chip? And it turns out it's
about 10% of the people over age 70 have
this in their blood. So this is
something that impacts a lot of people.
A lot of people have chip mutations
ready to go right now in their blood.
And the question is what happens?
So just to skip to the bottom right, the
first thing we think of is cancer. And
that does happen more frequently in
individuals with CHIP, but it's less
than 1% per year. That's not the main
outcome of people having chip mutations.
the more um important risk is in heart
failure, thrombosis and accelerated
atherosclerosis.
Individuals with CHIP have a 40%
increase in risk for diagnosis of
cardiovascular disease.
So how does that happen? Right? The
thinking is that if we have some kind of
mutagenic events leading to a clonal
expansion and a chip mutation that those
cells with the chip mutation, especially
when they form a larger clone, are more
likely to cause inflammation. And
inflammation can be bad for a lot of
different reasons, but especially for
the function of the heart and for
clogging of important arteries.
So if you look at individuals with chip
mutations, not just those with heart
failure, but those without any coronary
heart disease, we see that the
calcification
of coronary artery is worse in those
individuals with CHIP.
So yes, we have increased risk for
coronary heart disease, but we also have
increased
calcification of the coronary artery
even when it doesn't lead to coronary
heart disease.
So these cells with the chip mutation
are leading to some kind of process
that's increasing risk for heart disease
without necessarily causing a cancer.
So we're talking about a blood mutation.
Blood mutation impacting heart function
I guess makes some sense, right? But
could these mutations also have further
reaching effects? And our lab is very
interested in the brain as I brought up
before. So we wondered whether chip
mutations might be associated with a
neurological disease associated with
aging Alzheimer's disease.
So if we look in the brain and we
specifically look for chip mutations,
all of these genes here, oop sorry,
all of these mutations are chip genes.
We look at Alzheimer's disease
individuals and aged controls. We see
that they're more prevalent in
Alzheimer's disease.
Each one of these columns is an
individual and all these rows are
different genes with chip mutations. So
we see some Alzheimer's individuals have
multiple chip mutations detected. A lot
of them have at least one. And these
percentages when you compare across the
different rows, we show that there are
more mutations in those with Alzheimer's
disease than the controls. They're not
unique to Alzheimer's, but they're more
common in those who do have Alzheimer's.
So this is something that happens in the
blood associated with a neurological
condition. So how does that make any
sense? Isn't the brain supposed to be a
privileged space where they only have
their own cells and the blood doesn't
necessarily get there? Right? An
important thing to consider here is that
Alzheimer's disease is associated with
some infiltration of blood derived
macrofasages into the brain and also
there is a similar group of cells to
hematopoetic stem cells in terms of
microga in the brain itself. So there's
kind of two hypotheses we have for what
might be going on here.
In the normal brain, we have microg GA
that are the resident immune cells of
the brain. They can randomly mutate. We
don't have a chip mutations. This would
lead to normal aging. But if we do have
chip mutations, maybe as a result of
some inflammatory process, maybe some
towangles accumulating or we might have
infiltration of blood derived
macrofasages with chip mutations. Both
of those events could lead to a
population of cells in the brain with
chip mutations that could lead to
increased inflammation. So there's a
couple different possibilities for how
chip mutations, whether they're in the
blood or whether they're in the
microglea of the brain, could lead to
increased activity of microglea
inflammation and potentially
neurodeeneration.
Folks who study Alzheimer's disease know
a lot of those genes associated germline
mutations in terms of Alzheimer's
disease have to do with immune activity.
So this would be consistent with the
idea that Alzheimer's disease has to do
with immune function.
So,
we've talked about a couple of different
ways that sematic mutations can be
important. We've talked about ways that
germline mutations can be important,
too. So, now I'm going to start to
categorize these, and we're going to
talk about a third type of mutations and
how they can impact human health. So, in
a germline mutation, all of the cells of
the body have it. And for whatever
reason, it's more impactful on one part
of the body than another. We talked
about TM161B having this very important
impact on brain development. We also
talked about examples where the mutation
isn't present in every single cell. It
happens at some point during development
or maybe it happens after development.
But in any case, it's just a group of
cells that are related to each other
clonally that harbor the sematic
mutation. In this case, we see neurons
shown with the red sematic mutation and
intestinal cells shown with the green
sematic mutation.
But there's also another possibility.
Cells that are done proliferating,
they're terminally differentiated, such
as neurons in the brain, can still
accumulate sematic mutations, right?
These we would term private sematic
mutations. They're just in individual
cells.
But you know, there's like this this
phrase that people like to say, if a
tree falls in a forest and no one is
around to hear it, does it make a sound?
Right? We could similarly ask if a cell
acquires a mutation that doesn't
increase its proliferation, does anybody
notice? Does anybody care? Right? How do
we detect that? It's an interesting
question, but how do we ultimately
detect it when all the mutations I've
described to you so far have an effect
on proliferation that allows us to
notice them?
So to address this, Alex Kagan, who now
has his own group, did something very
clever.
So these here on the left are H& stains
of the colarctal crypts. So all of these
here are like the villi that stick out
into the middle of the intestine and the
colon in order to pick up nutrients and
water. They're constantly being
regenerated and replaced because they
suffer a lot of damage. But shown here
outlined in these dotted lines are
individual crips. These are just the
individual pieces sticking out.
And the reason they're special is that
each of these crypts derives from just
one stem cell.
One stem cell out of many that live in
this pool here in the inner intestine is
going to give rise to one crypt.
So that means that if we sequence just
one crypt, we can get an idea for the
mutations that were in that original one
stem cell.
So this is going to allow Alex Kagan to
ask two important questions. The first
is do individual stem cells in the
intestine accumulate mutations over
time? Do older individuals have more
mutations in their stem cells than young
individuals? And the second which you
might be able to guess from the fact
that we have four different mammals
pictured here in terms of these
intestinal crypt examples is whether
this age related accumulation of sematic
mutations has to do with lifespan.
So in this study we're going to look at
mice which live 2 years and humans which
live 80 years.
If sematic mutations are just a function
of time, then the old humans are going
to have by far the most sematic
mutations in the study because the
humans live the longest, right? But if
instead sematic mutations accumulate as
a function of lifespan, then a 2year-old
mouse is going to have just as many
sematic mutations as an 80year-old
human, meaning that the yearly sematic
mutation accumulation rate is going to
be much, much higher.
And it turns out it's the second option.
So here we have on a log scale we have
uh mean mutation rate per year. We have
mouse here up at 800 per year because
they only live 2 years. And then humans
way down here at much less living about
80 years. And all of these different
mammals that were also tested that
follow the same idea. Increased lifespan
means decrease the maniput mutation rate
per year. And that's of course this is
all correlative, but it's awfully
suspicious. Why go to the effort to
increase your DNA repair capacity so
much for no reason? Perhaps it has
something to do with lifespan,
maintaining a relatively high integrity
genome in these intestinal stem cells.
So, one of the things that we can do now
when we have the mutational profile of
an individual cell, instead of just
talking about one really impactful
sematic mutation that increases growth,
we're talking about a whole lot of
mutations, hundreds of mutations, maybe
even thousands of mutations, which
allows us to think about where these
mutations are happening to give us a
sense for mutational processes that
might lead to the formation of these
mutations. Now that we have so many, we
can start to categorize them and look
for patterns. And one of the important
ways we look for patterns is we look at
how what how each base changes. So which
base is changing to which base and also
the genomic context
and the way we look at that is a 96
profile.
So what I've got here is the six
different types of mutations that can
happen. We have cytosine to adinine
mutation, cytosine to guanine, and so on
and so forth. You'll notice that I have
cytosine to adinine, but I don't have
guanine to thymine. The reason for that
is, at least for now, we're only
interested in double stranded mutations.
So every C to A mutation is also a GT
mutation and so on and so forth.
So plotted here is the mutation fraction
on the x-axis broken down within each of
these six groups is called the tri
nucleotide context. So it turns out that
a lot of the sematic mutational
processes that we know understand have
unique patterns that have to do not just
with the base change but with the
neighboring bases.
So we could see here that in this
mutational process, this was extracted
from the data in that intestinal crypt
study that I showed you earlier. We see
these four towers poking out above all
the rest of the mutations that are
possible.
And in case this is difficult to see,
I'm going to give it away to you and say
that these are all at CPG sites. So
these aren't just C tot mutations in
general. There's C to C mutations when
that C is right next to a guani.
And folks who study methylation might
already know where I'm going with this.
It turns out that this is SPS1.
This is the result of a sematic
mutational process whereby spontaneous
damination of specifically
fivemethyctosine
leads to a misrecognition
during DNA replication where that
original fivemethyl cytosine looks like
a thymine and we get a mutation.
So a critical thing to note about this
somatic mutational process, this
signature SPS1 is that this accumulates
in fast proliferating cells because I
mentioned the process the spontaneous
damination and the misrecognition that
requires DNA replication. If a
spontaneous damination happens in a
non-replicative cell, this mutation
doesn't occur because you need the DNA
replication machinery to make the
mistake to even see it at all.
By contrast, I'm going to tell you about
just one other SPS signature called
SPS5.
So this signature, we see it's a little
bit more balanced across all the
different groups. This mutational
mechanism is not currently well
understood, but we see that it
accumulates even in cells that are done
dividing. So whatever is happening here,
it probably doesn't require DNA
replication because it accumulates in
cells that are terminally
differentiated.
So I'm just telling you about SPS1 and
SPS5 for now. But in this cosmic
database, this catalog of sematic
mutations and cancer database, there are
many dozens more of these sematic
mutation signatures.
So if we go back to our intestinal
crypts, one thing we can do with this
data now is we could extract signatures
and see which of these mutational
signatures is really driving this age
related accumulation of mutations. And
it turns out it's quite clear which is
doing most of the work. It's SPS1.
These other two signatures did not match
as well to specific SPS signatures and
were reported as just SPS and SPSC. but
one very clearly matched on to SPS1 and
that's the one doing a whole lot of the
work in terms of accumulating sematic
mutations and this makes sense right
because those intestinal stem cells have
to keep dividing they have to keep
making more and more of those crypts as
they're destroyed throughout their
function so lots of proliferation lots
of SPS1
so
what we can wonder now we've have
improved in technology. We don't need to
be as clever as Alex Kagan do this thing
with the crypts. Now we can study
individual cells and just amplify their
whole genome and do the same question.
Look at individual cells like postmotic
neurons and say are they also
accumulating some mutations with age and
as it turns out they are as well. So
these each one of these dots is a
singular neuron from the prefrontal
cortex of a pervison and we see that
there are more sematic mutations in aged
individuals
and these [clears throat] happen despite
being postic. All of this time here from
0 to 90 I guess is not time that the
neurons spend dividing but just time
they spend existing and nonetheless
accumulating sematic mutations.
We can also look at disease. In this
case, we have human samples. We could
think about what might impact sematic
mutation rates besides age. And here we
have two examples of DNA repair
deficiencies. This is cockine syndrome
and zerodmap pigmentotosum. And if we
normalize for age, even when we
normalize for age, the cockine syndrome
individuals, the XP individuals both
have more sematic mutations than the
neurotypical individuals.
So we see that DNA damage repair has
something to do with accumulation of
semantic mutations. We see that when we
have diseases where it's impacted that
also impacts sematic mutations.
And once again we can do our signature
analysis.
So we extract two signatures. This time
we find one signature A which is a lot
like SPS5 and signature B which is a lot
like SPS1.
And then we could do the same test.
Which of these processes is driving the
age related accumulation of sematic
mutations? And relative to the
intestinal crypts, we get the opposite
results. So signature A, which is a lot
like SPS5,
this one is doing a lot of the work. So
this is all making sense to us. The
sematic mutational signature associated
with post-motic cells accumulating
mutations is what's driving this age-
related accumulation in neurons. And
this is true in the prefrontal cortex.
It's true in the dentate gyrus. It's
true in our cocaine syndrome and zero
pigmentotosive individuals. We see this
across groups. This linear accumulation
by contrast SPS1 we don't see so much of
an accumulation over time.
There is evidence for SPS1 here because
while those neurons aren't dividing
during our lives, they do have a history
of cell division. So there is the
capacity for neurons to have SPS1
related sematic mutations, they're just
associated with developments and
presumably don't change over our lives.
It only goes up during our brains
development.
But you know, when we're looking at
disease, right, we kind of picked some
lowhanging fruit here, right? Right? We
looked at a DNA damage associated
disease, a mutation in the DNA damage
repair system. We saw more mutations.
That kind of makes sense, right? That's
not that surprising. So, we wanted to go
back again to Alzheimer's disease. And
here we saw a similar phenomenon. So,
here we have neurons from the prefrontal
cortex and the hippocampus in both
control and Alzheimer's disease. And we
see age related accumulation in both.
But in this red line, you can see that
the Alzheimer's diseases individuals
have more mutations than their
neurotypical counterparts. On the right
side, we can see that if you normalize
for age and just do a head-to-head
comparison, we see on average
Alzheimer's disease neurons have more
mutations.
And for those of you wondering what the
reduction in lifespan is in Alzheimer's
disease, typically it's there's a lot of
variability to this, but Alzheimer's
disease can be diagnosed an individual
lives somewhere between 3 and 12 years.
There's a reduction in lifespan of
somewhere in that range. And that's
roughly consistent with the increase in
sematic mutations that we see here in
Alzheimer's disease versus age matched
control. Once again giving us the idea
that the sematic mutation rate in
individual cells might have something to
do with our lifespan.
So we've done a couple of different
things now. We've looked at DNA damage
deficiency. We've looked at a
neurodeenerative disease in terms of
Alzheimer's. But Alzheimer's disease,
we're still not quite sure for a lot of
the cases what the cause is. What if we
could look at something where we know
the cause? a neurodeenerative disease
where we understand the cause underlying
the neurodeeneration.
So we looked at chronic traumatic
encphylopathy.
Some of you may have heard of this. It
gets some attention in the media. This
is often diagnosed in individuals who
participate in the military, individuals
who play contact sports such as American
football and boxing. Right? Chronic
traumatic encphylopathy is neuro
degeneration that happens after
repetitive head injury.
So this allows us to do a very
interesting experiment. We can look at
control individuals shown in the dark
blue and see a nice accumulation over
time of sematic mutations. We could look
at those individuals with CTE shown in
the red and see once again more sematic
mutations. But we can additionally look
at an RHI group. So this is those
individuals who have repetitive head
injury but were not diagnosed with CTE.
So it's not
just repetitive head injury that causes
sematic mutations. It have to have both.
You have to have the neurodeeneration
and the repetitive head injury to be at
a greater risk of accumulating sematic
mutations. Those RHI individuals have a
relatively normal amount of sematic
mutations. It's only those with CTE that
have more sematic mutations.
So now we're really getting through a
whole lot of different brain conditions
that have to do with neurodeeneration,
aging, DNA repair, right? And seeing
that private sematic mutations can be
important too.
So I've told you about a few different
sematic mutational processes now, right?
We started talking about germline
mutations when I told you about TMM
161B. I told you about how we discovered
this mutation by looking in the blood of
the individuals. Presumably all the
cells in the body have this mutation and
then for whatever reason this mutation
specifically impacts the brain. But we
can also have more targeted effects. We
talked about how in hemgalencily
it's a developmental sematic mutation
something that impacts only part of the
brain that leads to this disease. We
know that because the mutation is only
present in some parts of the brain. It's
not in the blood and the brain is what's
affected.
And finally, we talked about
accumulation of private sematic
mutations. So, we talked about how that
has to do with lifespan across lots of
different mammals. We talked about how
it has to do with disease as well as
aging in humans. And it's not just DNA
damage repair machinery that's
different. It's also other neurological
diseases that aren't directly associated
with DNA damage repair or sematic
mutational processes.
So, I've hope I've convinced you that
sematic mutations can have a big impact
on our health even if it's not cancer.
And I'm going to thank like my lab. This
is where I learned all of my the
semantic mutational stuff. This is all
of us celebrating all the postocs who
are moving on to bigger and better
things. Right? These are my funding
sources up here. And I got the I had the
pleasure of working with a lot of these
individuals. I haven't worked with all
of them, but they're all first authors
on the papers that I talked about today.
And I'd be really excited to answer any
questions that you have.
That was fantastic. Um, if you have a
question, please come up to the
microphones in the middle of the room.
Um okay I will start. Um I'm wondering
how much this impacts uh organs or
diseases that you didn't mention. For
example, I study kidneys.
>> Should I be interested in somatic
mutations or is it like does someone
look into this and there was nothing
there or is it unexplored space for
other organs?
>> That's a great question. So it kind of
feels like sometimes in the Walsh side
we just pick a random disease and
there's going to be sematic mutations
there, right? But there is a process we
have for thinking about what's more
likely to have a sematic mutational
process as the root. The brain is an
especially good candidate because all
those neurons are postmotic. So when we
have the development of the brain, if
there are sematic mutations that occur,
those sematic mutations persist forever
even if they don't cause a proliferative
advantage. Presumably in another system
where there's more turnover of the
cells, if there's a damaging sematic
mutation, that cell might just be
replaced by something else. So in
general, if we have some kind of, you
know, if we go back to like some of
these examples, hemaggalinsphily is in
hindsight a very good example of
something that might have a sematic
mutational process associated with it
because it has a defined region of the
organ that's affected and it's has it's
full of postmotic cells. So thinking
about other organ systems, there are
definitely other examples that exist. We
talked about proteus syndrome which is
theoretically happen anywhere, right?
But one of the things we look for to be
suspicious about sematic mutations is if
a defined region of the organ is more
affected than other parts of the organ.
Awesome.
>> This is Pam. Um I have a question. Well,
I have two questions. Um the first is
for people with like CTE for example or
some one of these other brain conditions
with more sematic varants. Um do you see
can you see a signature of that in the
blood at all or is it really specific
only to just wondering if if like um
yeah you probably wouldn't see in the
blood but I'm just asking. And then
another question is do you have an
understanding of what the mechanism is
of how like increased trauma would lead
to more sematic varants?
>> Yeah. Okay. That's these are fantastic
questions. The first question is about
whether there are also more sematic
mutations in the blood of individuals
with CTE. So the first thing I'm going
to say is no. We didn't check. So we
don't know. But we would hypothesize
that there wouldn't be because we're not
just looking generally at the brain when
we're looking at that sematic mutation
accumulation. We're looking specifically
at the neurons. So those neurons are
going to be somewhat special. They're
all postmotic. They live in the brain
forever. If we by contrast saw mutations
that we thought were happening in the ga
of the brain, that might be something
that we thought would also apply to
other parts of the body. But in this
case, we have an event that's specific
to the head terms of repetitive head
injury. we're specifically seeing this
mutational process in the neurons. So I
would guess there probably isn't a
increase in mutations in the blood but
we didn't check. The other thing is like
how do we think these mutations might be
happening. So there's various um
symptoms associated with CTE right you
look at the brains of the individuals
you look at the pathology we can see
that there are areas of the brain that
degenerate faster than others there's a
lot of impact that happens that could
affect the folds of the brain
specifically there some pathology that
suggests souls might be especially
affected for example ultimately it's
very difficult to tell um model organism
research on CTE is still just kind of
getting rolling it's very difficult to
do a lot this work because CTE can also
only be diagnosed at death. So unlike
Alzheimer's disease, we can't deal with
living individuals that have the
condition.
>> Thanks for the great talk. Um my
question was a little bit kind of the
same as the last question there. Um uh
asking about the mechanism that you
suspect in CTE uh related to I guess
some repair processes after injury. Um
but I guess I could continue that and
say does that uh sort of uh questions
about the mechanism say something then
about the mechanism of uh Alzheimer's
disease of how you get these sematic
mutations.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So these are both
neurodeenerative diseases, right? They
both have increased sematic mutations in
the neurons, right? I think that one of
the things that we could say sort of
putting both studies together is that we
may have a commonality between them that
neurodeenerative diseases may have
something in common. We see some um
sematic mutation signatures that are
similar between the two. A lot of the
baseline SPS5 SPS1 signatures are
similar but there are other mutational
signatures that are different. So I
think putting them together I think
there's still a lot more work that has
to be done to get increasingly
mechanistic. But I think that what I
would surmise is that something that
damages the DNA or the ability of a cell
to repair its DNA more accurately is
going to have long lasting consequences
and potentially lead to some increased
death of neurons that can't be replaced
because those are the cells post my
talk.
I'm wondering if you could briefly touch
on the um like the computational
challenges in studying somatic mutations
especially when you're talking about the
cells that aren't proliferating and they
have like how many reads like how do you
measure that?
>> Yeah. No, that's I I decided not to
touch on that at all in this
presentation because that could be like
a whole four-hour long talk. Um just
touching on some of the challenges you
have to deal with. I mentioned that, you
know, Alex Kagan had the privilege of
looking at a whole group of cells that
presumably all harbor a mutation. That
makes your life much easier. You have
many, many copies presumably of the
mutation that exist in that sample. So,
you get a lot of cracks at it. By
contrast, if you have to amplify the
genome of just one cell, you have to be
really, really confident that you're
doing it right. So, there's two kind of
broad strategies I can tell you about
for how to do a single cell whole genome
sequencing experiment. One of them
involves getting the amplification to be
very reliable. The other one involves
tagging the two different strands
separately. So you could check your
work. If you find a mutation on one
strand, you check the complimentary
strand and see if you agree. So in the
first strategy, you try to amplify the
DNA in such a way that you're not
propagating error. So you look at your
template DNA, your original genomic DNA,
and you set up your chemistry so that
you only amplify off of that template
rather than amplifying off of the
amplification of the previous round of
PCR. That helps a whole lot. And you can
check your work by looking at known
germline mutations. So you could see, am
I detecting all the germline mutations I
expect to detect? do the mutations I see
next to the germline mutations match up
in terms of what I expect in terms of
hetererozygous snips and stuff like
that. The other way you think about it
is strand tagging. So strand tagging
means that at that first step when you
separate the strands of DNA you tag them
with a primer so that when you call
every single mutation you can then
computationally check to see if on the
opposite strand of DNA you agree. A lots
of the mutations associated with library
prep are going to be on single strands
rather than both strands, especially if
they're processed separately. So tagging
the two different strands called duplex
sequencing is going to give you a really
big boost in your sensitivity and
accuracy.
>> Great. And then um we have one more. Um,
I was uh we're wondering if the
proliferation or turnover of the cells
is going to impact how many summatic
mutations it gets. I'm wondering if
there's other characteristics of cells
that make them more or less susceptible.
Maybe variation in the DNA repair
mechanisms and certain cell types.
>> Yeah. Yeah, that's a fantastic question.
So, it's definitely true that cells that
proliferate faster are going to be more
prone to accumulating sematic mutations.
We see that across systems. We also see
that different cell types accumulate
sematic mutations at different rates. So
the lowest rate of accumulation of
sematic mutations in any human cell
types have been tested so far is
something you might expect. It's the
germ cells. Sperm is the gold standard
for the lowest accumulation of sematic
mutations because those mutations are
going to be passed on to the next
generation. Right? We need to keep that
DNA very very perfect if we can. Neurons
have about half of the accumulation of
sematic mutations over time as do
intestinal crypt cells. So different
cell types definitely have a different
amount of prioritization in terms of DNA
repair and keeping the DNA integrity
high. And that's going to depend on
their function, how long lived they are,
and lots of other factors. And I think
we're just getting started about like
really rigorously profiling exactly
which cells have what kind of capacity
for DNA repair.
questions in the room.
All right, great. We'll thank our
speaker one more time.