Uh so hello my name is Maria. I'm a
second year postto fellow uh with the
Smith Center and let me introduce you
Dr. Richard Bono. Richard Ced focuses on
developing who is sorry the vice
president of machine learning for drug
discovery at gintech computational
science. Richard's research focuses on
developing machine learning methods to
power drug discovery. In particular, he
is focused on biomolecular structure and
structure function relationships that
underin drug rank discovery. His work
integrates structure biology approaches
biioinformatics, chemiratics and natural
language processing to derive new hybrid
methods for design. Richard received his
a PhD from University of Washington
prior to his role at Gintech. He was the
director of New York University Center
for Data Science. Richard, we're all
excited for your talk and the floor is
yours. Thanks very much for the invite
and the introduction. Uh today I'm going
to keep this a little bit high level but
we'll dive into just a few things around
active learning and a few things around
generation and sampling. But um the
first thing I want to say is that the
the title here beyond the funnel um you
know the the spirit of this talk is is
to sort of show you some of the efforts
that we carry out at GenEnt to integrate
machine learning into drug discovery.
And some of those things that we have to
do are bookkeeping, some of them are
end-to-end integration in the machine
learning sense of the word and others
are process optimization. But the goal
is to try to find the places where we
take a huge numbers of years and and and
person hours of work and we condense
them to a single lead candidate or we
condense them to a single uh functional
hypothesis and therefore we make a place
where if we fail we don't really know
how to go back. And so we're really
going to talk today about end-to-end
integration with the hope that at any
given moment we always have a large
ensemble of leads, targets, hypotheses
so that we can uh be very fast and very
parallel instead of sequential when we
approach the drug discovery process. And
you know I'm somewhat new to this. Um
I'm part of uh the Genentech um uh
computational sciences uh unit. This was
one of the first times where
computational folks were were elevated
to VPs and SVPs at Genentech. And so I
think this is um part of Aviv Reg's
vision to make computation a real part
of drug discovery. Um I work with John
Marion and this new unit uh Genentech
computation sciences. So if you like uh
genes or cells or mechanisms, you know,
still reach out and talk to us if if
you're looking for things to do in this
area.
This is my unit and again you can I'll
I'll kind of go into where this fits in.
Um but at we were a preient design uh we
were a startup company for about seven
minutes and then we were I sent a note
to Aviv and the rest is history. Um
we're now a unit or a department at
Genentech that that's divided in these
ways. Um, so the the one of the some of
the divisions here are are somewhat
canonical or old-fashioned. And that
would be saying that we need someone to
cover each of the two major modalities.
And so Adams are atoms. All of the
target genes and mechanisms are all made
out of similar stuff in the human. But
the way that we make drugs is still very
ti very strongly tied to two of the
different major ways that we screen for
hits and synthesize the material. And so
even though we're very revolutionary um
we still um we still divide in this very
classical way. The rest of how we divide
things is to have a handful of uh folks
who have no mandate. They just wander
the halls in their in their bathroes
thinking about machine learning. This is
led by Kyongyang Cho who was involved
with the attention mechanism and
involved with a lot of really cool work
with Yosua in the beginning of this deep
learning revolution. Uh we also have
folks that are focused on infrastructure
and we divide them into engineering and
the large language model folks. Due to
the size of these models, they end up uh
thinking about engineering as much as
they think about science. And so we kind
of have the uh uh the theory and the
practice, the application and the theory
divided differently on different days.
Um and in the end we identify as
scientists and so we are always thinking
about technology and platforms but when
we actually dive into the individual
drug discovery projects it's always
quite a bit of fun and if I use the word
portfolio it it means um individual
targets that we're trying to
drug um so this is a picture uh that was
made u mostly by Sarah Mustafabi who is
who's our new vice president of
computational biology and translation.
Um, and I guess she's not that new.
She's about a year old now, which means
she's 5 minutes older than I am at
Genitech. But the idea here is that we
have this interloop or this molecule
making part of the machinery. Uh, we
have the target discovery and
prioritization part of the machinery,
but they use common infrastructure,
common larger uh, language models which
are the interface to this whole system.
So that as we're figuring out what
hypotheses, what targets, what pathways
we think are important to modulate for a
given disease, we are also uh in real
time seeing what what we could do to
modulate those genes at the sort of
composition of matter or molecule level.
And again, we've got some older
divisions and some newer, more
technologically uh motivated divisions
mixed in here. Um, we're really excited
about how we orchestrate this whole
system with larger machine learning
models. Today, I'll mostly give you a
large molecule drug discovery focused
introduction to what we do here. Um, and
you know, the key message really is is
the the utility of active learning, the
utility of using models to collect the
next sample. Um there's lots of other
moving parts but that's the vignette
that I'll drop into in in detail today
or you know in detail I guess talk
detail.
Um before I you know I start I'll just
kind of show this this picture which
shows you the the drugs or the the
medicines that have been approved and
that are on the market um and that
topped out in terms of sales. Um, now
again, we've got all sorts of things
that we know about these drugs from from
our our work as scholars, but also just
reading the newspaper. Um, and so
there's a lot of different mechanisms
here. There's a lot of really
interesting biology behind these drugs,
but what I want you to look at here is
just how wildly different the
composition of matter of all these
things are. So, we have peptides, but
then they have some really far out
chemistry to make them work, you know,
as far as clearance and the mechanism of
the drug over time. Um, we have
antibodies, bicepecific antibodies. We
have pieces of of viral capsids and
coats. We've got RNAs that then express
proteins and and different things that
are also very very very carefully
engineered. And so there's a huge amount
of bioengineering and chemical
engineering, you know, for the actual
manufacturer and process optimization of
these. And there's a lot of molecular
engineering that goes into all of these
things.
um a lot of them are antibodies but at
Genitech we're devoted to research along
many lines across many modalities and so
for every modality you see on this slide
we we have uh efforts at Genitech to to
optimize how machine learning can
improve uh the design of those
molecules and again we're going to drop
into lab in the loop for antibbody drug
discovery or antibbody based drug
discovery when we say antibbody we still
are doing lots of interesting things.
We're making them pH and ATP sensitive.
We're adding them into formats that have
multiple veilances and you know cross
linkers that have strange functions,
transport mechanisms like the brain
shuttle. But at some point we do have to
design uh the affinity part of that and
we have to do that in a context where
we're paying attention to all those
other properties.
Um, so these are the key ingredients I
think for any uh any recipe that uh that
that designs antibodies well and that
does so in a drug discovery context. And
so the first thing to notice is that the
this the key theme on this slide is this
loop. And you know we can say without um
inventing any new math or without
reading any nurips papers or anything
like that that it makes sense to collect
some data and anytime you collect data
if you can you should update your models
and some of that's engineering some of
that's moving data
around but once you have a model what
outputs from the model should you test
and so I encourage everyone to to really
think about active learning and model
driven experimental design is something
that works substantially better today
than it worked two years ago and and
really really like quite a bit better
than it worked 10 years ago. And there's
a couple of different high throughput
biology synthesis
um the way that sort of CRO's for making
DNA and proteins are structured. There's
a lot of things that are process
optimized or just high throughput
biology. There's a lot of other things
that are also uh technologies that
enable this that that are on the machine
learning side, but active learning to
power this is key. So when we're doing
this, when we're turning this cycle, we
might be making libraries. We might be
making plates. We might be doing things
that actually have expensive tests that
require animals. And there's very small
number of tests like that that are
allowable. But you should know how many
tests you can make and you should know
the, you know, the various elements of
error in the model. Tracking those
things, you could figure, you should
figure out not just what to test, but
how to diversify what you test. And then
the key thing that people don't really
think about that often is the bet size.
how many things you should you test
given the time delays, the cost of a
time delay and the overall cost of each
step here. And so that's something that
that can be done uh
today. Um obviously we need deep
predictive power for how we actually
generate these these antibodies and
we'll talk about that today. But I think
the actual generative AI that produces
denovo hits for proteins, we've all seen
that whether it's through media
narrative, whether it's through, you
know, reading the minutes of the Nobel
Prize or whether it's uh through um
actually following that field closely. I
think this is something that uh we have
a lot to contribute at Preient, but um
this is part of part of the story that I
think is told quite often. And so I'm
going to talk less about that today and
more about about this. Um and then the
last thing these are sort of more
controversial things things that where I
think the the story is still developing
but um at Genitech we really believe
that cross modality thinking is key and
so whenever we can actually have a unit
or team work on a simulation for small
large molecule and peptides cell
therapies we should do that as opposed
to have them really drill down into the
specifics of the screens or the modality
that they're they're thinking about. Um,
this is something that that I'll show a
few examples of. And then the last thing
I'll end the talk with just a little bit
of thoughts about how agents can be used
to orchestrate workflows and perhaps
allow some of this to run
autonomously. Um, but before we dive
into that, um, I just want to highlight
this key problem or this key formulation
of the active learning problem. Um,
there's lots of different ways to start
thinking about active learning, but one
of the ways to think of it is that with
generative AI that's efficient at
inference time. So, you amarize your
cost of of using and building this
model. You spend a huge amount of time
to train the model. And then after that,
there are lots of different ways you can
sample diverse sets of things from that
generative AI. And so, you have a nearly
limitless number of hypotheses about
things that would work. um proteins,
small molecules, um synthetic biology,
cell biology, uh setups. You know, we
are usually in cominatorial spaces where
the things that actually work, function,
that hit the TCP for a given project,
they're probably in in the very large
numbers of zeros
regime. Once we have that that core
generation, we then have to apply lots
and lots of filters. Can it be
manufactured? Does it will it stay in
the blood for a long time? Will it
aggravate the immune system? That
usually narrows things down, but we
still have error in the inference of
these multiple properties and we're
still starting on a, you know,
practically from a budget perspective,
infinite field. How do we then select
the subset that we want to submit for
testing? And you know, this is the core
concept that we often use when we think
about what are we going to do next in an
experimental design setting.
um is this idea of Pareto frontiers and
here I'm showing a a picture where we
have uh for example two properties one
would be yield and one would be affinity
and in this case these are real designs
for an antibody that we care about this
is I think you know interlucan 6 which
is something that we're uh it's a proof
for release we can talk about it I'll
show you some data for that one and so
the things that we should test should do
something novel or you know further from
the origin
with respect to both of these
properties. And ideally, we should test
the things that are at the frontier
here. And this makes sense and this can
be difficult to compute when you've got
lots of properties. But it's it's an
under control problem. And this is
slightly different from some of the
other key um principles behind
experimental design like deoptimality or
block random. If you read a lot of early
work in regression that might even be,
you know, might be so old it's difficult
to find. There's a lot of discussion
about experimental design from models
but a lot of it assumes uh you know iid
sort of independence of variables and
then a lot of it is also um you know
furiously difficult to compute when you
have a lot of data and a lot of
dimensions. But another you know really
really really key thing that I think
keeps us from using that that ancient
wisdom is just that everything that we
do in in living systems is really really
strongly dependent on each other. not
just in terms of the variables having
some correlation or some uh block block
diagonal structure or something that
breaks the math. The bigger problem is
just that they're dependent in a sort of
a life or death fashion. And so for
example, if we have an antibbody and I
am very excited about all sorts of
properties on its surface, but it
doesn't fold or express. And I don't
even know why it doesn't express. It
just doesn't express. I don't get any
yield. without being able to make the
thing, you certainly can't test anything
else. And then if it doesn't bind the
thing it's supposed
to, Yan Woo, who's a VP in charge of
antibbody engineering at Genitech, is
she's very devoted to thinking about lab
and loop and computation, but she is not
going to be able to convince her
scientists to do something with an
antibbody that doesn't bind because from
her perspective, it's dead, even if
there might be imunological or surface
properties that we want to test next.
And so this is this little tree, but
this tree is like a bush and the bush is
from a mathematical perspective burning.
It's a it's just a nightmare because
basically we've got, you know, millions
of things here, hundreds of things here,
you know, off we go. And so if we can
build Gen AI so that more bigger
fraction of things are binders, well,
that's great, but we never avoid this um
key problem. And the the paper that I
put this a little bit out of date here.
I think the paper that I would recommend
taking a peek at and then you know
reverse citation search will give you a
lot of other things that Natasha has
done but this is Natasha Tavasov
Sovska's uh entry into this space with
her one of her good friends Giwan Park.
uh the two of them figured out ways to
use vine copulas and some other
mathematical trips to take the
dependence tree of properties they might
measure then use that tree to figure out
ways uh to act like this even though the
reality is is interdependent like that.
And so that property dag work and the
paper bow tide are two things that
essentially let
us then get together with our 60 closest
friends in antibbody engineering and
actually try this um active learning uh
cycle to design
antibodies. And uh this is this is the
the the recent paper. The first author
is Nathan Frey. The last author uh is
Vladimir Gregorovich who's one of our
co-founders of Prussian along with
myself and Kyongyang Cho. Um this this
paper represents a whole lot of work. Um
but basically for many different
properties and for uh the six antibodies
that we were allowed uh to talk about in
this paper um because on the biology
side or for some other reason
partnership they were no longer uh
frontline projects. We were allowed to
talk about six uh uh antibbody design
efforts here. Um, we are allowed to talk
about most of the properties that were
involved in this. Um, but this is
essentially the the pipeline that we've
applied to all large molecule drug
discovery projects across the RO family.
Um, but here we're showing the results
for a handful of of projects where we
had design rounds and I think this is
again interlucan six. We had design
round one, two, three, four. And if we
believe this Pareto front or this active
learning is working, we should see that
our binding goes up and our expression
goes up. And our binding here is in uh
log of KD. And so uh as we go up here,
we're getting to 10 the minus 10 KD.
We're getting to um
100,000 etc. fold improvement in these
seeds. These plots at the top are the
distributions of therapeutic antibodies
for a handful of properties computed in
Charlotte Dean's therapeutic antibbody
profile or the tap program which is at
this point pretty much an industry
standard for filtering things before
testing. Um and then we also have BVLISA
here. This is back basil
virus. This is yeah basillus virus
eliza. So you basically rupture bacteria
and see whether or not that mess
interferes with a with the binding of
your antibbody. It's a really um it's a
proxy essentially for clearance in the
bloodstream. And so we showed that we
stabilize these properties, stabilize
these properties and improve the two
things that we tried to optimize
against. And again um the key thing here
is that over time over a small number of
designs we improve binding by a factor
of 100 for multiple antibodies and we
improve and diversify the set of
antibodies substantially for all of
these different targets. Um and these
are a handful of different uh families
that include well behaved folds membrane
proteins and and other things like that.
And again, you know, I'm just I'm
showing this one last time because uh
active learning and and model driven
experimental design is something I've
cared about for my whole career, but
it's not easy. It's really difficult.
People graduate, people move to their
next career phase. Grants start and
stop. And when you do things in biology,
it doesn't take minutes or weeks, it
takes it takes years. And so, it's
difficult to have multiple rounds and
really see whether or not you're model
driven or automatically model driven. uh
uh design works and I don't think it
works in every context but for molecular
design it seems to be an ideal
playground for experimenting with those
ideas.
Now I said that I wouldn't talk a lot
about um uh automated uh denovo design
of antibodies but it is something that
we have um we have up and running and we
have integrated with library design. And
the key thing here is to think through
what it means to have the ability to
paint an epitope and design antibodies.
And so the first thing that this helps
us do is to actually optimize and
diversify antibodies. So a lot of
times when we start projects we almost
always have a nanomol or binder to start
with and of course we could we could
compute these things computationally and
then iterate but genitech is really good
at making antibodies and has been for I
don't know however many years two too
many years to count greater than five
right and one year is is infinity in the
machine learning field right so um you
could of course identify binders that
bind different places. If you can use
denovo, you can actually diversify not
just the sequence, but you can actually
rationally choose different regions
around an epitope that you care about to
try to come up with new functions. Um,
the way that antibbody uh drugs and
medicines work is often that you bind
and you bring the complement pathway
that's hanging out in the constant
region and you induce cell killing. But
that is one of 15 different ways that
antibbody drugs work. They work through
aidity bringing receptors together. They
work uh targeting things. They work in
in just you know really numerous number
of of of mechanisms. Once you get to
multipecific formats playing around with
the epitope and figuring out what's the
exact geometry that optimizes the
structure function relationship
important to the disease is super
important.
Um, I think I just said complex formats,
but one of the things that we care quite
a bit about are the ability to engineer
or rationally engineer things where you
might have a targeting domain, a killing
domain, a T- cell recruiting domain, or
a receptor engaging domain. And so, um,
try and quattrapecific formats are
becoming actually somewhat routine. When
we hand those off to development
sciences and product development, they
almost always have liabilities. And so
the need to be substantially more um
active in designing complex formats is
something that's
important. The fact that this is fast I
guess is a the least uh exciting thing
intellectually but maybe the most
exciting thing from the process
optimization part. And then structure
activity hypothesis. Here this is the
idea again with binder identification.
If we're rational about the initial
design, then we also probably have a
good model of of what what's
happening. All right. So, that's another
key thing. We need denovo hit finding
not just to avoid screening and
immunizing animals, but to be rational
and to be uh model driven when we
design. Another key thing is we have to
figure out how to scale to lots and lots
of different um projects. And so here
this is um I'm switching gears to show
you a slide from my small molecule
group. And here we have this idea that
we have a large large number of things
um including um some things like potency
modeling that we build inhouse active
learning which is this sort of overall
sample selection. We also have things
that we uh use open access code or we
license code to do. But we have a large
number of technologies that we have to
apply to a large number of projects.
And the right way to put that into an
augmented design framework is something
that we think about a lot. And so I
don't I won't go into that in detail
today. But here we have issues of
interface, issues of the active learning
driving but still allowing the chemist
to override uh and other things like
that. And and this is something that's
been really successful at Genitech and
has led us to think about how far we can
push it. So beyond interface, can we
actually think about autonomous agents
and can we think about models uh that
have been trained in such a way that
they know the location uh and they have
good vector stores for all the data at
RO. RO is 125 years old and and and that
goes back to times where in Switzerland
there were union laws, you know, that
whatever your mother tongue was, you
were allowed to put that in your lab
notebook. And so the the lab notebooks
in RO are in a great number of
languages. They're handwritten. They're
hundred years old. So I just just from
like a kind of a liking machine learning
perspective, it's challenging and weird
enough that it could be fun. Um but we
need to build our own models for a
number of reasons. One is that we have
our own special data. It's not just the
internet and and a bunch of books. Um,
we we also need to know that whatever we
do, it can be compliant with regulatory
processes. The EU just passed a whole
bunch of laws about what can and can't
be done with machine learning, and a lot
of those are actually have specific
clauses that target machine learning.
Um, and then a lot of the things that we
do involve handing things off to
clinical trials. And so there has to be
some ability to put error estimates and
safety estimates on these things which I
think you need to be able to at least
see the parameters to do that. And so
Kyouongyong Cho and Steven Raw who's
formerly at Fizer put together a team to
build our own large language models. Um
this is something that's cross crossro
crosspillar and is also being sponsored
by Aviv and John Marion. Um but in the
beginning we started off just saying for
whatever reason we need uh to have
models that are distilled to the
smallest size possible that function in
ways that commodity large language
models work. And so we built large
language models. We worked with large
open access language models like the
llama herd. And we found the sort of
sweet spot for some of the tasks that
that were required from commercial down
to research.
Um the thing that we're excited about
now and the thing that I'll maybe take a
beat to discuss a little bit is this uh
this uh trend that I think is being
adopted widely across different
companies and different uh efforts to
build these models. We want things that
have deep expertise in vision and
molecules. This is important for
biology. This is important for molecular
design. We want agents that are trained
not just on the data but also have deep
tie-ins here, programmatic tie-ins. And
then lastly, we want uh models that were
trained and enriched either on the
architecture or the training subset side
to be good at reasoning. And uh we put
these things
together. Um we're really focused on
tool calling in the design space. And
our example or deep dive uh for
reasoning is uh safety. So can you look
at the literature and our internal data
and make hypotheses about compound and
um uh safety? Um, and here there's two
things. Some of it's about toxicology,
which has deep and ancient literature.
Um, some of it's about ontarget
toxicity. So, if you do the thing you do
and it seems to be safe in a mouse, will
it also be safe in a human? And the
answer there is about it's, you know,
it's no a third of the time and it can
be very surprising. And so, there's a
lot of a lot of work there in safety. Um
for multimodality
uh we're we're really thinking a lot
about the points where the green part
molecule design touch the uh the the
target discovery stuff that Sarah's
groups are working
on. Um we do have permission from the
lawyers to release most of these models
as open access models and so this won't
be this won't be top secret for much
longer. Um but uh we do have some models
that are trained on everything at RO and
other models that are trained with the
intent to release and you can imagine
that makes uh everyone nervous. So we're
working through that and uh you know
stay tuned if you're interested in in
playing with these models. Um overall
you know one of our
key takeaways here and I'm showing you
this this somewhat older model here.
This is updated a little bit but this
isn't our our frontline model at this
point. But if we look at models where
we've pushed really hard to distill them
down, they're very very small. They take
up, you know, hundth of the memory on
the GPU that the larger public models
take or the larger enterprise models
take. We're still able to um in a safety
context um build competitive models
without a huge amount of fine-tuning. um
in the context of um uh tool calling I
think this is a case where um just the
last year of work has shown huge amounts
of progress. These numbers even a year
ago for even the biggest enterprise
models were you know below 50%. Um we we
see that we're able to get up to, you
know, various um various uh correct
response for the next tool. Correct tool
request. And again, the correct tool
request is more about are the inputs and
outputs compatible. This is about
whether or not the user believes this.
This is actually something where there's
a like scale that the user uses to say
does did this make sense? And then tool
choice is again about not just
compatibility, but more compatibility
with the the objective for the next
phase in the workflow. And so we we
split these things up, but you can
imagine uh the work to build these two
plots was 70% metrics, 20% machine
learning, and whatever's left, you know,
messing around with our high performance
computing just to get the the darn model
to train in the first place. Um, when we
put this all together, we do have this
sort of user workflow tool interface uh
combinations and we've got something
that's actually getting uh fairly
fullfeatured for small and large
molecules and it's something that we're
we're very excited about. And so this is
a a slide that's far from comprehensive,
but it's showing a query and some ideas
for what the model has sort of pre
prepackaged. Moving through that, we get
questions about antibodies. We light up
a few tools. We can use rag to see what
was used for that inference and what
what we might also look at. We can rank
models and rank outputs, model outputs
to test things. And we can queue up uh
uh automation or experiments. Um and
then augmented design is something that
we love. It looks cool. It's fun to
make. You get these cool interfaces and
then the chemists and the biologists
don't really want it, but we're making
it anyways because, you know, we're
people, too. We want to have some fun
there.
Um, I think when it comes to these these
ideas of how we put all this together, I
feel really I wouldn't say comfortable,
but I feel like I know what to try next
on the active learning side. I feel like
when it comes to agents, there's as many
open questions as there are um next
steps. Uh, I think there's a lot of need
to continue sharing our data layers and
how we register models and encapsulate
tools. There's a lot of work that still
needs to be done there or a lot of
discussion. And then you know the key
issue for us is you know if you're
making a medicine people have workflows
but those workflows aren't people who
can make a medicine in a year. It takes
too many years and too many people. And
so do we embrace the long tale of all
the different methods people use or do
we start to use these efforts to
orchestrate things to also kind of clean
up things and ask people to use fewer or
more standardized subset of tools.
The answer to this might be that there's
a popular answer which is embrace the
long tail and there's a correct answer
which is ask people to change what they
do and we'll see where we get with that.
And that's it. Um I I'll stay on this
slide for for now and for questions.
Thanks. Uh I think we have time for a
couple of questions but not more.
Hi. Hello.
Okay. Here. Yes. Hello. Thank you. It's
very nice talk. So, my question is uh
you know you have this uh lab in the
loop uh generate data and uh predict
antibody and so on. So, uh what's a
relationship between the scale of the
data set and the performance of antibody
design? So how much data you need
basically? Yeah.
So there there's there are a lot of
extant antibodies and a lot of protein
sequences. Um and so
for the generative core like the
language model that suggests mutations
or is let's say the proposal
distribution generator the underlying
thing. I think right now we've seen that
increasing the scale of those models,
feeding them new protein sequences is
less important than how you balance, you
know, using ideas about evolution or the
tree of life, how you balance what goes
in there. Um, when it comes to affinity
and some of these properties, there are
still things like clearance in the
animal where we need proxy assays and we
need more data. and then everything in
between
affinity expression we're in a state
where our models are very predictive we
think things work but I think for the
core unsupervised generative models were
there and for a lot of these other
properties were actually working hard to
collect new data and so that's just the
the quantity and we we see that we could
use a lot of additional data for many of
the properties we care about um not the
core ones not binding not stability not
affinity um now the the the Subp part of
this question is how do you go about for
things like immunogenicity or clearance
or high concentration behavior. How do
you go about collecting new data and
there we have seen that the active
learning motivated uh collection data
collection is vastly more valuable than
random or historical data and and so the
the data we've collected over the last
two years is as valuable as the data
from the last 10 years for example. Also
a short question for I noticed there's
an anti-correlation between the yield
and the affinity for the antibody
design, right? There's anti-correlation.
I didn't notice that. But no, the higher
affinity has a lower yield.
Oh, you're talking about that PTO front
picture that I show. Yeah, that I think
that's one of those pictures where, you
know, my thesis advisor should have told
me that there were too many P, you know,
points on that plot and that they were
like landing on each other. Generally
speaking, um,
we could make things a lot more stable
and we would So, you're you're right in
one regard. There is that that
correlation. The most stable and the
best expressing proteins are very
unlikely to be the best binders. in the
best binders could involve all sorts of
hydrophobic and large loops that would
then be problems for those other things.
And so I think I think that
anti-correlation for the extremes of
those properties is probably, you know,
probably something we'd observe. And now
I don't know also if that's also a
trivial geometric result of how you draw
Pareto fronts. So we we should think
about that a little bit too. Yeah,
that's a good question.
Okay, let's thank the speaker again for
the amazing talk.