let me Define a system as a set of
pieces that have relationships which
performs a function what I need to add
to my definition of systems is that the
pieces and their relationships work to
produce some functionality or
performance that is greater than the
parts individually and I'm going to call
that emergence right now I'm showing
pile of sand and a funnel and I'm going
to ask what emerges when I put them
together Tim keeping emerges and I love
this example because these are two very
different objects that don't have a a
relationship now I have an hourglass and
I get timee keeping out of it emergence
is not always a positive this is
actually a picture of Katrina and when I
look at the storm that was Katrina plus
the levy system in New Orleans what I
have is an emergency emergence and
emergency have the same root word
because I'm combining two different
pieces and looking at a system that has
Behavior greater than the Su of its
parts for more MIT moments from MIT open
learning like subscribe or follow