So let me tell you about zero sum games.
Uh let me start off with the key
definition
and we're going to study what happens
under the simple definition. So first
let me tell you the abstraction and then
we'll do some examples to try and make
it concrete. So specifically, we'll be
interested in what's called a two-player
zero sum game.
And a two-player zero sum game has a few
components. So it's described by the
following things.
First of all, there's a row player.
A lot of times we'll call this player
Alice.
And Alice has m different strategies.
These are the moves that she's allowed
to make in the game we're playing.
There's a second player which is called
the column player.
And usually we call the column player
Bob.
These are just the standard conventions.
And Bob is going to have n strategies.
So already you can see that the game
looks different for the two players.
They have even different action spaces
of what they're allowed to make as a
move in the game. And the crucial thing
is the last component which tells us
what are the outcomes of the game. Who
pays who how much depending on what
strategies you play. So finally what we
have is we have an M byN matrix which is
called the payoff matrix.
And we'll call this C. And the way that
this matrix C works is that the entry CI
J is the amount that the row player i.e.
Alice
gets
in payment from
the column player.
if they play
I and J respectively.
So notice that the row player Alice has
M strategies and there are M rows in
this matrix. The column player Bob has n
strategies and there are n columns in
this matrix. So you should think of this
payoff matrix as being indexed by their
strategy set. Every choice of a strategy
for the row player just selects which
row we're interested in.
Every strategy for the column player
just selects which column we're
interested in. And then we look into
that entry in the matrix and that
describes the net payment from Bob to
Alice. That payment could be negative in
which case the money goes from Alice to
Bob. But in any case, right now in the
case of a zero sum game, we only have a
single payoff matrix that describes you
know what happens. And it's called a
zero- sum game because if you add up the
wins and losses of Alice and Bob, it's
zero. So of course you can consider more
general games and we'll talk more about
that towards the end, but this will be
our basic abstraction.
So let's see some examples to get some
intuition for this. There's a very
simple example that
can get us started. This is called the
matching pennies
game.
So the way that this works is that Alice
and Bob
simultaneously
choose
either
H or T.
So in particular their strategy space M=
N equals 2. They only have two choices
of actions. They can choose either heads
or tails.
And now what we have to do is describe
what the payoffs are. So if they match,
if these two coins match, then you know
Alice gets $1 from Bob and otherwise if
they don't match then Alice pays Bob $1
instead.
Right? So this is a very simple example
of a zero- sum game. In fact, we can
write it in this formalization that I
described right here just by writing
down what the payoff matrix is. So in
this case, the payoff matrix is just a
2x two matrix. And in particular,
it'll look like this
one -1 -1 1 where we have some
conventions
of what the different rows map to in
terms of the strategies. So the first
row maps to the choice of Alice choosing
heads.
The second row maps the choice of Alice
choosing tails. And then similarly for
Bob but for the columns. And so the
entries in this matrix just describe the
payoffs of this game. So let's make sure
we have you know the right intuition for
this. So let's think about this zero sum
game. Uh which player has an advantage
if any? So, who would you want to be if
you got to choose to either be the row
or the column player or would it not
really matter?
Just asking for your intuition.
>> Yeah. Doesn't matter.
>> Doesn't matter. Why?
>> I mean, because it's it's the same
payoff for
>> Yeah, that's right. So, you know, this
is very intuitive that neither of these
players has an advantage. It doesn't
matter if you're tasked with playing the
role of Alice or Bob, right? But for
more complicated games, it's maybe not
so obvious who has an advantage. And
this is where we're going to use ideas
from linear programming to try and
understand who actually has an advantage
and in what sense do they have an
advantage? So maybe for simple games,
it's easy to reason about them just by
staring at them and figuring out who
you'd rather be. But for more
complicated games, maybe it's not so
simple. So let's do a more interesting
example.
Uh and we'll come back to this example
later on once we've developed the
theory.
So let me just write down the payoff
matrix.
So let's say our payoff matrix C is a
3x3 matrix. So each Alice and Bob have
three different strategies. But now the
game won't be symmetric in such an
obvious way.
So the payoffs are going to look like
this.
So Alice can either choose the strategy,
let's say A1, A2 or A3. Bob can choose
the strategy B1, B2, and B3. And as
before, the entries in this matrix
describe the payoff of one player to
another.
So let me get some volunteers. So, who
wants to play this game?
I need two volunteers.
Yeah, come on down. Anyone else?
No one else wants to be on camera? I'm
going to select someone.
[laughter]
Don't be shy.
You guys brought some money with you,
right? No. Okay, that's all right. I'll
spot you.
I have these convenient baggies of
Monopoly money. So, uh, what I want you
to think about
is
in this game, who do you think has the
advantage? So, the row or the column
player?
And can we make predictions about, you
know, if they play rationally, what
their strategies ought to converge to? I
think this isn't so obvious, but uh let
me start with you. So, who do you want
to be, Alice or Bob?
>> You want to be Alice? All right.
I'm afraid you're stuck with Bob. All
right. So, what I'm going to have you
guys do is, you know, grab some chalk
and I'm going to ask you guys to write
down uh which strategy you pick. You
know, A1, A2, A3, B1, B2, B3. Hide your
answers from the other person so they
don't see it. And then we'll reveal them
simultaneously and figure out who's
doing better. So, we'll play a few
rounds of the game. So, pick a spot on
the board and uh you know figure out
based on the payoff matrix
um you know what exactly you want to
play and we'll see how we do.
>> Yeah. Why don't you use this one so that
you guys uh Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> You can ask the audience for help too if
you want.
[laughter]
Uh oh. Don't.
>> Yeah. Maybe cover it up.
Yeah.
Okay. Are you guys ready?
>> All right. Reveal your answers.
B1 and A1. All right. So, uh Alice,
congratulations. You win $2. Can you pay
the lady?
All right, let's do another round since
maybe you guys are just getting the hang
of it. All right, so uh think hard. Last
time she played A1, so maybe you want to
change your strategy. I don't know. It's
up to you. Um A1 worked out pretty well.
I don't know if you want to change. So
think hard and then write down your
answer.
Okay.
So, we've got uh A1
and B2. So, you owe him a dollar now.
[laughter]
>> Uh he's learning.
You're still up, but uh now some of your
winnings are going away. Let's do
another round. What do you guys want to
play this time?
Okay. All right. So, let's see. B3 and
A2.
[laughter]
You lose three more dollars. Uh
>> oh. [laughter]
>> How much do I have?
>> You have seven total.
>> You're going to go bust soon, though, if
you keep [clears throat] it up.
All right, let's do another round. Let's
give her a chance to get back on top.
All right. Uh, so write down your next
strategy.
Okay. B3 and A1.
All right. So, Oh,
she just won it all back. [laughter]
>> All right. So, you guys are pretty close
to even. Uh, so let me just test your
guys intuition. You're not necessarily
supposed to have intuition about this
yet. So, after seeing them play, right?
Um, who thinks Alice has the better
deal?
You have to vote for something.
It's okay if you're wrong. We'll build
up intuition as we're going along. Who
thinks Bob has the better deal?
All right, let's try that again. I got a
grand total of like two votes. Who
thinks Alice has the better deal?
All right, who thinks Bob has a better
deal? All right, so pretty mixed. All
right, so thanks for your help and uh we
can, you know, figure out the theory of
how zero sum games work and we're going
to be able to answer this question. But,
you know, for things like matching
pennies, as I told you, it's very
intuitive. You guys all got the right
answer about who has an advantage.
They're both the same. But as soon as
you move to bigger games, and this isn't
even much bigger. This is just a 3x3
game. you know already it's not so
obvious who has the advantage. So one of
the things that we're going to do at the
very end of lecture is we're going to
talk about really gigantic games which I
could never even write down on the board
because there are all kinds of games
that show up in things like you know
advertising for presidential elections.
Maybe you want to figure out, you know,
how to allocate your total advertising
budget across a whole bunch of
battleground states to figure out how to
win the most electoral votes. These are
exactly the kinds of things that can and
are modeled as gigantic zero sum games.
And we're going to develop the theory
for how to think about these things. So,
it's good that we don't have intuition
because, you know, we can make progress.
All right. So, let me introduce a little
bit more terminology.
Let me tell you, you know, what it means
to solve a game. And there'll actually
be a few different notions of how to
solve games, and they'll all behave a
little bit differently. So, the easiest
concept to wrap your head around is
called a pure Nash equilibrium.
So this is a concept that you know makes
sense regardless of whether the game is
zero sum or not. You know for general
two-player games I could have two payoff
matrices. One of which that describes
what Alice wins and one of which
describes what Bob wins but it's not
necessarily a transfer of money from one
to the other. So uh a lot of the things
we're doing though the only way to think
about it as a linear program will be if
we're working in the zero sum game even
though this concept makes sense more
generally. So what is a Nash
equilibrium? It's a pair of strategies
I J. So this means that the row player
plays I the column player plays J. And
it has the following property which I'll
just describe informally but then we'll
make it mathematically precise. It has
the property that no player
has any incentive to deviate.
How many people have seen the movie a
beautiful mind?
It butchered this concept. So please do
not get that definition from that movie.
Um so we'll do the correct definition
here. So what do I mean by incentive to
deviate? Let me turn this into a set of
linear inequalities. That way we can
think about it in a more mathematically
precise way. What I claim is that the
row player, if he's playing strategy I
and the column player is playing
strategy J, then the row player
has no incentive to deviate
if and only if
for all I prime CI prime J as at most
CI.
So the way to think about this
inequality is that the column player has
already committed to J. That's what we
mean by J being a pure Nash equilibrium
is that row player has decided I'm going
to play I. He's even announced it. I'm
playing I. The column player has
announced I'm playing J2. And even with
that knowledge of what the other player
is doing, they still can't do strictly
better than what their current strategy
is. So if the column player has
announced that they're playing J, the
only thing that's relevant is the J
column of our payoff matrix. This would
be the payoff if the row player sticks
to his current strategy. He still plays
the strategy he announced, strategy I.
And hypothetically, if instead he
changed to another strategy, I prime,
the claim is that he doesn't get uh any
more money, any positive win from making
that deviation. So he might tie in terms
of changing to another strategy, but he
doesn't do strictly better.
And similarly for the column player
has no incentive to deviate if and only
if for all J prime CI J prime is at
least CI J. Now just to make sure people
are paying attention, right? So here
obviously the deviation is happening
over the choice of I versus I prime.
Here the deviation is happening over the
choice of J prime versus J. Why are my
inequalities flipped here?
Why is my notion of no no incentive to
deviate? a less than or equal to
constraint here when I change I to I
prime and why is it a greater than equal
to constraint when I change J to J
prime.
>> Yeah,
>> if the payoff is like the players
>> exactly that's right. So really the
payoff for the column player is just
negative of this. So when I multiply
through by minus one everything
switches. So this is a very natural
notion. This is called a pure Nash
equilibrium.
But already we can see some deficiencies
of pure Nash equilibrium. Right? So even
if we come back to this matching pennies
game, right? So is there a pure Nash
equilibrium?
What do you guys think?
I see someone shaking their head in the
correct direction.
>> No, there isn't. Can you tell us why?
Any intuition?
>> I guess if
if I'm the broke player, um I always
want to choose one that'll give me one
and then if the tails person like
switches their uh strategy, they'll
switch the other one. That's right.
That's right. That's exactly right. Let
me just rephrase it slightly. You know,
Nash, a pure Nash equilibrium, you know,
corresponds to announcing what your
strategies are publicly and still there
being no reason to switch, right? So,
whatever those strategies are, imagine
that Alice announces she's going to play
heads. Bob announces he's going to play
heads. So, then who has the incentive to
deviate? Bob. He doesn't want the
pennies to match. So if he deviates the
tails, then he's going to win a dollar
and he'll do strictly better. And that's
true for any particular starting
configuration. There's always one player
who has an incentive to deviate.
So unfortunately, there's no pure Nash
equilibrium. Right? Now, even though
there wasn't the pure Nash equilibrium,
we can already intuitively see the way
the game would be played. Maybe Alice
and Bob just choose randomly, right? And
that would be pretty good because an
expectation they would win no money. And
that's probably the best that they can
do. But for this type of game, you might
have the intuition that I cooked this up
in such a way that again there's no pure
Nash equilibrium. So when there is a
pure Nash, it becomes very obvious, you
know, how to play for the most part. Um,
but when there's no pure Nash
equilibrium, all of a sudden you have to
ask, you know, how you should play. And
the key point is that maybe the notion
of playing shouldn't necessarily be a
deterministic choice.
Because the problem is that when you
make deterministic choices, you can't
commit in a way where you never have an
incentive to deviate. So this takes us
to you know the next notion which will
be critical for us which is uh you know
a finer grain notion of an equilibrium
which is called a mixed Nash
equilibrium.
Basically it's one which allows
randomization.
So let me define it. This will be the
key thing that we talk about today.
So a mixed nash equilibrium
[snorts]
is a pair
but now this pair is going to mean
something different. So it's a pair XY
with and I'll tell you what this means
in a second. X belonging to delta M.
I'll tell you what that means. Y
belonging to delta N.
Again with the property that
no player has an incentive to deviate
has a positive incentive to deviate.
So I have to tell you what this notation
delta subm means. And what this means is
just a distribution
on the set M. So the way to think about
it equivalently is that you know X is a
vector
that has non- negative entries
and the sum of all of these X I from I=
1 to M is equal to one. That's what the
constraint is. So what's going on is
that instead of the row player choosing
one fixed strategy like strategy I, he's
going to randomize over different
strategies. And the probability that he
puts on each different strategy is given
by the associated coordinate of this
corresponding vector x. So when I write
x belonging to delta m, keep in mind
that this is really a set of linear
inequalities, which is great because
we've been talking about linear
programs. It's just the constraint that
x is an m- dimensional vector. All of
its coordinates are non- negative and
they sum to one.
Same thing is happening here except with
the fact that it's a distribution on n
not m because the column player is
randomizing over the choice of which of
the n columns because that's the number
of strategies.
So this is the same basic idea as a pure
nash equilibrium. We still have this
notion that no player has an incentive
to deviate
but uh now we're augmenting the set of
strategies right. So instead of me
announcing I'm playing strategy I and
you announcing you're playing strategy
J, I'll instead announce that I'm going
to sample my strategies from the
distribution X. And you will announce
that you're going to sample your
strategies from the distribution Y. And
we can ask even after you make that
announcement if you have any incentive
to change up your strategies. So let's
be a bit more precise about you know
what exactly I mean by no incentive to
deviate because this will come up later
when we do the proof of you know a very
powerful theorem I'm going to cover very
soon. So you know what does it mean for
the role player to have no incentive to
deviate now when we're talking about
randomized strategies.
Well let's first do the following. So
first of all the expected
payoff
to the row player
is the sum over J = 1 to M. The sum oh
sorry I
I= 1 to M J = 1 to N of CI J X I Y J
and in matrix vector notation this is
just the quadratic form of X and Y on
this payoff matrix C. So all I'm doing
is I'm saying all right you've announced
that you know you're playing strategy X
and you're playing strategy Y. The first
thing I could care about once you've
announced that those are your strategies
is, you know, how much does Alice win in
expectation.
And this is a very simple, you know,
probistic computation because all this
is is it's the probability that Alice
plays strategy I because that's given by
the I coordinate of X times the
probability that Bob plays strategy J.
They sample their strategies from their
distribution independently.
And then this is whatever the payoff
would be. So this is just computing the
expected value, the expected winnings
that Alice has. And in our case, it
works out to a very nice expression in
terms of vectors and matrices.
But now we can talk about what it means
for the row player to have no incentive
to deviate. Right? So in this case, when
the row player is playing a randomized
strategy, what I claim is that the row
player has no incentive
to deviate
if and only if for all I prime the sum
from J = 1 to N of C I prime J Y is at
most XRPOSE C Y so what's going on with
this expression there's a reason I'm
taking a little bit to build up towards
it right you should see that already it
bears some similarity with what's going
on here where the inequality is less
than or equal to but I'm allowing some
variation because I'm changing my
strategy from my strategy X that has
this payoff on the right hand side to
instead being the strategy that just
selects I prime.
So this is really calculating what would
happen if I play according to X against
Y versus I decide I'm going to just play
strategy I prime against the strategy
YJ. So what's going on right here in
this expression is it's the same
expected value computation. Bob is still
playing according to Y and this is the
probability that Bob selects strategy J.
But Alice is now deviating to the
strategy I prime. So she always selects
strategy I prime and this is her
expected payoff and I want that this
expected payoff is less than or equal to
what I would get if I just stuck to my
pre-announced strategy. So even though
you know you can interpret this as a
system of linear inequalities, it's
important to be able to translate this
back into words to understand what it's
modeling. So does this make sense?
Yeah.
All right.
So, let's talk about the column player
and then I'm going to ask you a
question,
a somewhat tricky question
that'll be good food for later.
So similarly
the column player
has no incentive to deviate.
If and only if for all I prime the sum
from J equals 1 to N C oh sorry sum or
for all J prime the sum from I = 1 to M
of CI J prime X I is greater than or
equal to the payoff.
So this works the same way. You know
Alice is just dev uh Bob is just
deviating to a single strategy J prime.
The inequality gets flipped because the
payments are going to Alice not to Bob.
But this is what it means at least. This
is how to turn this definition of a mix
Nash equilibrium into a system of linear
inequalities.
Now let me ask a diagnostic question.
Right?
So the way that I've defined it, you
know, these inequalities,
they capture
deviating
from a randomized strategy, but to a
pure strategy.
Why not
allow
more general deviations?
Okay. So the way to think about this is
when I defined the notion of incentive
to deviate right here, you started off
with a strategy I and you considered
what would happen if you deviate to a
strategy I prime. So you started off
with a deterministic strategy I and you
deviated to another deterministic
strategy I prime.
Here I define the notion of a mixed Nash
equilibrium in terms of the players
having randomized strategies.
Alice is announcing that she plays
according to X. Bob is announcing he
plays according to Y. But my notion of
deviation was just Alice deviating from
her randomized strategy X to a
deterministic strategy I prime.
Bob's notion of deviation was deviating
from a randomized strategy Y to a
deterministic strategy J prime. So why
didn't I consider deviations to
randomize strategies?
This is an important concept and we'll
see it a few times in the lecture.
Anyone have any intuition?
I claim it's the same.
So imagine that
Alice had a deviation to some other
randomized strategy XP prime that did
better. What I claim is the only way
that she has a deviation to an X prime
that does better is if there's some
fixed deterministic strategy that does
better too. because how well she does
when I take X and replace it with X
prime is just an average of how well she
does for each of the different row
strategies she can take.
So this is a very important concept
and what I'm claiming here purely game
theoretically is that you know if Bob
has pre-announced that his strategy is Y
and he's committed to that then I don't
have an incentive to deviate to I have
an incentive to deviate to some
randomized X-pime if and only if there's
a fixed deterministic strategy I prime
that I have an incentive to deviate
So it's not totally obvious, but
hopefully it'll become clear over the
course of the lecture. That's really a
statement that has to do with weak
duality.
So when we talked about linear
programming and we talked about weak and
strong duality, this is really, as we'll
see, the crux of what's going on. And
there's a view to think about, you know,
what weak duality is that happens purely
through zero sum games. So in fact the
starting point of understanding linear
programs was actually zero sum games. So
it happened with vonoman's famous work
and it was of course famously you know
augmented to not necessarily zero sum
games by Nash. But this is really how
people first thought about the concepts
of weak and strong duality. So now I get
to tell you about uh probably my
favorite theorem in class.
Let me write it up here.
This is an amazing result which you know
we will prove today. Uh but the depth of
this result
I think you appreciate more and more
over time because of how many amazing
consequences it has.
So this is something called the minmax
theorem
and it was proven by vonoman.
Let me just write it down as a
mathematical statement. There's some
value lambda star which is equal to the
max overall x belonging to delta m of
the min
overall y belonging to delta n of xrpose
c y. But I claim that this is actually
the same thing as
switching the max and the min. So the
min overall y in delta n the max over
all x in delta m of the same thing
xrpose c y. So this is my favorite
theorem in the entire class we're going
to cover.
So what this statement is even saying
and why it's so deep and powerful this
takes a little bit to digest. So let's
go through that right now.
So right now all I said it's called
vonoyman's minax theorem is that these
two things are the same interchanging
the max and the min.
Okay. And I'm going to call these two
expressions one and two. So let's
interpret this expression game
theoretically
in terms of what the semantics are for
these two different expressions.
So what does this result imply?
Well, what I claim is that it's really
telling us that two different ways to
play the game, actually three different
ways, are all equivalent. It doesn't
matter.
So, expression one where I have a max
and then a min, right? I claim that
what's going on with the way that I've
ordered the max and the min is that it's
a certain semantics for how the game is
played, which sounds like it's unfair to
the column player. Because what's going
on is that the column player
chooses
a distribution
on strategies
announces it
and the row player best response.
Did I get these backwards? One second.
I think it it's backwards. All right,
let's do two. Okay, so what's going on
in expression two is that um you know,
first we have this outer minim.
So first this uh oh wait, uh let's see.
Nope, I had it right the first time. My
mistake. All right.
Doesn't matter whe they're equivalent,
but let's just make sure we get the
parsing correct. Right? So imagine that
I take that expression, I cover up the
max first in my expression one. So
what's going on is that the column
player is playing this min strategy. So
he's trying to find this uh you know
this strategy Y that's a distribution on
columns.
But now once he's chosen what that
strategy is, right? Once he's chosen
what that strategy is, then the max
player is allowed to choose the best
response. So even after the column
player is fixed and committed to playing
Y, then the row player chooses the
strategy X that maximizes it. I'm going
to get this slightly. Yeah, let me just
make sure I got these things right.
Uh,
yeah.
All right. I might have gotten it
backwards, but that's okay.
And for strategy two, it'll be the same,
but the row player goes first.
So the way to think about it is that you
know if the way that I described the
semantics of the game to begin with
started with one of the players having
to pre-commit to their strategy app
priori that would have sounded like I
really changed who had an advantage
right because now you know it has to be
that Alice is going first or Bob is
going first that person has to commit to
what their randomized strategy is. See,
the way to think about it is that when
we just had the notion of a pure Nash
equilibrium, then all of a sudden,
changing the order that the two players
play completely changes the meaning of
the game. So, think about the matching
pennies example. If Alice goes first,
you definitely want to be Bob because
whatever Alice chooses, you can choose
the penny to not match and then you
always win a dollar. So when you're
committing to deterministic strategies,
there's a huge advantage to who commits
first to their strategy and who gets to
adapt.
But what we're saying here is that it
actually doesn't matter who goes first.
That the best that you can do in either
of these two scenarios where Alice
pre-commits to her distribution then Bob
goes or vice versa is actually the same
value. It's the value lambda star.
So in fact what this uh you know minimax
theorem is really telling us is that
these two ways of playing the game and
even the way where we simultaneously
choose what our distribution on
strategies are are all completely
equivalent.
So this may not yet seem like a very
powerful result but um I'll give you
some more intuition later
but for right now let's um let's prove
you know one very powerful thing.
So when I talked about a pure Nash
equilibrium, that was a very natural
solution concept. But unfortunately, we
had simple games like the matching
pennies example that had no pure Nash
equilibrium.
Now a mixed Nash equilibrium is more
promising because we've augmented the
strategy space so that Alice and Bob
choose distributions.
What I claim the correlary of this
theorem is that every zero sum game has
a mixed Nash equilibrium. So that's the
first thing we're going to prove and
then we'll come back and we'll prove the
minimax theorem based on our
understanding of LP duality.
All right. So let me state that
correlary and then let's prove it.
I claim every two-player
zero sum game
has a mix Nash equilibrium.
So the main question is, you know, where
am I going to get my strategies that are
purportedly mix Nash equilibrium,
right?
This part's not so obvious, but it's
really going to come from the two
expressions right here.
So here's how the proof is going to
work.
We're going to let lambda star
uh equal the max min which of course is
equal to the min max.
Right? And now the main question is
where are my strategies going to be? So
what I'm going to do is I'm going to let
Xstar
and Ystar, these are my purported mixed
Nash equilibrium, they'll be the optimal
strategies
in two and one respectively.
So the way to think about it is in these
different scenarios, right? So xstar is
you know the answer when the row player
is forced to go first.
Y star is the answer when the column
player is forced to go first.
And what I'm going to prove is that
these pair of strategies really are a
mixed Nash equilibrium.
So now let's put it all together.
So we can take XAR transpose C Y
and I claim we have the following
inequality.
So what does this inequality mean in
words? Right? So we know that lambda
star is the payoff when these two
players play xstar and ystar
respectively. Right? And so what's going
on here is that when the row player
pre-commits to xstar,
I claim that no matter what the column
player does for his strategy that the
payoff is at least lambda star.
That's what it means for this
formulation in two to have the value
lambda star is that I can choose my
xstar strategy and no matter what
happens after I pre-commit to that
strategy I get the value at least lambda
star no matter what that strategy is. So
this is literally just translating the
statement of how we're playing the game
in scenario two into a system of linear
inequalities the same way that we've
been doing thus far. Right? I'm going to
call this set of inequalities a because
I'm going to have to put it together.
And similarly we can do the same thing
the other direction.
Xrpose C Ystar
is at most lambda star and this holds
for all X that belongs to this
distribution on M things, right? And
this holds because you know when uh the
column player has to go first. This is
what it means to have a good strategy in
scenario one is that the column player
chooses this distribution yst star. And
no matter what the row player does, we
still get the value at most lambda
squared. We're losing at lambda star.
We're losing at most lambda star
dollars. So I'll call this system of
linear inequalities B.
And you know together
what these two things imply
is that they imply that xar transpose c
y star is equal to lambda star.
Just by putting these two constraints
that we have over all y and over all x
together, we get exactly what we wanted
that the payoff really is lambda star.
And so what this means when we put it
all together is that
a + b plus c mean that
the expected
Win loss
is lambda star
and no worse.
So no one can actually do better. So
this really, you know, just the
statement of this minmax equals max min
is really just a translation of the
statement that uh no one has an
incentive to deviate. As long as we're
careful about how we get those minimax
strategies, right? And the way we get
the minimax strategy is we piece it
together. One of the strategies comes
from this scenario of how we play the
game where it's unfair to the column
player. and one comes from this scenario
where it's unfair to the row player
instead who has to go first. So are
there any questions? That's the first
main punchline is that all uh zero sum
games with two players are guaranteed to
have a mix Nash equilibrium and that
follows just from Bonoyman's minmax
theorem which we're now going to prove.
So any questions?
Good.
All right. So now let's prove the minmax
theorem.
The first thing I'm going to do before I
prove the minmax theorem is I'm going to
tell you a lema that makes precise
something that I asserted earlier.
that the notion of deviation
you can without loss of generality just
deviate to pure strategies. Let's make
this precise and then we'll prove it and
we'll see how it's really weak duality
types of arguments in action.
So here's my key helper lema we're going
to use to prove the minmax theorem. I
claim that the constraint
or rather the system of constraints
xrpose cxy
is at least lambda and this is true for
all y in delta n. Let me call this the
constraint system three I claim is
equivalent
to the constraint
xrpose c ej is at least lambda and this
is true for all j belonging to n and I'm
going to call this constraint system
four.
So this just makes precise the thing
which I asserted uh earlier.
I'm just saying that when we have a
system of constraints, this is an
extraordinarily complicated system of
constraints because there are infinitely
many constraints.
One for every choice of y that's a
distribution on n things. And I want the
constraint that no matter what you
choose for y, my payoff when I play x is
at least lambda. That's what this
constraint is saying. No matter what
randomized strategy you try, I get at
least lambda. I claim that this system
of constraints that's captured by this
equation three is equivalent to this
much simpler system of constraints that
when I play X, I just have to consider
strategies for U that are deterministic
strategies. So here EJ is the vector
that has one one and the J coordinate
and the rest of it is zeros. So what
this corresponds to is instead of Y
being a general distribution, it's now a
fixed choice of of playing strategy J
and I just need to ensure that against
every one of your individual strategies,
I get at least lambda. So this is the
crux of what I was saying earlier that
uh I only need to consider deviations
which are deterministic strategies. It's
really the statement that these system
of linear inequalities are actually
equivalent to each other. You can derive
one from the other.
So let's prove this fact. Uh the proof
is very simple.
So one direction is obvious because you
know whenever I satisfy the constraints
in three I better satisfy the
constraints in four because you know
this is just a subset of them. It's a
very particular set of distributions I
look at but the more interesting
direction is when I satisfy all the
constraints in four how exactly can I
prove that I satisfy the constraints in
three.
So here the key point is that you know
if I satisfy all of the constraints
in four and I want to prove I satisfy
the constraints in three what I'm going
to do is I can take an arbitrary
uh you know constraint y that belongs to
the set three and what I can do is I can
take this vector and I can break it up
into the sum of simpler vectors. So it's
the same thing as the sum from j= 1 to n
of yj ej. Remember ej is just this
placeholder that has a one in the j
coordinate and a zero everywhere else.
So this is just a simple equality
breaking up this vector y into each one
of the pieces for each one of its
coordinates.
And now I'm in business because when I
consider an arbitrary constraint of the
form xrpose cy is at least lambda,
I claim that I can derive it
as follows.
I can take the sum from J= 1 to N of Y J
X transpose
C EJ
let me just put the inequality inside.
So the way to think about it is that if
I take this vector Y and apply this
substitution and use linearity I can
just pull out all the YJS and the
summation. And now what's going on is
that this inequality right here is just
a weighted linear combination non-gative
linear combination of the inequalities
that arise in three. So each one of
these inequalities shows up in three
because it corresponds to an EJ. And
this tells me that I can actually go
from satisfying these equations in
three, add them up in order to derive
any constraint I want that arises in the
constraint system three. Right?
So this should remind you of, you know,
weak duality because what's going on
when you write the duel to an LP is
you're really asking when I have a
maximization problem, how can I set up a
companion LP? That's a minimization
problem that deres an upper bound on the
largest value of the max I can get. The
way that you form the duel is really by
taking the inequalities in your original
system and adding them up with the
appropriate variables. So your duel is
just asking what's the choice of how to
add up those inequalities to derive the
best constraint. That's exactly how you
prove weak duality and it's really the
crux of what's going on from a game
theoretic standpoint here too.
So, are there any questions? Make sense?
Once we have this lema, now let's prove
the minimax theorem.
And because we already have all of the
tools of linear programming duality, uh
we're just going to prove it by
appealing to LP duality.
So, let's prove the minimax theorem
using this helper lema.
So what we're going to do is we're going
to write down an LP
for playing
in scenario one.
So the proof strategy is very simple for
this. What we're going to do is I told
you that the minimax theorem is really
about saying that two different
scenarios for playing the game are
equivalent. We're going to write down an
LP that captures each of these
scenarios. That captures scenario one
and that captures scenario two.
And what we're going to observe is that
those two LPS are actually going to be
dual to each other. So that's the way
that the proof of the minimax theorem
goes. So I'll suggestively write P for
primal.
So we want to maximize lambda
such that
one second.
This would actually be scenario two. So
let's do scenario two. Sorry for getting
it backwards. All right. So for scenario
two, we want to maximize lambda subject
to the constraint that xrpose
c
ej is at least lambda. This should be
true for all j in my strategy set n. I
want that the sum of the x i from i = 1
to m is equal to 1 and all of the x i's
are non- negative for all i.
So really what's going on is I'm trying
to maximize this value lambda. That's a
lower bound on how well I do. But you
know part of the action is really the
choice of what the x is. So I want to
find a strategy X which is a
distribution on the strategies with the
property that um no matter what the
other player plays in response I've
chosen X no matter what the other player
plays in response for every strategy J I
will guarantee that an average I win at
least lambda and now I don't just want
to find an arbitrary X that satisfies
this condition but I want to make lambda
as large as possible. So I want to
maximize my safe value so that there
exists a strategy X so that no matter
what you do I get at least this value
lambda in expectation. And this is the
same thing as scenario two because you
know once the row player has committed
to playing the strategy X then what
would the column player do? they would
choose the J that minimizes this
quantity so they lose the least amount
of money which is the same thing as
asking that it's for always uh at least
lambda. So that's my primal and now I
can do the same thing
in scenario one.
So I'll suggestively write D for duel
here. And here what I would do is I
would minimize overall lambda. I would
want the constraint that ei transpose c
y is at most lambda for all i in m. And
of course I want the constraints that my
vector y is a distribution. So the sum
from j= 1 to n of y j equals 1. All the
y's are non- negative
on each of the coordinates. And so here
it's the same type of thing but in
reverse. My column player is going
first. My column player is choosing a
strategy so that no matter what the row
player does, you can guarantee that an
expectation I lose at most lambda
dollars. And I want my lambda my upper
bound on how much I lose expectation to
be as small as possible. could even be
negative if I win dollars in
expectation.
So these are the two uh you know LPS
right and you know the proof of the
minmax theorem now is very simple
because what you can do
is you can check
that P and D
are ds to each Okay.
And moreover,
both are feasible.
Why? Because I can just choose any X
that's a distribution, any Y that's a
distribution. That'll be some value for,
you know, finite value for lambda in
both of these two scenarios. So
feasibility is not a problem. And once
you have that both are feasible, you
know that strong duality holds.
So we know that their optimal values
are equal.
So this gives us vonoyman's min max
theorem. P is equal to you know max min
which is equal to d which is the same
thing as min max.
So [clears throat] this is also not just
the cool application of um of lp duality
but it really gives you a better way to
think about LP duality. So what is weak
duality? Well, one way to think about
what that concept means is, you know,
when I'm in scenario P and I'm playing
according to this uh scenario 2, one way
I can prove for you that you can't get a
very large value lambda is if I just
have to exhibit a good strategy for the
other player. Once I have a feasible
solution to this linear program, that
tells me how the column player has to
play. And that tells me that my row
player can't do all that well. So these
two things act as certificates of each
other. Whenever I have a feasible
solution to one side, then it implies
something about the other side not being
too good, right? And that's really the
crux of what weak duality is all about.
And strong duality just tells us that
actually the best certificate we can get
you know for P from D is actually equal
to the optimal value that we can obtain.
All right. So any questions make sense?
All right. So we covered a lot of ground
already. So we talked about zero sum
games. We talked about pure Nash
equilibrium and how sometimes they don't
exist. We extended our solution concept
to mix Nash equilibrium. And once we had
mixed Nash equilibrium then there were a
lot of basic questions like um you know
do they always exist? We proved that
they do exist by courtesy of the vonoman
minmax theorem that told us where xar
and yar came from and then we proved the
minax theorem just as a consequence of
lp duality.
So one of the amazing things I told you
that this is you know one of my favorite
theorems. Um so actually first let me
tell you the uh let's go back to the
example we had earlier where I had you
guys play uh you know that game. So we
can ask the same questions uh you know
that I asked back then.
So when I wrote down that C matrix let's
just write it down one more time.
So I had this payoff matrix C that was
3x3
2 -1
3 2 2
- 3 -1 2 - 3.
So we can ask the same types of
questions. Who's in the better position?
Maybe you still wouldn't know the
answer, but you know, how could I find
out who's in the better position? So,
how would we answer this question now?
Now that we have all this technology,
what should I try and compute?
>> Yeah,
>> I guess the optimal solution
Yeah, that's right. So, one thing I can
do is I can compute the game value
lambda star
lambda star which is called the game
value.
Remember the game value captures if both
players played optimally
who would win how much in expectation.
So one way I can answer this question of
who's in the better position is I can
compute the game value lambda star. Now
in simple examples like the matching
pennies computing the game value is easy
because it's zero. We know what the best
strategy is. Every player plays randomly
and then everyone wins nothing in
expectation. But now for more
complicated games where it's not so
obvious who you would want to be, I can
just feed this to my linear programming
solver and I can compute whatever the
lambda star is. So in fact um the thing
you can show is that lambda star is
actually one3
a third of a dollar.
So what this means is that uh so who
should I be the row or the column
player?
the row player, right? So, if we had
played with real money, then you
actually would have won money if you
played according to the minimax optimal
strategy. Maybe sometimes you get
unlucky and you lose some money. But
it's not actually this game of, you
know, um, whack-a-ole where one player
plays a good strategy and the other
player switches to try and get a better
strategy and do better in response. In
the beginning, uh, you know, you lost
money and then you quickly came back.
But we know what this game of
whack-a-ole converges to, at least if
both players play rationally because
both players should really just play
their mix Nash equilibrium. And you can
check that uh, you know, the XAR that
does this. Let me just write it down.
So you can actually solve this just with
a you know by hand or plugging it into
an LP solver.
And what you'll end up getting is that
uh you know xar is equal to 5 9th 0 4
9ths
and y star is equal to 0
2/3
and 1/3 right
and we can check that xar transpose c is
equal to this vector 2/3
1/3.
So that's my proof that the game value
is at least a third is when I play that
randomized strategy when I am the row
player. Well, this vector right here
just describes whatever the column
player responds to, you know, uh what
would be my expected value? The column
player should never play this strategy,
right? And they'll only play among these
two strategies. and I've guaranteed
myself that I'll win at least a third of
a dollar, right? So, did our two uh
volunteers play optimally?
So, you can think about it. What this
tells us is that in the optimal
strategy, you should actually never
play, if you're the row player, strategy
two, but that happened. If you're the
column player, you should never play
strategy one. I don't mean to pick on
you. It's a hard game. And that's why I
picked it was because it's not obvious.
And this is really what's powerful about
this solution concept is we took
something that we had no idea how to
play and we just figured out how to play
it. We figured out how to play it
optimally.
Now in fact um let me ask you an even
tougher question because really my goal
is not just to teach you about zero sum
games but to give you to you as a
vantage point for how to think about the
key concepts from linear programming in
a more intuitive way at least in a way I
like to um so one thing you'll notice
right I take xar and I take xar
transpose time c right
and um you know I get this vector 2/3
1/3
Now only these things are tight with the
game value. These are the only things
that match what I claim my lambda star
is.
What concept from linear programming
theory tells me why I must have a zero
here?
This is a very tricky question.
We already covered weak duality. weak
duality in the context of game theory
was how these two different scenarios
for playing the game, one which seems to
advantage the row player, one which
seems to advantage the column player,
figuring out how to play one of those
scenarios bounds what's possible in the
other scenario. That was weak duality. I
claim that when I take xstar transpose
time c and xar and yar are my purported
optimal solutions and I look at where I
have tight inequalities
that these values for the payoffs are
actually equal to lambda star the game
value that anything that's not tight has
to have a matching zero.
What concept? I hope Peter covered this.
Yeah. Is it basic?
>> Uh, it's related very close. What about
complimentary slackness?
So, this is complimentary slackness
because whenever I have an inequality
that's not tight,
right? Like this one right here. This is
not a tight inequality. It's not equal
to the lambda star. I better have the
corresponding variable is equal to zero.
The only way that I can have strong
duality hold is as long as that's true.
And if instead I took C * Y star
and I wrote it out, I would get you know
1/3.
So I don't get any constraints but you
know if instead I had some value was not
equal to 1/3 then the corresponding
thing in X had better be equal to 02.
See the way to think about complimentary
slackness is that if this is my
purported optimal solution, if Xstar and
Ystar are my purported optimal pair,
then as soon as Ystar has some positive
mass on this outcome, then I actually am
winning more in expectation than 1/3. So
my game value cannot be the correct
answer. So it's really also you can
think about complimentary slackness as
this constraint about the compatibility
of their two strategies and the
associated vectors of expected payoff.
So let me briefly mention um you know
this is way beyond the scope of this
class but you know uh one of the reasons
this is my favorite result at least in
the things I teach in undergraduate
classes is uh actually my PhD thesis
started in some way from this. So I had
um you know a result that I wanted to
show in graph theory which I'm not going
to explain what it is but it's a very
complicated and kind of surprising
result. So I remember I went into my
advisor's office uh in Okami and then I
told him I proved this amazing theorem
about you know all kinds of graphs about
a structural theorem about them and he
said uh there's no way you proved that.
Um that doesn't even sound true to me.
So he started writing some concrete
examples. You know what would your
sparsifier look like for this graph? I
couldn't do it. He gave me another
example. I couldn't do it. He gave me
another example. I think he started to
feel bad for me because, you know, he
seemed to get the hint that maybe I
hadn't actually proven it. And he said,
you know, how could you prove this if
you can't construct any of them, you
know, on the graphs I give you. And the
way that I proved it was I actually
appealed to a gigantic zero sum game
where I was playing one of the players,
the row player, and he was playing the
column player. So, I didn't have to
prove that such things existed by
actually constructing them myself. I
just had to show that any strategy he
had for disproving their existence
didn't work.
And that gives you a very indirect way
to prove existence of pretty exotic
objects, things which are hard to wrap
your head around otherwise. So even
though you might not see this until much
later if you see it, these types of
things are really under the hood of a
huge amount of comnatorial optimization.
It's not just about zero sum games I can
write down because sometimes it's about
trul gigantic zero- sum games that are
just exponentially large or impossibly
large to wrap your head around. And you
know instead of you know this whole idea
about playing the game in two different
scenarios instead of me having to prove
to him that they existed I just had to
prove that he couldn't prove me wrong.
This gives you a great way to prove all
kinds of exotic things that otherwise
sound counterintuitive and like they
should be false. So what's really
amazing is when you take a lot of
results across theoretical computer
science that sound false to you and you
don't have the intuition that sounds
like they shouldn't exist. It turns out
that when you pull on the thread a lot
of times this is what's under the hood.
Many times.