So today we'll be uh talking about the
portfolio management as one of the
application lectures. Um so I will share
some of my uh research work uh from a
practitioner's point of view. So rather
one rather than from pure theoretical or
mass point of view. So as we mentioned
at the beginning of the term uh we've
been uh teaching this class since uh
2012 and in 2013 this class was recorded
uh for MIT open courseware. Uh the link
I put it here is uh the lecture from
2013. Uh some of you may have watched
that lecture. It was actually turned out
to be one of the top most viewed uh uh
courses. Our course is one of the top
five actually on open courseware. Uh so
I want to promise you uh in today's
lecture I will give you a lot of new
content. uh so you you will uh make your
you know showing up the presence here
worthwhile so we can also make it uh
interactive.
So this is the outline of what I will be
uh talking about today. So first I'll
talk about what is really all this uh
portfolio construction is about coming
from very basic level then I'll talk
about what is the endowment model how do
we manage a endowment fund then I'll
talk about the portfolio theory and
illustrate in some really special and
simple cases for you to understand the
math then I will really switch gear and
talk about the limitations of these
theory right the theory was proposed in
the 1950s I mean of course a lot of
people have worked in the field try to
overcome the shortcomings of these
theories so I myself has been uh
spending a lot of time thinking about
these problems so I will talk about my
own research work uh in terms of how to
improve uh the portfolio construction
theory for example how to improve the
risk measurement using volatility and
sharp ratio and to and how to model uh
crowding behavior and also you probably
heard the power law also power law uh
how this behavior actually originated uh
from the crowding behavior. Now I will
summarize.
So before we start the lecture uh I want
to do an exercise with all of you. I'm
going to hand over a piece of paper to
all of you. Yeah, please pass it down.
Make sure everyone gets one piece of
paper. What I want you to do is to write
down your own investment portfolio.
Just hypothetically think about you have
$10,000 to manage
and uh put down investments you like to
have in the portfolio. put down the
percentage of each investment.
And uh I also want you not to think too
hard and also too long on this. Just use
your intuition. Imagine you are now a
fund manager, right? Sitting at a
pension fund or endowment fund or hedge
fund, right? Just ask you to pick a few
investment and uh then just hand it back
to me. uh after you finish then we will
talk about from where you started how to
do the portfolio management.
So just spend a couple minutes don't
overspend your time. So why I'm talking
so you can write down your choices.
So when you receive that blank sheet of
paper so you must be thinking what are
the criteria for me to do this right?
what are the considerations?
So this is exactly I want to lead you
into how to think about these problems.
First of all you need to think about
what's the objective of doing this
exercise right? So always say oh I want
to get a great return for the
investment. Sure. So you have a return
objective but is that what is the great
return? Is that 10% 50% or 100%.
What is the time horizon we're are
talking about, right? And because
investment is highly uncertain,
what's your loss tolerance, right? You
think about you have $10,000, how much
can you afford to lose, right? So that
those are the questions. Then when you
pick those investments, you should also
ask yourself
what's your own ability of picking a
winner, right? Why do you think you have
an edge in predicting that market or
investment?
Then of course, how many investments you
should have in the portfolio? Is that
one, five or 50 or 100? Right? how
diversified or how well mixed that
investment portfolio should be. Right?
Then ultimately the most important
question is how do you size each of the
investment?
It comes all down to sizing. Okay. So
portfolio construction I will show you
later. It's really about when you have a
list of investment you like, how do you
size them accordingly in rel you know
relative amounts to each other to the
whole portfolio. So now please hand it
back
uh because uh you I I want you to listen
to me not uh just spending the time on
writing down your portfolio.
Okay. Uh you can uh it's your choice.
Name or no name is fine. Yes, I'm I'm
not going to call you names but I will
probably use some of uh your answers as
examples uh to talk about uh
investments.
So uh as we are collecting uh these uh
uh uh portfolio choices
so I'm also uh going to talk about in
your decision making process.
So when you choose investments, you
probably were thinking about what
markets right first of all you will be
selecting your investments from and uh
what are the instruments?
>> So
are we mostly finished? Uh so by the way
uh for you uh we are doing an exercise.
We ask you to put down uh your
investment portfolio. just put on the
percentage whatever you can do. Okay. Um
so anyway um you're done. Okay.
Okay. Uh for the rest of you if you want
to take a longer time that's fine. I'm
just going to use some of the examples.
Okay. So uh the decision making process
I was talking about you need to decide
which market to pick your investment.
Then you need to think about what data
to collect right? what kind of signals
you can derive and what the models you
need to build, what factors you need to
take into consideration,
what predictions you need to make,
right? Then assemble them into
strategies, then we're talking about
sizing and allocate your capital
portfolio construction, then optimize
it. Then at the end really to manage the
risk.
So
now you can see what we really come down
to is how to compare different
investments to understand the
relationship between different
investments is to understand the return
and risk profiles of all the
investments. So what is risk? So in the
in this chart we are talking about here
I'm using volatility for the time being
which uh represents uncertainty right of
the outcome. Um later on I will kind of
come back and is telling you volatility
is not really the best measure for risk.
Uh but let's save that for later. But
before we talk about the investment
choices, let me look at some of uh what
you uh have written down. So one
portfolio here has
uh half in S&P
uh straddle. So this is actually option
strategy and uh then 30% in VIX related
ETFs then 20% in uh dollar index
futures. So sounds like someone has uh
done an internship somewhere knowing
option strategies.
Uh
so this portfolio has about uh eight
investments. The largest one in it is
cash 20% and uh 20% in QQQ which is
NASDAQ uh ETF.
Let me see.
This one is uh 70% bonds, 30% stocks.
This one is quite interesting because
when we normally talk about 60 40 or
7030 portfolio, the
the bigger piece tends to be the equity
piece. Uh but this one probably has more
uh risk neutral or risk uh parody type
of construction. So we'll get to that.
Uh this has many single name stocks.
Microsoft being on the top and uh this
is a 50% S&P 50% Vanguard
Pale uh fund. Uh
probably that's what is written. And
this one 100% S&P.
Yeah. Very uh much representing the
average market. And uh
so this one probably
has five stocks, 20% cash. Yeah. 50% US
Treasury bonds, 25% S&P. Okay. So fairly
uh similar. So now you got the idea. uh
and Peter and I used to uh kind of
reveal uh over the years year-to-year
change of the investment selection only
three years ago in 2021
most of the class chose some
crypto currencies
and uh dogecoins being the top one being
selected by everyone. I haven't seen any
crypto
investments today. So that just tells
you the index investing ETF seems to be
the theme of this year. You know, I
don't blame you. I think it's I think
it's pretty good idea. You know, S&P if
you don't have particular uh edge you
feel you like to have investing in index
is pretty good choice. So on this graph
I'm showing you here return versus
volatility. So we already touched upon a
lot of people choose chose cash right
cash basically you can view it as a zero
volatility as some minimum return you
know Fed just cut interest rate is still
over 4% um you know close to 5% and they
may cut more but uh compared to the
interest rate where it has been in the
last 10 years this is actually not bad
place uh to park your capital. Bonds
have slightly higher return, a little
more uncertainty of uh return. Um stocks
definitely have more but the index has
less volatility and the index
return wise it may not be uh lagging uh
the broad uh stock market. I mean as you
know the index now is heavily weighted
towards large tech large cap tech stocks
and uh lately those large cap tech
stocks has been have been doing really
well. So if you long QQQ or S&P, you
essentially long the magnificent seven
stocks, right? And uh so the ETF uh
investment choice here is a not a bad
choice or index investment.
Further up on the right is the private
equity and venture capital choice. Uh
which I haven't seen anyone put it down.
So uh you you may be more thinking about
the public markets but private equity
and the venture capital are basically
investing in private companies not
publicly listed on stock exchanges. So
those companies tends to be illquid. You
cannot get your money out easily. You
have to stay with them for a very long
time. But a lot of times you have more
influence on the company's operation and
uh venture uh for example you invest in
startup companies those companies can
grow very fast can also fail very fast
uh so the outcome the uncertainty range
is very big but overall over the years
they tend to produce higher returns to
justify the uncert uncertainty or risk
premium you are uh dealing with.
So coming back to the return objective
and loss tolerance. So we should think
about uh when you write down your
portfolio right so you try to maximize
your return for sure right is anyone
here disagree with you should maximize
your return probably not right at the
same time you should minimize your risk
in this case minimize your uncertainty
right so you want to maximize the ratio
of return over volatility right that's
one of the objectives
but you may have constraints as well,
right? There are certain investment you
may not want to uh participate in. Uh
for example, uh many universities
declared uh we don't want to invest in
fossil fuels right for the environmental
concerns. And in the past like tobacco
companies or you know some kind of
weapon companies you know people have in
principle uh reasons to go against them
and uh so there are constraints of what
you uh investment universe should be.
Then there's liquidity, right? Uh you
know how much you need to use the money,
the $10,000 you you had in the
portfolio, you may not want to use it in
all in the investment or your liquidity
investment all the time. So you may want
spend 5% a year for example, right? Uh
so you need to take into account your
spending needs
and uh also on the downside how much you
can afford to lose is really a very
important question. So if your $10,000
becomes $5,000 do you will you feel
really bad? you would just say I'm gonna
stop investing alto together right so
that's I cannot afford to lose maybe
that's situation I saved uh for next
year right I put aside just want to earn
some return I don't want to lose it so
then your risk tolerance is very low is
very different
so for many asset owners uh inflation is
also a important concern because wealth
represents relative purchasing in power.
So how much wealth you have is not
really just a dollar amount you have in
your bank account is how much you can
buy, right? So when the price of goods,
services are going up, your purchasing
power is going down, right? So that's
inflation and it's also relative to the
next group and people or person how much
they can buy, right? So for universities
that means you want to hire a professor
you know if there are competing offers
how much more you can offer to the
professor to uh get them to come to your
university.
So uh so there's definitely absolute
return angle for the requirement of the
portfolio right and there's also a lot
of people nowadays talk about beating a
benchmark beating a index you know you
many of you have chosen S&P as an index
but if you can produce more return on
top of S&P return so that's called the
alpha right so relative return that's
also often being used as a measurement
of investment skills. So you don't
justly just put in a beta or broad
market investment. You actually can
extract more return.
So
asset liability matching cash flow is
very important. Right? So 2008 taught
many asset owners uh a big lesson. When
you don't have the right asset liability
uh match when your portfolio has a draw
down your liability side will basically
dominant uh dominant on your balance
sheet you need to cut your spending
budget you know stop your uh uh building
projects and the layoff people right so
that those are painful uh uh lessons uh
you need to have the cash flow well
planned so time horizon I mentioned is
very important. When I gave you that
piece of paper, I didn't say time
horizon on purpose. I want you think
about you should ask the question this
portfolio is for how long is that? For
one day or for a year or for 10 years,
right?
So in the investment world, people
always compare returns like year to
years, sometimes even quarter to
quarter. like peers try to say oh I
outperformed A outperformed B so
therefore A is better than B so this is
actually lot lot of times unhealthy
exercise because for long-term investors
you should really focus on long-term
return but inevitably in the real world
people look at uh short-term returns so
you cannot ignore it but that's the the
uh the peer pressure for a lot of
investment managers is that's the career
risk because they bored may think in the
short term they are not good and try to
replace them.
So coming back more on why investing
right. So on the on the left if on on
your left if you look at the um personal
income and spending as one person's age
uh as age as a function.
So your income level kind of peak
somewhere in your mid career. Okay. So
let's call it around age of 50, right?
So you're earning the most, you probably
also spending the most. But as you as
you as a student, you probably don't
earn that much. You don't spend uh that
much either, right? I mean, same is true
when you uh over the peak point. You're
getting into the retirement stage. So
you don't earn that much, you don't
spend that much. So you need to plan
accordingly of your personal portfolio.
So that's related to the question of
time horizon and also the marginal
benefit of having more wealth and money
starts to diminish when you have had
certain minimum amount. So that's the
bottom curve. uh your benefit is start
to uh uh kind of a plateau and uh so
also do you want to take more risk or
not at that point right but for
organization or endowment on the right
is a little different because it's a
perpetual uh portfolio is a very long
long time horizon and the spending uh
keeps going up uh as uh inflation goes
up so you cannot not basically be
complacent and say I just put all the
portfolio into some conservative uh
investments. You have to keep producing
those kind of returns.
So the endowment is set up for a
university typically they spend 5%
uh of the portfolio and on top of that
there's expected 3% inflation. So the
nominal return target is 8%. Right? Uh
so as you know it's probably not always
easy to make 8% consistently uh year
over year and especially when interest
rate is low. Uh you don't have a bonds
or safety bond you can put in.
Also endowment tends to have long time
horizon definitely more than 10 years.
That's what the people always say you
know universities have hundreds of years
history right and looking to have
another you know many more hundreds of
years
and uh on the university spending budget
operating budget now roughly about 40%
of the budget uh is coming from
endowment uh spending so you can see
universities are now more and more uh
reli relying on endowment returns and uh
that's uh because uh the you know the
research grants from federal agencies
and the uh industries are coming down.
So this has to be made up from the
investment portfolio
and uh so this is just a list of the
strategies endowments tend to invest in.
I mentioned cash, government bonds, uh
corporate bonds and credit products
meaning the issuer unlike US government
it has the risk of defaulting so
therefore will pay you higher uh
interest. Uh so they are hedge funds
betting on the macro markets right
betting on the Fed uh or stock market
the general uh direction they're also
quantitative funds doing the trend
following people usually call it CTA
yeah commodity trading advisors or stat
up which is to capture the relative uh
value uh between a pair of stocks or
actually many pairs of stocks. So it's a
statistical arbitrage they call it. So
which is really to uh find uh
statistical patterns to generate
returns. So this is heavily
computer-driven strategies. Many big
quantitative shops still doing a lot of
these. So there are fundamental equity
hedge funds. They buy stocks and also
sell short stocks.
And uh there are also the platforms you
probably heard you know the big
platforms they call it multistrat or
multi multi-pm
uh portfolio manager platforms they hire
hundreds of different uh teams uh
trading uh on the same platform you know
very different a wide range of
strategies but achieve a high degree of
diversification and they can level up uh
the portfolio IO quite a bit
and uh so I mentioned private equity uh
earlier there also real asset investment
real estate natural resources farmland
timberland those type of uh uh
investments and the new assets such as
you know crypto or intellectual uh
properties or legal claims and so on. So
basically anything you can think of can
generate return it can also be
considered.
Uh
at the first lecture I already
highlighted some of the uh features of
the endowment model. So endowment model
nowadays tend to focus on hiring
external managers and doing both public
and private uh investing and uh we hire
both uh generalists you know look at
everything and also specialists in
certain domains such as biotech you know
uh AI and so on.
uh we focus on both absolute return and
also relative return to the benchmark.
uh so we are mostly active managers. So
we uh we have some passive beta index
investment but it's a minority of the
investment is also u not always
permanent. So whenever we can find an
active strategy or a manager to beat a
benchmark or index we will always go for
the active uh uh investment.
Um yeah so as you can see this
investment process is centered around
manager selection right uh selecting the
good investing uh uh fund managers and
Harvard actually in the old days used to
have lot of internal uh fund managers
but that model has changed from uh seven
years ago. Yeah. To focus more on
external managers.
So now I'm going to shift gear a little
bit to talk about uh portfolio
construction problem. So shifting
towards the math part of uh the
discussion a little bit. So the classic
portfolio construction problem is stated
as such. Assume you you know your return
objectives. You have a loss tolerance
and you can predict each investment's
return volatility which is the standard
deviation
and also the correlation matrix of these
investments.
The question is what percentage you
should put in in each of the investment.
So that's the portfolio construction
problem right and the objective of that
as we mentioned earlier is to maximize
the return for the whole portfolio while
minimizing the portfolio risk in this uh
classic uh problem is to minimize the
uncertainty or volatility of the whole
portfolio.
So as you can see the portfolio
construction problem really is a sizing
problem of uh investments at all
different levels. You can relate that to
asset allocation problem. So what is the
asset allocation problem? So you group
those investments into different asset
classes. So as I showed you earlier, so
the list of these strategies, you can
also think of them as list of different
asset classes. So from top down
the discussion needs to be had is how
much you want to be in each category or
each asset class.
And uh sometimes people will say well
that's still way too many asset classes,
right? you if you have 10 to 15 asset
classes that makes the optimization
problem very hard. So people tend to
reduce them to uh big uh risk factors.
So sometimes you know say three to five
risk factors usually equity, bonds and
plus uh one of the other things could be
uh uh you know inflation, it could be
currency, it could be uh uh credit and
other uh dimensions. But the factor
analysis or can also expand into many
detailed levels. You can have you know
50 factors or even hundreds
uh factors but it's just a different
ways of grouping the investments to make
the optimization uh problem little
easier. Okay. So then what is the risk
management problem of a portfolio? So
risk management problem in many ways is
actually the same problem as portfolio
construction. is the sizing problem. But
in addition, you need to think about how
to avoid concentration, right?
Concentration of course is also a sizing
problem and also ili liquidity and
what's unaccept unacceptable losses and
unwanted risks to constrain uh the
portfolio.
So I'm going to spend a few minutes on
the portfolio theory which is
illustrated in two assets.
Asset one has a return R1 volatility
sigma 1 and will have a weight in the
portfolio of W1. Uh similarly for asset
2. So the sum of the two weights should
equal to one. W1 plus W2
and the portfolio return which is
denoted here as R subp is the weighted
return of R1 and R2 right and the
variance or in this here is the sigma P
squared the volatility squared can be
expressed in terms of the weights and
the volatility of each of the two
investments.
as well as the correlation row between
the two investments. So this is a very
uh common equation you probably have
seen uh many times uh in uh in any uh
you know probability or stat uh
statistics class classes.
So let's look at the
some special cases.
So when the correlation row is positive
one meaning the two assets are perfectly
correlated one moves up the other moves
up at the same time one goes down the
other one goes down at the same time
right so that's called perfect
correlation
so if row equals to one
and we can simplify the uh sigma Sigma P
which is the portfolio volatility
becomes the weighted sum of the two
volatilities W1 * sigma 1 plus W2 *
sigma 2 or you can also express the W1
in terms of Y minus W2 right so
therefore solving for W2 in terms of
sigma P and the sigma 1 and sigma 2
so
then you can derive
the overall return of the portfolio R
subp in terms of W2 because W2 above is
a function is a linear function of sigma
P. So you know in this case the return
of the portfolio RP is a linear function
of
sigma P. Okay. So this is on this chart
you can see that straight line when row
equals to one that's the special case
when row equal to minus1
that means they are perfectly
uh negatively correlated. So one goes up
the other one goes down.
So when that is the case you will
actually easily derive that this sigma P
is actually you have two branches of
solutions. So depends on the value W1
sigma 1 compared to W2 sigma 2. So
that's the two uh separate lines on the
left. That's the other solution. In the
middle is the other values of uh the
correlation between negative one and
plus one and including
uh zero correlation row equal to zero.
So what if the first asset has zero
volatility sigma 1 equals to zero. So
then from the equation earlier we can
derive sigma p the portfolio volatility
is simply w2 * sigma 2 right because
sigma 1 is zero and therefore w2 the
waiting on the asset 2 is sigma p
divided by sigma 2 right that's a
straightforward uh result
and uh the portfolio return r subp P now
can be written as
R1 which is the first asset with zero
volatility which you can think as a cash
right we mentioned earlier cash has zero
volatility so this cash or riskless
asset has a return R1
while
it's RP is still a linear function of uh
sigma P right but it's a straight line.
In this case, you can see the slope of
that line is determined by the
difference of R2 minus R1 and divided by
sigma 2.
So by the way, so this is so-called
capital allocation line in the uh
portfolio theory. Okay. So we can uh
look at let's say constructed the
portfolio you already have a sigma P
which has many assets in it right and
also RP by adding one riskless
asset or cash which returns RF RF is
basically like a risk-free return you
can draw a tangent line over
uh the sigma P point you pick the uh one
point on that efficient frontier I
should explain efficient frontier
meaning that on that return versus
volatility chart because you have
different waitings right so let's come
back to this uh let's look at the uh
this curve here so for different W1 and
W2s you can have different resulting
portfolio return and portfolio
volatility Right. So this line
the upper part of this is called
efficient frontier because by lowering
your risk and moving your return up
that's your objective. You are improving
the portfolio. So any point on this line
is a potential solution of that
portfolio construction.
So why when we add the risk-free asset
uh on this RF point so we can basically
combine that risk-free asset with the
existing portfolio
to uh further improve the risk uh the
efficient frontier to move up to that uh
straight line.
So that slope R P minus RF divided by
sigma P is so-called sharp ratio in
simple terms think about your return
over volatility right so that's kind of
a uh the sharp ratio definition
um sometimes you also hear the term
alpha and the beta that's compared with
a benchmark right so in this case you
can uh write down the portfolio return
minus the risk risk-f free asset in
terms of alpha plus beta times benchmark
minus the risk-free return and uh uh the
beta is a function of correlation of the
portfolio to the benchmark and the ratio
of the volatility.
Um what if
you want to lever up the portfolio and
uh borrow more? So meaning make the
weight of the first uh risk-free asset
to be minus 100%. And make the other
asset be 200%. So still sum up to one.
So that means you're borrowing money uh
in in cash. You're putting the proceeds
into the risky asset. So, you're moving
the volatility up to this point
by investing more into the second asset.
So, that's also possible. That's a
typical exercise people do in risk
parody portfolios. By the way, if you
don't follow uh any of those, that's
fine. The reason I want to talk about
this is really give you some flavors of
what the portfolio theory uh is about
because then I'm going to tell you uh in
practice a lot of these needs to be
improved.
So the example of portfolio with two
assets we talk about the 6040 uh equity
bonds right some of you wrote down 70
bonds 30 uh% stocks uh that's very much
similar to the risk parody uh portfolio
which they try to make equal risk
contribution coming from the bonds and
equity by borrowing uh more to invest in
the bonds because bonds typically have
lower volatility than equity. So you
need to have more to make them have
equal risk or contribution. So that's
the idea. Again today I'm not going into
the uh math. Uh in the previous years
sometimes I spend more time on that but
I feel I want to uh uh talk about other
things bit more today.
But before we move away, I want to talk
about the importance of rebalancing.
Um
uh because we had this uh 2013 uh OCW
video just uh two weeks ago. I think
somebody uh made a a clip out of that
class uh speed it sped it up to 1.5
times and made a three minute uh uh
video of uh the only free lunch of uh uh
diversification which is exactly this
example. So, I'm going to go through it
uh with you quickly. Just think about
you have two assets or two uh assets in
a two-year period. In year one, the
first one doubles and then year two it
has. So, I think it's a little easier to
uh to show on the on the blackboard, but
the other one
does the opposite, right?
So they both started here. The first
asset doubles
then halves. So this is a year one.
This is year two. The second asset
halves first then doubles.
So those were the R1 and R2s. So if you
start as equal weight of the two and
after year one you can calculate the
portfolio is up 25%.
So this is just a simple math you know
the first
asset one is 50% weight asset two is
also 50% weight one doubles one halves
so total you made 25%. Okay. But if you
don't do anything at this point, so
asset one will be dominating the
portfolio. Asset two will be just a
small portion. Right? Then because asset
two then doubles, you're coming back to
the same point. After two years, your
portfolio's return is exactly 0%.
Okay? Even though you had a divers
diversified portfolio with perfectly
negatively correlated assets,
but if you rebalance at this point
to equal weight,
then your portfolio in year two will
make another 25% return in year two.
So you're making compounded return of
25%
two years in a row, right? So, some of
you may point out that isn't this just
uh betting on mean reversion, you know,
uh and uh if if you think it's a trend
uh trade, you shouldn't do this. That's
right. Uh the question you should ask
yourself, what is the basis of your
sizing or waiting of the two assets?
Right? So you started with the equal
waiting meaning that you think the two
asset have the same likelihood of
performing and the same amount of risk.
That's that's why you size them equally
and of course uh you also know they are
negatively correlated.
So at the year at the end of year one do
you maintain that view or not? If you
think is that still the same projection
of risk and return then you should
maintain the equal weight. You should
not change the waiting unless at the
year one your projection has totally
changed. You think asset one will
continue to outperform asset two. Yes,
in that case you can change to a
non-equal waiting. So that's the point.
If you believe they are
they have the same probability
distribution and uh there's no reason
for you not to rebalance. So people say
this a free lunch the only free lunch is
diversification but you have to
rebalance to uh to eat it. So that's on
that. So then I'm going to shift the
gear uh to talk about the limitations of
so-called modern portfolio theory in
short MPT.
I mentioned this was mostly developed in
the 1950s
and uh Harry Marquiz pioneered uh in
this area. He actually got a Nobel Prize
in the I think early 90s uh for his
work. Uh so all I have just described uh
to you so far the mathematical part has
a lot to do with his work. Okay. Uh but
you can tell already right. So a lot of
these depend on your confidence in the
capital market assumptions
which is the projections of return
volatility and the correlation matrix of
these investments. Right? And uh the
mean variance optimization problem
of often has unlimited number of
solutions and you have to put artificial
constraints to bound the solutions. They
are very sensitive to uh small change of
these capital market assumptions.
So in practice is very hard to use.
Probably not many people use it.
So
with those questions I myself have
always been curious about this and have
done uh various uh research work uh in
this. So today I'm going to highlight a
few uh the first one is more related to
the sizing question using a different uh
approach. Um
I call it you know a gain loss ratio. Uh
the second part I will talk a bit about
you know the effect of crowding behavior
and how to model it. And uh lastly I
will talk about
uh you know the power law distribution
uh coming out of these crowd
interactions why these are all relevant
to a portfolio construction.
So issue number one uh for the MPT. So
volatility is a poor measure of risk.
Why do I say that? You know because
volatility
is just the standard deviation or the
range of uh uncertainties.
So if I am long uh out of money call
option, think about it, right? You have
one investment. Um Stephen, you uh
studied you worked on options. You
probably can get this uh easily.
If I've long out of the money option, do
I wish my the volatility to go up or
down?
Do I want my portfolio have a high V or
low V? Right. I want my portfolio Yes.
Yeah.
>> Higher volume.
>> Yes. Right. The higher V, the better.
Right. So on the other hand, if I'm
short uh all the money option, I
probably want to have lower V, right?
The better. So because I don't want to
uh get exercised.
So really depends on, you know, your
gain situation, your payout or your
potential loss.
And the shop ratio is derived from
volatility. So basically suffers from
the same uh issue. So over the years
there are methods like a sautino ratio
uh try to uh differentiate the upside
range and the downside range. Uh I think
it's a good measurement but it uh it
doesn't give you uh direct link to
sizing. You know the ultimate question
we need to answer is sizing.
So the new way to compare different
investments uh uh I'm basically uh uh
using or I came up with is to use
expected gain and expected loss. I call
the G and L. Uh here I both use positive
numbers. So when I say loss, these are
absolute uh numbers.
So we are looking for the best skill
which is gain much bigger than expect
much bigger expected gain than much
bigger than the than the expected loss
or written in different forms in the G
minus L which is the return divided by G
+ L. Okay. and you change the format a
little bit, it becomes 1 - 2 L / G + L.
This is really
exactly the sizing percentage
uh from uh Kelly's criteria in the
binary uh bedding.
So this number is bounded from minus1 to
+ one. So it can be directly translated
uh into uh sizing and uh so let me give
you a few examples to help uh you
understand this. So if you are flipping
flipping a a coin, right? You know the
head has a certain probability and the
tail has certain probability and when
it's a head it has a payout you will get
or lose and when it's tail you have a
payout or lose. So expected gain is the
probability of the head times the
payout. Right? If you bet on head,
expected loss is the probability of the
tail times the payout on that side. So
in that discrete example is fairly easy
to understand. But in the continuous
example is the terminal distribution.
Let's say you have a probability
uh density function describing all the
outcomes.
Then you need to use that probability
density function times the payout,
right? Integrated over all the losing
part and integrated over all the gaining
part to get the expected loss and the
expected gain. So it doesn't have to be
always separated by zero. Right? If you
have a target return, so you integrate
over say from minus infinity to the
target return. That's your expected
loss. That is what needs to be included
in L.
So when you do this
your optimization problem is no longer
return versus volatility but in the
vertical axis is gain in the horizontal
axis is L is loss. So you need to
basically maximize G while minimizing L.
So this is all relevant because as I
just explained earlier minimizing
volatility is not not always for your
benefit right when you are long option
you need to you need to have higher
volatility but in this case when you
specify expected loss that's what you
need to budget and control your uh
investment.
So in the investment game we gave you at
the beginning, I hope you have all of
your submitted uh your choices uh in
September and some of you rebalanced
uh in October.
I wanted you to track the daily gain and
loss in dollar amount.
And uh at the end of the game which is
mid November, I want you to summarize
all the daily gains and also summarize
the daily losses to derive the G and the
L. So some of you said you know in order
to win this game why don't I just pick
the highest volatility stock right uh to
have the best potential
uh to produce highest return yes but
your higher volatility investment will
suffer on the denominator which the G
plus L uh this ratio will indicate the
quality of your investment even Though
your G minus L which is the return may
be good but the denominator will
normalize it right to make it basically
uh comparable to other investments.
So the optimization problem. Yes,
please.
>> In practice, what like do you use to
estimate the expected gain?
That's difficult to like estimate like
the distribution of the pricing.
>> Uh yes. Uh but no more uh difficult than
getting the return and the standard
deviation.
Yeah. So it's the same amount of work.
It's just that you are separating the
numbers. uh you're calculating half
distribution instead of the whole
distribution.
So it is uh so especially when you do
the optimization problem as I'm uh about
to explain uh these lines basically for
example the 45 degree line indicates g
minus l equal to zero so zero return
line so you don't want to uh pick any
investments below that 45 degree line
you want the lines have higher slope
right so indicating higher g over L
ratio but when you combine them combine
let's say two uh assets into one uh
calculating the combined portfolio G and
L which is actually pass dependent uh
which actually should be because when
you have two investments the final
outcome of the expected gain and the
loss uh indeed will be pass dependent
that means you probably need to do a lot
of Monte Carlo
uh simulation uh to derive that. Yeah.
But it's no more work amount than the uh
traditional uh distribution uh
calculation.
>> Yeah.
Okay. Um let's move on to uh
modern portfolio theory issue number
two. How do we predict future based on
the past? How confident can we be in the
capital market assumptions return
volatility and correlation?
So because we human thinking uh process
right our thinking process always
extracting patterns from the data. So we
have observations this I'm just
outlining the typical thinking process.
You have observation.
You have measurable data. Try to
quantify them. Then you try to extract
useful information or recognize
patterns.
Then you try to build models having
inputs, outputs and the conditions. Then
you predict output from the inputs and
the conditions. Then you repeat your
observation.
Then you iterate try to calibrate your
model parameters.
When you are very good at it, you can
actually control conditions and inputs
to get the desired outcome. Right? So
that's
that's true for any subject, physics,
engineering, finance, right? But finance
involves uh uh human behaviors which is
much more complicated.
So the historical patterns may not be
repeatable, right? And also the crowding
behavior and also adaptive behavior of
human players will make the process much
more complicated.
So I want to show you a video.
Let's see if this works.
So what are you watching is a video of
birds or bats
in a totally selforganized way
to form
a group behavior.
What they do is they watch the
neighbors.
They adjust their actions
and uh
the group as whole displays certain
patterns.
The financial markets is very similar to
this.
So uh except there's a central
observation
you can actually see which is the stock
price you know you can also look at your
neighbors too but nowadays it's much
easier to look at the central
observation.
Okay. Um in the past I've also shown the
uh London Bridge video. You probably How
many of you have heard the the
Millennium Bridge of London? Uh yes.
Okay. It opened is a Millennium Bridge
around 2000 on the you know first day
when people walk on it starts to sway
and then people try to keep their
balance they all sync they become
synchronized in steps that made this
sway even bigger. So market does the
same thing. When panic feeds into panic
or greed feeds into greed, market can
form bubbles and crashing and these kind
of behaviors are not uh easily uh
predictable but it's a part of crowding
uh behavior.
So how to how to understand and model
this kind of behavior? So we can look at
as a a feedback loop, right? Uh so S
here is uh the agent's action. Uh O is
the observation.
A is kind of a amplifier or agent's
action feed through into the uh
observation. As you can see the change
of their observation is the sum of the
agents action times the uh power they
have which is a then agent's action the
change of agent's action ds is
influenced by external force as well as
the feedback loop of the observation and
plus some random noise. So that's the
basic uh framework of crowd uh modeling.
When the agents behave in the normal
conditions, they are more rational. So
they are less reactive to the
observations or you can call it the
feedback loop parameter B is actually
taking a lower value. But when
observation changes more volatile uh in
a more volatile fashion the agents tend
to react more they get into a reactive
state. So more agents in the crowd get
into reactive state
the crowd actually becomes more
synchronized.
So if we look at the the order parameter
which I defined as
uh the ratio of the sum of all the
actions together divided by the sum of
the absolute uh number of the actions.
So if they are all synchronized so that
number should be one right? If they are
not synchronized at all that number can
be very close to zero. So what the first
chart on the left shows is
the order parameter as a function of
number of agents in the crowd in the
reactive state. So then when more agents
become reactive to the observation the
order parameter can become very high.
the crowd gets synchronized
and on the right you can see the order
parameter is also a function of the
random noise term in the previous page.
The higher the noise the less likely the
agents uh the crowd will be
synchronized.
So this type of behavior by the way is
not new in physics uh in
in some of the you know circuit uh
engineering circuit systems when you
inject a noise you can also reduce the
order parameter synchronization but in
social science this actually uh is a
also a similar behavior.
So I further simulated uh the bubble
process. So when you have a external
force showing on the up left it's kind
of ramping up then come down then
oscillate.
The number of agents in reactive state
starts to peak up then also drop when
the external shock uh diminishes.
The observation as a result also follows
but then comes down. But if the external
shock on the other end maintains at a
higher level forever
eventually all the members of the crowd,
all the agents
get into the reactive state. So they the
whole crowd become synchronized. the
observation basically goes uh shoots
through the roof. So it becomes a very
unstable uh system. So that's the bubble
at that point. When the system becomes
unstable your bubble will burst.
Uh so that's the part of the crowding
behavior. So the purpose of showing that
is when we look at portfolio management
these type of bubble forming and
bursting process is a very important
aspect of our understanding beyond the
fundamental uh analysis right this is
all about behavioral uh uh finance right
um
has nothing to do with the fundamental
of the economy or the fundamental of a
But then you probably also have heard
power law distribution, right? So what
is power law distribution is the winner
take all the 8020 rule or the Matthews
effect. many different terms describing
essentially a social phenomena that
uh the
small number or percentage of the Asians
taking a majority share of something in
the in the group. So let's think about a
wealth distribution, right? So 20% of
the people probably have 80% of the
wealth and uh this is also true. You
look at the top 20%
within that 20% the top 20% has 80%
wealth. Then within that is still true.
This is so-called scale free or scale
invariance.
This is the unique property of power law
distribution. So in mathematical terms,
so the probability of B * X, X is the
random variable, B is a scaling factor
equal to some function of G of B times
the probability of X. So this you can
prove mathematically
if and only if this P of X is a power
law distribution that scale-free
property uh maintains.
So example of power law distribution
I mentioned the wealth distribution
venture capital funds returns the top
tier funds tend to get you know majority
of the profit of the startup companies
there's a book published two years ago
is called power law so by uh uh
Sebastian uh Manaby uh you you should
check it out very interesting it's not
mathematical but It talks about how the
top tier VC firms winner take all uh
phenomenon.
City sizes same thing big cities gets
bigger right why in the network theory
because all the nodes want to connect to
a more popular node to attract more
traffic. So the in network space
internet connections web pages or social
uh media posts this type of power law is
very common but in nature we've observed
a lot of uh normal distributions
such as height right so a lot of people
probably centered around uh you know
call it between five to around six uh uh
feet, right? Maybe just under six feet.
Uh this the majority of the population.
Uh it's not like most people are very
short, but there are few giants really
just much taller. So that's power law.
Power law does not exist in the height
distribution.
So now we comment on social many social
phenomena obey power law distribution.
But why? Right? This is the question
always uh make me very curious.
So what's the cause
of such a skilled wealth distribution?
So eventually I realized this actually
has a lot to do with the crowd
interaction. So the same mechanism we
looked at earlier the agents
have the feedback loop that's the reason
of the cost of this type of power law in
nature you don't have that kind of a
feedback mechanism once you are born you
grew to certain height your height
doesn't change but in social phenomenas
that is that's keep changing
So agents have different powers
influencing the market in financial
market. It can rich can get richer. So
we need to model each agent differently.
So we call heterogeneous agents.
So for a random variable uh x the normal
distribution we're all familiar with
right is the e to the x minus the mean /
2 sigma square. But for power law people
a lot of times get confused about the
terminologies.
The parados's law talks about the
cumulative uh uh density uh function uh
of the probability
uh and uh zip zip zip's law talk about
the rank of that uh uh outcome. So
basically the random variable X versus
the rank of X which is more displayed in
this chart
but they all related when we normally
look at the power uh power law in
probability density function.
So that behaves like this versus the
normal distribution. So even
distribution of course is a you know
delta function.
So the parameters of these uh three
different ways of representing power law
they are all linked by that formula. So
power law probability density function
is c overx to the power of a. A is
related to uh the cumulative density
function power K as well as the zips zip
law of parameter B.
So if we look at the the feedback
mechanism
we can
derive that the agents with more power
in this case
which is represented by a varying over
time can gain more power when they bet
in the right direction that when the
observation shows their betting is in
the right direction.
So that's how rich get richer. So that's
how concentration of power uh is formed.
The super agents will be uh born in this
case a system may may not become stable
when that happens and uh I mean this
actually can be expanded into a
discussion of entropy you know what is
order what is stable but this is beyond
the scope of uh this lecture.
uh just to come back why this is all
relevant to portfolio uh management. So
I want to summarize uh in this page of
what we learned today.
Um so portfolio management is about how
to size each investment.
You need to clarify your objectives. You
need to know your loss to tolerance.
Diversification helps but you need to
rebalance.
Volatility is not risk. Shop ratio
doesn't capture skill nor provide
sizing. We should use the new ratio I
presented to you. Capital market
assumptions are not reliable and the
crowding behavior can be pushed markets
to extremes.
You should pay attention to powerful
super agents. Who are the most powerful
super agents you can think about?
Anybody has any idea in the market?
Yes. Yeah. The Fed.
>> So when you invest in the market, you
have to pay attention because they have
such a big power to change the direction
of markets. Yeah.
And uh in the old days, some hedge funds
have more power, but I would say
nowadays definitely the governments.
Yeah. So you need to understand the key
drivers of your portfolio. Um so I want
to stop the lecture here. Uh I want to
take some questions then I will save a
couple of minutes talk about the
investment game. But before I get there
uh let's open up uh for questions.
I packed in a lot of content for today.
I know uh the idea is not necessary to
uh ask you to follow in details because
some of the math you probably need to
derive it yourself to get a feel. But I
want to give you the concepts what the
portfolio construction is all about.
It's about sizing, right? Of
investments. Sizing is about comparison
about investments. So how to compare
them? That's that's what it really comes
down to. Uh so for that
please questions.
>> Yes. questions about like so I know
another thing that can influence
investments is taxes that you have to
pay on like the capital gains or how
long you hold something can vary like
how much taxes you might pay or certain
types of investments might be more tax
sensitive than others is that something
that is considered like
in terms of like investment decisions
>> yeah so that's a that's a great question
you Endowments are taxfree, right?
Right. So, don't consider that. But if
you run a family office, you have to be
very uh careful to plan your capital
gains, right? So, the family offices or
private investors tend to invest more in
long-term private equity because they
don't have to realize those gains. They
invest less in public uh equity for the
tax reason. So, it is a very important
uh parameter.
Yeah. Any
other questions? Yes.
>> What is the best risk measure?
How should you measure risk?
>> Uh so I I still think uh we should try
to understand the uh potential loss or
expected loss. So that's the L I I
discussed earlier. uh you know because
people tend to think you know gain and
loss are symmetrical but normally it's
not the case right because you can
construct your positions have a very
asymmetrical payouts so you need to
understand when when you buy an option
of course your maximum loss is the
option premium you're paid right it's
very clear but when you buy a stock that
may not be so clear right so you need to
understand how much the stock can lose
it can move down and the com what's
likely range it can move down to and
those kind of things so you need to I
think the risk measurement should be
shifted or focused more on the downside
uh protection understand your downside
so which is really expected loss
>> nice yeah the question of like expected
loss versus case loss how do you
>> yeah those are two different things
right so roughly you can Think about
worst loss maybe a you know few standard
deviations away I mean expected loss
probably is really the uh weighted
average of outcome times the payout that
kind of a thing uh so you cannot
construct your portfolio all based on
worst case then you will not be doing
anything right so but so that's why
expected loss is a probably a better way
to uh measure
and for sizing your investments, but you
need to be aware of your worst loss.
Yeah. In in case something happens.
Yeah. Yes.
>> I was going to say going off the worst
case loss kind of like when would you
implement stop losses? How effective
have you found those? Um just kind of
like a little bit more on that as well.
>> Yeah. So, uh yeah, you you I think this
is a very good question both of you uh
brought up. Uh stop-loss is an
interesting concept, right? So stop loss
uh typically is not set at the worst
loss, right? It's kind of set usually
quite close uh probably even closer than
the expected loss. They uh if you're
trading at the hedge fund platforms,
they give you a very tight stop-loss uh
for the reason that they try to
artificially construct asymmetric payout
for the portfolio managers or the
traders. When you lose a little bit,
they cut your position in half, then you
lose another few percentage points, cut
another half, then get you out. So when
you make money, they try to uh let you
ride on the wins to create that kind of
a asymmetric optionality. But uh uh that
forces you to pick investment has that
kind of a probability distribution,
right? So if you think a investment has
a worst case loss which is uh very bad
but has a very low probability let's
just say right and uh so you need to you
need to think about you know if that
almost like uh the firm that takes that
risk for you right because they they are
responsible to cut you out right but if
you think the upside is very big then
you should take that bet right you get
it Yeah.
>> Worst case scenario, you get fired, but
for them
>> Yeah.
>> Right.
>> Right. That's kind of that's Yeah.
That's the kind of the the you know, a
lot of the issues with uh uh hedge
funds, right? They get a cut on the
profit, but they don't bear the downside
responsibilities, right? So, they long
they are long a free call option. So,
yeah. So, that's why a lot of people
want to be a hedge fund manager.
So I I will just touch upon the
investment game. Okay. Uh we already uh
talk about it. When we pass November
15th, we can you know look you you
should keep track of G and L numbers and
uh uh let us know how you performed and
I I will try to verify. But last slide I
want just you know coming back to the
point a lot of people ask how to become
a hedge fund manager right? So I wonder
I maybe I want to pull you the audience
here a little bit. Uh is there a value
you know you think from that trading or
investment game to do some paper trading
games or do you think you want more
lectures on the research process how to
do data collection signal generation the
know back testing all the all the things
and the portfolio optimization as we
talk about today or some people say I
just want to uh learn more about how to
become a manager how to do fundraising
how to build a team, how to negotiate
the terms and how to uh assemble systems
and back office legal taxes and so on.
Uh so I'm actually thinking maybe
there's something you know we as an
organization or some other people should
really just help the younger uh
potential PMs a little more uh to
incubate them to become a a better found
manager. Uh if anyone of you think
that's something uh valid this this idea
you can talk to me you know email me or
just come to me after class uh maybe
this something in beyond what we talk in
this class could be useful to any one of
you.
So with that uh thank you very