let me just do an example inspired by
Steph Curry's performance I looked up
his 3o field goal percentage he makes
44% of them let's assume that every
three-point shot he has the same
probability of making it what's the
probability that he misses the next
three shots and then makes the three
after that would it be 56 Cub time 44
Cub exactly 56 cubed * 44 cubed and how
did we get to that well these are
independent events so to get the
probability of the intersection between
the event that he misses misses misses
then makes makes makes we just take the
sum of the probabilities of each of
those events or
015 now what's the probability of any
particular sequence of three misses and
three shots made right and you your
answer would have been exactly the same
for more MIT moments from MIT open
learning like subscribe or follow