[Music]
Hello, this is Laura Hessie Fischer and
you're listening to Today I Learned
Climate from the Massachusetts Institute
of Technology.
Here's something that people ask us a
lot. Are we worried about the materials
that go into solar panels and batteries?
Sure, they help us head off the dangers
of climate change, but what if making
them pollutes our air or our water? And
yeah, we are worried about this. like to
name one important example. Many
batteries contain nickel and cobalt and
both of them are toxic metals that can
harm miners and the people who live near
the mines. But this got our team
thinking, why do we only hear these
questions about new energy technologies?
We shouldn't forget that our current
energy system, which depends primarily
on fossil fuels, causes serious health
effects because of the emissions of air
pollutants that are involved in the
combustion of those fuels. That's Dr.
Mary Rice. I'm the director of the
Center for Climate Health and the Global
Environment at the Harvard Chan School
of Public Health. And I'm also a
practicing pulmonologist at Beth Israel
Deaconist Medical Center in Boston. When
they're not treating patients, Dr. Rice
and her colleagues study what climate
change is doing to our health. And they
also study what the coal, oil, and gas
that cause climate change do to us. But
how big of a health problem are fossil
fuels really? After all, we've been
burning them for hundreds of years.
Wouldn't we notice by now if they were
harming us? I think we often don't
appreciate the harms because we're all
exposed. And so there's a tremendous
amount of death and illness around the
world due to air pollution exposure
that I think is really underappreciated.
So
I'd like to tell you a story about air
pollution and how the scientific
community realized how deadly it really
was.
In early December 1952, a cold fog
descended upon London. And because of
the cold, Londoners began to burn more
cold than usual. And at the same time,
the final conversion of London's
electronic trams to diesel buses was
completed. And the resulting air
pollution was trapped by a heavy layer
of cold air. The smog was so thick that
people actually couldn't even see. And
in the weeks that followed, the medical
services compiled statistics and found
that that fog had killed 4,000 people.
And another 8,000 people died in the
weeks and months that followed.
This became known as the Great Smog, and
it was one of the first times that
medical researchers looked at two
crucial pieces of data together. How
much smoke was in the air from burning
coal and diesel? and at the same time
how many people were dying of heart and
lung disease. And it turned out that
when the first line went up, the others
shot up right alongside it. And that
event in some ways was the beginning of
environmental epidemiology where the
researchers could look at the data and
make a clear link between pollution,
exposure, and death. We've now had over
70 years of public health research since
the Great Smog. And time and time again,
we found the same link. When people are
exposed to more air pollution from
fossil fuels, we get sicker.
But what exactly is it that makes us
sick? Well, burning coal, oil, and gas
can put lots of things into the air that
are unhealthy to breathe. Nitrogen
oxides, ozone, carbon monoxide. But the
most dangerous is what scientists call
fine particulate matter. And that means
little particles of carbon and metals
that are suspended into the air and can
be inhaled.
And they're small enough to be breathed
in all the way down into the alvolar
sacks, the part of the lung where gas
exchange takes place.
And in that area of the lung, the
particles cause inflammation,
irritation. Think about when you get a
splinter. Your skin gets inflamed,
right? You know, red, swollen. Now,
imagine that happening inside your lungs
day after day just from breathing in
dirty air.
And that inflammation has a spillover
effect into the rest of the body leading
to health effects in distant places. And
that explains why particulate matter
pollution has been linked to heart
disease, brain disease, cancer,
developmental uh delays in children,
cognitive health effects, uh changes in
pregnancy outcomes,
which are all illnesses that we see more
often in people who spend a lot of time
around fossil fuel pollution. certain
occupational groups are more heavily
exposed, right? So, if you work in the
transportation sector, you're exposed to
air pollution at your daily job. If
you're in manufacturing, exposure can be
quite high. Traffic pollution has also
been declared a carcinogen by the WHO
and that's in part due to evidence from
people in the trucking industry who were
heavily exposed to to traffic and had a
higher risk of lung cancer. Air
pollution from traffic can even affect
how kids think and learn.
A study in Massachusetts by my
colleagues found that uh kids who lived
within 50 meters from a major roadway
had lower non-verbal IQs and they
actually had a worse ability to do tasks
that require hand eye coordination
compared to kids who live further away
from roads. Then there are what we might
call environmental pollutants. So, these
are ones that can linger in the
environment for a long time, sometimes
with some particularly nasty impacts.
When coal is burned, sulfur dioxide is
released into the atmosphere. Sulfur
dioxide contributes to acid rain and to
to respiratory illnesses.
Coal also emits mercury and other heavy
metals into the atmosphere.
When you're pregnant, you learn that
mercury is a neurotoxin, which doctors
advise staying away from because of the
effects it can have on unborn babies.
And that mercury and other toxic metals
like lead can also wind up in water and
soil, especially near coal mines. The
use of coal and oil and gas creates
pollution at almost every step, well
before the fuels are actually burned.
fossil fuel extraction, refining, and
manufacturing of byproducts all have
emissions that are unhealthy for
communities and for workers.
And I mean, it's not hard to believe
that breathing thick clouds of coal dust
can't be good for you. But come on,
don't we have regulations to protect us
from that? Well, yeah, we do. Thanks to
policies like the 1970 Clean Air Act,
gas burning cars have catalytic
converters to filter out air pollutants
and coal and gas power plants have
devices called scrubbers that do the
same thing. The Clean Air Act of 1970
has been a real success story. It's been
estimated to avoid 230,000
deaths every year. Well, unfortunately,
there's no safe level of air pollution.
Almost every human on Earth, even in
wealthy countries, breathes air
pollution at levels that are unhealthy.
Wait, that can't be right, can it? I
mean, I care a lot about clean air. My
weather app has one of those like little
air quality trackers from the EPA, and
most days it says that my air quality is
is green. You know, it's good. On the
rare days, it's yellow. I might skip my
morning walk. Well, actually, what I
learned is that this tracker is focused
on levels of air pollution that might
make us sick within hours or days. It
does not show us the low levels that
might accumulate and contribute to
illness over years.
In the US, on the whole, we have
impressively clean air. But even in the
US, we are all exposed to a certain
amount of air pollution, even on those
good green days. For some of us, that
pollution can add up. And that
especially includes children, the
elderly, those with pre-existing
illnesses, and people who happen to live
or work in more polluted places. In the
US, poor neighborhoods often have a
higher density of traffic, more highways
that crisscross one another, poor
neighborhoods are more likely to have a
dense concentration of manufacturing.
So, there's differences based on the
neighborhoods people live in. Even if
you live in a neighborhood with clean
air, our morning commutes can expose us
to much higher levels of pollution.
A major health concern is diesel buses
because kids are exposed to air
pollution on their commutes to school.
As a pulmonologist, I worry a lot about
the respiratory health effects of air
pollution in kids.
Let's zoom out for a minute. We know
that being around fossil fuel pollution
can make you sick, but how many people
are really suffering from this?
Now, answering that is tricky. You know,
no one's death certificate lists air
pollution as the reason that they died.
But public health experts can study what
happens when our exposure rises and
falls. Public health experts can also
compare people who are a lot alike, but
who breathe in different amounts of
pollution. The best numbers that I've
seen from the recent state of global air
report by the health effects institute
estimated that over 8 million people
died from air pollution in 2021.
An estimated 2.3 million people died of
air pollution exposure in China, 2
million in India. In the United States,
an estimated 63,600
people died. That makes air pollution
the second leading risk factor for death
after high blood pressure. To put that
in perspective, the total death toll of
the COVID pandemic was about 7 million.
Air pollution takes more lives than that
every year. And most of that air
pollution comes from burning fossil
fuels.
Look, every technology has risks. And
maybe having cheap, easy access to
energy is worth some exposure to air
pollution. But as someone whose job it
is to help build perspective on climate
change and climate solutions, I do find
myself thinking about this a lot. In
fact, I think about it every time I meet
someone who tells me that they're
worried about the lithium and batteries
or the silver and solar panels.
I think that there's a tendency to
assume that whatever we're doing now
must be okay and that therefore the
risks of doing something new must be
very worrisome.
But what if the greatest costs are the
ones that were already bearing?
We have so much to gain from a public
health standpoint from switching from
our dependence on fossil fuels to
renewable energy. And importantly, those
health benefits are immediate. I'm not
talking about the changing climate here.
I'm talking about the immediate benefits
of cleaner air for our kids, for
ourselves.
And that doesn't erase my concerns about
the materials that go into solar panels
and batteries. It just reminds me that
we're not adding these technologies to a
world that until now was pollutionfree.
I mean, today the world mines about 9
billion tons of coal a year, or more
than one ton for every person on Earth.
Oil, too, is pumped out of the ground in
incredible amounts, more than 35 billion
barrels a year. That's enough to
overflow two bathtubs for every person
on the planet. And that energy system,
as we learn today, comes with loads of
pollution.
And I have a lot of hope that our future
energy mix will come with a lot less.
That's our episode for today. But if you
have your own questions about fossil
fuels and clean energy technologies to
replace them, well, we love hearing from
our listeners. Leave us a voicemail at
617-253-3566
or visit climate.mmit.edu/
ask. Today I learned climate is the
climate change podcast of the
Massachusetts Institute of Technology.
Aaron Kroll is our writer and executive
producer. David Lashansky is our sound
editor and producer. Madison Goldberg is
our associate producer. Michelle Harris
is our fact checker. The music is by
Blue Dot Sessions. And I am your host
and senior editor, Laura Hesy Fischer.
Thank you to Dr. Mary Rice for speaking
with us and to you, our listeners.