It's my pleasure now to welcome Dr.
Deni, Dr. Deni Bodto, co-founder and CEO
at Muan Vision. So, Muan Vision uses
cosmic ray muan tomography to
non-invasively x-ray mining assets,
enabling real time surface fluid and
density monitoring for safer and more
efficient mineral discovery.
>> Here we are. Thank you, Thricia, and
thank you, Eduardo. And hello, everyone.
My name is Tanky BTO. I'm the CEO and
co-founder of M Vision. Previously I was
an MIAT scientist and I've also worked
in oil and gas exploration for 15 years.
Mining metals is key to our future. Yet
the industry squeeze between massive
increased demand and chronically low or
grades. That means that much more earth
needs to be moved mined and much more
energy water consumed to process the
same one ton of copper. Mu vision wants
to break this cycle. Our mission is to
boost efficiency, safety and
sustainability of critical minerals
processing while supporting the industry
transformation towards digital
operations.
I will pick as an example the heat
leaching process which today is a
hundred billion dollar industry and
accounts for 20% of worldwide copper and
other metals. Heap leeching is the
preferred solution for lowgrade ores
that are expected to soon be a primary
source of new copper. In heat leaching,
minor is crushed and then stacked into
huge piles which are then irrigated with
an acid containing solution that ideally
distributes uniformly dissolving the
metal containing the mineral grains and
being collected at the bottom. In
practice, there are many reasons why
moisture across the leeching acid is not
uniform. This leads to two problems.
volumes with too little fluid will
produce less metal and volumes where too
much fluid has accumulated may trigger
potentially catastrophic landslide. So
the question is ultimately how much
moisture and where is it you have inside
a leeching heap. But how can you
quantitatively and accurately measure
that? Uh this is an important question I
believe for any implementation of any AI
or machine learning uh um uh solution as
you heard from Brian before. After all,
most sensors still provide pointlike
information which in this case will be
completely insufficient and even the
most advanced X-ray or geophysical
probes only measured at across a few
inches at best. So what is our solution
to this problem?
>> In the last few decades, scientists have
finally been able to look inside ancient
pyramids and volcanoes. Muon Vision is
now using that same technology to
revolutionize mining. The breakthrough
behind this revolution, muon
radiographic imaging, also known as
murography. Muons are subatomic
particles naturally formed when
radiation from distant supernova
explosions collide with the Earth's
atmosphere. Muons constantly penetrate
every square meter on the surface of the
Earth.
At Muon Vision, we've developed a
subterranean technology capable of
detecting and recording muons as they
travel deep underground. We then use
that data to create 3D density maps of
large above ground structures like
tailings dams and leech piles. In a
mineral leech pile, for example, Muon
Vision's technology can identify dry,
low density areas where leeching fluid
isn't reaching. When operators can see
this issue, they have the chance to
adjust their processing and prevent
hundreds of millions of dollars in
assets from being left behind. In
tailings dams, the same technology can
also precisely determine the static
vertical stresses on the material as
well as friatic levels, thus validating
the dam design and helping increase its
performance. When you see deeper, you
can work smarter. Muon detection
empowers you to look inside mining's
largest structures and optimize for
efficiency, profitability, and safety.
See deeper with Muon vision
in the
>> Okay, thank you. So, our solution is
ultimately a nuclear imaging detector
and is analogous to take a diagnostic
X-ray over an unprecedented large
distance scale. This allows us to scan
inside these high-v value assets in
order to identify, locate, and quantify
underperforming volumes or regions. And
with that information, we can then
recommend practical and already
available remedial strategies. After
all, you can't manage what you don't
measure. Our diagnostic surveys can
generate value in numerous ways in
leeching operations. Primarily by
significantly boosting metal recovery
via optimized digital operations as well
as identify secondary leeching
opportunities. Equally important, more
precise leeching is also less costly and
can optimize cars water budget. Finally,
our service helps manage multi
catastrophic slope stability and reduce
unnecessary uh the risk of unnecessary
personal exposure. I want to conclude by
showing you an example of our technology
at work. So think of a leeching heap in
its initial state as a dry sponge and
our density measurement as a balance
scale that is inserted under the heap.
Now add fluid. Now this displays the air
and increases the bug density of the
material. Something we do measure
accurately by observing the
corresponding decrease in the immune
flux during this transient phase. But
now look at what happens after the first
100 hours. Although the irrigation rate
is the same, the heap has now lost
weight and has settled into an
equilibrium where you have considerably
less moisture than planned. Why? While a
simple explanation because the high
irrigation rate has caused preferential
flow channels. In other words, the fluid
escapes more quickly and less metal will
be produced. This is a well-known and
hard to predict problem and something
you simply cannot look by just looking
at the heat from the outside.
To conclude, we have developed a new
applications for neon radiography, a
well-known niche technologies. This has
allowed us to build a unique patent mode
around its many high value potential
applications. We are seeking
collaborations and partnerships across
industries to advance high value use
cases and commercialize our solutions to
long intractable problems. Thank you.
>> Excellent. Thank you so much. We do have
a few questions and a minute or two to
um for you to to elicit your response.
So you mentioned tailing dams. Can you
briefly illustrate how your technology
adds value in this case?
>> Yes. Uh we pl I think I'm still sharing.
Uh essentially the value that we will
bring teley dimes first of all it's a
well-known issue in the in the mineral
processing industry and you know as left
horrible legacies around the world. How
we bring value? Well consider what is
the state-ofthe-art today for analyzing
tailing times. In the best case
scenario, lowc cost technologies like
taking a sample which typically is not
deep enough are used and the next sample
may be several hundred meters away and
this is very hard to understand what's
going to happen to something which is
large dimension by by definition. So the
value we bring is to validate these
asset models measuring key properties
like stress as well as moisture content
as well as density non-uniformities
which are not expected uh to be there in
the first place and of course provide
long-term monitor.
>> Excellent. Thank you. And and quickly
the last uh question are there other
applications for moan radiograph um
outside what you have discussed today?
uh there are we believe of course
murography is a passive technology so
it's difficult for us to accelerate it
most applications fall in the mining
space we have built a patent portfolio
on slope stability and leeching heaps
but there are classical applications
like void detection and mineral
exploration which are accessible to
everyone as well as we believe novel
applications in mining plants uh similar
heavy industries are likely to have uh
uh potential applications as well. Thank
you.
>> Excellent. Well, thank you so much. It
was such a pleasure. Incredible
presentation.