All right. Well, my name is Tony. I'm
the CEO and co-founder of Stack Aai. I
did my PhD here at MIT together with my
co-founder. And Stackai is building AI
agents for the enterprise. We are having
an approach that basically connects very
much data with LLM with SAS platforms.
The way we do it is um with a platform
that is basically encapsulating
everything as nodes that you can connect
together. The nodes that we have are
from the most common databases and where
uh uh content management systems that
you have in enterprise. It goes from
SharePoint, Salesforce, Snowflake to the
different LM providers that you have
there. OpenAI, Coher, Anthropic and so
on. The idea is very much that you can
drag and drop nodes and connect them
with a visual editor that you can see
here. It's very small but hopefully you
can see that there are nodes that you
can connect. Once you have this back end
which by the way is LLM agnostic,
knowledge base agnostic and SAS tool
agnostic. You can deploy it with
different interfaces. We connect with
all your communication channels. It can
go from email, Slack, teams. Um it can
be from messaging systems but also end
to end interfaces. This means with UI
and UX included. Chat GPT interface is a
very common one but also form interfaces
with fixed inputs and fixed outputs.
badge interfaces that looks like
spreadsheets and of course API endpoints
that you can call uh your IT department
can connect to very easily. The idea is
that once you deploy this platform and
these AI agents it can go from mostly
back office automation uh from IT
support desk to other kind of tasks that
are repetitive or those that are not
that repetitive but that have like some
level of reasoning and then you feel
confident they can uh you could auto
automate. Once you deploy that, you have
an analytics dashboard where you can
monitor all the runs, users, tokens
used, errors, and so on. It's a very
visual interface so that even CIOS can
plug in, see what's happening, what are
the AI agents that you're deploying.
We're working with very big companies
that are deploying many of those and
observability, predictability, rolebased
access control is critical for them. Uh
we are so two type two compliant, HIPPA
compliant for all our teleaalth medicine
uh customers that we have. We have
public uh companies in the tele health
space as well and GDPR for all our
customers in uh Europe. We uh also offer
on premise deployments. We have a
defense company for example that needed
everything in their on premise and I'm
not even talking about Azure kind of
deployments. I'm talking about raw
servers but we also do virtual private
cloud Azure AWS GCP you name it. We've
done deployments across the world even
in Australia. Um we operate across the
world as I was saying US, Canada and uh
Europe are the main customers but also
Asia Pacific, Japan and so on. Uh in
terms of uh industries we're a very
horizontal platform where we focus on uh
healthcare companies, finance and also
logistics though we are working with
defense companies, public sector,
Massachusetts government is also
interested in our platform and so on.
MIT is actually a big customers of ours.
We have 3,500 users here. So very proud
partners and um in terms of like use
cases uh I'll just touch on some of
these but Freya is one that I love
because they were uh operating in Europe
and they had uh lots of logistics kind
of like operations there and they have
to handle a lot of languages Nordic
languages mostly Norian Swedish and so
on and the idea that they could do
everything in Stati without using all
the third party software was very
enticing to them also they've deployed a
lot of use cases right now they have
more mostly on the support desk IT side
of things and uh since then I mean
they've automated uh many things that
are from operations to uh business to
even marketing and SEO optimization of
the website like there's lots of use
cases that can be applied with stack
we're also working with uh live MD
public healthcare company uh in the tele
health side of things what they mostly
do is like conversations patients to
doctors and what they've done is like a
copilot that helps doctors interact with
the patients without having to change uh
tabs and and and windows. So basically
they have the conversation with the
patient and the right information about
the patient is displayed right next to
their conversation. The we're also
working these are anonymized use cases.
Unfortunately I cannot share uh push the
customer but basically one of the
biggest digital banks in the world. They
have 100 million customers right now and
they've automated risk and compliance
via copilos that they deploy in Slack.
And then we have one of the top 10 civil
engineering firms in the US that are
building billions of dollars for bridges
and stadiums and things like that. And
they've indexed 7,000 of the employ the
CVS of the employees that they have
internally. And now they are managing to
connect these employees to the right
RFPs, the requests for proposals or
projects um to automate this whole uh
process of creating these uh
documentation. And with that they are
able to apply to projects much faster
than their competition. Something that
they were before doing by calling the
Ohio office. Hey, who do you know that
is an expert in glass ceilings for
stadiums? Now they do it
conversationally uh much faster with our
platform partnership asking for
distribution partners. Now we're talking
with big uh consulting firms that are
happy to partner with us to distribute
this uh platform but also on boarding
new customers in different industries,
regulated industries that deal with a
lot of unstructured data are our you
know bread and butter of sorts. So if
you are one of those, let me know and uh
feel free to reach out directly to my
email or the
enterprise.com. Thank you so much.
Thanks Claus. How do you compare your
solution to hyperscaler solutions like
agent space or copilot? Very good
question. Um one customer put it really
well. Copilot studio feels like internet
explorer versus Google Chrome. So your
choice to select one or the other. Um
but it's much much easier, much faster.
Um you you'll see the value in minutes
instead of days.
Um and how long are your sales cycles
considering everything that you said? So
for example, the the civil engineering
firm, it took two weeks. It's kind of
funny because the CIO saw a video about
us and and and he was like, "Hey, I like
this." And he skipped through the whole
process. He was the CIO also, so he
could skip a lot and we went straight to
that. But for example for life MD it
took three months through procurement
compliance. There's also like all the
red lining for the contracts and stuff
like that. So it can take uh longer than
that of course like the defense company
I was telling you about took about six
months and that was the most complicated
one I would say. Thank you.