all right so let's get started let's
welcome Henry vanen bam uh he is the
senior vice president machine learning
research chem informatics and atom wise
Inc and also a professor in
UCSF the stage is yours all
right thank you and thank you for uh
thank I want to thank the organizers for
the opportunity uh to to speak here so
developing and using generative AI for H
identification and uh and optimization
um I'm at Adam wise Adam wise is a um AI
first preclinical small molecule drug
Discovery uh company and you know when
we're thinking about AI in drug
Discovery especially for small molecules
the conversation very quickly turns to
faster and cheaper um but we believe
that the the True Value uh for Pharma is
delivered by either first-in-class or
best-in-class uh medicine so
first-in-class is there no known ligans
for that particular particular Target
and Best in Class is we try to escape
limitations of uh of known
chemotypes and so we develop technology
to focus on either first in class or um
or Best in Class um we have our uh
internal pipeline um shown here um in
particular I want to highlight tik2 CNS
and i4r um both would be first-in-class
uh uh medicines for us and in addition
to these uh we also um have um uh
programs with our external big PHA uh
Partners all right we believe that uh
that AI in particular can uh can add
value to First in class and and and Best
in Class by exploring designs that are
Beyond human intuition and what I mean
by that is in a more traditional sort of
AI uh AI workflow in um in drug
Discovery um the models score a lot of
uh a lot of compounds and then the
medicinal chemists look at it and decide
which compounds we are going to make um
an an essay and that's what you see in a
more traditional sort of CAD workflow we
had adom wise um and what you get is
sort of the consensus between the
machine learning uh models and the um
and a medical chemist what we do at adom
WISE is trying to build on the Synergy
of uh of of these two and and really
look at the union so our models
typically evaluate millions or billions
of of compounds especially in uh in hit
Discovery um and uh and generate in a
way an order list of let's say 400 or
800 uh compounds and we order that uh
that list no matter what even if our
medicinal chemists don't recognize
immediately that this is a compound that
could be uh that could be successful in
other words we don't build a human
classifier on top of a a Ai and that's
important because when I put on my AI
hat I don't I want my models to learn
from what they predict right and that's
very critical to um in a in an active
learning uh
cycle all right when I say models um our
our models are um are what we call
Global models Global structure-based
models what I mean by that is they are
trained simultaneously on um on uh about
7,000 uh uh targets um about 20 million
uh bi biological data points that go uh
that go into that and in a in a in a
typical training run we generate about
1.1 billion Co co- complexes now these
sound like hug huge numbers of course
but if you think about the universe of
um um of possible compounds this is just
a drop in the in the bucket right the
reason we employ um Global models is
that we want our models to learn the
mechanisms of of molecular recognition
because we feel that is transferable
across the uh the entire uh the entire
proteome and that's a little bit in
contrast to um you know the more Target
specific models where you have one
target you look at the compounds that uh
that are known for that Target um and
you train a model uh based on that the
limitation of that is it's often very
difficult to um to generalize away from
the from the chemotypes that are already
known from that uh from that
Target all right um we tested our our
our model mod um actually we we do
continuous testing but um but in in this
particular case we went out to our
partners and um and academic uh
collaborators um to run a very very
large hit Discovery campaign on 318 uh
targets um Al together and we got quite
good results we we found hits for about
74% of uh of these targets and I want to
in particular call your attention to uh
uh this graph over here each dot
represents a Target in this um in this
plot on the horizontal axis you see the
number of examples that we have in our
training uh set for this particular uh
uh Target and so what you should be
particularly um devoting your attention
to is this rectangle here these are
targets for which we have no data in our
um in our training set and so what that
means is these are really the first
in-class targets um that could be uh of
interest and you see that we actually
get um pretty pretty good hit rates for
uh for those uh for those targets we
published this study uh just earlier
this year um AI is a viable alternative
to high througho screening a 38 Target
study the paper has 689 authors uh by
far the longest list that I've ever been
um uh uh uh part
of all right so what is critical um what
is critical if you're interested
interested in first in-class uh Target
is to to overcome a a covariant shift
between your training data and and the
data that you're uh that you're
performing inference on so training data
is often you know very very nice
molecules often drugs that have been in
a clinic and so they look very different
than the kind of hit molecules that you
typically get out of uh out of a screen
and so machine learning models don't
know very well how to um how to deal
with that so there are two aspect
effects to it first of all we so what
they just talked about is is really the
extrapolating to uh to new new
chemotypes so want to understand want
the model to understand like what could
potential new chemotypes look like the
other one of of course is extrapolating
to new targets um so the vast majority
of training data is available for
Kinesis no surprise and so if you're
interested in cytokines you need to
think about how do we make the model
aware of uh of of cyto so general
generalizability of the models is really
key to unlocking first inclass and
best-in-class uh compounds at least
that's the way uh we see
it and so about a year ago we realized a
way or we found a way
um um to um help our models overcome
that coari shift by self-supervised
learning so we have these uh these big
gnns and we we figured out a way to self
to to pre-train these models on chemical
data and Target data um for which there
are no labels so for which there's no
potency data for which there's no um
activity data in a way taking a a page
out of the book of uh of llms right
large pre-trained models that we then
sort of fine-tune based on uh on on
label data and that has really changed
the way we think about a model so we
pre-train our models on on a large body
of unlabeled data that gives us a base
model and then we use the 20 million uh
data points to in a way um develop a
task specific model and task specific
here means either an activity model so a
classification model uh for our
compounds or a regression model and this
really goes to this Union of human
design versus AI designed compounds
because if you if you pre-train your
models on unexplored chemical space it's
these compounds that that human
typically don't have a lot of intuition
um about our models responded quite well
um to this so this model here is the
model that I just showed you for the 318
targets and so for a long time we were
having um a lot of difficulty building
more expressive models because as soon
as you added more parameters they
started overfitting pre-training solved
that for us so we see vastly more
expressive models we've been able to um
increase the number of parameters for
our GNN uh 20 fold um we see huge um uh
improvements in both classification and
uh and regression performance by uh by
by taking this
approach all right so let me shift gears
a little bit and and talk about what
we're doing in um in generative AI in uh
in hit Discovery and talk about our our
latest model uh which we call
neurogenesis ngt um for uh for
short generative AI in drug Discovery is
um there's a lot of Buzz um about it but
the main problem in in generative AI in
in drug Discovery is that it comes up
with these fantastic compounds but you
can't make them they're extremely
difficult to make and and that is how
hallucination manifests itself in
generative AI in uh in drug Discovery
and that was um sort of summarized very
nicely um in a paper in Jacks uh just uh
just last year it's a real problem um of
course because you know what is key to
driving a drug Discovery campaign is
that you have access to to compounds
that are readily synthesizable um you
can't wait months for a compound to uh
to be to be
synthesizable so the flip side of this
is that you have commercially available
combinatorial synthesis libraries um and
those are massive compound spaces of
synthetically accessible compounds that
you know cost maybe 100 or $150 um a pop
and they have been growing very very
rapidly over the over the last few years
the latest um enamine is a is a very uh
well-known provider of these kind of uh
combine libraries their latest one is
about 70 billion compounds um the
largest we have in house is 16
quadrillion compounds I want to point
out that the scale here on the Left End
side is in billions of uh of compounds
so these spaces are huge and that comes
with the problem of its own so how do
you now search these vast compound
spaces for um for uh for hits well we
figured um we take um The Best of Both
Worlds we use these Comin combinatorial
synthesis libraries libraries as the
universe from which we want to generate
uh compounds so we use generative AI um
to generate compounds out of these huge
csls so let me walk you through very
quickly on how we uh how we approach
that for that you need to know a little
bit how a CSL Works a CSL is nothing but
um a large set of building blocks called
synthons that you see here plus a set of
rules on how put to put these syons
together um so here this is an example
from enamine three building blocks a
rule and you get a compound out of it um
so the way we approach the problem is we
we frame retrieval of compounds out of
the CSL as an autoencoding uh problem uh
so nothing new here this is a
variational auto encoder so we encode
the library in a latent space and we
design the encoder in such a way that if
you sample latent space the compound
that you get back is guaranteed to be in
this uh in this CSL and that is um
actually not that hard because what you
need to learn is a synthesis Rule and
then the ideas of the of the um of of
the two R groups or three R groups or
four R groups um depending on how many
there are for uh for that particular
um uh
compound so that's all good and well and
you can sample uh you can sample your
latent space but how do you now get um
compounds that are um uh that have
desirable properties right like Pat
earlier this uh talked about you know
that we're not quite there yet um using
Mo on um uh on on these kind of compound
uh compound queries um and so how do we
how do we go about that here is a very
simple example of course lipinsky rule
of five could be something that you're
interested in in retrieving from the
from the uh library and not not that we
are very interested in liins R 5 but
everybody uh knows this one of course um
so to approach that problem we took our
um our variational Auto encoder and then
used reinforcement learning to train uh
a policy to induce a distribution over
uh over latent space um in such a way
that compounds that satisfy these
properties have a a High um uh a high
probability of being sampled um in that
um in in that space so I should add here
we made um so typically when you do that
when you typically when you train um a
policy with reinforcement learning it's
it's typically mod seeking so it focuses
of on a very small part of uh of latent
space and so we made um a a um a
specific effort to to train this policy
uh so that it's actually Mass covering
so that you get a large variety of
compounds um in latent space that
satisfy um this uh this
property okay we put this uh we put this
through the test in a in a in a case
study that was actually published just
this week in the Journal of uh of
medicinal uh chemistry where we used a
uh a CSL of three trillion compounds
uh to test our uh to test our method um
very quickly um we we wanted to we
wanted to try this on a on a challenging
challenging example so we chose a
gpcr um it's it's called mc2r um and
it's um it's agonized by um by a by a
hormone act it's a therapeutic Target
for uh for Cushings Disease and actually
kinetics uh a biotech is going into pH
uh uh phase two clinical trials um with
with an antagonist
um and what is important to realize here
is that selectivity is critical and
challenging and that's why that's part
of the reason why this uh Target is uh
is is challenging um um this hormone
activates all all of this uh gpcrs ISO
forms so
um it's a it's a hard
problem um when we started this problem
there were no mc2r antagonist in the
literature so again this was an kind of
an example for uh for a first in class
uh application of our uh of our method
when we do hit Discovery we typically
screen against an uh an against a
confirmation Ensemble of of receptors so
we took an activated mc2r domain uh we
typically include an alpha fold model
even though those are often uh APO uh
APO structures and then we took a
homology model from an MC for our uh
Crystal structures as I said we took a
three trillion uh compound library that
is uh called unreal um and um actually
um it's now also available from uh from
enamine and um we also of course wanted
to um compare our methods to what we
thought was a state-of-the-art method um
to uh to search these large libraries um
that was published I think two years ago
it's called v v synthes really fragment
growing up
approach um yeah very quickly um our
method actually did very well um we
found um uh our hit rate was about uh
12% um for our method slightly higher
than um then v v synus um a hit we
defined as more than 50% inhibition at
uh at at at 30 micromolar um and then
with the hits actually we selected a
subset of of hits that um that uh
actually had favorable um
solubility um we took them into a dose
response essay um we found micromolar
hits um uh with our method as well as
with uh with the vnus method they're
pretty much indistinguishable in uh in
terms of uh of of of potency our
compound is slightly smaller so has a
slightly better um liant deficiency um
an important point to uh at least what
we thought was important was if you look
at this Disney plot um over here that
the vynus compounds tended to Cluster
together they're all um pretty similar
what you see from our method is that uh
our Mass covering um approach actually
paid off you see a lot more diversity in
the scaffolds that you uh that you get
back and as every medicinal chemist will
tell you if you have uh a couple of
starting scaffolds in a drug Discovery
campaign that will help you out uh
tremendously so more diversity means
more shots on goal
um and um you know
serendipitously maybe um our our
compound actually uh turned out to be
the most selective uh among isoforms uh
as well um that brings me to the end of
uh of my presentations um key takeaways
key takeaways at least for me sure data
is King
but you know 20 million data points if
we like we cannot add data fast enough
to uh to train our um machine learning
models um with better data right that
would be enormously costly effort so I
would say data is King but
self-supervised uh learning rules for
now um the key to better performance is
upscaling the models um without
overfitting I think again
self-supervised learning can can help
you there um just went over the uh the
ngt generative AI so I'll just leave
those uh slides up and uh and I'm taking
[Applause]
questions thank you
questions hi thanks for the talk I had a
question about the how you avoided mode
seeking for the RL did you use anything
like um recurrent experience repeats and
stuff to help it maintain like a wide
distribution or can you talk a little
about that no we we developed a um a
family of uh of what we call Alpha
divergences so it's essentially um K
divergences with a with a parameter that
um that you can um that you can select
so that it becomes either more mod
seeking or um or more more mass covering
and so you train the policy with that
family of uh of K di virgin
and that gives us the uh the mass
covering um policy thank you sure
details are in the paper go
ahead uh hi next Ty I was wondering if
you tried using conditional generation
in place of the policy for a generation
and and if so how it compared we didn't
um and you know it's interesting like in
machine learning I think nowadays
methods commoditize so quickly that you
know you put something out out and like
a week later a grad student has made an
improvement to your method that you you
know spend like nine months developing
and and so that's great about the field
right um so you know there's many many
ways to solve this problem so yeah I
would say get behind your computer and
uh thank you sure okay one quick
question yes oh first as as in as in
alumni information and to
for for the variation of out quor have
you tested how it Compares with
so-called moleular molecular language
modules like for example Mega mulber or
M former where you also can sample
Lattin space and potentially generate
molecules this dat properties
yeah so for us it was important to to
solve the um synthetic accessibility
problem it was really important that we
generated compounds that were in the CSL
and so if you look at more former or
more former XL um you know it it's
exactly the problem it creates great
compounds and then we go to to enine or
any vendor and they scratch their hats
and they say yeah this is a list of 400
we can maybe make two I was
on receiving ends of of those requests
so I fully understand I see yes
um thank you all right one very quick
question sure you have shown a heat rate
of 12.5% there was a bar PL what's the
range of heat rate across drugable
versus undruggable targets what is your
current
observation well undruggable would be 0%
almost by definition 0% then you had
success you showed right so what what
does the current heat rate Spectrum
looks
like um yeah I well my slides are gone I
I think if you look at that that first
rectangle that I showed on that that
plot there um so these were targets for
which we have no data in uh in in our in
our training set the hit rate varied
from 0% to uh to 25% so it really
depends on on the targets you know
interesting there too was if you looked
at the horizontal axis there were also
Targets in there for which we had
thousands of compounds in our data set
but we didn't find hits with uh with a
model yeah so it the take away from that
plot is there's almost no correlation
between you know the amount of data that
you have available uh for a Target and
and the hit rate that you that you get
yeah all right so let's thank the
speaker one more time
[Applause]