my name is Ariel first and I am the Palm
cook Career Development professor of
chemical engineering I started at MIT in
2019 and my lab generally focuses on
energy Equity that's the idea that
marginalized and disadvantaged
communities have been disproportionately
impacted by
industrialization and they're often left
out of the conversation and Technologies
to combat the um the challenges
associated with that and the kind of
pollu associated with that so the idea
of energy Equity is that as researchers
it's our job to develop technologies
that are accessible and um also we
strive for energy Justice which is to
remediate those prior harms I get made
fun of a lot by my students because I
always say microbes are the coolest
microbes can pretty much do everything
that we've tried to do chemically
they're like tiny little chemical
factories that can produce whatever we
want and they have 4 billion years of
evolution on anything a student can do
during their PHD so we try to harness
what Nature has already evolved to um
produce greed materials to um
make probiotics and other
Biotherapeutics that um can help humans
and also to make processes like
agriculture more sustainable by using
microbes that would natively be in the
soil instead of chemicals um one of our
major breakthroughs in that area is that
surprisingly many microbes when you take
them out of their comfy cozy home
wherever they live uh they don't like to
keep living without their neighbors and
without the nutrients in that
environment and so they're actually
really hard to formulate to deliver back
to these environments so whether that's
your gut or the soil um or even the
built environment and things like
self-healing cement and so what we try
to do is develop materials that are
based on bioderived components so things
like green tea extract or components
that are founded wine and coffee and we
can form little suits of armor on the
microbes that protect them from these
stressors and allow them to be delivered
to where they need to go microbes can be
used for many different Industries uh
right now one of the areas we are very
focused on is microbes and agriculture
mostly because in Native systems that's
what supplies nutrients to plants and
protects them from p and things like
that so the fact that we use chemical
fertilizers and pesticides right now is
basically destroying what was natively
there so right now the microbial
agriculture Market is about a $4 billion
Market which sounds large but the
agrochemical market is $250 billion and
we think with our uh kind of Nano suits
of armor that allow us to make these
microbes and manufacture them at scale
that we can deliver these and replace a
lot lot of those
agrochemicals so when we think about
agriculture it's actually one of the
major contributor to to greenhouse gases
so CO2 emissions from one of the main
processes to make nitrogen fertilizers
uh represents about 2% of global CO2
emissions and agriculture in general is
about 11% of us CO2 emissions so it's a
pretty significant contributor this is
mostly because of the production and
transport of those agrochemicals um we
see innovation in the space as people
trying to make those chemical processes
Greener that's a lot of What organic
farming is but what we really want to do
is move from chemicals to what we call
regenerative agriculture which is the
idea that if you deliver live microbes
back to the soil they'll be able to
sustain themselves and keep the soil
healthy for long past just the
application of those microbes so right
now most of the people working on
regenerative agriculture
um are very wealthy Farmers so the
challenge with not being able to store
and transport microbes is that you can't
transport them to where they need to go
so Brazil is one of the leaders in these
techniques generally regenerative EG so
wealthy Farms there have these giant
fermenters on site where they can
deliver the live microbes the problem
with that is that it's very limited and
who has access to this technology and so
bringing it back to our lab's goal of
energy Equity we wanted to develop a way
that everyone had access to this
technology not just people that can
afford these
fermentors um and this challenge in
formulation has been a problem for about
three or four decades with very little
innovation in the space people have
added chemicals to stabilize microbes
and other um biologics mostly for human
consumption for Biotherapeutics but none
of them really work so um we found these
Networks that are comprised of basically
minerals that you would take in vitamins
every day plus these components like
green tea extract and they make these
little cages that protect the microbes
from outside stressors