Okay everyone. Um so so today uh we're
going to learn some of the fundamental
estimates of projection theory for balls
in the plane for the setting of real
analysis. Um there are kind of two goals
of the class. The first goal is to adapt
the techniques that we learned last time
in finite fields. So the double counting
technique and the forier technique to
uklitian space. Um and the second goal
is to start to explore. So there's a
difference between uklidian space and
finite fields is that in uklidian space
we have to pay attention to how the how
our sets are clustered. And so the
second goal of the class is to start to
explore uh clustering can cl information
about how the sets are clustered and and
how that comes into the store.
Okay,
so here's our setup.
We'll have X will be a set
of disjoint
unit balls
in um in the ball of radius R in the
plane.
Okay, so that's our set of points, set
of balls. And then we're going to have a
set of directions called D. So D is a
finite subset of S1. It's 1 / R
separated. So the distance between any
two points of D is at least one / R
D. Um and then S which depends on X and
D
is the maximum size of the projection.
So I look at all the ang all the
directions in D and I project the set X
in that direction and I take its measure
and the maximum of that is called S.
Okay. So projection theory we try to
understand how these things are related
to each other and in this uklidian
setting we also need to care about how
this set X and how the set D are
clustered.
So that's measured by I guess call them
clustering functions. So n subx of
little r is the measures the most amount
of x in any ball of radius little r. So
this is the maximum
over c in r2 or um of the size of x
intersected with the ball around c of
radius r.
So this measures how x is clustered and
we're also going to measure how d is
cluster clustered. So n subd of row
is the maximum
over any uh so sigma in s1 and arc
of length row of d intersect zip.
Okay.
Okay. So our big goal is in terms of
this information and and how big d is
and how big x is. What can we say about
S?
Okay.
Okay. So, we're first going to do the
double counting approach.
And the argument is in in spirit the
same as last time. But we'll see that
when we try to do the double counting
that we did last time that the n subx
function and the n subd function will
come into the store and it leads to the
following bound. So theorem one I'll
call it theorem 1 r r r r r r r r r r r
r r r r r r r r r r for the real case.
Uh whereas last time we had something
called theorem one which when I do it
again it'll be theorem 1 f for the
finite field case and eventually we'll
compare them.
Okay. So if we have this setup
then
the number of directions is bounded by
let's see
okay so you'll notice that this is not a
formula that I have memorized
[Music]
s overx times the sum over different
scales else.
Cool. Okay. So, it's a sum over
different scales and we often in this
class will sum over a diadic sequence of
scales, powers of two or whatever. Um uh
okay and um and the so the formula
doesn't yet look that similar but the
the idea is the same as last time and
then eventually we'll compare the
formulas and see that under certain
assumptions on this it's actually very
similar to last time.
Okay.
So the proof is to double count a
certain quantity which which we which we
called coincidences last time. So the
key quantity called star
is the number of
b1 and b2 in x. So these are these are
unit balls.
So remember x is a set of unit balls. So
these are two of the unit balls. Um and
um theta and d I guess we'll say they're
not equal to each other although that
won't matter as much this time. um
uh so that pi theta of b1 and pi theta
of b2 are similar to each other and in
this setting we won't count they don't
have to be exactly the same I would just
like them to overlap so my condition
will be that the intersection of these
is non empty so that's my key quantity
[Music]
actually in this setup. I'm going to I'm
going to allow them to be equal to each
other. Um that makes the double counting
a little easier and in a sense it's
we'll see it's it's part of what's up
here.
Okay. So um so there's a lower bound
which is straightforward.
The lower bound says that this this star
is at least the number of directions
times in each direction
x over s^2
* s.
So in each direction these x different
balls have been projected into only s
slots. So a typical slot has x over s
balls in its fiber. And so we have this
many squared choices for to pick B1 and
B2 in the same five
s times. So lower bound is is really the
same as last time.
Same as last time, same as the homework.
Okay. So now let's look at the upper
bound.
So I will uh for now I'll fix B1 B2 and
I'll say that the distance between B1
and B2 is around R.
Um so here's my picture
B1 and B2 and the distance between them
is around R.
Okay. So now I'm interested in
projections where the projection of B1
and the projection of B2 overlap. And so
the angles for those projections are in
a little angular range. The angle of the
projection must be somewhere in this
range here.
So what um what I'll say is let's say
that V is the direction from B1 to to to
B2. So v is um center of b2 minus center
of b1
over the norm of that.
And
if pi theta of b1 intersect pi theta b2
is not empty
um then
theta must be pretty close to v. What
I'll say is that the angle
between theta and v is smaller than
around 1 / r.
Okay.
Um so now
the number of theta so that pi theta of
b1 intersect pi theta of b2 is not empty
that would be bounded by well the number
of directions in this little arc. So
that would be nd of 1 / r. So we see the
spacing uh the spacing function of the
set d comes into play here.
Okay, so that's what happens when we fix
B1 and B2.
And the case B1 equals B2 is allowed.
And I'll make the slightly funny
convention that then R is one. They're
unit ball. So the distance between them
is sort of one. And this is true. Then I
mean V is not well defined, but this
condition includes the whole range of
angles. So it's it's true.
Okay.
So look if B1 equals B2 we take little R
equals 1 and it's slightly exceptional
but but all the bounds are true.
Okay.
So if we want to upper bound star now we
need to count the number of choices for
B1 and B2.
So now I'm interested in the number of
pairs
B1, B2, and X with the property that the
distance from B1 to B2 is at most R.
Okay, how big is that? Well, I have norm
of X choices for B1.
But once I choose B1, I don't have all
that many choices for B2 because B2 has
to be close to B1. It has to be in a
little R ball.
So the number of choices for B2 is at
most nx of R. So at this moment the
spacing function of X comes into play.
Okay. So now we can combine these to to
upper bound star.
So star is um is now upper bounded by
x * nx of r time n d of 1 / r
uh ah sorry so star
is upperbounded by the sum over the
diatic r
of this quantity.
Okay, so let me say why. So star is this
set of coincidences.
It's a B1 and B2 and a theta. And for
each coincidence, I know I I sort these
coincidences by the distance from B1 to
B2, which I call R. So I take the the
coincidences where the distance is
around R, and I sum over the possible
Rs. Once I fixed R, um, I have this many
choices for the pair B1 B2. And once I
fixed B1 and B2, I have this many
choices for theta.
So that's that.
Okay.
Uh, the rest is algebra. I'll sketch it
quickly on the board and that'll be the
end of the proof and then we'll pause to
digest and check it.
Okay. So al together
we have x^2 s inverse d is bounded by
star which is bounded by
the sum over r datic
of x nx of r and d of 1 / r and then I
just get the d by itself.
If you move this stuff over to the other
side, you get the formula on the board.
Okay, so let's pause there for questions
and comments.
All right.
All right. So, um, so I wanted to, uh,
get a sense of start to explore this
function nx of r by looking at a few
different examples of sets x and writing
down what is nx of r. It's not
difficult, but having a few different
examples in our mind, it'll help to
orient us as we keep going.
um and and actually will help also to
digest this formula. So this this proof
was clean. This formula is a little bit
messy. So after looking at some
examples, we'll digest this formula and
think about a situation where it works
out a little more cleanly.
All right.
[Applause]
All right. So examples
for n sub x sub rar.
Okay. So number one, x is the one
neighborhood
of a curve like a nice like a circle or
parabola or something. So here's the
ball of radius r and inside of there I
have a nice curve and all along the
curve I have unit balls.
That's x.
So if I have this set, how many unit
balls do I have in a ball of radius
little r?
That would be around r.
Okay.
Do a second example. Um
second example, it would be very spread
out. You know, if you imagine that these
points are like positive charges that
repel each other and they push as far
away from each other as possible, they
would arrange themselves in something
like a lattice inside of here.
So, okay. So, I'll call this the uh well
spaced example, the most spread out
example. So, it looks like this.
So it's a let's say it's a well spaced n
byn grid
and so the distance between neighboring
balls would be like r /n.
Okay so now what would nx of r be like?
Um well it would be one for quite a
while if our radius is less than rn. um
then this would be one but then
eventually as the radius gets bigger it
would get bigger than one and at that
point it would be um its fair share of
the total number total size of x. So
once once r is bigger than this
threshold, every little r ball contains
the same amount of x. And so the density
of x is like n^2 r 2. The area of the
ball is like this.
Okay. And um I'll do a third example
which is the points could be very um uh
clustered
cluster.
So we could have n squared unit balls
in um in an n ball. So the the picture
would be like this. We have our ball of
radius r. Inside of there we have a
smaller ball of radius n and we pack the
smaller ball with unit balls of x.
Okay. So now what is uh n subx of r?
Well it grows like r 2 until r is as big
as this n ball. And after that there are
only n squared balls at all. So you can
make a little r bigger. It doesn't grow
anymore. So it caps off at n^ squ if r
is bigger than n.
Okay.
[Applause]
So now I will draw um some pictures of
of of these three functions.
You can compare them.
Okay, we'll do some pictures.
I'm going to normalize in my pictures. I
have to choose an n. I'm going to choose
n= r to the half. Uh, and that's helpful
because it says that the total size of x
is around r in all three examples. It
makes them a little easier to compare
with each other.
Okay. So now I'll make a graph.
Basically I'd like to put on this axis
little r and on this axis n subx of
little r. Um but this graph like many
graphs in math looks nicer if we use log
is a log log plot. So on this on this
axis I'm going to put the log of little
r and then the nicest base for that is
big r. This goes from 0 to one. And on
this axis, I'm going to put the log of n
subx of r. And it's natural to use the
same base. So this goes from 0 to one.
This could go above one potentially, but
because the size of x happens to be r,
we're going to stop there.
Okay. So now what do these three
examples look like? The first example is
a straight line.
So that's example one.
Um,
the second example grows more slowly
than the straight line for a while. It
doesn't grow at all for a while and then
it grows quickly to catch up. So that's
the second example. It lies below the
straight line. Uh and then the third
example grows more quickly than the
first example and then it reaches a
certain point and it stops growing. So
it looks like this and it lies above the
straight line.
Okay. So um so in this theory there
turns out to be that things that grow
the the straight line case is an
important case and then there's an
important distinction between things
that are below the straight line things
that are above the straight line.
Um so the straight line case
would be that n that that the size of x
would be r to the alpha for some alpha
and then n sub little r of x or n subx
of little r
would be little r to the alpha. That
would be the straight line case.
And the uh below the straight line case,
uh x would still be r to the alpha. So
the end point would be the same, but now
in the middle, we're going to go below
what we had before. So n subx of r would
be at most r
Okay. So this thing here is called a
regular alpha dimensional
spacing
and this thing is called a alpha
dimensional spacing.
Um
I'd like and I'd like to make one more
definition. And I'll say that X has a
housegrowth spacing
if it has alpha dimensional spacing for
some of
but another way of saying that is if you
look at how many points of X are in a
ball of radius R to the beta it's
bounded by the total number of points of
x to the beta.
And this is this is equivalent. This is
still below the straight line.
Okay. So over here um we would have we
have example one and and in general if
you have any if you have a submanifold
in any dimensional space it will behave
like this and alpha is the dimension of
the sub manifold. Also some self-
similar caner set kind of fractals like
the caner set um have this kind of
spacing where alpha would be the
dimension of the of your caner set.
That's why it's called alpha
dimensional.
Um
and um and these things this thing
called housedorf spacing I called it
that because it it appears naturally in
the theory of housed dorf dimensions.
Um
yeah, so it's maybe worth saying briefly
that in the geometric measure theory
literature, a lot of the stuff we're
talking about today was originally
described in the language of housedorf
dimensions. Um but my impression is that
that's not really that helpful. Like if
we if we defined housedorf dimensions
and then we wanted to prove things about
housed dorf dimensions we would add an
extra layer of definition and then we'd
have to check the extra layer of
definition. Um but then in all the
applications that we'll talk about we
would never use those definitions. We
would go back to this theorem the way
it's stated now and use that. Um, so I
have a bit tentatively but I've come to
the conclusion that house dorf dimension
is not really a helpful notion for this
subject and and so I'm going to leave it
out.
Okay. Um, but any questions or comments
about these
different ways that a set can be spaced?
>> Yeah.
>> I'm wondering like is the And the pro 01
for the pro lower bound.
If we try to calculate lower bound for
B1 B2 like is distance like somehow
R from R1 to R2 like with that and
compare this with the upper bound with
different distance from B1 and B2. that
information that
>> yeah okay so the question is um when we
were processing the upper bound for this
we sorted it according to the distance
so we really have a set star sub r where
we add the condition that the distance
from b1 to b2 is around r and the
question is if if we looked at the lower
bound we could also sort it by r and and
would that be helpful yeah Um
um yeah I that is a a good thing to look
into. Off the top of my head I don't
know if it would be helpful. Um you know
it's uh our our lower bound with this s
here depends on taking all of them. Um
but it would be interesting. Yeah it
would be interesting to think about.
Other questions or comments?
Okay. Okay. So, let me show you uh so so
I so I claim so okay it seems that um
this spacing condition
say housedorf spacing is helpful in the
theory. Um and one way that comes about
is that a lot of the theorem statements
become a lot cleaner if you put in house
spacing.
Um so let's do that here. Let's suppose
that X and D have housed doororf spacing
and we'll use that to simplify this
thing.
[Applause]
Okay. So corollary one real is that if
we have the the setup
and x and d are housedorf spacing
then we get a simpler inequality which
matches quite well what happens in
finite fields.
Then d is bounded by um s plus x.
Okay.
So, I'll prove this and then I'll try to
argue actually. So, so okay. So, this
looks a little nicer than before. It
might still not look that nice to you.
Um but I would summarize it like this.
Um either
either s e either s is pretty close to x
or d is smaller than s and that's what
we had in finite fields. So why is it if
s is a lot smaller than x? This is much
less than one. So we can rearrange that
and we get that d is less than s.
Okay. So, what's the proof? Well, um,
we're going to have an expression like
nx of r n d of 1 / r.
And so now let's suppose
that little r is big r to the beta.
And um and then being housedorf
it tells us that nx of r the beta n d of
r the minus beta
there that is bounded by x to the beta *
d to the 1 - beta.
That's what being housed tells us.
So being house of dwarf allows us to to
relate nx of r for any r to the size of
x which is nx of big r and algebraically
it works out like this and for d it
works out like that.
Okay. And then by amg this is smaller
than x plus d.
So every one of these complicated things
they're all bounded by x plus d
and the number of them is only log of r.
So, okay, sorry. So, I should put a log
of R here.
Um,
okay. So, now we're just going to plug
this in up there. I'll have an x plus d
up there
and a log r factor. The x in the x plus
d gives me this and the d and the x plus
d gives me that. It's just algebra.
Okay. Now let's compare this with the
theorem we proved last time in finite
fields.
So theorem one in finite fields said
that if we had x in fq2
and d in fq
and s is the maximum
theta and d size is pi theta of x.
Um
then
either S is around X or D is bounded by
S.
And the numerology is now the same in
finite fields or or or if you have balls
with the house space.
Okay.
Um so in general the numerology in a lot
of things is the same between finite
fields and balls with housedorf spacing
and so now I'll so this was theorem one
from last time I'll track through also
theorem two from last time and the
conjecture from last time and we'll see
that they all match up
Okay.
So I have
projection theory
in FQ2
versus um in
versus unit balls in B2R
and B2R with housed door space.
Okay, so here was theorem two last time
in finite fields.
So if we have our finite field setup
which is over here
and S is smaller than Q.
Um then conclusion is that the number of
directions is smaller than SQX.
And here's what we'll prove in the real
case correlary to R. So if we have our
setup of the day and X and D are housed
and S is a good bit smaller than R.
Then maybe this needs a little bit more
um than d
smaller than sr /x.
Okay. So I I use this symbol with the
extra tilda that's hiding something like
a log factor similar to the log factor
that appeared over here. Like if you if
you compare the real case theorem one
and the finite field case we lost an
extra log r factor and that h that will
happen sometimes. Um
so uh notation
a less sum b means
for every epsilon bigger than zero there
exists c epsilon. So a is less than or
equal to c epsilon r the epsilon.
Okay. But if you compare these um Q
corresponds to R.
That makes sense. There are Q ^2 points
here and there are R squar unit balls
here.
Um and these basically match up except
that there's a minor sort of loss here.
Okay. And so this is this is the forier
method that we'll turn to in a little
bit. Um there is also a conjecture about
the sharp behavior.
So conjecture
if P is prime
and we have our finite field setup
and S is smaller than the minimum of Q
and X. So either of these are sort of
trivial. S is always at most Q and it's
always at most X. So we're make it less
than that. So we're sort of in a
non-trivial range.
um then
b should be bounded by s^2 overx which
would be sharp if it's true and it
matches the behavior in an integer grid.
Okay, this conjecture has an analog
uh over in the real case and the real
analog is uh is due to fenberg. It's
called the fenber set conjecture. So it
says if we have the setup and X and B
are housed dorf
um and S is significantly less than the
minimum of R and X. So again S is always
smaller than R. It's always smaller than
X and we're saying it's significantly
less than that. So it's sort of
non-trivial.
um then
the number of directions would be less
than tilda tilda s^2 overx.
You see that these conjectures again
match up.
Cool.
Okay. Now I mentioned on the first day
that one of the fundamental thought
problems of projection theory recently
had been solved. This is the problem. So
this conjecture has been proven. Um so
this is a theorem from 2024
of Orpinan
Schmurkin
Ran and Wong
conjecture is true.
in the first but finite field is still
open.
>> Yes, thank you. Yeah, conjecture R is
true. Finite field is still wide open.
Yes.
Cool. So actually another reason I was
excited to do projection theory this
semester is that a bunch of the
architects of the recent developments
will be visiting. Pablo Mkin is going to
be here for about a month. He's going to
talk in the analysis seminar. I might
rope him into talking in this class. Um
Kevin Ran is going to visit and give a
talk. Hung will be here at at some
point, although maybe not during
classes.
Yeah, I'll say let me say something very
briefly. So these these two conjectures
I presented them as being parallel to
each other. I think that's fair. Um and
they're both quite difficult. Um this
one people have managed to prove which
is exciting and um and this one is still
open. So uh the difference is that in
this problem there are many different
scales. We've sort of seen the many
different scales in in what we just did
with double counting. We had to think
about all these different scales and
we're going to do it again with the
forier method. So far you might have the
impression that these different scales
are just a nuisance. They make simple
arguments more complicated and the
expressions longer. Um but but actually
having these many different scales will
turn out to be a help. Um so they play a
key role in the proof of this that
somehow because of all these scales if
if if something goes wrong something has
to go wrong at many different scales. Um
the argument also has different cases
depending upon whether the sets look
like set have spacing like number one or
spacing like number two. There are
different things to play with. They're
both helpful in different ways
and and none of that structure is
available here. So So probably
completely different ideas would be
needed.
Okay, good. So the second half of the
class the goal is to do the forier
method in the real case and build up
towards towards doing this. Um let me
remind you first of the main thing we
proved using for analysis over finite
fields and then we'll set up a version
over over the rings.
[Applause]
Okay. So part two of the class for a
method.
Um okay so the main lema that we proved
over finite fields is like this.
So let's say fancy L is a set of lines
in
FQ^2
and um F
is a sum over all these lines of the
characteristic function of the line.
Okay, if that's true, then we can break
up f into two pieces. a zero frequency
piece and a nonzero frequency piece. So
then
f is equal to f0 plus f we called it f
high zero frequency high frequency.
So that
so the support of f0 hat is just zero.
In other words, f0 is constant.
Um and we can find out exactly what the
constant is. And based on that we can
say that the L2 norm squared of this is
the number of lines squared.
Then the support of the high frequency
part is the complement of zero.
And the high frequency part
has an L2 bound. L2 2 is L * Q
right
I remember teaching a intro to real
analysis class once and I and so I I
tried to answer the question on the
first day what is real analysis so there
are several you know there are lots of
different things you might say something
about convergence and infinity or
whatever but another thing I proposed is
um analysis is complicated equals simple
plus small.
We study something complicated. The real
analysis point of view is to try to
write it as something simple plus
something small.
So this is our function that maybe we
feel is complicated. We don't understand
it that well yet. We wrote it as
something simple. This is a constant
function which makes it quite simpler
than a general function. And then this
bit and the point here is that this is
smaller than fot or f. Now that that
only becomes true and this only becomes
at all interesting when the number of
lines is much bigger than Q. But when
that h when that happens this L2 norm is
much smaller than that L2 norm. So
complicated equals simple plus small.
Okay. So uh so our goal is I will
describe to you the version of this lema
in over the real numbers.
[Applause]
Okay.
So instead of a line, so infinitely thin
line, what we're going to talk about is
a rectangle or I usually call it a tube.
So capital T for tube is a one by R
rectangle
in the plane
in any direction.
Okay. And so basically we're going to
add up characteristic functions of
rectangles.
Um but when you do for analysis
characteristic functions of rectangles
or characteristic functions in general
are not super nice because of the
discontinuous sharp cut offs their 4A
transforms are not very well behaved. So
what we often do is we work with a
smoothed approximation of the
characteristic function.
So
C subt is a smooth
approximation
of the characteristic function of T.
Okay. Um so another thing about this
step of doing for analysis on R2 instead
of finite fields is that certain things
are a little bit messy. for example,
it's a little bit messy to write down
the formula for C subt.
Um, so I'm going to try the approach of
not doing the messy details in class. So
in class I'll give you an overview and
then on the homework, uh, I'll do all of
the details and and and you can check
the things and make sure you understand
how it works.
And uh and I do that partly because I
feel like sometimes the messy details
obscure sort of the main trajectory of
what we want to do. It's good to sort of
first learn what you want to do and then
um once you know where you're trying to
go, fill in all the little steps to get
there.
Okay. So for this class, I won't say
anything more precise than C subt is a
smooth approximation of the
characteristic function of T.
Okay. So now here is our
um main lema
in the real case.
Okay. So instead of L is a set of lines,
T is a set of 1 by R rectangles
in the plane R2.
And then f is the sum over all the
rectangles of this smooth characteristic
function. And that plays the role of the
function f up there.
Okay. And then we're going to break this
function up into pieces. There are going
to be sort of low frequency pieces that
have the advantage of being kind of
constant and there are going to be some
high frequency pieces that have the
advantage of being small.
Uh but the difference between the real
world and and FQ is that in FQ there are
only two kinds of frequencies. There was
zero and not zero. Um but uh in in the
reals there are a lot of frequencies.
There's large, medium, small, very small
and all of those are they're each going
to to to be there. Okay. So instead of
having two pieces, we will have many
pieces.
So f is going to be the sum of f little
r little r goes from one up to capital r
and is diatic just like in theorem one.
So we'll have log of r many pieces and
these are the different scales of the
frequencies.
Okay. Uh we'll do this so that
the support
of fr hat
is contained in the ball of radius one
over little r. So that's the frequency
information
and um we will say something about the
L2 norm.
Okay.
Now, um, our bounds on the L2 norm
before only depended on how many lines
there were, not about how the lines were
arranged. Uh, but that won't be quite
true anymore. Like, like we've seen in
other places, it will matter how these
tubes are clumped. So, if you have many
tubes that are clumped together inside
of a um Yeah. Okay. So, let me let me
put the other part of the definition. So
n subr of t is the maximum over tilda
which is like a two little r by two big
r rectangle
of the number of t in our set of t that
are so that t is contained in t tilda.
So here's a picture.
So here's tilda.
This axis is little r basically and this
axis is big r basically. Maybe it's good
to put two big R. Um, and inside of here
there may be a bunch of R twos.
So just like uh oh and I I guess to be
consistent with before I should actually
do this.
So n subx of r measured whether many of
the balls in x were clumped together and
n subt of r measures whether many of the
tubes of t are clumped together.
Okay. So the bound will depend on that
thing and it is
formula is
okay.
n subt of little r
um times the number of tubes
time little r inverse time big.
[Applause]
Okay, so you can see that I don't
remember this formula that well. Um but
one thing to notice about it is that as
as this number gets bigger then our
bound for this gets bigger.
Um I also claim that this tracks with
the finite field case. Um so if you plug
in little r equals 1 that's the highest
frequency part. Um n subt of one is is
going to be just one. If if the tubes
are disjoint then then or the tubes are
distinct then anyway um uh so then if
you plug in little r equals 1 this
number will match with the high
frequency case. And if you plug in
little r equals big r, then this will
match with the zero frequency case. But
now we also have all this in between
stuff.
Okay,
any questions or comments about this
statement?
So I'm going to do a proof sketch.
proof sketch main are details on
homework two.
How's homework one going?
If you're interested, there are office
hours after class today and after class
on Thursday.
Okay. Um,
okay. There's a fora analysis proof and
an important character is well we're
take the fora transform of each of these
ct hat and the support of ct hat is
going to be contained in t star where t
star is defined as follows
it's the set of c and r2
so that
the dotproduct x1 - x2 c is at most has
norm at most one for any x1 and x2 in t.
Um here's a picture.
So in x space here is our tube t and I
take a couple of points in it x1 and x2
and so so our c is going to have a small
dotproduct with any vector like that.
And so um okay the dimensions of this t
are this is one and this is r.
Okay. Now in csp space um t star is
going to be sort of perpendicular to t.
There's t star and it has length one and
width like 1 / r.
So geometrically the idea is that if I
take my vector here and my vector there,
the long component of this one has size
R and it gets paired with the short
component of that one which has size one
over R which gives me around one and the
two short component the short component
here has size one which gets paired with
the long component here which has size
one.
Okay. Um and this is analogous to the
lema we had in the finite field case
that that the characteristic function of
a line hat was supported in the line per
which is like star.
Okay.
Um
okay
so that's the first important ingredient
where the 4A transforms live and I guess
you're doing the homework now where
you're checking what what line hat looks
like and then in the next homework
you'll check what ct hat looks like and
you'll see it supported like this.
Okay. So now I'll tell you who F subr
is. Um
so let's next do so the f subr comes
from from littlewood paley theory where
you can take any function and you can
break its frequencies into diatic pieces
the little wood pale pieces. That's what
we're doing here.
Okay. So,
so little wood pale decomposition.
So, I'm going to write one as a sum on
my diatic little rs
of ad r of c. So this is a a partition
of unity on in 4A space. It's a
partition of unity. So these are all
positive
and um the support
of A to R is contained in in an annulus
where the norm of C is at most 1 / R and
at least 1 / 10R.
And that's true for R strictly between 1
and R. And at the end points we need to
have not just an annulus but something a
little bit bigger to cover all the
frequencies. So the support
of ADA capital R
is contained in the ball of radius 1 / R
and the support
of ADA1
is contained in the set of C where the
norm of C is bigger than 110.
All right. Oh, I guess one maybe I
should mention one one thing that we see
from this
is that the support of f hat is
contained in the unit ball because every
t star is in is in the unit ball.
Okay. So now I can say who f_sub_r is.
So f is just taking f and taking
multiplying on the frequency side by 8
r. So I take fhat I multiply it by a r
and I take the 4 a transform back.
So this is also equal to f involved with
a to r inverse 4 a transform.
Okay. And because this is a partition of
unity
that tells me that f is indeed the sum
over r of fr.
So that so we can check off our first
conclusion.
Um and from this formula this here is
the for transform of FR hat
is a R * Fhat and that tells us that the
support of FR hat is contained in the
ball of radius 1 / R. So we can check
off that part of the conclusion.
And then the difficult and interesting
part will be to figure out the L2 norm
of each of these pieces FR.
Okay. Um now this operation of
localizing frequencies to to an annulus
around 1 / R you can do it with any
function not just with f. So you can
also do it with each of the ct one at a
time. So ct comma r would be I take ct
hat I multiply it by a to r I take the
for a transform back and so f is the sum
over all the t in my set of tubes of ct.
Okay.
So the next thing I'd like to do is to
visualize together this function a to r
check and this function ctr
do a visual
of ad r check um and ctr.
Okay, so the function A to R itself A to
R of C that's around one on the annulus
of size 1 / little R.
So when I take its inverse for a
transform
um a to r check of x
will be around
it'll be around um 1 / r 2
of most of x less than r.
So the you know the biggest this could
possibly be is integrating this would be
the area of this annulus which is 1 /
r^2.
Um and then because this is smooth once
I look at x's that are significantly
bigger than r I start to get a lot of
cancellation in the integral and let me
write down the formula for this. So a to
r check of x is the integral e to the ix
a r of c dx c.
So if x is smaller than r, there's no
significant cancellation in this
integral because the c is around 1 / r.
Um but then when x is bigger than r,
there starts to be cancellation in this
integral. And because this is smooth,
the cancellation is quite dramatic. So
this is rapidly decaying
x.
Okay, so that's what the size of this
function is like. Um but but also um
there's some cancellation in it. So if
you integrate this function
well if you integrate that you get a to
r of zero which is zero because a to r
is supported on an annulus and not a
ball. So this function has some
cancellation in it. It averages to zero.
Okay.
Um so
I I can graph it. Um C sub R check is
radial.
So here is the radius norm of X and
here's ADA R check of X and it would
look something like this.
And we have to do this carefully but the
negative part is going to balance the
positive part to integrate to zero. So
imagine rotating this
Um, and this scale here is is that's
okay. Now, these different exponents
here are
work out nicely.
Um and and a a different way a way to
describe it is that if I take the
integral of the norm of a total r check
of x dx
um well it's around 1 / r^2 times the
area of the ball of radius r which is 1.
That integral is around 1.
So um so if I were to take some function
and convolve it with the absolute value
of a total r check of x that would
roughly be the average value of f
on the ball around x of radius r the
sort of weighted average. It's not
exactly the standard average but that's
roughly what what it is.
So is it the case that like
um convoluting with a function on the
end
like if data r is like on the end
basically behaves the same as if it were
on the fall radius.
>> So the question is how would we compare
an ad r that's supported on an annulus
with a similar function that was
supported on the whole ball. Um yeah,
it's mostly similar because of the
annulus. There's more cancellation. So
if we did it on the whole ball, we
wouldn't have this integral property.
>> Okay.
>> And the ne there may or may not be a
little negative part if we did it on the
whole ball, but the negative part would
probably would be dominated by the
positive part.
Okay, so that's what the function ad
looks like.
And now that we understand that we can
understand the function CTR
because CTR is equal to CT convolved
with ADA R check.
Okay. So the norm of ctr of x is around
r inverse times the characteristic
function of a thickened tube.
So if I take the r neighborhood of t.
So if this is uh t
I could take a fat neighborhood of that
would look sort of like this.
So that's the R neighborhood of T. Um so
PT itself is basically supported on T
although it's smoothed out a little bit.
And then when I take the low frequency
part the R the one over R frequency part
then it gets spread out and it gets
smaller.
Okay. And it also has some cancellation
in it. So if the the graph of this
function mostly depends on the
transverse direction and then it looks a
lot like this. So this would be the
transverse direction and this would be
the height.
So here I'll put that in the picture.
So this transverse direction maybe I'll
call y.
And then we could make a graph where
here we put y and here we put ct
r of y and we would see the same thing
uh positive negative.
Okay. And this length scale here is r.
the negative part would cancel the
positive part because if you convolve
something who integrates to zero with
something else then the the whole thing
will integrate to zero.
Okay, so that's what what these
functions look like.
[Applause]
All right.
So before I erase this maybe I'll say
sorry we mentioned earlier that if we
have a smooth function supported on this
tube we take its 4A transform it's
essentially supported on this dual tube.
That proof is a slightly fancier version
of what we were just talking about. So
we were just saying that if you have a
smooth function on a certain annulus or
a certain ball then its fora transform
is essentially supported on a dual ball
and then it's rapidly decaying outside.
So the this first statement is exactly
the same as that except that we have a
tube instead of a ball. Having a tube
instead of a ball makes it a little
there's a little bit more writing or
thinking involved but it's the same
idea.
uh and you'll and and it'll be the
details will be on the homework.
Okay.
Okay. So, um in the finite field case,
the the the the heart of the argument,
the key thing called the key lema was an
orthogonality lema that said that the
high frequency parts of two different
lines are orthogonal. and um something
like that is true here.
So lema on orthogonality this is like
the key letter. So it says the following
um uh t1 and t2 are are are tubes one by
r tubes
um then
the ctrs are usually orthogonal. So if I
take the inner product of CT1R
with CT2R,
it's usually really small.
R the minus a,000, something that's
really small compared to everything in
our proof. Uh unless the two tubes are
quite similar. And the way we'll say
this is there exists tilda which is like
basically
it's basically a little r by big r two.
I'm going to magnify it just a little
bit.
um that contains them both
tilda and inside of here and I have this
t1 and t2.
Okay, so we could have some intuition
about this from our visualization of
ctr.
If I were to take T1 and T2 in in the
same Tilda. So this thickened
neighborhood notice is basically the
same as Tilda. If I pick T1 and T2
corresponding to the same Tilda, then
when I when I thicken them both, I get
basically the same rectangle.
And in fact, then the functions CT1R and
CT2R are basically the same function. So
they are not at all orthogonal.
And that's the only thing that can go
wrong.
Um if the thickened neighborhoods are
disjoint they certainly are orthogonal
and the more interesting part is that if
the thickened neighborhoods are
transverse to each other they are
orthogonal
and we we can we check that by by for
analysis.
Um
so proof sketch.
if the
if the angle
between t1 and t2 is bigger than maybe r
epsilon 1 / r or little r big r.
Um then
the support
of CTR hat intercepted the support T1 of
CT2R
hat is empty
right so the support of CT1
so this is the support of CT1 hat
intersected with the annulus of size 1 /
are
intersected with the support of CT2 hat
and these are two rectangles that are
transverse to each other. Uh and so wow
and you can you can check the
intersection.
>> Why does it rule out the translations of
rectangles?
>> Yeah. And so that's case one. So the
other case is if um the R neighborhood
of T1 is disjoint
from the R neighborhood of T2 or you
know a little bit more than R. Um then
we use the formula
CTR is CT1.
So that so then we have here
integral ct1 r c2 r complex conjugate
it's the integral ct1 convolved with ad1
and ct2 convolved
a r check and and these two guys have
disjoint report.
[Applause]
Okay.
So now we are ready to estimate the L2
norm. Um so our orthogonality lema says
that these different CTRs
are usually orthogonal with a few
exceptions and we're going to use that
orthogonality to estimate the L2 norm.
But we have to keep track of how many
exceptions there are.
All right. So, L2 estimate.
So, the last thing we need to check is
FR L2 squared. So, FR is the sum over
all of our T of ctr.
L2 squ.
So that's this thing inner product with
itself. So if I expand it out, it's the
sum T1 T2 of um
the inner product of C T1R
C T2R.
Okay. And the key point is orthogonality
lema tells us that most of the inner
products in this sum are negligible.
There's only a few that are not. Let me
give a bit of a name to the ones that
are not.
[Applause]
So this scenario
here
I'm going to abbreviate it as saying
that T1 uh is related to T2. T T T T T T
T T T T T T T T T T T T T T T T T T T T
T T T T T T T T T T T T T T T1 is close
to T2.
I guess we could put a little r here.
So this inner product is negligible
unless T1 is related to T2.
Okay,
so let's look at our big sum of inner
products
and I'll break it up into two parts.
It's the sum where T1 is related to T2
inner product plus the rest of them and
the rest of them are really tiny by the
orthogonality lema. So the rest of them
are negligible.
Okay. Now each of these inner products
I'll arithmetic geometric mean it. So
that's less than this sum t1 related to
t2
of ctr
l2
ct1 r l2 2 plus ct2r l2.
Okay. So I want to know how many times
does each of these functions ct1 appear
in this sum
and the number of times is the number of
different t2s that are related to t1
and that number is basically the number
that appears in our main lema.
This thing that we were counting here
how many tubes lie in a little r by big
r big tube. That's exactly how many
tubes t2 are related to t1.
So this thing
uh
we can say the number of t2 so that t2
is related to t1
this is bounded by nr of t. So this
whole sum is bounded by
nr of t times just the sum on all the t
and t of ctr l2.
Cool. And then finally each of these
functions we've already described.
Hopefully I didn't erase it.
[Applause]
Yeah, so we described it. It has height
r inverse and it's supported on a little
r by big r rectangle. So we can compute
its L2 norm. Um
so this is n subt of r times the number
of tubes times uh the height was r
inverse. So that's rus 2 times the
uh so this is the amplitude squared
and this is the area
for this ptr.
Okay. And that was the thing that was on
the right hand side.
Okay. Let me summarize the proof for the
last minute. Um let's look back at our
statement here.
So if we look at this sum of sum of
tubes, we're going to break it into
different frequency pieces. Littlewood
pale theory. And then um the
highfrequency pieces are usually
orthogonal to each other. If you take if
you look at two tubes and you look at
the frequency one over R part, they're
orthogonal to each other unless those
two tubes are in a common fat tube
little R by big R.
And so you take advantage of that
orthogonality where it's available and
it gives this bound.
Okay, good. Let's stop there for today.
uh we will wrap this up on Thursday and
and then uh discuss how similar ideas
apply in a different looking context in
civ theory in in number theory.