Okay. So I want to start with a
timeline.
So
Shannon
discovered um
the noisy coding theorem.
um
Hamming
discovered
um
Hamming codes in 1950.
Um
Reed and Solomon discovered
Reed Solomon codes
in 1960.
Um, concatenated codes
were discovered in 1966.
and Burleamp
Massie
decoding algorithm
for read Solomon codes
was discovered in 1969.
So this is a lot of steps and it turns
out that the burlac massi decoding
algorithm for read solomman codes along
with concatenated codes was what made
um
using eric recting codes practical.
And in
Voyager
deep space
was 1977
and one of the Voyager aircrafts is
still transmitting signals to Earth
and they're doing that using Reed
Solomon codes which as I'm going to
which is what I'm going to tell you
about later in the lecture. And after
all this stuff, Reed Solomon codes were
still used until um
oh, I don't know around
19 mid 1990s.
Actually, they were still used until
probably around 2000. But in the mid
1990s, these three French engineers.
So read Solomon codes do not actually
meet Shannon's bound from the noisy
coding theorem. Reed Solomon codes come
within a factor within a constant factor
of it. But you know between 1948 for the
next 40some years coding theorist has
struggled to find a technique
for actually meeting Shannon's bound
and
in 199 something
this paper appeared by three French
engineers.
I mean, they weren't even
they weren't even coding theorists. They
were three people at a
at a French telecom company and they
claimed to meet Shannon's bound with a
completely different technique and none
of the coding theorist researchers
believed it until they programmed up and
it worked
and even that it took many years for
them to explain why it worked and in
fact they still don't understand why it
worked, why turbo codes work. They do
understand why uh similar type of codes
called LDP C codes work really well. But
um
so
now um you know after this discovery
read Solomon codes gradually faded out
of use in new applications and turbo
codes and LDPC codes and polar codes
which were discovered in the 2000s took
over.
So,
but I, you know, I find it kind of
amazing that you needed
something like three discoveries
to actually make
Shannon's Thurm practical.
So, what is a Reed Solomon code?
Okay. Well, it's based on a
ancient theorem from mathematics
uh polomial
of degree D
over
a finite field.
has
at most
d roots.
[sighs]
Okay. So a read Solomon code
you have a message
M0 through MK
well MK minus one because we're starting
with zero.
Associate the polomial
P of X = M0 + M1 X + M2 X^2 +
M K -1 X K -1.
So
this is the message and once you have
the message you
construct this polomial although um I
mean
we're not going to actually um transmit
the polinomial what we're going to
transmit is
um
the code
which is P of
0,
P of 1, P of 2, all the way up through P
of N minus one.
Now you know to do this we need
n is less than or equal to
okay so this is over a finite field and
for this lecture we will assume the
finite field is the integers mod p in
real life
um
read mo read sol read read solomon codes
were actually they actually use the
polomial Z over the finite field with 2
to the K elements but that's because
they're using binary and 2 to the K is
very convenient for binary
but the theory is exactly the same if we
take Z subp and um so for this well we
need n minus one different elements in
the field
and are n different elements in the
field and for that we need n
is
is at most p
and in fact as an aside you don't have
to use 0 1 2 through n minus one
for the um
for these points points. You could just
use any n distinct points, but
you know, the lecture notes start out by
saying choose end points and then they
say later we'll use the points 0 through
n minus one. So I'm just going to start
out with 0 through n minus one.
Okay.
and
note
read Solomon's codes
are linear
and the generator matrix G
is equal to
1 0 0 0 0
1 1 1
2 4
um 8
etc. 2 to the k -1
3 9 27 etc. and 3 to the k minus one
all the way up to well how many um
how many values of the polomial are
there
are
I mean how many numbers do you plug into
the polomial there are n minus one so
this last row last column is one n minus
1 n -1^ 2ar through n -1 to the k -1
and I should note that these numbers are
all mod z subp. So if P was 13, this
entry would not be 27 but one.
Oh well, I mean 27 is one mod 13 but
[snorts]
yeah. So this is the generary matrix G.
And if you put in m0 m1
through mk,
the i entry in the code word is just 1 +
m1 * 3 1st + m2 * 3 2 + m3 * 3 cubed
etc. Which is the value of p of x at 3.
So they're linear codes
which
means that
um we want to find how many
errors they can correct.
So remember
okay so
need
to find
minimum
weight non zero
code
If weight
let's give this a name C. If weight of C
is equal to D we can correct
D -1 / 2 errors.
thermum
and that's because the minimum distance
between any two code words is d minus
one / two
minimum
Wait.
Nonzero code word
has weight
n - k + 1.
proof
the code word.
Well, we know what the code word is.
It's just P of 0, P of 1 through P of N
minus one.
where
P = M0 + M1 X +
M K -1 X to the K -1
is the
is a polomial of degree K
and remember that the polomial this
polomial is actually the coefficients
are the message so it could be any
polinomial of degree K of degree K minus
one sorry
and now we use this theorem that I
reminded you a A little while ago, a
polomial of degree D has at most d
roots. So
P of X has at most
k minus one zeros.
So at most k minus one of these entries
are zero, which means at least
n minus k + one
um
values
of p subi
are non zero
because you have
n values in the code word k minus one of
them or fewer are zero which means this
many have to be non zero. So the minimum
Hamming weight
is n - k + 1.
Suppose we want to correct
um
e errors.
Well, we need
minimum distance
to be greater than equal to 2 e + 1.
And
that means we need
n - k + 1 greater than or equal to 2 e +
1 or n minus k is greater than equal to
2 e.
Okay. So that are our read solomon
codes.
Now
remember that
to
have an have a usable code, we not only
need to be able to
encode,
but we also need to be able to correct
errors and decode. So the question is
how do you decode?
So this is what I will spend probably
the next half hour telling you.
Okay.
And I am not going to give you the
not going to give you the burlac massie
decoding algorithm
because that is conceptually very
or I shouldn't say very that's
conceptually fairly difficult and I'm
going to give you a much easier
decoding algorithm to explain which is
not as efficient as a burleamp Massie
decoding algorithm and there's another
decoding algorithm which is probably
equally efficient which is based on the
uklidian algorithm for finding you know
greatest common divisor but I'm not
going to give you that one either
because again that's fairly difficult
conceptually
How do we
decode?
So this decoding algorithm is based on a
theorem.
So
the
suppose
we have
a code word
C equals P of 0 P of 1 through P of N
minus one
we get the transmission H
rather we receive
the thing the um
code word with some errors in it.
C tilda equals R comma R1 comma R2
through R NUS1.
And these guys
are not going to have a polomial where
RA equals P of I. For some of these,
we have
RA equals P of I. But for some others,
we won't.
Assume
there are L less than E
errors.
Then there
are positions
I1 I2 through IIL where
P of I subL is not equal to R.
P sub I sub K is not equal to R of
R sub
I subK.
So we have at most L errors and we
assume there are positions in positions
I1 through IIL
and L is less than or equal to E because
we're assuming there are fewer errors
than the code is able to decode.
So this is the hypothesis of the theorem
and I need to put the theorem itself on
a different board
are the
then
um
continued
There are nonzero polomials
f and q
[clears throat] and q of x
of degree
less than or equal
K + E - 1
such that
Q of I is equal to
R subi * F sub I.
Okay.
So this looks like a totally crazy
theorem. What does it have to do with
decoding?
Well,
um I mean you will see what have to do
with decoding when I give you the
decoding algorithm. But first let's
prove the theorem.
Let f ofx equal
x - i1
x - i2 through x - i subl is equal to
the product of x - i subk k = 1 through
l.
So this is
you just take all the positions which
are in error. Of course you don't know
which positions are in error when you
receive this
this word which is you know the code
word with at most e errors. [snorts] But
we'll let f ofx be that
because and um
and we will let
q of x
= p of x * f ofx.
Okay.
Oh, I think we
If
I I should have put this down.
Q of I= R subi F subi
for I = 0 1 through N minus one. So this
is only true at the positions
which give you values in the code.
And of course this
you know r subi is not defined for any
position other than 0 1 through n minus
one. So
this condition is probably a little bit
unnecessary but still I'm going to write
it. So if
I is in I1
through I sub
L.
Then
f of
i equals zero. Right?
Because
f ofx was just the product of x minus i
sub k where i is
in this set
and
q of x = p of x f ofx
= z
or q of i = p of I * f of i
equals z.
So
we wanted to show that q of i = r sub i
* f of i. Q of I = R subi * F of I
equals Z
because remember Q of X was P of X * F
ofX.
Okay. So the other alternative is if I
is not in
the set of positions where things are in
error
then
well if there are no errors then
r subi equals p of i
and q of I is equal to P of I *
R sub I
um
Q of I equals R P Q of I= P of I * F of
I
which is equal to since RA I equals P of
I it's R subi *
F of I
and that's what we wanted Q of I= R
subi* F of I. So whether or not I is in
the position containing the errors Q of
I= P of I * F of I.
Okay, so that's the theorem. We have
these
um
two polomials f ofx and q of x which
have this relation between them.
How do we decode
linear algebra?
So the lecture notes give you a explicit
example of how to decode but I am not
going to go through it in class because
you know it's really fairly tedious to
um go through and I will just
explain the theory.
So we have Q of I = R subi * F of I. So
this is a whole bunch of equations. Q of
0 = R0 * F of 0. Q of 1 = R1 * F of 1. Q
of 2 = R2 * F of 2 all the way down to Q
of N -1
= R sub N -1 * F N -1.
So these equations
you can think of these equations as
linear equations and the coefficients of
the polinomials.
And
okay, so what do they look like in terms
of the linear equations in the um well Q
of 0?
Well, I should probably say what the
coefficients are. Q of X = Q0 + Q1 X +
Q
sub
um K + C - 1
X to the K + E - one and F of X = F0
plus F_sub_1X plus
so this has degree e.
Um so it's f sub e
um x to the e.
Okay.
So what do these equations look like?
Well, the first one q of 0 is just q0.
So it's Q0 equals R0 F0.
The next one is Q of 1. So it's just Q0
plus Q1 + Q2 plus dot dot dot plus Q.
And what was the degree? K + E minus one
is equal to
R1 F0 + F1 plus D plus F sub. And the
next one is F of 2. So it's q0 + 4 + 2
q1 + 4 q2 + dot dot dot + 2 to the k + e
minus one
q sub k + e minus one. Of course
this is mod p. So you don't
so the numbers don't actually grow huge.
And this equals
um
R sub 2 F0 + 2 F1 plus dot dot dot plus
2 to the E F sub.
Okay, I'm going to claim this is a
linear
equation
in
coefficients
of
Q and R. Well, what are the coefficients
of Q1 and R? Well, there's Q0, Q1, Q2, Q
plus C minus one, and F0, F_sub_1
through F sub.
And it's clearly a linear equation in
the coefficients.
So
linear
algebra.
Okay.
We have a bunch of linear equations
and a bunch of variables. How many
solutions do they have?
Well,
Let's see
how many variables.
Well, there are e + one variables in f
ofx because they're e+1 coefficients.
And there are k + e minus one + one
variables in q of x because there are k
plus e coefficients.
So a variable, how many variables there
are? K
plus E
um plus E + 1.
How many
equations?
Well,
there are n equations because we have
one for q0, q1 all the way up to q of n
minus one.
n equations.
But somewhere we have n minus k
equals 2 e.
And up there we said we needed n minus k
greater than or equal to 2 e to correct
the errors. But let's assume that n
minus k equals 2 e because that's the
minimum
that's the minimum we need to correct e
errors.
So n minus k = 2 e. So we have k + 2 e
+ 1 variables
and k + 2 e equations.
And these equations are all linearly
independent. And how do you see that?
Okay, I'm not going to really
explain this in full detail.
But remember G is equal to 1 0 0 0
1 1 1 through 1 1 2 4 8 through 2 to the
um
n minus one
3 9 27 through 3 to the nus1 etc.
So this is a Vandermon matrix
and Vandermon matrices
have
full rank.
And this is a theorem which we could
easily have proved at some point in our
course but we didn't and I'm not going
to prove it today. But this is the
generating function. This is sorry the
generating ma matrix for our code and it
has full rank. And by using
that fact and a similar fact on the
right hand side for the fs, you can show
that these linear equations have full
rank. Which means that um
we have n minus k equals
we have k + 2 e um linearly independent
equations and k + 2 e + 1 variables and
that means
there exist
there exists
a nonzero So
solution
and in fact
um
you can use the fact that f sub equals 1
because f was
yeah
f was this
and so f sub equals 1.
Use f subb = 1 to get a unique solution
assuming
l equals e.
Okay, I don't know what happens when l
is the number of actual errors is
smaller than e. the maximum number of
errors you can correct. Um,
and other error correction algorithms
for um, read Solomon codes, you
basically have to go through all
possibilities
of
how big L is and check each one out.
Except there are usually much simpler
ways to do that than going through all
of these um, possibilities.
[clears throat]
Okay, so we have
one solution
to all of these equations.
And that means we can figure out what
q of x and f ofx are
because we know that q of x and sorry q
of x and p of x are because we know that
q of x and p of x satisfy these
um
I'm sorry we know we can figure out what
f ofx and q ofx are because we had
um linear equations
for the coefficients of q of x and f
ofx. So we can deduce q ofx and f ofx.
So linear
algebra
gives
q of x and f ofx
and we had p of x
this was the message
* f ofx
= q of x.
So p of x = q ofx
over f ofx
and we have gotten the message back.
Okay,
so that's how to decode read Solomon
codes.
The last thing I want to do is tell you
about concatenated codes and what
and why these make read Solomon codes
truly practical.
So we have n = k + e
plus 2 e sorry
for read solen codes
and let's assume
Assume
the Reed Solomon codes
over
the finite field
with 2 to the eth elements.
So
I don't know whether professor Mitra
mentioned it before but there's a finite
field for every power of a prime and no
one of the very common finite fields
used for read Solomon codes in practice
is 2 to the eth.
So
let's say n =
256 that's 2 8
k = 150
and that implies that e = n -
k / 2
because we had
um n minus k= 2
And 256 - 150 / 2 is 53
can
encode
let's see K was 150 150 bytes
if we assume a bite is eight bits
into
256 bytes
Correct.
53 errors,
which means 53
is the number of bytes that can have
errors in them.
And
if you think about this
in general
cannot
correct
an error rate
greater than n / two
because the number of errors you can
correct is n minus k / 2 And even if you
use the smallest possible code which
encodes a single bite that's eight bits
um you cannot correct more than any of
our two errors.
Okay.
Let's assume
the bit error rate
is Um [sighs]
10%.
So you're transmitting zeros and ones
and you're
um grouping them into blocks of eight
bits, but each of your bit is
likely to be
have a 10% error.
Probability
a bite
that's a group of eight bits
is in error
is 1 -
1 - 110th
to the 8th.
Okay.
which equals 57%.
I mean this is the probability that each
of your bits is not an error. So you
raise it
to the eth. That's the probability that
all of your bits do not have an error.
And the probability of an error is one
minus this. That's 57%.
So if you're trying to use a read
Solomon code with blocks of size eight,
um
you cannot find parameters that will let
it correct the error.
I want to say what do you do? You use
concatenated codes.
You can look
in code tables.
And these are available on the web.
Find
that
there is
uh
8 seven code.
This encodes
eight bits
into
19 bits
and the distance
is equal to seven which means it
corrects three errors.
Okay.
So, we should call that code something.
So, why don't we call it
C inner?
Okay.
and
use
read Solomon code
and somewhere I had
this example
of
150 bytes into 256 bytes and corrects 53
errors. So I guess that is the
that's n and 150
and um corrects 53 errors because the
distance is
7.
So how do you canatenate two codes?
So the first thing you do is apply
the outer code to your message.
Wait.
Yeah.
What does that look like? Well, your
message you break into blocks of of
eight bits and eight eight bits can be
represented as numbers between 1 and 25
between 0 and 256. So your message might
look like
um 317,
251,
109,
113,
75, etc.
And
it has 150 of these
150 of these things.
So now you encode it in
your read Solomon code using your read
Solomon code and you get 250
code word
length
looks pretty much the same 113 11 17 257
etc.
And there are 250 of these numbers.
Take each of these numbers
code
using
C inner.
And now to decode you first decode CN
and you get this code word and now you
decode it using the
code the um
decoding algorithm for read Solomon
codes and you get your message.
And you have
taken your message
um take
I guess 8 * 150 is equal to um
I think 1,200 bits.
N2
what was our
1987 bits codes into
19 * 256
which okay I did not do this
multiplication
before I
before class so 250 * 20 is um
is around 5,000 bits.
So you've taken 1,200 bits to 5,000
bits.
You have um
and you can ask what
is the probability
you decode
successfully
with a 10%
bit error rate.
Okay, so I used um Mathematica for this
but at a 10% error rate
um
if you have
Eight bits
10% error rate
probability of greater than equal to
three errors
is
11%.
And now the chance
and what did we have? We have an 11%
error rate in the bytes. We have
256 bytes. And if there are fewer than
53 of them in error, you can decode
with high probability.
And you know how with from probability
theory, you know how to figure out the
probability that you cannot decode. But
the probability you cannot decode
is approximately
10 to the -60th
which
is really incredibly small.
So that means that
you can you know if you take a
canatinated code and use this code for
the outer code and this code for the
inner code and you have a 10% error rate
on your bits,
your information almost always gets
through completely intact.
And actually so this
you know 10% error rate um
we've taken 1 1200 bits to 5,000 bits
we've multiplied the number of bits by
four. Now if you look at Shannon's
theorem
if you have 1 1200 bits and a 10% error
rate you should be able to get by with
multiplying the number of bits by two.
So the ideal code would give us 2400
bits and we've used twice that many
5,000 bits. So that's not that horrible.
I mean if we use turbo codes or LDBC
codes or um polar codes which were
invented much later than Reed Solomon
codes, we would reduce that to something
very close to the to Shannon's bound.
But you know this was good enough for
you know let's see
[snorts]
yeah so this was good enough for 30
years I mean
the um all the machinery for using read
Solomon codes had been discovered by
1970 and they remained in widespread use
well they remain in widespread use
Today, anytime you play a CD,
of course, very few people are playing
CDs anymore, but anytime you play a CD,
you're using Reed Sullivan codes.
Okay, [snorts]
there's one last thing I want to say.
Um,
well, I've told you how to decode the
outer code. How can you decode the inner
code?
I mean, it's a 198
seven code.
There are 2 to the 19th which is
approximately
um 500,000
code words
and can use table lookup for these.
You have your computer
have in your computer a complete table
of all now there are 500,000 um possible
yeah there are only 256 code words but
those get mapped into 19bit
um
words And there are 500,000 19 bit
words. And you can use table lookup to
decode. You can just list all possible
500,000
words you might receive. And to decode
them, you look up in the table to find
the nearest code word. And that's the
decoding.
And nowadays, this is incredibly easy.
In 1977 when Voyager did it, I suspect
that the Voyager spacecraft did not have
enough memory for 500,000 table lookup
words. So, they must have done something
cleverer. Well, one thing you could do
is instead of using um
instead of using
uh read Solomon codes with eight bits in
each block, use ones with smaller number
of bits in each block and then you will
get a smaller um code word. Or another
thing you could do is for the inner code
you could use a Hamming code words and
Hamming Hamming code and Hamming codes
are very easy to decode.
although
they really do not get quite as good
performance as you know three error
correcting codes
and there are other things you can do
too so I don't actually know what they
did
for Voyager
but I
um it's probably somewhere on the line
and I could look it up okay so that's
all I have on Eric recting codes and um
in fact this is my last lecture of the
course because professor Mitra will be
giving the next two non um
non-exam lectures and we have one exam
for you. Okay.