okay actually so before I I continue a
few admin uh one administrative
announcement uh how okay there's a
signup sheet
describe you guys saw this very fast
inscribed uh like uh it's all taken so
that's great if anyone how many people
here are taking this class for credit
and did and did not sign up to
scribe okay so come talk to me we'll um
okay I want to mainly gauge the numbers
uh but uh that's fine H so let me tell
you two options either you can scribe
with someone that's okay with me but but
it's okay if you don't scribe there's
other things small things in the in in
in the scribing regime that can that I I
can happily hand out so just come talk
to me if you didn't scribe okay uh and
thank you so much for scribing for kind
of uh picking up the spot so so quickly
okay so uh before I explain the two to
one the the problem with the you know
from one claim to two claims I want to
recap a a little bit because I had some
questions in the break and I want to
make sure uh to try to clarify okay so
what are we doing here the verify the
prover is arguing that in layer I
starting with layer zero
the value at a certain point in the
layer the eventually it's in the
extension the beginning it's not the
extension the value is some Vi Star now
we know that so he's actually claiming
that Vi Star is the value of the
extension but by this calculation we
know that in the some in in other words
he's claiming that Vi Star is this sum
of this gigantic thing so he's claiming
V Star is sum over p in h to them some
over W1 W2 in h to them
of okay so the claim is that Vi Star is
equal to sum of multivariate low deegree
polinomial what we're going to do we're
going to do this exact blackbox some
check
protocol where beta the value we're
claiming we're claiming is Vi Star so
the Prov is claiming that the sum of
this entire thing is going to be F okay
this function is f and he's claiming
that the sum so if you call this entire
function this thing
F the Prov is claiming that Vi Star is
equal to sum on P
W1
W2 of f p W1 W2 in h to them each each
one in h to them so the Prov is is
claiming that VI started this sum and
this F is some kind of low degree
polinomial so what we're going to do
we're just going to do blackbox this Su
check you don't you don't need to
remember what the sum check protocol is
okay but if you remember you just the
pro constantly checks sends kind of
Univar lowre polinomial being checked
blah but if you don't want to remember
what it is don't remember the only
important thing to remember is that the
end and during the subject protocol the
verifier just sends r this he doesn't
need to know anything he sends a random
uh field element gets back a univ pomal
does some check sends a random field
element He never actually needs to know
what this flda is the only point where
he actually needs to verify compare
something with filda is where he needs
to
check that
F Tilda of z0 Z1 Z2 is equal to some T I
don't know to some element
that came out from the subject protocol
some field element T that came
out but the thing is so how does he
check it in the Su check we said let's
assume he has Oracle access to
it but now he doesn't have Oracle access
this gigantic
mess so what do we do so first thing let
me help say okay he does have oral
access to add Tilda and M Tilda let's
assume that but even then he doesn't
know what this VI he doesn't know the he
can't compute the Lo extension of one
layer below so he doesn't know the
extension on Z1 and
Z2 so these are really the only things
he doesn't know if beyond the adld mlda
which way who he knows if he knew them
then he can check and he can catch you
the prover but he doesn't know them so
now we say Okay so we're not done we
don't just do some protocol I mean I
said you car is only some Che but it's
many some checks not just one so we're
not done so now we say you know what the
ver the prover will give the ver
fire the values these two values he say
you know what you can't compute them
unknown I'll tell you what they
are now of course he's going to cheat
because he if he tells honestly he's
going to get caught because our by the
subject protoc with very high
probability this T is actually not the
right
value so because of the soundness he's
going to catch him this is not the
correct value so now when the verifier
so now the verifier tells the approver
give me these two values
if he gives the correct value then the
verifier will compute the correct F and
he'll notice the cheat and he'll reject
him so now what we know is if the prover
wants to win he must
give false answers one of these answers
or both must be false otherwise he's
going to be
caught okay and therefore we reduced a
claim from layer I the two claims and
layer I plus one
is there is there any question about
this do is does anybody want me to
repeat what I just said maybe in
different words or is this clear okay so
now what what uh a what do we
do okay
so so let me
actually
a okay so what do we do so the a
is so in the actually the GK paper
itself well what we did is uh we did
kind of another protocol for go to two
claims to one claim but actually there's
a much much simpler idea which is
actually Rachel's idea
a where you don't need to do anything
actually so here's the idea don't do
anything actually it's not a problem
I know it's funny but it's actually not
a problem why is it not a problem so we
reduced from one claim to two claims
fine continue with two claims now I'm
saying what do you mean continue with
two claims you're gonna get four claims
and eight claims that's
terrible so the
yeah what oh it's Lisa's idea okay
Lisa's idea okay
um a so you go right it was Lisa's idea
I forgot a so you go from from so you
you just continue with two and now
you're saying if you can do with two
you're GNA get to
four so the point is you're not you're
going to stay with two and you're going
to stay with two and stay with two and
stay with two why so here's the idea
okay we reduced it to
two claims about layer i+ one
so now when we go down we're going to do
two sum checks we're going to do again
the exact same sum check but twice
because now we have two claims so now
we're in okay so let's see Let Me Maybe
write it so it'll be a little clearer so
let me actually write a little bit the
the notation so now let's for let's call
this I have this function uh let's call
Fi the sum fi is a function of
p uh yeah P W1 W2 and all it does is it
does a
add it reduces the value of checking on
P to checking two elements in layer I +
one I'm just I want to have a neat
notation so we'll be able to see it so
it does some it it does sorry it checks
if it's
add p w 1 W2 if so it checks add and it
adds a v
i well we'll do the extension but VI on
a W1 plus uh VI + 1 VI + 1 and
W2 plus
malt so I'm just I want to give this a
name so we'll have it this is I this is
i p W 1
W2 time VI + 1 W1 time VI + 1
W2 so for each and every uh W1 and W2 we
check whether you know uh we want to go
to one layer below so we check that the
the whether it's a if it's an add we do
an add if it's a malt we do a malt and
at the end we also multiply this
with Kai of p and w zero
right uh
no hey one second that was the claim
um let me call it
Z this is fi of Z
okay uh good and now we can think of
this as a polinomial because it's all
extended okay and what we check we check
we got a value VI and we check or Vi
Star we checked that Vi Star is the sum
of F this is z star that was the
star we check that it's
f i z i star
of P W1
W2 of of P W1 W2 in h to
them okay so this is where we start
right we have a a value on layer we have
a a fixed zi star in layer I there's a
claim that it that the extension that
point is equal Vi Star and we know that
the sum just by kind of this calculation
that Vi Star should be if you are honest
it should be sum of this
polinomial F and we do a sum check and
when we do a sum check we reduce and now
we reduced it to a claim after this so
we do so now in the G
protocol first we do a sum
check for so for each layer
what do we do su check corresponding to
f
i uh for proving that Vi Star which we
got from the previous layer okay we got
it so in original it's from the it's the
claim V v0 Star is the claim of the
approver the original kind he claimed
that c x that c of x equals v0 star
that's the original v0 Star and then we
check we do some check that this is
equal to X f i zi star these are both
the claims that we started with on
a
a sorry uh so we the sum P W1 W2 on f i
zi star of P W1
W2 so we do we do this Su check at the
end of this sum check we reduced it to
checking two things we reduced it to
checking
V
Tilda a two things v i +
one one star and v i + 2 two star so we
have two v's now and on
two wait
what oh one sorry sorry I one yeah I +
one and then two points we call it Z1 Z2
but these are random points from the
prover okay that these are so this
should
be Z1 and Z2 respectively these are now
star because they're going to be
fixed okay so now we have a new Su check
so this boils down to so now what we
want to do we want to do two sum checks
first some check that VI I +1 star is
equal to sum f i + one and we call them
star so we have
Z let me call this now uh we call the Z
Star okay Z one
star and P W1 W2 but we have another one
VI I +1
2 which is f i +1 V2
star
sum P W1 W2 P W1 W2 so now we need to
prove
this we have two
subjects okay and note it's not even
it's even two subjects of of different
functions too this is with Z1 star and
and this is a Z2 star it's kind of a
little different the functions
yeah
fabulous exactly you got it that's it
it's as simple as that so what do we
do we so I'm saying do two
subjects how do I do two so won't it
grow to four no the simple trivial
observation do two subjects with the
same random from the
prover okay so the G says when you have
this do two Su
checks with
same
prover Randomness uh verifier sorry
sorry
verifier
Randomness so at the end what do we have
if we is the same Randomness we need to
it reduces to verifying f i +1 Z1 star
and some Randomness from the verifier
which uh we let me call it uh I'll call
it again z0 Z1
Z2 it's fresh and also he needs to check
f i +1 Z two star on z0 Z1
Z2 how does he check them what is this F
let's go back
we have all this is the F right like the
the the all this so we said look and til
the door wor he can do on his
own Mt till they can do on his own what
does he need from the verifier and sorry
and this Kai he can do on his own what
does he actually need from the from the
prover what he needs from the Prov is v+
One V plus two Tilda because we're going
one left
on
Z1 and on Z2 but it's the same Z1 and Z2
in
both so all he needs from the from the
prover is the value of V Tilda and Z1
and Z2 and he's
done so yeah two two values we started
with two we ended with two that's it you
continue like this all the way down so
so to summarize how does the what is the
gkr protocol it's just a bunch of two
subjects in parallel D of them that's
all that's what we do okay and in the
middle the prover gives information the
prover needs to give the Vil does to
help him out but that's it yes you need
to like inter the you do it in parallel
yes it's very important good good
observation game it's very important
that when you do when you go from layer
I to layer I + one the two subjects are
done in parallel if you do it
sequentially then now the second subject
you know the coin so you can cheat okay
but you do two subject so you do so
here's the GK protocol you start with
Alpha
layer you do two so okay Al lay two some
check but it's just one it's for the
same thing so you can think of as just
one sum check so you do the sum check
twice for the the sake of it but really
one you do some check you reduce two so
you do the two Su checks it reduces to
two values in
layer i+ one but not just it reduces it
reduces to a point here which you can
compute from two from two values in
layer one one below so so I asked the
provs give me the two values he must
cheat if he I mean if he cheated
originally he must continue to cheat so
I have two values and then I do another
sum check with the same Randomness same
exact Randomness so I do a sum check I
go one layer
below I again I I need to check I get a
value of f but two values of f to check
them I need to ask the ver the prover
give me two values on this layer I plus
two below I get these two values by
soundless of the sum check they must
what they should not be correct and then
I do another Su check another check
another until I reach the leaves the the
input once I I reach the input what what
what did they give me gave me a point in
the low degree extension of my input
that I can compute in linear time it's
just a sum of weighted sum over my input
values so I just computed on my
own that's it that's the
protocol okay so it's really just two
subjects in parallel with same
Randomness prover sends two values in
the low degree extension of next layer
two SS represent two values two
s that's the
protocol yeah so those are not the
same you're saying the same with each
other not the same as yeah exactly yeah
yeah yeah these These are actually per
layer right this is like i+ one this is
like I you know yeah it's exactly so
they're they're the same for I but in
different eyes they have different uh in
different layers you choose the
randomness fresh yes thank you yeah
any like has security proof of like the
parallel version that's does it just
come
from
Yeahs good let so let's do the security
proof I'm trying to think what's the
best to eras here I'll eras this okay so
let's do the security proof the
soundless so first I guess the the um
the completeness really follows from the
completeness from the sum check like if
you do things correctly the sum check
should work you just get the complet is
pretty trivial the uh complexity why
like the
complexity uh we'll do the sound in a
minute let's first do the complexity so
what are we doing we're
doing two subjects per layer we have D
layers so we run in time uh so okay
let's first do the the complexity so so
what is the uh communication
complexity so we do D pairs of subject
protocol so I already run in d what is
the communication complexity of each
subject
protocol number of variables degree and
log F number of variable is 3 m order
M the degree is H minus one or but the
oh I just erased okay uh so the depth
the number of variables like log s over
log log s the degree is log s so
everything is like Po log
s so we don't need o uh and times the
log F we will take F to be polog s2o so
everything is D times polog s okay so
I'll put it aside we'll take F Well it
can be very big but it will be poly logs
okay that's the the field okay ah
sorry it's log it's um
poas yeah so log is log yeah log is p
logs
okay a great so uh this is communication
complexity what about the verifier onun
time so of course he does the com he
does the
so in the care all he does a bunch of
some Che protocols so he just sends
Randomness and does whatever uh you know
uh does these I guess the the the
runtime of the of the Su protocol and
then he gets at each time two elements
from the approver and he just needs to
check like consistency of this F right
he all assuming he has till and M as an
oracle the only thing he checks is like
that this times this plus this is equals
some value so that's just a bunch of
field elements it's nothing uh so really
it's it's the same as this not much more
and what does the prover do the prover
just does a bunch of su checks but the
Su so the prover run
time well he does d sum checks or 2D but
will do a lot of order times the number
of VAR variables M which is uh less than
log s time H to the m which is s so
already he's like poly s so the D
doesn't matter actually essentially be
polys because the D is polys H to them
is polys and the time to compute he also
runs in the time to compute this
polinomial this kind of function but the
time to compute this is also like poly
and H to the m because each one of them
is like sum of H to them terms times
like a very simple polinomial that kind
of the low degree extension so overall
he runs in time poly
so really so this is what you get and
this is what we
wanted
okay so the verifier runs in time D the
number of some check time poly log s
because each time he does something very
very
small okay so let's talk about the the
soundness that's kind of the interesting
part okay so for
soundness the soundness analysis goes as
follows it says
if the prover
cheated there they successfully cheated
so he lied but we accepted him we want
to argue that this happens with a small
probability so for this to happen and
there must exist a layer when he went
from a false claim to a true claim
because at the end he gave us a true
claim because I'm checking in the
beginning he gave me a false claim so
somewhere I had to go from false to to
true so let me I want to look at the not
notation so I won't mess it up this time
um okay so so here's the the sound
is so let's denote so so
suppose we have a cheating
prover that cheats with probability
Epsilon and then we'll see also what
thaton is kind of what's the best
probability you can Cho
so suppose there's a p star that cheats
with probability
Epsilon so cheats meaning he gives me a
false statement but I accept
him then I'm looking um okay so then for
every
actually a okay uh for every I in
D I want to denote the randomness that
was used by the sum Che by the two
parallel sum Che protocols let's denote
by z i0 z
i1 and Z
I2 the randomness
use of
v in the I some check
protocol in the two kind of parallel use
the same Randomness so let's just Den
know by Z i0 that's kind of the z0 Z1 Z2
but in each layer it's different okay
now
[Music]
um and okay and let's denote the
resulting
claim so
denote resulting claim of the after the
the I uh
by a VI Tilda and Z i1 equals V
i1 and VI Tilda on
Z
I2 equals
vi2 okay so this is kind of the the
claim the what the verifier sends me
after the Su protocol okay so I the Su
protocol I gave him a bunch of z z i z z
i1 I2 this is in the I kind of pairs of
some protocol and then I can't comp then
he for the next layer he gives me kind
of the values okay so uh
uh so this is just notation so with this
notation what does it mean for for the
prover to cheat so let's denote by kind
of a bad event bi the EV so I'm going to
not by bi for bad the event that that in
round I minus one he cheat he was he was
faulty Nam gave me cheat but
miraculously in round I everything is
fine okay so Den note by
bi is the
event that what
that in round IUS one vi v IUS one uh on
z i IUS one one
either this is not
true
or VI I minus or the other one is not
true so one of them is not
true so bad is the event that in round I
minus one at least one of the claim is
false but in round I and in round I both
of them are true miraculously
this is also an
equal and VI and
Z2 is equal to
vi2 note that if the Prov cheated it
must be the case that the probability so
because the pro cheated with probability
Epsilon by our assumption it must be the
case that B1 or or BD
is at least Epsilon because he CHS with
probity Epsilon so the pro Epsilon he
starts with false and gets to
true so either the you know he already
got to True after round two like after
the first one or someone went to true so
one of the bees must hold one of the bad
event must happen for him to
cheat but so okay let me denote the
Epsilon here
but by Union bound this is just sum on D
of probability of
bi okay so we know that he can cheat
with probability and with probability
and most some of the probability of bad
on
I now what does it bad so you know let's
look at probability of bad and I so let
me actually even this there's two types
of bad eye there's bad eye where this is
bad bad eye zero and or bad eye one and
bad ey two where this is bad okay so I'm
just let me denote this by some and uh I
and D
sorry the
probability so this is just notation I
want to call this b i0 or bi
i1 or B B I2 so let me Define bi
i1 is that bad where this is bad
where this is kind the the one is bad so
this means that VI IUS one Z IUS one one
is bad it's not like it was false and
this means that two was false okay so B
says one of them was false let's
partition it either the first was false
or the second now maybe both it's a I
said or okay but I know one of them is
false now I'm going to Union bound so
I'm going to say again this is equal to
sum on I and
D sum on B in one or
two
probability of b
i now let's look what is the probability
of bi what is this bad event bi it's
let's think of bi for one for Simplicity
this is
false but the layer below is
true if this is false and the layer
below is true it means that he cheated
in the subject protocol this is exactly
means he cheting subject protocol
because he managed to start with the
false claim of the subject protocol and
get you to a true claim and the kind of
at the you know at at at the F at the
like at the
bottom because if if he didn't give you
a true claim if he gave here true you
would you would uh you wouldn't accept
him you would actually call him out so
if you accepted him when he gave you a
true claim in I it must mean that he
cheated in the I and that subject
protocol
yeah oh sorry yes yeah sorry
a union bound everything is small equal
thank
you
uh oh sorry this is equal this is
definition yeah yeah this is just
definition
yeah okay yeah so B i1 okay so let me bi
is the event that this or this and both
of this bi1 is just the EV that this is
false and this bi is the event that this
is false oh and
this okay exactly so that is the bi is
the event that in in layer I minus one
one of the answers is false but in layer
I both are true that's
bi bi1 I'm partitioning into two bi1 is
that actually it's the first claim
that's false and the next layer is true
bi2 is that the second claim was false
and the layer below is
true so I'm kind of partitioning the two
there's two subject protocols I'm saying
we said look you cheated in one of them
either you cheated in this one or you
cheated in this
one okay so bi1 said you cheated in the
first subject protocol because this was
false and you managed to get it true for
some
reason bi2 says you cheated in the
second subject protocol you started with
false and you got
true so going back to the question about
okay let let me just finish this so
what's the probability of cheating in
the sum check protocol well we have it m
* D divided by f m is less than log s uh
D is less than log s so let's say log
squ
s divided by f
so really the probability you cheat
Epsilon is smaller than log squ F
divided s log squ f is just kind of M *
D for us because m is like log s over
log log s uh D is H minus one which is
log s so essentially log squ s over s so
as long as you take F to be to be oh
sorry a yeah yeah so as long as you you
take F to be significant so now just
take F to be you pay with poly log F in
the communication and everything so take
a big F and you're
good now about the comment of like isn't
it dangerous that we use the same
Randomness for two some
protocols it's not dangerous and the
reason it's not dangerous because we're
doing a union bound the point is we're
doing a some two subject protocols but
actually we don't look let's forget that
you we're doing with you another I don't
care let's just look at one of them
we know that on this you can't cheat
even if you're doing a lot of other
things on the side on this we can't
cheat and we know that on this you can't
now you may it may be correlated I don't
care it may be that you cheat on one if
and only if you cheat on the other the
fact that you cheat on one is good
enough for me I don't so the union bound
kind of takes care of of of the fact
that we use the same
Randomness questions yeah the is it is
the gkr applying in like a black box way
exactly so G KR uses the Su protocol
completely in a blackbox way you don't
need to ever open the bo to know how it
works
so okay yeah exactly so I'll tell you
what you need about the sum protocol the
the one property you need so you can use
any quote unquote subject protocol as
long as it has the following property
the property is that the protocol is
public coin namely the verifi the the uh
the actually that even doesn't matter
let me even the verifier sends some
Randomness let's call it T1 to TM I
don't care what else he sends actually
whatever but at the end of the day it
reducing it reduces to the verifier
needs to check F and T1 of to TM so the
only thing I'm really using about the
subject protocol beyond the the
guarantees is the fact that at the end
of the day the verifier checks F on
random points generated by him
because that is what allows me to do the
two uh the two sucks in in in parallel
and as I said by the way in the original
gkr we didn't need that we could use any
some check because we we actually didn't
do two gkrs there was kind of a two to
one trick that went in there but the way
I presented it here which is simpler we
need the property we need about the sum
check is that the protocol T is that at
the end it reduces to verifying a single
point of that of the verifiers choosing
yeah um what happens at the very end
when you like get theay good how do you
define oh okay so the okay so the okay
so what happens in the input layer in
the input layer at the end the verifier
needs to
compute oh okay uh and the verifier
compute like VD which is the input layer
on uh I don't know
zd1 is it's kind that equals vd1
and VD and
zd2 is equal to vd2 he needs to check
this so the verifier will check this how
will he check it oh he can check that on
his own why let's see how long does it
take to check this let me see where the
low degree extension is buried okay
let's see what is the low degree
Computing the the low degree extension
he knows the uh so
V this is low degree
extension of X1 up to xn it's just
extension of the input that's all so n
is small n is small n is much smaller
than than than S yeah so n is very very
small much smaller than of course the
pro look the verifier needs to read the
input he needs to run time end he needs
to know what he's verifying so he reads
the input n you should think of it is
much smaller than S otherwise there's no
point in all this and to to check this
to check a point in the Lo of extension
of X takes time linear in N times
polylog in the field so quasy linear in
N because to check the sum the to check
load of the extension you just take the
only n of them because you're doing
something over n you can Pat it by zeros
to get as as you want but there's only n
nonzero FS here so you're doing sum of N
elements X1 of to xn and each one times
this small polinomial that you can
compute that's a polylog computation
needy variables for
cut exactly you just set them up to zero
yeah
exactly yeah actually in the original
paper the way the notations work is more
complicated because we didn't set them
all to zero so we had another s and but
setting all to zero is just simple
because you have less notation
other
questions
yeah1 do they come from like the fan in
two like are like left inputs and right
inputs or no uh no okay the fan in two
came from the fact that add here has
only three things it's like the input
and two output like P is the gate above
and it only has two children that's the
fan in two otherwise you'll have many
the the way the reason okay yes the
answer is yes actually because
the yeah okay yeah sorry yes because
because they have only fan in two
there's only otherwise you'll have like
vw1 plus vw2 plus VW3 plus vw4 yes sorry
I did no no so if you had a higher fan
yeah with lower dep could you do just
more some checks lower yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah you can okay
good point okay Leo has a very good
point what Le was saying he's saying
look you assumed fan in two but you paid
for it in Another Log number of rounds
uh don't assume it just don't have F to
have p and many children W1 up to W
whatever uh but then uh reduce it to
more true but you can't have too big fan
because you're going to pay for it in
the communication complexity and
everything so as long as it's most kind
of poly log you're okay so it's yeah
yeah but you're right you don't there's
no magic about
two okay we're out of time thank you so
much and uh enjoy your break next week
for some reason your holiday what