well here we are out on the MIT athletic
fields and I'd like to demonstrate the
principles of rocketry using not a
chemical rocket but a water rocket now
we have to put the propellant in it
which is the water so I'm going to fill
it about a third of the way we need to
leave enough room for the air we are
ready to go now I'm going to put in the
energy that we need for the
rocket and since everything we do in
space flight we're very concerned with
safety I'm going to put on my safety
goggles and now we'll pump it up to
about three atmospheres 5 4 3 2 1
launch
beautiful
boom that's a pretty tough
rocket for more MIT moments from MIT
open learning like subscribe or follow