[MUSIC PLAYING]
ILAN MOYER: When you see machine
learning in popular culture,
it's very abstracted.
And you have the sense
that there's something
very complicated going on.
And this class has
opened the curtains.
FAEZ AHMED: When we
started the class,
I showed off our best
text-to-image generator
of a group of elephants
walking in muddy water.
If you look at
that image and you
look at the one from
2022, 2023, 2024,
you can quickly see how
fast the field has evolved.
LYLE REGENWETTER:
There's a lot of reason
for mechanical
engineers to think
about machine learning and AI to
essentially expedite the design
process.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
EM LAUBER: Artificial
Intelligence
and Machine Learning
for Engineering Design
is a course that takes
machine learning and AI theory
and applies it to real-world
engineering design.
CECILIA ZAGARA: I think my
favorite part was probably
the challenge problems.
ILAN MOYER: They gave us starter
code, which gave a solution.
But it wasn't the best solution.
And our task was to--
OK, how can we do better?
MALIA SMITH: The first
challenge problem
was building a
linkage mechanism that
would trace a certain shape.
It was primarily an
optimization problem.
CECILIA ZAGARA:
We had bikes that
had a certain portion
of the bike hidden.
And we had to figure out the
missing portion of the bike.
LYLE REGENWETTER: And
we tried to set it up
in a sort of
friendly competition
so that students can try
out different approaches
and compete.
ILAN MOYER: And so they
were very engaging.
I didn't realize
how competitive I
was until I worked on some
of these challenge problems.
FAEZ AHMED: It is really
important for our engineers
to know AI and machine learning
and optimization methods.
CECILIA ZAGARA: There's
coding in everything nowadays.
And this class,
while the product
was for engineering
design, whether it
was bike frames or city grids,
it all also came down to coding.
EM LAUBER: So it really
gave me the space
to explore the application
of what I had learned
and the practice skill of
literally how to code it.
MALIA SMITH: The best part
about the final project
was that it gave every
student the opportunity
to apply what they've learned
in the class to an area
that interests them a lot.
FAEZ AHMED: I think
it is always amazing
what our students can do.
EM LAUBER: My final
project for the class
was taking a framework
of a cat tree design
with different modules of poles,
platforms, ramps, and then
developing a utility
function to evaluate
these cat trees to customize
it to the cat household.
ILAN MOYER: I created software
that is designing a new type
of 3D printer architecture.
MALIA SMITH: I chose
markered motion capture data
and looked at predicting ground
reaction force of runners
and seeing if we could
predict that force.
And it was really gratifying
because it worked so much better
than I thought it
was going to work.
FAEZ AHMED: When people think
about mechanical engineering,
they're thinking about
hammers and hardware things.
But mechanical
engineering is very broad.
And within mechanical
engineering,
the aspect of machine
learning, AI optimization,
is playing a big role.
CECILIA ZAGARA: In the
environment we're moving into,
it is definitely
going to be very
foundational to our society.
And I think getting
an understanding of it
is very valuable.
ILAN MOYER: I think
of my grandmother, who
really resisted the
computer and eventually used
it to write books.
But it took her a long
time to get there.
And it feels like, OK, this is
another one of those inflection
points.
And do I want to
be the person that
is kind of stuck in
the past, or do I
want to at least have open eyes?
[MUSIC PLAYING]