energy we use and how we cure diseases.
It has the potential to drastically
reduce our reliance on greenhouse gases.
But there are enormous challenges to
getting promising advances from labs to
the market. Standing up a large-scale
manufacturing facility can run up to$2
billion. The field is full of regulatory
hurdles and workers need advanced
training. Jay Christopher Love looks
ahead at promising biio manufacturing
solutions and what it will take to scale
them. Please welcome Professor J.
Christopher Love.
[Music]
It's a pleasure to be here. Let's talk
about how biotechnology can be one of
the most important technologies in the
21st century. In order for it to realize
its potential in enabling
sustainability,
uh changing the accessibility of drugs
and medicines and foods globally, we're
going to have to rethink manufacturing
to achieve that. So, in the next 30
minutes plus the time that we have for
questions together, let's really look at
three things. One, what is the
bioeconomy and what is the potential
that it unlocks?
Two, what are the challenges in thinking
about transforming manufacturing as it
stands today? How do we not just build
more of the same, but actually overcome
some of the fundamental challenges in
the way that it's practiced presently?
And then three, let's look ahead to what
that technology base might look like
that really changes the game for
enabling biotechnology across the board.
If we think about biotechnology, some of
you may think about this in the context
of medicines or perhaps in food
products, things that you maybe interact
with. What you might not realize is that
biology now has the potential to impact
nearly every product and material that
we interact with. Up to 60% of all goods
could be manufactured with materials
sourced from biological sources in the
next 10 to 20 years. And in terms of
growth and economic impact, the
bioeconomy is estimated to be anywhere
between, you know, a few trillion to to
maybe a 10 trillion dollar industry in
the next uh 15 years with the US
accounting for maybe about a trillion of
that. And so it has this opportunity to
really impact all of the different ways
in which we think about the world around
us in relation to all of these other
technologies we're talking about.
It also offers this really remarkable
benefit that I think we all kind of
appreciate. Everyone likes going to the
beach and having a nice day in the sun.
The sun is a really uh large source of
energy and biology is actually quite
good at capturing that. May not be as
efficient as as we would like it to be,
but it is a source of renewable impact
and biology by its nature uses that
energy and transforms it into things
that it intends to produce. What's cool
about biotechnology now is that we get
to impact what it is that it does with
that energy. And so this has led to a
lot of ideas like circular bioeconomies
where we might be able to generate uh
you know use biomass that's that's a a
waste product in one in one uh value
stream and use that as an input into
another value stream and to do this in a
way where we're extracting the most
information and content and value out of
each of those different stages along the
way.
This is an ideal picture. You can see
it's a cartoon. Our our challenge now is
in how do we realize this and how do we
make this this a
reality. What I will tell you is that
and this is just one study. There's a
couple of studies that have now looked
at this in terms of dollars invested.
Biology is one of the most efficient
ways to transform
sustainability. So built materials built
built infrastructure concrete
transportation these are all
contributors to greenhouse gas. Uh but
biology because of its potential impact
on how we think about food technologies
and sustainable practices in agriculture
per dollar invested actually has the
potential to uh to really drastically
change that that that that
infrastructure th those greenhouse gas
numbers. So biology provides this really
efficient path towards improving
sustainability globally. So this all
sounds really fantastic and great and
you know I think that a lot of you may
have seen this in a variety of different
ways in which there's now emerging parts
of this ecosystem that are being played
out uh in in in the current environment.
But the question that we've been
thinking a lot about is how do you
really transform and unlock this
bioeconomy? We heard earlier that the
the defense base in the United States is
largely built from small and medium
enterprises that participate in that
infrastructure. It adds resiliency. How
do we think about the manufacturing
infrastructure that's necessary in order
to enable this kind of picture of a
bioeconomy that can transform materials,
foods, and
medicines? One of the kind of arguments
is that we will need a really large
supply chain in order to do this. And so
what this really means is that we have
to take
ideas from the research, right? A lot of
us at MIT think deeply about how to make
uh new kinds of organisms or engineer
organisms to do particular tasks. This
is a common space now called synthetic
biology or engineering biology. Uh
metabolic engineering is a way to sort
of create fine chemicals and other
materials that you might
need, medicine, cell therapies and and
all of these are these are ideas that
are coming out of academic centers and
startup companies. But in order for
those to actually reach the marketplace,
manufacturing still stands in the way.
It's like big secret, right? is a
manufacturing conference. Manufacturing
is the key. But manufacturing today is
messy. It's hard to do. It's uh very
manual. And so how do we efficiently
enable this type of economic cycle to
pair with that idea that ideal state of
a circular
bioeconomy? And one of the challenges in
this is that we actually now have
created a different kind of supply chain
needs. So, the types of supplies that
you have to make, all of those very
exciting things like mRNA vaccines that
we just heard about a moment ago or
organs on a chip or artificial tissues,
all these things that are like right at
the forefront of biomedical innovations
or food products like cultured meats,
these all rely on a supply chain of
lipids and DNA and proteins and and
things that come only by biology. These
aren't things that we can make easily by
chemical synthesis, but those materials
themselves are created from chemicals.
And so we're kind of inserting this new
part of our supply chain that's going to
be necessary to think about how do we
address that and then how do we use that
to generate all of these different
ideas. So the problem is getting messy.
It's not simply that I want to make one
kind of product now, but I need to be a
wide range of different kinds of
products and I have to do this
affordably and at scale.
One of the real challenges in the kind
of current infrastructure for
manufacturing using biology is that it's
really hard to do. How many of you have
been to a biommanufacturing plant or run
one? Yeah, a good number. They kind of
look like this picture over on the right
of people. They're gown up because you
want to maintain aseptic operations.
There's a lot of stainless steel that
tends to be in these plants. They're
kind of modular and compartmentalized.
You see here a picture of some of the
reactors. There's another suite that's
charged with recovery of the
products. This picture and the time and
cost of building these types of
facilities doesn't match the pace of
innovation that we're now seeing in the
ideas for what we can do with biology.
The biotechnology is happening faster in
the lab than we can keep up with. And so
right now there's a large effort to
think about where do we have capacity
globally? How is it uh used? Europe has
a really strong uh infrastructure for
fermentation capacity here unlike the
United States. Uh but a lot of this
capacity is already spoken for, right?
Companies own it. They use it for their
own products and there's not really a
lot of available capacity. So where do
all of those new products go? If I'm a
venture capitalist, I'm not going to
invest, you know, $200 million in a new
plant. And we were talking before about
value added productivity. This is really
poor industry for this. you know, we
have to process a lot of material with a
lot of workers in order to get, you
know, what's a relatively small volume
of material back. So, the process
intensity in these plants is really low.
You can kind of even just see that in
the picture of how much space there is
relative to that. And that has a large
impact, that costs the environment
something. When I build a really big
facility that I have to put a lot of
people in and walk around in and have
all the gowning to maintain that
asepticness and the raw material flows,
that puts a large load on HVAC. So the
the recirculating air accounts for about
50% of the total energy cost in one of
these large facilities. So if you build
a $2 billion plant, you know, most of
your carbon footprint is coming from the
HVAC that you have in that facility, not
to mention all the support utility and
the uh waste disposal that goes along
with running and operating these
plants. From a energy perspective, it's
bad. From a water perspective, it's
perhaps even worse. Right? This industry
probably uses 10 to 100 times more water
than most other ones. It's not very
intensified. And a lot of this has to do
with how biology works, right? We're we
get dehydrated. Uh this is this is
natural. So some amount of water is
required. But how do we recycle water
more efficiently? How do we make sure
that we're not using steam for
sterilization? That's an energy cost and
a water cost. Where can I put these
things? Uh I spent some time on
sobatical at at a large
biioharmaceutical company and every day
the executive vice president walk by and
say, "You're a smart MIT professor. Tell
me how I stop shipping water around the
world." Because in this industry, water
shipment is a is a big deal,
particularly for for finished products.
So, how do we do things that don't have
the same transportation tax on water
that that is kind of currently enabled?
So, if I just build more of the same,
not only is it costly, there's very
little capital interested in doing it.
And but I also have to face additional
sustainability challenges by scaling up.
and oh yeah the world's getting more
complicated in ways that you know I
think we all appreciate you know
geopolitical uncertainty the logistics
that kind of come with that where is my
supply chain come from today in this era
of globalization biotechnology relies on
a very diverse supply chain from around
the globe uh you know I think there's
market headwind in in a lot of different
directions on biotechnology currently uh
it's very hard to manufacture these
things at scale for for uh for for new
kinds of food products The
biioharmaceutical sector uh has been
successful in bringing products to
market but there's an increasing demand
on kind of the reliability of those in
the public markets before uh seeing the
value inflections uh consolidating
supply chains on the vendor side.
There's very little room for innovation
in technologies now uh that are
different than what's kind of currently
being operated just because of the scale
at which it's being done for a very
small number of manufacturers. And then
the climate and we've talked about but I
think is maybe not fully appreciated is
the acceleration and pace of new. We
just heard a talk about AI. Many of you
probably seen AlphaFold the protein
folding tool. Companies are now like
ideulating new ideas for drugs that are
very very specific and targeted to
particular rare diseases and such using
these types of technologies. And so the
number of ideas that are being generated
really does outpace our ability to think
about the manufacturing. one of those
large facilities like I just showed you
maybe has 20 slots a year and if you
know 15% of them are free because
they're not being used for other things.
How do I get that backlog
through? So we can't just keep building
more of the same kind of infrastructure
in order to actually be successful here.
So if we were to then think differently
right biio manufacturing works we get
drugs to patients they have access to
medicines that currently exist albeit
mostly in North America and Europe 80%
of all the registered monoconal
antibodies for biioharmaceutical
treatments and cancer autoimmune disease
etc are registered in North America and
Europe and not the rest of the world
although certainly much more of the
global population lives in the global
south you know how do we think about
what those traits need to look We have
to think entirely differently. We have
to think from a different mindset as to
what the qualities are. Agility is
important. We saw this during the
pandemic. If you had had u some of the
components for being able to run
bioreactors hanging around your garage
or somewhere, you could have sold those
on eBay to a bioarmm company for quite a
bit during during the pandemic. There
was a lot of uh swapping of parts and
and and uh supply chain components to be
able to enable their medicines.
Sustainability. How do we build a new
technology base if we don't also think
about sustainability and particularly in
an industry where by nature it uses a
lot of water, it uses a lot of
electricity to maintain aseptic
operations. Uh so if we're going to
transform how we make materials and
build a new manufacturing base, we have
to think from the beginning about that
sustainability question. Uh flexibility.
So that facility that I showed you the
picture of and when I build a plant
today for a billion dollars, it's
usually designed to make one product.
Maybe I'm lucky enough I can make a
handful of products that are all sort of
related in that same one. But to change
it over from one to the next is cost
additional capital investment and time.
So these facilities are really designed
for manufacturing very well. one thing
that doesn't really jive with this this
kind of current state where we have a
lot of new ideas coming into the
marketplace through startups and
academic uh sources and then empowerment
I think uh you know one of the things
that that we've seen as a trend in this
industry is
consolidation there's been a lot of
different uh companies that have
participated in manufacturing but now
there's very few companies that supply
into manufacturing and there's very few
companies that have the capabilities of
really manufacturing at scale this leads
to less competition ition. How do we
know that we have the best medicines or
the best food products, you know, in
other markets and other sectors where we
have competition and there's competition
through the ability to bring products to
market, you know, that enables better
solutions. So, as we think about what it
means to create affordable medicines
that are accessible everywhere, you
empowering others to be able to
manufacture a critical quality. So, I've
done a really good job, I hope, uh, you
tell me later in the break to set up why
we should do something different here.
question is what do we do different
right biology is hard this is the story
that I often hear you know like biology
I can't I don't I don't know anything
about it it's this weird thing and like
I can control stuff around it but what
do we do with the biology well so we
should think a little differently how do
we start to really think uh where this
could go and so I'd offer this as an as
an objective or a goal right most of you
probably have an inkjet printer at home
um some of you maybe have 3D printers I
could use the same analogy of 3D
printers as as this one and maybe that's
a little more timely
But, you know, for 80 bucks on Amazon or
Google, your favorite source, wherever
you like to go shop for these things,
you can buy an inkjet printer that'll
print you something that has the same
quality as something that you can
produce at a commercial scale. And when
you've created that idea yourself,
you've used whatever latest AI tool to
make that amazing graphic that's going
to, you know, be your next brochure.
When you want to tech transfer it to
commercial scale, you just literally
send the file and it prints more. Right?
We see this in additive manufacturing
too. Things are designed for
manufacturability and they're done in a
portable format that allows for that
immediate
transfer. And this is really enabled
because we have standardized systems.
It's not that the products are
standardized, it's that the
manufacturing techniques are
standardized in order to enable that
particular objective. And so the
question is in bio could we do something
similar? And just to make this maybe a
little more pointed and and to think
about what this could look like. I'm not
offering here that we should replace the
current manufacturing
infrastructure. And you know I think one
good example of this is to to dig deeper
into this idea of commercial printing.
Uh this is a a graphic that a couple of
my students put together kind of
estimating the volume of pages per day
as a function of time. And you see this
goes back it goes back a little further
than u Ben's indices earlier this
morning. You know back to back to 200
when the first wood block printing was
enabled. The Gutenberg press was
generated manual process. You know
the in in that era you could print you
know roughly one page per year per
person. And then we had the first
industrial revolution. So that kind
automated that particular process.
Automation is an important
transformation step. Uh then there's an
increase in the overall volume as we add
more facilities, more capacity. And then
there's this other inflection point at
the top there. This offset rotary
printer. This is now automated
continuous production. If you think
about a printing press, it's a batch
process. I do one at a time. If I go to
continuous and automate it, I can
produce a lot more. Today biio
manufacturing is largely done in batch
mode and manually
operated. So with this centralized
continuous manufacturing you can produce
about 300 pages per year per person.
That's you know roughly you know 100
100,000 printers globally and these are
kind of order of magnitude engineering
estimates. You'll forgive us if it's a
little off. But I think what's really
interesting is if you think about
another technology that emerged in the
1950s and this was done uh by Xerox and
Park which was one of the you know major
research institutions
uh in the corporate sector in that time
they developed the idea of a Xerox home
copier automated small
footprint batch manufacturing.
those technologies improved. You know,
part standardized competition emerged in
the manufacturing of the
manufacturing inkjet printers. And with
that, now today, there's almost the same
capacity globally with this distributed
manufacturing capacity as we have with
centralized. Both of these two
manufacturing strategies coexist and
they both have uh you know similar kinds
of purpose but they kind of allow for
different kinds of manufacturing uh
goals. And so if we think about this in
terms of biio manufacturing what does
this look like? Well today this is the
model. It's that highly manual you know
very you can see that in the picture but
like you literally are doing lab
experiments at 10,000 liters and moving
that fluid around. You don't want to be
the guy that drops it on the floor. Few
million dollars of uh of lost material
when that
happens. And they move this around from
process to process. Very manual, highly
skilled labors. Most most of the
employees in these uh facilities have
advanced degrees. Uh often uh masters or
PhD level. And there's very few
facilities globally. We have a lot of
capacity. And if you look and you Google
the numbers, there's a lot of capacity
people will say. But again, a lot of
it's spoken for and there's very few
folks that actually control that
capacity and it costs a lot to build it.
So no venture capitalist is going to
say, "Hey, I have this really great
biotech company. I want to go build new
manufacturing at $200 million to see if
maybe your product makes it through the
clinic." That's just a very bad risk
profile. So what we, you know, I think
are going to start to see here is that
there's an increasingly high need for
certain high volume lowmix
manufacturing. This might look a lot
like what we're currently doing, but
just at a very very large scale. I don't
know that this is going to be the most
common manufacturing strategy, but we're
going to see it for certain things. For
certain food products, we may need to be
able to do this to get to the right cost
per kilogram of something like a
alternative food substance. Uh some
materials and and some medicines. So
like insulin or perhaps ompic, you know,
some of these weight loss medicines,
medicines for infectious disease, very
very large scale, lowmix manufacturing.
uh will will certainly continue and
we're seeing you know investments in
some of this globally right now but I
think the part that we're going to see
more and more of and there's already
trends in the marketplace is towards low
volume highmix manufacturing this is low
capex is think about that inkjet printer
analogy uh these are highly automated
systems they take the worker out of the
facility right it's a it's a it's a box
that they can interact with and it can
produce you know regional scale products
new products you know things that are
and other kinds of biology. So
cell-based therapies, things of this
type. And of course, once you kind of
have proven a market, you can either
scale out with that kind of capacity or
if you really need to, you can scale up.
So I think, you know, there's a new kind
of space in biio manufacturing where
there's an opportunity uh to think about
new new
solutions. What are those features that
you would have to have to enable? We
might say what are the user requirements
or the specifications has to be highly
intensified. Not everything's going to
fit in the box. So, I got to take out
everything that I don't need. So, that's
going to have to mean that I really
think about manufacturability up front
of my products to fit into these types
of facilities. Uh, and I want to
minimize the number of uh lowv value ad
steps that I have along the way. If I
have to move my fluid from one step to
another one, but I have to hold it for
an hour or two and do an adjustment and
then put it in, that that's not very
efficient. It's not going to fit in my
box very nicely. Modularity.
We see this in in other in other
industries like additive manufacturing
uh even the semiconductor industry where
you have these defined modules that have
si certain fit forpurpose applications
in the manufacturing role that they play
and they do it for that and it's kind of
plug-and-play. It kind of works as as
intended. Uh we've heard a lot about AI
and and machine learning augmentation.
How do you use these tools to
efficiently transfer from one scale to
another one? How do you use it to help
predict what the process should be in
order to use it? I don't have to think
when I tell my printer to print my
idea, use the PDF, use the procript, get
this font. You know, it's a problem when
it does. It gives you an error message,
right? How do we use that type of
augmentation to broaden the workforce
that can participate in the bioeconomy?
And then all of this will really hinge
on automation. This will reduce the
volume and the footprint of these
facilities. So, these are the features.
How do we get there and what might it
look like?
um the biioharmaceutical industry is
already making a switch in these
directions. So I mentioned the idea of
continuous production as being a key
inflection in printing. We're seeing the
same trend occur in the
biioharmaceuticals. This is a nice cost
analysis from a few years ago. Uh
looking at the top line there, this is a
traditional stainless steel facility
like the one that I showed you. Cost
about a billion dollars to produce in
capital. Gives you very high efficiency
in the overall production rates per
year. But the net present cost when I
start day one is quite high. Right?
Market adjusted forecast. In contrast,
if I switch to a continuous technology
in this case using singleuse
technologies, these are sort of plastic
bags and materials of this type and you
wait a minute wait a minute. You just
told me that you want to be sustainable.
You tell me about plastic bags.
Interestingly, in this industry,
switching to plastic is a huge
environmental savings. 90% of the water
and the waste that is treated and used
in those traditional stainless steel can
be eliminated and reduced by going to
these types of single-use technologies.
And the amount of single-use material
that's used in these types of facilities
is like a very small fraction compared
to the total global plastic output. So
in terms of value of where we spend our
plastic dollars, if you will, uh this is
actually a very efficient one. And when
I do this, I get, you know, a lower net
present value to build that facility and
modular expansion to be able to cover
the same production volumes over time.
So the bioharmaceutical industry is
moving in this direction. And what
they've kind of realized is that there's
actually a I'll call it a canonical
model for what this modular footprint
might look like. This is the continuous
production of monoconal antibodies.
These are the largest selling
bioharmaceutical products by class
globally. uh you know treatments for
cancer, autoimmune diseases. Uh Katruda
is a good example of this from Merc. Uh
they make these in these continuous
processes where the materials flow
constantly from one to the other. It's a
big innovation in this space where it's
largely been done by batch and using
these types of strategies. You can now
get to about $50 to $100 per gram in
drug substance. That's still too
expensive for the whole world to be able
to sustain and afford. Right? So if we
wanted to be able to uh provide
medicines into to these types of
medicines into the into the global
south, we really need these to be about5
to$10 per gram. And if we wanted to talk
about alternative proteins for food use,
it needs to be about $5 a kilogram. So
we still have a long ways to go and
that's where part of the opportunity
lies. But I think really seeing like
where this sort of intensification
allows you to do this now uh in a very
uh pragmatic way. This isn't the limit
though.
If we start to think differently,
remember I mentioned the biology as
being a core catalyst in all of this. If
I use the biology to my benefit and
think differently about the biology that
I'm imposing, I can actually start to
make further reductions. So if I
engineer ukareotic microbes to replace
the mamleian cells, I can start to get
rid of a lot of the high value steps or
the high high cost steps in the
particular production processes and
start to simplify this even further. So
how do we use holistic design that
incorporates both the engineering and
the biological processes to be able to
reduce the overall cost and time to
market? Well, part of the answer is that
biology is now like software. So we've
heard a lot of talks about
softwaredriven manufacturing.
Biommanufacturing will be a biology
softwaredriven industry. And we're
already starting to see this. If I want
to create strains that have the ability
to produce particular proteins, lipids,
RNA molecules, I can just go sequence
the genome. I can read about it. I can
model it now. I can and I can ask
questions in in some AI models now to to
start learning about how to think about
that engineering. And then I just go use
Crisper or other gene editing tools to
make the changes and move on. So this
allows for reusable underlying parts
that you can start to use uh to do the
manufacturing. And to this end, we
started a consortium at MIT that's
really thinking about open source
platforms for new biologies to
facilitate high volume production uh
using these types of u manufacturing
hosts as well as engineering in some of
the quality elements that are required.
Happy to chat with folks uh offline
about this if it's of interest. But what
this lets you do is now suddenly
simplify your manufacturing process. I'm
showing here three different
manufacturing processes that we've
identified you can do in six to seven
steps. These would normally take between
15 and 20 steps in commercial processes
today. Each of these would require a
different facility built in order to
accommodate them. But you can see these
all look very similar in the way that
they're sort of outlined here. And
that's the point. You don't worry about
the details, but they all look quite
common to each other. So now what if we
could put that in a box? We had an
opportunity to think about this question
to build an automated benchtop
manufacturing system that would allow
you to put those uh microbial systems in
and operate a process like the one that
I just showed you to be able to make
medicines. And we showed that in 72
hours we could make clinical grade
materials that would be sufficient for
you initial uh studies in the lab or
potentially a first in human trial.
We've now made lots of different
proteins on this same platform and you
can make really new new ideas come up.
You have a new yeast organism, you can
drop it in and you can use this as a
starting point. So now imagine you know
a pandemic comes and you have to develop
a new vaccine. We had this chance during
the covid pandemic to actually build a
new recominant vaccine candidate uh that
ultimately went into phase one studies.
It took us 30 days from the time that we
got the DNA sequence to having a process
and the materials necessary to be able
to uh advance that candidate forward. So
innovating with real speed in kind of
new types of small footprint
manufacturing is really important. The
user interface is also important. So
we've spun out a company Sunflower
that's advancing some of these
technologies and their whole mission is
to think about how do you make it so
that no one can make a mistake. Everyone
who has ever run a bioreactor has
plugged the base port in on the wrong
pump at some point. That just cost you
at least $100,000 in parts if you're in
a pilot facility, and it could be as
much as a million dollars in materials
when you are at scale. So, how do you
use software and good engineering
interfaces to allow users to to not have
to be experts in the manufacturing
process, but to be able to do these
things simply and as they want to? and
how do you allow that to then transfer
at scale so that it's the same
experience as you move from one stage to
the next one. They've taken and
demonstrated this idea that box that I
showed you at the benchtop. They've
actually now done it in a a system that
would fit here on the stage uh and
during the pandemic had a chance to make
some uh vaccine candidates for uh SARS
KB2. They ran a pilot scale system in an
office space in the Boston area, made
materials, and then they transferred the
the persons, the strains, and the
software to a warehouse in California
and made it on a system of like the one
that was shown here. All, you know,
within a couple of
weeks. This is pretty interesting. That
system that would sit here on the stage
could make 10 kilograms of protein per
year. To put that in perspective, and I
was running the numbers this morning,
herptin, which is used to treat breast
cancer, there's about a thousand
patients annually in Austria that need
that treatment. One system of this type
could provide that entire supply for the
country. What could you do with multiple
ones? Right? So, how do we think
differently about scale out to enable
wide kinds of products across a number
of different things? Our friends at
Sartorius have looked at this question
in terms of process intensity and CO2
emissions and shown that continuous
processing with these types of organisms
does allow for reduced uh equivalent CO2
compared to other uh compared to other
batchbased strategies. So suddenly we're
seeing that not changing just one piece
but changing the entire paradigm and
thinking differently about this is
allowing for these types of uh
transformations. And we're not the only
ones that are starting to think about
this. I I picked a couple of examples
here of other uh types of technologies
that are emerging uh for mRNA, other
ones for protein modular facilities that
you can stand up and build very quickly.
Uh live viruses for for certain gene
therapies or vaccines, cell therapies,
all based on very similar kinds of
ideas. How do we intensify the actual
process? How do we reuse parts? How do
we build scale in by scaling out?
And so I think you know as we look at
what an agile and sustainable next
generation biommanufacturing is going to
incorporate it will be distinct modular
technologies not a plant per product but
a a modular technology that can make a
few different products a few different
cell therapies or a few different mrnas
or a few different proteins. How do we
think about the holistic design uh in
order to use the biology to our
advantage? I think we're going to see
more purpose uh towards manufacturing by
design in that that way. And then we
really have to think deeply about the
user experience. Software is good. It
helps with a lot of different user
tasks. We all know how to use our cell
phones. How do we build that in so that
it's not this complicated thing that I
have to like be an expert in to know
what what knobs to push? Uh this is
where a lot of the deviations in
manufacturing occur today and one of the
challenges in tech transfer. And so if
we look at the European bio economy, you
know, and this is a map that I pulled
that I I like because it shows where the
printing presses were over about a
hundred-year period. uh around the 15th
century. You can see they're highly
distributed, right? So this is
information flow. What if that's
medicines? What if that's food products?
You know, I think if we think about what
this means, it's decreasing the capital,
always a good thing. Shortening supply
chains and adding resiliency, reducing
land and resource utilization. That's
important here as it is everywhere. Um
adds new kinds of jobs that are based on
tech skills as opposed to, you know,
manual labor. Uh, and I think the other
advantage that's probably, you know,
something to unpack at another time is
how does this allow for better
efficiency in regulatory processes? If
you know what the manufacturing strategy
looks like in advance, you aren't asking
as many questions about it. Um, so I'll
stop here with just a couple of points
of homework, right? A faculty member
from MIT can't come to a classroom and
not offer a little bit of homework. Um,
so I'm going to give you a couple of
things. One, we got to dig into the
science of biio manufacturing. What I
mean by this is we have to know more
about how to do great manufacturing. We
sometimes like punt it over the fence
and say manufacturing is just going to
happen. We need to understand how to en
enhance the productivity for a lot of
these product classes. The yields just
have to be higher. We need new ways to
recover product. This is going to be
especially important for foods where
chromatography is not feasible. Um we
need to design these solutions with
sustainability in mind. We want to get
rid of interfaces and reduce water
utilization. We have to increase the
automation and predictive tools. Where
are ways that we can enhance that and
build that in um upfront and on on
purpose? And then I think you know this
is a little bit broader is we need to
think about ways to promote deployment.
We need more manufacturers operating in
this space. So how do we you know think
about organizational structures
differently to increase the number of of
small and medium enterprises. A system
like that one that I described you right
I mean ballpark I'm going to say is
order of magnitude like a million
dollars. That's a pretty low capital
barrier compared to, you know, a 50 or
$200 million plant to be able to stand
up. How do we get more structure, more
organizations participating? And then
what are the financial tools and
policies that would allow for that? How
do we create the pull to rebuild that
biio manufacturing base or to build it
up front? I'll stop there. I know
there'll probably be a couple of
questions. Happy to chat also and we'll
have some time in the workshop tomorrow.
But thank you all.
Okay, some questions. What do you see as
the potential role of non-farma
manufacturers in these supply chains
beyond just being customers for
bioproducts?
Yeah, awesome question. So that supply
chain that I showed you, we need to make
lots of proteins. We need to make lots
of lipids. uh and so like the
requirements for those to be used by
pharma sources aren't the same as what
they have to go through in order to
actually release their their final
product that will be used in humans. Uh
there are some regulations around that
aspect but we actually just need more
capability in that that area. So I think
a lot of what we've talked about here
applies uh equally well in that space in
addition to the applications like food
and materials where you know the the
regulatory requirements are a little
different and a little lower than than
the bioharmaceutical sector.
Well, I'm going to say thank you, Dr.
Love, uh, for your comments, and I think
it's very interesting. I'm sure you're
going to have a lot of conversations at
at lunchtime. So, awesome. Thanks,