(knocking on door)
- [Interviewer] Hey, Katie.
- Hey!
- [Interviewer] Thanks for taking the time
to hang out with us today.
- Of course! I'm so excited to be here.
- [Interviewer] Now,
you're getting your PhD
here at MIT CSAIL.
What inspired you to
work at the intersection
of machine learning and mental health?
- I was initially drawn
to machine learning
because I think it's really interesting
from an intellectual standpoint,
and then I quickly grew
even more interested
when I realized the
immense potential it has
to make a societal impact.
And I think one area
that is particularly ripe
to have an impact in is mental health.
Because a lot of people
struggle with mental health,
and compared to other aspects of health,
like physical health,
our understanding is relatively limited.
- [Interviewer] I completely agree.
Now, for those of us not in the field,
can you walk me through the challenge
of accurately capturing
mental health metrics
using machine learning?
- Yeah, let me talk through an example.
So some of my work has looked at
how we can automatically
monitor mental health
from speech data.
You can imagine that
when someone's depressed,
it changes the way they speak.
They may speak more slowly
and in a more monotone manner.
And so we can use machine learning
to pick up on those changes.
The main challenges that other
things also change speech,
such as how tired someone
is, who they're speaking to,
what recording device is being used.
And so we have to disentangle
between these various factors.
- [Interviewer] Now, what
specific mental health conditions
are you focusing on?
- I've worked on speech data
from people with bipolar disorder.
I've also worked on wearable sensor data
that we've collected from
people who have depression.
And then finally I've looked
at stress and anxiety.
- [Interviewer] You've been
at this for about five years,
so how do you see
personalized interventions
improving mental healthcare
in say, the next decade?
- One of the big challenges
with mental healthcare
is that the best treatment
for one individual
can be different from the best treatment
for another individual.
And it's hard to know which
treatment works best in advance.
So machine learning can be used
to help understand
interpersonal differences,
to enable more tailored treatments.
- [Interviewer] Now,
to deploy these models
in the real world,
we always hope that
they're safe and accurate,
but how do we ensure that?
And do you have any ethical concerns?
- Absolutely.
I think when we think about deploying
machine learning based health technology,
we need to consider how we evaluate
other types of healthcare
interventions, like medications.
We should apply the same
scrutiny when considering
whether we should use mental
health technology on patients.
- [Interviewer] Absolutely.
Now a big part of research
is dealing with difficult
challenges all day long
and trying to solve them.
So tell us about something
particularly challenging
that you solved.
- Yeah, so a problem we
see time and time again
when working with mental health data
is that when we visualize the data,
so say we have speech here on the x-axis
and heart rate on the y-axis,
the data is highly
clustered by individual.
So here we have person one,
and over here we have person two.
And these inter-person
differences are so pronounced
that it can make it hard to
determine the differences
we actually care about,
which are within individuals.
So when is this person
depressed versus not?
And so I developed algorithms
that allow us to better
focus on the differences
we care about and ignore
these other differences
that make it difficult to learn.
- [Interviewer] That
does sound challenging.
Now, do you have a
favorite software or tool
that's indispensable to your work?
- One tool I've liked a lot recently
is called Weights and Biases.
It allows me to automatically
track the progress
of my experiments and visualize
the results in real time.
(elevator dinging)
- Oh, hi Katie!
- Oh my gosh, hi!
- So good to see you.
- You too.
- So to put this in really simple terms,
can you explain the
role of causal inference
as if I was a 10-year-old?
- Sure! So causal inference is a field
that studies cause and effect.
And it's important to
distinguish causal relationships
from those that are just correlations.
For instance, if I take vitamins,
I wanna know if they will
actually improve my health,
versus they're just something
that healthy people do,
so they're correlated with health.
- Oh yeah, that makes a lot of sense.
So can you explain the
role of causal inference
as it pertains in your research
on machine learning and health?
- Yeah, absolutely.
So when we use machine
learning to, for instance,
recommend treatments to patients,
we need to make sure
that the relationships
we're considering are
causal relationships,
that the treatment will
actually have a causal effect
on the patient's health,
and isn't just something that
the machine learning model
has picked up as co-occurring
with better health.
- Thank you. That's very helpful.
- [Katie] Of course. Good to see you!
- You too. Hope you have a great day.
- [Katie] You too.
- [Interviewer] So a big part of research
is balancing the theoretical
with the practical.
How do you do that?
- I like to use the practical
challenges that we encounter
when thinking about
mental health applications
to motivate my more general
machine learning work.
- [Interviewer] Now,
what about limitations
to current approaches to
mental health monitoring?
How does your work address those?
- One of the main limitations
is that monitoring right now
is restricted primarily to
observations of patients
in the clinic.
My work examines how we
can use data from patients
outside of the clinic as they
go about their everyday lives
to get a more comprehensive
picture of health.
- [Interviewer] Could you talk to me about
what you find to be the most
fulfilling aspect of your work?
(elevator dinging)
- There are a couple
things. First is the people.
I get to work with brilliant, motivated,
just wonderful people.
And then the second
is that I'm constantly challenging myself
and learning new things.
- [Interviewer] Do you have any current
favorite applications of ML in healthcare?
- Obviously I'm excited
about mental healthcare.
But in addition to that,
I'm also really excited
about machine learning
for helping people improve
their physical fitness.
- [Interviewer] With all these wearables,
I do tend to think about
navigating privacy concerns
that are inherent in using
AI for health monitoring.
- Definitely.
That's a really important
thing that we think about.
There's many ways we consider privacy.
One is making sure we have
great security practices.
Another is making sure we
only collect the data we need.
And then finally, we also make sure
that we're transparent with the peoples
whose data we're collecting
and we obtain informed consent.
- [Interviewer] Over
the past couple years,
we've had increasingly more conversations
around mental health and therapy.
So how do you see the
integration of these AI tools
in mental healthcare changing
societal perceptions?
- Incorporating AI in mental healthcare
can help make it more accessible.
And I think in doing so, that
will help to reduce the stigma
around accessing mental healthcare.
- [Interviewer] When
you lie awake at night,
do any philosophical questions come up,
considering the role of AI in
understanding human emotions?
- One question that comes up is,
what does it even mean
to experience an emotion?
AI may be able to simulate
having an emotion,
but does that mean it
really experiences emotions?
- [Interviewer] What about the
balance between human empathy
and machine precision playing out
in mental health interventions?
- I think we definitely need both,
and I don't think they
necessarily need to be intention.
If we equip mental health professionals
to improve their ability to help patients
using machine learning tools,
I think we can have both.
- [Interviewer] And what
about this potential
future relationship between
human therapists and AI
in mental healthcare?
- Yeah, I think mental healthcare workers
are already using AI tools
to help, for instance,
summarize clinical notes.
And I think we'll see this
continue into the future,
where AI is used to enhance
the ability of therapists
and other mental healthcare
professionals to do their jobs.
- Oh, hey, Katie!
- Hey Gabe!
- Can you tell me about
a moment in your research
that changed your understanding
of machine learning's potential?
- Yeah, so actually, when I
first started doing research,
I worked on a project
where we were detecting
changes in the severity
of bipolar disorder from speech data.
And when I got my first model
working, it was so exciting,
and it really demonstrated to me
how machine learning has this potential
to help in really important applications.
- Cool, thanks!
- Yeah, of course.
See you, Gabe!
- Yeah.
- [Interviewer] You've
been at this for a while.
I've asked you a lot of
questions about your research.
So throughout all this,
how do you maintain a sense
of curiosity and wonder,
especially when things are
complex or frustrating?
- I think for me, a big part of it
is recognizing that when challenges occur,
that's where most of the learning lies.
I've found that I've made some
of my biggest breakthroughs
at moments of peak frustration.
- [Interviewer] Now since
we're in a different building,
I thought it'd be a great
time to ask about life
at MIT CSAIL.
Tell me about your most
memorable experience so far.
- One of my most memorable
experiences came early on
when I was giving one of my
first lab meeting presentations.
And I found that within just a few slides
of my presentation,
I was stopped and asked so many questions.
And I think that really reflects
how engaged everyone is here.
Everyone was so invested in helping me
and offering suggestions, and
that's really stuck with me.
- [Interviewer] Now, what
about a typical day at CSAIL?
- My days vary a lot.
I do a number of different things,
from coding to writing to
preparing presentations,
to having brainstorming
sessions, whiteboarding.
So it really just depends
on the project and the day.
And I love the degree of
flexibility that I have.
- [Interviewer] Yeah, like
hanging out with us all day.
Now, I know community is a
really big part of research
and it's a big part of the ethos at CSAIL.
Talk to me about a collaboration
that maybe brought a new
perspective to your work?
- So partway through my
second year of my PhD,
I started working closely with
my friend and collaborator,
Rob Lewis.
And we worked on a number
of different projects,
ranging from more applied
in the mental health space
to more general machine learning projects.
And I've just loved having someone
to go into the weeds with.
We do a lot of brainstorming
sessions together,
and some of my most
productive research moments
have come through that collaboration,
so it's something I've appreciated so much
during my time here.
- [Interviewer] What's it like
working with your advisors?
- Working with my advisors
is a wonderful experience.
Not only are they brilliant,
they're also incredibly
supportive and engaged in my work.
One thing I really admire about them
is they both value doing really
high quality technical work
and making sure that the
work has the potential
for real world impact.
- [Interviewer] And how do
you incorporate their feedback
into your work?
- That's a great question.
I think about the advice
they've given me a lot
as I'm going about my
research, week to week.
But then I also have
meetings each week with them
where we discuss together
how I can incorporate their feedback
and thinking about what
I'm going to do next.
- [Interviewer] Okay.
Now, do you have a
favorite spot on campus?
- Yeah. I love going to the
river, at the Charles River,
and walking along it.
I find it, it's a great
way to clear my head,
especially when I'm working on
a difficult research problem.
- [Interviewer] It's
beautiful and peaceful.
Is that your favorite spot in Cambridge?
- It's among them. I also am a big foodie.
So I love this Mediterranean
tapas restaurant called Oleana.
- [Interviewer] Oleana is amazing.
If you're watching this
and you haven't been, go.
Now, what's your favorite aspect
of living in Massachusetts?
- I love that Massachusetts has a mix of
everything I like in a
state, in Boston, in a city.
There's great food, there's fun breweries,
there's pretty nature,
Boston's a pretty city.
And then on top of that,
there's access to nature.
I love skiing and hiking
and it's great that I can do
both of those easily from here.
- [Interviewer] Let's rewind a bit
and talk about life before MIT.
Talk to me about your experiences
at the University of Michigan.
- I loved my time at the
University of Michigan.
I actually grew up in Ann Arbor,
so the city has a really
special place in my heart.
And my time at the University
of Michigan was so fun.
I met so many of my best friends there.
It has this really high
energy culture that I love.
And then the other thing about it
is it's where I really
cultivated my research interests.
It's where I first started doing research
on machine learning for mental health,
and first thought about
applying to do my PhD,
and so ultimately how I ended up at MIT.
- [Interviewer] Wow. All right.
So what are some of the differences then
between living in Michigan and Cambridge?
- Well, I was hoping that
when I moved to Cambridge,
I would escape the Michigan
winters and have better weather.
That hasn't really turned out to be true.
It's maybe a little bit better.
But what I like about living in Cambridge
is it feels like a bigger
city than Ann Arbor,
which is very much a college town.
So there are more restaurants,
more people, more going on.
- [Interviewer] Okay,
so the bar is really low
for weather in Boston.
But anyways, I wanna talk
about your internships.
I know you interned at
Microsoft three times.
Tell me a little bit about that.
- I really liked my
internships at Microsoft.
The first two were in
software engineering,
and I was so excited
because it was my first
time working at a company
in general.
But what I didn't like
as much is I felt like
it was a little bit limited
in terms of creativity.
I was told to code things
and then I'd code them.
So I was actually very excited
when I got to intern at Microsoft
Research this past summer.
I had much more freedom in terms of
directing the course of the project,
and was able to work on
cutting-edge research.
- [Interviewer] Now, did
any of that influence
your current work?
And either way, just tell me about
some current published
papers you're working on.
- Yeah, so one recent paper
was around detecting stress
from a biosignal called
electrodermal activity,
which sounds scary, but
really what that is,
it's the electrical
conductance of your skin,
which has to do with how much you sweat.
So when your fight or flight
response is triggered,
it changes sweat activity,
and then we can actually measure that
to track changes in stress.
- [Interviewer] The field
is rapidly advancing.
It sometimes feels like it's almost daily.
So how do you stay current
with new advancements?
- It can be tough,
but I find there's a
few things that help me.
One is Twitter.
Academic Twitter has a lot of posts
where people are sharing
the latest advancements.
And then I read a lot of papers,
and then finally I talk to people.
I find it's helpful to know
people who are in the know.
So I'm always talking to other people
about what they've been reading about.
- [Interviewer] How do you
prioritize all of your tasks
and just manage your time between research
and your personal life?
- It can be tough, but I
find what's important for me
is scheduling things in my personal life,
so I hold myself
accountable to doing them.
So I love playing soccer and I
have regular soccer practice.
I love running and I book time for that.
And then I also make a lot
of social plans with friends
to get me out of the office.
- [Interviewer] Okay.
So now can you share a book or a paper
that's greatly influenced you?
- Yeah, so off the top of my head,
one book that's influenced
my research a lot
is called "The Book of Why."
It's by Judea Pearl and Dana Mackenzie.
And it's about causal
inference and its importance.
- [Interviewer] What's it
like to mentor students
or new researchers who come to your lab?
- Getting to mentor other students
is one of my favorite parts
about being a grad student.
I find that it's so rewarding
to get to pay it forward
and help other people
find the joys of research,
and gain the confidence in their ability
to take on challenging research problems.
Oh, hey Rob!
- Hey Katie. How's it going?
- Good. How are you?
- Good, good. It's great to see you.
What are your aspirations for
the next phase of your career?
- I think a couple things come to mind.
One is I would like to move more towards
having a real impact on real patients.
And then the other is I
would like to continue
to mentor students,
and I would like to increase
my scope in doing that
and actually become a
professor and have my own lab.
- These are all really admirable goals,
and I'm sure you're gonna get there.
I have one last question for you.
What advice would you give
to aspiring young researchers
who dream about getting
to a position like yours?
- I think one thing that's
been really big for me
has been reflecting on what
my genuine interests are
and following those.
I think machine learning has gotten so hot
and there's all these things
like large language models
that everyone's really excited about,
and it's easy to get caught up
in what other people are talking about.
But it's important to think about
what genuinely gets you
excited and go for that.
And then the second thing
is to really go for it.
I've found that by reaching out to people
and expressing my interest
and making connections,
that's been huge for my success,
because so much of my success comes from
the people that I get to work with.
It was good to see you, Rob.
Nice hanging with you all.
I'll see you next time. Take care!