on a technical level of using the tool
of um the imaging tool uh we use it to
probe how synapses are formed. What
influences that? What influences the
fact that they are dismantled.
Um so those are pretty basic uh
you know features of how brain cells
alter their connectivity
but uh you can apply once you understand
um how to visualize it and what the
baseline is of normal
um kind of brain plasticity is. You can
use any mouse model for any disease. Um,
and you can use that tool to ask what is
wrong in terms of
how synapses are formed and dismantled
in the disease model. And many diseases
do have a synaptic phenotype. In fact,
synap genes that encode synaptic
proteins are like a hot bed for
neurodeeneration mutations.
um uh mental health genetic uh
mutations. Uh so so it's a powerful tool
to kind of probe mechanism of what goes
wrong in these sorts of situations. So
that's one aspect. Um
the second aspect that uh we work on
relates to the genes or the synaptic
genes or proteins themselves.
And um
we know that one of the driving forces
for plasticity is basically activity.
Sort of like in the same way as like you
go to the gym and you work your muscles,
your muscles that you work become
strong. connections in your brain that
you use a lot become stronger. So it's
the use the activity of these
connections that is really
driving their strengthening.
So the and connections that don't get
used basically eventually dwindle away
and go away. So um
use or activity is driving the change.
And so these proteins that are synaptic
proteins that are sort of implementing
things um they're very often regulated
by levels of activity. And so a long
time ago we did a screen for genes that
actually respond to neural activity sort
of as a way to identify who might be
participating in these events. And uh
these genes have turned out to be
extremely interesting
um in terms of their synaptic functions.
And even though again we started looking
at it as a basic feature of how the
brain modifies connections, it turns out
that the two genes that we picked as our
first new discovered genes that are
activity regulated have both turned out
to be uh really important also from a um
sort of a disease perspective.