now those of you who have been around
MIT for a while know that MIT one
University one MIT we call it has five
schools and one college and the five
schools are
engineering science architecture
planning Humanities and the MIT School
of Management plus the College of
computing the Sloan School of Management
has a very unique
Mission and it works globally to educate
and do research and back in
2013 they opened an office in South
America in Chile to serve as a central
point of contact for many of their
activities whether they be educational
or research or collaboration or
networking and that was very
successful and it turns out that they
then focused on where should we have a
physical presence in Southeast
Asia and they pick Bangkok to be the
center of aan to bring people together
from all across the region for all of
the activities that support the mission
of the Soul School of Management and
what I'm going to do now is just spend a
very few minutes talking about that
office I was honored to be at the ribbon
cutting just a couple months ago with
many of you here in the audience many of
our corporate uh sponsors of this
program and the industrial Asen program
have also kindly sponsored the Azan
office here in Bangkok the ribbon
cutting was held on the 30th of October
and there you can see the sponsors as
well as the then interim Dean Georgia
paracas of the MIT SLO School of
Management during the ribbon
cutting the mission is to act as a
bridge to bring action learning
convening activities faculty from all of
MIT together with the purpose of
building visibility and Community while
also driving the economic and social
impact throughout the region of
aan and you can see that they have
decided upon a structure of governance
that includes an advisory Council which
is is being formed this year the first
year of operation my understanding is
that there'll be a full-time executive
director of The Office who will be
stationed uh here in Bangkok they're in
the process of recruiting for that
position and the three pillars of the
office include faculty research action
learning and convening activities and
the faculty research has in fact been
very robust for many years here in
Bangkok with funding from industry and
the government as well including
Innovations and water and agricultural
systems carbon reduction uh Urban
metabolism and increasing access to
Market
information here are some of the MIT
faculty who have been participating over
the last number of years in these
projects and I'm sure that if you would
like more details and what they're doing
they will be more than delighted to have
you contact them action learning
includes a folky on col U Cambodia
Indonesia Malaysia Philippines Singapore
Thailand and Vietnam that's been going
on for two decades 800 or more Sloan
students have worked on projects in the
aan region and there have been 18 aan
lab projects completed since that
program was launched in the spring of
2023 Community connections have measured
in the thousands major conferences have
been
sponsored and three reap cohorts which
bring together people from Academia
government and Industry as well
to prove that you can bring these people
together to make the world a better
place it's expected that Sloan will
enable significant impact here in the
region a central Hub provide a presence
literally on the ground here in Bangkok
to support the aan initiative and
identify key priorities to listen Len to
people like you for what you expect from
MIT in the region if you'd like more
information on the program the it is run
by the MIT Sloan School of Management
Global program office they're located at
One Main Street that's the same building
that I'm in in our industrial a on
program there is their website you can
contact them directly if you'd like some
more information or feel free to contact
me and I'll point you in the right
direction
[Applause]