um thank you for the introduction and
great to be back at MIT um and excited
to talk to you all about my research and
um kind of my vision for where I think a
lot of cool research can be done in a
for Earth very broadly um yeah I'm a
senior applied research scientist at
Microsoft research I did my post talk
here at Microsoft research New England
and now I'm technically at a Redman team
just haven't moved yet so it was a very
short commute for me um I want to start
my
by this little um oh it even has the
sound nice by this little um time lapse
so what you what you see here is a time
lapse of objects in lower Earth orbit
since the
1960s up until all the way to today and
what you can see is this kind of steady
growth of more and more objects over the
last six
decades now many of these objects you
see here are Earth observation
satellites so satellites that sense some
aspect of our plan
it
and the question for me since a long
time has been you know with all of this
sense sense state of our planet what
what can we do with it um and what do
these satellites
observe and yeah we're about 10 years um
off from today bit more but you see it's
getting really cluttered up there and I
don't know if you you've noticed but
sometimes you look up you can for
example see the Starling satellites uh
in this like little neat lines traveling
through the sky so it's looking very
different to even when I was a
child
now as I said there's more and more
satellites being launched almost every
day what you see here is just kind of
the expansion of the esa Mission so the
European Space Agency um up until the
2030s um obviously these satellites
produce a massive absolutely massive
amounts of data and um I think to kind
of put that a bit into perspective if
you think about the latest Generation Um
large language model something like gp4
we don't exactly know how big the
training set for those models were but
it's hypothesized or estimated that was
around one petabyte of tokens we
training data and keep in mind that for
for this data to be generated open I
basically scraped every single existing
text that exists and um some people you
know think also they kind of translated
YouTube videos and made that into text
so we don't know exactly right um to
compare Earth observation data with that
the kind of current estimate of all of
the earth observation data out there is
800 petabytes with another 100 petabytes
being generated every year so we're kind
of working on completely different
orders of magnitude
here and it isn't really just um
satellites uh a large portions of all of
the world's data have Geographic meta
metadata attached to them right so
beyond the satellites we might have
something like a a Geotech tweet so
social media post that has been sent
from a specific location and then we
have also Al like derived products like
elevation or species range Maps um at a
given
location now I really believe that
there's lots of potential in combining
these uh geospatial data sources from
different ground and remote sensors
together to support decision- making and
for this we can leverage their joint
geography their joint um yeah geometry
being being able to map them on the
sphere of our planet um and I'll show
you a little example of what I what I
mean with that for example we could
combine this Geotech tweet which is from
Annapolis it's about a flooding event oh
no that was too fast I wanted to do this
right so this is a a tweet about a a a
flooding event in Anapolis we can
combine that with real-time
meteorological data that comes from a
satellite for example to make some
informed decision for example should an
evacuation um order be issued or
not so this seems very intuitive right
this combination and support decision
making so why isn't this being
operationalized at large scale and I'm
breaking this down very very roughly but
um I think there's kind of three
overarching problems that currently
exist the first one I got to already is
the sheer scale of this data the second
one is that this data is very
unstructured and multimodel right so we
working with you know images video very
very different data modalities
unstructured is they're like in
different archives um different from
different providers some some of them
are behind pay wall some of them you
have public access
to and the latest big problem is that a
lot of this data is unlabeled right so
um while we have satellite imagery for
the whole world we only have kind of
limited labels that tell us what exactly
is in this satellite image at this
location at this point of time and with
uh my research um I'm kind of trying to
tackle all of these problems at once
very ambitious but I think um there's
some interesting Solutions here um for
the large scale problem very kind of uh
yeah invoke uh solution is to use nor
networks kind of the best scaling method
that we have to deal with large amounts
of
data to tackle the kind of unstructured
multimodal um nature like I said I
believe we can fuse different modalities
different information of of our planet
together in their joint um locations in
space and time and then lastly to tackle
this problem of of the largely
unscalable uh UNL data I think we can
leverage advances in self-supervised
learning so learning um without
labels and the type of models I want to
talk about today and that I believe have
the potential to fulfill all of these
parameters are geographic location
encoders um and these are highly
scalable neural network models that use
self-supervision to learn semantically
meaningful representations of our planet
from these large amounts of Earth
observation data and throughout this
talk I'll kind of show how we built the
first generation of these models and
then where we go from
there and um the way I want to structure
this is first I want to talk a bit about
the origins of the spatial modeling
problem then I'll outline location
encoders and how they currently look in
part three I will talk about how to S
train them with s supervision and in
part four I will talk about the kind of
looking ahead what is up next
all right so let's start with um
learning from Geographic data so the
classic um uh description of this
Geographic modeling problem is that for
a given location let and long we want
some output and what we can leverage
here is the first law of geography all
things are related but near things are
more related for example for a good
temperature estimate at our current
location the best thing we can do is we
can look up the closest available
temperature sensor and and then weigh
our estimate somewhat on the distance
between us and that sensor and so we can
get from few spus observations we can
kind of build a dense map that exploits
this spatial
smoothness um classic interpolation
problem traditionally in Du uh
statistics we would use a g gion process
for this um in in in geography it's also
often called cing so we would basically
learn a continuous function over space
using using
kernels one problem with these kind of
traditional uh methods is uh that they
scale pretty poorly right so gion
processes and kernel methods have cubic
complexity and um while there is some
work on for example deep caution
processes that help that a little bit we
kind of still struggle with the pure
scale of that data Gan processes are
also not the best models to work with
kind of very complex data types like
images or
so and lastly at least vanilla gion
processes are also not able to deal with
the kind of spherical nature of latitude
longitude coordinates you can use
something like a spherical kernel but
again there's some some
shortcomings so uh we are machine
learning people right so why don't we
just replace the Gan process with a
neural network and uh solve all of these
problems unfortunately that's not uh not
so simple either because um new networks
also have some problems sure they scale
better but they also for example don't
necessarily work on um spherical
coordinates and can deal with the kind
of non-clear nature of geographic
coordinates so what we do here is then
we want to kind of build the best of
both worlds uh neural network
architecture that is able to deal with
the spherical nature of the coordinates
and that is the geographic location
encoder and the idea here is
to First embed our location coordinates
or latitude longitude using some
positional encoding this is if you're
familiar with Transformer architectures
is basically very similar to our
Transformers to positional encodings and
then we put a neural network on top that
learns a weighted function of these
positional encodings to solve our task
at
hand and hopefully this can then scale
to really high dimensional data and
again we kind of do the same thing we
would do in a GP and learn this
continuous function over
space the other thing we can do with
this is um that location encoders also
give us the flexibility to integrate
them with other neuron Network models
specialized for different inputs for
example images and this is the idea that
um behind Geographic priors so for
example here we have a image
classification task where we want to
classify the image of this uh this fox
this this is an arctic fox if you think
about this task kind of location
agnostically um it might be a bit
difficult to exactly place as animals
foxes are all around the world but
knowing the location of the fox will
allow a model to learn uh internally
some some sort of species distribution
model and will um have the model learn
that you can only find the species in
certain um
latitudes and so Geographic priors are
relevant for for many different um
applications not just kind of species
classification but for example also for
building segmentation or soil carbon
estimation all right so done with part
one the kind of description of the
spatial modeling problem let's let's go
into part two um the location encoding
uh uh yeah Basics and this is mostly
based on our iar 24 Spotlight paper um
which you can all check
out so here I briefly describe how uh
location coders should be designed um
how they were designed in the past and
what the current stateof the art
is all right so let's start with a few
formalities about encoders I'm not going
to go into all too much detail um but
basically this is the very simple form
they take you have your locations C so
these are latitude longitude coordinate
pairs um that are fed through a
positional encoding this is purely
functional transform right so there's no
learnable parameters there and then the
output from this positional encoding is
going to be fed into our neural network
which has learnable parameters and that
is our location inorder quite simple but
of course we can do a few different uh
modifications here and the first one I
want to talk about is the history of the
different positional encodings that were
used the kind of first positional en
coding we can look at in the machine
learning literature is from a 2015 cvpr
paper that does very very simple one hot
encoding of the coordinates so the idea
is that you split your whole world into
grid cells um each of the grid cells is
um yeah one value in your tensor let's
say and all of them are zero value
except the one grid cell that your
location Falls in that's a one so very
simple similar to other one encoding
methods in in other areas obviously not
the most sophisticated positional
encoding and so in 2019 allet cvpr um we
saw kind of the first bit more
sophisticated version of uh positional
encodings and that was the first
sinusoidal one um same paper as the
paper I talked about before with
Geographic priors and image
classification of um an
images and so here the idea is to um use
S cosine activations very much again the
same attrition as for Transformers um
and so here you project your latitude
longitude coordinates in from two
dimensional space into four dimensional
space doing cosine lat cosine long and S
lat sign
long and over the recent years the kind
of state of the art has been to make
more sophisticated versions of this for
example the multiscale sinusoidal
encoding where you basically do the same
s cosine functions but you do it at
different frequencies um basically by
dividing um dividing the um values by
this Alpha here which is your scaling
factor and you can do that at arbitrary
intervals to get more and more F fine
grained um uh
embeddings all right so this is kind of
the work up until maybe 24 um but there
has not really been a fundamental shift
in the way these positional encodings
were done in in this kind of sign coign
formation and the work that we're doing
is changing this and I'll get to that in
a
second the other part of the position of
the location encoder has remained vastly
unchanged over the last years and that
is the neural network component so
basically what people have been used
here is simple um fully connected layers
or simple MLPs um this is also something
we're going to change in our
paper and the reason why we adapt this a
little bit is that existing location
encoders um up until us had two major
shortcomings first performance of these
location encoders falls off drastically
around the poles and the reason for that
is that these location encoders use sign
cosine um positional encodings um that
isum in space and around the poles this
diverges the most from the true
spherical space of of our planet and so
we should probably replace them the
other problem is that simple uh fully
connected networks are not necessarily
equipped to learn these kind of smooth
spatial functions that we want uh smooth
functions over space that we want and so
we want to tackle both of these problems
at once in our uh work and the solution
for the kind of first problem uh in the
positional encoding is that we using
spherical harmonics functions in setad
of simple s cosine activations and the
um the answer for the second problem is
that we don't just use a fully connect
networks but we use sinos soidal
representation networks so s activation
functions
um yeah let me get a little bit into
into the first component the spherical
harmonics positional encoding so
spherical harmonics are widely used in
ge6 fluid dynamics to model our planet
so this is kind of the St status quo in
in
geophysics um and I'm not going to um go
much into the math here but basically
spheric LM monics are um orthogonal
basis functions that are natively
defined on the
sphere and um they come in different um
numbers of degrees L and uh or as M um
this is kind of the full function here
but I guess in the interest of time also
not going to go too much into this um
and while there is a closed form
solution for um for the spheric
harmonics uh we can also analytically
pre-compute them which is really nice
later on in our neural network training
because that makes everything much
faster now there is a really cool
theorem that says that any function on
this sphere can be approximated by a
weighted sum of spherical armonics
functions and so the question now
becomes how do we get these weights for
the weighted spherical armonics
functions and our answer is that we use
a neural network to get these weights so
we use a neural network on top of our
spherical harmonics positional encodings
to yeah hopefully approximate any
function on the sphere and to better
learn smooth spatial patterns we use a
neural network uh architecture that
comes out of vision especially 3D Vision
and that is the sinusoidal
representation Network that was actually
proposed by Vincent sitzman who is right
here at MIT um and yeah they've been
shown to be extremely effective at
learning neural implicit representation
which are again these functions that are
continuous in space and you can think
about this from a kind of 3D Vision
perspective uh as a point Cloud problem
we have Point clouds in 3D space and you
want to build some um continuous mesh or
map out of them and basically we have
the exactly same problem uh on the
sphere of our planet and the trick with
s sinal representation networks is
really really really really simple and
it's just changing the activation
function in network to sign activation
function that leads to some
computational issues um if if you stack
a lot of these layers because
computation gets gets more important uh
gets more expensive but we're not really
dealing with large neural networks
here all right and then again we
hopefully can um learn this kind of
weighted sperical harmonics to solve
functions on the sphere and um let's put
things together um we can use location
encoders just like we would use caution
processes or other interpolation methods
and learn from kind of sparse
observation a continuous map in
spherical space for example we can use
them to learn a map of land mass
globally right so here we sample let's
say 5,000 locations on the planet we
give them each a zero value if it's
water not land mass or one if it's land
mass and then using our um spheric
harmonics location encoder we built like
a dense map and you see depending on how
you set your scale this works quite
well let's look at the two components of
our uh new location encoder separately
um so first siren neural Nets are better
than existing linear or fully connected
backbones for learning spatial patterns
which you can see here right so on the
top we have kind of the exact same
positional and quarter backbone or
monics but on the top you see a linear
neural network and on the bottom you see
a siren neural network um the L5
hyperparameter here um that's basically
the number of lra polinomial we use in
our sperical harmonic so the higher the
more fine grain our spatial resolution
is which you can also see and you see
that the the S neural network just gets
much better
resolution now let's look at the other
component the spherical harmonics
positional encoding and here we want to
specifically focus on the polls areas
remember there I said that existing
methods often fall short on the poll
because the assumed ucan space of kind
of Foria transforms diverges the most
from the actual spherical space um let's
look again at our arctic fox so here we
do arctic fox image classification and
you can see that a model that uses one
of the existing positional encodings
that is not um spherical harmonics based
um has much more artifacts that are
completely far from the poles compared
to our method um another example here
this this a different um this is
synthetic task
Fibonacci checker board prediction um
here you can see in the figure the red
line is our spec harmonics method and
you see that it remains quite accurate
around the polls whereas other s cosine
base methods fall a bit off
here all right so that's it for part two
to recap so far we've discussed how to
design state-of-the-art location
encoders and how to train them directly
right so here the input was L long and
the output was some value right landm
yes yes no or um some climate variable
right so we have like a direct um
classification or prediction problem the
next part of the talk will focus on
pre-training location in quars with
unlabeled Earth observation data and how
this can help us improve modeling
Downstream and this I should have
updated that slide so this work is based
on our paper sack clip which is not
under submission anymore but a tria AI
paper uh next week in Philadelphia if
you're
on and why do need the step um so far
we've basic basically only talked about
spatial
interpolation but a big question in
geospatial modeling is of course also
can we do extrapolation and um spatial
extrapolation describes the problem when
we want to make a prediction
geographically far from our training set
and we cannot rely on the first law of
geography or just kind of looking at
nearby um observations because we just
don't have any nearby observations and I
believe that using this globally
available Earth observation data and our
um location and quoda models that we can
actually make a big step towards kind of
more General approaches for uh
Geographic extrapolation which is one of
the kind of big long-standing problems
in uh geospatial
modeling and to kind of outline the
intuition for that a little bit um I
want you to think about the Earth as a
bounded space right it's a completely
bounded space we can kind of capture all
of the planet with satellites and sure
some areas might have more or less cloud
coverage but in the end we can kind of
observe everything plus there are
sensors that see through clouds like
radar um and now if we assume that Earth
observation data is roughly relevant to
a lot of tasks we can hopefully leverage
this kind of data to capture ground
conditions that are relevant to our
tasks um and Infuse them in our location
and quarters and have them available for
the whole world
but the question is how do we go about
this pre-training all right so again the
intuition is location encoders fail when
deployed in unseen
areas question is can we pre-train them
on globally available Earth observation
data so no error remains
unseen and to revisit our kind of Arctic
fox um prediction task instead of doing
this conditioning on the geographic
location um like from scratch basically
just feeding in the coordinates can we
instead of just the coordinates feed in
some semantically meaningful Vector
embedding that represents this
location and to get to this embedding um
and to explain the intrution for how
this pre-training works um I have a
little game that we can play and the
game is called uh where is this
satellite image so um hopefully you can
yeah basically geog guesser but geaser
is like with street view imagery now you
have the satellite view right so um yeah
anyone have any idea where this image is
Sara Sahara okay any other guesses we
have
Sahara that's uh Northern Africa e
Eastern what Eastern Africa Eastern
Africa
okay any other guesses Boston
har Boston Harbor Boston Harbor okay I
think so I actually need to see because
I don't think you can see it so well
scale like what is this oh oh yeah yeah
yeah so this is
um 2.5 by 2.5
km I think it's a bit hard with the Bea
view this is always a bit the tricky bit
of the the talk because it kind of
always depends like at least the screen
is very big okay so everyone's guess was
very
wrong this is a picture in the in the
Arctic somewhere in
Canada and um so this now we know where
this picture is what I want you to do
next is I want you to think about if you
now know this location think about what
characteristics in this image might make
you think of that location and um again
so I have I I happen to know where this
is um and so I can walk you a little bit
through what I think are kind of
relevant characteristics so in the top
here we have this little little white
patch I don't know if you can see it
well which could be snow then we have
this rugged kind of
maybe glacial morine and then down here
and this is the bit you can't really see
because of the contrast but there's the
coastline here right so there's some
water here and all in all these three
features might give you some indication
that this is kind of in the in the
Arctic Circle and the true location um
can actually be predicted quite well
with the neural network and this is
exactly how we're going to pre-train our
location
encoder and the way we do this is very
much similar to clip clip is a model by
open air that matches text and image
pairs only in our model we we match um
image and location pairs right so we
take a bunch of globally distributed
Sentinel to images with their
corresponding locations and then we have
a contrastive learning objective where
we feed our images through an image
encoder locations through an location
encoder and then we match the correct
images with the correct locations in a
batch and the idea is understand that if
this training succeeds we can take
forward this location encoder and obtain
semantically meaningful embeddings for
every single location on the planet and
if we train this on enough data this
model should learn to interpolate and
even work for unseen locations because
because it will interpolate from the
nearest seen observations leveraging the
first law of geography and learn this
kind of smooth embedding map so to
say and yeah so the way this works um is
that you have like a bunch of different
um image embeddings you get of course
and you have a bunch of different
location embeddings you get but
throughout this matching process you
learn to align them and to transfer the
features that make an image look unique
to a location into the location encoder
and so now Downstream you don't need
images at all anymore because you assume
that the most important image features
are now part of the weights of your
location encoder and you just have a
model that takes in latitude longitude
and returns these embeddings the
embeddings in our case are um 256
characters long so they're not really
able to capture super super granular
structure like how many cars are in this
picture or so they only capture very
high level
features and one of the high level
features that they capture that we can
show is biomes right so here you have a
dense biom map of the whole world um and
now again think of a interpolation task
right so you take 5,000 uh random
locations and try to build this map from
scratch again from these 5,000 locations
sparse location uh sparse location build
a dense map if you do this just using
the location encoder trained from
scratch no pre-training with our sa clip
method you get to this map so you get um
not a very good um accurate map of
biomes now if you do this using our
pre-trained um location encoder instead
you get to very accurate biomap so we um
basically see through this that our our
sack clip
embeddings excuse me capture at least
some degree the conditions that make out
a
biome now this is an interpolation
problem and uh when I started this
section of the talk I said that sap can
be really useful for extrapolation right
so what am I doing with interpolation
and to explain that a little bit I will
we play a second round of the game and
the second run of uh of the game um has
now this image and again question is
where is
this can I again have some some
thoughts yeah same size 2.5 by 2.5
kilom any thoughts Australia Australia
okay South Africa nice okay so I assume
you see some it's it's like reddish you
think it's in the desert
okay turns out it's not at all in South
Africa or in Australia but it is a
desert right it's in Arizona now
obviously sa will get that right right
because you know it's big big AI model
it knows everything turns out sa also
gets there completely wrong right it
thinks also that it's is a desert but
just like you it just thinks it's a
different desert and it turns out that a
lot of places in around the world
actually look very similar and if you
just look at satellite imagery alone
there's no like features that actually
make it
distinguishable um now you might think
that this is a failure mode of the model
but it's actually not at all the case
because S Clip predicts a different
location because both locations again
have the same features and what this can
tell us is which areas around the world
are visually similar and this inside we
can then leverage to train models for
one area where we don't have labels on
another area of the the world where we
have labels that is visually very
similar that is the
idea and to kind of H out on that
intuition a little bit here's a
similarity map of sa embeddings with
different anchor locations around the
world right so on the left side we have
a location in the Congo Basin we take
that location and we compare it to every
single other location on the planet and
see how similar is that location and
obviously the most similar locations are
going to be other locations in the Congo
Basin super high similarities score the
rder the more similar but we also see
that very geographically distant
locations like in the Amazon or in
Indonesia also have high similarity
scores even though they're very
geographically
far same with the on the right side a
map of the US East Coast again the most
similar locations are also in the um
Northeastern us but there's also a lot
of similar locations in Europe or in
South uh uh sorry in East Asia like
China Japan kind of built very built-in
areas and again the intuition is we
might want to train a model for the
Congo Basin but we don't have any
training data available there but we
might have training data available in
the Amazon or in Indonesia so if we
train a model on that sort of data it
should transfer quite well to that new
unseen
area and we can test that intuition to
some degree by doing um Geographic
domain adaptation experiments so here we
basically hold out the whole continent
as a test set and only train on all
other continents as training set this is
a few shot setting so we actually give
it very limited number I think it's
about 100 of points in the in the test
continent just because um in this
example we try to predict Eco regions
and Eco regions can be unique to a
continent and slip gets that much better
than some existing location in quarter
models there is some that exist already
for example geoclip is trained on
flicker images so these are social media
images um mosaics is not a location
encoder but like a direct feature
extractor from a satellite image
database and CP is also location and
quarter trained on I naturalist
imagery yeah yeah I even have this in
here um yeah so location quars exist
already but none of them has really been
trained with this idea of kind of broad
Geographic generalization and
generalization across tasks in
mind um another thing um that I
unfortunately um can talk about too much
because we did this internally at
Microsoft but I can give you a little
bit of the intuition it's kind of my
favorite application of s clip is in um
yeah building Mass prediction um so
often models that are trained on Western
data fail when they're deployed in in
other countries around the world in low
income countries especially and building
segmentation is a classic example for
this here we have a satellite image of
buildings in the US where you can see
that buildings are on the left side
where you see buildings are very
rectangular they're arranged in a in a
grid and they're kind of spaced out on
the right side we have the same kind of
resolution satellite image for Somalia
and still kind of a residential area but
you see that buildings are smaller
they're in all sorts of shapes and
they're kind of irregular um arranged
and so a model that would be trained on
us data might do pretty poorly at this
um data in Somalia now the cool thing
with slip is that it has seen both of
these areas right it hasn't learned to
do building segmentation in both of
these areas but it has learned something
about the unique characteristics of both
of these areas and it turns out that if
we do um a model transfer and add S Clip
into the mix that this actually helps
improve these uh these modeling
efforts a similar idea um is something
that some other researchers have done so
this from Nathan Jacobs group at washu
um here people have used um S clip to
condition um image diffusion model for
satellite imagery so diffusion models a
generative model for satellite images
and the authors here condition um
condition the model on a open street map
mask so that kind of produces an image
that has the same kind of buildings and
streets as in the open street map mask
and then they also condition it on set
clip and the the best way you can kind
of see the effect that slip has here is
that um keep in mind slip captures kind
of very high level features of a
location like climate zone um humidity
and so on and if you compare images just
generated at for in for example de Mo
Iowa to bould Colorado you will see that
the um satellite images generated for de
Mo are much Greener and the reason for
that is that de MO is much more humid
right there's much more um um yeah
humidity there's much more vegetation
there and this is exactly one of these
big high level features that slip
captures and so it helps to kind of
ground this model a bit
geographically all right so um this is
kind of where we stand but with STP this
is kind of the experiments we've done
Where Do We Go From Here with this kind
of
research and what I really want to posit
is that geographical encoders are a
whole new class of geospatial foundation
models that have Global coverage and are
designed for general purpose they might
not be the biggest models right the ones
that we've trained so far are actually
quite small but they fulfill this kind
of globality aspect of the foundation of
the foundation model
and I've kind of broadly outlined what I
believe are going to be the the main
thrusts of research in this area in the
next six is
years five is years and um I think the
kind of first uh immediate impact of of
such models um that we're already seeing
today is that they are a great way for
providing cheap and Global location
embeddings in especially in settings
that are quite resource constrained
right not everyone can kind of afford to
train a big computer vision model that
takes in satellite imagery that everyone
might have access to satellite imagery
or be able to store it instead you can
just download our cyop model which is a
few hundred megabytes if you remove uh
the image encod and just take the
location encod it's even smaller and
then you can for any location on the
world you can just query the
corresponding location embedding and
replace your image for some tasks that
might be enough for some tasks it might
not be um and in fact we're seeing
already um uh quite a few kind of new
papers on this I think bunch of the kind
of big tech companies have have caught
up on this I think the latest uh uh
institution to release one is Deep Mind
they have one that is more based on
socio economic data and census data but
also really cool
research in the medium term uh I think
uh sorry also in the short term I think
the next steps for expanding these
models are also very clear so far we
only use sentinel 2 imagery which is
Optical satellite imagery there's many
many more um remotes sensing data
sources we can adapt like radar like
yourve products like vegetation indices
we can also work with data at different
spatial resolutions and of course
integrate the time component right now
sap only takes an latitude longitude we
do sample data from two and a half years
I think so we basically implicitly
average over time or marginalize over
the time component we still represent
all seasonalities but having that time
be like a free floating parameter um
that you can manipulate yourself would
obviously be really
cool now um in the medium term I think
location encoders can be very useful for
augmenting some sort of je spatial
intelligence in llms um I haven't looked
this up super recently but the last time
I did it kind of still held true and
that is that kind of llms are not
excellent at kind of geographic question
answering so here I kind of just dropped
a pin in the Pacific and asked uh this
is gp4 to get me the annual mean
temperature of the closest uh location
that it has access to um and this
location is somewhat close to Hawaii so
I would expect it to give me the annual
mean uh temperature for Hawaii but it
kind of gets that distance calculation
completely wrong and instead drops me
somewhere in the Philippines um and so
hopefully these kind of models uh
location embeddings might again be able
to condition bigger Foundation models
geographically and help with answering
questions like
this I think generally this kind of
alignment of embeddings from different
modalities is super interesting here um
because it can really help with this
translation between um modalities so
from image uh to location to text to
video and um I think we already see kind
of first schol examples of this so this
is from um a a python package um Sigma
Geo that um or Sam Geo that basically
already integrate some sort of um llm
component in in like a GIS tool you can
basically type in a prompt like tree and
the model will kind of translate that
into Vision embedding space and then
segment all of the trees in that image
for
you it's like a more like a gimmick at
this point but I think we're going to
see a lot more of this in the in the in
the future
now um looking kind of further ahead I
think we are eventually arriving at a
very big question and that is can we
learn physical environmental and even
social processes of our planet from data
alone using neural networks and can this
help us identify and track changes in
our planet H might this even help with
scientific discovery and extrapolation
right if we learn like a good Laten
space representation of our planet that
is dynamic from his hisorical data can
we play these effects forward and um
analyze Trends such as climate change
the answer to this um I think is very
unclear um but I think these kind of
intermediate steps on the way are very
useful in and of themselves and um I
yeah I myself am very curious about this
questions um I'm actually more
optimistic than I was maybe a year ago
we're seeing great progress not
necessarily in remote sensing but in
other kind of adjacent areas of Earth
Systems modeling especially in climate
and weather modeling I think we're
seeing nor networks actually being
really really good that makes me also
more optimistic for this line of work
and um yeah maybe to to end the talk uh
I'd like to direct you to um our um icml
position paper on this whole topic where
um especially as Ro who the first author
on this paper and and us we argue that
we believe that it's kind of time for
for people to treat Earth observation
and remote sensing data as it's a
distinct kind of application area with
within machine learning rather than
having it like you know at a workshop
here and there but I think really it is
unique enough and is potentially
impactful enough to have its own kind of
yeah sub area just like we treat
biomedical um imagery or so and yeah
with that these are the two papers I
talked about today um thank you to my
amazing co-authors whove worked with me
on this and thanks everyone for coming
and for interest in this topic and I'm
excited to hear questions
[Applause]