well thank you so much for that kind
introduction and uh it's a great
pleasure to speak at this conference on
a topic that's of critical importance to
not only every stakeholder here uh but
broadly defined uh the challenges around
sustainability for the globe uh so what
I'm going to tell you about is a science
story but very critically has really
really deep and important implications
for thinking about decarbonizing
chemical
manufacturing um and what I'm I'm hoping
to really convey to you is just enough
science so you can ask the right
questions when you're thinking about
implementing any of the frontier
decarbonization Solutions in your
industry in your company whatever it may
be that you're thinking about so without
further Ado I want to get started I want
to thank the people that did this work
this was really led by a really
phenomenal um graduate student in my
group who's now a postto at Lawrence
Livermore National
Laboratory so I want to start out by
just emphasizing that the chemical
industry and chemical manufacturing
specifically contribute significantly um
to CO2 emissions so on this axis here we
have CO2 emissions here in in million
tons equivalent per year um and you can
see many of the compounds sort of the
top chemicals produced globally
contribute substantially to overall
emissions burden things like your btxs
propylene ethylene is one of the highest
ones that goes into all the Plastics we
produce methanol is a sort of Gateway
intermediate to a whole host of
Downstream products everything from
pharmaceutical manufacturing to to
chemicals to materials um you will
notice one very interesting thing
ammonia has to have its own axis um uh
separated from all the carbon containing
materials here uh and that's really
because ammonia feeds uh the world right
so so we produce ammonia at a scale even
larger than all of these but if you sum
all of these up you get to really
substantial fractions of the carbon
budget um and these only increase more
so when you think about some of these
intermediates being used as alternative
fuels in a future um decarbon Energy
System right this is only the uses right
now for chemical manufacturing itself in
many respects the demands for these may
go up in safs or in other areas where
you may want to use these chemicals so
given that there's this huge amount
largely of
carbon-based chemicals um that
contribute substantially to the carbon
footprint there's been a lot of academic
activity asking if there are ways to
Source these materials not from fossil
fuels in energy intensive and carbon
intensive process CES but rather to
actually use waste CO2 as an input to
the production of these materials um via
by and large electrochemical and in some
cases thermochemical processes as well
so this was really stimulated a lot by
the discoveries in the 70s and 80s that
showed that at even room temperature
electrolysis of el simple um uh
electrode materials like copper silver
and gold would serve to generate a wide
array of some of these particular matly
important products things like carbon
monoxide a key chemical intermediate to
a whole bunch of products um some of the
undesirable ones as well like methane
key intermediates going be talked about
in the next uh talk formate for example
ethylene ethanol propenol for example
that can be converted to things like
propylene ethylene and so forth right so
so there's been an enormous amount of
excitement in the prospect that room
temperature electrosynthesis May Avail
access to these products directly from
CO2 in a single step uh and in the
ensuing years there's been literally
thousands and thousands of papers I
think we're up to the point where
there's probably a thousand papers every
year on this subject and so I want to
help you cut through all that clutter
and make sure you know the right
questions to ask when you're thinking
about any of these Technologies right um
so one of the problems one of the key
problems is that the production of these
various products is not selective right
so the lack of selectivity means that in
order to actually make any of these
products at scale and to do so in an
economically V able fashion means that
the selectivity to these products needs
to be substantially improved and in
particular one needs to eliminate the
undesirable products usually C1 products
like methane that are of low value right
and that's still a very much a frontier
challenge we're making progress in that
area and I'll talk about that the the
the next topic you also make parasitic
hydrogen which can be valorized but in
certain cases is not the the principal
goal of this reaction the second point I
want to make here is that even for some
catalysts that are seleced it say
generating carbon monoxide there's a
really big elephant in the room problem
which is that to achieve the selectivity
you need to operate in an electrolyte
environment that is alkaline now if any
of you have had freshman chemistry
you'll know there's a fundamental
problem with that CO2 is an acid it
reacts irreversibly with alkaline
electrolytes and this is what has been
appreciated in the last couple years is
what's known as the carbonate problem
though in the popular literature and in
a venture capital community that has
invested l Lally billions of dollars in
this effort it is completely not talked
about so let me explain what that is and
explain why that's critical to being
able to address that if you want to do
anything in CO2 reduction but the Crux
of the problem is that the conditions
necessary to allow for high efficiency
of producing one product from a
selectivity standpoint are the very same
things lead to inefficiency from a
carbon standpoint and from an energetic
standpoint I'll explain that tradeoff in
a moment okay so first part first we're
going to try to ask how can we control
this selectivity challenge in such a way
that we can eliminate methane production
and instead selectively form products
that we'd like to valorize and the next
part of the talk is really assessing how
can we unlock a way to do selective CO2
conversion without carbonating our
electrolyte okay so this is all kind of
recent work from our group and I'll try
to in a whirlwind fashion walk you
through what we've learned here so the
key things you want to try to maximize
for the production of the zyro products
things like ethylene multicarbon
products but not the single carbon
products like methane
right and and in doing so what you
really want to track is the relative
rate of these and what's been learned is
you can control this a lot by how you
tune the pH environment of the medium
particularly because some reactions are
pH sensitive while other ones aren't um
and that's really understood through a
lot of mechanistic thinking that our
group developed in terms of the
individual steps that lead to carbon C
coupling and ultimately the high value
C2 products but despite this The General
mechanistic ke for how CC bonds are
formed on the surface has remained
largely unchallenged and unchanged for
the better part of 40 years and so we
wanted to ask a very very fundamental
question could we design an electrolyte
that would fundamentally alter the
mechanistic manifold to allow us to
unlock a selectivity uh opportunity that
isn't available in traditional
systems so what we figured out was that
the key to this selectivity being
challenging is because most most
electrolysis is conduct in aquous
electrolytes and the problem with aquous
electrolytes is that water as a proton
donor though it is efficient is
extraordinarily promiscuous in a sense
it can deliver protons to many
intermediates along the reaction pathway
leading inherently to in un selectivity
in the overall
processes so what we figured out is if
we could instead exchange a water-based
electrolyte with something that was aoic
we could instead introduce a selective
proton donor that we could tune in its
structure and its PKA and other
properties to be able to engender the
desired selectivity that's exactly what
we decided to do I'll just quickly show
the data that we found here that in the
right type of medium a DMSO medium with
a phenol-based proton donor we can
completely eliminate the production of
methane altogether we don't detect any
from this type of medium and all of the
carbon dioxide and carbon monoxide that
we reduce is going simply to C2 products
that are valuable things like ethylene
glycol that can directly feed into the
market um athane ethylene that can then
be subsequently valorized these are
still baby steps towards an overall
system but what I'm trying to emphasize
to you is that we need to completely
reimagine how we're doing CO2 reduction
to be able to make viable uh access to
the types of systems that we would want
to use for decarbonizing chemical
manufacturing okay I'm going to skip
this real quickly this just shows the
kinetic details that we've uncovered
from this system and showing that the
Crux of it relates to changing the rate
liit step to a much later portion of the
reaction sequence that allows us to get
much higher selectivity for the desired
C2 reaction
products okay so by this sort of change
in mechanistic thinking we're on the
pathway towards the rational design of
the electrolyte environment in a way
that allows us to get high selectivity
without the other trade-offs I mentioned
early
on okay so let me switch gears now for
the remaining part of my talk and just
talk about this really key problem that
unfortunately no one outside side of a
small subset of the academic Community
is talking about including hundreds of
millions of dollars spent by Doe to to
support some of these efforts so um uh
what is the carbonate problem it's
really comes down to pretty much
freshman chemistry which is the
realization that CO2 reduction catalysis
is most selective when your electrolyte
is alkaline essentially it's basic but
CO2 is an acid gas and and because CO2
is an acid gas you basically have these
very simple sort of freshman chemistry
type of reaction so CO2 reacts with The
Alkali in the electrolyte to make
bicarbonates that can react further with
Alkali to make carbonates and because
these reactions are irreversible in an
alkaline environment you will
irreversibly change the composition of
your electrolyte over time the biggest
advances in engendering very high
selectivity for the desirable C2
products have all come from conditions
where you're not running your reaction
at steady state you're essentially
irreversibly over time consuming the
reactor constituents that you need to do
the reaction that's fine for publishing
a paper it's impossible at an industrial
scale so what I just want to emphasize
is that if you start with an alkaline
media the base you generate in that
Medium will carbonate that will go into
the bulk of the electrolyte you will
lose that electrolyte constituent you
will alter the pH environment in the
medium and that will ultimately lead to
the carbonation and a reduction in the
CO2 utilization efficiency the problem
is is so pernicious in fact that if you
look at the math to being able to
actually reconvert those carbonates back
into CO2 and the alkal the energy cost
of that is larger than the energy you're
storing in the products you're making so
99% of all the papers you see in the
literature actually what should be
called fuel wasting devices rather than
fuel or chemical producing
devices right um and again I I can't
stress enough that this needs to be
really appreciated in deeper level in
the in the community outside of again a
small set set of the academic so how do
we decided to address this well we
realized is that the bad actor is the
water itself right water reacts with CO2
to make bicarbonate so if we could find
a media where the water activity is
lowered sufficiently we ought to be able
to orthogonalize the reduction of CO2
from its undesirable carbonation via an
irreversible reaction and so that's what
we basically did we found that if you
could if you can mitigate the water
activity by again choosing non- aquous
solvent and then designing a proton
donor that was itself non-nucleophilic
with respect to reaction with CO2 you
could actually carry out this reaction
in a way that could engender High
selectivity while also enabling and
cailing the actual conversion of CO2 to
an undesirable byproduct and this
actually works quite well so we can get
very very high selectivities in this
case for CO2 reduction to carbon
monoxide rivaling the best values that
are observed in aquous media in this
DMSO acetic acid electrolyte media and
we've now studied many other
electrolytes for this process um the key
point I want to stress here is that we
can show quantitatively by NMR analysis
and other methods that any amount of CO2
that's taken up in the medium unlike in
water is IR is reversible it can
actually be exchanged in and out so the
reaction can run at steady state without
irreversible carbonation and what we can
also show is that after the reaction is
done you don't generate a substantial
quantity of any of the deleterious
carbonates that would other wise form in
an aquous alkaline
electrolyte okay so what I really want
to emphasize here is that the Crux this
problem is how you control the
electrolyte environment to be able to
steer selectivity versus CO2 reduction
without having compromising carbonation
reactions form in the medium we've
started to understand the principles for
threading this needle and we're just on
the verge of Designing more advanced
electrolytes to be able to develop
systems that might actually be viable um
for for industrial decarbonization uh of
these chemical
processes okay I just want to summarize
by saying that you know there's a large
opportunity in thinking about
reimagining what's been done in the last
40 years to try to do CO2 reduction and
what's happened historically is people
have identified certain conditions and
tried to engineer the heck out of it and
and what we've sort of realized that you
have to take a step back and re redesign
from the start if there's some
fundamental impediment that's preventing
the viability of that system and I've
given you two kind of examples of that
in this case um and I just want to leave
you with just saying that there's a lot
of opportunity in the decarbonization of
chemical manufacturing but it really
does require a deep understanding of the
mechanisms underpaying those processes
and how to control those precisely to be
able to engineer a system that's viable
for the overall reactions you'd want to
do so with that I'll stop and be more
than happy to take
questions so we don't have questions
online so
if you have questions the audience here
or those
remotely please feel free to
ask
okay thank you worldwind indeed but
fascinating I'm interested to hear your
opinion on what is the biggest barrier
then for industrial scaleup given that
you now have uh a viable chemical
approach yeah so we have a viable
chemical approach for doing the cathodic
reaction with selectivity without these
competing side reactions we're working
right now on creating a corresponding
anode reaction that would also be able
to efficiently operate in the overall
system we think that's very tractable we
made a lot of progress already towards
that um but one thing that should be
noted about really any electrochemical
technology is that they are in a sense
very bespoke maybe I can say a little
bit more about that you know if I have a
catalyst uh in a traditional thermal
thermal process right and I make it into
a palladized bed I can put that into a
standard off-the-shelf type of reactor
and there are many that are made many
manufacturers that make them and I can
use that as a sort of way to rapidly
scale that process um but when you think
about electrochemical Technologies the
nature of the electrolyte the nature of
the Catalyst all of them have to play
well with each other and so as a result
of that in many respects each
electrochemical technology is its own
bespoke scaling challenge um and that is
one of the things which is a whole topic
unto itself that that that places
challenges they're surmountable but that
places challenges towards Rapid scaling
of a lot of electrochemical
Technologies you had a on the on the
chart you had ammonia at uh at its own
Planet uh can you talk a little bit more
about it yeah well so um I think that
there there's a whole other side of my
research group that focuses on on how to
think about decarbonizing uh ammonia
production you know ammonia right now
contributes about 1% greenhouse gas
emissions that's only for the ammonia we
currently produce for fertilizer
production there's a view in the future
that ammonia will need to be generated
as a hydrogen Vector which means then
the needs for that are going to only
grow right um there are some particular
challenges with that because the current
process for making ammonia is performed
at very very large scale but it's
actually really efficient from an energy
standpoint uh the only problem is it's
very hard to downscale that technology
and it's particularly hard because that
large scale means that you often have to
pay billions of dollars to build a plan
and only actually get return on
investment over a very very long time
right so so what we're trying to focus
on in our group is figuring out ways to
take traditional habbos synthesis of
ammonia and do it in a small enough
scale that it can work with renewable
green hydrogen for example can be done
in a more portable fashion where they're
stranded renewable electricity those are
all the catalysis and science challenges
that revolve around that very very big
elephant in in the room I would say um
but they're very much needed if we're
going to use ammonia's erector and if
we're going to um uh see that as a
component to a future hydrogen economy
Yogi uh final question
here yep yeah similar to your that first
question your your Fe and selectivity
are impressive how about like your
current density how how high can you get
it up to so we're in the early stages of
the electrolyte design here but we have
had systems where we can in initial
efforts into the hundreds of milliamp
current density um but that's not yet
ready for industrial scale deployment um
and so there's still much work to be
done in those those respects right so I
I think we'd be the first to say that
we're still at the baby steps of this
process remember our competition has had
40 years on us but we'll get there in a
year or
two okay everybody let's uh thank
Professor seren jth thanks Yogi