Okay. So last time we were looking at a
metric space. So this is a metric space.
um and we looked at um what we called uh
open subsets. So open subsets
and so an open subset is so over here is
now a subset of x is set to be open.
If for all
x in O there exist
[Applause]
are greater than zero. So that the
entire ball around x is contained in in
O. Right? And so the picture is that
here you have uh x here you have some
open subset O. And so if for each point
X in O there is an entire ball here
that is contained in O then O is set to
be open. Right?
What the one of the a few things that we
proved is so one thing we proved
is that uh that that's uh so again XD is
a metric space
then we defined sorry I should say we
defined the ball
uh B X
B R of X. So here x is
in x
r is some positive number and then this
thing here is then the y
in x such that uh the distance from x to
y is strictly less than r.
And we showed that uh uh P R
of X is open.
Right? That P R we say also that P R X
is a ball
of radius
R centered at X.
Okay. Now there's a few other things
that we
discussed.
[Applause]
So one thing is that so uh on sets
on subsets
we have three operations.
uh one is intersection.
So this is that if you have if u alpha
um is a family
of subsets.
Then we look at the intersection of all
these subsets.
And so X is in this intersection
just means that that X is in U alpha for
all alpha.
The second operation we looked at was
union.
And so again u alpha is a family of
subsets. Then we say that x here is in
the union of the u alpha.
This is the same as saying that there
exist
alpha such that
x is in u alpha.
And the third thing we the third
operation we have is that if you have a
subset
capital u
then uh we have the complement. So the
complement
of u
uh is the x
such that
x is not in in you right that's a
compliment and so there was these three
operations
uh on subsets right and why this is
relevant Here
this is relevant because if
uh if u alpha so we have the following
uh lema
again we have a matrix space here and we
have o alpha is a family
of open subset
of X
then then the union
is also open.
Okay. Now why is this the case?
Well, it's it's a the case because if so
if
X here is in the union of the O alpha
then this means that there exist
alpha such that
X here is in O alpha right but since O
that O alpha is open this means that
there exist. So not only is X in that
but there exist
Rh
that depends on X and alpha uh R
positive so that the whole ball here
such that the whole ball centered at X
is contained in U alpha O alpha sorry
right but if it's contained in O alpha
then this imply
[Applause]
If it's contained in O alpha
then we have that then this imply that
it's of course this ball here
is contained in the union
of of these guys.
Right? But that's exactly what it means
that to say that the union is open.
Right?
The other lema,
the other lema uh related to this is
well and there you have to be careful
uh that if you have uh finitely many. So
again you have a metric space
and and O1
up to O N finally many
uh open subsets.
If you have finitely many open subsets
then the intersection of these
is also open.
Okay. Now why is that the case? This is
uh this is the case because if you have
so if x here is in the intersection of
these guys
then it means that this is equivalent to
saying that x here is in o i for all i
right i = 1 up to n
But then for each but this means
but since
oi is open then for
for oi there exist a r i. So this means
that since
OI is open,
there exist a R I. So that such that
the ball here
with radius X but sorry with radius R
but center X. This one here is contained
in OI. Right?
This is for each eye. Right? But now if
we take there's only finally many I. So
you can let R
be the minimum of these guys.
Right? If R is the minimum of these guys
then the ball of radius R around X.
These are the points where the distance
is strictly less than R to X. Right? But
that is of course contained in BR I of
X. This is for each I you have this. But
this one here was supposed to be
contained in OI, right? And so you see
that this ball here,
okay, this ball here is contained in
this for each
for each eye. So this means that this
ball must be contained
in the intersection of these guys.
And I'll just write it out again just
emphasizing that I'm only doing this for
finitely many oaks. Okay. So by and
that's exactly what it means that the
intersection is open. And again you know
you could draw a little picture here. It
might be helpful to draw a little
picture. You have you know this here is
01.
Here you have O2
and here you have 03.
You have a point in the intersection.
There's a ball here that is contained in
this. There's a ball, another ball here.
So that's contained in this. And there's
a third ball, this ball here. So that's
contained in that. Right? And then you
kind of look at the smallest ball, you
know, you look at the smallest radi
uh and and that ball is then contained
in in in the intersection of the tree.
And the intersection of the tree is
this. Yeah.
Okay. Now, why why do we have to be
careful? Let me just remind you. Why do
we have to be careful here?
And so the examples example that we
looked at last time was that if you take
if you are on
so the example from last time is that if
x here
is a real number
and you're looking at O N here is a
natural number
and you're looking at
that this is this interval here from min
-1 / n to n.
Well, then if you're looking at the
intersection of all of these,
right, the intersection well that's just
that's just a one point
zero, right? And of course zero is not
an open subset, right? Because if it was
an open subset, a whole ball and a ball
here on the line is like a little open
little interval that doesn't have the
two end points, right?
So this here is so note
that uh in this example each OI or each
O is open
but the intersection of the OS
uh is not open
and the problem again is that there are
infinitely many Os right
okay now again one of the things we
proved was and
maybe I was just here uh on that board
uh uh one of the things we proved last
time was that
if you take a ball
then it is actually an open
Let me
let me prove
a
variation of that.
So suppose you're looking at so let's
have a lema here
that if you have again a metric space
here and r here is bigger than zero. Now
let's look at the X and then take away.
But now I'm looking at the set. So let
me look at the set Y here. So X
X X is some fixed point in this metric
space and you're looking at the Y in X.
So that the distance
to X
from Y is strictly bigger than R. Okay.
So in other words, if this here is X,
this is the space X. Here you have the
point X. Then you have here this here
including this the circle here are the
points that have distance at most r from
little x. Then this is this set here
outside
this this disc where the boundary is
included.
So outside.
Okay. And so what I want to prove here
is that this here is this here is an
open substring.
And the proof is very similar to how we
proved that a ball is open. Again the
key ingredient
is the triangle inequality.
And so
right so let's try to prove that. So,
so we take um we take Y here
in this let's call this set something
let's call it E.
So suppose you have X here Y here in E.
So this means that the distance from Y
to X
is strictly bigger than R. I want to
prove right. So I have here I have my
picture here.
This is X. This is this ball here and
then I have a Y that lie outside it. And
I want to find a little ball here around
Y that is entirely contained in the
complement of this ball.
And so I do the same that I did last
time. I we set I mean you know almost
the same not exactly the same but so we
set s here equal to right. So the idea
is that you're looking at this distance
here. This distance is dx
y. This part of it is r, right? And so
you it seems reasonable.
this here, if this picture was right,
then this thing here would be
uh s and this s here would be dx
y - r.
So that's what I'm setting uh s equal
to.
And the first thing I notice that
because this is strictly bigger than r,
this thing here is strictly positive.
And then I take set here in that ball.
Now it's centered at Y. It's have radius
S.
And then I want to look at the distance
to and I want to estimate. So one to
estimate
to estimate from below
uh the distance from X to set right well
the triangle inequality if you just
think about the triangle that's
something like bounding a distance from
above right so if I want to estimate
something below Oh, then basically the
this thing I want to estimate from below
have to be on the other side of the
inequality, right? And so
so how does that work?
So I have
so let's again
draw a little picture to so I have let
me do it little bit on the side. So I
have this ball here
and I have this Y here and then I have
the C here
and I now want to say I want to estimate
so I'm saying that the distance from
uh so so
this is what I want to bound from below
And what I know is that this set here
is I know something about the distance
to y, right?
So this here I know, right? And so you
see this thing here by the triangle
inequality is now bounded by by the
distance
from x to y,
right?
And I know that this thing here is less
or equal to this here is the one I want
to estimate. So I'm just leaving that.
This one here, it's because set is in
the ball of radius s around y. So this
thing here is actually
strictly less than
s like that. Right?
And so now you can just move this one
here over on the other side and you have
that dx
y - s is strictly less than d
uh x comma z.
Now we have to fill in what s is s is up
there. So this thing here is this this
this this thing here is equal to this is
dx. I'm just copying that. But I fill in
what s is and s is d xy
minus r.
But you see those two cancel and you're
left with a r. And so you have that r is
strictly less than this which is exactly
what we wanted to prove.
And so again, you know, the the you
know, it was it was almost exactly the
same proof that we had to prove that the
ball was open. Um we're just using here,
you know, the thing is what we're using
here is that again we're using that the
triangle inequality is like you're
bounding some distance from above and so
you kind of have to use it the other
way, right? with having the sinks that
you want to bound from below on the
other side of the inner corner.
Okay. So the next thing is then and we
talked a little bit about that uh last
time. The next thing is closed subsets.
So this may seem like a triviality
because it's defined
sort of in a way trivially. So what is a
clo but it's actually a really useful
notion
and yeah
uh and so this is
so a subset
C
is set to be closed again X is a metric
space
to be closed
if the complime element
is open.
So that's how you define a closed
subset.
And so again as we observed right since
since the empty set and
x are both
uh open.
The complement of the empty set is the
whole set. So it means that X and the
complement of the whole set is the empty
set. It means that those sets are both
open are also both closed.
Okay.
Now um
right so now there is a
another way you could have defined a
close subset another way and this is
because you have the following statement
here.
So a subset
You have a following theorem
that
again you have a metric space
and C here subset of X is closed
if and only if
if and only if for all sequences
in CN in C. Sorry. If if and only if for
all
sequences
XN where
where
XN is in C. If you have
all sequences
all let's say convergent sequences
so all convergence sequence where the
sequence lie in a in in in
C then the limit
X is also
in C.
Okay. So we want so I claim that if you
want to check that a set is closed
instead of checking that a complement is
open you could check that and and this
seems like if you were literally going
to check it right on any given example
explicit example you would never do it
this way but it's very useful for
proving things okay and so the thing is
that instead of proving that a
complement is open. Instead, you could
just prove that whenever you have a
sequence in that set, then then is the
limit also in that set? If that's the
case for all sequences, then the set is
closed, right? And so, so we need to so
let's try to prove that. And again, it's
useful. It's sort of useful, you know,
theoretically, but in practice, this
would be totally
useless.
But it is useful to proving things.
And so now why? So we need to there's
two things we need to prove.
And so there's two directions. So assume
first
that
um that C is closed
and and let
and let
Xn
in C
be a convergence. in sequence.
We want to show want to show
that
the limit
x is also
in C.
Okay.
Now if
um right if since
um xn converts to x
um then
for all
r greater than zero
there exist
uh x n in the ball here
of radius
uh r around x right because it's
converging right so this means that that
for each uh r you must have this
but now you see that um If
if X here if X was not in C, right? If X
is not in C, since
C is closed,
the complement
is open.
And so this means that now X here is is
assumed to be in a compliment. But it
means that there exists some R. So that
the ball here of radius of that R
would be contained in the complement,
right?
But the complement but this means that
there is no XN in that ball, right?
Because all of the XN's are in C, right?
And this here is entirely contained in
the complement. Right?
So you see that. So this is the
contradiction right. So if we if it is
closed and you have a convergence
sequence that sequence is lying in this
closed set then the limit must be um
must be also contained in the set right
because otherwise there would be like
the limit would lie outside and there
would be a little ball centered at that.
So there was no element in the sequence
that was in that ball but then that
sequence couldn't converge to the center
right
and the other thing so this is one
direction the other direction that we
need to prove is that
um
is that if and this is again you know
it's useless
you would never go about to prove that a
set is closed in an example But it is
useful sort of more theoretically.
So suppose you have a set and you knew
that whenever you have a sequence in
that set then the limit that is
convergent then the limit is also in the
set. So, so the next thing, so we also
need
also need
to show the Converse and again the
Converse.
So we need to show
that if that if uh
that if for all sequences
xn
which line see n is convergent
Then
the limit
x is also
in C.
Then
C is in fact
closed,
right? So that would be the converse,
right? So we prove if and only if it has
this property.
Okay? So now let's assume that so so so
suppose we have this property that all
convergent sequences
that uh the limit convergence sequence
in the set
then the limit was also in the set. Now
let's prove that the set is closed. So
to prove the set is closed, we need to
show that the complement is open. Right?
So we need to show
that the complement here
is open.
So take
X here in the complement
if if
for all
are greater than zero.
Right? So we need to prove we need to
prove that. Sorry. So let me say it like
this. So we take some x and we need to
show
that there exist some are bigger than
strictly bigger than zero. So that this
ball here
is contained in the complement.
Right? That's what we need to prove. We
need to prove this for each x in the
complement. Now suppose that this was if
this was not the case.
Then I can look at for each n then for
each
each natural number here. You can look
at the ball. It's always going to be
centered at this x.
But I'm looking at it with a radi that
is smaller and smaller. Right? If for
each n natural number
if that ball was not contained in a
complement so this means that for each n
you could pick so pick
xn in that set so just you just choose
right because we are assuming that the
complement is not closed is not open so
it means that there would be exist a x
so that No ball here
would be entirely in the complement. So
this means that you would that this one
here would not be entirely contained in
complement. So this means that there
would be some XN and this XN here would
actually be in the set C.
Right?
But now of course the distance here
from xn to x this distance here is
strictly less than 1 / n. So this means
that so this imply that the xn converts
to x right and now the assumption was
that whenever you have a sequence that
was converging these guys lie in c then
the limit here also lie in c. So then
you have from the assumption that X here
is in C. But this is the contradiction.
You were assuming that X was not in C.
Right?
Okay.
And again this here is is really really
useful but it's only useful kind of as a
tool to proving things. It's not useful
for checking whether an example is open
or closed.
Um like let me just quickly give you a
couple of examples. Uh probably should
have done that already.
Uh
that if you're looking at
you know so what are closed subsets
right? So closed subset could be you
know so here are some examples closed
subsets.
So if you are if it's an R a closed
subset is like some interval from let's
say from 0 to one where both these
points both zero and one is included.
This here is closed
and why is it closed? because the
complement here is open. It's easy to
see that the complement is open. Um
uh something like if you include one of
the endpoint but not the other, this is
neither closed nor open,
right? And and also if you're looking at
like the complement say from zero the
complement of so if you're looking sorry
if you're looking at this thing here uh
union with say from two to three this is
also is also closed.
Okay. Now uh and and a and uh maybe one
more example is if you just take a
single point this is closed
right and again you just check that the
complement is open.
Uh now so now uh
the next thing we talked I think we
talked very briefly about that last time
also because we talked a little bit
about closed subset but but so if you
take so you have the following theorem.
So if you have a metric space here
and you have a family C alpha of closed
subset
then the intersection of these closed
this here is also closed.
And if you you have just finally many
closed subset
then the union of finitely many closed
subset
is also closed.
Right? And so here it's exactly the
opposite thing as for open sets that you
can take any intersection
and is still closed. But if you take
union you can only do it for finite
many. So this exactly the opposite. Why
is it exactly the opposite? It's because
that in order to prove that something is
closed it means that the complement is
open.
So and then we have these basic
relations for right. So the proof of
this again.
So the proof of this
and so these were these operations on
set that we went through
that if you take X here and you take the
complement
of intersections of subsets right this
thing here is the same as the union
of the complements
like that Right? And you see that since
this is closed, this means that the
complement is open and you can take any
union of open sets and is still open. So
that's why you could take any
intersection, right? And so the other
thing is that if you're looking at the
you to prove that this thing here is
closed, then you're looking at the
complement of this union here.
But this thing here is now the
intersection the complement of the
intersection
of uh the C1
uh up to
um sorry this is the complement of the
this is the this is the
Um,
intersection of these guys
like this,
right? And you see here since C one up
to CN since they're closed, these guys
here are open. And so you're looking at
finite intersections of open sets and
that's open. Right? So again for closed
sets it's like the in terms of taking
intersection and union it's exactly the
opposite.
Okay. Um now the next thing I want to
talk about is a cover.
Um
so uh so so you have a metric space. So
the separation is
so we have a matrix space here
and we have a subset a here is a subset
of x
and then we have a collection and then u
alpha
is a family of subset
of subsets.
of of x. And we say that
that uh that uh u alpha is a cover
of a
if
um if a here is contained in the union
of the u alphas.
Sorry. This is what it means to cover.
That's it by a family name.
Um,
a subco
is
right. So if you take imagine that you
have the like a whole bunch of sets and
together they cover a a subco means that
you don't need to take all of the u
alphas if you can just take some of them
and they will still cover it. So is so a
cover is a
a subf family
of the given
family
you alpha
such that the union of those
of those
still cover.
Okay.
So let's look at a couple of examples.
I mean, you know, for if you take a
family that cover something, then the
family itself is a subco, but that's a
kind of trivial subco,
right? And so,
um, you could look at so just here as an
example.
Suppose that the metric space is is x
with the usual as sorry with the usual
metric.
And suppose now that the u alpha is
actually u ns and those are interval
from minus n.
Uh let me just make them open. It
doesn't matter you know for a copper
there's no assertion whether they're
open or closed or on either. So if
you're looking at those sets well if you
take the union of all of those sets
that gives you everything. So this
family is a cover of of the real line
right? Of course, if you take a proper
sub cover, right? Meaning, right? I
mean, you well, you could take a So,
this here cover all of it. But you see
that this particular cover have the
property that you n + one, right? This
is contains the previous one,
right? So, you don't really need all of
them to cover R. You could start
if you wanted to. You could start with
at some very large N and then you could
go on from there, right? But you can't
have there wouldn't be finite many of
the UN that would cover, right? You
would you need infinite many to cover,
right? Because otherwise, you know,
there would be some sort of last point
in both both in.
Okay. So that's a cover and a subco
and um an open cover
open
is then
where each
uh u alpha
is an open subset.
It's not usually I mean you it's really
this diff that's Yeah.
Um
it
uh so that's a open cover. So each of
the sets that is in the covering has to
be open.
And and the last definition we need is a
finite subco
is a cover
is a subco
consisting
of finer many sets.
F.
Okay. So that's a finite circle.
And so now this leads to uh the and
again you know in this example here u an
R where this here is a cover there is no
finite. So, so it's a note
that this
this particular
this this copper
does not
have a finer subco,
Right? If you just take finitely many of
these, they are not going to cover all
of R. Right? But actually in this
example, you see also that the cover is
an open cover. Right?
Okay. So this now leads to uh the
definition of compactness.
So
you have a metric space
So x comma d is a metric space.
A here is a subset and we say
that a is compact.
If
for all
copper
for every sorry let me see if for every
of for every open cover.
So if for for every open cover
of a
there is
there is a finite sub cover.
Okay, that's that's uh
right
now uh and the thing that is really
useful
is uh and we won't prove this
today but I'll prove it next time.
So this is the following
result.
So so why why is this notion useful?
Right? So one of the key one of the key
property when you're thinking about
sequences one of the key property
uh was for sequences on the line was the
the cushy convergence theorem and the
cus convergence theorem again said that
whenever you have a cus sequence then it
was automatically convergent and it was
often much easier to check that a
sequence was a cus sequence than to
actually find the limit and prove that
it's converging. to that
the but to prove the kushi convergent
theorem we needed the balsano via stress
theorem right and uh so so this is
because so why is it useful this notion
of compactness so it's useful because
the there's a metric version
uh version
of the bzano vas I assume
uh for matrix bases
and so this is the following theorem
um and again I won't prove it now but
I'll prove it next time that if you take
a matrix case and a here is uh a is a
subset
and uh a is compact.
Then any
any sequence
in A
has a convergent
subsequence
that's that's right. So remember that
the bulano vis again said that if you
take a bounded
uh bounded sequence uh in in I then
there is a subsequence that converge.
Okay. Um so now um uh let's prove a few
things about
um um
uh right let me also look at a couple of
more examples.
So, so the first thing I want to just
discuss is that so this is like the key
this is our key application of
compactness
that you have this metric version of the
balsano vio
and so
um
and now um but let's prove a couple
things about
compact subsets.
So, so we have a metric space here
and I have a here is
a is is
compact.
Then I want to show that this implies
this implies two things. One is that a
is bounded.
And the second one is that a is closed.
Okay.
Let's prove first that a is bounded.
Well,
you could Yeah. No. Uh, you could look
at
So, you could look at a very trivial
cover of A. So,
so you have here A.
Well, obviously
if you take all balls,
let's say with radius one and you take
all balls, but now the center here
is could be anything in A, right? For
each element in A, you take a ball of
radius one around that point.
But that's first of all these balls are
all open and of course this thing here
the union of these guys well the union
contained in particular all the centers
but the centers is already a so you
trivially have this right
now since a is compact
this means that a must be That's these
are this is an open cover. So it means
that's finitely many of them already
cover
a. So you have finally many
like this. Okay.
But now I claim that this automatically
implies that A is bounded because you
see
you have all these balls here
and A is somehow contained in the union
of these guys, right? So this means that
for any element. So this means that for
any x. So
if x here is in
um is in a then there exist
one of these finitely many i where i is
one of these finitely many. So that the
distance
to this x i
is smaller than one. Right?
We would like to say that a is contained
in a large ball. Right? So now
and that right. So, and now
now you just take the, you know, you
pick one of these X eyes. Let's pick the
first one.
And let's look at the um let's look at
the maximum
of these uh
the from the first one to the other one
and let's add one to that
right that you take maximum over finite
many numbers. So this is a nice finite
not many numbers and this here is you
call this here R.
Now you look at the ball of radius R
around X1
and I want to show that any X. So want
to show that. So want to show
that for any
x in a
then we have that x is in this bowl
like that.
Okay.
So um right so now we know that so since
since x here is we know that x is
contained in the union of these ball. So
we know that x is contained in this ball
here for some i.
where where it's one of these little n
many mini eyes,
right? So this means now that the
distance and so you know that the
distance to this
little i is at most one, right? And so
now if you're looking at the distance
from x to the first one then this here
is less than the distance from
uh this to x i plus the distance this is
the triangle inequality again x i maybe
let me just make very clear that this is
the first one to the first one right
this is the triangle inequality
right But these distances here
are right this here plus
this
uh is um
right so this here is so sorry this
thing here is bounded by one right it's
actually strictly less than one
so this here is less than one plus
this thing here
and you see this thing here is of course
this is how we define R. This is
strictly uh this is actually uh less or
equal to r and so you have that this
thing here is strictly less than r and
that's what we wanted to prove.
Okay so this prove that if you take a
again a metric space and you have a
compact subset then it's automatically
bounded.
What about the second one? Suppose you
take a a subset is it closed?
Now let's use the theorem that we just
proved.
So we need to prove
Okay. So let's prove that that this A
here is closed.
Okay. So now if A is closed. So to prove
that A is closed
by the theorem we've just we proved just
a little while ago.
Theorem we proved earlier.
We showed earlier.
uh we need to show
that if xn is a sequence
sequence in a and xn is converging to
some x we need to show need to show
that x is also in a
Fine.
Suppose not.
Suppose not. We want to show that this
leads to a contradiction.
We want to get a contradiction.
So you have you have this x here and
you're assuming that x is not in a
but you yet you have a sequence in in a
that somehow
tend to tend to this
um this is the sequence xn and it's
tending to this element
Well,
we saw earlier that we've defined
something called
we def e
here which is the x the y
in x. So that the distance
from X to Y is strictly bigger than R.
Then we saw that this here is an open
set. Right? We show that this here is
open.
This is for each R.
So I'm going to now find a cover
of of A. I'm going to find an open
cover. And the open comma is that for
each integer,
for each n here,
I'm going to look at e
1 / n. So this means that I'm looking at
the set at the y.
So that the distance from y to this this
x here that I want to show is in a that
these things here is bigger.
than 1 / n. Okay.
But now I claim that a here
is contained
in the union
of these guys,
right?
Because you see these guys actually
these these guys here if you have
something
that is not in any of these right
this means that the that this inequality
fails
with each n but this means that so if x
here if sorry it's set is is not is in
the complement of the union of these
Nice.
Then actually then you have that this
thing here
is less or equal to 1 / n for all n
right you have that that's a complement
right of the union but if it's less than
one n for all n it means that it must be
zero right so it must be so it means
that this distance here so you conclude
that this distance
is zero. But this means that this set
here is actually your x, right?
So the complement of these guys,
the complement of this union here is
simply just the point x. But you were
assuming that x was not in your set a,
right? The complement here, the union of
these guys. We have proved now that the
union cover everything
but x. So in particular it cover a
because we're assuming that little x was
not in a right.
Okay.
So so this is a nice open cover of a
but a was supposed to be compact. It
means that finally many of these cover,
right?
But now this family has this property
family has this property
that you see these guys here. If you're
looking at E 1 / N, this thing here is
contained in
E 1 / N + one. Right? If this number
here is smaller, then it means that this
set here is larger. Right?
So you have this. And so you see that if
finitely many if a here was contained in
finitely many of these guys here.
If it was containing a union of finally
many then you just take the one of these
ni that is the largest right. So this
means that a here would be contained in
some
one over of some n some for some i right
because there's one of these numbers
these nis that would be the largest
right but this means that this means now
that a right that there is some lower
bound for the distance
to x in A right it doesn't there's no
elements that is so this means that that
this means that there exist there does
not exist
let me say for all
for all
y in a
then the distance here
from y to x
is strictly bigger than one over this n
I right this is just some fixed number
right this is obviously you know right
but this means that you can't have a
sequence in a that is converging to x
right because they they all stay away
from from x right they stay a certain
positive distance away from from x so
this means And so this is the desired
contradiction. Therefore
there is no sequence
no sequence
except that converts to X and the XN
RNA. But that's what we assumed in the
beginning, right? We assume we just we
wanted to check that whenever you have a
sequence in in a n that is converging
then the limit was also right. So so
that was supposed to have been such a
sequence. So that's a desired
contradiction.
So this prove this proof that if you
take a compact metric space then if you
take a a a metric space and if you take
a compact subset the compact subset
could of course be all of X that's fine.
Um but if you take but I want to allow
more generally that just to say that
just having a subset that is compact
this means that it's bounded and closed.
If you are in Rn
so you have a theorem and we'll talk
about that next time also
that there's a theorem that say the
converse is the case but that is not
actually
that does not generalize to metric
spaces. So it's a theorem here.
Well, I mean it does generalize but not
like this. It's not that this particular
statement is does not hold.
So uh so in
Rn
with the usual metric say the usual
ukidian metric if you will you can just
think about R.
If a here is comp is closed
and bounded
then a is is compact.
Okay.
uh and uh I wanted to talk about an
example but I don't think I I have
enough time to
uh to to actually talk about that. Let's
talk about this. Return to this next
time
uh because we only have four minutes
left. uh
and
and um and so instead let's prove
a theorem here
that if we take the theorem
if you have a metric space
a here is a subset of x is compact
Suppose that C here is a subset of A and
C here is right. So this is of course in
X. So C is also a subset of X and C is
closed.
Then
the claim is that then C is also
compact.
Right? And we have three minutes and we
don't need three minutes because it's
actually very quick. Um and so the thing
is so proof of this so C here is assumed
to be uh closed. So so this means that
since
C is closed
this means that the complement of C
is open.
Right?
So now
uh so now let's
let u that o alpha
be
a copper
of c
then we can so o alpha is a copper of c
and now you can add the complement of c
to it.
So if you're looking at C,
so C here is now of course
uh you C here. So in fact a here
you can think about a as so a is clearly
contained in c
uh union with the complement of c
and so this means that a here
the o alpha cover c. So this is
contained in a union of O alpha union
with this last set right.
These guys are assumed to be open. This
here is open because c is closed. So
this means that you have now a is
contained in this is an open cover of a.
So this means that finitely many of
these right. So this means that A is
contained in like O1 union up to some O
N. And then quite possibly you would
also need this one here.
But now you see but C here is contained
in here. So this means that C is
contained in this. This here was not
part of the cover. But it's not needed
if you just want to cover C because none
of these elements cover anything in C.
Right? So this implies that C actually
must be contained in O1 union up to O N
because this here does not cover
anything in C. So this proved right that
C there was a finite subco that cover C.