Our
next speaker is Vir Shvet who is a
professor at the MIT computer science
and AI lab. He is also a co-founder of a
company called Neurom Neurom Magic which
uh right now I believe is part of Red
Hat and also which is part of IBM. So
let's uh join me in welcoming Shamir.
>> Hi everybody. Um yeah, so uh I'm going
to tell you a little bit about um
inference. AI inference sounds boring
relative to all these fantastic things
that people do with real materials. Um
so um
um you know
AI models especially open AI models have
been just through a fantastic journey in
the last um couple of years and people
use them everywhere and I think this is
just going to keep on going. Now these
models kind of belong to a different
family of um software.
Um there's been like a fundamental
change in how what the software is that
we're building. In the past we used to
build software that I would say was kind
of input driven.
You have a small program with a few
parameters and then you know you run the
program and it is the data right the
huge data that you run on whether it's a
database or or another application that
determines you know how much time it
takes you to run this thing. So
everything is proportional to the amount
of input
and this is kind of fundamentally
changed because now we have these AI
models and these models actually the
program is enormous right the number of
parameters actually determines your
performance and so we've now gone from
what I call input driven to parameter
driven and this kind of means that we
have to change the way we actually
orchestrate running these programs
in particular, right? This has to do
with what we call um AI inference. So I
want to go back for a second and think
not about AI inference but about
inference in general. What we think
about inference which is running
software in data centers, right? And if
you look at um you know the historical
way that we run software is we have
essentially this thing called an
operating system, right? So the
operating system is a layer that sits
between the applications which are
historically I I guess mostly databases
but also other types of servers and u
web servers things like that right and
the hardware which are CPUs
and this has been like that for many
many years and we're at a kind of
beautiful stable point if you you know
we have brilliant operating systems
researchers at MIT but kind of their
work now is kind of boring for industry.
Okay, I'm not I I don't wish to insult
anybody, right? But everything's stable.
Okay, there's not much changes in the
hardware. There's not much changes in
the software and therefore there doesn't
have to be a lot of change in the
operating system. We're pretty happy.
The thing that the operating system is
doing for the software is kind of giving
us this buffer, right? where the writers
of the um you know the applications the
databases they just have to write to the
operating system or the virtualization
layer right and then the people that
design the hardware they just write
drivers for the operating system you
know and comes a company like Red Hat
IBM right sits in the middle and
provides you this kind of smooth way of
running everything so that you can
change the hund hardware underneath you
can change the software above and it
doesn't really matter to you that's
really what an oper operating system is
doing.
And now the world has changed and we
have these parameter-driven
um you know algorithms this all this Gen
AI inference right and now right we have
a different game the applications are no
longer databases they are actually you
know um you know kind of uh models
bigger and bigger models as we go along
with all kinds of agentic applications
and things are kind of moving right
moving really really fast here, right?
And in the same at the same time because
our demands in terms of the software are
changing so rapidly, the hardware is
also trying to catch up. So we've got
all these types of new accelerators. You
know, every other every few months
there's a new version of some
accelerator, some piece of hardware that
somebody's designed.
And so what we need right is a new layer
there in between something that will
play the same exact role that you know
that that uh the operating system played
this time for the models and the um and
the hardware that they run on top of.
Okay. And the the beautiful thing about
this game, the thing that makes it
interesting, right, for scientists,
right, for developers is that it's
rapidly changing.
Okay. And this means that this layer,
okay, is changing like I I want to say
every week, okay, new versions of
things. We need to invent invent
technology. Now, it's kind of funny
because a lot of this technology, okay,
is are these are just variations of what
we already have done in operating
systems research. So we have to thank
you know people like like France Kashuk
at MIT who have already given us
wonderful ways of actually designing
scheduling and control and all these
other things. Okay. And now though we
have to apply them in a different way to
a different problem. Okay. And so this
is actually what's happening in this um
in this space. Um and you know and um
the kind of reason why um Red Hat IBM
bought my my my startup Neural Magic. I
started that company in 2018. We started
doing inference and um with the advent
of LLMs. Okay. Things just exploded.
Okay. And the reason right is because
suddenly we need a replacement. A
replacement for this operating system
paradigm. We need a new way of
insulating the models from the hardware
so that any new player in the
accelerator space can join in and
replace an Nvidia GPU without a problem
that you can have a data center that is
not uniform all Nvidia GPUs. I mean,
it's nice to do it with a uniform thing
if you're doing, you know, if you're
doing training, but if you're doing
inference and you're doing this in a
modern data center, you want to let the
customer pick what type of hardware he
wants to run on. Okay? You want
competition. You want to encourage that
below. Okay?
And so if you build this intermediate
layer, you're allowing any changes you
want underneath. And in the same time
right the applications the actual models
can change very rapidly. All they have
to do right is fit to this intermediate
layer right they only need to fit to the
inferencing layer. And if we achieve
this okay and we're very by the way
we're very far from achieving it. Okay
but if we do we'll be golden. And so VLM
okay which is kind of the specialtity of
my company. We are the core uh
developers of the VLM kernels and the
VLM internals. Okay. What VLM gives you
is one of those um you know kind of
operating systems for ML and this is
really I think this is where we're
going. So we're going to have open
software above a variation a variety of
hardware below and we're going to have
um you know VLM style um intermediate
layers that are essentially going to um
you know replace the operating system.
So a modern kind of um operating system
replacement right um the the inference
server will be able to connect any type
of software any type of model with any
type of hardware and make it you know a
level playing field for everyone to to
kind of exist in and there's incredible
buyin from all of the hardware and
software providers for this kind of a
solution
and I think with that I'll finish and
Um, you're welcome to ask any questions.
>> Questions for near.
>> Yeah.
>> Hi. Um, so I was I was also like I I
know a little about like VRM and uh I
read like there was a opensource
community out there that was uh they
have like all the codes auditable and
everything. Uh so like what does your
company do like uh in this field?
>> Great question. So, so when you have a
piece of open- source software like
Linux an operating system or VLM a uh
you know runtime right so the open
source developer developed this uh
software but enterprise companies cannot
rely on the open-source software to run
missionritical applications and so
companies like Red Hat, IBM, Oracle etc.
companies like that provide right a
solution that is stable and so for the
business world the stability of the
software right is the thing that is
given and of course you know there's a
there's a little bit of a kind of a also
uh uh when when you say open source
right uh VLM is an open-source uh
product developed by I would say three
companies really together so yes there
are developers out there that are
sitting at home and coding for the fun
of But mostly it's done within companies
that have an interest in the success of
the product. Yeah.