thank you for the invitation and the
introduction so I'll uh Jump Right
In so um as you can tell from the title
this is about reachable sets so
reachable sets I won't give a formal
definition because there are the
variations of that but primarily in this
talk we'll deal with a given dynamical
system a set of initial conditions and
typically we also include a set of
disturbances and the question is
starting with the initial set subject to
the disturbances where do you land what
are the possible behaviors so this is
important for verification of safety if
your reachable set excludes unsafe
behaviors that's a certificate of safety
we also do this as a stepping stone for
control synthesis or to find control
invariant sets which is important for
autonomy applications so one of the
things we do is use a symbol symbolic
abstraction of dynamical system by
splitting the state space into cells and
then use reability analysis from each
cell to see what other cells you can
land in and use that to create a finite
State
model so I won't go into the many
applications but autonomy has been one
of the driving applications This Is Us
uh trying some um a platoon of vehicles
in urban traffic uh the vehicles keeping
six meters from each other how is this
relevant so in the design of these
controllers we actually use model
predictive control but controlled
invariant sets are embedded into the
model predictive control in order to to
to um avoid unsafe
behaviors so um the problem with
standard methods for estimating
reachable sets and this has a long
history if you go back many decades uh
there's foundational work by
B secas on reachable sets and later on
variations of that in continuous time uh
which translate to Hilton jobi methods
those are very powerful for precisely
estimating reachable sets the problem is
that the more State variables you have
and this is increasingly the case with
the type of systems we're de dealing
with nowadays or they will not scale
well okay so in practice we need things
that can scale to large systems
and for doing so we found the idea of
sampling trajectory is very
useful so I'll show you several variance
of this but the main the common idea
among the different things I'll show you
is we generate sample trajectories by
High Fidelity simulation say and then we
see where those trajectories land okay
and then we try to reason about the
neighboring trajectories that did not
get sampled okay and so this is
basically a problem of
generalization and so you're trying to
generalize from samples to unsampled
neighboring trajector so we use
different methods for doing so uh one of
them you know questions how do we
generalize in one line of work we use
dynamical system properties to be able
to reason about what we haven't sampled
a Natural Choice you're here um with um
Jean Jac slotin so contraction theory is
one natural source if you knew some Bond
on how much trajector can diverge from
each other so contraction is a generic
name that also gives you growth bonds
right doesn't have to contract then you
can you can tell how far apart
neighboring trajectories can diverge
from sample trajectories and that can be
used as a way of um of uh covering
trajectories that you haven't sampled so
we did some related work in 2015 there
was couple of follow-ups um but the idea
there is clear basically taking
contraction ideas and turning them
turning them into algorithms no
foundational work on contraction Theory
itself um another line of work had to do
with monotone systems these are order
preserving systems and a cartoon that
explains the main idea here uh is shown
in the middle so say you have a box of
initial conditions and the system
preserves order with respect to the
standard order right then if you
simulate trajectories from the two
extreme points the two extreme um
corners of the box wherever they land
because of the order preserving property
all of the trajectories in between will
be sandwiched between those so you get
get a natural bonding box okay so we
were able to extend this quite a bit
because monotonous the by itself is
quite restrictive but then we extend
this two class of systems that we call
mixed moton um so I'll give you a little
glimpse of that the first few slides and
now we'll switch to a learning approach
where we don't use any dynamical system
properties we just used generalization
in the statistical sense so we try to
develop probabilistic guarantees
of uh accuracy of a reach set that we
obtain from the samples okay so that
will be the buk of this
talk um so this book that you see on the
right uh summarizes most of the earlier
work not going so much into the uh
sampling and probabilistic Bounds okay
so we'll start with the what we call
interval reability analysis because we
are using these um axis aligned
intervals hyper um hyper boxes if you
want to call them or hyper intervals um
so let's start with that and I'll show
you the connections to monotonist but
what we'll present is a lot more General
than monotonicity so let's say we are
given a dynamical system defined by
differential equation like the one you
see at the top and the let's call the
the solution map at time T starting at
time t0 F subt okay this is a nonlinear
dynamical system so we don't know the
solution map so the reachable set from
that from a set of initial conditions
the box that you see on the left is
going to be the image of that box under
the uh solution map which you don't know
we're not going to know that exact shape
but the idea is can we quickly with very
light computation find a bonding box
over it and like I said before if you
have a monotone system in the strict
sense that preserves orders you would
just take X underscore look at the image
of that under the solution map by simply
integrating the differential equation
that would give you the lower corner and
now you'll do the same thing for the the
x x over bar and that will give you the
upper corner of the bonding box it would
be very simple what we are doing is a
little more General than that so the
main condition we're asking for is not
monotonicity although it encompasses
monotonicity as a special case so assume
that there you can find a constant
Matrix K such that the Jacobian of the
solution map which is denoted as partial
FD partial X Plus that constant Matrix
is s stable s stable means that even
though the entries depend on X their
signs do not change they're either all
positive or negative okay so the claim
is that under that condition you can
find the find the bonding box
efficiently uh you can basically find
the corners of the bonding Box by
evaluating
functions for only these upper and lower
points xcore and xar okay the little f
is derived from the actual solution map
and I will tell you what it looks like
in the next slide but the idea is that
you can just do two simulations to be
able to bond uh the actual
reset okay now the simplest case here is
when that Matrix K is
zero and the sign stability is consists
of all non- negative signs okay imagine
the Jacobian has all non- negative signs
that means the system is monotone it's
order preserving it's an increasing
function of every variable okay in that
case that little F that we use for
bonding the for finding the bonding box
is very simple it's the solution itself
you evaluate the solution big ft at
xcore to get the lower Bond and you
evaluate at xar to get the upper B very
simple right so this theorem is
extending this idea first it doesn't
need all positive entries it can have a
mix of signs okay second even if you
have entries that change sign if those
entries are either upper bonded or lower
bonded you can add a correction term in
the form of that constant Matrix if you
have a lower bond that goes negative you
can put a positive K entry in K to push
it up so it's always non- negative and
vice versa okay very simple idea um
so in the general case where you have
mixed signs and the Matrix K to make it
mixed signs um the little F function
takes the form that's explained here I'm
not going to go into the details but
let's perhaps look at the case where K
is equal to zero that's more informative
then what you're doing there again the
little F consists of the big F which is
the solution map and you're looking at
the entries if the dependence on an
entry has a negative sign the derivative
right then what you do is for the lower
end you enter the upper Bond
of the initial sets bonding box right
because the dependence is in the
opposite direction you're increasing
with respect to this variable so you're
mixing and matching the entries you put
in but at the end of the day all entries
you know the little function f comes
from the big solution map and you're
only evaluating it at a combination of
the uh the vertices okay and finally if
you need if you need to use that
constant Matrix K that creates an
additional term in the function little F
okay so that's the main idea um here's
the problem though so basically what I
explained here assume that you can find
a constant Matrix K such that the jobian
plus that constant Matrix becomes sign
stable being able to find such a
constant means that you either have
upper bonds or lower Bonds on each entry
of the Jacobian right so that's the main
underlying assumption here how can I do
that because in the first place I don't
even know the solution map we are
dealing with a nonlinear system ft is
unknown in addition of course you don't
know the Jacobian of that okay but we
can actually
evaluate both the solution map and the
Jovian of that map for a given point how
do we do that we just integrate the
differential equations of course that's
clear uh for the solution map itself
you're integrating the differential
equation from X and what comes out is
the the solution at time t uh for the
Jacobian we have the notion of
sensitivity right what is the
sensitivity of an of a solution to
initial conditions if you pick a you
know standard book on differential
equations they'll tell you that you can
also append the differential equations
with the sensitivity equations integrate
them and that will give you basically
the Jacobian of the solution map so we
can do this run these two in parallel
and obtain both the solution map and the
Jacobian for a fixed given point right
but that's not enough for bonding the
whole jacobia so how do we do that so we
have a few methods each one has its um
limitations and advantages the first one
is one where we look at the sensitivity
equation and we realize that it looks
like a you know time varing Matrix times
the sensitivity m Matrix S right so it
looks like a linear time wearing model
okay and if you can cover the jobian
that's entering in the sensitivity
equation with an interval
Matrix then you can use interval
arithmetics to get a bond on the
solution of that sensitivity equation
okay there are ways of doing that uh it
goes back to the PHD thesis of Maas alov
at Technical University of Munich some
years ago and so you can do this and get
a solid Bond on the Jacobian that is not
going to depend on X and that's
basically what we were looking for but
as you can imagine that tends to give
you very conservative
bonds so that's the downside of that but
it's a sound method so you get a you
know you get a bond that's correct the
other solution is uh relaxing the
sunness a little bit so you can just
take a bunch of initial conditions
integrate those differential equations
and you get you evaluate the Jacobian
for all of those and then you take the
maximum you found or the minimum you
found for each entry to find your K of
course there you've lost soundness
because you you know the actual maximum
or minimum may happen at points that you
did not integrate right uh on the other
hand you get non-conservative bonds so
that's another end of the tradeoff and
we also came up with a in between
solution a high approach so to speak uh
that has the benefits of both Solutions
it is sound you get a guaranteed Bond
and um it is not conservative if you
take many
samples uh but on the other hand the
computational cost of that is a little
higher than the first two so what we do
here is actually a simple idea although
the equations grow so the idea is to go
one step lower in doing this interval
arithmetics which is conservative right
instead of using interval arithmetics to
bond the Jacobian we look at the
derivative of the Jacobian the second
sensitivity of the solution so to speak
which I denote as s XX second derivative
right now I'm going to use the interval
arithmetics to bond the second
derivative okay even if it's
conservative I don't care that much
because the only purpose of that bond is
to is to find the bond between this the
points that I've been sampling for the
Jacobian right my goal is to bond the
Jacobian I take
samples and I want to to make sure that
in between the samples you know I grow
the bond so that nothing can escape
right so for that in between Behavior I
use the second derivative Bond even that
if that's conservative if my samples are
dense enough the resulting Bond I get on
the Jacobian itself will not be
conservative okay and turns out you can
generate the second sensitivity through
an equation like this um but again as
you can imagine that leads to more
computational time
required so here's a very simple example
comparing all the things I mentioned um
the first method we talked about that I
said is conservative so this is a third
order system the unicycle model uh we
only looking at a projection into the
first two State variables um so the red
one that you see is the result of method
one it's a little
conservative um method two has no
guarantees but it works um it gives you
the blue box that looks like the
tightest and method three how
conservative it is depends on how many
samples you're taking like I said The
more samples you take the tighter it
will get um it starts pretty bad if you
start with one sample that's even worse
than the first method but the you the
the finer you make your Grid it's going
to get closer and cl closer to uh the
least conservative method too okay so
this is just to illustrate the ideas um
of using
monotonicity basically without requiring
the traditional uh definition of
monotonicity relaxing it in multiple
ways so while we were playing with this
we realized that you know the method two
which is sampling base and doesn't give
us guarantees is the is the one that has
the cheapest computation and gives us
the tightest bonds but no guarantees so
there was a student at the time who had
just started Alex stport and I told him
maybe we should look at that method more
closely and try to give some
probabilistic guarantees of of our bonds
on the Jacobian and he asked a very good
question he said you know if you're
happy with problemistic bonds why don't
you just simulate trajectories
themselves rather than doing that to
find a bond on the Jacobian and plugging
it back into your favorite method it's
too convol let's just simulate the
trajectories try to bond where they land
with appropriate sets and derive
statistical guarantees for the accuracy
of that estimate of the reset so that's
essentially what I'm going to present
next I told him you should do that and
that's the rest of my talk pretty much
so we're going to talk about a data
driven reachability method again this
time we don't need any information about
the model other than the ability to
integrate the model to get sample
trajectories therefore the model could
be arbitrarily complex High Fidelity
whatnot
okay so this is Illustrated in this styz
picture you have the initial set the
solution map ft Maps you to this orange
shape okay and in this first version of
what I'm going to present our goal is to
approximate that with a norm ball and
later on we'll lift that Norm ball
restriction we'll make it a lot more
General but I think for a first path
Norm ball makes it easy to understand so
what we do is we attach a probability
distribution to the initial set a
distribution whose support is the
initial set um this may have physical
meaning perhaps you know some statistics
about where the initial conditions are
going to come from or if nothing else it
could be just something you made up
maybe a uniform distribution over that
set which only serves as a rule to draw
samp
okay so we attach that distribution to
the initial set and under the solution
map F that get maps to a new
distribution okay and the support of
that final distribution is the exact
reachable
set okay now we're not going to go know
that exact reachable set because we
don't know the solution map so we're not
going to know the final distribution
either but we have the ability to draw
random samples from that final
distribution by drawing samples from the
initial distribution and
integrating indirectly right so that's
the whole idea so we take random samples
from the initial say integrate that
amounts to selecting uh random samples
from the final distribution and we use
that to approximate the support of that
okay so starting out with the normal
estimates what of course you can always
if your goal is to bond the reachable
set you can take the whole space or a
hugely conservative set but that defeats
the purpose the purpose is to have a
tight uh approximate of the Reet so then
our goal is to find the smallest
possible Norm
ball where the center of the ball B is a
decision variable and the shape that's
encoded in The Matrix a is also a
decision
variable um
so
that that normal captures one minus
Epsilon of the probability mass of the
final distribution and that's our
measure of how much we've captured the
actual reachable set okay and Epsilon
here is a user specified accuracy
parameter you want to capture 99% of the
reachable set fine you take Epsilon to
be 01 okay so the B the Norms you're
dealing with I did not restrict them
they could be two Norm one Norm whatever
you like if you use infinite Norms uh
then you're going to get box shapes if
you use infinite norms and the diagonal
a you're going to get axis ofine boxes
which ties in with the interval methods
that I was talking about
earlier so the problem we want to solve
then is a chance constraint optimization
problem you want to minimize the volume
of a norm Ball parameterized by this
Matrix and the Center Vector which let's
call them Theta collectively subject to
the constraint that the probability Mass
captured by that is is at least one
minus Epsilon okay again this is not
something you can solve you don't know
that distribution but we can relax it
with scenario optimization that means
you're going to take random samples
integrate therefore you've taken samples
from the final
distribution and you now minimize the
volume of that um normal subject to
capturing all the samples okay the idea
is very simple uh the more technical
part is in in obtaining some sample
complexity bonds uh telling us how many
samples we should take so that we can
give give guarantees that is required by
the original problem and we'll come back
to that um just to break it down into a
simple optimization problem if you were
dealing with two Norms you could use the
log determinant of a as a volume proxy
for the norm
ball and then your constraints will of
course be that the Matrix a be positive
definite so it gives you compact sets
and all of the samples samples being the
successors of the initial the samples
you selected from the initial set um are
captured inside the ball and everything
is written as this simple convex
optimization problem okay now again okay
this spits out an answer what can I say
about the the resulting set how accurate
is it or is it going to match the 1us
Epson accuracy bond that is desired well
that depends on how many samples you've
selected there's vast literature on
scenario optimization and Sample
complexity bonds so we're not deriving
anything new here we're just adapting
them to this problem so what we would
like to be able to say is the Shaded
expression at the very bottom we'd like
to say that our estimate which we call R
hat obtains from the samples captures 1
minus Epsilon of the actual probability
Mass question is how many samples should
I take to guarantee that turns out
there's no number of samples that can
ever give you that guarantee because
your samples could come you know you
could be unlucky that day or you may
draw samples from only a small section
of the initial set and they will of
course land to a small section of the
the ACT reach that and you can never
capture 1 minus Epsilon right so any
statement like this has to be
qualified with another probability Bond
on the confidence in that statement
which is standard in in this literature
so the outer probability at the bottom
is the confidence basic you're saying I
capture 1 minus Epsilon and I'm 1 minus
Delta confident in saying that okay you
know Delta is basically guarding again
drawing ly samples okay so given the
accuracy level defined by Epsilon and
the confidence level defined by Delta
the formula that you see at the top and
there are so many variants of this but
usually they look alike you know in
terms of the logarithmic dependence on
the confidence and so on um so if you
take that many samples you'll guarantee
um the bond that's at the bottom
okay so n little n here big n is the
number of samples you need to collect
little n is the state Dimension okay as
you can see the growth in the state
number of states is pretty mild and
square and that's why we are pursuing
these sampling based methods because we
want to be able to scale up to large
systems uh where is that number coming
from it's basically the number of
decision variables there we had the
Matrix a n byn but it's symmetric so
it's half of n² plus the diagonals right
and then and we have the center uh point
B that adds another n so that's why you
have that number over there looking like
n s + 3 n if you are really worried
about
this quadratic growth in N you could
actually restrict your choices for
example in the very extreme case I'm not
saying you should do this but if you
really wanted an order of one growth you
could just take your a to be a number to
be decided times identity and B to be
zero that means you're looking at ball
you know actual balls right um spheres
that are centered at the origin of
course the estimate will be very
conservative but you know the now
there's only one one parameter to choose
so it's order of one if you want order
of n rather than n squ then you can
choose your a to be diagonal that's
going to make your Norm balls axis
aligned which again creates conservatism
but again it's order of n so that's
Illustrated in the middle and if you're
flexible can explore different axes then
you choose a fully populated A and B
then it's order of n
Square here is the low Chic oscillator
which is something we tested these ideas
on so the first one is illustrating how
many samples you would need I I'm
guessing Epsilon in this case is 10^ -2
and Delta is 109 confidence is cheap
because it enters logarithm of 1/ Delta
um that's the number that we typically
use in the examples so the first one
requires the least number of samples and
in the second one we get an AIS aligned
ball in the other one it's a little
squished okay and the number of samples
accordingly are increasing now the
difference between the three cases is
not very dramatic here because this is
only a system with three state variables
right so you know quadratic versus
linear is not a big
deal um okay
so now so far we talked yes quick
question so the bounds that you just
showed are independent of the function
the F function that defines the
differential equation that's correct and
do you need any assumptions on F no no
lip Shi nothing I mean some people use
lipes types of bonds to be able to
eliminate this alter confidence thingy
but um we don't need know of
that so let's now generalize Beyond Norm
balls so really there's nothing special
about the norm ball all we need is to
use approximating sets of this form as
suev sets of a parameterized set of
functions okay a function G of the state
and parameters to be decided okay and
let's say we're using the zero subev
sets of that as our reset estimators so
to be able to turn this into an
optimization problem we'll need a volume
proxy so we assume that whatever
function G we're using for it zero subl
set we have some way of gauging its
volume okay that's what's the volume
function means it's just the proxy like
just like the log determinant we were
using before and normal is of course a
special case of that if you define your
function G as shown there and Theta to
be the decision variables a and volume
of data being negative log determinant
of a so with that you can actually do
much more interesting reachable set
estimates um and the optimization is
pretty much unchanged you're looking for
the data that minimizes the volume
subject to the subev set containing all
the samples you
selected so it's a convex problem if the
the volume proxy function is a convex
function of theta and if the function G
whose zero subev sets we're using as re
set estimates are convex in Theta but
not convex in Theta I'm not asking for
convexity with respect to the state
therefore the suble level sets don't
need to be convex at all but convexity
in Thea is required under those
conditions not only do you get a convex
optimization problem but also the sample
complexity bond that we saw before still
applies uh same formula except that we
have n subeta number of decision
variables and that was you know this
number before because the decision
variables was the N byn Matrix plus a
vector um so here's an example of the
types of things you can do with this
generalized formulation for example you
can split your States region of interest
in the state space that you know will
contain your samples and break it into
cells in in this case think of it as
tiles or boxes right the algorithm
you're using is the simplest thing that
anybody could imagine um you know
Elementary School student could possibly
come with this if you explain to them
what the legibility is
so you run a bunch of simulations from
samples if a tile gets hit you include
that tile in your estimate if a tile
doesn't get hit you leave it out
algorithmically it's as simple as that
now we have to dress this up a little
bit mathematically and formulate a
function G and volume proxy so we can
apply our sample complexity theorem okay
not for the algorithm itself uh it's
straightforward you can Define these um
indicator function for each cell for
each tile and then multiply them by a
coefficient Theta which is the decision
variable and the way youve defined it
for the sub zero sub Lev set to coincide
with the tiles that got hit you um
basically Theta needs to be zero right
the Theta for a cell needs to be zero so
that the Subzero suev zero sub Lev set
is included and with that of course you
want add as few tiles as possible to be
included and you can encode this in this
volume estimate using one minus data
because that way if data is zero it's
bigger so it's a penalty and you're
trying to minimize that
okay do you have any questions up to
this point maybe I can briefly pause yes
so the first method based on Norm balls
would suggest you know maybe a Next Step
would be to construct an open cover
where you're choosing the shape or the
size of the balls and also the location
you guys considered that I mean I
imagine this is simpler in terms of
complexity
because you don't have those extra
decision
variables pre- partition your have you
thought about the open cover approach no
I don't think we have yeah so the extent
of what we considered is already in the
slides
yes so like what
howle complexity depend
on it doesn't because we just choose
that right I mean it's a fixed
number so when
you
comp a constant yes so like but for
example for different kind of damic
system for
yeah I mean these bonds will inevitably
be conservative because they are not
using any information about the Dynamics
nor the period of integration yes I mean
that's the Holy Grail you would like to
be able to incorporate that knowledge as
well I think that's something that
people should think about but we want to
start at this level just statistical
generalization from samples and not
using any knowledge about Dynamics
so that's basically limited setup here
let me continue so I don't run out of
time but I will go faster so we have
more time for question um so like I said
here the function G needs to be convex
in Theta but not in X that allows
non-convex Subzero zero subev sets but
wouldn't it be nice to also eliminate
the convexity Assumption on Theta if we
could do that then we could use more
interesting functions such as sums of
radial basis functions and their Subzero
level sets if you look at the typical
expression for that you will see that
the parameter Sigma mu um and the
threshold gamma actually enter in a
non-convex way not Sigma but the others
do um and then the volume proxy in this
case is the sum of the sigma squares
right so um radial basis functions are
commonly used uh for bonding uh sets so
we want to be able to use them so to be
able to eliminate this convexity
assumption on the parameters we turn to
this so-called weight and judge approach
in a paper by compy and grati who are
scenario optimization guys and using
their method we were a able to eliminate
their convexity requirement and B
dramatically improve the sample
complexity bonds there's a drawback
though now you can't a prior say I need
this many s and this level of accuracy
will be guaranteed that you can't do
that what you do that's why it's called
weight and judge so what you're doing
now is you're taking samples in batches
okay getting your approximation you
still don't know what the accuracy level
is but given the confidence you
want
and given one more piece of information
which is how many of the samples you've
selected are essential to the
optimization problem in the sense that
if you yank them out the solution of the
optimization problem changes okay so
those are called support scenarios and
the number of the support scenarios and
the confidence level then give you an
Epsilon the accuracy Bond okay so you
you collect a batch do all of this find
an Epsilon if you're happy you stop if
you if it's larger than what you wanted
you collect more samples continue okay
although it's a little more tedious at
the end of the day if you look at how
many samples you needed to guarantee a
certain Epsilon you'll be much happier
with the total number than the
Alternatives you saw before where you
committed ahead of time okay much more
efficient uh sample complexity wise
here's a simple illustration is a six
State quador model again you're only
looking at a projection onto the two
dimensional space in one case you're
looking at again this Union of intervals
in the other case you're looking at a
Union sub level set of a sum of three um
radial basis
functions and the number of samples you
end up with and the resulting accuracy
levels are listed in this table just to
give you an
indication okay so this is a bit of an
intermo so we'll talk about an example
uh to illustrate some of the things
we've seen before this was a model that
we were playing with for a while I don't
work on exoskeletons really but there
was a student who was set on uh working
on those so what we did was to derive a
controller for the sit to stand motion
of a peric patient uh with the help of
the exos
skeleton so and then we now we want to
after the design is done we want to make
sure that it's safe to use for uh
patients and of course patient will not
come in one mass and one length of leg
and you know the parameters will change
right so in this case what we are doing
is we're treating the the variance the
variation and the parameters as our
initial set there is no difference
between dealing with an initial set of
States versus initial set of parameters
you can just treat parameters as state
variabl set their Dera equal to zero you
can apply the same methodology so in
this case the initial condition is
really not different you're sitting
right but what's different is some of
the parameters even the same patient
could after eating or wearing heavy
clothes would have a different mass and
so those numbers can change so it's good
to to see how much from a nominal
trajectory you've designed you will
deviate in when those parameters change
in this case you can actually attach
possibly a physically
meaningful um probability distribution
to the initial set because those
parameters may come from some
distribution anyway so the next slide is
showing you some simulation results um
the red bond is obtained from the
sensitivity method that I was explaining
earlier the second one that didn't have
formal guarantees and the blue one which
is very tight uh is obtained from
Scenario
optimization um and for the blue one the
number of samples that was required was
10 to 1,3 36 that came from uh the given
Epsilon and Delta
requirements now usually when you do
reachability right you know you you get
some
conservativeness and if you use that H
to see your next um level of
reachability analysis then you'll get
even more conservative right so the
erors keep growing what we are doing
here and the reason why these look so
tight is you asked me about the the
choice of T right so we split the time
interval of Interest into um segments
and each time we're doing these
simulations from zero up to that point
so like from 0 to1 0 to point2
0.23 that way we don't have this you
know inflation of the errors and that's
why how these bonds are looking so tight
otherwise you'd have some crazy growth
in
those all right uh so we we have some
toolboxes to implement some of these
methods I described tra is for the inter
reability analysis I described earlier
it's pretty flexible it's matlb based
you can there are some built-in
functions but it's open source and it
allows the user to add new methods uh a
postdoctor researcher at the time Pier
Jean mayor is back in France but he's um
he's still maintaining this toolbox we
also looked at parallelization one of
the nice things about sampling
is you know you're basically integrating
differential equations and you can
paralize this so we did some uh speed
test with a par we first did a
parallelized
implementation uh that was reported in
this in C to20 uh I think the tool is
called perk p i r k I forgot what it
stands for but it paralyzes the
computations and uh these simulations
are showing how with different um gpus
the different number of cores you can
scale even even
better okay so one last approach data
driven quite distinct from the scenario
optimization method this one is based on
the empirical risk minimization
literature although we don't need many
details from that literature so I'm just
basically compressing everything I need
into this theorem so in this case what
we doing is we select our reach set
estimates are had from a family of sets
Okay I'm going to narrow down that
family on the next slide but in the most
General case it's a it's a class of
sets and we choose one that has the
least volume that contains all the
samples we're not solving any
optimization problem like in the
um scenario optimization case now as
long as the class of fun class of sets
you're
using um has a VC
dimension of M or less than the
following um sample complexity bond
holds and you know I'm sure in this
Elite crowd many of you have been
exposed to VC Dimensions if not you will
be at some point I couldn't go through
this but it's basically a combinatorial
measure of the complexity of the set so
if that's a finite number M then this
sample complexity Bond will work okay
now in our case our choice of functions
are uh zero or suev sets of functions so
you can almost use the VC dimension for
uh sets or functions interchangeably as
long as you interpret the sets to be
subel sets so if I
select functions from a function space
of finite dimmension M okay then the
suble Lev set is going to have a VC
dimension of M okay and that's what we
going to do for example if you use
pols of fixed order naturally this is a
finite dimensional function space um and
you can use the zero level sets or any
suble sets of the polinomial as your
reset estimate and you can use this
sample complexity Bond now we are going
to use a polom not just any polinomial a
very special one called a christopal
function in fact if you look at the
definition of christopal function what
we are using is the inverse of that so
let's call it to be precise the inverse
christopal function of order K which
consists of this function that you see
here you form a vector of
monomials up to degree K in the state
variables and you form this quadratic
expression where the Matrix in the
middle is the So-Cal empirical moment
Matrix which again uses these
monomials evaluated at the sample points
okay at the end of the day it's a
quadratic
expression and the vectors Z contains
monomials and when you multiply them out
you're going to get a polinomial of of
degree 2K and that means this is a class
of functions coming from a function
space of dimension
given by this expression n + 2 K choose
n so we can apply the theorem okay so
what we do is we collect our
samples find the
smallest level
set of this polinomial that contains all
the samples okay and use that as your
reset estimate okay now the the bond I'm
giving you is very generic right it it
was true for anything of VC Dimension m
but we narrowed it down to pols right in
fact a very special type of polinomial
so it's a very generic Bond not very
specialized to this type of function at
all but it works the question is why are
we using this type of polinomial the
answer comes from the machine learning
literature christopal functions have
been known for their support estimating
quality support approximation for
distributions okay and that's precisely
what we are doing as I said at the
beginning um the support of the
distribution we are looking at we're
drawing samples from is the exact reset
so that's why we thought this would be
relevant and one of the benefits of
these functions is that the suble Lev
sets morph into complex change pretty
easily and we didn't in fact observe
this in our numerical experiments again
looking back at the Lawrence
oscillator already with a 10 order
polinomial you get pry nice um alter
Bonds in addition uh if you take more
and more samples you start actually
spotting holes in the reachable set and
this is easier to see in the duffing
oscillator case it's a Time bearing
duffing oscillator and it it's it's
known for its chaotic Behavior so when
you select more samples uh you start uh
the suble set starts detecting some
holes and if you do more more Hol all
start appearing okay so it's a
completely different approach by but the
the main idea is again data driven and
the probabilistic bond uh except that
because of the very coarse nature of the
sample complexity Bond we using we get
very large numbers okay so before people
start leaving let me conclude
so reate is critical for many
applications I did not go too far into
the applications but um I narrowed it
down to a very you know self-contained
formulation and we show the promise of
sampling approaches the question was how
to generalize from the samples to
unsampled trajectories and we use two
lines of work we in one we use dynamical
system properties particularly
monotonous types of ideas and the other
one we just use the prob probabilistic
structure and the regularity of the sets
that we are using as a estimators
regularity in this case appeared in the
form of a finite VC Dimension so to
generalize you need something to to to
use right so in one case it was the
Dynamics themselves in the other case it
was the regularity of the
sets okay with that I'll leave you with
some references where these results are
discussed and I'll be happy to take any
questions and it's 5:00 p.m. I'm
impressed with my timing
[Applause]