Um good morning. Uh my name is
Sebastiano. I'm a first year
post-docctoral fellow at the Eric and
Wendish center. And it's my pleasure to
introduce our next speaker, Jean Philip
Ve. Um Jean Philip is the chief R&D
officer at Okin AI biotech company using
machine learning to discover and develop
treatments for unmet medical needs. He's
also the co-founder and executive
chairman of Boptimus and professor at
the ecoldin in Paris. Um his research
focuses on the theory and pract and
practice of statistical machine learning
and its applications to computational
biology and medicine. JP has earned his
PhD in mathematics and has held roles at
Google brain as well as academic
positions at the caldermin and
institute. His contribution to the field
has led Jean Philip to to several awards
including a major science prize from the
Institute of France. JP, we're very
excited to have you here and we're very
excited for your
talk. Well, thank you. Thank you for the
intro and and the invitation to be here.
It's a real pleasure and it's always so
I mean these are my best workshops you
know we're not too big with real AI real
biologist meeting together this is where
things happen so uh I'm going to give
presentation which comes you know
compared to a previous one a bit more
from the AI viewpoint
um because you know this is me I cannot
pretend I'm a biologist and I'm going to
discuss you know the the a topic which I
think is is is really mainstream now
which is the national foundation models
and how the latest AI technologies could
contribute to different ways or new ways
to uh to understand simulate biology.
uh first let let me mention because you
know so I have academic position but I'm
now in the industry just you know for
all of you maybe not of you not all of
you are aware of you know what what all
of this means uh in industry you know
lots of biology especially in this in
such an institute is is geared toward
developing new treatments better
treating patients and so I must say that
already today and it's been the case for
the last few years AI is used and deeply
used in many aspects of of drug
discovery, development, diagnostics,
etc. Forget about the details of that
slide. This is just a slide taken from
Arin. Uh but it shows that you know Arin
is using AI in order to solve the
problems in in drug development and
really uh machine learning computation
budget is used from the beginning. So
you know uh developing a drug means
understanding biology. This is mostly
what is done in academic labs, right? to
understand the cancer for example
identifying processes targets. Then once
so this involves also computational
approaches. Then the second step often
called you know drug discovery in these
in these approaches. Once you have a
target design a good drug a good it
could be a small molecule could be
antibbody this kind of things. So
obviously today genai is heavily used
already to to design candidate drugs but
then it's not the end of the game. Of
course once you have a candidate drug
you optimize it and there is all this
translational work which is where should
I use my drug to which patients which uh
which are the likely responders etc. And
here again it's a you can think of it as
a massive you know collaborative
filtering problem where you have
patients you have candidate drugs or
candidate targets and you want to find a
good match. So just for you to know and
you know each of these topics could
involve uh you know a full day of
seminar but AI is already used and and
with you know some success. However,
it's fair to say that in spite of you
know all the smart people you doing that
all the great data we have uh the
statistics are not very very good and uh
typically you know after years of uh
development of a new treatment finding
the best science the best antibbody the
best molecule optimize you test it in
clinical trial meaning you test it on on
humans to test if you will save lives
and we're still today at the stage where
uh Nine out of 10 drugs that are tested
in clinical trials don't make it to the
market either because they are toxic or
because they have no effect they don't
treat the patients or other you know
less uh more business reasons but so
something is missing and you know my the
the whole by the way this is very high
level but this means that in spite of
the great science that we have we are so
far away from other fields like in
physics where you know we have equations
and we can fly rockets to the moon Most
here in biology we are still probably
missing deep understanding and capacity
computational simulations uh prediction
models that that translate from research
to real patients. Okay. So I would
summarize my my presentation by okay
this is a fight you know we have lots of
knowledge lot lots of experience but no
real computational simulation that would
allow us to just say well developing a
drug is easy you know you just uh find a
target uh and then your your computer
would simulate if the target works on a
patient and it would today does
not okay um in that so in that field
this AI is a help um there are many ways
to to to introduce it but all of you
have heard and and probably maybe have
developed or are working on things like
Alpha Fall. This is a big game changer.
I just mentioned it because it's popular
and also just to illustrate again if it
was not obvious to all of you that
something has happened in the field.
This is a specific problem in biology
here. We're talking of predicting the 3D
structure of a protein from its amino
acid sequence. And that's a field that
where again there there has been lots of
smart people developing smart ideas over
the years but where the performance of
the prediction was plateauing has been
plateauing for more or less know couple
of decades and then came a different
approach AI based approach big neural
networks which borrows ID of course from
what was done before but pushes it to a
new scale and and with a few new
technologies that really changed the
field suddenly the performance is better
and turns out to be useful.
uh something important uh is that when
when I talk of new approaches of AI and
this is uh this is what I will now
discuss in my talk uh there is something
that is interesting which is that a lot
of the recent progress in AI in biology
like alpha fold and beyond is based on
approaches that are slightly different
from what machine learning was 10 years
ago and it's really a lot of emphasize
on purely datadriven AI meaning if you
have lots of data
then it's possible we discovered ways to
train neural networks so machine
learning models in a unsupervised way so
I can call that self-supervised or
unsupervised but meaning with no human
annotation with no specific you know uh
objective function in mind to solve a
problem just looking at data and
managing to learn from data a good
representation you know a good
simulation of the data so that then it
can be fine-tuned or used to to solve a
variety of tasks. Right? So this thing
is is you know my definition of a
foundation model. Foundation model is
really something so neural network
typically that is uh that has that is
typically very complicated. So it's not
like a few simple equations. It's really
billions of parameters which are
optimized but trained just to look at
data a bit like you know biologists have
done and you know a scientists have done
forever. look at data then eventually do
hypothesis do experiments look at more
data and aggregate this knowledge into
your brain today we try to do the same
but the aggregation of knowledge is done
in a computational system
okay so u of course this idea u maybe
five years ago would have been uh well
you know it's a cool idea but it will
never work I think all of us here
probably every day you use some some LLM
some uh Jim MNI, GPT, etc. And suddenly,
you know, something that that sounded
crazy five years ago is not crazy
anymore. An LLM is just a foundation
model of language. So, GPT, Gemini, all
these things. They are just systems
which have read texts taken from the web
with no specific things made. But I've
tried to learn to speak just looking at
at at raw text. And what we realize
today is that they speak pretty well.
It's not perfect. you know I won't enter
into the question of whether this is
intelligence or not but at least it's a
very powerful system that just from our
data has learned to answer questions has
learned to generate text etc. So the
question is could we do the same in
biology like uh and this is you know it
could be a bit provocative to say well
maybe we don't need so much humans there
maybe if you just collect lots of data
and find a way to train this equivalent
of LLM but from raw data what could they
learn and could they build a system
computational system that then can be
queried can be used you know to address
many questions uh the previous talk I
think gave a few examples of how this
can be done if you want to identify
structures in a cell. But maybe we could
pre-train a system that then could be
queried uh up to can you design me a
good drug for these patients. We don't
know. Okay. So we are not there yet at
all. It's very hard to know whether we
will get there but I think there's lots
of progress being made. something more
complicated in biology that in in
language is that you know
language language at least there is one
modality which is text which is the
modality used to train LLMs in biology
as soon as you say let's train a
foundation model of biology first
question is okay what is biology what
are we talking about are we talking
about molecules cells tissues organisms
ecosystems etc so there's uh you know
lots of levels there's lots of
modalities it's a mix of images genomics
etc So it's a broad field uh where you
know I have my you know me and my teams
we we explore it but it's like there is
an endless uh combination of things we
could try and I think this is going to
be a very exciting topic in the years to
come. Uh it already started you know I
mentioned alpha fall but I think these
days if if you if you follow you know
bioarchchive etc every week you have new
foundation models. uh I would say that
as of today most of the foundation
models and and most of the publications
that come out uh tend to be on on
specific modalities specific levels. So
you have I I will go through a few
examples but we hear a lot about
foundation models for small molecules
for proteins for single cells for
tissues etc. Uh by the way you know the
field is really growing fast. there are
hundreds of citations. So I show a few
examples but please uh please pardon me
if you're not work there. They're just
you know it's just a mini sample but
just to say that these high impact
publications are coming and there they
really have you know each of them is
really bringing lots of of novelties and
and when you look at the results at
least for specific tasks we see that
this approach seems to be working in
maybe not yet in all dimensions but I I
will give a few examples of where it
really brings a new performance
improvement. Okay. So foundation models
of budge are coming.
uh let me deep dive to a few of them
before then coming back to how we build
a more unified view of biology. So I
would just mention and again I take
risks here especially in in front of
this audience because I will cite some
work which are not mine at all which I
found interesting a bit a bit outdated
by the way just to show that it's it's
it's already there. So proteins maybe
has been the the first you know there
was alpha fold and then lots of work uh
training LLMs on proteins. One good
reason being that you know we know how
to train large language models on on
human language. If you replace a text by
a DNA sequence or an amino acid
sequence, you more or less can use
exactly the same architecture, the same
transformer. Click the button, it learns
to speak not the language of humans, but
the language of biology. And and so this
you know this uh this work I mentioned
here are a bit old already in that
field. But they demonstrated that in
principle just doing that gave new
capacities like generating proteins you
can query proteins you can predict the
impact of mutation etc to some level
okay so this is already uh coming of
course there's this super exciting field
of single cell genomics uh and I'm sorry
again I see only one paper out of
hundreds I know the the broad and many
people here are deeply involved in that
field but the fact that we have access
now to the capacity to generate large
volumes of single cell transcripttomies
for example we're talking of tens or
hundreds of millions of single cells
suggests that we can learn the biology
of single cells or try to build a
foundation model of single cells that
could allow us to have a virtual single
cell one strain maybe allowing it to
predict the evolution of cells you know
time evolutions or the response to
pertubation etc etc so there's lots of
work and there are many people in this
room much better than me in that in that
field but this is really, you know, a
great example of how the current AI
technology can really match the current
biotechnology and biology topics. New
technologies, lots of data and and and a
great object to study in this case,
singing
also. Now let me spend a little bit more
time on on what's what's beyond cells
because understanding one cell is good
but you know if you work in cancer for
example everybody knows that it's the
interaction of cells uh complex
interactions tumor micro environment etc
which which matter probably more than
understanding what one cell does in a
petetro dish. Uh so how do you go from
one cell to many cells to interactions
between cells? uh here there are many
technologies but uh you know when you
think of how to get large volumes of
data um it's often no there is single
cell genomics for single cell but for
tissues uh something that is quite
common and for which it's very easy to
get lots of data are images in
particular these types of images in
hisystopathology because this is what's
used in in in many clinics in the world
right as soon as you have a suspicion of
cancer you do a biopsy you look it under
the microscope and if you have a scanner
then you can make it digital and
suddenly collect millions of of images.
So of course the depth of the
information maybe is a bit shallow
because it's only an image but remember
this is these types of images are what
is used today by most uh clinicians to
do a diagnostics and often to to sell a
treatment right so there is information
there. So a question is if you have this
this data well can you you know could
you uh build a foundation model on that
that would mimic in a sense what
pathologists are are learning right you
look at total lots of images to
understand the diversity the patterns
that you can have and maybe then from an
image do a lot of uh prediction tasks
u maybe I just skip that so just to uh
just to anchor again these um this
comment in the real for this is one
example out of many of systems that
already exist and already use foundation
models uh to help patients. That's one
system which is actually uh that was
developed by aren. So which is used in
the clinics for one task in this case
it's in coloral cancer from the image to
predict uh the status of microatellite
instability which is a good predictor of
response to imunotherapy. So this is
something that you know is is important
for clinics. There is a genetic test
that is the the standard to to decide of
the MSI status but uh adding to the
genetic test a pre-screening phase by
images can be a way to accelerate right
the filtering out patients who are
likely to be positive or negative. So
that's the kind of thing that you know
that finds its way in the in the
clinical protocol and this thing is just
one machine learning application where
you have an image as input uh you know
uh a prediction to be made MSI positive
or negative and that's typically the
kind of things which already today
benefit a lot from these foundation
models. I will I will show some results
but uh in the same way as once so one
it's a machine learning problem but
boosted by the recent approach the the
modern AI approach to say if you can
pre-train a model on millions of
histopathology slides then you can also
improve the performance of downstream
tasks like this task which which is
already in the
clinics. Okay. So
uh how do you train foundation models?
uh if if you're I mean uh I know this is
a mixed audience uh in LLMs like in
protein sequence natural language most
people know that uh it's just trained by
predicting the next word from the
context so you see lots of text and you
train a statistical model to you know to
say well if you have seen this thing
what is the next word and if you know
how to predict that you get an LM of
course for images it's a bit more more
different because there is no notion of
sequence but just for information you
you know the field has tried many ideas
has converged to a few that seem to be
working so FYI the kind of thing that
seems to be working today is to mix so
it's again it's self-supervised meaning
here I'm just talking of suppose you
give me millions of
images what could be an objective
function for neural network when it sees
the images to optimize the way to do
something okay and the things that that
seem to make sense that seem to work at
least uh is as of today mostly a of two
main ideas. One is called contrastive
learning. So is ide to say if you have
an image of a tumor then by yourselves
or through you know through different
measurements you can take a picture of
the same patient or the same tumor but
changing the color changing the
orientation changing the bit the
geometry and just constrain so teach you
know let the neural network learn that
it's the same tumor right so in a sense
learning the biology and not the
artifacts of the thing this is one key
ID the second key ID which is quite
similar to what's done in autogressive
LLMs except that it's not a sequence.
It's just what's called generative
learning. So you take an image, you you
hide part of the image and you train the
neural network to reconstruct the hidden
part. This can be done without human
intervention because it's pretty
computer that takes an image, removes
part of it and trace a model to you know
to predict what it has removed. So this
is really this notion of self-s
supervision where no human intervention
the computer can do it by itself and do
it at scale. Okay. So when you do that
and uh then you can train a foundation
model of of pathology and once you have
done that you know what what it is at
the end I mean there are many ways to to
query to use it but one of them is that
the model has learned to represent
images. So it can read an image and map
an image to a representation in numbers
right fixed vector representation often
roughly about a thousand numbers and
then from this representation you can
fine-tune it to solve tasks. So for
example I mentioned the MSI prediction
is one such task meaning if you have a
smaller set of images with annotation
you can fine-tune your model so that it
can predict MSI. Um here I show one one
work so I think it was one of the early
work one of the first foundation models
for pathology which was done at alken in
23 it's called
ficon and uh so we developed here you
know it was a foundation model for
pathology trained on tcgi data basically
public data so not not big but not super
big I would say uh but already when we
tested it uh after fetuning on a number
of tasks and here I won't go to details
But it's a mix of from an image you can
predict a variety of genomic alterations
like bracka bracka mutation in breast
cancer for example or you can find to
predict survival so for prognosis or
predicted uh predict molecular subtypes
systematically we got some big
improvement compared to what was done
before which is more standard machine
learning and by the way you know just to
uh to to go beyond internal validation
we also tested it on the kagle challenge
so I I really like you know challenges
is like Caroline mentioned this is how
the field can uh you know progress by
step because after a challenge everyone
observes what works what doesn't work
and we we can follow up on the best
ideas and so there was at the time there
was one challenge on breast cancer
cancer subtype classification organized
by UBC that we won actually with quite a
margin uh and basically the main
difference between our approach and the
others were the use of this foundation
model so much less impact than alpha
fold but in a sense similar pattern to
say well if suddenly you decide to take
a different approach uh build foundation
model and check them they just improve
the field right so and it's systematic
across a lots of
application now on once we were there of
course there was this uh exciting
question say well we have trained a
model on CGA but all the LM field tells
us that if you grow your model if you
have more data then maybe the
performance will improve again uh which
is something we don't understand
perfectly Why? But it's intuitively the
case that the foundation models benefit
from volumes of data. Okay, so that's
what we did and this is one of the
reasons why by the way we created this
new company by Optimus which is solely
focused on developing foundation models
for biology. It requires some you know
capital. It's expensive. Therefore the
the idea to have obviously you know some
some capital but so so we released um
last year some models but more recently
last month a model which we call H
Optimus one. And just to give you an
idea of the scale where we are today, um
this is a model that instead of you know
5,000 images from TCGA is trained on
more than 1 million. Uh and importantly
coming from many patients, right? So to
get patients we did partnerships with a
variety of labs. We worked with more
than 4,000 clinical practices. So we are
the you know I'm sure we can go beyond
but already we move from thousands to
millions. uh something uh if you're in
the machine learning field important is
that here we're talking each image is
very large. It's a gigapixel image. So
in fact to train the model we cut each
image into thousands of smaller patches.
So the the number of small image that
the the the computer sees to train the
model is in the billions.
Okay. Uh so we did that. It's available
on face if you want to try it. Um and
and does it work? Well, you know, we we
we played the, you know, we tried. So,
by the way, I just mentioned our work,
but that's a field that is booming as
well. There are there are lots of other
very nice nice models that have been
proposed over the years. Uh, but just
this is this is some of the results. So
I won't go to you know there there's a
link to where the results are detailed
but this is a summary of 18 tasks where
you say I have trained a model and I use
it to predict a genomic alteration
prognosis classification etc. Then you
can measure the performance if it works
well or not. And here this these slides
aggregate the performance right AU u I
think there are a couple of things to to
be said here. So one is every you know
every every column is is a different
model. The one I presented earlier that
one kaggle last year which is you know
quite important
is it's not even here is a predecessor
of falcon v2 uh it was falcon v1 right
which is much below there. So first
comment is that between 20 end of 23 and
25 you know we move from uh let's say
80ish to 85ish
uh by just changing the foundation model
right no other innovation you just
change one component of your system all
the all the rest is the same and you see
that we're in a in a in a field where
the the progression in performance of on
task that matter uh can be in the range
of five 10% easily just by changing the
fundamentals So I think it's not the
end. I don't know if how far it can go
if it's a question of more data, bigger
models, other modities etc. But uh as we
speak and this is what I was saying
where I said every week there is a new
model, a new publication. We're in a
very active field where we see progress
which hopefully impact the patient.
Um this maybe I can skip
uh because now I'd like to you know to
uh to take the the last five minutes to
discuss what's next. So I insisted on on
foundation models for images. I
mentioned many people are doing things.
Now the real question the real exciting
question that I'm sure many people share
uh is okay suppose we have a virtual
cell we have a virtual tissue we have a
virtual protein how they fit together
and remember that on the application
side the real question we care are how
can you design a drug for a patient so
it has to be a good protein that changes
a cell in the correct way in such a way
that in the tissue in the tumor micro
environment it ends up with benefits at
the clinics right So these things are
connected. They have to be
connected. Um this is so this is uh
exciting and hard. Uh I can quickly
share some of the avenues we've taken
already. So you know to go across
modalities there are questions of how do
you get data that connects scales and
modalities. Something that in terms of
existing technologies that we that we
started working on is special
transcripttoics which is a good bridge
between single cell genomics single cell
transistomics and you know tissue
organization.
uh and in particular you know one thing
that you could decide as a task is
suppose you observe an image can you can
your con can your system could you
design a system that allows just from
the image to reconstruct the genomics so
that eventually you know the idea to go
that way is that because this is the
pathology is cheap and in large volumes
if we had a way to from the image
reconstruct much more than the image but
maybe some some gene expression etc then
suddenly we could map millions of images
to that genetic level that would allow
us to investigate a correlation between
organization of of gene expression and
response for
example. So um you know we we worked on
that and it turns out I don't know if
FAL is in the room maybe but uh there's
been a great actually a great paper at
at newips last year which is a benchmark
super useful not not a challenge I mean
similar to a challenge that proposes one
such task which is uh you know
collecting images and among other tasks
from an image can you predict gene
expression. uh we did test our models
they work very well again these are many
models uh fon is here you see this was
top-notch two years ago now it's quite
quite behind for the phis I think there
are two comments here one is that again
in two years you know we go from 36% to
42% performance I skip the details the
performance here is a correlation
coefficient between the predicted and
the real expression average over many uh
many many cancers But so there is big
progress. Uh still I must say that the
the row performance 42 is is very far
from one that would be the optimal. So
there is a long way to go. Probably
there is it will keep growing. Probably
there is a limit and so probably this
will we cannot predict all gene
expression just for machining just
because there is not enough information
but I think there is still room for
improvement there. Okay. Okay, so it's a
good first step and here you really see
the you know the benefits just of
training better foundation model because
again all the columns is the same
algorithm it's just you change one
component which is the the foundation
model that you use
um how can we go further so a couple of
ideas um one is that we need more data I
think any initiative to systematically
generate and share data is is welcome
um one one you know one of them is a is
a is a very cool data set being
generated by sponsored by AIN but with
uh several hospitals in Europe and in
the US to systemat system systematically
generate an atlas of cancer in
particular using special troytomics
technologies together with single cell
bulk exom sequencing images etc so
that's the kind of uh you know that's
the kind of data generation that I think
we really support uh the the field of a
bi and and foundation models are really
ready to ingest all of this data, take
this data, they will just improve the
models and move us maybe towards more uh
multiscale multimodel foundation models.
And I will uh I will finish saying so
you know we are working hard to release
the next generation of foundation
models. Unfortunately I cannot go to too
many details until you know the products
is is launched etc. But the real thing
we're working on and I'm thrilled that I
would love to have discussions and and
and see other ideas is how do you you
know integrate these modalities uh
images genomics patient records proteins
uh given that we have a lot you know a
beautiful system in biology which is
this multiscale approach we know that
what you see in in full body is a
consequence of molecular interactions
but the the path from one of to them is
is is well understood. suit conceptually
but it's it's it's a bit hard to uh to
model. So you know one idea for example
is that because each foundation model
you can see it as transforming building
blocks into one object like a foundation
model for proteins is how amino acids
together from a protein. Then if you
look at single cell foundation models it
tells you how a set of genes and gene
expression defines the phenotype of a
cell. When I mentioned the tissues, it's
a way to say, well, if you know what
each cell is, then when you put them
together, you have a representation of
the tissue. So, computationally,
mathematically, it seems to make sense
to have some hierarchical structure in
some in some neural network. So, this
brings questions in AI about what is the
good architecture of the model, but also
what is a good objective function, what
is a good tokenizer to transform the raw
data into building blocks, etc. So lots
of cool ideas and you know I'm talking
especially I understand there are many
pos dogs here. Uh I think there is
enough research for all of you if you
want to go in that field. Um thank you.
I stop here. Uh and and I will thank you
know the teams at AI and Bopus who did
most of this work. Thank
[Applause]
you. We have we have time for one
question. I'll go here.
Thank you for the great presentation,
John Fleipp. Um, you
mentioned there's new models coming out
every week
and perhaps the consensus on what the
best model for a given workflow might
also change at a similar
frequency. How do you ensure researchers
are constantly equipped with the best
model? Um, and what are the biggest
bottlenecks to quicker and widespread
adoption of these models? Um, making
sure that they get in the hands of the
researchers researchers that can apply
them for their um for their workflows.
Yeah, great question. So, you know, what
I described is I think just the fact
that this is a fastmoving field.
uh
so you know they are the people who
develop these models and they are the
people who use them. So when you ask the
question how can can a user be sure to
use the best model. I have no answer. I
think you should just take the the ones
that that are available that exist today
knowing that I don't know if it's a good
or bad news but probably in six months
there will be a better one. So but you
know in research you you just cannot say
well I will wait six months to see
what's the best in six months because
it's just moving too fast. So you know
the maybe a good answer is I think these
benchmarks these challenges are really
helpful. Uh and you know I've been I've
been doing research for and science for
quite a few years as well. What's
complicated is when you just look at
publications individual each of them
saying well look my model is the best.
Uh we've seen this was the case for
alpha fold you know with the competition
CASP. uh even though everyone can claim
them all as the best the day you have a
competition like CAS that says look
there are many ideas but one of them is
just so much better than the other ones
the year after everyone is using it is
it good or not you know we also need to
have exploration but at least maybe the
the simple answer to the the the first
aspect of the question is uh trust the
benchmarks trust the challenges etc uh
so that um so that for today you know
what what state of the art at least.
Um I'm not sure I fully understood the
second part of the question actually. I
don't know if we if you want to
the second part what what are the
biggest bottlenecks to make sure that
researchers are able to adopt these
models. Um so say you have a specific
model that is meant for specific use
case. Not every single researcher that
could be using that model is using it.
How do you how do you tackle that? Yeah,
I'm not sure. So bottom uh so maybe my
one part of the answer is that a real
foundation model at least what we what
what what the field is trying to do uh
is meant to be a general purpose tool
meaning as soon as it's specific or good
for one task and we have many model
maybe alpha fold by the way you know I
mentioned it as a foundation model maybe
it's not the first version but the more
alpha fold and and similar models are
have been created we realize that we can
do good straighter prediction by having
a good foundation model of of protein
sequences. Okay. So I said alpha may not
be a foundation model. Uh but the later
generations are built on foundation
models that can predict structure that
can predict function that can predict it
etc. So u I'm not sure it's a good
answer but at least I would say that uh
in terms of foundation models the ones I
would trust or the the ones I would
investigate or try to build as a
community are quite gen general purpose
like um you know I can maybe mention the
the AI virtual cell initiative which is
really to say can we have a foundation
model so AI system that is just here to
simulate cells and we don't know for
what what uh what purpose? But really we
uh we just want it to be useful if you
want to predict response to perturbation
or if you want to uh to do cell cell
type classification or to do other
things.
Thank you.
Cool. Yeah. Let's thank the speaker one
more time. Thank you.