and good afternoon my name is Tim Moy
and I'm a recent graduate of the EMA
program here at MIT Sloan and I'm also
the co-founder of seab Bio today I'm
excited to tell you about our technology
to improve the efficacy of microbial
products by protecting microbes during
processing and
storage now as we all know microbes are
essential for human health in fact we've
been able to harness the power of
naturally occurring microbes to improve
digestion and Skin Care but that's not
all their use can be beneficial in a
wide variety of Industries for example
improving access to vaccines or in
agriculture fixing key nutrients like
nitrogen or phosphorus for plants or
even serving as pesticides and in the
built environment sequestering key
minerals from the air in fact in some
chemical processes they've been able to
reduce the need for Harsh chemicals and
high temperatures in
manufacturing but as anyone who's ever
worked with microbes can tell you they
are incredibly difficult to produce many
teams of scientists and Engineers can
work for upwards of a decade trying to
identify or engineer new microbes that
have really good promise with end users
or consumers but the second those
microbes are exposed to production and
transportation stresses they
unfortunately die and companies are
making those terrible tradeoffs of
either not producing their product
resulting to the cold supply chain which
is not only costly but not always
available or accepting low yields which
means really poor performance for their
consumers I'm proud to introduce a new
MIT developed technology that protects
microbes against these extreme
conditions we've been able to protect
microbes against the drying process
protect Anor robes from oxygen exposure
as well as extreme heat and humidity
what you can see on the bar chart here
is that using our proprietary technology
compared to Conventional excipients when
our microbes are exposed to temperatures
as high as 50° Cen or even 50% relative
humidity we see over six orders of
magnitude or a million times more cell
survival and what's really exciting
about our technology is that it's
readily formed in the video here shown
in the lab you can see the formation of
our for uh formula by the solution
turning from clear to dark blue not only
is it readily formed but the ingredients
are incredibly inexpensive and they're
generally recognized as safe by the
usfda and most importantly they do not
alter the cellular function that
companies have worked so hard to
develop now we know that our technology
is one of many approaches but we believe
it it's the only approach to enable the
widespread adoption of beneficial
microbes other Technologies can provide
protection but our codings are the
unique combination where they can be
implemented into existing Manufacturing
Systems can provide ambient temperature
storage and higher and are universally
compatible we've tested these on over 30
different types of string
and what's more is they're incredibly
inexpensive they're over a 100 times
cheaper than the next competitive
technology and at seab bio we see
ourselves as partners in enabling the
use of beneficial microbes and we're
looking for companies both domestic and
Global that are either looking to
manufacture or improve their existing
microbial products what this looks like
is we start with an intake meeting where
we learn about the key stressors that
your microbial products are exposed to
and then jointly develop a custom coding
for your product and ultimately what
this means is that you can get to new
product improvements launching new
products as well as developing those
hard-hitting claims that allow you to
maintain your industry leadership in
fact with one of our partners we've been
able to extend the shelf life of their
product by over six months and with
another we've been able to remove the
need for using 4 degree temperature
storage so if any of these benefits
sound exciting to you my contact
information is below and as I mentioned
here it say a bio our mission is really
to enable the full potential of microbes
in everyday life and I'm happy to take
any questions now or in the breakout
rooms team thank you so much so you've
talked a little about um ACTC consumer
products and Therapeutics at some of the
um vertical can you give a more specific
example of um how you've um worked with
one or had conversations whatever you
can share yeah so typically those that
are working with microbial products You
Know Who You Are um what we typically
like to understand is what is the strain
what are the stressors and then we work
to build a sort of a work plan and sort
of proof of concept study uh that can we
that we can use to demonstrate the
efficacy of our product and how long
could that take how what's the variation
yeah and so typically we've seen this go
from anywhere from 4 to 12 weeks it's
actually a really quick process um but
unfortunately we're unable to speed up
the stability process so if you need one
year of stability unfortunately it might
take a year of time um but we are really
quick and it and we've seen a lot of
success with our partners