So I'm Marco Turkete. I'm a MIT PhD
alumna and co-founder of
EVA. Uh so uh while it's pretty clear
that AI is revolutionizing many
industries, uh the um the uh the actual
bottleneck right now is actually the
availability of compute. In fact, if you
look at this uh this graph, you can see
that um uh to train the next generation
state-of-the-art model requires every
year an improvement in uh uh 4x in the
uh in the computation demand. Instead,
uh at the same time, the GPUs are
improving only by 30% year-over-year,
which is uh impressive, but not enough
to meet the demand. And moreover, as you
can see, uh to train this next
state-of-the-art model, uh it's already
requiring uh more than $200 million. And
this is just the tip of the iceberg
because actually the uh compute cost uh
that is required to develop such a model
is actually already in the five
billions. Uh so uh what are we doing at
to solve this uh this issue? So at we
are developing the next generation of uh
uh clusters which uh uh are going to um
are going to give an improvement of 72x
uh in terms of throughput per dollar uh
uh with respect to uh Nvidia uh
blackwell. So if you look at for example
uh how this translate in the training of
a um um like a model such as llama 3.1
you can see that uh with this kind of
cluster the improvement in uh time to
train is u uh from u um uh 80 goes from
80 days to less than two days and the
cost to train this model goes from $47
million to alpha million. So how are we
able to uh to do that? So uh the way we
are uh we are approaching this problem
is that we are building actually the
deepest AI technology stack ever. In
fact, EVA is built upon a breakthrough
in semiconductor technology uh that is
down at the level of the transistors and
at the same time we are uh um we are
doing an approach uh that is uh uh that
comprises like uh uh hardware and
software code development such that we
are able to uh uh be um compatible with
uh legacy libraries and uh and also we
are going to be able therefore to have a
turnkey uh deployment of our
hardware which brings me to my uh last
point. So uh which is we are uh uh uh
want to invite you in a uh partnership
uh with us a collaboration. In fact, we
would like to invite all enterprises
that requires a lot of uh uh compute uh
to um uh to uh adopt to uh on board on
our digital twin platform. Uh the reason
why we're doing this is because we would
like to um uh our future customer to be
able to uh uh run their tasks uh on uh
on our new architecture seamlessly. Uh
this uh will allow you essentially when
we uh deploy our uh um our clusters in
Q1 of 2027 uh to transfer uh
effortlessly uh all your uh uh AI cloud
compute uh to our hardware and and and
so enjoy all the uh improvement in terms
of performance and cost that I uh talked
before. And um um and uh therefore uh uh
if you are uh uh from one of the
industries such as the one that I'm
listing on the right hand side of the
slide uh so from uh generative AI or uh
BFSI uh biioarma or defense and so on.
Uh uh I would like to uh invite you to
join us in building the uh future of AI
together. Thank you very much.
Thank you, Marco.