[Music]
uh to start the Forum uh it would be
great if each of you uh could take a few
minutes to provide an overview of your
libraries experience uh leaving a big
deal um you know which deals did you
leave what were your driving motivations
and what has the outcome been um so far
just a brief uh overview I know we'll
dive into this more in detail followup
questions but perhaps we you know could
start in the order of introductions um
an if you could kick us
off sure I have to do the dreaded unmute
so here I am I remember to unmute and
Lang Yukon library before I dive in I
want to give a huge shout out to all of
my colleagues at Yukon library who did
incredible work uh carrying out my idea
to save us a whole lot of money and also
all of our faculty and administrative
Partners at the University who also were
incredible supporters and had Amazing
Ideas so shout out to all of them so the
the reason we uh unbundled all of our
big deals at Yukon over the course of
we're actually in our final year and a
half um is really about budget so budget
drove all of our decisions to do this we
Yukon as many people know has lots of
budgetary issues over the years uh We've
cut a lot of f a lot of Staff positions
all kinds of stuff but in 2019 December
of 2019 we were looking at serious two
and a half three million cuts to our
budget and I could no longer take it in
staff we'd gone from 166 staff in 2012
to 100 in 2018 when I got there and
there was just no wiggle room um and so
really thinking hard about this and
having experienced Journal cancellations
from the beginning of my career in 1996
at multiple institutions I was ready to
just say we're done we're getting out we
have we have the software technology to
make it easy for people we'll figure it
out let's come up with a plan let's not
break any contracts when they come up
for Renewal we'll just end them and uh
so that was our plan so we had to cut
between two and a half and $3 million
from our collections budget and I didn't
want to do the Death By A Thousand Cuts
so it was like let's just do it let's do
it um and then uh so we did we we had a
CP you'll hear a lot about this later
but we had internal external groups that
worked on it we got University
Administration involved um and we also
our goal was really save money save time
get people what they need that was
really our Focus um and uh right now um
we are down to about about we had a $4.5
million ejournal spend and we're down to
about 2 million now by 2025 we'll be at
1.5 and we're spending between 150 and
300K providing articles on demand so
that's a huge difference and people are
getting what they need when they need it
super fast um I think the hardest part
to to do something like this is PR you
have to pay attention to PR the rest of
it libr Ians can figure anything out but
if you don't have your PR in place your
communication plan in place your admin
in place it's not going to happen well
um and I think that that role of the
University Administration is key and I'm
going to stop there because I think I
answered all the questions you wanted me
to
cover thanks so much an uh P if you'd
like to go
next thanks Nick and thanks for hosting
this uh important conversation so I'm uh
Pari I'm the vice president for library
and information technology here at bnal
um so at bakal um we are a merged uh
libran an IT organization so I lead both
those
teams and I've been here for um about in
my 17th year um in this
role so just as a backdrop about
um why we all here today so we actually
started this conversation in the fall of
2019 with a faculty governance
group and and it kind of came about as
we I was developing a fiveyear
projection of what a budgets are because
our budgets were staying flat we were
not
getting um any uh additional funds uh
and that was University wide I mean the
library was not singled out I mean no
everybody was kind of had to deal with a
flat budget so as we were kind of making
these projection I just had to share
that one chart with the faculty
governance group saying this is what the
deficit looks like in the next 5 years
if we don't start taking action
now and looking back I think that was
the single
most piece of information that kind of
got this conversation started and they
looked at it like okay now what are we
going to
do and for us um when we kind of started
this conversation it was not about
cutting budget cutting
budgets it was about really um
sustainability and and that's the way we
kind of frame the convers ass on
campus and the task force that we formed
we called it the collection development
sustainability Task Force and and we
were really intentional about not
focusing so much on on the budget but
about the experience um so we here have
a little over 400 faculty at Bak
now and what we were finding was every
year um we H we H H anywhere from 40 to
60 faculty I mean not they are not all
new lines but a lot of visiting faculty
that are coming in filling in for
sabatical or
um uh folks who are leave and obviously
they they're here for a year or two and
we had no room in our budget to kind of
take into account any new programs that
we were starting any new faculty
requests that any new courses because
like well there's no money in the budget
to do any of those things so I think we
we kind of really looked at how do we
kind of sustain and look at things
5 10 15 years out um and and how do we
kind of form that
experience uh another example was in
2017 we we launched a brand new College
of
Management but we have nothing in the
library that could support that new
College to and and and so we um kind of
really stepped back and looked at okay
we need a different model on how we do
this so we started looking at
um uh really kind of working with a a
really fantastic faculty committee that
we have uh it's called Clea and U uh the
academic Administration the proos the
college
Deans
and like I mentioned so we've I formed a
a a task force which included Librarians
um and also since we a merged
organization I actually had my IT
project manager lead this project
because we needed strong strong project
management in this and so she was a real
champion of not just project management
but also managing the change on campus
so the two most important things we
learned through this process was change
management and project management I
think everything else kind of if you
have those foundations everything else
kind of falls into
place uh and we start this actually
process believe it or not in the spring
of 2020 uh as the world was shutting
down but we kind of continue to keep our
going and we had faculty U
representation on our on our task
force and it was kind of really um
meeting with all different groups
answering questions because there so
much um misconception about what we were
doing oh this is about you're cutting
things uh I'm not going to have access
to what I need so once we kind of
addressed all those questions I think
the conversation really changed I mean I
remember going to um a a meeting of the
of the uh Department chairs for the
College of Arts and Sciences there about
45 of those and after we presented what
we were doing actually people started
clapping yes we all behind you and and
why we doing this and and so um and one
of the things I said early on which
really kind of made a difference was we
are not taking access
away you're still going to have access
to what you have today and you'll have
access to more things you we don't have
access to today because we don't have
the resources to get them and you might
not have immediate access but you'll
have it in a in a short time frame I
think kind of really um debunking some
of those myths that people have about
when you say you're taking something
away I think that really shifted the
conversation and then got the faculty by
and and um and I think you probably read
in the in in the in the write up that
spark did we when we kind of made the
change in January um of 23 I was
expecting like my email box is going to
blow up it's been over two years and I
haven't received a single email from any
faculty member saying what what we did
was not
right I'll stop
there the great note to end on uh
already seeing themes emerging um yeah
Stephanie I'd like to go next
yes for us uh the the whole Adventure
was driven by a large budget guts uh on
our acquisition budget uh the cut was of
$1.75
million uh out of an acquisition budget
of 10 million at that time so and it's
10 years ago it's a long story it goes
back in time uh so it forced us to
consider drastic drastic measures uh so
we decided to attack to those very heavy
piece of our budget the big the big
deals um we began our first unbundling
uh of Wy uh only because uh it was the
next to be re renewed uh and we did an
analysis of W's title inspired by the
California Digital Library methodology
at that time TW 10 years 10 years ago
and and we we we broke the first deal
but we soon received very thoughtful
comments from our work Comm
not not about the the idea of missing
title but about the
methodology that was the the the main
focus um they were supportive of of big
deals on on bundling idea so what we did
is to to gather a task force of those
faculty that have been the more critics
of our
methodology uh there were faculty
members students uh and we we created
group that group to improve the
methodology and we had the help of a a
library school and bibliometric uh
teacher V arier who now holds the new uh
UNESCO chair of open science so it was
pretty strong committee it was really
interesting to hear them think think
about the methodology so they did
recommendation and I may talk about
those recommendation later to enhance
and adapt the methodology and we built a
powerful analytical Tool uh with where
we could find usage stats citation
results of a survey that we did
availability through of of those sources
through uh OA uh sources or or archive
that we have B uh so at the end uh uh we
ident out of a total collection of
50,000 uh journals we identified
five thousand titles that were really
essential for our community so 10% only
and it really gives us a interesting
idea of where we we add to with with
which uh um commercial publisher we had
to focus uh and then we established a
formula um uh to identify the fair price
we were going to uh uh attribute to each
of the big deals so it was the amount
that we were going to to be that was
going to be available to each of the
negotiations so at the end to to be
rapid at the end we unbundled um Wy
Springer Taylor and
Francis uh and uh we only do did a title
by title with them for some essential
title and for all I would say all the
other big deals and small deals we
renegotiated everything with the
methodology with the results with the
Dem mind of this fair price we
attributed to each of the the the sour
sources so it was really
intensive for our acquisition team but
we have been able to uh to to to have to
to reach the amount of of budget cuts
that we had to do I will say
there wonderful uh thank you m so much
Stephanie and uh uh Chris if you want to
go next for for MIT to round us out yeah
thanks so much and and thanks to to
sparkk and acrl for hosting this and and
uh it's really great to hear other
people's experience and I really
appreciate uh Ann and others who who who
kind of lead with local context matters
so much and um uh yeah I'm really struck
a new by that our local context at MIT
oh I'm Chris Berg I'm the director of
libraries at MIT um our local context at
MIT is different in a lot of ways um one
particular way uh that sort of is
um uh sort of an overarching theme that
impacts the story that that I'm going to
tell today is um that MIT is a place
that has as an institution has a long
history of supporting open and having
openness as like a core part of the
culture like you know we are one of the
birthplaces of Open Source software open
course whereare you know started 20 some
odd years ago one of the first all
campus OA polic IES in the US so like
long long history of open that is really
a part of the culture um so so the story
that I want to talk about for us is very
specific to our decision in June 2020 to
to cease negotiations with ele and since
June of 2020 we have had no journals
contract with
ele so that's it's not an un we've
unbundled some other things we've you
know tried to avoid big deals for quite
some time um up until June 2020 we had a
TI already had a titleby tile deal with
El and in June 2020 after trying very
hard to negotiate with them uh we're not
able to reach an agreement um and walked
away that was prompted not by budget
considerations again another really
difference here um it was prompted by um
a set of
principles that grew out of a process
that was several years long so and and
I'm not even going to tell the whole
story because that'll take too long but
let's start in 2019 in
2019 uh a group uh an Institute Wide
Open Access task force um released a set
of recommendations one of which was that
the that MIT should develop a set of
principles to be ratified by The Faculty
about open scholarship now it turns out
ratifying a set of principles at The
Faculty level I don't know how that
would work on your campus it's really
hard and we never got around to that TR
true story but we did in the committee
on the libraries decide to take that to
a very specific level and develop what a
set of principles for negotiating with
commercial Publishers and that's the MIT
framework that many of you endorsed at
the time thank you very much and may
well be uh familiar with um and that
that set of
principles um you know
many sort of grounded in this idea that
uh a principle that authors should not
have to give up rights to their own work
authors should not have to wave their
own institutions policies or funer
policies in order to publish right so
there were some real very clear
principles in that framework um uh that
supported
you know a move towards more openness um
in scholar Communications and for the
Publications coming out of MIT and we
started there again wasn't about budget
for us um it was about the fact that
again there's there was there was a
fairly widespread consensus across
campus that open is
good um we had an open access policy and
and a a task force that was tasked with
you know coming up with recommendations
about how we could be even more open
right and so so the framework and then
the that being the lever to walk away
from ele was about where does the where
does the Institute have um uh an a lever
with Publishers to make a difference
that isn't scholar by scholar like the
only place that MIT is at the table with
the Publishers is through the
library and so in addition you know
instead of or in addition to negotiating
prices for reading that's where we can
start to talk about principles for
publication as well and so that's so
okay long story short and I the the
other questions will get there but it
was a year long yearslong process of
developing these principles in
collaborate close collaboration with
faculty and others socializing those
principles getting buy in for those
principles uh collecting allies and
building Coalition across campus and
support of the uh the institution so
that by the time we got to the point
where it was clear that El was not going
to offer a contract that met the
principles all I had to do I mean all I
had to do at that point we just had to
say look they wouldn't they wouldn't
meet these principles and here where
they fell short
and you know I had faculty and and
leaders Across The Institute said well
you got to stick to your
principles so that's our story it's a
little different but a lot of
similarities as well and and like
an uh you know ain's here to keep me
honest and to fill in some details at
certain points um but truly there were
so many people across the libraries and
across MIT put in years of work lots and
lots of work and frankly um who who uh
it displayed a significant amount of
Bravery in taking this stance and so big
shout out to that to to everyone across
the libraries and The Institute who who
helped make this
happen thanks so much for those uh those
intros and on sort of that note of
appreciation too it was really an
impossible you know sort of choice on
like who to profile like what order you
sort of U you who to have join these
panels I mean I think we need to be
doing more of these but you I just want
to flag the cancellation tracker that I
mentioned at the top um you just also by
way of recognizing the other
institutions that have you sort of put
in the the difficult work here and also
have really valuable experiences to to
share so you know we'll uh dive into you
sort of a discussion with this panel but
just wanted to at the top make sure to
highlight you know the many many other
institutions many of whom are probably
here in the room um you that have this
kind of experience and have done this
this important um and sometimes
challenging work you know so already uh
sort of the theme of Faculty reactions
uh has come uh to the Forefront you know
pretty unsurprising uh I think but you
know speaking with many libraries there
are negotiations Community practiced uh
that are considering these moves or you
speaking to them before um they made the
decision to leave a deal or unbundle um
you the the reaction of faculty
potential reaction to a change like this
you frequently come up as you a barrier
uh for even proceeding um down down this
path uh you and I think and since Yukon
uh you know and now it's plans not just
to leave one or even a couple or a few
big deals but to systematically unbundle
from all of them uh uh I think it' be
great to start with you just to hear a
little bit more about um you know what
you've already started to share about
you sort of faculty's reaction to this
systematic move um you and sort of how
you got
there absolutely so um let me pull up my
notes here um as I said in my intro the
hardest piece is PR getting Buy in
getting people to understand what's
actually going on and I think that that
once you gain the support of
administration and I think it really
helps if you also include them in the
work that you do for example we had an
internal uh group that looked at the
Logistics but then an external group of
40 faculty who we pulled together the
Provost and I were co-hosts of this it
was called future of journals and we met
this was during um uh from December 2021
through March of 2021 um for like
multiple weeks maybe nine weeks once a
week we met and we had a a Google doc
where we just answered questions added
questions expanded on them in the
meetings but we had what I would call
Four Champions faculty champions from
across the University from Health
Sciences to uh to Medieval studies um
every single field and um we asked we
also had some post dos in the room and
all of my senior leadership team were ex
officios as well as our head of
Acquisitions and basically what we did
was we educated all of them about the
situation and then we asked them what
would be the parameters to make this
work for you and they basically came up
with two easy to find quick return that
was all they cared about if they could
find it easily through their own
Discovery that we already had in place
Google Scholar any of our databases and
they could get it within three minutes
they were fine with it and then at the
end of all of that after we' answered
all of their questions over those months
we held a vote can we do this project
and it was unanimous unanimous no
questions because we'd spent all that
time educating them hearing from them
teaching them about OA scholly
communication serials crisis every
single thing you could possibly imagine
and why we were doing it to save money
and one of the most powerful things the
Provo said was we don't have to do this
project but I have to find $4 million to
cut shall we cut your
department and that was a real that was
the Provo said that to the committee and
it was real eye openening like this is a
real thing this is going to happen and
so then um that was the hardest part
right but actually it was the easiest
part because we took the time to help
them understand the situation and then
those people became our Champions and
that was amazing so uh long story short
we did all the background work we found
article Galaxy scholar we got used unsub
we you know started on our project we
had open meetings we met with Deans we
met with administrators we met with any
department or school or college that
wanted us to meet with him the provos
got so excited he was demoing the
interaction and things it was like oh my
God the Provost is conducting
bibliographic instruction it was
hilarious but that buy in was phenomenal
right because as people would say why do
you need the provos well I don't choose
my budget the money comes from them I
don't really care what journals we
subscribe to if it all comes down to it
I'm not using them I know it's my
responsibility to provide provide them
with people but the limitation is the
budget and it comes from above so they
have to hold themselves
accountable so we also had uh an email
that many people myself our
Communications person head of
Acquisitions it was I think it was like
journals questions at yukon.edu um that
anyone could ask a question about
anything about the process I would say
we averaged one email a week every time
for like three weeks every time we
unbundled from another publisher and
there were only about five faculty of
all 9,000 or however many we have at
Yukon there were five faculty who were
angry as hell that's it five and we just
mostly what we said to them was here are
your colleagues they served on the
committee please talk to them
but also this is the situation we're
spending $400,000 where we used to spend
4 million or whatever the number is and
and it was hard to refute that so it was
really only five people because a lot of
times the seamless it was a seamless
switch over uh the dean of The Graduate
School um was talking to me he was
totally behind this process and we had
just uh canceled or unbundled from or
uncontracted from sage and uh he was
like so when are when is Sage on the
list and I said oh we did it last year
and he said I didn't even notice most
people and I think I think it was Pam
that said this um or Stephanie most
people didn't even notice that that that
because of the way we designed it it was
just another click on a citation that
you would
discover that would only show up if you
were faculty and so most people didn't
even know notice that we unbundled it
was all behind the scenes they were just
getting what they wanted when they
needed it plus instead of a three minute
turn around 97% of the time in 10
seconds it appears in your email in 10
seconds so how do you argue with that
you can't argue with it so I would say
making sure that you're getting people
what they need you find out the
parameters of what their requirements
are to do their work
well and then make it happen and make
sure you have talked to all the right
people and you have Champions I'm going
to stop
there amazing Stephanie I know uh
Montreal's experience was similar in a
way just in you know unbundling from a
number of uh deals relatively quick
succession um so one of you could go
next and sort of speaking to that that
faculty reaction component and managing
and preparing for it yes there's a lot
of similarities between the reaction of
my my communities and an's community
and I think it's because of the same
thing we put a lot of energy in our
communication so we we really we uh we
we did all we can to mobilize The
Faculty
students head of departments University
officer we we wrote article to explain
what was happening why the all ecosystem
of of of of scly publication we did
meeting with with departments
presentation we built a
website uh we uh we were we explained
them the the oligopolistic situation we
were uh uh facing the the budget uh
situation we were facing and when we
were meeting with a faculty we were
always accompanied by V laier so it was
really uh giving a um scientific seal uh
at this administrative uh process so it
was really interesting in bringing the
conversation elsewhere elsewhere and
giving credibility
uh so globally a very good reaction and
I would say support what we were feeling
is they were proud to see our move they
were standing standing up by the
arrogance of Publishers and what it was
really interesting is that some of them
have been really active um students um
wrote to uh Springer for example they
wrote a letter to Springer our director
or University president he wrote to the
CEO of Wy uh and uh some of the faculty
uh wrote also to commercial Publishers
to to to tell them their intention not
to publish not to translate not to
review not to participate to to any of
their publishing process so for us it
was a it was the result of a good
understanding of what we were doing that
was and I would say uh when the faculty
were writing to publisher the phone rang
in my my office at that time not
necessarily when our principal wrote
so it was interesting so so I would say
a pretty good understanding but a lot of
work in communication plan
so thanks uh so much Stephanie that's
incredible uh about the students writing
uh and also separately just bless people
doing the reactions like it's so helpful
uh Chris uh do I know MIT sort of has a
a bit of a different path here that I
hope this will answer one of the first
questions to come in about what's the
difference between unbundling and going
out of contract right unbundling you
know being you know breaking up a big
deal but you know resubscribe or you
know breaking up a big deal but
resubscribing to maybe a core number of
titles or having some sort of a contract
with the publisher versus you know going
completely out of contract and having no
subscription you know no contract at all
with that that publisher which I know as
you said MIT is done with with El severe
uh which is a bit of a different thing
to M you manage I would imagine um so
it' be great if you could share you sort
of mit's experience and sort of uh
managing faculty's uh reaction and
supporting them through this yeah um so
much to say about this um you know first
the good news the bottom line up front
like we kept track of reactions like
either emails that we got or uh actually
Erin's team did an amazing job together
with our Communications folks of
tracking tweets about our
announcement um yeah so we so we kept
track of the feedback that we were
receiving and in analyzing it here's
bottom line up front 10 to one
positive so that's you know a bit of the
story that we like to tell um and it's
remained I don't think we've gotten a
negative uh any negative feedback about
being out of contract with ele in well
over a year I think um at least nothing
that's risen to my level so um and uh
you know some of I I think an point
about PR matters is is so important we
had um both the MIT news team uh you
know folks in the libraries who work on
communication um together with some key
faculty allies and the then um chair of
the faculty committee on the libraries
um we were putting out statements and
news articles right and left about why
we did this um and so that sort of you
know there was an a a way of sort of
going on the offense um and instead of
having to defend ourselves against
faculty concerns um and I mean we'll get
to this a little bit later I mean
honestly the the main concerns that we
had were about speed of of um access
because we did have um the deals we had
signed previously with ele all included
Perpetual access so it was just speed of
access to new things published from June
2020 afterwards um and I'm going to let
Aaron during another section talk about
how we solved that problem um but I I
wanted like there was one tweet that it
always stayed with me so if folks will
let me read it um this was not long
after we had gone out of contract a
graduate student uh at MIT tweeted this
I was mildly annoyed for being paid
paywalled at molecular cell due to MIT
cancelling the El severe contract but
then I remembered that I 100% support
this decision by the
libraries I mean you can't ask for
better right
like so and and that was somewhat
typical um and again it was all because
of the faculty and the library staff who
did the hard work of um really you know
educating and
explaining why we why we wanted to stick
by our principles and negotiating a
contract that would allow our authors to
maintain their own rights to their own
work and be able to follow the the
policies that the institution has um
there was there was a real sort of
almost du logic to that if you will
that's not an official
term so anyway can I just jump in for a
second so okay Nick um please just to
add that I think our Mark interest it's
super interesting to listen to you all
because I think our in some ways there's
much similarity and in some ways our
marketing strategy was slightly
different so to this out there as Chris
said because we were taking this sort of
principled argument we act our marketing
strategy also included the fact that we
were taking or not we the libraries but
in not being able to successfully get
elere to move they were losing access to
content right so it was less about
making it you know immediately
accessible it was like we're taking
we're for these reasons you no longer
have access to elare content and we had
to explain that and like an said I would
just Echo that too that we had a we had
some vocal opposition um but it was a
very small number of of people and so I
also think like it was hard particularly
when it was happening um and
particularly for our Frontline staff to
to put that in perspective and to
remember it's a very small number of
people with um strong opinions and many
many many other people also were aligned
with that that tweet that that put out
that Chris that Chris just read so
thinking a little bit about about how to
put the feedback in
perspective um I think was also an
important lesson uh as we went through
this
process I'm G to jump in one other thing
the other thing that helped us was um
when we did have a faculty who who had
you know real gripes about it um we were
often able to leverage our faculty
colleagues who were in their Department
in their discipline who could talk to
them personto person and say I too rely
on these journals and it's also a pain
for me but here's why I support it
instead of just a librarian talking
about principles this was you know we
could get not that there's anything
wrong with that I'm a big fan of
librarians talking about principles um
but but we had some faculty who were
willing to really get in the trenches
and have those
conversations thanks so much Chris and
Aaron and I think you sort of building
on this theme of uh uh you sort of
making this as easy as possible for
faculty you know to navigate the change
and access um par I know that was a
Hallmark of bucknell's uh you know
success um you know and sort of your
quick response times for getting faculty
access to articles U you after the
decision um to move away from the big
deal um so it' be great to to round out
the section just by hearing a little bit
more about your experience and sort of
giving faculty you know confidence that
you know they weren't losing access it
was just going to be arranged in a
different way or even to what you said
they might actually be gaining access to
more materials than they had otherwise
yeah so I I think um a lot of my
colleagues touched on this but I think
the one of the important things that we
always need to keep in mind is always
answer the question
why because a lot of times we kind of go
to the end result without kind of
defining the process and and and and the
why so in our case that was kind of the
most uh the Hallmark of why we doing
this was front and center of every
conversation um
the other thing that I uh said in in U a
job when we I formed the collection
development task force committee um one
of the first things I said at the
meeting
was we need to make sure we're not doing
this to faculty but we're doing it with
faculty and um and I think that was
important because we made them part of
the
process and if they felt it and and and
this happened uh over a year and and and
at every conversation they we could have
listened to them uh a chair of our
faculty committee presented at faculty
meetings and he was the one who was
presenting not me so faculty we hearing
from faculty but what was going on or
just giving an update of where we were
in the process so so it wasn't that we
announced it and then we did it a lot of
things were happening we held uh open
houses in the library uh we were on the
agenda for the faculty meetings we we
attended um uh the college meetings uh
Department chairs meetings so we have we
had a whole change management plan in
place as to how we can kind of address
this um and I think that really kind of
helped at the end of the day it it um I
mean I joke around now but we were all
nervous about the day this change happen
what's going to happen and it was a
non-event and and it was a nonevent
because of all the things we had been
doing for the past year
um and U so I think that's kind of an
important perspective to keep in mind is
because a lot of times we kind of want
to get to the end result but kind of
neglect the process and and and the
community engagement um in the mix um so
and in our case I think we had a really
strong project manager who was keeping
us on
track um and and saying okay here are
the things we need to do and um and here
are all the meetings that happen and
here is what we owe to the campus
community on on this St so like we had a
really forward-looking plan in place and
and she kept us on track and if um I
didn't do something she walked into my
office and told me so that I had to hear
the things that I I needed to do so I
think that's really uh an important
element um for us in in in the state I
kind of said at the beginning of my
remarks was we were not going to do it
to faculty we're going to do it with
faculty thanks so much and you one
question I just want to pull out right
here um that someone raised was you know
for institutions with subject Librarians
what role did they play um and I just
want to address that quickly before sort
of moving off because I think you know
how different institutions structured
managing faculty reaction doing faculty
Outreach could be really helpful for
folks um and so you know we'd love to
just quickly go around and hear you know
for you know any of you all uh any of
for any of the panelists um you know if
subject Librarians were involved you
know or if you know there's anything
that you'd share just about sort of how
this work was structured within the
library
briefly yeah
an so um we use subject Librarians only
to share information with their the fol
that they liaz with so if they we asked
people to um be available to answer
questions but um uh I will say that the
only population that really struggled
with this project was internally in the
library many of them subject Librarians
who just couldn't wrap their brain
around the fact that we weren't doing
Title by title that we weren't giving
faculty an option to weigh in on which
titles to um uh to resub subscribed to
or whatever and but we really just gave
them the role of being information
conduits about the project and about the
effect that it would have and we also
asked them to be ambassadors um and that
was mixed it was um that's a very honest
answer but it really was not a
cancellation project and that was hard
for internal people to get their minds
around it was just changing the way that
we pay for what people need
mut it had to happen to one of us on uh
this webcast or otherwise it wouldn't be
complete uh yeah thanks an Erin yeah we
formed us a very small committee and and
like par mentioned it was it was the
beginning of the pandemic so pandemic
you know March April May we ended our
subscription with elsir in June so we
did not actually have a big complex
project management cycle we were all
running on everybody was running on
fumes so we formed a small committee
that did include um subject uh that
included folks from our our liaison um
area and we um we they're doing much the
same thing sort of in the communication
role um we put together talking points
for the layons and we did we've done
that several times um along the way
because um we've we've been in a few
waves of negotiations with with El over
the years so you know the reason that we
didn't resubscribe the reason that we
didn't resubscribe you know or re come
come to a transformative agreement um so
we developed some talking points um for
the communication process the um subject
Librarians um some of them um were
exceptionally helpful in being the
mediator and communicating with uh with
their faculty um which was amazing and
wonderful some of them needed a little
bit more support in that you know
Endeavor and so the scholarly
Communications team tried to provide
support in that endeavor and we had a
sort of an escalation protocol up to
Chris if you know people were feeling
like they were not getting resolution
very few of them needed to go up to that
level um but we did try to provide
support and I think you know had we had
more time I think we would have been
able to do that more comprehensively and
better and that's a recommendation that
I might give to others um I also just
want to know I know the subject L ones
were specifically mentioned but I also
just want to point out the that the
circulation staff and the inter Library
loan staff are also the front are also
very much the front line and unlike the
subject Liaisons they don't have enough
background um to be really able to
defend the you know the decision of the
library or explain the decision explain
the decision of the library right um and
so that's another place you know I think
we we did we did well in the situation
that we were in um had could we do it if
we were to do it again I you know I
think we would think a little bit about
making sure that um that any you know
that that all of our Frontline staff are
able to talk to our users
so um I'll just kind of jump in our case
actually we had I had one of the uh
subject Librarians Co co-chair the
committee with our scholarly
Communications officers so they were
part of the process and then their uh
one of their roles was to kind of take
this back to the peers and talk to them
about and keeping them engaged
throughout the process so so I think
that uh format uh worked really well I
just want to go back to um one other
thing that uh I want to kind of really
highlight um
early on in the conversation when we
started talking to our faculty committee
about this we actually brought Nick and
from spark to come talk to the committee
to have an outside perspective and I
think that really helped them because
they were not just hearing that from us
but from from experts out who are
dealing working on this at a at a at a
scale of throughout with institutions
throughout the country so I think that
was a really also important element
about because they don't do this on a
daily Bas it right I mean I can send
them 10 articles they're not going to
read it but having uh Nick come to
actually a committee meeting and and
talk to what's happening um at the
national level and um and that was
really I think an important and um and a
critical time for Focus for the faculty
to really kind of okay yeah we're not
the only ones doing this so and and this
is um how others have done it in the
past and this is uh how we can going to
move forward with this project so I just
want to thank Nick for kind of being
part of that process as
well go ahead Stephanie uh I have
something to say uh in response to part
being uh way too kind uh but would love
to hear your answer on the subject
Leah's on uh librarian uh excuse me
subject libring question
first I was just going to add the the
role of of Li and librarian in our
University they they they were always
also um ambassadors so a communication
role but also as we uh we were in a
title by title selection they had the
final word uh so the selection have been
done with through the analysis of of
very important data but but also at the
end it was really the the the mediation
role or the last last call is there
something and is there some very few
title you you would add or or or would
with withdraw and they they had this
role but it was really thin as a role I
would say except by the this
communication uh they had to
do thanks Stephanie and I think you know
as a Core theme here it's really helpful
to see the different the way that
different institutional contexts you
know translates into different
strategies um you know here that that
work you best for um individual
institutions and and what that looked
like at Montreal um and you just to
parm's point um you know if you we can
be helpful s can be a resource um you
know for institutions that are planning
to unbundle and it's helpful to have
that kind of an outside presentation um
you know I think these are the kinds of
things that like for spark member
libraries you know this is exactly the
kind of support that we want to be
providing so please don't be shy about
reaching out if we can be helpful in
that way um you know I also think with
the drawing experience related to
unbundling there's probably a lot of
knowledge in the community that can you
know play a similar role um you know but
to the extent that it's you know helpful
to have an organization like Sparks
speak to like that kind of a group um
you know that those are ways we'd love
to to support members so please do U
reach out if we can be be helpful
there you know already unsurprisingly um
you sort of how each of you has provided
sort of continuity of access has already
come up and what we've talked about
already come up a bunch in the questions
uh in the chat
unsurprisingly um and I think it's one
of the things that I'm most excited to
be able to unpack a little bit more here
um and build on the profiles um you know
so I know somehow we're already um
two-thirds of the way through this
session um but you know would love to
just quickly go around and hear um you
know briefly you know sort of how each
of you approached um you know providing
access in L of a big deal um and sort of
you know what decisions you made at you
sort of which point points um and I
think we might unpack this a little bit
more after the first round but you know
just quickly going around to hear you
know how you all provided access outside
of a big deal um would be would be great
um so
uh uh maybe we can go in backwards order
that we just uh did the last question
Stephanie if you want to start if you
don't mind I'll be very fast because
it's so long ago there are new sources
and but our inter Library Rel Lo at a
fee so we we freed that first uh we we
bought a journal article archive and
also we promote OA article that were
available uh through um onpay wall apps
that we install uh in library PC though
that are the three main uh measures that
have been uh put for
us thanks Stephanie uh
par so for us that was a really
important El because we didn't know um
how much request we're going to get
right that was a big unknown so before
we even um
unbundled I created a a one-year
position for I inter Library loan I said
okay this is going to be dedicated to
kind of be dealing with some of the
unknowns that are going to come um and I
think that uh was really comforting to
The Faculty that we are actually not
just saying it we putting resources
behind supporting them them um and as a
year after that um that position was no
longer needed we we transitioned that
rooll into um a permanent role but u in
in a different way but I think it kind
of just showed that we were just we had
a plan in place that the day we turn the
switch off we have be putting the
infrastructure in place to support our
faculty and
students thanks uh eron do you want to
speak to MIT experience sure so we again
we were sort of we were trying to make
the point that ele was not cooperative
and we could not come to an agreement
because they were not cooperative and so
we did not initially uh have an
alternative access plan for Beyond
standard in our library loan we did um
as Stephanie just mentioned we sort of
we encouraged on pay wall we encouraged
we we put together a website that talked
that gave folks tips on how to find o OA
articles in Open Access repositories and
and we sort of made the point that LC is
making this difficult for you and this
will be to some extent this will now be
difficult for you um and then we started
getting complaints about turnaround of
inter Library loans so I should say that
um MIT also uses rapid so our turnaround
rapid our turnaround was you know
somewhere between hours and you know a
day like rapid turnaround for IL rapid
IL is great is fabulous too um but we
were hearing from that small vocal those
that small number of very vocal faculty
that waited an hour or two hours was not
um was not sufficient so um so like
Yukon we're now using reprints desk
about 18 months later uh we decided to
uh to get commercial document delivery
so we're using reference desk and
article Galaxy um the costs have come
nowhere near um the cost you know the
cost of our our previous subscription or
what we with a proposal that we got for
a transformative agreement um we uh it's
completely unmediated so it's no staff
time or effort there was you know some
setup but once we got through the setup
we decided in like December of 21 that
we were going to do this we were up for
the beginning of the semester in you
know in January of uh of 22 so it took
you know a couple weeks of evaluation
set up and testing but it's completely
unmediated we're providing access uh to
faculty staff and students alike you
know there's no anybody who puts in a
request gets their request
filled um and uh we're really that that
has reduced our complaints uh to on
turnaround to near to to near zero um I
will say that Chris and I have some
friendly disagreement about whether or
not we should have done that from the
GetGo or whether we should have waited
18 months um you know I I came into MIT
I started at MIT in May of 2020 and I
come from a technical services
background which is very focused has
always my my entire career has been
focused on how do we get everybody
everything they need as fast as they can
so you know I came with that that that
kind of background um I certainly
understand that for many organizations
you need to have a plan in place like
that um Chris makes a very compelling
argument that um we gave so I'm very
compelled by her argument that um we
that we demonstrated responsiveness to
the community they told us that IL was
not fast enough we solved we solved that
problem for them and um and therefore we
have built up other credibility um
throughout the Institute uh for you know
for demonstrating uh demonstrating
responsiveness and I'm happy to you know
if there's further Q&A at the end we can
talk a little bit we get lots of
questions about our article Galaxy re
princess setup so we can talk about that
more in depth specific questions and
I'll also put it out there that Mi we we
at MIT are very happy to talk to
individual libraries contemplating this
um and talking about um you know what
has worked for us and what we recommend
so and I see an saying the same thing so
I'm uh you know I'm happy to talk to
anybody our scom folks are happy to talk
to anybody our in library loan folks are
happy to talk to anyone um but it's been
very very low it's not it's not at all
staff intensive besides you know
managing the budget and paying attention
to the tracking of it there's no uh
there's no mediation in day-to-day
workflows so if I can jump in really
really quick to
um to expand a little bit on my uh my uh
support for us having waited to
implement a faster uh delivery system
until after we'd gotten some set of
complaints is tactically
um it meant that we did have like you
know if we got some complaints we could
respond if we started with the most
responsive and the quickest version of
access that we could possibly give them
which is I think what we have now then
if we got complaints about that which
you know some we we have heard from some
that seconds is too long um but if we
had started there we would have nowhere
to go except to
resubscribe and so this way we had a you
know we oh we heard you it hurt it hurt
more than you know is acceptable so you
know we can go with this one um so there
there was a a shrewdness to the tactics
there
absolutely totally totally get that and
the other thing I just wanted to throw
just to throw a little bit more data 90
so 92% of our articles come within a
minute and mentioned three seconds I so
that's within the minute um and 97% of
them arrive within an hour so um we uh
and I think I think an you may have said
this earlier too like it's really hard
even if we have faculty complaining now
it's really hard to say um that there's
you know that you that you can't wait a
minute and that that Savings of $2.5
million a year is not worth the the it's
worth a couple of basically a couple of
seconds right less friction it's been
helpful in that way too
I think I'm the only one left on this so
actually one of the requirements of the
future of journals committee was that
that be seamless that the project had to
be ready to go and perfect before we
actually rolled it out so we uh after
the internal committee I charged them
with either we'll hire uh programmers to
create a a seamless uh uh interface and
get people what they need when they need
it or we'll find somebody to do that for
us and so we found um reprints desk
which is article Galaxy scholar and we
insisted on single sign on and so we
actually worked with them very closely
for six to nine months as they
implemented single sign on and held off
on turning it on until that was ready to
go given that that's what the committee
had asked us to do to do this project so
we really tried to stay true to what we
promised them uh we also held off for a
year on ele the provos gave us a million
bucks for one year only to keep
subscribing to elsir as we worked out
the Kinks with Ela but I will say you uh
many of us know that Publishers will
give like a three-month buffer period
between when you end your contract and
when they actually turn off access so we
ended El in December I think it was 23
and they turned off access January 1 and
didn't tell us and so we had to do some
scrambling luckily AGS article Galaxy
scholar has tons of great information
and so um we were able to track the
number out of like 1500 articles 12 did
not arrive um within an hour um so you
know it was like whatever we've got the
stats at first we were like oh no we
need to get this information out there
we thought we would have time to let
people know no we had to do it right
away but that was the only glitch but I
would say um that was a requirement of
the committee I totally support Chris's
approach on that it's like help people
understand the reality of what this
actually means um to the work that you
do and I'm I I'm very much in support of
that but as I said we wanted to to
Really honor what what they did for us
that committee was so
great all right I'm strategizing how
we're going to get to all these
questions in the next 21 minutes uh
lightning rounds I think unsurprisingly
one of the things that's come up in uh
the questions that we're also planning
to touch on relates to to savings one of
the you sort of earlier questions to
come in um you know as some saying that
they're at a relatively small school
using zerob based budgeting so how did
you know um uh those who made this
change project demand um and budget for
document delivery um you know and so
sort of like to kind kind of combine
these questions of you know it' be you
know wonderful for you all just to sort
of speak a little bit more to you know
the savings that you know that the net
savings that you realize and sort of
what the trajectory has been uh over
over time um but also how you prepared
and the way that the this you know
questioner was was asking and sort of
you know projecting those savings and um
you know whether they were real you know
sort of at the beginning of the process
or only became real you know six months
a year in
anybody want to to jump on that one
first so um yeah I mean the savings are
real right and um I know
um and they stayed with within the
library so it wasn't that they we didn't
shift them back to the university so I
think that helped us kind of plan for
projects but also helped us kind of
undertake some some different
initiatives uh focused on the academics
and faculty and students um and so so I
I think that's one of the fears that a
lot of folks have is okay if if we do
this and and have these um substantial
savings is that going of money going to
go back to the university and then why
are we even doing this so I think that's
a conversation that I would encourage
you to have with your CFOs before you
can of do take this process and have a
clear understanding uh and a clear plan
in place that this is um uh you're doing
this um not to kind of shift this back
to the university budget but um
hopefully that you can keep it within
your libraries and and reinvest it in in
ways that going to me meet today's and
tomorrow's
needs yeah and I think you're about to J
in yeah what was the question again
exactly remind me sorry Fair it became
sprawling there uh well I was answering
one one of the things online
so yeah you could just sort of speak to
uh you the the savings that Yukon
realized uh you sort of whether they
sort of became real to the liary
immediately when you made the decision
or only you know over time and then um a
participant had asked a question about
uh you sort of how you projected demand
U you know for you know for the cost
associated with il document delivery um
you know into the future right um so of
course we didn't realize anything
immediately because there was a lot of
setup time and we did do it over time as
our contracts ended that's when we did
the negotiation with the Publishers so I
think we've done like two one or two
every year of the big bundles um Elsa
had a whole year actually two years all
to itself so it was very slow but the
cost realization I I have a chart um and
we are in year five and we've gone from
4 and a. half million to 2 and A5
million and in our Journal spend um how
we predicted I actually used the data
and information from the um uh UC system
uh El project when they you know just
kind of extrapolating from how much they
were spending on articles per campus to
provide that I just extrapolated based
on number of Faculty number of ILS
number of titles um and we found a
number that way but that's that's the
data that we used and the data that we
shared with um our faculty and it's been
pretty close I mean we did give it a big
margin 150 to
300K within the first year and the first
year we were at hundred something and
now we're close to 300 but we've also
done a lot more of the of the um ending
the contract
so I'll stop
there so I'll jump in um so uh Ed might
again finances weren't the driver for us
um so we knew when we canceled our
contract it
was what about a 2.7 million a year
contract um and uh we we sort of Walled
off that money and it's you know called
it the elere savings bucket to keep
track of it um to see if we would need
to use it for um IL you know special I
or whatever um eventually when we did um
contract with reprints desk and then pay
per article
um behind the scenes in the first year I
think we saved almost
90% it was about 300,000 total um and uh
I think in this second year of course
it's going up because there's more
content that's been published that we
don't have access to um but it's not
going up it's certainly not I think it's
about
400,000 this year right so substantial
substantial savings I mean the
the story you know basically the bottom
line here is the old deals even the
title by title deals that we used to
sign did not provide economies of scale
because we were buying stuff that nobody
read we knew that with our print books
we know that we have tons of books on
our shelves that nobody
reads people you know we were buying way
more than we needed at way higher of a
cost so I you know there's there's
substantial savings to be had um we are
looking and working with um the
administration here with uh some other
values aligned organizations and folks
across the US and
elsewhere um and some of our own faculty
to try and develop plans for how we
might reinvest those
savings into something that would uh
Advance the same principles that caused
us to walk away we're actually again
since we did didn't do it out of budget
concerns we're not super you know we're
not really um uh wedded to the idea that
we would funnel it back into some other
Library
operation um it's more about let's if we
you know we did this on principle let's
use the savings to advance those same
principles but the the I'll just kind of
add a Different Twist to this
conversation so after we did the lcbs so
we were going gr the other big deals um
so we we be using onab and really kind
of making data informed decision how we
going to do this so um I'm not going to
name names but there was another big
deal that we went with and we said okay
we going to we found similar savings
that we're going to
cut um and we when when we back went
back to
them they kind of just gave us a a over
25% discount because and let us keep
what we had because and and so I think
you can kind of use this this formula to
kind of negotiate in other ways um and
because they know that you've already
done this and you're serious about it um
and and that kind of helps with um other
negotiation that they going through the
process every
year I just want to add oh sorry sorry
go ahead I just saw Stephanie come on
you earlier wanted to the an back you
okay I I'll be really rapid uh we we
saved $1 million uh but the saving melt
in the sun with the years that's true so
at that time as we are in Title by title
selection uh we have been able to um to
lower the the the the cost of of
subscription and then we went back in in
the subscription uh but with the very
lower price so so we rewrite the
historical pricing we had with those uh
publisher and today we are in a
situation uh with uh in transform
transformative agreements and that type
of of big deals number number two that
will might be another session complete
session thinking about the impact of
those big deals so what I would say is
we are about to face the same crisis or
very difficult situation so hearing my
colleague is really inspiring my
director of collection is is freaky at
the other side of the phone but but but
really we we will have to do something
because what we're doing in reinvestment
we're putting putting money in OA
initiatives 2.5% of our acquisition
budget and we are uh we are trying to
find an interesting model and we're
we're work working in the province of
Quebec where I'm from in in Canada uh we
are working heavily uh were involved in
in a diamond OA um uh initiative with uh
that have been fund by by the province
of Quebec uh so for five year we're
building an infrastructure with Udi with
pkp with uh the 18 18 libraries of the
pro uh University libraries of the
province of Quebec with journals from
the province of Quebec so we're trying
to build something so the energy I want
to put is there trying to build an
alternative but I know we won't have
choice but to attack again uh those
those deals and to withdraw ourselves or
or we will see how we will manage it but
we want to uh just work uh other type of
solution uh that are really important
also because as you can hear I am a
French speaker so we have this French
literature uh scientific literature
local literature scientific literature
that we have to to protect and to
promote and and and all the literature
scientific literature but there is very
something very specific that have been
to to be protected and and promoted so
so it it's not easy even 10 years after
we will it it's a continuing process I
would I would say to end
it I just want to say I put this in the
chat um we also spent a significant
amount of onetime money which we have
because we had a lot of uh staff
turnover a significant amount in buying
back files so that that decreases the
amount of articles that you have to get
um uh oneon-one um and that was huge and
then um I'm trying to think of what the
other thing I said um so buying art uh
the other thing article Galaxy scholar
preferences Open Access articles so it
will provide the Open Access article
first and we've done the analysis and
it's anywhere from 30 to 40% of the
total articles so you're not actually
buying all of those articles it's
actually just finding the Open Access
ones and making them available which is
really really good um so just wanted to
add that
in yeah it's so important right now with
you know the OSP memo on the verge of um
you know coming into to force over the
the next year or so um certainly top of
mind for for us spark uh yeah eron would
love to hear from you I'm to Pivot
quickly to re yeah I was actually gonna
say exactly that so um so at MIT we had
we had I think first mentioned Perpetual
access to elere so we only lost you know
we we still had access to our pr2020
content but we we have been looking at
our reprint desk data to see what people
what years of publication people are
requesting so 50% in the last year 50%
of the requests were for Content
published this year year 25% was content
published one year ago and the other 25
was like the year before that or year
before that we don't have extensive
longitudinal data so take that for what
it's worth but what people are
requesting is current content so yes
being on the spark call I want to say
that we're really hopeful that with the
ostp memo that um more current content
is going to become open access without
embargo by default and then that will
actually fill a significant amount those
numbers that that just shared about the
the 30 to 40% you know we're hoping that
number will go up um and then uh and
then that will level out the cost so the
costs are increasing year every year the
longer we're in contract out of contract
but we're also hoping that that will get
mediated or mitigated by the by more
Open Access content being put forth out
immediately and I think that also
addresses a question that I saw in the
Q&A there are a couple questions in the
Q&A about um you know aren't the article
costs just going to spike and that is a
possibility that is absolutely a
possibility that the article cost could
just Spike um so we still need we still
need more Open Access content to be put
out in the world this doesn't solve for
that problem we're working on that you
know we we feel like we're working on
that problem too and we obviously really
appreciate Sparks uh work in that in
that
area thanks eron uh so I know now only
have seven minutes left uh but
reinvestment has come up quite a few
times also something that we wanted to
touch on so um you know I think it would
be really helpful for folks to hear you
just again briefly you sort of how each
of you are you sort of thinking about
deploying your savings I know that's
already sort of been touched on but you
just to tie this to another thing that
has come up in a a number of questions
and the that have been submitted um you
have have sort of raised you sort of how
your decision to unbundle or go off
contract um you know relates to your
about various types of Open Access
agreements that you might um enter into
like read and publish agreements or
other you know Open Access agreements so
you know would love to just quickly go
around sort of um you know learn a
little bit more from me you about you
know sort of whether there's a
reinvestment component to your savings
um um you know this other question sort
of how this work sits with other types
of um you know other strategies um like
U you know Open Access
agreements anyone want to first
there I I'll jump in on the
transformative agreement reading publish
kind of agreements um and Aon will
correct me because I'll get something
wrong um
but I think one one piece of our story
that we haven't told yet is that two
years in so in in summer of 2022 El
actually came back to us and said are
you sure don't you want to talk again um
maybe that's the part that we wouldn't
want on the recording sorry that was a
little snarky um
so we did talk to them again we we
reiterated the principles we whittel
down some of the principles and said
which ones were super important to us
and bottom line they came back and we
told them we were very clear with them
that we weren't interested in a standard
read and publish deal um part some of
the other principles of the MIT
framework have to do with equity in the
system and we think it's really as
important that everyone has access to
read without economic barriers that
people have access to par participate in
the scholarly conversation and to
publish their work without unnecessary
acade uh the monetary barriers um and uh
so we told them we don't you know that's
just not going to work for us and what
they came back with was a their basic
standard read and publish deal and pages
and pages of why it was a good deal and
we said no again um do we have some read
and publish deals with other uh vendors
yes we do um you know I'd be I'd be
lying if I said we haven't signed some
um we have signed some that move toward
that that move towards the framework
that show good faith in understanding
what we're asking for and and providing
some transparency around cost for
example um and other concessions around
um uh open access policy waivers and
things like that um but on the on the
issue of transformative agreements a
standard read and published deal um um
it not only is not um aligned with the
principles that MIT wants to stand for
but also we've done the analysis there
as well and bulk bulk payments by
libraries for apcs also gives no
economies of scale to an institution it
actually costs more because they price
it at the highest possible average and
they put these ceilings on the in the
deals and they're just not good deals
from our analysis
so that's not the reinvestment but I
think I already talked about what we're
doing run that that we're working to
find a way to reinvest our money um to
advance our principles so I'll stop
there thanks Chris anyone else want to
jump into build on Chris's
point about transformative agreement of
saving or saving savings transformative
agreements both yeah what I would what I
want I would say is here in Quebec and
and and probably in Canada also we are
going to
not reconsider but think about the
impacts of those transformative
agreement about the the accessibility
the the the diff the equity of access
same thing than Chris said a few uh
minutes ago uh and we we just look at
plan s in in Europe and they are going
to leave those type of agreement we
should Sweden have done the same thing
uh a lot of European countries are
considering to to leave that that type
of of initiative so why should would we
continue that I think and plan s has
documented pretty interesting results
about those transformative agreement
that they began in in 2018 in Canada we
began a little bit later so we have I
would say two two three years of
experiences so all I would say is we
should be inspired in in that area by by
the European and look at what they are
doing and why they it's PR pretty well
documented so uh we are going to to
consider going out or or work not not
and I don't think that transformative
agreement transform anything
so consider that we have to to find a a
plan s a plan a plan
T to to keep on continuing with
that thanks so much uh and or parum uh
and know we're running right up to the
the end but um want to make space if uh
there's anything else that you all would
like to share and respond to to this
point now I I think um so bnal has um an
open access policy since 2011 um for
faculty and um and so we are kind of
looking at ways now from the savings
that we've had how do we kind of
reinvest that um in really open access
initiatives on campus so so that is um
on our list um I I don't really kind of
we not at a place where we I can say
we've done these uh things but that is
one of the re reinvestment strategies
that that we have in place because um
Open Access is um we promote it with our
faculty we have a a policy for um like I
said we were one of the first small
liberal larts institution to adopt a
uh policy that the faculty actually The
Faculty adopted uh and so uh I I think
there's a lot more work to get be done
on that
front I think connecting uh this work to
an Institutional open access policy is
uh a good way uh to to start to come to
a close and I also uh just want to
respond you know there's a great
question in the chat which we didn't
have time to to address about you know
sort of is there any discussion about
libraries being the keepers of the
scolly record what cancelling Journal
means in that context um you know I
think you know as Aon said I think we
could have a whole discussion on that
but I'd say you know from my perspective
you know I hope what this does is help
to move towards an ultimately more
sustainable scholarly publishing
ecosystem that has um you know Library
Publishers has you know Community
government infrastructure that's really
at the core and that that's what you
know sort of libraries being The Keeper
of the scholly record in an open
environment um looks like um I wish we
had time to go back around to respond to
that question uh because I think it's
such an interesting one but I really
appreciate um you know the panelists
taking the time um to to join us I also
want to flag when this session closes
there will be a survey that's you know
not only like how the session was but
there are two questions there um ones
asking for feedback if there's you know
anything else that you would find
helpful in either considering um you
know leaving a big deal or considering
Investments um in some of the open
initiatives that we've discussed you you
can share your email address so we can
follow up with you there um uh you for
those resources and also if you have any
suggestions uh there'll be a place where
you can can add those so your responses
to the survey be be really helpful um so
thank you all so much uh thanks for
bearing with us trying to Sprint through
all the things I think we got to about
half of what the speaker prepared for uh
so thank you for all the preparation
some of which we got to um but I think
you know there's a lot that could come
out of this um including cluding the uh
strategic priorities working group of
our negotiations Community practices
interested in having a follow-up
discussion um building on the Forum um
you know particularly around the sort of
reinvestment um of savings component of
this um so be on the lookout for more on
that uh coming the near future um so
again just want to thank our fantastic
speakers once again uh and thank you all
so much for joining us uh this afternoon
take care everybody