all right so if you haven't figured it
out we're going to do something entirely
different now than everything that we've
heard about this afternoon which is
great because this is the last Talk of
the day so I I'm in the space section I
gather because I do astrochemistry
research and I'll talk a little bit
about that and about the applications of
this work specifically to my research
but the the work that I'm going to
present the new techniques that we have
developed are agnostic to the
application that you're working with
right and the real question is if you're
handed a bottle that contains an unknown
liquid in it how do you figure out
what's in that liquid right and that
sample could be from anywhere right it
doesn't necessarily have to be related
to space now I'm interested in that
bottle being the universe right I want
to figure out what molecules are out
there in space right but chemical
mixtures like this are ubiquitous and
they present a lot of problems to us
right so you can imagine trying to
figure out what is in the emissions
coming off of a Coal Fired power plant
right what's coming out of those Smoke
Stacks are are scrubbers working
appropriately are the technologies that
we have developed to make the uh
emissions from these things as
environmentally friendly as possible
actually working right you could design
a detector to measure carbon dioxide
that's not a problem that's not the
question at hand the question at hand is
what else is up there is it just carbon
dioxide right you can also ask the
question well what if you're dealing
with a spill right a waste tanker tips
over and dumps a whole bunch of organic
chemistry waste into a natural water
habitat right you scoop up a sample of
that you want to know what's there right
you want to figure out what's in that
sample that's polluting that environment
or even in the laboratory or in
industrial settings you're developing a
new pharmaceutical process a new
reaction scheme and you want to figure
out what side products are you making is
there something in there that's killing
your reaction is there something in
there that's poisoning your catalyst is
there's something in that that will
poison your patient right and in my case
of course I I'll I'll talk about this a
little bit just as the the interest
application here space right I'm an
astrochemist I want to figure out what
the chemical components are along the
entire process of forming stars and
planets so going all the way back to the
Big Bang which made all of the elements
uh the the hydrogen and the helium uh
that make up the universe those got
fused together in stars to make carbon
and nitrogen and oxygen and sulfur and
phosphorus right what's that process
look like what do the clouds of gas and
dust that are formed from those raw
elements look like what molecules are
made at different stages along the
process of forming stars and planets
right now popular television would have
you believe that we already have the
tools to do this all right so if this uh
media clip here works I'll show you a
clip from one of my favorite TV series
here bones uh that shows you how you
figure out what the chemical components
of a mixture are you just use the laser
l a s a r analysis
Suite uh let's see do we have
audio
maybe maybe not that's all right it'll
freeze frame right
there can we try
again nope apparently not all right so
what they're putting out here right and
it's going to pause right there
ohes all right we'll try one more time
it's a 2C
clipes yeah so apparently you take this
mixture and you put it in this machine
and 10 minutes later it tells you that
it contains
cardamum cardamum is not a molecule
right cardamum is a spice the flavor of
which is dominated by a dozen say
different specific flavor compounds that
maybe you could design something to
detect right but this is absolutely
insane now I have Cherry Picked a
terrible example here right there are
less insane examples in the shows where
they use a GC Mass Spec and they say it
contains this alcohol and this Esther
and this Ketone those are mildly more
realistic right but this is still the
realm of Science Fiction we don't have
the capability right now to robustly put
in a sample of anything you want and
have a machine tell you precisely what
is in it right
and that's what I want to actually work
toward we do have a number of powerful
analytical tools though right and most
of these are spectroscopically based so
the interaction of light with matter so
we have infrared spectroscopy infrared
spectroscopy tells us about the
vibrational motions of molecules so how
the carbons and hydrogens and oxygens
Bend and stretch with respect to one
another in a molecule these are distinct
fingerprints for those molecules they're
also distinctly um they group together
in uh very characteristic uh wavelength
ranges so the C double bond o stretch of
one molecule looks an awful lot like
that same stretch in another molecule
you get these characteristic modes which
can tell you something about the
chemical contents of your system right
you can also use techniques like NMR
right this is telling you something
about how the nuclear spins the actual
components of the atoms themselves are
interacting with one another how the
structure of that molecule is built up
you could of course use Mass
spectrometry which will tell you about
the mass of the molecules that are in
your sample as well as breaking those
molecules apart and telling you how they
fragment into smaller and smaller pieces
and there's actually a technology that's
been around for a while but it's only
now seeing some commercial application
uh and that is rotational spectroscopy
or what's being called microwave
rotational resonance this is the
signatures of the molecule that the the
molecules give off or absorb as they
rotate freely tumbling end over end in
space these also turn out to be um
highly distinct right they are unique
fingerprints for these molecules at
least in the gas phase now that's what
I'm going to be focusing on today I'm
going to tell you about analyses using
microwave spectroscopy because that's
what my lab here at MIT does all but the
techniques that I'm going to talk about
work for any of these other sorts of
analysis tools anything where you can
have a unique fingerprint for a molecule
that's in a database and you want to
match that to that same measurement in
the lab
we can use the machine learning tools
that we're developing here to do that so
what's the application here why am I
using rotational spectroscopy well as I
said I'm an astrochemist and
astrochemistry is the study of molecules
in space where they are how they got
there and what they are doing and I am
interested as I said in understanding
how chemistry evolves from The Big Bang
through the process of forming a
molecular cloud of gas and dust that
will eventually collapse down to form a
star that will eventually form planets
and those planets will be seated with
the raw organic materials for life that
at least on one example we know of
actually occurs and arises right and I
want to understand on a molecule by
molecule and reaction by reaction basis
how that happens and to do that I have
to know what molecules are in that
mixture at each different stage I have
to be able to look at the cloud and say
these 150 molecules are here that way I
can think about how they're reacting and
evolving and it turns out the way that
we do that is using rotational
spectroscopy 95% of molecules detected
in space are seen using their rotational
Spectrum which is why I do rotational
spectroscopy now I added a slide here
just while I was sitting over there a
few minutes ago because apparently it's
MIT and I'm allowed to show you
equations so I'm going to put an
equation up here I'm going to tell you
how a rotational Spectrum arises and
what it depends on uh don't worry this
the only equations in the entire talk
and they're really simple here right so
to first order
the frequencies of a molecule's
rotational Spectrum meaning the
frequencies of light that the molecule
gives off or absorbs as it rotates and
tumbles end overend in space is given by
2 * B * J + 1 so what are these well J
is just a quantum number it's an integer
or a half integer it's just a way of
keeping track of the actual uh quantum
mechanics that's happening here the
quantization of energy B is something
called the rotational constant right
this contains all of the unique
information about the molecule that
matters right so what's in the
rotational constant well a bunch of more
fundamental constants like Plank's
constant the speed of light the number
eight and this thing here I the moment
of inertia of the molecule which if you
think back to freshman physics is the
reduced mass times the separation of
those masses and if we're talking about
just two atoms here in this simple case
the reduced mass is M1 M2 over M1 +
M2 okay I'm done that's all of the
equation in the entire talk I think but
why did I put them up here well look
back at this set of equations that
determine the rotational spectrum of a
molecule what does it depend on it
depends on only two
things the masses in the molecule and
how they're arranged in space right and
that is it everything else is a
fundamental constant which means that
the rotational frequencies of a molecule
its Spectrum are uniquely determined by
the 3D structure of that molecule that
means that no two molecules by the laws
of physics can have the exact same
rotational Spectrum it is a unique
fingerprint right every molecule has a
unique Spectrum determined by its
structure so here's just a few different
random examples right acetic acid glycol
alahh and methyl formate here they all
have distinct spectral patterns in the
microwave region of the electromagnetic
spectrum and those allow us to then
uniquely identify these molecules if we
can measure those Spectra but to
highlight just how sensitive microwave
spectroscopy is to Atomic Structure I
don't even need to change the molecule
to get a different Spectrum I can change
a single Neutron if I change from carbon
12 to carbon 13 the entire rotational
spectrum of the molecule will change
because we've changed a mass one Neutron
is enough to change the Spectrum so
here's an actual spectrum of a source
taken in space uh Source in space that I
took with a rad radio telescope here and
what we're seeing are lines coming from
this molecule hc5n you can see on the
right hand side here the main line here
it's you know much much stronger going
off the graph here of one of the
transitions of this molecule but most of
these other lines are from transitions
of this molecule in its isotopically
substituted form so this one here is
from adding a neutron to the nitrogen
this one here is adding a neutron to
that carbon to that carbon to that
carbon that carbon that carbon and then
swapping that hydrogen out for a dyum
tiny changes in masses completely change
that Spectrum it makes it this unique
fingerprint and that means that we can
uniquely identify these if we can
measure the Spectrum in the laboratory
and compare it to our Spectrum wherever
we're working with in my case again
space so here's an actual example here
is a spectrum of a source called tmc1
I'll tell you a little bit more about
later taken with a radio telescope this
is an inter Cellar cloud and what you're
seeing here are signals in the radio
regime of molecule that have
rotated 450 light years away emitted
photons to relax and those photons have
traveled 450 light years passed through
all of that empty space through the
solar system through all of those
satellite constellations through the
atmosphere and landed in our tiny little
telescope for us to detect and now if we
want to know what we come from what they
come from we just overlay the spectrum
of a molecule we think is likely to be
there from the laboratory in this case
the cyanomethyl radical
ch2cn right we measure the Spectrum on
Earth that Spectrum doesn't change no
matter where you are in the universe
this is the only molecule in the
universe that could give this exact
pattern this exact set of lines because
any deviation from that exact molecule
would change where these lines lie so
that gives us this unique identification
right it tells us this molecule is
present in the mixture that is this
astrochemical
Cloud
so if we want to pick apart what's in
these mixtures at the moment we do this
almost entirely by hand right so what's
the process of analyzing one of these
chemical mixtures either in an
astronomical Source or we can take a
spectrum using our our instruments in
the lab here in the basement of MIT so
we take that Spectrum this one you can
actually automate to to an extent right
so here's an example of a spectrum from
uh a laboratory here on Earth this is
just a a discharge mixture where we blew
up some acetylene with some carbon
disulfide we made a whole bunch of lines
here right this contains hundreds of
different molecules this is the
rotational spectrum of every molecule in
the sample all emitting at us at once
now we need to pick apart what's in
there right what molecules are giving
rise to these signals well what we want
to do first is identify all of the known
components right identify the pieces of
spectrum that belong to molecules that
we have previously measured the lines
are in a database that pattern is known
to us and once that is sorted out then
we can focus on the unknown molecules
the new
things well the problem here is that
doing this for a trained PhD
spectroscopist this process H takes
somewhere between days and weeks for a
single Spectrum right to actually
painstakingly go through line by line
think about what might be there pull
them up from the database look analyze
and move on so it's a lengthy process
and if we actually want to identify the
unknown components this takes even more
work right this is a process that can
take months realistically to do because
we don't have those Spectra in a
database right what we have to do is use
our chemical intuition we have to think
about well these are the molecules that
are currently in the mixture the known
components what else might be there and
then go procure a sample of those
molecules put them in the instrument
measure its spectrum and then compare it
and see whether or not those signals are
present in the mixture or not a
painstaking process that involves a lot
of human interaction and so what we
wanted to do was try to bring Automation
and machine learning to bear on both of
these tasks to try to speed this process
up so most of what I'm going to focus on
today is this identification of known
components because this is essentially
what they do in Bones right you put in a
sample and it spits back out what the
components are that it knows about that
it has in a database and it does it
pretty much instantly it doesn't need
days or weeks of human intervention so
can we do this with machine learning
well we can actually do a lot of this
get close using standard conventional
practices so how might we do this well
well we could go line by line pull a
line out of our Spectrum fit a gaus into
it figure out what the center frequency
is and then just query a database of all
Spectra of all known molecules and find
the lines in that database that are
closest to the line in our Spectrum
right so say we have two molecules A and
B here clearly a is the better match
right it's right on that Center
frequency we could assign that no
problem this is this is Trivial this is
already done with traditional uh
computational approaches now we actually
know more from rotational spectroscopy
than just one line we know the whole
pattern has to be there right so then we
could go and expand out and say well if
that line belongs there well do other
lines of that molecule also show up
right so in the top we have molecule C
that has all three pieces of its
Spectrum showing up exactly where
they're supposed to be in the relative
intensity ordering that they're supposed
to have whereas in the bottom well
molecule D here aligns with this one
really well but if this was actually the
correct assignment there'd be another
line over here and we don't see anything
in the Spectrum right so molecule D
probably not there this is also
something that can be done with
traditional Computing but here's the
problem I haven't told you about one
other important factor and that's
experimental error right the line
frequencies in these databases have
errors associated with them because we
measured them in the laboratory there is
some uncertainty so here's a more
realistic scenario I have a line from
the laboratory and it turns out there's
five different lines in the datab atase
from five different molecules all of
which agree with my measured frequency
within the
error now what do I do all right the
automated assignment algorithm would say
well I'm just going to pick the one
that's closest in frequency and move on
with my
life but that might not necessarily be
the right approach right and in fact a
lot of the time it is not and this is
where the hum has to come into play
right using what we call chemical
intuition now it's the last Talk of the
day and everybody is sleep so we're
going to do an interactive session here
all right so I'm going to tell you you
all have chemical intuition whether you
know it or not even if you haven't taken
chemistry since high school right
so here's a mixture I'm going to tell
you that these six molecules are known
to be present in a mixture right you've
done an analysis you know for certain
that they're there and now you're trying
to decide between two different possible
additional components that came up from
your analysis right is parole or is
vinyl alcohol more likely to be a
component of this mixture all right so
think about it for a second and then
we're going to
vote all right hands up if we think
parole is the more likely component of
this
mixture and for vinyl
alcohol
excellent why I didn't actually tell you
what any of these molecules were in fact
I didn't even label what the atoms were
now look the black one is carbon the
white one is hydrogen the red one here
is oxygen and the blue one is nitrogen
fine you didn't even need to know that
right because humans are really good at
pattern recognition right you either
consciously or not saw this o group over
here this alcohol group and said I see
that four other times up here I don't
see any ring systems in here right and
uh I see mainly two or three carbons so
this one is just a better match right
that is the same same kind of intuition
that we have as chemists of course I
would look at this and think alcohol
instead of just looking at the
structures but clearly just looking at
the structure
works that's something computers are
pretty good at right just looking at
structures and finding patterns all
right let's do one other one here it's
slightly trickier here's another mixture
six things right this time it's all
carbon and hydrogen I want you to decide
between decane here and cyclobutane
here think about for a
second hands up for
decane all right hands up for
cyclobutane all right that's about a
50/50 split and that's intentional these
are much closer right now if I had to
choose I'd choose the cyclobutane here
only because there is another ringed
system in that mixture already right
there's the three ring system up there
and most of what I have here have small
number of carbons but these are much
closer and much more similar to each
other than these right and there's
probably other dimensions here that my
chemical intuition is not like
distinctly identifying here right sort
of uh subliminal things that I'm just
sort of thinking about as I go through
that so what we want to do is we want to
be able to analyze an actual mixture and
apply chemical intuition to figure out
what the most likely choice is so if I
now tell you that this line from this
previous one came from a reaction
mixture that contained Benzene and
methyl cyanide here I you can identify
immediately what the correct carrier of
this line is it's Beno n trial B up
there on the right yeah that is again
chemical intuition so how do we train a
computer to do that right traditional
Computing methods for Loops logic gates
cannot do this right it's just not
possible to write a complex enough
algorithm to sort out chemical intuition
in this way so instead we're going to
use a machine learning approach to to
teach a computer to have some chemical
intuition so how are we going to do that
well we're going to do that by teaching
the computer the language of molecules
so we all did the recognition here by
looking at pictures right and computers
are fine at image recognition but
they're much better at working with text
right so turns out we can represent
molecules by unique strings called uh
smile strings or selfie strings these
are two different ways to do this right
the these are unique representations of
this molecule that encode encode the
elemental uh structure the composition
of the molecule and how they're bonded
together right so this actually makes up
if you think about it in terms of a
language right uh letters inside words
that make up a sentence that is the
molecule right so this is fine so what
we're going to do is we're going to use
natural language processing algorithms
to treat the structure of molecules as
sentences as language so we package all
of this stuff up and then we run it
through something called an autoencoder
here right the details of which don't
matter there's a bunch of these
different things here two of the most
common ones to use here are moltu and
viit gay uh these are again natural
language processing algorithms the same
sort of things that help Siri and Alexa
process your speech and turn it into
something meaningful and what it turns
out at the end is a vector
representation of the molecule right it
learns the language of molecules and it
says can represent this molecule as a
string of numbers those numbers
represent everything the computer has
learned about that molecule it's
position in chemical space you might say
right now these vectors can be dozens or
hundreds of Dimensions long so chemical
space can be dozens or hundreds of
Dimensions large but we can represent
then every single molecule as a position
in chemical Space by one of these
vectors and that means that molecules
that are chemical Al similar that the
computer has learned are chemically
similar should be nearby in chemical
Vector space so we could just look at
the distance between these vectors and
so it actually works right so if we
start with Benzene we can look at the
distance from benzon nitri it's not that
far away but it is going to be quite a
distance in Vector space from glycine or
from this travesty over here which
includes sulfur and multiple oxygen
atoms on there right so it gives us a
numerical way to represent how closely
related in chem space these molecules
are to one another now what we want to
do is we actually want to graph that we
want to represent areas of chemical
space that are the most important for
the mixture at hand right and so we do
that by constructing an actual graph
where the nodes on the graph represent
all of the molecules that we could
possibly want to consider and they are
spaced so that molecules that are
similar to one another are very close by
we then connect those nodes to one
another so that molecules can share
important
so if we know that an area of chemical
space is important because molecules
have been detected in our mixture that
means that other molecules that are
nearby in chemical space should also be
important and the size of the nodes is
going to represent the relative
importance right so these graphs that we
built so far are hundreds of thousands
to millions of molecules large we just
scrape databases of all molecules known
to or dreamt of by Humanity in code them
and generate a graph so how does this
actually work for us well I can look at
a small portion of this graph here and
there are actually tiny little dots here
representing the nodes that we start out
at none of them have any weight right
the molecules that are close enough to
each other in chemical space are
connected by these conduits that allow
them to share importance and what we do
is we say well maybe we know something
about our mixture maybe we know we
started with Benzene and furan so we
give a lot of weight to those nodes to
start with and then we let the network
relax we let weight from these nodes get
shared with the other nodes that are
connected with with it and then those
nodes that are connected with it share
their weight at a lesser and lesser
degree until the whole network has
burned in we run it thousands of
iterations until the network stops
changing until we've built a graph that
represents what our mixture looks like
in chemical space and this is going to
be our chemical intuition because we
know that things that are nearby in this
graph are chemically similar and the
computer can do this so how does it
actually work in practice well here's a
spectrum that we've taken a rotational
Spectrum in the laboratory we run a peak
finding algorithm this is instantaneous
traditional Computing to find all of the
lines their frequencies and intensities
and then we go line by line we pick the
strongest one so 8315 we query a
database and say these are all of the
molecules that have a transition in the
database within the error this is the
point where a human would look at them
and try to make a chemical intuition
assessment but now we don't have to now
we just ask our graph what is the
relative weights of these three
different molecules in chemical space
and then we can apply traditional
scaling metrics to that how close is
that line match in frequency to our
measured line right and we can apply
those intensity matches as well right
are there other lines that should be
present that are or are not and past
that if any of these molecules reach a
certain threshold well we assign the
highest molecule score to be present in
the
mixture but this is great now we know
something else about our mixture we can
feed that back into the graph and we
update the graph again because because
now we have more information about
what's there we've evolved our chemical
intuition and then we go back to the
next line and we repeat this over and
over and over and over and every time we
add a new molecule we recheck every
prior assignment so that we make sure
that what we know at the end matches
what we knew at the beginning right so
we are always checking for prior errors
so how does this actually work well we
were lucky we have colleagues up at
Harvard that ran a number of mixture
experiments using microwave spectroscopy
that we weren't involved in which was
great so they had huge data sets
hundreds of lines hundreds of species
they had gone through the painstaking
process of manually assigning all of
them weeks and weeks and weeks of humans
looking at this data so we knew the
correct answer and we fed this algorithm
which we call a maze here because that's
what my graduate student wanted to call
it right that information and said
assign these mixture components so we
did three different mixtures one where
they just blew up Benzene on its own
this generated 406 signals in their
range of interest and a maze managed to
assign it with 97%
accuracy this is better than the human
spectroscopist did we corrected
misassignments the human made we went
back and looked at what the machine
suggested and the Machine was correct
more often than not this took a human
weeks this took the computer 14 minutes
right orders of magnitude Improvement in
the speed and it wasn't just a fluke
there were also data sets here we blew
up Benzene with nitrogen and Benzene
with oxygen and came out with even
higher degrees of accuracy it turns out
if you have more and more signals it's
harder and harder to make mistakes right
we're approaching perfect accuracy here
and we actually understand why the
misassignments it's being made are being
made right and we're able to do it here
in at most 29 minutes in fact uh you
know we're not computer programmers this
is a chemistry graduate student and
chemistry professor we've made a few
improvements to the code and we can get
this down to about 10 minutes now for
one of them um but if we had an actual
computer scientist on this we could get
it down much faster right but weeks to
minutes
right it's incredibly good and it's
incredibly accurate right and this
actually is now doing what you see in
CSI or bones you put a sample into an
instrument you take the microwave
spectrum and you feed it into the
algorithm and it assigns the components
right as long as they are known as long
as they are in a database so in my last
few minutes I want to talk about what
happens here on this second portion
iding unknown components this is a much
harder question right how do we figure
out what's there when we don't know
what's there unknown unknowns well it
turns out we can actually use our graph
our knowledge of chemical space now that
we've built up to make highly informed
suggestions about what might be there
for us to look at really really reduce
that time and human intervention it
takes to think about the problem so this
is where I'll give you an example from
my own research again I said uh
previously I looked at this Source
called tmc1 This is a cold Dark Cloud 10
degrees above absolute zero of gas and
dust in the constellation of Taurus this
is a place that stars will eventually
form but they haven't started yet and I
use the green Bank telescope here in
West Virginia to measure its spectrum
and this is the Spectrum we got back out
I challenge you to find a difference
between this spectrum and the one in the
laboratory they look very similar
because they are the same it's a
chemical mixture and this is the
rotational spectrum of all the molecules
in it so what we did was we fed this
spectrum to a maze and we asked it to
assign almost everything in it we
tricked it a little bit we only let it
assign the 200 or so strongest signals
and didn't let it operate on some of the
weaker ones and we also intentionally
withheld a number of molecules we knew
to be present we just made it think they
weren't in the database we removed them
right so they were fake
unknowns so this worked really well it
again about 98% accuracy nailed all of
the things that were there did it in
about about 10 minutes but then we asked
it well you have a graph at the end you
can rank based on your chemical
intuition what other molecules are
likely to be present and so what we did
was we looked at all of the molecules we
withheld our graph had 300,000 species
in it and we wanted to know what was the
rank the suggestion of all of the
molecules we knew to be present but we
had
withheld well it ranked one of them
number two as the second most likely
molecule to be out there based on its
intuition and the worst one was hanging
out here down in the bottom at number 92
it had no knowledge of the spectroscopy
of these molecules we fed it nothing
about our chemical intuition it just
said out of the 300,000 molecules in
this network these molecules are in the
top 100 and these are species we all
know to be we know already are present
in this Source we know the correct
answer so it's doing an incredible good
job at narrowing down the range of
inquiry that we have to use to do this
search for unknown components right now
of course we can think can we then feed
that into some other sort of machine
Learning Network and generate molecules
or have it automatically run experiments
and that's where we're going next right
but already this is a huge Improvement
in the amount of time it takes to do
this unknown component
analysis so I'll just wrap up here by
saying that okay we're never going to
actually measure and identify card and
and Tamarind in here right that's
that's a pie in the sky dream but we
actually are at the point where we can
feed a maze a spectrum and it can return
in minutes the actual chemical
components with incredibly high accuracy
and in fact better than a human
scientist could actually do uh so I'll
wrap up there by acknowledging my group
and especially Zack freed here graduate
student uh who is now in his fourth year
who did basically all of the work for
this he's absolutely incredible um
funding sources and how you can get in
touch with me online if you want and I'm
happy to answer any questions you might
have thanks for sticking to the end of
the
[Applause]
day any questions from the
audience and if all you want to do is go
to the reception I won't be offended
if you're doing spectral why don't you
have to do the red shift to do the
comparisons so for Interstellar sources
you do have to correct for the red shift
that is absolutely true um and so what
we do I mean just in general is that you
observe carbon monoxide it's the second
most abundant molecule in the universe
has an incredibly well-known and
Incredibly sparse rotational Spectrum it
is always the strongest line in there so
we go look in the frequency range where
it's going to be because we can
generally guess what the Doppler shift
will be in the regions of our galaxy
find that line see how much it shifted
by and then assume that all the other
gas is moving by that amount too that
gets Us close enough that we can then
dither around and identify the last ones
um that's actually one of Zach's most
recent innovations that was also
something we had to do manually that
Zach can now use machine learning tools
to do automatically um so this is uh
something that we're going to to work
with the national radio astronomy
Observatory to incorporate into the data
products that the NSF facilities provide
to to astronomers to make this
determination of Doppler shift
automatic thanks um what is your
research more focused on or your
personal interest is it capabilities of
spacecraft forms of life uh the you know
composition of surfaces Etc composition
of inter Cellar clouds that's the big
one um so this cold Dark Cloud of gas
and dust tmc1 um this is where a star
will eventually form so this is a we we
think representing the kinds of material
that our solar system formed out of
billions of years ago um it turns out
that based on a bunch of circumstantial
evidence there's strong uh strong
indications that about a quarter of all
carbon in the universe is in the form of
what are called polycyclic aromatic
hydrocarbons they're these ringed
molecules like Benzene but with many
many more Rings fused together and we've
had strong evidence for that but
circumstantial uh since the 1980s in the
infrared uh and the discovery that my
group made a few years ago was that
using rotational spectroscopy we have
detected individual PHS for the very
first time in this cold Dark Cloud tmc1
confirming that yes these molecules are
present they carry an incredible amount
of the carbon but one of the really cool
things is that the phes that we're
seeing In This Cloud at 10 Kelvin
particularly two of them uh called
napthalene and Pyne they're the same
phes that were recently detected um by a
sample return mission to asteroid ryugu
in our own solar system sent out a
spacecraft picked up a sample of this
asteroid brought it back analyzed it
here on Earth and they found napthalene
and pyrene and in fact the isotopic
analysis here on Earth indicated that
napthalene and pyrene formed at 10
Kelvin right which I think is incredibly
cool it tells us that the chemistry
that's happening in this cold Dark Cloud
before the star even turns on is
probably preserved to a degree
throughout the entire incredibly violent
process of forming a star and forming
planets it also tells us that the
chemistry of our solar system was
probably set in no small part by the
chemistry occurring at 10 Kelvin in that
cold Cloud that we formed from right one
of these direct links and because ph's
are so abundant that means that they're
carrying a huge amount of the carbon the
carbon that makes up us right that is
essential for life so that's my primary
interest is figuring out what these
other carbon bearing molecules are out
there and how they evolve alongside this
process of forming stars and
planets any
questions just one last one and we can
take it offline if you need um are there
any other data cleaning processes you
have to do that are major um that you'd
like to talk about yeah so it depends on
where you got your data source from so
if you're in the laboratory one of the
biggest things is instrumental artifacts
right so our instruments don't always
produce a clean Spectrum you can get
Spurs mixing in from different frequency
sources whether or not your frequency
source is pure or not um contaminants in
your actual chamber leftovers from
previous experiments and those sorts of
things again we can do with comp
traditional computational approaches we
can write some logic gates to remove
those the astronomical data is much
harder to clean right and the problem is
because in a laboratory we can very
precisely control the conditions that
we're under in space we can't do
anything all we can do is passively
watch and we get everything along that
line of sight to us and our source so if
there are other intervening clouds
between us and there which happens
sometimes you have multiple Doppler
shifts right so you see multiple lines
of the same molecule all overlapping on
one another right if there's actually a
star there some of the material is being
accreted by the star and so depending on
the orientation that you're seeing it
you'll get these weird tail tailes in
Doppler shift space where you're seeing
the infall of the material as it's
pulled onto the star that can cause
problems you can also get weird
absorption features from molecules at
different temperatures between you and
your Source all of these things are
challenging to clean out um but they are
part of the process and and again part
of the algorithms that that Zach is
putting together for that it's much
easier if you have it here on Earth in
the laboratory
okay thank you very much professor
[Applause]