Welcome everyone. Uh my name is Adriana
Mats Neves and I have the distinct
pleasure of uh welcoming you to the
Renee Salazar speaker series. Um we are
joined by Felix Moronta Barios today and
three of our uh cohort members from the
BSSP program, Maggie, Jada, and Marissa
who will be facilitating this
conversation. Before we kick off, I just
want to give you a bit of a uh
introduction as to what the Renee
Salazar speaker series is meant to do.
Um it's actually meant to highlight
researchers from within different
scientific paths and and disciplines
just so we can learn more about our
fellow brothers and sisters in science.
Uh foster collaborations amongst uh high
level researchers and younger
researchers like we're going to see
today. Highlight role models from varied
personal and professional background
experiences. promote promote uh
opportunities to network and
opportunities to do research. So we hope
that you have a very engaging discussion
and conversation today. Um Latin X at
Broad specifically has the mission of
building community amongst broadies and
offering opportunities for connections,
learnings and belongings. We have a very
vast uh calendar of events especially
for Hispanic Heritage Month coming out.
So please feel free to reach out to me
directly or anybody on the steering
committee if you want to get involved
with that. And without further ado, I
have the distinct pleasure of
introducing Felix Moronavario's PhD who
is a senior program assistant in the
regulatory science group at the
international center for genetic
engineering and biotechnology
ICGB where he supports uh building and
policy development in biosafety,
biocurity and the governance of emerging
biotechnologies including gene drives
and synthetic biology with a strong
focus of advancing science informed
regulation and responsible innovation.
Particularly in the global south, Felix
contributes to international initiatives
that strengthen regulatory frameworks
and promote equitable access to
biotechnology. In addition to his role
at ICGB, Felix served as co-chair of the
global young academy for the 2023 2024
term, leading global efforts to amplify
the voice of young scientists in science
diplomacy, policy, and education. He has
been active in international advisory
panels including the World Health
Organization's working group on gene
drive research and has collaborated with
UNESCO and the interamerican institute
for cooperation on agriculture on issues
related to biotechnology governance.
Fedelix holds a degree from the central
university of Venezuela and earned his
PhD in in biology from the University of
Alagante Aleante in Spain. He is
passionate about science communication,
public engagement and the role of
sustainable science development. Thank
you so much for being here FedEx.
>> Oh thank thank you Adriana for that
fantastic introduction. Thank you so
much and thank you so much for the
entire team for the invitation. It's an
honor to be here and to talk with the
with your audience about well my work
and the history of how I arrived where I
am now. And this is just a a little part
of professional life of of a scientist.
So if you permit me, I am I will uh
propose to start my conversation just
sharing some slides about my in
institute. I'm interested to uh for you
all to know what my institute is about
and some other um insights about the
work that we do in my group. Um so at
the ICGE
uh this is the international center for
genetic engineering and biotechnology
and we are an intergovernmental
organization that is working in the
intersection between uh research
training and technology transfer in life
sciences with the goal of promoting
sustainable development uh the
sustainable global development and we
began as uh
we began as an special project of
UNIDOM. This is the United Nation um uh
office for the industrial development.
And then almost what yeah 40 years ago
uh we became 30 years ago we became an
independent organization fully
independent but still we operate within
the United Nations systems. We follow
many of its administrative procedures
and as an intergovernmental organization
we are made by the network of almost 70
member states countries and our
laboratories are hosted in Africa in
Italy where I am now in South Africa and
also in India and yeah I I will be happy
to see many other Latin American
countries and from Africa and from the
global south to join this uh group of
country and to complete this map. And
the ICGB is governed by a board of
governor and with one representative of
each member state and this board meets
every year to help guide our direction
of the institute and in many ways this
function like a mini united nation like
a General Assembly of the United Nation,
but for biotechnology, bringing bringing
diverse national perspective together in
a with a spirit of collaboration.
And um our work is organized around six
core pillars that you can see here in
this list.
And in addition, we focus on
crosscutting priorities such as gender
and jobs, south cooperation and with a
strong focus on the least developed
countries
and our instrument of actions are these
six that you can see here to deliver our
mission. So the first one is about the
research in our laboratories and this is
just a very
[Music]
short summary of our diversity on on the
research part on infectious diseases
non-communic non-communicable diseases
and these are the group that are
distributed between our three components
in again Italy South Africa and India
medical biotech industrial bio biotech
and uh and also plant biology and
biotechnology.
And in this last group is where my
groups has been assigned. Okay.
So, and we also work with a council of
scientific advisors that they provide
with advice. to how to run our
institution and it's made by uh
well-renowned
scientific personalities including Nobel
Prizes
and and then the other four instrument
of actions are fellowships. This slice
is not updated. Sorry for that. But uh
constantly we have many calls for
fellowships, PhD and postto fellowships
and also for short-term fellowship for
people from our member states to come
national from our member state to come
to our laboratories to perform a part of
of their research.
Um we also help to organize help
providing financial help uh for
researcher again in our member state to
organize meeting and courses and also we
provide uh grant research for
researchers located in our member
countries to perform their research
there with a with a a relevant context
no in national context.
Um we also have a text transfer and
biotech development unit to develop uh
bio similars with pharma compliance
laboratories and premises. And the last
but not the least instrument of action
is technical assistance and again this
is where my group uh is working the
technical assistant for the regulation
of biotech and its program. So this is
the ICG regulatory science group and we
support countries and organization
agencies in the safe regulation of
biotechnology
and we work to build uh to build and
also strength systems that can
effectively identify, assess, manage and
monitor biotech products especially in
the face of the emerging
biotechnologies.
And we organize our activities into
three main uh areas. Capacity
development, knowledge and policy
engagement and diagnostic and applied
projects.
For in the case of capacity development,
we uh most of our work is focused on
institutional
capacity uh development. For instance,
development uh developing or updating
biosafety legislation and regulatory
systems.
some example and also strengthening
institutional policy for the safe use of
emerging bio technologies. This is a
some example of our recent projects and
also the individual capacity uh building
activities that we provide um organize
and provide international workshops on
environmental assessment of genetically
modified organism and we have developed
and we are developing constantly an ICG
e-learning platform
in the area of knowledge and policy
engagement. Uh
we produce we make desk research we
produce derative reviews on biosafety
legislation.
uh and also we produce great deterative.
We write reports for UN agencies as this
one on synthetic biology or policy
briefs to uh address to international
and global leaders and also we
participated in several policy dialogues
for biocurity governance and strategic
foresight um or more recent this more
esoteric part of biotech that is called
mirror lives and uh a small part of our
activities devoted to diagnostics and
applied projects. This is something that
we have recently implemented in Africa
for strengthening the um surveillance um
uh epidemiology of public health
laboratories in Africa. And this is my
group. We are today just four groups.
This is my supervisor Wendy Craig and my
other two colleagues. and we rely our
extensive
network of collaborator for filling any
gaps that we might have in our projects.
So that's it. Uh that's it. That was uh
short and quick. Uh but I hope that that
provides you guys with a a very broad
idea of what my organization is and what
more or less we are doing in my group.
And I will be happy to discuse for the
rest of the time about what I told you
or any other uh issue about biotech and
present and uh interesting topic or
future interesting topic of course of
biotech.
>> We are joined by uh three students from
the broad summer scholars program and uh
they have prepared a list of questions
ahead of time to facilitate the
conversation. So, Maggie, uh, would you
kick us off, please?
>> Yeah. So, the first question we'd like
to ask is, what first sparked your
interest in biology and how did that
interest grow into a career in science
and policy?
>> Yeah.
Okay. Uh,
I mean there many things, many things. I
mean, this is something now in in
retrospective. Uh
I can think that I mean I always
was fascinated by living things and by
science and perhaps this is not it was
not unique for me because I think that
any child is fascinated by living
things. Uh but I remember no to be very
mesmerized of how plants grow and how
insects behave and how our bodies work.
And I remember I was watching Animal
Planet and discovered a channel instead
of MTV or Cartoon Network or some
something like that. And but that was
something that I bring with me for the
rest of my life. No, there was an
interest that was growing growing
growing so much and uh this interest
innate interest by by science and well
then I decided to start to study biology
without really knowing about what kind
of work a biologist uh does honestly.
But then during the the career during
the university I discovered that I I was
in the in the right place. So there
there was a combination of things.
>> Thank you for your answer. Um our next
question is can you tell us about like a
moment uh in your life when you ended up
realizing that you wanted to make
science useful um outside of the lab?
Yeah.
And okay. Yeah. Thank you, Marisa. And
again, it was not
usually it's not an anka moment. The one
moment that you say, "Oh, this this was
not it is a combination, but the moment
arrives." No. And you say, "Okay,
something need to change here." And uh
when I when I finished already my
career, I I was a graduated student, I
started to make research, no in a
laboratory, thinking in a uh the with a
scientific method and making a
hypothesis and experimentations and blah
blah and having uh hypothesis and
proving the theories all the history
about science and then publishing my
first paper and nobody reads my paper.
Absolutely not. So that was extremely
technical and it was of course address
to my piece. So I was trying to tell my
family to my wife and my mom and my dad
what my work was about and
I didn't know how to do that. and they
were bored because of my histories of of
experiments of failed experiments or
suddenly my paper. So the my work years
of work and nights of works and well
many things
were not uh reaching the people the
society and that was a norm. It is a
norm. Absolutely it is a norm in our
laboratories.
uh and then I realized that I was not
happy with that situation. Absolutely
not. And I couldn't wait for anyone to
solve that situation. So I started to
take training in science communication.
But in in that moment when I realized
that my research was not at reach in the
public, I said okay I realized that I
would like to make something for that to
happen.
>> Thank you. That definitely shows a lot
of your perseverance. Um, so our next
question is, what skills from your
research career helped you transition
into international work and science
diplomacy?
Yeah, again a combination of of of uh
skills. Absolutely. And
that transition was not from one moment
to another. It was not from one day to
the next day. This is a transition that
is built step by step slowly
and well I already told you guys that I
started during my PhD to take training
on science communication and that was
extremely helpful extremely helpful that
was the first thing I mean that was the
basis the foundation for my transition
science communication get trained in
science communication I mean taking
courses and certifications in science
communication.
That was life changes to
and and then I started to write a blog.
uh so trying to put in practice what I
was learning in science communication
and I open a blog I started to work on
my personal branding
and I cannot see at this moment my time
because that that part was
10 or 12 years ago and now I don't want
to read what I bought in that time I
don't want to see my my former website
uh because I don't like it anymore. Of
course, we all change and we evolve. But
that was extremely healthy. Extremely
healthy. So that put my name there in
the stage that started to position
myself as a
was not a leader because I was extremely
young but as as an emerging
leader let's say. No and and making to
start expanding my network you know so
it was that science communication then
personal branding absolutely and these
pieces of decision or action then open
the door for other things no like uh I
was accepted for uh to take a training
on scientific advice and then a training
made on science diplomacy and what
difference is these two topic but the
basis was science communication and
personal branding.
>> Thank you so much. Um there's a question
from the audience. So yeah they ask
where do you think is the most
interesting environment for a young
scientist to grow right into?
>> Yeah. Wow. Okay. for young scientists.
Well, young scientists absolutely a
research laboratory is
mandatory.
Absolutely. No doubt. It is like that.
This is our way of life
with all the the imperfections of
academy etc. But is the way it is and it
is okay.
But it need to be complemented.
Absolute. So for building a
socially relevant career because I think
that this is key and this is important
to build a social relevant career.
It is important to devote and dedicate
time to civil organization. something
that connects you with the real problems
that are not the problem of from your
family or your neighborhood
are more complicated and complex
societal problems. So being voluntary
uh volunteering to civil society
organization providing your skills as a
scientist is extremely helpful. So and
that will enrich your
your training your yeah her development
as a early career researcher and to and
I'm including here in civil society
organization
um
like organized
students or
sciencemies
that they are also with a very good
connection with society and of or things
that are not related to science but
still uh science has a component there
environment
um something like that food the use of
the land there are many things yeah
>> all right wonderful thank you um so next
what does your work look like on a
day-to-day basis when helping countries
implement biosafety measures
Yeah. Yeah. my daytoday
uh basis.
I don't want to say that it's boring
because it is not. But honestly, the
most of my days I am in my desk uh in
front of my computer writing emails,
reading reports and writing reports.
But I enjoying it so much. It's not a
mechanical work. Absolutely not. I need
to put there huge amount of intellectual
uh effort because I need to be very well
educated on emerging biotechnologies in
the more complicated as molecular aspect
of the last uh genome editing
technologies because I I need to
communicate that to policy makers and
decision makers and I need to do it in a
language that they understand
but because of my
um my training and my formation as a
scientist I can understand both worlds
not the academic and I have learned to
understand the policy work so I am there
no as the bridge between these two world
this is 70
yeah 70 maybe 80% of my time the rest is
extremely exciting because it's
traveling I work in an inter
governmental organization and our
training because I am a trainer now too
uh and scientific advisor. I
need to go to the countries to
ministries governmental agencies to
other international forum to other UN
agencies and to provide our work. So I
am in my desk reading, writing,
implementing project from my desk and
traveling.
Thank you for answering that question.
Our next question is um in your opinion,
how can genetically modified organisms
or GMOs both help and even potentially
harm biodiversity?
>> Okay. Um
yeah
I mean it it is it is not my opinion
it's scientific evidence here scientific
evidence and GMOs can for instance help
reducing the need for pesticides and
this is something that has been
very well established and measured know
that the use of pesticide has been
dramatically reduced thanks to the GMOs.
you think that they are many of them are
resistant to pest. So it is not needed
to to apply the same amount of
pesticides.
For instance, now they are developing uh
crops that are more resilience to uh to
climate stress and this is something
that of course is going to provide
benefits uh to the biodiversity and
environment in general. These are just
two examples. Uh we need to think that
the GMOs are the genetically modified
organism. In the case of plants, they
are improved plants. This is made by
breeding. This is plant improvement.
So we are uh taking advantage of
genetics knowledge, genetic knowledge to
improve our crops.
Uh but of course as any technology any
human technology
there are associated risks.
There are risk in building a bridge.
There are risk risk to take a plane and
travel. There is there are risks to turn
on your when you turn on your kitchen.
There are risk there.
The thing is how to manage those risk.
No, how to uh how to cope with those
potential risk and biotechnology do
exactly the same. No, it is important to
maximize the benefits of GMO and at the
same times minimizing the potential
harm.
For instance, if a GMO is not well
managed, let's say, uh well, it it could
affect absolutely wild species, wild
plants or the soil microbes or perhaps
more more broad
ecosystem. It is not well managed. But
this is something that uh
is not happening. G GMOs is one of the
technologies or the product that is more
um regulated
and and yeah regulated in the world. So
so far there has been no any
important
harm to biodiversity at least in the
scientific literature. There are other
there are testimonies and any other
sources of information but in scientific
literatur.
>> Thank you. Uh we also have a question
from the audience. So could you describe
an example of a case in which you and
your team managed to make a difference
in a country's policy and in addition to
that what was the process like? What
were the challenges like? And what was
the time span?
Yeah.
Yeah. I I can highlight highlight one
particular example. It was due during
the COVID pandemic.
I was working in a project for
modernizing the uh bios safety
regulatory framework of the Republic of
Panama in Central America.
The thing is that the it exists an
international agreement and the
international agreements are legally
binding documents. So if a country sign
that international agreement that
country must
put in place laws and regulation for
that agreement to make to to
make it happen in that country. So in
the the in the beginning of the year
in when it was 1999 the 2000 2000
was 2002
the cart agenda protocol by safety was
signed and established by most of the
countries of the world. This is a
international agreement that established
rules for the transboundary movement of
GMOs.
Okay, that's fine. Now the countries
during those years most of the countries
they draft their biosafety laws and they
started to implement the cartagin
approach.
We are talking of the about 20 uh uh
2002 year 2002. So this is 23 years ago.
In that time
genome editing
uh didn't exist. It was not discovered.
Crisper and many technologies that are
now
uh in almost any molecular biology lab
in that moment no clues about that
technology, no clues about synthetic
biology and many other things.
So now the countries are working they
are regulating regulating their biotech
product with a agreement that was signed
predating those uh scientific discovery.
So they need to update their uh national
laws.
So that was the call from many
countries. Panama was um uh was able to
mobilize resources and to bring us in
place for helping them to modernize
their regulatory framework. It was a
fantastic experience working with uh
national and with officials
officers from Panama. The challenge,
yeah, it was for me was um unexpected
and is how difficult before different
national agencies to sit together and
draft uh a document. No, that is that it
will be good for their country.
What what does this mean? I mean uh
biosafety
uh biosafety committee no from a country
or of the biosafety competent authority
usually is made from different people
from many different minister no a group
from the minister of agriculture a group
from minister of um uh environment
ministry of of uh trade commerce
ministry of uh health so and they need
to sit together to establish this
regulation and that's difficult
difficult. They they all come through
with their mindset on agriculture or
health and that's the idea of course but
they need to you know the knowledge
needs to permeate between this silence
national silence and that was something
that was a learning experience for me
that this is not uh that easy.
>> Thank you so much. What's one example of
a successful biosafety project you
worked on that made a difference?
>> Uh
yeah, I mean because I work
building capacities or strengthening
capacities in biosafety.
Uh
for instance, we recently implemented a
project of regional workshops on on
biosafety no particularly in the
environmental risk assessment of uh
genetically modified organism. There
were five regional workshops in the
world covering all the continents and
each of the workshops in all the
continent were tailored to the problems
of that region. So we provide with the
theoretical part of course of the risk
analysis with uh risk assessment
and so on and then we want the the
attendees and they are a mixture of
regulator scientist farmers
etc. uh we want them to analyze
hypothetical cases for uh assessing
potential risks of a genetically
modified organism. For instance, we went
to Central Asia where where
is uh is produced is the main crop. So
we developed an hypothetical uh
genetically modified wheat adapted to
the environmental condition of central
Africa. In the workshop for Oceanania
and the Pacific Island, we developed a
case study of genetically modified
rodents, mice as an invasive species in
Ireland. And then for Africa, we
developed a genetically modified banana
hypothetical case.
uh recently in Brazil we developed a a
case study on genetically modified
mosquitoes for fighting deni and other
uh context relevant diseases.
So and this very uh large multi-year and
international global project was uh
extremely successful. I mean because we
we were able to train a diversity of
people and
um our hope is that they implement what
they have learned during our training in
their countries.
>> Maggie, apologies. I think you're muted.
All right, thank you. Um, so our next
question is, how could science help
bring countries together or solve global
problems like food security or climate
change?
>> Yeah,
thank you Maggie. You know,
there has been precedents on how science
can improve international relations.
uh typically during the cold war
for instance there were
uh big scientific projects that helped
release a little bit the tensions
uh for the establishment I don't know of
uh research institute for
space exploration for instance was
another topic and there are several
examples of ho how
how they can help alleviate problems
uh because science provides a common
language not something that can be
understood and also a shared
evidencebased
approaches. Of course the political
tension are not solved absolutely not
but science helps uh to create spaces
for dialogue and cooperation and that's
amazing. For instance, here where I
live, I live in a little town that is
called Trieste in Italy. And we are in
the border with Slovenia in the
northeast of Italy. And this little
town, little city, Trieste is the city
in Europe with M with the bigger number
of researcher per habitat in the entire
Europe. And that's amazing. And that's
because here there are several
international scientific organization
like mine about biotech and genetic
engineering and there is another one on
physics and there is another couple of
international organization and UNESCO
offices and so on and that was because
this was the last city
uh before the communist block
uh now when Slovenia was part of
Yugoslavia and the communist country.
So, and here in Trieste was a point of
en
point of two encounter the first and the
second uh world the the capitalist and
communist blocks from the world were
here in Trieste. So when this city was
developed uh so much thanks to that
scientific bridge there. So these are
just examples. Now for the current
global problems like like food security
that is
sadly a never ending problem and now um
more concerning the climate change
problem
is more or less the same thing. We need
to think that we are in a common space
that is the planet earth and no a single
solution no a single country was would
be able to solve any of this problem and
there is need for a more
diplomacy and science diplomacy approach
for solving this problem.
>> Thank you for that uh answer. Our next
question is why in your opinion why is
it important to share science in
people's native language?
>> Yes. And this touch me
uh inside no that's because you are
noticing that English is not my mother
tongue and I have been one of the
affected no but because this strong
limitation
of the of the language
I must recognize however that it is
extremely beneficial to have a common
language for sciences. Absolutely. So I
very much support the use of one single
language for
uh
for having this global discussions and
you know trying to solve the global
problems no doubt and yeah in the past
was Latin,
Greek, French whatever language. Now
it's English and it is okay.
We need to consider however that most of
the population most of the population
doesn't speak English at all. So if we
want for the scientific evidence and the
global discussion to arrive to society,
we need to talk uh in their languages.
Absolutely. they need everyone should be
included in this solution especially
when they are the affected community
with the problems or the potential uh
deployment of technological solutions.
Uh so uh yeah uh they absolutely need to
be reached by
context relevant scientific information
including including no in their native
languages.
>> Thank you so much. What advice would you
give to students who are interested in
both science and making a global compact
impact?
Stay curious. Stay curious and stay
open. Stay open. And
yeah, these students that are interested
in both both making a global impact and
in science. Yeah. Stay curious, stay
open.
The foundation on science in the values
of science must be protagonist during
your entire lives guys. Absolutely. This
is something that the scientific method
should be the guiding light in all your
actions.
Um it is important to adapt.
This career science is extremely
changing. You need to adapt to any
challening or
nice situation. So adaptation is key.
And don't be afraid to step outside the
lab. There are
several options or there there is life
beyond a a a lab bench.
And this is built again with well
strengthening your soft skills beyond
science and yeah expanding your network
and being active and doing things that
are socially relevant.
All right. Thank you. Um, so not too
long ago,
um, you and your colleagues published a
paper titled Navigating Biosafety, uh,
regulatory frameworks for genetic
engineering in Africa, a focus on genome
editing and gene um, drive technologies.
Could you tell us a bit about what you
and your colleagues found?
>> Yeah. Yeah, sure. Thank you. Thank you
for highlighting that paper. It wasn't
that by the
late 2024 we published this paper when
we analyzed no that the regulatory
frameworks in across Africa
and we looked at how different African
countries are approaching the regulation
of this emerging biotech and we found
that it is a lot there is a lot of
diversity that there are countries that
are ex
doing so well no countries that are well
advanced in the regulations there but
other are still with no regulations.
So there is a a huge difference there
and a very terogeneous regulatory
environment there.
But the good thing is that they all
recognize these gaps and these
challenges and they are all open to this
to perform or to strengthen regional
collaboration in making sure that all
the regulation are both both
science-based or science informed and at
the same time that are again locally
relevant for the problems and to be
relevant for for the context.
Thank you for telling us about your p uh
your paper. Uh our next question is why
might some people be unsure or maybe
even afraid of gene editing and how can
scientists and the governments help the
public feel much more informed and safe?
>> I mean yeah thank you thank you for your
question. Um it is completely normal to
be causian and to be a threat of new
technologies. This is something that is
in our nature. When the electricity was
invented there was there were there were
group of people opposing electricity.
There were anti- electricity groups
when the uh the train was invented.
There were anti-trained group of people
and protesting in the street because
they they didn't want trained in this in
their countries
and then yeah and so on with the horses
there were anti-horses group of people
with the car there were anti-car group
of people with any technology that is
deflecting that is completely different
that is no precedence in the history
there will be uh opposition
and biotech is not the exception.
This is another human invention and
technology.
Uh so with um genome editing um gen with
gene editing is has been exactly the
same with first with GMO 30 years ago
and still there is some. Yeah. So now
there is a there is still an important
opposition to GMOs and now with gene
editing
it seems that things are going to be
better for the technology for the
biotech.
uh but still some resistance out there
and I think that the key things here is
transparency
uh explaining how these tools these
tools work what kind of safeguards are
in place for avoiding
harm and what kind of risk and benefits
are and building this trust takes time
but it it start with listening not just
explaining this uh dialogue and what I I
am seeing now
is that hopefully we have learned from
the mistake from the past the mistake
that were done during the GMO era 30 20
years ago
for instance that that the the products
were more
designed for the benefit of farmers so
the consumer
were not feeling that this kind of
technology are uh a benefit for them and
this with genome editing is changing
now. For instance, there are developing
crops that are biofortified so we can
get more nutrients in our foods or or
the climate resident crops. There are
some benefit that we can see that
benefit for everyone not not just for
the farmers.
Um so yeah exactly so more an expanded
um
benefits and also transparency.
>> Thank you so much. How do you explain
complex science and ways that help
policy makers and everyday people
understand what's at stake?
Yeah,
this is a tricky one and it's not that
easy and this is a learning process and
and it is an evolution how to explain
these complex issues to policy maker and
technical complex and technical
uh I'm still learning because again
policy makers are not a homogeneous
group. They are extremely diverse, very
heterogeneous, intergenerational,
etc. So, it's extremely challenging.
I try to use analogies,
histories, visuals whenever possible.
What I don't use is jargon, scientific
jargon. And I try to avoid it as much as
possible and I try to focus on on in the
so what. So we have a new technology. So
what? No. So this what does this mean
for food on the table? What does this
mean for this is disease control for
pest control?
So that that again that connection with
the social part social relevant of that
um technology
and but again this is something that
need to be adapted. There is no one
sizefits all uh specified for uh
explaining these complex technological
issues for policy maker.
>> Thank you. Um, how do you believe your
work has grown you as both a human and a
scientist?
>> Again, let me see if my work
>> could you repeat?
>> Definitely. How do you believe your work
has grown you as both a human and a
scientist?
>> Okay. Yeah.
Well, to Yeah. Being perfectly honest,
the do doing this kind of work is
I mean separating totally your
professional and personal life
is not possible. It is a mindset. Not
being scientist is a mindset.
Absolutely. I'm I'm I'm sure of that. Uh
this is something that is with you uh
for your entire life and it dictates so
it dictates so much your way of life
your decisions your way of I don't know
to raise your child the way you engage
with your
society your neighborhood your friends
etc is something that is it becomes part
of of of of your person.
So uh from a personal life uh I would
say that
my work has improved my personal life. I
have learned many skills that I try to
implement in my personal life on
diplomacy on management
trying to cope with different group of
people
in intercultural
discussions. This is something that it
is beyond my my work. So what I h I have
worked there then with my intercultural
group of friend I try to uh take some
bites and from what I learned there to
my personal life in my professional
lives lives uh again it is a learning
experience this is learning by doing
just managing projects and trying to
implement international projects uh is
something that always enrich your
toolkit no for being a good
worker let's say uh and something
crucial always is your network is your
network uh so attending conferences
um
is extremely important but also your
online presence is ext is not trivial
that's that's not bal absolutely not
having a good online presence and Being
professional in your online lives life
is something that is can improve and
change your professional
career.
>> Thank you for your answer. Um I have
another question. So, how do you make
sure that like new science such as GMOs
end up respecting what people in a
specific country believe in or
respecting what they care about?
>> Respecting. Okay. Um,
okay. In in this case, I mean, I I
cannot answer in the place of the
developers. I'm not a developer of GMO.
Absolutely not. Uh so my again my work
is try to help governments know to make
a safe use of the or how how they they
can ensure
that the GM crops are safely uh used or
something like that.
Um so it is up to each of the government
to decide
uh if a biotech application is aligned
or is not contradictory
or it's not going to create tensions
with their population. So there are
socioeconomics aspects that from any
technology again is not is not uh
specific for biotech. There are soio
economic um aspect and I'm including
here yeah uh for inance ethics and well
many other things that the governments
need to consider our role as a scientist
are sciencebased
advice or evidence and uh yes we need to
give
uh responsibly
advice on how to apply science but the
part of social economics is not
according
uh international agreements
are not part of the scientific risk
assessment. So this is part of the
decision makers
need to consider other
sources of information for instance the
ethics religious people indigenous
people minorities etc. So that's the
role of a decision maker to to keep an
eye on all these spectrum of sources of
information to then take a decision.
Science is just one little part of the
source of information
and all they are important. It's not
that science is more important. No, no,
no. They all are important.
[Music]
>> All right. Thank you very much. So
lastly, why do you think it's important
to engage with communities where biotech
work is being performed?
Well, but basically because they they
are the ones most affected. No, they are
the they they will be the the the
affected communities.
For instance, I am recently very much
uh not involved but I'm I'm working um
I'm developing literary reviews on gene
drive. Gene drive are is a technology
that is looking for modifying and listen
this is crazy modifying wide population
of mosquitoes.
This is something that has never been
done. Absolutely not to modify a wide
population genetically modify a wide
population of mosquito. This is extreme.
Absolutely. And they are looking for
modifying this mosquito for um ending or
help ending malaria. Malaria is a one of
the more deadliest uh diseases in the
world. So there is a a public health
issue that is that genetic intervention
is looking to solve. No, this is gene
drive. So the release the potential
release because this is not happening
yet. The potential release of this
genetically modified mosquitoes with
gene drive are going to happen in rural
parts of Africa for instance. that is
the most affected part of the world with
malaria
and what we are doing what they are
doing from 10 years ago they are already
working with these communities with this
local community from the to co-develop
the inception of the experiments even so
this is part of the uh of the new of
they are trying not to repeat the
mistake from the past. No, for instance,
with GMO, they suddenly arrive, we have
this GMO and it could save your life,
blah blah, eat it or plant it. No, this
was an extreme failed mistake, an epic
fail. Absolutely. Now what they are
doing, they are sit in the same table
from the inception of the experiment
with the local communities. Let's try to
co-develop the experimentation.
What are the needs? What are your uh
conditions for a potential release of
mosquitoes in 20 years? And they are
engaging and working with them now with
the community and I think that that's
the way it is for that kind of extreme
interventions.
Well, Felix, thank you so much uh for
this wonderful conversation and I want
to thank our amazing panelists, Jada,
Marissa, and Maggie uh for facilitating
in the conversation as well. I learned a
lot and I know that they did as well. Um
everybody, thank you so much for being
here. Um and if you get a chance, please
let us know what you thought of this
talk by answering the survey that I just
dropped in the chat. Thank you so much
everybody. Have a great day.
Thank you Adriana and thank you Jada
Maggie and Marissa. Thank you so much. I
have enjoyed this conversation.