The quantum advantage occurs when a
quantum computer can perform a
calculation in a reasonable time that a
classical computer is unable to complete
in any practical sense. It's important
to note this definition does not state
that the calculation performed should
meet any threshold of usefulness.
Therefore, what we want to focus on
instead is a different milestone, one
known as quantum economic advantage. By
that I mean when a quantum computer
solves a commercially relevant problem
in a manner that is cheaper, faster, or
better than a classical computer.
Imagine a scenario such as trading in
the financial markets. It's possible a
business would pay more for a quantum
computer to execute a multi-billion
dollar portfolio optimization task
because it provides even a small
improvement in time relative to
classical devices.
For more MIT moments from MIT Open
Learning, like, subscribe, or