[Music]
so hi everyone welcome back to the last
introductory lecture and uh this lecture
is going to put together the concepts we
learned in the first two lectures on
biology and technology and uh we'll
learn about the experiments that were
perform to generate the data for the
data science Challenge and how we're
going to work with that data during the
challenge so uh the data itself comes
from an experiment of perturb seek done
in t- cells and so let's start talking
about uh the experimental overview and
then after we understand the experiment
we'll go into what the data looks like
so the experimental overview so first I
just want to start with a recap from
what we learned in the first uh two
introductory lectures so the first
lecture we learned that um te- cells
become exhausted in the cancer
environment and they transition from
progenitor t- cell states to affector t-
cell States and finally terminally
exhausted t- cell States these
transitions are driven by the gene expr
programs in the t- cells and the t- cell
states are marked by different abilities
to kill tumor cells with theor T cells
and the progenitor t- cells being much
better at killing tumor cells or cancer
cells than the terminally exhausted te
cells so that's a recap of what we've
already learned in the first lecture and
in the second lecture we introduced a
perturb seek which allows us to do a
simultaneous readout of the gene
expression in a single cell as well as
the perturbation that cell Reed and how
that worked is we used the crisper cast
9 gen editing technology to knock out
individual genes in the te- cells in
parallel and then we introduced those
te- cells into cancer let the te- cells
fight the cancer for some time isolated
the t- cells and then Ed sequencing to
read out both the perturbation that that
cell received as well as the resulting
gene expression in that single cell and
so this lets us read out perturbations
in parallel as well as the gene
expression uh measurements or expression
values for single cell
okay so with those two Recaps the t-
cell exhaustion and how perturb seek
works we can now talk about the
experiment that was performed um by uh
Mark Schwarz who is a physician
scientist an oncologist at the Bro
Institute and Dana Farber Cancer
Institute and so what uh what experiment
was performed was Mark took U mice who
had melanoma and he gave them uh te-
cells and these te- cells will migrate
into the tumor into the melanoma and
they will fight the cancer and 2 weeks
later Mark took out the tumor and
isolated the t- cells and performed
single cell RNA sequencing which we saw
in the uh second lecture and what he saw
when analyzing those t- cell States uh
that came out of the Single Cell RNA
sequencing analysis was that a high
proportion of te- cells were in the
terminally exhausted t- cell State and
that's uh not surprising because uh we
know that in the tumor environment te-
cells get driven towards terminal
exhaustion now then Mark wanted to know
you know if we take these mice with
melanoma what happens if instead we give
them te- cells that have been
genetically edited and now individual
genes are knocked out in these te- cells
and we can ask do these Gene edits when
we knock out a gene does this affect the
ability of the te- cell to respond and
kill the cancer cells to kill the
melanoma so Mark prepared uh t- cells
with different genetic perturbations he
gave those to the with melanoma those T
cells proceeded to fight the melanoma
and they went through their
differentiation Pathways and then after
2 weeks Mark isolated the te- cells from
the tumor and performed perturb seek and
the outcome of the perturb seek
experiment is we have single cells and
for every single cell we know what
genetic perturbation that cell receive
as well as the resulting gene expression
in that same single cell and so when we
analyze the gene expression for those
single cells we might find that
perturbation a a was associated with t-
cell killing so the effector T Cell
State and perturbation B might have been
associated with the exhausted t- cell
state so that's the experiment uh that
was uh done and this is what you're
going to be working with in the data
science challenge so let's just go
through a little bit of question and
answer with some more details of this
experiment so first question you might
have is how many genes were knocked out
so remember um there are 20,000 protein
cating genes in the human and mouse
genomes so uh how many genes were
actually knocked out well Mark knocked
out 73 of those genes and this is um you
know not 20,000 because as we said in
the previous lecture the amount of work
to do that it would take about 50 years
so we did a more manageable number of
genes and then most genes are going to
be in the training set and seven have
been left out for validation and testing
and this is what you're going to be
working with in the first uh challenge
those seven genes and predicting their
effects on the t- cell States next
question is well why did Mark choose
those specific genes so um we don't know
what most genes do or what most genes uh
how most genes affect t- cell
differentiation so Mark used prior
knowledge to kind of narrow the search
space so one thing he did was a
scientific kind of literature review of
genes with uh potential roles in
controlling differentiation Mark also
looked at human uh patient data uh from
uh melanoma trials and he looked at gen
from t- cells and melanoma in particular
T cells that were expressing tcf7 which
is a critical Gene and T cell
differentiation and he looked at what
genes Mar those T cells so that's like
where he chose the genes from and then
we can ask how many single cells were
sequenc so we did this perturbs
experiment and we isolated t- cells how
many cells did Mark isolate so Mark
isolated um 70,000 cells and because
there's 70 genes that means there's
about 1,000 single cells for each
genetic perturbation on average
and then finally um are there negative
controls in this experiment um are there
perturbations that are not expected to
have an effect and actually yes there
are the experiment was carefully
designed to have negative controls so
there are 30 what are called
non-targeting controls which are
perturbations are that are not actually
going to make any Cuts in the genome and
affect any Gene in the cell and these
just have no effect on the on the gene
expression no effect on the t- cell
States and so this can give us a
background sense of what unperturbed te
cells would look like in the context of
this melanoma model so the data that
comes out of the perturbs experiment
consists of two pieces the first uh is
the gene expression Matrix and the
second um is this assignment of the
perturbations that each cell receed so
remember the gene expression Matrix will
tell us the expression level of every
single Gene in every single cell now
this perturbation table tells us what
perturbation what genetic perturbation a
cell received so cell one received a tox
perturbation so the tox Gene got deleted
and then we can link that perturbation
to the resulting effect on the uh the
gene expression within that cell so cell
one had a tox deletion and has this set
of gene expression values so that's this
really nice linkage we can do in a
perturbs experiment between the
perturbation and the result on the gene
expression in the same cell
[Music]