Welcome to the
featured presentation
portion of today's program.
Each talk will be 15 minutes
with an additional five minutes
for Q&A. So each
talk will actually
be about 10 to 15 minutes.
We told the students
15 minutes max.
[LAUGHS] All right.
Our first speaker
is Lansing Horan,
a graduate student in
Professor Jack Harris' group.
Lansing's research is in
fusion plasma physics,
and he will be presenting today
on "Shadowgraphy Measurements
of Radiatively Cooled
Magnetic Reconnection Layer."
All right, Lansing, do
you want to take it away?
All right.
Good afternoon, everybody.
Thank you for the
introduction, Anza.
My name is Lansing, and I'm
a third-year NSE student.
Today, I'll talk about
"Shadowgraphy Measurements
of a Radiatively Cooled
Magnetic Reconnection Layer."
This presentation
will aim to break down
this title into the key terms.
So we'll start with
magnetic reconnection.
So to orient you into what
magnetic reconnection is,
it is a fundamental process
that occurs everywhere
in the universe, where
there is magnetized plasma,
which is most of the universe.
So to start out, we have a
simple two-dimensional cartoon.
Imagine we have two blobs of
plasma on a collision course,
and that these blobs of
plasma happen to have
anti-parallel magnetic fields.
If we assume that
the plasma is ideal,
this means that
the magnetic field
lines will move with the plasma
flows, like that shown here.
Now, due to an
electrodynamic effect,
whenever we have oppositely
oriented magnetic field
lines close to each
other, we generate
a large electric current, such
as that shown here in green,
pointing out of the board.
The benefit of this
current, or one implication,
is that it allows the magnetic
field lines to further diffuse
into each other, eventually
overlapping at the center
and achieving
magnetic reconnection.
This is where the magnetic field
lines overlap and annihilate
themselves at the center.
The object in our system that
we'll focus on for this talk
is at the center in yellow.
This is the reconnection layer.
This is simply the region where
magnetic reconnection occurs.
It is a small location of the
overall plasma environment.
So with that background,
why should we
care about magnetic
reconnection?
What ramifications does it have?
So first, as we can see with
this animation of a solar flare,
which happens pretty
frequently with our sun,
magnetic reconnection is
often an explosive process.
In breaking the
magnetic field lines,
it allows for violent
plasma eruptions.
And then secondly, reconnection
is a heating mechanism.
The plasma is energized
where the magnetic field
lines annihilate.
Energy is transferred from
the magnetic field lines
to the plasma.
This leads to additional
interesting effects
that we'll talk about
in the coming slides.
So with this background
for magnetic reconnection,
let's talk about the
specific type of reconnection
that we're interested in--
radiatively cooled reconnection.
So the question naturally is,
How does radiative cooling
affect the reconnection layer?
Again, I have a simple
two-dimensional diagram here
on the slides.
And we just learned
that reconnection
is a heating process.
So the plasma in
the layer is hot.
In order to cool itself off,
it's going to release energy.
It's going to emit x-rays.
This has the effect
of, of course,
decreasing the
temperature of the plasma
in the layer and
also, of course,
lowering the thermal pressure.
But we still have
the constant streams,
the flowing streams from the
left and the right of the layer.
And so if the thermal pressure
of the layer is decreased,
it allows those
inflowing plasma streams
to further compress the layer,
thereby increasing the density,
m.
The last bit of
information that we
need to complete an
interesting circuit,
an interesting
positive feedback loop,
is knowing that the X-ray power
scales with the density squared.
So if we're
increasing the density
by compressing the
layer due to radiation,
we're actually ending up
with more X-ray emission
than what we started with.
So this is a positive
feedback loop.
So the answer to the question
at the title of this slide
is radiative cooling drives
the layer of plasma colder
and denser as time progresses.
So there's an
interesting interplay
between reconnection as a
heating process and radiation
as a cooling process.
So why should we care about this
specific type of reconnection?
The first and foremost reason
is this type of reconnection
with radiation is pervasive
across a huge range
of astrophysical conditions.
It occurs everywhere
in the universe,
both in local environments
like the solar chromosphere,
as well as environments galaxies
away, such as the M87 black hole
accretion disk.
Secondly, theorists believe
that the radiative spectra
that we receive from
space plasma environments
that we record in
telescopes is the result
of magnetic reconnection as
the driving heating process,
inducing that radiation.
So this is our key, if not
only, observational signature
for astrophysical environments.
So if we want to better
understand the radiative spectra
that our telescopes
capture, we need
to understand the
fundamental process that
generates that radiation,
which is magnetic reconnection.
OK.
So with this
background, we can have
an open question in this
specific very niche research
field.
And that question is, How
does the layer structure
evolve in time during
radiative collapse?
But before we can immediately
answer this question,
we need to figure out, How
do we even address this?
How can we actually gain
any understanding here?
So by my count, there
are four different ways
that we can evaluate
magnetic reconnection theory.
First is computer simulations.
These are great.
These are powerful.
But like a lot of
simulation work,
there's always the question
of initial conditions.
It's not always clear,
which initial conditions we
should assume in our
numerical modeling.
And these could have a great
impact on the end result
that we receive.
Also, there's always
the question of,
How much can we really
trust the numerical outputs
that we're getting?
Because we're not sure
if we're accurately
modeling all of the
richness of physics
involved in this process.
The second way to evaluate the
theory is in situ measurements.
This is just saying,
What if we take a probe
and send it to the location
where magnetic reconnection is
occurring?
But for our case
of trying to learn
about astrophysical plasmas,
this is a non-starter.
These environments
are too extreme
or simply way too far for
us to ever send a probe
and actually measure
reconnection at its location.
A third technique is
remote observations.
So this is what I
mentioned before,
where we have
telescopes which capture
radiative spectra from all
throughout the universe.
But we can't infer everything
we need from radiation alone.
It would be better if we could
have other plasma parameters,
like the velocity, the density,
the temperature, in order
to more fundamentally
understand where
this radiation is coming from.
So that leaves us with our
fourth and final option,
lab experiments.
And that's what we'll focus
on for this talk here.
The benefit of
lab experiments is
we have a controlled
environment to measure in detail
and up close the specific
plasma physics at play.
So bringing it back
to the open question,
we're going to answer this
with a laboratory astrophysics
experiments.
This brings us to the
secret hidden part
of this title, Sandia's
Z machine, which
is the location,
the facility where
we conduct our experiments.
For those of you who don't know,
the Z machine at Sandia National
Labs in Albuquerque, New
Mexico is the world's largest
pulsed-power device.
This is a cut, a slice
through the center
of the overall machine.
It is absolutely massive.
It is 33 meters in diameter.
And just for reference,
in red, that's
about the size, the height
of a typical person.
This whole machine is
in a giant warehouse
out in the middle of the desert.
And working our way from the
very outer diameter, and then
inwards, starting out with
the capacitor banks in green,
this is where electricity
is charged up prior
to an experiment
on the Z machine.
And then this machine is
so complicated and large
and designed in order to deliver
a huge amount of electricity
to a very small area in
the center of the machine,
in the vacuum chamber.
In the bottom right, this is an
actual photograph of two Sandia
technicians working
and preparing
for an experiment prior to
a shot on the Z machine,
again, to give you
a sense of scale.
And one of the last
things I'll show
is at the very tip of
those orange arrows
in that little tiny
circular region, that's
the size of our experiments.
This is where all of our plasma
physics are actually occurring.
So we need this
absolutely massive machine
to deliver 20 million
amps of electricity
to a volume that's maybe
100 cubic centimeters.
We need the Z machine in order
to reach high-energy density
physics regimes.
Again, to give you
a sense of scale,
at the outer diameter
of the machine,
the power per volume density is
about 200 watts per cubic meter,
just as an order of magnitude.
For reference, a light bulb,
60-watt light bulb is about
300,000 watts per cubic meter.
So 200 is pretty benign.
Like, not much interesting
is happening there.
But interestingly, at our
target at the experiment,
we achieve about 200,000
trillion watts per cubic meter
in terms of energy density.
This is why we
need the Z machine.
This is the only machine
where we could actually
reach this insane level
of energy density.
For reference, a
nuclear fission reactor
is about 10 billion
watts per cubic meter.
So this brings us to Magnetic
Reconnection on Z, MARZ.
That is the name of our
collaboration with Sandia.
This is a picture
that we started out
with on the title slide.
This is a picture of
the load hardware.
So this is our
experiment basically
at that really small volume at
the center of the Z machine.
On the next slide, I'll explain
why we feel that these, what we
call wire arrays--
but for now to give
you a sense of scale,
each wire array
is 40 millimeters
in size, which for reference
is the diameter of a ping pong
ball.
The space between
each wire array
is about 20 millimeters,
so half a ping pong ball.
And on each array, it
might be a bit hard to see,
but arranged in a
cylindrical cage,
there are 150 aluminum wires
on each of the wire arrays,
so 300 total.
And each of these metal wires
is only 75 microns thick.
So that's the size
of a human hair.
This entire system is
incredibly complex,
takes months of planning.
And I don't know how the Sandia
technicians actually build
these things, but it's amazing.
Shown in purple is the path
of the electrical current
that the Z machine delivers
to our metal targets.
We reach 20 million
amps of electricity
in less than a millionth of
a second on the Z machine,
which, again, is
what we need in order
to generate a lot of radiation
in our plasma environment.
So everything I just showed you
was two exploding wire arrays.
And the reason that
we use these devices
is because they allow us to
generate magnetic reconnection
in that laboratory environment.
So with that current path in
purple on a single wire array,
this has the geometry we need
to generate radially diverging
flows of plasma emanating
from each of those wires.
And so if we place two wire
arrays next to each other,
the most interesting region of
this diagram is in the center.
So we see that we have
flowing streams of plasma
coming from the left and the
right meeting at the midplane.
And they're carrying
anti-parallel magnetic field
lines.
This is consistent with
that cartoon example
of magnetic reconnection.
So this is why we
field what we field.
So bringing it back
to this question.
So now we have the background.
We have the theory.
We have the experiment.
But now we need to
choose, How do we actually
diagnostically measure this?
How do we get any information
about the layer structure?
That brings us to the
first word of the title--
"shadowgraphy."
Before I talk about the specific
application of shadowgraphy
on our experiments, I just
want to give you some intuition
for what shadowgraphy is.
It's a phenomena that we
are all familiar with.
When we've been outside
on a bright, sunny day
next to a pool, we've
seen the rays of light
strike the surface of the water.
And due to the wave
patterns at the top
as well as throughout
the pool, we've
seen that there's interesting
patterns of light and dark
that form at the bottom.
So this is, essentially,
due to the changes
in the index of refraction
bending the rays of light.
So in our case, we're going
to apply shadowgraphy,
where our light
source is not the sun
but instead, it's a
high-intensity laser.
And our medium is not water,
but instead, a plasma fluid.
So that's shown with
this cartoon here.
We are looking at the top-down
on the two wire arrays.
At the center, we have
our reconnection layer.
This plasma only exists for less
than a millionth of a second.
But we carefully
time a laser pulse
to shine through the entirety
of the reconnection layer
during that experiment.
Looking at cross sections
of the laser beam profile,
so looking at the side,
initially, ideally our laser
beam profile is uniform.
It's flat.
It's traveling through vacuum.
But at the bottom right, we see
that the image of that laser
beam profile that we
collect has artifacts,
has the imprinting of
the reconnection layer
itself within it.
We see that the rays of light
have been deflected outwards
away from the region
of highest density.
So this is the last thing
I will show you for today.
These are going to be the
experimental datagrams
from our Mossbauer experiments
from April of last year.
And a shadowgram is just the
name of what we just saw,
the camera snapshot of the
laser beam intensity profile.
And for reference,
at the top, I'm
showing you the side
view of our system,
again reminding you that
we are shining the laser
beam into the board through
the entire reconnection layer.
So from our
experiment last year,
these are the four images
of our laser beam profile
that we collected.
These are the first images
of a radiatively cooled
magnetic reconnection layer,
not a very popular field,
but we were the first.
And moving from left to
right, the amount of time
is only about 40 nanoseconds.
So we can see a huge
amount of variation
in a very short time frame.
And I'll remind you
of our open question--
how does the layer
structure evolve in time
during radiative collapse?
And I'll quickly give you
four qualitative observations
we can immediately
make from these images.
First, in the center, we
see a dark sensual void.
This is the result of
the reconnection layer
being denser than
its surroundings,
deflecting light outwards.
Second, we see enhanced bands
of intensity of bright features
outside the reconnection layer.
This is the result of shock
waves which form in our system
because our plasma flows
are moving supersonically.
Second, especially
in that third image,
we see small-scale variation
in the Z direction moving
up and down in our images.
The fact that we
see these variations
indicates that we have
instabilities of interest
in our plasma, which we
hope to further quantify.
And then fourth,
especially shown
on that final frame, the
fact that dark, sensual void
in the images
appears to be getting
larger and larger with time
is consistent with the idea
that the density in
the reconnection layer
is increasing as time
passes, the layer compression
due to radiative cooling.
So with this, we've broken down
all the key terms in the title.
And very briefly,
four quick takeaways.
First, magnetic reconnection
is an energizing process.
It heats the layer of plasma.
Second, radiative
cooling is pervasive
in astrophysical plasmas,
and it drives the layer
to be colder and denser
as time progresses.
Third, the MARZ platform
on Sandia's Z Machine
allows us to study
extreme plasma physics
in an up close and
detailed manner.
And fourth, and finally,
laser shadowgraphy
is the technique that we're
using in order to image
how the layer structure evolves
during the radiative collapse.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Any questions?
No questions is OK.
I'm good with that.
[LAUGHTER]
I asked this earlier,
but does this
need, like, two independent
plasmas to hit each other?
Or could you see this in
a tokamak, where, like,
if you have some crazy thing?
Oh sure, yeah.
Oh yeah, sorry.
Yeah, so it could be two
initially separate plasmas
that happen to be on
a collision course
and then impact each other.
It could be that, or
I think more commonly,
like a plasma itself is often
of a very fluid and turbulent
thing.
So naturally, if you have
this big plasma soup,
it has a lot of turbulent
motions within it.
So it's almost like
internal to the plasma.
These magnetic field
lines are moving around
and getting twisted about.
So it's almost inevitable
that eventually there's
going to be a region, if
not multiple regions, where
magnetic reconnection occurs
even within the same blob.
Does that make sense?
Yeah.
Would that sort of
turbulence be enough pressure
to get one of these
reconnection events?
Or do you need them to
slam into each other?
I think I believe the
inflow of velocity--
I don't think you need it to
slam into each other per se,
but you do need--
I mentioned at the
very beginning,
we were assuming
that the plasma is
ideal, which means
that the field
lines move as the plasma moves.
So what we do need
is not necessarily
them to slam into
each other, but we
do need a mechanism
for the field lines
to actually move independently
of the plasma flows.
And there are different ways
that you can go with that.
There are different
ways that can happen.
But I don't think that's
requisite of close
slamming into each other.
Cool.
Thank you.
Question.
I can ask you one.
Your images, your shadowgrams,
the very integrated effect
of what has happened
to that laser,
how much effort do
you expect to have
to do in trying to reconstruct
backwards what essentially
happened?
Oh, sorry.
How much what?
How much work in reconstructing
what is actually happening?
Construction resume?
Yeah.
I might have a slide on this.
OK, I don't think I do.
Sorry.
So that's currently what
we're working on right now.
We're trying to-- sorry,
let's go back to the images.
We're trying to
take these images.
And for instance, we want
to quantify the density jump
across this shock front.
So the way that we're
doing that is a combination
of numerical modeling.
We have a Monte Carlo
ray tracing code
that we can use synthetically
to go about this.
But we also have--
we're trying to take an
analytical approach as well,
where we can have a
forward model, if you will,
where we assume a shock
profile and then tune
the parameters
within that function
that best reproduce the
intensity profiles we see.
So that's currently
what we're working on.
And that's why I didn't
include it in this talk.
But we're working on that.
OK.
I have a sort of
general question.
So you're showing
these shadowgrams.
When you guys were setting
up this experiment,
were there any
particular challenges?
Like, did it work right
away, or was there
a lot of troubleshooting
you had to do?
Just when we do experiments,
right, things really
work right away.
So I'm just curious
how that went.
Yeah, yeah.
So in the lead-up to this
experiment, which, again,
was one year ago in April,
we spent at least six months
preparing for fielding this
diagnostic for the first time.
Our experiment here,
this was, I think,
maybe the second or third
experiment that Sandia actually
used laser shadowngraphy on.
So it's a very new technique
for their facility.
And we did a lot of, like I
mentioned, the ray trace code
that we have.
So we have 3D and HD modeling
of our plasma system,
like the entire system and the
evolution of the reconnection
layer.
So we took that 3D electron
density mesh and then fed it
through the ray trace code.
And then we used that sort
of simulation type modeling
in order to design the actual
fielding of this diagnostic
in the experiment.
So we got to choose where
to position the lens, what
the focal length should be.
How do we--
It doesn't really
work the first time.
Yeah, yeah.
So it did work for the
first time, which was--
Congratulations.
It was kind of very fortunate.
Very high stakes because we
only get one or two shots on Z
a year.
So if it didn't work, then--
Yeah.
So it actually does--
that shows how hard the
team worked on that.
That's really impressive.
Yeah.
But there was a lot
of preparatory work
to maximize our chance of work.
Yeah, of course.
So yeah.
Thank you.
Yeah.
We need to move on.
[APPLAUSE]