okay so today we're going to continue
our discussion of oligopoly you remember
last time we started by saying look
there's fundamentally when you have
multiple firms in a market there's two
ways they can behave they can cooperate
or not cooperate and we talked about
what happens when firms don't cooperate
and the basically how leads to worse
outcome for everybody involved because
the dominant strategy basically is a
prisoner
dilemma and but so obviously firms can
do better if they go into the market and
instead of competing they form a
cartel and the way to form a cartel is
quite SE simple in theory the firms
would get together they would say we're
going to act as if we're a monopoly
we're going to treat ourselves as one
firm at the end of the day we'll just
split the
money so we'll basically treat ourselves
as a monopoly for decision making and
we'll split the money at the end so for
example remember from last time we had a
a demand curve of the form P equal 339
minus q and your marginal cost of
147 okay and we solved this Monopoly
problem last time remember when American
was the only firm in the market the
Monopoly solution was qal 96
P equals
243 okay that was the Monopoly
solution so the cartel case what firms
do is they each say look we want 96
flights total let's just each do 48
flights and let's split the profits so
what does each firm get well profits
what are profits profits are price minus
average cost times quantity well price
is
243 in this example average cost equals
marginal cost for the relevant range so
that's
147 times 96 flights total Market
profits are
9216 or alternatively each firm gets
4608 so that's when they cartelize
that's the profits they make price minus
average cost times quantity in our
example average cost equals marginal
cost so price minus marginal cost times
quantity gets you 9216 in total profits
are
4608 per firm compare that to the
profits each firm makes in the Cornell
equilibrium in the Cano equilibrium as
we solved last time under
Corno as we solved last time we found
that um the price um the price was they
charged
$211 okay uh minus 147 was their profits
per unit and they each did 64 flights so
their profits for each firm were
4,096 so profits are 20 or profits are
15% or 12.5%
higher if they if they
cize because they keep the price higher
they make more profits per unit so if
they caliz each firm's profits is 4608
rather than 4096
so Cooperative equilibria deliver a
better outcome they competive than
non-cooperative equilibria in in an
oligopolistic Market generally true once
again you'll learn in 1412 you learn fun
examples where that's not true but
generally true for this course it's true
now that raises the question why don't
all
oligopolistic markets feature
cartels and there's really two reasons
okay there's one that economists focus
on and one that lawyers focus on the one
that economists focus on is the
incentive based explanation which is
that cartels are fundamentally
unstable they're unstable in the same
way that the prison's dilemma creates
instability which is the person's
dilemma I can only solve it if I really
truly trust you if I'm afraid you're
going to rat on me then I'll rat on you
it's the same in the cartel there's an
incentive to cheat and that's because
when you cheat I'll show you
mathematically when you cheat you get
all the benefit but only bear half the
cost what I mean by that well let's show
you what I mean by that imagine that
American quietly without telling youai
they've agreed to this equilibrium
they're each going to fly 48 flights and
they're each going to make
4608 Now American without telling United
says you know I'm going to do 50 flights
I'm gonna up my number of flights to 50
well the only way American can do that
given the downward sling demand covers
by the price coming down so if the if
American does 50 flights that raise the
total to
98 so if American cheats and does 50
flights then the price goes
to then big quantity goes to 98 so the
price Falls from 243 to
241 the price has to fall if you're
going to sell 98 flights instead of 96
flights okay what does American make in
profits well the profit for
American are
241 minus 147 * 50 because they're doing
50 flights now okay that's their new
profits okay and so the price is falling
but they're flying 50 flights and so
they get new profits of
4700 their profits have gone up by
cheating what's United's profits well I
think you know the answer United's
prophets gone down what's profits United
well they're it's
241 minus 147 but they're still only
doing 48
flights okay so their profits fall to
4512 4512 sorry this just got compressed
so price is
241 cost is 147 they're still doing 48
flights 241 - 147 * 48 is
4512 so by
cheating America has raised their
profits but lowered the profits of
United and if you do the math United's
profits have
fallen by as much as Americans have gone
up and but the total profits in the
market have shrunk look at the total
profits in the market now total profits
in the market are now
9212 instead of
9216 you do 4512 plus 4700 you get 922
12 total profits have fall in the market
why because they didn't do the op the
Monopoly
solution but they fall in a way that
makes American better off and United
worse off what's going on what's going
on is aversion of the poisoning effect
remember the reason the when they're a
monopolis they wouldn't raise the
quantity to 98 is the poisoning
effect but when American raises its
quantity it gets all the benefit of a
higher quantity but spreads the
poisoning effect with
United you know those Americans get all
the benefit going to 50
flights but the poisoning effect gets
shared with United the lower price so
America is incentive to cheat because by
cheating you get all the benefits only
pay half the
costs and that's why cartels are
unstable because basically cartels
feature a version of what we call the
public goods problem which is whenever
my action delivers benefits not only to
you to me but to
you then I might not behave in the favor
that was best for both of us and we'll
come back to that later in the semester
but it's my action by limiting my
quantity if I'm American by limiting to
48 I benefit not only me but you so for
by cheating and going to 50 I benefit me
and we share the costs and therefore
it's a better thing to do so our our
cartel is fundamentally unstable because
any actor in the cartel can make more
money by
deviating okay does that make
sense now the lawyers would saywell you
Economist and your stupid math you can't
even write in the board it's all
squished let's just come to a second
reason why we don't like cartels which
we don't have cartels which is they're
illegal cartels are illegal so basically
um in the late 1800s cartels were common
this is the way much of major industry
organized itself from oil to Railroad
Industries this is called the a of the
robber barons or the Gilded Age there
were giant families like the
Rockefellers and the vand builts that
basically cariz giant Industries like
oil and
railroad okay now how did they enforce
this how do they enforce this well they
the lawyers for Standard Oil I forget
which family that is if that's
Rockefellers or Vanderbilts one it's
Rockefellers lawyers for Standard Oil
said
basically we're going to create what
we're going to call a
trust and the way this trust is going to
work is all firms in the industry will
agree to turn over their pricing and
production decisions to a common board
or trust and that common trust will make
the industrywide pricing and quantity
decisions and then we'll split
it so basically now you still could
cheat but they tried to set up a
non-cheating mechanism by having the
sort of objective mechanism that was
outside them that got to decide and then
monitored how much oil they sold and uh
what price they
got okay now this was wi this is in the
open this wasn't secret they said were
forming this trust and that led to a big
backlash in the creation of what you
might have heard of is the
antitrust movement and the development
of antitrust law antitrust law is
basically
anti-cartel rules and regulations rules
and regulations to try to break down
cartels now lawyers would say we have
these so who cares about the economic
incent well the answer is because the
reason economists care about economic
incentives more than laws or as least as
much as laws is because the laws don't
always
work okay so let me give you a couple
examples one example is the Hollywood
movie
industry so basically um the industry
the Holly M industry has long been
dominated by a few big firms the firms
have changed a little bit over time but
it's MGM you know Fox a
Warner and these films produce firms
these firms produce films and sell them
to movie theaters and movie theaters
then show a variety of movies you know
the Megaplex all the movies they're
showing in the 1930s and 40s these firms
started buying up the movie
theaters and when they buy the movie
theaters they'd say we this is now a
Warner movie theater it can only show
Warner
Movies so it essentially created this uh
cart this anti-competitive practice
where it would not let movie theaters
bid against each other for movies they
would just say look if you're a Warner
movie theater you only show Warner
movies and therefore MGM movies couldn't
compete in certain markets that allow so
let's say you're the one movie theater
in town you're a Warner movie theater
you can charge whatever you want because
there's no MGM movie to compete with it
if want see MJ you got to go to the next
town so this is exactly kind of
anti-competitive practice that antitrust
laws are designed to break up and they
did but sometimes it's harder because
they're less out in the open so let's
take the case of
Airlines uh in the early 2000 oil prices
went
up and Airlines started adding oil
search charges so rather is raising
their prices your ticket for the airline
would say here's your price and here's
your oil search charge because oil
prices have gone
up okay in 2004 British Airways and
Virgin Atlantic were the two dominant
airlines flying across the
Atlantic and they met in secret and
reached a
deal and their deal was that they would
coordin in a coordinated way jack up the
oil charges and the oil charges went
from $10 to $120 a
ticket and they agreed they wouldn't
undercut the other person because they
weren't really able to charge at that
point they were just higher prices just
an excuse that prices have gone up and
they basically said look we won't
undercut each other we'll have a cartel
the cartel instead of coordinating on
the explicit price to take will
coordinate on this bonus part of the
price something economists often call a
shrouded attribute an extra part of the
price you don't pay attention to
Consumers won't notice as much because
they're less price elastic to these sort
of hidden parts of costs and we won't
undercut each other make a lot of
money so basically um they got this deal
at worked but here's once again why
economistic incentives matter the
lawyers for Virgin Airline caught wind
of what their Executives had agreed
to and the lawyer said you know what if
if British Airways ever ever says ever
tells what we're doing to The Regulators
British Airways will get away with it
and we'll be screwed so what did they
do they went to The Regulators because
it's an end it's it's a repeated game
with an end they knew that at some point
someone was going to cheat so it might
as well someone's going to break it up
it might as well be them they did they
went to the regulars reported the scheme
got a slap on the wrist and British
Airways got an enormous
fine uh virgin Airway paid nothing
British Airways paid $500
million okay so this instability is not
just mathematical it's just generally a
feature of why cooperation is hard
cooperation requires trust and
consistency and that's hard between
natural
competitors it's hard to make that
happen so that's you know cartel
instability the laws help but here was
something they were getting around the
law what broke it up was not the law
what broke it up was
incentives so Economist trust incentives
over the law okay now there's a third
example which is quite interesting which
is sometimes cartels can operate in the
open and get away with it let's talk
about the National Football League the
NFL the NFL is the most important
football organization in America the
most profitable important football
organization in America football's the
most profitable uh sport in the country
adver advertising is incredibly valuable
leing football games increasingly so
because now we all watch it's the one
place in the world you don't
stream so we stream everything we watch
now so we don't have ads you can't
stream Sports so Sports advertising has
gone through the roof because
advertising in other context is less
valuable used to be could advertise
everywhere now you can't it's really
just Sports at the last place people
watch ads so it's incredibly valuable
now the NFL is 32 teams essentially 32
businesses competing in a literal sense
with each
other so this and there's a huge
incentive to
collude let's take the New York Giants
and the New York Jets and you know the
New Jersey Giant New York Jets but it's
the same same
Market let's say that they both let's
say the TV station says the major TV
station says look we're going to
broadcast whichever team gives us the
better deal well the Giants and jets
will have to compete with each other
give the TV station a better de deal
let's say they look we'll agree not to
do that we'll just tell the TV station
this is our price it's 2 m you know
basically instead of a billion dollars
it'll be2 billion dollar we each have $2
billion dollar either take it or leave
it and TV station end up broadcasting
both or maybe one TV station takes one
another TV station takes
another and more generally what the NFL
does is they only sell the TV rights for
the league they don't sell TV rights for
individual teams so individual teams do
not sell their TV rights which could
lead to competition the league just
sells the TV rights which causes a
cartel essentially they're saying if you
want to broadcast football you got to
come to us and we're only going to we're
going to charge a super high price as a
result quite frankly watching football
is a bit of a pain in the ass at this
point so you've got Network TV which if
the local team is on you can only watch
the local
team otherwise there may be one other
game
on you've got Sunday Night Football
which is on network TV you we got
Thursday Night Football which I think is
on Amazon or ESPN Amazon Thursday night
who's got Thursday Night Football am
Amazon you've got Sunday morning
football from London which is ESPN
plus then you can do what I did in Pony
up $350 to buy Sunday ticket if you like
an out of town team you want to watch
your team which lets you watch any game
you want on Sunday except the Sunday
morning games where you still have to
buy ESPN plus as I learned much to my
chrin so it's incredibly expensive to
watch football
if you want to see all the football
games it cost you a pretty penny why
because the league is colluded and set
up a structure where basically firms
can't undercut each otherwi firms and
say look a lot of people want my team
I'm going to go strike a separate
deal indeed in
1957 the Supreme Court 1957 even before
I was born that's how long ago it was
the Supreme Court ruled that this was
anti-competitive and they couldn't do
it they did yet it's still done and the
NFL will make $40 billion this year off
their collusive
cartel
why because Congress stepped in and said
well we're going to grant them an
Anti-Trust exemption we're going to say
football is such of a national important
priority that we're going to actually
exempt football from our nation's
antitrust laws so I said last time in my
previous lecture I'd prove to you that
Congress cares more about football than
economics
okay they cared more about the football
league than actually making football
affordable for us to watch so by
granting them antitrust exemption they
allowed them to collude and have this
one League that makes it incredibly
expensive to watch
football okay questions about
that one other fun example um we're
going to discuss international trade in
a few lectures we'll it's really
interesting topic we'll spend some time
on it but the bottom line is economists
generally feel free international trade
is is a good thing we'll come back to
subtleties but roughly speaking We
Believe free Inter National trade is a
good thing and for years that was
reflected in the views of the Republican
Party the Republican party was a party
of free trade Democrats were the party
of less free trade okay that's changed
over time but that was the traditional
when I was a kid there was the free
trade party and the less free trade
party okay Ronald Reagan you don't get
more Republican than Ronald Reagan
Ronald Reagan in 1981 faced a problem
which is Japan was starting to make cars
that americ Americans like more than
americanmade cars and Japan was killing
us in the car market they were people
Americans were buying Japanese cars
instead of American cars and the US
autom manufacturers mad they said you
should limit how many japanese cars come
in and Reagan said I'm a free trade
Republican I can't do that or at least I
can't appear to be doing that so what
did they do they said I'll tell you what
we're going to negotiate a deal we're
going to call a voluntary export
restraint a Veer we're gonna say to
Japan look you can do what you want
okay but we're going to ask you to limit
how many cars you sell in
America we're going to say let's say
you're selling two million cars a year
we're goingon to ask you to limit to one
and a half million a year we're not
telling you I'm free trade we're just
asking you why did Japan
agree why did Japanese automakers
agree to reduce how many cars they sell
in
America I mean it's not geopolitics it's
economics
yeah yeah it's essentially the US celiz
the Japanese Auto industry we basically
said we won't let you compete your price
down remember I talked about government
can fix Monopoly by regulating a low
price this is government regulating a
high
price regulating a low quantity so it
basically japanes said sure you're
basically our companies we the companies
would love to compete less we just can't
do it so you are basically enforcing
calization on us you're enforcing the
fact we can't drive the price down of
our cars thank you very much the
estimates are that as a result of this
deal the average Japanese car price in
the US Rose by
14% And us consumers the best estimat
are lost $3 billion do in consumer
surplus for the fact they couldn't buy
cheap Japanese cars they
wanted so these are all examples of
different ways calization can happen
it's hard governments can play both a
constructive and destructive
role okay questions about any of
that okay so what I want to do now is I
want to do a little comparison between
the models let's compare the models
we've now covered three models we've
covered perfect
competition Monopoly and oligopoly at
least the Coro and once again I've said
this a million times I'm sorry to bore
you but the Coro Cas is the very tip of
the iceberg there's a million other
interesting cases you can learn about
1412 okay let's look at what each of
these three cases imply so we have
Monopoly we have perfect competition I'm
sorry we have
oligopoly by which we mean
Corno and then we have perfect
competition okay let's see what these
these imply for the quantity
produced and what they imply for profits
per
firm okay well we know that if they
monopolize the market quantity is
96 and the profits for firm Are
4608 I solv that up
above we know from up here that if they
don't monopolize each firm produces 64
we solved that Coro problem last time so
the market quantity is
128 and the profits are for
4,096 or 12.5% cheaper
I solved that up
there what about perfect
competition what is the quantity sold in
this market in a perfect competition
everything you need to answer that
question is at the very top of the top
board what is the quantity sold in this
market in perfect
competition
yeah 192 and how'd you get
that right price equals marginal cost is
the key condition for perfect
competition good answer price equals
marginal cost cost is the foundation
perfect competition that means the price
is 147 that means the quantity by the
demand curve is 192 same person what are
profits price is
147 well price is 147 what's
cost 147 zero perfect competition leads
to zero
profits so this is a really important
table because look what you see as the
market gets more
competitive more units are sold and
profits
fall more units are sold and profits
fall okay and the general feature you
get generally true the oligopoly case
will lie between the Monopoly and
perfectly competitive case that's
generally true okay we get sort of bound
the outcome by the Monopoly perfect
competitive Cas alop case will be
somewhere in
between okay questions about this why
this lines up the way it
does what does this mean for
welfare well we could go through and you
asked to do some of this last night and
calculate the producer consumer surplus
for each of these
cases okay but you get a long night I
won't make you do that I'm going to
teach a shortcut now that you wish I
taught you yesterday Monday okay the
shortcut is remember what causes dead
weight
loss trades that are beneficial to both
sides that are not made or in other
words deviations from perfect
competition so we know the answer that
this must be the highest welfare outcome
because we know from the First
Fundamental welfare
theorem that this maximizes
welfare guess what the size of the Dead
weight loss is proportional to the
quantity in other words the more you
shrink the market from the optimal level
the bigger the dead weight loss the more
trades that don't get made cuz look the
structure of the problem these first two
equations okay these are the same the
structure of problem has not
changed so as you shrink quantity all
you're do is creating more and more dead
weight
loss because dead weight loss is about
trades that aren't made that would be
beneficial any trade at a price above
147 is
beneficial any any ticket bought in an
airline at a price price above 147 is
beneficial because it wouldn't be bought
if the consumer didn't want it and it's
above
cost so as the quantity Falls as the
price rise above 147 the quality Falls
below
192 welfare is going
down total social welfare is going down
producer Surplus is going up but
consumer surplus is falling
faster okay because dead weight loss is
proportional to
quantity the more you R quantity from
the perfectly competitive case the
bigger the dead weight loss you
create okay the more you restrict
quantity per competitive case the more
trades that aren't made that are
beneficial okay questions about
that okay that's one point I want to
make the second point I want to make is
I want to talk about what happens when
you have many firms
what happens when you have many
firms well we've talked about one firm
Monopoly we've talked about essentially
infinite firms which is perfect
competition we've talked about two firms
which is Corno what about three four
five six seven eight firms what about
ends that are between zero and
infinity well it turns out and you could
sort of see this here that the Cano
equilibrium approaches perfect
competition as the number of firms goes
to
Infinity the oligopoly model approaches
the perfectly competitive model as the
number of firms goes to Infinity as the
number of firms goes towards one it
approaches a monopoly model olop covers
this whole Space depending on the number
of
firms okay and in particular you can
derive this but you don't have to the
markup that you get in oligopolistic
Market is minus one Over N time Epsilon
the elasticity demand remember the
marker for monopolies was this without
the N you tested on that last night that
was the markup without without oligopoly
and Monopoly when you add oligopoly all
you do is add the N to that
denominator all you do is add the end to
that
denominator and so basically the markup
Falls in alistic market for two
reasons one is as the number of firms
get large the Prof the markup up Falls
and thus the profits fall the other is
the elocity of demand gets large just
like we talked about Monopoly the
profits fall the markup Falls so what
constrains an oligopolist an oligopolist
in this model is both how many firms
they're competing with and how elastic
the demand is for the
good
okay
so that but it's not only that n has
sort of this is sort of the direct
effect of n there's an indirect effect
of more firms too indirect effect the
indirect effect is it's harder to have a
cartel the more players there are so n
going up not only lowers profits because
through this mechanical mechanism n up
lowers profits because it breaks
possibilities for Cooperative equilibria
so for example um for a long time the
only two countries that sold Mercury on
the World Market were Italy and Spain
Mercury like is in lots of stuff okay
Italy and Spain and they formed a cartel
and they successfully kept pric up like
OPEC does for oil now but then other
nations in particular Russia started
producing Mercury and the cartel broke
down because they couldn't they didn't
trust those damn Russians and they
couldn't form a coalition and the cartel
broke down so the other reason n matters
is not just mechanical reason but the
sort of logistical reason that cartels
get harder the bigger end
gets and then this raises the last thing
this raises is how do we think about
government policy in olop
markets and in particular a very rich
Arab government policy is Anti-Trust
policy okay this is a hugely topical
issue some of you may be reading about
the Google case that's going on right
now where mit's own Mike Winston is the
key expert witness for the government my
colleague is the key expert for the
government in the Google case what's the
Google case the Google case is that
Google has
monopolized the market for search
engines which we all sort of know right
we Google things we don't Bing them okay
so basically it just it's easier to say
I'm going to go Duck Duck Go something
which just sound weird right Googling
and they they have the linguistic
Advantage as well and part of the reason
they do that that came out in this trial
is that they pay Apple 10 billion dollar
a
year 10 billion a year to make Google
the default search engine on
iPhones and we're all subject to default
bias we all just goes what the defaults
are I mean you can always switch or
search gention but no one
does and the key question this trial is
does Google have 98% more 92% market
share because they've paid off the
companies to make them default or
because they're better Google's just
saying look we're better search
engine you you wouldn't penalize a
company for being better if we're better
we should get more market share and
that's absolutely true and that's the
incredible difficult part about this
case is the judge has to
decide does Google have 90% market share
fairly by just being a better search
engine or unfairly by paying off Apple
so no other search engines get a
chance this is an incredibly exciting
area of Economics the even bigger cases
coming the Google's just a warm-up
because what's coming next okay is the
app is is it Apple Amazon I forget which
is the next big one Amazon's the next
book one right so
Amazon Amazon right of course when you
go on Amazon of course it's Amazon you
can buy stuff from Amazon from Amazon
Marketplace about 40% of stuff that's
sold on Amazon is sold on Amazon
Marketplace which is other vendors that
come to Amazon and sell on their
platform because it's great because you
just you know you Google search engine
you Amazon shopping right when you want
to shop you go and then therefore if
Amazon doesn't sell you find these
vendors turns out Amazon charges these
vendors enormous
amounts Amazon takes something like a
quarter of the profits they make some
huge amount and they do all of things
like making them pay fees they L where
they're listed on the list they have to
pay more to be hir in the list
Etc and the government is suing saying
that that is antitrust Behavior because
we don't have a competitive market for
these firms since Amazon dominates
online
search as Amazon dominates online search
they have a dominant position to
monopolize the ability of firms to sell
their
goods well what's the counterargument
well the government's going to say look
at the data Amazon has more than 50% of
the entire online shopping market is
Amazon they're they effectively dominate
the market Amazon's goingon to say
where's something like 8% of the entire
market for goods in
America why should you only consider us
competing with online things we also
compete with The Gap we compete with
brick and mortar
too why should we why should you say we
dominate just because we dominate online
these these little these little folks
who advertise on us could always just go
sell in the gap or sell in brick and
mortar as well
what's the right answer that's going to
be a hard thing a judg is going to have
to decide but that's why this is an
incredibly exciting and interesting area
and you found this interesting my
colleague Nancy Rose worked for the
government she was a government's Chief
Economist doing exactly this for two
years and she's teaching 1420 and she
teach you all about how this works and
the exciting cases and how governments
think about this but it's a very hard
and exciting topic and obviously very
topical okay and one thing that this
does that's sort of more personal relev
to my research is think about Hospital
mergers so basically if two hospitals
want to
merge the benefit is there could be cost
efficiencies so two hospitals are across
the street from each other and they want
to merge they could be cost efficients
they could share resources they could
shrink the number of beds maybe so they
don't have so much excess capacity Etc
on the other hand they get more Market
power so the typical antitrust case
unlike these Amazon and Google cases
which are very exciting right now the
typical trust case is a little more
mundane which is when two firms merge
it's a trade-off between efficiencies of
merging returns to economies of
scale versus Market
power and essentially what you have to
do is evaluate which of those dominates
so for Hospital mergers for decades we
let Hospital mergers go on we just said
yeah whatever Hospital want to merge we
let them merge we said look this just
huge efficiency of scale turns out we
were totally wrong when hospitals merged
they don't get efficient at all they
just raise
prices they could get more efficient but
they don't they just raise prices so now
we're starting to crack down in hospital
mergers but that's exactly once again
the kind of interesting example we talk
about in this field
okay now let me go to the last topic
which I should have it you know uh
prepped you for more last time because
it related to some of the questions I
got which is I got a lot of questions
roughly of the form why do firms have to
set the same prices we don't think of
firms as competing on quantity we think
of firms competing on price you've got
this weird model where American and
United compete by deciding how many
flights to have that's not how firms
compete they compete by setting their
price and so you were saying that
quantity competition is right not the
right model price competition is the
right model so now let's go to analyzing
oligopoly in alternative world where
firms don't compete on quantity and let
the market decide price they compete on
price and let the Market side
quantity here we move from the Corno
model to What's called the bertron model
all these French French guys got to name
the I got to name the oligopoly
models the brron model is radically
different than the Coro model because
the Tron Patron model has a simple
conclusion which is with price
competition all you need is two firms an
N of two to get to the perfectly
competitive
outcome why why with price if United
America were truly price
competition why would you only need two
firms like that to get to perfect
competition why is that true if they're
competing on price not
quantity
yeah it it it's the same as our entry
logic remember entry logic as long as
our profits new firms will enter well
it's the same logic as long as our
profits the other guy will undercut so
if American starts making profits United
will come in a dollar less they'll still
make money they'll steal the market so
America come a dollar less that'll
continue until price equals marginal
cost now in fact it won't right
nothing's ever that perfect but
theoretically as long as price is
Epsilon above marginal cost some the
other firm will come and set price to
half an Epsilon above marginal cost and
take the
market okay so basically the betron
model
is totally radically different it's just
look two firms is perfect competition
there's Bas there Monopoly and perfect
competition no
oligopoly one firm's Monopoly two firms
plus is perfect
competition that a very radically
different prediction and quite frankly a
lot less interesting so this raises sort
of two points the first point is well
what's the right model to
use and the answer roughly speaking is
it depends on the kind of Market you're
thinking
about basically the answer depends
basically price competition is more
likely when you can instantaneously meet
demand quantity competition is more
likely when there's lags of meeting
demand let's think about breakfast
cereals versus
cars breakfast cereals compete on price
okay because the truth is if I'm lower
price all of a sudden people want twice
as many apple cinnamon cereals I boom I
make them they're on the shelves the
next
day cars if suddenly we want twice as
many cars it takes months to produce
them
so they can't just say under cutting
price and meet demand if you're undercut
price you can't meet demand so they more
likely to compat on
quantity now in reality of course as
always it's a mix of the two but roughly
speaking the way to think about it is
price competition is more likely in very
very rapid turnaround Industries
quantity competition is more likely in
more in Industries with more complicated
production processes where they're
lags and obviously nothing's at that
extreme but that sort of is the
intuition but it's not it's not a very
clean distinction so you really need to
know both models it's just the K model
is kind of more fun butron model is kind
of
boring okay so that's the first point I
want to make the second point I want to
make which is really
interesting is let's say you are
breakfast
cereals you're in the perfect Patron
competition case perfectly competitive
it's easy to create backf for
cereals what do you how do you still end
up making profits what do you do if
you're a breakfast cereal company
in this brron equilibrium to try to make
profits what can you
do
yeah exactly you can product
differentiate essentially you can create
little monopolies you could say sure
there's perfect competition for Cheerios
but now evented apple cinnamon
Cheerios and for a while at least I have
a monopoly in apple cinnamon Cheerios so
now I can go back to making
money okay so I'm not using cereals at
random it's a great example so around
World War II there was essentially three
types of cereal in World War II Cheerios
cornflakes and Quaker roats that was
it okay uh but by
1970 there was more than 150 breakfast
cereals to choose from uh including ones
that are very similar like apple
cinnamon
Cheerios okay by 1970s So ba but
basically I'm sorry let back up I said
this wrong 1953 type Cal by 1970 there
150 Cal but it wasn't differentiation it
was that stores had realized they can
make generic versions so they made odios
which were Cheerios different name but
they were Cheerios and then they could
just sell them they could sell them at
Epsilon above marginal cost and make
money so essentially the serial
companies were not making profits
anymore because generic products have
been introduced to essentially mimic
what they were making so they
differentiated in 1989 General M apple
cinnamon Cheerios it's less old than you
think okay it's before you guys but well
after me apple cinnamon
Cheerios now when apple cinnamon
Cheerios came in they were delicious
objectively okay and there was no good
substitute so they suddenly face fairly
inelastic demand so they could raise
prices above marginal cost so General
Mills while getting competed to death on
regular Cheerios could suddenly have a
highly profitable apple cinnamon Cheerio
line and they patented the apple
cinnamon formula so for a while there
wasn't competition now there's generic
Apple cin materials but there weren't
for the first few
years okay so by product
differentiating they ended this death
cycle of Patron
competition is that good or
bad let's come back to welfare yeah oh
and just checking your nails question
answer rather uh is that good or bad
yeah well is it good or bad depends very
much on your model we think it's
probably good because of the principle
I've talked about reveal preference
which is if people didn't want apple
cinnamon materials they wouldn't buy
them so you've created a new in product
differenti you've created a new
product that consumers want indeed my
colleague very famous economist and
Jerry hman actually estimated that the
introduction of apple cinnamon Cheerios
raise consumer surplus by more than $75
million a
year because they had this new thing
they
wanted now on the other
hand they were paying a Monopoly price
for it so we are better off in a world
with apple cinnamon Cheerios than
without it but we're still not as good
off not not as well off if they weren't
if there wasn't more competition bring
apple cinnamon Cheerios so it doesn't
mean in other words in Economist we talk
about the we talked about the First
Fundamental welfare theorem the best we
can do we also talk about the second
best which is well the best we can do
given constraints we live
under so having apple cinnamon chur is
the best we could do it's the second
best we are better off having Apple C
than not but the first best would be
apple cinnam materials with a regulated
price at the perfectly competitive price
or at least above it enough to invent
new products so indeed today only five
five firms make most cereals five firms
there are 5,000 types of cereal
5,000 so that
raises another interesting issue so
overall economistic product
differentiation is good we think
essentially it's driving variety people
like variety if they didn't they
wouldn't buy it that's
good but there's starting to be an
interesting question in industrial
organization of the problem of choice
overload which is in some sense are we
actually do we have too many choices in
economics we assume more choices good
that's our fundamental assumption but
what if now you just get to the you get
to the supermarket you look that you're
like it I'm gonna have toast okay
because you're like I just can't decide
there's so much well you could get to
the point we're actually worse off from
that much product differentiation that
wouldn't be in a standard model that's
looking forward to something we'll cover
at the next to last lecture we call
behavioral economics
which I'm so excited about I dropped my
mic uh uh I guess that's a mic drop um
so uh that's in behavioral economics we
talk about we'll talk about this but the
point is the standard economic model
would say at this person correctly
answered more product differentiation is
good but there's two caveat to that one
is it's still not as good as if we had
it at competitive prices just like
patents are good but still not as good
competitive prices and the second issue
is there's a question whether proct can
actually go too far and can you get
Choice overload and that leads us to
more interesting psychological models of
behavior that we'll come to we talk
about behavioral economics okay
questions about
that okay let's stop there and we will
come back uh next week