Our next speaker is Johannes Lintner. Um
Johannes um if you please come down
here. Yeah. Set on your computer.
Johannes, as Jesse was mentioning, did
his postto studies with um Anul Kundi
at Stanford and now works as a machine
learning scientist at Kelly Co Life
Sciences with David Kelly and several
others. And um so we are very pleased to
have you here today, Johannes. and um
your title is predicting gene regulatory
function from DNA sequence with deep
learning.
>> Great. Thank you for that introduction
and thank you for the organizers for
inviting me today to give a talk. Um see
I'll be using this one.
Great. Okay. So uh this is my disclosure
and so um today I'll be sharing some of
our work in David Kelly's group um where
we develop sort of these u machine
learning models that allow us to predict
various types of gene regulatory
function uh from DNA sequence and sort
of what we aim to do with these models
is to functionally interpret uh genetic
variation to aid us in interpretation of
of various uh variant data sets. Um so
as we all know the human genome consists
of these various um regulatory layers
ranging from you know chromatin
accessibility to transcriptional
activation to post- transanscriptional
processing like isoform processing and
other u regulatory steps and um in
Dave's group we developed these uh
parametric machine learning models that
take you know the genomic sequence as
input and are then trained on various
data sets to predict these regulatory
functions from sequence and there many
you know uh interesting and important
downstream applications uh for these
kinds of models in Jesse's excellent
talk you know one really cool
application is to actually denovo design
or or edit uh regulatory sequences uh
the the application I'll be focusing on
today is to actually use these models to
to functionally interpret uh genetic
variation
so as a as a brief overview I'll start
by describing uh a neural network model
that we developed called Borsoy that
allows us to predict raw RNA seek
coverage patterns from DNA sequence and
then hopefully I'll have time to
highlight some of our uh most recent
work where we extend the this modeling
framework to actually predict uh
pseudabbulk cell type specific uh single
cell RNA seek coverage patterns and sort
of adding a cell type specific spin to
to the model.
So beginning with Borsoid and as a
general introduction to the problem that
we're trying to to tackle here uh you
know the human genome consists of more
than three billion base pairs. The vast
majority of these nucleotides do not
actually code for a particular protein.
Instead these nucleotides make up a
complex uh sequence regulatory code that
governs gene expression through multiple
layers of regulation. You know, for
example, at the layer of chromatin, uh
we have enhancer and repressor elements
spread out throughout the genome that
control the transcriptional activity of
genes that can be very far away.
Then as a gene is transcribed into
premrna, it's further subjected to
additional regulatory processes
including splicing and polyinhilation.
And to some extent, these processes are
themselves regulated by a sequence code
embedded in the primr molecule.
Finally this uh now mature MRA
transcript can go on and become protein
product and along that journey it's
again uh further subjected to these
various regulatory steps such as MR&A
degradation or control you know mediated
by translation efficiency or other
mechanisms and and these mechanisms are
themselves controlled by by a sequence
code at least to some extent that in
this case now is you know embedded in
the mature mRNA transcript
and you know it's well known by now that
numerous non-coding genetic variants are
you know implicated in genetic disease
by uh disrupting these various um
regulatory functions.
But you know to this day it remains
extremely complicated to take any given
genetic you know non-coding mutation and
understand at a sufficiently detailed
level how that mutation is potentially
impacting each of these regulatory
functions. And to make things more
complicated, you know, these mutations
may have cell and tissue specific
effects.
So in Dave's lab, we're trying to
approach this by training these
high-capacity uh machine learning models
um on on large scale molecular data in
order to predict these regulatory steps
from sequence alone. And with those
kinds of models, we can then use them as
kind of simulation engines to simulate
um the impact of any individual mutation
in isolation. And really by applying
interpretation techniques to these
trained models and to their predictions,
we can try to elucidate what in the
underlying sequence grammar was actually
disrupted by by that mutation.
And you know, as a as a brief motivation
for why we're interested in doing this
at Calico Life Sciences, you know, we're
very interested in studying the the
hallmarks and and mechanisms of aging
and aging related disease. And one
powerful uh way to do that is to to
study genomewide association studies uh
as many other people in in this uh room
do. Um but as we all know it's can be
extremely complicated because you can
get hundreds to thousands of significant
hits and you know these snips can be
confounded by linkage disequilibrium. Um
meaning that it's it's very hard to to
tear apart the actual causal variance.
Not to mention actually functionally
understanding how those mechanisms are
acting. And so that's where we're hoping
these machine learning models can come
in and help us, you know, prioritize
variants that are more likely to be
causal and by giving us grounded
interpretation of what in the sequence
was disturbed.
So one um rather flexible and and quite
powerful approach for modeling many of
these regulatory functions um is to
reduce the problem to that of learning
to predict genomewide sequencing
coverage essays as kind of
one-dimensional coverage profiles given
only you know the genomic sequence as
input and this approach was popularized
by the informer model that was developed
by by DeepMind and and by my PI David
Kelly at Calico. Um and uh recently in
Dave's lab, we developed this new model
called Borsoy that takes that idea kind
of one step further where we're now um
teaching the model to actually predict
raw RNA seek coverage patterns in a
tissue specific manner uh from sequence
alone. The intuition here is that if a
parametric model can learn to predict
RNA seek coverage patterns, you know,
over the exxons of a gene, it must have
implicitly learned about many different
regulatory steps sort of in one single
model, right? It must have learned about
transcriptional activation and chromatin
accessibility. It must have learned
about, you know, uh, splicing and
polyation in order to to identify the
the exxons and the relative magnitudes.
So, we think that here you're learning
about many regulatory layers in sort of
one go.
So architecturally speaking, the model
borrows from many different ideas in the
ML literature uh but of course builds on
many of the successful components from
the predecessor and former model. So to
start off with the the Borsa model is
shaped as kind of like a unit basically.
Um it takes in this huge chunk of
genomic sequence uh roughly half a
megabase. The sequence is is then
transformed through a number of
convolutional layers interspersed with
with subsampling layers. The
convolutional layers are sort of
learning different you know salient
regulatory motifs and the subsampling
layers are reducing the sequence length
into a manageable length such that we
can then apply uh these um self
attention blocks that allow us to quite
efficiently transmit long range
information from one position to every
other position in just sort of one one
layer of computation. Um
and then finally to actually predict RNC
coverage we want to do that at a
reasonably fine resolution you know
because some Exxons can actually be
quite thin. Uh so then we borrow these
um unit uh the approach of of of unit
layers from the computer vision
literature where we're now upsampling
the signal signal again with
convolutional layers and these kind of
skip connections. uh now finally
predicting coverage at 32 base pair
resolution.
So to train the model we're using both
human and mouse data. So we're training
the model in sort of alternating batches
of human sequence and mouse sequence and
we uh curated uh u basically
one-dimensional coverage profiles to
train on. Uh so so basically the input
to the model is this very large sequence
and the output is a collection of uh
one-dimensional coverage profiles a very
large collection of coverage profiles
and uh we collected I think almost 1,000
uh human RNA seek experiments from both
the incode and GTEx consortia which are
you know these amazing resources that
have these um coverage profiles
basically made available for for public
consumption.
Um we coupled the training of the model
with um we trained the model to jointly
also predict various epigenomic coverage
essays which we noticed improve the
model's ability to generalize and make
better RNA coverage predictions because
it's then learning to rely on more
salient features. Um and then we also of
course included um cage uh data
measuring expression at the five prime
ends of genes from the phantom
consortium.
So after having trained the model on um
on human and mouse sequences, uh we can
now apply it to predict RNAC coverage in
held out sequences of the genome that
the model didn't see during training.
And qualitatively you can see that the
model can quite accurately you know
identify the exxons and place coverage
over those exxons uh roughly on par with
you know with what the measurements look
like. And now if you were to sum the
total amount of predicted coverage over
the exxons uh of the predicted track for
a given gene, we can drive a single you
know scalar gene expression prediction.
And if we compare predicted to measured
gene expression values uh we actually
observe quite good concordance on on
held out test genes across these various
uh sequencing experiments that we train
to predict.
So what's nice with these kinds of
machine learning models is that uh
they're not necessarily just a blackbox
uh predictor. But now when we can make
these RNA coverage predictions, we can
apply various interpretation techniques
to those predictions in order to
elucidate what features in the original
you know huge input sequence actually
contributed to the RNA seek prediction.
So to illustrate that what we did here
is that we centered the borsoy uh you
know half a megabase input window on the
liver specific CFHR2 gene which is known
to be liver specific and we then
predicted RNA seek coverage in five
distinct tissues including liver and a
few other offtarget tissues. We then um
what we do then is we sum the total
coverage over the exxons of the CFHR2
gene. So we get like a scalar gene
expression prediction per tissue. We
then apply this interpretation technique
where we rely on the differentiability
of the neural network model and we back
propagate the gradient of the RNAC
coverage prediction per tissue down all
the way to the sequence level so that we
estimate the gradient of the prediction
with respect to the sequence. So you can
think of that sort of as a as a
sensitivity map that tells you how much
the the RNA coverage prediction in that
tissue is perturbed given a slight
perturbation to the input sequence. And
if we do that, what you see in the upper
figure there is basically um the the
most salient region that occurs a bit
outside of the the CFHR2 gene. And what
we find is basically all these you know
well-known liver specific uh
transcription factor motifs that are
effectively predicted to drive the
expression of this of this gene. Now if
you you know repeat that exercise for
many different genes by you know
recomputing the input gradients for for
for many different genes and you cluster
these uh gradient scores with a denovo
motif discovery tool called TF modiscoco
we recapitulate many known you know
transcription factor binding motifs and
one thing that's quite nice is that you
know um if you look at the motifs that
are are known to be tissue specific uh
the model really only places high
importance on those motifs in the
original input sequence when making
predictions for the corresponding
tissue. So the model is sort of relying
on these sequence features in a tissue
specific way.
Another really nice thing uh now when
you have a parametric model of RNA
coverage prediction is that you can use
this model to simulate the effect of in
theory any sequence that you input to
the model of course to varying degrees
of accuracy perhaps. Um but now we can
use this as a tool to actually simulate
the impact of genetic variation in
isolation. So to illustrate that here
I'm showing you a particular gene that
has a fine map causal EQL snip uh sort
of it's kind of a deep intronic snip
that occurs at the center of this gene.
It's kind of marked by that the black
star and then I'm showing you two
different RNA seek coverage predictions.
So these are coverage predictions made
by the borsa model in whole blood. In
blue I'm showing you the prediction for
the reference uh sequence and in high
sort of overlaid in red is the predicted
RNC coverage for the mutated sequence.
So as you can see the borso model
predicts higher coverage almost
uniformly across the exxons meaning that
the model thinks this is sort of a gain
of expression u snip
and now if you actually go out and and
uh you know curate and and aggregate RNA
coverage in individuals from geeks that
either have or don't have this mutation
um we recapitulate the same trend
meaning that the borsa model could quite
accurately predict the effect of this of
this snip
and then of course we can we can again
now apply interpretation technique in
this case uh in silicone saturation
mutagenesis where we just systematically
mutate every nucleotide surrounding the
mutation and we can then get a picture
of what you know this mutation is
potentially creating or destroying at
the sequence level. And in this case,
you know, this motif or sorry, this
mutation is creating a transcription
factor binding motif that is predicted
to work in synergy with nearby um
previously sort of dormant regulatory
motifs that now together kind of create
this strong enhancer element and and
that's what's driving expression here.
And so going beyond just one single
example, you know, if you then create a
set of possible of of um positive GTEx,
you know, fine mapped causal EQL snips
and you task the model with
distinguishing between, you know,
finemapped causal uh EQLs versus a
mashed set of of neutral snips. Um the
the Borso model could basically
distinguish between those two sets based
on its prediction more accurately than
the previous state-of-the-art models
could. Now of course very recently I
think deep deep mind came out with this
new model called alpha genome that seems
to improve upon this even further. So
that's very exciting.
But then another thing that I want to uh
emphasize uh about modeling raw RNAC
coverage patterns as opposed to scalar
gene expression predictions is that it
gives us the opportunity to reason about
a genetic variant not just in terms of
how much it affects the total gene
expression val amount but also how the
relative coverage profile may change due
to a mutation allowing us to actually
reason about how a mutation may impact
isoform processing and other events. So
to illustrate that here I'm showing you
a fine mapped causal polyadonilation QTL
uh highlighted in black that occurs sort
of in in this um very long threep prime
UTR of this gene and this snip is
basically estimated to have an impact on
threep prime processing and and
polyonilation basically increasing
cleavage efficiency and the Borsa model
at the top coverage plot predicts an
increase in coverage upstream of the
mutation and a decrease in coverage as
you can see because the blue is higher
than the red downstream of the mutation.
Meaning that the model basically thinks
that this this mutation is indeed
increasing cleavage efficiency and and
if you look at the bottom plot coverage
plot uh that's basically recapitulated
in individuals that have or or don't
have this mutation.
Finally, if we apply an interpretation
technique, but now instead of, you know,
checking the sensitivity with respect to
just total gene expression amount, we're
now computing the interpretation, the
ISM with respect to the ratio of
coverage upstream versus downstream of
the mutation. And we can see that uh now
we're getting an
in in the sequence we're getting an
interpretation that highlights a CSTF
binding motif which is sort of a
canonical polyation efficiency element
and yeah if if you uh take the borsa
model and you task it with
distinguishing between finemapped causal
polyqtls versus matched negative snips
uh the model is you know outperforming
the the previous state-of-the-art models
at that task and with a similar
reasoning about how the predicted you
know relative RNA seek shape changes you
can reason about splice altering
variance as well quite accurately but I
won't have time to to go into that here
okay so now I want to highlight some of
our uh more recent work where we
extending the this modeling framework to
predict cell type specific expression
profiles
so yeah the motivation is is um very
very simple you know the borsa model was
trained on all these you know uh diverse
uh collections of RNA seek experiments
in tissues as well as you know cell
lines from from encode and from GTEx. Um
but it was not trained on any cell type
specific data at least not in terms of
you know um primary primary cell types
which is of course a big limitation
seeing as I said that we wanted to use
this model to interpret G-W was studies
but as we all know many G-W was losi
have you know are thought to have cell
type specific effects and so that's a
big problem so to remedy that we went
out and we um curated and downloaded uh
many different uh publicly accessible um
single cell earning seek data sets and
generated basically bigwig tracks of um
you know pseudabbulk uh coverage for
distinct cell clusters based on the
original annotations from these studies.
So we downloaded single cell data from
uh table sapiens from tableau muris and
tableau mirror scenis as well as an
adult brain atlas from the big
consortium.
And we now train this new model that we
call borsoy prime. We call it borsoy
prime. Uh well the prime word comes as a
nod to the fact that all of these single
cell RNA seek data sets are generated
with a threep prime end sequencing
protocol. So you know you're getting
coverage pileups now at the site of
polyonilation. Uh so that's that's where
that name comes from. Architecturally
the model is very similar to the the
original Borso model but now with the
bigger distinction that we're training
the model now to predict um single cell
RNA seek you know suitable coverage
tracks for 850 distinct uh human amount
cell clusters.
So after having trained the Borso prime
model, we can now use it to predict RNAC
coverage at a cell type resolution. So
here I'm showing you uh predicted
coverage in micro GA as well as two
other u sort of offtarget cell types uh
for the CIBB gene which was kind of a
gene in in the held out portion of of
the data um that we didn't train on. And
as you can see the model is correctly
you know predicting high coverage in
microglea but low coverage in other um
cell types. And if we aggregate total
coverage in um you know the predicted
bins overlapping exxons of individual
genes we can derive scalar gene
expression values uh and for held out
genes these predicted cell type specific
predictions are matching up quite nicely
with the measurements. And then finally
of course again if we apply
interpretation techniques such as input
gradients and we apply them to these
cell type specific predictions we now
end up with um you know cell type
specific input gradients that we can
cluster with TF modiscoco and recover
you know u motifs and and drivers for
individual cell types like for microglea
you know we're finding spi1 and subp
motifs for example
okay and this is probably the final
slide I think so uh the you know the
final power here now comes in the fact
that we can uh interpret and reason
about um genetic variation at a cell
type level. So to illustrate that here
I'm showing you the predictions in
microglea for a particular snip that is
fine mapped and causal specifically in
microglea and the the interpretation of
the snip highlights this sort of weak uh
ETSs- like motif that seems to increase
expression of this gene.
So beyond one example, we we benchmarked
uh the model on a few different um EQL
uh data sets, fine map EQL data sets at
cell type resolution, including two
smaller studies with EQLs estimated from
from in micro GA and in neurons and then
a larger um single cell EQL data set
from the 1K1K as well in PBMC's. I think
maybe one one uh plot that I want to
maybe emphasize is the scatter plot for
the microglea data set to the bottom
left um there. So as you can see on the
x- axis you have the predicted uh
variant effects of these fine mapped
causal uh eql snips with a high pip and
on the y- axis you have the estimated
beta coefficients from the fine mapping
and you know it's true that the sample
size here is quite small but still the
model is the the variant effect scores
derived from the model predicted tracks
are quite concordant with the estimated
beta coefficients. Now, crucially, if
you look at the bar chart, oh, sorry, if
you look at the bar chart to the right,
you're seeing that actually it's only
the variant effect scores that are
derived from the micro GA predicted
tracks that are concordant with the
estimated beta coefficients in the cell
type. If you look at variant effect
scores derived from some other brain
cell type and some other predicted
track, the variant effect scores have
basically zero concordance which kind of
emphasizes the model emphasizes that the
model is now truly sort of making cell
type specific predictions of variant
effects.
Okay, so in summary, the Borsa model uh
learns to predict several different
layers of gene regulation from DNA
sequence and u the Borso prime model
sort of extends these capabilities by
learning to predict sort of cell type
specific um suitable single cell RNA
coverage profiles
and I just want to end by highlighting
some other work uh uh from our group uh
for example Diani's method for including
these borso variant effect predictions
to improve functionally informed genetic
find mapping
or Hans's work on uh transfer learning
approaches for actually fine-tuning the
Borsa model towards your own
experimental uh data sets to get sort of
a custom model uh for for a particular
new data set. And we also recently
included uh more post-
transanscriptional regulatory essays
into this modeling framework. For
example, we now have the uh capability
of u predicting RNA seek half-life time
course experiments like transcriptional
shut off experiments in this sort of
profile prediction framework which
allows us to sort of uh you know
estimate MRA decay rates and and those
effects uh in terms of genetic variance.
Okay, so that's all. So thank you for
listening and I'm happy to take
questions.
[Applause]
Thank you very much um Johannes for a
fantastic talk. We have time for an a
few questions um with Millina. Do you
want to stop?
>> Really beautiful talk. Thank you so much
for sharing. Um there there's a lot to
talk about. I wonder about one question.
wanted to seek your input particularly
in the context of looking at the
benchmarking against the fine map EQTLs
>> where the difference between EQTLs and
JVAS fine mapping or JVAS variants is
that the EQTLs are typically much larger
in effect size compared to actual JVAS
detected um variants that have more
common subtle effects.
>> Yeah. the examples that so just to back
up when in in our work when we retrained
Basset back then or used onformer and
Borzoy more recently you know they seem
to up to line up super well with crisper
validations for large effect variants
and less so for subtle effect size
variants. So I wonder I wonder are you
thinking about this and what are what
are your five cents?
>> Yeah, I I think that's a great point. Um
and that's also very much what we see in
that you know when the model is making
very confident high effect predictions
the you know the sign of the prediction
is almost always correct and um it's
it's it's really in in these small
effect size variants where there seems
to be a lot of uh wobble in the in the
interpretations and you know I think one
one really big um thing that we noticed
maybe going from informer to the borso
model was that there's tremendous amount
of epistemic uncertainty In these
models, you know, there's only 20,000
protein coding genes to learn these
relationships from. And so from one
model replicate to another model
replicate train on the same data but
just different random initializations,
you know, some motifs can even flip
direction, right? Because the model is
uncertain about uh the connection. And
so I think ensembling these models more
more and more and more going from you
know informer to boroy we'd now you know
ensemble the model with four different
replicate models and I think alpha
genome now is ensembling up to 50 model
replicates or or something like that and
and they're clearly getting improved
variant effect concordance by that. So
so that seems to be one approach
forward. Um,
I think ultimately we're still kind of
data limited and we need more training
sequences.
>> Great, Brad. Oh, that was a terrific
talk. Thank you. Uh, I kind of have two
related questions. The first is what
kind of data do you think is most, you
know, powers your model the best? What
do you want? Do you want knockouts? Do
you want sequence variation? Do you want
other data types? and you know what
what's needed for your next generation
of models. And the second question is
how important was the metadata knowing
you know exactly the cell type the
conditions it was grown in and all this
other stuff and do you think the
importance of metadata will will
decrease over time when your AI models
can sort of impute it?
>> Yeah, that's a great question regarding
the first question. So we observed a
really really big gain in performance
for a number of tasks but in in
particular for variant effect scoring
when we jointly trained the model to
predict both RNA seek coverage and DNA
or taxi coverage in matched tissues or
cell types probably because you're kind
of pushing the model to look towards
enhanced regions and other salient
features to to better generalized RNA
coverage predictions. So like yeah
adding more modalities and more essays
definitely seem to be an approach for
improving the model further. I'm really
not sure to like at some point I feel
like there's going to be a saturation
effect. We're probably covering many
cell states already in the you know
training data that we have. Um but yeah
like individual perturbations of various
you know transcription factors or like a
yeah genomewide you know perturbation
that data sets that could probably be
great for teasing apart you know um you
can imagine you know you have one
coverage profile that really shows you
what gene expression should be if you
knock out each individual transcription
factor that could help the model link
that observation down to the to each
regulatory motif um more stringently I
Think another axis where we really need
to grow more is just we need more unique
sequences to train on to make these
models more accurate and people have
been exploring you know personal custom
genome fine-tuning now with limited
success. Um there's also this big trend
now in and self-supervised learning of
many different genomes from other you
know related species that could help us
improve these models further. I think
that was the answer to question one and
then did you have a second question
>> just about where do you think how
important is metadata going forward?
>> Right. Right. I you know I think
metadata is important for the tracks
that we ultimately want to use when
scoring genetic variants and
interpreting them. But like in terms of
adding more data for the sake of
improving model quality in terms of you
know adding this all this attack data
over here even though maybe we don't
have perfect annotations for it or
perfect metadata it might still have
positive interactions in making us do
better for predicting RNC coverage um if
we can rely on correlations from that
attack data. So I think it's a mixed
mixed bag.
>> Great. We have a fi two final questions.
So uh I have a two questions. So first
question did you use your model to test
the you know known disease causing
mutation to see whether you know your
predictions are consistent with the
known uh effects. The second question is
did you uh let's say compare your model
to alpha genome to see uh if your model
works better than our genome or is it
comparable?
Yeah, good questions. Regarding the the
first question, um we we have started,
you know, applying and using the model
um for you know specific use cases
related to genetic disease. In terms of
benchmarking, we've relied mostly on
EQTL studies so far just because those
are typically great resources and you
can you can set up these classification
tasks and and comparisons against beta
coefficients uh to to really quite well
you you have a pretty good benchmark
capability there. Uh regarding the
second question, we haven't yet you know
the the Borsa model came out a couple
years ago and alpha genome came out a
few months ago. So we haven't had a
chance to to uh use the alpha genome
model yet. It's also we're a company so
we're not allowed to just yet use that
model. Um yeah
>> great sorry Liz I overlooked um we had a
question up there maybe you might you
will need to take your question in the
break actually. Um hey here
>> so quick question on this um similar to
the more data approach there is also a
parallel line of models being developed
recently shorter context uh single
modality from an lab and also deep star
MP screens uh do you think these two
approaches short context long context uh
and NP will they be unified in the
future in a single model.
>> Yeah, I think that's a good question.
And you know, I think these shorter
sequence models trained either on MPAs
or or endogenous essays are really nice
models. And
you know I I think one one thing with
this approach of doing you know kind of
massive multitask learning like with
Boriso and former alpha genome is that
it's computationally efficient in the
sense that you can you can score genetic
variation with regard to many different
outputs in one forward pass which makes
them quite nice when you're wanting to
investigate some you know genetic uh
data set where you're broadly interested
in in variant effect scores across many
different types of cell states.
um
which may be harder to do with models
that are strictly single task. On the
other hand, those models are way more
efficient in terms of having a shorter
sequence window. So each prediction on
its own is is um computationally
retractable. Um, in terms of combining
uh these data sets,
maybe I mean, you know, if you if you
trust that MP measurements work the same
way in an indogenous context, it would
make sense to try to say fine-tune these
models on MP measurements. I think very
recently there's been some really cool
data sets, new technologies coming out
where it's, you know, it's MPAS, but
it's actually in the indogenous genome
like the the big in platform and and
dark matter DNA, you know, where they're
they're actually doing these really
large rearrangements of the genome and
measuring that out synthetically and in
reasonably high throughput. And I think
those types of data sets are definitely
worth, you know, thinking about how to
combine into here.
>> Thank you.
>> Great. Thank you. I think our brains are
ready for a break. So please join me in
thanking all speakers from those two
great sessions.