so uh last week was a crypto day so I
didn't get to see you so let's kind of
do a quick kind of recap of where we
were uh and where we're heading to so
last time I saw you at least in this
room uh was two weeks ago where we
talked about
how to use uh the gkr protocol to
construct what's called a PCP a
probabilistically checkable proof and
what's a proof the idea is it's you take
a proof so take any NP language let's
say that has a proof like let's say
three set you take a witness or a proof
so a satisfying assignment and you
actually make it longer okay so you
don't shrink it you actually extend it
it's bigger but now to verify it you
don't need to read the entire a
proof what you need to do is just read a
few locations in this proof so you can
even though the proof is actually became
longer you can verify it much more
efficiently by reading just a few
locations and we actually showed how to
constructed how do you get a PCP and the
idea of how how uh to get a PCP the idea
was well let's look at the gkr protocol
for three set so let's do a PCP for for
NP okay so any NP you can convert to a
three set you know three set is and be
complete so convert whatever you want to
prove into a three set formula now you
have a witness now what do you do you
the you you want to generate a PCP what
you do is you you pretend you're a gkr
approver that has this witness the
satisfying assignment and want to
convince the verifier that this is a
valid witness so what do I mean by run
the gkr protocol what I mean is let's
look at the so given fee let's say three
set
instance what you do you look at the
circuit C sub Fe that takes as input a
satisfying assignment an assignment and
outputs you know zero or one whether
it's satisfying or not this is a very
low depth circuit it's just as kind of a
bunch of checks and add the local checks
and and add them all together and now
what what we do is how do you generate
the PTP given this witness given this uh
uh uh witness for fee what you do is you
run in your head the GK protocol for the
circuit so remember the GK protocol is a
protocol that proves that a low depth
circuit that a w that an input is you
know that a given input even though it's
weird the verifier doesn't know the
input so it's kind of weird to think of
gkr in this context gkr the context of
GK was there's an input everybody knows
the input the pro and the verifier but
the circuit is large and the prover
wants to convince the verifier that the
output is
something here it's kind of weird the
input is more or less as large as the
circuit okay because the checking if a
witness that satisfying assignment is
valid for a 3 CNF not the 3nf is the
circuit here is almost the same size as
as the witness and so it seems like why
using gar here is very weird it doesn't
seem like the right application and in
particular the verif Fire doesn't even
have the input so how can you use gkr
that seems very unint
counterintuitive so the IDE is no let's
pretend that he does have the witness
what do you even pretend oh don't worry
we'll give it to him so in the PCP we'll
write the witness not only we write the
witness we're going to actually write
the low deegree extension of the witness
in the PCP okay so what is your big
proof it first contained the lree
extension of the witness sitting there
then for now for each now think of the
gkr protocol for each and every kind of
question of the verifier the prover has
an answer write it down in the PCP so in
the PCP write if the first message of
the verifier you know the first message
is a bunch of like well the F first the
approver goes first so you send the your
univarate polinomial then the verifier
sends a field element now you say well
if the field element was one here's my
answer if the field element was two
here's my answer for each and every
possible field element you say the
answer okay now there's only poly log
number F it's not so bad okay then you
give him the answer now for the prover
sent another field element now he said
for any possible next message here's my
answer and so on so essentially you kind
of open up this G gigantic tree now
first you see why this is huge like it's
it's it's like exponential but actually
G has a very nice
property that the Prov messages actually
only depend on the last very
few messages of the verifier so if you
remember the gkr it's a bunch of su
checks protocol it's like a just a
sequence of su checks and the PR's
message depend only on the messages in
the last subject so it's kind of very
few and kind of where you start it's
very few messages so to be a little more
precise each Pro in gkr each Prov
message depends on the last kind of what
it is it was log n over log
login
messages from V from the
verifier where this is like the number
of variables if you remember when we did
you
and it was a bunch of a bunch of sum
checks and each Su check was over M or 3
m variables this is the
m and the field is poly
Logan and here is the size of the
circuit so think of it the size of the
of the witness the size of the 3 CNF
it's all up to polinomial factors it
doesn't
matter and so now okay you depend you
need to depend on all these messages
from the verifier but there's only that
many each time even if you look this to
the power of this is only ply that's how
that's exactly how we chose h&n so it
will be P that's why we chose these
weird setting parameters and not just
two and and login but the point is
because gkr has this kind of
memoryless property of the of the Prov
you can expand all the gkr into a big
proof of size
polyan now what does the verifier do the
verifier simply uh it so that that's
what the PCP is the PCP you write for
every possible kind of uh you know you
got write all the possible answers of
the provs and the Lo of extension of
your witness that's what the PCP is how
do you verify this PCP well you pretend
you're a GK Pro verifier you say okay
get let me see your first question thank
you now you're saying I'm going to
choose a random field element and I'm
going to look at the answer correspond
to this field element and then I'm going
to choose my next random field element
and you just kind of
go through this kind of tree and and
randomly and make sure and at the end
you need to verify if you remember gkr
at the end you need to verify to verify
you need to check your input on a random
point in the low degree extension this
is how GK works well you have the load
be extension uh uh sitting there uh as
part of your PCP so you check
that okay that's basically it except
there's one component that we're missing
and that's going to appear in your pet
which by the way is going to be out this
weekend okay so this weekend the pet is
going to be out originally the due date
was after Thanksgiving I'll move it to
before just to give you an incentive to
not take it with you on your break if
anybody needs an extension just let me
know okay so you'll have almost a month
no not quite but close Okay but if you
need an extension just let me know uh
it's this is very arbitrary the okay um
okay so uh so uh what's the problem the
problem is so if indeed
the so what about soundless okay
soundless seems like it should follow
from just gkr okay you're interacting
with like a approver a gkr prover and
someone should just fall from the gkr
except that there's one point here which
is what if the PCP prover doesn't give
you a low degree extension of some input
so if he gave you a low degree extension
of an input and this input did not
evaluate to one namely if he's not
satisfying assignment then this input is
not evaluate this because one does not
exist in that case of course uh you know
it would the sound would really follow
from GK
soundus however one needs to think there
may be a malicious prover who doesn't
give you here a low deegree extension of
some double so what he should give you a
lot extension of w it means like some W
goes from f
to the m to F and it's of degree H minus
one in each variable okay if it's a
degree H minus one in each variable then
it it extend it's a Lo extension of kind
of the W sitting in kind of in so then W
is just W sitting on H to the m that's
kind of the little Cube where W is
sitting if indeed he gave you a low
degree extension of some
W then you're good if this W that he
gives you is of degree H minus one in
each variable then you're good but what
if it's high
degree what if this W W's what if he
gives you some W star which is very high
degree then is it
sound so in the homework you'll have
exactly this actually it's not sound and
you'll ask to find actually an attack
and then there's a way to make sure so
now what the verifier needs to do in
addition is to do what is called a low
degree test it's a test that verifies
that this W star has low degree okay so
this is what the homework assignment or
one part of the homework assignment is
about okay but this is module making
sure that this is actually the verifier
can't make sure it's low degree but he
can make sure it's close to low degree
so it agrees with some low degree
W like on one minus Epsilon fraction of
the points so you can test that it's
very close to low degree if it's very
close to low degree then most likely
wherever you'll ask you ask randomly it
agrees with kind of the low degree and
therefore that's kind of the idea okay
but uh but but this is the PCB and the
verification just adds a low degree test
and we'll expand on then the pet okay so
that's kind of what we did most of the
class and then we talked at then we
talked about okay so now we have a
gigantic PCP it's very large but you can
verify it by looking at very few
locations which is nice how many
locations like the communication
complexity of the gkr which on circuits
of depth log n which or order log n
which is for example threat then the
communication complexity is poly login
so you can verify this by reading only
poly login locations as opposed to n
locations so it's like an exponential
Improvement but again you have this
gigantic PCP and now the question is
okay but who's going to note here's
something to just make sure you
understand it's very important that this
PCP is kind of given to the
verifier before the if the verifier C so
okay the PCP is very large now one can
say okay you know don't send the PCP
I'll tell you what my queries are just
give me the answers to my queries
instead of sending me anyway I don't I'm
not going to read them so why send it
over just send me the answers to my
queries that will not be sound if the
verifier if the approver gets to choose
the answers based on all the queries
that he sees sound this breaks down
completely okay and so it's very
important that he first tells you what
the PCP is and then you query it okay in
particular what the damaging the hard
the the way the cheating Prov can cheat
is by
you know when you tell them give me the
PCP in location I if you ask for it
together with location J it will give
you one answer but if you ask it for
location J Prime he will give you
another answer that that's how he can
cheat but if he needs to fix it ahead of
time then no it's one answer doesn't
matter the other locations you ask and
that's what makes this
sound okay you can actually go back to
gkr and see if you use this PCP with gkr
where you give the queries ahead of time
it's like you give the sump queries all
ahead of time everything breaks down
completely okay so it's very important
that you first committed to this entire
PCP and then one can ask well if you
give this how does the so the entire
thing says look the verifier is a weak
device that's the idea he's weak he
cannot do the computation how can he
store this gigantic
PCP so it seems like that's very nice
but how do we use this
thing and the way we use this thing the
way it's used today these things are
used today and the way they're used is
using cryptography so what we do we use
cryptography to take this gigantic proof
and squish it okay and this is used
using what's called Collision resistant
hash functions so this is what we're
gonna kind of we're going to uh talk
about uh today we started last time but
we're going to continue today but before
we go into how we squish it and make
kind of everything succinct let me first
what what once we use cryptography we
can no longer ass get sound against any
all bounded kind of cheating prover
because
cryptography can be broken by all
powerful uh adversaries cryptography
assumes the adversary is not strong
enough to break our assumptions for
example the collisions and hash function
that we saw and we'll review it in a
second so now when we talk about proof
systems we need to relax the notion of
what we mean by a proof system by the
way who's scribing today okay great uh
we need to relax the notion of what we
mean by a proof system to what's called
a computationally sound proof system
namely you cannot cheat assuming you're
polom bounded if you're all powerful and
can break my crypto no guarantees but as
long as you cannot break my crypto you
cannot cheat so I just wrote it here
this is copied from last time uh so what
is so instead of interactive proof we
call it an interactive argument and we
say that an interactive argument for
some language L think of it like say NP
language but whatever language you want
to think about is a protocol between
aover and a verifier the completeness is
the usual namely effect is in the
language uh then you'll convince the
verifier with probability one okay and
if it's an NP and you know witness
you're also efficient okay the soundness
that's where the changes instead of
soundness you get some computational
version of soundness and the
computational version of sound says the
following it says there's some parameter
security parameter when you talk in
cryptography there's always security
parameter which kind of says how much
time do we
believe uh real world adversaries can
run in okay uh so what the sist says
that any real world real world cheating
prover real world mean runs in time
polinomial in the security
parameter we're going to denote secur
parameter by Lambda uh throughout this
uh class sometimes they call it by n but
n and sometimes K here n is going to be
input size so I don't want to so we're
just going to use Lambda so for any P
star of size polinomial in the security
parameter he can win only with
negligable probability namely there
exists a negligable function mu again
negligible means it's smaller than any
inverse
polinomial such that no matter which
security parameter you use and any X so
think about the P star he's polom in the
security parameter he chooses an X
adversarially the probability or an X is
chosen okay it exists for any X the
probability that he convinces now the
protocol depends on the security
parameter so the verifier may may choose
like a hash function according to the
security parameter so everybody knows
the security parameter every run
everyone runs in time polinomial in the
security parameter and that's why we
give it as input the security parameter
in unary uh so an input X in this and
security parameter there's a protocol
and the probability that this cheating
prover convinces the verifier to accept
is this negligable function mu okay so
again we offer soundness only for poly
Lambda cheating provs okay so now you
should think of the cheating provs as
like a family of provs one for every
Lambda okay it's like a for any security
parameter you're allowed to give a
cheating prover but they're all let's
say run in time at most Lambda to the N
to the 10 okay so polinomial in
Lambda any questions about the review
before we go on to the new uh to
today
yeah is like like hide with this no no
no no good good good so two things first
of all we're not at all talking about
hiding okay if the if uh if we didn't
want succinctness you can take the pro
we just give you the witness here you go
check on your own okay and then but we
we'll want we'll want another property
from these interactive arguments which
is succinctness or or yes sickness or
you know yeah exactly for for NP for
example and
yeah that me formulas yeah exactly three
set is just think of it it's it's a
exactly uh just three cnfs you know it's
and of a bunch of lit of a bunch of uh
Clauses each one is like X i1 or X I2 or
not X
I3 small yeah so any any 3 CNF any 3 CNF
is of the form like uh Clause one and
Clause two and Clause n let's
say you can get a Boolean formula with
fan in two of size order log
M because you just do kind of the and
and you know all the ends and then you
have these little literals at the bottom
and each one is constant size it just
depends each Clause is constant
size so it's really a
log M
circuit okay so you can take any three
set which is just an end of a bunch of
literals and write it as a log uh depth
circuit can you go directly to SJ can do
the PCP over SJ
by doing aromatization instead of going
through G okay to to do to get a PCP I
need to go the way I construct the pcps
by going through gkr I do a gkr on this
kind of circuit I open up all the
possible Pro Pro's messages and that
what constitutes the PCP in addition to
the low degree extension of the input
that's going to be the PCP and the
verifier just kind of verifies behaves
like the gkr verifier and checks that
the witness he gets the the extended
witness is of low degree like it does a
low degree test with the low degree test
we didn't talk about but it's going to
be in the
homework so that's how the PCP works and
now I'm kind of talking about how you
use this long PCP together with
cryptography to get these succinct
arguments that's kind of the next step
how to use cryptography to just have
like a fully succeeded protocol let's
say for NP we want a protocol that has
polylog communication because you have
an instance of Link n and theover wants
to prove to the verifier that X is in
the language and you want the
communication to be only poly log in for
example okay okay one thing I do oh did
you have a
question like like is interactive
protocol necessary because in like the
traditional like the complexity Ser PCP
the W has to be written down in advance
and not be and it cannot be
aded so it's the whole point the prot
try to like fix that problem sense where
you forcing to Comm exactly exactly
that's exactly it that's exactly it h
exactly one thing I do want to say note
that I ask for the cheating crover to be
polinomial in Lambda okay uh because
usually that my assum that's what my
assumptions usually look like I want to
say if I use Collision resistant I would
say well I use some Collision resistant
function uh with SEC parameter that says
that my assumption is that a PO Lambda
size circuit cannot find collisions okay
my my cryptographic assumption usually
assumes that the they are hard to break
against provs against adversaries that
run in time po
Lambda but this is may be may seem very
weird and very weak why because you know
our goal is to come up with succinct
arguments okay succinct in particular
one example to think of to keep in mind
is let's say the input n can be really
huge but I want the communication
complex be poly login so think of Lambda
as being like poly
login okay everything is going to grow
with with the security parameter but
let's take the security member to be
poly
login now it seems weird you're like
wait really so the cheating Pro if the
instances of length
n and the security parameters of length
poly log in the cheating Pro were not
even giving him the opportunity to
read the input so it's a very weak
guarantee so what does this guarantee
tells you let's say I want you to prove
to me that a given X is in the
language and my only guarantee is if you
run in time that's only poly logarithmic
in N you can't
cheat okay what if you run in time men
you
know so that seems like a problem
especially if look if n is too big for
anyone to read
then in some sense why like nobody's
going to use it anyway and if n is we
able to read it if I'm able to read it
then you have the time to run in that
time so you run in time n I'm not going
to assume you run in time polog n so
this seems very weird okay you should
not be happy at this point you be like
wait something is going on I don't like
this definition it's
meaningless like this SEC if look if you
don't want suc synness you can make
Lambda B size of N and then you're happy
if Lambda is of size X like the in
instant size then you can say yeah the
instant size is some N I am I allow my
my real my honest Pro run runs in time
poen I allow my malicious Pro to run in
time poen and that makes sense to
me but now saying no the honest Pro he
can actually run in time men the
malicious cannot like no the malicious
usually has more power than the
honest so it's a very it's really a weak
guarantee that kind of
you know uh especially if we want to
take the security the idea is we're
going to take the security F really
small okay really really small but if we
take the security paret so small we
should give the adversary more power
than poing the security parameter
because it just doesn't meet real life
what the idea is to the idea of this is
to kind of capture real life setting not
to make a model that makes no
sense so if we take Lambda to be very
very small then the actually real world
would can run in time more than po
Lambda can they can run time
poen so it doesn't capture yeah if P3
the circuit how do we even think of
plugging in like a variable link X into
a circuit he can't they can't even read
X you're right yeah for
example so you can say oh P star can't
Redux you're right they can't Redux they
it's a circuit and yeah it can't
Redux this is a big problem okay so the
way I defined it is really doesn't make
much
sense
yeah why we need LDA to be PO is it so
that the resulting interaction is
exactly so great question the question
is why do we need it to be poly log in
you know let's so what I think where
maybe you're going to saying you know
what let's make Lambda enter the Epsilon
for a constant Epsilon enter the
[Music]
0.001 then the communication complex
then we say look uh the original proof
grows with Lambda which is n to the
point to the power of
Z
001 which is much smaller than n so
we're still happy but the cheating
prover can run time any poly any
polinomial in so it's polyn so that's
good you're right and that's that's a
good setting to think about in that case
there's no issues so one thing what
you're saying is you're saying let me
fix all your problems just take Lambda
to be think of it as n to the
0.01 and you're done or n to the Epsilon
and you're
done okay if you think about n to the
Epsilon everything kind of Mak sense you
allow the cheating prover to run in time
p n the instance is n and we're good
okay so that that's one way to think
about it so usually the way we think
about we say for any n we choose a
security parameter that depends on N
okay that's usually how we say how we do
it we have an n and now we say okay
which security par do we use it's kind
of a function of n so that's what one
example choose that to M and then you
solved all the problems but what if I
want more succinctness than that maybe
ENT to the 0.01 is not it's okay but I
want better I want poly login so what if
my Lambda that's one option but another
option is polyan that's even more
succinct so that's what I want now
you're saying well if that's what you
want you get a definition that makes no
sense and you're right but then what I
can do is strengthen the definition
so how do I strengthen the definition
I'm going to say you know what PO is one
option but let me make let me actually
make my assume make a stronger
cryptographic assumption I'm going to
assume some I'm going to say for any
adversary that runs that for any P star
that that um executes a circuit not of
size poly Lambda but of size 2 to the
Lambda to the
Epsilon I'm going to allow my adversary
to run time 2 to the Lambda to the
Epsilon more than
poly now it's a stronger assumption okay
so now I want to say an adversary that
runs in time two or of size two to the
Lambda to the Epsilon cannot break my my
my hash function he cannot find
collisions it's a stronger
assumption but now this makes
sense so I can take Lambda very very
small but I'm saying even if the
adversary runs in time that's much
bigger than than Lambda that's actually
two to the Lambda to the Epsilon even he
cannot
break my crypto and that's why when we
talk about suing proofs most often we
talk about this kind of assumption like
subexponential assumptions come up a
lot K we see that actually but often uh
if when if we want to implement so when
if we want to implement if we want to
take Lambda to be poly log in it makes
sense to require for this for for the
soundest to be to make sense to to
correspond to real world applications it
makes sense to require subexponential
assumptions of of of our underlying
cryptography okay so just to kind of
close this parenthesis one can talk
about poly signs cheating provs it will
give you more standard assumption but
the soundus guarantee you get may not be
strong enough depending on how Del how
security parameter relates to the input
size if you want lamb to be very very
the security parameter to be very very
small and yet you want to offer security
against adversity the run time poly n
then you will need to make your
assumption
stronger okay but but but given this is
kind of a end a design Choice okay for
now we just going to think of you know
for any given P star of size poly Lambda
or more I don't know whatever we choose
here that corresponds to the Assumption
okay so if we have a t- secure
assumption then for any t- size so in
general more gener you can think of
replace this by T of
Lambda right any T it can be poly it can
be subexponential it can be
whatever okay and then we choose the T
and now the T kind of governs the
application but also have a t now we can
just prove it using math we don't need
to think about it anymore okay so that's
kind of uh
a the how Lambda relates to n okay and
how the strength of the Assumption
relates to
n okay any questions about about
that okay so now let's uh go ahead with
how we use uh so that's what we want I
want to come up with a succinct
interactive argument for all of
NP okay I want to show how uh I can take
any NP language let's think of three set
why not it's complete I want to prove to
you that a a 3 CNF formula is
satisfiable I have a witness of length N
I want to prove to you that it's
satisfiable but with the communication I
want it to grow only with
Lambda okay Lambda can be polog and I
don't even want don't don't go now to
the choice how we chose the Lambda but
now I have a security par Lambda I want
the communication to only go with the
security parameter not with
n okay so how do I do it so the idea is
well I'll use my PCP I have my PCP I'm
going to use crypto
to squeeze it how do I use Crypt to
squeeze it it's exactly what Collision
resistant hash functions do they take a
big thing and they
squish them down so now I'll take I'll
take my PCP the prover will take his PCP
he will squish it down using a collision
resistant hash
function okay so he gives a verif here
you go here's a like a squish like a
digest you know of this PCP okay the
verify takes this thing it has no
meaning so what does he do now other the
proof okay thank you very much but I
want to see the PCP on a few locations
so now what can the prover do the pro
can't okay so Collision isn't hash
function as as is uh are it's a way to
kind of compress in a way that you can't
you're kind of committed you because you
can't find collisions later so you can't
open you can't kind of after you gave
the uh the hash value you can't open to
x and x Prime you can't give x and x
Prime that both hash to the same
value but I don't want you to give me
you can't give me now you're hashing an
entire PCP the PCP is Big you can't just
I never want you to give me me the
verifier never want to receive this PCP
I can't even hold it I want to receive a
few bits of the
input so what we need is a collig in
hash that has a special property that's
you can open bit by bit so instead of
giving me the entire kind of input the
entire pre-image of the hash value I
want you just to give me a few bits here
a few bits here and a few bits here and
prove to me that they're they correspond
to to what to the input you have
so I'm now I'm going to Define this
primitive once I have this we're going
to see it's going to be very easy to
come up with the actual interactive
argument okay so the Primitive is a a
what's called a collision resistant hash
with local opening let me Define it so
we're going to have a collision
resistant hash function with local
opening
and this consists of five algorithms the
first one is the first two are gen and
Dalal these are exactly these two
algorithms is is what defines cud and
hash function so this we saw last time
I'll just repeat just to recall gen
takes his input a one to the Lambda the
security parameter and
outputs hash key so this is some key
eval takes his input hash key and any
input X from zero one star
anything okay any string of any length
and it
outputs a hash
value we denote it V and that's fixed in
0 one to the Lambda I I call sometimes
Delta and sometimes Lambda right sorry
it's Lambda a you output a hash of a
fixed size which means you can take very
very long things and you digest down you
digest them down to a value of size
Lambda okay so it takes an input of
arbitrary size can be huge can be two
Lambda four Lambda ton huge and it
digest down to a string of size of
length
Lambda okay now there's two more
algorithms two or three okay so now
there's an algorithm called
open open I just want to make sure I
want to tell me don't give me theti I
want to I want to so V is just digest
has no meaning I want to tell you now I
want the I bit of X don't give me all of
X what you have I can't hold it I just
want the I bit so open so what do you do
you open how do you open you have the
hash key you have
X which you computed the value V and now
you have some I in kind of 01 to the
length of X so this is kind of which
index I want you to open
and what you
output is a bit B which is kind of
correspond to x i the I bit a bit and an
opening value
row okay this is some kind of uh string
and this is of
size Lambda so
small or it can be po Lambda
okay an opening of size poly Lambda
yes who's uh running the open good who's
running the open good the person who
generated the hash so let's say you're
the Prov you want to prove to me uh that
Fe satisfiable you generate a PCP I
don't want your PCP it's too big you
give me a hash a value V thank you very
much now I want you to open the PCP and
some location I so I tell you here's I I
don't know your PCP I don't know your
input you give me some row I like an
open give me XI if you only give me XI
you can cheat you can give me whatever
you want I don't believe you so I want
you to give me kind of row I this
opening is like a proof that indeed what
what I hash down in the I location is
sitting XI this is what you think of
rowy it's like a proof yeah shouldn't I
be in
oh sorry sorry sorry sorry thank you
sorry it's an index not in01 sorry it's
an it's an it's an index with one until
the length of x one to n let's see yeah
thank you very
much questions
yeah just
like I guess it's just interesting that
you have to retain the higher hash value
X like maybe that's necessary for
correctness to be able
to uh confirm any bit of X but I don't
know it just seems interesting that in
practice you would have to store keep
storing all these hash values right so
what you wait let me make sure what your
your comment is not that to open you
need to know the entire
X and why do you need to know the entire
X in a sense to open to bit eye so in
some sense
look I mean to open to bit I all you
need to remember is row I that's kind of
what you need to give for the opening
but all the row eyes together give
contain all the X so that's why you need
to to kind of store all the X and you'll
see the construction soon so it'll be
kind of uh uh clear uh okay the last
algorithm is what we call Ver
verify and verify takes his input a hash
key a a hash so now I'm verifying you
gave me x i and row I how do I know it's
good so I take my hash key the hash key
the value that you gave me i x i and row
I and this algorithm outputs zero or one
namely accept or
reject okay so I can kind of
verify uh whether the row is a valid
opening okay and now what are the
guarant es so you can hash and then you
can open like
a what is the guarantee the guarantee is
first of all if you do everything
honestly I'll accept you okay so there's
two
guarantees the first guarantee is just
correctness and the second guarantee we
want is Collision resistant so we'll see
so for
correctness uh before actually let me
just uh a sorry let me just say these
are all PPT algorithms okay all of them
are polinomial time uh actually the only
everything is these are I should say
these are polom poly time algorithm and
this is
PPT so this is a randomized algorithm
poly time so it runs in time poly Lambda
generates a hash key these are all
deterministic algorithms okay they run
in po time so EV Val takes his input X
he runs in time x of course
uh open runs in time x but verify runs
in time uh poly Lambda why because hash
is of size poly Lambda this is of size
Lambda because I required it and XI is a
bit and this is a size poly Lambda
because I required it so the verific the
the verifier runs in time poly Lambda
okay so when you send me a hash value I
get a value of size Lambda when I want
to you to open to a certain bit I can
check it in time po Lambda independent
of n i mean Lambda may depend on N but
it doesn't grow with n yes why is all to
be why is
Jal is not these are polinomial
time ah why is it not allowed uh it
doesn't need to be it just doesn't need
to be uh probabilistic I I'm not I'm not
inherently opposed to using Randomness
and algorithms but it just doesn't need
to be whereas gen has to be probalistic
okay great thanks good question uh okay
so uh the correctness guarantee just
says that uh let's see for every
Lambda every hash key generated like in
the image of gen and every X okay not
every X we get completeness up to X in
01 to the two to the Lambda okay so it
it or I should say sorry smaller or
equal to two to the Lambda so let's
think of the security parameter it says
least of size log log n n is the size of
X okay we never take security parameter
to be smaller than log n okay and and so
that's why like uh we always assume that
the size of X is at most two to the
security parameter the number of bits in
x okay so for every x what we uh we want
that uh the probability that verify oh I
forgot to say for every
I the probability that verify an
HK
eval HK of X this is
V what else do I have i x I and row I
which is
open this is kind of the row it outputs
one with probability one so if you are
honest you take some input x uh any hash
key and you give me a hash value and
then you open it I'll accept
you okay if everyone's doing what
they're supposed to do for any X and for
any hash key we'll get output one by the
way
sometimes one can Define also with high
probability over randomly choosing a
hash key but our constructions work
often in the worst case but one can also
a weaker definition is for kind of hash
key randomly
generated and here you have one minus
negligible where the probability is over
over the hash key here actually sorry
here there was no okay before there were
no probabilities because I just chose
forever but one can think of a Rand hash
key randomly generated and you can have
a negligable probability of error we
won't need that because this I mean some
schemes but many schemes are just uh
probably one yeah you mean that corre
always holds for
anys right yeah I didn't go to soundness
yet yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah we'll see
sound for in a minute but correctness we
can get for every hash key but the one
can thing
constructions that actually it's only
even correctness with high probability
but but often we think of it a
correctness one yes for you have that
restriction on X again why for prance
you you have that restriction on the
length x okay the length should be this
than Le that right yeah yeah yeah you're
asking why yeah because uh our
constructions often we'll see a
construction and we'll see that if the
length is too
is okay the the reason is we can our
constructions grow with log X that's the
truth it just grows with log X and we
want the output to be Lambda so the fact
of the matter is the way we construct
these schemes our construction the hash
value grows with log X but we we don't
want to kind of say it we want to just
say Lambda because it's nicer so we just
make sure Lambda is at least log X and
then we're
okay okay great
question okay any other questions before
go to
soundness okay so soundness that's the
more interesting one soundness says
intuitively that for any bounded poly
Lambda or t bounded if there some you
have some the soundness is like you can
call it t
soundness okay and T you can poly sound
poly soundus you can with two to the
Lambda to the Epsilon
soundness but there's some t and it
says any adversary that runs in time at
most of size at most
T the probability that it can find a
value and an index a hash value in an
index so that an that index he can
successfully open to both zero and one
is negligible okay so it essentially
means one once the adversary gave you a
hash value for any index he cannot
generate a valid opening both for zero
and for one it's impossible for him okay
so let me write it formally so for
any poly
T again think of T is like linear so
poly Lambda poly T
size
adversary the
probability and the probability is over
hash key he gets a random hash Key
choses by J chosen by Jen
okay gets a random hash key chosen by
Jen this adversary given the hash
key he tries to open some index in two
different ways so he his goal is to give
you a hash value V an index I and a
valid opening row zero that opens to
zero and a valid opening Row one that
opens to
one that's what he outputs so the
adversary outputs gets a hash key he
outputs a hash value an index and two
opening for that index that's what he's
trying to do one corresponding to Zer
one corresponding to one and the
probability that both of them are valid
opening the probability that for every B
in
01 verify verify agrees so verify given
hash key v i
and a zero B and row b
outputs one this is
negligible okay so again what soundness
is like Collision resistance in this
setting so this is kind of a another way
to usually people call this property
Collision
resistance and the Collision resistance
property says that once the adversity
chose a hash value the probability that
for any index
okay he chooses for any index I the
probability that he can
open in a way that verifies in an
accepting way to both zero and one so
for any for every B row b is a valid
opening row zero is valid for zero and
Row one is a valid open for one that
happens with negligable probability okay
so for every row there
exists negligible
such
that okay so this is the Collision
resistant
property any questions about the
property okay so now I have two things I
want to do the first thing oh sorry I
unordered two things things I want to do
one is show you how you construct this
thing and two show you how to use it to
construct an interactive
argument any preference on the on the
order what goes first who wants uh
construction
first who wants uh interactive argument
first okay we'll do interactive
arguments and then we do construction
was not that if anybody wants to weigh
in say so cuz it it wasn't very
significant the result but
uh okay so interactive argument first
yeah
okay okay so here's
the this is what known as the kilan
mikali
protocol okay
okay so actually I want
succinct interactive Arguments for NP
okay so I'm going to show you how to
construct a succinct interactive
argument for any NP language
okay so here is how I'm going to do it
the prover first so we have a prover and
a verifier and here's what the they both
share a witness X the approver wants to
prove to the verifier that X is in the
linguage and he has some
witness okay you can think about it as a
3 CNF we talked about 3nf complete
anyway it can be nice to have like
something Concrete in mind so you can
think about X as being a 3 CNF and W of
satisfying
assignment okay what does the prover do
the first thing any guess what the
prover first do first
does thank you comput the PCP that's the
first thing he does so he takes w and
converts it to a
PCP okay and if you want to have
something Concrete in mind he does he
opens all the gkr adds a low de
extension of the witness that's a huge
thing that's a PCP he can't ship it over
that's too big what does he want to do
instead hash okay he needs a hash key
he's like I want a hash can anybody give
me a hash key right oh let me sorry
because it's an argument I should say
they also share security
parameter so the first thing the
verifier does is he says sure I'm going
to here's a hash key I'm going to
generate
it and here you
go now what does the prover
do thank you very much so I compute he
sends over V we usually didn't okay we
send it sends V which is
eval of hash
key and the PCP
P okay so the verifier gets this V this
digest it's a bunch of bits with no
meaning he wants to open this PCP right
like he want okay so what does he do
what is the the verifier gets the V
cannot doesn't understand a thing what
does he want from the prover what will
he ask the
prover exactly it selects a randomly
selects a bit and ask to open it which
distribution how will he choose which
bits to open from this
PCP exactly what the exactly what the p
as the PCP verifier so what he does he
runs the VP
PCP and the PCP verifier tells him oh
sure ask I want up I don't know some
I so okay let me just mention sorry I'm
going to construct an interactive
argument for NP from two ingredients
yeah one I'm going to use a PCP so we
already we have a PCP in our head the
gkr PCP yeah we have it and two this
Collision resist s hash with local
opening these are two ingredients that
we're going to use in this
construction and we're going to assume
remember when we talked about PCP when
we defined it it was like before we went
to kind of crypto land and we said
there's two parameters CNS completen and
soundness we said that a PCP comes with
two parameters completen and soundness
CNS and uh usually we think of the of
the completeness as one because all our
pcps have actually complet one that's
kind of it's easy to construct them with
completeness one
soundness we pay for soundness so the
more queries you get the better
soundness you get and here we're going
to always assume that the
soundness is
negligible okay so uh we give enough so
for example if we do one uh gkr if you
just run the gkr verifier once if you
remember remember you kind of query one
point in the low degree extension but a
field element in gkr is of size one over
polylog so the soundness you'll get it
sorry the field size is polylog so the
soundness you'll get is one over polylog
which is pretty not great I want
negligible so I'll need to repeat the
gkr enough times like log times so that
it will be become negligible I want my
soundless to become negligible the
reason I want the soundness of the PCP
to be negligible
is because when we Define interactive
arguments we wanted soundless to be
negligible okay these two will kind of
the soundless I get from my interactive
argument will kind of depend on the
soundness I'm going to get from my PCP
so I'm going to assume here that I have
a PCP with negligable soundness that I
ask so if I have a PCP with sound is
half I'll just repeat it polylog like
I'll repeat it let's say Lambda times
and now my sound becomes one over two to
the
Lambda okay so uh
uh I'm gonna always assume that it's
negligible in in
Lambda okay so I run the PCP verifier
yeah orle access to the proof what do
you mean that what is the previous
version the previous version where you
had to query the proof Oracle okay so
when you had okay so you said let's
remember the PCP model where I had the
PCP as a an Oracle and I quered it that
was very succinct but if I had an Oracle
in which world do I have an oracle what
this Oracle is a nice like who puts the
PCP in the sky for me where is the sky
it's not sitting on a cloud you know
what it's like a well Cloud I guess now
has many
meanings uh but you know so it can be
sitting actually on a cloud but that's
kind of the point we don't want anyone
to store this P we don't want to assume
someone actually holds this thing so in
that model where you assume you have an
oracle everything is successed now what
I'm trying to do here is get rid of that
assumption that I have an oracle great
yeah what about even before the P if you
were to just do interactive gkr on
circuit okay good good great great so
the question is look just do an
interactive Gare and the circuit and the
and and this CA fee that's maybe here oh
no it vanished uh you can but here's the
problem you can do GK and essentially
it's what we're doing in the PCP in some
sense but here's the issue but you're
saying GK you don't need to deal with
with hashing right that kind of your
point very very good point however in GK
anybody see that's actually AIT a good
anybody see what's wrong so let me
repeat your your point the point is the
following look G is succinct think of
three set it's very low depth it's
succinct the communication is very
succinct why are you now going to crypto
and opening GK just do GK be done with
it why are we doing all of
this very good why because gkr works if
the verifier knows the
witness if the verifier knows the input
in gkr when we talk about GK we said
look the verifier and prover both hold
an
input and the ver verifier wants to know
the output of this circuit and the input
that he
has okay and indeed at the end the
verify
needs to check the final thing against
his input you know is is in the end
going to get kind of a value in the load
exension and he checks oh does this is
this consistent with the input I have in
my
hand now he doesn't have an
input so what do you do so actually let
me tell you
something the way these things are
actually implemented it's very
interesting to say because the way
they're implemented is actually more
along what you said what they do is
first they commit to just the witness
you're saying why are you committing to
en PP you have a witness commit to that
or commit to the low degree extension of
the witness and actually in practice
that's what they do they only committed
the L and then they applied this
interactive gkr or now they have even
better protocols iops but that's for
another
time you once you the wi do normal gkr
and then you can only need to open the
andt that you care about exactly so what
you can do you can first the approver
can tell the verifier sorry the verifier
tells the approver I know you you claim
that you have a satisfying assignment
give me a load to extension of your
assignment but hash it down because I
don't want to hold this entire thing now
I have a hash now we're going to do G do
g g then they need to check a random
point in the in in a random point in the
low degree extension I'll ask the appr
now open but now you're committed ahead
of time and then you have to to make
you need to add a low degree test to it
yeah
exactly so many of the implementations
that's exactly how they work and
actually a lot of the work currently in
the last couple years is actually not so
much an improving G that too but a lot
of the work is actually on the
commitment how do you construct this
commitment that's kind of the most
efficient and so on
um okay great uh so
yeah no the verifier the witness because
the witness is too large exactly exactly
we don't want to give the verifier of
the witness because it's too large so we
don't have knowledge I don't care now
about zero knowledge usually when people
implement this they add zero knowledge
on top kind of as a but for now I don't
care at all about hiding I just want
verification like just to verify
correctness yeah no I'm no like all of
the hiding zero knowledge is kind of
orthogonal yeah so the commitment that's
given to the verify is only Ed for
verification it's never actually open
it's never opened completely yeah it's
never good point so what you're saying
this hash will never be completely
opened okay so the the approver computes
this PCP he sends it over the PCP will
never be opened in its entirety it's too
big or the witness never going to be
open its entirety instead what happens
is the verifier generates PCP queries
and he sends the PCP queries i1 up to
iil and what the prover does he only
opens the
locations Pi
i1 up to Pi i l so he only gives him the
PCP and these locations and opening row
i1 up to row
I yeah this is DET mention before like
everything inall sometimes it's not
sound can these be at the same time or
they have to be multipal rounds okay so
if you do a PCP then they can be sent
exactly at the same time because a PCP
was committed to the PCP and we're done
if you do Gare you need to do everything
sequentially right okay yeah if you did
so if you did the version that was uh
proposed here where you don't you don't
do PCP at all you have your witness and
then you need to do gkr completely
Interactive
but if you have a PCP then it's
committed now you don't have to do
anything sequentially that's it the guy
is kind of stuck so you can do
everything at the same time so great so
you send all the queries you get back
the answers what does the verifier do
how does he decide if to accept or
reject what tests does the verifier
do
yeah fantastic exactly what does he do
he runs two things he runs the PCP
verifier with kind of i1 iil Pi i1 up to
Pi
I with X also X comma and checks that
it's one and it also checks all the
opening so it checks the
verify of hash key
v i j Pi I
J row I
J equals 1 for every
J uh Pi i j is kind of
oh uh no because um the P when you
verify a
PCP okay the verifier never knows the
entire Pi he never read the entire Pi
but to verify of course he needs to know
the instance like he needs you need to
check it against the instance so the
proof is succinct but the verifi work he
has to read what what the claim is okay
so it's the verifier will run in time
linear in X that he needs to read what
what the claim is but the
communication is very small so the
communication is hashy which is poly
security parameter V which a security
parameter I went up to I which is going
to be at most security parameter and the
opening which is security parameter so
everything here only grows with the
security parameter okay poom security
parameter not with X so if the security
parameter is poly log n n being the
length of X then you have communication
poly log in to verify well okay this
verification has it's a size poly log in
like security parameter because the X
doesn't come in but of course to verify
the PCP you need to read the input you
need to read what the claim you're
verifying so here you do run in time
linear in these pcps usually the runtime
of the verifier is linear in the input
length and let me mention actually
there's this notion which we won't go
into this semester uh but it's called
PCP of proximity where the verifier
doesn't even need to read the input he
just reads a little bit but now of
course he if he only reads a little bit
then how does he know
that the input is correct maybe he
didn't read one bit and that flips it
from True to false you know so the only
guarantee he has that if he's accepted
then this input is close to an input in
the language that's why the proximity so
there is a notion where the verifier is
actually sublinear in X he runs in time
much less than x but then the guarantee
is weaker the sound is guarantee is
weaker the sound is just says that if
you accept you cannot accept statements
which are
far for being in the language but you
may be able you may accept sentence you
may accept claims that are false but
close to ones that are in the language
so it's a different it's a proximity
type uh soundness guarantee but without
if you really want soundness yes or no
you have to read input there's nothing
you know nothing you can
do unless the input is kind of in an air
craing code or you change something
above the model but otherwise you have
to read the input
any any questions about the construction
forget about soundness and so on just
about the con like about the proof just
about the
construction okay so I just want to
point one thing that I said let's send
i1 up to iil really the way the PCP
verifier works is he gets his input like
uh let's say the security parameter just
to know how many times to repeat the if
the original PC if the original PCP
let's say is a size a has sound is half
he needs to know how many times he needs
to repeat it so there's some security
parameter and some random he also knows
the input link like n in binary so this
can be very efficient
and he uses
Randomness what my point is instead of
sending i1 up to I instead he could have
just sent the
randomness okay he could have sent the
randomness and tell the prover okay you
see this Randomness compute run this
yourself
okay why am I saying this it's like okay
fine like why is that interesting the
reason this is very
interesting is because and also here by
the way here instead of
the this is a randomized
algorithm actually here it's here it's
not important let's just leave this as
is I want to focus on this here why is
this important because later not today
but later in this class we'll start
actually next week
we'll see that a we'll want to go after
we'll prove this and we'll be very happy
and we say wow we have a succinct
argument and it's so succinct we can
have all security parameter success
happiness but then of course every time
we have something we want some more and
then we'll say you know what we don't
want
interaction why interaction we want we
want to go back to kind of actual proofs
so we want to eliminate intraction and
what we'll see is a way to eliminate
interaction from protocols where the
verifier messages are completely
random okay and that's why I want I want
you to remember in your head that here
this message can be completely random
okay we can make all those also this
random but we don't need to because it's
the first message it's kind of the first
the first message is kind of special and
that it's kind of the first one so we
don't need to kind of eliminate
intraction from it it's kind of the
first one uh so that's fine the all the
later messages of the verifier will need
to if they're really random just random
bits then we can show how we can
eliminate an interaction that we can
actually get rid of the interaction so I
just want to point out this message can
be is completely random these ior tile
are not random they're actually
correlated but the you can just send the
randomness yes I guess this side but why
is first message special you imagine
that like I don't know there could exist
hash key which is really bad or
something so if you like it feels like
you should still be sampling the first
hash key oh you definitely sampling it
no no you're going to sample this hash
key for sure I'm just saying the hash
key itself is not necessarily random
bits depends on the hash some hash some
hash keys are random some hash keys are
very have some structure dep depending
on which hash function you use you know
so some hash Keys indeed some hash keys
are just random and then this message is
just random
some hash keys are not random I have
like I don't know lwe structure what if
so for those who know what LW but I have
some special structure so now I'm saying
I guess all what I was saying is if the
messages from the verifier to the prover
we're truly random we're going to see we
can eliminate interaction so I'm telling
you you just notice it's completely
random and now you can say wait this is
not necessarily random I don't know how
hash ke is distributed depend on the
construction maybe it's not completely
random they said don't worry this
doesn't have to be it can be an
arbitrary
distribution good good good good good
good good so you're saying hey send the
coins here too well inste do the same
put here R and send
R you can however not all hash functions
there may be hash functions that are
secure if you only give the hash key but
on not give the randomness use to
generate the hash key maybe with this
Randomness you can break the Collision
resistance so some some hash functions
are okay some are not like the hash
function that we'll construct you'll see
it's fine actually it's Randomness but
that's under a specific assumption and
some are not it's not okay to give the
randomness but I just want to point out
that for later to eliminate interaction
using What's called the F Paradigm we'll
talk about it next class the first
message actually doesn't need to be even
random it's only the later messages have
to be random so I just want to emphasize
This Is Random
there were other questions
yeah n n is the size of X yeah so sorry
I said yeah n thank you is the length of
X
thanks H so the PCP verifier needs to
know the length of the instance he's
working with to know which queries to
ask yeah Tina
because okay because yeah good so uh
the I just want to emphasize that to
generate these queries you don't need to
run in time that depend that's poomi in
N it's enough to run in time polog in in
order to generate the queries that's why
I give it in it doesn't matters so much
because here anyway you need to run time
linear so you're like why am I making
this
point yeah uh it's not very important
even though sometimes it is important
when later you want to talk about
proximity and stuff then all of a sudden
it becomes an issue so yeah just this is
just to emphasize that the PCP verifier
at least when generating the queries
doesn't run in time linear in N you runs
in time actually linear in security
parameter and poly Log In N to generate
the
queries okay
questions okay so let's uh go ahead and
uh prove the let me see I change the
order so I just want to make sure sure
I'm not a skipping
um okay yeah let's do it okay soundness
a complete let's let's analyze this so I
want to prove that it's complete and
sound this protocol yeah so fix an NP
language your favorite one let's say
three set and I want to argue that you
know if the prover is honest he indeed
has a satisfying assignment or a witness
the verifier will accept him with
probability one and if he's honest he
does everything like he should and and
if and the sound is if he tries to cheat
and gives me an xn in the language we're
going to catch him he's going to be
accepted with probility
negligible okay so that's the
[Applause]
goal any questions before
we no okay so let's do it so okay let's
start with completeness because that's
really easy the focus well I can just
say completeness is not doesn't not
worth writing it's so trivial so what do
I want what does completeness say he
says if the Prov choose X is in the
language and he has a witness he's going
to be accepted with probability one why
why is it going to be accepted well
let's see what he does he chooses a PCP
the PCP let it has completeness one
that's my assumption it's soundness
negligible and completeness
one okay I assume that about my PCP
otherwise the completeness is like the
complet of the PCP so I uh he chooses a
PCP he hashes it now he gets PCP queries
from the verifier he opens the PCP now
he's accept these are acceptable with
probability
one now he generates also open these
rows are from open right so I didn't
maybe I should write I didn't write it
but row i j is by Computing open on hash
key Pi i j right that's
the
yeah that's how he generates roig J and
what do we know we know by completeness
here or correctness like you know he's
accept with probability
one
so uh the probability that both the PCP
is accepted the PCP verifier accepts and
the hash verifier accept is one because
both of them is one I I took perfect
completeness from both of them so it's
just that's all we
do so this is just pretty
trivial yeah
questions are you guys okay moving to
the soundness that's kind of the
interesting part okay so how about
soundness okay so what's the idea the
idea for soundness is the following I
want to
say so Suppose there exists a cheating
prover that ches X not in the
language okay and manages to cheat so
let's suppose and let's try to break the
Collision resistance okay so
Suppose there
exists uh T time whatever
uh so okay we assume this
is where with t soundness or security I
I call C Collision
resistance that's my assumption now I
want to argue if I assume that the
Collision resistant has is T secure
namely even someone in time poly T
cannot cheat then I want to argue
Suppose there exists a oh
sorry we're going to okay we're I'm
going to get back to this okay what
exactly this is we'll see it actually
needs to be quite big but we'll see that
Suppose there
exists a
poly cheating prover P
star that cheats namely that uh uh and
the and there exists like for every
Lambda or there exists like a bunch of X
Lambda
not in the
language
and there exists a non-negligible
Epsilon such that the Prov succeeds with
that
probability the
probability that P star talking to
verifier an input X the verifier accepts
him is at least Epsilon so do that for
every
Lambda this is be precise this is x sub
Lambda and they get
Lambda okay so suppose a cheating prover
for any Lambda he chooses some x sub
Lambda and P star and V accepts him even
though X is not in the
language okay
one the my only assumption is that X
Lambda is smaller than 2 to the Lambda
so I choose my security parameter so
that the security parameter is bigger
than log the the size of
X
okay then H actually it's it's it's not
even needed for for sound this this
actually was needed for completeness
because we only had completeness
for these X's for S actually it doesn't
really matter okay so let's see what do
I want to do I'm saying Suppose there
exist a cheating prover and this
cheating prover
convinces okay now what did let's see
what did this cheating prover do he
committed to a he kind of send he hashed
a PCP now he I don't know what he did
he's a cheater but he gave me a hash of
something should be a
PCP then he opens this PCP
so what do I want to do I want I'm gonna
to find I won't argue I can find a
collision why can I find a collision
what is the idea the idea is the
following I'm GNA run this cheating
prover I'm gonna ask the cheating prover
okay here's a Hashi give me a
v then I'm going to run him many many
many times and many PCP verifiers I'm
going to tell okay you know what here's
I want to from the PCP verifier give me
me openings again here's I went up to
give me openings again give I'm going to
kind of rewind him and try to give him
tons of kind of messages I want to I so
I'm GNA kind of rewind him okay so again
what do I want to
do given a hash key okay given a hashy I
want to find collisions for this hash
key how do I find Collision for this
hash key I'm going to give this Pro the
hash key he gives me a value V then I'm
going to tell the
prover I'm going to choose a random a
random R I'm going to tell him open
these locations he
opens good now I'm saying okay okay okay
actually let's rewind him forget that he
I sent him these let me give him R R2
different R
open okay and forg R three I'm GNA run
this step tons of
times R1 R2 R3 R4 a lot of them and I'm
gonna have a lot of openings from
him I'm gonna run it so much that I'm
just gonna have tons of opening like I'm
gonna run him more than like poly one
over Epsilon and more than poly like
poly One epon n so the point that I'm
going to run it much more than the num
like the size of the
PCP times one over Epsilon but if to
some power to some to the third whatever
run a lot of times now what's the idea
the idea is the following
if there are no collisions so if there
look I'm going to run now if at any
point every time that he gave me an
opening that didn't work it's zero it
like didn't work okay so I'm going to
throw it out that okay look there's he
only succeeds in probability Epsilon so
all the time that he didn't succeed okay
well failure but one over epon of the
time he
succeeded and in all these times in all
these one over Epsilon and sorry Epsilon
of the times he succeeded in all these
Epsilon times I got got a lot of good
openings now let's look at all these
openings that I got if somewhere there's
a
collision I I found him I I I I found a
collision so I'm
happy if nowhere there's a collision
then essentially I I found a PCP from
him I completely constructed like maybe
not the entire PCP but a lot of it and
the rest I'm going to put zeros I'm say
you know okay these identically zeros
but the argument is that if there were
no cision I got a PCP that's accepted
with probability at least poly in
epsilon which is not
negligible so that's the high level idea
but let me say everything I said now
slowly okay so suppose I have a cheating
prover that succeeds in convincing for X
not in the language I'm going to
construct I'm going to find the
Collision to the hash function so we're
going to construct
adversary a that
breaks the Collision
resistant or the the Collision resistant
property okay how do I break the Collen
resistant property here's the idea so a
okay so given so he's given a random
hash
key and his goal is to find
collisions how does he find collisions
what does he do he gives so here's what
a does
first
compute V which is p star on hash
key that's the first thing I got a v
then I do the
following many times so for
I go goes from one two up to poly in n
and one/ Epsilon so many times what I do
is I
run like what P star given HK and he
gave V would run
on input RI RI corresponding to a okay
let me call this
J J corresponding to a kind
of i1 up to I
L I just didn't want to confuse this eye
with these
eyes okay so I'm going to run many times
I'm going to choose many RS oh I didn't
say sorry
choose sorry for I goes to one
choose a random RJ so for J go from one
two up to poly in n and one over Epsilon
I choose a random
RJ how many how much random bits like
the PCP verifier I'm going to kind of
I'm going to behave like the I'm going
to give it the randomness of the PCP
verifier corresponding to i1 up to I and
I'm going to compute his answers which
is pi i1 up to Pi these may be ious
answers I I denote it by pi but of
course it can I mean it's not
necessarily correspond to an i PCP he's
malicious and
opening okay so this is how I find
collisions
I I get a hash key I give it to the
cheating prover to get a
value then for I
for M * for J goes from 1 to m m is
going to be poly and n and one over
Epsilon
what do I do I choose Randomness for the
PCP verifier and I tell the approver
what are your answers for this
Randomness with the same V I didn't
change the
V okay so he gave me a v in in the
second message and then I kind of run
the third message with him many many
many
times M times and expect to see
answers okay now what do I do those for
which the row doesn't work like those
for which row doesn't accept you know it
has a bad the verify doesn't this
doesn't accept I throw out and it's
meaningless he could put whatever he
wants I throw it I throw it out but
that's only Epsilon fraction of them
because the turns out the prover I
assume the prover is accepted with
probability Epsilon so Epsilon I throw
out okay but I I chose much more than
one over okay This only affects you know
so except for the Epsilon the rest are
good yeah sorry I th as I said that yeah
I th I'm left with Epsilon okay I
thought one minus Epsilon I'm left with
Epsilon but Epsilon is good enough
because I chose more than probably one
over Epsilon that's why I have here one
over Epson because Epsilon are are bad
which is why okay so I still have a lot
left okay so now what do I do with the
ones I have
left so I want argue so here here's the
claim the claim is that
um me write it here so the claim is that
I should be able to find Collision so
the algorithm the algorithm a what it
does the way it breaks and so
find
output a collision if one exists I I'll
write it here why my output so three
output
Collision if one
exists that's it so I got what do I mean
if one exists many of the eyes here I
asked many
times right because I I I did poly an n
n meaning kind of the witness length
yeah more than like think of the witness
length to the power of the
third divided by Epsilon like w the P
size of the PCP divided by Epsilon to
the third that's how you should think
about it or to the times like security
parameter okay so now what what's the
point the point is I saw the same eye
many many
times because I asked many many
queries now I want to argue that if so
there's two option either every time I I
asked for an
i he if he gave me a valid opening it's
for the same one
or at one of the eyes he gave me valid
openings one for zero and one for one if
that's the case I won I found a
collision and then I I broke the hash
function so if I if you believe you
cannot break hash function then you
cannot break then the scheme is secure
which is kind of what we're trying to
do but now you can say but maybe you
didn't find a hash function maybe you
didn't find a collision
maybe the cheating
prover whenever he answer he he answer
when he answers correctly it's always
with the same like for every eye if he
answers correctly it's with the same
piie
eye he never answers correctly with pi
ey being zero with pi ey being
one then look then what happened I I
take all the things that he asked me and
I piece together a PCP from him okay so
okay so why I I say okay so the question
is suppose I suppose I output suppose
that a collision happens with negative
probability if it's not I W I'm done
okay I want to argue now if not if a
collision
so if a
occurs
uh thank you
with negative
probability then I want to argue I can
come up with a PCP
then there exists a
pi that I can construct from this
adversary such
that V
PCP of Pi
accept with non- Nega probability
and that's a contradiction because I
assume that my Pi is sound with NE I
mean uh sound is hold with probability
you know you break sound is only with
negative probability so I'm I'm going to
argue that if you don't if the
probability finding Collision is
negligible then actually can come up
with a PCP that's accepted with non
netive probability but X is not in the
language so that that breaks the my that
can't happen
because I know the PCP has soundness
negligible so that can't happen and
therefore I must have Collision was not
probability and hence broke the
Collision so why is there why is it the
case that I can find a PCP that's
accepted because what am I going to do
remember let's think I never found
Collision it's negligible so you know
for all practical purposes never okay
let's think of the fact we never
encounter a collision so then what do we
do I take this PCP I take this adversary
I run it oh I I start pieing up a PCP I
say oh Pi 1 here good Pi i1 every time I
ask it again I know he'll give me this
answer because there's no
collisions and I start kind of slowly
piecing together an entire
PCP now there may be some form some
places of the PCP that either that he
will never open correctly never he'll
never give me a valid
opening then I can't I don't know I
don't moreover there may be some places
of the PCP that somehow this verifier
never
asked that can also be so I'm G to write
all the places that actually
opened I'm going to write down whatever
didn't open look this adversary can
always let's say it can always take one
minus Epsilon fraction of this PCP and
never open it and the rest open
correctly because he's only the Epsilon
right so there can be always I don't
want to not really one man's epon the
PCP because we ask many queries but
there can of course be some parts of the
PCP that he just never never answers and
it's okay because because of this
Epsilon okay so in that part I'm going
to whatever I don't know I'm going to
just put
zeros okay but this is my
PCP and that's it now this is pi I'm
going to call this
Pi now you're asking why is why would
the verifier accept Pi with non-
probability well because
this P star is accepted with probability
Epsilon
and this if v v is gonna ask okay so
what's the concern the concern is well V
now is going to ask like places that are
zero here right so the point is we're
say what's my you're con
look P star succeeded maybe P star
succeeded but here if P star succeeded
we have here pies then this will succeed
too because it's p star answers like
this but you're saying but maybe here
there zeros maybe here there are zeros
but why are there zeros let's remember
why did I put zeros here because P
failed on them that's why there's zeros
there I asked this place many many times
and every time petar said no so he won't
succeed on this or there's also another
option that VPC never asks that that
question in which case he still won't
ask that question
okay so again the claim is that this PCP
will be accepted with probability close
to Epsilon because the
probability that we will hit
locations where we
fail he and he succeeds is very very
very small so whenever we fail he will
fail too with very high
probability because if he succeed there
we would have succeeded we asked so many
questions we would finally get the right
answer that's
the high level idea okay I don't want to
go into more details I can send there's
a link in the website exactly on the
proof but there's two reasons I don't
want to go into more detail first
because it's tedious H so if you you
know if you're interested just look look
at the
paper but also this is not the right
proof this is not the right proof and
why is it not the right proof because
note I cheated you actually I actually
lied I promised you that I broke
soundness but I didn't actually there's
a very
minor a I don't know if to call it bug
but I I
lied and this doesn't quite
do it doesn't quite break the Collision
resistant
with my okay when I say A breaks the
Collision resistant I need to say a
break p
T Lambda adversary that breaks right I
said I assume T Lambda that you cannot
break the Collision time T
Lambda so I said let's us say there's a
t Lambda time P star and I'm going to
break my my the Collision the I'm G to
find the Collision in time poly T
Lambda that's what gives me a
contradiction I right I I argue my
assumption is that there exists a CIT in
hash that cannot be broken collisions
cannot be found in time polity to break
that I need to say if there exists a
cheating
Prov then I can break the Collis time
po now let's look at the runtime of this
adversary the peace times of time poity
that's
okay but what might does my adversary do
my
adversary he he tries to generate an
entire PCP and and then he says if I
succeeded I can't succeed and therefore
I must be Collision but to generate
entire PCP he needs to run in time Po in
N what if T of smaller than
n now you can say ah come on uh T Lambda
must be bigger than n otherwise this
kind of this def I don't like this
definition because I we should allow the
cheating proof to run time poan if you
don't something's wrong with
definition I don't know maybe yes maybe
no I I have now a definition that says
you know time T of Lambda maybe you want
T of lamb to be smaller than n because
the application makes sense because you
use it in a way that actually the pro
will never run in time
n so you know I have now some T of
Lambda how it connects to N I actually
don't know and I want to ensure that you
know I can break the adversary the the I
can fine Collision time t to the Lambda
but actually I run P star which is time
t to the Lambda that's fine but I run
him n times one over Epsilon is fine
because Epsilon is like Epsilon in
Lambda or ta to the
Lambda okay it's one over po t to the
Lambda fine that's good t to the Lambda
T of Lambda sorry but this n n can be
bigger than T of
Lambda so
so really this works if this this
definition is good if only if T of
Lambda is bigger than n so this is a
good proof
If and this is kind of kind of bother
cryptographers because even though it
makes sense to assume the T of Lambda is
bigger than n it makes sense to let the
cheating prove a run in time
poen it's
um it's annoying that we need to do
that so I think we should take a break a
f minute break after the break I'll tell
you just a very high level idea there's
a beautiful paper that came in 2002 by
Barak and gold that they showed how to
get around it how to do it for any they
get around they actually don't construct
an entire PCP they do what I think is a
more a clever and more beautiful kind of
what I think of as the right proof uh
for this uh and we'll see that after the
break and then we'll do the construction
of the Collision resistant but there was
questions before
yeah great
question I don't the rewinding for okay
so the question is was is the rewind in
necessary and it's a great question the
answer is for all I know yes the
rewinding is necessary a this question
was very important also for postquantum
because you know today we're worried
about quantum computers and if the
cheating prover is a Quantum device you
can't rewind him because once you
measure a Quantum state it collapses and
so proving postquantum security of this
protocol it was Pro actually it's known
to be postquantum secure but it was a
lot of work because when it was work
that required to kind of rewind the
cheating prover in the quantum like to
rewind the quantum cheating prover and
why can you rewind so they showed you
can actually do it but just to answer
your question do you need to rewind yes
uh kind of we don't have a StraightLine
proof of of
soundness for this
protocol you know so it the the the
other proof I'll show you after the
break doesn't quite construct the PCP
but in order to find collisions we need
to run him at least twice I run him and
then because how am I gonna find
Collision I give him queries he's gonna
give me answers how how how can I find
collisions from that but if I run him
once and I run him again with the idea
is I'm going to run him I'm going to
choose like a random query eye I'm once
going to run him eye with some queries
and then I'm going to run him ey with
other
queries and the only way you can cheat
is if you're not always consistent and
that but at least I need to rewind you
twice
so that's
the any any any other questions
yeah
this no I don't think the the right the
the the actually when you look inside
the hash functions it just becomes messy
I think actually abstracting out the
hash functions and just thinking what
property gives you makes the proof
cleaner uh put it kind of to put boxes
around things you know and just
modularize kind of what you need
actually helps the understanding and
helps simplifies the proof uh it's uh
yeah I I think the the problem with this
proof is that it requires constructing
an entire PCP and some saying why do I
need to construct an entire PCP so the
other proof kind of shows that you
actually don't need to do that and
that's why you could the pro doesn't
need to run time linear and N just runs
in time the depend on
T A any any other questions before the
break yeah n here is the size of PCP
yeah you're right n is the size of the
PCP but I'm thinking here because I'm
thinking of three set I'm thinking the
input the instance n the witness and the
PCP are all poly
related so it's because I have your
polinomial it doesn't matter but I do
want to say uh in some settings you can
think of the witness can be much much
smaller than instance or much much
bigger than the instance so for example
take nondeterministic time t x is of
size n but the witness is of size T of n
which can be super polinomial in
N then this becomes polinomial in the
witness the PCP is always or okay the
PCP is always polom related to the
instance and witness now sometimes the
witness is bigger sometimes the instance
is bigger and the relation does not need
to be po nomally related if they're all
Pally related it doesn't matter here
because I put a poly but sometimes the
witness can be much much smaller like
log click the witness is size log
squared but the input is n and sometimes
the instance can be small and the
witness can be big so what I mean here
is input plus witness length here I just
put one of them because I assume three
set they're all the they're both the
same so yeah but that's a good what
really I need to put here's PCP length
that's the truth um yeah great great
Point fantastic other questions before
we
break okay let's do a five minute break
and then we'll return