Hello everyone listening and watching.
Uh welcome to this short video where I'm
going to give you a demo of how to use
the interactive mapping module of the
protein institute genomics to proteins
portal a discovery platform to link
genetics training outputs to protein
sequence and structure. Um so as we
access this uh module it is going to ask
um you to sign in using your Gmail
address. So let's do that and after
continuing we will land up in this
homepage for interactive ma mapping
module with two different subm modules.
You can start with a human gene protein
identifier or you can also just uh start
with um a protein structure. So in this
particular tutorial I'm going to give
you a demo of the workflow starting with
own protein structure and the previous
tutorial that is published has the demo
for um starting with the gene protein
identifier. So let's begin the workflow.
Um here the first step is uploading a
structure which you can either predict
from alphafold or you can download from
protein datab bank. So I'm going to use
um a structure that I have downloaded
here 605i
uh mmcif file and there are one chains
available here chain A. I will uh select
that chain and hit load with that. Now
you have a sequence viewer where the
sequence um um that is parsed from the
structure is mapped and also you can see
the structure
uh and then you also now can upload uh
annotations. The allowable formats for
annotations for mutations score and
features are shown here. So we'll close
it and we'll load the sample
annotations.
Uh important to note that you can either
paste your annotation in this comma or
tab separated format or you can also
upload your data as CSV or Excel file
and you can in fact continue without um
any annotations at all. So we'll start
we will um go with these mutations and
uh submit the annotations
um and this um cells will be editable as
I have demonstrated um in the previous
video uh of for demo with starting with
protein with a gene protein identifier.
So we'll submit these annotations
and now um these mutations are mapped
onto the structure. Um so I demonstrated
it previously but we can change the
colors of these annotations. For
example, um if I want to show the benign
mutations in blue, um and then denovo
mutations in orange.
Now we have the benigns mapped as
the desired color and then pathogenic
and then the denovo mutations. Now after
executing this workflow, you can share
this uh workflow with u um
collaborator's email address. So I'm
going to just um type in
sample email address here. And now I'm
creating a link. You can also add
another email address. So you can share
with multiple collaborators at the same
time. Then it takes uh you to create
link. Now after you have created the
link we can copy it and try to paste it
um in the browser now um it will ask the
your collaborator to log in using that
authorized email address
um which I'm doing here and after that
uh the uh collaborator need to uh needs
to paste this link one more time to load
this entire session that you have
created. it um and then the
collaborators can see um the output of
the session.
Um so hope this is helpful uh to use and
execute workflows uh using the broad
institute genomics to proteins portal
interactive mapping module to analyze
your own data.