so I will speak about tensor methods for
omix data analysis first I want to kind
of give them insight into why we in
these days come up with very uh
complicated uh like fanasy method enters
the bioinformatics
domain and because now we are in the
area of Biotech right so here in the
broad Institute also there are uh like
um groups and centers actually they are
creating a really valuable data set and
right they are sharing with public now
we are able to generate or access
terabytes of data and it suppress the
point that we cannot right just look at
and try to get insights out of our data
so we need principal models to get these
complex patterns in our biological data
sets so just to give the more insights
into I think audience here are very
familiar with this stuff insights into
how and why now we are able to access
that much data set faster than before
think about the Human Genome Project to
get the first human reference DNA right
it took like around 32 years but if you
look at uh complete 85% completion for
sure it's way earlier right and it costs
uh uh like millions of dollars every
resource report a different numbers so I
prefer not to exactly say but now thanks
to the reference we we have and thanks
to the new technologies we have
sometimes it takes as short as one day
and depends on the Technologies you use
right it doesn't cost in this case that
much now we are able to sequence and we
are able to get the data faster but it's
not just the quantity of the data is
increasing dimensionality and variety of
the data is also
increasing okay so here I will give a
belowed example of the broad Institute
most of they use this smti fruit bowl
and fruit tart example a lot first time
I think I heard from Ab re she was
giving this example and I start
understanding difference between
different Technologies like that so here
so we kind of started From bu like for
sure there are different Technologies
but one of the starting point is like
starting from bu genomics when you have
a tissue we are looking at average ex
gene expression in this tissue they call
this like a sumti you know what's
happening on average but you don't know
you don't have the
heterogenity and then when you move the
Single Cell right
now when you move the Single Cell in
this case uh then now we have uh we we
have more uh expression for every cell
in this case we know like more
information about heterogenity in this
tissue right in this case it's like you
know that you have very
right you have like your micro phases
you have t sets but you don't know the
exact
location but now uh some some
technologies was also developed here now
we have different spatial
transcriptomics Technologies with
different resolution they C like a fruit
tart right you know which kind of styles
you have and now we know the locations
of these Styles more or less again it
depends on the
resolution and it's not just this I
cannot laser I want people online also
try to see the
lases anyways let see about it you fix
for the next talk and we also have uh is
like now uh we can collect multi sample
data sets for for example different
Patients Group we are looking for
different diseases and we can use
different om platforms get data on
mutation copy number gene expression DNA
mulation and actually we get this m data
so you have bunch of matrices to analyze
right now it's actually if we go more
like a data perspective we start from a
vector right we start from a vector here
uh for a bulk then we are going for
Matrix for every tissue then we start
collecting omix data from different
platforms you have a bunch of matrices
to analyze so the dimensionality keeps
increasing so for these high dimensional
data sets I will introduce the tensors
so we will come back these examples and
how we will discuss how the tensor
methods could be
useful okay so what's the tensor again
we said we will uh use tensor to
represent and analyze multimodal High
dimensional data sets and tensors are
multi-dimensional array right you can
you start from sorry you start from for
example scalers uh like scale like
scalers like time points and we use most
of time vectors what we said for the
bulk data time series data we had Tech
vectors we went to the matrices so we
keep going actually we don't stop and
the moment we go like you are putting
more dimensions and more variations the
simplest case will be three-way tensor
and the moment you put more Dimensions
it's going to be higher order
tensors and we said they are considered
generalization of matrices the higher
Dimensions so here there's a notation
crisis and sometimes I also cause this
notation crisis sometimes they say for
example for this Cube order three tensor
or three the three-way tensor or
three-dimensional tensor everybody use
this how to say their own notations I
will mostly call order three or threeway
tensor okay so here the other idea just
to give more mathematical details goes
to Second talk here it's going to be
primary will be more generic and we'll
go through the case studies but
mathematically what's happening lots of
traditional data analysis methods were
Matrix based and Matrix correspond to
linear Maps we use linear algebra a lot
and when you go this High dimensional
data analysis methods tensor based
tensors are corresponding to multilinear
maps and we use multilinear algebra
tools my PhD was like in algebraic
geometry and multilinear Algebra I work
very theoretical then I discover
applications during my post and I am so
happy it so it's mostly like multilinear
algebra
tools okay so tensors uh why they start
getting popular in different areas of
data science they give a compact way to
represent multimodal data for example if
you think
about if you think about the color
images we have uh height WID and color
channels so this can be represented by a
three-way tensor and think about like in
theid we can also add the time as a
different variation so if you put have
the videos it's going to be fourway tens
and actually in the computer vision
image processing uh the tenser methods
are heavily used and uh one of the area
I use for multi sample multitissue
genomics data you are looking at how
gene expression is changing across
different tissues for different
individuals in this case we are trying
to look at the triple interactions
multilinear interactions to represent
present these ones in a simple case we
can use three-way tensors and to analyze
this one we will use tensor
factorizations which I will introduce
and other possible data sets like
perturbational data sets in this case
you can have so we have a cell line
treated with a drug and we are trying to
understand what is the effect of this
drug right you can look at the change in
gene expression so this triple
interaction between cell line and drug
and genes can be represented by a
threeway tens
in the simplest case and I will give an
example we can use tensor factorization
to understand the triple
interactions okay there's also other
domains like Network learning social
competing it was heavily used in
chemistry by informatics again it's not
very surprising in the in losss of areas
we start getting high dimensional data
and these tools start being more popular
because they are serving to
community good so I will give some
simple
notations is
this okay first I want to solve my
problem s with the
clicker I cannot use
it yeah people online will not be able
to see this part okay so let's say so
the notations I will introduce like
similar to Matrix notation let's say x
is a d way tensor of size N1 * N2 * n d
so N1 correspond the first modality N2
correspond the second modality and I
will denote the i1 I2 ID to entry by X
i1 I2 ID right so if you have a tensor
of same size two tens of same size X and
Y when I say same size it will have same
size in every modality so you can take
the inner product of these sensors the
inner product will be given as we
multiply um entries for corresponding
indices and we sum them right actually
here I'm not going to be able to go all
the details there are lots of like we
have Matrix multiplication there is a
different way to multiply tensors
multiply tensors with matrices but it
has its own operations its own way to
define rank we will little bit speak
lots of think doesn't gen directly
generalize the ters and we will Define
forbus Norm because we will use it a lot
if you just use this inner product you
can induce the forbus norm it's the
square of the entries we are summing and
we take the square root we'll use it a
lot
okay so I will go
ahead there is one more uh like more
technical part but most technical Parts
go the second talk because I want to
speak about rank one tensor first so
when we do tensor factorization we will
try to look at um rank one tensors in
our data then I want to explain why we
care about rank one tensors because they
will give a unit of an expression
pattern and I will give solid examples
about it so first let's start from rank
one Matrix so if you have vectors u in
rn1 and v in rn2 so you can take the
other product of these two vectors U
other product V it's like U * V
transpose in the simplest case so it's
going to be rank one Matrix and we do
Matrix factorization actually we are
trying to write our Matrix as sum of
rank one
matrices right but you can have like the
vectors let's say U1 has uh in rn1 you
is rn2 you can take the other product of
D vectors and it will give you a d way
tensor so this tensor it's simple and
the name is also simple tensor and they
also call it P tensor so it is called a
rank one tensor why it's important so
actually if you look at the I can look
at the entry T i1 I2 ID right this i1 is
from one to N1 I2 is from one to N2 I is
from one to ND this uh entry will be you
go your first Vector you want and you
took you take the I want entry you go
second Vector I2 you are getting the I2
T and you go your last Vector UD and you
are taking ID T so it's separable signal
so it represent a separable signal which
can be expressed as the combination of
independent factors from each mode so it
will give us a unit of an expression
pattern
and just to give little bit
probabilistic connections probabilties
connection is actually more details but
I want to give the simple SK for rank
one t let's say you have uh the random
variables independent random variables
right we are going to look at their
joint distribution you can write the
joint distributions of these V variables
as the product of their marginal
distributions right so let's say p
probability of X1 is i1 X2 is I2 X3 is
ID it can be written as product of
separate distributions and I can
represent this one with a d way tensor
and ti1 ID will give this uh joint
distribution and if you look at how we
write we separate the marginal
distribution it's other product of these
distributions actually rank one tens
represents a system where each Dimension
correspond an independent random
variable and the tensor entries
represent the product of probability
or related measure associated with each
independent variable okay I'm not going
to go actually higher ranks for respond
to conditional independent variables but
we're not going to go details but in
discussions you can ask more
details okay now we kind of spoke about
a lot about it and we were going to go
why is Xi element of integers upst n so
we get this question let me go Okay so
so this is a good question it doesn't
have to be element of integers up to N I
actually yeah it's kind of a labeling
mistake it can be uh X1 is U how to say
can be represented values let's say uh
lower case X1 and it can take different
values not necessarily integers from one
to ni okay it's my typo thank you for
pointing
out
okay okay so now we have a tensor let's
see uh like let's say this is the
modalities of genes cell types and
samples so we are looking how gene
expression is changing across different
uh cell types for different samples
these samples can correspond to like
different donor profiles as well right
so here okay what are the traditional
approaches so we are more comfortable
using Matrix based tools tools and
traditional approach is like becoming a
data ninja we have our tensor we slice
it or we unfolded it but the knowing the
slices and unfolding SOS important
because it will keep appearing in the
optimization part of these algorithms so
for example here we can slice this one
along the first modality so let's say
you have 20,000 je
now welcome you have like 20,000
matrices to analyze but I think it's a
lot of work sometimes people okay they
don't go in the gene level but in this
case instead of analyzing one one
concrete structure right minear
structure you may end up with analyzing
20,000 matrices okay for sure maybe you
can decide okay I'm going to slice this
across sample second modality so in this
case if you have let's say 100 samples
you end up with uh in this case Okay the
second modality do cell types sorry if
you have 10 cell types you can end up
with 10 different matrices and analyze
them factorize them and merge all the
inter like how to say interpretations
you have to merge them and again this is
this is like horizontal vertical and
lateral slies actually you can do along
the third modality this was most a
common approach you get the they they
get the data and they work on those
matrices but we are not going to do like
that we are going to keep the Integrity
um of the structure of the data the
other way most the people do
unfoldings so let's look at this one we
have bunch of slices for the first
modality we kind of put next to each
other and form a big Matrix so this
becomes gen times number of set times
times number of samples and we can do
this one for the second modality s types
times a long Matrix or samples time long
Matrix these are mostly common M common
approaches not the tens approaches
Matrix B approaches but one thing to
notice when you matze the data
informations on the interactions uh
relation between different modalities is
lost so we will have more discussion on
that
one okay for example just to I will
introduce tensor factorization I want to
uh make sure I mentioned about Matrix
factorization as a foundation so here
most of the time let's say we start with
this big data and people do Matrix
factorizations in here let's say there
are different Matrix factorization based
on the constraint you you put in your
factors orthogonal non- negative most of
people prefer non- negative because it's
easy interpret the results so here let's
say uh you will get genes times factors
let's say you are factorizing to rank R
is like low rank
approximation right and you will have St
types over each sample times factors so
here what happens when we flatten we are
concatenating two variations into one
Dimensions if it's actually higher order
sensor you will concatenate many
variations into one dimension
so here Matrix factorization what's
happening mathematically I'm writing my
Matrix as sum of rank one matrices right
I have here Lambda I GI like for example
this guy will correspond to G1 times CI
right C1 and here Lambda tells me how
strong is the signal GI in this case
gives the Gen slum Factor CI gives the S
typ latent factor for the tensors we
will go very deep and we will see okay
how we can interpret these factors for
example here we are looking which gen
are up regulated down regulated what
what are the pat ways and then when we
go s types over each sample and we are
trying to see which side types are
active in which samples so it becomes
like trying to decode these two
Dimensions okay here what we are going
to do we are not going to flatten we are
not going to slice is there any way to
factorize it as it is and
yeah oh yeah sure
um in the cell type so cell types are
mostly categorical in this case right
they're categorical data so we have and
the you sell neurons different types
yeah like T microage yeah so how do you
represent them in as a
matrix okay so here uh it's actually it
start with how we start uh our Matrix so
our Matrix is actually it's like a gene
expression uh for let's say uh C cell
across this s uh across this sample
right every time we are speaking about
gene expression in setup lating factors
right we will discuss this one what
happens we are looking at what are the
weights for corresponding cell types and
for example if T cell has a high weight
we will see say that the gene expression
program is activated in T Cell right
maybe I should have mentioned how I set
up my Matrix but in Cas we are looking
at gen expression for specific St type
for specific samples
okay okay so here we are going to look
at more generalization of Matrix
factorization I will introduce two
common tensor decomposition but there
are multiple tensor decomposition
methods but these are the most popular
so we will discuss in the next Talk
technical details they are the most
popular not because have said they are
the best because they were the first
ones okay so like Tucker decomposition
is one of the most popular and first
and let's say again we are looking at
how gen expression is changing across
different cell types and for different
samples so these are data for example t
i j k will be expression of gen I at C
type G for sample K and let's say the
size is number of genes times number of
cell types times number of samples so
that one can be so big in any case you
may start with like around 20,000 genes
right so here first thing we will do we
will reduce the dimension so most of
time we are not really looking at yeah
we work with 20,000 genes but we are
trying to find metag genes or Gene
clusters right we are trying to get this
Parts I can uh find gene expression
programs so we reduce the dimension here
let's say next talk we will discuss how
you reduce the dimension and how you can
find the Rings to the reduce the
dimension we go to R1 * R2 * R3 so here
when you do Matrix factorization from
one Matrix you get two matrices now we
when we do a simple ske three-way tensor
decomposition from one tensor we are
going to get three matrices one for each
modality and we get we will discuss we
also have something for tenser I will
discuss it first I get Gene factors it
is number of genes times R1 R1 is the
reduced Dimension it means you have R1
latent factors and we will look at what
they correspond to they will correspond
the gene expression pattern and for
samples it can be this is really
important I care about it so it's number
of samples times artery let's say I have
200 patient profiles but at the end
there are two subtypes maybe driving the
gene expression programs maybe disease
non disease right or you can have like
uh different subtypes of the cancer that
we will discuss so this one will help
you to find these main uh I'll say donor
variations and actually it will have you
the class Discovery with the sample
factors and saltating factors will have
you to see in which cell types this um
gene expression programs was activated
so we reduce Dimension there as well for
cell type sometimes you not necessarily
reduce so there is this thing mostly
this R1 R2 R3 is less than number of
genes number of cells number of samples
it was and for genes definitely but for
times sometimes cell types you can even
go to a uh R2 can be greater than number
of cell types why for for example maybe
you have a t- cell it's activated
differently for disease condition and
you have a te- cell which has a
different program for non- disease
condition so you put T Cell as one uh
variation but you may end up with two t
cells program and we will discuss them
and C look at the correlation between
different factors we will also discuss
it more mathematically for the Matrix
factorization we have the coefficients
it dos how strong is the signal so here
we will have the core tensor to say have
strong signals between different factors
okay let's go
here uh what's happening mathematically
I have a tensor I'm writing my tensor as
some of rank one tensors let's see here
this is G JK gives the how strong is the
um signal and GI is the gene latent
factor CJ setup latent factor and SK
will be sample slant Factor K sample
slant Factor so this is like a rank one
tensor expression pattern and core
tensor will tell me how strong is the
signal between these
factors so here you can have R1
different gen latent factor R2 different
genes uh setup latent factors and R2
different sample latting factor and G ik
that's why it's R1 time R2 * R3 it's
like a matter of indexing so people
summarize this one and show this is cor
tensors times Gene factors you put all
the the factors next to each other and
it becomes column of a bigger Matrix as
we discussed and S types factors and
Sample factors okay this is one of the
most common and I want to quickly
introduce another one is um heavily used
CP decomposition it's a special case of
this one that's why I started from here
in CP decomposition everything is
oversimplified it says okay ranks over
each modalities is same R1 is equal R2
is equal R3 sometimes it works perfect
and if it doesn't work we go to Tucker
actually and in this Cas in this case
it's like uh then here you don't need a
um core tensor you just need a
coefficient here g i j k is not equal
zero if and only if I is equal J is
equal K so we just end up with Lambda I
times g i c i SI I I'm going to
introduce more visually this is
called actually if I start discussing
what is called it would take one hour so
every one different research groups they
discover this method at different times
and they all thought that they are the
first one discovering this method there
is a long list of names but I'm going to
give the most common one canonical
decomposition parallel factor analysis
they shorten it they say CP but if you
see a paper and if you see okay they are
calling it in a different way it's not
my fault okay I just say what is Comming
and most of time they use alternative Le
Square to solve these questions which in
the next next to we will discuss details
that's why they call
CPS in CPS just to go quickly I start
from my three-way tenser and I'm getting
three Factor matrices all of them has
the same reduced Rank and mathematically
actually I'm writing my tensor as sum of
rank one tensors you actually you cannot
really write because we are working on
noisy data we don't really write as
equal we are looking at approximation
next talk we will discuss how good is
approximation how we can choose rank
right and we also have noise we will
discuss about okay which kind of
assumptions we will have on the noise
and on the factors which could work for
genomics data okay and now actually in
this talk I will mostly go over some
case studies there are many applications
of cancer factorization in omix data
analysis but I will try to give four or
five
applications but first I keep speaking
about rank one tenser let's see what
rank one tenser represents so this is
more detailed version of this example
will be given in our talk it is from our
project classical hkin lyoma let's say
we have this tensor uh genes times cell
types times samples we were working on
over 20,000 genes for 10 cell types and
40 uh samples like this is um 40 tissues
taking from different patient Prof
different patients so here one of the
rank one tens appeared in the factory
ization uh for example here we had again
Gene sting Factor setup sting Factor
sample sting Factor this a unit of an
expression pattern but how does it look
like so gen latent factor is has length
20,000 and we look at um which genes are
up regulated non regulated or which Gene
clusters together up regulated non
regulated then you can look at the pet W
you find the Petway which is J set
Petway promotes tumor side proliferation
and survival of tumor C so this is the
first goal we find un expression program
in one shot you can look at all the
triple uh triple interaction
simultaneously then next question you
ask okay this program is activated in
which cell types and we go to our cell
type factors here okay so the height of
corresponding to these different colors
correspond to these 10 different cell
types the height actually gives what is
the uh what is the weight at what is the
loading so actually it shows that only
tumor C has high loading so we say this
gene expression program activated in
tumor s which makes sense tumor
proliferation right then we look at okay
this is activated in which patient
groups then you'll go look at your
sample slat Factor so here again this
height correspond to the loadings and we
have three groups uh first group of
patients again is unsupervised so we are
not really putting labels in our
algorithm so it is HK lyoma patients and
dark blue ones hkin lyoma patients with
ebb virus open blue hkin lyoma patient
without ebb virus and orange one
reactive lyph patients and this actually
says okay this program is activated in
hkin Pati so even if you didn't know
labels so we know it but we didn't use
it that kind of unsupervised method it's
already they're able to find the uh how
to say stratification of your data donor
conditions so that's how we are going to
use it and in the applications these
patterns this kind of rank one tensors
will keep appearing
okay let's go just I will have three
slides to kind of compare it with couple
of some methods but more details will
come in the next talk so again we
already discussed non- negative Matrix
factorization and PCA most of they
unfold the data and you can lose the
heterogen how to say interactions
between different modalities and
interpretation becomes very hard you
merge the analysis from your multiple
unfoldings or multiple slices and non-
negative Matrix factorization is not
unique here okay I am always in the Tor
domain also I create some conflicts most
of time when you read tensor methods are
unique this is too theoretical so they
will say okay one of the I'm both
speaking limitations I'm speaking truth
they will say okay nmf is not unique but
tenser methods are unique first work
with the noisy data you will see if it's
Unique or not it's Unique theoretically
but it's not stable next talk we will go
over it but theoretically it's Unique
under my the
conditions stable here in stable yeah we
will discuss it more stable is like when
you run the same algorithm you don't
always get the same factors because it
will be heavily dependent on the initial
guess right theoretically it may be
unique but it's not going to be stable
and we are going to address it and again
rank selection is nontrivial for both
both of them and for tensors we have a
pipeline to discuss and the most
important higher Dimension is
challenging interpretation for Matrix
methods and for deep learning approaches
in the Deep learning approaches there
are two things one thing it depends like
it's devolving but latent space
interpretation sometimes is very
difficult not even possible here we
already discuss our latent space rank
one tensor always already was giving us
latent factor it's very interpretable
other thing for deep learning approach
appr es sometimes we have unit thousands
of data right unit loss of funding but
sometimes we work in some public data or
one of the project we work we work on
gasta it's not easy to get so much data
right you can also work with small
numbers of data sets with these methods
because in deep learning inference on
patterns on a new data set is as good as
training data set in the cases you don't
have a big training data sets
factorization based methods be utilized
and the last thing differenti Express
expression methods for the differential
expression methods for the gene
expression you have to give the groups
you say group a versus Group B B it's
you already know but when you have a new
data set and you don't know what is like
what is driving the gene expression
programs you don't even know the
subtypes of cancers in this case
unsupervised methods like factorization
methods will be more beneficial actually
we will have concrete example here for
the eods need to give predefined
condition and it doesn't consider sample
heterogenity maybe I have two patients
but they can also have heterogenity
between them so it's actually kind of
hurting the whole
analysis good so I will now give some
examples of the application some case
studies one of the common example goes
with multi sample gene expression data
sets and it can be you can consider
multiple cell types or multiple tissues
here for example we start from a single
cell data right you can find the cell
types and we may have we it's so similar
to what we discussed like a genes gene
expression over different cell types for
different
donors okay so there are actually lots
of sources to get this kind of data set
gex UK Co cohort illuminate body lab and
human tissues for sure tcga cancer
genome Atlas right again as we discussed
in the previous slides traditional
approaches often um assume that gene
expression patterns remain consistent
across different contexts right or
samples are independent or homogeneous
but we Al in tensor factorization we
respect the heterogenity so if you
structure this one as a matrix you have
some challenges it may hinder to
revealing sat type specific tissue
specific or individual specific patterns
so we want to really go donor specific
or condition specific patterns also you
can if you Matrix size you can ignore
individual heterogenity and one of the I
think next case study they're actually
looking at how this gene expression
patterns are driven by biological
factors like race gender age right you
may need some
correlations so there are okay this is
the main pipeline but it's similar to
what we discussed we factorize right and
this case maybe I'm not going to go over
it again after factorization we are
trying to see the meaning of our latent
factors so here for example we looking
at uh Gene factor three and you so here
I just put top 20 genes but for sure you
do like a Petway analysis gen set
enrichment analysis to find what is the
function there and you go to cell types
latent factor three to see identify SS
with high loading you say this pattern
is activated there and you look at your
donor conditions like donor latent
factor three here you can test for you
look at coar effect test for correlation
of this donor factors with um whatever
clinical information available healthy
disease like a gender right this kind of
things and this is a case study
multicluster I want to also give the
some uh like studies so people are more
interesting to reading a lot around so
it will give a resource second they had
uh gex data and they had 544 individuals
across 53 human tissues including 133
brain sub regions so it's like
18,41 * 544 * 53 tenser and they did a
tensor decomposition I guess they were
um I'm not totally sure they might have
just reduced up the 10 main factors
right they use something called semi
non- negative tensor decomposition is
what it means for the tissue latent
factor they force non negativity so they
can interpret the results easily so
means in my application I force non
negativity for every Factor so the
interpretation is
easy okay again they did the same find
gin clusters tissue cluster individual
clusters and they test the correlations
of the individual clusters to clinical
attributes they use tenser methods here
you can check more details for
clustering classification Coit effects
for example for clustering um there are
multiple groups in this study uh this is
in a they do gen clustering tissue
clustering with PCA it's one of the
cases uh because of loss of heterogenity
as well clustering doesn't become very
perfect PCA also we will discuss people
also as normal distribution it's not
totally true for genomics data here the
clustering with tensor factors they show
it becomes like more you can see your
more identified clusters but they also
look at different uh different um tasks
again you can see theils here and I want
to quickly go another application
I want to cover at least three four
application we can discuss later details
another application I really like mics
data now we can get data from genomics
platform transcriptomics epigenomics
prics
metabolics I couldn't say it again there
are different resources to get this kind
of data but now actually we are like
okay for one patient I have more and
more and more information okay but can
we use all this information right now
for the tester methods what we are going
to do we will try to there are different
ways to merge though we will try to
merge this data to a big tensor and we
will try to do
factorization and yeah um so when we get
DNA mulation data for example it's
usually not on the um not Gene level
yeah not gen level right yeah most of
the time they do more Gene Centric uh
right for example most of the studies
Amir we are working on something like
that now we are looking at average
metalation for Gene level okay so they
try to come you try to find the common
modality lots of them merging happens
Gene level it's a good question thank
you
yeah points thanks a lot of these data
sets have U obvious links between
entities like genes proteins metil sites
can this be taken into account yeah this
can be uh can you ask again they are
yeah yeah so you can draw clear links
between a gene and a protein for example
and then you have measurements in these
samples is uh those links something you
take into account in the like if for
example you can also even give this is
more um regularized tensor factorization
protein protein interaction networks or
other kind of maps you have it can also
learn a map but it is um that method
little bit more complicated from what I
discussed but there are actually methods
like that they learn from the like
graphs right the relation between
different proteins your genes and
proteins and they kind of like gives you
more inference right thank
you okay here uh one of the way again
the way you merge it also depends on
your data and I will give one example
and there are different styles of
merging actually now we have this kind
of data set and we are trying to merge
by ourselves it's like here let's say we
are merging these data sets again you
get a big tensor but what happens when
you factorize we will discuss
again again this is like we form a big
tenser it's not like you have access to
all of them like once you have access
then you are trying to find overlapping
information for the like for example
trying to see okay 20 let's say 2,000
genes and express and all the profiles
and we try to find overlapping matrices
like overlapping modality okay here
again we have some donor Matrix right
and we have donor latent factors and
Gene Matrix Gene factors and omic
factors and here we get gr Dr o r and if
you look at this rank one t ijk it
captures the interaction between the I
gen for J donor but K omix platform but
I will explain what it can mean and
which kind of results we get from it
from the case
study this a um commonly use case study
Monty it's momic non- negative T
decomposition for Gene level they go
okay for the metalation you you have
information based on the promoter but
they go to Gene level integrate
integrative analysis so they for example
had gene expression metalation Mi Mna
and they factorized this one and when
they factorize actually what they try to
find and what they find in this case so
they
um data has 597 breast cancer 314 colon
cancer and 305 stomach cancer actually
they form three different tensors for
them and work them separately and most
importantly for example for breast
cancer they are looking for four
different
subtypes right they have luminal a
luminal b her to and basil and Monte in
this case was able to detect subtype
specific or clinical attributes specific
right because we have more information
about donors we can later use Gene sets
that show strongly regulated by certain
omics and it also shows for example it
was both strongly regulated uh by
metalation and mni expression so you can
see also kind of correlation between
different omic types they can refer the
uh like same type of uh Gene
regulation and it's kind of like main
conclusion is integrating momic data in
a gene centent manner Improv detecting
cancer sub type specific features and
other clinical features yeah is there a
reason why they um construct different
sensors for the three types of cancer
they can yeah so you can also put all of
them together actually then in this case
uh it can it's not a lot of data it can
find uh breast cancer subtypes colon
cancer subtypes and stomach cancer
subtypes but maybe when you work in a
smaller data set I'm not not sure if
like finding subtypes becomes easier but
I think the mostly our approach is kind
of approach we put all the data together
and we first run we will say can the
methods tell us right okay this is
actually kind of one cancer group second
cancer group it's like I think there is
no need to actually make three
caners but like again it's like a try I
would put all of them together but at
the same time I would put them
separately to make sure am I getting
more information like that or when you
put them all together maybe you can also
put more noise in the data
right okay so I have how many minutes I
don't
know good okay data imputation and we
will have sell interaction sell
interaction will be the last application
but there are more applications here
data imputation so here one of the
projects we work so let's say cmap dep
map you have lots of like uh data for
drug effects right you can have a a drug
a sell line treat with a drug and you
can look at gene expression change
before treatment and after treatment
right then in this case we can seually
what is the effect of this drug so you
have
this uh triple interaction drugs genes
and cells and has lots of missing data
because even developing a drug right so
it takes lots of time lots of funding
sometimes 10 years it should drink Co it
you were really thinking okay drug
repurposing must be really good it's
like we were really giving importance to
direct repurposing sometimes we don't
even have time to develop a need drug so
can we learn the signatures of the other
drugs to infer something about like okay
uh this drug actually in the goal lab I
think stepen Corel had the paper right
he was showing some non uncol drugs can
be used for cancer as well so this is
the main biological goal but it's a
mathematically missing data problem
right so here in this kind of this is a
paper triy this one and in this kind of
missing data problems people try
different things these are kind of
simple methods but one of them actually
you have your tensor can you find your
low rank approximation and use this
approximation latent factor to rebuild
your tensor but I will also discuss
there are multiple limitations in this
approaches as well here they just use
CPD composition it might not be best way
to approach this kind of questions the
self specific prediction and application
of drug indust expression profiles this
is the paper so I will
discuss using low rank approximation
directly might not be best because next
talk we will discuss that CPD
compositions are not convex Also let's
say you have a matrix with totally empty
column when you do factorization this
empty column when you try to inut will
come as one one one one one right you
should try to avoid this kind of like it
will just try to take everything sh
out um just for a reminder was CPD the
one where where the um old equal each
yeah right thank you again this is not
the best one it's the most simple one
it's commonly used right it's like
because people get used to it it's
already transferring from matrices the
tensors took time and transferring from
CP to other metods will take more
time we will discuss in the next talk
what are the limitations of C so now I
will Rego this one like missing data
problems so and I want to give which
kind of research idea which kind of
research is available in tensor methods
one part is actually goes there are
different uh groups one part very
optimization based one part is very
algebraic geometry because this stuff
rank one tens correspond to Second
varieties and stuff right one part also
very data Orient oriented so actually
whatever you are doing is you are
generalizing Concepts from matrices to
high M so if it's always good to start
from matrices for missing data let's see
what they are doing for matrices I have
a x is like data with Miss Missing
entries they do kind of there are
different ways for the Matrix
factorization uh uh base approaches they
do approximation right uh to lower ring
approximation plus and noise but if you
do low rank approximation actually back
in time they were doing minimizing the
rank of the approximation right it will
already have imputed values but this not
a rank is not a convex U how say rank is
not convex so it doesn't give you conx
problem and people were trying different
ways one of the ones they tried and it's
very solid is nuclear Norm so they said
instead of minimizing the rank of the
Matrix they minimize like some of
singular values they minimize the
nuclear Norm of matrices so lots of
theou groups actually they are trying to
do this one for t level right I also
work on this one but nuclear Norm of
tensor is something you can approximate
there is lots of research here we cannot
exactly find it right nuclear Norm
convex Tade of for rank for matrices for
ters as well if you can compute I will
just give like this is a question how
and I will give a case study which use
this definition they try to
approximate nuclear Norm for T SE let's
say you have a three-way tensor you are
factorizing and you are trying to
minimize some of coent this is the CP de
composition Lambda * UI v i w i rank is
equal in each domain so we set I is from
one to R it's like some of R rank on
tensors right every Vector has a norm
one here Norm of UI VI W is equal to one
and we are trying to minimize some of
lambas because they look similar to
singular values of matrices this Al
another domain what could be the
singular value decomposition of 10 aners
can you find autopal decompositions this
actually also different domain to work
as well so this is called nuclear
decomposition and people use
approximations of this one because it
promotes par intensity DEC composition
encorage simpler low rank representation
of multi-dimensional data and it's a big
resource for data
imputation and and for example there is
this study I will go quickly because I
want to speak about last T interactions
they use for uh imputing single sty data
in single sty data we have lots of
missing points because of the Dropout
effect in they use different published
data sets here and they compare their
method for drct impute sa s impute magic
cmf impute this uh is this consense
Matrix factorization here what happens
actually just to go quickly they start
from a single cell data and they get
tensor out of it maybe just go quickly
over it for one cell here they are
looking at here in correlation and they
find K nearest cells and they they get a
matrix for every cell and they look at
different type of so this Matrix they
vectorize every Matrix and they look at
different kind of distances between
these matrices they find the P closest
one so for one cell you have P Matrix K
* m * P right and they do tensor
imputation by approximating the nuclear
Norm it Bec becomes more powerful than
the like classical CPD compositions
because CPD composition based imputation
they just look at the low range and they
integrate and they imput their data on
this uh five different actually there is
more data set and it's uh performing
better than it's kind of 2021 paper all
that methods which were popular at that
time okay I have time or couple okay so
I want to quickly go over in the one of
the last application
but there are more application here I
like putting as uh as the last one so we
will speak about s signaling so we know
that communication is key so I really
like this game of a telephone you start
from some uh words and you whisper then
you whisper sometimes you can start like
a message that I love mango smoothies
that are super sore and you can end up
Mangus give super powers I knew it right
so it can get complicated so we don't uh
we want to understand actually how our
STS are communicating I hope they're not
communicating like that but in some
sometimes when you have diseases or when
you have cancer in the environment maybe
communication actually get blinded right
communication gets problem so it's
really important to understand this um
Li receptor interactions and
communication pway so here quickly so
here it is one of the type of the
communication pattern we have not the
only interactions and our standing cells
send these moleculars which we call
light and our target cells have
receptors right right liant cell and
receptor should meet and how we
understand if these cells have Li
receptor PS we look at gene expression
for corresponding Li and receptor and if
this Li and receptor meet and it creates
a response
right and here I will see quickly case
study uh 2022 paper Tor cell to cell so
this is to understand L and receptor
interactions uh for different context so
they have again their sender side
receiver side they look at the LI
receptor payers again you can look at
every expression for the specific L and
receptor they do also sometimes
geometric means different things to
calculate communication score but think
about you have different standard set
and receiver set and you are looking at
different like receptor payers you have
multiple matrices they form a 3D
communication
tensor and you can also look at
different context
like time points study object body size
disease condition and different context
will give the fourth dimension and
actually they are looking for 4D uh
communication tensor this context aware
communication tensor again they applied
haer the composition in here again I
also have some questions have to say
Improvement suggestions for that and
choice of the rank was not really given
in there and next talk we will decide
okay how to make sure about the rank
stabil factors ation and they assume
normal noise which is not always true
for genomics but they were able to find
Lon receptor payer activated in specific
standard and receptor cells uh for
different context for example what they
were able to
find they identify multiple modules
associated with distant communication
processes like uh Li receptor
interactions linked to sever of Corona
virus disease and autism spetic disorder
and I just want to speak about something
now we also have spal data it could it
can be used in this context so when we
find L receptor pairs we hypothetically
say that okay I think this Li receptor
interaction must be happening but in
some cases right in this cases if these
cells are not close to each other it's
not possible so we have special
transcriptomics data you could also
embed spal maps and you could also make
specially aware algorithm to find Li
receptor pairs it would improved version
of this one I give my research ideas if
you're working on it invite me as well
okay last thing so I couldn't cover
everything so I have a master class in
University of Toronto November 25 to 29
it will be available over Zoom which is
free registration right so if it's like
a 10 lectures it will start from the
basic how we can apply these models it
will use different toolboxes there are
different toolboxes available for tens
methods tly is python based tensor la
forat la package t toolbx for again
Matlab my group is using all three so I
will have to cover all three so we will
go through all these applications on
real data set and our survey paper on
tensor Bas approaching for omix data
analysis application challenges and
future directions coming soon Amir is my
PhD student he's here Daniel was in
broth Institute now he's in upan medical
school thank
you so as promised in the first talk uh
we are going to discuss like limitations
with the some existing methods and I'm
going to uh give a more probabilistic
model consensus ztf which is like stable
tensor factorization which is developed
for zero zero inflated multi-dimensional
data which works perfect for omix data
we give like technical details
development of the algorithm and
applications okay so here we discussed
some tensor methods now it's time to
Rego over it quickly and then discuss
some ch challenges with the existing
beloved methods right so here we
discussed aop paraa just remind of some
people might have missed the first talk
right so let's say we have this tensor
like we are looking at how gen
expression is changing across different
cell types for different donors right it
it could be also across different
tissues and different donors it's like a
multi sample uh gene expression data and
like one of the simple method we use we
said like uh kand par de composition I
will call it CP de composition we are
reducing the ranks you can start working
with 20,000 genes but again what you
care about like metag genes or Gene
cluster gene expression patterns maybe
you have like 10 gene expression main
tangent expression pattern which is D
driven by different s Ty conditions and
donor conditions that's what we try to
find right so we have uh in this case we
will have number of donors times are it
will give us donor factors and we
discuss how we can use donor factors
let's say I have 200 patients but maybe
there are four five condition like for
example disease non disease subtype of
the cancer which drives uh like uh which
drives different kind of gene expression
pattern so that's what we are trying to
find as donor factors uh it will help us
to find subtypes like different donor
conditions and here actually there's a
I
was there's a question on Zoom okay okay
yeah maybe I'll ask it okay okay and
then we will have Gene factors and we we
have donor factors here sat factors and
we give kind of examples how rank one
tens looks like but we will give more
examples when we discuss application of
our method so if people miss the first
talk they will still see like how to
interpret this factorization so again
what what's happening mathematically we
have this tensor and we are writing this
one some of rank one tensor so rank one
tensor we set actually we get this one
like other product of these vectors we
have Gene latent factor if you have
20,000 genes this one has length 20,000
cell typ latent factor if we have 10
cell types this one has length 10 and
every entry is like the loading
significance of the St types for this um
for this profile and like we have some
samples latent factor again if you have
two 200 samples then you have like 200
length Vector here so we have like we
take the other product of these ones
right this becomes unit of an expression
pattern and we are trying to see how
much of these expression patterns we
have we do lower rank
approximation and so here there is again
we actually approximate our tensor is an
approximation plus a noise right we
discussed this one actually it is again
getting three different matrices one for
genes if I take all genes latent factor
together I will form Gene latent factor
if I get all s types latent factors
together I will get a big Matrix of sell
typ latent factors as move okay I need
to learn how to use this it's like and
for the samples as well okay what we
didn't discuss next time here classical
CP decompositions and classical tens
factorization back time it's develop and
it's heavily used in image images but
it's okay to in this case assume Goan
noise but when we are working on like
real word application it's not like we
don't always have a normal noise so here
one of the question we will address in
this call uh talk how to truly
incorporate the distribution of the data
which kind of noise assumptions we can
have right also how to choose the rank
this is a really hard question it's like
because I don't know to start with I I
will have a 10 expression patterns right
how to choose the rank how to test for
you are really choosing like a good
fitting right and which kind of
constraints we apply some people apply
orthogonality but mostly I don't for I
don't want to force Gene spaces to be
orthogonal to each other I mostly assume
non- negativity so that interpretation
is easier but to non- negativity you
should make sure that your data is non
negative I know when you go through scai
right you're normalizing your data you
end up with negative numbers so make
sure it's like if you use non- negative
factorization you have non- negative
entries and uniqueness again so there is
a create big debate in this area so
theoretically tensor decompositions but
again we are not really finding exact
factorization one thing actually we are
finding approximation so theoretically
if you find exact decomposition it's
Unique under milder condition but we are
in the real world we work with noisy
data we find a approximation we will
discuss uniqueness in the next slide
factorization will not be unique and we
will have to address it
okay so here just to see what's
happening in CPD composition so what we
are trying to optimize again there are
different methods for the optimization
lots of optimization groups are trying
to solve in different way I will give um
not necessarily best but most common one
most common again not necessarily best
approach most common approach sometimes
common approaches are common because
they're
simple right so here for CPD compos I
have a tensor okay I have a tensor and
I'm trying
to I cannot use this one approximate
with another tensor right so it's like
we are trying to minimize the error we
are trying to minimize the error right
it's like the we use the forbus norm
what do we introduced in the first talk
it's like square of the entries and
you're summing them and you are taking
square
root and most of the papers they are
looking at explained variance like in
PCA also we look at explained variance
to see if it's is a good fitting
algorithm but we will discuss that this
is not enough we will go through
different metrix as well so they kind of
normalize the distance
here okay normalize the distance and one
minus distance if the fit is one it's a
perfect approximation it means you
recover everything it's hard to find
unless you are working on synthetic data
right we always first test our algorithm
synthetic data is like oh we put
everything and we recover them so
perfect fit is one if you don't put
noise right because it should also
account for the noise and fit is zero
when approximation is awful nothing is
right I mean you wouldn't have zero you
would a 0 point something right okay but
to start with it's like I'm factorizing
T2 three latent factor matrices G CS
with rank is R is not a convex problem
so it can be given as like three and
minimizing so this like we are trying to
minimize distance it can be given as
three convex problems so to understand
this for three way if we have 10 way
it's 10 convex problems so understand
this on we will go back in the primary
we introduce unfoldings for example if I
have a tensor of 10 * 20 * uh 6 I can
write a matrix say 10 times 120 so I'm
writing first mod unfolding then you can
write uh 20 * 60 and this is second mode
unfolding then you can write 6 * 200
third uh right mode unfolding so you get
three matrices unfolding appears in the
optimization steps and so what the
instability will come from so we start
with the initial guess we have an
initial guess for Gene latent factor
sample latent factor so latent factor
for three modality that's how you start
for like alternating list Square here I
fix
CNS okay then I need to so we are going
to solve for G this algorithm and we use
like Leist Square here there is lots of
tensor operations I will introduce this
kind of operation as advertising master
class that I advertised in the first
talk like if you're interested to learn
more about operations you can uh follow
over Zoom I think it might be also
recorded at some point and just posted
so here we have C products it's like
look at these ones these latent factor
matrices they have the same number of
columns because the number of columns is
equal to rank right if the columns are
matching you can take matching column
wise um we call it chronical product
actually you get the other product of
vectors right because I have R column
vectors I can just take the other
products C1 G1 C2 G2 that's how you get
a bigger
Matrix and here we fix for C uh CNS and
we are solving for G then we are fixing
for S and G solving for C it goes like
that until you hit a threshold so most
it says then it goes back and look at
the fit or look at the distance and it
says right as in lot of algorithms okay
if the result is not changing passing a
threshold you stop but this since is not
convex you don't have to go to Global
minimum as well right we will see in
some stable cases actually sometimes you
can get stuck we call it one points so
it may also happen and it's heavily
dependent on the initial guess and there
is a big other area I'm not very active
in that area but I want to be active
what is the good loss function So when
you say two matrices let's say X and Y
how you can uh say distance between
these two Matrix actually same distance
in the same way same similarity how you
can say this Matrix X and Matrix y
similar to each other sometimes people
look at the um ukan Norm is like the
forbus norm the same right squared
errors right mean squared errors but in
this case you are only looking like in
the for minus Norm are they numerically
close to each other right but like we
might also care are they like as a
distribution probabilistic to close each
other right actually when you use a for
minus Norm base CP de composition most
of them you assume Go
distribution right here there are
different loss functions people use K
lier I'm not going to go details but if
you go distance Matrix with tensor uh
tensors actually it's a big topic like
sometimes they use more kernelized
functions right and then they are
looking at the similarity in this level
so it also brings some
nonlinearity just to say all the
decomposition methods I um explained
today they are multilinear because of
also lost functions and structures they
can find Multi linear patterns but with
these ones I discussed today you cannot
find nonlinear patterns yet
so again we will discuss these ones and
before going deeper discussion and I
want to say what are the classical
approaches some people goes through
maximum likelihood approach which is
like as we discussed you are minimizing
a distance and you put some
constraints right in your Factor
matrices you use uh your distance like
most common ones again this for bions
and probabbly sigma K Divergence but
there are also like different groups are
trying more probabilistic distances it's
going to be actually how in the next
year's area will get
shape okay and there is Bean approach
today we will use this kind of
approaches so here most of the methods
actually think that you have a normal
distribution but in the approach I will
follow today in our method I want to
learn from the data what's the
distribution of the data and I want to
incorporate the through distribution of
the data so here given the observe
tensor and we are going to see tensor
approximate ABC is it likely right like
again we are factorizing this one in the
goal in here is the estimate postered
posterior distribution of the factor
matrices given the observed tenser and
any prior information you might have for
single Sal data we have lot of reference
and we have lot of Prior information
about sparity right and prior
information we will specify for the
factor matrices and for our tensor by
kind of imposing some distributions and
we will have a hyper parameter set we
impose the distributions but then we
will actually ask the algorithm learn
about the true
distribution and posterior is this
knowing your tensor and the hyper
parameter set this the prior information
what's the probability when you
factorize your tensor you get this
latting Factor matrices right again not
for say learn from the algorithm
actually uh this is like more
probabilistic approach the posterior
distribution is analytically
interactable people estimate this one
they use techniques like marov chain
Mont Carlo variational inference we use
variational inference maybe I'm not
going to go details I'm going to just
mention about it and with our method in
any case we have the toolbox available
so we will discuss this once
more okay then I want to have a little
bit more discussion on the numerical
instability right why even like we are
trying to uh solve this problem like if
there's no problem there's nothing to
solve right first I want to convince you
there is a problem right one thing to
start is like for the matrices I said
like lots of things from matrices it
doesn't generalize the tensor directly
for example even the rank rank of a
matrix let's say three * 6 it has to be
less than equal three let's say I have a
tensor 3 * 4 * 5 I cannot say rink is
less than equal three but it's way more
complicated and the other thing this
Bard rank issue doesn't appear with
matrices so if you have a rank three
tensor you you cannot approx so rank
three Matrix you cannot approximate this
matrix by rank three matrices there's
nothing like that so border rank is
actually let's say for example I have
this tensor this is 2 by two so actually
first SL is 0110 2 by two by two second
slide is one 0 0 right so it's actually
a nice Cube okay so this has rank three
and you can write this one Su of three
rank one tensor this E1 is z e uh E2 E2
is 01 right it's kind of shown this is
the rank you can find exact approxim not
approxim exact de composition but it can
be approximated by rank two tensors so
these are the r uh rank two tensors if
you get the limit of this it will give
you the T your tensor so it doesn't
appear in Matrix so what happens in this
case when you sometimes run some numbers
because actually you are trying to find
like you know that it's rank T tensor
but it a but rank n can so all the
numbers can explode so it's like don't
worry it's normal it can happen there is
a numerical instability it's not this um
T rank they call not upper
semicontinuous there is a problem there
and one of them is the Border rank other
one we discuss convergence problem after
all is not a convex problem right it
doesn't have to go the minimum uh like
that's a global minimum and dependence
on the initial guess so I want to show
it here here I start from a rank three
tensor synthetically generated three * 4
* 5 so normally right so with little bit
noise it should be very stable right
because I already know the rank so even
in this case I run this sensor
factorization with different initial
guesses 40 time and every time we run it
you can see in some cases we can still
get different fits different fits means
you get different factors So based on
your initial guess your results can
change
but in this case okay so it's not like I
reconstruct my images it's like you know
you work in biological domain I want to
trust my factors I want to say okay I
think I found a really important gene
expression pattern I need more funding I
need like I need to go over it I need to
prove it you should make sure about the
significance of your factorization so
here that's why I was more PE about this
stabilization
here so are you saying that um when you
try to um pick a rank you're not looking
at reconstruction but you're looking at
uh inability of lat yeah so it's a good
question so we will discuss I both look
at reconstruction then I'm also looking
at the stability of factorization both
of them actually we will Define four
metrics to look at to choose the
range okay so kind of limitation we said
the composition is not stable especially
for noise data but can you find
non-noise data it's like convergence is
not guaranteed rank selection is still a
challenge and it's like if you always
say some Goan right you don't explicitly
put the three distribution of the data
and interpretation of latent factors so
it's a
pipeline so here in the first talk we al
already
discussed like T like tensor methods
outperform classical Matrix based
methods now we are going to discuss
actually how to improve this uh
classical tensor methods
okay so first thing I want to address is
like a stability so we kind of develop
consensus based censor factorization
first I will go through this how to make
sure the stability of the factorization
it will also help us to choose the
correct Rank and later we will go
through ban framework how to incorporate
a through distribution of the data right
actually this kind of models can be also
applied actually whatever you develop
for tensors you can also use for
matrices right just right even our
toolbox okay it's okay for tensors of
any Dimensions including two
Dimensions okay so here we have uh let's
say I run this algorithm like 10 CP
decomposition let's say 100 times n
times every time you run you are going
to get a gene latent factor matrices
number of genes times R right so you
have bunch of matrices so I'm running
multiple times now because I want to
make sure the results I'm getting are
they like repeating so if I have a very
significant signal that signal should
keep coming back right for sure if we
are in a stable range so for sure it
will not come as it is it will come with
some noise later we will cluster but it
should keep appearing so here I will see
if these different runs of the
factorization
consistent so are they connected with
each other so first for every uh
factorization run we are uh forming
something called connectivity
Matrix in connectivity Matrix for
example here we have R Gene clusters we
are assigning genes to specific clusters
you can go in different ways based on
maximum loadings is one of them so we
are saying if Gene I and Gene J is
connected if they are assigned to same
cluster right they are going to form a
gene group so in connectivity Matrix is
like I is one if Gene I and g j belong
to the same class and zero otherwise and
for every R we keep repeating it every R
we are looking at connectivity between
different gen and at the end we look at
a consensus Matrix which is the average
of connectivity matrices so think about
if everything is stable some this let's
say we get two genes they should be
always in the same cluster or always not
in the same clusters numbers should be
zeros or one average should be mostly
zeros and one and the moment you have
get dispersion between zero and one then
it means you have instability so we are
trying to see the dispersion so it's
calculated by something called cinetic
correlation it's actually one minus dis
dispersion so one of our way to choose
rank for sure we will use explained
variance still we are going to look at
cinetic correlation so how connected
different
runs and after that it's not like we are
doing to choose the rank we are choosing
initial guess so that when you run the
algorithm it will not change a lot so
here it says actually we when we are
going to concatenate all of them it's
like you normalize every relat Factor so
that Norm is one so they are comparable
with each other you form a big Matrix
but I claim that rank is R so I claim
that there are R gen clusters it means
they have to write cluster together
right for for example as I said yes one
gene latent factor uh will keep coming
it will come with the noise but you can
cluster it so here we will find our
clusters maybe I will also red discuss
one in the next slide we will take the
median maybe I can start from here so we
are in this point let say A1 is our Gene
modality we concatenate all of them Norm
normalized here we are looking are they
clustering first you remove the outliers
it can be sued random this of the
algorithm and we are doing clustering
actually we went so simple K means but
then and different groups they said okay
your method was good so you just went K
but they did more like uh more
theoretical and nicer clustering methods
I can also give this papers as well so
here uh we are taking the median of each
clusters right because it's less
susceptible the outlier and we are
forming our new latent factor Matrix
this is the goal is I want to just count
for the repeating
signals so after you form your latent
factor Matrix like this is for genes you
f
your Gene modality and you are solving
for other two right so you have a fixed
initial guess for genes and you solve
for the other two like in here right is
like I get genin consensus I fix it and
I solve for the samples and cell
types okay so again since it also start
with an initial guess uh for jeans there
is actually you go through different
iteration you can get slightly different
answers but they not they're not going
to be too different but we are going to
measure it it's not going to be just
saying oh it's not too different we have
experiments on it okay we are going to
do some experiments on consensus it's
working or not but uh so our algorithm
is consensus zero inflated um Zer
inflated post intensive factorization so
now I want to cover like zero inflated
po Parts but consensus and Ed eded
consensus approach you can add to any
factorization method right you can
factorize and you can add the consens
part okay okay here for the beian tensor
factorization these are tensor this is
cell types dat Factor cell types samples
and genes so here again I mostly speak
about poon and zero inflated poon but in
our toolbox you can change the
probability assumptions you can use
different distribution it's not just for
poon okay here what's
happening so we approximate our tensor
this is the this is the Assumption with
rank R we are think it's like for gene
expression is like the rate that you are
capturing the genes it mostly follows
poon distribution but people also use
actually negative
binomial but it's very sparse sometimes
like you have more zeros ex excess zeros
that you wouldn't expect from a poon
distribution so I want those account for
The Spar that's why we go zero inflated
but we are having a gate parameter we
will adjust the sparcity so here we say
TI JK like gene expression uh like this
is the entry expression at Gene I for uh
setup J for sample K follow suppos
distribution and the uh mean can be
calculated by using this um I say rank R
de composition and now if you have some
information about like latent factors
the modalities you can put it we put
gamma priors in this part
sparity also makes it easy to interpret
also it makes sense to IND sparsity for
the Gen factors because not every is
active uh in like Petway right so here
we set a gamma prior for the latent
factors but you can adjust the shape and
rate and the algorithm will learn except
shape and rate of the gamma priors this
is for sparity we say R tensor follows
Zer inflated poon mean comes from the
factorization and
it might have but it might have you are
allowed to use or not more zeros than
you expect from poon like it might have
sparity then we have a gate parameter to
adjust for sparsity this gate parameter
gives the excess zeros so what are the
benefits of this uh methods for we will
discuss
applications and first in the synthetic
data we will discuss okay does did it
work how say dual of it and it potential
benefits to uncertainty quantification
in Corporation of more realistic noise
and in a way principled weight includes
prior information again this is based on
poome but you can change the uh your
distribution okay so here I start from
synthetic experiments then I will go to
more genomics data set uh and like I
will discuss like our main projects that
we use this
algorithm okay so first of all to
discuss we have lots of like tensor
based methods as well does it have many
advantage to uh go through like more uh
zero inflated Poston based distribution
so we call it zip
distributions so we have um we have
different examples in the paper one of
them we created 10 times 20 times 300
tenser with rank nine and for the latent
factors we assume gamma distribution
with this uh shape and rate
parameters okay and we are generating a
tensor that mean is given by this rankar
factorization and there is a varying
probabilities of excess zeros we Chang
the uh sparity level right we put
different sparsity levels and we are
looking at explained variance we are
factorizing finding a low rank
proximation and we are looking at how
good is the uh explained variance so we
are using classical non- negative
cpls there is also another method paraa
paraa actually also stands for CP
composition it is uh developed for
sparse uh data they do L1 um L1 Norm
regularization to IND sparcity we also
tried this there is like for example
tranced gashi tensor factorization again
assumes gashi distribution this is the
closest one gamma po tensor
factorization it assumes postum for data
gamma for latent factors but it doesn't
count for excess number of zeros even
that one failed and our ZIP TF Z
inflated Post in tensor factorization so
when the probabilities of xcess Zer are
low all of them performs well but the
moment probability of XX Z is increasing
since our method keeps adjusting the
parameter it stays stable but other
methods their performance keeps going
down here we compare with the tensor
methods then we will also in
applications compare with the Matrix
methods as well here because we like the
idea is like why we are developing a new
tensor
method Okay so here it Justified that we
are going to use zip TF uh but do we
have to use consensus now the next
experiment will be zipf with consensus
and without
consensus what we are trying to do with
consensus with the consensus when you
run your algorithm you want to make sure
that in each run you will get more or
less similar results right so here we
are running the algorithm 100 times here
we are going from 0.6 for sparcity right
right here quite sparse data we run zdf
and C zdf 100 times in every runs we are
looking at the similarity between the
lat factors we look at cosine similarity
I mean ztf is already like more or less
stable for this algorithm but we can see
in C zdf in the green one similarities
are increasing because you are really
finding good initial guess for your Gene
clusters and again this is little bit
Nuance okay the latent factors for
different runs are similar but are they
similar to original signal in this C
figure C we are looking at similar to
original signal consensus ZF actually
gives very similar uh results to
original signal so ztf to count for
distribution consensus approach again
you can take this pipeline put other
methods as well to increase
stability good now this is the last
synthetic data I have then we will go to
lupus and hkin fora the real data
set so we use splatter simulation to
gener at synthetic single cell RNA
sequencing data set this was like a
quick check okay does it work for
genomics data we have 1,000 genes 3,000
cells and six donors and we embedded
five gene expression programs defining
cell type identities cell type specific
gene expression programs and we also
embedded uh three gene expression
programs defining donor activities so we
have eight programs then we will run our
algorithm we will see can we really
recover these eight programs so first
thing for the rank we are looking at
explained variance and cinetic
correlation that we discussed during the
consens approach right so it kind of has
like in eight we have good explained
variance and Co and correlation and we
are looking so we were clustering our
latent factors right uh through
different runs we were looking how good
is this clustering you can can look at
inertia silet scord to see how good is
this clustering we look inertia has to
decrease for inertia and the silette
score at eight also how to say they
agree with each other so rank selection
is eight which is not surprising to be
honest because we have 18 expression
programs plus a
noise okay so we are going to say okay
rank is eight but are we really
recovering what is embedded as a gene
expression program actually I will tell
we also doing with different Lo fa
changes for differential expression from
low to high to see if the results are
getting affected I'm going to discuss it
here for example I have eight latent
factors Gene one gene eight let's say
the g G2 the right Factor two is highly
correlated with ground TR identity gen
expression program one so we are look at
piercing correlation and the right
factor eight is highly correlated with
grandr activity gen expression program
uh one one of them is identity one of
them is activity actually so these are
our right factors this is the activity
programs all the factor correspond to
one activity program so it is able to
recover actually gen expression
programs and again we use suppl
simulation to embed activities and cell
type programs use different differential
expression log fold changes sdle
025 to very high
0.27 0.75 at but like we also have
different levels to see compare
different methods here we compare with
non- negative Matrix factorization a
morti LDA suggested for a reviewer
because it's more de learning base some
meths appear because reviewer wants it
which is actually very good method this
is not negative cpls consensus nmf it's
like nmf they use a different way of
consensus approach and zipf is our model
C zipf our model with consensus seor you
can see it's like in both of them we are
looking at average piercing correlation
between our factors and the truth uh
true factors so it's actually at
performing our other models in here
actually we have more
experiments good now it's like I will
discuss two application one of them will
be lupus and one application I will
discuss In classical hkin in fora to see
actually biologically which kind of
patterns we can
find okay so this one is public data set
classical hcha is the project I start in
golop lab it will be our own data set
but for Lupus we are trying to
unsupervised discover of disease
subgroups and multilinear gene
expression programs in the peripheral
blood of patients with why I am
interested because I have Lupus so I am
interested in lupus studies so it's like
we apply to C zdf to uh Multiplex single
cell RNA sequencing data over 1.2
billion pbmc's
uh from patients with SLE so we have
three groups this is a really good one
right we have eight Lupus patients with
manage right sometimes you have Lupus
but you don't always have active flare
you feel like you're healthy until you
get heat and eight lus patients with
active flare and eight lus eight
patients like healthy controls they
don't have Lupus they're lucky and we
have 10 cell types and we form our data
24 donors five cell types and 13,520
genes and notice that most of the time
when you work on like gene expression
data people are reducing their genes to
highly variable genes here we don't have
to do that sometimes when you have also
rare cells you don't want to do that one
is last so we keep all our genes like
after some
filtering so here we look at the rank
selection you look at explained variance
and cinetic correlation which agrees at
22 and we are looking how good is the
clustering of the factors from different
runs actually we kind of look at inertia
silette score so we kind of agree on 22
I will quickly see like which kind of
important factors we
get okay so here just to say this is the
U map of the cell types so this one
correspond to one rank one tensor so
this column correspond to samples cell
types and this is like genes but I
cannot put all the gene Factor I'm
looking at top 2 significant gen and we
run Petway analysis for example in here
we are finding T Cell like gene
expression program we run this one later
for T cells this is Factor 10 uh then
which is activated in almost all over
patient profiles right we have healthy
black SL flare like blue andle manages
pink again we have another Factor this
is like a uh mon sites program activated
in all over patients actually here we
are finding cell type identity gen
expression programs with this factors
but we want to find something more can
we find condition specific actually we
also have condition specific programs
here these are the conditions like the
um map of the conditions healthy SLE
flare and slle manage so we have some
factors for example Factor 21 one of
them it correspond to patients with SLE
food
there right Factor 21 here and you can
see from the patients profiles it's
really uh has higher weight in patients
with SL flare and when you look at
Factor 21 it's also kind of we do the
Petway analysis it's kind of how to say
what we find as a pet F I cannot move
this one it agrees with the literature
and Factor 21 actually it's like all the
patients too much doesn't matter if it's
flare or not a flare we also have S
patients
uh this Petway actually gives type one
interferent Petway observed in viral
infection which is commonly seen in
Lupus
patients actually it goes even more
detail lopus patients with active flare
has a different program with manage has
a different program so this is important
to know because if we don't know the
again labels of the data we could with
this uh this kind of methods we can find
it right but for differential Express
analysis you cannot find it you have to
know the labels for example so we later
R number of differential expressed genes
was 55 When comparing s patients against
Health donors and it's 120 to when you
compare patients with with active flare
to health donors but if you don't know
this information about the subgroups
your differential expression analysis
wouldn't give uh a lot of information so
the takeaway from here in scenarios
where the source of ingroup heterogenity
is unknown czd can highlight subgroups
based on expression profiles and
identify gene expression programs
driving the heterogenity that may be
missed by supervised uh differential gen
expression analysis and we I still have
time okay so I will go through hkin
infoma so this is going to be it's like
our project with the golop lab and yeah
because I was also post at golop lab so
here actually this um
factorization uh make us aware of
labeling mistakes because some programs
were always some patient factors patient
profiles were keep appearing in
different gen expression programs and we
ask the clinicians I will go over this
example is it a Constance but we figure
out it's a labeling mistake it can't
even find labeling mistakes because it's
totally unsupervised right it's trying
to learn from data okay so
this okay this paper first is like czf
with more applications I work with vesh
in he's in bro Institute in golop lab
Daniel was in golp lab but now he's in
upan medical school so you can um you
can see more applications and more
technical details in the paper and um
all the data all the tutorials
everything is publicly available in
GitHub and again you can also change
your distribution and apply assuming
different
distributions good so next application
this micro environment project actually
it's a very uh bigger project we don't
only use tensor factorization I start
discussing this project in 2020 I was
thinking okay is going to take as long
as like Boston big digging project
remember they were reorienting tunnel
but hopefully it's finishing this month
I'm happy sometimes it can haveen in
Broad you know your have projects takes
forever it's like so we are working on
tumor micro environments tumors are
complex sell ecosystem you have diverse
non malignant cell types and States a T
Cell nature killer cells you have also
diverse malignant cell States here we
have different cell types we really care
different cell States we really also
care about cell cell interactions that
we discussed in the first talk like L
receptor interactions as well so here we
work in classical lymphoma this is a
malignant Vell lymphoma so if you zoom
in you have this agin double nuclei size
they hkin read standard size they
compromise only 1% of the tumor so this
is something unusual are bad guys only
1% 99% good guys but they cannot go kill
them so they are surrounded by immune
cells normal immune cells are supposed
to go and kill tumor cells but actually
in our case immune cells are supporting
the promotion of tumor cells there's a
reprogramming
here so they are difficult to grow in
culture they don't survive in imuno
deficient Mass it means they need their
micro environment so kind of studies
then Works what's happening around this
tissue I'm not going to go over it but
we also use lots of spatial data to see
the
organization so and the other thing main
therapy is very harsh chemotherapy
people survive Homa but then they suffer
uh even if they survive they suffer from
the longterm effect of chemotherapy our
goal was trying to find imy Targets
which we were able to identify finally
before I become 6y old
so again here we are using single
nucleus data we use so many different
data sets I'm going to just presenting
one piece so it is hand 10 hkin for
patients multiple replicates half of
them has abon by virus half of them
doesn't have epon virus there is a
correlation between having epon by virus
and having hutkin lymphoma it's
interesting because it looks very
innocent virus it's not that innocent
right so here we also anot did 15 cell
types right I will give more details
about the data here after some filtering
we end up with 19,000 jeans 15 cell
types and 40 when I say 40 donors 40
samples right because for some donors we
are repeating different tissues as a
different replicates so I didn't want to
also over filter my jeans because hkin
lymphomas are like rare cells in this
group I didn't want to you know
mistakely get them out of the um out of
the
data okay so
here the main goal again unsupervised
stratification of these donors into
subgroups and identification of gene
expression programs that drive this
those
certifications and in one or two weeks
this should be on bioarchive with the
name genome scale spatial mapping of the
hkin informa micro environment
identifies Factor required for tumor
cell survival I think name is very
descriptive I I think we we are keeping
this name but there might be changes but
it's going to be like uh me and vges it
will come from the goal plan and for
sure there are so many people get
involved from
broad okay so here again I I'm just
going to quickly go to results are
metric suggested start in rank 12 okay
what we see in the rank 12 in the rank
12 in the lower ranks actually I want to
give an idea what you what happens if
you go lower or higher ranks for example
let's say this is one again rank one
tenser okay dark blue H virus positive
open blue virus negative and you have
reactive L notes maybe I can quickly go
over it actually it gives this one the
last column last row I took ex as it is
so this is the one we discussed in the
first talk gen L factors give J start
pet way promotes tumor cell
proliferation and survival of tumor STS
activated in tumor again height is based
on the weight and it is activated in we
are looking at the base on the weight
activating hen for patients okay this is
what happens in rank 12 and when you
increase the rank it's so beautiful so
it's I always suggest start from a rank
and try to increase it this signal
divides into two it will divide into
tumor for virus positive tumor for virus
negative we increase the rank and I will
maybe rank 20 I will directly maybe go
to result and what what happen when I
increase the rank there are again
different factors right it's not going
to be just C type identity so it is
going to be condition specific so let me
maybe just speak about this one so here
we have a gene expression program we
actually biologically work on it and
validate it for tumor cells for mostly
hkin lymphoma with uh virus negative
except one donor appears in virus
positive and here we get another gen
expression program tumor SS for virus
positive one donor appears in wirus
negative and we figure out is a labeling
mistake that was the one we like why
this one keeps coming then we foret
actually it's positive it's negative it
was good and actually so there is also
some heterogenity right uh like they
join but in have like different um
different uh ways and actually we double
confirm actually if you use DG test
negative plus was positive like
significant genes you would get it
concur with the genes we find with this
Pro um
factorization and again we find
something this is I just want to go Gen
expression program for fiberblast for
hkin infa patients and fiberblast mostly
for reactive lymph not patients but
there is some heterogenity and this
heterogenic can actually harm
differential expression a differential
Express Gene analysis right and another
Finding again monoy program for HK
formula monoy program mostly appears in
uh reactive n not again this
unsupervised an algorithms able to find
by itself for sure for this project
though okay last thing I want to do
people always ask what happens you
increase the rank colot if you increase
the rank palot you're overfitting you
start finding a program activated in one
specific donor you're not interested in
it so you should find the s balance so
we uh start what the metric suggests but
we kind of look at higher rank as well
so in this paper actually I think couple
of minutes I can say this is more
General than tensor methods we work on
we also use special data cell types and
States within the tumor micro
environment like what is surrounding
these uh malignant cells we use special
data which cells are in reach which cell
States and cell types and what are the
tumor specific survival and growth
signalings and mechanism of immun Evas
because we want to transer uh get
insights for drug res met immunotherapy
response and we are going to suggest uh
some immunotherapy targets work on inter
intrapatient heterogenity cross talks
Petway within tumor micro environment we
use tensor factorization for Li receptor
interaction it was very powerful and
immunotherapy targets and the last but
not least to give more ideas what's
happening in this domain now actually
deep learning approaches are very
effective but Laten space is not
interpretable and tensor approaches are
effective but is multilinear nonlinear
now there is new communities they're
merging these two areas like they do
tens n networks or they use tensor
factorization in these layers so it is
I'm new in this area I'm very excited if
you start working invite me integration
of tensor methods and deep learning
approaches it's a very good promising
area for sure if you're more theoretical
there is always need for theoretical
improvements both theoretically like
optimization and you can find
applications in many different domains I
know here people are most interested in
omix state analysis but like
Neuroscience right and like computer
vision we use a lot of images uh in bro
as well so there are lots of different
applications thanks