i guess then
we'll start maybe i'll just kick off so
i'm dan huttenlocker
i'm the dean of the schwartzman college
of computing
uh
came back to mit about three decades
after getting my phd here
uh and then a few months later kovitz
started so it's been an interesting uh
interesting trip
uh i've been working i've had the
privilege and pleasure of working with
eric uh for gosh a decade or more now
uh eric was uh
ceo of google at the time and was very
and google was very involved in the
cornell tech campus that we built in new
york city that i was leading that
project
and then
starting in new york and continuing
after i moved up here
eric and i worked on a book together
with dr henry kissinger
called the age of ai in our human future
which uh
came out in the fall and uh well i guess
november so the very late fall
and we thought it would be fun to uh in
the mit context just have uh so as
doglar the eecs uh
department head and my deputy dean in
the college of computing
uh ask us some questions related to some
of the kinds of topics we talked about
in the book and then turn it over for
audience questions
so eric thanks so much for joining us
here today
thank you and um dana you actually
worked for me under my command i did um
for a couple of years as a visiting
faculty member at google
where we first met yep and he became the
dean of carnegie
cornell tech
and uh which was really transformative
and i think that convinced mit that he
could actually manage which he really is
very good at so
your transformation here has been
fantastic and
and that was actually 2007 it was uh
getting to be a while ago so it's more
than a decade 50 50 you should be good
at math 15 years
and
but what is mit is doing now
i've gotten to know mit well enough
to know that mit is
making the transition
from a culture which is sort of
obsessive about strange details is my
description of mit
into some of these broader themes um
and uh my first meeting here i don't
think i ever told you this when when uh
raphael is a fantastic president
said i should come by and visit they
presented me a project which was still
being
developed in lisp
and i thought okay we need to
update that a bit so i think we've made
some progress
right
we still love to obsess on the details
but the big picture is also super
important
well uh i'm very delighted to welcome
eric to mit today and have this
conversation with dan and eric
on a very important topic about you know
how ai transforms the human society and
i think this is a great conversation to
have with two leading thinkers in this
area
who both bring
a wealth of expertise and experience and
as dan mentioned they just recently
wrote a book on the topic
which contains a very deep analysis of
these important issues but what i found
most important about the book is it
provides a
framing and a language to really
systematically think about these issues
and ask the right questions which is the
most important thing to start with on
such complicated challenges but also
suggest paths forward so we have a lot
to discuss
but before we dive in i just want to
make sure to remind the audience that we
would like to invite you to participate
in this discussion so if you're joining
us virtually you can submit your
questions using the box
at the bottom of your screen please do
so i will try to get to as many
questions as we can during the q a later
but i'll start with some questions just
to set the stage and uh you know start
our conversation get our thinking
together uh the first one is a very
general question but
there's so many answers i i'm just very
curious about your perspective on this
and that is basically the difference
between the public conception of a.i
uh
which is
you know largely shaped by science
fiction movies
uh and the you know ai as the people in
the area field ai researchers think
about it and uh you know you can also
think about this as a question between
you know difference between artificial
general intelligence agi and ai as we
know it today which is something you
touch upon in detail in your book so
maybe we'll start with eric so
well dan and dan and i can can do any of
these together the
so if you talk to people about ai they
basically believe the following thing
there will be a
female robot that will be invented
that will slay all the men
and uh which actually may be a good
outcome in some future human scenarios
um
but i try to explain to people that that
there's so many assumptions in that and
we have a roboticist here in the room
i'll let you decide
or describe what is possible in robotics
but
where we are right now with ai is we
don't quite understand how to generate
volition
we're very very good
at pattern matching
and dan of course is a is a world-class
computer vision expert which is where
this stuff came from so what i like to
explain is that
the first round of this which was 2011
2012 imagenet which all of you know
about
was really the triumph of the computer
vision over the human vision people
and the computer vision
fits in all sorts of ways and dan can
describe the visual system and why it's
still the primary source of progress
vision is not the same thing as volition
it's not the same thing as objective
functions
so
my instinct and dan you you may or i
think you dan is generally more
conservative than i i write stuff and
then he deletes it in our partnership
um i never delete any of his stuff it
seems
unfair and so so in my idea
what happens is
we're going to get stuck in this pattern
matching period and we're going to build
extraordinarily powerful systems which
we can describe
the language model work that's going on
now is
it's at a pace that's breathtaking
but that's not the same thing as you
wake up in the morning and you decide to
take a vacation
work on something new learn and learn
how to play the piano see a new friend
we're just not there yet
dan
and i think that's great i think the
thing i would add just back to the the
science fiction side is you know fiction
needs a good villain
it's very hard to write good fiction
without some kind of conflict in it uh
and and the the the notion of the
machine as a villain uh is is something
that's existed for for a long time uh in
in fiction
and i think you know in the days before
ai was becoming a reality it was much
less relevant what the fiction said i
think today
uh
you know people watch westworld or
whatever you know that's uh that was out
there uh and um and and that sort of
fiction really informs
what they think about the ai that
they're interacting with every day right
so you talked to alexa or google home
and you just watched you know some
science fiction on
on
uh you know on streaming video
uh just the the temporal juxtaposition
of those causes you to expect that the
ai you're interacting with is gonna
interact in ways uh where this wonderful
storytelling is being done
uh and and i think as eric said the key
issue is that you know
ai
does not have
uh you know volition intention uh it's
it's really about uh perceiving the
world and organizing the world
uh
and
one of the problems with this narrative
disconnect between the reality what
people think is that people are now not
understanding what the problems that
real ai will create
uh which i know you're going to get into
in some of your questions but what
happens to jobs what happens to fairness
what happens to geopolitics
and i think the
most important question which is dr
kissinger's question is what does it
mean to be human when there's an
intelligence
that's not like us
but really smart
how do we perceive ourselves
sort of how we got into this
good
fascinating it's very much
a good segue to my next question and
you know something you mentioned in a
number of places in your book uh and
i'll read exactly your words ai with its
without significant fanfare or
visibility is integrated into the basic
fabric of human activity and i found
that fascinating like it's shaping so
much of our so many aspects of our lives
it it's not visible we don't know it we
depend on it but we don't know it so how
is this change transforming the human
experience
and you know things like human
perception
cognition interactions between humans
well let's let's start with what's going
on at mit um and again
you all are the experts of what's going
on here
but
what i've reviewed is that
systematically every aspect of mit's
research is being changed by the
presence of these new algorithms
presumably that's beneficial presumably
that leads to faster drugs you have this
extraordinary success here with jim
collins and allison and so forth which
you all know about
uh so there's this enormous wave of
progress that's going to happen
and
people may or may not give ai the credit
for the progress but the progress is
coming
and that's a good thing right it's a
really good thing
so then the next question is okay so and
this is going to happen whether
whether we as individuals choose it or
not there's too many people working on
it too many benefits you know let's say
you're a luddite and you don't want
drugs to get better you can't stop this
now it's going to happen
so then the next question is what
happens to society
in the book we spend quite a bit of time
talking about
targeting
and professor madre and i were talking
earlier about
the chinese work in regulation
this is shocking the chinese want to
regulate stuff
and they're very concerned about micro
targeting
right very interesting i think that's
roughly what you said
and why would they be concerned about
that we don't really know but that's an
example where people are beginning to
think well maybe this thing's just a
little bit too powerful
in terms of its impact on on our society
my simple answer and then dan you can
i think you agree with this yep think
about if you were founding a social
media company today so you quit mit
please don't do this
form a startup in a year you have
millions of users and
your job is to maximize revenue
you maximize revenue by maximizing
engagement the best way to maximize
engagement is by maximizing outrage
because outrage is the thing that
everybody talks about
so here we are and we go from mit which
is perfectly rational you know
engineering sort of scientific place to
a place where people just make up
sorry i shouldn't say that but you get
the idea
and there's no
there's no
limit on that there's no way to stop
that
and i
to be very clear i don't know how to
solve this problem
but that's a real problem that's coming
from this technology
you know i said if you if alexander
graham bell today were alive today we
would say what do you think about the
telephone and he would say i love it and
he said well when you invented the
telephone it didn't occur to you that
criminals would use your phone
and he goes no i invented it for myself
so it's not like this is the first time
when an invention from you guys
got misused by humanity
and required a response
so as usual eric lays out these uh grand
landscapes where i i um there are so
many things i could say let me let me uh
so i i really liked this
sort of distinction you made between
sort of ai at mit
and places like mit and ai in the world
so i think ai at mit
largely serves as a partner
right it's something that we are
deliberately using
in in more and more uh
laboratories and more and more
investigations across the institute you
know using machine learning modeling to
help accelerate discovery uh in in more
and more and more disciplines
so it's really uh
becomes uh
almost a thought partner
as you develop things
and so that ai partnership model is very
deliberate and it's one of the things we
talk about some in the book
but then when you look at ai as used uh
in most people's daily lives including
ours i mean
at least the part of our daily life that
isn't mit
the vanishingly small part sometimes
uh the um
you know
you're driving with the navigation
system on
you know you're
you're deciding what movies to watch or
what books to read because something
pushed some recommendation at you
uh you know if you're a social media
user you're being inundated and things
and all of these decisions are being
made
by
by algorithms usually machine learning
algorithms
and so that's the very sort of passive
part
where
even us experts don't stop and think how
much we're depending
uh on these things every day making
decisions for us sort of presenting an
option to us that we just follow without
blindly without thinking about it and so
i think this contrast between
ai is a sort of conscious partner in
work uh which we're very privileged at
places like mit to be able to do
and ai is sort of you know something
that we passively comply with is a
really really important distinction
and you bring up the recommendation
engines i think that the recommendation
engines which have really blossomed and
have been very successful because of ai
are the first example of something where
people are going to have to figure out
what what how do you regulate them how
do you address whatever failure modes
they have
and my guess is that p that countries
will do this differently
and it will be done generally badly
right
so
it seems to me that
one thing mit could do
would be to try to figure out what
happens after deep learning
to change this landscape you know there
will be a point where deep learning is
mature
and the phd topics are no longer as
juicy as they are today
and then there's going to be something
after that it's always the case so what
will it be
and i think that's a legitimate mission
for for you for you two right because
you work in this space
to corral the smartest people in the
world to work on
very good very good
one thing i'm actually personally very
curious and i was very glad to see it
also mentioned in your book uh is
basically to look backwards
it's of course very important to
understand
impact of technological change on
society and uh throughout history we've
had many you know important moments of
technological change
you mentioned in your book that only
rarely has technology fundamentally
transformed the social and political
structure of our society so i thought
that's a very powerful statement and
like why is ai different
is it really
much more transformative than you know
if you think about
some landmark moments agriculture
printing press or even in the industrial
technologies do you think it will lead
to more fundamental social changes or
consequences than what we had before and
is it the scale why i don't think we've
had this kind of innovation in history
in the following reason
currently at least as we understand it
ai is
imprecise it makes mistakes
it's generative in the sense that it can
generate new things
it can actually have emergent behaviors
if it begins to interact that are
unpredictable
and the most important thing is it's
learning while it's doing
so
i'll give you an example
uh and we mentioned this in in the book
you've got a two-year-old you give the
two-year-old a toy the toy is ai enabled
kid kid
the toy keeps the kid
you know behaved and so forth until the
kid gets older and the toy gets smarter
so now they're 12.
the toy and the child
and
the toy says i don't like this tv you
know show
and the kid says i agree with you
how do you feel about that
okay
do you say well it's okay you know i bet
the best friend for my kid is not a
human it's a robot but i understand it
but remember that this
toy is learning
so how do you feel if i then add its
ability to
learn something that we didn't
understand
that it thinks is true and it tells the
kid
and what if it's wrong
right so now we have there's all sorts
of rules in america around textbooks
so each state has a list of textbooks
that you're allowed to show teenagers
whether they follow them is not the
point
right so do we have to have a list of
approved learnings for toys for kids
and they're not allowed to learn this
well can you imagine that debate
i just don't think we have even a
framing for a technology so powerful
that it does all of these things and
it's learning at the same time
i i think uh so first of all i think
that's a really compelling example uh um
and uh
i i i did when you when you helped us
craft it as we were writing the book
eric's very good at saying we need to
understand this
and then not giving up
uh the um but but i think one of the
things about ai more generally that's
that is so important that this example
shows
is um is its ability to
[Music]
perceive the world in ways differently
than people do
and then to interact with people
uh at a level that it can change how
people are perceiving the world right
and we've never seen a
technology like that it's the impact of
it of what it's doing on the people
that is different
right
before that we could sort of predict
what things would do that gun was
invented we understood it was for
electric power was invented we
understood it as for transportation we
understood what it's for what happens
when it starts doing its own thing
about the fact that this general purpose
and you know maybe it's across it's not
really a tool for something but it's
really across many many problems domains
well there are many but but they haven't
heard of it but there have been very
many many general purpose tools in in
the development of technology but
they've been bounded by some physical
limit or what have you
but because this is around intelligence
it doesn't seem to have a bound
so we had a big fight about this and i
gave the agi speech which goes something
like
there's going to be in the next 20 years
something which has human level of
intelligence that's going to be as smart
as we
incredibly flexible and it's really
going to put us in our place and dan
said no eric that's wrong
what dan said is
it's much more likely and i think he's
right here
that these things will not be human-like
they'll be
very intelligent but not like humans
they'll have their own logic
and what was interesting was i fought
him over this issue for a while and then
i was talking to these people here in
fact
about
essentially synthetic biology
and i had assumed that synthetic biology
would build biological systems that are
identical to current biology but when
you talk to your synthetic biologists
they say we use the principles of
biology but they operate differently
they solve different problems
yeah like and to to those of us like
of your in my generation
where you know
students we had these little logic kits
that we built stuff out of with
electronic circuits which now have all
become a pretty much solid state
they're basically building
essentially in their view in synthetic
biology they're building that kit of
parts
right
but but but the important point here is
that the process of designing these
biological systems will look different
than the
natural biological systems using the
same principles
we should think of the same thing will
occur in
now that is going to drive us crazy
because all of a sudden you're going to
have this physicist computer thing
that thinks the way a physicist
does but the physicists don't feel like
it's physics
and the rest of us don't understand
physics we won't understand it either
right we're gonna have to sort all that
out
i'm already there with the language
models today explain
explain this
um
so give some background on the language
yeah so um so there are a number of
these uh
language models today that are trained
on large amounts of of of uh text
uh and that can then produce
uh extremely realistic looking text from
very very small prompts
uh and one of the ones that we we
uh quoted in the book because it was so
striking with respect to
uh sort of the nature of the
capabilities of ai
is gpt3 which has already since been
surpassed by a number of of other
such systems which was developed by
openai
and
the sort of prompt was asking
gpt3 to talk about
itself
and
the the sort of dialogue that it
synthesized
included gbt3 saying
you know
i'm a language model i'm not intelligent
like you are as a human
and you know i can speak intelligently
but i don't actually have intelligence
all i have is a model of what human
language looks like and i can produce
things that look like human language and
so what i find extremely frustrating
already about these models is that
um
because human language is such a
powerful means by which we communicate
our own understanding with one another
human to human forget about ai for a
minute two humans what do we use to
communicate our understanding language
for the most part
uh and so
when something is very good at
synthesizing powerful language but
doesn't really necessarily have an
understanding that's driving it
uh that that that's something that i
find insanely frustrating and so
and i think it's worth building on this
in the following way so if you talk to
people doing research some of whom are
here in this area in this area
first those large language models are
exploding they're exploding all over the
world there's a race if you will in
terms of scale and size of language
models
the training cost of gpt3 which is
almost two years old was about 100
million dollars if you include the
electricity and the computers and the
people and so forth
the new ones are 10 times greater and
using engineering techniques
it's not going up linearly with the size
of the model thank goodness
and they're getting much much better the
evidence so far is that the models get
better with absolute scale they're not
seeing a mean reversion yet
they haven't hit some limit to how much
they can know
so the strange thing about these
language models is you train them and
then you try to figure out what they
know
which is the complete inverse of how
programming is done you typically know
what you're doing well here you train it
and then this interesting things happen
and the most recent
there are two recent things that have
gone on one is that microsoft
has offered a series of products which
are programming
assistance
and the reason to think that's going to
be successful is first you're always
better off in computer science when
you're building something for yourself
because then you get it right and you
use it and you you iterate with it it's
just the nature of the field
and second you get a strong training
signal back
when the computer proposes the next line
of code and you say no that's wrong it
then puts that into its learning regime
so there are four or five startups that
i'm aware of that are now basically
trying to build programming assistance
of
serious power
to do that
now that's an example of a highly
specialized intelligence
and you could imagine that eventually it
could get to the point where you could
say write me a program that will
generate a browser
and it will know enough to actually
write the code
now that's not the same thing as
volition
but it's scarily close to it
another one is a product called lambda
which was developed in the research labs
at google
the technical details were released this
past week
and one way to understand it is they
trained it on
a relatively large corpus of human
conversation so it feels conversational
and it's backed up by a lot of data this
is google so obviously they have a great
deal of research around around search
and answers and so forth
and it's you can ask it very complicated
questions so a predictor for the next
five years in this is the models will
get much larger
they'll be completely multimodal that
means text and video and so forth and
they'll get really good at
summarization and answering questions
now i don't know what that means for
businesses or i can imagine businesses
where that matters but it has a big
impact in terms of human day-to-day life
because
now you type in a query into google
hopefully
and you see all these answers and then
you figure out which one is crazy and
which one is correct and so forth
hopefully google gives you the right
answer
this next thing you'll just type your
question and then this summary will come
out
and it's highly likely to be accurate
that's a big change
yeah and actually it points at an
interesting uh sort of change that's
been happening
as these algorithms develop generally is
um
is sort of increasing homogeneity sort
of loss of heterogeneity you know the
world in general we benefit from the
fact that we all have different views in
this room uh i'm sure i can find topics
that we all disagree on but the um
but
algorithms tend to so you know it'll
produce a summary
that uh
you know given the particular query you
you gave uh and there you know there's
more richness in the language model than
that but it these things are generally
you know they'll take sort of the most
likely summary given a particular query
as opposed to at least today even if you
get a bunch of garbage back from google
you see some of that heterogeneity
so this is i think another struggle that
we have as ai gets better and better and
believe me there's plenty of machine
learning in what google gives back today
it's not
uh but but you still sort of play an
active role it's filtered a lot but you
still get some sense of of what's there
when you start getting
compelling sounding summaries that may
just be
okay that makes sense that's my
understanding of the world and so i
think this is another
some of the broader philosophical
questions that we tried to sort of
investigate and raise in the book is
some of these kinds of changes
if we don't think about them and we
don't think about how ai is interacting
with us
we'll substantively change uh how people
interact with them i'll give you a
simple example when i'm when i spend my
time in dc talking to politicians if
they're democrats i talk about utility
functions and economic growth with
republicans i talk about national
security and i say the same things
but i understand my audience well enough
to shift what i say in words and
emphasis
uh when i was doing this when i was at
google i would go visit a country and if
the country would typically have a
dictator and a number two that was not a
dictator or vice versa
and i would
for one i would say the internet will
benefit you economically and growth and
the other one i would say that you need
to do this
and basically not talk about the
openness that it invite
in another case i would say this will be
openness and democracy and all that
i do this naturally we all do
so when the system understands
what your biases are
and the summary is no longer the same
summary that everybody else gets but
it's tailored to you
that is another set of issues so what
happens is the moment in computer
science
remember the moment something happens
then you have the the problem of
recursion right so it's there's always
going to be a successor that uses that
so
the ultimate outcome could be
highly
highly specialized narratives
that are specific to you
you have no idea why it's specific to
you because it learns something about
you that may or may not be true
but nevertheless you got it and dan got
something different and ozu got
something different in and of itself who
knows
it's it's the
the it's the um
much more omnipresent version of the
annoying thing that you know netflix
learns something about you that actually
has nothing to do with your taste and
keeps recommending all kinds of stuff
you don't want to watch
and when this started you know the
recommendation engines were relatively
simple um i used to give the example uh
when i was selling google google ads but
the tv would show
an ad for diapers
and there's no diapers in the house well
that's a wasted ad impression it should
know something about the house
well now in 20 years we've gotten to the
point where it knows everything about
the house
right
so
just to follow up on some of the things
you mentioned i'd like to sort of focus
on the pace of change and how we adapt
uh to this how we stay ahead of this and
you do i think
i found it fascinating that you also go
back and you know
similar to the previous looking backward
that i talked about you consider sort of
the
evolution of human thought
around reason with lots of philosophical
underpinnings and pioneering
contributions from kant to wittgenstein
and then you sort of mention i think
very much and i'll refer to my notes for
that is that online platforms inundate
users with opinions of millions of
others depriving them of the reflection
needed to develop that wisdom and the
social values i sense an underlying
worry or concerns about you know how
we're going to be how our existing
you know philosophical constructs or
societal institutions will be whether
they will be sufficient to deal with
this change so what are your thoughts on
that how do we
deal with it how do we
you know change our uh social uh
government uh
uh frameworks to be able to stay ahead
of this change yep so i'm going to
very s uh carefully not answer this
question
well just because so much of what we're
we've been trying to do in the work
we've been doing together is you know as
you noted a suit to provide framing for
people to to start to think about those
things more and i think
to me the historical framing that's
very relevant and important to your your
uh your question here is
um
if you if you look at um sort of
evolution of human thought around the
time period where in the west the you
know movable type printing press
uh moved us from a world where you know
most people got information
through word of mouth
or from organized religion
to where they could you know
literacy became more and more uh
widespread and people could read what
they wanted to and form opinions from
from from what they saw published
and and the huge impact on society was
moving from a world where
faith was the main way that people
understood the world around them to a
world where
human reason and faith together were how
people understood the world
and i think one of the the big changes
with ai and we don't understand what it
means yet
uh is that there's another change
happening
that when you have another entity that
is
you know similarly intelligent to humans
at least in some cases
uh
that's going to lead to some other way
of looking at the world
and it could be
that we come to view
you know humanity at large comes to view
a.i as this omniscient oracle
and then it sort of becomes another kind
of faith
right so you sort of you move from
from you know faith to faith and reason
to you know faith reason and another
kind of faith
uh or it could be that you know
ai evol is developed in ways that people
can really engage and can learn more and
can become
you know much more educated in
interlocutors of the world around them
uh and and in fact act to
reinforce human reasoning so i mean
they're
they're very different possible outcomes
that can come from how ai is developed
how humanity
starts to use ai um and and those kinds
of broad framings i think are incredibly
important and often
you know
not what we're thinking about when we're
when we're deploying these kinds of
technologies
the um
let's leave it at that i think that's
good
okay i'd like to move away from the
worries of it and then focus on the
positives like a new technology for the
greater good to improve human lives and
uh
condition and i know this is something
you both care a lot about
what are some areas that ai will have
the potential for immense positive
change in the you know short term long
term i think we would both answer this
with
one word it used to be plastics in the
movie now it's biology
right
yeah
one of my friends said that you know
physics requires math in the same way
that biology will require ai
the the biological systems are so
complicated and so incomputable in in
eric's terms
that the only way we're going to
understand these complicated living
systems um is through the kind of
modeling that ai it's as though ai was
invented to solve this problem it looks
for patterns it looks it looks for
changes
it can do generative work
uh for every analysis that an ai system
it can generate an equivalently
interesting answer
so
here at mit you have many people who are
using this to basically look at very
complicated biological processes for
various drug discovery and things like
this
the hallison example maybe you should
talk about is a it's a good example of
how traditionally stovepiped industries
have actually
worked together as a team
and i will say further that i think here
at mit every science project will have
an
analogous ai team with it
i think that's why steve schwartzman
generated
college i think that's why you came here
i think one thing you mentioned there
that i would just underscore
is that um you know so many existing
uh
things that we use in scientific and
engineering discovery
are for analysis
and
ai both enables analysis and synthesis
and so many problems that we're trying
to solve in science and engineering
synthesis is a key aspect of the problem
so it really transforms the landscape
and i i would agree that i see the
biological and life sciences at the core
of that but
um but you know materials and chemistry
and other things are also very hard and
even parts of physics frankly where the
math
only
gives you a very uh uh um you know broad
brush uh understanding of things where
ability to do analysis and synthesis
with machine learning i think is really
going to transform things yeah one of
the things that's interesting is that
the canonical model for ai research was
you get
lots and lots of data you analyze it
real world data so data matters a great
deal
and then you come up with insights
so i'm sitting in a meeting
at a research group that's studying the
question of
reasons that were never apparent to me
whether a mouse was sleeping or not
and it turns out that mouse sleeping is
difficult to detect
for reasons again i don't understand
and they couldn't come up with
training data by measuring it
so they built a simulated mouse using
normal mechanics
and they figured out how mice sleep
enough and then they generated the
training data synthetically
and i thought that's like a violation of
the first principle first principle is
you have to have lots of training data
well these guys generated it
so i think the second phase of ai
is that scientists are going to
use the known principles
of the world and generate the training
information using techniques like this
and that will then drive
both traditional learning reinforcement
learning and so forth
there are some things that would be
amazing for example if some of you could
invent a universal simulator
it could be used against across all of
these fields that would make a big
difference reinforcement learning
requires a fast simulator
because you're in reinforcement learning
you're looking at multiple forward paths
and you're optimizing the
the choices
i do think the power of simulation in
machine learning is something that uh
we're still only scratching the surface
of with reinforcement learning
i'll ask maybe one last question we're
running out of time unbelievable i have
so many more questions but i'd like to
also contrast some of these technologies
and what you're experiencing with social
media a topic very you know uh something
we talk a lot about at mit i know eric
you're very interested in uh like what's
the impact of ai technologies in that
domain where it's you know
even more interesting because these
systems help us you know deal with this
uh incredible amount of information but
at the same time they learn from us
shape our behavior and you know lead to
very profound uh social political well
everybody saw the coverage last year of
the what are called the facebook files
where internal documents were stolen
from facebook and leaked
and
there was a
big hubbub about that regulatory hub up
and so forth i don't know how that's
going to get resolved
but there were a series of
interviews with people who worked inside
of facebook
as opposed to people like me who just
make stuff up about this
and they asked them
how would you actually solve this
problem
and they said go back to the linear feed
i said that's interesting
so what had happened was in the last two
years ai who's a leading ai researcher a
facebook a leading ai researcher had
amped up the feed
using the signals
to make it more impactful and so forth
and they i assume that they did this
legitimately and for good reasons
so that's a good example where
you have a generally well-run company
um trying to do its mission in the world
and then they adopt ai and then they get
this huge impact in blowback
maybe they didn't understand the impact
they were getting or maybe they
misjudged the impact that they would get
but they're paying big time for it
there's a current example
um
and i don't know how that's going to get
resolved yeah i think social media
generally is a very you know the use of
ai in social media and social media
today
don't don't fool yourself into thinking
that today's social media could operate
without
massive use of machine learning uh and
and automated decision making it just it
doesn't scale
uh but but i think
the use of ai is acts as a big amplifier
of
everything that humans do
what's good
you know what we view as good what we
view is bad what we like about ourselves
what we don't like about ourselves
and i think you know partly
facebook
has gotten sort of caught up on you know
in
in making the
feed be so much more driven by by ai
recommendation
they've gotten caught up in that
amplification
uh that implication phenomenon so some
of the things that they're amplifying
presumably
are very valuable to their users and
that's getting a certain kind of
engagement and others are things where
you know various researchers at facebook
said
why are we amplifying this
uh and teasing those apart is not always
easy you know i told you
that i i'm a simple principal i'm in
favor of free speech for humans
not for robots
okay
so this amplification problem is very
real i'll give you another example and
this is from maybe seven years ago at
youtube
um
youtube would show
a video of something pretty nasty
and the recommendation engine was so
good that it would keep showing it
and there was evidence that this would
drive people into
terrorist or near terrorist activities
and so the way this was solved was the
company
defined a class of categories which were
special
and they were not to be amplified
so they if you saw one they weren't
censored but they weren't amplified so
you could find it and you could watch it
but it wouldn't suggest another one
and furthermore we wouldn't model we
wouldn't monetize it so that's an
example of a fairly crude and simple
change that you could make where you've
got
normal stuff and then let's just say on
the edge stuff there's clearly that
stuff that's illegal
but uh things which could be interpreted
as recruitment videos for bad acts
and we would and we had a process that
would judge that
so that's an example of the kind of
change that you could make
i don't think you're going to solve the
problem
in a fundamental way
and and i think there's a project here
looking at this there's other people i
know working on it but until we come up
with some new some new ideas
everyone involved in the content
business is going to fundamentally have
good content questionable content and
forbidden content forbidden content
you're not going to do
so child pornography things like that
the questionable content you're going to
have to not monetize it you're going to
have to not recommend it
and then you as the provider can make a
decision as to whether you want to host
it at all
and under american law
those decisions are made by the private
companies
i would just underscore
in the
you know not free speech for for robots
uh
that
the point that you made but i think that
people
often miss and that's why i just want to
underscore it is that when a social
media
algorithm is recommending is pushing
something at you
that's the robot speaking
it may be you know it is some human's
speech maybe maybe it was robot
generated speech to begin with but
assume it's some human speech that's
that's
you know that's human free speech
but the fact that it's pushed at
millions or billions of people
is actually the robot deciding to speak
and that is a very uh
complicated set of issues that we really
need to address as a society
yeah and then there's all sorts of
complicated problems we had one case
where we had we were studying this there
was a
person this was his speech but he set up
a twit tweeter bot
to tweet every hour 24 hours a day now
he wasn't awake every hour
so is that a permissible amplification
of his speech or should you say he can
only do that two-thirds of the day
you see that's where the the judgment
comes in
very good so i'd like to invite our
audience uh for some questions uh uh
and you know i think we'll have
microphones uh that eric has
hi um yeah i think for everything so far
uh in terms of um artificial general
intelligence uh an actual level of
analogy the field of orbital mechanics
made leaps and strides once people
started making or questioning uh bad
assumptions like circular orbits and
once people start asking the right
questions like what actually causes the
earth's orbits so for agi what are the
assumptions that we need to challenge or
the questions that we need to ask to
actually make the leaps and strides in
that field
well i think one of the questions since
i'm pro agi and dan is anti-agi
okay
let's just say that agi may be a
destination we never get to
it may be a construct that defines the
human progress toward these goals so
forth
or it may actually happen i don't think
we we know so that's the first question
and i define agi
as the ability to generate its own tasks
because that's the thing that to me
defines human intelligence over other
kinds of intelligence there are other
definitions
and
how would you build a system
using our kind of intuitive reasoning
it could generate new ideas
the
deep mind answer because i spent a lot
of time with them is that
you can using reinforcement learning
come up with predictable combinations
which you cannot explain as to why they
came up
and if you can't explain it that's
similar to human intuition
you know it but you can't explain it
so that's that sort of religious pitch
but my judgment is we don't have an
answer to the question of how do we go
from these
beautiful analytical systems which are
extraordinarily good
to where they generate their own
activity
you agree or disagree
i would actually agree
so what is your time frame for agi dan
well i'm still back on your initial
question of can it happen or not
i think you see the
of problem
other questions
and while they're getting to that i'd
like to share something and my
nine-year-old is very interested in agi
and reading your book and i was actually
telling him that you know the difference
between you that dance time frame versus
yours uh is different and he looked at
me and said i agree with dan but i'd
like to hear about eric's perspective
well if he's
let's see if he's nine his expected life
expectancy is age 100.
so in the next 91 years i think dan and
i would agree that there will be some
form of agi yes we may or may not see it
i will tell them that
so so your son is in a great position
i'm still not sure it'll have its own
motivation but uh let's see
where's the
i can't see yeah
so you you guys mentioned uh ai for
biology um and you guys also talked
about sort of the increasing capital
needs of training you know
state-of-the-art ai models right so the
typical like r0 grant amount is what
like 250 000 a year from the nih if
you're a well-funded startup you could
raise what 25 million in a series a
google just started their ai for drug
discovery
program where they could easily put you
know like 250 million a year into it if
they wanted to right so
it seems like ai research even applied
research in other fields is sort of
becoming
capital
intensive to the point where it could be
antithetical to like the principles of
open research
is this something that you guys could
see like challenging the development of
the field in the future it seems like a
concern uh an incredibly well put
question and i'll give you an example of
alpha fold
which you understand how fulfilled was
done elf folds a huge achievement
alpha fold was initially the technical
details of alpha hold were not released
and now i'm no longer at google so i'll
just say this without i don't mean to
criticize or praise
the baker lab
watched the video of alpha fold
reconfigured all of its stuff in some
complicated way i don't understand
and then started to produce
answers to human proteins
and then google then through deepmind
released everything
so
was it the
competition with alpha phil with the
with the baker lab that caused that
that's some articles have said that or
was it just
the lawyers slowing them down because
corporations lower slope slow people who
want to open source things down i don't
know
but the important point is we got the
information out and and understanding
the protein that affects humans and
their folding structure is a nobel prize
kind of achievement because it's like a
huge platform for knowledge in biology
so my guess is you're going to see the
usual mess you're going to have
corporations that keep it proprietary
you're going to have corporations that
behave the way google did which is their
release it you're going to see private
philanthropists which includes me that
are going to fund these models
and then you're going to see other
mechanisms
my guess is that some country the
obvious one would be china will actually
make this a national priority and we'll
just publish it all
so i think it'll resolve itself
but one of the things that's different
from
20 30 40 50 years old
is all of the progress is now occurring
in these corporations because they have
so much money relative to you
but we're smarter well
no dan since we hired all your people
[Laughter]
right we just transferred them from you
to me
uh no but more seriously so i agree with
you that i think that this is a
serious uh challenge
but i also think um that we're you know
when the research community gets focused
on challenges a lot of progress can be
made and important progress and a big
focus for a lot of machine learning work
now actually is training with much
smaller amounts of data
uh and um and you know in the
reinforcement learning setting with much
uh you know smaller numbers of
iterations of a simulation
and and i think this is an area that we
can and will make enormous advances in
uh but right now we are in a
uh whatever the opposite of a sweet spot
is with respect to this uh i do think
it's a big challenge but but but i think
that um there's already early signs of
progress in a number of ways that uh but
this is how it sort of happens right you
get this polyglot model
it's messy by design because of human
creativity and maybe ai creativity in
the future but eventually there will be
databases
and there'll be a database
of everything you need to know about
this aspect of biology and a database of
everything you need to know about this
aspect of physics
and it'll be generally understood to be
correct and those become the platforms
for the generation behind you
right you're struggling through this
strange problem of i don't have access
to it and these guys have it they won't
give it to me but the next generation
will have a common platform that's how
it always works and that's the reason to
be optimistic and more generally i
believe that constraints are really
important part of the creative process
and so you know academics have to work
on some different problems because we're
constrained we don't have 250 million
dollars worth of compute to put into
something
and so these more efficient algorithms
are something that we can and are
working on and to show you my
perspective uh as a computer scientist
who's been in the industry for a long
time
i was reasonably convinced that
universities were put with respect to
this stuff that we had simply drained
all the talent we'd taken all the money
and that there was nothing for them left
to do in these eight areas this is my
own arrogance clearly completely wrong
right and when i look at the last five
years of progress in science
astrophysics biology chemistry material
science a whole bunch of fields in
physics i don't understand
i listen to these guys presentations and
they are
world-class applications of some of
these underlying concepts and they're
different
so i think we're seeing a to be clear i
think we're seeing a renaissance in the
universities
now that the universities have got their
act together they got enough funding
people have a language you see a certain
amount of common goals you're seeing it
it feels very different from five years
ago i don't know if you agree with my
bias or not
well
to me
yes i mean i totally agree and i think
you know
part of
what we're trying to do with the college
of computing generally is that
computing and you know most notably ai
become part of the intellectual fabric
part of the way that people
conceptualize problems in a whole wide
variety of disciplines and i think that
you know there's still a lot to be done
to make that easier across
uh you know a wide variety of areas but
but i think that this is uh
definitely a golden age of of that kind
of transformation i mean i'll give you a
caltech example uh i first
figured out the world was different than
i said a few years ago when i was
visiting a group called the klima cli ma
model and mit is one of the partners in
this
mit does a lot of the the
surface c and modeling this is basically
climate modeling
and so the professor at caltech who's
one of these impossibly brilliant
physics types people is explaining the
most and he's talking about navier
stokes equations and he says well we
can't model clouds i said like what's
wrong with you why can't you it's just
not computable
so all of a sudden we show up with the
plug
that solves all of his other physics
problems because clouds are essential to
climate modeling
and so i visited with the team these are
all physicists
and they're impossibly intelligent
obviously
and they're all applying these tools to
physics which for them is relatively
simple
and i thought ah i got it we had to
build this basic set of platforms
they had to then plug it into their
model
another caltech example is that there is
a set of problems in chemistry which
involve relaxation of energy state to
find the lowest energy state that then
produces the right chemical reaction
well all of a sudden a bunch of graduate
students figured out you can use these
libraries to do it so all of a sudden
everyone at caltech was doing it
that's progress
like i said we're smarter
i'd like to maybe take a question from
the online
audience i have about 50 questions here
so i'm having a hard time picking one
two questions in four minutes i know i
know i was like oh gosh okay maybe we'll
just pick this one
for a long time ai has been regarded as
a collection of separate studies based
on entirely unrelated separate
principles i wonder if anything like a
general purpose ai is emerging
well i think you know what's happened as
much as i agree with eric that deep
learning is going to hit its uh
limits at some point here as everything
does
i think you know the extent to which
uh
deep learning
much of the application of which
actually started in computer vision in
my area
of research has uh you know developed
such that it's usable across a wide
variety of domains
if that if that's not the closest thing
to a common
approach i'm not sure what is so i think
you know in some ways many people in in
machine learning research they sort of
bemoan the fact that it feels very
sort of like everybody's
kind of developing the same algorithms
and then applying them to a lot of
different problems and
we've sort of lost the diversity of
various different ways of looking at
machine learning and ai problems
but again you know as eric was saying i
think these things go in cycles
uh and we'll hit an end and then
there'll be a time period where you know
there's a big diversity of approaches
again i mean 25 years ago people were
working on alternatives to cmos
and chips and then for many engineering
good engineering reasons cmos took over
there are still tiny pockets of people
who are not working on cmos in
universities somewhere in the world
but it sort of essentially eliminated
all variation for a while
and now as cmos begins to hit its
natural limits those people have an
opportunity again
my guess is that's what's going to
happen with deep learning
uh i remember 15 years ago looking this
is again before 2011
people would explain all these ai
theories and symbolic language analysis
and so forth and so on and i go okay
fine you know whatever
but
that has essentially been completely
usurped by these new technologies over a
decade
which is a relatively short i mean it
seems like a long time to you all as
students and faculty here but it's
actually a short time in human history
for such an extraordinary transformation
one more question i'm like
we want mit students to pursue
inventions and breakthroughs fearlessly
on the other hand we also hope they can
slow down ask why and think about social
and ethical responsibilities of
computing how do we strike a balance how
do we mentor them
[Laughter]
nice easy ending question
uh so i mean one thing that i think is
very important and actually this is
something that that that uh eric and
wendy schmidt have been very involved in
generally is
how do you train people in more than one
discipline right so the schmidt scholars
and the sciences is you know
postdoctoral scholars who do a postdoc
in a lab different from where they did
their phd
and i think that uh today to really
dig deeply into the social and ethical
questions around computing you need to
do something like that you need to say
you know i got my csphd i'm going to
spend a postdoc you know working in with
uh you know
in a scholarly fashion in
some discipline uh in the social
sciences or humanities um i think that
that right now we don't have that level
of expertise
without that kind of cross-training
we had one one questions from the
audience
hi um thank you so much for the content
so far i guess
it might be the last question today uh
so i'm gonna try and phrase it well um
i'm wondering
i guess maybe there's two parts to this
question one i'm wondering um how you
imagine an ideal human future and second
of all
what do you
what were your goals behind writing this
book
and how may or may not it relate to i
guess eric schmidt your work with the
national security sorry
ncsai sorry national security commission
on ai
um
i think the utopian future goes
something like this
humanity has spent so much of our time
dealing with basic needs and fighting
with each other so if you look at
history it's basically farming
the development of modern economics and
war right roughly speaking
and so you could imagine a situation
where the end stay this is when your son
is elderly
uh probably hard to imagine but it will
it will happen
um
that you can imagine this scenario that
the the needs of the average person are
largely met
through improvements in food and
material science
housing is inexpensive at least a
construction perspective because of all
of these developments that are going on
here at mit and elsewhere
and that people are free to
to pursue more things that are
interesting to them
and that the other thing that happens
with ai is we learn how to educate
people
i would argue that the that we haven't
talked about the impact of ai on
education because we haven't seen it yet
but it makes perfect sense to me that ai
systems should be able to figure out how
you learn
and and allow you to learn in the most
efficient way
and that should be true for every single
human being on the planet and it should
be free
i defy you to argue that that's a bad
thing right it's got to be good
right for humanity
so in that that sort of utopian view
we'll still fight because we like to
fight over things but we'll fight over
things which aren't dangerous
and we aren't harming people and things
like that
and that's a really good way to
understand this
the the
the work of the book
essentially paralleled the work of the
commission
because in the commission we talked
about
basically how did how to make sure that
ai
was part of our national security
strategy in the united states
we made lots of recommendations most of
which involve building talent
the government is slow to
there's this huge gap between the talent
here and the talent and the government
daniela who who is here
runs a whole program with the military
there's an air force group at lincoln
labs and so forth there's lots of really
smart people who are working on it but
there are
immigration people sending into the
military to bring their understanding of
ai up to this new standard
i guess maybe i'll get the last word
so to me
the book
so first of all i totally agree with
what eric said and i'm a terrible
futurist so it's good to have work with
somebody who can see the future better
than i can
uh but um but i think uh to your
question of the objective of the book
uh it really was to get people thinking
about ai in broader terms
i think that people come at it either
with a utopian view or a dystopian view
but the reality is going to be somewhere
in between people come at it with either
a technological understanding or a lack
of technological understanding uh and so
the idea was really to try to set these
changes in the context of hundreds of
years of humanity
and provide that as framing to have more
discussion of the kind that we've been
having here today and i hope that all of
you will continue to do that it's really
important
and your and your generation
is the one that's going to do that more
than ours
and let me uh let me finish by saying
that um
it's a privilege to be here it's a
privilege to be
crazily they made me a
a visiting professor here for which i'm
ill-suited but i'm very grateful
and
the quality of the talent in this
institution is so great that you should
be able to win
so what i need you to do is i need you
to work harder work faster take
advantage of this these things don't
occur that often in life this is this
period where this enormous
cambrian explosion of ideas
there are going to be enormous winners
in this
and you all to the degree that you can
shape them in the values that we're
trying to represent here
are really crucial small teams can have
an outsized impact we've seen this in
many many areas
and i would suggest some things to to to
work on i think i mentioned the
education one
um somebody's gonna break through this
there's an uh there's a school of
education here there's a bunch of people
working on it here at mit that i've been
working with somebody's gonna figure out
a way to do this at scale that will have
a huge impact
right
working on underlying algorithms
figuring out where to generalize these
algorithms so they apply across all
these fields and then applying them in
each field in a clever way
to really deliver breakthroughs and this
means you know and when i talk to normal
people as opposed to tech people
a number of people said i just can't
take it there's so much going on and i
said you haven't seen anything yet we're
at the beginning
of the power of these tools to transform
science and business and society but
it's up to us how that happens and
frankly it's up to you how this happens
and that's why it's such a privilege to
work with you and you
um and the other teams that i've had a
chance to work with here at mit
thank you very much i have much more to
ask and talk about that we're at the top
of the hour so thanks very much for the
fantastic conversation thanks everyone
for joining us
and stay healthy more than anything and
thank you thank you
[Applause]