And it's uh my great pleasure to open
this Eric and Wendy Schmidt symposium on
AI and and bio computing. Um, AI is not
my field, but I'm perceptive enough to
see that this is a pretty remarkable
moment um for the field. And it it comes
that remarkable moment, I think, comes
at an interesting time in in history in
in biomedical research because we're
about three or four weeks away from the
25th anniversary of the uh first draft
sequence of the human genome project.
And I remember feeling at that time that
that also felt like a a special moment.
It was hard to
really get your head around exactly why
it was special, but you could tell
something remarkable was going to change
in the world of biology and in the world
of medicine. I think it's fair to say
that in retrospect perhaps the
short-term immediate benefits
of having a human human genome sequence
in hand were a bit overstated. But at
the same time, I think the long-term
benefits of having an anchoring for
biology and medicine with with the human
genome were also substantially
understated. And you know if you take
graduate students today and ask can you
imagine you know doing biomedical
research without that foundation of the
genome they
would it'd be hard to understand um how
you could really do research um without
without that as a as a foundation. I
feel like there's that level of
potential to really disrupt and
transform how we think about biomedical
research in the setting of a
matured field of uh machine learning and
and and AI. And so that's why to me this
feels like a really remarkable pivotal
moment where it's not clear yet I don't
think what that new world of biology and
medicine is going to look like. But I
think we can all agree that it's going
to look very different than it than it
than it does today. And so what a
remarkable moment to be in science when
over the next decade you all are going
to figure that out and then it will be
clear. It'll still evolve but the most
transformative change is going to happen
over the over the decade ahead. And I I
I mentioned this also um cognizant of
the worrisome
uh potential impact of decisions that
the US federal government is making with
respect to uh funding for biomedical
research. But even despite that
headwind, I still can't imagine a better
time to be in science. That's going to
be annoying. will slow us down a little
bit but I don't think fundamentally
because the drive particularly in AI and
biio medicine is going to be too strong.
It's going to move at an amazing pace
you know faster I believe than advances
in in in the genome um took place. And
so what better time to be uh a student,
a faculty member, a staff scientist in
academia or in industry uh working out
the decade ahead. So um with that um
brief comment um I'm happy to to open
the symposium and introduce the
organizer of the uh sympony uh symposium
Caroline Ooler who is also the director
of the Eric and Wendy Schmidt Center at
the Broad Institute and a professor uh
at MIT and electrical engineering and
and computer science. and we're just
really lucky to have Caroline's vision
and leadership um at the Schmidt Center.
Um I unfortunately I'm going to have to
step out but look forward to popping
back in um uh during the day. So hope
you have a a wonderful symposium.
Caroline,
[Applause]
thank you very much Todd for opening up
this uh symposium and welcome everyone.
So excited to see so many of you already
here. Um there has already been such a
great energy in the room and outside and
I'm just uh really looking forward to
two exciting days of um stimulating
research and discussions. Um so before
getting started with the program, I
thought I would like to say just a few
words um about the Eric and Wendy
Schmidt Center. So um it was launched in
uh July 2021 um thanks to the amazing um
generosity and vision of Eric and Wendy
Schmidt and also thanks to the great
support um of you know the current broad
leadership and former broad leadership
Todd Golop and and Eric Lander. Um it
really took this huge team um to put
this together and to get this started.
Um, and I'm just very excited uh to be
able to continue building it and bring
together this community um that we have
here together.
Um, so in terms of I just wanted to say
a few words about also what its vision
is. Um so the Eric and Wendy Schmidt
Center is um its vision is and and its
goal is really to create a global
community of researchers uh that make
biology a key driver of foundational
developments in machine learning to then
create the theoretical and computational
and algorithmic paradigms that enable us
to understand the programs of life and
how they are connected really across all
scales. So from proteins to cells to
tissues and organisms. And we really
strongly believe that the biomedical
sciences are you know not only uniquely
suited to being a beneficiary of
research in machine learning but also
one of the greatest sources of
inspiration for new foundational
developments in machine learning. So we
really want to build this two-way
street. Um, so not just a one-way street
of getting um bringing in machine
learning that has been already developed
into the bi into biology, but really
also going the other way around um of
changing what machine learning is today
um through biology. And so in order to
do this um to really build this two-way
street um we're here um have in
particular uh built a you know a a a a
program for post-doal fellows where
we're attracting machine learning
researchers to the broad that may
actually not have any prior biological
background but have a strong interest in
biology and then we're connecting them
uh to really important biomedical
problems um which then of course have to
first be translated into the language of
machine learning to make them amendable
to computational thinking. And of
course, these problems will not be able
to be solved um just by one person or
one group, but actually we require a
really strong collaborative effort
across disciplines to then be able to
solve these problems. And so we're very
excited about our post-doal program and
all of the fellows that are here. You
will hopefully meet many of them today.
They're really the basis of of the
Schmidt Center and making the scientific
effort possible. They're bringing into
the broad a very deep um machine
learning background and expertise
together with their mentors um at MIT,
uh Harvard and and others outside and
then they're connected to really deep
expertise in biology um at the broad and
this is really the bread and butter. Um
so hopefully you'll be able to uh you
know talk to a lot of our fellows and if
you're a PhD student we have a call for
post-doal fellowships um every year in
December. So please um consider that as
well. Um now we do want to bring in you
know go much beyond uh the Boston
environment um and bring in the global
machine learning community to biomedical
problems. Um and so we've uh decided to
do this through the vehicle um of
challenges or competitions
um where we try to first identify a
biological problem that is or a
biomedical problem that is really
critical to be solved but can also spur
foundational research in machine
learning. And so in these uh machine
learning challenges, it's I think some
of the first of their kind where it's
not just about a prediction problem
where you know we hold out some data and
then you'll predict and uh we'll we'll
rank all algorithms based on this but we
want the participants to actually have
an influence on what are the next
experiments that we're performing. Um
and so here you know the best teams on
the prediction part are actually their
experiments. So they're also going to
tell us which experiments we would like
to see and those experiments are
actually going to be run. So machine
learning researchers across the the the
globe can have an influence on you know
which are the next experiments to be
run. Um and we're currently ending our
second um challenge which was on you
know connecting um uh images so
pathological or pathohistological images
to spatial transcrytoics. Um and you
know in both of these challenges we're
very excited. we had over a thousand
participants. So hopefully if you didn't
participate um the next challenge, we're
we're preparing it. Um so we will be
launching it um later this year. It will
be um a somewhat of a continuation of
the first challenge on predicting um
unseen perturbations. Um and so stay
tuned. Um and I really hope you will all
be uh participating also in the next
challenge. um so that we can all you
know somehow push forward this field
which requires just so many new ideas in
order to really make
progress. So with this um welcome to
everyone. I'm uh super excited to get
this started and look forward to two
really uh great days of amazing science
and stimulating discussions.