We chatted briefly before this and I I I
went through all the different areas of
questions that I was going to ask
everybody while we're up here and I
decided that I would pull the rug out
from under everybody and and and change
and create a new question. Uh, one of
the things I I noticed in in sitting
through the presentations, which were
fantastic, by the way, is that uh
something I'd like to tease out a little
bit more is some of the business use
cases. And and and
when you talk to people at MIT about AI
or almost anything is they they like to
talk about not doing things that are the
obvious. And the obvious thing to do
with AI is well, we could maybe reduce
the number of copywriters we can have.
But the big payoff is when you could
start thinking about your business
differently and transforming it. So, I'm
going to throw out a use case and then
maybe uh there'll be a few others that
you could you could put in there. But
take the example of if I want to book a
trip to London, I'll go on to a travel
site, an aggregator, and I'll search for
my flight, my hotel for London. I'll
book that. Maybe I'll schedule Uber to
pick me up. And when I do that, the
travel site gets paid by a commission
theoretically on the flight that I book
or on the hotel that I book. They'll be
showing me an ad while I'm doing that
and they'll get paid for that ad. And
then when I go to a completely unrelated
site after I book my trip to London,
they'll be offering me uh tickets to a
play in London for some reason. and it
knows that I'm going to London because
they've sold that information to to to
other entities.
Now, when that interface for booking
that trip becomes
pick your LLM, claude, chat, GBT, and I
just tell my agent, book me a trip to
London based on my preferences where I
live and make all the arrangements for
me. And it then it does that on my
behalf. Uh, I'm maybe no longer getting
ads that uh the the booker is being paid
for. I'm not even going to any other
website potentially. Maybe you don't
need an aggregator at that point because
the agent just goes out and finds me the
best flight based on my preferences.
And and that to me it starts to change
the entire revenue model of the web and
becomes something that is more of just
doing things a little bit more
efficiently, a little bit better to
being things that well this this
actually throws the checkerboard up in
the air and and and what how does that
land after that? So what what do you
think about those things and and based
on your perspectives where you see do
you see other sort of big nobody here is
from Sloan but you know that sort of
business perspective of things changing
based on an agentic web or the future
agentic web
you have a
>> yeah um you know for context uh our our
team at Leela AI we are creating
multitudes of agents that are more
visual
And so they're able to see the real
world and use real time on what they're
seeing to uh decisions, take actions on
behalf of our customers and stuff like
that. And so um when we initially went
and showed this to uh manufacturers and
industrial customers, they said, "Oh,
this is great. I I don't have to hire
five of new people. I can just use your
agents and I don't have to hire people."
Um, and that may be partially true, but
what we discovered after talking to them
more deeply is that at least in the
industrial manufacturing world, they're
highly understaffed. So what instead of
saying we can replace people or we can
let some people go, it it becomes like
we really should have had five people,
we only have one person in that job. So
if we can help this person become the
equivalent of of four more people uh and
augment them and amplify them with these
agents that will actually make us a much
better organization and have lots of
other positive outcomes. So for our
customers not not a travel agent on the
web thing. We're looking at more like
how do you uh make a better outcome for
manufacturers, industrial customers.
It's all about amplification,
augmentation. The agents become uh sort
of like supporters of the existing
people who have expertise. I don't think
the agents that we have today are have
enough expertise to really operate
autonomously in in fully autonomously in
in industrial applications. It's a
little bit scary to say, oh, this agent
just shut down our conveyor belt. That
might be the right thing to do, but it
might also be have been a false alarm
and then we're losing a million dollars
an hour because that conveyor belt is
shut down. So that we I don't think
we're ready yet to let them loose in the
manufacturing world where we work, but
they can amplify people and that has
enormous benefits that we've seen with
our customers.
>> So yes, so I I want to add to that that
there are two I mean the two very
separate applications and I think very
separate business model. One is consumer
which is what you were talking about and
one is business. We IBM model similar to
you. We just work with business luckily.
Uh because I think there the business
model is pretty clear. You go to
companies you you know you improve their
you know the operations you know they
save money they pay you right. It's it's
very simple for consumer. Luckily I
don't work for Google so I don't need to
think about it. But but yeah like you
said this is going to be disruptive for
for for that you know part of the the
business. And I I'm not sure that I have
good answers.
>> Okay.
>> Prauma, you you work with a lot of
different companies that are
collaborating with you on project NANDA.
Uh what how are they looking at this?
>> Yeah. Uh I mean great points here and
agree with uh all of that. Uh from like
a more academic perspective, one of the
uh maybe let's say a paradigm shift that
will happen with agents, distributed
agents is as follows. So as I'm sure all
of us agree today data is key right
training any AI model any large model is
really dependent on how much data you
have access to but also this is a
blocker because uh uh most of these big
models today are trained on largely
public data. Uh uh now the paradox here
is uh not all data not all data of
humanity is public and in fact the more
valuable the data the less likely it is
to be public. It'll be siloed behind
enterprise walls. It'll be in a
hospital. So there's a lot of critical
knowledge, let's say, of our collective
society that is still not reflected in
these amazingly capable models. So one
of the most exciting things that uh sort
of uh we think about a lot is how uh
agentic AI or networkked agentic AI will
shift the transaction
uh unit from data to intelligence. So
here's what I mean by that, right? Uh
you can have these data sources that are
siloed that are that are private. You
can have an agent on top of it. And this
agent need not communicate with other
agents the data entities, the raw data
itself which may be protected for
privacy and many other reasons, but it
can communicate in insights from the
data, broader statistics. And so you can
leverage a lot of this siloed data
without actually having to transact this
data. And this may be like a new avenue
to think about, you know, revenue
strategies or new ways to optimize
across organizational silos that does
not exist today.
>> If that makes sense.
>> Interesting.
I I I think shifting gears a little bit
and and what you touched on uh Cyrus, uh
let's talk a little bit about
accountability and risk. So you're
you're saying that in an industrial
setting and I I
monetary loss by shutting down a a a
factory could be pretty significant, but
also somebody gets hurt is another one.
A lot of the applications you're dealing
with I think are safety related.
>> Yeah.
>> So what what happens when something
unfortunate happens there is uh when
somebody says it wasn't my decision, it
was it was the AI agent that did it. How
are we handling accountability risk? Is
is is there a a plan for that when when
we do get to it?
>> Uh that's a really great question and I
would say that there's a lot of
variability out there right now and how
prepared a lot of organizations are to
deal with the point when there is a
decision that is an autonomous decision
that was taken with either minimal or
not no human oversight. No humans in the
loop, right? That's where we're heading
towards in many uh environments. And if
those errors, if those decisions are are
not correct, if they're mistaken
decisions, who's to blame? Um old, you
know, I forget who said this, but you
know, you you can you can't blame a
computer program. You can only blame the
person who wrote the computer program.
>> It's Winston Churchill.
>> It was Winston Churchill. Yeah, that's
coming up a lot lately, and I forgot who
said it. Uh but in any case, it's a
little hard now because as Dan said,
it's stocastic, right? So, if you roll
the dice and the LM spits out something
that's correct, great. Everyone gets a
happy credit to the to the people who
are operating this LLM. But if the LM
comes back with a decision that's wrong,
then oh, it's the people who wrote the
software that runs. That doesn't make
much sense. So, I think we need to all
think deeply. I don't have an answer
yet, but we don't have to think deeper
about the ethics and morals of using
these kinds of very very powerful
systems to uh make unchecked decisions
that are mission critical decisions.
Now, a decision to let's say book this
flight or that flight, sure, I I spent
200 bucks more than I should have.
That's in the end not mission critical.
As you pointed out, if uh there's a
situation where people get injured, um
that's sort of another level, maybe
multiple levels higher mission
criticality. And so looking at the basis
of a system and asking is this decision
correct or not? And can it be explained?
And that's where I think we have to
really dig deep. Can the systems we're
using explain why they made that
decision? And if they can explain, can
we verify that the reason that the
system is given for making decision is
the actual way that it came to that
decision? Because we see a lot with LLMs
is they're sick of fans. They're great
at saying, "You're so smart. Here's the
answer to your question. It was a great
question. Here's the answer. It's a
correct answer." Right? And then you
take that because it's such a positive
tone of voice in the way that it's
talking to you. You believe that it's
the right answer. And then you can even
ask, "How did you do that? How did you
answer? How did you figure that out?"
says, "Oh, I did this and this and
this." And then if you to bother to look
at the reasons that it gave for its
decision, you dig deep and say, "Are
these a real thing? Does this make any
sense? Is the evidence the real
evidence? Oh, it made up a website. Oh,
it made up an academic paper. Oh, it
made up a number that wasn't even in any
web page." Right? Then you realize, wow,
this this reason is a is is not I don't
call them hallucinations. I'll call them
confabulations. These reasons are not
right. So unless you can really trust
not only the answer but the the the
explanation of the way that it got to
the answer and maybe you can introspect
and open up the black box and look at
the what's going inside the LLM to
understand what's really happening not
what it says is happening what's really
happening inside unless you can do that
I don't think we should let them have
missionritical decision-making power
without human intervention so I have a
sort of maybe a controversial stance
here but I think we need to find better
options than large language models to
help us I think we're we're sort of hit
a wall with LLMs and we need other ways
of making decisions. Some we're working
on at Leela AI, but that are not uh
monolithic the way that the LLMs are
today.
>> So ways
that do the same thing, but are more
transparent, more explainable,
>> do the same thing differently and and
have to be explainable, transparent and
and and actually verifiable that the the
explanations are true. They have you
have to be able to verify those quickly.
May maybe a whole new startup idea in
there somewhere.
>> Yeah.
>> Um good. Any any anything to add?
>> Yeah. Yeah. A couple of things to add to
that. So So first of all, um I think
there's two aspects. One one is the tech
what what can we do more from the
technical point of view? Explanability
is of course really important. Um I I
think there is a limit to how much we'll
be able to explain inside the box. I
think we can do more than we do now, but
there's a limit. Um they've got billions
of parameters. Um
the other thing is I mentioned it in my
talk uncertainty quantification. It's
really important if we can get the LM to
report reliably what it what's its own
certainty about its answer. Now you
would say why would if I don't trans the
answer why would I trust
the model reporting. So there's actually
ways to do it and we have work that came
from the MIT IBM lab on first you need
to calibrate the model. So calibrate
means that when the model says
uncertainty, it's it's really true in
the sense that if I have a model that
predicts what's what if it's going to be
raining or not today. If the model says
that it's 70% certain, it means it will
be correct 70% of the time and wrong 30%
of the time. So it'll re so it'll say
how much is going to be wrong. Um that
will I think that will add a lot of uh
trustworthiness and also we could do
something about it. If the model is not
certain enough then okay we put that
aside. That's one one aspect. The other
aspect is more from I guess legal than
the law makers and standardization. I
think that's really important. There is
actually a standard. It's ISO 42,0001.
Um it was created I think two years ago.
Um and it's for AI management systems.
Um I know that anthropic was first to
get it in Microsoft and just recently
from the open community IBM we got it
just just recently. So so yeah we need
we need standards and we need lawmakers
to say well what can we do and what can
we not do. Interesting. I I guess um
picking on you again a little bit, I was
intrigued uh with your generative
programming model and um could you
elaborate a little bit more on uh
basically talk about the problem of
maybe maybe call it prompt spaghetti and
then how that addresses it.
>> Yeah. So so I think I I I mentioned in
the talk and we we can you know can have
a discussion on that. So, so, so the
yeah the prompt spaghetti comes from uh
from that trial and error process uh of
creating uh these agents. uh if it's a
simple agent then then it's easy it
doesn't become spaghetti but but once uh
you try and encode a very complex uh
workflow and there are many constraints
and what you see because of that trial
and error or maybe you're working with
another LLM to help you write that
prompt it becomes very long and it's
also there's no standard way of the
order of things and how so so you look
at these prompts and these are like I'm
looking at prompts that people even from
IBM consulting so we're getting some of
these prompts and we're seeing what they
what they're doing and so so you see
you'll have like an instruction and then
you have a piece of data and then all of
a sudden you have kind of an incont
incontext example and then another
instruction but then there's another
incontext example for the previous
instruction there's no order and no uh
um so really that's that's where uh the
prawn spaghetti is coming from and and I
think the answer is like I that was my
mantra in the talk is let's think about
it like computer scientists or like
software engineers and and say okay what
are we trying to achieve what is the
control flow and then let's follow that
control flow mainly in code and wherever
we need to call an LN
So is the hopeful sign for people with a
background in software engineering that
all that experience is not going to go
to waste?
>> Yeah. So so I have my own incentive
because my son is now in college
studying computer science and I want him
to be employed in a couple of years. Um
but but yeah, I think there's hope for
programmers.
>> Yeah, that that's always nice when
you're paying for college.
Uh so uh another aspect that I'd like to
touch on and and I think we we covered
it a little bit but what about
jurisdictions and and what about policy
if you're talking about decentralized
system famous systems famously don't
really respect international boundaries
ordinarily it's that they they sort of
go global. So how do you see that moving
forward in terms of maybe US regulations
being consistent with EU regulations in
other parts of the world?
>> Yeah, I think uh certainly uh there will
be a future where we have to start
thinking about uh some very specific
policies pertaining to agentic
interaction and orchestration as I
touched upon earlier. I think right now
of course these don't exist broadly
because today we are currently solving
smaller problems but still important
problems uh which are still policy
problems. How do organizations allow
agents to talk within an enterprise or
between enterprises? And so uh a lot of
the critical aspects to think about is
of course guardrailing ensuring that uh
safety critical information is not
regurgitated. I think comes back to uh
also what Cyrus and Dan were mentioning
which is explanability and
interpretability having that kind of
trust in agents and uh I think this may
also be part of policy for example maybe
uh uh there for certain mission critical
as Cyrus mentioned uh aspects there may
be a necessity to have uh uncertainty
quantification or trust or verifiability
before these sort of autonomous blackbox
entities are deployed in those settings.
There may also be data sovereignty
aspects uh famously in EU right uh for
example uh questions such as uh where
does an agent or an LLM actually
actually reside because uh an LLM is a
reflection of the data that is trained
on. So where does this model actually
reside if it's being served across the
world? Uh what does resolution what does
serving look like for these agents
across the web? uh I think these will
all be uh questions that need to be
carefully thought about and addressed as
part of policy but uh uh maybe we are
building towards it right now and uh uh
I think we first need to collectively
agree upon what are the important
questions to ask and then policy will
determine how they need to be answered
>> on the issue of privacy and and I know
Nandanda deals a lot of trying to
maintain privacy which is a is fighting
the good fight. Uh one of the things
that makes me a little bit uncomfortable
is that when you start talking about
privacy and private enterprise that
there always seems to be a financial
imperative to not respect that privacy
uh to exploit the data that you have. Uh
how do you see that working out uh in
terms of incentives?
Does you or any of our other other
panelists have something to say about
that? Is is there a way to address it?
>> I I can get started and then hand over
to the others as well. But yeah, I think
uh again uh to me uh this again goes
back to the argument whether to sort of
reap the benefits of these large AI
models. Do we need all the data to be
centralized or is it okay if the data is
distributed?
>> Right? And with sort of this idea of an
agent web and agents transacting as I
touched upon earlier in intelligence and
knowledge rather than in data, this is a
positive sign towards privacy because I
can hold sovereignty over my data but
still uh maybe for example ask questions
about something to do with my health
without exposing all my health records.
uh uh aspects like these uh could have a
like sort of this idea of an agentic web
could have positive impact on personal
privacy. That being said that there are
still a lot of questions to be answered
uh with respect to uh controllability of
agents like if I have my agent
autonomously interacting with some other
agents maybe this agent can be prompt
injected to reveal a lot of my private
information. So how do I prevent that
from happening? uh how do I safely
orchestrate these agents how do I
discover trustworthy agents so coming
back to these I think a lot of these
problems that we've talked about trust
reputation privacy uh guardrails a lot
of these are very closely intertwined uh
but to I feel like uh future is uh
promising
>> otherwise you wouldn't be working on
project nanda uh well that is um
>> in in preparing for this panel we were
talking beforehand that I spent spent a
bit of time creating two different
personas on chat GPT and I told them
both I want you to be highly competent
computer scientists. One is a big
proponent of decentralized AI project
NANDA and another one is skeptical and
it the interesting thing about it is
that both of those personas gave pretty
compelling arguments in terms of what
are the problems and we talked about
that in terms of interoperability. How
do I get heterogeneous agents to talk to
each other? I can't even get a program
my own company wrote to talk to talk to
each other. Uh the the power
requirements, resource requirements, and
of course as you can come up know very
well that there are answers to all of
those things.
>> Yes. I is is the is the knowing that
nobody has a crystal ball, do you see
the future as being something a little
bit messy or are you obviously you're
optimistic in general, but h how do you
see things playing out? And then if I
could put everybody on the spot, do you
what do you see? Is it when do we have
an agentic web? Is it five years, 10
years, or is it is it always going to be
something something hybrid?
She has start.
>> Go ahead.
>> Okay, perfect. Uh I think
uh Okay, so how do I see the near-term
future? I think it'll be uh nebulous. Uh
but not in a bad way. I think it's
because all of us are collectively sort
of uh reconciling with this new
technology, figuring out how it works,
what are its limitations, uh figuring
out policy protocols, interoperability.
So I think it'll be a bit nebulous as we
collectively arrive at a steady state
some uh protocols that we all agree upon
architectures that make sense uh broadly
uh but I don't think that's like uh at
least agents broadly existing across
enterprise and for consumer use cases
and uh interacting across organizational
cyers I don't think that's too far out
maybe a few years out uh in the future
just looking at how fast this technology
has developed right again chat GPT came
out in November 2022
uh that's like 3 years ago I remember I
was a PhD student at that point of time
and a lot of my peers were sort of
thinking oh like is our thesis gone now
because this thing can really do
everything that we can do but much much
faster so uh this paradigm shifting
moment is only 3 years ago from there
we've gone to like these much better
reasoning models to agentic models that
can actually do things. Uh now we are
talking about guardrails and trust and
accountability and talking about
interoperability. So I don't think this
is too farfetched. I think this is in
near term. Uh uh I don't think it's a
given uh that like this uh utopian
asentic web is what we'll see in the
future. It could be like the app economy
or it could be like cloud providers.
could be in like uh a few uh providers
as opposed to like uh broadly open like
the web. Uh we think it should be open.
Uh I know there will be uh uh differing
perspectives with pros and cons and I
think we'll arrive at some sort of
hybrid in the future.
>> Great. Um I'll put in my two bits.
Thanks for that. It was a really
interesting uh answer. I I would say
that today we're seeing our customers
ask us to allow some other agents that
they're working with in other parts of
their organizations to speak to our
agents. So this request is already here.
It's not in the future, it's today. Um
how can our agents talk to your agents?
So we and then there's going to be some
simplistic ways and it's going to get
better and better for sure. So I I think
uh it's not too early to start figuring
this stuff out. In fact, it may be ready
for a little bit too late. And then the
other thing I'd say is that I do think
that autonomy, you know, there's a lot
of automation stuff that's been
happening. There's this thing called
robotic process automation, which was a
big deal uh in the software world for a
while, and that's sort of that that
trend is pushing more and more things to
get automated. Um, so that's not going
away. The pressure for automation
continues and can will continue to grow.
And so I I see everything that's
automatable, safely automatable, will
get automated over the next five years.
It feels that way to me. Um and and then
after that, how do we make it safe for
the rest of the stuff to get that's you
know as we continue to automate more and
more and that's where I'm a little bit
concerned that um we are overly uh
invested in some some some very popular
approaches right now that may not turn
out to be the right ones for the high
trust high mission criticality use
cases. So that that's just I I I want to
say that if we need to have a plurality
plurality of approaches and right now we
seem to have sort of a monoculture uh in
in in the way that we're representing
knowledge and the way that we're asking
to build these systems that can help us
make decisions. Um there's there's
there's some there there many kinds of
agents not all of them have to be based
on LLM. That's that's what I'm trying to
get.
>> That's what I was getting at is or
thinking about is that I I sense a
controversial opinion there. or is is
there if do you want to expand on that?
>> Sure. Um
>> I mean if you think LLM suck just just
tell us.
>> I don't think they suck. They're good at
what they do but uh every time someone
bumps into a thing where it's like oh
this LLM keeps on giving me the wrong
answer. Oh, it's only right 50% of the
time. I'm just going to sort of ignore
that and move on. How common is that
situation? I think it's way more common
that people are uh putting on. And I do
think that the solutions they're coming
up with a bit more like putting
band-aids when there's something sort of
wrong at the core that's never there's
never there's never going to be this
kind of really humanlike reasoning and
planning and uh sort of common sense
understanding capability. I don't think
it's going to come out of LMS. So I
think we need to invest in other
approaches and there are people doing
that. Uh but uh we need to invest more
in those things than to keep on dumping
billions into build building data
centers for LM. That's that's that's
that's what I'm going to say. I was
thinking maybe if we can get some
funding for AI startups. U then that'll
happen.
>> That that that's a good way to do it.
Yeah,
>> I'm making a joke there. So
>> it's about the the main things that are
getting funding these days. Um
so
let's talk about open versus controlled
and uh
do you see open standards like NANDA? Um
how do you see that playing with more
the the the closed ecosystems that may
be required or enforced by say corporate
uh entities? you do you see there that
conflict or you see any uh way way to
solve the compatibility?
uh so I think the good thing is a lot of
the innovation and a lot of it is coming
from industry in this case uh both at
the protocol and uh infrastructure
aspect a lot of this is almost all of it
is open source if you think of it think
of MCP or A2A all of this is largely
open source which is great uh I think
these things need to be open source they
need to be collaboratively developed uh
that being said there are very
legitimate use cases and requirements
where things need to be private
protected sort of uh firewalled uh
access to critical agents uh cannot be
like you know open to everyone uh and I
think that's perfectly fine uh that's
how the current web also operates not
everything is open to everyone and this
uh uh should be accommodated uh so uh
for example when I was talking about our
uh thinking about interoperability and
registries. Uh the reason why we are not
thinking about building the one registry
for AI agents but more thinking about
building the switchboard is exactly this
because uh practically speaking it is
very legitimate for industry players to
have access to their own agent
registries and have control over who
accesses them versus who does not. But
when someone wants to go outside the
silo as Cyrus mentioned uh when someone
wants to interoperate with other agents
there should be a way for that to be
possible. So I think it has to be this
sort of pragmatic approach uh rather
than uh gunning for everything has to be
open. Uh so I think that's that's the
way forward.
Um Cyrus uh just to return back uh
before it it seems if I could paraphrase
what you said is that it at least at
Leela the with your customers the
agentic web is happening now and it's
happening because people are paying you
to do it which
it from a business point of view it's
great to have a market signal that that
that this is happening and it's it
bodess well for the future of agentic
systems.
in in in general, do you see other than
what we've mentioned here already, do
you see any killer apps or industries
where this will have the most return or
or things happening sooner? Is there any
projections that that forecast that you
can make in those or may maybe from IBM
and and your customers that you're
dealing with? Are there are there things
that you see happening sooner rather
than later?
Well, I think I spoke a lot, so I think
Dan should go first and I'll go after.
>> Yeah, I'm Yeah, I'm not seeing it yet.
So, I can't just say, "Oh, this industry
is like I Yeah, I can see this
happening." I mean, I'll go back to also
your previous questions about and I
agree with Puma about things will be
hybrid and in some you know sections
there will be a web and people will be
more sharing it and other others not. Um
I I think the big blocker is going back
two questions before is the privacy
issue, data privacy. Uh there's a whole
field in machine learning. It's called
federated learning. Um it's been doing
great academically. It almost had no
impact on business because at the end of
the of the day, you know, it was
supposed to be the kind of the story we
always tell healthcare and hospitals
will train their own models and they'll
share the models, but they'll keep the
data. Never happened. Um I think this
will still not happen. Um especially in
those industries, healthcare, banking,
things like that. Um but there could be
others where you know organization will
be willing to be more sharing but I'm
not like I can't point what would that
be.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. And to the your point about you
know what are the other big wins for
having uh agentic systems out in the
wild and being used by our customers I
can't speak for lots of other but in the
indust other other other verticals but
in the industrial vertical and the
manufacturing vertical um even within
there there's multiple uh use cases that
have proven at least in our experience
to be extremely beneficial for
customers. Uh we spoke about a little
bit about let's say um safety and so you
know it's not like an agent's going to
turn off the machine but we see our
agents doing things like um noticing
when there's uh people not following the
rules right there's some safety rules
that have to h happen in an environment.
So if our sensors see someone's not
following those rules you have to make a
very contextual decision on whether this
is something that needs to be noted or
not. So those kinds of decisions our
agents are making and that's turning out
to be extremely valuable. And so when
you ask any CEO of any manufacturer or
industrial, what's your number one
concern? I don't want anybody getting
hurt or injured on my watch, right?
That's actually often the number one
concern that we hear. So agents that can
deliver on that are going to be highly
desirable and will deliver lots of
value. Um especially because if you
think about safety, you have to the more
eyes you have on someplace, the safer it
is usually, right? So if you have visual
agents that can be everywhere that your
people can't be, that blankets it with
these uh many agents that are looking
for certain signals and and and that
creates safety. So that's a big one. The
other ones I think are uh agents that
are sort of like industrial engineers,
uh artificial industrial engineers,
artificial manufacturing engineers. So
they're looking at what they're seeing
and saying is is there a better way to
do this? Is there a more efficient, more
productive way of spending our time? And
so they can come back with
recommendations saying, "Hey, I noticed
that if you move this around and lay
change the layout, you could have people
walking 40% less per day and still
getting their work done without having
to walk so far. So that that kind of
stuff, those agents are are I think
going to be extreme. They've they've
already shown their value and the
customers want more of that. And the
last one is quality. So uh there's
there's a right way to do things that
can create good products. There's some
things that people do or even robots can
do that can create defects and create
quality problems and having agents on
the lookout for that and supporting
people and and uh giving them support
when they're maybe about to do something
that would cause a quality problem.
Those are things that are also really
really big. So those are the three
things that I've noticed that I think
agents if they're distributed and
working all over an organization can can
really deliver a lot of value.
>> Perfect. I I think in the the last
minute or two we'll just uh maybe open
it up for the audience. Are there any
burning questions that anyone has at
this point and uh wants to put it to the
panel?
>> Oh,
>> not really a burning question. I'm more
curious on what you what you mentioned
size. You said something about have
reached that peak in terms of contextual
you know reasoning or actually coming up
with an answer. You you also mentioned a
very thing which got me very curious.
You said something about
having other ways or other different
type of agents. People are already
working on it. I was more curious on
what you meant by that.
>> Yeah, sure. There's active uh work being
done on um
systems that can approach the same kinds
of problems that people are trying to
solve with language models but using uh
hybrids that include symbolic
representations and symbolic processing.
Uh you can call these neurosymbolic
models. And so these models are hybrids.
They're not stochastic and purely based
on tokens in tokens out but more uh
there's there's actually a word world
model inside of it that can have
different uristics and different kinds
of um learning uh pro processes and also
different kinds of inferial processes
that are not doing the same kind of
inference that LM do and they do develop
internal ontologies sort of automated
ontology building automated uh graph
building automated knowledge network
building so you still get the
scalability
But you als
Facebook's meta's emphasis on uh allin
on language models was never going to
achieve the uh type of intelligence that
Yan Lun who's been working in AI for 40
years or 30 years maybe but anyway he he
he sees a dead end and So he left
Facebook and Meta to found his own
company and do things in a different
way. So keep an eye on him and us and
others. There'll be other ideas. There's
many ways to get there. It's not there's
not only one way and I think the other
ways have a more likelihood of
succeeding than the current scaling of
LMS because as somebody said maybe you
said that you know there's there's no
more public data to find. So if you're
hoping to get better results from adding
another trillion words or another 100red
trillion words there are no more public
sources of that data to train on. So
then you say, well, okay, maybe our
algorithms can get better, but the
algorithms are incremental, right? Is
GPT5
order of magnitude better than GPT4? And
will GTP6 be? No, they're not. They're
incremental improvements, but they're
not that next order of magnitude. So I I
see the the wall being clear. And uh I'm
not alone in that uh in that in that
feeling right now.
>> Okay.
>> Not on this stage.
Well, I I think I just want to thank Dan
Cyrus Praduna uh and uh the whole panel
and also the audience for your
participation, but we're going to wrap
things up now and make sure you get out
and get your bag lunch before all the
good sandwiches are gone. So, uh let's
let's hear it for our panel.