so let's now turn to our panel of alums
so um maybe we can start by asking each
of you to introduce yourself um and
we'll do that uh maybe by asking you
what you did prior to joining MIT where
you went to school maybe what you
studied um if you did have full-time
work experience you can mention what
that is and then you could tell us a
little bit more about what you're doing
now um so we can just use this slide to
kind of go down the line so um ana would
you like to start great so hi everyone
I'm Anka um also like my full name is
anesti um I'm half French half Spanish I
studied mechanical engineering at
Imperial College London uh I didn't have
full-time experience but I did have some
internships so I worked at Tesla
Bloomberg Amazon um and then decided to
join the MIT mband program so I
graduated last year um I'm now an alumni
and I'm working as a machine learning
scientist at a startup in New York
that's called AR in Ai and they just do
like AI solutions for companies
essentially excellent
toet all right Emily you're next hey
everyone I'm Emily um like Ana I just
graduated from the mban program in
August um but before the mban I did my
undergraduate at um Cornell University
um I'm also from New York so this is my
first time living outside of New York um
before that I did not have any work work
experience but I did do an internship at
regeneron and now I am I I am a data
scientist at Dynamic ideas which is like
a um I guess you'd call it like a
boutique consulting
company excellent all right Angel your
turn hi everyone I'm angel I'm a current
student class of
2025 um I'm originally from shinen China
down south right next to Hong Kong so
prior to MIT um I work as a data
scientist at a Tech startup in Boston
area for one year focusing on real East
machine learning applications and before
that I did my undergrad at Bentley
University U with a double major in data
and math really nice to meet you all all
right thanks and
Britney um Thanks Jen hi everyone I'm
Britney I'm part of the mban class of
2023 um and before coming into the mban
I similarly came straight from undergrad
so I was doing my uh major in statistics
and minor in data science at the
University of Virginia and then since
graduating from the mban I'm in the
Washington DC area uh working as a data
scientist for
Visa all right well thank you for those
um introductions and sharing a bit more
about your background um to start let's
let's talk a little bit about the
community within um the business
analytics program and you know the
greater MIT Sloan community so you know
I recognize that you know as a as a
prospective applicant it can be quite
quite intimidating to think about
joining MIT the class profile you know
is very impressive you know you hear
these stories and see you know um
exposure of MIT in the media and it can
be you know um you know intimidating
especially as a woman to think about you
know um you know becoming a part of this
community that's um you know very
technical and very quantitative in
nature and you know sometimes not not
necessarily true but sometimes can be
stereotyped as you know this sort of
cold Cutthroat kind of place um so my
first question is can you talk about you
know your experience or how you were
able to um uh you know get yourself
involved in the community or the culture
at MIT Sloan and anybody can take
it I guess that could kick off so since
uh I have you know uh more current
experiences and I guess all of my fellow
and bance could jump in later um I know
that Jen mentioned that there there will
be a certain level of technical
rigorousness to the program but um I
would say don't shy away from the
technical nature and the challenges that
will be facing you um there's a very
strong community at M and also in the
bigger part of like outside of mben
could support you along the way so
definitely take advantage of you know
all kind of opportunities ask question
and seek out support to grow grow with
each other like within my um current
cohort there are people with a lot of
different mixture of background some
people are more you know their love and
good at theoretical math and some other
are programming Geniuses so definitely
lean on each other learn with each other
and benefit from each other's skill set
and grow with each
other I I think part of what we're
trying to um emphasize with students and
the way that you know the work is
introduced or expected to be completed
is that we bring people together with a
diverse set of skills and with
complimentary skills um and you know
together you know you have the tools to
succeed where you know if you were just
stick you know alone as an individual it
might be more difficult to develop all
those skills so maybe we could talk a
little bit about you know working with a
team of people on some aspect of the
program um where you had to work
alongside people who you felt were
really different from
yourself again anybody can I can speak
of it I know that um a lot of people
like you said then like they have so
many diverse experiences they come from
very different backgrounds whether
that's like their undergrad degree or
whether that's the country that they
were raised and like educated um in and
I feel like that really shows when we're
working working on group projects where
um you can see that some people are much
better at like brainstorming ideas and
like coming up with new Solutions other
are much better at like just being like
product driven and like implementing and
and driving driving like action and
others are more about like making sure
that everything's like quality-wise in a
good good State and I feel like all of
those contributions from different
people and different mindsets really
helps to like Drive even when we were
doing projects like drive a project
forward and really like make it
successful I would say like this program
isn't made for you to just come on your
own and like do it all on your own and
succeed on your own it's really about
like finding what are your strengths
what are your weaknesses how can you um
find people that complement those and
work together to achieving like really
good outcomes in work homeworks
whatever sounds great um could you talk
about you know an example of a memorable
you know course that you took or a
memorable story about one of the faculty
members that you know were um either
teaching or supporting one of the
initiatives you were involved
in um I'm just wanted to build on
something that like totally agree with
everything Angel and um ana have said so
far um I think that one of the best
examples of this is the aab and the
Capstone experiences of the mband that's
one of the reasons that the program is
so wonderful is that we actually get
real life opportunity to provide value
to organizations through analytics um so
in the fall students will have the
opportunity to team up in pairs or
groups of like three to four students
and they're partnered with a uh host uh
aab company so throughout the duration
of the semester they'll be doing a
project for that company um for me it
was working with Visa definitely um
helped me get to my current position um
and then of course there's the Capstone
experience where you have your uh
partner and you and your part are doing
a essentially like a summer internship
for a company that you're also partnered
with and so in both of those situations
you're working with you know ideally two
different companies you're working with
a small group of students in your cohort
um like you know Ana and Angel have said
you're working with students from many
different countries that's one of the
things that Drew me to mban is just the
pure diversity of background of the
cohort getting to talk to people who
have had different background
experiences and life experiences was a
lot of fun and really makes the
experience very Rich um but I think
those two project experiences basically
help us to translate whatever we've been
learning in the classroom um at slan
into you know real projects and I think
those really help uh to stand
out
excellent all right um you know maybe we
could talk a little bit about you know
some of the activities you may have
gotten involved with um as a student at
MIT Sloan so you know actually I have
another slide here here that talks a
little bit about um you know some of the
clubs that are focused on women's
initiatives at MIT I don't know if any
of you were involved in any of these
things but you know regardless whether
you are involved in any of the you know
women's specific organizations at MIT or
any organizations at all can you talk a
little bit about how you were able to
get more involved in the the Sloan and
MIT
Community um I could say something about
that yes and Mar SLO does have a v
variety of support system for women and
as we can show in here there are a lot
of dedicated clubs for like identity and
you know professional setting or um you
know just hobby based me currently I'm
involved with quite a different clubs
and I'm actually serving as the
president of community as swim so women
in management and we did a lot of fun
events throughout the year um like for
example weekly speaking series that we
go to Network and talk to excellent and
Brilliant women in different Industries
um not just in data science but also you
know like Consulting and business in a
lot of different domains but also I got
to meet some of the um
other like very achieved um slow needs
out there that are not just very data
scientist focused I met this uh person
from SDM who has been a tech like a tech
leader an engineer lead at earbus for 10
years and I met um like a women who's
also like a submarine officer so I
really got to meet a lot of people
outside of my original Bubble and uh we
enjoy a lot of fun event together two
weeks ago we have this orange wine
tasting event which is my very first
time legitimately tasting wine so um
there are a lot of fun events out there
and a very great supporting system um
making slow and and and such a welcoming
and inclusive
environment
excellent um all right let's um let's
switch gears and talk a little bit about
resources to support you and finding um
you know work or helping to support you
in your career so um our attendees may
have be familiar with this already but
we have a dedicated team of career
advisers that support with um that
support mband students from you know
having uh regular sessions we call them
career core sessions or you know
building the tools and the skills that
you need to set yourself up for success
for recruiting not just for the job that
you get after MIT but for ENT your
entire career and how to think about
kind of networking and emailing and you
know what it means to work in different
Industries um but we also have lots of
different industry clubs and lots of
different you know conferences and um
organizations across mit's campus that
helped to give you more exposure to um
to Industry through some of these
student run organization so um my first
question is can you talk a little bit
about how you may have worked um with
Tracy or any of our career advisers to
help support you in your career
search I can start um so like you said
we have like an amazing team of like
helping us with careers especially Tracy
um I remember that in fall semester they
really prepare you to just like get
ready for like career like applications
and stuff and in in spring semester um
and so that will cover everything from
like making sure that your resume is
like on point and like you're LinkedIn
and all of those like tiny things of
like how do you interact with someone
new like how do you present yourself
which can be can sound like very easy
things but when you actually get to the
moment um knowing having those skill
sets and like those tips and tricks
really help and make a difference um I
would say one of the biggest like like
one of the most helpful helpful things
for me um at MIT was the number of
networking nights that we had I think
I've never networked as much as
throughout MIT year which was really
useful in like getting to know people
getting to even if it's not like to
recruit like to work for them and their
company it's just getting to know what
they do and figuring out is that what I
want to do in the future and like is
that the path that I want to take is
that the industry that I want to work it
is this the the job that fits my needs
and skill sets um and so having that
opportunity to network with people
through like I don't know we had had
analytics nights we had Capstone um
events with companies just bringing so
many people together and giving this
that opportunity to talk and meet new
people was was really
amazing excellent anyone else want to
touch on any of the things they might
have gotten involved with or worked with
Tracy
on yeah Tracy is just the best like
cannot emphasize enough um she's given
us so much good advice like Ana said
about you know anything from you know
etiquette at career fears when talking
to recruiters to little tips and tricks
for your LinkedIn as we approach you
know more of the job search in the
spring so she's been super valuable um
throughout the program um in addition to
that I also wanted to add that MIT and
Sloan specifically have a very
supportive Network um especially with
alumni and so for example they've always
had these events such as slone's helping
slones or Sloan wide Career Fairs where
not only can you um interact with other
M bands but more or less you're talking
to salones from the MBA or the mfin so
other programs as well and um all
there's just this really supportive
culture at Sloan and that's something
that's really nice about it um in
addition to that any sloy or mban is
likely to you know be you know on a whim
able to do an informational interview
with you so if you're looking for jobs
or just exploring different Industries
in the spring or earlier uh most alumni
will just pick up the phone or hop on a
quick quick call with you so the culture
that we try to Foster at Sloan is really
wonderful and supportive and so
definitely take advantage of all of the
career opportunities at uh mban through
Tracy and that support but also the
wider Sloan Community can also be super
valuable awesome all right well now that
three out of the four of you have kind
of launched into your career can you
talk a little bit about you know
something that you learned during the
course of the program that you know have
has been able to help you to succeed in
the work that you're doing
today I guess I can start um so yeah I
work at Dynamic ideas which is one of
Professor brutus's companies um for
those of you that know don't know
Professor bruus kind of helped to found
this program so he has a big part in um
all things and ban um but something that
I find interesting with my day-to-day
like tasks is that I'm really getting to
apply all the technical skills that I've
learned throughout the year so all the
machine learning and optimization um
kind of getting to do both which is um
really cool but on top of that I'm also
um interacting with clients and stuff so
that kind of goes back to what everyone
was talking about with Tracy and the
networking events just getting
comfortable talking to people who might
be higher up or people from different
backgrounds and industries um so just
getting to apply both like the technical
and the soft skills in my job every day
has been really
rewarding great anyone else
I can go so in my case I didn't really
have any like business analytics data
science background at all I had come
from a purely engineering background um
and honestly this was the opportunity to
just discover a whole new world that I
hadn't been introduced to previously the
whole like business analytics data
science AI world and without this
program I would never have been able to
like get a job that get the job that I'm
in right now just because I didn't have
any of the skill sets required so for me
this program is really useful in just
getting getting getting you up to speed
with everything that's happening right
now especially now that like AI is just
like really really evolving super
quickly and it's hard to like keep up to
date with everything I think it's like
the perfect time to join join a pro pro
program like this um and it was super
valuable for me to be able to like just
even access the
industry
excellent all right so um you know
before we turn over to the audience Q&A
and I'll um ask you know if everybody
could type in their questions in the Q&A
and then we can um you know I can
moderate those questions live you know
the one last question I'd like to ask
each of our panelists is you know
sometimes at these events um of course
telling us a bit about your background
is important and it's um great to share
you know your background with with the
audience and perspective students but
there's never we're never able to
provide enough um you know enough to to
prospective applic about what do the
current students in the class look like
what are some of their backstories so
you know without naming names I'm hoping
that you know each of you could just
share um a story or a bit about a
background of another female student
that was in your class so you know you
could just share you know what was it
about this individual that kind of
impressed you and you know um any kind
of um you know background story where
they went to school where they worked
the country they're from you know any
anything that would be kind of relevant
to you know helping prospective
applicants to gain a better
understanding of who they might be
sitting next to in
class um and so you know um if if each
of you could just share like a tidbit
about you know one of your fellow um
slones so maybe Angel I'll start with
you yes a quite a lot of individual is
jumping to my mind it's very hard to
pick one I would tell you that um I
would say um this person e is one of my
closest friend in the program currently
and um she's graduated from chingua
University which is the best university
in China studying physics and math com
before uh joining MIT I am particularly
impressed by her um background as in
quite a lot of us do not share you know
like data signs or pure machine learning
um knowledge before the program he h
into this uh field to this program
without that background but so be
thriving so I'm like particularly
impressed by that and also I knew her
from her prior story as in uh industry
industry experiences she work in quite a
lot of different domain domains from
social media company to like fashion Etc
and how she being a man like maneuvering
through different industry and trying to
shovel down into the places where she
eventually wanted to be that's
particularly inspiring for
myself exciting thanks Emily how about
you um yeah this is also a hard question
for me and I can't say Ana because she
just introduced herself but um I guess
someone for me like early on that I
thought was like I guess inspirational
is um our classmate Julia so she had two
years I believe of work experience
versus I came straight out of college I
had like pretty much work experience
other than like an internship here and
there um and she was probably like one
of the most outspoken people in our
class and she really inspired me to you
know ask questions and like stand up for
myself like even if you might feel
scared to like ask questions to like a
important speaker or like a professor um
and on top of that just working in
projects with her or working on
homeworks with her she was really good
at um kind of thinking from a business
perspective like what is the impact not
just like the nitty-gritty technical
details um and uh I guess for someone
like me coming straight out of undergrad
it's good to collaborate with people
with different work experiences maybe
people that are older than me um yeah
awesome all right and
Britney yeah um I think in my class one
of my classmates definitely had an
unconventional experience they actually
had gone to undergrad studying pre
health and then had gone through medical
school so they actually did have a
medical degree um and decided to
transition totally into the world of
tech and data science and so I think you
know that's just one example of you know
even if you have very diverse
backgrounds of what you're studying if
you are interested in data science and
you think you could really work hard and
you know come to Sloan and um commit
yourself to it anything's possible and
they did amazingly in the program and
now are working at a biotech in uh
Cambridge so I think it's just one
example and they really enjoy it and can
even use their previous bio knowledge to
improve analytics in that field uh so
yeah just another example awesome and
Ana how about
you so I was thinking of a girl who came
from like a more complicated complicated
background like more family issues or
like the country where she originally
was from was having some struggles um
and what impressed me the most is like
despite having that more like not
unfortunate background but you guys know
what I mean just like not as an easy
path as other people may have she like
fought for herself and just like
achieved like aimed to achieve the
biggest thing like you could try to get
which is like an in uh an incredible
University in the US um like this one
like which is a really well-known uh
program and just getting getting getting
in like interviewing not being afraid to
like Aim High Reach High um and getting
through this whole year is just very
very impressive for me like what someone
can achieve um never be afraid and like
yeah awesome all right so now I'm going
to turn it over to the Q&A so I can see
a couple people are trying to use the
raise your hand function um we just to
keep things kind of streamlined we're
going to ask everybody type their
questions into into the Q&A and um and
then we'll do our best to get get to
everything so the first question is
about um does Sloan offer any type of
mentorship programs um through the
school and you know did anybody here get
involved in those and so did did anybody
here get involved in any of the
leadership coaching or mentorship
programs that
loan um there are a number of different
things you can get involved with from
the leadership Center through the career
development office and um as well as
swim which is the Sloan women in
management organization they have lots
of different kind of match making and
mentorship programs that you can opt
into um none of them are required but
there's lots of different um you know uh
opportunities to engage in mentorship
programs and then similarly you know as
an Alum with we will um be asking you to
kind of um you know volunteer to give
back to some of the current students um
the follow-up question to that was also
if there were any veterans here um and
their insights about using this program
to you know uh you know transition uh I
would assume to kind of uh a
professional experience I don't think we
have any veterans here but um you know
we certainly have had many veterans come
through our programs and use our
master's programs to kind of upskill and
you know create um more expertise in an
area that would allow them to transition
out of the military um okay so the next
question is do we consider students with
10 plus years of
experience um you know the simple answer
is this this program is really designed
for students who are pretty early on in
their career it's considered um you know
a master A specialized master's program
for people who have on average five
years or less of experience as I showed
before about um you know 80 % of the
students are actually coming directly
from undergrad in this program and then
the rest have usually you know two to
four years of full-time work experience
so um the the simple thing to think
about instead would be to do the
traditional MBA program with a focus on
business analytics we do have an A a
road map or kind of we call it a
certificate that you could focus on
within the MBA program or even possibly
an Executive MBA with a focus on
business analytics um all right so then
the next question is this is an
international student applying to MIT
and they're confused about applying
between the MBA and the master business
analytics program um and looking for a
little advice um what about you guys do
you guys have any advice to people
considering mban versus the 2-year
MBA um I'll say that from my experience
talking to students in the MBA program
they do have a few more years of work
experience and that's a lot of uh
they're bringing that back to the
classroom to share with their
perspectives with fellow students and
with professors and that's a big part of
the course content um whereas I think in
the mband as Jen said we're a lot
earlier on in our careers um and we're
coming here to learn the technical
foundation for what we can do later on
in our career um so that's a little bit
of a distinguishing Factor however I
will say that as part of the mbn program
we do get to take a lot of business
related electives in the spring so for
example many of the students in my
cohort really loved power and
negotiation or consumer Behavior digital
product management communicating with
data these are all classes that you can
choose to take in the spring if you want
and you get to interact with mbas you
get to learn from their experiences and
add to that classroom culture even as an
mband so um I would say if you're early
on in your career but still interested
in the business aspect mban is
definitely a good
option completely agree great answer all
right so the next question is focus on
Anka but I think um anyone here could
really comment on this is a pretty
common question we get about you know
coming from an engineering background
you know how did you best prepare for
the master of business analytics program
any classes or skills you might have
tried to develop prior to matriculating
um I don't know if you want I think um I
decided quite late late on in my degree
that I wanted to to do the mband program
so what I tried to do was in the final
year of my studies I I had the option to
take some electives and I tried to
tailor those a tiny bit more to what I'd
be studying at MIT so not exactly the
same but I tried to take some more like
statistical um courses numerical methods
um some more like introduction to
machine learning um even my like thesis
of end of end of year end of appro like
degree thesis uh was slightly um
tailored towards machine learning and
that gave me some like Head Start of
what I could expect from this program
and I think that was really useful um I
don't think I did much more apart from
that just like keep being curious and
like learn like wanting to learn about
new things maybe reading some papers
maybe reading um some textbooks I think
that's that's always useful for sure
great any other general advice about
preparation prior to joining the
program yeah go for it
Angel uh well after I got admitted and
then I reach out to some LOM Ana and
Emily and asking them for suggestion so
I'm going to quote whatever they told me
it said maybe some refresher on linear
algebra and also there are a lot of
great resources out there like Cera and
MIT open course where you can find
related content that can better uh
sharpen your technical skills like or
maybe even math like particular areas
that you found theode in yeah great
advice um all right so the next question
is um is this program suited for those
within interest within interests at the
intersection of data science and public
policy um and what are some of the
skills in this program that are
applicable to the public sector so um I
don't think anybody here is working in
um in something related to public policy
or at least not yet but we have
certainly seen over the years so this
program has um close to 10 years of
alumni at this point um we have
certainly seen people transition from a
more technical role to a more policy
Focus focused role later into their
career but you know typically you would
need to have that kind of solid
foundation of analytics or data science
first and then using that kind of
operational knowledge to then be able to
influence policy type of decisions and
um you know I know here at MIT there's a
lot of work uh being done uh with
generative Ai and policy as well as you
know things happening at the computer
science and artificial intelligence lab
it's called called Cale as well as the
schwarzman College of computing and a
lot of this work is very much in
partnership with government agencies and
you know policy that's um looking at
kind of the ethics of generative AI
among many other things how it's being
used in health care and other things um
so certainly there's exposure to this
type of thinking and um you know
opportunities to work potentially as a
research assistant in some of the space
um while a student at MIT but you know
for the most part we see people going
into kind of more traditional analytics
data science or Consulting type of roles
immediately after graduating and then um
potentially pivoting more towards a
policy type role
later um all right so what are some of
the ways in which the MBM program pushed
you out of your comfort zone um and how
did that help you to you know build
overall growth or helped you and your
overall growth so examples of you know
where you felt you were pushed out of
your comfort
zone I think for me I mean obviously
you're like pushed out of your comfort
zone in terms of technical aspects for
sure just like that is like every single
day with like new problem sets new
questions new projects you're always
like trying to think out of the bubble
and um and really like push to learn
like learning more uh but on top of like
the technical skills I think there's a
lot of like personal skills that are
also developed um I know like being
surrounded by so many people that have
so many different talents have achieved
so much already um it's very impressive
and there's this feeling of like wow I
also want to do amazing things and that
just kind of creates a creates um
environment where everyone's really
trying their best and trying like to to
do amazing things um and and for me
that's incredible also even I remember
we had um some classes where we were um
trained like we we were helped with our
like uh verbal speech and like
communication skills um I think that was
super interesting because I had never
taken one where I I received so much
feedback just genuine feedback on like
how can I um construct my sentences
better how can I answer um a question in
a like more solid um convincing way or
how can I transmit more confidence or
maturity and all of these things that um
was really was really interested and I
had never never really had the
opportunity to to like learn about
before
awesome I just have a quick question
I'll answer do we have Forte fellows in
the business analytics program and
unfortunately we do not the Forte fellow
program is really focused on the MBA
program but um we do have fellowships
available for um you know students who
apply to the business analytics program
they're limited um but there are some
merit-based fellowships available um all
right so
um the next question is about kind of
managing your time this is like the
million doll question we always asked
there's so many different things
happening how are you able to you know
succeed at everything and balance your
time among networking events community
events and coursework any advice for
that you know figuring out how to
balance your time or how to optimize um
what you're
doing I can start with this um something
I will say that was helpful for me at
least with managing my time is the fact
that at least in the fall semester all
the mband have the exact same schedule
so you're taking all the same classes
going to the same office hours whatever
um so something that was helpful for me
was getting into like study groups early
on and just like all of us we know the
same deadlines um and we can kind of
help each other solve problems um I
guess looking at different perspectives
like also helps to solve problems more
quickly um and then on top of that going
to office hours was really helpful
because sometimes you you'll just be
staring at a problem and you might be
kind of stubborn like me being like no
no no I want to figure this out but I
mean we have some great um PhD students
as our Tas that are always willing to
help and um they have different
perspective as well which is really
beneficial for um just like learning so
yeah great awesome um all right oh go
ahead no I was just gonna say one thing
I think a very important thing that I
learned too during my program is not to
get too like focused and stressed about
one particular thing like maybe a
homework assignment or an exam I know it
can be very very stressful because you
know those are the main things that are
related to grades and like when you're
in your University the only thing you
care about is getting a good grade uh
but at the end of the day I would say my
biggest recommendation is there's so
much that you can do in MIT and there's
so many opportunities whether it's like
um different like activities or meeting
new people or networking events or like
there's so many things even doing a um a
project with like a a professor or
whatever and my my my recommendation is
essentially make sure that prior like
you understand your priorities like what
do you want to gain out of this master
um what do you want to like discover
what do you want to learn about and keep
those as priorities and don't let some
like homework that you haven't figured
out 100% of it um like take up all of
your all of your
time good
advice um as an international student
how challenging was the job market
I mean I will um I can start by saying
the job market in general is challenging
it's not necessarily more challenging
for international students except you
know from our experience most of the
students that are international that
come to this to study with us and
business analytics are hoping to stay in
the United States at least for their
first role um and so kind of that on top
of you know a challenging job market in
general um can you know can uh be
stressed certainly but our career
development team is really dedicated to
partnering with you and helping to
support you throughout your entire
career search you know this past year
the graduating class um a little over
30% of the students went to Capstone
companies so that's um a great
opportunity for you to kind of get to
know the company and get a feel for the
organization and about 30% of students
went to Capstone Partners um for
full-time employment um and then another
15% or so also found jobs through um the
analytics lab class so that's similar to
Capstone you're able to expose um and
get to know a bit more about how
companies operate through um you know
the analytics class and the projects
that you work on within that class um
and you know uh there's lots of there's
lots of different paths that people take
but we do understand most students are
looking to stay in the US um and luckily
we are a stem certified program so that
allows you for you know up to 3 years
of um an ability to hold a Visa and work
in the United States but do our
panelists have any other advice or um
you know
suggestions no I would I would say um
you're definitely right like MIT has
really strong connections with companies
that that's mainly because they've
worked with them for like many years
through Capstone analytics lab um and
that just means that like these
companies really trust uh students that
come out of the mban program they have a
lot of a lot of mban alumni in in their
companies already so it's like very it's
much easier to just join their company
because you'll have people that have
gone through the exact same uh program
as you um and they'll just be more
they're just more willing to hire you
which is really nice and again there's
so much support like every time there's
a new job opening we're we're um told
about it we're informed we have the
opportunity to apply we can have a lot
of referrals to from previous alumni
which is very useful so I would say like
the job opportunities that we get are
amazing so don't stress about it a lot
of people are willing to are wanting to
stay in the US and definitely achieve
that um so yeah awes all right so um a c
one last question um that's been asked a
couple different times is always a
question I like to wrap things up with
is you know do you have a piece of
advice for you know people who um are in
the process of you know navigating the
application process or thinking about
which master's program to to attend so
anyone have any advice to share for our
audience
today I'd say that um if you're thinking
about applying to mband just be yourself
I know it sounds cheesy but really mban
really values diversity of background
whether that's like different countries
background of experience in terms of
whether you have work experience or not
background in terms of what you've
studied so just be yourself and let your
authentic um experience shine through in
the interview process I think that's the
most important thing and then also come
to MIT with an open mind because you're
going to meet so many inspiring
wonderful people from around the world
and you'll learn so much so just coming
in with an open mind and being yourself
I'd say that's the main
thing great advice anyone have anything
else to
add just don't be afraid to apply I know
it sounds it sounds easy but like I
remember myself back like two years ago
just being like there's no way like why
would I even apply they're never going
to take me like it's it's MIT but um
yeah don't don't not give you the the
opportunity like definitely apply you'll
see what what the results are later on
but you would regret it if you wouldn't
apply