There are a couple different kinds of
quantum computers. The most general is a
universal fault tolerant quantum
computer. In principle, this computer
can run any type of algorithm, quantum
or classical. But there only certain
algorithms that are known to exhibit a
quantum advantage. One example is Shor's
factoring algorithm. Shor's algorithm is
used to break public key cryptography.
For example, RSA encryption, a scheme
that's commonly used for secure
communications. The security of RSA
encryption is based on the premise that
factoring a large integer number into
two smaller prime numbers is a very
difficult computation for [music] a
classical computer to perform. So for
example, if you're dissatisfied with
your current level of security, just
double the length of your public key and
it will become exponentially harder for
a classical [music] computer to break
that encryption scheme. In contrast,
Shor's algorithm can perform the same
task with only a marginal increase in
difficulty as the length of the key is
increased.
Find your MIT moment. Visit
learn.mmit.edu.