All right, so let's get started. Let me
introduce our first speaker, Professor
Donna Freriedman. She is a professor at
MIT's chemistry department. And
recently, Donna has taken on the
responsibility as a faculty director for
the new MIT quantum initiative about
which she's now give us an overview.
Over to you, Donna.
>> Thank you um for that kind introduction.
and I'm really excited about the
opportunity to share some of the
directions that MIT is um pursuing in
the quantum space. So recently we
started cumit the MIT quantum
initiative. We had our official launch
event on Monday. I'll tell you a little
bit about the framing of this and how
we're thinking about developing our core
tools in quantum and connecting to our
broader community. And then I'll leave
um a bit of time for questions because
this is a new initiative and this is
something that I think we're pursuing in
a way that's a little bit different than
the other quantum initiatives that
you've heard of. So to start, and I
think that this is probably an audience
with some level of expertise in the
quantum space, but I'm going to take a
minute to frame out how we're conceiving
of the quantum space for cumit. And so
one way that we can think about the
quantum space is that quantum is
fundamentally a collection of tools. We
have quantum computers, quantum sensing,
quantum networks, quantum metrology,
etc. those tools in their development
have been um if anything superlative at
MIT and I'll talk a little bit about the
history and MIT's role and the present
and future and what we're doing during
this um brief webinar but what I want to
highlight here is that there are two
components to building up quantum one is
continuing with the tool development
building the best quantum computers in
the world I think that Will will talk
about that a bit next. Um, he has a
great uh he has some great progress on
building the best quantum computers in
the world and I think that you'll hear
other speakers talk about alternate
methods as well. Um, quantum sensing is
something where we take the fragility of
quantum states and the potential to
interact them and entangle them and use
those delicate states to measure the
world around us. This is something where
MIT also has tremendous excellence in
terms of building the tools. Um for
example, my colleague Pa Capillo wrote
the defining review in this field
framing the problem and she's done
elegant work um taking quantum sensors
into new regimes. Uh we have quantum
networks. I'll talk a little bit about
the network between MIT and Lincoln Labs
and quantum metrology is arguably older
than this second quantum revolution and
something that has been uh largely
reinterpreted as part of it which I
think is quite lovely. So I talked a bit
about the quantum tools here but I said
there were two components. There's the
component of building but then there's
the component of implementing. If we
think about tools in any form, the core
thing that we need is users and cumit is
very focused on building the interface
between the tool developers and the tool
users and thinking about this in a
code-design approach. So if we take for
example a quantum computer, what CUMA is
focused on is building for example the
connection between the hardware, the
error correction, the first layer of
quantum algorithms, the second layer of
algorithms which starts to connect to a
user problem and the external user. And
so if we think about this saying a
quantum computer for example will solve
a chemistry problem. If we only develop
from the core from quantum computers and
we don't also push in from the chemistry
side we're missing a huge part of the
equation and we're effectively missing
the value proposition. What cumit will
do is work with chemists work with
endusers in all spaces. Um, and I mean
that on the corporate end, on the
academic end, on the government end, um,
on the national security end, and think
about where there are problems where
quantum tools could create a
transformational impact and bring
together these lines of individual
users. And so by bringing uh teams
together, we believe that we'll we will
better understand the places where
quantum tools can change the world
around us. And this is a problem that in
a sense is perfectly suited for academia
because academia is an amazing place
where failure is a good thing. If we um
try 10 problems and only one of them
works, those other nine problems can be
really interesting research
publications. They add to our
understanding. And so the fact that
failure is in a sense success in the
academic frame really enables academics
to take on a lot of the high-risk um
work in this area. And this is something
I think is really promising for
partnering with companies that have
their challenging problems which can be
addressed by specific well-designed
quantum tools. Um I'll also briefly
mention uh the history of MIT. So,
arguably, I think you've probably heard
that we're living in the second quantum
revolution and that all of this work
comes out of the core idea that quantum
is a tool that can be used not just for
observation of the world around us, but
for control. Um, this is potentially the
place where the second quantum
revolution started. And this is a
conference at Endicott House. If you'd
like um to see the names of all the
participants, there's a QR code in the
bottom corner of the window that you can
use and that will give you all of the
names of the human participants, but
sadly not the dog. Um, and so this is
MIT. MIT started the second quantum
revolution. And I would be remiss if I
didn't mention that MIT is at the
absolute frontier of the second quantum
revolution 40 years later. We are
leading in translation. Um I think that
I've picked these companies very well
considering the other participants of
the webinar. One of the notable
successes of quantum is using quantum
sensors to sense gravitational waves.
For example, we have um a quantum
network between MIT and Lincoln Labs
which I believe is 43 km. And between
MIT and Lincoln, we are really pushing
the field forward. And so this amazing
collection of scientists is very well
poised to start to develop these
connections with end users.
I'll also note that a big project at MIT
that I won't talk further about is
developing a physical home for quantum.
And this is something we're looking at
in building 39 to have a physical code
space. And this is something where we're
broadly interested in partnerships. Um
not sure when my talk started. So I
am going to end by briefly talking about
the structure of cumit. And I think this
will be a good transition to Will who is
an integral part of cumit. So the way
that we've structured this is in a very
toolbased way. We've um because we're
MIT we have the world leaders in every
area and so each quantum pillar is a
tool. We have quantum sensing where Pala
Capillo who is one I mean world expert
in quantum sensing both on the tool
development side and on integrating with
end users. Her work has been so
thoughtful and deliberate. I don't even
know what to say about Will. just
absolutely one of the world leaders in
quantum computing and you'll hear from
him next. Um CQE um is will lead CQE
which is transforming into one of our
quantum pillars and I'm sure he'll talk
about um his amazing contributions
there. We also have Vlad and Vulletak
who um I think you might hear about with
uh Quer
Cuer
um and
Pablo's work on materials for quantum is
unmatched and then of course we have a
Lincoln lab liaison because any quantum
program at MIT would not be complete
without Lincoln which is a huge
component of MIT's quantum footprint and
uh Jon Yoder is our liaison there and
she's been absolutely amazing at making
sure that our work is coordinated with
Lincoln. Um so with that I think I will
conclude and thank you for attending and
open the floor to questions.
Thank you very much Donna uh for this
wonderful overview and uh we definitely
want everyone to type your questions.
This is the right time and so I will get
started. Um
Dana, so could you talk about um what
kind of companies that you are looking
for as a as a let's say ideal partners?
Is there US company? Is it okay non US
company? Is there any specific sectors
that you're looking for? We're looking
for broad participation both on the tool
development and so there you can think
about partnering directly with quantum
computing companies. um you know for
example working directly with a quantum
computing company on um
algorithms and algorithm end users is
something that we've been pursuing
lately thinking about how we can create
these lines from hardware all the way to
users. Um that's a great example of the
type of partnership we could have with a
quantum computing company. Also, we're
interested in partnerships as they
relate to the physical space. Um, but
we're also interested in developing
these end users. We're very interested
in working with companies that have
challenges were um quantum computing,
quantum sensing, etc. can address these
challenges. companies um you know closer
to my own space as a chemist in the um
pharma space and the chemical design
space where there are key bottlenecks
where today's tools cannot solve these
bottlenecks. We'd like to work with
companies to identify the problem and
take a code approach that goes from um
challenge to implementation. And we
think that this is a truly perfect time
because quantum is as the title of this
webinar says um it's at a point of
acceleration. This is a transformational
moment in quantum.
Wonderful. So another followup question
is that uh for companies who is now
interested in developing talents uh
build up capabilities but they are not
ready to invest in millions or you know
100 people on those what advice you
would have for them to start up uh maybe
take the first few steps and working
with MIT how MIT can help those kind of
companies
>> um you know I don't know if Will will
cover this but there is um an education
program that will um has been
instrumental in um that I think expro is
the uh correct term um and I think that
that would be a great starting point
engaging on that education level.
>> Wonderful. Thank you. Uh so we have a
question here. Let me just uh read out
to you. Um, so this is from Steve Bush
and I am a end user. What can you say
about the lack of good benchmarks for
scientific computing applications?
Um, I will admit I don't fully
understand the question. So I think that
um, but I'll interpret it in the way
that makes sense to me. So I think that
it's it's really tough to have
benchmarks, right? because you're both
developing algorithms and you're
implementing them. And so I think that
um and so you might be referring to the
fact that a quantum computing algorithm
can be highly successful um and then a
classical algorithm can take it over
because nobody developed the right
classic algorithm. And so this is
something which is um part of
ongoing development finding the right
algorithm and finding the questions that
really can't be answered classically and
I think that there's a huge space there.
Um
I think almost I'm not sure
I'm not benchmarking is really important
but I think if you identify a problem a
quantum computer can solve it and it
wasn't solvable before maybe it doesn't
matter as much if there would be a way
to solve it otherwise if you put in you
know 10 times as much effort. I think
being able to figure out what the
problems are, finding the right path to
solve them expediently
is the core goal. Um, and my apologies,
benchmarking is a broad category. So, I
hope I got a bit of your question.
>> Yeah, wonderful. Thank you, Dennis. So,
the next question is about storage of
data. So today uh you know we still
storing data in binary format and now uh
for the compute side where we use
quantum cubit format. So the question is
why don't we use this the cubid format
in storage as well.
Um the shortest answer to that is um
coherence time. And so I I think that um
maybe a broader answer is more
appropriate which is I don't think
quantum computers are ever going to
replace classical computers. This is an
area w which will be developed in
parallel right and so quantum computers
will be used to solve certain problems
where a quantum computer is the best
tool.
Right now for data storage, classical
computers are the best tool. And I think
that for any application of a tool, you
use it where you need it, but you don't
apply it where you don't need it.
Perhaps AI is a good example of this uh
that we've seen in our everyday lives.
Sometimes um it's the right tool.
sometimes um
it hallucinates 20 references and is not
the right tool and quantum and AI in a
way have very little in common but the
same framing of use the tool that you
need.
>> Thank you. I think our time is up so
thank you very much Donna. Thank you.