We're here at the Harvard University
Botney Library looking at a first
edition of Robert Hook's Microraphia
published in 1665. This is the first
book to show the microscopic structure
of materials and it has a number of
remarkable drawings in it. One of the
main themes of material science is that
the properties of materials are related
to their structure and so being able to
see the structure at a microscopic scale
is very helpful. Here in this
illustration is a drawing of sponge. And
when we look at the scanning electron
microraph, we see that the structure is
remarkably similar to what Hook has
drawn. It's interesting to see today the
images we see in a scanning electron
microscope at a similar magnification to
those that Hook saw in his optical
microscope. And it's remarkable to see
how many of the features that we see in
these much more fancy microscopes that
he was able to capture in his drawings
with his simple optical microscope. Find
your MIT moment. Visit learn.mmit.edu.