Okay, good morning everyone and good
afternoon and good evening for those of
you who are joining uh via live stream
remotely from other regions. Uh this is
Mickey Kato uh program director at
office of corporate relation OCR. Uh
today I am a host of this health science
forum together with my colleague program
data Sher. Sher please stand up say
hello. Thank
you. Okay. And
uh as you may know this is a landmark of
uh located at Kendall Square. I'll
briefly explain about this unique MIT
innovation ecosystem.
There are five important element on this
ecosystem. As you can see our OEARD
office of cooperative relations connect
university which is MIT and
entrepreneurs which is uh MIT startup
exchange program member startups and
large corporation which is ILP member
company
together and MIT has five school and one
college and life science research uh
intensively uh research at various uh
department and schools. For example, at
the school of science, department of
chemistry and the department of biology
and school of engineering, a department
of chemical engineering and department
of biological engineering and
electronical ECS, electronic engineering
and computer science and Schwartzman
College of Computing. uh we have uh
computer science and artificial
intelligent lab which is called
Cale and media lab at school of
architecture and planning. This is just
an example that many researcher
conducted broadly at
MIT. So MIT campus exist over 65
research laboratory and centers and
programs. Many are life science related.
About $840 million sponsored
research research expenditures and about
20% come from industry including a
member company and many patent filings
every year. MIT was ranked number two in
the US university patent granted uh last
year. Uh this ecosystem uniqueness is
shown in this map. Uh as you can see
everything is uh located in walking
distance. You can see uh red color
circle. The largest circle is 15 minutes
walking distance from MIT dome. If you
not try please walk you can do
it. So it's very convenient everything
connected tightly. And another aspect
you can see this pink color name shown
here. There are many uh located life
science related companies in this area.
Not only large corporation but also uh
startups. This is a ILP member
portfolio. Over 200 large corporation
are ILP member. Now 30% North America,
20% Europe and 40% Asia and Pacific. As
you can see there are many life science
related IP member companies. uh today we
invite uh member candidate company as
well. So those of you who consider to
join uh please contact to each regional
program directors. So program directors
uh please stand up uh only sharing now
sorry
okay and Yuri okay please contact teun
is Korea and Yuri for South America.
Yeah. And OR has two programs, ILP and
startup exchange program. Startup
exchange program intensively connect
startups to industry members for their
business development and more than 800
startups are registered as of today and
many are life science related. Today the
presenter we invite uh four startup for
pitch lightning pitch and also one
startup at the poster
session. Uh today health science forum
uh covers broad scope of category.
Number one advanced diagnostics number
two optimized biommanufacturing process
for cell and gene therapies. Number
three, Noel drug delivery system. Number
four, AI and machine learning for
biomolecular modeling. Number five,
pressure medicine for cancer uh
treatment. And today we have five
faculty members talk for these five
categories and four startup lightning
talks for these five categories as well
as poster session by postdocs and
student and startup and poster session
will be held during at lunchtime at this
next uh room this side. So please enjoy
uh chat with uh presenters of posters
while having lunch.
uh just a logistics issue. Uh please ask
question after each speaker's talk. Uh I
we will use microphone. Uh today we
don't use pigeon hole. So please raise
hand. We deliver mic. So please ask bab
and for those of you who who join deot
you can ask question uh by using Q&A
button on the zoom app.