welome welcome thanks for the interest
we look forward to uh getting to know
you and uh having you here and working
with you in the future my name is Alex
I'm an associate professor in the
operations research group as well with
Hara and and many others and uh I teach
I've been teaching in this program for
six years now uh which doesn't make me
sound too young um I was teaching
analytics Edge for three years at first
and now I'm teaching uh the optimization
course
uh so roughly speaking I'm going going
to talk a little bit at a higher level
about what we try to do in the program
and what what what I teach um uh
contributes to the program what I do in
research contributes to the program and
that really has to do with this overall
diagram that youve probably seen um
several times which is the the overall
pipeline of analytics from data to
models to decisions to impact and value
and uh and really we we're thinking
about three steps of analytics here
right the all of the descriptive
analytics the data management the data
visualization the dashboards that try to
get us like a sense of what our our data
what do we what do we have visibility
into um what do the data tell us what
seems to be the case what's going on
what's Happening um which was really the
focus of analytics in the 2000s early
2010s um which is still the case of like
many data made many data science
organizations because you know data
quality is an important thing um and
then we'll move we're moving from
descriptive to productive analytics
where we're trying to get insight into
what's going on and why is something
happening and what's going to happen in
the future and so that's really the
world of machine learning that uh that
we're all accustomed to by now um and
that is Al maybe the data science of the
2010s and early 2020s uh where more and
more organizations are building a very
deep analytics team with machine
learning engineers machine learning
scientists with data scientists data
science engineers and so on so forth um
what what what we pride ourselves um at
Sloan is to close the loop and go all
the way to the prescriptive analytics
which is kind of what should we do about
it right and it's not only a question of
what does our data tell us about today's
system and tomorrow's system it's also
how can we impact the system to steer it
into a better Direction um to steer it
into a world of higher value higher fact
World cost better efficiency better
customer service and whatever your
objective is um and this is really where
optimization starts playing a role and
that's why we have designed the
curriculum around machine learning and
optimization as the two main
pillars so I have been teaching
optimization for three years um this is
an example of that pipeline in action um
so I was talking about descriptive
predictive prescriptive analytics just
one company one example of um like that
entire pipeline over time for that
particular example which is UPF um and
at UPS um they started oops sorry they
started um putting together a
um an interesting communication device
that was called diad that was just
trying to coordinate the action of all
of the drivers in their Fleet using
mobile uh mobile devices so uh like
really old school operations I why this
is doing this I
apologize um really old school
operations where a centralized
dispatcher would start calling people
saying hey next you go there next you go
there next you go there and then when
they started doing that they realized
wow there is a lot of value associated
with centralized control Fleet
optimization Fleet Management and
routing optimization the problem is that
this is really really hard to do for
many reasons one is that we don't really
know where people are two we don't
really know what are all of the
components of demand and travel times
and three even if we know it's really
really hard to optimize this is an
example of a very difficult optimization
problem vehicle routing optimization
where even if you have perfect
information you have so many possible
decisions to make that it's completely
unfathomable to the human brain and even
easy algorithms cannot handle that easy
or existing algorithms cannot really
handle that at scale um to deliver the
value that is needed um because you're
evolving into complex temporal and
spatial Network what you do at noon
impacts what you can and cannot do at 6
PM what you do in uh in the in in the
Bronx impact one you can canot do in
Manhattan and so all of these things are
interconnected and so you need to
optimize so many decisions all at once
and that's really where the algorithms
and optimization can help make better
decisions and so here is what happened
at um at UPS in the 2000s they started
putting telematics which is events of
sensors in their trucks to have
real-time visibility into where people
are and what they are doing then package
flow technology which is a prescriptive
analytics um um software of you know
machine learning to predict travel times
and predict customer demand and then
they built on top of that this um tool
called Orion which is onroad integrated
optimization Network or something like
this um that is doing the routing
optimization and the centralized
um an exceptional research development
and um deployment project to 10 years uh
and resulting in very significant
savings both in terms of monetary
amounts but also in terms of uh carbon
emissions um and um and so what is also
interesting in this example is that uh
and there is a paper that I use in in
teaching that we can discuss in in the
future but um but basically
we tend to think as as data scientists
as that really the technical part being
really what is what is important where
you have you need to do the research you
need to do the development you need to
do the it systems what is interesting
over there is that the research was 10%
of the time 10% of the cost okay so what
else 20% development what what is that
it's basically integrating our
algorithms with the it systems having
end to end pipelines which is something
that you're going to do a lot of as well
to just make sure that things work in
production work in an automated system
okay but what about the remaining 70%
deployment change management working
with people making sure that they adopt
the tool how they adopt the tool when
they adopt the tool when they do not how
they use it as a decision support system
and so they have done amazing work to
kind of ensure that integration um one
of my favorite examples is actually
creating a video game where a driver
could compete with the tool understand
where they were making different
decisions and and then they would all
analyze the data from the video game
simulation so they could improve the
tool on the one hand but also convince
the drivers that the tool was making
better decisions sometimes um all right
so this is uh this is one example of
what we are aspiring to do in each
organization that we are um involved
with um and at our level to start with
we need to to learn optimization so this
is what the what the course will be
about so this is one of the core courses
in the in the program uh the
optimization class that I'm currently
teaching with with the current cohor uh
so we're trying to do that we're trying
to do that by developing models that
enable to translate uh practical
problems into mathematical models that
are tractable and amable to analysis so
linear optimization integer optimization
nonlinear optimization and
whatnot um we are going into algorithms
how do these methods work um what
solvers are available how do they work
what is doable versus what is really
really hard and what do we do when the
algorithms are not enough and how can we
create our own algorithms to do better
and then we're also getting into um
practical um practical implications uh
including uh you know how to build
models that are most relevant to
decision makers how to use them ASC
decision tools and what does
optimization tell us in terms of how we
should manage our systems
better the the the plots at the bottom
uh show us the sheer Improvement in
hardware and software techn Oles today
we are in in a world where a lot of
problems that were un unimaginable not
so long ago now are solved routinely in
practice um and that is unable that is
really unlocking the capabilities of the
world of optimization in a way that is
um uh that is inspiring exciting because
it creates a lot of
opportunities uh and so I do a lot of
that in my research um let me jump here
directly so I have um three main areas
of research that active at this point
one is in urban Mobility um um the other
one is in decarbonization and the last
one is in Social good so my um Urban
Mobility I I look at microtransit in
particular so how to create design and
operate systems that are hybrid between
Transit and right sharing what does that
look like how to design it how to op
operate it how to optimize it right so
how to make Transit more flexible or uh
and how to use high capacity Vehicles as
compared to um Uber lift es DD and other
things um in the world of
decarbonization two projects that we
have active at the moment are one
project on the operations of electric
trucks um and one project on and one
project on the uh operations of Cloud
Supply chains in particular Big Data
Center so this is a collaboration with
Microsoft um and then uh in um social
good we had we did one project vaccine
allocation I can talk more about this as
well we have one project on Wildfire
suppression and one project on organ
transplantation and all of them are
basically some uh resource large scale
resource allocation over time and over
space in order to move people from place
to place deliver Goods to people um
deliver data to people in data centers
but also perform Mission critical
activities like providing organs
providing vaccines or suppressing
wildfires
so this is an example of a project that
we did in the midst of the pandemic
actually in January 2021 so very very
hectic project at first where we were
optimizing for the incoming ban
Administration uh where to locate the
vaccin vaccination centers and then how
to distribute vaccines for like what it
was called at the time the 100 million
vaccines in a 100 day campaign for the
first three month of the administration
and then trying to Pro to get a sense of
who would get vaccinated as a result and
what the death fall of the pandemic
could be the objective being then to
minimize the death to of the pandemic uh
by optimizing the location of the
vaccination centers and what the what
the the chart on the right is telling us
is that the propos strategy was
improving the efficacy of a vaccination
campaign by 20 to 30% as compared to
just having something simple that is
let's put vaccination centers where
there are a lot of people or where there
are a lot of cases we can actually do
better than that and so optimization
matters in that case optimization can
turn one vaccine into 1.2 or 1.3
vaccines if you if you manage your stock
pile effectively so that was that's one
example of what we've been doing where I
can talk way more about it uh of course
I look forward to uh see you soon on
campus