The GVAS study aims to perform the
largest sequencing project to date of
individuals with SCAD. We are working
together to create a research community
of individuals highly motivated to
investigate the genetics of SCAD and set
the foundation for future research. This
community is enhanced by the
contributions and partnership from the
ICAD registry and SCADAD Alliance which
also aim to better understand and
support patients with SCAD.
>> We invite members of the SCAD community
to join the GVAS research study and
share it with others.
>> Your partnership will be key in
understanding why SCAD happens and how
it can be prevented and treated.
>> Visit gvasstudy.org
to learn more and enroll into the study
and visit scadalliance.org. org to find
resources and support groups for members
of the SCAD community.