So last time we defined canonical forms
of a linear program
and
they're maximize
cranspose X where these are vectors.
with such that are sorry subject to
ax is less than or equal to b
and x is greater than equal to zero.
And the duel for the canonical form
duel
we showed was minimum
B transpose Y. So we've taken the right
hand sides of the equation and turned
them into the objective function.
A transpose Y
is greater than equal to C. So we've
taken the objective function of the
primal
and turned it into the right hand side
of the equations of the duel and y
greater than or equal to zero.
And last time
we showed weak duality
for any
feasible X
in the primal and any feasible Y in the
dual solution. Now feasible just means
they satisfy the constraints.
Um
cranspose x is less than or equal to
branspose
y.
Um
so this is true
for
when the optimal value is
um finite.
So a linear program
can have
finite optimum
It can be infeasible.
What's an infeasible program?
Um, x1 greater than equal to 5 and x1
less than equal to three. So this is a
basically trivial example of a
infeasible program. there are no
solutions and most infeasible programs
it's much harder to you know you cannot
tell that it's in feasible just by
looking at it and it can be unbounded
and let's give you an example of that
maximize x
x greater than 3
okay you can see that
you know you can find a visible x such
that has any value for the objective
function and um so these are actually
it's pretty clear that these are the
only three possibilities.
Okay.
Now I'm going to tell you
well something that follows immediately
from weak duality. If the primal is
unbounded,
the duel is in feasible.
And that's because if there were some
feasible solution to the duel, then you
could find a solution to the primal
which is larger than that.
And this is a contradiction of weak
duality. And similarly, if dual is
unbounded, the primal isn't feasible.
And there's one more possibility.
Possible
dual
primal
are
both
invisible.
So, this doesn't happen very often, but
it can happen and you probably should be
aware of it.
We're not going to discuss it any
further. Sometimes we give a homework
problem asking you to find an example
where these are where this is the case.
And it's not that hard a homework
problem. So if you want to figure out
how this can happen, you can go home and
you know figure it out or you can
probably look it up on the Wikipedia and
find it that way.
So
okay.
So what first thing I want to do today
is talk about
um
what the primal and dual look like for
things that are not in canonical form.
And
I'll first give you the
treatment in the lecture notes and then
I will give you my own treatment which
is slightly well it's not really
different but it's slightly different
and I think it makes it easier
but
so let's look at a proof of duality.
Um,
maybe I should
do this by example because I like doing
things by example because it's easier
than [snorts] sometimes it's easier than
doing them abstractly. So let's say max
3x1
+ 5 x2 - 2 x3.
Um, x1 + x2 less than or equal to 8.
X1 - X3 is greater than or equal to 1
and X2
plus
Okay, I did this wrong.
I want to leave a gap here so you can
line up the variables.
Greateral 1
and x2
+ x3
= 4.
Recall
proof
of duality.
The duel has a
variable for each constraint in the
primal and a constraint for each
variable in the primal. Dual
each
time the variable.
Oh, I'm sorry. I left out the
um non- negativity conditions. X1 and X3
are greater than equal to zero and X2 is
unconstrained.
So there's a
um dual variable
for each primal constraint.
Good.
And now what we did
was we um
took this
equa the inequalities multiplied them by
the new
variables in the duel and added them up.
So we have y1
* x1 + x2 is less than equal to 8.
y 2 *
x1
- x3 is greater than equal to 1.
Y3
times
x2 + x3
= 4.
Okay.
And when we add them up, we want these
variables to or we want these
inequalities to all point the same way
because if we add, you know, x1 + x2
less or equal to 8 and x1 - x3 greater
than equal to 1, it doesn't tell us
anything. So that means that here we
have to have y1 greater equal to zero.
Here we want to flip the sign of this
inequality. So we need y2 less than or
equal to zero. And here
well it doesn't matter whether y3 is
bigger than or less than equal to zero
because when we multiply it there'll be
an equality and when we add them all up
it'll still be the right inequality. So
here we have y3 unconstrained.
[applause]
Okay.
So going from
a less than or equal to sign and the
primal if the primal is a maximum
maximization gives you a positive
variable. A greater than equal to sign
if the primal is maximization gives you
a negative variable and an equal sign
gives you an unconstrained variable.
Okay.
So now
the um
and the
we remember we wanted to maximize 3x1 +
5 x2 - 2x3. So the first column
gives you
y1 + y2.
um
is greater than or equal to three.
The second column gives you y1
+ y3
is greater than or equal to
um five.
Is that right?
And the third column
gives you
-
y 2 + y3
is
- y 2 + y3 is greater than 2
um minus 2.
So these are the constraints of the
duel.
And similarly when you're going from the
dual to the primal everything works the
same way except
less than or equal to sign greater than
equal to signs turn into positive
variables. Less than equal to signs turn
into negative variables. And again equal
signs turn into unconstrained variables.
So, I don't like doing it this way.
Yeah. You have a question?
>> Oh, should yal?
>> Yes. Yes, it should. y1 + y3 equals 5.
Thank you.
Okay.
So, what what was I going to say? I was
going to say the reason I don't like
this is it gives you negative variables
and negative variables are hard to think
about and um when you're thinking about
them you're liable to make mistakes. So,
what I'm going to do is I'm going to um
yeah,
another way to take the tool.
First
make
all
equations
the correct
less than equal to or greater than equal
to the correct sign. So here what we
want to do is we want to take the second
equation and turn it into a less than
equal to sign because if we have a
maximization
and canonical form
you want less than equal signs. So that
turns into
3x1
+ 5 x2 - 2 x3
subject to
x1 + x2 less than or equal to 8
- x1 + x3
is less than or equal to minus1. X1
and X2 + X3 = 4.
And
I forgot to write down
X1 X2 greater than or equal to zero.
X3
no. X1 X3 greater than or equal to zero.
X2 unconstrained.
So now we can just you know write this
off. We take the transpose of the A
matrix which is
Y1 - Y 2
Y1
+ Y3
and Y2 + Y3
um
X
X2 was unconstrained. So this is an
equality
and x2 and x x3 and x1 both had greater
than equal to signs. So these are
um
less than or equal to signs.
the minimum
because the original the primal was
maximization, the dual is minimization.
And we just read off the right hand
sides of the
equations inequalities and we get 8 y1 -
y 2 + 4 y3.
And
we called this w. Not that it really
matters subject to
these things. And we take the
um original
objective functions and use it for the
right hand side. So 3 5 and minus two.
And finally
the third equation was an inequality. So
y1 y 2 gal to zero. and y3
unconstrained
and we don't have this
um hard to think about variable y2 less
than equal to zero.
So this is the way I like to take duals.
Okay. So the next thing I want to do is
talk about complimentary slackness.
Any questions about the material so far?
Okay.
And um
complimentary slackness. We are going to
um
well why don't I write the theorem down
and then we'll prove it.
So again, we're going to have two linear
programs and
we're only going to prove it for the
we're going to prove it when the linear
programs are in canonical form. But in
general, you know, it's true for any
linear program.
Um,
suppose
X is a feasible solution in the primal
and Y is a feasible solution in the
dual.
Then
X
is optimal
in primal
and
Y is optimal in dual.
If for all I either
y i = z
or a subx
i = b sub i. So this is either saying
the i variable in the duel is zero or
the i equation in the primal is
satisfied with equality.
And
for all J
either
X subj= Z or
A transpose Y
J = B subJ. So this is saying either the
J variable is zero or the J equation in
the dual.
Okay, this is not B, this is C.
Either the J equation and the J variable
is zero or the J equation in the dual is
satisfied with equality.
Okay.
So we'll prove it
and we'll only prove it for or rather we
will prove it for um
linear programs in the canonical form.
But because it's true for linear
programs in the canonical form, it's
automatically true for all linear
programs.
There's no reason you have to prove it
for an arbitrary linear program and it's
just extra notation.
Okay, so we should write down the
programs in the canonical form and um
maximum
Z = C transpose X
A X less than equal to B X greater than
equal to zero. This is the primal and
the dual is the minimum
w=
bpose y.
A transpose y = c is less than equal to
c
and y greater than equal to zero.
Okay. [clears throat]
So, what we have is
done.
Well,
we have a transpose y is less than true
c.
So let's start with cranspose x. And now
let's plug this equation into here.
Cranspose x is less than or equal to
well cranspose is yrpose a. So this is
yranspose a x.
Now yrpose ax is equal to yrpose
ax
because the matrix multiplication is
associative
and we have ax less than equal to b. So
this says is less than equal to y
transpose b.
So this is just
weak duality.
Suppose
both of these
both lesser equal to signs hold with
equality.
Well, then we know that for this to be
optimal, they these signs need to be
hold with equality. And if this holds
with equality,
well
then
um
let's rewrite this equation. yrpose A
minus C
X = 0.
Oh, this should be cranspose.
And let's rewrite this equation.
That's just
ypose
ax minus b equals z.
Okay.
So if we have two dotproducts of vectors
are zero and each of these
vectors contains only positive entries
then and every
every piece of the dotproduct one of
these two equals zero.
So y transpose i = z or
um
a x
sub
i equals b sub i.
And here it's just the same thing.
Either x j equals z or
Y transpose A J
transpose A
subj equals
C transpose J.
So this is one way of the ine equality
of the inequality. Now suppose the other
way holds that means either XJ equals Z
or YRPOSE a J= CJ. Well that means that
this product is zero which means that um
this is an equality. And similarly on
this side
if either this equals Z or this equals Z
then this dotproduct is zero. And that
means that this is an equality. So
cranspose x equals yrpose b which means
that the
um
that you know cranspose x and yrpose b
are optimal solutions.
Okay.
Now I want to go back here and
tell you something neat you can do with
complimentary slack.
Okay.
So
x1 = 4
x3 = 4 is a
feasible solution,
right? Because
4 + 4 less than or equal to 8
- 4 + 4 is what?
Um,
x1 + this is an x2, not an x3.
4 + 4 is less than 8.
-4,
I forgot. x3 = 0
-4 + 0 is less than equal to -1.
And 4 + 0 = 4.
So this is a feasible solution. And in
fact, it's the optimum solution.
And if you know it's the optimum
solution to the primal, you can use
complimentary slackness to find the
optimum solution to the duel.
So here we have two variables which are
not equal to zero which means we have
two equations
which are
satisfied with equality. So that means
that we must have
um
so the two variables which are not equal
to zero are the first and the second
which means the first and the second
equation are satisfied with equality. So
y1
= y2
okay I hope I'm doing this right.
No, I'm not doing it right because I
this equation is y1 - y2 is less equals
= 3. So y1
- y2 = 3 and y1
+ y3 = 5.
Now there's up here there's an equation
which is not satisfied with the equality
and the um
and the optimal solution. That's the
second equation which means y2 equals z.
And now you've written down these three
equations
and there are three unknowns so you can
solve it. And so y1 = 3 and y2 = 5.
And now you can plug this in and see
whether
this
equation for the primal and this or this
feasible solution for the primal and
this solution for the dual give you the
same
objective function. So let's do that. we
have x1 + x2 is 3 * 4 + 5 * 4 that's 32.
So objective function
and down here we have 24.
Okay, y1 = 3. I obviously did my
equations wrong. Y1 = 3 and Y Y Y Y Y Y
Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y 2 = 0. So
Y1= 3. And we have 3 + Y3 = 5. So Y3 =
2.
Apologies for my arithmetic.
So that means that we have
24 + 8 is 32.
Objective function equals 32.
So these
so this is an optimal solution for the
primal and this is an optimal solution
for the dual.
Okay.
So the last thing I want to do is give a
I don't know if I'm going to call it a
proof or not because
maybe I give a justification for
strong duality.
If you look online,
there are roughly
two kinds of proofs
or three kinds of proofs of strong
duality.
The first you define the simplex
algorithm which is a way of getting the
optimal solution for linear problems and
then when the simplex algorithm finishes
it gives you what's called tableau from
which you can read out the solution to
the primal you can read off the optimal
solution to the dual and then you can
stare at it and
use the um Well, you can stick, you
know,
no it tells you that the optimal
solution to the primal is equal to the
optimal solution to the dual.
So that's one way of proving um strong
duality and it's you know absolutely
rigorous. Another way of improving
strong duality is borrowing this lema
from analysis called Farcash's lema and
applying it. The problem with this is
that Faros's lema is basically strong
duality
in different notation.
So you haven't really
I mean I guess it's a proof if you
believe Farcash's lema but it doesn't
seem to give you any more real insight
than my just telling you that strong
duality holds because
that's what it's doing.
And the third
uses mechanics in n dimensions and we
need a few basic theorems for mechanics
and then we can prove strong duality.
So
I mean we have to accept these theorems
from mechanics. I don't know if there's
any way of going through mathematics and
proving that these mechan theorems from
mechanics really hold. But
if I mean if you accept the theorems
from mechanics then you absolutely have
a proof of strong duality and showing I
mean I find this really pretty amazing
showing that mechanics is consistent in
high dimensions
is the same thing in some sense as
proving strong duality of linear
programming which is a connection I
never would have accepted expected. So
we're going to pro give you the
justification from mechanics
and let's see.
Um
So a linear program
set of hyperlinks.
THE CONSTRAINTS
the constraints say you're on one side
of the hyper plane.
and the objective function.
We want to find
feasible point
furthest
in direction of
objective function.
So what do we do? Well, we pretend each
of these hydroplanes is a solid
surface.
And
okay, this is a bad drawing.
And what we're going to do is we're
going to drop a ball
and gravity is going to take it in the
direction of the
increasing or decreasing objective
function
and it's going to hit this um hyper
plane. And now it's going to roll in
this direction and it's going to hit
this point. And now
we're going to assume
well
actually maybe we should make another
plane here.
It's going to roll down to here. And
this is the lowest point on the proper
side of all the hyperplanes. So it's
just going to sit there. And mechanics
tells us that the force of gravity on it
is balanced by the force
being pushed on this point perpendicular
to each hyper plane. So the sum of the
forces exerted on this ball by the
hyperplanes is equal to the force of
gravity.
And this
is a theorem for mechanics indeed.
Okay.
So now let's write down the
um linear program
that solves this problem.
minimize
cranspose
x
subject to
ax is greater than equal to E.
And this is just saying the point
is on the correct side of every every
hyper plane.
And this is just the force of gravity.
You want to
make the point as low as possible.
And um well
x is a arbitrary point so x is
unconstrained.
Okay. So now we can ask what's the duel
of this problem.
So this is the primal.
the duel
well
it's going to be max
banspose y
and now all of these x's are
unconstrained.
So that means all of these equations
must be in must be equalities. So we
have a transpose y equals c.
And
here we have a whole bunch of
inequalities which means we get y
greater than zero.
Okay. So this is the
linear program and its dual that we will
show
have the property of strong duality.
So, a hyper plane,
the equation was um I left out some
letters there.
The equation was um
a I1
X1 + A I2 X2 + dot dot dot + A I
N X subn
is
greater than or equal to B subi.
So what is the upward force on this
hyper plane?
Well, if you have a hyper plane and you
have a ball resting on the hyper plane,
the force on the ball is perpendicular
to the hyper plane.
So, it's in direction.
Um I want to say a i1
a i2 through a sub i n
and [clears throat]
you know if the it has to be positive so
it's some
constant c.
So the force is c a i1 through a sub i n
with c greater than zero.
Okay,
C is a bad number for this bad variable
for this. Let's see.
Let's call it F.
And I should probably call this F subi.
Okay.
So we have
we have
there
must be
some forces
and I'm going to call them y subi
instead of f subi just because
y subi is the right name for the
variable because it's a dual variable.
such that
summation.
Oh, wait.
such that
if v subi is equal to this direction a
i1 a i2
through a sub i n
then
summation v sub i
no if
yeah that's right then summation y sub i
v subi is equal to See
actually
maybe we should make this cranspose.
And because these forces all act away
from the hyper plane need
y subi
z.
Okay.
If
The ball
touches
the E hyper plane.
Then
a subi
if the
ball touches the e piper plane I'm going
to say ax
ax the i term of ax is equal to b subi
because if the ball touches the E hyper
plane then the constraint is satisfied
with equality and
this is true.
The ball
does not touch the hyper plane
then what's going on? The ball does not
touch the hyper plane
then
the hyper plane does not exert any force
on the ball.
then y sub i equals z.
And these two things are enough to give
you complimentary not are enough to I
mean these two things well first look a
lot like complimentary sness but they're
enough to give you strong duality.
[snorts]
Okay,
let
Okay, we have y subi
no y transpose
ax [applause] minus b
is equal to y i
guess
summation y sub i ax minus B
and I want to claim either Yi equals Z
or AX subi equals B subi.
So this
equals zero.
Now this goes ypose
ax - b
equals z. And let's look back at the
linear program. And
we have
ypose
y equals c.
Right?
So
ypose a is cranspose.
So this says
oh this should be yranspose b. So I when
I took this I forgot to move the
yranspose into the parenthesis.
So this is cranspose x and so we have
cranspose x minus yanspose b = zero and
cranspose x = ypose bison.
Okay,
so that actually is the end of the
linear programming duality lecture notes
and I suspected I might have a little
time left. So I am going to tell you
about Kunig's theorem which is an
application of linear programming
duality.
And I did not prepare this as well. So
hopefully I won't make any mistakes
there.
Suppose you have a bipartite graph.
Okay.
So, let's draw an example.
U matching
is a set of edges
that
do not
I want to say that do not
meet at any vertices.
So this
is one edge of a matching. This might be
another edge of the matching. This might
be another edge.
And
here's another edge.
So that's four edges in this matching.
Okay. Now I want to claim now I want to
define a vertex cover.
Vertex cover
is a set of vertices that intersect all
the EDGES
that meet all the edges.
So let's see what would a vertex cover
in this graph look like. Well,
you might use this vertex.
You might use this vertex.
You might use this vertex. And you might
use this vertex. Does this cover all the
edges? No, actually it doesn't. So let's
not use that vertex.
You could use this vertex.
And that actually does cover all the
edges because
Yeah.
Okay.
The
size
of the maximum matching
is equal to the size of the minimum
vertex cover.
[applause]
Okay. So what we have here is we have
yeah we have four in each of them. So
this is an example where equality holds
and the Kix theorem says equality holds
in all graphs
and there's one which
one direction is easy
size
of Any vertex cover
has to be bigger than equal to the size
of any matching.
And why is this?
Well,
I mean a vertex cover has to cover each
of the edges in the matching, which
means it has to be one of the end points
of the each of the edges of the has to
contain one of the end points in each of
the edges of the matching which means
that it's
has to be the size of the maximum
matching at least
and Kig's theorem says that they're
equal.
Okay.
So, how do we prove equality?
Well, one way to do it is write down a
linear program for the maximum matching.
write down a linear program for vertex
covers.
Show that they're duals and then show
that
there is an integer solution to each of
them.
So I do not have time to do all of that,
but we can at least write down the
um
the theorem for the maximum matching
the
So how are we going to write down
uh
how are we going to write down a linear
program for the maximum matching?
What should the variables be?
Edges maybe.
Okay.
Um,
so we want to maximize
the sum of
x sub.
Okay.
And now we want to say that
at most one of these edges, if we have a
vertex here, we want to say at most one
of these edges is present in the
matching. And we're not going to be able
to do that because these are not integer
variables. They're real numbers. But
let's um write down zero less than x
less than one and summation
e
okay v is contained in e. So for every
vertex the um
the edg the verticy the edges containing
that vertex
x sub is less than equal to one. So this
is something like
there's at most one
edge containing every vertex
which means that we do not have two
vertices two edges intersecting in a
vertex and are matching assuming the
matching is
assuming that all the variables are zero
or one and that's exactly the um
criterion for the match maximum
matching.
Okay.
Um
let's find the duel.
Well, the duel I mean we have an
equation for every vertex
and some extra equations
and a maximization. So the duo is going
to be a minimization. It's going to have
an equation, a variable for every
edge and it's going to have some extra
variables
dual. Um,
okay.
So
one constraint
per edge
and here we have
one per vertex.
Here we have extra per strength
per edge.
And
I guess we can also
have non- negativeity constraints.
So let's see the duo is going to have um
I should write down what these
equations what these variables are dual
let's call this
y sub
d and z sub e the equations
Um,
so
now
dual
equation
for
each or inequality I should say
for each
um edge.
And what are these inequalities going to
be? Well, y subv appears in
the equation for x subb
and
z sub appears in the equation for x
subb.
So that means that
y subb plus
z subb
well let's see minimum
summation y subd
y sub plus Z subb
is less than or equal to
um what
this is greater than uncle
I'm Sorry.
And um
YV and Z sub.
So what does this really mean?
Well,
what you want
is
you want uh
a vertex cover, which means you want a
set of vertices that are adjacent to
every edge.
Um
okay, so actually we I I did that wrong.
Minimize y subb plus z sub
because the right hand sides are one for
y subb and one for z subb.
Um
okay.
Okay, I seem to be I seem to have gotten
myself lost here,
but um I can go back and talk more about
[clears throat] the program for um
the primal program.
Um and why the primal program is um
yeah so that's the primal program up
here.
So the primal program
a solution
is a
weight
on each edge.
So sum of the weights
we e
d and e
um
is less than or equal to one.
So suppose we have um fractional
solutions
that means that there's some edge
where
you might have two some vertices where
you might have two edges which have 0.5
going out of it. Now
um we might have another edge going out
of 0.5 out of this one because
this plus this is lesser equal to one
and we want to maximize it. So we would
have another one
going up. So um and this might be 0.25
and
um let's put one up here. Um maybe
another 0.5 and another.5.
Okay. [cough]
[clears throat]
In a fractional solution,
you can always find
find a cycle
of fractional edges,
right?
Because
um
well
I mean if you do cannot find a fra if
you find a cycle of fractional edges
what you can do is you can increase the
even ones and decrease the odd ones and
set one of them equal to zero and always
get a better solution.
Ah,
hey.
And first all of these cycles are even
because
this is a bipartite graph. So that means
we can increase the odd ones and
decrease the even ones and we get one
zero one zero one zero
and it has the same objective
function
and zero fractional EDGES
and doing this we can always get rid of
the fractional edges.
Now there's another possibility which is
you know you have 0.5
and what you can do is you can now
increase this one to one decrease this
to zero increase this one to one
decrease this to zero and um
And because if you can find a path, that
would mean that this vertex does not
have any fractional edges next to it
aside from this one. And this vertex
does not have any fractional edges next
to it besides this one. And that means
that you can increase the odd edges and
decrease the even edges. And
either you um end up with the same
objective function or you increase the
objective function. But we were assuming
this was optimal. So you always end up
with the same objective function. So you
can always decrease the number of
fractional edges and
keep the same objective function which
means that eventually you find a
solution where there are no fractional
edges and that is your
maximum matching that you wanted to
find.
And if you take the duel of this and
stare at the duel, you will see that it
gives you, and I screwed that up when I
was trying to do it, but it will tell
you, you will see that it gives you a
vertex cover. And again, you can have a
fractional vertex cover, but a very
similar argument will tell you that you
have
you can find a optimal vertex cover,
which is an integer solution to the
linear program. And that shows Kunig's
theorem.
And we will be doing things that are
more like this,
you know, taking linear programs for um
interesting problems. And we will do
this with zero sum gains and maximum
flow. And show first that the
fractional solutions can always be
um
massaged to give you inter solutions for
maximum for maximum flow. And this will
tell us give us a duality theorem that
the maximum flow equals the minimum cut.
And for zero sum games,
you know, a game is a two player um
thing. And we will show that the linear
the primal linear program gives you the
optimal strategy for the first player
and the
dual linear program gives you the
optimal strategy for the second player.
And because they are duels, they have
the same objective function. And that
tells us that they if the first player
plays his optimum of strategy, he can
always guarantee a win of say W on each
turn
on average. And if the second player
plays his optimal strategy, he can
always
um achieve a loss of at most W on each
turn. So the first player and the second
player,
you know, first player can guarantee he
wins plus W and the second player can
guarantee he loses no more than minus W.
And so this is the value of the game.