[music]
Oh.
Oh. [music]
[music]
>> [music]
[music and singing]
>> to some miracle. Only listen to my
general.
[music]
My attitude out of control. Tell me what
[music] to do. Mr. General
[music]
>> [music]
>> Heat. Hey, Heat.
[music]
Heat. Heat. [music]
Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Shame meat. [music]
[music]
>> [music]
>> But he cannot find no real friends.
[music]
Hey, [music]
[music] keep busy.
>> [music]
>> Keep busy.
Keep busy.
[music]
>> [music]
>> like
Johnny
like [music]
Johnny Jenny Johnny Journey Jenny Johnny
Jenny Johnny Journey Jenny Johnny Jenny
[music] Jenny Jenny of a journey of a
journey of a journey of a jenny of a
Jenny of a Jenny of a journey. Come
>> [music]
[music]
>> on.
>> [music]
[music]
>> special edition in your AI. I couldn't
copy. I'm leaving clues in the fitting
[music] room in this hot tea. No, I'm
not thinking about no exes. No, they
miss me. [music] I got the whole room
spinning like
the bars.
[music] Want to rock with Jenny? Keep
your head down there. Like Jenny
obsessed like Jenny like like Jenny
Jenny Jenny like Jenny Jenny really
[music] like Jenny Jenny Jenny Jenny
Jenny have ever met Jenny Jenny Jenny
Jenny Jenny Jenny Jenny Jenny Jenny
>> [music]
>> But you haven't met
[music]
my shing.
They can't deal with me cuz I'm
priceless [music] yet I still
get out of my way
trying to
[music]
keep shading
with me and I'm crazy
with [music] Jenny. Keep your hand down
like who else like [music]
like
[music]
Jenny Jenny Jenny Jenny Jenny Jenny
Jenny Jenny [music] Jenny Jenny Jenny
Jenny look just
>> [music]
[music]
>> Woo!
NICE. [cheering]
>> [applause]
>> the end. Sorry.