My name is Ukech Daniel Uboa.
originally from South Sudan,
currently residing in Nairobi,
but, registered as a refugee in Kakuma
refugee camp.
The objectives that describe me well,
innovative, passionate and adaptable.
Working, working with Appen,
has been a very enlightening experience.
my experience in Appen has improved
my analytical skills and tech.
The tech skills as well.
For refugees
to have better access to digital
one is providing them with access
to technology
in terms of, access to the internet and,
providing them with computers, devices
like computers and smartphone.
The second point is providing them
with adequate training and equipping them
with skills for them to be able to
to walk in those in those, platforms.
The other point is providing them
with legal support as well.
Working with
international organizations
come with its challenges.
Different countries
come with different legal policies.
Many, many organizations,
or many platforms
does not recognize
refugee identification cards.
And when applying with those, windows
and documents, you might not be able
to be you to be considered in
when applying for those opportunities.