A digital twin is a digital
representation of a physical asset or a
system or a process. In the real estate
world, we're talking about a digital
twin of a building. What we'll see is
huge advancements in specific components
within a building. So, we'll see digital
twins of HVAC systems, of electrical
systems, of mechanical systems, of
security systems and space optimization
within a building as well. And what will
happen is over time that they will
integrate into creating one entire
platform to showcase what's taking place
within that building. From that, what
we'll be able to do is create digital
twins, not just of buildings, but of
entire cities. And that's where we're
going to find ourselves delving into the
smart cities of the future. And from
that, we'll be able to create greater
efficiencies from a transportation
standpoint, from an operational
standpoint from within the city, from a
housing component, even the sewage
systems of the cities and then from that
make the decisions that can really make
significant improvements in a short
space of time. For more MIT moments from
MIT Open Learning, like, subscribe or
follow.