I'm Anantha Chandrakasan,
MIT's Provost
and the Head of the MIT
Generative AI Impact Consortium.
It's an absolute
pleasure to welcome you
to the inaugural symposium of
the MIT AI Impact Consortium,
or MGAIC.
The energy in this room
reflects the enormous interest
in the topic of generative
AI and MIT's ability
to drive progress
through collaboration.
There's been a tremendous
amount of interest and work
in industry and in academia
in creating large language
models and its
broad-based applications.
This consortium is focused on
the impact of generative AI
across domains such
as manufacturing,
life sciences, transportation,
design, energy, and so on.
To maximize impact, we
need to bring researchers
across research domains.
MIT is uniquely positioned
to catalyze that convergence,
bringing together researchers
from across the institute
to work across domains and
also to work with our industry
collaborators.
I want to thank the founding
members of our Industrial
Advisory Board, Analog Devices,
Coca-Cola, InterSystems, OpenAI,
SK Telecom, Tata Group, and
TWG Global for stepping forward
as partners in this work.
I would also like
to thank McKinsey
for providing deep insights
and advice to the IAB.
The deep commitment of
the founding members
reflects a shared belief that
bold research done in the open
can shape a better future.
Thanks to their support,
we're able to fund
more than 60 interdisciplinary
projects on campus.
This consortium is more than
a platform for research.
It's a model of how we engage
industry, energize faculty,
empower students, and
deliver impact all at once,
and it is a commitment
to our openness.
So I was really impressed that
these companies signed up,
knowing that all of
the work that we do
is going to be open source.
The work will not just benefit
just the member companies,
but society at large.
And that's why the solutions
that will be emerging
will be open source,
interdisciplinary, and designed
for public good.
And today's program
gives you a glimpse
of what is already happening
and what is coming next.
You will hear from MIT faculty
at the forefront of research,
from innovators shaping the
future of entrepreneurship,
and from students
whose work reminds us
the next generation is
not just ready to lead.
In many ways, they
already are doing so.
This is a pivotal moment.
Generative AI is moving fast.
But the questions it
raises about equity,
creativity, responsibility,
and impact are enduring.
I truly believe it is
our job to make sure
that as the technology advances,
our collective wisdom keeps
pace.
I want to extend
my deepest thanks
to our faculty co-directors,
Professors Vivek Farias, who
is here, and Tim Kraska,
whose dedication and insights
have helped shape MGAIC into a
bold, collaborative initiative
it is today.
So let's thank them.
[APPLAUSE]
I would also like
to take a moment
to thank the amazing staff
of the MGAIC initiative,
the MIT Schwarzman
College of Computing,
and the Office of
Innovation and Strategy
for their amazing
contributions not
only for organizing this event,
but the ongoing activity.
So let's also give them
around of applause.
[APPLAUSE]
It is now my deep honor to
introduce President Sally
Kornbluth.
She has consistently championed
the idea that MIT must not only
respond to the rapid
evolution of generative AI,
but help shape its trajectory
thoughtfully, ethically,
and in service to the
nation and the world.
I'm deeply grateful
for her leadership
in establishing MGAIC as
a presidential priority
and for her continuous
support for the initiative.
Please join me in giving a warm
welcome to MIT President Sally
Kornbluth.
[APPLAUSE]
Thanks so much, Anantha,
for the introduction.
And I just have to say,
today is Anantha's birthday,
so this is a great birthday.
[APPLAUSE]
He's been really outstanding
in his leadership
in bringing this
consortium to life.
So I guess in the
context of MGAIC,
that makes him the chief
magician, so thank you.
[LAUGHTER]
Let me also give a warm
shout-out to our other magicians
here, our faculty co-directors,
not to mention Vivek and Tim,
and to the whole team
of faculty and staff
who organized today's program.
So thanks to all.
Also to the students, to
the early career researchers
who will share their work in
this afternoon's poster session.
And I know that we're all
looking forward to hearing
from today's incredible
speakers and panelists,
starting with the
legendary Yann LeCun.
Today's symposium
is the first of what
I hope will be an annual
flagship event for the MIT
Generative AI Consortium.
Now, at MIT one thing we
do love as well as numbers,
are great acronyms.
UROP, MISTI, DAPER, DUSP.
So we've now added--
this is a little bit of
acronymical sleight of hand
to call this MGAIC,
M-G-A-I-C. But hopefully,
you'll forgive for that.
Easy to remember, fun
to say, et cetera.
But I would argue that
calling this effort MGAIC
also points to something
quite serious, why
we're here together.
Obviously, in this
audience we've
got some fans of the
great scientific sci-fi
master, Arthur C. Clarke.
So remember Clarke's third law.
Any sufficiently
advanced technology
is indistinguishable from magic.
Now, I know I'm
not the first and I
won't be the last to connect
Arthur Clarke's observation
with the black box sensation
of using generative AI.
But put in your prompt.
You get a polished
answer back so fast
it actually feels like magic.
And of course, everyone here
knows that generative AI
does not work by magic.
And yet, even the experts, many
of whom you'll hear from here,
can't always explain
how something does work.
That makes gen AI fundamentally
different from really other
technologies, and it creates a
very important responsibility
for an institution and
a community like MIT.
This audience includes
experts, aspiring experts
on every part of the AI menu,
and I'm certainly not one.
But to explain the
kind of responsibility
I'm talking about, let me
offer as an example something
from my own field in
the life sciences.
My lab explored deep
behavior of cancer cells.
And today, when I talk to
cancer researchers and clinician
scientists on our faculty,
they say that AI already
touches and improves literally
every aspect of their work,
from how they design
experiments and analyze data
to how they keep and manage
records, to how they diagnose
and care for their patients.
They're positioned now to
capitalize on a great many AI
advances immediately.
And I hear tremendous
gratitude and enthusiasm.
So part of MIT's
responsibility is
to keep those advances
coming for the world.
But those researchers and
clinicians on their own
are not in a position to address
AI's risks and mysteries.
How to guarantee accuracy and
guard against hallucinations?
How to get sufficient
patient data
to make the systems work while
also preserving confidentiality?
How to validate the results and
achieve enough explicability
that users feel
safe to trust them?
In short, how can you manage
the magic so that all of us
can confidently rely on it
for critical applications
in the real world?
And so they're counting on
all of you-- our faculty,
our researchers, our students,
together with our consortium
members--
to help.
They're counting
on you to tackle
the whole suite of technical
and ethical challenges
whose solutions
will allow society
to make the most of this
astounding technology.
And in the myriad
of other realms
where AI is also changing
everything, the rest of society
is counting on you too.
It's a big responsibility, but
judging by the depth and breadth
of interest on our campus,
I have every confidence
that we'll succeed.
The excitement is everywhere.
The two new undergraduate majors
we've created in these fields
were effectively
sold out overnight.
And when we announced our first
round of MGAIC seed funding,
we were stunned to receive more
than 180 research proposals
representing every
school in the college.
They covered an
incredible range of ideas,
from fundamental research
to practical applications,
from responsible deployment
to workforce transformation.
Many depend on collaborations
across departments
and disciplines, and crucially,
collaborations with industry
as well.
So I want to close
with a special nod
to the consortium's founding
members, as Anantha did.
Analog Devices, Coca-Cola,
InterSystems, OpenAI, SK
Telecom, Tata, and TWG Global.
What enables the magic
in the MGAIC consortium
is your commitment to explore
very important AI challenges
with us in the best open
source tradition of MIT.
We wouldn't be here
today without you,
and we're deeply grateful
for your willingness
to join us in that vital work.
So thank you all
for coming, and best
wishes for a fascinating day.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]