soft robotics. It's a branch of robotics
essentially where instead of using what
people normally associate with robotics
like rigid materials, we're replacing
that instead with 3D printed soft
materials and using that to make an
actual robot. If we look at the world
around us, a lot of the biological
organisms are actually not rigid. So not
at all like what we imagine from robots.
As humans, for example, we have the soft
skin covering us and that allows us to
very easily and safely interact with the
world. The hope for this research and
where I think it could lead to is the
development of more soft robotic modules
with incorporated highresolution tactile
sensing that can actually perform a lot
more useful tasks and safely interact
with the world. Find your MIT moment.
Visit learnmit.edu. edu.