[Music]
so for a lot of people around the world
we're now using AI for a lot of our
projects and work and everything really
and in this case with climate change we
want to use the data that AI has and try
and make different solutions to this
ongoing problem in our world and we
learned that not all AI has credibility
and it can't be right all the time so
you really have to make sure to check
your credibility of your your sources
like you would with any other project
even though it might seem that AI always
has the right answer everyone is biased
and you could even argue that chat gbt
and AI is biased you really don't know
but our generation has to really work
with AI and get to know it better so we
can use it to the best of its ability
for more MIT moments from MIT open
learning like subscribe or follow