[MUSIC PLAYING]
ARMSTRONG: Houston,
Tranquility Base here.
The eagle has landed.
DUKE: Roger, Tranquility.
We copy--
SPEAKER 1: It was
pretty inspirational
for me to see the moon landings.
Even though I was
only five years old,
I remember it very distinctly.
SPEAKER 2: I started
this whole journey
wanting to be an astronaut.
And I became addicted to flying.
And all I wanted to do
was fly all the time
and became so passionate
about aviation.
WOOD: So I was able to be at
Kennedy Space Center in 1999
when the Chandra space telescope was launched.
And it was a nighttime launch.
It was absolutely gorgeous.
The whole sky
looked like daytime.
And that mission was
the very first mission
where a woman was actually the
commander of the Space Shuttle
mission.
It was inspiring.
NARRATOR: MIT'S
first female graduate
in aeronautical
engineering, now AeroAstro,
was Isabel Abel, class of 1932.
While still a
student, Abel helped
Amelia Earhart become the first
woman to fly the Atlantic solo.
But it would be
another seven years
before anyone in the aircraft
industry would hire her,
at which point her
career took off.
I have found on the
whole, she said,
that once the original
barrier is down,
women are well-accepted.
MIT's AeroAstro women
have been knocking down
barriers ever since.
WIDNALL: My father
rode bulls in the rodeo
and my mother was a
juvenile probation officer.
So it sort of gave me a
certain leadership style,
willingness to assert oneself.
I came to MIT as a freshman
in 1956, one of 23 women
entering the Institute.
It didn't feel like a
welcoming place for women,
and I made a kind of
conscious decision
that I would worry
about that later.
But as I moved into
the department,
I got a lot of really
good support from faculty.
NARRATOR: Sheila Widnall rose to
a host of influential positions
at MIT and beyond,
including Vice President
of the Academy of
Engineering and President
of the American Association
for the Advancement of Science.
In 1993, she became the first
woman Secretary of the Air
Force, serving for four years.
Throughout her
career, she's played
a pivotal role in the
advancement of women at MIT.
WIDNALL: If we look at the
history of women at MIT,
it's a set of steps.
It's not a smooth ramp.
It's up, then we do something
else and we go along,
and we do something else.
It's an issue that you just have
to keep on the front burner.
NEWMAN: Science and
engineering are not
the domain of any one gender.
We're equally good at it.
And I always think putting men and women
and just diversity of all types really
helps us come up with different solutions.
I had never been taught
by a female engineer.
So, but there's a lot
you can learn from that.
I was taught by plenty of
wonderful male engineers.
I learned a lot from them.
But I think it also fueled
my passion a little bit
to serve as a role
model and to make sure
that girls thought that this
was absolutely a career.
An aerospace engineer,
that's not just
for men, that's for
girls and boys alike.
My BioSuit research is just
a great example of that.
So that's a kind of a
revolutionary approach
to a new spacesuit design.
It looks like a Spiderman suit.
That wasn't just for
aesthetic reasons.
I'm applying the
pressure directly
to my skin to give
you a full mobility.
You can climb, you can bend.
If Rachel could come out.
Rachel Foreman,
graduate student, MIT,
is going to model the
BioSuit for you here.
As soon as I did this second
skin or this shrink wrap, now
you can tell the difference
between the genders.
So now there's a female suit
and there's a male suit.
And I was overwhelmed, and
I still am, by young girls
that are so excited
about this space suit,
but it's a space
suit for girls now.
And it makes a great
connection with them
and they say, maybe I
can think about being
an aerospace engineer.
At MIT, 48% of our
undergraduates are female now.
That's quite a difference from
just a decade and definitely
two and three decades ago.
URANGA: We are not many
women in AeroAstro.
It's fine.
Probably the main thing, difference between MIT
and any other place I've seen, people
are valued for their ideas.
Not for who says it.
LOHMEYER: I think there's
still some improvement that
can be made.
We can definitely boost the numbers.
But I think what is different is definitely
the sense of community
and sense of belonging.
And maybe if you
have a day where
you don't feel like
you belong, you
can find someone that you
can talk about those things
with, whereas before maybe
it wasn't as possible.
BUCHIBABU: I think being a woman
in this field is actually fun.
It's fun being a minority, believe it or not.
You're more memorable.
You're more recognizable.
And you're also more relatable.
People tend to come talk to you
first, and that's kind of nice.
And I think it's fun being
in that kind of environment.
So that's also my
other motivation
in being in this area.
And kind of bossing around
the boys, that's fun too.