Why don't we get started? Nice to see
you all. So, the thing I asked you to do
um in your learning journals for today
um was to do a little reflection on your
personal edtech history. Um so what are
tools,
experiences, platforms, systems that
either had some like very positive
effect on your learning trajectory? You
like discovered a love of something
because you did that or were terrible
and disastrous. They ruined your
learning experience. They made you feel
bad. They inhibited your learning in
some way or they were just interesting
or engaging or or useless or some other
way distinctive. Um, go ahead and now if
you didn't do that assignment, you can
probably still make up an answer to that
question. So, you'll be okay for today.
Um, um, but turn to the the person or
two next to you, get in small groups and
just share a little bit with each other
about this little like snippet of your
personal edtech history and we'll do
that for five minutes or so and then
share out. Does that make sense? Ready?
Go.
Did um
did did anybody happen to be in a group
where multiple people in the group
mention the same thing? Were they all
different? What were the most similar
ones? Anybody? Uh there was a computer
literacy class like similarity. Okay,
good. So there's like a class which is
called like computer literacy, digital
literacy, and it's kind of like a pretty
like here's how to use PowerPoint.
Here's how to type. Here's how to um do
like pretty simple things with
computers. Good. Yeah, that's a feature
of of a lot of different kinds of uh
school systems. And was it successful in
your environments or was it a drag?
truck.
Yeah. Yeah. Good. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. You know, um there there can be
there can be a bias of like, oh man, we
got to like put technology in the
schools because the kids are going to be
really fired up about the technology in
the school. No, actually like if you do
boring things with technology, they're
just as bored as sometimes even more so.
Um anybody have things that were like
really positive experiences for them
that somebody that you or somebody in
your group talked about things you're
like, "Yeah, that was that was great.
That really made school better?" Well, I
mean, I I talked about like the
Smartboard and just like the
implementation of it and like every
classroom I feel like especially as like
our generation was growing up. Um, and
like I don't know like I made like a
little like side story about how like
that's the first time I felt like the
students became the teacher because the
old ladies at our schools like didn't
know how to like recalibrate it or like
turn it all on. So, it was always the
students like coming up and showing the
teacher how to use it. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Good. The sort of inversion of of
expertise. How many how many of you were
in schools where smartboards just kind
of appeared in the middle of your
educational trajectory? Yeah, you all
are like in this sweet spot. How how
many of you would would say that they
were anybody at schools where you felt
like they were very effective where they
substantially improved learning? How you
thought yours good? How many of you were
at schools where like this is like no
one is using these things? They could
have just bought chalkboards or
whiteboards or things like that. Yeah.
So overwhelming majority of that. Yeah.
Smartboards are like a totally
fascinating case study. um a a vast
amount of money was spent on these
tools. Um uh that that seemed to have
essentially no positive impact at all on
learning. In lots of places, they really
weren't used as like interactive
whiteboards. They were just like, oh,
like a a whiteboard. You know, we Khalil
and I were joking that uh um that they
actually didn't work very well in his
school in particular because they
require like slightly different
lighting. Um like like you need to dim
the lights a little bit to be able to
see them. But the, you know, the
classrooms they were built were not
built for dimmable lights. They were
built for lights that would be shined on
whiteboards or chalkboards. Um, and so
like the rest of the there's a whole
bunch of the rest of the infrastructure
that didn't make Smartboards work. Like
maybe your classroom didn't work. Maybe
there was no training for your teacher.
Maybe there were no curricular materials
that were available to integrate with
the Smartboard.
Um, and yet, you know, like like how is
it the case that that we could be in a
room full of people all across country,
all across the world, you all raise your
hand or like we all bought smartboards
and they all didn't work. Um, like why
like why didn't the first people who
bought smartboards be like team this is
not a good idea? Like spend your money
on something else. You know, every
dollar we spend on education technology
has an opportunity cost. Um, every time
you spend a dollar in a school, you're
trying to make people's learning better.
Um, and there there are very few dollars
that we spend that make learning worse.
Does anybody feel like the smartboard
like actively like made you dumber or
learn slower or something like that?
Probably not. Like probably your smart
like it's probably the case that no one
none of you were harmed by smartboards.
I think that's pretty unlikely. Um, but
every dollar your school your school
spent on smartboards could have been
spent on some other technology, on some
other curriculum material, on art
supplies, on professional development
for teachers, on a zillion other things
which could have improved your learning
experience, um, and not just been like a
very expensive version of a whiteboard
or something like that. Um so there's a
lot in that discussion of smartboards
that I think is helpful for us to think
about um how you know not just not just
of the efficacy of any particular techn
you know it's the efficacy of any
particular technology how particular
technology um is situated in different
kind of places at least one example from
Dana who's like no these things are
great you know like we bought them our
teachers got trained with them students
were able to help use them like it
worked in that one context even if
almost universally it didn't work in
these other contexts so those are all
things we're going to have to unpack and
figure out and then we're also going to
sort of answer this question like if
there's this thing which like
overwhelmingly doesn't work um why did
schools spend so much money on it like
what would what were the incentives what
was the logic who was spending this
money um all these kinds of things are
questions we can keep asking um anybody
have like really like disastrous stories
though that's kind of like a benol like
weird that thing didn't work but anybody
have a like man this was terrible kind
of experience with technology
Okay. Uh to our smartboard. Uh in one
case, students were able to install like
so they can customize the brushes and
the student just chose like kind of an
awful picture of a teacher to put as a
brush and they used as a kind of a prank
on them which is you know technology
allows you to do more creative pranks.
Good. Yeah. Yeah. So, so expand
expanding our way of humiliating
faculty. That could be one good. In
seventh grade, my school decided to give
everyone a Chromebook. But in seventh
grade, I feel like everyone is not
really mature. So, in class, like
everyone would find a different game. It
was like the snake IO game or like the
paint IO and the entire class would be
on the game like while the teacher was
teaching. So, then they would have to
block different websites. But like a new
website would appear every week. So,
they just had to keep blocking more and
more. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. But yeah, block
like blocking websites is a good way to
teach young people how to use VPNs. Like
if you were like I want to teach young
people how to use VPNs and like blocking
websites is pretty good. But but in ter
I I wrote an oped once years and years
ago. Um I pro like just after I was
teaching probably 2006 or seven or
something like that. Um where I
described them as kneeh high fences
around the internet that that adults
trip over and and young people just jump
over. Um uh um good. Yeah. So here so
here's this tool which actually now is
like Chromebooks are pretty ubiquitous
in schools. Um there are plenty of
places where there's push back against
the these kinds of technology for like
people telling just the story that you
described like like you know our devices
are canonically designed to capture our
attention as much as possible and to
particularly like capture our attention
in ways that have us look at
advertisements like you know for people
who are designing phones and computers
and websites and things like that that
is like a central focus like how do we
get you looking at this thing as much as
possible and in particular like how do
we then get advertisements to slide in
front of these things so that people
will pay you to look at us. that is not
a set of characteristics that are good
for a learning environment. Um, but on
the other hand, we could I'm sure and
some of you may have mentioned them, but
we we can go to schools where
Chromebooks are implemented and the kids
are not playing snake IO all day because
they're doing like interesting learning
activities that are well supervised that
would not be possible without the
Chromebook, without the apps, without
the access to the internet and things
like that. So we could also think about
like what happened in your school um
that had this kind of purchase and then
there there was clearly not the rest of
the infrastructure in place to have that
purchase be meaningful whereas the exact
same purpose in other places was
supported by professional learning and
curriculum and like all the other things
that might have potentially made that a
valuable learning experience.
Um, so I was talking to her and I think
we had a bit of a different experience
from most of the people in the class
because we didn't do like our basic
learning in the US. So it's from
Ethiopia, I'm from Brazil. I think we
use technology to a much lesser expense
extent than here. Um, so I remember
there was like one significant
experience for me in terms of using
technology growing up which is going to
media lab to do English classes. Mhm.
Um, and I think it comes to your point
of like having a purpose to having
technology and that was very clear like
you can't really do listening and
speaking exercises unless you know you
actually have something to listen to and
something to repeat and like each person
would have time with their booth where
they could practice by themselves. Mhm.
So I think the fact that it was very
purposeful um and that it changed from
the day to day because I think also
there's an aspect of like we're going to
computer lab we're doing something
different floors and it was a different
scene with like different lighting like
the fact that it's different made it
much more interesting and when
technology gets to this very common
place you don't even you take it for
granted like you don't really value all
that it can bring so yeah we discuss a
little I mean those kind of language
classes are a great example of this. I
know you probably all have taken
language classes where like the teacher
goes around and you like each say hello
to the teacher in the foreign language
and it takes like 10 minutes to let
everyone say hello. Once you all went to
your individual booths and you could
imagine designing technology where every
person simultaneously says hello and
some algorithm evaluates whether or not
you say hello correctly and then you
know it says something back to you and
other kinds of things. You're like wow
wow we each are getting our own teacher
um that maybe isn't as good as the human
teacher but all of us get one at the
same time. That's pretty cool. I would
say like adding I think to what you said
with purpose it's also like you went
there to do the like English practice it
wasn't used for any extraneous reasons
something like with like Chromebooks
like I have a younger sister who's in
high school right now and all her
homework has to be submitted on like
canvas or something and then she also
just loves like watching YouTube and
stuff and then my mom's problem is like
I can't remove her technology or limit
her technology because that limits her
school work so what do you like you
can't control her like what she's doing
on the Not only that but the vast
majority of our how we learn to be
parents is by observing our own parents
um and this gener you know you know
parents of roughly my age younger um
certainly the next generation coming
along um we can't turn to our own
childhood examples to figure out how to
navigate something like this um it's
very difficult to come up with like good
parenting strategies from first
principles you're like a professional
parent or professional caregiver getting
training or other things like that like
what are you supposed to do? Um and uh
no it's a I I think a lot of school you
know schoolwide infrastructure has a
bunch of unintended consequences. Um the
idea that like at night we're going to
lock kids into their devices you know
like that you know it and and it can
also different differ by kids. So for
kids who have like really good executive
function who can be like I'm going to do
all my homework and then watch the
YouTube videos like maybe there's cool
different things that we could do with
the computers but for kids who are like
you know yeah it's weird like do do
homework on the machine which always has
YouTube on it like literally you're one
click away from really fun things all
the time but like you know do your
quadratic equations really um it's nuts
right like like there must be millions
of kids who cannot like are not good at
that. Yeah, I think kind of to add on
that fact, so I also went to an
international school in Ethiopia and uh
it was a really interesting experience
of how rules around technology would
change almost like on a weekly basis at
some point. It was like at some point
like you can't use any social media and
then like phones were banned and then
they're like, "Oh, like if you need to
call your parents though, you can't call
them." And then it was like limited time
and then like VPNs came and then it was
like it's always so interesting of how
like teachers and faculty would always
try to make like new rules and each time
like they would have to get broken or
like something would have to change and
I think it was always like almost like a
comedy show of how much like it changed
throughout the time. Um uh when when uh
internet filters were first widely
introduced in schools, one of the
problems came up is the vice president
at the time was a guy named Dick Cheney.
Um, and uh, and there are a lot of
searches that were filtering out Dick.
Um, but you need to figure out about
Dick Cheney. Um, so then, you know, like
like someone sets a rule, the rule isn't
right for the context. Um, GPT is
another set of things right now that
people are doing with tons of rules
about these. These are good things.
We're going to keep talking about them.
I'll take a break here so that we can
move on to some other things. You all
have valuable case study experiences
from your time in schools that we can
bring into our conversations together to
think about what um uh you know how new
technologies operate.
To do a good job of making sense of
technologies um we need to understand a
little bit about how people learn. So
we're going to spend two classes looking
at two um pretty well-established
contemporary philosophies, pedagogies,
sciences about learning. Um, today you
read a bunch about cognitive load
theory. Um, I'm going to ask you to do
another exercise actually in the same
groups that you were in would probably
be fine for this one. Um, I want you to
draw a visual
representation of what the authors of
the cognitive learning of of the
cognitive learning theory articles you
read and other things call human
cognitive architecture. um like what are
the key sort of components of the brain
of thinking um of memory in order to
have learning happen. Um another thing
that you could draw in this visual
representation is based on this human
cognitive architecture um there follows
a series of instructional principles.
There follows a series of like better
and worse ways to teach people. Um, and
so you could also try to illustrate how
this human cognitive architecture um,
uh, leads to different kinds of
instructional principles. So groups can
either, um, go and take a chunk of
whiteboard and use some of those
whiteboard markers or part of why I'm
doing this is just I really like this
paper, but it kind of got folded. Um, so
I just want to get rid of it. Um, but
you can take one of these and sort of
huddle around on one of the tables and
and draw. So if you're if you're a paper
person, you can draw on these and then
stick them up there in a few minutes. If
you're a whiteboard person, um you can
do that. We still have all these markers
here. Um I haven't given you um totally
clear instructions in part because what
I want you to do is to um figure out how
to think through some of this uh on your
own a bit. But get in your groups, talk
with each other about what you think are
sort of the key components of cognitive
load theory and the human cognitive
architecture that sort of leads to um
cognitive load theory. And don't go more
than like 2 minutes before starting to
put pen to paper. um it, you know,
you're not going to be graded on whether
or not you're right, but let's see if we
can get a couple of different
representations of uh of what these
folks are talking about, how people
learn, and based on how people learn,
how should we instruct them? Does that
give me enough to start messing around
for a little bit? Ready, go.
All right. What you've seen a couple of
these now. What are some like what are
the main building blocks of this model
of a brain? What is the key features of
human cognitive architecture?
I feel like almost everyone had like
working memory and long-term memory.
Okay, two big pieces here that are
important. Working memory and long-term
memory. What are some of the
characteristics of long-term memory?
It's cool. There are different schemas
stored inside of long-term memory. Okay.
So, we we store stuff in blocks. We want
to talk some more about what these
schemas are. That seems important. It's
kind of limitless. It's limitless. That
is bonkers. No one has discovered the
boundaries of the amount of stuff you
can store in the human brain. You like
you have a finite amount of space. Like
you have a finite number of ounces. You
have a finite number of neurons. There's
a lot of them, but a finite number. And
as far as we can tell, there are no
known limits to how much stuff you can
store inside your brain. That's amazing.
That is an amazing feature of your
brain. Um, anything else that seems
important about long-term memory? All
the stuff can be there. How cool.
It's also unconscious.
You you yeah you you cannot think about
all those things at the same time. It is
it is unconscious. Um how long does
stuff stay in
there? It falls out, right? You forget
stuff. Like if you're interested in
learning, the fact that you forget
things is really important. Um so stuff
goes into longterm memory. It leaks out
into long-term memory. Some of the very
earliest experiments in psychology done
by a guy named Ebing House um were about
the forgetting curve. Um it was
psychology experiments that were mostly
as I understand he mostly did by
himself. He basically like tried to
remember stuff and then tested himself
and then saw how often he forgot things
and noticed that there were sort of
mathematical properties to the
forgetting curve and things like that.
All right. Long-term memory um it's uh
it's functionally limitless. Um it's
unconscious so we can't directly access
it. um we can put things of different
levels of complexity in there. Um what
schemas do is allow us to sort of uh um
aggregate information elements into more
and more complex kind of things. What
are some of the key features of working
memory?
Very limited. Very limited. But how many
things can you hold in your working
memory in any given time, give or take?
Maybe this article didn't emphasize it.
Most people know this. It's kind of like
a fact that that is out there in the
world. Like seven. Yeah. Uh for a long
time people thought it was seven. A
better guess seems to be even less than
that. Three to five. Um but somewhere in
the very you know so here's another
beautiful thing about like you all come
from all different parts of the world.
You can look around this room and you
can see that you're different in all
kinds of ways. You have different
genders. You have different skin color,
different hair color, different eye
color. All kind. All of you have
essentially the exact same working
memory. All of you can hold three to
five things in your head. Um it doesn't
seem to decline as you age. Like there's
other problems with aging, things like
that, but people of all different ages,
everyone, every human you will ever
meet, the eight billion people on this
planet, they can all hold three to five
things in their working memory at any
given time. It is like a beautiful thing
that unites all people on Earth is this
common feature of cognitive
architecture.
Um, how do you how do you how do you get
or like like what are the what are the
things in working memory? How do you get
them or access them or do something with
them?
I was going to say like as much as we
can only hold like three to five things
like those things you can say like are
like schemas and like they can be super
complex and that's how you're able to
like solve really hard problems. So as
much as like like the example of the
restaurant like you have like the chairs
and the tables that's like the basic
things and like the food that you eat
and the workers like all these things
make up a restaurant which are like
super confusing but your working memory
just knows it as this like really large
like one object and so in your working
memory's mind that's only one thing but
it's really a compilation of like
hundreds of things. Yeah. Good. So we
could organize sub things into larger
things in schema. The reason why we're
using imprecise words I would say is in
part like you know this is not the
revealed you know word of the creator
about your brain this is like the best
models we can come up with and our
models aren't perfect like what exactly
is a thing in working memory I think
it's a little bit sketchy how much our
understanding of that is however even
with sketchy models like we can still do
useful things on let's do a quick
working memory exercise do any of you
speak
Sanskrit oh wait I can't do I can't show
you this just yet well here's Uh,
actually, I'll do these first and then
I'll show you this next thing. Um, grab
a piece of paper and a pen. You can, if
you don't have a piece of paper and a
pen, you can um pass that around. Um,
here are two that I really like.
Um, this one I think illustrates really
nicely the idea that the working memory
is the bottleneck. If you are an
educator, one of the main things you're
working against is people's limited
working memory. If people had huge
working memories, you could like tell
them all kinds of complex things. You
could be like, "Let me just explain
everything and they would be
like,"Great, now it's all in my
long-term memory." Um, but you actually
can't do that. People can only attend to
a small number of things at any given
time. And for noviceses, those things
that they attend to are necessarily
going to be simpler than for more
complex people. So, so for the for the
people in cognitive load theory, um, as
they think about instructional
environments, the the bottleneck of
those instructional environments is the
limits of your working memory. Anybody
anybody read the Sweller article?
Anybody remember how um uh how cognitive
load theory got started to begin with?
What was the sort of canonical
experiment that got that got John
Sweller kicked off onto cognitive load
theory? You like making a students do
like some kind of weird math like adding
and subtracting and multiplying multiple
things. Yeah. Yeah. So, you solve a math
problem. You're given number A and
number B. And there's only two
operations you can do. It's something
like you can multiply by three or
subtract 69. Those numbers aren't
exactly right. But those are the only
two operations you can do. And somehow
you have to get from number the first
number he gives you to the second number
he gives you. People do multiple forms
of this problem. It turns out that in
every every solution is always
alternating between these two things. Um
add 69 multiply by 3 add 69 multiply by
3 add 69 multiply by three. Nobody
notices
this. None of the people in maybe not
none very few people in the experiments
notice this pattern. This is deeply
troubling for John Sweller because John
Sweller is in a moment in math education
where people are like really big on
problem solving, really big on
discovery, really big on intuition. And
he's like, "My guys, people are not
induced inducing the key principle
that's here. Like they're doing a kind
of mathematical operation, but they're
not figuring out the important thing
here." Like think about how much
consequences that has for math
instruction. it's, you know, they're
solving the problems correctly without
understanding some key feature about how
you solve them correctly. That's bad for
mathematics instruction. Um, and then he
comes up with this theory like why
weren't they able to do that? Um, and he
he describes it as um that people do
this thing he calls means and analysis.
They're constantly looking where they
are and thinking about what would get
them to the next step. Um, if you're
constantly thinking about where you are,
where you want to be, and what might the
next step is, those are like three
things to block up your working memory.
And so now you don't have a whole lot of
working memory left. And it turn you
know his theory was that people like
essentially filled up their working
memory. Their working memory was like at
capacity. It had overwhel there was too
much cognitive load too much cognitive
load on the working memory. And so they
couldn't figure out this underlying
principle. Um and so swellers, you know,
and then he just gets fascinated for the
rest of his life about thinking about
what is the human cognitive architecture
like where is the cognitive load, where
are we overburdened, where are their
bottlenecks, and what would be
instructional designs that would help us
relieve those bottlenecks, work around
those bottlenecks. Um in particular,
really skeptical of this idea, um that
you just like give a bunch of novices
stuff and they can kind of figure it out
on their own. um you know with enough
time, enough exploration, things like
that. Um so that's a bottleneck here
that I really like. And I really like
this picture that has this sort of
infinite long-term memory. I mean, in
theory, it should just go up forever,
but it's big enough that works. Um a
nice thing about this one um on the side
is it notes that the where does where
does stuff get into working memory? Kind
of from two places. You can pull it out
of long-term memory. You can remember
stuff and then you can put it
temporarily in long-term memory. Or you
can attend to it. You can see things in
your environment. You can watch stuff.
You can read things. You can listen to
people and talk to people. As I'm
explaining things to you now, you're
taking these constructs and to the
extent that you're listening and
attending to them, you're putting them
in your working memory. Um, if we mess
around with them enough, if we get you
to apply them, think about them, if you
write them down, some other stuff like
that, it will eventually get stored in
your long-term memory. Um, and then
there's this nice piece here that like
stuff sort of not only goes from working
memory to long-term memory, but things
kind of fall out um and get forgotten.
And yeah, you know, I I think pairing
these words together, um, when stuff in
working memory gets stored in your
long-term memory, they call that
learning. When stuff, um, in long-term
memory gets put into your working
memory, when you become conscious of it,
we call that remembering. That's kind of
nice way of sort of summarizing that.
Um, there
are one of uh, in this model, um,
everything that you learn essentially is
kind of a fact that you remember. Um
there's a great quote by Daniel
Willingham who's a psychologist that
memory is the residue of thought. Um
when you think about stuff that you
remember and and in this model people
tend to think of the things you remember
as discrete facts. Um you can probably
think about and the accumulation of
those discrete facts is what leads to
expertise that understanding um is in a
sense uh the accumulation of lots of
these facts. there probably some domains
that you could think about um where that
model feels really good and makes sense
like oh man you're like man that person
is a really good economist because they
just like know a ton of stuff about
economies and they know a ton of facts
about economics and they remember lots
of different
calculations that you know like would
you say that Maya Angelo was a great
poet because she had way more facts than
other poets do that seems like a sort of
unsatisfying description of how people
become great poets but something to sort
of wrestle with and think about a little
bit okay you have your piece paper with
you. Um, I'm going to show you a
phrase and I want you I want you to copy
down I'm going to show it to you for
about 10 seconds. So, hold your pens up
in the air. You're going to look at this
thing for 10 seconds and then I'm going
to take it off the screen and I want you
to copy it down. Okay,
ready? I want you to copy this down.
Look at it. Memorize it. Look at it.
Five. Four. Three. Just this row. You
don't have to do that one. Just this row
in the middle. Two. one. All right, copy
down as much of that as you
can. All right. And three, two,
one. Everybody, everybody hold up what
you did. Show it to each other. How'd
you do? Oh, man. These are these are a
little bit disappointing. All right,
let's do let's do a second one. Let's do
a second one. Let's see if you can do
any better than this. All right, I'll
help you. You might feel better about
this one. I'm going to give you a set of
writing now that has roughly the same
number of marks in it. It's not the
exact same number of marks. But one,
like one of the things we could do to
calculate how difficult this is, is to
just like count the number of marks on
the screen. I'm going to give you
another thing like this with roughly the
same number of marks. Let's see if you
can do any better. Uh, I want you to
look at this and then get ready to copy
it down. This English phrase in the
middle. Ready? Five, four, three, two,
one. Okay, copy it
down. Oh, you're finished
already. You're really good at that.
Nice. Good. Um,
uh, why why were you so much better at
this one?
Yeah. Yeah. Th you have those squiggles
are organized into schema. When you were
very very young, you observed these
English letters. Actually, if you
learned English in the middle of your
life, whenever you started learning
English, um like just now, you observed
these Sanskrit letters. You know, for
those of you who are native English
speakers, you can't remember the time
probably in which like there would be no
distinguish distinction between English
letters and Sanskrit letters. So, when
you were copying down Sanskrit, none of
this has any meaning to you. So you're
like literally memorizing the order in
which these lines appear. Um which is
really hard because there are lots of
those lines. There's about the same
number of lines. I haven't actually
measured this but it's take take for
grant it's close. Um but um you know
that that two combinations of line is an
L. And you know that an L and E and a T
is a word let. That has some kind of
meaning and you can actually like let
the entire world be happy. Even sort of
bundle that into kind of a phrase that
you can memorize in your head. And so
copying down that number of things is
trivial because this is organized in
your head in a in like a tightly bundled
schema in a way that you have no schema
for understanding these kinds of things.
Probably like the first thing you
started putting in your schema was like
well there's a line that goes across
there and then a bunch of things that
drop down after that. I don't know
anything about sanscript so does that
give you is that an illustration of like
how schema operates in your mind? um
this completely overwhelms your working
memory efforts because you have to
recall the orientation of each
individual line to be able to copy it.
Um this does not at all do that um
because you've already bundled those
lines into schema. Um another famous
example which I think is written about
um is that chess masters um when chess
masters look at a chessboard they can
they like all the pieces they can
remember easily all of the pieces in
their arrangements because if you know
nothing about chess like me you have to
be like okay the pawn is in the second
row black square um and the king is in
the first row white square and the
bishop kind of moved over here but
that's not what chess masters are doing
chess masters are going like, oh, that's
the, you know, the the Turkish Armada
gambit or something like that. And
they've sort of bundled all of those
positions together into one thing. So,
even though we can only attend to three
to five things at any given time, um,
those three to five things can be
enormously complex. Um, and that's what
lets us think about complex and
difficult things. Okay, that piece of
schema makes sense for you? Um, all
right. So, these are these are some
pretty good fundamental models of human
cognitive architecture kinds of things.
Anybody want to ask any questions or
make any observations about some of
these key elements, how our brains work?
I some research to that. Uh there's like
a weird alphabet that's just like
alternative to like writing in Latin and
English. So it just like went toward
mapping between English or Latin
characters to that alphabet. And as a
fun thing, I just wanted to learn it. So
I did all of that like remember the
mapping and even though like hey if you
show me just like a glimpse of it, yes I
can tell you. So it's not like a process
of how long will it take me to remember
but it was very hard to actually
transcribe things fast from one thing to
what I know it is but also as I did that
more I started to like I started kind of
like to remember how I learned English
as well with some of like the for
example at the end like that says ing I
started kind of internalizing that. So
whenever I saw like that kind of
structure of whatever shape these
characters and kind of oh yeah I know
that's I don't have to think
individually about each character. I
started to like chunk them more and more
into specific components that made like
transcribing things much easier. Yeah.
Yeah. I ing is a great example of what
it probably requires uh you know five
different line strokes or something like
that. Line dot one ng something like
that. And then eventually you bundle it
as an ing and just memorize those
characters together. And then eventually
you realize it's a gerand and it has a
particular kind of modification to verbs
and things like that. And you're not
even thinking about it now when you look
at the word jumping. Um but you went
through a process of sort of learning
all of those kinds of things. Okay,
good. Um so based on these models of
human cognitive architecture, what are
some of the key kind of instructional
consequences that come out of this
model?
If you overload the working memory,
students can't store the necessary
information in the long-term memory.
Good. Um, so what what teachers should
be thinking about in some in this model,
what teachers been think about all the
time is like how much cognitive load,
how much stuff is in people is like
being like could potentially be
overwhelming people's working memory. Um
what are some ways to conduct
instruction that respects this
bottleneck of working memory? What are
some what are some effective strategies
for dealing with that? Uh guided
practice is one of them that I saw where
it's like a completion exercise. uh
because then it's not completely novel
to you and you have
more you you can basically abstract more
ideas into schemas that are kind of
bigger and then execute them much faster
instead of just focusing on the smaller
aspects of that problem. Good. So, so
guided one version of guided practice
you know probably one of the most
well-known phenomenon in education
psychology is called the worked example
effect. Um, and the idea is if you show
people how to solve a problem for
noviceses, that is a more effective way
to learn it than have them just try to
solve the problem. Um, that a pretty
typical instructional sequence that
works pretty well is first you do a
worked example. You say, "This is how
you solve this kind of problem." Then
you would take parts of a problem and
have students just do those parts. That
might be a kind of guided practice kind
of thing like okay you know you just
factored this polomial and it took you
four steps um here and the first thing I
did is I just showed you the those four
steps. The next thing I'm going to do is
I'm going to show you three of those
steps and have you do one of them. Um I
just showed you a canonical way to write
an introduction paragraph. Um here is an
introduction paragraph that's three
quarters written. It doesn't really have
a good hook. Um write a sentence that
would fit in this paragraph. That would
be a hook that engaged the reader. You
don't have to do everything else that an
introduction has to do. you don't have
to introduce the topic because we've
already done that, you don't have to lay
out an argument, you don't have to
establish your expertise, just do this
one thing. Um, and then you can imagine
like, all right, instead of, you know,
if it's a four-step process, then you'll
do two of the steps, then you'll do
three of the steps, then eventually
you'll do all of the steps. Um, and you
might alternate which of those step, you
know, do a bunch of one step, you know,
missing problems where the one step
that's missing is sort of different
phases in there. Um, but we're going to
sort of decrease the scaffing. The idea
is um is that you can get people in
their working memory just to attend to
that particular thing they're trying to
solve um to store that thing in the
long-term memory and as they have that
more in their long-term memory and
access it as they start seeing the
relationship between different steps um
as they start you know their schema for
an introduction is not like wait what
it's the hook and then the thesis and
then my expertise is that you bund you
start like recognizing those things as
an introduction and that you know sort
of takes up less space within their
working memory. Um
uh so they call this the completion
problem effects. Replace conventional
problems with completion problems
providing a partial solution that must
be completed by the learners. Um this
list came out of sweller 1998. Um all of
these things get constantly tested and
improved. Um so one thing that people
realized um is an effect which I think
is not on this list called the expert
reversal effect but I think it shows up
in some of the readings that you did um
which is that for noviceses the worked
example effect seems to generally
speaking hold true for experts in a
domain open-ended problem solving does
seem to work better um than um just
going through worked examples. So once
people get good enough at a thing, um
it's a good idea to let them solve
open-ended problems presumably because
their working memory is not overwhelmed.
They're not overwhelmed by cognitive
load, figuring out what they're supposed
to do next. And so it's a chance for
them to refine their abilities to apply
things in different domains to get
better at particular portions of things,
stuff like that. Um now, what is a
novice and what is an expert? Like that,
you know, that is different in every
domain and you'd have to, you know, it
would have to be it'll be different in
nuclear engineering than it is in poetry
or whatever else it is. But like
generally speaking, these are things
that sort of seem to hold.
Um, how do these cognitive load
theorists conduct their research? How do
you how do you, if you're a cognitive
load theorist, how do you establish that
an effect like this is
true? What kind of research methods
would you use?
Well, you could do one where you just
like directly ask the person so they
like have their own just like
understanding of like what they're able
to handle or like you could like set up
the problem so that you can just see
directly from like the work that they're
able to do like how well they're like
cognitive load is being held. Good. So,
one question that cognitive load
theorists will be interested in is like
when when do you feel overburdened by
cognitive load? Um, it's kind of
interesting that people are actually
quite lousy at selfassessing their
learning in all kinds of ways. Um,
there's a classic study, I don't think
we'll read about it, um, where, um,
people assess their baseball knowledge
and then take a test about baseball. Um,
and the results are like the most
perfectly spread scatter plot you've
ever seen. There's basically like no
relationship at all between your self-
assessment of your knowledge and your
actual knowledge of things. Um, so this
is one of the this is one of the real
challenges in cognitive load theory is
that we're not really aware of our own
cognitive load. We're not really aware
when we're encountering desirable
difficulty, which is like giving us a
good amount of challenge um versus
undesirable, you know, where our
cognitive load is, you know, our working
memory is overwhelmed and and we can't
build things. So people have tried to do
work along those lines. Um, what are
some other ways of assessing whether or
not an instructional effect is better
than another instructional effect?
I think
Um in one of the papers it talked about
like physiologically measuring the
cognitive load just by like using heart
rate and things like that. Skin
conductance other kinds of things. Also
said that this like very unreliable as
like a measure of the cognitive load as
well. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Knowing when
knowing when knowing when people are
working memory is over. It's kind of
funny, right? This is like the heart of
the theory. Like how do we tell when
your working me working memory is
overwhelmed? And it's like pretty hard
actually to tell. um you know we don't
we don't have a great grasp of like how
many you know there's some kinds of
exercise we do which especially like
really simple problem solving kind or
puzzle kinds of things where you can
like really tightly control how many
elements are in working memory but if
you're like actually trying to teach
something someone in the real world like
the Kreb cycle or something like that
like you know how many things are in
working memory every time is a lot
harder to sort of check. So a pretty
common set of methods that they'll use
are experimental designs in which you
have one group be a control group and
then you have another group be an
experimental group. Um you measure
people's skill at some in both groups
you measure people's skill in some kind
of baseline. Um, so you say, um, you
know, we're gonna we're gonna design,
you know, we're going to go into a a
math a school where they typically use a
lot of open-ended problem solving, and
we're going to instead have the teacher
just do stuff using worked examples. Um,
and we're going to see whether the
worked example condition is better than
the business as usual condition. And in
fact, to make sure that there's no
difference between the kids who get the
regular condition, the business as usual
condition, the kids who get the work
example condition, we're going to
randomly assign the teachers. We'll go
we'll get 20 or 30 or 40 or 50 teachers
sign up for the study. Half of them will
do the old thing, half of them will do
the new thing. We'll measure all the
kids skill at baseline and then we will
measure the skill um from uh the groups
afterwards. Oh, you know if if this kind
of model works
um you know like the two groups at
baseline in any group there's going to
be a
distrib polinomials or you know add
single digits or um conjugate Spanish
verbs or whatever it is but in any given
classroom like you know there should be
a distribution of skill right some
people are having a hard time with it
most people are doing fine and some
people are doing really good um at
baseline these two groups should be
identical right because we randomly
assign your teachers to two different
groups and random assignment is magical
um and people you know like every once
in a while it doesn't work but for the
most part like the two groups should be
the same. What should happen afterwards
um is that now here's something that
makes learning research really hard. Um
what kind of learning will like learning
will happen in both conditions, right?
Almost everything we do makes people
learn somewhat like it there are very
few things that we do that we're like
boy that was completely ineffective.
Like even if we're not using the most
optimal techniques students still learn
stuff. So in the control condition,
let's call orange
control, there's still at time two going
to be improvement. T1, T2, you're going
to see the sort of distribution move.
What we want to see though is something
like this, like, oh, we learned more in
the experimental
condition when we went from T1 to T2.
Um, and in particular, we're interested
in like the way cognitive load theorists
do this, they're particularly interested
in averages. like in general are kids
more or less better off having do this
like this has 10 teachers each of whom
has 20 kids has 200 kids this has 200
kids is one group o you know sort of
better than the other um sometimes you
can do some of this stuff some of this
stuff happens in the field some of this
stuff happens in laboratory kinds of
experiments um one uh let's see if um uh
so this is a modality effect which is
kind of cool um replace a written expl
explanatory text and another source of
visual information such as a diagram
with a spoken explanatory text and a
visual source of information. It turns
out again we don't to I would say we
don't totally understand this um that
your working memory seems to handle
visual and auditory inputs differently
and so you have a little bit more
working memory to work with if you're
hearing stuff and looking at stuff than
if you're reading stuff and looking at
stuff. Why? Nobody knows. Evolution, who
knows? But it's kind of cool, right? Um
so how might you study something like
that? um you take a textbook um and you
bring a bunch of students into the lab
um and you have them do some kind of
textbook learning exercise. You you
measure them beforehand, you measure
them afterwards. For some random half of
the students who are walking into your
lab, they probably are taking like a
freshman psych class and they have to do
this for, you know, extra credit or
something like that. Um and you give
them the like auditory enhanced version
of this. And if the people in the
auditory-enhanced condition in the
modality effect condition do better um
then you've sort of like you didn't have
to go all the way into the field. You
didn't have to like recruit a bunch of
teachers in real classrooms and things
like that. You can sort study little
bits of this in the lab. But again, the
thing that these folks are particularly
interested in is um changes in average
effects. Um we sort of like these models
tend to assume that we're teaching stuff
that everyone should learn. um it would
be good if all the kids in my math class
learn to factor polomials and we want
strategies that on average have more of
those kids learn more about factoring
polinomials and other things. I'm sort
of emphasizing this point because a
bunch of stuff that you're going to read
for next class doesn't necessarily make
those assumptions. It's still about
learning um but um thinks about doing
research differently and thinks about
goals differently.
Um okay, here are uh oh good. We just
did question number three here of things
that I wanted to talk with you about.
Um, number one, we emphasize what what
for cognitive load theorists, what is
the bottleneck that they're most
concerned
with? Working memory. There's a limited
number of stuff that you can operate
with in working memory. So, you got to
think about, especially for noviceses,
how do you reduce the complexity of a
learning environment?
Um what is
um what what are what what are the what
are the goals of cognitive learn load
theory? What are like the end states of
proficiency?
Um for cognitive load the thirst, what
does it mean to be good at stuff?
Would it be to have built up a bank of
schemas and be able to retrieve them at
any time? and uh use them to work more
quickly through a problem. It could it
could be more quickly. So definitely I I
think the first part I would say you're
spot on about that you have memorized a
bunch of stuff. The stuff that you've
memorized is organized into schemas of
varying degrees of complexity. There's
some things that don't organize well
into schemas but you know but we just
memorize them anyway. Um, famous things
that don't fit super well into more
complex schemas are, um, a bunch of
Asian languages have characters that
don't like have a lot of logic across
them. Like you just have to memorize
these things and there are a lot of
them. Um, and that like like schemas
will only get you so far. Um, but an
important thing about there's no
relation I think about it this way.
There's no relationship between sort of
proficiency and the learning process
like like what do cognitive load
theorists think a really good surgeon is
like a really good surgeon is both
proficient at certain kinds of
well-established techniques but also
flexible intuitive like you you know a
patient has cancer and you cut them open
and it's some kind of you know like set
of physical problems they've never seen
before you know they don't want doctors
who are like oh I must memorize the
procedure and just do what I'm told they
want doctors who are flexible they want
poets and playwrs who are creative. Um
they want, you know, teachers who are
engaging and effective. Like their
vision of proficiency is the same as
almost anybody else who studies teaching
and learning. Um just because they have
methods that are sort of like it doesn't
mean that they want people the rest of
their lives trying to reduce the amount
of working load, you know, load on their
working memory. They want people who who
can do all of the things that we think
experts should be able to do. But they
say the way you get expertise is not to
take a surgeon and be like just get in
there and start cutting people up and
like see what happens. Like you want to
train them through a particular series
of processes that has them um you know
memorize a particular series of facts.
Those facts can be assembled in
knowledge or techniques or other kinds
of things and then flexibly deploy those
things they memorized um to do good work
in the world. Um, so, so don't don't
confuse the way that cognitive load
theorists want people to learn. Um, you
know, which which can be like like
pretty structured, have this devolving
scaffolding. That doesn't mean that
that's what expertise looks like when
you get to the end of that process. We
might teach people to be really good
computer programmers through a set of
worked examples, but doesn't mean that
we want computer programmers who just
like copy things that they've seen in
the world. We want those computer
programmers to be flexible, creative,
novel, inventive, all those kinds of
good things.
Um, you read two other pieces that I
didn't uh talk as much about, but does
um we talked a little bit about sweller,
the story of a research program. um that
this research comes out of a particular
historical context um which is people in
math pretty fired up about problem
solving and this guy John Sweller being
like I think there are some real
problems with open-ended problem
solving. I think it doesn't do what we
want it to do and there might be better
approaches to try.
Um what what what did you take away from
the Michael Pashan article? So, Michael
Bashan's a teacher in New York City. Um,
just teaches math to a bunch of
different grades and he's trying to make
sense of all this research. What did you
take away from the things he was trying
to make sense of?
So the title of his piece is not a
theory of everything. What what did what
did that allude to?
I could give like a read response and
say applying cognitive fluency theory to
cognitive learn theory and just like you
know restricting it to where it is
putting the boundaries making sure we
understand what it is and what it's not
to make sure that when we're discussing
it we're not stepping beyond it and
starting like confusing things together
and not know what we're talking about.
Good. So some of it is him saying like
all right like what like what exactly
are these terms and how are they used
how they mean over time? Um when Michael
Pashan says not a theory of everything,
what are some of the things that
prominently it is not a theory of
is it motivation? Yeah. Why why do you
think so Michael Michael teaches math in
in a school in New York? Why do you
think motivation would be something that
would be of pretty keen interest to
Michael? I think that could like affect
how likely people are to remember their
content, right? They're like if you're
really interested, really motivated that
could affect. Yeah. Yeah. I think I
think you have a subtext of Michael's
argument which like my guy, you know,
like your clogged working memory is not
the problem I have. My problem is my
kids don't care. Like like if you're not
actually interested and engaged and want
to learn these things, who cares if
you're stuck, you know, like it's not a
problem to be putting seven or nine
things in their working memory. The
problem is they will put zero things in
their working memory. um you know the
the the the pro the the problem is not
the bottleneck that appears here. The
problem is you can't get them to do
this. You can't get them to attend to
anything. Um I think there's part you
know and and and for him as a teacher
motivation is just a central pro like a
central problem of what he does every
day. How am I going to convince these
fourth graders in front of me that it's
worth learning these this math? Um, and
that I think part, you know, reading
between the lines, I think that's part
of what feels really important to
Michael. Um, and John Sweller says this
theory doesn't do that. Um, this theory
doesn't attend to issues of motivation.
Uh, you know, now the good thing about
doing that, um, and I think Michael
comes to this conclusion in some
respects is like, yeah, it's probably
not a good idea for every theory to try
to do everything. you know, it it
doesn't diminish the contributions of
cognitive load theory to say it doesn't
attend to motivation, but it probably
should draw our attention to the fact um
that working memory is not like the
single bottleneck that exists in all
learning environments everywhere.
They're all kinds of other bottlenecks
that might be around. Again, some of the
stuff that we're going to read about
next week thinks of motivation as a very
central issue um as maybe like the
central issue to teaching and learning,
which doesn't mean that this other
theory is better. Um but that the the
theories that we have are just models.
They help us sort of make sense. You
know, nobody actually understands how
the brain works. Nobody actually
understands how people learn. Um that is
sort of beyond our but there's a lot
that we can know about it and we can
build these models which help us make
good predictions. Um but they don't help
us predict kind of everything. Um uh the
other thing that I think Michael's
article is really good for highlighting
is that these theories change. Um how
many of you read in the original article
about this thing called gerine load?
Yeah, that researchers in cognitive lo
theory have basically given up on
germaine load. Like it was an idea they
had for a while. They were working on
it. They thought it would predict some
stuff. They thought it would explain
some stuff and after a while like I
don't think this germaine load idea is
all that useful and people have more or
less given up on it. So these theories
are sort of constantly changing and
evolving too. You know the version of
cognitive load theory um that I might
teach in this class 20 years from now is
not going to be the exact same as I
would have you know in the 1980s when
John Sweller was just sort of putting
these things together. some you know
some parts of it have sort of stood the
test of time I would say you know
particularly this idea you know the the
idea of extraneous load seems to be
enormously helpful um if you put too
much stuff in front of noviceses they
won't attend to the right things and
they won't remember the things you
really want them to remember or they
won't you know they won't be able to
attend to what you want them to do but
if you reduce some of that extraneous
load and there are a bunch of like very
specific strategies that we can use to
reduce that extraneous load you know
some of which are you know very very
fine grained um if there are multiple
sources of information frequently
pictures and accompanying text um like
don't put the picture over here and the
text over here put them in the same
place and people will learn better um
that's great that's you know um like
think think about how many people today
in the United about 57 million kids in
K12 schools tens of million people in
higher education like if all their
textbooks got a little bit better by
adhering to this principle like everyone
would learn you know a tiny tiny bit
more but you know amvertised over 57
million kids going to school for 13
years that could be a lot of learning
Um, that's pretty cool. Uh, all right.
220. What are the last things that I
want to leave you with? Um, you now
have, um, 50% of the ideas that you will
need to do assignment number one. Um, so
again, assignment number one, which you
should go to the syllabus and read, is
you're going to pick an educational
technology. You're going to explain it
that if that educational technology is
more inspired by instructionists, by
people who are really fired up about um
direct teaching of things, the cognitive
load theorists or
instructionists, you know, the worked
example effect is an instructionist kind
of idea. There are lots of education
technologies which are instructionist in
nature. You're like, how are we going to
tell people how to do this thing so they
do it better? Um there are other um
pedagogies, educa um education
technologies which are much more focused
on experience, much more focused on
apprenticeship um how do we get into the
world and muck about and do things and
that is what you will read about for
Monday um which is you know sort of like
like and both of these ideas are
ancient. I mean I think I mentioned you
before this quote from Plutarch um that
uh education is not the filling of a
pale but the lighting of a fire. Um, you
know, the cognitive load theories are
like, "No, pale filling is awesome. This
is like super effective. We can measure
how much stuff goes into the pale. We
can measure how much stuff leaks out of
the pale. We can measure like the
optimal flow rate into the pale. Pale
filling is cool." Um, we're now going to
find the sort of contemporary versions
of the flame kindlers. People are trying
to really get their minds around like
how do you get people to learn and kind
of naturalistic apprenticeship
reactions. So, you're going to have to
find a technology. You have to explain
whether it's more instructionist or
constructionist, more inspired by
cognitive load theory or situated
learning. Describe how the features of
that technology reflect these
pedagogical values. That's like the
first couple pages of the assignment. Um
you have something like 1,200 words, but
you can include pictures, you can
annotate things, you be like, "Look,
this is like a little screenshot of the
thing and like here's, you know, where
instructionism is written all over it."
Then in the last part of the paper, you
have to take this same technology and
imagine that it was redesigned or
designed originally by people from the
opposite pedagogical perspective. So you
might go and find a technology be like
man this is like straight cognitive load
theory. What if this same technology
with the same kind of goals was designed
by situated learning constructionist
kind of people that is a t so you can be
thinking um as you're doing all of these
kinds of readings um what are some of
the key principles that I could use? How
would I apply these key principles to
education technologies? which education
technology am I most interested in? How
am I going to learn about the other
pedagogical philosophy so I can apply in
the same way? Um that should give you
some stuff to work with. Okay. Um 2:25
we'll meet on Monday. You'll read stuff
about situated learning. We'll do
similar kinds of exercises to make sense
of it. Um if you uh have questions, come
swing by, take your books with them,
write your names in them so that you
don't get them confused with other
people's. And uh you can expect another
email from me hopefully in the next
couple days. I remember almost every
week. I don't promise it comes out. It's
like a courtesy service, but it's like a
little summary of what you need to do
for next week. Okay, I'll stick around
if anybody needs anything. Otherwise,
um, have a wonderful weekend and I'll
see you on Monday.