so here so from this clim we can show
this is in this relation R so in fact we
also need a s for this relation R and
this uh so in this construction we need
a s Construction for this relation R and
uh so this follows from the so for this
kind of C it follows from the the work
uh so it's
almost almost can handle all of the SP
relation up to some parallel repetition
so I will not go into the detail of this
work um so if you're interested you can
read it yourself so this is the work uh
so is c for efficiently verifiable
product relation uh it's the beautiful
work by uh so this is the home uh hrr
home ground L Body and the Ros
BL
okay
uh okay so finally
uh so so let me ask a question okay yeah
uh could you say again why we need like
why the cih we saw in last week plus is
good enough uh right good question so so
last week the S you saw is for
searchable relation so that means uh the
relation so the relation
here so the the S relation
here
uh so the right so the relation here
need to satisfy the searchable property
so it means uh so this beta so for any
fixed Alpha there exist a unique beta uh
such that this Alpha Beta is in this
relation R and moreover there is a
efficient algorithm uh some some
efficient algorithm F such that it can
take this Alpha and the output such a
beta so that's a search efficiently
searchable mean uh so here so here it's
possible that for fixed Alpha there
there might be multiple uh multiple beta
that can satisfy this relation because
for a fixed PCP uh there might be
multiple queries that can make the per
PCP be accepted yes good question
yeah so what what the hrr shows that uh
if the if the sparse relation has
efficient W fire algorithm then uh most
of the then you can you can build a s
for them up to some par repetition yeah
roughly speaking it's a yeah
so okay so so uh so now we have a
construction of snarks but let's see
what's the proof size for this
snark so uh so the so the proof size
consist of the first message and the
thir R message so the first run message
consist of l l of hash values so you can
think each H value is also F separate
text so it's a PO Lambda bits so in
total the first round message uh consist
of uh po
c times po
L but is but it's independent of the
K and the third R message uh is K
times poly log
c times
Pol because for each in the thir R
message for for each instance you send
uh Q PCP answers so the size of Q is uh
is Lambda times poly log
C so in total you have you send K of the
K of them so in total it's K times
this okay so so this is already
non-trivial because it's a uh so this
this number it could be much smaller
than K * K * W so right because the
second term is almost order of K and the
first term is almost C so yeah so this
is already non- trial but it's still
large
so uh so the Bigg issue is if you look
at the verification time so
the the verification time is you all see
is
uh uh K * policy the reason is the
verifier need
to uh verify the PCP answers for each of
the instances for for X1 to
XK so the so in this step so each PCP
verification need to take C time and in
total it need to take K times
policy yeah why is there a PO
oh so that's the that's because the each
each query is uh so each query so if you
remember yeah so here so each quy sze is
Lambda times poog
C so it's a yeah so they're not just
single uh right so so here so here we
have a Lambda term because we need to do
the parallel ation so you take a you
take a PCP with constant uh uh s this
arrow and you amplify it uh LDA Times by
parall repetition
want yeah so you can have PCP with
perfect perfect complains yeah so you
don't need to worry about the when you
do the par reputation okay so so the
verification time is still very large uh
so in fact you don't have any savings if
you do this directly so on the
verification time so and the so let's
consider uh for
a for a general snarks for B MP or barks
so what's the verification time so
remember the wif fire in in a bark the
wif fire need to read uh at least the
CRS and all of the statement to verify
the proof so so the verifier uh need to
at least read all of the instance so it
seems that there is a lower Bond on the
verification time the lower bond is just
at least K * X
okay
so uh so next I will show you how to
reduce the verification time and the
proof size of barks but uh uh we will uh
first
uh right so we will uh consider a
variant of bark and it don't have this
lower bound on verification
time so the idea so I will Define a new
notion of uh
barks uh let me re erase this
so in this notion of Bo is called uh so
it's called
the index
SP or you can also call it a
snarks for uh batch index
so so the idea is so in the original
definition of barks the Wi-Fi need to
read off the instance because the
instance are nonuniform so in this
notion uh we will consider a special
case when this uh instance are uniform
so intuitively it means there exists
some circular
U such that the is instance is generated
by using the circuit U and the
index so so
intuitively it says the instance can be
described in a uniform Way by only use
the index and if this is the case
then then what the pro try to prove is
X1 to XK is all in this language
l so so now it is equivalent to say uh
so for index for each index
I there exist witness wi uh such that
this c c and the
UI W equals 1 so so then we can Define
so essentially this is you can build
this as a new uh MP relation so the new
MP relation is the is defined as follows
so the instance is just index and it
verifies uh there exist a
wi such
that so this is just a rewriting of this
right so so
this
so uh right and then you can you can
view this as a new new uh mp uh MP
verification circuit that s c Prime so
it only takes wi and the I and the wi
input and it internally compute this you
and the Wii C so this Inspire us to
define a new notion called uh index bark
so a index
bark definition uh a index SP
uh is a
bark uh for this uh for this kind of
relation so it it is for this uh this
kind of language where the the language
is just some general NP language but the
instance is treated as an index
for this
language and the prover so the
pro the we still have a uh CRS and
the the prover tries to convince the
wiif fire that uh all of the indices
from one two ET to K is in this language
so the only Pro also so only Pro only to
read index K and uh it has witness from
W1 to WK for each of the index and the
WiFi only need to take K as
input so so now the
verifier so this K can be represented as
log K bits because it's just the index
so so what's the uh best verification
time we can hope for
uh anyone
else so oh good so the verification time
is uh so the verification so the wif
only to read this index K and the
proof so the wif can be as small as uh
verification time only need to be uh
some log k
can be as small as this much so only
depends on l k and the Lambda
so okay so this is
uh uh
right and for this index bar we also
require the completeness and the
soundness uh in the same way as
before uh any questions yeah actually
should I think this you think part
in yeah so you can think it's a
yeah so you can think it it's uh you can
always uh absorb it in the in the
relation circuit so you can you can
think it's part of the relation right I
guess are we going to pay for the size
of description of you anywhere or is
that uh right right good so the
verification circuit in fact they need
also to depend on C right because the
verifier need to read the circuit
yes and is there like a unique instance
to this problem then like
yeah so so now the the point is now the
verification time don't depends on
linear in K so previously you need to
read all the instance and now you the
verification only gr log in
yeah think of C as part of the input
c c as part of the input uh So
like
um or I guess C Prime which like stor
you in it uh right yes yes right okay so
that is then how would so V still has to
read
what a lot of yeah so you can uh so it
depends on how you define it so you can
Define it for a fixed C and you have
such a proof system or you can define a
proof system for any c then you need to
you need the verification time to grow
with the c size C is it defining it for
a f c kind of
like like not that helpful because we
just solving bch for like a b
Set uh but you can you choose C to be
universal circuit then it's a
yeah then it's
General uh good question so right I
think yeah if you take a universal you
need to you to use the U maybe yeah yeah
it's good to think c as the input
yeah okay so and uh and the and uh so in
the remaining time of this lecture we
all prove uh we all prove the following
theorem
so there exist a
a index
Spark from lwe and the Pro proof
size is
uh po uh log so you grow log in
K uh C and
Lambda and the verification
time is uh log K C Lambda
okay so both of them are
uh uh almost match the best you can hope
for up to some
polinomial
so and
uh okay so here I want to emphasize
the so I want to emphasize here
that in fact you can if you know how to
build uh this index bark then you can
build barks with almost the same
verification time and proof
size so in other words uh in fact any uh
a batch of instance are without a loss
of generality uniform uh in sense
so
so so what I will show you is uh in fact
if you know how to build index
Mark then you can use it in a generic
way to build
barks so the reduction works as follows
so suppose we
have so so now we want to build a bark
uh for a bunch of instance from X1 to XK
so the idea is uh we will first build a
mirle harsh of all of the
instance
so and we have some has
root so now uh we have the prover send
this has root to the wif fire and the
prove that and use and then we have the
approver to show that for any index
I uh there exist a local
opening row
I uh so the local opening remember is
the root two Le path for each of the
leaf okay so there ex local opening
row I for
XI such
that
um such that the local verification will
pass for this
XI local
verification so the local verification
algorithm will take the h root and the
index I and the
XI which is the open value and also this
local opening which is the root2 de
pass and moreover uh there is also exist
a wi such that the original circuit is
satisfied so so the idea is you just has
all of the instance from X1 to XK and
you send the uh H value to the wifire
then you prove for each indexi there
exist opening XI to this has and uh this
uh C of XI is satisfied so in this way
you convert uh gener so you convert a
batch of NP instance to a index uh to a
batch index in
instance because so now now the
statement only grow so so it prove
something for each index I so you can
view so you can view this uh so you can
view this
part so you can view this part as some
circuit c c Prime so C Prime will take
index I and the winess row i w i and
check the check the two
things then you can generate generate a
uh index bark for this instance for for
each of the instance from X1 from one to
K
so and and this uh uh and then you
generate a index bark for for this kind
of instance so so now you send this to
the wifire and this is your
bark
yeah
so okay so the so if the if the uh if Pi
is small and the H is small your total
proof size is also small so that's the
idea so next uh I will only focus on so
we'll come back to this point later uh
when we uh so because the proof of
soundness of this transformation is not
trivial because in fact you all you all
see this is not so so the nonadaptive
soundness previously is not sufficient
to prove the soundness
because this circuit will depends on
this hash and is chosen adaptively by
the adversary so we will come back to
this point later to show how to prove
the soundness of this
transformation okay so next I will show
you how to build this index
Park so so our starting point is uh
is still this protocol so as I just said
uh earlier so the first round message is
small because it only depends on C but
the thiron message is large so how can
we further compress the thiron
message okay
so so in the context of index bark all
of the instance are just indices so I
can replace them with one
Tok and the idea is a we're going to
dedicate we're going to uh remove this
round
message we're going to remove this round
of message and
uh so we're going to dedicate this uh uh
verif the verification of this message
to the prover so the prover will have
this this uh open the query The Columns
in his hand but uh he is not going to
send them to the wifire instead the
prover is going to verify do the
verification by itself and prove to the
verifier those verification is indeed
correct so so the uh construction work
like
this so the
pro still send this
uh H1 to
HL to the
wifire and the prover is going to
compute this uh
uh PCP query using the
cush and then the approver and the wiif
fire is going to run another protocol
so another snar
uh and this snark uh on the prover side
he has he's going to uh use the columns
the open columns uh
as the input to this
protocol and in the end the WiFi is
convinced that this uh
uh the the third round message verifies
so what does this mean is the pro is
going to prove
for uh so the prover is going to prove
for there
exist the pro is going to prove to this
ware in this protocol
the following language so there exist uh
L
columns Q such
that yes such that uh two things so one
is uh
the one is for each uh for each column
for each Que in the query the set the
has
is competed correctly it's consistent
with the first message so the HQ is is
the
SSB of
the column the Q is column so I omit the
uh SSB key here okay and the second for
each
PCP for each instance so for any I in K
so here the instance is just the index I
the is instance XI just XI so he will
verify this
uh so
the PCP verification of
I uh
Q
yes and the The Q's column
uh the ice coordinate of the Qs
column and we collect them
together okay
so so this is the this is the statement
this protocol wants to prove and the pro
is going to supply it with the uh
widness which is this
okay so that's the high level
idea so but to achieve this uh so so
suppose we can rewrite this uh statement
as a batch index statement then I can uh
apply the same construction again on top
of this statement so we can apply the
same thing again to this through this
new statement and uh I can do the
recursing so that's the idea so how do I
but the issue is how do I represent this
as a batch index language so how do I
how do I represent is as a index as a
batch of index language so how do I
represent it as a batch of
index so so now you can see uh maybe you
think okay so this is a almost index
because index language because this is
at least this part is uh this is clear
for any index I
so right this is for any index uh index
I in K there is something so this is
similar to our index language but this
part is not
clear so the the reason is uh Q is very
small uh but the MP widness is very
large so so if you if you treat this Q
as a instance then the widness size is K
because each column has uh K entries so
for each column contains the PCP
coordinate for each of the instance so
the column size is
K but if if I treat this column uh
column Q as a widness then uh when I do
the recursion the proof size will grow
with the size of K because because it
because the because again I will have
this kind of this kind of hash
values some some L Prime but for but
those actual to l l
Prime H1 Prime to h l prime prime so
they are for the for the new protocol
and the new instance so they will grow
with the size of K so that's too large
we cannot uh afford that
so so next I will uh rewrite this
instance as a batch of uh statements and
the statement size will be K but the MP
widness will be
small okay so how do I rewrite
it so so let's look at what what this do
this verification do
so so for each this verification we have
a column Q
so and this size is
K so it will it will recompute this s SB
and check uh if it is if it's the same
with some HQ which is the h was sent in
the first
round
so so the idea is that suppose this
SSB uh suppose we have some more
structure of this s s hash then I can uh
local verify it so that means uh if I
build this SSB with
some so
see for example if the SSB is built in
merco tree as a merco tree then I can
replace this verification by verify
that uh for
each uh index I for each index I in
K there exist a local opening row
i
q so row IQ is the local opening for the
you can think for each index I I have a
I have a
I have an entry the entry is uh column Q
the highest position of the column q and
I have a local opening for
that row
IQ so I only to show there exist such a
local opening for this
has so so here HQ is the has value right
so for uh for HQ
yeah I only to verify
this so now now I get a a batch of MP
instance right
so
uh yeah so let me rewrite this
so suppose I have a uh SSB buil in the
mer Treeway
then so the protocol will uh work like
this so initially we have H1 to
HL and we have this
Q so in the new
protocol uh we are going to the Pro is
going to supply with with the quired
column
uh for this que and also a bunch of
local openings for each coordinate in
this uh Q
okay
so so and this protocol will
prove uh so this protocol is a new
uh index spk
protocol it will prove for a new
instance L for for new language l l
Prime let's denote
it so L
prime it contains all the index
I and uh for each index I I need to show
there exist a
uh witness which
is column
q
i so this is the is uh PCP answer and
and uh and they are corresponding I also
need this Q row
IQ uh such
that so first I need to verify the PCP
answers right
and the second I need to verify the
local opening is correct so I need to
verify the so there is some local
opening verification
algorithm the local verification
algorithm will take the H root uh for
each
q and uh so I need to verify this for
for
areq and this local verification
algorithm of SSB will verify row IQ
yeah uh any questions so this is the
new so this is the new
instance new L
Prim so for each I uh and so the pro
need to prove uh so the pro need to
prove one two 2K are all in this l l
PR
right so yeah uh any questions
yeah we this and the idea is that the
the number the same but the Witnesses
are not gr uh good question so if you do
this recre it will forever because the
because uh from the beginning we have K
instances and then in the next level of
the recursion we still have havek
instances
so exactly so that's what what we will
do
next uh any question yeah so HQ is a he
of statements sorry HQ oh right so HQ is
part of the statement right
so the statement X1 to
xq uh oh you mean where is the X where
is HQ comes from yes oh good so HQ is
the same as HQ here so so you have so
initially we have a bunch of statement
from one to K and each of them has NP
witness from Omega 1 to Omega K and we
arrange this uh we compute this PCP
Matrix and for each column we has it to
H1 to
HL so and the HQ is just the q's Q's
column of this m of this h12
HQ yeah the the index Q among this h12
hqe local version of the SSP is some
variant of the F A yeah so that's what
I'm going to talk about next yeah so so
now you may ask uh so how do we
construct such a SSB with uh merco style
construction
so because the construction I just
showed you doesn't satisfy this property
so this is a
SSB so SSV with this local opening
property so what it says is uh the idea
is so if we build the H like a merco
tree we have this uh local opening so
for
example and
the the issue is how do we uh how do we
still have the someware this someware St
isal binding property so the idea is
just uh so at each note of the tree
we're are going to um pick under the
hood of f one of each
children so so you can think uh
initially we have some X1 2 XK
uh in the clear and uh we we have some
so at each at each level we are going to
pick either is is left child or right
child for each noes in this level for
example in this level so suppose this is
your index I then what we can do is for
each node in this level we're going to
pick uh pick the left
child and uh and at this level we're
going to pick pick the right
child
so so at each each level we're going to
have some uh
fhe homic encryption of some bit so some
bit B1 and uh so let's say this is
B2 and each level we're going to
homologically evaluate this using this
B12 and B2 to uh
to choose to pick the children on the
hood of FH in the same way as
before so so this can give you SSB with
local
opening okay but uh what we will so so
one property we uh further require about
this uh SSB is the local opening
correctness
okay so we require this property because
uh remember in the s
proof we need to ensure uh if the wifire
if the proof is accepted in the thir
round then the proof the proof con
contains some opening of the
SSB and we need to show this opening
must be consistent with the uh SSB
extracted value so originally this is
easy to ensure because the Wii sees the
entire opening but now it's not clear
whether this can still holds because so
now the verifier only sees a local
opening of the
SSB okay so it does not uh SE all the
X12 XK it only sees the root to leave
path of some XI so we need to we need
our further uh local opening correctness
so the correctness of local opening says
that
uh so so this uh SSV with local opening
has some uh local verification
algorithm so it will take uh it will
take the H root H and the some index I
and the x i and the root to pass for
this XI and it can decide whether to
accept or reject okay and the local
opening property says that for any uh
index i h x i and row I so if
the so if this
uh uh local verification
passes then it must be case
that uh
the extract the
value uh of the hash equals this XI so
so here
uh
yeah the local verification let me
see so the local verification also need
to use the SSB
key to check this okay
so here uh if this is true and uh the
SSB key is generated for
the for the index
I yeah then I
need if the local appication passes then
the exed value must be XI so this is not
triv correct this is not Tri hold if you
use just this construction because uh um
ious so a malicious f it will contain
the RO to pass to this
XI but it also need to contain the
siblings of this so in this
authenticated path it also need to
contain the siblings of each node in the
past but those siblings may not be well
formed FH SE text so so indeed you need
to further add some put strum mechanism
here so you need to Hally encrypt the so
at each level of the F you need to use a
different F key and at the next level
you need to you need to hopic decrypt
the F SE text at the previous level to
ensure it's a Well phone SE text so I'm
not going to the detail but you can you
can fix this this easily by your own
yes okay so so now so
now
uh uh any question with this constrction
yeah why
using SSB in a m fre style instead
of uh good question so if you directly
use SSV in a m tree style uh um maybe
there is some uh separate Tech size blow
up so each time you yeah so each time
the sear T size is Lambda times larger
and the
yeah this new
version index bar when when we hash the
column yeah we have has it in the mic
side instead of hasing it in one uh
right right you mean we don't has it U
as entirely we we has in the M tree
style yes yes yes yes yes that's where
are what we are
doing okay any
question okay
so uh so if you do this contraction
directly then uh this contraction will
Loop forever because the recursion will
never end so initially we have K
instances and at the next level it still
has K instances so next what we will do
is we will use a two to one trick to
reduce the number of instance each time
so let me
so so let's denote
the so let's denote this circuit so this
part of the circuit as some C
Prime okay some C Prime so C Prime will
take some index I and the widness wi
Prime so the winess wi Prime correspond
to this part so so this part is the uh I
prime okay so the so the two to the one
trick is
this uh suppose you have K instances so
for so now you want to verify all them
uh are so you have in instance from 1
Tok and their winess are W1 Prime to WK
Prime and you want to ensure so the pro
wants to prove to the warier that all of
them are correct are in this language Al
PR okay so what you do
is
uh you look at any two adjacent indices
uh
instances and uh just the
combiner Okay so
so now the combined instance is still
one but it's a uh but the Witnesses are
concatenated together so you have this
uh W1 Prem and W2 Prem and
uh and the next two instance are W are
three and four so you have this three
prime and the W4 Prime
and you the final one is K and the w k
so you combine each adjon one to get to
get the second
instance and you do this for any two two
of them so in the end you have K by two
instances but the cost of doing this is
the size of the winess will blow up by a
factor of two so
okay so so now we obtain so let's say
the original uh language is L Prime so
it contains of I uh such that there
exist w i
Prime
uh so now so c c Prime is the
verification cir of L Prime then then
here the new
instances uh is the following so it
defines a new language Al L double Prim
so double Prim is still contains all I
but it uh the winess are uh 2 I minus
one and the 2 I and the W 2
I uh 2 I
prime so so this is this concatenation
concatenated witness is a new
uh MP winess for this L double and you
need to verify uh C Prime of this uh 2
IUS one W 2 IUS one is one and
also 2 I and 2 I is
one
okay so so by doing this the size of the
the the number of the instance will half
each time when you do the recursion
so so after so right so in fact we will
prove this for L double par and uh and
we only proove for one 2K uh by two they
are all in L double
par yeah in in the recursion yeah so
that's what we all
do okay so so now the question is uh at
the end of the recre
so uh at the end of the recre each time
um so at each level of the recession the
number of instance were half so at the
end there will only be one instance so
what will we do uh at that
point uh anyone
knows
directly yes yes right so we directly
send the witness and the Wii can verify
it
okay so so now let's calculate the
uh so this is the construction and let's
calculate the proof size for this
construction so the so initially um so
initially we send this uh H1
to HL and that cost so so so the size of
that is
uh po
C right uh policy policy and
Lambda and
uh and we have this
Q uh competed by the
S uh but at the next level of the
recursion so so at the next level of the
recursion we will we also have this
first run message for that for
that uh so let's denote it by uh H uh H
Prime so what's the CLE of this message
so remember this is the index bark for L
double PR and it has circuit the
verification circuit C double
print so what is the size of this
message so this is a
efficiency
yes so so in the next level of
verication we all do the same for the
using the same protocol so so originally
the verif the NP verification circuit is
C so we have first R message this much
so in the next level the MP verification
circuit is see double par so so the size
of this message is uh poy cble Prim
Lambda but there is a issue uh if you do
this recursion directly
so so let's exam what is size of C
double PR so C double PR will contain so
each C double PR will contains uh two
copy of c c
Prime right
so so C double
Prime uh oh I should say okay so I right
so I should say this is
the so this is the couble prime so right
so it I'll take index I and this as the
winess and verify these two things so so
the size of the couble Prime is roughly
uh 2 *
C and the so what is the size of C uh C
Prime so the C Prime so C Prime is here
uh so C Prime the first part of the C
Prime is the PCP verification so here we
will have a issue because the because
the PCP verifier need to know what is
the he at Le need to know what is the NP
relation so the PCP verifier runs in C
time right so so the so we all have a
issue here
because because the C Prime is uh
roughly C uh at least
C so if we do this directly so you can
think at the top level we have this poly
C and uh at the next level we have this
poy C Prime which is uh 2 C so so this
is 2 C and at the next level of
recursion we have 4 C so so we have uh
log K level of recursion because each
time the number of instance
half so the number of uh so the depth is
l k so in the end we have K * C which is
large so so the proof will grow with K
time K time C which is large so so the
final idea is uh we are going to use a
PCP uh with some special property so
this this kind of PCP has this uh online
offline verification property so this is
called
PCP with
fast online
verification
so so those PCP uh has the property that
so for any PCP prover and verifier so
given any NP instance X and W you can
generate a long
proof right so so this is just a normal
PCP but the verification algorithm of
the PCP is uh has more structure so the
verification algorithm so originally the
PCP verifier need to verify for x q and
the PCP
Q so so now the PCP verifier uh can be
composed decomposed to two parts so
first uh so there is a offline
pre-processing phase so the
pre-processing phase only depends on the
relation circuit
C okay so this is a PCP for the language
l so the pre-processing phase will take
the relation circuit as input and uh it
will use the query to generate some
State and this state will only grow uh
the size of the state is polinomial in s
in
X so so the point is uh so in some case
when the relation circuit is very
large so the pre-processing phase will
gr well runs in the size of the relation
circuit but it will output of a very
short
State and the uh secondly in the online
phase there is a online verification
part so the online verification will
only used such a short State and the
X and the right and the Q and the PCP
verific uh and the PCP answer to decide
whether to accept or reject so the point
is uh the online verification phase uh
only depends on the so it's a polom Time
algorithm so which means it only depends
on X and the size of
Q okay so so you can imagine if the c c
is the C is a very big circuit and the X
instance is small then this means the
pre-processing phase will uh the
pre-processing phase will take most of
the time but the online verification
will be very fast it only depends on the
instant
size and the S of the query so this this
property is Satisfied by most of the
algeb right construction of PCP
so yeah uh any
questions so I will not go into the
detail because the so it uh so in fact
this property is used in many practical
snug construction because in the
Practical snar construction they also
need to use PCP or some form of the PCP
such as linear PCP so in those
construction you also have the problem
that the relation circuit is very large
but you want the ification to be small
so what they do is they can do some
pre-processing on the relation uh to
generate some short verification State
and given the verification State you can
verify the statement in a short
time
okay so so so now we will use this uh
PCP with this uh uh this uh
further with this uh property and uh
then we can
so then we can further modify the
construction to to only do the online
verification here in C
plan okay
[Applause]
so so what we will do here is uh we
first generate the s
using the S to generate que and then we
do the pre-processing to this queue uh
to generate some short
State and this will use the relation
circuit C so we can do this because uh
we use the same PCP query for all of the
uh PCP pcps so right so so is for all of
the PCP they are using the same PCP
query so I can do this pre-processing
so once I have this state I this short
State I can hard code it in this
construction of C Prime so I I replace
this with the
online oh sorry so this is a local where
verification so this online verification
of the
PCP so it will take the state and all
the
rest so now this will solve this
recursion issue because the because now
the circuit C Prime will will not
depends on C instead it will be poog in
C the reason is that so here uh you so
you can check here because the C world
uh it will only involve online
verification so it only so it's uh part
IAL of
the is a polom in the lens of I which is
log K and the
yeah uh right and and the and the local
appication of the merco has is also
small so it's also po some poog in K so
that you can check is
a so this is
poog log K and Lambda and then you can
you can take this recreation in inside
of this uh analysis and see uh finally
the proof size is only poly
loging so the proof size is the total
proof size is
uh poog
in in C and the poog in
K and
polyda yeah
oh I
guess the
Bas yes yes so the so the so in fact
after you do this once so at one level
of the recre the witness is already very
small so because the witness is just
it's just the PCP opening so it's poly
loogy so finally the at the end the
final level winess is also very small
so I I don't I probably don't have time
to cover all the security proof but I
will show you the most important part of
it and
uh so the so the so how do we prove the
security of this
construction so so now the construction
is here so
to prove the security it's natural to
use the so suppose we have some security
of this uh index bar then maybe we can
use it recursively to prove the security
of the entire
construction but uh but we have a issue
here so isue is L double Prim it all
depends on the first
message because the so L Prim will use
this L PR so this C so this c will
depend well use the hash root this HQ so
this H root come comes from this hash
this hash value and of the h12
HL so so this means the adversary can
potentially choose this uh uh choose the
next statement depends on the CRS
because CRS is first cud anniversary so
this is not captured by the nonadaptive
sound soundness before so we need a new
definition of soundness
and the issue is that we don't know how
to achieve fully adaptive soundness so
the Adaptive soundness means that the
cheating adversary can choose the
instance depending on the CRS and the so
what we what we prove is some semi
adaptive soundness
so this this s this notion is not only
important in this security proof it will
also be crucial for your next lecture so
when you compile this uh batch index to
of snar 4
P
so so it defin as follows so it says
that so it allows the cheating improver
to choose the relation Circ
uh but it cannot choose which uh index
to cheat
so so let me Define it so we
say
uh uh index spk is
sound if there
exist if so first I need a another uh
key generation algorithm uh CRS
generator so I'll call it uh generate
bar so it will take
the security parameter as input and
index I star and will generate some s
star okay and uh I
require and this uh
CRS uh generator is IND distinguishable
with
the real uh
CRS and furthermore uh for each uh
nonuniform PBT adversary cheating
improver P star we need to have the
following
property
so P
star when P star received the CRS
generated by
the by this this generator
star uh it can choose as relation
circuit c and a maliciously chosen
relation circuit C and a p
star such that uh the probability that
the wirefire uh accept for this
uh this
K and the the is instance uh the I Stars
instance is not in the relation circuit
defined by
this C star is
negligible
so yes uh so the intution is that so
suppose uh the intution is that the SSB
is binding for some location for some
for some instance so you just set the uh
generator bar as the generator that
output that kind of SSB so SSB will be
binding for the iar position then you
cannot cheat for the is IP instance but
you do uh you do have the option to so
cheat improver can choose a different
circuit relation circuit C but it cannot
cheat for those uh D starts
position uh right so that's
uh that's a semi adaptive sness so to
prove this uh sness for this
construction the idea is that uh so for
any for any I star that is not in the
language so you can you can see uh so
from the correlation intractability so
so essentially the idea is that if I
star is not in the language and uh for
any cheating
proof uh right so you just uh switch
this uh generat bar to for this
iar and uh and you can argue if iar is
not in the language then I star over
two so because we do the two2 one trick
so it will translate to a new instance
at the next level
then it's also in not in this it's not
it's also not in the out dou PR so if
the if the allary doesn't cheat for the
CR so that's the idea so that means
the so for
any so so if it's not in the
yeah so if the if the if the query and
the hash values out by the chover does
not uh satisfy the the say relation R
then you have
this then if the I star I star position
is force then it translate to a another
new Force State
statements so you can so you can you can
use this uh claim to uh inductively
argue that uh initially if you have some
fixed iar then you can track C this uh
fixed I at each level by divide by two
and run up to it and finally you can
catch it because the last so the last
statement uh so in the in the last lbel
of the recursion we just send all the
witness so you must be able to catch it
so that's a idea okay so that's uh uh
that's all about
the class today yeah uh any questions
Construction
Construction sort of any sort of
adaptive soundness or is it like yes so
it only get this kind of adaptive
soundness I see like some notion of
this index oh so for the uh so for the
index bark we kind get a semi adap on
this and for General
barks
uh I need to uh I think it's also yeah
it also have some similar lotion meths I
think can you that like is there some
other construction ad or is very uh
that's a good question so so in general
so given any non-adaptive sound snark
you can always upgrade it to adoptive s
by using complexity leveraging so but
you are pay uh due to the instant size
in the security proof so but in the
barks uh if you the two so if you to the
uh the instant total instance size is K
times x so it's very large so yeah I'm
not sure you can really do that I see is
it clear PR that like only applies to
adap oh right so right right so there
seems to be a gap but I'm not sure how
how large is the gap so yeah so maybe
there's some maybe you can use it on
clber complexity leveraging to almost
close gap for example