So today I'm going to share with you
some of the research that my lab is
doing that's focused on understanding
who is the beneficiaries of genetic
research studies and how does that
translate to who gets benefits in the
clinic. And so what we are trying to do
right now is figure out what can we do
to address those disparities even
without collecting additional data. And
so we are a human genetics lab. We focus
on studying human genetic variation. I'm
often quite jealous of my colleagues
that have a lot more control over their
systems. They get to control what their
mice eat. They can mutate their genomes.
They can see what happens. I always tell
everyone, I can't do any of that. I
can't control any of the people in my
study. All I can do is take advantage of
all the things that have already
happened. What we're doing as a human
geneticist is trying to leverage what's
already existing in the human population
and then pull insights. So you can
imagine how quickly confounders can come
into play here. The very standard way
that human geneticists try to address
this type of confounder, not knowing who
slept well last night, what you had for
breakfast this morning, whether you made
a good choice or a bad choice in terms
of
exercise without being able to control
for that. What we do is just collect
massive amounts of people trying to
diffuse out those variables so that we
can determine what are the genetic
connections to traits despite all of
those confounding variables. And so this
requires pretty large sample sizes and
as you can imagine very expensive
research
studies. In total though, we're looking
at a very small fraction of your genome.
You're about
99.9% similar to every person in this
room. only 0.1% of your genome is going
to be different, but the genome is quite
large. So that represents about 6
million base pairs of difference. So
when we're trying to figure out what are
the genetic changes that make someone
develop schizophrenia versus depression,
we have to look amongst these six
million base pairs of difference and try
to pull salient
conclusions. The way this is done
typically is through these largecale
association studies. These studies are
quite simple on the surface. We're
collecting large groups of people that
have a trait and large group of people
that don't. We then collect all of their
genetic information and assess genetic
variance one at a time. Do we see an
association with a particular genetic
change in people who have the disease
versus those that don't? So, we're going
to look for genetic differences that are
found at increased prevalence in the
disease population relative to the
controls. These are then said to be
associated with disease. Now, what's
tricky here is this may be different
than some of the genetic information
you've come across before. Maybe you've
heard about Down syndrome, which is
caused by an extra copy of a chromosome.
Every person that has an extra copy of
that chromosome has Down syndrome. We
haven't found a single human where
that's not true. But for the majority of
diseases in the human population, that
is not a simple pattern. So there's
typically many people that have
different variants that cause the trait
we're looking for. So, what we're
thinking about more is not a genetic
cause of a trait, but a genetic change
that increases your risk or likelihood
of developing disease, just like smoking
increases your risk of lung cancer. And
so, these large-scale studies go through
and identify DNA changes that associate
with increased risk. And then the goal
of the biologist is to understand why
those variants would cause you to be at
increased risk. Could that help us
figure out how to prevent the disease,
treat the disease, or even just diagnose
it so we know what we're looking to to
um
affect? So, this type of study has been
performed for about the last 15 years.
Um here's what we've gotten so far. Each
one of these bars represents one of your
chromosomes, and the little dots are
representing DNA variants that have been
linked to a trait. These are all of the
results we had up into 2008.
By
2012, 2011, we had more. And then
2015,
2019, by 2020, we're getting off the
scale of my plot. And I had to downsize
to get enough pixels on this screen so
that we can see all the results we have
up into 2024. This is what happens when
sequencing studies start exploding and
people become more interested in
understanding their own genomes and
being um consenting themselves into
genetic studies. What this represents is
600,000 clues about how diseases work if
only we could interpret them. So this is
a huge amount of information that many
groups including my own are trying to
figure out why would this set of varants
increase your likelihood of developing
one disease versus
another. What's the problem? The
discovery cohorts are incredibly biased.
The vast majority of that data I just
showed you comes from the European
ancestry populations only. So about 80%
of all our genetic studies are performed
only on European ancestry. And this has
led to pretty big disparities in the
clinic. For example, we have some
genetic variants that we can use to
predict who's likely to develop colon
cancer that are incredibly effective in
Europeans and completely ineffective in
those of Asian descent. So we're
thinking about who's benefiting from all
this genetic research and what can we do
to translate that information is a major
problem for the human genetics field.
And this is a wellrecoognized problem as
the NIH has put substantial efforts into
increasing genetic diversity. We're now
seeing massive studies being performed
across different continents across the
world and more of a concerted effort to
engage with populations that may have
been reticent to be involved in genetic
genetic studies. But this takes time and
money. Collecting thousands and
thousands of genomes takes decades,
takes very long time, and allows you to
finally fully pull some
associations. In the meantime, what kind
of things can we do? Can we start to
think about different ways that we
analyze the data in order to pull
information from some of these smaller
studies that represent um these
populations that are pretty much um
missing from the benefits of genetic
research.
Not only are some populations missing,
some diseases are also underrepresented.
So you can imagine where voting in
Congress and their choices about NAH
funding has also influenced all of this
results. Uh breast cancer very well
studied, Alzheimer's disease very well
studied, opioid addiction, not so much.
Right? So there are some traits that
have historically not been as well
funded in the um federal research which
has led to these cohorts being under
reppresented. And so our goal here is to
try to develop methods that allow us to
pull insights now instead of waiting for
new data. And the way that we go about
this is trying to think more deeply
about how the genome functions in
changing the models to find effects
despite not having huge power. So one of
the areas that we focus on specifically
is opioid addiction. Uh this is a pretty
critical public health crisis. Since
2017, opioid overdoses have been the
leading cause of accidental deaths, even
surpassing that of automobile accidents.
Uh, and this was only exacerbated during
the 29 co9 pandemic. So, it's a massive
problem. But you may be asking
yourselves, what is is this a genetics
problem? Right? So, is addiction a
genetics genetic trait? And we can ask
that question by looking at twin
studies. So take advantage of a very
naturally occurring phenomenon where the
same genome is born into two individuals
and ask do you see a correlation in
their phenotypes? Do you see individuals
who were born with the same genome but
raised in separate environments having
the same trait? And in doing this type
of analysis you find that opioid use
disorder is about 60% heritable. Height
is about 90% heritable. Schizophrenia
about 80%. So it's right along these
lines. Maybe a slightly larger
environmental component, but still
clearly a major role for
genetics. But the problem is that we
have not discovered what are the
underlying genetic causes or
contributors to opioid addiction. For
most diseases, we're talking about
hundreds of genetic risk factors have
already been identified. For opioid use,
we're maybe five known risk factors. um
and they're all involving actual opioid
receptors and cellular
processes. This has largely been
attributed to sample size and power, but
also some of this is due to the fact
that addiction might just be a more
complicated trait. More variables are at
play that make each individual with
opioid use disorder slightly different.
Different causes would make it very
difficult to pull together, especially
in small cohort studies.
So you can think of opioid use disorder
and other related uh types of substance
use disorders as multiple stages where
first there is an experience of exposing
to the drug, a binging period typically
followed by withdrawal, withdrawal
symptoms leading to relapse and
recreating this cycle over and over
again. In each stage of this disease,
there are different opportunities for
genetic risk factors to come into play
and different causes to cause the trait.
So, for example, who's going to be
exposed to an opioid to begin with?
Well, there are genetic connections here
to someone's impulsivity or willingness
to take risks. There's actually genetic
factors underlying that ease of access.
So, there's some social factors. Some
people are not going to be prescribed an
opioid in the clinic and some will be
more likely to. Some may have higher
pain tolerance and say after that after
that orthopedic surgery I do not want to
take the opioid. I'm going to stick with
ibuprofen. Right? So there may be
differences at all those levels that
have different genetic
correlations. We also see massive
variation in one's response to opioids.
Maybe you've been prescribed an opioid
before. Some people experience euphoria.
Some have pretty nasty side effects and
don't want to continue taking their
dosage. So, it really depends. And it
turns out if you enjoy your first opioid
experience, you're 20 times more likely
to have addiction in the future. So, if
you have anyone in your life that has
ever have been prescribed an opioid,
describes a very happy feeling
afterwards, maybe help them monitor
their intake until their uh prescription
has run its
course. The other challenge here is the
withdrawal. Some people experience much
more severe withdrawals making them much
more prone to relapse and that's
incredibly problematic because that is
where overdoses tend to occur. So it's
in this relapse phase that we see the
majority of opioid overdose deaths
occurring rather than like the first
exposure stage. So you're talking about
a trait that's not only underststudied
but multiffactorial with distinct
causes. you can see where the challenge
lies and why we haven't made much
progress in understanding the genetic
risk for this trait. And so we've been
tackling this question looking at these
smaller disease studies but trying to
account for this heterogeneity this
mixture of causality. And so we can
study genetics by looking directly at
the sequence. But we can also study
genetics by looking at the output of DNA
sequence. We can look at the genes and
what kind of products they make, the RNA
molecules that are produced, the
proteins that are produced, and then a
specific type of element that my lab
studies, which is the element that
controls that process. So, your body has
to dictate which genes are turned on and
off in different contexts. It's one of
my favorite things to teach the
undergraduates because it's something
they know, but they don't know that they
know it, right? You only have one
genome. You have this basically the same
genome in every cell of your body. Yet
your heart beats, your neurons send
impulses, your immune cells fight
pathogens, all coming from one single
blueprint. And so understanding how that
happens is all about controlling which
genes are turned on and off at what
time. And so this process called gene
regulation is what we focus on. It's
this effect of these little triangle
represented elements that decide when
those RNA molecules are produced.
Turns out majority of our genetic risk
is actually coming from disrupting these
regulatory elements and not the proteins
themselves. And so our approach was to
go directly at patient tissues and
capture these gene regulatory elements
and ask how they are disrupted in
addiction.
We collected about a hundred individuals
who either died of an opiate overdose or
died of an accidental death, typically a
motorcycle accident, to compare their
brain tissue samples and did a
experiment that allows us to look at
those regulatory element
activity. To give you a sense of what
the data looks like, this is one tiny
fraction of the genome of your six
billion base pairs. This represents
about uh 20,000 base pairs right here.
And these little squiggles represent
which gene regulatory elements are
active. How you interpret this data
requires a number of different
strategies. So we're not going to go
into too much detail, but I always think
it's interesting to see what these
traces look like. And how do you go
through and look at the entire genome
and decide what differences are actually
interesting or valuable to study.
The standard approach is to try to go
through and identify something that is
consistent, something that is different
in everyone who has the trait that the
controls all have something different.
So for example, we'd look for an element
where the big triangle peak here is high
in all of our controls and flatlined in
all of our cases. You can use a lot of
straightforward modeling, some linear
regression type analyses to identify
these consistent
changes. This often results in very
little information from small studies
because you're requiring consistency.
What we wanted to do is allow for that
heterogeneity. And so instead of
portfoling these sort of standard strong
impact analyses, we look for changes
that are specific to each individual
with opioid addiction. So say of our
control population, this is what we
expect to happen. Is there any novel
information, any surprising information
in the one sample that has opioid use?
So we're performing this very highly
individualized analysis.
So here's a little cartoon view of what
this looks like. This is what standard
approaches look for. A small reduction
that's consistent in hill height or
triangle height in this cartoon. What
our approach does is looks for changes
that are more akin to here where it's
consistent in the controls and then one
individual has a big change that's
really unexpected.
We can go through and define these types
of changes for every
individual and look at what comes out of
it. And as you might expect, when you
apply an analysis looks for
individuality, most of the things are
individual specific. Only about 10% of
these changes are found in more than one
person with opioid
addiction. But what the way is
interesting about how these elements
work is they don't work independently.
So these individual elements that are
controlling genes, they actually work in
combinations. So all of these little
triangles here are responsible for
controlling the same gene. And so we
start by linking all of these
differences back to the genes that they
control. And then we suddenly see a lot
higher degree of convergence across our
opioid cases. So of the elements that we
identified as being individual specific
only 10% were found in multiple patients
but if we focus on the genes that are
affected by those little triangle
changes then we see that happening in
60% happening in multiple patients. So
what we've been working on with the help
of the seed grant is how to formalize a
convergence analysis. How do we quantify
the areas of the genome where there's
the most overlap or grouping of these
individual specific changes? We started
applying this to our opioid cohort and
found five major genes linked in our
first brain ho brain study and 50
additional genes in our second brain
study. We're really excited about these
results. We started looking at these um
in this in cell culture. So in in
neurons growing on plastic. uh we're
seeing some very interesting insights
about the role of insulin signaling in
addiction. Uh so with this analysis
we're now formalizing to enable us to
think about these target genes and apply
them to other traits such as
schizophrenia and
autism. So that I'll wrap up. Um so this
is a work across a number of individuals
and I want to make sure I highlight the
cohort of individuals that allows us to
collect this data. We do not do any
autopsies or dissections. we have
collaborators that collect the data so
we can focus on the computational
analysis and that's this group of
researchers here. So thank you very
much.
Thank you so much. Questions for Olivia.
Thank you. This was fascinating and very
well presented. Um my question is is I I
applaud you for looking at opiate
addiction. It's um such a huge problem,
but it's also a highly stigmatized one.
And my question is about the ethics of
like once you have um actionable data
that could be useful in a clinical
setting, how would you work with the
ethics around that? And particularly um
in this moment where we have a lot of
mistrust of science and um you know
things like like the the 23 and me
acquisition are are really making people
very anxious about what people might do
with genetic information about them. How
would you think about that and where
would we even begin? Yeah, it's a great
question. It's something we think about
a lot because of all the diseases we
study, this is the only one that's fully
preventable. Right? So, never exposed to
a substance, you're not going to develop
addiction, right? But there's a huge
risk of applying this type of result to
the clinic without thinking about those
types of boundaries. So, say we could
predict who's at highest risk for
addiction. Does that mean they shouldn't
be prescribed a painkiller? Probably
not, right? Until we have some new
alternatives. That's some very exciting
new painkillers are on the market now.
So, hopefully we can start phasing out
prescription use. Um, but what we want
to think about is ways of increasing
monitoring. Maybe if you're a high risk,
it's not that you don't get access, but
you'll get a week at a time prescription
instead of a month at a time
prescription. So, more intervention.
Some places, I think it's uh common in
Texas, for example, to not prescribe
opioids in the orthopedic surgery
center, but to refer them to a pain
clinic. So this just this extra step of
having to contact a pain clinic to talk
to a doctor to get access to an opioid
actually reduces overall opioid intake.
So there are there are ways in which we
can monitor this sort of making sure
that people have the knowledge but also
the policies to keep how we would
restrict access very carefully selected.
Um we also have to be super
conscientious of the way we design these
studies. uh the very first like machine
learning model for addiction predicted
race and not addiction. Um so you can
imagine how quickly that could be
problematic if applied in the clinic.
Great.
Hi. Um I had a question if you were
considering also hyonic activity or
transcription factors because you said
regulatory ailments but I'm not sure
which one you implied with that. And
also if you're talking about one or the
other. Are you considering the activity
of the other one? Yes. Yeah. So, we're
we're actually measuring histone
modification. So, when I talk about a
regulatory element, we're measuring uh
the proteins that are altered that
control how the genome is folded. Um,
and what I didn't have time to go in
today is we started predicting what
might be driving these changes. And so
we have a few transcription factors that
we think are candidates for causing
these effects and then they might be
better um therapeutic targets because
they cause many downstream effects. So
good question.
Any further yes then
thank you. Um I understand this is uh
this research is heavy on genetics but I
was wondering if this um research
accounted for environmental factors at
all. Yeah. So, you know, a lot of our
models attempt to, right? We look at
things um like age, um the substance
that you're using. Um that's one of the
hardest things to control for. Most
people with opioid addiction are poly
substance users, so they're using
fentanyl as well as heroin or some mix
thereof. Um and so that can really be a
major confounder. Um age is another big
one. Surprisingly, the biggest
confounder is something called the
post-mortem interval. So, the time
between death and tissue collection. And
so we can try to model that effect out
but we have to be very aware that that
might be a driver.
Uh hi absolutely love your presentation.
I just had a question about uh the
causes of these addictions as we know
with a lot of addictions that childhood
trauma and childhood abuse and various
factors lead to addiction and I was just
curious to know if you factored that in
your computational analysis. Right. So
the benefit of looking at human tissues
is that you capture everything that
occurred in the lifetime. So some of the
things that we look at may be a direct
effect of opioid exposure and that's why
the brain DNA organization has changed,
but they could also be pre-existing
opioid exposure. So we're looking uh
currently we're starting exposing cells
on plastic to opioids and seeing what
changes in that very simplified system.
Um and what it looks like is in one of
our one of our brain cohorts that we've
studied in the frontal cortex. Um that
is where you see more signs of these
effects being early childhood adversity
related. So high stress in early
childhood can change the way in which
the brain is organized. The epigenetics
of the brain um and has pretty lasting
impacts and we see some evidence of that
here. So a postto who just started
that's looking at how the effects of
stress and early development may
influence response to opioids.
Awesome. Further questions. Yes.
Um hi thank you so much for your
presentation. My question was going to
be about uh data being biased. Uh is the
data gender biased? I think the data
that is coming from the past is most of
the time male dominated. Is it something
that we should be cautious about? Yes.
So we have most of the studies have been
published have like been cognizant of
gender differences of sex differences uh
because we're collecting X and Y
chromosome related information. We can
see that very clearly. It's in the
followup that you see the most
disparity. So which LOSI you're studying
mostly are studied in mice, right? It's
when we follow up on experiment and
that's mostly done in male mice. Uh but
the actual discovery is pretty well
balanced with some notable challenges.
So uh one of the strange challenges for
us is that it's hard to find accidental
death female controls. Um women tend to
die of chronic diseases and less likely
to draw um to die at a young age of an
um accidental death like a motorcycle
accident. Um and so that's it's a great
thing that we can't find enough controls
of accidental death, but it's also a
challenge. So we have to be very aware
of that so that we're not
misrepresenting in women with addiction
in the in the study. Great. And final
question. Um yeah, I'm a statistician so
forgive me if this is too naive a
question, but you said something very
interesting about complex traits. Um
namely that I'm assuming complex traits
here are the more the number of base
pair differences or something and or
combinations thereof. Uh and
interestingly those are also precisely
the traits which perhaps uh occur in
fewer people um like the more complex a
trait I'm assuming there are fewer
people in the population that have that
trait. It's inverse actually. Oh I see.
So the the more if there is a trait
that's caused by a single major effect,
it's more rare because that effect may
be selected against with uh evolutionary
pressures. But when it's complicated of
many different little causes, they can
live in our genomes for longer. So it's
actually the most common traits that are
the most polygenic or have the most
genetic factors that influence them.
Okay, that that's good to know. Okay,
thanks.