I'm Sarah Hansen and today I'm talking
with Anna Bell. She's a super smart
programmer, author, and senior lecturer
at MIT. Her computer science videos on
our channel have captivated millions of
learners around the world. Today, we
talk about Python, growth mindset, and
rubber ducks. I have to know what the
ducks are now. Like, I I can't continue.
Then I ask her, with the emergence of
AI, do we even still need to learn how
to code? What's the value proposition of
learning a language like Python? Do we
still need to do it? So, not sure if
this exactly answers the question. Oh,
tell me more. Find out her answer today
on Chalk Radio. Hi, Anna. Hi. How are
you? I'm good. You're here. I'm so
excited. Yes, me, too. This is one of
our pilot episodes for something new
that we're trying, which is a video
version of our Chalk Radio podcast. Many
ways, it's an experiment. How do you
feel about experiments? Are you an
adventurous person? No, not at all. Oh,
great. We're going to be great. Yeah, I
like stability and I like boring days.
Oh, well, I'm not sure we're going to
have one of those with these with these
ducks and so I I actually don't know
what the ducks mean. Um, so I think
you're going to tell me a little bit
later, but as we Yeah, I think we're in
for an adventure and a little bit maybe
of a choose your own adventure. Mhm. So,
you're at MIT, you've been here for
about 10 years. Um, and you spend most
of your time thinking about and teaching
people who are new to programming,
introducing them. And I'm wondering what
that means to you, why you're interested
in teaching in particular, like people
like me. What do you get out of that?
And tell me about that experience. Um,
so I recognize that I well I don't want
everyone to become a computer scientist,
but I do think that everyone should
learn programming as a skill. So
programming is should become sort of
like what math is now where you kind of
learn it in um elementary school and you
obviously use it here and there in your
adult life. But I don't know, you know,
when you've last used calculus, right?
like we don't all need to become
mathematicians after we've learned basic
math. Similarly, I do think people
should learn basic programming, but they
don't have to become computer
scientists. So, the reason that I enjoy
teaching students intro programming and
exposing them to intromputer science is
because it was really hard for me to
understand programming when I first
started and I just always remember how
tough it was.
And I'm at right I teach at MIT and
there's obviously a lot of really smart
people here. And I think as you teach
more and more it's easy to forget how
hard it was to start learning. And so
you know as an intro course you know you
might make the problems you give
students harder and harder each year
just because they get maybe boring for
you but it's not boring for the
students. And I try to recognize that
every like every semester I just
remember it was really hard for me.
they've never seen this before. So, it's
really important to make sure that they
have a really good experience. You
mentioned that when you first started
programming it was difficult. Y I'm
wondering like what made it difficult
and then what are you doing in your
teaching to make it less difficult? I
honestly don't know what made it
difficult. The the beginning was easy
just kind of understanding the basics of
just you know writing uh the basics of
creating an algorithm is basically three
things. So the first is a sequence of
steps. So step one, step two, step
three. Um some sort of way to control
the flow of those steps. So usually you
go step by step, but at some point you
say, well, if this is true, do this,
otherwise do this. So like a branching
kind of idea. And then there's also a
way to control the flow by asking the py
the program to repeat certain lines. So
it's like, well, if this is true, go
back and repeat this a million times,
which is very easy for a computer to do.
So a sequence of steps, a way to control
the flow of those steps, and then a way
to stop. Those are the three things that
make an algorithm. That's that's how you
write a program. And the grasping that
was not hard. It was just sort of once
you've gotten over that learning curve,
it's learning sort of some of the more
advanced concepts that were
um that were harder some of the details
for how that specific language works. So
I started with Java, not Python, which
was a little which was harder than it's
a lot harder than Python. There's a
bunch of details that you need to think
about there. So I had the opportunity to
watch some of your lecture videos. Yeah.
And I noticed that you make space and
time for students to practice like right
in the class itself. Um definitely
outside the class as well, but like in
the actual space where you're teaching.
And I'm wondering if you could talk
about that a little bit, why you do
that.
Yeah. So, I think I mentioned this
before. I sort of see programming like
math is now, but this will be, you know,
many years from now. Um, it's a skill
that people need to get that they don't
have yet. And so, if we think about the
way we learn math in school, it's a lot
a lot of practice, right? You just
always constantly practice adding,
subtracting, multiplying, right? The
kids. Yeah. So I think it's very
important for students to actually get
the time to to do to do that practice.
The way I run the class is a sort of a
flip classroom or a blended learning
style where students watch sort of the
basics through video first and then in
the actual classroom we do active
learning. So, uh, I go over maybe
something that's a little bit more
confusing and then I give them time to
break with the hope that me forcing them
to have them actually start coding,
they'll be able to see, oh, um, I
totally understood what she was talking
about in the video and I can totally
code that, but then when they actually
when I'm forcing them to actually do it,
you know, starting with a blank slate,
it's pretty daunting. And so I want them
to get over that bump where it's like
you have a blank piece of, you know,
blank editor or whatever. And then you
just have to start writing something
down once the more you do it, the more
you feel comfortable with it. So there's
all these breaks for all these
activities that I that I try to keep the
class lively, of course, and and kind of
indirectly have them practice these
skills like just just write something
just write something down. Yeah. And
also that does two things I think. Um it
deemphasizes perfection. You're like
this is practice like Yep. I think like
an artist, right? So just like get a
sketch, write a few lines like just get
something down. Yes. And then we can
improve it. Yep. Um and then that speaks
to something else you've mentioned
before and that's like growth mindset
and that programming is not like a gift
and you have it or you don't but it's
really something that can be developed.
Yeah. A lot of a lot of you know you see
some people who are really good at
programming they didn't get good just
because they had that skill they were
born with it right there's a lot of
growth mindset involved in that and
anybody can reach that level of being
good at at something programming
included just by lots of practice trying
different things challenging themselves
so not just sticking to things that are
obviously way too easy because then
you'll never grow but you kind of like I
don't know if you know this um the state
of flow. It's like this chart where you
kind of want to be in this like middle
band
um but kind of oscillating between doing
things that are too easy and then
challenging yourself and doing things
that a little bit harder. Um and not you
don't want to always do two things too
hard because then that's discouraging
and you'll stop. But you don't want to
do things that are always too easy
because then you'll never grow. I wonder
if we could write an algorithm for
staying in the flow like it tracks like
oh this is too easy for you get in a lot
of the education platforms right are
trying to give uh students based on
their responses you know even in math
questions right and be like oh this
student totally got all these let me
give them a harder one and it's like oh
that was too hard let me yeah how did
you find your way to programming is this
something that you've always wanted to
do or did it develop along the way um so
my my parents immigrated from Romania
and we went uh we immigrated to Canada
and my dad was a electrical engineer and
then he went into software engineering
and uh being an immigrant uh immigrant
parents from Europe uh we were highly
encouraged my sister and I were highly
encouraged to get uh some sort of
engineering job right so it's just what
what what is done and so uh computer
computer engineering or computer
science, something along those lines
seemed to be the best option uh given
sort of where things were going in the
future. This was the '9s. Um so just the
beginning of the internet, the beginning
of all that um right that boom. Uh, so
my dad recognized that that was sort of
what the what the future would be and he
said, "You should probably learn to
program and potentially go, you know,
and probably go into that sort of
career." And I wasn't super interested
in anything else, so I just said,
"Sure." Um, and so he taught us Java
when I was about 12. Um, I have a a
picture here. Oh, yeah. Let's see it.
Okay. And it's in this really cool
frame. Oh, I love that frame. Okay. Uh,
very fitting. And so this is this um
this is very '9s. Like this exudes '90s.
Peak '9s right there. So we've got the
room with the computer, right? Like as
was in the '9s. You all had like the
room with the computer. Yes. And then
like the big chair and the side ponytail
or whatever. That's me on the on the on
the left there. That's me. Yep. Yep. And
that's my sister in the on the chair. Uh
sitting on the chair. Yeah. And that's
when we first um or maybe before like
very close to the time that we had first
uh started programming. My dad just
said, you know, here's you know, here's
some really basic things. And then I
only got to the the if like the the
branching part of the control flow. I
didn't really get to the repeating part
of the control flow. So I made this
choose your own adventure program where
it was like I forget what it was like.
get out and you know exit a castle or
whatever it was and it was just like a
bunch of if else if else if else if else
if like something like that. It looked
really ugly but I had a lot of fun doing
it. But in a way you're helping people
choose their own adventure today through
programming like gaining independence,
critical thinking, uh doing things that
they rely on other people to do like
they can do themselves. Like that's kind
of incredible that you do that. It's
pretty fun. That's that's what I get out
of it. I like I said, I don't want
people to become computer scientists. I
just want to empower them to I don't
know like if they want to make their own
app, they can totally do that using
really basic computer science skills or
programming skills, not necessarily
computer science skills, but yeah. Yeah.
So, uh controversial question. Uh I
asked you before the show a question and
I have not seen the answer yet but um
the question was um in an environment
when there are coding tools out there
that allow people to build things um
what's the value proposition of learning
a language like Python to do that? Like
do we still need to do it? And what's
the value proposition of doing it? So
you're going to reveal your answer. I'll
reveal my answer.
So, not sure if this exactly answers the
question, but I said trust, but verify.
Oh, tell me more. Okay. Yeah, I've
certainly definitely used Genaii tools
before. And for even for really simple
things, it can get it wrong, especially
um mathematical things and even
programming things. And so, I have sort
of a I would say a basic knowledge of
programming. And I Wait, I'm not ready.
IoT is a little more than basic for
everyone out there. More than basic.
Continue. Um, and so I was able to start
with what Genai gave me as a as as a
program and kind of kind of tell, you
know what, it in this particular test
case, it doesn't really work that well.
And I didn't have to go back and ask it
to fix it because that requires a lot
more sort of back and forth with the
with prompting. And I was able, you
know, to just fix it on my own. It
wasn't that hard of a fix. And, you
know, as soon as you go back and prompt
the the genai again and again and again,
you start to introduce sort of
variability of English language, right?
You're like when you're talking to
someone online, it's really hard to tell
what they mean or right, there's all
these double meanings. Um, and Genai is
all probabilistic. So they're basically
going to, you know, pick the highest
probability of what you mean and then
when they give you answers back again,
they give it to you with whatever the
highest probability for the next word to
be, that's what they spit back at you.
So as soon as you introduce sort of that
prompting back and forth, it can
introduce errors that potentially stack
on top of errors, misunderstandings, and
things like that. So having a really
basic knowledge of programming could
allow you to maybe start with a piece of
code that the Genai gives you back so
you're not starting with a blank slate.
It's not super daunting to write it
yourself, but you start with something
and then you potentially test it and
then debug it and then, you know, figure
it out. Okay, now I trust that it works
well. Yeah. I feel like the ability to
verify is the human component. Yes. And
that is sort of what creates the balance
with AI. Like if you let AI make all the
decisions, then you've lost your
self-reliance. Um, and you can't choose
your own adventure because you're going
to get a bunch of errors and it's going
to lead you down the wrong path. So, you
need the knowledge to be able to choose
um a path that makes sense. Yeah. I have
to know what the ducks are now. Like I I
can't continue. So, okay. And a pig. I'm
Is that like noisy data or just noisy
data? Okay. So, okay. Uh every semester
when we run our classes uh on intro to
programming and computer science, there
is one particular class that is on
debugging. Okay. which is the process of
okay, you wrote a piece of code and it's
not running as you expect it to. So how
do you fix it? That is the debugging
process. And so a a lot of times a bunch
of the errors might be things that you
can easily fix but most of the time uh
your program runs fine and it gives you
an answer but the answer is not what you
thought it should be. That's kind of
where like uh programming is kind of
different than like English for example
because in English like if you write a
sentence somebody else can interpret it
however they'd like. Like one example we
give to students is the chicken is ready
to eat. What do you think about when you
when I say the chicken is ready to eat?
Well I'm a vegetarian so I don't want to
actually eat the chicken but I would
like because I'm a vegetarian I assume
the chicken wants to eat his food. Okay,
there you go. But I would assume I enjoy
meat.
So, so I my uh my take on that is uh I
have a chicken on the table and I'm
going to eat it. Right. So, there's two
interpretations to that. But when we
write code, there's only one way to
interpret that piece of code that is
written, right? So, um, so that's where
things go wrong in our code because
we're like, well, it should work because
in my mind, like when I kind of thought
about it, it's supposed to give me the
right answer, but it doesn't, right? And
so, obviously, the program is the one
who's wrong because the computer is
merely following the algorithm, the set
of instructions, and there's only one
way to follow those instructions. That's
basically what that whole lecture, that
whole class is about. And then I bring
out this big box of ducks and I say and
I say, um, well, uh, programming is
actually kind of
creative
because the solution to a problem, I
mean, you could brute force a bunch of
things, but often times the solution to
a debugging problem is just to take time
away from it and then potentially
explain exactly what your you think the
code is doing to someone who knows
absolutely nothing about programming. It
could be you. Yes, I'm available. Or it
could be a rubber duck. Oh, so this is
called rubber ducky debugging. Oh,
because uh it's an inanimate object that
doesn't know anything about programming,
right? And it forces you to scrutinize
every single line of code that you
wrote, even ones you think are correct.
Um, most often it's the ones that are
that you think are correct that kind of
are are the issue. It's kind of like
like where did I put my glasses, right?
And you spend a long time looking for
them and they're on top of your head.
It's that exact feeling. It's like where
is that error coming from? And it's
going to be something super simple. So,
the rubber duck is what um helps you
figure that that problem out because
you're explaining it in very grave
detail to something that doesn't know.
And if ducks are not your thing, there
are frogs. Oh, and the pig pigs, of
course. Of course. Or friends, you want
to explain it to them. But friends can
be judgy. Friends can be judgy. Yes. So,
I used to explain my code to my son when
he was one. Yeah. Yeah. When I had
issues cuz he doesn't know anything
about programming, right? And so it's
the act of talking it through. But you
said it has to be in great detail. Yes.
You can't skip because that's when cuz
you already like clearly your code is
wrong
because of you. And and so don't skip
any details. Right. That's I feel like
this very much like life outside of
academia. like you 90% of the time the
problem is probably you you know and
it's like you have to figure out how to
interact in the world or with others. So
I brought all this all these ducks a
wide variety. So now I have a a question
for you. Which duck would you like to
keep? This is a hidden personality test.
Oh
we'll probably have to cut this because
it might take a long time. Um I would um
this guy. This guy. Yeah. He's a little
bit offbeat. Yeah.
Um, you know,
eye-catching and I feel like I could
explain stuff to him. I get to keep him.
Yeah, of course. Thank you. That's so
great. You put one for the set as well.
Really? Oh gosh. Does someone from the
crew want to like pick a duck for the
set? You took the one I would have
picked. Oh, no.
All right, then. Um, there's another
mohawk guy right over there. Yeah. Yeah,
we'll go two mohawks. There you go.
Thank you. Yeah, of course. What a gift.
So, you can use it for programming if
you decide to start or as you said in
even in your day-to-day life, you can if
you just explain the problem to Yes. You
know, something that doesn't judge or
Yeah. Um this idea of taking a break
like the process of programming itself
seems quite intense. There's like an
image in popular culture of like a
person working alone in the dark like
with a hoodie and like tap tap tap. um
for hours on end. Like that sounds
intense. Um so there's two pieces like
is that accurate and two like do people
work in isolation like that or is it
more collaborative? Um so I tend to
encourage collaboration. Okay. Uh I have
certainly put a hoodie on and the hood
on in the past just like a leave me
alone kind of state. Uh mostly for you
know homework and things like that. But
I for for students learning to program I
definitely encourage collaboration
because it's when you talk to somebody
else you kind of see their viewpoint and
in programming I know I talked about
like an algorithm but for you know for a
particular algorithm or even just to
solve a specific problem there's a ton
of ways to solve it. So I learn from in
the classroom when students when I ask
students for how did they solve a
particular problem after I give them
some time to think about it they have so
many different approaches to it that I
would never have thought of and it's
important for students to see all these
different approaches because my way
might not be the way that they think uh
to approach the problem. So I encourage
kind of working together especially as
you're learning now after you find your
groove maybe it's you know not necessary
but yeah as an outsider to this I didn't
realize there was such room for
divergent thinking so that's really
cool. Yeah, but the taking a break. So,
especially at a place like MIT, like I
don't I don't know if like taking a
break is on the menu really. Um, but it
should be. I'm guessing it should be.
Yeah. And then I'm wondering if you can
talk to us about like the thing you
created in the world to help people take
a break and why it's important. Sure.
So, this was a project uh for I don't
know. I just had an idea. I was like,
let me just make a coloring book. um
like you know one of those uh coloring
books that you just kind of doodle in
into. And I thought let me just make it
um computer science themed. And so each
one of these is you know like here's a
circuit and it's like here's a network
right of connected people and then
here's a like a matrix kind of thing
right with bits.
So uh it was just kind of all these
ideas from uh computer science and the
hope is that if you are stuck and you
don't have a duck right then you can
take a coloring book doesn't have to be
this one but just something that uh
gives your brain a break but it's this
idea of mind wandering and this is an
idea from uh psychology where mind
wandering is not bad like if you're
folding laundry right you're doing a
very repetitive task
your brain doesn't have to super focus
on it. And so that's when inspiration
comes because you're kind of
subconsciously thinking about other
things, maybe problems that you have or,
you know, things that you're worried
about. And that's kind of when solutions
come. Just like, you know, when you're
taking a shower, that's mind wandering
as well because you're doing a test that
you already know how to do. You don't
need to dedicate any thought to it. So
your brain kind of dedicates thought to
other things that um might be worrying
you or on your mind. That's great that
you've created that. Do you feel like
programming
is like what's the percentage of logic
to creativity when it comes to
programming? Are we like 50/50, 8020?
Interesting. 6040
maybe 50/50 I would say. I think
creativity comes into the process at all
the different levels. So when you're
coming up with a problem or something
that you want to solve using
programming, right, you have to be
creative like right. Um so just coming
up with that is mostly is creativity
when you're deciding how to solve the
problem or how to uh how to write the
code sort of maybe what algorithm to use
or how to structure it or like what
pieces to use and where. um that
requires some creativity potentially,
you know, putting things together that
you might not have put before, you know,
pieces of uh uh programming concepts
together that you might not have put
before. And then you're obviously going
to uh run into an error after you write
the code the first time. And so then
tons of creativity comes into play
there. Uh but you know, drawing or
talking to a duck. Um, I'm liking
programming more and more, I have to
say. I know once you're programming,
it's kind of like reading a really good
book. Like, you're in this zen space
where you're just like, "Yeah, this is
working." Like, I totally see where I'm
where this is going. Like, I know what I
want to write next, you know? Like, the
code just kind of fits together. So,
just like being in a good book is is
awesome. Wow. And then the more you
program, the more you want to program
cuz you're just gaining these skills
along the way. So, it's like you're like
I play video games, so you know, you're
just constantly like looking for new
ways to level up, but there's no cap.
It's uh really fascinating because
unlike video games, most of them like
you could use open-source
um coding languages and financial
barriers don't come into play to get
that area for growth and that like that
dopamine hit of like leveling up,
increasing your skills. It's just Yeah,
it's just kind of a different Like you
said, it's a growth mindset, right? It's
a different way of of It's a different
fun. It's a different fun. It's a
different fun. I I'm like more and more
I'm like maybe I want to try this one.
Well, oh, there's a book right here.
Get programming. Learn to code with
Python. Yeah. So, this I wrote a while
ago.
Um, it's a book made lots of books or
lots of things claim to be for
beginners, but I wanted to write
something that is actually for people
who have never programmed before. So, I
think we don't even get into writing
code to like chapter 7 or something like
that. It's mostly kind of just setting
up motivation, but not not boring like I
wanted it to re read like a novel,
right? Like you're just like, "Oh, I'm
just following along." Um, so if you
want to start, you could also, you know,
you could try this book. You can keep
this hot. Oh my gosh. I have to tell you
a secret. Yes. So, I requested this
through interl loan at my home library.
So, and I asked um one of my family
members to pick it up and I was like,
just so you know, it's really for me.
Like, cuz they would be like, why is she
getting this book? This must be the
wrong thing. I was like, it's not a
mistake. Like, it's actually for me. And
but I didn't really believe that, but
now I feel like it is for me. Oh, great.
Like I do want to read it now, learn.
Yeah, anybody can can start for sure.
Yeah, that's just great. Um, do you have
any like hot tips for newbies who might
um want to start or even people who are
like deep into programming, deep into
the hoodie already? Like things you're
interested in reading or you think other
people should view or listen to um to
start or continue their journey? Mostly
tip for mostly tips for newbies I would
say. Okay. Um don't get discouraged.
Learning curve is steep. Yeah. Okay.
Yeah. It sucks. But can I text you when
I Yes, you can text me. Thank you. If
the duck doesn't work. If the duck
doesn't work. Yeah. No, it's it's I
mean, you're learning a new language.
Like it's called a programming language,
right? And it's basically learning a new
way to write things that you already
know how to do in or how to write in
English. Yeah. You're just structuring
it structuring it in a completely
different way and a different language.
So it the learning curve is steep. But
don't get discouraged with Genai tools.
Now though it's easy
to get started right that's not from
scratch. So like I mentioned earlier, if
you're stuck on a problem, just ask
prompt it to give you a solution and
then work on the trust but verify
uh piece where you'll actually get
valuable experience debugging, right?
Because you already start with a piece
of code. So like the confidence level is
already kind of there. You're like,
okay, I'm not starting blank. And then
you can, you know, try to fix it or
agree that it works. And both are really
valuable skills to to practice as
beginner programmers. I love the idea of
starting with code and practicing
debugging. That feels like low stakes
and doable. Totally. Yeah. Um, what have
I not asked you that I should have asked
you? I want to know what games. What
games? What games you play? Oh my gosh.
Like video games? Y I like driving a
lot. So I drive in the real I do not.
You said you don't like being stuck in
traffic. No, I don't like being stuck.
So, I like to drive. So, I also enjoy
driving games. Okay.
Not just around the track, but like
through random cities and things like
that. Escaping the police and you know,
like the You have a whole other side to
you. Me for speed.
GTA played Need for Speed. Yeah. Yeah. I
have the setup with the wheel and Yeah.
Yeah. Oh, wow. Well, thank you so much
for being here. I learned about myself.
I learned about programming. I have a
whole new world view on what is possible
with and through programming. And that's
just an incredible gift. And I'm so glad
we get to share that with a lot of
people who might also take that gift and
run with it. So, thank you. That's
awesome. Glad to hear. Thank you for the
chat. This was awesome. And thank you
for the duck. Yes.
[Music]