I was born in Turkey in 1967.
I grew up in a middle-class family.
My mother was a
teacher and school principal,
and my father was a
university lecturer and a lawyer.
Since there were no video games,
I guess I had wide-ranging interests.
I was interested in some sorts of sports,
so I wasn't very good at it.
I was interested in cartoons and reading.
When I was quite young,
as I had just started middle school,
Turkey experienced a military coup,
and that kindled my
interest in issues of politics
and their relationship to economics,
and those were actually quite formative,
because they are the
topics that I still research.
These were turbulent times in Turkey.
The military coup was
still unexpected for most,
and it was a bit of a shock,
because the democratic
government that was in place
was toppled, and suddenly
there were greater controls
and soldiers everywhere.
So it was an experience for all of us.
That was what drew me to social science
and drew me to academia
in the first place, indeed.
So I finished my high school in Turkey,
but after that I left
Turkey and I went to the UK.
I did my undergraduate
studies at the University of York,
and one of the reasons for that was there
was very little academic freedom
or freedom of speech
in Turkish University,
and I wanted to really
delve into these topics in a way
that I thought would not
restrict my freedom of inquiry,
and that was one of the critical things
that made me decide to look abroad.
It was natural for anybody
who was sort of up and coming
and had some ambition to
also think about the U.S.,
which was the center
of gravity of economics
and where academic conditions and various
things were much better.
So I actually applied
to the U.S. for jobs
and came and gave some job
talks and got an offer from MIT
and a few other places,
and I decided to come to MIT.
I mean, I think MIT
was at the time viewed
and is still the best
economics department.
You don't have,
especially as a junior faculty,
many burdens or red tape or
other things that detain you
from pursuing your passions and learning.
My passion has been about understanding
long-run economic growth,
what makes some countries
rich, some countries poor,
and especially thinking
about the role of technology
and what shapes
technology in that process,
as well as the
historical roots of that process.
Oh, I think, I mean, I'm
extremely grateful to MIT.
It's been an amazing journey for me.
I've learned a lot from my colleagues.
I always tell people I
finished my PhD at the LSC,
and then I came to MIT
and I did a second PhD here.
The more I have experience
with different corners of MIT,
both in terms of their research and in
terms of their commitment
to academic excellence and student
welfare and student learning,
I'm very, very impressed always.