I think I grew up thinking, "Oh my gosh,
we understand so
little about everything."
So there's just everything you can
discover. I really liked nature. Just
looking at, you know,
the plants and the bugs or anything, that
was really fascinating to
think about why that came about.
I'm originally from Japan. You know, I
grew up there and I got PhD there.
Something really formative for me was my
father, huge admirer of Albert Einstein.
He was always talking about finding the
truth and thinking about
the world and, you know,
the science. I'm totally imprinted about,
you know, doing
science and something really
sacred about doing science. That's how I
grew up. So for me, the
scientist is not a job.
There was a thing I thought, "Oh, that
would be super cool to be."
You know, looking back, my father never
tried to teach me anything.
He was really good at picking
where my way of thinking was unique. And
he goes, "Oh, that's such a really
interesting new idea,
a unique idea, a creative idea." And that
was kind of positive reinforcement.
Now I feel I can spot some really new
idea that's coming from
other people I can spot.
When I thought about going to the
company, I felt like that
was kind of suffocating.
I felt like at least if I go into
academia, I might have
intellectual freedom.
So I felt like that was
something I felt I couldn't give up.
And then, you know, by a few of those,
you know, accidental events, I end up
with doing a postdoc
at a Stanford. And in my probably, you
know, the second week, I
realized, "Wow, oh my gosh,
I feel like I'm breathing." And then,
well, then I realized,
"Actually, this is really fun.
I don't care in what form. I just want to
continue doing these kind of
things." Not being limited by
anything other than the actual nature or
myself, it was such a
liberating feeling, like,
"Okay, this is great."
I had visited MIT a few
times as a seminar speaker,
that kind of things. I like
like the way how people think. People are
really open to
unconventional ideas. You know, I have
had a few, you know, the MIT Underground
in a lab. I mean, that's just
how to say, they are amazing.
You know, there's some distinct MIT
characteristics. In a good
way, people can't let go.
I'm really fascinated by, you know,
evolution. I went into some sort of cell
biology, developmental
biology, and then some evolutionary
aspect comes in. And I started feeling
like, "Oh yeah, I can do
that." Every day, I'm creating more
mystery than I answered.
I'm really looking forward to finding
more and more and more, right? I mean,
that feeling doesn't get old, I would
say. I think that's a really
great thing about being a scientist. You
live with a little bit of
delusion. Still, the most
important question I'm going to solve.