hi everyone thank you all for joining
today's seminar both here in person the
Spy di Clips going on right now and also
whoever is listening to us online H it's
a great pleasure to have rusbe taban
here with us today h rusbe is an
associate professor and the n Rising
Star endowed professor at the department
of electrical and computer engineering
at University of Florida his research
interests include semiconductor micro
and Nano electromechanical systems for
frequency control applications microwave
Acoustics and novel fer electric
materials and devices his work has been
um recognized by many many awards
including the DARPA director's
Fellowship award DARPA young faculty
award and ASF career award uh he also
associate editor of the IAA Journal of
microelectromechanical systems and
sensors and actuators physical uh rusbe
has also been um and his students they
all of them have been uh recipient and
finalist of many outstanding paper
awards at top tier conferences including
the i e mems i ifcs iedm nms and
transducers so it's a great pleasure to
have him here with us today thank you
for joining us um before I hand it over
to rusbe just as a reminder for those in
the room you can obviously ask your
questions directly whoever is listening
to us online feel free to type your
questions through the Q&A option of the
webinar and I can help moderate the
questions for you thank you the floor is
yours thank you thank you
fos I appreciate the introduction and
also it's a great pleasure um to give
this seminar today and meet with Este
steam faculty um of MIT U the title of
my talk um ferroelectric haa and
semiconductor for frequency control
applications and uh well I like the
second line of my title unleashing The
Power of nanomechanics on chip uh
because we would like to talk about how
mechanics um could be uh transforming in
a lot of electronics
Microsystems talking about mechanics U
before uh the age of electronics um
mechanics has been dominating the world
of
engineering um so we all know mechanical
engineering uh has roots that dates back
all the way to en shyan times they uh
mechanical tools uh primitive tools such
as um pulley levers and wheels was
invented and enabled a whole lot of uh
engineering and diverse uh one of the
most interesting and uh to me my
favorite um highly sophisticated
mechanical systems um are these U set of
clocks or chronometers that developed by
John Harrison in 18th U
Century um at the time U having a
accurate time control or Precision timee
keeping was crucial for a lot of
different applications um uh for example
determining the longitude in Maritime um
navigation or Precision Metallurgy or uh
terestrial investigations um they all
required an accurate measure of
time and um well John Harrison over 50
years he developed these engineering
masterpieces that are entirely
mechanical to enable um having a very
accurate measure of time um to the point
that his latest version called H5 only
had one second of error after three days
of operation something that was
unimaginable at the time um so if you
look into the way
that look into a closer look into the
very first version of these clocks you
do see a whole lot of mechanical
components including a bunch of harmonic
oscillators um including the spring the
pendulums are all coupled together and
then connected through gears pulley and
levers um to the clock handles to create
the clock rotation that result in what
we see using these
handles so um obviously a whole lot of
engineering mechanical engineering has
been gone into such a system system to
enable such a performance and eventually
a handheld
device fast forward um with the
electronics era things start to change
um the invention of electronics and
invention of the integrated electronics
and its proliferation for different
applications obviously opened up the
door to a whole lot of new applications
um and obviously electronic systems
replaced a whole lot of mechanical
counterparts um however still some of
mechanical components specific
mechanical components was very
Irreplaceable and they actually made
their way there evolved their V into
electronic
Microsystems the specific type of these
devices has been mechanical resonators
uh that even now they are crucial
components for time and frequency
control um on the left you do see um a a
a probably very familiar um picture um I
I doubt if anyone here uh cannot
recognize this metallic package that you
typically see in any sort of electronic
board that hosts a quarz crystal as a
piso electric resonator is a mechanical
resonator that upon application of
electric field a mechanical vibration is
being generated and that's being used to
generate um clocks and it's obvious that
clocks are crucial for computing for
Signal processing and for
communication um on right U you see uh
just make making sure right and left is
correct yes on your right you do see um
another type of very crucial component
uh bulk acoustic fave resonators um that
are the backbone basically making the
backbone of our Wireless Systems and
what are these These are basically pis
electric tint films that are excited
through application of electric field in
an RF resonance mode and then once a
bunch of them are connected together as
it is shown here they are actually
making a bandpass filter um that is key
for spectral processing in a a a
congested V of wireless communication
the takeaway here is mechanical
resonators are essential and obviously
they play a major role in creating these
kind of frequency control and time
control applications and at the same
time if you look into these devices
they're typically the only uh devices
that are cannot yet be monolithically
integrated on Baseline semiconductor
chips but what's significant about
mechanical resonators that make them IR
replaceable um is basically a very
important property of them which is
quality Factor quality factor is the
most important figure of Merit of of any
resonator regardless of it is an
electrical resonator or a mechanical
resonator and it basically is a measure
of how good it is as a frequency
selector resonator as a frequency
selective component typically has a
transfer function that is a peak and the
sharper the peak is it means the higher
the quality or the higher the quality
factor of the resonator is clearly you
want to have the sharpest Peak possible
to have the best resonator and if you
compare a mechanical resonator
Q with an electrical resonator a simple
LC tank you typically see that the que
of a mechanical resonator is few orders
of magnitude higher compared to
electrical um oscillator on LC tank for
example you expect achieving Q's in the
order of million in a mechanical
resonator while the Q of LC tanks are
typically limited to 10 or 20 and the
reason is if you look into the the the
physics that defines this quality Factor
the sharpness of the peak it corresponds
to the inverse relation between the
energy is stored in the system and
energy dissipated in the system and
fundamentally electrical systems are
more prone to dissip
therefore the quality factor of
mechanical resonators are much
higher but how does the higher quality
Factor translates into frequency control
applications if you talk about a clock
generation or generation of an
oscillator the quality Factor shows
itself in in the
noise that actually is shown
qualitatively here the lower quality
Factor typically induces capturing more
noise and then once you make an
oscillator your oscillation would not be
a perfect sinos soid dool as you
wish when it comes to filter
applications or spectral processor a
higher quality Factor corresponds to a
sharper Side Band skirt of your your
filter enables a better selectivity
between inband and out of band obviously
the resonator that has a high quality
factor is basically is a more selective
filter and at the same time has a lower
loss so clearly mechanical resonators
are probably
much better in terms of providing
quality factors so that it is not
possible to replace them with electrical
counterparts that's why if you open a
specific or a u uh kind of a common um
smartphone such as the iPhone 13 for
example and you start to investigate
different components that are used in
the board you'll notice a bunch of chaps
here they're marked in red that they
contain few at least one or few
mechanical resonator within and it's
it's very interesting because if you
compare apparently the number of the
chips that contain mechanical resonator
is numerous while the only there's only
one cheap that hosts the processor for
you so your processor is basically a
single chip but those that are doing the
mechanical resonance resonator is within
them there are there are many the reason
is clear uh when it comes to wireless
communication you probably want to have
a whole lot of filters because you do
have different applications you have LTE
you have Wi-Fi you have Bluetooth each
of them happening at different frequency
you probably need a separate filter for
each of them there you go with different
chips and when it comes to clock
generation some of the clocks you just
wanted to use them for generating clocks
for computing some of them are more
accurate clock for navigation or for
other applications or higher frequency
applications therefore at the end of the
day we'll end up with a whole lot of
resonators fast forward 10 years what's
going to happen we're going to have
computers that need probably instead of
one clock 10 clocks because they want to
operate in parallel with different cores
so they probably need much more clocks
we're going to talk about wireless
communication that extends all the V2
mimet vaves we're going to have billions
of users by Internet of Things added to
the wireless communication ecosystem
which means that we probably instead of
having these many filters we will need
much more than that to give you an
estimate all of the cell phones that we
have having typically in the range of
200 mechanical resonators
within thinking about the addition of
these all these new users and the
extension of the wireless to millimeter
V Spectrum it's easy to imagine we will
probably need 200,000 resonators and
then imagine if you wanted to have each
of them in one of these chips and then
integrate them obviously on a scalable
so what is ideal then is is it possible
to go through the same approach that
processor event is it possible to
integrate all of these mechanical
resonators through a single Universal
platform and even better is it possible
to integrate them somehow at the front
end or the back end of our seos or
semiconductor chip that way we obviously
provide a path for extreme scalability
without having the concern to have too
many chips and
different uh to to take different part
of our board
so we are not the first to think of the
significance of such solution um back in
1960s the idea started to integrate
mechanical resonators with
transistors um Nathanson 1967
demonstrated a the resonant body
transist resonant gate transistor
concept there it was basically a beam
that was sitting at top um of a channel
between a drain and source and once the
beam was oscillating at a frequency in
the range of a few tens of kilohertz
then the the current that could passed
through the channel between the and
Source could be modulated and it
actually could be filtered corresponding
to the frequency of the gate that way he
managed to put the resonator besides the
electronics on a single chip and then
obviously with doing that he managed to
make oscillators or even coupled
resonators together to make filters
clearly after 1967 and with the the
emergence of the era of solid estate
electronics and monolithic Electronics
uh clearly this non-solid estate kind of
architecture was not feasible so it was
not continued however more recently
there are other research groups who
started to looking back into integration
of micro and non mechanical resonator
either on the front end of the
camos or on the back end of the line um
of the the the cheap uh here are two
examples the first example is uh a
megahertz seos back end of the line
integrated uh metal insulator metal beam
resonator that is then connected
directly to amplifier to make an
oscillator and uh it's basically the
work done by my colleague at Taiwan
chinua University um shangan Le group
and another work that is done by my my
colleague and friend Don Weinstein where
they integrated the resonator actually
benefited from the standard camos
devices on the front end basically the
finfets to excite mechanical resonance
through the use of dialectric gates and
they managed to basically achieve high
frequency resonators all the way up to
gahz on seos
sorry let
just my my apologies just
jumped okay sorry for the int
Interruption so uh what was the problem
with um these Solutions so the problem
with these Solutions however is all of
these devices similar to the resonant
gate transistor they benefited from a
specific electromechanical transduction
that was not really uh efficient um so
the way that they operated they
benefited from electrostatic
transduction where you apply your
electric field across a capacitor that
is either filled with a dialectric or it
is filled with with air gap or vacuum
and then upon application of electric
field you would convert uh the voltage
into some sort of force through kums law
the problem of that transction is it is
not really efficient which means that
the energy exchange between electrical
signal and the mechanical motion was not
really efficient the way to define that
or to quantify that is true a u the
basically a parameter that I'm going to
use it a lot of times during this talk
so it's um it's called KS square or the
coupling between electrical domain and
mechanical domain it actually is the
ratio between the energy that is
transferred to your mechanics um based
on the energy that is inserted in
electronical in electronics domain the
problem of electromechanical translution
that has been used in all of these
applications was it was very inefficient
so if you compare the K square of camos
Ms capacitive CS Ms it has been in the
order of 10 to the minus 4 which is very
a small number and if you compare it
with aluminum nitrate a 10 film p
Electric that is used to create filters
you're talking about a number of 1% to
10% so you can see nearly two orders of
magnitude less efficient um these
resonators are when you wanted to
convert the energy from electrical
domain to Mechanical
domain another major problem of all of
these typically devices is um when we
want to talk about making a clock um the
the materials that are being used here
to create resonator is either metal or
um silicon or silicon dioxide um they
are typically very temperature sensitive
it it in terms of of the elasticity
which means that if the temperature
changes their stiffness changes a lot
and that immediately translates into the
shift of the frequency that's something
that you don't want to happen because
when you wanted to make an oscillator
you want to make sure the frequency is a
constant um that is not affected by the
temperature variations so if you want to
give you some number if you
compare the uh capactive mems with with
quartz you're talking about the
temperature sensitivity for uh reson
implemented in front end of the line or
back end of the line um is in the order
of 30 to 100 part per million shift in
the frequency per degree C which is
orders of magnitude again larger
compared to another p Electric resonator
that we had quartz which is typically
less than one part per million per
degree C so so we do see that although
the goal has been very attractive and it
has been efforts to enable this
integration there are major challenges
um for the integration
however starting
2011 a new discovery happened that
opened up a whole new opportunity for
integration of mechanical resonators
with seos and the discovery was the high
dialectric material that has been long
being used um to serve as a high
dialectric in advanced semos devices
which is the
haia haum dioxide or haia it basically
turns that if you apply certain
thermomechanical treatment on it you can
convert it into a specific
crystallinity that is polarized and
therefore it can serve as a piso
electric um so so the effect is
basically investigated uh by observing
the fedo electricity which means that
you do have a polarized film and upon
application of a voltage we can change
the direction of this polarization but
at the same time since it is a polarized
material then it turns out that you can
also um benefit from the p Electric
coupling in this material at the time it
was a very small P electricity that was
observed what does it mean it means we
already discovered rediscovered a
material that has been already within
the seos and now we can somehow convert
it into a pzo transducer that probably
is much more efficient for translution
of electromechanical
resonators back in 2019 the started to
see can we make a high frequency
resonator out of this 10 nanometer or
sub 10 nanometer new ferroelectric hnea
film and yes we were successful we
demonstrated the very first nanoscale
resonator and the resonator was quite
kind of sophisticated in terms of the
stack and I just purposefully add this
to show there a bunch of different
layers in it including a layer of
aluminum nitrite um so we we developed
the resonator that we could actuate it
with aluminum nitrate and this time we
used the haia or a sibling of it haia
zerconia that was polarized through the
specific processing that we developed
and we tried to use it as a
electromechanical sensor and we have
been successful so we managed to excite
mechanical mode at 12.8 gahz and then we
benefited from this very thin half zunia
in the order of 10 nanometers to translu
and to sense the charge es through p
Electric effect okay successful however
although this was the very first
demonstration of a gahz resonator using
haia or haia zerconia as a transducer
the major problem is if you look into
the insertion loss indicates the couling
is very weak so you have an insertion
loss of nearly 9- 70 DB indicating your
electromechanical coupling is a still
very very poor well this actually
contradicts the purpose the purpose was
having a pzo that provides a good
coupling apparently the coupling was not
really good so to understand how we can
solve the problem of the coupling I have
to first briefly talk about the specific
process that we use to crystallize the
films so uh haia or haia zerconia has a
specific crystalline characteristic that
it is a multimorph so it can happen when
it is
ordered to have different
crystallinities so it can take a
tetragonal crystalline form it can take
a monoclinic or it can take
oromic out of all of these crystalline
form that it can take at room
temperature there's only one of them
that is polarized and is ferric and pis
electric which is the
utomic and once we do the AL to have a
10 nomer let's say half zerconia in
order to crystallize it because it's
initially a morphus you you need to
apply this specific boundary condition
that is basically achieved through
adding metal electrodes with a different
coefficient of thermal expansion and
once you put a material with different
coefficient of thermal expansion and you
apply it an RTA rapid thermal analing
the tensile stress that is being
generated starts to crystallize it and
then if you do that carefully you manage
to crystallize the majority of the
domain into your desirable ferroelectric
oromic or the polar
base so therefore the key in formation
of a polar film is the stress you have
to apply the tensile stress well guess
what when you make a resonator you
typically want to levitate it and as
soon as you levitate it which means that
you have a substrate that you release so
you have a freestanding membrane well
you immediately just get rid of all the
stress so you relax the tensile stress
and clearly what would happen is as soon
as you relax the stress you suddenly see
surprisingly the polarization
significantly
reduces indicating some transformation
is again happening upon release looking
into dialectric constant it turns out
that the dialectric constant is also
increasing giving us signs that
apparently our favorable orthorombic
polarized um crystallinity is now being
converted back into something else
apparently monoclinic phase which is
undesirable and that is basically the
reason why the ks Square becomes again
very small because you release your
resonator and you just relax The
Strain so we started to further look
into it and we may test the structures
and in order to identify the uh the
relative distribution of different
morphologies either oromic or non-polar
phases we did an xrd on the sample
across different releasing steps so we
started with a solidly mounted film then
we half relased it then we fully
released it and over the all of these
steps we did an xrd to identify the
contribution of different morphologies
in our film and as we expected once we
looked into the xrd turns out that
initially the defraction Peaks
corresponding to the oromic preferred
was the largest but as we released it
other Peaks
started to promote that corresponds to
the monoclinic phase so which means that
you already have a resonate a a membrane
that is tensile stress and then it shows
a good polarization but as soon as you
release it again the domains starts to
go back into your nonpolar and therefore
you will not have a good p Electric
transducer so here came one Innovation
we said okay if we care about the stress
well the only way that we can have
access to a stress is either through the
top surface bottom surface or in the
middle so why not instead of growing the
film entirely interrupt the growth and
add another material in between that
enables to sustain the stress here is
what we did that instead of having a 20
nomer half NE zerconia we started with
10 nomer we inserted Institue we
inserted an in layer of 1 nomer alumina
and then we added another 10 nanom halfa
so that the thicknesses are the same and
we did the same process of
release favorably we did see that the
utomic peak stayed where it was and we
did not see any promotion of the peak
corresponding to the monoc clinic
therefore we call this approach
formation of a super lattice because if
you wanted to keep doing this scaling it
all you need is after every few nomer
you insert few nomer few layers of
alumina again half again alumina and
then these inter layers considering
alumina is a very hard material ensure
it sustains the tensile stress so that
even if your film gets released you will
not see the reduction in the
polarization so this is what we call
alumina haia zerconia superlattice this
is what we use to make
resonators
so next we we started to make resonators
and the first thing that we tried to do
we tried to extract the p Electric
coefficients um because if you want to
know what is the K Square you need to
know what are the p Electric
coefficients the relation between the
strain and the applied electric
field and we actually measured the
polarization loop after application of
different cycling which is cycling a p
Electric or fer electric material is a
well-known approach to basically vake it
up to operate in a in a proper p
Electric regime and we actually did that
and it turns out that initially we had a
very large displacement in 1K after
1,000 uh switching cycles and it was
however it was very nonlinear and
unstable but as we kept doing this
cycling and cycling it trained or it
basically made sure or V waked up the
film to the point that it became became
like a linear transducer and here is the
outcome so initially we had very large
displacement but very
nonlinear but after
cycling we managed to get this butterfly
Loop displacement Loop which is what we
expected to get for a linear p Electric
here you do see this butterfly Loop
which actually goes across the Hy's Loop
of a Ferro electric and then the slope
because the y- axis is the displacement
the x-axis is the volt voltage the slope
shows the p Electric coefficients and
once we extracted it we measured nearly
nine picometer per volt which is nearly
twice that of aluminum nitrite the tin
fil material that is used to make
filters so it turns out with creating
the super lattice with sustaining the
stress we managed to achieve actually a
very large electromechanical coupling so
once we have that electromechanical
coupling the next step is creating Nome
mechanical resonator
so we we basically implemented
resonators we put interdigitated
transducers and then applied electric
field and then depending on the distance
the peach size of these interdigitated
transducers we can excite acoustic waves
across this
Channel with different wavelengths and
obviously that results in resonators
with different frequencies because these
acoustic waves propagate back and forth
reflect back at these stressfree
boundary and it results in a resonator
with different frequencies so we made
resonators with different IDP sizes
which is the Lambda changing the Lambda
from six to two the the frequency is
inversely proportional to the
wavelengths so the the the smaller the
Lambda became we managed to get Peaks at
higher and higher frequencies therefore
we successfully demonstrated gigahertz
resonators with much better insertion
loss if you compare the insertion losses
instead of- 70 is now minus 20 this is
still far from the ideal but we managed
to improve it by nearly 50 DB because of
this super lce
formation so we also achieved a very
high quality factors the fq product
which is a important an important figure
of Merit for the resonators uh is
basically is
nearly 5 10 to the 11 which is well not
as good as a single Crystal silicon
carbide or silicon but for a material
that is developed by Al is a very high
quality
Factor we also investigated a very
interesting feature of these transducers
and the fact that they are fero electric
it means that depending on if you apply
a bias depending on where you bias your
film you can operate in the regions
where the polarization is z Z which
means that your film becomes a nonp
electric through DC tuning that means if
you apply different DC
voltages you can Gull your
electromechanical translution and
effectively turning your resonator
off here is actually uh this is
demonstrated by applying different
voltages we manag to switch the
resonator off which means that we can
have a
resonator and we can have at the same
time an intrinsic switch without the
need for any external switch and this is
where very uh interesting because once
we wanted to array a bunch of these
resonators in future applications we
probably want to be able to bring them
in and out have them on and off um
without having uh basically a whole lot
of switches to cover that right and then
that intrinsic switching is doing this
purpose so the question is if you want
to have a free standing membrane is it
feasible on seos but well think about it
seos probably once you do the back end
of the line you're terminating it with
some um insulators and some metals and
if you wanted to release or make a free
standing film it could be challenging
because you have to Edge some
sacrificial material underneath your
resonator to make it
levitate however an alternative approach
is instead of etching underneath the
resonator which could be challenging for
seos integration we started to use
another type of uh boundary that is
called brag mirror BR mirror is
basically is an acoustic band Gap
structure that you can identify the
thicknesses of the materials with highly
different acoustic impedance such as
tonan and silicon dioxide and then once
you stack it over the entire stack acts
like an acoustic mirror which means that
you mimic the stressfree or the uh
membrane that is underneath this air gap
you mimic that with this brag
meter at the same time we pushed to
miniaturize the resonator size so that
we can integrated back end of the line
of 150 nomer seos and then we manag to
make resonators that are nearly 4 Micron
by 4 Micron and they operate in
thickness extensional mode here you can
see the energy diagram showing the
energy is kind of concentrated at the p
Electric layer and then we managed to
suddenly increase the frequency by
scaling the size all the way to 17
gahz and we also managed to switch them
on and
off however having all of these set we
still have problems so we dealing with a
PL or structure well go back into the
discussion that we have if you want to
have 15,000 of these devices well it's
still taking a whole lot of area right
these are not a small devices each of
them is 100 micrometer by 100 micrometer
so well is it really realistic to make
one of these large devices at top of a
tiny seos chip that is probably very
expensive probably not another problem
is yes we are improving the insertion
loss but is still far from what we want
if you want to have a filter you have to
make sure your insertion loss is is near
zero you do not induce any loss so yes
we improved it from -70 to minus 20 but
we still need to improve an outer 20
well the reason that the insertion loss
of these devices is still large is
because the p Electric property that
they're using is the transverse you're
applying the electric field across the
film and the motion is transverse
Direction there is another modality in p
Electric films that is longitudinal
which means that if you apply the
electric field and the motion is in the
same direction your K Square becomes
much larger so maybe a better idea is to
go after those and at the same time one
major challenge that we have is okay yes
you can change the distance between the
electrodes the Peach size of the
electrodes to increase the frequency but
how far can you do that because at the
end of the day you have very long filter
fingers of the electrodes and then they
become narrower and narrower once you
wanted to make them closer together to
make to go to higher frequency well the
major problem is if they become too
narrow they become too resistively lossy
so which means that they are going to
degrade your quality
Factor so because of that we started to
entirely look into the new architecture
of res Ator and the architecture is
called a ferroelectric gate th acoustic
resonator this is a three-dimensional
acoustic resonator architecture there
you have silicon nanoes and then you put
this feto electric halfa gate all around
it and then you pattern your
three-dimensional
electrons immediately as soon as we go
from planer devices into
three-dimensional
devices the significant of
three-dimensional devices is they're
taking much a smaller footprint for the
same reason that finfets are being
developed to replace plane or
transistors if we benefit from fin
resonators we can integrate a large
number of resonators at different
frequencies all on a single chip that
again serves the purpose of massive
scaling another major advantage of these
fin type resonators is the fact that if
you look into the the the mode they are
operating in a Vitz extensional mode
that are actually the animation is shown
here and they are actually operating in
the bulk acoustic mode that is defined
by the width of the resonator the
takeaway message you can change the
width of the fin very simply using
lithography and then once you change the
width you can change the frequency so
which means that as it is modeled here
as you change the width of the Silicon
fin you can change the frequency all the
way from 0o to 30
gahz all it takes is to Define fins with
different wides using optical or EB
lithography we fabricated these
devices at our clean room and then a
major step here is to define the
three-dimensional electrodes so we have
an input Port of the resonator and
output Port of the resonator the
resonator is aligned in a specific
Crystal orientation for better
fabrication and better performance and
then if you wanted to increase the
effective transction area which is the
area of the electrode on the sidewall
you can benefit from several things in
parallel and then having them in
series here is the cross-sectional tem
um of the
resonator and as you can
see we manag to make resonators that are
very large in aspect ratio for this
specific case for example we dealing
with a width of like nearly 100 100 to
150 while the height of the resor is in
excess of six Micron which means that we
manag to make a structures that has a
very high aspect
ratio and then by doing so we manag to
go the frequency all the way higher so
if you look into this structure there is
a central silicon Fin and then it is
wrapped around by the fedro electric
gate if you further zoom in you see that
the federal electric gate is again the
non laminated right is a super lattice
of alumina and haia
zerconia and then it actually is wrapped
around the electrodes are patterned
inside in a three-dimensional Manner and
obviously a major part of this project
was to develop a sophisticated
fabrication process to enable these type
of
devices the
measurements so we scale the width of
the fin and then we manag to to scale
the frequency so we made resonators all
the way from 8 GHz to 13 GHz all in the
same batch on a very small area and
again we managed to switch them on and
off by applying a DC bios thanks to the
fer electricity of haia
zerconia one other thing that can be
achieved is if you connect a bunch of
these resonators together you can make
band pass filters one architecture is
shown here is called the ladder filter
where you connect these resonators with
a slightly different frequencies to make
a band pass filter with a desirable
passband width here's the three the the
side view of it you can see how the
electrical connection is is
achieved and if you compare the
footprint of these resonators with a
pler resonator it can illuminate the
significance of three-dimensional
fabrication compared to the planar so
here you can see a typical filter in the
same area of a typical planar filter
commercial filter you can Feit at least
56 filters and you have not even pushed
the limits of integration which means
that once you benefit from the third
dimension you can
extremely scale down the integration and
that's exactly what we wanted we wanted
to have a technology that could cover a
wide range of frequencies and wouldn't
take so much space we just just
integrate all of these resonators on a
single chip to take a very small
footprint here's the performance of
filters at different frequencies all
integrated on the same
die we manage to cover the entire band
expand from 8 gahz to 12 gahz and as you
can see by benefiting from the the the
the higher p Electric coupling tanks to
the longitudinal p Electric effect we
managed to improve the insertion lost
significantly although there is still a
a large room to improve so you can see
that we made filters that could be
selected on and off by the fer
electricity and then we can cover a very
wide spectrum by an array of
filters so now that we kind of addressed
how resonators for filters can be
implemented and could have favorable
properties compared to the plan or
counterparts let's look into the clock
application to so we said haia can it
replace quartz to answer that question
we have to compare the most important
characteristic of quars fit which is the
temperature stability so what we did is
we started to temperature characterize
our halfa zerconia resonator here's the
comparison of a measured half zerconia
resonator across the temperature change
fromus 40 to 120 and then the Y AIS it
shows the frequency drift
at cut quarts as expected has a very
small frequency drift so you see that as
we go from minus 40 to 120 you only have
nearly 60 part per million of frequency
drift on the other hand our resonator
showed extremely large temperature
sensitivity which is very unfavorable so
as you can see the line is so sharp and
steep that you cannot even see how far
it will go the slope is extremely large
so the bad news half zonia very
temperature sensitive so well does that
reduce the chance of it to become or
replace the quarts to generate a clock
well there may be some light at the end
of the
tunnel if you look into
haia there's a very interesting feature
about halfa as you change the
temperature which is demonstrated by a
group in North
Carolina and you keep doing the xrd you
can monitor the evolution of
crystallinity
and it turns out yes maybe at room
temperature you're at utomic but if you
go high enough and by High I mean 700 or
800 deg C you will start to change the
morphology again from utomic into
tetragonal so why does it matter it
matters
because if you look into the ab initial
calculations for a hypothetical
tetragonal half zerconia it turns out
that it is a stiffer compared to monoc
Clinic phase that is p Electric that
means at some
point
this oromic will be converted into
tetragonal that multimorph
characteristics results in a up bending
of the elasticity temperature
characteristic which means that although
halfa has a very negative frequency
dependence but if you look into the
second order of it because of the fact
that at some point it will like to
become tetragonal it
results in a some sort of turnover
Behavior which means that yes the first
order is negative but the second order
of its elasticity is positive which
means that yes over over the temperature
increases but at some point it will it
decreases but at some point it will
increase
surprisingly this is exactly opposite to
another material that is available on
SEMA silicon the oxide is exactly
opposite has a very positive linear
temperature dependency but its second
order temperature dependency is
negative well so is there a chance that
we make a mixture of the two and
compensate both first order and second
order temperature dependency and here is
what we
did the investig tigated uh different
structures and we finally figured out
the optimum thickness of silicon dioxide
and haia to make a silicon dioxide half
silicon dioxide a stack and once we do
that we suddenly managed to entirely
compensate the linear and second order
temperature dependency and then here's
the measurements you can see the
uncompensated one you can see the quartz
and then this is when we stack it with
silicon
dioxide the significance of this result
is after 90 years of the discovery of
the at cot
quartz which is the reason that we use
at cot quartz to make a stable Crystal
clocks we managed to make a seos based
resonator that has a better temperature
stability so if you compare the blue one
which is the haia oxide fully seos
materials and you compare it with quartz
an
unintegrated kind kind of a component
you do see that yes we manage to go
above temperature stability of the
quartz and that opens up a whole lot of
opportunities because in future instead
of making a processor that requires an
external quartz clock maybe you can just
make the clocks at top of your Computing
course instead of relying on a single
clock well for each of these Computing
cores for AI you can rely on a separate
independent clock okay so that that
opens up a whole lot of opportunities
but there's still a major challenge when
it comes to using these haia oxide for
clock generation and the problem is
already seen you see that let's say
although the temperature characteristics
shows very stable but when you look into
the shortterm fluctuations it's very
noisy why is that well the fact that the
line withd is kind of fluctuating it's
actually nearly 1 PPM of short-term
instability is because of the quality
Factor yes the quality factor of halfa
resonator is good but is still not even
close to quartz quartz typically is tens
of thousands at the same frequency of
these resonators that show a que of
nearly 500 to 600 how can we solve it
and here comes my last
slide you can solve it and the way to
solve it is the fact that you can unlo
the very unique mechanical properties of
semiconductors as soon as you put your
half or ferroelectric besides
semiconductor materials you can benefit
from unique features of semiconductors
one of them is a concept called
self-amplification
self-amplification is actually if you
think about
semiconductors if you dope them and type
and if you apply a DC current through
them
because of the P resistivity of a
semiconductor and also because of the
termal expansion coefficient that
typically once you heat it up through
applying the electric field it is
becomes larger and then a smaller
depending on the sinusoidal voltage that
is applied you can come up with some
sort of energy pumping mechanism that is
called pisor resistive heat engine not
going to go much into the details of it
but in short if you make a super lattice
of endo silicon and silicon germanium
you manage to get very
large and highly efficient P resistive
heat engines and the significance of
these heat engines is you can apply a DC
current and they automatically can boost
the quality factor of any resonator
fabricated in
them so we tried the substrate we put
our fero electric trans p Electric uh
transducer at top of this um super
lattice and we appli the DC current we
tuned the properties to provide very
large self-amplification and we managed
to benefit from this unique feature of
semiconductor to amplify the cube from
1,500 all the way to 5,000 and beyond
that the peak becomes so much nonlinear
that was not even possible to measure it
which means that yes the que is low but
the fact that you are close to
semiconductors opens up a whole new
regimes of operations including the self
ampov ification mechanism that helps to
boost the queue and cover some of the
issues that you may have with the
quality factor of haa
resonators with that I would like to
conclude my talk so we talked about non
mechanical resonators and why they're
indispensable although they're
mechanical components but they're
indispensable in modern electronic
Microsystems we talked about how to make
resonators based on all of seos
materials specifically if a new type of
P electric or fero electric um
transducer haia that is processed to
have polar morphology we demonstrated
new resonator architectur such as the th
ferroelectric gate th acoustic
resonators that enables massive
integration of resonators and they
scaling all the way into tens of
gigahertz we demonstrated how you can
temperature compensate and halfa a halfa
resonator to get a better temperature
stability uh compared to at cut quartz
and then finally we demonstrated the
significance of having
a
a seos based fed electric beside the
semiconductor to benefit from
semiconductor unique characteristics one
example is self-amplification mechanism
for enhancement of the quality Factor so
I would like to um recognize the
contribution of all of my students and
the groups who did all of these research
and also um our our nonscale research
facility and the sponsors and I'm open
for questions thank you thank
you thanks for your space so we have
time time for a couple of questions
anyone in the room wants to
start hello hi Jessica from kadur from
Quantum coherent Electronics group are
you just describing a parametric
amplifier Q multiplier in your last
slide um well it's not necessarily A
parametric amplification parametric
amplification is when you tune a
specific part of your oscillator at a
certain frequency you benefit from the
nonlinearity to boost that this is
another mechanic and the mechanism Works
based on the back action of the thermal
expansion versus the negative P
resistivity so the way that it works is
if you apply a a current across the uh
material that has a negative P resistive
coefficient once it becomes hot it
expands and when it become expands
because of the negative P resistivity
its resistance reduces so you pass more
current into it so this becomes like a
positive feedback uh so it turns out
that we typically call it the p
resistive heat engine mechanism indeed a
nonlinear mechanism because you're
applying a DC but you are not really
tuning a a specific part of your
oscillator so I in my opinion it's not
necessarily the parametric
amplification okay I I have a couple
other
questions
uh on slide 14 you said that you reduced
the loss to minus 20 but it looked like
it was minus 40 am I not understanding
that no that's right that's right I mean
the devices that I'm showing here is in
that range okay but but you manag to
improve it by probably scaling the size
this specific resonator is very narrow
we have a very small aperture but with
resonators that are larger in size such
as this
one we can go all the way to minus 25 or
minus 20 yes okay and then I one last
question on uh slide
25 I was just just curious it looks like
your rejection is about maybe 15 DB can
you talk about the rejection out of band
rejection a little bit rejection in the
order of minus 20 DB out of band
rejection and the rejection is basically
defined depending on the number of the
resonators that you have so when we talk
about rejection we basically have a
ladder of capacitors because we're out
of band we're not experiencing the
mechanical resonance and we can always
tune the rejection depending on the
relative area of the shant element in
our filters relative to the series foru
a specific type of resonators if you
look into them the area of shant is
typically twice or one and a half times
the area of the resonator in series and
by increasing that if you go to twice so
if you increase the size of these we can
improve the rejection at the cost of
losing a little bit of the pass band um
so so there always a tradeoff but but we
clearly have to do a whole lot of you
know engine ing to just get a to tweak
the best filter architecture and then
Define the electrodes accordingly do you
have a do you have a sense for what your
ultimate rejection is possible to
achieve if you allow me to have an
insertion loss PM of 10 DB we can get
into 100 DB of rejection right because
you can Cascade these filters after each
other right and then once you Cascade
them rejection becomes multiplied but
the pass band insertion loss is also
increase so at the end of the day we can
improve the rejection the problem we
have is on insertion loss is still quite
large like five or 6 TB and one of the
reasons is all of these metallic kind of
uh routings at that frequency is really
lossy so well we have to first of all
make them much closer together because
there there's too much of loss right I
mean this is a whole lot of loss I mean
there's no reason to make the fins that
far apart um and then we can start to
think about okay how can we improve the
filter rejection and at the same time
improving the the ppan insertion loss
thank thank you
sure thank thank you for a very nice
talk U looks like your materials
themselves are are doing amazing things
I was wondering for your your
nanolaminate structure you mentioned
you're trying to keep a large degree of
tensile stress yes even after releasing
do you know how large the tensil stress
is I would I would almost expect for
that thickness the large tensil stress
the layer would crack yes yes very good
point so if you measure the tensile
stress for the unreleased structure
residual stress in the film is as large
as 2 gigapascal it's huge stress once
you release it it becomes in the order
of 500
megapascal it doesn't crack and it was
surprising to us because you expect this
is like a ceramic material right and
then should be supposedly pretail but it
turns out that once you scale these
materials down well the idea that we
have from bre turn material does not
hold that these such lower thicknesses
to the point that we even pressed it
with a probe and I don't have a movie
with myself but we did push it with
probe and it never broke it BEC like a
plastic it became like a so bent and
nothing happened to it so it really
withand this much of a stress and uh
well we have to see if he age it for
like a one year what's going to happen
but so far we haven't seen a cracking
incident thank
great talk thank you very much um um I
understand the applications of the
Precision and accuracy of this higher
threshold of Technology what are some of
the cool areas where it's not
necessarily semiconductor or military
for example with um solid state
batteries does battery management need
this kind of accuracy and precision in
in life sciences uh as they are doing
more and more investigation on the
clocks related to aging can something
like this be applied in
silico so to give an answer I just first
give an answer to the second question
well when we talk about uh if you think
about life sciences to be honest as an
engineer I typically look into how they
made a stuff right I mean we get
inspired because in my opinion nature is
probably the best engineer he's already
engineered things that are much better
and some of these materials are
engineered according to what nature does
for example the temperature compensation
that we we we we had the mixture of
silicon and hco the idea came from
quartz quartz is a material that is in
nature and for the same reason that qu
becomes a temperature stable we figured
out because it's a a multimorph material
well we figured out the same thing can
happen in haia regarding the first
question um other type of a applications
energy storage probably maybe not well
you can think about modalities where the
bending of these resonators can be used
to store the energy um not with p
Electric property but there are other
type of behaviors in the same material
one of them is pyroelectric effect
pyroelectric effect is the same
ferroelectric material if you apply a
temperature gradient it generates charge
which means that well there are chances
that you can benefit from those type of
behaviors for energy Scavenging but at
the end of the day maybe not a direct
relevance but having a frequency
reference is always needed for a lot of
applications including some systems that
that enables um energy storage or energy
Scavenging
sure maybe I'll end with one question
from our online audience uh so there's a
question that's asking you compared haia
zerconia to aluminum nitrate and said
the indicator is much better for haia
zerconia but in your case uh half zonia
is per electric and aluminum nitride is
p Electric could you give more
explanation on how to compare these two
materials it's great question so let me
go back to the
slide six maybe so what is the
difference between P electricity and fer
electricity so I start this way
any material that is polarized in their
molecular structure is
petric right what do we mean by
polarized it means that if you apply a
strain the center of gravity for
positive charges does
not coincide with the center of gravity
for negative charges that means that
okay if you apply the stress you're
making an internal dipole into inside
your material that translates to the
charge right so the p Electric effect
you apply a stress you induce
charge ferroelectric
materials are polarized but you can
switch their polarization which means
that yes there are even probably a
broader range of material there are an
umbrella that they do show P electricity
because they are polarized but not only
they are polarized but also their
polarization Direction can be switched
and what does it mean by switching the
polarization Direction it means that if
you previously applied a stress and you
induce a specific negative charge across
a capacitor in same direction if you now
apply a DC and switch to polarization
apply the same strain you can in induce
a negative an opposite sign of the
charge so that's basically the
difference so again any sort of material
that is polar is p Electric
ferroelectrics are pis electrics that
their polarization can be switched up
and down so the placement of the atom
there is a loose atom there that upon
application of electric field could move
up or move down that's why p Electric
materials are typically used for
transduction mechanisms photoelectric
materials besides the transaction can be
used for memory because if you can
switch something on and up well it could
be a state of one and zero okay so
that's the difference excellent so let's
thank rusbe for a great talk thank you R
so we are going to have a short
reception so feel free to stay around
here so he can talk to him more thank
you all for joining