For our next speaker, we're going to uh
go to uh maybe even the most important
part of AI and that's the uh the person
in the loop. Uh I want to introduce
Demetrius Bertimus who is the vice
provost of MIT open learning and also a
professor at the MIT Sloan School of
Management. And Demetrius is going to
talk about training a billion people at
least to start. Let's hear it for
Demetrius. Good
afternoon. So I have this title training
one billion learners in AI. Not
a not a small title I don't think. So uh
let me give some initial remarks about
uh how rapidly computing has changed the
world in the last 70 years 75 years
starting with uh the first computers,
the microprocessor, the internet,
uh mobile technologies and so forth.
Definitely in the last 40 years or so
this type of technologies has changed
our lives. on the other hand it might be
less known but AI has also been
developing somewhat in parallel uh m
many se several of these developments
have happened at MIT uh where you know
um many of our faculty have played a
very significant goal I have some of
some of the most uh some of the
significant developments one of which
has been the development of deep
learning so Um
the in my opinion AI is disrupting many
industries some of which you have heard
yesterday and today u more are coming in
my opinion
uh having been an educator all my life
uh I believe one of area one of the
areas that is ripe for change is
education and uh and this can be seen
I'll tell you more details in a minute
by AI's uh development since uh with
LLMs changing a lot of industries but
specifically in education the ability to
have personalized tutors, personalized
education, guidance systems, LLM
assessments and so forth.
uh so I feel I am in a period of time
where uh the opportunities for uh
changing the world are substantially
uh substantially larger than in the
past. So uh what our objective is so I I
joined um uh I've been 40 years at MIT
but I've joined open learning uh since
September. So I have been seven months
in a job and I came with a vision of uh
of
affecting teaching AI to a billion
learners. I'll tell you first the
personal story. So I'm not new to open
learning. I in 2013 I uh developed one
uh one of the early MU books uh it's
called the analytics edge and over its
10-year history or so it has reached
about a million learners not a billion a
million and I have seen close and
personal the effect it has had on
individual learners I tell you two
stories one was I visited New Delhi and
I met a very young fellow who I've never
met him in my life 22 years old who
hugged me and thanked me for a class for
this class that enabled him and later
his family to himself to find a job in
the in the IT technology of India and
then uh brought his family out of the
slums. Another example similar in nature
some years ago. Uh I went to a
conference in Poland and there was an
Italian lady roughly 35 years old who
also hugged me. My wife was nearby and I
have to admit it was a a a moment uh
that I paused a little bit. She thanked
me again for a similar story. She was
she had a PhD from Milan. She had uh a
young family. She took the class and
found a job in the Lux in Luxembourg on
the on the industry. So clearly while of
course I do not know all the stories
this uh um these stories suggest the the
uh very significant effect that
education can have to the world. So of
course um so we have about a thousand
people here the class that uh I taught
taught brought about a million. So a
billion is not completely ridiculous
although I would say aspirationally
significant. So uh and why do I believe
this is realistic? Uh well I don't know
if you how many people here what know
what open learning
is? Do you know what open coursework
is? About the same number. So in the
last 25 years this in my opinion the the
story of open learning is a particularly
inspiring one. Um in the last 25 years
open learning uh have developed um
material that have it didn't reach a
billion but it basically it definitely
reached tens of millions if not hundreds
of millions of people um and uh in
particular it's not only the original
OCW which is 25 years old around 2012 we
had the massively online MS uh of which
we have about 300 uh 300 s classes that
uh we are open it we have opened it to
the world. We also have professional
education what is known as uh expro and
also uh horizons as well as the micro
masters which is a combination of ms in
a particular area. So we have some
experience on developing material uh
that are uh modular as well as give rise
to um to credentials that are stackable.
So uh in addition to this we also have
the the very big developments of AI as I
mentioned namely uh Gen AI in the last
two or three years after chat GBT or so
have uh enabled technologies that um in
my view were not available in the past
for example um the ability to do
personalized tutors. So if you want to
reach a billion people you don't there
are not enough TAs for that. So the only
way to do it is in an automated way and
uh we have developed in open learning
um tutors genai tutors that are able to
interact in a personalized way in in a
personalized way with with learners.
Another example is a guidance system. So
currently we have a new website in open
learning called learn.mmit.edu.
edu
learnmit.edu. Please check it. Uh and
you can enter and that has access to all
of open learning's uh uh um materials
and you can using this guidance system
you can ask I'm a I'm a engineer who is
interested in X in let's say learning AI
it will guide you appropriately giving
you appropriate resources that's a part
and you can have a dialogue that
personalizes the interaction. We also
have uh we are developing systems that
do assessments using genai. So uh in
particular in addition to these
technologies we also have uh the
aspiration of teaching what we call
universal AI. What is universal AI? So
universal AI has multiple components.
The key module is uh
um four lectures like a module as
opposed to a le to a class which is 26
lectures. So this is designed into
smaller uh byes u perhaps four lectures
that are more easily updated in a field
that is exponentiating and diff and and
and uh and becoming very different from
from one year to the next. Uh so there
are foundational courses that
foundational modules that teach you the
the basics. They start with um with a
real world problem. They continue with
um real world data and we don't focus so
much on the mathematics of the machine
learning or the AI but rather on how
they are they are being used. We also
provide codes uh that people can use and
um in the end we teach people how to
what AI is and how to utilize it in a
way that improves their lives. Um either
retooling for new jobs uh learning to
enter scientific career or a law career
the advantages that AI is that's why
it's called universal it is able to
address every field in the world. So the
first part is a is a foundational
pieces. Uh we also as I told you we have
a tutor and then finally we have
vertical areas AI plus X for Olex AI in
the climate AI and medicine AI and
negotiations AI and entrepreneurship and
so forth. So the combination of
foundational tutors uh and more
deepening again in a module setting is
sort of what we call universal AI.
Universal in that the audience is
universal and the the fields that are
represented are also universal. Now
another remark that I have is that MIT
as an institution has about 11,000
students graduates and undergraduates.
So in other words, MIT has uh as as an
institution is uh has adapted to educate
some of the very smart people in the
world, especially younger ones. So
roughly 11,8 billion is about one in a
million people. However, if you are
going to reach a billion, you have to
think about new pedagogical approaches.
You cannot teach in the same way. um you
know a very mathematical development
would perhaps might be very much
appreciated by the MIT students might
not be as appreciated from the from the
bigger audience we aspire to reach.
So as I mentioned the delivery is um in
the direction the the quality is still
the same. However the delivery is more
one of
uh the underlying human stories that
motivate the problem motivate the
development is very much present.
Um so our our aspirination and our hope
that in indeed we will be successful in
reaching so many people is uh to be able
to connect in an accessible way and in a
somewhat authentic way where the the the
the human story is present and aspire of
course to to to help people in their
lives and their work.
As I mentioned before, uh in addition to
teaching AI, would like to leverage AI
and we have actually already developed
many things that are central to
the to the UI story. Of course, UI is
our first target. I'll say a few words
in in in a minute about our other
targets. As I mentioned, tutors. This is
something we have already developed. In
fact, we currently use it in one of the
classes I teach to to to see how it
interacts with real users and the the
evidence so far has been very positive.
We also uh geni can as I mentioned the
guidance system where in the learn MIT
edu site it gives you guidance how to
navigate within the website. It gives
you it also has the ability of real-time
feedback. So intelligent organizations
typically learn from the users and if
you aspire to have a lot of users you
you better listen to them what has
worked well or what has not worked well
even more important and what things are
missing. So we have developing a system
that takes feedback from from the world
summarizes and genai is particularly
good at that and then presents it in a
way that can help decision making at the
level of open learning. Another another
part is is what I call holistic
assessments. One of the most significant
issues in uh online education is how to
assess exams so that it is uh it it has
integrity. Um so we have developed a
system we are developing a system where
we take feedback from all parts. the
time people have spent, the homework as
how well they did in various exercises,
the way we interact with users, the way
they interact with the tutors and create
a system for holistically assessing. And
finally down the road we have we are uh
um working on
online translations in different
languages because I think Genai allows
to basically give the same lecture in
their mother language across the world
and mobile technologies. So not only we
try to to teach AI, we would like to
leverage AI to to improve the
educational offerings. So um what I
think also is particularly exciting um
that has always been in my mind for many
years I've been uh an MIT professor not
not in um not in open learning is the is
the promise that online education can
have
on personal education personalized
education. So personalized education
what I'm doing to I'm trying to educate
on our on the future cannot be
personalized. I'm not addressing
individuals. I'm I'm giving a broadle
lecture but but uh but with online
education and especially with Gen AI we
are experimenting with ways to
personalize the examples the pedagogy
the the exercises to the individual and
and I think the genai allows you to do
things in a cutting edging way of course
our effort is through universal AI in
the beginning but we have also lined up
many other areas but we are launching in
September biology ology uh we have we'll
have a new program in climate in energy
healthcare manufacturing and we hope the
humanities as well. So um so the other
in other in other words our initial
effort is with AI using AI in future
efforts not to in the distant future we
plan to work in other areas of important
society like climate, energy,
healthcare, manufacturing and humanities
to um to hopefully um reach uh more
people.
So um so that's sort of the punchline of
the talk but I would like first of all
to thank you and also tell you that uh
we have a booth here if you are excited
about this vision you would like to
participate through your institutions
personally and so forth talk to us and
uh and to be able to reach u so many
people clearly it requires a movement
it's not MIT you know we need a movement
of many people on that note I thank
[Applause]
So I only see one vote on this
one. So what is the most exciting what
is most exciting for students and
learners in the area of AI and
technologies. Well that's why I would
like to develop uh summarization so that
uh this is just my opinion. Uh I expect
that learning AI and its power through
uh real world examples through uh real
world data uh and discussion on uh in in
with real world environments. I think
it's exciting. Is it the most exciting?
I do not know but I definitely believe
it's
exciting. All right. Thank you.