I'm thrilled to invite Jennifer on stage
Jennifer is our keynote today and she's
the professor in the department of
electrical engineering and computer
science at the center for computational
biology and the bioengineering program
at the University of California Berkeley
I think we all know a lot about Jennifer
already so I'll just give her the stage
and please thank you oh I feel
privileged I don't have to knock on the
door this is great um so it's a pleasure
to be here and I think I only have a
small part of my talk that will piss Pat
off so um we'll see where is Pat very
good very good it's a little like nursy
Indulgence uh it's not in nurs but okay
so I'm going to yeah just kind of have
four parts s of a general overview of
what I think people are thinking about
and doing in the space of uh machine
learning or now ai and uh protein
engineering then I give an overview
where I'm just just going to tell you a
flavor of some of the things we think
about and the challenges and then the
third one is the one that will'll piss
Pat off which is just a little bit about
uh a particular nugget of a problem in
diffusing on discret Spaces uh that I'll
explain and then I'll go more detail
into one um on re-engineering aav for
therapeutic use and I'll probably at the
end skip a few slides because I've
injected some new stuff but uh but it'll
it'll all work out uh is this oh yeah
there we go okay so I don't think I need
to argue to this crowd why it's
important to be able to make further
advances in protein engineering it
touches not only on drug Therapeutics
but also on agriculture and
environmental um kinds of problems uh
and so if you just put on your kind of
abstract computational thinking hat as a
computer scientist uh you realize this
just a huge combinatorial space so even
if I have a protein that's of length
only around 50 uh amino acids long the
number of combinations is already
getting near the number of atoms in the
universe and so forget the fact that I
don't even know how to measure things
that I like at a high scale and so forth
just like at some very fundamental level
this is a huge combinatorial space that
need to search through and find what we
want and so of course there's a
precedent for doing this it's called
Natural Evolution has given us you know
it's why we're all sitting here with all
these lovely proteins in our bodies that
uh let me give this talk and breathe the
air but it's it takes so long that the
purpose of protein engineering is of
course to accelerate that into something
finite in our in our lives and so there
have been these two main um ways that
people in doing protein engineering and
only until recently one of them had a
Nobel Prize now both sections get a
Nobel Prize uh and so this sort of data
free um approach is this sort of Rosetta
biophysics based approach that Baker
drove forward for many years and it says
almost rest in peace so there are a few
Corners where people claim that this is
still quite useful above and beyond the
machine learning approaches that have
taken off um and then there's of course
the wet lab of directed Evolution and
the reason we're all here together and
I'm talking to is because ma machine
learning is interleaving with all of
this sometimes people pretend it's
taking it over but of course um we still
actually rely on on combining many ideas
from biophysics from data from the wet
lab and machine learning in order to
have some
successes so I when I tell people that I
work on protein engineering which I
started to do about seven years ago
people say oh didn't Alpha fold 2 solve
your problem and so I and I just want to
emphasize that Alpha fold 2 was a
tremendous success is incredibly
powerful tool but it goes from sequence
to structure and if I were to want to
use it for protein design if anything I
would need it to go from structure to
sequence because protein design is about
I tell you what sequence to make in the
laboratory right nothing else works I
can't tell you the structure can't tell
you the function I need fundamentally
the sequence and so there are these
inverse folding models so my student K
Su actually at Facebook um basically
trained Alpha fold in Reverse um at
scale um to get one of these inverse
folding models and those are a useful
component of machine learning based
protein engineering but they don't solve
the problem and something that's
overlooked in a lot lot of the fancy
Machinery of generative models and so
forth is that we don't actually know the
link typically between the structure or
the sequence and the function unless it
is structurally mediated um it's like a
lot of binding may be but for example
catalysis we don't know how to change
like an active site to get an enzyme to
do what we want and so when I first
started working in this area I was very
confused there would be a new paper out
every week claiming to have solved uh
protein engineering and and I and it was
all sliced and diced and strange ways
and so um one of my students want um
kind of put this uh idea together you
could divide the AI task into some
prediction tasks this is a little
arbitrary but I think it's helpful to
think of this way so machine learning
prediction tasks and then the next slide
we'll have what I call Design tasks so
the prediction tasks would be I give you
the sequence you predict the structure
that would be Alpha fold or I give you
the sequence you predict the function uh
or I give you the structure and you
predict the function and so people are
working on all three of those problems
and then there's going to be three more
on the next slide and Al together these
are kind of little chunks of the overall
problem of protein engineering that many
people work on and then we sometimes
assemble them together into some
pipeline so in terms of design tasks
fundamentally we want to design the
sequence and it'd be great if we could
just spe specify the function and design
a sequence and be done we can't
generally um do that very well uh
another task we might set ourselves is
to say I I condition on a function and I
you tell me the backbone structure and
then given the backbone structure then
you generate the sequence and then I'm
piping together two different models and
this is actually one of the ways that
people uh do things right now but they
can kind of as I said only do
structure-based function they can't say
you tell catalyze you know that reaction
go um this is just not possible at the
moment so okay so that's like an
overview of some of the types of
problems both prediction and design that
all get used in a basket together to try
to do the overall uh and of course
protein engineering means very different
things depending where you're starting
from what um throughput of data you can
measure what's already known about the
protein and so forth but U generally
speaking there's a few Trends in how
people use machine learning uh to
advance the field of protein engineering
and a really big one for example um
Facebook and now the the sort of
spin-off company that Alex Rivas has
been heading uh doing a lot of
representation learning and so for those
of like and that's a sort of buzz
buzzword but a real world in machine
learning in all kinds of areas not only
in the sciences and really what it means
is is that you to give data to a
computer it has to be in numeric form
and if it's not in numeric form if it's
in a graph form or it's in a sequence I
have to get it into bits uh and you can
do that with sequences of amino acids
very trivially um through some just
deterministic um encoding but these
encodings are not sort of the most
useful and the idea of representation
learning is to take a huge set of say
protein sequences and learn a numeric
coding that understands something about
sequences such that I can use that
encoding for other problems that have
data and therefore get better
statistical efficiency is the Hope um
okay so that's representation learning
and you may do that um yeah uh and then
a second really this is like sort of a
Hot Topic is conditional or generative
models and conditional generative models
we all know that uh chat gvt is a
generative model the next to does next
token prediction similarly you can have
a generative model over protein
sequences or um uh and you may condition
on the structure so you may say tell
give me this is the backbone structure I
desire please tell me the amino acids I
should use or a distribution over them
uh or sometimes you may condition on the
family in a perfect world you could just
condition on the function uh but again
that like to do that it's not sufficient
to have fancy machine learning Machinery
you need to have the information that
actually links these somewhere in there
and then another um thing that people
have spent a lot of time is are these
generative models for the backbone
structure and they're kind of there's
one from David uh David Baker's group
and then there's John Ingram at all um
that sort of did it at the same time and
these are using these sort of um
well-known diffusion models that Pat Uh
alluded to and again there's these are
like really elegant and and they can be
very powerful but you have to
fundamentally know something about the
function in order to use them properly
and again if you don't have that missing
if you don't have that information that
links the structure to the desired
function then all that fancy Machinery
is not going to buy you anything I'm not
a downer on this I just think this is
overlooked I think these are powerful
interesting models that are um are
already probably maybe
useful um so and if you if you want an
overview sort of primer of some of these
ideas of generative models you can check
out a recent uh primer that my students
and I wrote uh posted here uh and then
maybe this one is also this is one of
the least sexy problems but very
important problems is how do I estimate
some link between the sequence and the
function so that I can uh know about
that that that how to engineer for the
function I desire when it's not just
structurally mediated in particular and
for many problems when we start an
engineering campaign we have few or no
labeled data and so we rely often on the
kind of information that Alpha fold also
relies on to do structure prediction
which is evolutionary data so you just
as Alpha fold doesn't work well if you
don't have a set of homologous proteins
to help inform the structure prediction
uh similarly if you don't have
homologues to start off an engineering
campaign then you're starting off kind
of with zero data and so we we really do
leverage this evolutionary data to help
us start a campaign that will be
iterative and we gather more information
but helps direct us um to start the
first round of
[Music]
experiments and then of course uh like
alphaf 2 was amazing and alphafold 3
might be but as Pat said we don't
completely know because we can't access
it but I think some of the really
important problems in any case whether
we had access fully to Alpha volt 3 or
not are this idea that actually we
really kind of want to know the main
confirmational states that a protein
takes on maybe we sometimes want to know
the Dynamics as well and fundamentally
we just can't do that right now um like
the closest way to do that is basically
mcro Dynamics and that doesn't work um
particularly well and is very expensive
and so this is one of the wide open
things that people can't really tackle
that is felt would help uh improve the
successes in this general area and so
sometimes uh I've I've gotten into a
surprising number of arguments with
people that now that we have generative
models we can just generate more data so
that we can get the models that we want
because one of the problems here is we
just don't have the data to get the
Dynamics and so I woke up one Sunday a
little annoyed with telling people over
and over we can't just fill the data Gap
by using generative models um which if
you is to some people strikingly obvious
and to others um strikingly not obvious
anyhow you can check this out if you
want to hear some of my thoughts about
the hype in Ai and Science and why
structure prediction in particular was a
task that could be solved well static
structure prediction uh okay so that's
sort of loading you up on on what's
happening in this field in general and
so now let me give you an overview I try
to find the areas that aren't too
crowded that I think are impactful and
so on the one hand uh we do some
methodological development just on our
own I don't run a wet lab and then we
also collaborate with wet lab
investigators to keep ourselves kind of
honest and working on real things but
this was this what I'm going to tell you
now is like a little vignette about my
entry Waypoint to the field of protein
engineering which I got into by accident
um by thinking about a certain kind of
problem that ended up looking a lot like
this so in standard supervised machine
learning you take a set of um X's uh
like a protein sequence that is paired
with a known label this is multiple
labels you can just think of one label
like this is sequences maybe this is gfp
fluorescent something like that and then
because they're paired your goal as a
machine learning person is to set the
knobs of your predictive model here a
neural network such that that on the
training data you map the X's to the Y
correctly and you have to be a bit
careful so that it works on unseen data
and doesn't just memorize your data and
that's basically the game of supervised
prediction but when we do design what
we're fundamentally doing is saying if
we do machine learning based design then
we assume we've sort of encoded some
knowledge in a network that Maps
something about the sequence to the
function and then we want to invert the
model so we don't want to adjust the
parameters anym anymore we assume we've
done the best we can at learning this
functional mapping what we want to do
now is specify a property like higher
fluorescence than I ever saw in the data
set or better um catalytic efficiency
that I saw in the training data set
leave these knobs fixed and actually
optimize for the sequence that will give
me the most um highest value according
to this neural network because that's
kind of the best I can do if this is the
approach I'm going to take and so this
is actually much much much harder than
supervised learning for several reasons
um and so let me just give you one sort
of it's my banana analogy so it turns
out in computer vision people have
something that smells a lot like um
machine learning based design in the way
I just presented it and I should say I
you may think oh well generative models
don't behave like this but under the
hood everything has this problem that
I'm about to show you whether it looks
like this or it's an actual um
generative model but you specify so the
machine learning people take this neural
network and they train it on many many
different classes of objects banana kiwi
car or whatever and then it's a
state-of-the-art classifier and they say
I want to understand what my neural
network thinks a quintessential banana
is so similarly to how I might say give
me the highest catalytic efficiency they
say turn the banana node to one and turn
the other class nodes to zero leave the
parameters fixed start with a random
image and iter iteratively optimize it
till I have the most banana like image
and so when you do that you get abstract
art and so you know if you were to try
to go print this and put it on the table
you couldn't right it could just be a 2d
thing you couldn't make a 3D object of
this even though it's plausible it has
the right curvature the right colors and
so by analogy this is actually what
happens if you try to do machine
learning based design and you try to
squeeze the network for all its worth
and you're squeezing it outside of its
comfort zone is really what's happening
is it only understands things near the
training data and when you try to do
what I call extrapolative Design it's
almost certainly going to fail and just
give you nonsense and so this is the
sort of the initial this set the stage
for the initial set of work that my
group did when I started to work in this
area which is fundamentally navigating
this tension between how can I
extrapolate from a learned function that
tells me about the the property I care
about um but I have to understand that
that model doesn't I can't trust it
everywhere and there's fundamentally
always going to be such a tension if
you're trying to do this sort of
extrapolative design if you're trying to
design things within the scope of
properties you've already seen then I
think you have a much better chance but
often that's not what we're doing um so
right so there I'm not going to go into
details but some of our earliest papers
are trying to basically get at this
either by
um but well by just pointing out the
problem because people were just doing
optimization saying they were doing
protein engineering we trying to really
get at technical ways to help understand
where can I trust the model and how far
can I go before I should collect a new
round of data which is a bit of a risk
assessment and you may um have different
risk for different problems but and
maybe I'll just highlight this one paper
that Hunter nissanoff um LED and came up
with the idea for which is to say we
know that machine learning models
typically outperform biophysics model
based models um that may exist for the
same problem near the training data but
as I go further from the training data
like all bets are off for the machine
learning model whereas since biophysics
based models typically only at most tune
maybe a couple of scalar parameters on
real data they should they should be
kind of equally good across the whole
space but worse than the machine
learning models near the training data
because machine learning is powerful uh
if you use it properly and so in this
paper he says Let's Get The Best of Both
Worlds where we understand as the
machine as the machine learning model
kind of degrades and becomes more and
more uncertain let me seamlessly blend
the the predictions from the biophysics
model sort of gracefully as I go further
away from the data um I'm not I'm not
going to say much about the other ones
in the interest of time
um but if you're interested in this sort
of whole space Also Clara and I wrote a
sort of perspective slash I don't know
tutorial weird piece that is basically
talking about all of these problems of
how do I do extrapolative design can I
actually design for novel properties
using machine learning like how do I
think about that and it's it's a general
framework of a discussion but it's
anchored in protein
engineering okay and then so some of the
other topics that we've touched on
include the fact that often in The
Sciences I mean it's less so now but
people will just take existing neural
network architectures like convolutional
neural networks Transformers that were
in particular let's say convolution was
designed for images like there's
something about spatial smoothness and
so forth and so this is what we call an
inductive bias in machine learning it's
it's putting in some of your own
knowledge into how you design the
architecture of the neural network and
it's not so much the case now um people
are thinking about graphs and other
things but often we just grab whatever
worked in computer vision or natural
language processing and directly apply
it to our scientific problem without
thinking about what those assumptions
were and if they make sense and so we
have uh one is a collaborative paper
with um amorality and and information
Theory group and we have a follow-up
that's not at out but the idea here is
to say if we're making functions uh
trying to estimate functions that go
from sequence space to a property of
Interest then I should think about
inductive biases in the epistatic
landscape which is sort of the comple
lexity of the interactions between the
sequence positions and we know that most
biology is very kind of low complexity
on that scale it's often linear addative
in positions sometimes there's pairwise
and the higher I go in the order of the
epistasis probably the less likely it is
and so the idea is can we encode that
into our neural
networks um and so now uh and then this
this is also an accidental paper uh so
what we set out to do here is some of
the papers that were coming out uh in
the early
days of saying how can I do low-end
protein engineering I have just a few
supervised examples can I design for a
property when I have only a few
supervised examples to train my model
and and can I use large unsupervised
data sets to combine with them and do
better and they these were creative
interesting papers but we couldn't tell
if they were just interesting stories or
they were real results and so we started
to compare and this is a little bit
outdated now but um so we ended up with
this big comparison and the and when
they when we published this they wanted
to highlight our new method but the
point of our new method was that it was
really dumb and simple and beating the
really fancy big machine learning models
and so I think that was a lesson like a
lesson that is often um hidden in a lot
of these papers that simple simple
things without these big models actually
work really well and also in fact
there's something fundamentally wrong
with this paper and many of these papers
is they all work on a bunch of data sets
that are looking only at one and two
mutations away from a wild type but but
the whole point of machine learning is
to do more than that and then we
sometimes Benchmark on these data sets
and we did because that's all we could
do at the time it's becoming a little
bit better now um and these two I'm
going to tell you about in more detail
so I'm going to write write um in a
moment but right so sometimes we have
these kind of you can see maybe Pie in
the Sky maybe a bit more theoretically
oriented projects that uh we think are
useful to help clean up some of the
thinking and that will lead to hopefully
practically use useful algorithms and
models as well but we we like to work
very closely with people who have a wet
lab to make sure we're working on real
problems and maybe pivoting or tweaking
where we were in our computational lone
heads and so uh so there's a number of
them and I the one I'll talk about Mo uh
in a second is is the first one with
David Schaefer which is the most mature
of these and is already published but I
I I like to put my acknowledgements to
my group in the middle so I don't get
stuck without them in the end so I'll
just say these are the people of the
work I'm talking about today that made
it happen or are making it happen um so
in the next two projects I'm going to um
talk about David and aosa who are now at
Dino although which is here in Boston I
think neither is in Boston uh and they
LED this aav project and then um
Stefan uh Hunter and bear led the the
I'm going to tell you a little nugget of
a project that's a bit about some
diffusion models uh and then Khloe is
the one that did that kind of big
comparison and showed that a simple
model worked uh I think that's those are
the main acknowledgements for this talk
okay so right so this is I just sort of
inserted this in today uh uh pat pat you
can close your ears now so um so because
this is going to end up talking a little
bit about diffusion but I'd like to set
the stage here which is here's something
that happens a lot in machine learning
based design is I have a generative
model for something just like sequences
all sequences and I can build such a
model kind of Fairly easily because if
all I want to do is generate a plausible
protein sequence that's likely to fold
and be stable and I can I have tons and
tons of proteins in unir and I can train
a big unsupervised model on these and
that's pretty easy of course no one
cares about just randomly generating a
protein sequence right what I want is I
want to generate a protein sequence X
conditioned on some uh property that I
care about so I want to do conditional
design and so what we usually do not
only in The Sciences but this is even
what chat GPT does they take a big model
and then they kind of re refine it in
some way to get it to do what they want
and this can be people use different
words uh I technically what you're
really trying to do is take an
unconditional model and make it into a
conditional model for some property you
care about so the question is like how
can I do that if I have this P of X I've
trained it and I have either a
predictive model for the property I care
about or a set of data how can I adjust
like given that I put all this work into
P of X with a ton of data how can I kind
of Squish P of X around to get the
correct conditional distribution and
this is you can think of this both for
proteins there's sort of an analog in
the small molecule spaces is a problem
that kind of appears everywhere um and
so there's and and also people like
don't really I don't know why they don't
talk about this they just present one of
these as this is obviously the right way
to do it and I think it's interesting to
ask which way provides where what are
the pros and cons of these different
methods and I'll I'll talk a little bit
about that but the first thing you can
do is just kind of actually bake it in
which is to say you don't start with an
unconditional model you ju you just
start with um all the x's and Y you have
access to and you just directly build
this conditional model and then you
sample X conditioned on y this is not
very commonly done another thing you do
is you start with that P of X this
unconditional model and then you use the
predictive model or the data and you
update it and you have to retrain the
model it has a new set of parameters and
now you have this one static model that
you can sample from for the condition
you care about and the third one and I
feel like John Ingram in his chroma
paper highlighted this um particularly
nicely which is that you can also take
this P ofx model and not change it at
all but play like Lego blocks with your
like a classifier over the property you
care about and in the in the parlance of
machine learning and these diffusion
flow models we talk about guiding the
model and so what's nice about this it
is very plug andplay you can put all
this energy and and all this data into
an unconditional model get it to be as
good as possible and instead of having
to like retrain it for each new
condition you can take your classifier
and as you're generating a new sample
you they kind of play together to
generate the right kind of sample it's a
very technical area and I'm just trying
to give you a flavor here of how it
works and so this is I would say one of
the most popular ways in particular
because in the Sciences we do often have
a lot of unsupervised data and we want
to put a lot of these domain specific
inductive biases into a giant pfx model
and then we want to um be able to reuse
it to do different things for different
conditioning exercises is and so uh who
who knows B rule I I get to read on the
room whoa all right A lot of people know
base rule if you don't don't worry all
all I want to make a point here is that
if you have an unconditional model and
you have a classifier for the property
you care about then in order to invert
the order what you really want is you
want to generate sequences based uh
conditioned on a property you have to
use this base rule which is just this
very simple but very powerful widely
used equation and so I actually don't
understand this reference my my student
did it does somebody get it it's some
popular culture that I they always have
these jokes I don't know what they mean
but people laugh so I left it um but the
problem is like so I I understand it's
bad this is bad and that says down bad
so I'm happy to keep it on the slide um
so this is basically generally
intractable like we cannot deal with
this and if you don't know why don't
worry I'll just tell you and so what
that means is if I have a generative
model that's unconditional and when I
combine it with a classifier I have this
huge problem and so diffusion models are
very nice again don't worry about all
the math here I'm just going to tell the
story very simply but what happens in
diffusion models is you you do this
thing where you actually use the
gradient of the of the density that you
care about instead of getting just this
thing you want to take the gradient of
it and once you have that in your hands
you can generate samples by following a
procedure and what's nice is when you
take the gradient of this whole thing
don't worry what happens is that term
that we don't know how to deal with it
just falls out and this is one of the
powers of using guidance in in uh in
diffusion models is we can um we can
just get rid of that nasty that nasty
term so however that all the work in
diffusion and flow models for a long
time was just in real valued spaces so
on um like things like images which are
actually discreet but we think of and
treat as continuous uh and so but in we
care a lot about designing sequences or
you may care about designing uh uh um
small molecules and these are
fundamentally discreet objects right
like it's very different to generate a
real valued say 3D structure structure
or image than it is to say generate a
sequence of things and we know for
example chat GPT generates a sequence of
things but it doesn't use these very
powerful models at the moment these
diffusion and flow models which have
really shown to be incredibly useful in
this in um especially in computer vision
and now I was actually quite skeptical
that they were useful on discrete States
spases and I kept telling my students so
it's totally different why do you want
to use these models here but they
eventually convinced me and that's
another topic of discussion is like why
are these useful CU it's very different
um but what what happens is it's so
different in fact that you literally
can't even use the same underlying
algorithms models probability anything
everything falls apart and the reason it
falls apart is when you go to a discrete
space all these gradients don't exist
basically like you can get no you can't
compute them or you can't get
information from these gradients and so
all the underlying Machinery is broken
and so there's a fantastic set of work
by kampbell at all in particular that
gets a around this by using a very
technical Machinery that I'm not going
to go into called continuous time markof
processes and I think that's the most
elegant solution to do diffusion over
discrete State spaces and so what my but
what they didn't do what was missing was
how can I generate in a conditional
manner how can I condition on the
property I care about and there's no
point having a fantastic generative
model if you can't condition um and on
the property you care about and so
basically my students have filled in
this Gap so Hunter bear and Stefan this
project and and again it's quite
technical so I'm just trying to give you
an overview of the main idea here but
fundamentally you replace these
gradients with something called a rate
Matrix here uh you don't really need to
worry about the math and and just simply
by going into this continuous time uh
what happens is you I know I'm not
you're not going to get it here but you
could look in the paper if you want but
you get around the problem of the
normalizing constant um uh at the same
time as being able to kind of correctly
do diffusion in these spaces and so this
was something people actually have been
trying to do saying I don't know how to
do guidance in on on these kinds of
models and so now you can do it in a
like a like there's there's a lot of
derivations here so it's like it's a
very clean uh system that they've
derived where you really can do this
with the correct formalism
now um and I I mean I don't know who let
me just take a poll who in the audience
does this line mean something to and if
it's too few I'm not even going to talk
about this slide okay
like a few very briefly again the rest
of you just tune out for 10 seconds so
these are with the in in regular
continuous space you get the
conditioning um distribution gradient
that you want by taking the
unconditional one and and adding uh the
gradient of the classifier this is
called classifier um uh guided uh
generation and so basically what my
students show it looks very simple here
but again it took a lot of cleverness to
actually figure this out is you get a
very analogous equation and basically
the core entity in these models on
discret St bases becomes this rate
Matrix instead of the gradient and they
show that you get a very analogous
update and so you get a very similar
ability to Plug and Play very nicely and
and I'll leave it at that um
just and this was one of these um sort
of toy nups papers just to bring an idea
into the world so I actually think I
love nurs in the sense that I take nurs
as a like a publish creative interesting
ideas and don't believe the results of
venue but we have to put the results in
there so we you know and I think it's
not a bad idea you just shouldn't take
them too literally right so not claiming
we've like solved some new problem here
although I think the third one actually
is quite interesting and if we pushed it
further it would be potentially solving
a real problem but we basically applied
this diffusion over a discret state
spases for small molecules on a
particular toy problem we don't really
believe in but just demonstrates the
Machinery works one for um some
enhancers and DNA sequence and in this
case Hunter actually trained his own
inverse folding model and showed how to
use this Machinery to generate things
that um would be sequences that fold
just as well as a regular inverse
folding model but be more likely to
additionally be predicted to be stable
by guiding it um to be more
stable okay so now I'm going to uh go
into the like for those of you who found
that too Technical and weird hopefully
you can enjoy this part a little bit
more this is a a long this this project
took many many years it finally came out
um earlier this year which blows my mind
it feels like it should have come out a
long time ago but um so David Baker is a
colleague of mine who's a world expert
in um directed Evolution and in
particular one of the things he's
focused on for a long time is using uh
this Adeno Associated virus as a a
delivery mechanism for uh for
Therapeutics and so and this is this is
the team of folks that have worked on it
and so this actually has been very
promising there are clinical trials that
have shown this to be useful and you
probably have read about it in the news
now there's actually like this really
happening where people are are getting a
real win from delivering something with
an aav but there the problem is that all
of them basically have to be behind the
bloodb brain barrier so the antibodies
don't shut it down um there's a bunch of
cells we don't know how to Target we
don't know how to change the aav virus
to Target the cells we want and not to
Target the cells we don't want um so
there's a still although it is like
still a big it has had some good
successes there's a long way to go if we
want to use it more generally and so
what the the this project was about was
what I call uh from my perspective I
think an understudied and really lovely
problem for machine learning people to
think about is Library design when I'm
doing either like just from the get-go
what's the first library of proteins I
should measure in the lab and then
iteratively how should I go about doing
that and you could think of that as
classical design of experiments but I
think in the era of machine learning
there's a lot of kind of interesting
problems that get folded into there so
the goal was to say that Dave does all
these uh different campaigns to try to
change AV like this or like this or like
this
uh to achieve different things and every
time he does it he has to kind of start
from scratch um with what's essentially
a uniform library of proteins and so let
me clarify what I mean by uniform
library of proteins so in this case one
of the things that's got him a lot of
wins is to in his directed Evolution you
need a form of um to you need some
mechanism to induce variety to get to do
the evolution and one of the ones that's
very powerful in a is to insert a 21
nucleotide uh insertion into a very
specific part of the caps and this
produces a tremendous amount of variety
in phen many phenotypes um and so this
is something that they often start a
campaign with is they just say you know
what for this 21 Mr nucleotide let's
just U make random 21 Ms uniformly and
insert them um at scale like at
something like 10 to the six and then do
directed Evolution but when you do that
although this is a powerful mechanism
what happens with those libraries it
starts sort of at uniform it's not quite
uniform it's technically called nnk to
reduce stop codons but for if you don't
know what that means you can just think
of it as uniform over the space of
nucleotides with a small tweak and when
you do that you waste half the library
from the get-go and the reason you waste
half of it is half those viruses just
don't package like they're basically not
functional and the game of directed
evolution is a game of getting yourself
the best lottery tickets possible and so
here we know that half our lottery
tickets basically are failing from the
get-go and they've no hope of helping us
in our directed Evolution experiment and
you can filter them out but you're
losing those tickets so you're losing
like your shots on goal and so the idea
was can we create a better starting
library for any Downstream task that
Dave may have in his lab any um
engineering goal for aav and so what
does it mean that it's better it means
we have a just as much ideally just as
much diversity as uniform um or close to
that but have better packaging
efficiency on the whole for the whole
Library so that we get to keep all our
lottery
tickets and so so this is what we set
out to do and this is what we have done
and this is now one of the libraries
that he uses so the first thing we did
is we took his nnk Library which came
with sequences and some with log and
Richmond um I could tell you there's a
whole paper about like not how we did it
in this paper but I'll I'll give you a
teaser if there's time but we built a
supervised model from sequence base of
21 nucleotides actually I think we did
it at the amino acid level to the
packaging efficiency for the library he
was already using this uniform or nnk
Library don't worry about the details
here but basically we pick out a neural
Network architecture very simple one
quite small that just does best at
predicting packaging efficiency from
sequence on the nnk library and then we
wanted to check how well this model
worked so we picked four uh variants uh
that we one five that we had not seen in
the training data including the global
predicted maximum and then sort of like
a dilution series and show that this
model actually works really well across
the whole range so this model actually
understands the whole scope of the of
this problem we don't have a lot of
extrap ation issues here we just want
good packaging and we have seen some
good packaging and the model works in
the whole range and so now what I this
is sort of a simple uh idea here but one
that's missing from a lot of machine
learning library design so what you
really you almost always have some sort
of trade-off when you're designing and
what the trade-off we have here is each
point here is a library this is a
machine learning library design D1
machine learning library design D2 this
x here is the nnk library so every point
is a library and each Library specifies
I think I forgot to mention this it
specifies the probability of actg at
each of the 21 positions so instead of
uniform I can make it non-uniform but I
can only control it at each position
separately um but that's still quite a
bit of control and all the Machinery I'm
telling you about can be extended when
you have more control if you could do
full synthesis you can still do what I'm
going to tell you about here but so in
our case this nnk Library it has the
most um of all the libraries we computed
it has the most pairwise diversity and
that's cuz it's very close to uniform
and on this side over here if you take
this Library don't don't worry about the
spread this should just be a clean line
is an optimization issue but if you take
um one of Let's just say this Library
here this library has really high
expected packaging efficiency which is
this axis but it has really low
diversity and that's because there's a
tradeoff and so the nnk library has
really great diversity but it has crap
packaging efficiency and that's where
I'm losing most of my library over here
have a library that has fantastic
packaging efficiency but it has no
diversity because what is it doing it's
taking the one sequence the package is
best and it's making the whole library
look just like that sequence basically
and so we know we probably want to
operate somewhere in between those two
extremes and in this case we were pretty
lucky so in these trade-off curves if
you have a vertical position so this
machine learning D3 is essentially
vertically above the nnk library what
that means is I don't take any hit in
the diversity but I have vastly better
packaging efficiency so this is a Nob
brainer wind over the other Library what
we don't know is it possible this
library is better like we don't
generally know where we want to operate
on such a curve all we know is in
vertical lines the top point is better
so we decided uh on heris of sort of the
Kink here and then uh some other herti
we just picked these three libraries and
we measured the full tighter of these
libraries in the lab and checked that
indeed they have the kind of behavior we
expect uh to see and then um through an
experiment and sort of a decision making
process we picked this D2 to go forward
with and that's because after packaging
it and checking uh the variants it had
the most uh diversity variants post
packaging and so the idea was now we've
designed a new library that's meant to
replace this uniform nnk library that
will be better for any Downstream
engineering campaign for a property I've
not even thought about in designing this
Library just because I'm keeping more of
my lottery tickets uh in the sense that
I have a diverse library but almost
things are are more likely to package
and I'm less Lo likely to lose those
tickets and if I have more lottery
tickets I'm more likely to win the game
and so as a proof of principle that in
fact this was true we took a protein
engineering um task that the the model
and our procedure in our library knew
nothing about and the task was to infect
um non-human primate uh brain cells many
of which are very hard to infect and
what we showed is that even though our
model knew nothing about the brain or
these brain cells or anything that just
because we had sort of a better set of
lottery tickets that we had a much much
higher probability of infecting those
brain cells than the library that they
would have
used um and we're and now there's a
bunch of of follow-ups uh but it's not
on pre-print or anything yet but we're
using this type of thinking to keep
going further and further to make these
aavs more suitable for Therapeutics in
particular in the brain and on micral
cells um so I think in the interest of
time I'm going to skip over this but I'm
going to just make it a teaser uh and so
what I'm going to say is I said that um
I the whole thing started by building a
supervised model um over um the seven
amino acids uh which represent the 21
nucleotide insert to the what this is
technically is this log enrichment so
okay who who's computed a log
enrichment all right fewer people than
who knew Bas rule I'm very surprised by
you guys so this is a standard way to
deal with sequencing data is you um have
some sequence of interest and you put it
through a select X and then you and you
it has some amount in the starting
library and you count how many times it
happened you put it through a selection
um for example packaging selection and
then you get another account of how many
times it happened and then you compute
this like very simple log enrichment
which is really just the ratio of how
many times it was in the after the
selection before the selection just
normalized by total read count so this
is like a very widely used um
statistical estimate to understand which
sequences are more likely to package or
pass any selection at all outside of
protein engineering is a very very kind
of widely used idea and so this is
actually what we did to build these
supervised models but in some other
projects we realized this didn't work
and so I'm not going to go into it but
basically in our PL in our the AV these
were 21 nucleotides and we could just
count how many times they happened but
imagine that this was a really big
region and all you had were short reads
now you can't count and you can't just
get a log enrichment and you have a
problem and so basically if you're
interested go check out this paper which
shows you how to handle a variety of
situations can't natively handle but in
addition even in the ones you can handle
just has better statistical power so I'm
going to stop there and leave some time
for questions but maybe I'll just um
yeah and I'll leave this up if then if
if you want you can ask questions about
it or read it and and otherwise I'll
just take some questions now thank
you thank you Jennifer uh so I requested
you to come um down at the microphone if
you have questions so we have 10 minutes
for questions please come down and ask
and we have also online moderator for
the
questions hello I just wanted to ask uh
how do you measure the edge of data the
slide you showed with measure the what
the edge of data Edge Edge yeah you you
you mentioned that you use machine
learning and physics based approach in a
slide to combine them where the physics
based uh oh I see yeah so that's I think
which let me rephrase the question I
think you're saying I mentioned in one
of the like things I didn't have a whole
set of slides for that Hunter had a
project in blend in cohes coherently
blending biophysics based bottles with
machine learning models where the idea
is you want the machine learning model
to gracefully back gracefully back off
to the biophysics based model and you
ask the exactly the correct question is
how do you know where to start trusting
one and not trusting the other more like
relatively speaking and that is sort of
the Crux of the problem and that problem
requires that you have a decent handle
on uncertainty estimates and which is Al
like which is also quite a technical
area and I would say this is not solved
but there's reasonable things you can do
and the and so uncertainty in a lot of
classical statistical modeling you
always just think of sensor noise you
build a linear aggression and there's
like an error term actually which most
people forget about but there is and
that's you think of that as just like
the error of the machine from which you
got the data and that's like the
standard um type of noise we think about
in statistical modeling but but in these
kinds of problems where you have the
issue of extrapolation there's something
that's sometimes called epistemic
uncertainty and that's not uncertainty
from sensor noise in your data it's
uncertainty because you're farther away
from the training data it's like like
absence of knowledge about that part of
the space and so there are certain
classes of modeling techniques um like
Gan process regression which can be
quite good at that in many cases in the
modern era we often take an ensemble of
neural networks um and there's arguments
about why that works or not these are
are imperfect and that is the key thing
you need in order to do this as well as
an uncertainty estimate of some kind for
the biophysics based model although that
one you can handle if you don't have it
through some kind kind of slightly
clever but simple thinking um
than hey Jennifer thank you for the
really really amazing and interesting
talk thank you um I was curious so you
presented a slide
on basically three different ways of
looking at this problem of going from P
of x to or P of maybe P of Y conditioned
on x m and
you boxed like the basically the
freezing approach of taking a freezing
your model and then training something
on top of it um which was interesting so
just to be clear we're not training
really something on top of it we're
training actually quite separately like
they're not
trained uh well they're I guess they're
a little bit trained together through a
noise schedule but
yeah um sorry to interrupt yeah yeah
yeah okay I mean maybe idea pushes away
from my question then so my question
would have been if there was a reason to
take the same model uh or to have the
same initial model that's frozen that
we're training off of so yeah now I'm
like are you saying what's the advantage
in doing that so the advantages yeah so
like the advantages I could think of are
that I mean we could save memory and
training cost by reusing the model
versus what the fine tuning model like
I've seen some better performances with
some of the fine tuning approach well
first of all I wouldn't believe anything
you see almost anywhere until you do it
for your problem yourself in a way that
you are honest with yourself but I'm
sure I have no doubt that each of those
methods has a place where it is
genuinely best and I don't think and I
think it like I've I keep thinking I
want to write something a paper about
this but I have not done that because I
haven't done the work to do it but I
think one of and I again I think John
Ingraham in the chroma paper makes a
really nice point about this so he puts
this like he has this crazy in a sense
super wellth thought out model to do uh
to generate backbone structures so the
3D coordinates of each C Alpha carbon
and he puts all this domain knowledge in
about geometry and like a prior of
collapsed polymers and like like and
like all and again doesn't matter if you
understand but he puts all this domain
specific knowledge into that model with
some understanding of what he's modeling
which is um protein structures that live
in a 3D physical space that represent
proteins and so he can put all this
amount of thinking into there uh and and
now he has this model and when he's
doing that he may not know what
Downstream use cases he wants so but he
because he puts so much energy and
thought into that model it's very nice
if he can repurpose that model for all
these kind of other Downstream tasks
where he wants to condition on different
things and he can just now he has this
extremely powerful thing that he can
play with Lego blocks by kind of plug
and play and so I think like it's true
like he could now just take take all
that machinery and thinking and like
train it kind of all together as well
but I think in many cases these models
are kind of expensive and and even in
Industry people are taxed for um compute
and so forth so I think it is like a
practical issue you could in fact just
redo everything but I think it's nice
not to have to retrain giant models even
if you're just doing some low rank
approximation blah blah blah yeah thank
you
hi Jennifer um yeah so actually sort of
related to that uh uh that question so
one thing oh I was looking at that slide
where you're showing like this
classifier gu and one thing that was
confusing to me is it that like your
unconditional model has to be a
diffusion model or could it be like is
this kind of a general that's a that's a
good question as well so that paper is
focused on Flow matching and diffusion
models and I don't want I don't want to
my but my let's say my students are now
working in more General
versions of that and I don't want to say
it because I don't want I don't want
them to get scooped um but I there are
some more general concepts there and
some of the seeds of that exist in some
literature um but that paper is specific
to it's well I would say it's anchored
in diffusion and flow matching models
and uh but any basically if you have
under any under any model for which the
underlying process is a continuous time
markof process which has a which is
defined essentially by the rate Matrix
then all the math they did applies to
updating the rate Matrix from an
unconditional rate Matrix to a
conditioned rate Matrix and so in
principle there could be a broader set
of things based on continuous time
markof processes for which the exact
same thing would hold and then so that's
like a direct generalization of turning
the same machinery and then there's just
a more general idea of not exactly using
that Machinery but this kind of idea
let's say so so just uh clarify so then
the classifi or whatever predictive
model you're creating has to be in the
same it has to be a model which is like
kind of it's a diffusion model
prediction task or or you're Oh you mean
the two parts you're plugging and
playing there yeah so in that work
that's right they're both it's it's
basically saying I assume the overall
model is a continuous time markup
process defined by a rate Matrix now
tell me how to go from a a one M rate
Matrix which represents the
unconditional model to another rate
Matrix which represents the conditioned
model and it's so all the Machinery is
is converting rate matrices basically
and that's this that's the requirement
for that piece of work okay
thanks uh more questions and I can bring
up we can bring up the microphone if
you're sitting in the middle and cannot
walk down
okay then
um I have a more conceptual question
like I just want to understand from you
so you mentioned how powerful the
diffusion models are so before the
diffusion models existed the generative
model to be clear I said they're very
powerful for real valued spaces and I
don't think there's clear evidence yet
that they're powerful on discrete State
spaces and I have been skeptical but I I
now think they are um but it's a very
nuanced topic yeah so would you be uh
even on the continuous space um could
you give us an idea some conceptual or
philosophical idea of why diffusion
model is better compared to the that's a
question I have been asking a lot of
people like I have a vague intuition um
but I don't I don't have a great answer
and also I don't work in those spaces
and like I'd say the big wins are in
computer vision and so the people who
maybe deeply understand it are in
computer vision which I'm not but I have
the sense that there's something about
when you do in a standard gener in most
standard generative models you either
somehow just generate all like the whole
image at once in images or uh
and but something about in diffusion
you're you're taking like a random image
and then you're perturbing it a tiny
amount over and over and over and so
there's basically it's doing something
that no other models do which is is
touching all the pixels at once but just
a tiny little bit uh and and so that I
don't think that's a great answer but
that is like something that those models
do that other models don't is they're
just they're touching everything but
just a little bit and doing it over and
over I don't think that's a great answer
though yeah it's like uh incremental
learning somehow like from a very random
like if I want to put it in a
philosophical concept like think about
if I want to think think about something
a model that doesn't know anything and
has some noise and starts shaping the
data Maybe um and I also think a lot
about what's the philosophy behind that
makes those models so powerful that was
the question but I think that is true
it's incremental learning and
and yeah maybe we'll talk off offline
more thank you for that question um okay
so if there is no more question then
let's thank Jennifer one more time