I'm Caroline Ooler, a professor in the
department of electrical engineering and
computer science and the institute for
data systems and society at MIT and a
core faculty member at the Broad
Institute, one of the world's leading
biomedical research centers. At the
Broad, I direct the Eric and Wendy
Schmidt Center, which seeks to create a
two-way street between machine learning
and biology. And I'm Elina Clausnitsa,
an associate professor of medicine at
Harvard Medical School in Massachusetts
General Hospital and an institute member
at the Broad where I direct the broad
diabetes initiative which brings
together clinicians, geneticists and
computational scientists to uncover
mechanisms of metabolic diseases and
translate them into new therapies. Today
we want to share with you an exciting
challenge that's taking place this
December. So the Eric and Wendy Schmidt
Center and the Bro Diabetes Initiative
are proud to host the obesity machine
learning competition tackling metabolic
diseases. We are collaborating with
Massachusetts General Hospital, Beth
Islia, the Kones Medical Center and
Crunch DAO.
>> In this competition, we ask, can you
design algorithms that identify genes
driving metabolic disease and help us
find ways to rebalance the system? will
now explain the biology underlying the
problem, the data set, and what success
looks like in this competition. At the
heart of this challenge are adiposites,
the fat cells that help regulate our
metabolism. We'll talk about what
happens when there's an imbalance
between energy intake and expenditure
and how we can steer fat cells towards
healthier states. But understanding and
predicting how fat cells behave isn't
something we can do by intuition alone.
The systems are too complex. Each cell's
behavior is influenced by thousands of
genes and their genetic variations
interacting in subtle ways. Thankfully,
current technologies allow producing
vast data sets that measure the
expression of all genes at single cell
resolution. But these huge
highdimensional data sets are impossible
to interpret just by eye. That's why
machine learning is key. It could allow
us to uncover hidden patterns, predict
how genetic changes ripple through these
gene networks, and also identify new
ways to restore metabolic balance. Now,
for some of our viewers, it may have
been a while since biology class. So,
Molina, let's start simple. So, what
exactly are adiposytes and what do they
do?
>> Adiposytes are specialized cells that
regulate how our body stores and burns
energy. When nutrients are abundant,
they store fat as a safe energy reserve.
But when we need energy, for example,
during fasting, exercise, or when we are
cold, they release fatty acids into the
bloodstream to be burned as fuel by
other cell types.
>> H So are really track what comes in and
what goes out?
>> Exactly. That's it. Most of our fat is
white atapost tissue, which serves
mainly to store energy. Another function
of the atapost tissue is thermogenesis.
the production of heat by burning
nutrients. This function is partly
mediated by the expression of uncoupling
protein one or UCP1. Thermogenesis
occurs predominantly in brown atapost
tissue which makes up only about 1 to 2%
of total body fat. However, a fraction
of white atapost tissue can acquire
thermogenic properties through a process
known as browning or beeing. So brown
and beige fat burns energy instead of
saving it.
That's right. And under certain
conditions like prolonged cold exposure
or exercise, some white fat can actually
take on brownlike features. We call that
browning. It's like flipping a metabolic
switch, really. White cells that used to
store fat can start burning it instead.
If we could safely trigger that process,
it could help us combat obesity by
turning the body's own fat into an
energy burner.
>> H. And I imagine that when that system
gets totally out of balance, say when
energy intake exceeds expenditure,
that's when obesity develops. Yes,
chronic imbalance of energy intake and
energy expenditure together with genetic
predisposition drives the excessive
storage of fatty acids and white
adipocytes which can eventually lead to
obesity. Obesity affects 890 million
people worldwide. It dramatically raises
the risk of type 2 diabetes,
cardiovascular disease, and even certain
cancers. But the opposite can be harmful
too. When adapost tissue is reduced or
abnormally distributed, as for example
in lipodistrophe, fatty acids spill into
other tissues such as the liver, leading
to insulin resistance and other
metabolic disorders.
>> So both extremes, too much or too little
functional fat can really be harmful.
>> That's exactly it. Maintaining the right
amount and function of adapost tissue is
key to metabolic health. Two major
processes keep the system in balance.
The adapogenic shift which supports the
formation of healthy fat cells that can
safely store energy and the thermogenic
shift which activates fat cells to burn
energy when needed. If we can understand
the gene pathways that regulate those
shifts, we could potentially rewire fat
cells toward metabolic health. And
that's exactly where this year's
challenge comes in. Modern biology gives
us incredible tools. Single cell
sequencing, crisper pertubations, and
imaging that let us measure thousands of
genes across hundreds of thousands of
cells. But that also means that each
experiment generates massive data sets,
far too large for humans to interpret on
their own. So that's where machine
learning can make a huge difference. It
can help us map how genes interact, how
they push cells into different states,
and how those states influence
metabolism. But unlike the algorithms
that power product recommendations or
targeted ads, we need our algorithms not
just to predict, but to actually reveal
the underlying mechanisms, the causal
rules that really shape biology itself.
Recent single cell studies have shown
that edibletites exist in many different
states. They are far more diverse than
we once thought, but the genes
regulating those states are still
largely unknown. We can actually study
these adipocy states in a test tube,
saving us the complication of working on
human subjects. Edipus tissue contains a
population of progenitor cells that can
become fat cells under the right
conditions. In the lab, we can nudge
these progenitors to develop into
different adipocy types. And with
crisper cast 9 particularly so crisper
interference we can selectively knock
down genes during this differentiation
process by observing how the
transcriptto that's the activity of all
20,000 genes changes in each cell. We
can start mapping the gene networks that
drive these states. The challenge of
course is scale. There are thousands of
single gene targets and hundreds of
millions of possible two gene
combinations. Testing all of them
experimentally would be absolutely
impossible.
>> And that's exactly where you and machine
learning come in. Your task is to
predict how perturbations will shift
gene expression and change cell states.
So we can focus on the most promising
experiments. To make this happen, we
have collected large scale single cell
data from adipocy differentiation
experiments with crisper pertubations.
Each experiment measures how knocking
down a particular gene changes the
expression of thousands of others. We
have knocked down genes encoding for
transcription factors, specialized
proteins that regulate gene expression
in individual cells. One data set
consists of single gene perturbations of
150 transcription factors. The second
data set contains combinatorial
perturbations of 15 transcription
factors.
So this means that for each perturbed
gene, we can observe how it rewires the
cell's regulatory network and whether
that shift moves the cell towards a new
cell state. And for a few genes, we can
see how the pertubation is affected by
the simultaneous knockdown of another
gene as well. But of course, we have
only tested a fraction of all possible
20,000 perturbations and their
combinations. So the challenge is to
develop algorithms that can predict the
effects of the untested ones and
identify combinations that might most
strongly enhance metabolic health. So
here is the exact breakdown of the
challenge. In part one, you will predict
the effects of single gene pertubations
on gene expression and cell state. In
part two, you will predict the effects
of combinations of pertubations
capturing how genes interact with one
another. And finally, in part three, you
will propose new gene combinations that
are most likely to shift fat cells
toward either energy storing,
adypogenic, or energy burning,
thermogenic states, or potentially other
states. We are really excited to
announce something unique to this
challenge. The top ranked predictions
will be experimentally tested in the lab
here at the Broad Institute, meaning
your algorithms could directly guide
biological discovery in obesity
research. Note that a biology background
is actually not needed to participate.
The Schmidt Center will provide all
challenge participants with a short
online crash course and the Broad
Institute is a global leader in
biomedical research, particularly in
genetic sequencing. So this is a unique
opportunity for you to learn from
leading life science and computational
biology experts. The lecture series will
take you through the biology of
metabolic diseases along with the
technical knowledge needed to complete
this competition. You'll be really well
prepared for the challenge at hand. The
challenge will run from December 2025
through April 2026. You can sign up as
an individual or a team and we'll be
giving out monetary prizes to the
winners of each part of the challenge
totaling $50,000.
The top algorithms will be presented in
the resulting publications. And as
always, the resulting data, algorithms,
and code from the challenge will all be
made open source for the community to
use. To achieve the goals of this
challenge, we are going to need new
ideas. new ideas that break through the
bounds of the traditional approaches
that address the most pressing questions
and ultimately help us intersect machine
learning with biology.
What makes this challenge so exciting is
that it's not just a coding exercise.
It's a way to accelerate real biological
discovery. The predictions you make
could help pinpoint the key regulators
that determine whether a fat cell stores
or burns energy. And by experimentally
testing the top models in the lab, we're
closing the loop between computation and
biology, something that's been a
longstanding goal of our community. This
challenge will show how machine learning
can drive hypothesis generation in
biology, not just pattern recognition.
Instead of passively analyzing data,
we're using algorithms to suggest what
experiments to do next. And that's the
future, a partnership between biologists
and computer scientists where models
make experiments smarter and faster.
>> Right. If you have ever wanted to see
your algorithm shape what happens in a
biology lab, this is your chance. We
can't wait to see what you'll come up
with and what we can discover together.
>> So, join us for the Obesity Machine
Learning Competition. tackling metabolic
diseases and help unlock new ways to
combat obesity through science, data,
and collaboration. If you haven't
already, please register now. We're very
excited to work with you.