So hello everyone and welcome to MIT
Startup Exchange demo day. Thank you for
joining whether it's your first time or
you're back with us once again.
I'm Ariadna Rodenstein, program manager
with MIT Startup Exchange and shortly
you will hear from eight startups. I'm
excited that we're all going to be
learning about their innovative and
nimble technologies very varied and I'll
get into those areas in a moment. But
first, I'd like to share a brief
overview of our program.
So MIT startup exchange was created to
support MIT connected startups as they
grow, expand, and solve some of the
world's greatest challenges. And we do
this by fostering partnerships and
collaborations between the startups and
industry, primarily members of the
industrial leazison program or ILP
represented by so many of you joining us
today, but also the MIT innovation
ecosystem and beyond.
The startups in our program have a
strong connection to the institute. They
may be based on MIT licensed technology
or founded by MIT staff, faculty or
alumni. They may also be vetted by some
of our MIT peers including the engine,
start nano or cel startup connect plus.
We have around a thousand startups in
the program and they usually join at
pilot stage or beyond and they may
represent any sector and any geography.
Here you can see some of the trending
solutions and the trending technologies
of MIT startups and those involved are
those represented by the startups here
today. Of course we start with AI and
ML, big data and analytics,
sustainability, renewable energy and
materials, robotics, IoT and sensing and
healthcare.
So when it comes to value, everything
that we do is to support the exposure of
startups and connections to industry.
And we do this in a variety of ways,
which is a customized approach. And so I
hope that everyone can take advantage of
these benefits that are listed here. For
example, we launch calls for startups.
We call these opportunities.
And they're based on a corporate's
priorities and internal challenges. And
so startups can apply on our website and
if selected they can work with you as an
ILP member to help you with a problem
that you may be facing in your industry.
We also host one-on-one meetings, demo
days like today, other events like
webinars, conferences locally and
internationally and they have the
component of startup lightning talks and
an exhibit. We also host workshops and
trainings sometimes in conjunction with
our MIT peers.
And so what is emote? It's a virtual
forum to facilitate these corporate
interactions with industry ready
startups
and the goal is to explore potential
collaborations and partnerships but also
especially to do it sooner rather than
later. This way you can get to know more
of the startups that join our program.
The format today will be eight startups
presenting for four minutes followed by
two minutes of Q&A and then we're going
to move right on to breakout room so
that you can learn more and engage with
the startups further. For the Q&A part,
I ask that you either use the Q&A tab at
the bottom of your screen, indicate the
startup that the question is for. You
can also upvote questions, but also if
you feel more comfortable, you can
engage via the chat. You can post the
questions there. You can um directly
communicate with the startups, exchange
information, etc.
And as always, reach out to us if you
need help connecting with the startups
through our program or of course via the
your ILP program director. So with that,
a couple of reminders. The startup
presentations are being recorded and
also at the end of the event, you'll get
a brief pop-up survey on your screen. So
please help us with your feedback. So
now let's hear from the startups.