the MIT energy initiative presents MIT
design would harness 40% of the sun's
heat to produce clean hydrogen fuel
conventional systems for producing
hydrogen depend on fossil fuels but the
new system uses only solar energy
written by Jennifer Chu for MIT
news MIT Engineers aim to produce
totally green carbon-free hydrogen fuel
with a new train-like system of reactors
that has driven solely by the sun in a
study appearing today in solar energy
journal the engineers lay out the
conceptual design for a system that can
efficiently produce solar thermochemical
hydrogen the system harnesses the sun's
heat to directly split water and
generate hydrogen a clean fuel that can
power long-distance trucks ships and
planes while in the process emitting no
greenhouse gas emissions Today hydrogen
is largely produced through processes
that involve natural gas and other
fossil fuels making the otherwise green
fuel Fu more of a gray energy source
when considered from the start of its
production to its end use in contrast
solar thermochemical hydrogen or stch
offers a totally emissions-free
alternative as it relies entirely on
renewable solar energy to drive hydrogen
production but so far existing stch
designs have limited efficiency only
about 7% of incoming sunlight is used to
make hydrogen the results so far have
been low yield and high cost and a big
step toward realizing solar made fuels
the MIT team estimates its new design
could harness up to 40% of the sun's
heat to generate that much more hydrogen
the increase in efficiency could drive
down the system's overall cost making St
a potentially scalable affordable option
to help decarbonize the transportation
industry we're thinking of hydrogen as
the fuel of the future and there's a
need to generated cheaply and at scale
says the study's lead author Ahmed goni
the Ronald C crane professor of mechanic
engineering and MIT we're trying to
achieve the department of Energy's goal
which is to make green hydrogen by 2030
at $1 per kilogram to improve the
economics we have to improve the
efficiency and make sure most of the
solar energy we collect is used in the
production of hydrogen Gip study
co-authors are anaka patker first author
in MIT postto Harry Tuller MIT professor
of Material Science and Engineering Chia
uu of the University of waterl and one J
at Ewa Women's University in South
Korea solar
stations similar to other proposed
designs the MIT system would be paired
with an existing source of solar heat
such as a concentrated solar plant CSP a
circular array of hundreds of mirrors
that collect and reflect sunlight to a
central receiving Tower an stch system
then absorbs the receiver's heat and
directs it to split water and produce
hydrogen this process is very different
from electrolysis which uses us
electricity instead of heat to split
water at the heart of a conceptual stch
system is a two-step thermochemical
reaction in the first step water in the
form of steam is exposed to a metal this
causes the metal to grab oxygen from
Steam leaving hydrogen behind this metal
oxidation is similar to the resting of
iron in the presence of water but it
occurs much faster once hydrogen is
separated the oxidized or rusted metal
is reheated in a vacuum which acts to
reverse the rusting process and
regenerate the metal with the oxygen
removed the metal can be cooled and
exposed to steam again to produce more
hydrogen this process can be repeated
hundreds of times the MIT system is
designed to optimize this process the
system as a whole resembles a train of
box-shaped reactors running on a
circular track in practice this track
would be set around a solar thermal
Source such as a CSP Tower each reactor
in the train would house the metal that
under go the Redux or reversible rusting
process each reactor would first pass
through a hot station where it would be
exposed to the sun's Heat at
temperatures of up to 1,
1500° this extreme heat would
effectively pull oxygen out of a
reactor's metal that metal would then be
in a reduced State ready to grab oxygen
from Steam for this to happen the
reactor would move to a cooler station
at temperatures around 1,000° C where it
would be exposed to steam to produce
hydrogen
rust and
rails other similar stch Concepts have
run up against a common obstacle what to
do with the heat released by the reduced
reactor as it is cooled without
recovering and reusing this heat the
system's efficiency is too low to be
practical a second challenge has to do
with creating an energy efficient vacuum
Where Metal can dust some prototypes
generate a vacuum using mechanical pumps
though the pumps are too energy
intensive and costly for large scale
hydrogen production to to address these
challenges the MIT design incorporates
several energy saving workarounds to
recover most of the heat that would
otherwise escape from the system
reactors on opposite sides of the
circular track are allowed to exchange
heat through thermal radiation hot
reactors get cooled while cool reactors
get heated this keeps the heat within
the system the researchers also added a
second set of reactors that would circle
around the first train moving in the
opposite direction this outer train of
reactors would operate at generally
cooler temperatures and would be used to
evacuate oxygen from the hotter inner
train without the need for energy
consuming mechanical pumps these outer
reactors would carry a second type of
metal that can also easily oxidize as
they circle around the outer reactors
would absorb oxygen from the inner
reactors effectively derusting the
original metal without having to use
energy intensive vacuum pumps both
reactor trains would run continuously
and would generate separate streams of
pure hydrogen and oxygen the researchers
carried out detailed simulations of the
conceptual design and found that it
would significantly boost the efficiency
of solar thermochemical hydrogen
production from 7% as previous designs
have demonstrated to 40% we have to
think of every bit of energy in the
system and how to use it to minimize the
cost godem says and with this design we
found that everything can be powered by
heat coming from the Sun it is able to
use 40% of the sun's heat to produce
hydrogen if this can be realized it
could drastically change our Energy
Future namely enabling hydrogen
production 24/7 says Christopher muick
an assistant professor of chemical
engineering at Arizona State University
who is not involved in the research the
ability to make hydrogen is the Lynch
pin to producing liquid fuels from
sunlight in the next year the team will
be building a prototype of the system
that they plan to test in concentrated
solar power facilities at laboratories
of the Department of energy which is
currently funding the project when fully
implemented the system would be housed
in a little building in the middle of a
solar field patker explains inside the
building there could be one or more
trains each having about 50 reactors and
we think this could be a modular system
where you can add reactors to a conveyor
belt to scale up hydrogen
production this work was supported by
the centers for mechanical engineering
research and education at MIT and susc