Thank you for the warm introduction and
um really really happy to be here today
and share with you all a little bit of
uh my work on using AI and O techniques
for social impact and then time
permitting hopefully at the end also go
back to how some of the challenges we've
identified in addressing these problems
also inspired methodological advances uh
in AI.
So uh at USC as Sarah mentioned I
co-direct the center for AI in society
whose missions uh is to advance the
scholarship and application of AI for
the uh well-being of vulnerable
communities both human and other
species. Uh and we really focus on advi
advancing um responsible AI in
partnership with community uh
stakeholders, organizations and policy
makers. So um we share this kind of
enthusiasm and commitment to uh try to
work on problems that are well grounded
uh and in partnerships to make sure that
they address the real pain points that
uh will make a difference in the real
world. And so within the center we've uh
broadly organized different uh research
projects and and collaborations we have
in three teams health and well-being,
environment and homelessness. And uh I
will try today to give you uh several
examples within uh spanning some of
these uh domains.
So in my own work I I have uh focused on
using AI for conservation for habitat
and biodiversity conservation but also
uh more recently on disaster resilience
in particular thinking about mitigation
planning across uh lifeline
infrastructure against disasters such as
uh wildfires, floods and earthquakes. Um
and then finally climate change and its
impacts on human displacement, species
displacement, energy and health. And
what's the common thread between uh
these many different application domains
is that they involve the design of
policy and actions to manage a very
limited resources available for um a lot
of these kind of public good or social
good domains. uh where while where while
we are trying to maximize the best
impact
um uh under complex objectives and
complex constraints and so really this
real world application problems uh
become uh very interesting and very
impactful predictive and decision
problems and so as as Sarah said like
early on in my career I really um got
dedicated to kind of advancing the field
of computational sustainability where
really the goal goal was to kind of um
advocate and grow a community of AI and
computer science researchers more
broadly that are really grounded in
problems from uh social impact and
sustainability. Um thinking about how
our techniques from AI applied there but
also by looking at these problems um in
very very fine granularity thinking
about how we can improve our methods in
order to to uh address those domains. So
again today I'm going to try to give you
some examples of things we've done uh in
partnerships in both the predictive as
well as the decision side of things. And
so without further ado I have like a
very packed agenda of several examples
um kind of give you a foray of different
things we've done. Uh I'll start with a
recent example we we've worked on on
health and well-being and this is a
collaboration um with Amref which is uh
um an NGO that works across Africa in
order to uh promote health uh as well as
the Kenyan Ministry of Health and our
collaborators at Microsoft AI for goodl.
So what we were um doing in this
partnership is looking at how to
forecast malnutrition hotspots in
Kenya. In particular, recently uh
there's been a lot of advocacy about uh
uh the the problem of acute malnutrition
and the need to uh try to understand
better the driving factors and intervene
when whenever that possible.
So in particular in Kenya uh
malnutrition is a leading cause of
morbidity and mortality among children
uh with uh over 970,000 children um
under five uh that are suffering some
form of malnutrition in 2023. So this is
a pervasive problem. Amref is one of the
organizations on the ground trying to
address it by providing uh food baskets
and other nutritional support for
families who have uh children
experiencing malnutrition. And so one of
the uh the key uh thing that we
identified is how can we make that their
work more effective again having limited
resources to deploy on the ground. Can
we facilitate um targeting these
resources in the most effective way
possible? So what we identified as a way
to enable that activity is to improve
our ability to forecast spatially where
would be the hot spots of malnutrition
among children with enough in advance in
order to um uh allow for responses in
terms of uh providing resources and
allocating resources in the right
spaces. So we want to basically create a
model that's able to predict
malnutrition on the subcounty level one
month, three month and six months in
advance to allow for organizations like
Amref to then prioritize their resource
allocation. So we will work closely with
Amref and the Ministry of Health to uh
collect um historical data and identify
the the the modeling problem.
So right now the way that the this is
done in organizations such as Amref is
to look at the tracking numbers of
incidents or prevalence of malnutrition
over the previous months and use that as
a way to estimate what will happen next.
So it's uh using historical information
but not in automated or uh uh
sophisticated way datadriven but not any
kind of statistical modeling and
obviously they realize that they are
leaving a lot um that can be
exploited. So basically we came in and
said okay can we do this better. So
Kenya like many uh uh low resource and
middle inome countries across Africa and
and other continents are actually using
DHIS2
um as a system to manage their health
information. Um and so one thing um that
about this project is that we've built
it for Kenya with Kenya data but because
it's built on top of DHS2 which is
actually used across many other
countries we're hoping that we can
actually expand the footprint of this
work across uh other places
with similar challenges. So here we are
looking at um four years of historical
data uh from about 14,000 GOTAC health
facilities which keep track of the
number of cases of malnutrition among
children as measured by their uh mid
upper arm circumference and then other
clinical features like uh for example
infant feed feeding practices um uh low
birth weight etc. So the idea is can we
use this uh historical time series of of
our outcome which is the malnutrition as
well as clinical features to be able to
pred. So the goal is going to be to
predict whether a particular subcount is
within some level of prevalence. So
we're going to aggregate data on the
subcounty level summing up all the cases
reported across all facilities falling
in particular geographic region and then
uh um tearing that into this uh kind of
predetermined IPC 5point scale which
looks at classifies levels of prevalence
between 0 to 3% 3 to 10 10 to 15 to 30
and above 30 based on uh a previous
classification. Okay. So here I'm going
to skip a lot of the details but here's
some of the of of the results. By
basically combining this historic data
on outcome time series analysis plus the
clinical features we were able to show
that um we uh with even simple
lightweight models such as logistic
regression and gradient boosting trees
we're able to improve the accuracy. This
is um average you see across these five
different class predictions over kind of
the baseline which is window averaging
as a way to kind of quantitatively
um capture what they're doing right now
which is looking at historical trends of
uh of outcomes of malnutrition outcomes
and using those to predict the future.
So as you can see here, window averaging
or just simple statistic um historical
averaging is fails to predict accurately
across the medium to low uh prevalences
of malnutrition and and this non more u
complex nonlinear models like gradient
boosting are able to improve that
accuracy significantly. So although we
haven't like in this case invented a
brand new methodology bringing the right
AI techniques is actually uh helping our
partners to resolve a problem that on
the ground has a big impact for
them and so right now we are working
closely with the ministry of health to
try to actually deploy this on a
continuous way where they would upload
data and um uh forecast uh every one to
three months and uh inform their
resource allocation respectively.
So in addition to these clinical
features and historical data, we also
wanted to see well is it possible to
bring different data sources and and uh
that are not clinical that are able to
help us uh um make these predictions in
situations where for example let's say
access to this ministry of health uh
information DHS2 is not accessible. So
in particular we looked at remote sensed
data in particular data like modis that
is collected every eight days has
relevant outputs like the gross primary
productivity which could be correlated
with kind of like food scarcity and food
availability over some time windows. So
we aggregated GPP derived uh uh
statistics on a monthly uh basis to the
subcounty level and used that as like
kind of a an alternative for toal
predictor and we were able to show that
actually just based on this like
completely uh data publicly available
from another source. we are able to at
least match the the simple baseline of
window averaging which still requires
having access to uh malnutrition
historical time series
data. Um we obviously ideally would want
to basically have this data fusion
between clinical and um and um
additional environmental such as GPP and
see which one how much they can
synergize. uh preliminary results on
that show that at least with enough
clinical features uh um satellite data
maybe is not needed to improve accuracy
but I feel like there's actually more to
be done in terms of really evaluating in
which situations um that can fill in um
unexpected gaps and just by itself it's
already good to know that it it is uh an
alternative source. So for example um
with the kind of
um cut to US aid for for some time for
example DHS2 and other health data that
this uh um you know um organizations
were relying to was actually offline. So
what happens when suddenly things like
this are offline right at least maybe
you can use like satellite
data. Okay. So, what's the potential
impact of this project is that we're
really hoping to improve the efficiency,
accuracy and delivery of nutrition
supplements uh in this um um vulnerable
communities. We are hoping in next steps
to actually work closely with Amaref in
order to study the kind of like impact
on the way that they operate and how
many uh effective uh um uh deployments
of nutrition uh will happen under this
better prediction and and think about
how we can integrate the predictive
models with operational decisions such
as resource allocation which is very
interesting because at the end of the
day we don't just care about predicting
malnutrition per Today we want to enable
them to make more effective resource
allocation. So we're really excited
about this to actually um have a
long-term collaboration on the ground
and hopefully expand to other uh
countries as well. On the I'll switch
gears and uh show you some examples of
our work on decision making for the
environment. By the way, happy Earth Day
to everybody. I realize that I somehow
like serendipitously chose my seminar
date. I don't think anybody was doing it
on purpose but it was uh perfect. In
fact in retrospect if I had put two and
two I could have done a whole talk just
about by diversity conservation in uh um
inra day but I will share a little bit
of of of my work. I have uh um done uh
several different things related to to
conservation um and I'll talk briefly
about two of them. One of the uh the the
leading um
um threats to biodiversity is habitat
loss and fragmentation uh due to
anthropogenic uh pressures such as uh
deforestation,
urbanization, um agriculture and overall
climate change and therefore
conservation planning has a critical
role to play in protecting key habitat
uh before it gets destroyed. But how do
we make these decisions effectively
right in a datadriven way and again use
uh limited resources in the most
effective way possible. So a lot of my
work has been like bringing optimization
models to the conservation communities
in terms of uh conservation planning and
the most recent uh work that I've done
in collaboration with a large team of
ecologists and economists is to look at
the cost of institutional hierarchy
hierarchies in spatial conservation
planning. So what does that mean? That's
like a mouthful, right?
Um so as you know like conservation
planning is the problem of like choosing
with given some uh dollars allocated to
conservation which land should I protect
in order to maximize some kind of a
biodiversity objective for how many
species are expected to persist etc. And
so most of the literature and kind of
the research tools available out there
are focusing on this problem from kind
of a a single agent or oneshot decision-
making where I'm just saying okay I have
this money and I'm going to specially
decide which parcels I'm going to buy
and evaluate my objective right and I
want to do this in the most cost
effective way possible and increasingly
these models are actually really being
applied to large scale specially
explicit initiatives like the 30 by30
uh initiative and the uh key
biodiversity areas. However, one thing
that's missing uh is ignoring
institutional and governance structures.
So, usually you don't have that straight
connection between conservation dollars
and on the ground decision- making. For
example, uh even in the US is um we have
like federal government versus states.
So instead of using a single planner or
acting over whole region allocating
directly uh uh money or thinking just as
broken down multiple independent
planners we really want to take into
account this this kind of uh
institutional structure hierarchical
structure. So in this work we basically
focused on these uh collaborative
governance structures where we we want
to explicitly model the layers of
interact interacting conservation actors
who might have um misaligned related but
not perfectly identical uh conservation
priorities, right? They might operate on
different scales. They I guess might
have different value systems. Uh they
might have different instruments or
levers that they can uh control.
So in particular, we're going to look at
kind of like the US federal grant giving
to states where uh the federal
government is operating across the whole
USA. Their instrument is giving
allocating budgets to states but not
directly maybe protecting specific
parcels um and and and caring about like
federally listed species of importance
versus the states are operating over
their own specific region. um they
actually have the ability to spatially
make decisions about um conservation
priorities within within their states
and they might have locally important
keystone species and other endangered um
uh other uh species of interest economic
or uh cultural interests that they want
to protect. So there's this uh related
actors working with different
instruments at different scales and yet
they have to work together to achieve a
final outcome that hopefully is good for
everybody. So we can actually model this
hierarchical structure at least for for
federal versus regional decision making
or uh global versus regional decision-m
as a stack of barar game where one actor
moves first the leader and then the
others respond. So in our case, the
federal government is going to be the
leader allocating budgets to states and
the states are the followers which
receiving that budget then make their
own decisions maximizing their local
objectives and essentially um uh the the
leader the government could um
indogenize uh the the anticipated
behavior of of the followers in order to
make the best decisions for themselves.
Right? So if they ignore the fact that
these followers are going to be
optimizing different objectives than
themselves then they're going to be
doing a suboptimum resource
allocation. So to express this you
basically can think of it as a bi level
optimization problem where the leader is
optimizing some utility big U that is a
function of the decisions on the ground
that are performed at the lower level by
the individual states individual
decision- making the the leader itself
is allocating these budgets BR uh across
a whole total budget so it has this
continuous interventions but at the
lower level each of the states given a
particular budget is making discrete
choices about which land to protect or
not optimizing their own local
biodiversity
objective. So in particular in this in
this work we assume that the utility um
of both um the federal government and
and of the state governments are related
to some kind of uh ecological
persistence factor but the weight that
they put on different species or
different ecological factor is
different. Right? So in particular the
federal government might care about uh
endangered species act species versus
the local ones who uh have local
species. So we developed this framework
and and methodology where we are able to
um to model this problem as a very large
scale mixed integer optimization problem
and we applied to at the USA contiguous
uh continental um sorry contiguous um
what do I want to say
uh
yes uh uh um space. So this is basically
modeling the uh giving grants like such
as the land and water conservation fund,
federal uh giving and the cooperative
endangered species conservation fund. So
again here our uh funding decisions will
be on the federal level allocating
budgets on the lower level uh individual
discrete decisions about which counties
are going to uh uh get specific land
protected uh uh within them. And so uh
we actually use um uh as realistic data
as possible. We have species
distribution models for um uh more than
1,400 uh terrestrial species across the
US including uh federally important
species from the um threatened and
endangered species act and as well
species that are listed in what's called
swap plants or like the state action
plans that each individual state has.
that includes a much larger list of
species and then we have a cost estimate
for acquisition on the county level
based on uh expected
returns. So with this uh you know uh
real data set across the US uh we are
able to look at what happens when uh we
ignore versus indogenize this uh
institutional knowledge in decision-
making. So if the if we make federal
choices assuming that uh our the federal
objective is kind of like the king of
all kings and everybody's going to
follow uh the same uh the same lead the
the the federal government will make an
allocation something like that where
they would directly if they were able to
decide whether to protect land in order
to maximize ESA
species. However, this is not achievable
because the the federal government is
not directly able to work on the spatial
level. So, they're still going to have
to allocate budgets and then the states
are going to take those budgets and make
their own local decisions. So, then when
the corresponding states budgets are
allocated, they are allocated then to
different counties than what was
expected that idealized solution. So the
actual realized solution of the of the
the of the of the budget allocation that
ignores institution will shift the
expected decisions and then the the
realized objective in terms of federal
listed species will be lower. So that's
kind of like the the price of ignoring
institutions essentially. You can think
of that the difference between what the
federal government would have expected
to be the outcome for the ESA species
assuming that everybody's going to be
exactly making prioritizing the same
species as them versus what happens on
the ground when the misaligned
priorities are realized.
So by using our indogenized tackle game
uh model which indogenizes that
misalignment when in allocating budgets
we are able to do something smarter.
Okay. So the bille approach accounts for
the state decision making in the federal
budget allocation and um and basically
is able to allocate budgets to to states
that are more aligned in their
objectives with the federally uh for
with the federal ESA species. So in
terms of quantitative results, you can
think about this as the um the at at
best if the federal government was able
to swoop in and make specially explicit
decision, they can achieve some
idealized maximum. Uh but when it gets
realized with a misalignment, we in our
analysis, it basically loses about 24%
of the expected biodiversity outcomes.
But then when you come in and you do the
stack over by level method, we're able
to then uh recover that by at least
one/ird back to u uh expected or
anticipated biodiversity outcome. So
again indogenizes institutions is
allowing to take into account this
misalignment and um um empower the
federal government to make more informed
decisions. Yeah. Is it okay if I ask the
question? Yeah, sure. Um, so I think
this is really really cool work and and
particularly this like sort of
difference in terms of like decision-
making at different scales feels really
important in these spaces. But I guess
um it does kind of make the assumption
that the best solution is the idealized
solution based on the endangered species
act. But the endangered species act
doesn't list a huge number of threatened
species because the process of listing a
species is so political. Um, and so
actually some of those statebased
applications might actually be better
along some different dimensions of
biodiversity. Did you look at all at how
these different solutions might measure
for like different metrics of like
biodiversity sort of improvement or
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Definitely. So we
basically have this like plots where
it's looking at like oh what is like you
know the ESA only biodiversity versus
the combined biodiversity across all
species let's say the swap plants make
and essentially these different
approaches are are at different points
of the parto curve among them and um
often in fact depending on the
misalignment the you know ignoring in
institutions is is really like Pareto
dominated in a sense it would almost
sometimes be like worse in both cases.
Interesting. Because um because it's
already clear here like in a sense the
federal government will lose so much by
not taking into account the misalignment
that it will get worse response than it
will just let's say optimizing for
optimizing for the swap species and
still getting a benefit for the
federally listed species. But the bigger
overarching question is like are the
objectives that we are modeling the
right ones and that's obviously a much
bigger question.
But one can argue that but in all cases
at some point all of these actors will
have to agree on whatever they feel like
is the objective they want to optimize
and at that point it still makes sense
to think about this institutional
dynamics. there will always unless
you're thinking like oh I can convince
everybody to agree on a single objective
that's shared among all of them which I
feel like it's unlikely right and
there's obviously the power dynamics
about no but I'm on top therefore I have
my own objective it should dominate
other things yeah um a question I have
is do you have a do you have intuition
on why you're covering like only one
third like you know the what's going on
with the remaining 23 and um a related
question is do you model like gaming of
the um like of what the uh follower is
doing like uh you know saying that they
will they want to be what the leader
both very good questions so the first
one is the fact that there's uh some of
the u ESA species are in areas where
essentially there's very little other
species that anybody cares about so in a
sense they just like when you look at
what states will decide they just never
decide to go and protect land
So that's just because of the spatial
distribution of of some of these
pieces. Um, and the second one is very
relevant. So right now in a sense we've
gone one step further in modeling kind
of like the player dynamics in this
hierarchical structure. But obviously
there's much more complex things like
for example they could be gaming but
they also like more important is more
like how about cooperation right? So a
lot of neighboring uh uh bordering
states actually share a lot of their
species in their swaps because there's
overlapping habitat ranges. So there's
actually interest for them to coordinate
to protect those species that they both
care about. And so in our this current
model I'm presenting is actually not
taking into account in a sense lost
opportunity of coordination on the state
level. So that's actually something that
we are we're exploring now and we're
hoping to to come up with some
frameworks. Obviously it becomes more
and more complex as you think about like
more of the of the uh agent dynamics but
as a first step that was uh you know uh
one way to integrate the institutional
dynamics but definitely very very both
in terms of gaming and in terms of
cooperation wide open areas that for
additional
improvement. Okay. And so um in
conservation the second biggest threat
uh after habitat uh fragmentation and
loss is uh biodiversity uh loss due to
wildlife uh poaching, trafficking and
trade. It threatens animal populations
but it also threatens other sustainable
development goals like uh and threatens
equity, tourism, security and health.
And so I I think many people don't
realize the scale at which illegal
wildlife trafficking is actually
pervasive. It's like uh a huge
multi-billion dollar industry happening
globally across the world. And so IWT
refers to basically the poaching like
killing or taking out of their natural
habitat animals and then trafficking
them to other locations wherever the
markets are. And it threatens a lot of
uh um it affects a lot of species that
are highly threatened and endangered and
they're often like um collected either
because uh there's a demand for them as
pets alive or for their skins or other
uh products or um traditional medicine
for example. So there's many different
demands of when I get asked like oh but
why or like what's which exactly who are
the uh the people or the communities
that demand it? It's it's a very
multifaceted economy with different uh
supply and demand um uh factors. So
actually understanding what is
happening, how it's happening and and
how we can intervene is critical and yet
it's very difficult because very little
data is collected. I think I feel like
habitat modeling and species modeling is
way ahead of the curve in terms of data
collection and modeling efforts while
IWT is this like gray zone where it's
illegal in some countries, not in
others. Data is not collected in a in a
coherent way and there's really not
enough uh light being uh shown on this
uh really important conservation
problem.
Um obviously though uh a lot of
organizations conservation organizations
are trying to quantify the scale and
mechanism and impact of IWT and there's
like uh reports that are trying to
collect data and identify some of those
trends. Um but most of the reports that
are out there such as reports by the UN
aggregate observed incidents and
basically present raw IWT uh historical
trends. And that's obviously better than
not having uh quantitative analysis but
hopefully we can do better than just
counting right in order to understand
driving factors and so on. And the
problem with just counting is that the
data on which this is based which is
seizures right seizures of illegal
wildlife trafficking which is again kind
of criminal data it suffers from
detection bias, representation bias and
completeness bias. So um this severely
hinders our um ability to kind of uh
address and understand what's happening.
So coming from from from this
motivation, we wanted to see whether we
can use predictive modeling based on
this historic data to somehow help
identify features that make certain
locations uh more likely to be engaged
in illegal wildlife trafficking
activities and also try to fill in some
of the gaps gaps by being able to re um
predict uh undetected hotspots. And so
uh we chose to do this on the airline
global airline network because um
airline IWT seizure in was one of the
better documented kind of uh
infrastructures uh where uh IWT happens.
Obviously there's uh other uh modes but
um air um is one of the main ones and so
the first thing we did is to collect as
much data as we could. So based on kind
of like publicly or like by request uh
data um data access we were able to
aggregate uh uh 1,300 wildlife
trafficking incidents across the world
on the airport uh on airport uh network.
And as you can see here just in terms of
again the raw statistics um you can see
that there's certain hotspots of many
incidents being reported. Again, this is
with keeping in mind the fact that
reporting is incomplete
um and uh and and so just at face value
might also be missing some part of the
story. So we use this data to in a
predictive model to try to understand
how this uh historical IWT seizures
relates to features of the airport at
which the the seizures were either uh
confiscated or the recorded origin or
destination for that particular
trafficking incident. So um we are using
any kind of uh all the airports
implicated in IWT not just the seizure
location. And so in this model we
incorporate uh airport features that
vary by location. So looking at kind of
like structural components of centrality
metrics of the airports within the
global airline network. Right? So that's
kind of like structural network
properties but then uh development
sustainable development metrics such as
uh indices reported on criminal markets,
criminal actors and resilience. And so
here you can see based on on on uh on
the models we developed some sharply
feature importance which identifies the
fact that structural properties within
the network obviously drive a lot of the
choices. Airports with high uh network
centrality are very likely to be chosen.
They have a lot of edges and a lot of
ways to like go to different locations.
But other things also matter. In
particular, in our analysis, doing
prediction only based on structural
properties was much worse in terms of
accuracy than incorporating uh some of
the other factors like uh uh founder
crimes and uh state actors uh
territorial integrity etc. So basically
this model is allowing us to kind of dig
further into the driving factors
um that might not be understood before.
Can I ask a question? Yeah, sorry to
interrupt you. Uh you you do have
information about the prevalence of
certain species in geographies like also
what kind of markets the or what kind of
products and where these are sold uh in
terms of these species and if if these
are actually killed or used for some
other uses right so uh so the markets um
I mean there's some information but I
don't think there's very nicely compiled
information on the markets on the
species yes although the data um the IWT
data is so sparse that here we were
aggregating across all the species. We
didn't try to divide it by let's say uh
because then our data set becomes
smaller and smaller and smaller.
Ideally, we would want that because if
we are actually modeling let's say uh
the trafficking of a specific species or
like a a family of related species, we
could use information about like where
are they even present. So therefore we
kind of know what the supply areas,
right? And we could exploit that in our
prediction. Um and hopefully we can do
that um with with more information on um
as seizure data becomes more and more
reported. But do you have information on
lax laws like local laxity of
enforcement laws and you incorporate
that in the Yeah. So some of these
metrics are exactly measuring that like
for example how the strength of of of
like um law enforcement in in the
countries in which the airports are. It
also uh one of the features is like are
they part of sites which is this like
global consortium about commitment to
fight illegal wildlife trade. We we put
as many as these things as possible.
Many of these features are kind of on
the country level as opposed to on the
airport level. So we also try to
incorporate airport specific things like
the population of the city that it's
seen like other characteristics of that
location and so on. So so we try to put
in we didn't know what the driving
factors are. So originally we're trying
to be broad but again we have to keep
into account that the data set is small.
So at some point you start overfitting
as
well. Okay. And so then the other thing
that was really interesting to see is
the uh false positive of this model.
right? Knowing that there's like
detection uh u uh bias and so on.
Actually, a lot of these false positive
by talking to expert in the IWT
community are really not false. They're
just places where data is IWT incidents
are not being reported very well, right?
Like there's either no commitment to
report that much or uh for other
reasons. So it was very interesting to
use the model to also basically
something that you can do beyond just
doing like again what's in most reports
so far is just kind of
like data representation of what
historically observed but once you have
a model you can actually extrapolate and
do this kind of uh predictive analysis.
So interestingly enough a lot of these
airports are in countries which have
already been identified as high IWT
activities. is just some airports
essentially don't have good uh
inspections. So I beauty activity has
not been reported there although it's
likely to be occurring and other
countries like the US uh is not on the
naughty list but because the US makes
the naughty list so somehow it doesn't
appear on its own list of countries that
participate in IWT although it's
actually a known fact in the community
that there is a supply uh draw from from
uh from our own country um and so I'm
not going to say about research but I
wanted to briefly mention If anybody's
interesting, we have related to this
like a very large scale ongoing project
that I'm super excited about called
Operation Pengalin which is uh uh funded
by the Paul Allen Family Foundation
which is a multi-disciplinary
multi-prong approach of trying to
understand wildlife trafficking kind of
um grounded in pengalin wildlife
trafficking. Pengalins are the most
trafficked animal in the world. In the
last decade there's been uh uh estimated
more than 1 million pengalins as as
being uh trafficked and and uh demand is
increasing. And so this is a a
collaboration between uh technology
developers like our collaborators for
from Ariada who developed new uh biom
monitoring sensors like new camera traps
etc. uh ecologist and um uh conservation
criminologist, socioeconomic experts and
uh um conservation institutions such as
ZSL and and AI expertise. And what we
are hoping to do is by bringing all of
our disciplines together, understand
where the penglins are, their ecology,
um how are they being poached and
trafficked and what are like kind of the
local communities attitude and
alternative livelihoods and how we can
facilitate uh better understanding but
also better intervention in uh reducing
illegal wildlife trade of penguins. So
this is like an ongoing project um where
we're hoping to make a real impact on
the ground but also learn about and
create a framework of how to approach
IWT research from this
multid-disciplinary approach because a
lot of these things are usually done in
verticals. There's a lot of ecology and
biom monitoring studies. There's a lot
of soio economic studies. there's a lot
of like kind of just criminology and
actually we really want to identify the
data fusion and kind of data synergy and
analysis synergy opportunities across
disciplines to to achieve something
bigger than the the sum of the
parts. Um and so as a as a conclusion I
guess on the IWT part really want to
emphasize again it's a huge problem that
is I think not as broadly understood as
like let's say biodiversity and climate
change is um but illegal wildlife trade
is a huge industry um and uh
understanding and preventing it not only
helps biodiversity but also uh a lot of
other sustainable development uh factors
such as biological invasion, exonic
diseases, other serious as crime and um
ecoturism and other sustainable
development investments. And here AI and
O can help us as I showed examples of
predict using predictive models but we
also can think about uh decision uh
things like about where should we uh be
um for example monitoring where should
we be uh having more deterrence such as
inspections on uh on airports etc. So
both a predictive ML models and O models
can help uh this fight. I don't know how
I'm doing on time. Guess I have another
15 minutes.
Yeah, I think um we started pretty late.
Yeah,
but a little over.
So I've given you an example of like how
AI and um can help um um public health
and here and how AI can be used to
inform conser biodiversity conservation
efforts. Uh this is like a full array of
the different um application areas that
I feel passionate about. Um the next one
I want to talk about is an example of uh
the the kind of research that can inform
disaster resilience. Again, within
disaster resilience, uh my group has
worked on um things like optimizing
prescribed burn to minimize wildfire
risks, modeling human migration under
sea level rise, and uh some of the work
I'm going to uh share with you today, uh
disaster mitigation planning for
infrastructure resilience. So, we've
looked at road uh fortification against
flooding as well as um water
infrastructure uh uh fortification
against earthquakes. So in particular
critical infrastructure systems as you
know are very vulnerable to natural
disasters.
Um unclear what is happening.
No just decided to go to sleep for 30
seconds.
Um and um they uh they obviously have uh
service disruptions which uh which
impact disaster response. Uh they have
uh uh impact on uh long-term and
medium-term recovery as well as uh
economic impacts in terms of cost of
repairs and loss of productivity. And
you know uh disaster response um is
obviously very important but ideally we
want to take actions before disaster
strikes like what can we do ahead of
time in order to minimize the possible
impact uh when inevitably there's like a
hurricane or an earthquake etc. So I am
really a a very strong kind of
passionate proponent on proactive
investments in in in uh uh resilience
efforts such as uh disaster mitigation.
And so um I actually um purposefully
tried to connect to Los Angeles uh
agencies in order to understand what can
I do to help them make LA more
resilient. And um Los Angeles was uh
actually at the forefront um well some
six seven years ago where they actually
have like a very sophisticated ambitious
resilient plans. It was one of the 100
resilient cities initiative if you
remember. Um and so they actually put a
lot of thought into what can be done and
one of the goals uh that was identified
since Los Angeles is exposed to many
earthquakes uh is to really try to think
about how can we fortify our water
network in order to um minimize uh
negative impacts in the event of a
disaster. So they committed to this um
kind of initiative called seismic
seismic resilient pipe network where LA
was going to uh fortify part of the
water infrastructure with like special
pipes that are less likely to break
during the earthquake in order to make
sure that critical customers like
hospitals and evacuation centers and uh
you know fire stations actually have
water uh after uh or during the disaster
in order to facilitate response.
But okay, this plan was there. Now how
do you actually do it? And so one of
their chief engineers uh back in 2017 17
who was kind of the mastermind behind
this uh resilience goal really
identified the fact that the proper
layout of this investment fortification
has to allow the network to be resilient
in a cost-effective way. But but
actually um this is like a very complex
specially explicit network design
problem that they didn't have the right
tools to do. So the two of us connected
in around 2018. We're like I was like
well this is the kind of stuff I know
how to do combinatory optimization
network design. The their plan was to
basically put engineers uh to be
responsible for 2x two mile pieces of
the city. Each engineer looks at the 2
by two mile piece, decides what to be
upgraded and then moves on to the other
one and then they stitch it all
together. Now when you're thinking about
resilience, making localized decision on
2x two mile and then stitching them all
together is doomed not to be resilient.
But they don't didn't have the
computational tools to be thinking about
anything larger scale than 2x2 miles. So
we basically work closely with them to
understand what are the uh constraints,
what are the objective. and how to model
this problem mathematically in a way
that can scale up. And LA is
particularly difficult because it's like
I think the
largest single service area across um
across the country. It's like 473 square
miles, 4 million resident with a high
hazard percentage like 30% of customers
and pipes are actually exposed to
earthquake risk. So you have a large
portion of the of the network that
potentially you can choose to upgrade.
So these are still like many many pipes
but you have only limited budget to do
them. So here is the formalization of
the the network uh fortification problem
that we were able to to formalize. So
what you're uh uh you what you need to
do is given a water network and seismic
risk maps that basically identify some
of the pipes that could be exposed to
earthquake breakage. You want to select
a subset of these pipes such that all
critical customers which are nodes in
this network must be directly connected
to this fortified network consisting of
either upgraded pipes or pipes that at
zero risk of uh of uh breakage while at
the same time providing overall coverage
such that every resident so every parcel
within the city is within one mile of
that backbone fortified network. one
wild mile. This is basically they want
to make sure that in event of a of an
earthquake uh a fire hose can be
connected to a functioning water
provision and and reach like a a
building that might be on fire due to
the earthquake effects. Right? So we
have this kind of a um a complex problem
very large network with both uh this uh
critical customer constraints as well as
the coverage
constraint. So the data basically we had
a a a non-disclosure agreement with LWP.
They actually gave us the real water
infrastructure network their critical
customers. We got GS information from
USGS on the earthquake hazards and um we
basically created this uh um this this
optimization problem. So what does the
optimization problem look like? We
basically have this network in which
edges are the pipes. The nodes are
basically the connections between the
the different pipes and we have the cost
of choosing any edge or every any pipe
to be upgraded. And that cost depends on
uh how long the pipe is, what's the
diameter like how much material it has
and other things like how difficult it
is to dig it out, how old it is etc. So
they had a way of determining this cost.
Sorry, we have uh a set of nodes that
are the water sources. Uh the set of
critical customers that we want to make
sure that we reach and then this
coverage constraints which basically for
every residential area say okay at least
one of the pipes within one mile radius
better be part of that fortified
network. Um and we are hoping to find
basically the minimum cost solution that
satisfies all of these resilience
constraints. Um and so this becomes this
complex Steiner network problem with
coverage constraints. So Steiner network
problems are are wellstudied but here we
have this additional coverage constraint
which makes the problem even harder. So
we had to obviously uh try to figure out
how to model it and and how to solve
these problems. I'm going to skip in the
interests of time but part of this is in
order to get to something that is
actually you can put it in an
optimization solver. We also had to
think about how to contract uh the the
network representation. For example,
large portions of the network are not at
risk. So they become like a hyper node
that then gets shrunk. And so all of
pre-processing techniques in order to to
make the optimization models um uh
solvable well solvable still in a matter
of many many hours. Um so um we
developed this uh this model and and the
techniques to solve it and we were able
to provide solutions to them which were
uh according to our estimate
estimation between six to 23% uh most
cost effective than like something that
would look like more like the stitching
that they were planning to do. And you
know with some
smart backend uh pre-processing and
post-processing optimization we were
able to to make this um scalable enough
for us to be able to uh to address this
problem. Yet these problems are really
really hard to solve. I don't want to
underestimate this especially as you
want to increase the uh the uh the size.
So in the beginning we were like okay we
can promise you that you can do at most
like a service zone. So there's like um
I think about like 300 service zones
across the LA. So it's divided into sub
areas. Then we're like you know what we
actually can do it f uh better. We can
do like a district size. And then by the
end we were actually able to solve
really large portions of at once which
means the bigger the spatial extent that
you plan for the more cost effective
solution you find. Right. So because
you're actually seeing the the bigger
context of the decisions. Yes. So this
formulation doesn't allow for what we
call these non network solutions. In
other words, to have a lot of physically
small resources and locations, you know,
small uh
households or you know neighborhoods and
so forth. It just sort of brute force is
the solution of the green of it all. So
um I'm not sure I understand. Can you
repeat the question? You know there is a
lot of internet of things. You know you
can put a little water well in your
neighborhood rather than build a big Oh
yeah. Yeah. Like in a sense this is I
think this is not a traditional way of
optimizing degree in the centralized
way. Yes. Yeah. So this doesn't take
into account other interventions. So
here the only intervention we are
modeling is that we are fortifying the
existing uh water like centralized
lifeline infrastructure. There could be
an alternative or additional
intervention which could be like I put
local water sources that will provide
power in power infrastructure in
particular that's a huge area for us you
know that we can we can do a lot of
distributed energy resources solar and
this and that rather than just build a
network I think it's a huge question
about the tradeoffs
in water in water what is the tradeoffs
but I we I haven't looked at it but this
is very insightful comment because
obviously some there would be like some
uh parallel parallel interventions and
infrastructure choices that one can make
that are not just upgrading that hasn't
been considered. I guess we were mostly
following their lead in terms of what
they were thinking and and and and and
you know helping them solve the problem
that they had identified but even just
from like a water infrastructure like
civil engineering perspective they could
think of additional things that they
want to model explicitly um yeah
especially thinking that you you know
from an optimization perspective once
you have the basic model actually adding
these extra choices it's not that hard
that's the beauty of like you know using
something like mint integer programming
models where like adding side
constraints is not you know it's pretty
easy as opposed to like a custom
solution but it's more like gaming it's
more than just centraliz
you know so it's a very different
problem and I think you made a comment
that if you do bottom up you're going to
be losing that is with new technologies
I'm not convinced that that's really the
answer
Well, I think this is a different
aspect. I think you can have local
interventions like for example putting
uh
community you know systems or something
like that. You could still plan for
those things at a at a at a global level
like as you know as the LWP as it says
as the caretaker of this can still plan
the allocation of those community
resources not
necessarily otherwise you would have to
like simulate individual commu like
neighborhood choices to do that or not.
Yeah that's more like an emergent
emergent resilience. I agree.
Um and obviously like you can uh go
beyond just the optimum solution. You
can be thinking about additional metrics
in terms of like uh you know who is
affected and how much if you cannot
you're not able to cover all of the
critical customers and just counting for
example like some resilience metric
without looking at the spatial
distribution of benefits uh might be
problematic as well. So there's like
additional variance that one can think
of. I saw another question was just
actually related to this. I was going to
ask if there was a prediction step to
this or if the risk types or portions of
the network were deterministic and like
in in this analysis there were like
basically we're using the USGS hazard
layers but obviously one can think about
like okay this hazard layers are some
kind of aggregate of a portfolio of
possible you know earthquake scenarios
you could explicitly think about in like
a portfolio of scenarios opposed to one
aggregate layer or you could even think
about like predictions and so on. Um,
and these are all like fair game for
more sophisticated, more detailed
analysis of this decision-m. I
agree. Um, and so this I guess through
this foray of applications, I'm giving
you several examples that I hope have
illustrated how both machine learning
and operations research uh approaches
have an immense role to play in
addressing some uh of this pressing
societal problems. And there's a large
scope of of uh uh of things to do
especially when you work closely with
with um you know NOS's and local
agencies to understand the problems and
and uh and objectives and constraints
they need to face and identify like fit
for purpose solutions. I'm a very big
believer about like really grounding uh
this um uh applications in in real
partnerships. It's a two-way street. we
can provide uh useful models and and
algorithms and solutions to them. But
often they identify really important
challenges to our field, the algorithmic
field that push us to try to innovate
and and and then therefore enriches our
own discipline. And I don't know, it
seems like I'm not going to have time,
but I was going to tell you like on the
method side what this has meant for me
is like basically a lot of these
optimization problems that arise in
solving infrastructure resilience
problems so on are really hard to solve.
their large case scale and current
solvers for these mathematical problems
really do not cannot scale and solve
them. So then this pushed this um agenda
about how can we scale up uh discrete
optimization solvers to uh this more
realistic real world problems which made
me work on the integration of machine
learning and optimization from a methods
perspective. speeding up algorithms for
solving uh mixed integer optimization
problems by using machine learning
inside the algorithmic uh approaches
themselves where we're learning
automatically from the behavior of the
solver new huristics and algorithmic
design principles that then uh allow us
to solve this uh problems faster or find
better solution in quicker time. So, so
I have this whole other talk that I can
talk about how we combine. So, I've show
you examples of individual machine
learning and optimization for this
applicationdriven research. But when we
combine machine learning and
optimization to actually uh solve uh
these real world problems, it's a really
really exciting methodological area that
um uh I um I'm very passionate about.
And so if you're curious, ask me after
the talk because I'm not gonna have time
to to talk about it. But thank you so
much.