so I'd like to welcome everyone to a new
installment of MIT startup exchange demo
day my name is arat n rodenstein program
manager with startup exchange and on
behalf of my colleagues joining from
startup exchange and ILP thank you for
joining wherever you may be today it's a
rainy day in Cambridge perfect for this
demo day so you'll hear shortly from
Seven exciting startups all members of
startup exchange but first I'll give a
brief overview of our program
so MIT startup exchange was created
about close to 10 years ago now um to
support MIT connected startups as they
grow expand and solve some of the
world's greatest challenges and we do
this by fostering Partnerships and
collaboration with industry mostly
industrial yon um program or ILP members
represented by many of you joining us
today and also the MIT Innovation
ecosystem and
Beyond the UPS in our program are
founded um by MIT faculty staff or Al Al
alumni or also based on licensed
technology and they can also be vetted
by some of our MIT Partners including
the engine Ventures the e14 fund cell or
MIT Nano just to name a
few the startups in our program are
close to a thousand and they don't
usually a pilot stage or Beyond and they
cover all sectors and all geographies
and here you can see some of the
trending Technologies of the startups
and I've highlighted in bold the ones
that uh will be represented by the
startups presenting to you today of
course we start with AI and ml big data
and analytics AR and VR we also have
sustainability Robotics and autonomy and
life science and health
care when it comes to Value startups in
our program have exposure to a Global
Network of Industry decision makers and
corporates have access to vetted MIT
connected startups
we also have events which are an
important component we host a variety of
them throughout the year locally
nationally internationally and some
consist of conferences where there's
startup lining talks and Exhibits also
demo days like today other types of
webinars workshops trainings one-on-one
meetings and much more so the benefit to
you as an ILP member is that we can
tailor an event according to your needs
and the benefit to the startups is that
we can take you to other markets that
you're expanding into and you have this
ibility into new
ecosystems we also launch calls for
startups we call these opportunities and
they're based on corporates priorities
and internal challenges and so the
startups in our program can apply
through the website our website and if
selected they can work with you as an
ILP member and help you solve a problem
that you may be facing in your industry
so all in all this is a customized and
curated approach and I hope that
everyone is taking uh advantage of these
benefits and of course let us know any
questions and so what is demod day it's
a virtual Forum usually a couple of uh
every couple of months that we host to
facilitate introductions between the
startups and Industry and this is to
explore potential collaborations and
Partnerships sooner rather than later we
also hosted a live demo day in Silicon
Valley in June of last year so please be
in the lookout for more of these demo
days for next year and you can check out
the ILP and startup exchange websites
for that but I'd like to invite you to
the next one that will be virtual which
is on February
27th and the format today will consist
of seven startups presenting for four
minutes with two minutes of Q&A each and
then we'll jump right into breakout
rooms for the Q&A please post questions
to the Q&A tab that you have on your
screen and indicate which startup it's
for and then later on you'll be able to
also engage with the startups via the
chat we want to keep this very Dynamic
and interactive um as much as possible
and as always let us know if you need
help connecting with the startups so
before turning it over to the
entrepreneurs I'd like to um just uh
provide a couple of reminders one the
start of presentations are being
recorded and two you'll see a brief
pop-up survey at the end of the event if
you could please share your feedback and
uh help us keep improving these demo
days so with that thank you again for
joining wherever ever you may be today