My name is Sofia.
And, I am a lawyer in background
and training, which kind of
means that MIT
is not exactly the place where
you would expect
a lawyer to find herself.
I got the opportunity to join Cleantech for Europe,
a policy coalition
representing Europe's foremost climate tech
innovators and climate tech investors
towards European policymakers.
I had the opportunity
to co-draft a report on how Europe
can win the climate tech race
without subsidies
and called for a European
cleantech investment plan,
which was one of the main reasons
that I kind of understood
I needed to complement
my policy skills with business skills.
It was important that not only I do this MBA,
but the MBA has a very
strong focus on climate,
but also the university is very
committed to the fight
against climate change.
I really feel deeply connected
to the wider MIT community.
This is exactly why I was able to be a part
of the organizing committee of the
MIT Energy Conference for 2025.
This year, we're focusing
on scaling climate tech innovation.
For the world to reach net-zero emissions,
we really need a lot of technologies
to work
together.
We don't
necessarily need only one technology.
We need all these technologies to work.
This year’s topic
exactly represents what MIT is good at and
what MIT is
giving out to the world.
Which is this innovation
that we need to reach our climate goals.
Many of my role models
had run the conference before, particularly
the person who founded the project,
the MIT Energy Conference,
David Danielson.
As part of the conference,
we are continuing this legacy,
created by people who
are leading the climate charge.