Welcome to Nanosummit 2025. Uh my name
is Vladimir Bulovich. I have a privilege
to work at MIT Nano and I'm just
absolutely thrilled uh to see room
filled with students, faculty,
researchers, our corporate partners,
other entrepreneurs. I mean, this is an
incredible opportunity for us to tell
you of the multitudes of ways MIT Nano
is changing the way we think about the
future and what it's going to deliver.
Indeed, your presence is shows the
uniqueness of the community that MIT
Nano is built to serve. And hence, I'm
absolutely overjoyed to show you
throughout the day various ways MIT Nano
indeed intends to change the world
through your work and the opportunities
that you'll bring for everyone.
2025 marks the seventh year of MIT Nano.
When MIT first imagined building MIT
Nano, the goal was not just to create
new labs or acquire the best tools and
instruments. Uh the vision was much
bigger. It was to create a way a
catalyst for discovery. A place where
ideas and disciplines meet, where
conversations happen across the fields,
and where discoveries at the smallest
scale can grow into solutions with
global impact.
When MIT Nano opened in uh 2018, it
represented a bold investment in the
future of science and engineering at
MIT. Uh since then, the facility has
matured into a thriving community of
users.
The uh at this point uh we have over
1,500
annual users at MIT Nano Drone from over
300 different PI labs across the campus
and beyond.
You know what anchors us is not just the
plus tools but the people who use them
teach with them and push the instruments
to reveal the next great breakthroughs.
I often say MIT's two most important
deliveries to the world are our
knowledge and our people.
At MIT Nano both those circulate freely.
Students, faculty, and researchers
exchange insights, test ideas, and build
on each other's work in hopes of leaving
this place and the world better than
when they arrived. And last seven years
tell us that they keep continually
succeeding.
At MIT Nano, curiosity meets the
capability. Experiments generate
knowledge, expand understanding, and
provide the foundation for innovations
that have an impact across all different
disciplines. We have over 50 different
departments, labs, and centers that
utilize the MIT Nano. We were hoping for
that when we started. The fact that we
can now count it and actually recognize
the delivery of it indeed is
overwhelming.
Roughly 21% of MIT faculty touch MIT
Nano to get their work done. In seven
years of existence, that's quite a
growth. Annually, we keep adding about
20% of the user base. And so at some
point, couple of years from now, we'll
be talking about 2,000 users and not
just from MIT. About 20% of them come
from the external world that needs our
tools to make their discoveries happen.
We are a community, a community centered
at MIT, but the one that is here to
benefit the region and the nation.
Within MIT Nano, there are facilities
that open different windows into
innovation. Fab.no
gives researchers the ability to
fabricate um at the smallest scale,
transforming bold concepts into tangible
structures. Characterization.no
lets us look at materials with
extraordinary precision, revealing
properties that guide new breakthroughs.
And the immersion lab uh offers an
entirely different perspective, one
where technology and human experience
intersect, expanding how discoveries can
be applied in the world.
our programs. Well, we have many of
them. Here are just three to mention.
MIT Nano has created pathways that carry
knowledge and creativity beyond the lab.
For example, in star.no, uh we support
high-tech entrepreneurs as they take the
first step toward building companies
that can scale. And if you're here
yesterday afternoon, we held our very
first pitch.no Nano competition where a
dozen startups dazzled those who
participated.
Lifting up actually the exposition of
what is it to present new science and
technology.
Studio Nano fosters new ways of
communicating ideas helping researchers
connect with wider audiences. Our
collaboration with technological demon
builds bridges across borders
strengthening global networks of talent
and innovation. And so each of these
programs really extends our reach. We
have a well functioning facility. We
have an opportunity to within that
facility to bring tremendous number of
brilliant people. Next thing we need to
do is beyond the tools offer them ways
to engage through these programs.
The same spirit of bold collaboration
and curiosity shaped the sessions you're
going to hear today. We designed the
program you're going to experience today
to reflect some of MIT's strategic
priorities as outlined by our president
of MIT, Syornbluth.
The challenges the institute has
identified as most urgent for humanity
are the areas with nanocience has the
powerful role to play. After all, the
world is built from atoms up and we know
how to make every one of them exactly
where it needs to be.
You'll hear sessions on health and life
sciences to start us off. Nano provides
the tools, sensors, interfaces, and
delivery systems to transform how we
diagnose, treat, and even prevent new
types of diseases.
Manufacturing. Well, breakthroughs only
matter if we can scale them. So the
session will explore how breakthroughs
in nano can translate into real world
products and reliable systems that can
change entire industries on climate and
sustainability. Well, from clean energy
to carbon capture to resilient
infrastructure, nanoscale materials and
devices are central to our response to
the climate crisis.
We then follow these three sessions with
student talks and our researcher talks.
talks so-called picot talks from inside
the lab led by the people who guide the
students through the lab Anna Osherov
and York Scholvin
in celebration of MIT's culture of
discovery in education this session
highlights some early stage ideas and
researchers whose perspectives are
essential to shaping that future.
We will close this afternoon uh with a
session uh led by president emeritus
Rafael Refe who will tell us about
visionaries of nanocience and
nanotechnology that got us to today.
These are people whose creativity,
leadership and persistence have built
the foundation on which we all stand on
today.
Recognizing them is a reminder that
progress depends not just on tools or
facilities but on human imagination and
willingness to pursue bold ideas. As a
matter of fact, beyond the session of
celebrating the luminaries of time past,
we are going to name a space in MIT nano
after one of those luminaries. Please
make sure you attend the session and
you'll find out a lot more and then
we'll celebrate at MIT Nano.
So, as you move through the day, I
invite you to think big and stay
curious. And any questions that make you
want to ask speakers, please uh make
sure you ask them. Share a problem you
can't yet solve and see who in the room
lights up at the same thought.
Some of the most important discoveries
emerge when someone with one set of
expertise brings a different perspective
to another. That human friction leads to
innovation. Let's make sure today we
have plenty of it as we challenge each
other and inspire each other with new
ways of thinking.
MIT Nano is proof that when people from
different discipline share tools, spaces
and ideas, they discover new pathways
forward. We are a facility where talent
and knowledge meet opportunity, where a
sketch on a whiteboard can become a
measurement, a prototype, and eventually
a solution that impacts all of us.
So, thank you for being here today, for
contributing your ideas and for helping
us imagine and build the future
together.
I now have a distinct honor and a
privilege. One, to open the 2025 Nano
Summit and two, to welcome on the stage
our MIT president and remarkable leader,
Sel Cornbluth.
Well, thanks so much Vladimir uh for the
introduction and for your outstanding
leadership of making MIT Nano such a
vital part of the institute landscape. I
mean the physical landscape of course
200,000 square feet that allows for
impressive talent but also your huge
contributions to the landscape here of
ideas and exploration that really helps
make MIT MIT. So MIT Nano obviously
started before my time at MIT, but I
know that it was designed to be a
fantastic toolbox for this community or
as Vladimir describes it, a gathering
space that doesn't do all but enables
all. Now, for my part, I can't tell you
how excited I am that MIT Nano is
essential to making progress to high
priority areas where I believe that MIT
has a responsibility to lead. areas
where if we harness our collective
efforts, we can make a serious positive
impact. First, it's pretty fantastic.
Just as we're renewing our focus on
helping the nation regain strength in
manufacturing, MIT Nano is helping us
expand our industry partnerships,
explore pioneering approaches, and
importantly train our students in
everything from fabrication,
computational modeling, 3D printing, and
how to work successfully as part of a
team. And it's especially exciting that
MIT Nano is imagining new fields that
will shape the future of manufacturing
and helping young companies advance the
most promising technologies and then
develop them to scale. Now, with MIT
Heels launched last year, I'm focused on
bringing MIT experts and leaders in
biotech, pharma, and hospitals together,
making sure that they have the resources
and the infrastructure they need to
accelerate health care for patients
around the world. And they collaborate
on new knowledge, new tools, new cures.
And MIT Nano allows them a place to work
on diagnostics and therapeutics that
range from lipid nanop particles to
wearable sensors to a pill that releases
bacteria into the GI tract to treat and
diagnose disease and from human health
to the health of the planet. I'm sure
you know that MIT has begun an ambitious
push to accelerate climate solutions and
despite strong headwinds and reductions
in federal support, we are continuing
that work. The intersection of climate
and nanotechnology is sparking all kinds
of ideas like new and improved materials
that produce fewer emissions and remove
pollutants from the air and nanopores
that monitor environmental conditions in
the air, water, and soil. and new
methods of capturing carbon dioxide and
then turning that into useful products
and even plants that can store that can
turn their own stored chemical energy
into visible light for human use. This
almost sounds like science fiction, but
it's incredible. And all of this is just
scratching the surface of the nano
enabled research in manufacturing, in
climate, in life sciences and health
happening all across MIT along with
innovation in other key areas from AI to
quantum. And you're going to be hearing
a lot more about quantum uh at MIT in
the coming year. MIT Nano has truly set
itself apart in the institute's
signature way with an emphasis on
crossdisciplinary collaboration and open
access welcoming anyone who requires
nano tools to make things and then scale
up the things they make and you know as
Vlad showed the number of users is just
continuing to increase and here's
something I find truly heartening for
all of us who value science both
fundamental and applied even with the
advance nano tools. We now have
literally at our fingertips. We're still
acting on the same human instinct, the
same curiosity we have, the drive to
make things, to understand how they work
and how to make them work for us in new
and exciting ways. Now, I know you want
to hear from all the amazing speakers,
but before I go, let me tell you one
more thing about MIT MIT Nano that's
music to my ears, and Vladimir mentioned
it. This is really a fantastic training
ground for our students. Now, 40% or so
of students, even more actually, major
in computer science, but I've been told
by a reliable authority that when
students have the opportunity to work at
nanocale early in their MIT careers, a
significant number actually consider
majoring in something else. Now, I'm
not, you know,
I am not dissing course six, believe me.
Um but it's no surprise that MIT
students who spend so much time in their
lives interacting with digital system
often find making things using nano
tools deeply deeply satisfying. It's a
reason that so many MIT students are
drawn here in the first place. A love of
making things that matter and an impulse
to seek seek out the company of other
people who share that passion. Now today
you're going to hear from all kinds of
makers, faculty and researchers,
students and postocs, entrepreneurs and
industry leaders about the
transformative impact of nanocience and
nanotechnology and how working with the
very small can help us do big things for
the world together. Now finally I'll say
one thing. So, I have this uh I have two
dogs and I have this little dog called
Pico. And I was very I was very uh
appreciative to get a 10 to the minus12
t-shirt because they uh but but had I
known I was coming to MIT, I would have
named him Nano. So,
anyway, I want to thank you uh for being
here and I hope you all enjoy the day.