One of my favorites, this was my first
result in this field is the folding cut
problem. You start with a rectangle of
paper and you fold it flat. I'm not
going to make a lot of cuts. I'm just
going to make one complete straight cut.
In this case, I get a little swan. And
general theorem is you can make any
polygon you want. In fact, you can make
one cut and make any collection of
polygons you want. So, like on my
website, you can make the MIT logo with
all the little rectangles with one
complete straight cut and the the
outside shape will have holes exactly
where you want them. And uh you can
download this too if you want to impress
all your friends. Especially recommended
for like kids. Um it's a good good magic
trick. In fact, Harry Houdini used to do
this trick in the 20s before he was an
escape artist. He did general magic. Not
this trick. He made stars and we thought
about it and we proved you can make
anything. For more MIT moments from MIT
Open Learning, like, subscribe, or