My name is Charlesson Ricle. I'm the CEO
and one of the co-founders of Amplified
Industries. Um, so obviously AI is all
the rage pretty much in every uh
vertical right now. But one of the thing
which is interesting is traditionally it
has less success in heavy industrial use
cases. And one of the main one of the
big reasons for that is it's been
difficult uh it's been difficult to
collect high resolution good quality
data for those kind of applications. And
especially if you start looking at
remote operation, the legacy status quo
has typically been relying on scala link
which effectively means that you have
hundreds of pieces of equipments that
have to share um one effectively dialed
connection. What's exciting is there's a
big revolution happening in the field of
remote connectivity where through both
5G rollout and satellite alternatives
high resol high speeded uh internet
connection is becoming ubiquitous if not
today in the next couple years and so
our job at amplified is to take
advantage of this fact to build the
backend infrastructure of the future for
industrial application so that goes from
build developing our own IoT solutions
that are able to record, compress data,
send it through those different
modalities to our cloud system. They're
dual kind of AI processing and then
makes both like uh insights available to
our customers for our system and also
connect back to legacy historian systems
to provide them with the type of data
they can ingest and so what's
interesting is we can do that at about a
million time more data higher resolution
that legacy system for onetenth of the
cost. Our primary application today is
in oil and gas. So we've built
effectively an ecosystem of IoT devices
that have to be extremely rugged. So
talking about 10 year plus battery life
uh like deployed in harsh outdoors uh
climates have to be very simple to be to
be installed and use so that field
technician can deal with them and at the
same time being able to do do this uh
recording of data across a wide variety
of signals uh and send this at very high
resolution. And once this hits our
cloud, this is where interesting things
starts happening where we take in this
very high resolution data and we distill
it uh into both looking for operational
issues and we we leverage it to control
the equipment to make sure that it's
always operating in an optimal fashion.
So in the context of an oil and gas
operator, the benefits look like an
increased production, reduce drastic
reduction in operating cost through
minimized equipment failures, reduced
electricity consumption and also
virtually elimination of spills which
obviously is a major environmental
concern in this industry. So this is a
little video of an installation of one
of our systems by one of our technician
to give you uh to give you a sense uh
with using legacy equipment. Uh go
retrofitting a unit would take probably
a day worth of work for a crew and cost
between 15 and $20,000. We're able to
get it done in under 15 minutes for
120th of this cost. And so we are we are
growing pretty fast. We went commercial
uh in late 2021. Uh today we have more
than 2,000 devices uh installed in the
2,000 assets for other instruments in
the US. And a typical customer journey
would be what what I've put in here with
this private equity back operator that
started a pilot on three wells with us a
year ago and is now rolling out to his
entire production with already 200 wells
uh under our management. And in terms of
ask so there are primarily of two kinds.
Uh on the one end we're always
interesting starting new pilots
obviously in the oil and gas industry
but they're also interesting to look at
other verticals with remote uh
industrial assets. So think mining uh
industrial waters this type of
applications and on the other hand uh
very interested in having conversation
with people designing both industrial
equipment uh oil field service companies
and industrial software. I appreciate uh
appreciate your time and I'm very happy
to take any question.