Now there's a third example which is
quite interesting which is sometimes
cartels can operate in the open and get
away with it. Let's talk about the
National Football League. The NFL. The
NFL is the most important football
organization in America. The most
profitable important football
organization in America. Football's the
most profitable uh sport in the country.
Advertising is incredibly valuable
during football games. increasingly so
because now we all watch it's the one
place in the world you don't stream. So
we stream everything we watch now. So we
don't have ads. You can't stream sports.
So sports advertising has gone through
the roof because advertising in other
contexts is less valuable. Used to be
you could advertise everywhere. Now you
can't. It's really just sports at the
last place people watch ads. This is
incredibly valuable. Now the NFL is 32
teams essentially 32 businesses
competing in a literal sense with each
other.
So this and there's a huge incentive to
collude.
Let's take the New York Giants and the
New York Jets and you know the New
Jersey Giant New York Jets, but it's the
same same market.
Let's say that they both Let's say the
TV station says the major TV station
says, "Look, we're going to broadcast
whichever team gives us the better
deal." Well, the Giants and Jets will
have to compete with each other. Give
the TV station a better deal. But let's
say they look we'll agree not to do
that. We'll just tell the TV station
this is our price. It's two mill you
know basically instead of a billion
dollars it'll be $2 billion. We each
have $2 billion. Either take it or leave
it and TV station end up broadcasting
both or maybe one TV station takes one
another TV station takes another.
And more generally what the NFL does is
they only sell the TV rights for the
league. They don't sell TV rights for
individual teams. So, individual teams
do not sell their TV rights, which
should lead to competition. The league
just sells the TV rights, which causes a
cartel.
Essentially, they're saying, "If you
want to broadcast football, you got to
come to us, and we're only going to
we're going to charge a super high
price." As a result, quite frankly,
watching football is a bit of a pain in
the ass at this point. So, you've got
network TV, which if the local team is
on, you can only watch the local team.
Otherwise, there may be one other game
on.
You've got Sunday Night Football, which
is on network TV. You've got Thursday
Night Football, which I think is on
Amazon or ESPN. Amazon. Thursday night.
Who's got Thursday Night Football?
>> A Amazon. You've got Sunday morning
football from London, which is ESPN
Plus.
Then you can do what I did and pony up
$350 to buy Sunday Ticket. If you like
an out of town team and want to watch
your team, which let you watch any game
you want on Sunday, except the Sunday
morning games where you still have to
buy ESPN Plus. as I learned much to my
chagrin. So, it's incredibly expensive
to watch football. If you want to see
all the football games, it costs you a
pretty penny. Why? Because the league
has colluded and set up a structure
where basically firms can't undercut
each other. Otherwise, firms would say,
"Look, a lot of people want my team. I'm
going to go strike a separate deal."
Indeed, in 1957,
the Supreme Court 1957, even before I
was born, that's how long ago it was,
the Supreme Court ruled that this was
anti-competitive and they couldn't do
it.
They did. Yet, it's still done. And the
NFL will make $40 billion this year off
their collusive cartel.
Why?
Because Congress stepped in. and said,
'Well, we're going to grant them an
antitrust exemption. We're going to say
football is such of a national important
priority that we're going to actually
exempt football from our nation's
antitrust laws. So, I said last time in
my previous lecture, I'd proved to you
that Congress cares more about football
than economics.
Okay? They cared more about the football
league than actually making football
affordable for us to watch. So by
granting them an antitrust exemption,
they allowed them to collude and have
this one league that makes it incredibly
expensive to watch football.