Um I'm very interested to know uh your
experiences from last class. Um what
your thoughts were on the NETP
discussion and the small groupoup
conversations that you have. Did anybody
did anybody find themselves in
conversations that were of interest?
I think my group like it was a lot of
discussion on how like they themselves
are like trying to bring about these new
innovations. Um but a lot of this like
teacher lashback and like some people
are having a really hard time like
moving forwards and then like some
people are doing a good job because it's
all them agreeing that like they need to
get those who are proactive about it
like all together. Um, I also thought it
was interesting like I kind of proposed
a question to the group about like how
they see like all of these ideologies
like playing a part um in higher
education. Um, a lot of the times like
specifically the research that you guys
do is kind of focus on K through 12.
Yeah. But like how can this really be
implemented in colleges and especially
like at a university like MIT where you
have professors being hired not because
they're good teachers but because
they're experts in the field. Um, and I
think that it just kind of like prompted
an interesting discussion about um, like
where schools need to prioritize like
whether they're research institutions or
like educational facilities.
Cool. Other folks, what else did you end
up talking about um, with your ed new
education school colleagues or what else
was interesting to you about the
national education tech plan discussion
or anything else?
Ty and then Omar. Yeah, it was
interesting. Omar and I were in the same
group.
So, let's see if this overlaps, but
uh there wasn't a ton of conversation in
our group, but they did they did ask me
about my time as like a software
engineer and how we thought about like
iteration and in the software
development space and how then they
tried to start making parallels to how
they try to implement it in their own
schools. and we talked a little bit
about some of the differences and where
things might be more complex or harder.
Um, so that was like an interesting
conversation to try to take my
experience and reapply it. That's cool.
That's great.
Yeah. So again, there wasn't that much
discussion. You kind of went over what I
was going to say. So I guess I'll touch
on I'll touch on the the first part of
the session like the big uh
conversation. I was reading the chat and
it was pretty cool to see like everybody
like commenting on everything and and
seeing like a bunch of examples and
seeing either frustrations or
revelations that they never realized.
Mhm. About like you know the message of
focusing on not the technology itself
but like what what we can do and then
how technology can help and what we're
trying to do first. Um and that
revelation for a lot of um these
professionals is pretty cool to see like
develop in the chat. Uhhuh. Yeah. Yeah.
You get to you get to watch human
development in real time people
encounter whether with I I didn't follow
it that closely because I was talking.
Um did uh were there frustrations that
any anything on the frustration side
that sort of stuck out to you or seemed
memorable? Not necessarily frustration,
but sort of like, oh, that's why like
this is happening or like why. Okay, now
this is starting to make sense. So, it's
sort of like where frustrations were
like cleared up, so to say. Great.
Good. Hi, Armon. You got to come up here
and hang out with me. That's what
happens when you get towards the end.
Yeah. Also, Also and I were in the same
group. We had a spicy one.
Yeah. So like a lot of the discussion
was about um like a lot of the people in
our group or like the people like
designing the structures that they were
trying to implement and something that
was interesting was this like repeated
like oh like we designed something we
send it to like the administration
they're like no that's not exactly what
we're looking for trying it and it's
just kind of like constantly trying to
get something that they're like okay
like I like this as opposed to
like them being able to
like effectively communicate the points
that they want included. This was very
interesting. Or part part of the way I
read our group is that we had some
people who were kind of middle level
leaders um and they were trying to
convince more senior leaders to make
change and the senior leaders were much
slower and less interesting in that
which happens in basically every kind of
institution. like when you go and visit
an institution, one way to think about
it is it is designed exactly to do what
it's doing right now. Um that like the
like it functions the way it functions
because there's some set of actors who
want it to function that way. Um often
those folks are sort of people with
power and control and you know it exists
the way it does because that's what they
want. And then new people come along,
new people live in that environment and
they're like, well, this could be better
and this could be better and this could
be better and this could be better. And
then more senior folks are like, ah, but
we like the way we've done it all the
time. And so it's not uncommon for
people coming out. You know, I think
really healthy organizations sort of
recognize like, oh, we need to be
constantly improving. And constantly
improving means like throwing away and
destroying things that I have built over
my career because that's the only way
you sort of get better. Um, but pretty
understandable that people wouldn't feel
that way. like I've spent my career
building this thing. Why don't we just
keep doing this thing? Um and so they
were sort of struggling with uh you know
and in an interesting place where lots
of people in lots of organizations find
themselves is like okay we need to do
something different but the people in
charge aren't really supportive like how
do we kind of do it anyway like how do
you know like where change comes from I
don't know maybe I mentioned this I I
can't remember I can't remember if I
mentioned this particular story but one
of the people that I worked with on some
of the content that's in Iterate is this
guy Peter Sen who's at the management
school at uh Sloan um And a neat thing
about working with him is he's done a
ton of stuff in education but lots of
stuff in many other sectors. Um and it
you know it comes up periodically like
man you know teachers like lots of
people in education just don't feel
empowered to make change. Um they feel
like look I got hired in this particular
role like I'm a I'm a math teacher. I'm
a history teacher. I'm a chemistry
professor. Like it's not my job to fix
the university. Um and Peter once said
something to me along the lines of
everyone in every industry feels that
way. Like they're like CEOs don't feel
like they're empowered to make change in
the institute. Nobody feels like they're
empowered to make change in
institutions, but change still happens
all the time because people who don't
necessarily feel empowered still take it
upon themselves to try new things, put
new things in the world. Um, and uh um I
don't know, it's it's it's a story I
really like to retell educators because
it's like this is not an education
specific problem. This is like a human
problem. Yeah. Um I thought what Lou
said from the University of Kentucky was
really fascinating because I'm actually
from Kentucky um and I worked at an
organiz organization with her before
called the Kentucky Student Voice team.
All right, cool. And the way that they
like impact change is by putting
students in like stakeholder positions.
So, um instead of like influencing
change through like ineffective ways
like administration, they put students
like at the forefront. So, she's like a
really big leader in like driving I
guess like educational change in
Kentucky. So, I thought it was cool.
That's great. Oh, I'm glad you had that
connection. That's fun. How did you how
you had So, she at the university ran
the sort of student voice thing that
like high school students across
Kentucky could participate in and stuff
or Yeah. So, it was born out of
something called the Pritchard
Committee, but now it's like an
independent organization. And the I
guess organization has like adults and
younger students as like co- peers. Like
they put them on like the same level,
the hierarchy to like work together to
um I guess craft a bunch of initiatives
to improve Kentucky schools. Yeah. Yeah.
I there's there all kinds of education
technology has tons of cool stuff like
that. um in part because lots of young
people can get interested and excited by
technology and so bringing them in into
leadership role, partnership roles. Um
cities had that too. Uh there's a group
in Boston called the high square task
force um which does all kinds of they
usually do more sort of like you know I
don't know community organizing kind of
like adversarial like why are you doing
this to us? Why are you doing this way?
They have a they have a whole campaign
they're doing right now against either
Shaws or Stop and Shop which is separate
from their education work. Um but
they've gone to a bunch of grocery
stores in neighborhoods around Boston
and bought the same thing in each store.
Um and basically found that in some you
know sort of minoritized poverty
impacted neighborhoods the grocery the
groceries are more expensive than they
are in Newton and Welsley or stuff like
that and they're sort of holding uh Stop
and Shop is not happy with these kids
being a thorn in their side. It's great.
Um yeah yeah yeah. They're they're
pretty good at like getting pressed for
what they do and things like that. Um
they'll probably have to respond at some
point. Um, good. Um, well that's I I
enjoyed um letting you all connect with
them. It sounds like the meeting, you
know, every time you go into breakout
rooms, it's sort of uneven, but
hopefully it's a good sense for you to
meet some of the people who are in
higher education who are trying to make
the changes that we're going to talk
about, you know, in the past few weeks
and for the the rest of the semester. So
hopefully that was a neat opportunity.
Um, why don't you take a couple minutes
um before I launch into things just to
chat with each other and then we can
surface some of these ideas. Um but the
the learning journal prompt that I had
for you was to talk about like what role
does technology play um in your MIT
education thus far. Um and uh so talk to
the person next to you. Some of you
might not be from MIT or some of you
might be in graduate school and so you
have some undergraduate connections to
this as well. Those things are all fine.
Sort of technology and higher education.
Um, typically the the the things that
are most useful to talk about are um
either either systems or tools or things
that you think are like particularly
helpful or useful. Um, systems or tools
or things that are particularly damaging
or harmful or pointless or a waste of
your time. Um, and then also anything
that like has has started to seem really
familiar to you, but actually you think
has like interesting unfamiliar
qualities or or thing things that sort
of like feel standard and boring, but
actually they're important maybe in ways
that we don't want to think about. So,
so turn to the two or three people next
to you. Talk for a few minutes about
like if you were to explain to someone
not from your undergraduate institution
like the role that technology plays
there, what would be the couple of
stories that you would tell? Ready? Go.
Okay, come on back.
Be great to keep trying to hear from
everybody. So, would love to some folks
who haven't shared yet would love to
hear what are what are some uh what are
some MIT highlights or low lightss or
sort of distinctive parts of uh or or in
your undergraduate program distinctive
parts of technologies.
What do you got Jiren? Uh my group was
my group was discussing like MIT's use
of canvas and like precoid MIT had this
weird sort of proprietary thing where
they had their own what was that called?
Stellar. Stellar. Yeah. Yeah. So they
had like each each class had their own
different stellar website and it wasn't
standardized at all and it was it was
kind of a mess. It like had this weird
outdated sort of 1990s internet era
aesthetic to it. It was pretty horrible.
And then they had this sort of
proprietary thing called the learning
module which was basically Canvas like
MIT was just trying to make Canvas but
then during the pandemic they I guess
you know they decided to make canvas a
much more standardized thing. And so I
found that to be very helpful for
keeping everything organized and having
assignments you know done through Canvas
as opposed to being like oh crap what's
that website I have to go to search up
stellar MIT. It was weird. Um, but I
feel like because of that, a lot of
professors don't fully utilize all the
different things that Canvas has to
offer, especially when it comes to like
grades and inputting grades. Like
professors and TAs don't care about like
inputting grades and like a lot of
students would I I feel would really
like to see real-time feedback like on
their grades and how that actively
affects their final grade in the class,
but that just isn't uh that just isn't
professors don't do that. Yeah. Yeah.
Um, and then I mean another thing that's
sort of unusual, we'll talk about this
more as the semester goes on, but it
does seem a little weird that you would
have the exact same Canvas template for
a graduate seminar on chemistry
synthesis and an undergraduate seminar
on Renaissance poetry and uh like if you
know if if you're studying really
different kinds of things, does it
really make sense to have the same
structure for all of those different
kinds of things? Like it seems like
there should be some differences there.
What were you gonna say, Emily? Um, we
talked about MITx, which is you like
physics use it and then a lot of math
classes use it. And I like how it's like
even like it's sometimes like recordings
of like a concept introducing you to a
concept or it could be in writing, but
it's not as like dense as a textbook
where you're kind of like, oh, I don't
want to start reading this. And then
it's like right after when they
introduce it, you have like kind of
check questions where it's kind of like
checking for your understanding and it
immediately tells you if you're right or
wrong, which is really nice because like
for math, I feel like some like when
you're told like, oh, this is the right
answer. You're more focused on the
process of getting to it rather than the
answer itself, which is a lot more
beneficial when you're doing math. Like
you care about the process of how to get
to that answer, not the answer itself.
So I think it's really like really nice
to have that platform for especially
math classes. Um and you you know you
could imagine for all for all of those
autograded problems you've ever done you
know five years ago you very likely
would have done those pet sets on paper
you would have turned the pet sets into
a TA a TA you know TA would have gotten
hundreds of them um it would have taken
them a week 10 days two weeks to turn
around or something like that and so
that by by the time it gets handed back
to you might get the answer key sooner
um but the time you get that like it can
be days or weeks after doing a problem
that you figure out whether you got it
right or not and you just forgot how you
did it or like what you were thinking
about at the time. So there you could
definitely imagine some real advantages
to that kind of instant like you know it
can change the way study groups operate
too both for good and bad. Um but you
could imagine that like study groups
previously would have been like okay
let's all like write this pet set they
all write the pet turn it in you're like
hope that worked. Um, but when you have
the kind of autograding, you you know,
you can be like, "Wait, half of us did
not get this right." Like, "Why didn't
we? Who did, you know, what can we learn
from each other?" You know, there's all
kinds of ways that that instant feedback
can change the the relationships that
you have with with that learning. Good.
Other thoughts? Yeah. Okay. Um, I was
going to say something like Notability
has really transformed the way I um, for
example, organize all of my classwork
and the fact that everyone uses their
iPads now instead of going to paper and
pencil. Um, I think
um, yeah, just the fact that we can have
all of our lecture notes and then upload
it to Notability. We can annotate it and
then do all of our homework on here too
and be able to like compare screens and
things like that. And I think that's
really like before I only ever really
used paper and pencil and then switching
the fact that MIT gave out iPads to
everyone. And then um because we have uh
the resources to have Notability for
free or um and the fact that we like
submit everything electronically now has
kind of been a little bit of a game
changer. Does Notability have any social
features? Like do you just have your own
Notability or are there ways? Okay. They
recently added some like share your
notes kind of gallery search thing.
There's also the good old screenshot the
iPads if you want iCloud. You can just
text it to the to Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Good. Good. Share like you can
dual screen on the iPad which isn't
necessarily an aspect. Well, not build
you can also dual screen so you pull up
someone else's work.
There there's some like very specific
applications for some of those kinds of
things. Good. Other thoughts if you have
one more? We had like the same thought
of um cats has been kind of
revolutionary in that like I guess in a
way that's I've I've heard of this but
you got to tell us what it is again. It
is Catsup is an automatic tutor for 601
problems.
It it used to be like an old
introductory computer science course
that was required for most or six
majors, but they phased that out like
three years ago. Um I don't remember
what 601 specifically was, but that's
what capsu stands for. It's like a
recursive um acronym, but like I I guess
in a way like I've never I never got to
use Stellar, but in a way that sort of
has become the the new Stellar in in the
sense that like each class has their own
different website and you just like
upload problems on there. And I have
found it to be kind of nice because it
also has like a topic grader.
um it lets you like submit um stuff for
recitation like in class and I found
like it's pretty great. I like the
interface um but I I just hate the fact
that I have to like bookmark every
single different website or else I
forget them. So good. So logistical
things. I mean to add to that like
different course I mean I've seen it
most of it in core six yeah like
different core six um classes use it to
different degrees and diverse situ there
there is a little fault for it there um
there are some classes where the entire
class is on there and then you go to
your class in the basement with 40
people and they're all trying to log in
at the same time so that they're marked
as present and they're starting their
lab and everything just crashed. That is
that's that is so comforting to me
because I run this system called teacher
moments and we have similar problems but
like I'm not an MIT computer science
professor and the fact like and the fact
that their doesn't work either is
very like it's very comforting to me I
think that there's one thing that like
we kind of discussed um which is like an
application of the MITx um is like
typically most freshmen at MIT take like
the 801 802 teal
Um, and I feel like that gives like this
false advertisement of how education
technology is used here at MIT where
they like give you this like flipped
classroom idea. Um, and like some kids
like love it and then you switch into
another class and you never see that
type of learning again. And you're like,
well, I liked that, so where is it? Um,
and like for me who like struggled
through it because I was like a student
that was kind of behind going in. um
like then I switched to like my core 16
classes where it's like a professor
lecturing in front of you and all of a
sudden I now understand the concept.
It's like why did I lose a whole year?
Um so it's like kind of like that back
and forth between like like are you
going to continue to implement this in
other ways or is it just are we just
stagnant in this one idea behind it?
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That's that's really I
mean teal is an experience that a lot of
you have had if you if you're not
familiar. teal is a way that they do
introductory physics teaching. Um it
came about um because of high failure
rates particularly from people who you
know came from backgrounds where they
were less well prepared in physics. Um
and uh so you know 801 802 these
introductory physics classes would be
taught as lectures with problem sets and
things like that. Um it also actually
there's a long um a really we won't get
into a really interesting tradition of
research in physics education um which I
don't know three or three decades ago
maybe discovered um that when students
even at really good universities take
introductory physics historically they
were actually less Newtonian in their
thinking at the end of the class than at
the beginning. um like they were like
they got good grades. Um they could
solve all the kinds of physics problems,
but then they gave them this uh this
test, this sort of assessment called the
force concept inventory, which was a
bunch of conceptual questions about how
force works. And students would actually
do worse at the end of the class that
they would do at the beginning. Um so
there was this sense that like you could
spend a whole bunch of time teaching
people the procedures of physics and
they would actually come to like
slightly more misunderstand the concepts
as a result of that. Um which is bad. Um
and uh um so uh active learning learn
you know learning environments where
students are asked to not just listen
and take notes and then do problem sets
but to like engage during the
conversations about the material were
shown to improve that and then teal
stuck around because while people have
individual experiences with it um there
are fewer students who failed um 801 and
802 after teal was implemented and given
a few years to like ramp up and work
right than there were beforehand. Um
however just because on average teal the
teal system is more likely to have more
students persist doesn't mean that for
any individual student like individual
students can still not like it. Um and
it can sort of not serve them well and
it can not serve them well because of
their background preparation or because
they you know I mean lots of people who
come to MIT end up here because they're
pretty good at teaching themselves stuff
through lectures. Um, and so you know,
alternate methods, you know, when when
the physics department is trying to
think about what to do with that, these
are all the kinds of trade-offs that
they're considering. What were you going
to say, Har? Uh, slides, especially when
you're taking classes that are like core
six or math. When professors use slides,
I feel like it affects my learning
because I like when when they use chalk
in the board, they just like walking
through it because one, it slows them
down.
you also kind of catch up with them. But
they usually apply they go very fast and
second you just have to I don't know it
makes the learning process a different
things. Yeah. Yeah. No, I think I think
I think it's really interesting. You
know they're they're probably like
they're less likely to have errors on
the slides than they are when they're
working things out by hand. It's not
however it's not totally clear whether
or not errors are a bad thing in that
like sometimes people note the errors in
real time or they note them in real time
and they fix them and they discuss them.
Definitely like if you can only sort of
talk and move at the pace at which
someone can write um that's uh that can
have different kind of advantages. I
mean the slides are kind of cool in that
they get sort of like automatically sent
to you. They can be sent to you in
advance. You can take notes directly on
them. Is taking notes directly on them
actually better or is it better to have
to hand copy sort of pay attention
what's going on there? Um these are all
great questions and they're all
questions that actually have research
behind them. There are folks who you
know come up with experiments where they
test all of these different conditions.
What do we do when we tell students to
try to copy everything down? What do we
do when we tell students to summarize?
What if we give them stuff in advance?
What if we let them have computers? What
if we take away their computers? Um,
actually, you know, some of the best
places to do this research end up being
uh military schools um like the like
West Point and the Naval Academy and
stuff like that. Um because they have a
lot of required classes and because you
can be pretty sure that the students
will do what you tell them to do. Um
like you like you assign them to either
condition and they kind of like you know
they they do what they want to. Um good.
Maybe one. So an interesting thing about
our own experiences is that our own
experiences are really important sources
of data for understanding education
technology like like it's important for
us to look through the lens of our own
learning experiences and and they can be
very informative. Um the other thing to
remember is that if you're studying at
MIT you're probably weird. Um there
there are probably characteristics of
you which are not typical. Like if you
like if you generally find classroom
learning pleasant um you are unusual.
Um, if you think to yourself, man, I
really like just kind of like learning
stuff and figuring out on my own in
academic material, that is unusual. Um,
most people are not good at those things
and don't find them enjoyable. So, so
it's it could be helpful to bring your
own experience, but it's also important
to recognize the way like, you know, and
I I went to private schools my whole
life. I've had an extraordinarily
privileged educational upbringing. if it
doesn't in lots of ways I have to
recognize how that upbringing does not
prepare me well to understand the
learning experiences of most students
who go to K12 schools and public schools
in the United States and things like
that. So be conscientious of that as we
do some thinking. But this stuff is
good. All the things you're talking
about are are things we'll keep trying
to make sense of. Failure to disrupt.
Um this is a book about large-scale
learning um learning environments with
many many learners and few experts to
guide them. Um, and I would say the
heart of what I'm trying to do in this
book is to is to demystify education
technology for people and to and to say,
you know, with every generation of new
technologies, there will be folks who
come along that try to go to schools and
say, "This thing is totally brand new.
This is this is disruptive. Um, this is
innovative. This is going to this is a
gamecher. this is going to transform
education. Um, and my job is to be like,
eh, probably not. Um, it might be
helpful, but it's very very unlikely
that it will be any of those kinds of
things. Um, a one of the ways to
demystify technologies is to show where
they come from. Um, is to say these
things have patterns. The patterns are
recognizable. Um, they are patterns not
just in how these things are designed,
but how they get implemented and what
kind of effects they have. When new
technologies come along, we don't have
to we don't have to guess out of the
blue how well they might work. We know
roughly how well education technology
works in different kinds of circum. Now
new things there there will be new
things that are invented that are in
fact different but but most new things
are just a little bit new. They make
just small modifications, small advances
off off of past things.
Um and then the second half of the book
uh says sort of confronts the challenge
like why is it so hard to make progress
with education technology? Why are why
are things not disruptive? Why are they
not transformative? Why are they not
game changers? Um and I think there are
answers to those questions. I think
there are there are challenges that we
have as a field yet to figure out how to
tackle. Um and if we study those
challenges and make sense of them, then
we could probably do a better job um
moving past them. So the first half of
the book looks at these three genres of
learning at scale. It says that most
education technologies, especially the
ones where you try to teach a lot of
people with very few experts, fall into
one of three buckets. And you can figure
out what bucket each thing is in by
asking the question who guides the
sequence of learning activities. Um when
learners do stuff, they happen in an
order one after the other after the
other. Um and there are really kind of
three sorts of ways that those orders
unfold. Um the first is instructor-g
guided learning at scale. So there can
be some expert or team of experts who
says you should learn things in this
order. Here's part one, part two, part
three, part four, part five. And maybe
learners don't go in that order, but
overwhelmingly they will. Um and there's
sort of some logical sequence to that.
So I call those things instructorguided
learning at scale. Um a bunch of what
you read about for today, massive open
online courses. Um any kind of
self-paced online learning sort of falls
in that bucket. Um the second big genre
is algorithm guided learning at scale.
Uh so that's when you um a computer
poses you a problem, you answer that
problem and the computer evaluates your
performance and then based on that
performance it gives you either more
difficult problems or simpler problems
or the same kind of problem or shunts
you in some kind of different direction.
But basically the computer evaluates
your performance, decides on the basis
of that performance what the next uh
item in a sequence of activities should
be and then you go do that forever. um
lots of you are probably I I don't know
when I taught this 10 years ago maybe
students would have dabbled with these
things but it's far far more common now
like if you in school ever used Dreambox
or Khan Academy um almost all of those
things are some version of uh algorithm
guided learning at scale all all a bunch
of the testing that you've done if
you've taken the computer-based GRE
other things like that they use similar
technologies um the third bucket of
things we call peerguided learning at
scale. Um, so if any of you have ever
played around with the Scratch
programming community, there's no
instruction in Scratch. There's no
there's no like Scratch University or
like Scratch lesson one, lesson two,
lesson three, and that's very
intentional and by design. Instead,
you're immersed in this community of
peers. Um, and if you go to the homepage
of the Scratch website, there are
featured tutorials and featured projects
and things like that. And the way you
figure out Scratch is that you think
about some things that you want to do
and then you find some other people who
have done that kind of thing and you
copy them, you converse with them, you
take their project and you modify it.
Um, but you basically sort of design
your own pathway. Um, there are lots of
other learning environments, uh, Stack
Overflow, other kinds of communities of
practice. The the one that I talk about
at the beginning of the book is Rainbow
Loom. Um, any of you ever played with
Rainbow Loom when you were kids? Yeah.
Um, so you know when you bought a Did I
tell you the story yet? When you bought
a Rainbow Loom, there are like 10 cards
in the packet. So, you pull open the
packet, there's a bunch of these little
rubber bands, little like uh uh what do
they call that thing? Frame to stitch
the rubber bands on. And then there are
10 cards that show 10 different kinds of
bracelets that you can make. If you get
really into Rainbow Loom, 10 different
kinds of bracelets is not enough kinds
of bracelets. Like, you have to learn
more different ways of doing it. Um and
the main way you'll learn that is
through YouTube. Um you'll go to this I
mean, and here's the thing that sort of
boggled my mind about Rainbow Loom. So,
there's some dude who is in Michigan.
Um, he was like an automotive engineer
or something like that who was like, "In
my country, this is the way we make
bracelets." Um, and he's like, and he,
you know, he like comes up with some CAD
designs and he sends them to China and
China manufactures of these things and
they put them on shipping containers and
they send them to his distribution
center and eventually these packet, you
know, these these little like boxes of
Rainbow things get sent all over the
world. It's a total supply chain
miracle. Um the fact that you know some
dude in Michigan just has an idea and is
like let's have people all over the
world buy these things and they do is
amazing. But
simultaneously to that physical supply
chain infrastructure this giant global
community of Rainbow Loom learners
emerges um where there are people who
are running little classes at uh um art
shops and they're posting videos online
and they're sharing ideas with each
other and they're creating little
Facebook marketplaces. Um and the only
way Rainbow Loan could grow is if that
learning network grows alongside it. You
know that is miraculous. Um that is like
an amazing feature of online learning
that uh that you know people could
invent a tool to do this kind of
practice um and and a community could
develop to teach each other and
themselves this practice. Um, I think
there were uh Oh, the other thing I
really liked about that which I think I
mentioned is that um I don't there were
these two girls. I think their names
were Ashley and Steph um who made
Rainbow Loom YouTube videos and they got
millions of views and you could compare
their videos to like the actual Rainbow
Loom manufacturer videos and these girls
were getting like 10x the number of
views that the actual Rainbow like like
basically kids would rather learn um
from these kind of two random girls.
They ended up being Philadelphia.
They're very good at protecting their
anonymity, at least for a while. One of
them eventually became a makeup
influencer. Um, and and then they
revealed herself. But uh um but I find
these global networks incredibly
fascinating. Um and very very difficult
to integrate in schools for reasons that
we'll explore as we go along. Um so if
you buy that there are these three big
categories. Um a thing that we'll do
over the next um few weeks is we'll look
at how there are similarities within
these categories. Um so for instance in
instructorg guided learning at scale
there typically are sort of two key
technologies. There are two technologies
that show up over and over and over
again. Um one is a learning management
system. So a learning management system
canvas blackboard edex mood stellar a
zillion other things. They're sort of
platforms that organize learning
materials. Um a an unusual feature of
learning management systems is that they
have a feature that like product people
who study products called feature
convergence. Essentially it's very
difficult to like patent um or or have
intellectual property around like
components of a learning management
system. So anytime anyone invents
something good, everybody else copies
it. Um so they're all basically the
exact same system. Um like you buy them
from different vendors, but they're
basically one learning management
system. Um and then the second kind of
crucial feature of online learning
management of of MO or instructor guided
learning at scale are autograders. Um so
you have to be able to give if you have
lots and lots of learners if you want to
be able to give them feedback if you
want to be able to certify their
learning in any way. Um you either have
to spend zillions of dollars hiring
people to grade their work um or you
find ways of having computers grade
their work. Now computers can grade as
we'll talk about this at length
computers can grade some things but not
others. Um computers are really good at
answer at at evaluating questions where
the answer is is well known and certain.
Um they are much less good at evaluating
anything which has a kind of subjective
component to it. Um uh one way to think
about this is autograders are great in
early language acquisition and very
rapidly become useless in later language
acquisition. Um so they can tell whether
you've spelled ola correctly. We even
have some pretty cool ones that can tell
whether if you've pronounced Ola
correctly. Um, we can give you a
multiple choice question to see if you
can recognize the audio recording of
Ola. Um, eventually, however, what we
want to know are like what are the key
themes in Don Kiote? Um, and that we
don't have very good autograders to be
able to evaluate and and so forth. Um I
would say in addition to this sort of
technological infrastructure, these
genres of learning at scale, they tend
to align more closely either with direct
instruction kind of folks or sort of
apprenticeship uh uh constructivism
kinds of folks. The the instructor
guided learning at scale people, they
tend to be thornyike direct instruction
cognitive load theory kind of people.
They tend to be pale filling kinds of
folks. Um
uh algorithm guide to learning at scale.
um has similarities but differences. Um
so the the sort of crucial technology
behind algorithm guided learning at
scale is a set of algorithms called item
response theory. Um this was developed
in the 1980s by educational testing
services. The people who make what do
they do the SAT or the GRE? What is it?
What is what test does ETSs make? I
don't know. They make tests. Um and uh
um the like the basic toolkit of item
response theory has proven really quite
robust. Um all item response theory does
basically is it lets you figure out how
difficult an item is. It's a way of
quantifying how difficult an item is. If
you can quantify how difficult an item
is, if someone gets the item right, you
can give them a more difficult item or
less difficult item. It was actually
originally developed so that you could
give people tests of equivalent
difficulty without giving them the same
test. Um this proved important like when
we had national testing and we built
communication networks um because in
theory somebody could take a you know a
test in Portland, Maine um and later
that same day someone would take it in
Honolulu, Hawaii um and there's like
just enough time in there for someone to
call and you know and send all the
questions and answers and and things
like that. Um, and so it was it was a it
was part came about from sort of test
security. You want to make you want to
be able to make claims about about
people's ability. Um, and one way to do
that is to give everyone the same test.
Another way to do that is to give
everyone tests with different items but
of the same difficulty. Um, and so we
had to come up with some statistical
toolkit for doing that.
Um, what we came up with in the 1980s
and 1990s, we like we've modified it a
bit, but we still pretty much use today.
um we sort of know a bunch about its
strengths and weaknesses and how it
works. Um most of our autograders have
like just now maybe they're starting to
improve a little bit. Most of them
haven't improved that much in the last
two or three decades. Um I in some
specific areas, some parts of language
acquisition, some parts of computer
science, maybe they've improved better.
Um but these technologies for the most
part are pretty stable. um when someone
has a new entrant I I mean I'll you'll
read more of this story in chapter two
but there was a company called Newton um
which said that they could take uh they
could take any body of educational
content and turn it into an intelligent
tutor um and they thought that their
tutor was absolutely amazing that the
founder described it as a uh something
like a magical robot tutor in the sky
sort of knew exactly what you were
thinking and so forth. Um so he was
making all these like totally outlandish
claims and then his engineers um were
like had a blog about what they were
building and they one of their blog
posts was something like using two
parameter item response theory to
evaluate items. They're basically like
this you know so the leader is out there
being like these things is totally
amazing and the engineers are like like
here's the very wellestablished
technology that we're using to do the
thing that we like are selling you to
do.
Um the peer-guided learning at scale
looks pretty different from the other
two. Um, peer-guided learning
environments tend to be more
apprenticeship oriented. They tend to be
more wrapped into situated learning
things like that. Um, they tend to have
a different um, uh, technical
infrastructure. Um, instead of being
based in some kind of content holding
thing like a learning management system,
they usually exist on the web. Um, and
usually their killer app is not an
autograder, but a thing that pulls
content together. Like how do you figure
out what the right sequence of Rainbow
Loom um, learning materials is to look
at? And things like hashtags are really
important for that. Um uh how do you in
Scratch like how do you pull together
and come up with a set of featured
projects or a way of tagging projects so
that people can find their way through
them. Um so these are sort of the three
big buckets um that will explore um one
bucket each over the over the next bunch
of weeks.
Um, the second half of the book, which
pro I guess if this if that if that if
this project takes us a good chunk of
March, this project will take us a good
chunk of April, are four problems that
educators and education technology
designers run into over and over again.
Um, which I'll enumerate quickly just to
orient you.
Um, one's missing. Anyway, the first one
is the curse of the familiar. Um, the
idea of the curse of the familiar is
that it's pretty easy to make
technologies that do things that
educators already are doing and get them
adopted. Um, how many of you have ever
used
Quizlet? Okay, that that's about as
universal a group. Uh, Quizlet was
founded by MIT dropout um Andy
Sutherland who took a bunch of uh um
education classes with us and uh um he
built it to I think study French for
himself. Um uh a Quizlet is flashcards.
Um, if you went and you gathered a bunch
of educational experts around the world
and said like what like what or you know
what what is our what do our kids really
need to advance their learning? There
was there is no one who would raise
their hands and be like there's a huge
der of flash cards. Like we just don't
have enough flash cards at school. We've
run out of index cards. Something like
that. Um uh and yet um here's this
something you know maybe I mean they say
things like half of all high schoolers
every month use Quizlet. Um how much
does Quizlet improve teaching and
learning? Well, if you're replacing
regular flash cards with digital flash
cards, like how much would you expect
that to improve learning? Like maybe
some maybe there's a little efficiency
there. Something like that. You also
might say something like actually one of
the best things about flashcards is the
creation of the flash cards. Like
there's actually something important of
learning about like writing down the
prompts on one ends, the answers on the
other end. So maybe the paper ones are
actually better um than the Quizlet ones
in different kinds of ways. But the
point is um there's probably no one who
would make a bet that you know human
development would be profoundly
transformed by digitizing flashcards.
But if you look across many of the most
successful education technology
companies, they do something like
Quizlet. They take a thing which is
already happening in schools and they
digitize it, maybe make it a little bit
more efficient. There are handful of
projects that try to do something
totally different. Um and many of them
fail. And the reason why they fail is
it's really hard to convince people in
schools to adopt totally new routines.
So there are all kinds of ed, you know,
there are all kinds of like visionary
educators out there who think of like,
man, wouldn't it be cool if we could
teach math in this really different kind
of way? If we can teach computer science
in this really different kind of way.
Um, and then they build things that do
that and people go, that's weird. Um, I
don't understand this really new
different kind of way. So a bunch of the
things which might potentially lead us
to the biggest gains or changes in our
teaching and learning are really hard to
get people to adopt. That's the curse of
the familiar. Um the edtech Matthew
effect is that we very often hope that
new technologies especially free
technologies will be the term people
often use is democratizing. Um that they
will they will essentially what'll
happen is like every you know people
generally speaking agreed that folks who
have more resources have had more
learning experiences and therefore have
learned more than people with less
experience. Um but we hope that there
are technologies that will like
disproportionately benefit um the the
less affluent that they will help poor
folks sort of catch up to other people.
they'll create new kinds of on-ramps.
You know, maybe they help everybody, but
they particularly help this group. What
we almost always find is the figure on
the right, which is that new
technologies disproportionately benefit
the affin um is that they're very likely
to accelerate the learning of people who
are already advantaged. Um if many
people go into education because they're
trying to build a more equitable, just
society, um and it can be quite
frustrating if you keep building stuff
and it keeps helping the most affluent
people in society secure their position
um better. um we can document this
really well. It's actually in in a lot
of cases hard to understand why it's
happening and and we have very little
science or research that helps us
explain what alternatives would be. Um
we know you know we'll give you some
examples of some technologies that I
think don't do that that I think do
disproportionately um benefit people
from further further from opportunity
but it's really hard to figure out why
they work.
Um, a third challenge that education
technology folks come across all the
time, um, is that computers are good at
evaluating certain kinds of things. The
kinds of things that they're really good
at evaluating are those that are
routine, uh, that have common features
to them, that are highly structured. Um,
uh, computers are much less good at
evaluating, um, illststructured kinds of
things, things where, you know, that
that don't have much form to them or we
don't know what inputs need to go in
them or what the final output should
look like. Um, for instance, one of the
things that that we don't have good
autograders for is people's ability to
reason from evidence in natural
language, you know, either written or
auditory. The main thing that we teach
you for 16 or 20 years in the education
system is how to reason from evidence.
Like the most important things we're
teaching you how to do, we don't have
good autograders for. Moreover, the
kinds of things that computers can grade
tend to overlap pretty closely with the
kinds of things computers are good at.
Um, if computers are good at things,
it's going to be very difficult to make
a living doing those things. So, we have
like really good tests for the kinds of
things that are probably not so
important to teach people. Um, and we
have not very good tests on the kinds of
things that are really important to
teach people. That is like a bad feature
for educational system. Um, because
autograding of all kinds is way cheaper
than human grading. Um, so we
essentially build all of these systems
where conceivably we're like spending
money to cheaply evaluate the least
important parts of the system and we're
not evaluating the most important parts
that thing people ought to be developing
in those systems. Um, so that is the
trap of routine assessment. Um, a really
cool thing about computers is that they
can collect enormous amounts of data
about what folks do and that we can run
experiments on people um, and improve
those systems. So every time, not every
time, but you know, 1% of the time you
go to Google or Amazon or Facebook or
whatever that like they're doing some
little randomized control trial on you.
You know, the buy button is green
instead of red and we figure out whether
you buy more from green buttons and red
buttons. Um, and eventually, you know,
Amazon, Facebook, they do millions, I
don't know, they do many, many of those
experiments every year and their system
continuously gets better. Um, there are
a couple of problems with doing that in
education. Um the first problem is if
you go to folks and you say that what
you want to do is experiment with their
children as we've joked before like
people are not that enthusiastic about
that as an idea. Um it's also not clear
that um like surveilling people
constantly in public schools is a good
idea for civil society. Um an exercise
maybe we'll do later on is start
thinking about all of the data that MIT
has about you. Um and we might start
thinking like is it a good idea that MIT
has all of this data about people? is a
good idea for an elementary school to
have all of this data um about where
people are moving, where they're logging
in, how they're learning, their
healthcare, all these other kinds of
things. Um so it could it could be that
collecting huge amounts of data lets us
build really cool edtech products. It
also could be that it sort of in inducts
people into a surveillance society which
ultimately is not good for democracies
or civil society.
Um so in the second half of the class,
those are the or the second half of our
reading of this book. Um those are the
four dilemmas um that we'll spend some
time messing around with and exploring.
Um that is an overview of the task of
the reading together. Um and then what
we'll do for the last 20 minutes of
class um is to talk about massive open
online courses in particular. But maybe
I'll pause um back here you know
essentially on these these kind of two
slides
um and see if uh people have any
questions or things they want to
interject here
for the next slide when you mention like
the four as yet intractable dilemmas
when you are studying technology
education have you found issues that
used to be dilemmas and that at some
point we were actually able to solve and
these are the four that are like left.
Yeah. So, so I think so I think there
there would be some there would be like
um access and distribution problems that
you might have thought about as being
like really central to lots of different
places 20 years ago that would be that
would still you know if we're talking
about subsaharan Africa or other kinds
of places in the world are still serious
but you
know refugee camps places of protracted
conflicts lots of you know lots of
places where access isn't hard um but
there's also lots of places be like you
know in the United States like pretty
much every school has highspeed internet
now um and So whereas and we still have
to think about how we do that and how we
upgrade it and things like that but but
but that is a dilemma which has you know
diminished quite a bit over time and
some of you know for sure some of these
dilemmas we've made progress on I mean I
would particularly say the trap of
routine assessment is one where um you
know in the last 10 or 15 years there
are definitely there are definitely
places where you could say hey um we're
doing better automated assessment now
than we were before at different levels.
So um I mean computer science is
probably the place where we have the
most robust suite of autograding tools.
Um it doesn't cover everything that's
important in computer science but boy
like you can automatically evaluate
people on a lot of stuff that matters.
Um uh yeah I mean there's an example in
the book of uh of autograding spoken
language um for language learners. You
know that you can talk out loud and
Dualingo can tell whether or not you've
pronounced something correctly. That's
pretty rad. Um uh and then I think there
you know it it pro it'll be interesting
to see in the next few years but I'm my
hunch is large language models will play
an increasingly large role in at least
giving people meaningful feedback on
their written products. Um whether or
not we actually grade with them like
that may be sort of a bridge too far.
Um, I'm sure we'll use it in some
circumstances, but I bet there'll be
many, many circumstances. You know, if
if you told me 10 years from now, every
time a student turned in a paper, they
ran it through like an advanced version
of something like Grammarly, which gave
them not only feedback about their
syntax, but was like, "Hey, I don't
think you have any evidence in this
paragraph. You might want to go back and
look at that." Like, that wouldn't
surprise me at all. Um, and that could
help students a lot. you know, if
there's if there's someone who who can,
you know, if there's an automated bot
that can like, you know, give you
reasonable feedback generically about
your writing, that would be cool. You
know, that I'd ra I'd rather focus on
other things than giving you feedback.
So, I remember you mentioning in one of
the slides that computers right now are
like not very good at things that don't
have as much structure, but with things
like LLM, um, do you think that that's
going to change? Like I they will get
better. Um I I think there is still I
think even some of our earliest evidence
suggests that these are really thorny
problems. Um so like I feel like we're
starting to get some feedback about for
instance people using LLMs to help them
in coding. Um and there's a joke which
is something like um you know um using
co-pilots in coding will reduce your
initial coding time in half and then it
will double your quality assurance time.
um that you know basically because like
not only will it maybe introduce errors
but also the people engineering things
just won't understand what the bot is
doing and the bot is much better at like
very specific parts of building code
than it is in engineering a whole system
and so like it makes a bunch of
decisions that make sense for a
particular thing but don't make sense
for building a whole system and then
somebody has to go back and repair those
kinds of things. um are you know so are
so in terms of like um I don't I'll get
we'll get into this more when we talk
about autograders later but um Hal Abson
who's been on the CS faculty forever has
this wonderful quotation in one of his
earliest books on uh computer science
which says something like
um computer programming is a language
for computer for communicating between
two people about methods that's only
incidentally meant to be run by a
machine. Um and the idea is that really
good code is actually talking amongst
people um and not talking to the
machine. Um our autograders are really
good at figuring out whether or not code
like does things that machines
understand and our autograders for
computer science are not very good at
evaluating things like how well is this
code designed for collaboration amongst
people? How you know how sensibly are
the functions named and other kinds of
things like that. I I my hunch is we'll
make progress on it. Um my other hunch
is that it will remain like a pretty
hard problem for a pretty long time. Um
and also it's a problem we'll solve in
degrees like will we will we give better
automatic like five years from now will
we give better automatic feedback to the
typical middle school essay written in
almost any topic and will some of that
feedback actually be useful? Seems
almost certain to me. Um will we be able
to actually grade? we will actually say
something like like this p like this
paper is better than this other paper
with all the consequences that are
attendant to that. Um we already do that
to some extent in the education system
but I think we're still going to find
that we're not confident in the
assessment that these machines make. Um
but fortunately like these are all
testable hypotheses. So you know your if
your predictions were more optimistic
than mine you could very well be right.
Um let's talk about massive open online
courses for a bit.
Um, MOOs burst on the scene in
particular 2011 2012. So almost 15 years
ago now. How many of you have taken a
massive open online course? How many of
you have signed up for a class? How many
how many of you how many of you signed
up for one and finished it all the way
through? Okay. So people laugh because
that is a much smaller number of folks.
Um, this is one of the sort of
distinctive features of online learning.
Um,
uh, is that online learning is really
hard. Um it is if you were not alive or
sort of paying attention to education in
2011, 2012, 2013, it is hard to
understand h like how much people
assumed that these tools would
completely change higher education like
not be like a little bit useful maybe,
but like utterly rearrange educational
systems. Like people thought they were
going to be before MOOs and after mukes.
part of the hype of this the first sort
of really large scale class like this um
Sebastian Thrun and Peter Norvig um who
are computer science Sebastian Thrun
works on self-driving cars he founded a
company called Udacity Peter Norvig
worked at Google forever they were both
professors at Stanford um they created a
class called intro to AI um and they
sent an email around to the E mailing
list um saying anybody want to take this
intro to AI class um they were
particularly inspired by Salcon um I
think it was who was talking about the
like the the the MITx practice sets that
you were going through um they were very
taken by that model. You watch a little
bit of a video, you solve a couple
problems. You watch a little bit more
video, you solve a couple problems. Sort
of interle them along. Um they send this
email around, they're thinking, you
know, maybe a few hundred, maybe a few
thousand people show up. 100,000 people
sign up for this course. 100,000 people,
you know, multiples more than Peter and
Sebastian combined would have ever
taught on Stanford campus in their
entire career there. Um and and there
was a vision like wow this could happen
for everything everywhere. This could be
all of higher education in the future.
Um the amount of resources that
ultimately people like Peter and
Sebastian could put behind a course for
100,000 people like you could easily
spend hundred thousand dollars of build
building that course material and then
the cost of every marginal student every
additional student would be quite low
you know. So most people who are
teaching a class, you just like, you
know, you hire someone, you pay them
$60,000 a year in a community college,
maybe less, you pay them $100,000 a
year, leave college, maybe a little
more. Um, and they spend some of that
money making a course and 20 people take
it and that's that. Um, but imagine if
you could concentrate resources to make
like the best possible instructional
sequence, the best course ever. Um, I
was I did my undergraduate at the
University of Virginia. Um, and the
University of Virginia very briefly
fired their president um, in I think
2013 because she was not sort of
transitioning fast enough to this new
online world. Um, and and then um, uh,
the the board of governors sort of
underestimated her popularity on campus
and all the faculty and students came
out on the lawn and protested and she
got rehired. Um but you know um like
like you know imagine if MI you know
MIT's president UMass president got
fired this week because they weren't
moving fast enough on AI. Like that was
sort of like the equivalent of of what
was happening in 2013. It was just
madness. Um and I had just finished my
PhD. Um so I had just finished at
Harvard in uh 2012. I spent a year
working at an organization nearby called
Facing History and Ourselves. Um and I
got hired at Harvard as the first
researcher whose responsibility was to
sort of um create a research
infrastructure for Harvard X. Um there
were three big bets that when that when
Harvard and MIT came together to create
MOOs um to create
edex mukes have been created in other
places too. Um Corsera at Stanford most
notably there are three things they're
going to try to do. They're going to
provide new pathways into higher
education for people who have limited
access. um that basically there are lots
of places in the world where people
can't get into higher education because
they can't afford it because it's not
nearby the programs they want aren't
there if all that is online that as soon
as you can connect people to the
internet everybody can participate in
everything um people thought that it
would sort of reorganize disrupt
unbundle sort of profoundly change
systems of higher education so
universities might still be around but
they could be organized in totally new
ways um you know we were talking just in
the beginning about um how um research
universities often hire hire people who
are not particularly good at teaching.
Um well, what if like all the teaching
just got provided by these companies
that like specialized in generating
learning materials and then the you know
your research professors could just go
do their research and all of you could
take 611 from an online course. Wasn't
there a quote from the book that was
like in like 30 years there would only
be like 10 universities left in the
country and Udacity could be one of
them. Yeah. Yeah. That was Sebastian
Thur and the idea probably from that is
probably not quite as crazy it seemed.
It was probably not that there would not
be institutions of higher education, but
like you would go to UMass or Bunker
Hill Community College and all of the
classes being taught there would have
been made at, you know, um, Shingua
University, Stanford, Harvard, MIT, um,
CMU and a handful of other at Udacity
and a handful of other places. and like
going to something like UMass or Bunker
Hill Community College would mean taking
online courses that were created by
elite institutions elsewhere and you'd
get a dorm room, you know, and be in a
fraternity and be able to like have
some, you know, a human dots and extra
help and things like that. Um, but
people really like that like it sounds
ridiculous, but people like absolutely
believe that people people thought for
sure that higher education would be, you
know, if we went if we went back into
2012 and said that higher education is
like basically the same except having
more financial difficulties in 2024 than
it would in 2012. Um, there would be
lots of people who would be very
surprised um by by that.
Um, so this I guess this presentation I
I don't know when I developed this,
probably 2019 or something like that,
but it was sort of at the moment where
it was pretty clear that like none of
these bets were going to pan out. Um,
that uh that what that we were not going
to accomplish these things and I was
sort of trying to help a community. I
know like sometimes you talking to like
the people we talked to last time,
education deans and stuff like that or
provosts or um funders or or people
educated in education like why didn't
muks do the things that we wanted them
to do? Um oh first of all actually I
don't have to spend too much time
because it sounds like everybody has
taken a muk. Um but like the most
important thing that you need like like
the two most important buttons in a muk
are the previous button and the next
button. That's kind of like what makes
an instructor guided learning at scale.
Like there's a bunch of stuff that we
shove in the middle and then like you
click next, you do some stuff. If you
get it wrong or get confused, you click
previous, but you sort of linearly make
your way through some instructor guided
um set of materials. A bunch of it is
video or animations or text explanation
or stuff like that. And then
periodically there are some assessment
questions that that come along.
Um we realized as education researchers
almost right away um that folks who were
who are furthest from opportunity were
not the ones who were signing up for
mukes first um by this is a paper that
was published in 2019 in nature by
Ezekiel Emanuel who's actually a mostly
a medical researcher um but he was like
you know in the United States here's the
population with a college degree here's
the MOO student population with a
college degree you know in Brazil Russia
India China South Africa Here's the
population with a with a college degree.
Here's the percent of people from those
countries taking mukes have a college
degree. So basically we could tell
almost right away um that the people
that we were recruiting into MOOs were
folks who were already educated. Um I I
today I don't know that we we know
everything about why that's the case. Um
people who have earned an education
probably enjoy education as leisure time
activities more than people who don't
pursue an education. That would be sort
of normal. Um, but I would say that one
thing that we've discovered in various
formats is that online self-paced
learning is incredibly difficult for
people. Um, the VA like you all sort of
laughingly joked about that when I said,
"How many of you have started a MOO that
you didn't finish?" Um, and you all are
some of the best people in the world at
self-paced learning and you found it
hard. Um, the entire population, the
vast majority of people find online
self-paced learning really, really
difficult. Um, they have other
priorities in their life. It's boring.
Um and actually an interesting thing
about people is that when they're
studying something they really care
about they can be quite persistent in
learning. Um so like you study young
people who are like you know right now
um uh if you ask young young tween teens
um to explore skincare routines online
um they will pursue that with great
passion, great determination, persist
through lots of difficulties and be
successful. Um they will not do the same
with algebra. um you kind of wish as a
society that they were better doing in
algebra than skincare routines, but
that's just not the way human beings
seem to be wired. Um so online self the
VA now who gets good at online
self-paced learning like how do you
become good at being a good autodidact?
Um I think the best guess we have is
that you get an apprenticeship in the
formal education system. The best way to
be good at learning on your own is to
learn with a bunch of other people. Um
so that means the way to become really
good at taking these online self-paced
mukes is to go get a college degree. But
if your goal was to was to create new
pathways into higher education for
limited access, building a thing which
you really have to have spent a lot of
time in education to be good at is maybe
not the best strategy. Um but people
didn't know that at the time. Um this is
an article that I wrote with Marano's
adviser Jose. Um that was where we were
um we're trying to figure out like why
muks were not working. Um and uh one of
the things that we observed is the these
are charts of enrollment but they're
charts of enrollment by sort of human
development index category. So basically
way more people were coming from the
world's most affluent countries than
were coming from the world's least
affluent countries. And we basically
made no dent in it you know over the
first eight years or so. Um you know you
could you could imagine like oh well we
started with a pretty big gap. you know,
if these three lines on the bottom had
sort of continued to traverse up, then
maybe you could say, "Okay, we're making
progress towards our goals." Um, the
other thing that was kind of a problem
is is heading into the pandemic, um,
enrollments and sort of like if you're
trying to run a company or something
like that, it's really not good to have
this line go down. You'd really like if
this was Facebook's graph, it would just
keep going up exponentially forever. Um,
that was another problem with with MOOs
compared to sort of other social media
businesses. Like when you sign up for
Facebook or Twitter or something like
that, you're kind of stuck in there
forever. um when you sign up for a
class, the class ends. Um and then you
leave and go do something else with your
life. Um so why didn't this work? Um or
or or or
um actually we'll talk about the um the
second one next, but what were you going
to say, Maria? I was just reflecting one
thing that that I realized as well
recently is that like everyone now
creates their own course. Like every
influencer has a course on something
different, right? And I think that
probably also affected this like ability
of books to kind of spread because
originally like five or six
organizations were creating content and
nowadays this is very
decentralized. So even it's still hard
for people to complete these courses
online etc etc like there's also a lot
more um competition right there's a lot
of competition out there and traditional
institutions proved to be very effective
in that competition. So here's the thing
which shocked even me. Um at the
beginning of the pandemic, you all
remember this from like March 2020,
April 2020, like we sent you all home.
Um and here's something that could have
happened. There could have like there
were there were thousands of professors
in the United States who were teaching
introduction to microeconomics and a
bunch of them could have said, "There is
no way I can do a good job continuing to
teach you introduction to economics.
Like my kids aren't in school. They're
running underneath my feet right now.
I've never taught online before. Just go
to edex. go to go to John Hopkins, go to
MIT, take their courses and I'll give
you a test at the end and help you out.
Um, the alternative is that like I take
my lectures, I put them online and we
meet in Zoom once a week and I still
keep giving you your lectures.
Basically, every learner and institution
in the world preferred the latter
option. um all throughout the pandemic
at all levels of the education around
the world, we basically said like would
you rather have this really high
production value class kind of offered
anonymously from some institution that
maybe you've heard of but you have no
connection with or with your own like
harried professor who's taking care of
his kids while teaching you who doesn't
know anything about online learning and
people overwhelmingly pick the latter.
Um I don't know why we don't know you
know I don't know why we don't know why
they picked the ladder other than the
fact that human that like education is a
profoundly social enterprise. Um even
the comment you made about about
influencers having their own closest and
things like that like you have a
parasocial relationship with those
influencers in a way that you wouldn't
you know from Josh Angress who teaches
the economics class here or something
like that. Um all right let me try to
say two more things before we head out.
Um oh well some of these things are on
there. um that uh um the like the main
advantage that mukes have is they reduce
faculty labor. They pull faculty out of
the equation. You know, they they just
make them sort of television stars
instead of teachers. Um and if you you
know there's b like there's basically no
way to do the economics of mukes except
to dramatically reduce human contact. Um
but like what helps people learn is
human contact. like the like the way
that you persist in most of your
learning environments, especially when
you're learning something you don't care
about and are not that interested in is
like you care what your faculty thinks
about it. You care what your peers are.
You have all these sort of other human
things that keep you connected. Um and
uh and because of that, most people are
not good at self-regulated learning. If
the vast majority of people are not good
at self-regulated learning, if the only
way to get better at self-regulated
learning is to, you know, go through the
K12 system and go to college, then this
is not going to be a good system for
helping folks further from opportunity
get into college.
Um, the primary way that mukes were
going to disrupt higher education um is
there was a very in for me influential
article that said the act like the
actual innovation nothing was innovative
in muks a learning management system is
not new. Edex was not new. Corsera was
not new. Canvas was doing the same
thing. Moodle was doing the same thing.
Blackboard was doing the same thing.
Autograders are not new. We had all
kinds of autograders and all kinds of
systems. That the actual innovation in
MOOs was putting a storefront on top of
a learning management system. That the
thing that was actually different was
that like in the in the past if you
wanted to buy a Harvard course, you had
to buy eight a year and you had to rent
an apartment and you had to buy all your
meals from the institution. Like you had
to buy this like giant bundle of stuff.
Um, and so the bet that Harvard, MIT,
Stanford, other folks made is like what
if we sold just one course at a time?
Um, like what if you could ca could come
in and just take one intro to CS class,
one introduction to economics class. And
that's and and millions of people were
interested in that. Um, I mean, the
number of signups that appeared in many
of these courses were these
astronomically large numbers. You know,
CS50 at Harvard had millions of people
enrolled with just a couple of years. A
tiny tiny fraction of them finish. you
know, something like 1% of them finish.
On average, MOO's about 5% of people um
who register. About 10% of people who
click into a course once um will persist
in a class, but but pretty small
numbers.
Um however, it turned out um that just
like storefronts didn't solve all of the
problems at university stored. So,
people were excited to try out
storefronts. Um but storefronts by
themselves didn't confer legitimacy.
like really traditional things like
registar offices confirm legitimacy. Um
things that publish transcripts um and
degrees and diplomas confer legitimacy.
Um and so and so this idea that mukes
could move forward just by selling one
course at a time um proved untrue. So
then MOUS did something um which was
surprising to people which they said
well all right why don't we start
offering whole degree programs um how
about instead of taking just one MOO at
a time you'll take eight MOOs and get an
MBA you'll take eight mukes and get a a
data science degree a computer science
degree or something like that um there
were companies that have been doing that
for a long time those companies were
called online program managers um they
are some of the most sort of unreputable
companies in the higher education space
for a few reasons Um, one is they tended
to be pretty secretive. Um, so you would
sign up for an online degree from an
organization and you like think you're
getting this degree from the University
of Chicago, but you like you slowly
realize um that there's a company called
TU or Embinet um or or or Pearson Ebinet
Services or something like that which is
actually providing a bunch of your
educational experiences. Um, the Wall
Street Journal in the last couple of
years has had a bunch of exposees of
boot camps that are branded by state
universities, but they're actually just
run by a company. You know, it's called
like the Oregon computer science boot
camp or whatever, computer programming
boot camp, but nobody who teaches in it
works for the University of Oregon and
things like that. Um, uh, I mean, the
other problem that universities faced
was that, um, like a a key precept of
businesses is that you do not outsource
your core competencies. Um, so if you're
a university and you outsource your
janitorial services, that is a great
idea. If you outsource your accounting
services, that is a great idea. If you
outsource your teaching and learning,
that is a bad idea. The teaching and
learning is the thing that you do as a
university. Um, so uh um I don't know, I
wrote this paper in in 2019 um which
said something like, man, these massive
open online courses, they sure seem to
be behaving like online programs or
they're sort of partnering with these
organizations. You know, part of the
ways that they were compelling to
organizations is that they would go to a
university and say, "We will pay upfront
for the development of these degree
programs, but then for the next 15
years, we'll take 40% 50% 60% of all the
tuition revenue that comes in." um at
the you know in year one that might seem
like a good idea because you didn't
spend any money and you got this new
tuition revenue but like 10 years from
now you're like why am I paying you know
to you Corsera Edex you know 60 50 40%
of all the tuition revenue that's coming
in when like what they're doing is in
some respects not that hard like they're
running a learning management system and
doing some online learning we can figure
out how to do those things um this was a
bit of a controversial paper when I
published it and there was a whole bunch
of people um who said come on Justin,
that's really not fair. You can't you
can't say that mukes are turning into um
online program managers. But then two
years later, Tuyu, who was the largest
online program manager, bought EdX. Um
and uh and even that was a was a
convergence that I wouldn't have
projected. Um so I know um some of you
may know that um all of the proceeds
from um from the sale of Edex went to
this nonprofit controlled by Harvard and
MIT called Axom. Um, so, uh, so, uh, Tu
paid $800 million for edex. Um, and that
$800 million went to start a new
nonprofit. Um, like headlines like this
were kind of funny to me. You know,
Harvard and MIT led nonprofit to tackle
long-standing inequities in education.
Um, but like that's exactly what Edex
was. Um, Edex was a nonprofit designed
to tackle inequities in education. I was
like, well, that didn't work, so we're
starting a new one. Um, and it's like,
you know, like I just like how the big
headline is like, "This is this brand
new thing that we're doing. And by the
way, it's because we sold the last
version of this that we just did. Tiny
font at the bottom." Um, uh, this was
last year's sales price for Edex. Um, or
for TU 2. Um, and, uh, yeah, their stock
has declined 90% over the last five
years. You can sort of see the pandemic
bubble here. People did a bunch of
online learning. Um and then they were
partly they were less enthusiastic about
it but also as universities get better
at offering online learning um they
don't have to partner with groups like
TU anymore. Um this is actually today's
stock quote where it is down
99.36% over the last five years. Um uh
so you know um TU paid for edex like
substantially more than the entire
company of 2U is currently worth today.
Um, I guess I was just looking for like
clarification on like EdX and like MITx
and like Harvard X. Like is that all the
same thing? Like the MITx that we use
now? No. So, well, all right. So,
Harvard and MIT each put $30 million.
Um, they create units called Harvard X
and MITx. Um, those are like sort of
independent brands. The shared
infrastructure that those things used
was this thing called Edex. Um, Edex was
a company. It also created an open
source learning management system called
open edex. So the com the like nonprofit
edex was sold to to you to become part
of a company but there still is an open
source project called edex um which is a
a learning management system software
MITx and if there's still a thing called
Harvard X to some extent in their
products use this thing called open edex
as what they're doing like the
infrastructure but MIT like the content
that we look at when we go on MITx as
students is not owned by this company
uh Uh yes, but although it's sort of
slightly more complicated than that
because I think like I um they
definitely bought the right to display
all or most of maybe they could display
anything that they had instructors
permission to be able to display. Like I
took all of my courses off of Edex um
when it was bought by TU um because
because I don't want to support online
program managers. I don't think they're
good for higher education. Um some
departments did that, things like that.
They still might have some rights to
display some of it, but they still sort
of basically did what they wanted
because if you look at it, a lot of it
and like even open courseware is also
from like 2008 updated years. Yeah.
Which I guess makes sense. Yeah. You
know, and in some ways in theor you know
like like a lot of the argument is that
it shouldn't have to be, right? Like how
you know how much did uh um did did
multivariable calculus change since
2008? Like you know not that much. Um
and part of the way that you gain the
economy of scale is by sort of leaving
these things alone. All right, we'll
come back and I'll sort of finish this
in here except to say that we uh we
tried a whole lot of stuff to develop a
new science of learning and like
probably the main thing that we learned
is that like people who click a lot into
things do better than people who click
less into things. Um which you probably
didn't need a $60 million investment to
be able to figure out. Um but I'll
finish with this next time. Um you'll
turn in your papers by email and we'll
talk a little bit more about uh
intelligent tutors as well um both on
Wednesday and the following Monday. Um
if I can help you at all with paper one
or anything else, let me know.
Otherwise, have a wonderful rest of your
week.