Thank you. Um, it's a pleasure to be
here today with you. I figured I'd start
with a little introduction about my
background and then let Key introduce
himself. But, um, I've been at MIT for
about six years. And this is actually
the first year where my lab is about
half funded by industry. So I hope what
you can get out of the session
especially if you're a corporation
interested in engaging with MIT at
earlier stage as well as at later stage
uh innovation how you can engage and I
think that's something that meets done
really really well. Um so as uh Katarina
mentioned I currently have two startups
that are housed at the engine and one
that is housed in Houston and they're in
very different areas. We have employed
all of the resources that MIT has for
doing startups ranging from Dish Fonde
Center funding to the Delta V uh
accelerator program um as well as uh the
engine resources following spinout. So
uh that's a bit about me. Key would you
tell us a little bit about yourself and
how you've engaged with MIT?
>> Yeah, sure. So hi everybody. Um my name
is Kay Honda. I am the senior vice
president and head of corporate
venturing of limit makers. Um I've been
working for uh energy industries for
about 20 years right now and um
basically right now my role is to access
to the new technologies new business
ideas here in states and look for the
new business opportunities for the uh
the entireitsu group. Um Iditsu is the
basically the energy supplier but more
focused on the oil refining. So we
import crude oil from the different
countries and refining our refineries.
We have uh six group refineries in
Japan, one in Vietnam and supply supply
to the different uh customers uh such as
like airlines um shipping companies or
know industrial players and um I was the
so uh we set up Americas back in 2020
during the covid where we wanted to you
know uh focus more towards creating a
new business from the startups and I was
actually the few members who launched
the uh company started operations there
and I think it was about two three years
ago we started to so we set up a company
in Bay Area San Jose California and then
expanded the footprint to Houston Texas
where there's huge energy hub there in
states and together uh we expanded to
the east coast and we thought that you
know um Boston Cambridge area is a very
much um important place for us to
explore the startup ecosystem. So from
there uh we started to engage with MIT.
We started from uh joining the uh IOP
program as well as uh MIT energy
initiative because we are energy company
and we tried to be one of the you know
players that would um be part of the
like startup ecosystem. So started to
explore the space uh together with MIT.
So that was like a initial you know uh
initiative that we we had made so far.
>> Excellent. Thank you. Um something that
you had mentioned is that you actually
physically expanded to bring folks from
Iditzu to the west coast to Houston and
now to Cambridge. We've interacted with
Shin a lot who is the person who's based
in Cambridge. How do you think having
people in the city where you're trying
to engage with faculty and startups has
impacted your ability to do that?
>> Yeah. So I I believe physical presence
is super important for us. uh because
one uh the talking about the venture
side uh you know uh looking at the
startup ecosystem or um even uh
connecting with the startups it was
pretty new for us um is like a century
old company very you know stable b very
conservative company doing the oil
refining uh so we have to you know break
have a breakthrough to access to the new
technologies by having ourselves here
and actually you know talking with the
entrepreneurs or the faculty is here and
I I think you mentioned about Shing. Uh
Shin is sitting over there. Uh he's
taking care of the R&D side. So I'm on
the venture side, he's in the R&D side
and uh he's exploring the new uh let's
say the joint R&D activities uh with the
different uh universities including MIT
and I guess again sitting together in
you know same room uh on the same table
and then you know discussing what will
be the new opportunities for us together
with the focal entrepreneurs are very
crucial for us to explore this new
field.
>> Thank you. So along with that, what
qualities do you look for? So if there's
a startup in the room or a faculty
member who wants to engage, what what
qualities do you look for in an academic
partner or startup when you're thinking
about collaborating with them?
>> Yeah. So um from my venture perspective,
I guess it depends on what kind of
stages the startups are in. Uh we don't,
you know, restrict ourselves of sticking
to whether it's a early stage or whether
it's a later stage. we have a pretty
much broader uh perspect perspectives of
you know engaging depending on what the
startups which stage they are in. So um
but having that said uh I guess uh we
have been acting with the early stage
startup recently and I guess um the
we uh very much emphasize on what kind
of capabilities do they have what kind
of uniqueness whether it's it will be
like a technology wise perhaps it will
be like IP wise perhaps it will be like
a business model wise those kind of
uniqueness that we as edit don't have uh
is very important for us because that's
the fundamental for us to explore this
new business opportunities.
>> So along with that does it have a focus
area? Are you focused specifically on
the energy space? You mentioned being
members of mighty or is it a broader
interest in the ecosystem?
>> Yeah. Yeah. So uh we define like three
uh focus areas at this point. It's very
broad I would say. Uh one is so it's all
about the disruption. So we need to
think about what will be the disrupted
technologies for our business. Uh that's
because um there's a you know different
teams in our organization where um some
business units do have a new business
development team doing those by
themselves and I guess uh for our role
we have to go beyond that uh meaning
that what will be the disruptive uh
technology of the business would affect
to the current business units. So having
that said uh we focus uh three areas.
One is uh the disruptive uh disruptions
for the the current business. The second
is uh the disruption for the energy
industry as a whole and third is more in
general disruption for like entire
society. So I guess um po Paul in the
you know the previous uh presentation
mentioned about more around AI. AI is
very much you know new for us and I
guess um this is very important topic
for us to explore but to be honest uh we
are very much in a high you know high um
capex intensive oil refining area you
know we are not that good at you you
know uh installing software or perhaps
utilizing AI. So our team might be the
ones that would uh know fill in the gap
between the the conventional uh huge
corporates and installing those thinking
about the insttoring those you know new
types of technologies that would enable
us to be uh much sustainable as a
company.
>> Excellent. Thank you. That's a great
overview of what your interests are. Um
so when you think about the types of
kind of capital inensive tough tech
especially ones that I amu has looked at
um within MIT and within kind of the
startup ecosystem what do you think are
some of the biggest challenges you've
seen for translating that tech to
something that is scalable and
deployable?
>> Yeah. So we have been been seeing you
know um many uh interesting technologies
and I feel to to be honest uh the most
important part is funding I guess
because you know um I see many
entrepreneurs uh some are good but still
some are not that as good as you know uh
you know uh doing a research or perhaps
uh you know uh scaling up the
technologies uh compared with you know
thinking about the fundraising and um
there's A I I think uh in the previous
uh presentation um Michael mentioned
about the the you know difficulties
about the funding as well and uh it's
the reality where you know uh there's a
momentum of uh some of the uh technology
might be uh more attractive in specific
uh timeline whereas someone's some somes
are pretty difficult and I guess um
there's a you know um trends and
momentum that uh you the entrepreneurs
would face the difficulties. Um we you
know I feel uh entrepreneurs have to you
know have a different options to access
to those fundings. uh recently we so
actually we are trying to close one deal
today to invest to one of the startups
and uh I like the the founder and the
CEO of the company because there's a
different reasons but one of them was
she was listing all the you know the
funding options that she could explore
whether it's like a small small amount
whether it's like a larger amount and
you know the larger ones would take time
and then you know um so thinking about
what kind of funding option you should
have uh depending on which stage you
are, it's always you know important to
secure those funding so that the company
would run properly and you can actually
um you know push forward whatever the
strategy you have as a company. So, how
do you think about Idommitsu's role as a
funer um in terms of the timeline of
toughte? Because I do know that's been
kind of a a point of tension where
conventional VC a lot of times wants to
move very quickly and tough tech often
takes a lot longer to develop. So, how
do you balance that?
>> Yeah. Yeah. So um we have been learning
a lot uh by through you know um having
deal flows there and uh for us it there
were so many learnings of how we could
adapt to uh the how you know financial
VCs act in a high-speed way of making
the decisions to invest and um there's
some that we can adopt but but there's
you know in in reality there's there's
some that we cannot adopt and um
thinking about the timeline of so we see
more towards like a strategic way of how
we could commercialize and make the
business rather than just you know
thinking about the financial returns we
go hybrid. Um so in the sense uh we need
to make a you know longerterm
relationship with some of the
entrepreneurs uh that has a great
technology or the business ideas and
from there we think about what will be
like a milestones for let's say uh five
years 10 years uh what kind of challenge
they would face uh in each milestone and
uh what kind of you know uh enablers
they need to overcome those challenges.
So longer term relationship it's perhaps
it's close to what uh R&D side of
thinking um because you know you you
never can you know immediately uh
succeed uh commercializing any uh you
know uh technology the the commercial
plant in let's say one or two years it
takes time
>> thank you um so you've mentioned a few
ways that has interacted especially with
startups what do you think are the uh
most effective ways you found of
interacting with folks at MIT and
spinouts and also just kind of the
Cambridge startup ecosystem.
So I I think uh I haven't reached the
goal yet because uh I have been doing
this for about five years but still it's
five years many you know VCs have been
acting in this space for like 20 30
years and I'm still learning from many
many people surrounded uh here uh you
know many people many faculties or you
know many researchers uh every single
you know comments or the advice is very
you know um
very useful for myself and um I I guess
um for us it's it's important to
interact more with the different people
here and you know uh think about what
will be the a better way for us to
explore this uh ventures venture field
and um yeah um I I think uh going back
to your question in the initial ones so
having us physically in myself in Bay
Area uh Shing in Austin. Uh that was
very important for us because it was
much easier to for us to access to the
different people here. Uh I think
there's a you know I think a startup
because this is a pretty small world and
you might can you know get to know the
person who met in the Bay Area again in
the Boston and that's happening I think
that's happening again and again and so
um having us uh actual presence here and
you know making a progress of whatever
we want to achieve in a detailed
discussion that's uh very important for
us to have at this point. Yeah, I do
have to say from our perspective, it's
been very helpful to have in-person
conversations and I think both our
relationship with Shin on the R&D side
for my group as well as um working with
you through two of our startups has been
so much more helpful to have in-person
conversations and I think that really
does speed a lot of the discussion and
potential collaborations.
um kind of along with that, what do you
think you've learned or taken away from
your interactions at MIT that might be
different from Bay Area?
>> Yeah. So um the huge difference is um
it's obvious that uh this place is very
academia centralized uh meaning that
there is many there's many opportunities
but I feel like more around the funding
uh there's many investors there some
corporates are there if you think about
just energy side um it's not like Boston
it's not like Bay Area it's spread
around around all around states and I I
do understand that Houston has a huge
energy hub but still that's like
conventional uh energy industry there's
some you know startups are coming out
from there but then but the you know
energy startups are very much spread
around the states or even to the Canada
we you know access to the Canadian uh
startups well um so what's the so did I
>> just like what what are the key
takeaways from interacting with Boston
versus Cambridge versus or Boston versus
Bay Area
>> yeah so that um so um having the access
to the different characteristics of the
ecosystem is you know again uh learning
from us uh just having us in a barrier
didn't make sense for us because um
there's no much there are many academ
but still there's no much industrial
connections there um I feel that MIT has
been bringing uh industrials together
with this the entrepreneurs and also
some of the investors together in these
kind of you know conference es. So this
is very useful and helpful for us. Um I
would uh you know look forward to have
this kind of uh same occasions in
different places and that I think that
would also help entrepreneurs to expand
you know uh make su make their uh
business successful in terms of the
growth in terms of in raising the fund
and having the commercial you know
advice or you know the um pilot testing
or whatever the achievement they need to
have at this moment.
>> Thank you. So, you mentioned that there
are a lot of resources in both the Bay
Area and in Cambridge. Um, Houston, it
sounds like the ecosystems not as well
developed. I know Greentown Labs just
opened a site there and um MIT, the
Martin Trust Center, is building some
new collaborations there. But what do
you think is missing there to kind of
build up the equivalent of what we have
here
>> for the energy sector?
Um I I see uh Texas is the place where
many energy related startups doing the
pilot project there uh because they have
uh you know abundant resources you know
they have a uh great access to the
industrial players. So I I think it's
the matter of the different
differentiating the region by region. Uh
I don't think you know Houston needs to
be more like Bay Area where you know
it's it's impossible because Bayer has a
huge history of you know building the
software uh tech companies and that's
the you know attitude that people want
to have there whereas Houston is more
you know more energy spaces. So but you
know um for us uh understanding what is
the characteristics of the each
ecosystem we can leverage from there and
access to uh whoever we want to reach
out to and this is also I believe uh uh
tied to uh some of the startups that you
know uh misses the opportunities how
they could um reach out to the uh the
people that they want to reach out to uh
there's many people who could possibly
you know help them, support them in a
different ways and uh trying to uh
understand where you should head to and
what kind of help you wanted to receive
from the different uh regions and the
different players is very important for
us as well as you know entrepreneur side
as well.
>> Excellent. So along with that there are
probably some entrepreneurs in the room
who are thinking about how to better
engage with companies like Initu. Um,
how do you think a startup can position
themselves the best for a strategic
partnership with Initu or funding or
depending on how they want to interact
with you?
>> Yes. So, um, to be honest, um, we are
like a very, as I mentioned,
conservative oil refining company. uh
and on top of that we really think about
the strategic way of how we could uh
collaborate with the startups. So having
that said, we don't have we don't want
to do like let's say uh do the pilot
testing within two or three weeks. We
don't want to you know make decisions in
very very short term. We look for the
more future opportun opportunities uh 10
years or beyond. Um so in the sense I I
feel like um startups don't have to
adopt everything but still uh there
should
startups might need some kind of the
patience for understanding what the
industrial players what the corporates
thinking and um from the different
discussion uh I talk with one of the
well-known uh entrepreneur who has been
raising you know three-digit million uh
US dollars those fundings in the past.
He's a serious uh entrepreneur uh
working for the energy uh startup and um
he was uh really mentioning about the
importance of you know starting to
engage with the corporates as early as
possible because he knows that the
corporates take time and this is you
know this is the real uh we want to you
know speed up and we want it to be like
a a financial vis but it's uh but you
know um we can partially do but for 100%
we cannot be financial visas we have a
different appetite for here so um I was
very you know um convinced with uh the
the his comments where uh building a
relationship with early as possible with
the corporates that doesn't mean I
that's because I'm working in the
corporates but still you know that's a
reality in the industry and I guess um
not only about the funding but also the
engagement or perhaps even the small
miscellaneous is you know um you know um
takeaways from the corporates whatever
you want to build whatever you want to
you know um achieve uh through your uh
entrepreneurship you might can have uh
you know um different understandings
different find out from the uh corporate
side as well
>> yeah I do have to say that's been really
beneficial to us um our startups have
heavily relied on non-dilutive funding
especially government uh grants and
having it as a strategic partner on
those applications even just as a
potential customer down the line um
definitely adds a lot of value that's
not necessarily just investment right so
I think um thinking of ways of exploring
collaboration beyond simply just
partnerships for investing is a great
way to interact uh right
>> yeah um so you've interacted with a lot
of startups at this point. Um, do you
have an example of one that has kind of
exceeded your expectations or gone
beyond what you were originally hoping
for? And what what was the story there
and why do you think it exceeded?
>> Um, so I might would touch on uh your
startup. So we just started you know our
discussion. So it's in a very early
stage right now. Um so you might can you
know introduce some of your what you're
working for but um it has a so we are
oil refer we are energy supplier but we
do some agricultural business as well
and uh we do pesticidized fertilizer
side and uh actually uh I think um 70
more than 70 70% of the uh rice uh made
in California we supply the herbicide
for them so we are pretty much uh have a
good presence in states as
And um
I think initial you know interaction was
with you and Shing I guess uh talking
about the joint R&D uh around your
research area where uh you you mentioned
you are trying to launch the new startup
uh focusing on uh having a new
technology that would u enhance um micro
activities for the past installed to the
pesticides that resale. So that was kind
of like a you know um I would say a
quick win for us because we do have a
business units uh acting in states and
also uh the new technology might would
fit to whatever we sell and would make a
new additional value to our products and
um we so but again it's only at the
early stage so we need to you know go
through what will be like a good way to
pilot this testing and what will be the
uh way to value this uh new additional
value here. And so you know there's many
things we need to go through there but
still um in the past we didn't have much
uh discussion to be honest myself and
our team in the venture team we didn't
have much uh discussion with the uh
conventional business units because they
are too much busy you know focusing on
let's say running the refineries or
selling oil products. So um having the
new solution was you know uh not that
you know beneficial for us but uh having
this new technology adopting to the our
product was like kind of like you know
uh quick solution for us to explore and
you might can introduce.
>> Yeah um thank you for that. So um the
company that K's talking about is Seiya
Bio. We have a stabilization technology
that allows you to manufacture microbes
at scale that we couldn't before. And
we're initially targeting uh
regenerative agricultures using microbes
in place of or to enhance uh
agrochemicals. Uh we've actually been a
company for about three years now, but
we've mostly been running on
non-dilutive funding. And I think
something that was interesting and some
of the learnings we took away with that
are important, the importance of
corporate partnerships that don't
necessarily involve investment. So
because it's a very um kind of
straightforward and lowcost technology,
we haven't uh seen the benefit of taking
VC money and kind of going with a
conventional um VC funded startup model.
So what we needed were proof that people
would buy our products once we made
them. And so, um, you know, interactions
with Idomitsu and, um, figuring out how
we can partner with these companies in
ways that don't involve strictly just
funding, um, I think has really
benefited us as well. And, um, it's been
interesting to, um, have one startup
that's focused on kind of that and then
another one that's more on, um,
decarbonizing steel that definitely
needs the capex of a conventional VC.
Um, so I do want to make sure we leave
time for questions. We'll do a couple
more at the end, but um it would be
great if we could take some audience
questions now.
>> Who has questions for our speakers?
Okay.
Thank you.
Um great talk. Um I have a question
about um two of you. Um so how do you
define the success of the partnership
because uh for the corporation's
perspective of course the sensing and
the disruption is really really really
critical but um you must have the time
frame right in next three years to five
years 10 years. So how do you define the
success from this partnership? Because
of course MIT is a great partner and
vehicle to get this access to variety of
um technologies and cutting edge ideas
and all and also the startups but not
only the funding probably there must be
something um Mr. Honda wants to achieve
in certain time frame that requires to
achieve uh the strategic goal and also
from the MIT point of view. um you know
matching the corporations
you may have that expectation okay this
corporation can also lead the
commercialization
uh strategy also access to the potential
customers and provide references but
that's not enough to
get the company really going and also
achieve certain I don't know financial
returns or strategic value which is
quite
vague. So my question going back to the
definition of success and which time
frame
>> and how MIT is expecting to help them
achieve.
>> All right. Um yeah that that's a really
really good question and uh it's very
difficult for us to define the the
success. I would say it it will be uh
the same wording what we call like
strategic return from engagement with
the startups and uh every time it
depends on which deal we see uh some of
the early stage startup it takes time if
it's more like like like capex intensive
uh energy startups it doesn't happen
within like five 10 years you have to
have you know resiliency there and we
have to support them and try to build uh
make them successful and you know uh
eventually we want to have actual
commercialized business together with
them. But you know at the same time uh
if you think about uh the people working
in the corporate side uh they cannot
wait for like 10 years they want to you
know achieve something within that time
frame. So we are setting like a key
milestones uh what can we achieve within
those you know let's say the pilot
testing some of the knowledge that we
can you know u acquire from those stages
we might can you know not IP wise but
more around the general wise we can
adapt to the different perhaps the
research areas or perhaps to the um
thinking about the collaboration with
the different startups or different
corporates. So um in general we set uh
some kind of the KPIs and key milestones
when engaging with the startups but it
really depends on what kind of you know
uh startup we are dealing with and uh I
I guess most of them are more like you
know um occur in the information what
kind of uh proof that we can build from
those technologies and how we could be
uh supporting those startups. So not
100% for us but for like you know uh
together us and the entrepreneurs the
startups that might be one of the ways
we think of the strategic return that we
engage with the startups
>> and I will say not as much from the MIT
side but as a PI um one of kind of our
milestones is building a long-term
relationship with these companies. Not
every um project is going to be funded
by a company, but I think we've
established some fantastic
collaborations with initu especially
getting access to samples that can be
challenging for academics. So,
especially as we think about scaling
tech in um you know oil and gas if
you're thinking about reducing emissions
or kind of um reusing waste products,
academics getting access to those can be
really challenging. And so building a
core relationship where we know we can
go to IDM2 and ask them for samples and
they're willing to provide them to us
and then likewise when they have a new
problem that pops up they'll come to us
to try to seek a solution. We want to
have that relationship and establishing
that um I think kind of comfort level
with each other is really where we see
success.
>> Thank you.
other questions.
>> Okay. So, if there aren't other
questions, I just have one more question
for Kay, which is um we've touched on a
lot of different areas and hopefully
everyone will stick around for uh
networking after this, but um
>> is there anything we haven't touched on
that you think would be important for
folks to know either about Idomitsu
specifically and how they interact with
MIT and startups or more generally about
your experience?
>> Yes. So, um
let's see. Um
I I I think um again um
we have been feeling very beneficial
having ourselves here uh as well as
having ourselves in different areas in
Houston in you know uh Bay Area and I
see many uh resources that we can rely
on. um every time I feel uh I discuss
with the other folks in the team that
you know there's plenty of resources
that we can utilize but the question
will be how we access to those resources
the informations the people that we
wanted to interact with and I guess I'm
not promoting IOP
has been you know helping us to you know
connect to the different faculties in
MIT different startups in MIT so that's
very crucial uh but uh at the same time
uh for us uh it's more important to you
know generate those connections and how
we expand the connections to the
different people. uh even I'm based in
San Jose, I can access the people in
Boston and as I mentioned it's a very
small world. So how we could cover all
the connections that we want to reach
out to and know you know um it's it's
it's uh it's my role to you know uh make
the connections as well as how we can
speed up uh trying to reach out to the
right resources the appropriate people
that we want to reach out to. That's
that's uh you know very important
takeaways I have been facing within this
few years.
>> Thank you. And I have to say I agree um
startup exchange through ILP has been
invaluable for my lab and companies that
we've started to interact with potential
partners and funders. So thank you
Katarina. Um and thank you all for um
being here and hopefully we can talk
some more if there are questions you
have offline um after this. And um thank
you K for having this fireside chat with
me.
>> Thank you so much.