A lot of the industries, a lot of
households, neighborhoods, cities, even
countries are shifting to deploying more
renewable energy within their grid. And
with that, we definitely need a proper
energy storage system.
[Music]
I'm researching lithium ion batteries,
specifically the recycling and
rejuvenation process. After we use the
lithium ion batteries, they usually
reach something called the end of life.
In industry terms, it's defined as
reaching the 80% of its original
capacity. When the battery goes to that
stage, what we can do with it is either
throw it away or recycle it. There's
different methods to do lithium ion
battery recycling. One, the option is to
open this battery and check the valuable
materials in it and make sure that we
are able to reuse them. And this is
known as the recycling method. Two, it
could be rejuvenation, which is
basically trying to add more electrolyte
to see if this would improve the
battery's performance in the least
invasive way possible for the battery. I
decided to start working in the energy
field because of where I'm from and
because of all the energy crisis that
we've passed through. I'm from Lebanon.
We had the huge time of power cuts and
then a lot of people started actually
purchasing solar panels and installing
them on the roofs. with that you need to
back it up with an energy storage system
and that means batteries. And it was a
challenging time because a lot of people
just wanted to do that because they
wanted more electricity because they
would only had 30 minutes to like
maximum of like 3 4 hours a day of power
coming directly from the grid which was
not enough definitely for people's
everyday uses. That sparked my interest
in actually learning more about it. I
hope that my research will have um a lot
of impact on the world and on this
community around me. So hopefully we get
to an answer or at least part of an
answer sometime soon.