okay this uh lecture is uh applies to
every Matrix and it comes really near
the beginning of linear algebra uh
elimination is the the powerful way to
make the Matrix simpler get a lot of
zeros in it is what is actually achieved
by
elimination uh but then it's a little
question what have I done what how do I
describe the answer and I think
factorizations which you'll see are the
fundamental theme in linear algebra or
give a great uh description of
elimination you can see what you've done
and this
factorization
uh takes any Matrix a any rectangular
Matrix Square rectangular and finds a
column Matrix and a row Matrix that
multiplies so it's maybe the first of
our six factorizations that really
organize the linear algebra course so
ready to start on this so elimination is
familiar but this fact factorization is
more is newer okay uh so I'm going to
take an example there is a matrix a 3x4
pretty arbitrary
Matrix um so uh and I want to do
elimination to it let me just describe
elimination how it would start in words
I would say I want to turn that three
into a zero so I take three * Row one
and subra ract from row two and that
gives me a zero there and it gives me
something else and I take four times Row
one from Row three and that gives me a
zero I think yeah uh the that this is
the process that you repeat multiples
and and the subtractions can go upwards
here I can I could after I've taken
three of these away from row two I have
a new row two I can take some multiple
of that row two away from Row
one and produce that
zero I I don't plan to discuss all the
horrible details of elimination right
here just this but I'll tell you the
operations and for this Matrix I end up
with that Matrix that this is what
elimination goes to if we go the whole
way we get a couple of columns so how do
I how do I under understand this Matrix
Z which came from a well let's see if I
look at the rows I see two nonzero rows
and that that turns out they turn out to
be a basis for the row space the
combinations of those two rows give me
any all of the three rows of a and
notice that there's a zero row so the
rank is only two for this Matrix this
Matrix has only two uh nonzero rows in
when it after at the end of elimination
and so so there are bases for the row
space which is
two-dimensional and the columns the
first two so the first two columns here
are that's the destination that's the
goal of elimination to get these ones
and zeros so they tell us that these two
columns were and we'll call those those
those are the First Independent columns
these columns are independent of the
previous ones but the last two columns
are combinations of the first two so the
column space of this Matrix is the same
as the column space is sorry has the
same
same basis the same we we learn about
the column space of this Matrix from the
column space of this one so that's point
two The Columns of
a these first two columns are a basis
for the column space of a because they
became clearly the basis when we went to
Z and finally the null space if we want
to solve
axal 0 we this makes us this moves us to
solving ZX equals 0 that null space is
null meaning zero and that that on the
right hand side so to solve ZX equals
zero uh is easy as and we'll do it in a
minute and that will be the same
Solutions as ax equals z so that's
that's what elimination it chieves the
uh these sub these subspaces have move
in a simple one simple form or connected
in a nice way from A to Z okay ready for
the next slide yeah all right and I make
it
happen oh okay and now my new point is
to see that elimination process which is
has been taught in linear algebra for
quite a long time I want to see it this
step from the a that we started with to
the elimination Matrix that we ended
with tells me that this original Matrix
factors into a column Matrix times a row
Matrix C time R that's a that'll be then
the first factorization in the linear
algebra textbook it comes
first and then the great factorizations
of linear algebra like igen values and
singular values are build out of this so
but this is a factorization every Matrix
a factors by doing that elimination into
uh the column Matrix it has two
independent columns just as a has and it
has two independent rows just as a has
and what does that tell us that tells us
the two two equaling two there that the
column Rank and the row rank are the
same which is really the first wonderful
fact in linear algebra that if I take
any Matrix and if you just glance at
that you can't see how many rows are
independent how many columns are
independent but the number is two in
both cases always equal okay now I have
to
explain use Matrix notation to say what
that R Matrix is okay so I start with a
and I'm all I'll always use little r for
the rank the number of independent
columns and you remember that those go
into C so I'm just able to tell you what
the r factor
is so that's the maybe the a
key idea here that it's not not usually
in textbooks what is that R well it
starts with the identity Matrix and then
it has a matrix F that that accounts for
the dependent columns so the identity
Matrix is sitting in the in the columns
that are independent in a the first the
first uh uh L R
columns independent columns and then the
F
Matrix so the F Matrix the matrices
there are dependent on the columns in C
and that tells us that they're
combinations so so what's what's there
is uh those those columns of of the
Matrix a have the form C * F so f is the
Matrix that makes this correct and
annoyingly
there we may need to re reorder The
Columns because in my nice example the
independent columns came first columns
one and two but I could if I move those
off to the right then I need to get them
back to the left again for my nice
picture and it's that permutation P that
does it don't pay a lot of attention to
P here's the important part the the
independent columns and then The Matrix
that tells us how to get the dependent
columns from the Independent columns by
multiplying by F okay so that's the
that's the factorization and now I want
to use it oh I I did an example that
involves P that requires a permutation
yeah it's a good example to look at so
there's our original Matrix a and if I
look for the independent columns well
column one is great okay column two is
not so great because it's dependent it's
just two * column 1 nothing new in
column two so that's a dependent column
and then column three we do have an
independent column so the two
independent columns go into C and that's
the Matrix that multiplies R and you you
see how a permutation May in this form
the
identity is over over on the fully on
the left side that this has columns one
and two as special but it's the
permutation then that makes columns one
and put puts them into columns one and
three which are really the special
independent columns for a that and that
okay so that's just a word about p and
from now on I'll try to forget there
there might be a p Matrix okay if
essential
information what what does elimination
accomplish after all these thousands of
years that was vented in China uh more
than 2,000 years ago the the information
it is it tells us which columns are
independent then there in the identity
Matrix shows up in those columns and it
also tells us the Matrix the how the
dependent ones come from the IND dep
dependent ones you multiply C by some
Matrix F which elimination finds so
elimination finds all these matrices as
we saw in that example and now I want to
use that to see what that Matrix right
down here with with a slide or two uh
just exactly what steps of elimination
are are allowed so elimination has three
simple steps and all of them are rever
reversible uh like exchange two rows
because if I had a zero on the top left
corner I wouldn't want that so I would
do a row exchange I I divide I can
divide a row by a number if I had a two
in the top left corner I'd rather have a
one so I just divide that row by two and
this is the main step to subtract a
multiple of one row from another row
that doesn't change the row space just
changes the the rows themselves but
their combinations have not changed all
these uh three three steps are
reversible if I exchange two rows I
could exchange them again and I'd be
back to where I started if I divide by
seven then I could multiply by seven or
divide by
17th uh so so this is what
is
always if you get this topic in a linear
algebra course this is the Matrix that
you get to and what I want to do is
understand that
Matrix uh as coming as entering a
factorization of a so I can use
elimination this is so that but that's
the picture of what I get as we saw all
right so so that's this is the key fact
we're we're sort of like ending the work
of
elimination it can get it'll find out
how many independent columns there are
how many independent rows and that
numberb is the same because we're
looking at the identity Matrix and then
we we see how this is the simplification
of the of the Matrix a okay so what can
we do what do we learn from that oh so I
I I put in a few slides just to say how
would you code
elimination uh and it's really neat it's
so it's how how does elimination work
well column by column so suppose we've
got K columns done and we're ready for
the next one like we may have seven
columns taken care of we're ready for
column eight so this is what column 7
looks like because it's that same if
f0000 P picture it's those seven columns
are finished and now here's one and I
let U be the upper part upper half and L
be the lower half U is the half that's
or the part that's that's of the new
column that's that goes up at the top
and even with the zeros goes l
so what what do we do in what does
elimination do with this next column so
I'm describing elimination again in a
way you would code it uh I come to the
new column all right and I want to know
I'm I want something a picture like this
with K moved up to k +
one okay it's a lot to give you the all
the details of elimination but there
there everybody catches on to them by
doing a few either on a computer or or
by hand okay so our question is this is
I want a picture like this after one
with one more column in it and the
question is is this new column going to
feed into the identity well if if L is
the zero Vector if if it's all if it's
all zeros below the pivot then uh then
this U will go along with f because we
we're not getting anything new the we
still have K nonzero rows so at this
point we have K nonzero rows or or let's
say whatever number we whatever number
we have and if L is zero then the new
column is dependent on the old columns
and doesn't add anything new uh so so if
again I'll just repeat if L is the zero
Vector if I'm all zeros here then that
will go in with f if it's not all zeros
there then I then I'm going to do some
row exchanges and some pivot steps uh I
can I what I can do is clear out all of
L except for one non zero that'll be the
new pivot maybe the next I hope hope the
next
uh so if L is all Zer the new column is
joins with f if L is not all zero the
new column is independent so we we've
hit another independent column and we uh
do
elimination on that column to to get it
into the right form to be ready for
column the column K plus 2 is coming
next I I don't you the way to learn the
steps of elimination is to is to do them
on a few matrices and I won't do more
here okay so just but but I want you to
know what is elimination telling us so
the result of elimination tells us which
are the First Independent columns
they're the ones that end up with a one
with the identity Matrix there's and
they're the and those first
columns back in a are The Columns of C
the row space is not change those
operations of elimination don't change
the row space but but they give us a
nice picture so
so so the th this thing is this slide is
really telling us that the result of
elimination is the identity Matrix the C
Matrix
and zeros in in the low in the lower
rows we can see how many rows are
independent by how many the the nonzero
rows are all independent because they
that identity is is makes that so so
that's that's where we are uh at the end
of
elimination we have little r the rank
then the the the dimension of of the row
space the dimension of the column space
is little r and we can
see the basis for it in C and then we
also have that Matrix F so we got to C
and F and elimination
finished by giving us a picture of the
original Matrix much simplified lots of
zeros okay oh all right and let's just
apply it so here we go you this is the
payoff do you rem remember our Matrix
that had 13 27 that was my example at
the very beginning but it had some
combination of those two rows so this
third row I've just forgotten because it
turned out to be a combination of these
and and gave us a row of zeros so these
are the two equations in axal 0 we're
looking for the n space this is what
elimination is tells us how what how to
do it's a step to simplify the equations
from that messy looking two two
equations to this simple pair of
equations where the one and the one are
in columns one and two and and nice
numbers and the point is you can solve
those without taking a linear out of a
course but still take the course okay so
I'm looking for solutions to that okay
so I could find a solution if I said X3
to be one and X4 to be zero so X4 is
zero that's gone X3 is 1 so X1 + 3 = 0
X2 + 4 = 0 so X1 and X2 are Min -3 and
-4 and there's the one and the zero did
you see that we produce that solution
just by I it jumps out and let's see how
the next one jumps out so we suppose we
take those equations those are the
simple form of this horrible horrible
pair we got that we got it to a very
simple form and now I want to know
another solution and another different
certainly different one will be to set
X3 equals z so that's gone
X4 equal to 1 so that's five and six and
then I need X1 to be minus 5 and X2 to
be minus 6 to cancel a five and six
golden solution Simple Solution complete
so I've got two solutions to ax equals z
and the null space has the right
Dimension two and I found a basis for
that space and all other Solutions are
combinations of these Simple Solutions
The Simple Solutions have zeros and ones
in the dependent
columns I hope you can just see that
after elimination when we get to a
simple form like that it becomes a
picnic to solve it the equations are
easily solved just let X3 = 1 and X4
equal 0 and you get an answer let X3
equal 0 and X4 equal 1 you get another
answer so so that was that's the point
of elimination it's good to make the
what was the point of learning this
process or coding up this process it's
not I have to admit that it's not uh um
the most super efficient way to find the
solution uh because it involves
subtraction of rows of from rows
above and as well as subtraction from
rows below so it could be speed it
up uh and it usually is for for square
invertible
matrices for let let me ask you this
question if I had a square 4x4
invertible Matrix what would over here
what would be the the uh reduced form
after I do elimination
well it would just be identity identity
the identity Matrix if if I had a 4X for
if I have an invertible Matrix
elimination produces the identity Matrix
so it really goes all the way to
simplifying The Matrix and and you pay a
little price if if to get all the way to
the identity Matrix but to see the
theory it's it's a right thing to do we
won't do we wouldn't actually do it we
would stop at a triangular Matrix and
start solving from that point if we had
to pay for the for the for the computer
time all right and now here I've written
in with Matrix notation what that last
slide showed you and again what that
last slide showed you is that once you
have it have completed elimination it's
a cinch to solve a x equals z yeah so so
we we elimination puts a into that form
and then the solutions X are in this
form and If I multiply that by that I
get
zero so The Columns of X solve ax equals
z I have found the null
space I've computed the n space and
uh what I wanted to do was to show that
elimination does its job makes it simple
it makes the null space jump out you
just need the F it comes from
elimination the possible
permutations and you've got the answer
you've got the the x is that solve ax
equals z okay again uh it's not the the
code that's used all the time in in
Computing problems in physics or
engineering but it's for math it
elimination completed elimination as
we've done really gets you to the point
where you can read off the answer
okay so that's the point really is to
see how far elimination gets
you okay oh here so here's the comment
that I have just been making what the
method that we pushed all the way to get
the identity Matrix is not as efficient
as
gaus gaus the greatest mathematician of
all time he uh knew he knew enough to
stop when the Matrix was
triangular instead of getting to a
matrix that's could could well be
diagonal uh he doesn't do the
subtractions from upper rows he just
goes from subtracts multiples of a row
from lower rows and that makes the
Matrix triangular and then solving is
easy so just want you to and that's the
the the oper the steps that you really
everybody learns in linear algebra
elimination from The Matrix from a
square Matrix to a triangular one and
then solution is a
cinch okay
all right I'm near the end I just want
to
express what I did in Matrix notation
actually that's sort of the fundamental
idea of this of this uh lecture that I'm
sort of extra lecture on
elimination um is to see what's
happening in Matrix language we know if
you take the course and you grind
through a few examples of elimination
then you know the steps my this lecture
is about sit back don't panic with each
step but what's the big picture and the
big picture is that you started with a
matrix like this so you see it's a it's
a matrix with
submatrices so this the rank this this
Matrix W here is the is square and it's
full its rank is it's got if if there if
the whole Matrix a has R independent
columns and R independent rows then we
move them into this
position
W so so I want to start elimination
again you'll see I'll get it in one
quick line I want to start think about
elimination but let me suppose that I'm
starting with a matrix like my
example that that has a a square
invertible Matrix there and what does
elimination
do what does el well we know that this
is the result so this is what goes in
and this is what goes out just 2 by two
block matrices I call them a block
Matrix because these are blocks of
numbers not just single numbers of
course to understand the picture quite
good to take just single numbers we
might have the numbers 3 7 6 11
something like that and what does it
reduce to okay and the point is
elimination we we have we get the
identity
Matrix W goes to the identity
Matrix so elimination is really
inverting finding the inverse of w that
that's what elimination is doing
and that was my goal to find out what
the heck is elimination doing as I take
all these steps it's what it's doing is
it's finding it's it's inverting that
Matrix W but of course it's operating on
whole
rows
so it it some some the subtractions from
down here leave
zeros and the and the steps up here
multiply the W by its inverse to the the
identity this is what we recognize
that's the r Matrix after elimination
it's got if if there are if there are
dependent rows they turn into zero rows
the independent columns turn into start
with the identity after elimination
that's the whole point that's the point
of elimination to get from a general
Matrix to that kind of a matrix okay and
that's what it does that's the row
reduced Echelon
form that that elimination does so
that's really this is the simplest
explanation I could give now you might
say wait a minute this is assuming that
W up in that left corner is a nice
Square invertible full rank Matrix then
then we go here suppose it isn't suppose
I have a zero up in the top left corner
or something like that then what what
what do I do well I do some row
exchanges to get and maybe some column
exchanges to to get to to this W to get
to this
invertible uh block pivot you could you
could call it which which turns into ey
so I have to so the next slide will show
you the the possible steps I may have to
use some permutation some reordering of
the rows you got to be up for those it
can have a reordering of the columns and
that will get it into the position into
what we want that gets it into what we
want and then elimination gets us where
we really want okay so so this is a this
is we're at the end now this is the
picture of elimination where written in
its simplest Matrix form I I do
permutations of rows I reorder the rows
and the columns to get the first columns
and the first rows to be
independent and that that means that
they have a r by R Matrix W that's
invertible then H and J or whatever they
are but then then the next step of
elimination
the two jobs of elimination are get
things in the right order and get zeros
produce zeros so here I'm supposing that
I get them in the right order there and
then I produce the zeros there and also
produce a bunch of zeros in that
identity Matrix and this is the F this
is our friend F which we're giving we're
shining a light in this lecture on this
Matrix F that that got really ignored
for a thousand years so there you go I'm
not sure if were through for I I feel
I'm through I've see it says 14 of 16 so
there must be some brilliant ideas on
the last last things so interesting
point the question is where is that W
that Matrix of of um that invertible R
byr Matrix that that is the basis for
elimination that W up in the corner and
and the theorem is that if I find R
independent rows which there are in the
row
space if i cho if I find our independent
columns so suppose the rows are in a row
in a matrix B with r rows the columns
are in a matrix c as before with r
independent columns then where B meets C
can you see this on my so B is coming
along as independent rows C is our
independent columns and where they
meet I claim is an R byr Matrix that's
invertible indep it has independent rows
in independent columns so for me this
was the real math uh principle that that
wasn't so I wasn't so sure about but but
it works okay oh oh just to tell you uh
that the paper is in a journal called
mathematics magazine it's almost
published as I make this recording uh
it's the mass Association of America and
then there's also a website that has a
lot of math
papers put put in there before
publication and they have some crazy
long number to identify them but
it's this is the linear algebra textbook
that that uses this lecture actually
this lecture is not in the textbook it's
uh separate
because
the I didn't want to fill the textbook
by this complicated thing
where the idea is
simple where you you simplify your
Matrix a by elimination and then you can
read off all four
subspaces and all four fundamental
subspaces and the idea is to say what is
elimination actually doing to to put in
a little more of the details which are
in this talk but not appropriate for uh
to necessarily to go into the textbook
so there I there it is
um uh the paper that that takes these
steps is in a journal that many
libraries will uh take well thanks for
patience with this uh unusual step I
didn't know it was going to happen but
it just I was never happy with with
elimination without having a matrix
description what happens with the Matrix
pieces of the of my overall Matrix a and
that's what this lecture was about so
thanks for joining and uh best wishes in
linear algebra it's a beautiful subject
thanks