Hello, and welcome.
I'm Martha Broad.
I'm the Executive Director
of the MIT Energy Initiative.
And we are really happy
to have everyone here.
We're going to have
an amazing lineup.
We have a two-part
presentation tonight.
And we're going to start out
with this report and the authors
who are going to share with us
where we are with fusion energy.
And they've spent a
good amount of time
over the past year or
two working on this.
Then, we will follow
that with presentations
from the Plasma Science
and Fusion Center
faculty and researchers about
their exciting current research
into this promising technology.
And to get us started,
it is my pleasure
to introduce MIT
Professor Anne White.
She is the Vice Provost
and Associate Vice
President of Research
and Administration
and the School of Engineering
Distinguished Professor
of Engineering at MIT.
Welcome, Anne.
[APPLAUSE]
Well, thank you, Martha, for
the kind, kind introduction.
And thank you all
for being here.
It's a real pleasure
to have been
asked to say just a
few words and offer you
a brief introduction to the
potential of harnessing fusion
energy.
Fusion energy is an extremely
attractive energy source.
It's abundant.
It's clean.
It's safe.
We're going to combine light
nuclei to form heavier nuclei,
releasing energy according
to Einstein's famous formula,
E equals MC squared.
Now, we're going to do this
with some hydrogen isotopes,
deuterium and tritium.
We're also going to need some
lithium in our fuel cycle,
at least in the most likely
near-term fuel cycle.
And thankfully, the
deuterium and lithium
are pretty available.
And the tritium can be produced.
So fusion power plants will
not produce any carbon dioxide
directly, no direct
greenhouse gases.
Fusion is also inherently safe.
There are minimal proliferation
risks, minimal land and water
use, and no energy
storage issue.
So is this sounding
too good to be true?
Yeah.
Thankfully, it's not.
The great news is,
fusion on the grid
is a lot closer than you think.
And I'm not going to steal
the next speaker, Professor
Armstrong's thunder,
telling you why
now is the moment for fusion.
But I will just reiterate--
the potential and the
promise of fusion energy
to completely
transform our approach
to climate change,
mitigation, and adaptation
is really tremendous.
And that promise means that
getting fusion on the grid
is both an intellectual and
scientific grand challenge,
and also a true
societal call to action.
And in that sense, the work that
MIT has done on fusion, for many
of the speakers
that you're going
to hear from today and also
many others who are not here
in the room today, represents
the kind of ambitious impact
and solutions-oriented
work and collaboration
with external
stakeholders that will
be the focus of the new
climate project at MIT.
And MIT is a special place,
both for Fusion energy research
and climate action.
MIT has that special
sauce of entrepreneurship,
including in the
areas of deep tech.
We have a culture
of problem solving,
of always trying to lower
the barriers to collaboration
across disciplines,
and a history, also,
of mobilizing very large
sections of our MIT community
around these hard problems--
and not just
ourselves on campus--
but, of course, we
have the breadth
of our partnerships
as a strength
as well, working with
cities, with states,
with communities in the area
of climate and infrastructure
planning and policy.
And we work with
national governments
on developing, testing, and
evaluation of new policy tools.
This diversity of partners is
essential for making progress
on the climate challenge.
And we, of course, also
have a global reach
and a global network as well,
working with other universities,
governments, companies and
nonprofits around the world,
especially in places who
need climate solutions now
more than ever, not tomorrow.
So I truly hope that you enjoy
this very exciting event,
learning more about the
transformational potential
of fusion energy.
And you're really in for
a treat because you're
going to be hearing from some
of the absolute top researchers
in this field, and also some of
the most wonderful folks I know
and have the pleasure of working
with at the Plasma Science
and Fusion Center here at MIT.
So thanks very much.
And I'll turn it over
to Professor Armstrong.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you very much,
Professor White.
So in this study, as
Professor White mentioned,
MIT is a great place
for collaboration
across disciplinary boundaries.
The study that
we're going to dive
into here in the first
half of this program
brought together some
30 different researchers
from many different
disciplines, ranging
from nuclear science
and engineering,
to economics, to policy.
And I think that interaction
is typical of studies
we've done at MITEI in
other parts of campus,
where those different
perspectives are just
essential to develop the
kind of insights we're after
and how to move forward
as fast as we can.
As Professor White mentioned,
fusion has long captured
the imaginations of many who
are interested in 0-carbon
or emissions-free energy.
With more than 40 startups today
and more than 100 government
projects in the
fusion area, there's
never been as much momentum
and enthusiasm for the role
that fusion might play in
the future energy systems.
Two characteristics make
fusion particularly well suited
for the future energy system.
One is that you get
carbon-free, firm power.
By "firm," I mean that
whenever you need the power,
it's there in the
amounts that you need.
That's not only essential
for future energy systems,
it's not easy to find
carbon-free or emissions-free
firm energy sources.
Nuclear fission is another
contender in that space.
There are some other contenders
that aren't demonstrated yet.
But fusion is one that's
particularly attractive
because in addition to the
characteristics of firm
power, zero emissions, it's
also energy dense and scalable.
So it has the potential to
transform this system globally
as we move to a net-zero
emissions future.
So this is the time
to understand just
how fusion could impact
future energy systems,
what the scale of
that impact could be,
and how it might
play out globally.
And that's what we
look at in this study.
Among other things that
we looked at in the study,
we looked at how fusion will
compliment and coexist with
other low-carbon technologies--
intermittent technologies, like
solar and wind; a deployment
scale and global distribution
of fusion as we move forward;
a sensitivity of fusion's
penetration to the system
to cost; a sensitivity
to emissions constraints
as governments start
to ratchet down
the allowed emissions
in our economy;
sensitivity to renewable
resources, regionally,
around the world; and
critical materials and supply
chains for implementing
fusion at large scale.
So not only can
this understanding
be helpful for strategic
planners and policymakers,
but also for those involved
in fusion commercialization
because the study
set allows us to look
at economic targets for the
use of fusion and electricity
markets.
So this helps better
quantify for developers
of fusion technology,
people doing
cutting edge research, what
the target pricing needs to be,
what availability, and what
load following these fusion
plants in the future need
to be able to achieve.
So to dive into the study, I'd
like to turn the program over
to Randy Field.
He is the Director
of Research at MITEI.
And he also was
Executive Director
of this study, which
means he is largely
responsible for the great
results that you see here.
Randy?
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you very much, Professor
Armstrong and Professor White.
And I'd like to
thank all of you here
today who are attending
this MIT event.
Before I discuss the
fusion study itself,
I will take the opportunity to
give you a very basic overview
of fusion.
As Professor White
said, basically, fusion
is the fusing of two nuclei.
And in doing so, you
produce a tremendous amount
of energy, well over a million
times the amount of energy
from burning a fossil fuel.
And as already stated by both
Professor White and Professor
Armstrong, the beauty
of fusion energy
it does not generate
greenhouse gases.
It has a very high
energy density,
a very small amount of land
required for such a power plant.
And yet, to enable fusion
to be deployed at scale,
we have to have a
means by which we
can produce the very
high temperatures
and bring the fuels, the fusion
fuel together in confinement
in order to allow
them to fuse together.
And there are various categories
of confinement technology.
One method is known as
"magnetic confinement,"
where you use very strong
magnetic fields to enable
the fuel ions to be confined and
to be in close contact with each
other and away from the
walls of the reactor.
Another method is called
"inertial confinement,"
where you use lasers or
projectiles to rapidly compress
a fuel capsule in order to
achieve very high temperatures
in confinement.
And the third method for--
the third category
for confinement
is known as magneto-inertial
confinement,
which is really a combination
of the two prior methods.
These confinement methods have
been successfully demonstrated
in experiments.
And fusion has been achieved.
However, the challenge is really
in the engineering, the material
science, and in the economics.
Commercial success
of fusion requires
that we build an
economically-viable device
to handle the very
high temperatures
and the high-energy particles
that are released by fusion,
and also have the ability to
convert the released energy
into electricity.
Each fuel type and
each confinement method
has its own set of
engineering challenges
and innovative solutions.
As Professor Armstrong stated,
given the great potential
of fusion, it deserves
a close examination
to understand how fusion power
could transform the electricity
generation systems
in the decades ahead.
We started this project
in the fall of 2022.
And we organized the analysis
along four major work streams.
One of those examining
the global deployment
of fusion power plants in
all regions of the world
out to the end of the century.
And the second workstream was
examining the subregional grid
scale at the grid
scale to understand
how fusion would fit in
with the generation mix
when there are different
types of resources
available in different
parts of the regions.
We also assessed what
the critical materials
are in manufactured
components that
are needed to enable the build
out of the fusion power plant
fleet and to understand
what the bottlenecks could
be in that build out.
And lastly, we took a close look
at the cost drivers for a fusion
power plant to understand
what those cost drivers are
and how they could be addressed.
I also want to point out this
study is intentionally not
making predictions about
when fusion will be deployed
at a commercial scale.
And we're not identifying which
fusion technology will be first
or what it will cost.
But we are instead conducting
a scenario analysis
and a sensitivity
analysis to understand
the conditions at which fusion
can be deployed at scale
and commercially successful.
So with that introduction,
I'd like to now move on
to the key findings
of the study,
with presentations by
different members of the team.
I'll be starting with
Sergey Paltsev, who
led the Global Analysis
Workstream for the Study.
And Sergey is an economist.
And he's the Deputy
Director of the MIT
Center for Sustainability,
Science, and Strategy.
And he's also a senior
research scientist
at the MIT Energy Initiative.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you, Randy.
Well, one thing
which at least I've
learned from this
particular study
is be careful what you wish for.
And let me explain why.
So several years
ago, I was in one
of the wonderful MIT conferences
in wonderful Madrid, Spain.
And I was presenting what we
typically do, energy scenarios.
What are the transition risks?
What are the physical risks?
So we have this big
economy-wide tool which
covers all global regions.
So I'm doing my typical story.
And the second speaker on that
conference was Dennis Whyte.
And he has done very
exciting speech about fusion.
And well, I was a
little bit skeptical.
But I saw that the
public was sold.
I was like, wow.
But in most scenarios,
we don't really
have any fusion represented.
If you are going to take a look
into any International Energy
Outlook or, well,
any other outlooks
which are trying to
project where we are going,
you're not going to see any
fusion in all these outlooks all
the way to 2100.
So I thought, oh, that
would be a great study.
That would be a great addition
to what we do in order
to understand how fusion is
going to fit all these things.
And about half a year
later, completely unrelated,
Randy showed up at
my office and said,
we are thinking about
doing a fusion study,
so why don't you
try and see what's
the story in terms of the
economics of the fusion?
And well, here are the results.
And here were kind of my
previous electrical engineering
training.
So by my first degree, I'm
an electrical engineer.
But then I switched to what
I typically joke as the "dark
side."
So I got my PhD in economics.
And as you are very
well aware, economists
are quite skeptical people.
So you probably
even have a term.
Economics is a dismal science.
So we're always skeptical
about something.
And so this is where
I came to the study
where I was a
little bit skeptical
because the first
question which I had,
why do we need fusion, right?
So with all the
electrification, with all wind
and solar and other things--
and by 2050, we are going
to be at net zero anyway--
why we need this
expensive technology
and why do we need
to bring that?
And well, I put
that into our model.
And we get some of the results,
well, which were, in the end,
not that surprising, but
kind of taught us again
that, well, whatever
the story, we
need to make sure that
everything adds up
in terms of all the components.
And as Professor White and
Professor Armstrong and Randy
Field already
mentioned, we had a lot
of opportunities from fusion,
but a lot of challenges
on the technology side.
And the point which we are
trying to make-- at least, well,
my part of the study--
is trying to understand what
are the economic opportunities
and economic challenges?
And so these two simple
curves is an attempt
to understand, well,
what's the value?
What's the value of society?
What's the value for
the society if we are
going to develop the fusion?
And we have done a
very simple experiment
where we, first of all, run the
scenarios where we are achieving
the Paris Agreement goals.
So kind of on a
separate activities,
we have our MIT
global change outlook
where we are developing
different pathways,
how to get to 1.5 and
the different regimes
with overshoot, without
overshoot, and so on.
So in all of these scenarios
in this particular study,
we are achieving 1.5 goal.
And then, what we
have done, we tried
to understand what kind
of information, what kind
of signpost we can give to
the technology developers
in terms of the cost
performance of this technology.
In other words, well,
how cheap, how much you
need to reduce the cost
of overnight capital cost
or overall cost in order to
make sure that economically,
it makes sense.
It means that we didn't force
any particular technology,
but we have done the
emission reduction scenario
and technologies are competing
based on the economics.
So we are not
forcing the fusion.
We are trying to find what
are the conditions where
the technology is making
the economic sense?
And so these
particular two curves
shows you the value for the
global society between two cases
where fusion were
never invented versus
where the cost of the fusion.
And you're going to see
this abbreviation in terms
of the overnight capital cost.
Well, these are the
numbers for 2050.
So it means that,
kind of initially,
it starts much higher.
And then it's going lower.
So in the report,
there are actually
trajectories, what we project
in terms of the costs.
But what we have done is try to
understand what is the value.
And you see, well, those
are nontrivial numbers.
And you can actually aggregate
those numbers and compare.
And it turns out that, well,
under this condition where
the overnight cost is about
$8,000 per kilowatt, then, well,
if you're going to compare
the cumulative GDPs with
and without, you are
actually gaining about 0.4%,
0.5% of the global GDP.
And if you are reducing
cost even more,
you are gaining about close
to 1% of the global GDP.
So while that comes as
an additional benefit--
so you are still meeting
the same reduction.
You are still meeting
the same target.
But you are actually
helping the society
to reach the target
if indeed you
are going to reach this quite
aggressive goal in terms
of the reduction in the
cost of this technology.
So we also have looked
at, well, how much?
What's the contribution
in terms of the share?
And you see that while we run
different scenarios and kind
of while we run actually
many more scenarios,
but focusing on this, depending
on the different costs,
take a look at that top color.
I'm not sure.
On my slide, it's like
magenta over there.
It's something else,
but see that top color.
And the point is,
well, you still
see that color under different
assumptions about the capital
cost and the numbers
that it gives you
the global share between
10% and almost half
of the electricity, which
are coming from the fusion.
And while there are two
main drivers behind that--
well, one, as you can
see from these figures,
the world needs more
and more electricity.
And so the huge driver
is electrification.
And by the time where you
start exhausting the resources
for wind and solar,
and then by the time
where the cost of integration
of intermittent renewables,
intermittent sources getting
harder and harder to manage--
well, this is where the
story for fusion comes.
And so this is
actually the story
for any carbon-free
dispatchable technology.
As long as you can invent--
well, you can label fusion,
you can label whatever else.
So that's the value of something
which you are going to create
and you can deliver and
put into the system.
And obviously, well,
there are a lot
of things which are going
to affect these numbers.
And again, we try to
understand some of them.
And you can see,
well, kind of a lot
is going to depend
on, well, if we
are going to create almost
free storage of energy, well,
then it will go into
different solution.
Well, that's another
kind of big "if."
But there are certain
things which obviously is
going to affect the trajectory.
But also, you can
see that the need--
initially, see we see the jump
in fusion kind of by midcentury
in the US and Europe mostly.
But by the end of this
century, where Africa demands
much more energy, where all this
electrification is happening
in India and other places--
this is where we see the uptake,
the need for that technology.
And another point is,
well, obviously this
is very aggregate
look at the problem.
And so later on, you
will see a little bit
more detailed exploration.
And again, in the
report, we are doing
much more detailed exploration.
And even that
detailed exploration
is kind of not representing
all the challenges and all
the things which are going
to affect the development
of this technology.
And so the exact
numbers, obviously, you
need to take that with
very big degree of caution.
But the trajectory is simple.
So with all these
uncertainties, one message
becomes very, very clear.
Well, with
appropriate resolution
of technological issues,
with appropriate resolution
of regulatory issues
which are going
to be needed to support
this technology,
we will have a big impact.
And that is going
to help our society
to reach the aggressive
climate goals at cheaper
cost to the society
in comparison
if we would not really
spend our effort right now.
But in order to deliver
that by midcentury,
well, we need to start doing
this planning, this R&D,
this story right now.
And that's exactly what we
are going to hear later on.
That's exactly what MIT
is leading the world.
And I can tell--
well, I kind of recently
traveled in all places,
Australia, Brazil, Barcelona.
And while they all
asking, guys, you're
at MIT, well, how are
you going to create
that wonderful technology which
is going to save the world?
And, well, so far,
the secret sauce
is coming from this technology.
And we will see if that's
going to be delivered.
So you see that, after all, I'm
not that skeptical economist.
But at least I've
been sold by Dennis.
So now I'm going to switch
to, I'm not sure who.
But Randy will choreograph that.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you very much, Sergey.
Amanda Farnsworth recently
graduated from MIT
with her PhD in
chemical engineering.
And she was a key contributor
to the subregional grid analysis
workstream for this study.
Unfortunately, she can't
join us here tonight.
So I'll be presenting
her a piece of this work.
In this analysis, we basically
looked at different regions
of the United States,
nine different regions,
based on how the grid is
organized in the United States.
And asked the question of
how fusion would penetrate
those markets
differently, and analyzed
how that relates to
the resources they have
in each of those subregions.
And if we start on the far left
column, we see that two regions,
the so-called Atlantic and
Southeast region of the United
States--
they had the greatest
penetration of fusion,
basically at a price point
of $6,000 per kilowatt.
Fusion would be deployed
regardless of the carbon cap
being between 1 and 50
grams per kilowatt hour.
And let me just give you a
reference point for that.
So recently, the US average
grid carbon intensity
was about 450 grams
per kilowatt hour.
So we're talking about
deep decarbonization.
And what this means
is as you force
the grid to have lower and
lower carbon intensity,
it forces you to look at
what are my least cost,
least carbon intensive
technologies to do that.
And so the more you press
down on the decarbonization,
the more you need
the renewables.
And the more you need
things such as fusion.
And so is what we see here is
that in the North, or rather
in the Atlantic and
Southeast region,
because of the nature of
their current resources,
that's where you had the
highest penetration of fusion.
And we examined the
specific characteristics.
One is that those regions
have fairly poor onshore wind
resources.
They have very little hydro
and very little geothermal
resources.
They, of course, have solar.
But solar has the
characteristic of being
diurnal in its
resource, meaning you'll
have great resources during
the day and very poor resources
at night.
So there's a great demand for
firm power, such as fusion.
And that's one of the
reasons why we saw highest
penetration in that region.
That contrasts quite a bit
with the far-right column
where we look at Central,
North Central, and Texas,
where you have not only
solar, but you also
have abundant high quality,
low cost onshore wind,
which gives you a better
diversification in lower cost
resources.
And so what you see in
that case is that you only
have penetration of fusion
if your carbon constraint is
4 grams of CO2 per
kilowatt or less.
Now, it's interesting that even
though it has a penetration only
at the lowest levels,
if you push it down
to 1 gram per kilowatt
hour, even in that case,
you can have situations of 25%
to 45% penetration of fusion
in the market.
So again, it says there's a very
high sensitivity to the carbon
constraint, but
those regions do take
on fusion in those situations.
And I'll contrast that with the
Northwest, where, in that case,
you have a great diversity
of renewable energy,
including you've got wind
resources that are, say,
average.
But you have excellent
diversity of resources,
including the hydro and
geothermal in those regions.
And so what you see there is
a relatively low sensitivity
to the carbon cap.
But the penetration never
gets above 26% in that region.
So that's just a
snapshot of the work
that Amanda and colleagues
did for that cross analysis
between the different
subregions in the United States.
But what it really points out
is even in a single country,
depending upon the
region you're in,
you can have tremendously
different resources.
And those resources
can drastically
impact the deployment of fusion.
And with that, I will
now turn it over to--
I'll now introduce
Rory MacDonald,
who received his PhD in Nuclear
Science and engineering at MIT.
And he is a research scientist
at the MIT Energy Initiative.
And he worked on the subregional
grid analysis of this project.
And he zoomed in on the
potential role of fusion
in the New England area
of the United States.
[APPLAUSE]
Thanks very much, Randy.
So we studied
fusion's future role
in the New England grid in 2050
using a GenX model of ISO New
England and Quebec
hydro's resources
at three different
emission intensity limits.
This is a region with
relatively limited land
for onshore wind and solar PV.
And so other clean and
low-emission resources
have an important role to play
in meeting increasing demand.
And this analysis
modeled the fusion plants
in a bit more detail and added
more constraints to the grid.
So as well as looking at 20
years of correlated demand
and weather data,
these three plots
show the fusion fleet
installed capacity generation
and annual capacity factors as a
function of the plant investment
costs.
The left plot shows
how the fusion fleet
rose as the costs come down.
And the different segments
correspond to substitution
for different alternatives or
combinations of alternatives.
The ISO New England peak
load in these scenarios
was about 60 gigawatts.
So that 50% highest value
corresponds to about
a 30-gigawatt fleet.
The rightmost
point of each curve
is the capital cost at
which the first fusion
plant enters the grid.
So this can be thought
of essentially as a cost
target for fusion developers.
The cost targets
were $6,500, $8,000,
and $14,000 per
kilowatt for the 50, 12,
and 4 grams CO2 per kilowatt
hour emission intensity limits.
All the alternatives were
modeled with 2050 costs, which
means that these cost targets
are a little lower than they
might be, but they also
use 2050 emission limits,
which are very aggressive.
And so that would
make them higher
than they might otherwise be.
The center and right blocks
show the generation and capacity
factors as a function
of the costs.
At high emission
intensity limits,
we saw what we kind of
expected, the fusion plants.
So the fusion fleet,
the relatively expensive
acts as baseload.
And as the cost or if
the costs come down,
they substitute
for more resources.
We see more generation and
lower capacity factors.
But we were surprised
to see at the 4 grams
CO2 per kilowatt
hour emission limit.
Very expensive plants were
operating not quite as peakers,
but at low capacity factors.
And this is because the
alternatives and those sorts
of scenarios where you
couldn't run the natural gas
combined cycle with
CCS unit plants
for more than roughly
thousand hours per year.
Your alternative was
to build a lot more,
or a lot of extra renewables
and storage, which
was very expensive.
And so as long as
fusion plants were
able to be relatively
flexibly operated,
they could also be expensive
and still enter the grid.
So clearly, this
analysis depends
heavily on the alternatives
that fusion plants
are competing with.
And natural gas units with
CCS were the most important
of those.
So as a comparison, just
for this presentation,
we're showing what the installed
capacity of the fusion fleet
is with and without natural
gas units in the grid.
And we can see that if you
don't allow for any natural gas
or CCS, you essentially
increase all those cost targets
I've talked about
before by $4,000.
And we're not saying that
natural gas units with CCS
aren't going to be available
in New England in 2050.
But we wanted to
look at this scenario
because there are
plenty of places
in the world where natural gas
is not as cheap as it is here.
And it's not clear that
large-scale carbon sequestration
is going to be possible
in all parts of the world.
So-- I'm sorry.
And finally, we assumed a
fixed 95% carbon capture
rate for all CCS
units, regardless
of how the plant operates.
And the more we look
into it, the more
that doesn't seem like it's
always going to be the case.
So for all those
reasons, there may
be scenarios where CCS units
have a much lesser role to play
and fusion can step in.
Our corollary, there are
also other technologies
that could step in,
and that's something
that we didn't consider
in as much detail.
But it'll be a topic
of future work.
With that, I'm going
to it back to Randy.
Thank you very much.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you very much, Rory.
So Professor White and--
I'm sorry, Professor Dennis
Whyte, just for clarity,
and postdoc Theodore
Titus led the work stream
looking at the supply
chains for materials
and manufactured
parts for fusion.
Our assessment found that
different technologies
were at very different
stages of maturity.
And in the report, we
identify the issues as well as
the potential bottlenecks in the
supply chain for both materials
and for parts.
A key point is that we
do need additional R&D
to help develop materials that
are needed in the manufacturing
technologies for fusion.
This is more often the case in
the situation of technologies
that have almost no
market outside of fusion,
or a limited market
outside of fusion.
One example is the development
of tungsten heavy, which
is a very dense
alloy that can handle
the harsh conditions in a
fusion reactor but otherwise
[INAUDIBLE].
Whereas some things such as the
high-temperature superconductors
have a very strong market,
commercial opportunities
beyond fusion.
And those supply chains
are more mature, but not
necessarily at the scale
that we need for fusion.
And in fact, fusion has
helped develop those markets.
And that's pitching
quite well already, even
in the development of
our pilot technology.
So that's a very short
summary of what we
looked at on the supply chains.
The other piece of the
project was looking
at the question of cost.
So Professor Koroush Shirvan
and a graduate student,
Layla Aaraiinejad, led our
technoeconomic analysis.
In this cost analysis,
we examined prior studies
and publications that assess
the cost for alternative fusion
configurations.
We also conducted a
bottoms-up analysis.
One key observation of this
is that the fusion reactor
equipment is the leading cost
contributor to the overall plant
cost for fusion.
We also concluded that
how fusion is regulated
can have a very large
impact on the overall cost.
And the logical
upshot of that is
that fusion power plant designs
need to minimize the risks.
And governments need to adopt
the appropriate and effective
policies to ensure safe
use of fusion energy
while enabling fusion
to help contribute
to the decarbonization
goals that
exist in countries
and across the world.
We also observed that the
operating and maintenance
costs for fusion power plants
can be significant as well.
So some key takeaways
from the overall study--
and I certainly encourage you to
go to the MIT Energy Initiative
website, search for fusion,
and you'll see the report there
and you can get
into the details.
But a key takeaway
from this work
is that, as Sergey
had indicated,
fusion has a potential
societal value
in the trillions of dollars.
As we seek to decarbonize the
global electricity system,
fusion at the right
price can give us
great advantage to our
society and the scale
of multiple
trillions of dollars.
We also found that the
deployment and operation
of fusion plants is highly
dependent upon the fusion cost,
the cost and availability
of alternative low-carbon
technologies, as well as
what is the carbon constraint
that we're working with.
That is, how low
a carbon content
is our electricity being pushed
by policy and by governments
around the world?
We also know that
the growth of fusion
will be dependent
by region based
upon the economic and
electricity demand growth.
And also another key
finding within the report.
And what was led
by John Parsons was
the question of market design.
Market design can have
a very large impact
on the deployment of capital
intensive technologies
such as fusion,
as well as others.
So a question of how do you
design your electricity market
matters as well.
The other key finding is that
the ability for Fusion to scale
requires that we have the
materials, critical materials
and manufacturing
capabilities to support that.
Particularly for the
niche components,
we will need more
R&D in that field.
And for raw materials, we are
not anticipating showstoppers
there.
There will be some challenges,
but no showstoppers
to the deployment of fusion.
And on the slide, I'd
like to also acknowledge
the entire project team
and all the people who
contributed to the project.
There were many study
participants as well as
subject matter experts
and support staff
who supported this-- and as well
as this project was supported
by ENI, one of the key funders
of energy research at MIT.
So I thank the
participants and all
that supported this activity.
So with this, I'd like to
move into the next phase
of the program and invite
our speakers and panelists up
to the chairs in front.
And Professor Dennis White,
who was co-PI for this project,
he will be moderating
the discussion.
[APPLAUSE]
I'm going to sit at the end.
Great, everyone come up.
[INAUDIBLE]
Well, thanks.
So I'd like to--
so as a fusion technologist,
I guess I scared
or inspired Sergey
back in Madrid.
To me, the value of this--
I can say, for a
person who has worked
in fusion for a long time--
people who work in fusion and
there are several of them here,
we tend to work on us thinking
of it as the perfect energy
source.
And when we make it
work, everybody's
going to use it because
it's so wonderful.
That's not how the
real world works.
The real world works around
markets, around price,
around availability.
And I think for me, the
greatest reveal that
came from this study was placing
fusion, even in some sense
a limited way because we
only considered electricity,
but it really placed
markers on the ground for us
as fusion technologists to
understand what we must deliver,
in fact, to actually make
fusion have a difference.
It's the dream that--
the reason we all
started to do fusion.
So I'll actually start
in inverse in some sense
because what this made
me realize about how
important market design is.
But what market
are you going into,
how is it incentivized,
and so forth?
And particularly as we go
to a carbon-free energy
source, distribution
of energy sources,
fuel basically almost goes
away, essentially, as a cost.
And what happens is
that its capital cost
that starts to become dominant.
So I'm going to start
with John, actually.
Please introduce yourself,
and also comment as to what
you're thinking in terms of
market design for electrical
systems, which by themselves--
we just commenting up
in the-- as we were getting
miked up is that this itself is
evolving rapidly with things
like power purchase agreements
which are coming--
which are specifically
for high-end users
like Microsoft and Google.
So if you could please
comment on that,
I think that'd be a
good starting point.
Sure, so, yeah, I'm
happy to be here.
I'm John Persons.
I'm the deputy
director of research
at the Center for Energy and
Environmental Policy Research,
which, in short, is
a bunch of economists
at MIT working in this space.
And I think the big issue--
Dennis characterized
it really well.
We've had a electricity system
generation, which has largely
depended on fuel with costs.
And that means we've managed
our electricity markets where,
as fuel prices vary, we
switch which generators are on
and, over time might switch
from one fuel source to another.
And the markets
are mainly focused
on sorting out that short-term
operational characteristic.
What we haven't had
to deal with as much
are exclusively capital
intensive investments.
And there are some
technical problems
with incentivizing investments,
the long-term heavy capital
investments as a result of the
way we manage our electricity
markets.
This isn't just
unique to fusion.
In fact, all decarbonated--
low-carbon generation
technologies so far
are basically
capital-intensive technologies.
And you have to make an
upfront capital investment.
And one of the ways most
different societies have
decided to do that is to provide
a guaranteed revenue stream.
Whether in the United
States, it might
be with production
tax credits for wind,
for example, or for
solar and, in Europe,
feed in tariffs or contract
for differences or things
of that sort.
So you, basically,
are implementing
a very different model for
how you structure investments
in physical assets.
And we had gotten away from
that for a long window of time.
But if fusion is
going to move forward
as well as other decarbonized--
low-carbon generation,
we're going
to need to reinvigorate our
institutions that make decisions
about investments on behalf
of a whole electricity market
so that you can assure
an adequate income
stream to pay back the
financing of these big capital
investments.
Thanks, John.
Staying with, in some sense,
markets and, of course,
as a fusion person,
the question you always
get asked the most is when?
When is this going to happen?
And I would point out we have
to just for the study, we
have to make some
assumptions about when
it was going to appear.
We had to make some assumptions
and assumptions about doubling
rate of the capability.
But we saw the sense that it
wasn't shown in the slides.
But we took a look at this.
I mean, at MIT,
our theme has been,
let's try to make
fusion happen sooner.
But how soon is soon enough?
And this goes to
Randy and Sergei,
who I think really led
the charge on trying
to understand that part.
I'll take first dibs on
that [INAUDIBLE] Sergei.
But, basically, as you saw
in some of Sergei's plots,
let me step back a moment.
Because of
electrification globally,
there's going to be a tremendous
switching from the fossil fuels
for electricity.
And a lot of people will
be joining the middle class
in different parts of the world.
And so, overall, there's
a tremendous growth
of energy demand
throughout the world
and for electricity
throughout the world.
And so my view is it's never
too late to bring in fusion
because there will always be
more demand for electricity.
And even in Sergei's slots,
as we saw fusion take off,
you don't see the green go away.
The green stays put.
So it's not like you're
displacing wind and solar.
But they're living
together in harmony.
Yeah, well, another dimension--
well, typically, if you're
already seeing the report,
actually, the work has been
done like a year ago or half
a year ago, where
I'm getting to.
Well, right now, we are
seeing the explosion
of different projections, how
AI is going to affect the energy
demand [INAUDIBLE] and all
these data centers, all
these hyperscalers.
Well, John Parsons is
an expert in nuclear.
And the recent announcement
of Microsoft and Mile Island--
so everybody was
excited about that.
And [INAUDIBLE]
And [INAUDIBLE] commenting
on that kind of.
So the point is, even these
projections, which you already
saw, which are quite aggressive
in terms of the electrification
and energy demand,
we still may be
on the low side of what
actually will be needed.
And so that's one of the reasons
we need all of the above.
We need as much as possible
of this carbon-free energy
of very low-carbon energy or
almost carbon-free energy.
And so fusion is
giving us that promise.
And, hopefully, it's
not just a promise.
To add to that one,
a recent one is
Google announced a partnership--
or an agreement with Kairos
Power, which is built
on-- it's interesting.
It has adjacent technologies
to our own work as well too.
So this actually goes over
to Sara about technical work.
And please introduce
yourself as well too.
We also had to make
assumptions in here
that we called it a
firm dispatchable power
source with some certain
amount of availability.
If those go away, then it's
economic attractiveness
or it's market penetration
clearly get impacted maybe.
And we're going to hear
more about this in detail.
But could you sort
of comment to it
in the context of this study
about how important availability
component reliability is?
So I'm Sara Ferry.
I'm the group leader for
fusion materials and components
at the PSFC.
So a lot of our work is looking
at the different systems
that mostly tokamak-based power
plants would need in order
to become power plants and
going from a research device
that [INAUDIBLE] to
something that is
capable of [INAUDIBLE] energy.
And so this encompasses
everything from the breeder
blanket to really, really
reliable first-wall components,
all of these things
that are exposed
to very high
temperatures, corrosive
working fluids,
high-energy neutron fluxes,
high temperatures.
And we know that they're going
to need frequent replacement
or maintenance because
there's no perfect material
solution for these.
So in addition to thinking
about materials development
and selection, a lot of
what we have to work on
is thinking about maintenance
from the beginning,
so designing components that
don't take months to disassemble
in order to get
in there, in order
to do necessary
maintenance or replacement
and then get things back online
because, from the research
world, we often see major
experimental facilities
down for months
or years, whenever
upgrades or fixes are needed.
And we know that
is not going to be
acceptable in a power plant that
is designed for commercial use.
So there's a lot of
different axes to think on.
And I think one thing
we can be aware of
is that it's not
enough just to say, oh,
I'm going to develop a higher
performance material that's
good for this particular
part of the plant.
You also have to think about
the component as a whole
and how it will actually
be used because,
otherwise, you can design
yourself into a corner.
And it will be very hard to
get out of it when it turns out
that it's not very
easy to get in there
and do replacements or anything.
Thanks , Sara.
And, for me, as I saw this-- and
I'm going to turn to Rory now
around this-- is this
is exactly why we
have these kinds
of studies because
of the complex interplay.
As technologists, we
just tend to think, well,
I'm going to make the
technology better.
But what does that mean?
What does it mean from an
economic point of view?
What does it mean from a market
penetration point of view?
And there's a few things
that particularly came out
of your aspect of the detailed
study of the ISO, Rory, that
came as surprises to me of--
may be, in retrospect, not so
surprising about the importance
of the cost of the
replacement factors in it,
of the materials of
the nameplate power
capability of it.
And, also, another
somewhat of a surprise
is that we tend
to think of fusion
is steady-state power sources.
But, actually, what
popped out was, oh,
this actually has a role as what
we call a peaker, essentially.
Could you comment to that?
Yeah, and, to follow
up on Sara's point,
we kind of ran the
sensitivity studies
of [INAUDIBLE] three
months or six months
or a year to [INAUDIBLE].
We'll be seeing hundreds of
thousands of dollars of savings
in [INAUDIBLE].
Definitely has a big impact,
maybe even more so than the life
of [INAUDIBLE].
But fusion [INAUDIBLE],
your future operators
perhaps will be able to play a
game of prices are lower today.
Perhaps I'm not
going to sell power
to preserve some of
these components.
And so the operation of
some of these devices
could be quite complicated.
But yeah, we did see
that, particularly
for any plant that pulsed.
And so it had quite
a reasonable ability
to change its output every 20
or 30 minutes with those pulses.
Then it's not that they
ran in a peaker in the way
that a combined
cycle turbine would,
but they would be
on for days, weeks.
And then they'll be off for
a similar amount of time.
And that's where you've got
that drop in capacity factor.
And a lot of that, though,
was driven by the fact of--
by the choice of alternatives
that we did or didn't include--
so maybe to circle
back to your point
earlier about the
when doesn't matter.
The when matters a bit if
someone gets there first.
So if someone invents a magical,
perfect, clean fuel tomorrow,
then anything competing
with that clean fuel
might be in a bit of trouble.
But there are unique features
to things like fusion
that will also help it.
Thanks.
So that's great.
And as I said, I really
appreciated this.
I think these are
the kinds of models
that we take as technologists
and then try to understand,
what's the most--
so I get inspired
a little bit in my fusion design
class that actually happened
at that latter end of the
study is that I switched
from a perfect to a cheaper
set of replacement materials
because I realized that
was probably a good one.
So now we're going to take a
few questions from the audience.
[INAUDIBLE]
Please don't be shy.
Get ready for a good ride.
[LAUGHING]
Rory and I both come from
the vision side as well.
So it's interesting
that you're going
to tend to probably think
in terms of neutronics
more than people
who maybe have had
most of their career
in plasma physics.
And everyone's
aware of both sides.
But, when we first started doing
a lot of the work with CFS,
I think we found
that a lot of people
were maybe underestimating
how impactful neutrons would
be to operations
overall, everything
from material degradation,
plus, obviously, you
need that for the heat and
the breeding and the blanket
as well.
So I actually think that
being on the fission side
gives you a good advantage
because you're already
really used to working in that
particular type of environment
as well as also
being intrinsically
aware of the safety
issues that come
with any nuclear technology.
And so I think it
helps you maybe see
things in a holistic way that
I think is super helpful.
Congratulations on it.
And, actually, you'll see it.
To preview what's
coming, you'll see
that a lot of the new directions
of research here at MIT
are moving us towards
these key aspects
of the nuclear technologies that
are required to actually deliver
what we put into the study,
which is an attractive energy
source.
And, in a general
way, those have
tended to lag behind
because of a lack of people
working on it, actually.
There's a lot of
synergy between--
A lot of synergy.
--and fusion [INAUDIBLE].
So both communities are--
it's cool to maybe
have an opportunity
to bring both those communities
together more as well.
Don't be shy.
Is there somebody in the back?
Yep.
Hi, sorry, if I missed
this at the start,
but how was vision
treated in the study?
Because a lot of the
conclusions that I saw
about fusion look very
similar to conclusions
about the future role of
vision in other studies.
So, yeah.
Sure, so we were very--
we needed to make a decision
about this right up front
in doing the study.
Basically, fusion and
fission, as you indicated
compete for the exact same
place in the electric grid.
We talk here about firm power.
And Bob mentioned that
they're both energy dense,
and that's a particular
competitive niche
in the electricity market.
However, they have differences.
They will be advantaged
by different technological
developments.
They have very
different safety cases,
different political and
social acceptance issues.
And so what we decided
to do was focus
primarily on that
competitive space that
would be common to both
of them and identify
that competitive space, but
not try to understand or make
any predictions about
one versus the other
on those other dimensions as
they're going to evolve over
the next couple of decades.
So we didn't try to evaluate,
compare them or anything.
One last one.
Hold on one second.
I just got to bring you
a mic for our recording.
I'm sorry.
I was wondering if
you had a chance
to take a look at
the supply chain.
And are there any
critical materials
that are choke points outside
of our friends and neighbors?
Yeah, we did, actually.
The general conclusion
was there was not
any bottlenecks in there.
It actually comes from
the very nature of fusion,
it being so incredibly
power dense.
And what you're actually
building-- what you're building
has very few specialized
elements in it, essentially.
In the particularly
magnetic confinement,
basically, big chunks of steel
that are called electromagnets.
And the other-- what is termed
as the exotic components
is actually not very much in it.
There's a few exceptions
of things right now,
like beryllium, for
example, where we have--
but that's really--
our assessment was
that was really more a
market because there's so
little demand for it right now.
That's actually why it appears
that it might be an issue.
But, in fact,
there's alternatives.
And then the markets
could respond as well too.
So, in general, we
found there wasn't
really much of an issue there.
Good question, though.
But I think that was it for
the-- thanks for the panelists.
Yep, thank you.
[AUDIENCE]
So thank you, Dennis,
Randy, panelists.
And thanks again to the
entire group of 30 plus who
did the research in this study.
I'd like to shift now to the
second part of the program.
And I want to turn
the podium over
to Professor, Nuno
Loureiro, who's
the director of the MIT Plasma
Science and Fusion Center.
He's also a professor of Nuclear
Science and Engineering at MIT.
And he will introduce the
next part of the program.
Good afternoon, everybody.
Thank you, Randy, for
organizing this wonderful event.
I'm delighted to be here.
So we're shifting
gears a little bit.
This part of the
session's focusing on,
what it is that we're doing
here at MIT to actually deliver
a fusion energy?
So it's almost irrespective
of whether it's
going to be beneficial to--
well, I guess many
of us think of it
as, is it going to be
beneficial to mankind or not?
But some of us are in it just
for the science and the thrill
of doing great discoveries.
And I guess I fit more in the
latter category than the former.
But, of course, I understand
the practical considerations
are paramount.
This is a very brief overview.
The real stars of this
show are my colleagues
who are going to speak
right after me, focusing
different aspects of what we're
doing at the Plasma Science
and Fusion Center.
So this is a beautiful
picture of what the PSFC is.
You're looking at-- from
above, obviously, this
is Mass Ave. This
is Albany Street,
and the buildings here in
pink are the Plasma Science
and Fusion Center.
And the reason I'm
showing you this is not
to brag about my realm,
but rather to tell you
that this is the
scale that's required
if you want to solve the kinds
of problems that are posed
by delivering fusion energy.
This is not tabletop science.
This is science that requires
big infrastructure, huge teams,
a lot of money.
So the fusion world
is unrecognizable
compared to what it looked
like five years ago.
And I think the PSFC
team, led by Dennis White,
was absolutely instrumental in
changing what fusion is and as
compared to what was.
And so the landmark on
that was the launching
of the MIT CFS partnership
about five years ago.
And that's really
triggered the revolution
in how society is
approaching fusion research.
And the underlying theme
to this is that many of us
have had enough with the
conversation of 20 years
from now.
I think we are all
firm believers in now
is better than later.
And there's something we can
do about it right now that
doesn't have to wait 20 years.
Now, of course,
this is rooted in
deep technological
innovation, which
has been the staple at the
Plasma Science and Fusion Center
for as long as it has existed.
It's not just private funding.
The US government and
governments throughout the world
are also aggressively
promoting fusion in ways
that they weren't doing before.
And so I think the most
noteworthy event here
in the United States
was the White House
Summit a couple of
years ago on developing
a bold, decadal vision for
commercializing fusion energy.
So decadal means
10 years in case
you're not paying attention.
So this is a very
aggressive timeline
for when it is that
we are actually trying
to promote fusion on the grid.
And so, as a result
of that, they've
selected a few companies
that they are--
they've identified as
perhaps the most promising
in the road to
delivering fusion power.
And PSFC has very
tight collaborations
with several of these.
And the ones with
which we don't, I
think they very much want
to be involved with us.
That's a fair statement.
Now, this slide is a sort of--
for us, in the fusion field,
this is a slide that
you wouldn't even
dream of five years ago.
So, right now, we're talking
about venture capital,
upwards of $6 billion raised in
the last five years for fusion.
These are some of the companies.
This slide is almost
instantaneously outdated
at the moment you
do it because it
seems like every other week
there's a new fusion startup.
So it's a very exciting
space right now
with different
concepts coming online,
people sort of working
on this problem from very
different angles.
And some of these concepts are
more promising than others.
But I think this is
of approach that you
need where you need
more than one data point
to identify what's going to be
the most promising technology.
And, of course, we know in
science and in engineering
that competition is good.
So this is what a bubbling,
exciting scientific and
technological
adventure looks like.
A lot of people looking
at these problems
from very different angles.
So, very quickly,
to create a device
that produces more energy.
So if you want to
have fusion energy,
at least in the magnetic
confinement fusion approach,
you need strong and
efficient magnets
to confine the fusion plasmas
and innovating and really
setting the state of the
art in magnet technology
is the key thing that
brought us from five years
to where we are now at the
Plasma Science and Fusion
Center.
We also need peak plasma
fusion performance.
You can run worse plasmas.
You can run better plasmas.
And having the knowledge
of how to optimize that
is absolutely critical.
Turns out this is a
very complex problem.
And not only do you need to do
all the high-powered theory that
some of us wish they could
do, but you also need
state-of-the-art computing,
machine learning,
quantum computing.
And it's fantastic in
the sense that some
of the problems that we are
facing in the fusion realm
develop tools that are
actually transportable
to many other problems, problems
in other fields of science.
And that's also
very interesting.
We need a way to convert
energy into power.
So we didn't get into details
about how this actually works.
But, at the end
of the day, you're
producing high-energy
neutrons, and it's that energy
that you're trying to tap.
And so how you go
about doing this
is a fascinating scientific and
technological problem that I
would argue we
haven't quite solved,
and we need to put more
resources behind that.
And then, finally,
we need materials.
Fusion devices, the way that we
are conceiving them right now
will hold the
largest temperature
gradient in the solar system.
So the core of the plasma
that sits here is roughly
at 150,000,000
degrees centigrade.
But about a meter outwards,
you have a material surface
that's perhaps, at best, at
1,000 degrees centigrade.
And so the materials that are
going to withstand that neutron
flux and that heat flux are
very important for the success
of this endeavor.
In this session, you're hearing
most about magnetic confinement
fusion.
But the inertial
confinement fusion
has a very strong and honored
presence at the Plasma Science
and Fusion Center.
You may have heard about the
record shots on the NIF facility
over at Livermore.
Our team is heavily
involved in that.
And, in fact, they're a
central piece to that success.
So I just want to flag
this in case anybody
is interested in this.
You can ask me or us at
the end of the session.
This is largely a very
optimistic but also realistic
view of things.
But that doesn't mean that
we've solved every problem.
And, for example, one of the
problems we're facing right now
is the need for developing the
fusion workforce, the people who
are actually going to man
the fusion power companies,
for example.
So we need to expand
fusion education in the US
and I think elsewhere.
Dennis White has a
wonderful paper on this.
And the US Academy
is just not prepared.
We need more fusion instructors.
I mean, we have
proven here at MIT
that we can educate
our students very well.
So many of the people
you'll hear from today
were actually our alumni.
They are our alumni.
And some of us will go out, and
they start fusion companies, not
just CFS but elsewhere.
We need capable but sort
of fast, not decadal,
time scales,
experimental facilities
to test the different
parts that go
into making a successful
fusion power plant.
And this is always
going to be hard tech.
It's always going
to be big science.
It's never going to
be less than millions
and millions of dollars.
That's just the
name of the game.
That's the level of
resources that you need.
And, finally, if we're actually
serious about having a fusion
industry, we need to be very
serious about the fusion supply
chain.
And we need to be
very serious about all
the commercial opportunities,
not just directly in the fusion
supply chain, but in all the
spinoff technologies, such
as, for example, using
fusion heating systems
for geothermal energy.
There's immense commercial
opportunity here
that goes well beyond
the economic value
that fusion itself
might present.
So we won't have time to go
into detail in all of these
in the following presentations.
But I wanted to
at least leave you
with some of these key words
so that for your reflection
or to ask us later.
So, with that, I'll transition
to the next speaker, Professor
Zach Hartwig.
[APPLAUSE]
Hey, everybody, good evening.
So I'm going to follow
on Nuno's presentation
and actually talk
to you a little bit
about some of the things we
can do to accelerate but still
be at reasonable scale, which
is really the key thing.
So this is a picture.
We'll talk a little
bit more about it.
But it's a picture
of a facility that we
hope to build at the Plasma
Science and Fusion Center.
And I'll tell you a bit about
why it's transformational.
So I open this
slide with a quote
from a director of
Idaho National Lab who
I had a conversation with.
And he said something
which I really liked.
He said, if fusion is ever going
to be an energy technology,
it's a materials problem.
Yeah, there's lots of
other things in it,
but this is ultimately
where fusion has to go.
And so I really like that quote
because it kind of defines
this moment in fusion where
we're kind of moving away
from science program, and
we're moving towards an energy
technology.
It's a great quote
that sums it up.
So here you can see the
graphic we've shown, right.
There's 40 private companies.
You can see the bubble
of fusion that we're
in because, in the time since
Nuno gave his slide and I have,
we've raised an additional
$7 billion in private fusion.
That's great.
Dozens of companies who were not
there five years ago are there.
Those companies have also
changed the National program
efforts.
They're realigning to
support private fusion.
They're drawing in the
time scales by decades.
And this is actually caught
serious parts of the fusion
program quite out.
Materials who have been planned
to be deployed in 30 years
now need to be deployed in 10.
So what are those
parts of the fusion
program doing to address that?
Well, we need to address that.
Why?
Because every approach
that Randy mentioned,
doesn't matter what it is,
has a materials challenge.
And, ultimately, you
can tie those materials
to economic viability.
At the end of the day, that's
what materials do for fusion--
they make it work or not.
So that's why materials
are important.
We touched on this a little bit.
We don't have time to go
into too many details,
but we have common
challenges in fusion.
It doesn't matter really
what the challenge is.
One challenge is
we make neutrons
deuterium-tritium
fusion is the first fuel
cycle we're likely to embrace.
It's going to make neutrons.
Those neutrons damage materials.
They displace atoms
in the lattice.
They put helium and hydrogen
into those materials.
And that's a
significant problem.
And it turns out that the energy
that those neutrons interact
with the materials, that varies
as you move around this device.
And so the different damage is
happening in different regions.
It's quite an
interesting challenge.
What are some of
those challenges?
So we have structural materials.
Dennis mentioned these are
mostly power plants built out
of steel.
What can happen?
Well, you get
radiation-induced damage.
You get embrittlement.
Materials become strong, but
they can become very weak.
They can shatter.
You get creep.
You get swelling.
Materials actually will move.
You can actually
see the difference
in materials that have been
in a nuclear environment.
They grow.
This can be a problem.
We have chemical compatibility.
We want to put a structural
material in contact
with a molten salt or
a molten metal at 800
C. That's an environment
where corrosion
becomes very difficult.
We have other challenges.
So we have materials in
contact with the plasma.
We'd like to think
of the plasma,
at least in the tokamak being
held in a magnetic bottle.
But it's not a perfect bottle.
So the materials are
interacting quite substantially
with the plasma.
So we have issues.
Fuel, like tritium, is actually
sucked up into a material.
It's retained.
It can be very hard to get out.
We actually have
radiation damage
that can complicate many of the
interactions between a plasma
and a material.
And we're really just starting
to explore these interactions
in a relevant way for
a fusion power plant.
We have some more
exotic challenges.
We have things like functional
materials in a fusion power
plant.
We have superconductors.
Superconducting magnets form
one of the key cost drivers
of a fusion system in the core.
We're going to irradiate
those very expensive magnets
with neutrons, and they're
going to degrade over time.
And this is going to
have a significant impact
on the lifetime of the
device and the economics.
We have other things.
We have browning of optical
glass and mirrors and things
that we use to provide access
to lasers and other diagnostics.
Lots of materials challenges.
So what are we doing today?
And what are we planning to do?
OK, so what do we do today?
Well, one thing
we do primarily is
we use the fleet
of nuclear fission
reactors around the
world, test reactors,
to irradiate materials.
This is a picture
of the MIT core.
It's kind of a
beautiful picture where
you see the Cherenkov light.
This is just down
the street from us.
There's some significant
disadvantages.
Damage is very slow.
It takes a long time to
get to relevant regimes.
These are very
expensive measurements.
There are very few facilities,
and they're shutting down.
So that's a problem.
As we're trying to
ramp up this work,
facilities are shutting down.
The long and few
learning cycles means
we don't have a chance to do
rapid iteration to design,
to test, and then
to use that learning
to design a better material.
And they're not very
good fidelity for fusion.
We don't get the
right kind of damage.
We have much lower energy
neutrons than high energy.
What's the fusion world
doing about this problem?
Reactors don't work.
Well, currently the
world is planning
a device which is going to
be many billions of dollars.
It may be operational
in the 2040s.
This is a program called IFMIF.
It's mainly driven by Europe
and Japanese collaboration.
The US is considering
doing something similar.
It's a massive facility
operational in decades.
And we've heard
many times that's
not going to be acceptable.
We have companies who
need to make decisions
about materials in
the next few years,
not in the next [INAUDIBLE].
Low damage rate, limited
exposure conditions.
Maybe it's operational
in the late 2030s.
Probably not.
And how do you scale a
multibillion-dollar facility
to the dozens that
might be needed
to evaluate materials rapidly?
It's a really hard challenge.
So we have to think
very differently
about how we tackle these
challenges [INAUDIBLE].
And I thought what I
might do is show you
two examples of what
we're doing at MIT
that are kind of
upending this model,
doing things fast, doing things
quickly, doing things at very
high fidelity by being
creative, what we do at MIT.
So one of the
things we mentioned
is superconductors degrade
under radiation damage.
We don't want to wait around
to put those materials
in a nuclear reactor or wait
around for a fusion power plant.
What can we do?
This is a picture on the right
of an accelerator beamline
that's down on Albany Street.
And we've come up with a way to
essentially put superconductor
in cryogenic temperatures.
So minus 450 C, run
it with current,
and actually bombard
it with protons.
So we can actually
get measurements
done in the span
of minutes to hours
that might take weeks to
months to do elsewhere,
very low radioactivity.
It's right here on campus.
It's very easy to do rapid
experiments and even simpler.
So this is just a picture.
You can't have a talk at
MIT without a CAD drawing
and some indecipherable
graphics.
But we put the
superconductor here.
We cool it down.
We hit it with a proton beam.
Why is this important to do?
OK, so here's a plot.
This is accumulating
radiation damage.
So this is the time that
you run your fusion device.
And this is the
superconductor performance.
And one of the
things you see is all
of the work we've
done in the community
for the last few decades has
been done at room temperature
because it's really hard
to irradiate things cold.
And here is all the irradiation.
Here's how things
degrade when it's cold.
And, when things are
cold, they degrade 60%
faster than they
normally degrade.
So all of the work we've
done to date has just
been upended by this
result. Putting things
in the right environment,
doing it quickly
gets us answers that we
need to better design for.
The last facility I
want to talk about
is, how do we deal with
structural materials?
So we have a new
technique that's
been developed here where we can
actually use very high intensity
proton beams at higher energy.
We can irradiate bulk
material specimens.
And we get a bunch
of advantages.
OK, we can actually change
the energy of the beam.
We can modify the type
of damage that we're
introducing to materials.
We can do this in
bulk specimens, which
means we can put those materials
into things like tensile tests.
Instead of doing TEM imaging
and looking at micrographs
and other things,
we can actually
get engineering property
data, things engineers
want to design materials.
And so, right now,
my last slide,
the PSFC is gearing up to
basically build a completely new
facility, a "first of a kind"
facility that will be major,
which is actually leveraging
a lot of the advantages
of the infrastructure at MIT and
the expertise to basically build
a facility that'll damage
materials 100 times faster than
the application and hundreds
times faster than things like
IFMIF, big device I showed you
that might be operational in 20
years.
And we can actually do this
with off-the-shelf technology.
And we can have this thing
running in 18 months.
OK we can end up
with beamlines that
are doing lots of different
kinds of irradiation.
We can do them in
complex environments
where you irradiate
material in contact
with that hot liquid metal.
So we can investigate
corrosion, radiation challenges.
And I think, most importantly,
given the time scales that we've
been talking about,
we can get data
to companies that need it in the
span of years, not in decades.
Thanks.
[AUDIENCE]
OK.
Hi, everyone.
I'm Cristina Rea.
I'm a principal research
scientist at the PSFC.
so [INAUDIBLE] damages
that Zach introduced.
I'm going to talk
about disruptions.
So fusion plasmas, we
have to confine them
at very high temperature, high
densities, hotter than the sun.
And so we assisted highly
nonlinear [INAUDIBLE]
interactions and the
interactions of the plasma
with the device that
is confining it.
Sometimes, we are unable to
control the plasma because
of the growth of instabilities.
And what can happen?
So we are looking now
at the plasma and not
necessarily at the hardware
issues, the material issues.
So what happens now is that
we can incur in disruptions.
So the final disruptions
can be defined
as a sudden loss of control.
And I wanted to show you this
time series from the Alcator
C-Mod experiment that we were
hosting at the MIT Plasma
Science and Fusion
Center until 2016.
And the space will be
reused for the facility
that Zach was mentioning.
So here are normal
plasma operations.
So, typically,
during experiments,
we ramp up the current.
We conduct our experiments.
And then we ramp it down safely.
But what disruptions mean is
that this fast loss of control
evolves on timescales
of milliseconds.
And suddenly all current
and temperatures drop.
And this leads to the loss of
a confining poloidal field.
The current
transients, basically,
in turn, induce large
forces and currents.
And the rapid
thermal loss that can
occur on some
milliseconds timescales
can also induce thermal
damages and surface damages.
So time series are what
I work day to day with.
But it's useful to take a
look at in what it means,
like from the point
of view of a video.
Here we are looking at
video, which used to work.
And maybe it works?
Here, yeah.
This is a camera
view from the-- we
are looking at the inside of
the Alcator C-Mod tokamak.
That is the central solenoid.
The plasma is heating up.
And then, at some
point, it disrupts.
What you see there
are materials that
are being eroded off the walls,
as Zach was mentioning before.
And the growth of
such instabilities
that are occurring when
the plasma is pushed
to beyond the
controllability limits
that's associated to the
occurrence of disruptions.
So the direct cause
is melting of surfaces
that are enclosing the plasma.
In current
experiments, what we do
is typically we accept the
damage, we live with it,
and we continue to
run our experiments
to improve the operational
spaces of stability.
But, when we want to optimize
our plasma performances, what
we try to do is to mitigate
the damage by radiating away as
much and as fast as possible.
Going forward, we really need
to work on disruption prevention
strategies in order to
reduce the disruption
rate and the disruption risk.
And this means detecting
the precursor stages
and steering the plasma away
from the disruptive boundary
to interpret both metrics.
One tricky thing is
that disruptions are not
necessarily well described
from first principle models.
However, we've been operating
these devices for years
and years, and so we have
available a huge amount
of experimental data.
And so our team,
at the PSFC, has
been looking into data-driven
and machine learning
models, which can provide
an explainable proximity
to the unstable
operational space.
Here, in the top panel,
you can see again
the plasma current time
trace with the disruption
of terrain over here.
And then overlaid, there
is a blue time trace
which was obtained through
a machine learning model
that is tracking the approaching
of the unstable operational
space.
And it's giving a
warning that a disruption
is about to happen several
hundred of milliseconds
before the disruption.
This basically
enables us to take--
this was run in open loop.
So there was no action and
no intervention steering
the plasma away from
this instability limit.
But it gives us confidence
that we can actually
do experiments and maintain
the plasma stability
and expand the
plasma survivability.
In the top-- in
the bottom panel,
you can see also that we are
able to design algorithms that
are interpretable,
that are explainable,
and that we can design.
We can extract important
features and contributions
to disruptivity
relativity that are
useful information for
the plasma control system
to maintain and preserve
the [INAUDIBLE] itself.
And, indeed, if we
design these algorithms
and we close the
loop in real time,
we are actually able to
demonstrate that the plasma
survivability can be extended.
This is another example from
a grad student work that I'm
working with, Andrew Maris.
And we ran an experiment
last summer time
at [INAUDIBLE], where we found
the collisionality at the plasma
edge as an indicator
of a disruption
risk for a certain
type of disruption.
We were tracking
this in real time.
And, without the
controller in the loop,
you could see that the
plasma disrupts here
at around 3.5 seconds.
And, instead with the controller
on, we can extend the lifetime
and improve on the plasma
[INAUDIBLE] and the stability.
ML is great, but
we really need data
to basically build these
models and define these models
in an accurate way.
And so an additional example of
the work that the team is doing
is working on interoperable
and open source libraries that
are available for
retrieving quickly
data across many
different fusion devices.
And this actually
enables the assembly
of big databases for machine
learning applications.
We've just released this
product a couple of weeks ago,
and it's called
Disruption [? Pi. ?]
Connects to different
data repositories
across different tokamak
experimental devices
and prepares these [INAUDIBLE].
And this is really an
enabling instrument
because ML model development
is just the tip of the iceberg
while the data
preparation part is really
like what is [INAUDIBLE].
The disruptions team at
the PSFC is really big,
includes more than 20 people
between scientists, postdocs
and students and collaborators.
And ML and AI tools are
really used ubiquitously
across many different projects.
I was able to just give
an example of a couple
active projects.
We have notable
collaborations with CFS
where we are really working
towards the disruption
prevention strategies for SPARC.
And we are partnering also
with any ENI and the data
science [INAUDIBLE].
And, also, we have
collaborators [INAUDIBLE].
The widely spread
use of ML and AI
tools at the Plasma
Science and Fusion Center
basically earned the plasma--
the designation of a
collaborating center,
an IEA collaborating
center in AI and Fusion
and Plasma Science
around the topics
of research and education.
So this is a five-year
cost-free agreement
that we signed last year.
It builds on already actively
funded grants that we have,
and it revolves around three
main pillars, so development
of open science and fair
access to fusion data
and metadata information for
preservation and provenance,
tracking, the dissemination of
accessible research products
to enable cross-pollination
among communities
and accelerate the development
of fusion research,
and education training
and capacity building
in applied fusion science.
So we can work towards
a diversified workforce
to accelerate progress
towards [INAUDIBLE].
And that was my last.
[AUDIENCE]
Yeah, so we're going to
talk a little bit more
about the tritium aspects that
have come up a few times so
far during this session.
So, as you may have heard
or you may already know,
most of the proposed
fusion power plant
concepts that is
being pursued right
now by the private industry
will use deuterium and tritium
as fuel.
So, just as a recap, if you
were to zoom into that plasma
to see the particles
that are fusing,
you have a deuterium nucleus, a
deuteron, and a tritium nucleus,
a triton.
And those fuse, and
then this results
in a very high-energy neutron.
So that's 14 MeV.
So that's about
seven times higher
than the fastest neutrons you
would see in a fission spectrum.
And then helium ash,
also pretty high energy.
So tritium is scarce.
Deuterium is not.
But tritium is
very, very scarce.
And so we know that we're
going to have to figure out
how to breed our own using
the neutrons that come off
of the plasma fusion reaction.
So, over there, on the
left, in the arrow,
you can see, in the
plasma, just a reminder
of what that reaction is.
D plus T yields a high-energy
neutron and an alpha particle.
And then we can
capture that neutron
in the blanket that
surrounds the plasma core.
So we refer to this often
just as the blanket,
but you also hear the
terminology breeder blanket.
And so this reaction
is going to be
lithium interacting with a
neutron to produce tritium
and then some combination
of other things.
But tritium is the
important part there.
The breeding blanket also has
other important functions.
So this includes shielding.
The blanket moderates
and absorbs neutrons,
and this helps
shield the magnet.
So that's very important to
the longevity of the plant.
If the blanket wasn't there,
it would be much, much
harder to extract
useful lifetime out
of the magnets and
the other components.
Heat capture, that's a big one.
So that heat carried
by the neutrons,
we're going to capture
that in the blanket.
That's how we're actually
going to generate our power.
And then, finally,
the tritium breeding,
which is one of the
major focuses right now
of the US fusion technology
research community.
So this is making more
fuel in that breeder.
So it's going to
contain lithium.
And the neutron from the plasma
interacts with the lithium
to get tritium that we can, in
theory, extract and then use
again as fuel.
So there's multiple
forms of lithium
that you are--
lithium-containing materials
that you can choose for
your breeder blanket.
So conventional
blankets frequently
will use various
lithium ceramic solids.
There's at least
20 or 30 that have
been studied in the literature
over the last 50 years or so.
Here, a liquid lithium.
This is one that is being
pursued potentially by the UK,
has the disadvantage of
being very chemically
reactive with moisture.
So a big safety issue,
but very good breeding
because all of your volume
is just breeder material.
Molten lead-lithium, this is
a very popular one right now.
And then molten
salts like FLIBe.
So FLIBe is the current one
that has a lot of interest
in the fusion community.
This is the primary breeder
material being pursued
by Commonwealth Fusion Systems.
Although, I want to
reiterate, none of these--
there's no obvious winner
for breeder blankets.
We might wind up developing
many different kinds.
You might see many
different kinds deployed,
but, also, crucially, no one has
demonstrated a working breeding
blanket in a prototypic
environment at scale.
So even though some
of these concepts
have more research
behind them than others,
it's really anyone's game.
There's no obvious winner yet.
So beryllium and lead,
you'll see these a lot.
Beryllium in the
FLIBe, lead lithium.
There's also certain fluoride
lithium salts that contain lead.
These are important because
they're neutron multipliers.
So a neutron that hits one of
these that doesn't interact
with lithium is going to usually
go into an end-to-end reaction.
And what this means is
it gives you a nice boost
to your tritium
breeding in the blanket.
As you're designing
your blanket,
you also need to be thinking
about infrastructure
for chemistry control
and heat removal.
And, importantly, if you have
to think about one metric,
if you're listening to talks
about breeder blankets,
they're going to talk about
the tritium breeding ratio.
And they're almost always going
to just abbreviate this to TBR.
And the TBR is very simple.
It's just a number of
tritons that you're
producing over the number of
tritons that are being consumed.
And the TBR that
you need for a plant
to be tritium
self-sufficient is going
to vary based on a lot
of different parameters.
And that's going to be governed
by everything from just
the straight-up geometry of the
plant and its power production
targets to different
operating decisions
and design choices that the
operating company has made.
So this is not a
set-in-stone thing.
Sometimes you'll hear people say
that you just need a TBR of 1
or a TBR of like 1.05,
so a little bit of margin
for uncertainties.
And that's not true.
So if you were a
power plant designer,
you really want to think about
your entire fuel cycle system
and make sure that you know,
what is the minimum TBR you
need to achieve?
And then also, is your
blanket able to achieve that?
Because there's going
to be some upper maximum
theoretical limit on the
TBR that any given blanket
can achieve based on the
power output of the plant
and the geometry of the blanket.
It's really just it's a
straight-up neutronics problem.
So we are investigating
molten salt,
liquid immersion blankets for
the ARC class fusion power
plant.
This is the concept that
is being put forward
by Commonwealth Fusion Systems.
So the liquid immersion blanket
abbreviated usually to LIB,
it's basically a giant
tank of molten salt
in which the tokamak
containing the plasma
is sort of suspended or held.
And so the reason that
we want to do this
is that it's very simple.
So, in theory, you're going
to get some cost and design
savings just in terms of
the structural materials
and the manifolds that you need.
You maximize solid
angle coverage this way
of your plasma neutron source.
So, again, just coming
back to neutronics,
I want every neutron to
interact with breeder and not
with a nonbreeding
structural material if I can.
That's also going to
give me advantages
for activation purposes.
The gives you
efficient heat removal,
very important for
high energy density
concepts like ARC
and the ability
to have online
chemistry control.
So conventional blankets have
a lot of research behind them,
but they tend to
have a lot of really
complex, solid structures.
And this is going to give
you activation concerns,
lower TBR, and also challenges
for maintenance as well.
So the high-breeding
efficiency of the LIB
is important because
this is going
to let us do doubling
of the tritium inventory
a lot faster in a plant.
So conventional
blankets, we expect
to have a doubling
time of about 10 years,
meaning that the
time it takes-- you
have a certain start
up inventory of tritium
that your plant needs.
And you need to double that
because if you're a company,
you're going to want to
build more than one fusion
power plant.
And so if we were to use
conventional blanket technology,
it would take us like over
70 years just to reach--
from the time that you
start deploying fusion
to reach a tenth of a terawatt.
So that is not the type
of energy penetration
that we've been talking
about when we talk about,
why do fusion?
So even if you were to solve
every other technical problem,
if you didn't make
a better blanket,
you were going to be inherently
limiting your industry.
So, just as sort of--
our LIBRA experiment
at MIT is what
we are doing to advance molten
breeder salt blanket technology.
So this is basically trying
to use a GT commercial neutron
generator to get a
prototypic neutron
spectrum in representative
temperature,
molten-applied
salt. So this is not
going to be the same fluence
as a fusion power plant.
But everything else
is quite similar
chemically and neutronically.
And this lets us really
understand how tritium
is going to behave in FLIBe.
We're doing a staged
experimental approach
going from small to
much larger volumes
due to the technical challenges
as well as the safety
challenges that are
inherent in working
with high-temperature materials
containing HF and beryllium.
So this is really important
because there are enormous
uncertainties regarding how
tritium behaves in FLIBe,
a "3 to 4 order of magnitude"
spread for things like
solubility, diffusivity.
We need really good
information on this
in order to design a
working power plant.
We cannot go from this type of
spread in the data to a plant
that we know will work.
So that's why it's
really important
that we have experiments that
are designed for reliability
and repeatability.
I want to emphasize
that the breeder
blanket is just one part of a
very complex fuel cycle system.
We need to understand
how tritium behaves
throughout the entire fuel
cycle, so not just the blanket,
but also extracting it,
purifying it, storing
it, reinject it back
into the plasma.
These are all pretty low TRL.
So there's a lot of work ongoing
to advance these technologies.
And so, just to
recap really quickly,
the DT plants, you
want to remember,
they need to breed
their own tritium.
So, for a given concept,
how are they doing that?
What is their
breeder technology?
Do they have a
concept that is going
to double that inventory
at a fast enough time
to ensure the success
of the Fusion Industry?
And finally, here at MIT,
just down the street,
we're undertaking a very
ambitious and staged approach.
This is actively
underway at the PSFC.
It's really exciting
work, and we are really
looking forward to what comes
next out of this project.
Thank you.
[AUDIENCE]
Hello, everybody.
I'm Ethan Peterson.
I'm an assistant professor in
nuclear science and engineering
and at the Plasma Science
and Fusion Center.
And neutrons, Sara
just said, again,
it all comes back
to the neutrons.
And that's why I have a job.
So we're going to talk entirely
about neutrons for the next five
minutes, more or less.
And how do these neutrons impact
fusion power plant design?
Well, as you've heard
throughout the night,
they impact it greatly.
So the neutrons carry
80% of DT fusion energy.
And we use Monte
Carlo simulations
to calculate the distributions
or the populations
of these neutrons everywhere
throughout the power plant.
So they're born here at 14
MeV, and they scatter and lose
their energy as they travel
down to the thermal range.
However, I wrote here
that the mean free path
or the average distance between
collisions for 14 MeV neutrons
in steel is 5 centimeters.
And it takes them 500
collisions to lose that energy.
So what does this mean?
This means that fusion
neutrons travel extremely far
at high energy, and they cause
damage like Zach talked about.
They heat things up.
They cause dose.
They transmute things,
and they produce reactions
that make things
radioactive, which
is what transmutation is here.
And so, in the context of
designing a power plant,
how does this affect us?
Well, we have our plasma
here, and we have the neutrons
that are flying out.
And we have a few
different subsystems.
We have our magnets.
We have a vacuum vessel that
has plasma-facing components.
And one of the functions or
consequences of these neutrons
is that we need to
capture their energy
and generate tritium, which is
what Sara just talked about.
But we also have to
protect these magnets.
So they have very high energy.
Neutrons, displace
atoms, cause damage,
reduce the superconducting
qualities of the magnets.
We also have to engineer
these plasma-facing components
and structural materials
to be able to withstand
high fluences of high-energy
neutron radiation.
And we also have to protect
workers and the public
from direct and shutdown dose.
And so the fact that
all of these neutrons
are traveling very far
through this reactor,
they significantly impact
every single subsystem
that goes into the power plant.
And this manifests
itself in determining
system requirements on every
single subsystem, more or less,
in a fusion power plant.
Yet neutronics
calculations often
take the longest to execute.
So this slows down the entire
design iteration process
for every single fusion concept.
And so what we need is
fast and accurate methods
to compute the responses
of these neutrons
and quantify their
uncertainties.
And we'll get to this
a little bit later.
But the reason that we need to
quantify these uncertainties
is so that we can set
accurate engineering margins
because overly conservative
engineering margins are
going to make your plant
totally economically unviable.
So I'm going to walk
through a brief analysis
that I like to do called the
shutdown dose rate, which
is, essentially, the
dose worker would receive
going into the plant
to do maintenance
after some time of operation.
Call that the SDR.
And so how do we get there?
We start with our
neutron transport solve,
calculating with our Monte Carlo
code where the neutrons go,
what their populations are.
And this requires some
inputs of nuclear data
and some model definitions like
our little cute reactor concept
up here.
And what we do is we get
reaction rates, neutron reaction
rates, and we do what we
call an activation solve,
so how the atoms in
the whole power plant
evolve and become
different atoms over time.
And what that gives us is
activated material compositions,
everywhere throughout
the whole power plant.
And what this does is now
these activated radioactive
compositions constitute photon
sources or gamma sources.
And each of those
little bits of material
have an associated
photon spectrum.
And what we need to take--
what we need to do is put that
photon spectrum into our Monte
Carlo solver, do the
photon transport,
and calculate this map of what
the dose would be for workers
going into the power plant.
And this seems all very,
very straightforward.
And the reason I like to
highlight this sort of workflow
is that, along the way, we get
all of the nuclear responses
that we need to analyze or
assess any sort of subsystem
in the fusion power plant.
So, for example, from here
we get energy deposition,
damage, tritium production.
From this step, we get things
like waste disposal ratings.
So how do you store some
of the radioactive material
that you've produced in
your fusion power plant.
You also get just the
nuclide inventories
and [INAUDIBLE]
produced over time.
And then, from the
photon spectrums,
we have radiation
sources that we
need to account for when we're
moving them from place to place
and do shielding analysis.
Now, it would be great if
this was so streamlined,
and it was just very clear that
you put your inputs into one
code, and then you get
the shutdown dose rate,
but what it actually looks like
right now in the current fusion
neutronics ecosystem is
all of these barriers
between these different
steps of the code.
And these are different
codes maintained
by different developers, many of
which are under export control.
And, a lot of times,
the software plumbing,
which is what I call
these little arrows that
go from place to place,
aren't maintained
by any of those organizations.
And so you could
imagine validating
these types of workflows.
And quality assuring
them is extremely
challenging for something
that's critically
important for a lot of safety
considerations and regulations.
So these barriers, furthermore,
from a scientific and a research
perspective, prevent our ability
to propagate the uncertainties
that we need to propagate
from one step to the next.
And so, ultimately, we can't
put rigorously determined
engineering margins on
these types of calculations
in the current ecosystem.
And so what we've gone and done
over the last handful of years
is to develop this entire
streamlined workflow
within a single open
source code called
OpenMC, which was
invented here at MIT
by a grad student
and his advisor,
Ben Forget, the current head
of the Department of Nuclear
Science and Engineering.
And what this gains us is that
we have single sources of truth
for nuclear data and for
all of our model inputs.
And they're used by every
step along the process.
And there's one source of
truth for all of these modules
and the software plumbing
that's maintained
by a single development
team, but it's also
community developed.
And that's one of
the big drivers
that I think fusion
needs to latch on
to is taking advantage
of collaborations
and community-driven
projects like this to deliver
high-performance engineering
tools for the design of fusion
power plants.
And so, yeah, let's see
what's the endpoint of this.
Well, we'll keep going.
To end, the goal here is to
build an analysis platform that
provides us all of the
nuclear analysis end
points in the design
of a fusion power plant
and to make this streamlined,
user-friendly, high performance,
and allow us to propagate
these uncertainties to deliver
engineering margins
on these power plants.
And so, here, I've made this
cartoon plot of some example
fusion neutronics
analysis that I've
pulled from the
literature for devices
of varying size and complexity.
And the discrepancy
here is what I'm
calling the difference
between what we compute
and what we measure
in the experiment.
And it's not uncommon
to get factors
of 10 difference between what we
measure and what we calculate.
And because neutrons touch every
subsystem in the fusion power
plant, that's untenable.
And, basically, if you're
carrying 10x engineering
margins, many, many places
throughout your design,
it's not going to work out.
And so what this
ultimately means
is that, to have confidence in
our predictive modeling tools,
we need to find better
agreement between experiments
and simulations for these
very large, complex systems.
So bringing
something that trends
like this down to something
that trends like this
so that we can actually
design systems effectively.
So that's the end of my talk.
[AUDIENCE]
I think we're running
later than we should.
And that's entirely my fault.
I think I spoke for way more
than I should have.
So should we see if there are
questions from the audience
so that we don't
run out of time?
And, Dennis, it would be very
awkward for you not to be here.
So everybody should consider--
everybody should consider
Dennis White as
part of this panel
as well, if you'll be so kind.
Questions from the audience.
He loves to answer them.
I can suggest a slightly
provocatory one,
and that is the question
of whether fusion, energy
and fusion science is worth
pursuing even if this study were
to conclude that it will
never be economically viable?
And I have my own
answer to this.
And I'm actually-- this
is not a planted question.
I actually am genuinely curious
to see what people think.
Well, let me give you
the perspective for why
the answer might still be yes.
So, for example, one
thing I work on right
now is developing
quantum algorithms
for solving plasma equations.
And it turns out that the
fusion community is actually
arguably the most advanced
community in science
and engineering at actually
trying to answer this question.
Can one solve nonlinear
partial differential equations
on a quantum [INAUDIBLE]?
Now, I'm interested in this
because of plasma physics
and fusion.
But nonlinear partial
differential equations
are not the exclusive property
of plasmas [INAUDIBLE].
Like many fields, arguably, we
all feel at MIT [INAUDIBLE] that
are worth their salt--
I'm going to say this live--
require nonlinear PDEs.
And so we're sort of seeing
that the algorithms that we
are promoting for how to solve
nonlinear PDEs on a quantum
computer are actually of
interest across board.
So that's, for
example, one idea that
started in fusion, which I'm
sure we'll see many applications
in different systems.
But I wonder if, in materials,
in machine learning,
in the neutronic
calculations, in blanket
designs and
elsewhere, we're going
to see similar ramifications.
Dennis, you had your hand up.
As a species, I would
argue that we always need
to keep challenging ourselves.
So you saw how hard it is, by
the way, of these four talks.
It is not a cakewalk to make
fusion economic and viable.
It is going to be
very difficult.
And, honestly, we don't
know all of the impediments
along the way.
They're pretty well
characterized now,
but we've got to be honest
about-- we should do that.
And the reason that we
do it is because, when
we try really, really hard
things, we find out new things.
And I think a great example of
that-- because you alluded to it
very quickly was
the geothermal work,
is that namely heating
these exotic plasmas
is very difficult.
And we were forced
to invent some very exotic
kinds of technologies.
And it turns out--
called gyrotrons which
produce very intense
submillimeter wave Rf.
This looks like it
actually has some chance
of providing deep bore
drilling capabilities
for advanced geothermal.
Would you have
ever imagined that?
That's why we should keep
doing this is because--
we should keep pursuing
this because it's
at the frontier of our
knowledge and our capabilities.
[INAUDIBLE]
I think we were--
I mean, for what,
like 30, 40 years,
I don't think we thought that
fusion had an economic outlook.
And we still pursued it anyways.
And I think a lot
of great things
have come out of
[INAUDIBLE] incredible,
just from a science perspective.
I think we still value that
inherently, regardless.
And the HTS
superconductor, which
really is why we're on
this accelerated path.
Let's be honest because it's
the most science-knowing path
that we're on didn't
come from fusion.
It came from some
material scientists
doing incredible discovery
and advancements themselves.
And that's the cool thing about.
And it's, actually, I
think, why MIT succeeds
so well in something like this.
It comes from surprises and
multidisciplinary connections
that actually allow us to
make those deep innovations.
I didn't answer your
question directly.
And it was on-- maybe
it was Randy's slide.
Or maybe Bob's slide.
But the report doesn't
predict what fusion will cost.
And it doesn't predict
when fusion will happen.
And that's because it cannot.
We cannot actually predict what
something will cost until we go
out and do it in a
commercial environment.
And so I think Dennis
and I have talked--
what's that?
Yeah, your air bands
are what Ethan showed.
They're 100x,.
Who knows?
And it's not just
the technology,
it's the environment
that you're doing it in.
We cannot predict what will be
the environment in 50 years.
And, actually, something
Dennis and I have talked about,
one of the exciting things about
starting CFS and seeing what
happens with SPARC is not
actually a technology result
or a physics result. It's that,
unlike every federally funded
fusion program ever,
CFS will know intimately
what it costs to the
dollar to deploy fusion
technology in a commercial way.
And we've never had that before.
So it'll actually be one
of the first data points
we've ever had about what
fusion actually will cost.
And that's exciting.
Coming from a famous exchange
with the leader of the largest
fusion program in
the world that says
this project was designed
that we will never know
the cost of it, which I was--
which was a
political expediency.
But, actually, what this study--
and which I tell to my
international fusion colleagues
over and over again, if it
doesn't cost the right at the--
come in at the right cost
point, no one's going to use it.
And it's like this study
clearly showed actually that.
And another thing that might
pertinent to discuss quickly
is the choice that we made
here is highly curated.
We chose some of the
things that the PSFC's
working on because they
are mission critical.
But these aren't all the
mission critical things.
So perhaps we can
have a little bit
of a discussion about what
else we could be doing
if we had enough resources.
Sky is the limit, yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
[INAUDIBLE] go back to
the [INAUDIBLE] study.
So, Dennis, you might be
the most appropriate to
comment on that.
But, I mean, in Zach's
work with the cyclotron, so
building materials,
testing facilities,
building an actual
fusion-prototypic neutron
source.
So this is an active
area in the US right now.
We're doing the risk
reduction activity for that.
But knowing that facility to
do what we would want to do
is going to cost
around $1 billion,
so we're very resource
limited in that regard.
Better computational resources.
[INAUDIBLE]
Sure, we have
plenty of questions
that are unsolved
through which we
would benefit by partnering with
industry partners that are--
whose computational problems
are day-to-day problems.
They are addressing
those problems
in day-to-day solutions.
So, yeah, that's
definitely [INAUDIBLE].
OK.
Go back?
Yeah, I agree with
all of these points.
If they go back to something
that Nuno had mentioned earlier
in the talk about the importance
of training the fusion
workforce, I feel
like even if we
had a windfall of billions
and billions of dollars,
we wouldn't be able to
functionally spend it correctly
because we don't have the people
or the educators currently
in the system.
Inspired from this
study, in fact,
with Layla, who
we had mentioned,
who was one of the
contributors to the study,
then she and I actually
started putting together
a generalized cost
effectiveness or economic model
that showed about-- is generic
to any kind of fusion concept.
And what it was indicating is
that the key global parameters
were power density and the
ability to change the damaged
materials on a fast time scale.
In the economic
sensitivity, these
came out as the greatest ones.
And I would point out
is that we tend to not
think of those
because, in fact, those
are two technical topics that
weren't directly mentioned
in these, which is that the
higher you can get the power
density globally is attractive.
And then it could be
that we actually--
as long as you know when the
materials are going to fail,
we actually just replace
them quickly rather
than thinking about them
lasting a long time.
So I think there's
a whole set of--
the way I look at
it, as we cast fusion
into more of an economic
problem than a physics problem,
we're going to start
actually revealing
more of these challenges.
[INAUDIBLE]
So thank [INAUDIBLE].
So thank you for your talk.
It's a brilliant introduction
to fusion for those of us
who are not very familiar
with the challenges.
I saw on the slides mention of
the ITER experimental facility.
It would be nice if
you could maybe--
because this is a big challenge
that you're talking about.
And I would maybe ask,
what kind of collaboration
do you have with ITER?
Because I know from different
readings and stuff that
they've been doing
some good stuff.
So how do you describe working
together between Europe
and the US on
something like this?
I can--
OK.
Are you going to
load this one on me?
Jump under the gun, then.
Maybe Cristina.
No, Cristina.
No, yeah, we definitely
have strong relationship,
and we are providing
good contributions
to the ITER physics
spaces, which was actually
instrumental to the development
of the SPARC physics spaces.
So all the experience that we
gained by studying and preparing
for ITER--
[INAUDIBLE] is going to come
up if it's going to come up.
It's been instrumental also for
returning risks on the physics,
on some physics
aspects for SPARC.
PSFC members are actively
involved in ITER research
through the ITER expert
groups and topical groups.
So we join meetings
every couple of--
yeah, twice a year
in different areas.
We contribute to
specific investigations
by gathering data points
on experimental devices,
conducting modeling,
and connecting
through the different
facilities internationally.
So we are pretty much involved
in ITER research still.
I think there's some tension on
the technology side with ITER.
It's not-- nothing's bad.
We are really impressed
and supportive
of the ITER and the demo
teams, demo being the general--
the power plants that would
follow in the ITER concept.
But one of the issues that we
encounter on the technology side
is that-- so the demo
is based on ITER.
And ITER was
started in the '80s.
And so, when you start a
project and it has a 40-,
50-year timeline to completion,
the world and technology is
going to evolve
separately from you.
And so the designs
of the power plants
that the private
industry is looking at,
they're very, very different
than what ITER is looking at.
And, as a result, we're taking
on different approaches,
et cetera.
But the demo program in
Europe remains quite the same.
And so there's a
mix of things that
are very relevant to us and then
other things that are just not.
And I have found tension
in my own program
is that the US has a sort of
standard commitment to ITER.
And this is great, except
for the fact that we have
very limited funds available.
So if you only have a pie that's
this big and most of the pie
has to be allocated
to ITER and demo,
regardless of what the US
program is interested in,
that creates conflicts,
I guess, in terms
of what priorities need to be.
And, ideally, this goes
back to the blue sky thing,
is that we would like
to be able to do both.
But we are resource-
and people-limited.
And ITER is very important.
First of all, it reminds
us, this is hard.
And, in fact, SPARC is actually
the only other in construction
burning plasma
experiment, namely one
that gets high energy
gain in the world.
And SPARC is hard as well too.
And the quote-- because it's
sent back to me very often
because I originated it.
I said, so ITER has incredible
science interest and validity,
but it is not
economically interesting
because take the
cost point of it,
and you can see about how much
it would cost per unit watt.
It's so far off the
chart of what we just
showed on the plots.
So this is-- it almost goes back
to Nuno's original question is
that, would we keep doing this?
ITER, even though it didn't
have economic projection
or viability, was an incredibly
worthwhile science project
because it built the science
basis for what then we
could actually launch,
actually, into this as well too.
Programmatically, about
what it means as Fusion
as an energy source is a
much more complex debate.
But I think it is
already showing that it's
too slow and too expensive.
And, in some sense,
ITER, unfortunately,
can also be a counterexample
to people pointing to fusion
and saying, look, we told
you it wasn't going to work.
And I don't think that
that's the correct answer.
Is that nice enough?
That was very good.
[INAUDIBLE]
So this is a very
high-level question,
and excuse its
complete ignorance,
but I'm just trying to get an
idea in terms of proportionally,
how much money is being spent
or has been allotted, say,
relative to the space
program in the '60s.
It's a small fraction of that.
Yeah, it's-- compared
to the-- yeah.
Well, I mean, it's--
no, I mean-- it's--
cumulatively, compared
to the space program,
it's probably
around 5%, something
like that in the world
compared to what has been
used for the space program.
So I'm just going back
to Nuno's question.
I mean, it would
seem like this would
have similar importance to the
improvement of human existence.
Where's the money?
That's-- yeah.
We should end there.
Well, I mean, no, no, it is--
I mean, because
we're often asked.
It's like, do we need an Apollo
program or something like this?
It's actually-- I answer no.
And the reason for
that is because this
is a different kind of--
I mean, I could argue ITER,
which is at the $50 billion
scale, it's kind of an
Apollo-scale program.
Our end goal is actually
not to make fusion--
just fusion science work.
It's to make fusion as an
economic energy product.
And so those things like the--
was not that.
And so, in many
ways, I think we're
trying to make
more like a SpaceX,
that, namely, it has roots in
those incredible accomplishments
that were done in government
and public programs.
But it has to have a goal
of economic viability.
Otherwise, it's going to
impact in nobody's life ever.
I would argue that the fusion
design space is enormous.
There are many possible
knobs, generally speaking.
And it's very hard
to optimize anything
if you basically have
two experiments or three
in the world.
So we are not
sampling the space--
nowhere close to
where we should be
in terms of knowing
what it is that we
do better so that we can
maximize fusion power
production.
So I think we should be
building more of these machines.
And they are getting built
in the UK and in China.
Not here.
So if you were inspired
by anything you saw today,
please write your
congressman or congressperson
and say, why do we
have-- so point out,
it was actually up
on your slides, Nuno.
We have a cost sharing
program, which is basically
like SpaceX infusion.
And, against $7 billion,
the federal government
has allocated $45 million.
So only government can say 0.4%
is cost matching into this.
It's a bold, decadal
vision where we've
wasted three years already.
[INAUDIBLE] an
official [INAUDIBLE].
They stated that
this is a priority
to have fusion on
the grid by 2035.
So what we want to see is
the money match [INAUDIBLE].
But it is an important
part of American leadership
in this area where the
leading fusion companies are
in the US, a lot thanks to
MIT, I would argue, in this,
yet we are not getting the
commensurate support that's
needed from the
public side in this
because this is a big lift
about getting these going.
So I'm not kidding.
If you're inspired by this and
you think this is important,
pick up the phone,
write a letter.
It's like, this is an important
thing where we as a government
are lagging behind.
[INAUDIBLE] and all of our
audience for your participation
in this program.
I do want to invite you to
our reception downstairs
on the first floor.
And I hope I can also
show you upcoming events.
So on the 13th of November,
we have our next major event
at the Wong auditorium.
So this is an opportunity
to attend our colloquium
that we have each year at
the MIT Energy Initiative.
So we hope you join us there.
[INAUDIBLE]
What?
Yes, exactly.
So do plan to join
us for that event.
And I invite our
speakers and all of you
to join us for the reception and
continue the conversation there.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]