and uh I realized I made a rookie
mistake because uh every title that is a
question you know hints that the answer
is no right this this applies to
headlines called very slow headlines um
right if you ask a question for a title
then means you're not sure so let me
rephrase actually yes AI is ready uh to
transform chemistry and Material Science
um so please take it on the affirmative
not as a question um and I'll give you
some evidence of why I'm sort of you
ready to say yes um you know you all use
probably experienced GPT right if
anything has changed over the last
decade is things that touch machine
learning and deep learning right we've
we've really been seeing sort of
transformational change at a scale that
uh that is hard to perceive since we're
inside it but you know go was solved you
know it was supposed to be an
untractable combinatorial problem and it
was solved a decade ago and you know you
can see the examples of you know things
that we thought require lots of human
creativity and human Talent like making
good images turn out they can be just
interpolated from known images in ways
that we really didn't expect like I said
5 to 10 years ago and then in the
physical sciences or in the in the
Sciences we've got our big examples over
the last you know four to five weeks
when two Nobel prizes were awarding two
AI Technologies right one for for for
the foundational work in physics and
another one for the alpha fall prot
structure prediction task right and this
has been a combination of compute
algorithms and data right being able to
deploy big data sets or make them uh put
them into this uh gpus that Nvidia makes
and that's why one they're one of the
most valuable companies in the world and
algorithms that are specific to the
tasks um and I for instance will never
write a cover letter in my life I'm
going to ask GPT to write a cover letter
for me and I suspect you know people
that apply for jobs that you companies
or my school are using GPD for cover
letter this okay we want that in
material science and chemistry right we
want to have ai tell us well this is an
amazing drug this is a absorbent that
will capture CO2 out of the air this is
a battery electrolyte that will enable
uh you know lithium metal batteries um
for Aviation okay well this is kind of
slightly different than what AI has done
in most other places right because we're
asking it to be better than the best
scientist has been so far which is kind
of a much harder task than just getting
a picture of an astronaut on the moon
right now we're asking for the best
possible picture of an astronaut on the
moon one I want to you know patent and
sell um and we're never going to have as
much data as some of his other tasks
right there's a lot more images in the
internet than there are electrolytes or
you know etching materials um to our
advantage perhaps is that we know the
rules of the game right physics governs
or should govern everything we do in the
in the physical sciences meaning that
there are underlying equations that we
either know and should be able to
exploit or you know can assume are there
even if you cannot explicitly write them
and although that's not necessarily a a
a foregone conclusion I'll give you more
um so what are things that AI does today
and you know maybe your companies do
companies out there do uh what what we
call actual property prediction right
just like um you know you trust a
Machine Vision algorithm to classify
whether a picture is a cat or not
because there is plenty of cut data to
to train it on if there is enough data
in the thousands maybe tens of thousands
of something we can totally train neural
networks that go from matter to property
and this could be you know toxicity of
molecules ionic conductivity of crystals
you know fluoresence of proteins so all
of these materials classes of chemical
classes have had neural networks make
for them that allow structure property
predictions um we can use AI for
synthesis planning right not just
telling you well this is a good chemical
but also to plan how to make it in
chemistry because data has been very
structured for a long time the chemists
are very laboriously collecting the way
they make chemicals there are big
databases and there are
retrosynthesis as a product services
today so you can just go to the Internet
and look you know chemical synthesis Ai
and you will find vendors that will give
you today the GPT version of chemical
synthesis where you say how would I make
this chemical and the AI says well buy
these precursors put them together in
this way you will be able to make this
molecule that exists today it's
commoditize for molecules for materials
is a little bit tricky right because you
know when when you say materials maybe
you're thinking of you know steel and
maybe here somebody else is thinking
about nanop particles for drug delivery
right material
are a a way more uh heterogeneous class
where we really don't record synthesis
in the same way right there's no one
unique repository for how to make
materials actually M make materials
could mean casting for some people and
it could make mean so gel for other
people so that's happening right now how
to have llms large language models read
this literature and deploy back
protocols to make stuff is happening uh
as we speak uh and then then In The Same
Spirit as these protocols there is llms
or agents for orchestration right where
individual pieces of AI with sort of
narrow Focus tasks coordinate one
another to orchestrate a more complex
function that we again thought a human
person would need to do right and there
is example in chemistry there is example
in in metal organic Frameworks which are
materials at the end of the day where an
agent reads a paper another agent
summarizes a recipe maybe an even agent
talks to the robot to make the chemistry
I'll talk more about that but in general
we're seeing sort of AI being sort of
the glue between different agents some
of which are Ai and some of which like I
said are a traditional simulator I have
a lot on on simulations or maybe all of
these are you know just Googling right
maybe it's an agent just goes and
Googles or goes to the patent database
and checks if this new chemical has been
registered by somebody else so this
orchestration is is definitely happening
as we
and then generative AI right you I mean
we've seen it work for faces in you know
2018 we already could make we the
community could make photorealistic
faces of madeup people um and over the
years we've been able to make you know
chemically
realistic versions of molecules to some
degree and definitely definitely of
proteins right protein design is we're
seeing it pick right now with you know
cida has raised a billion dollars out of
Noel award the
um David Baker it's definitely happening
right now and materials again are we
design an analo are we designing soft
matter this we've got a broader mandate
uh but the algorithms are coming along
as you can see from the date of those
papers things things are happening right
now um and then there is a place that is
particularly interesting to me which is
the combination of AI and simulations
because it turns out with if if we
really know the physics we can make
arbitrary amounts of data right we can
just simulate more we'll pay more
compute but compute is in is scalable
right you just rent another computer get
more data so we can generate data in a
way that most other tasks don't and we
have this very well defined
computational workflows that can benefit
from AI so there is in my world in
atomistic simulations when we look at
atoms from one resolution down from from
what Professor Bonnie was saying um
typically we get about three things how
well we're going to get the end energies
and the forces of how these atoms talk
to one another right typically we do
quantum mechanics really really
expensive how many atoms do we get to
simulate right typically we're C you
know tens of thousands hundreds of
thousands some some herculian efforts
can do Millions but but that's already
rare and because of the way we simulate
the world in one fento second increments
it takes forever to simulate materials
so we would typically stop at sort of
time scales of nanocs to micros it's
actually very hard to simulate something
like protein folding that takes
milliseconds so each and of these all of
these things are being actively
researched by foxm in my group but also
meta de mine Intel and Nvidia both you
know Academic Teams and and tech
companies are thinking about this Fusion
of AI and simulation so like I said ml
potentials Mean Machine learning models
that substitute quantum chemistry meta
has released 110 million on data points
to train these models on openly they
just put them out there for everybody to
use um and I I you know I suspect
there's more coming Deep Mind made them
but didn't didn't release them right so
kudos to meta for for opening data and
boo to to Google for not opening it U
accelerated MD like I said we can only
get to see Nan or microsc of time scale
but if you're looking at a protein that
is responsible for some disease its
Evolution takes milliseconds or maybe
seconds okay well how can we run this is
faster right we do this in my lab for
for battery materials right I want to
understand how lithium moves inside a
battery material but I cannot wait to
see sort of the time scale in a in an
atomistic simulation so how can I
accelerate while preserving all the
physics play some sort of using machine
learning as a surrogate model for these
simulators and something that again
we're pursuing actively which is
learning the types of Continuum or sem
empirical models that people
parameterize with pdes from the all atom
uh you know fully resolved quantum
mechanical evolution of of systems so I
have a couple of specific examples that
maybe will relate to sort of some of
your interest one is going Beyond
traditional simulations of
surfaces so if you've been close to
material surfaces you will know that
theoreticians typically model material
surfaces as a you know perfectly per
amazing pristin cut of the solid well
that's not how surfaces look like in the
real world right the moment you know
maybe you know at very low pressure when
you're doing epitaxy you know everything
is amazing but the moment things start
happening surfaces undergo
reconstruction you know some atoms move
around they creep up on top of one
another if you're growing a material the
material is physically stacking up more
layers all of this is Way Beyond the
traditional Assumption of tiny unit
cells that are P pristine um so this is
a place where machine learning can
definitely help and over the last you
know this was last year I put a paper
where we sort of we did the whole
two parts we need good energies and
forces so we train a machine learning
potential on tens of thousands of
quantum mechanical calculations such
that we can scale it to larger sizes and
and longer time scales so we we get sort
of we do Quantum we do AI to make our
energies and forces better and then we
do AI to sample the face space of what
the surfaces could look like um and this
is a diagram of sort of the amount of
learning it takes right this is not
something that people come in and click
a button yet this is active an active
area of research but it's possible so we
can make surrogate models of quantum
chemistry that are fast enough and
scalable enough that in this particular
example we were able to recover the
experimentally known reconstruction of
of a complex material like EST strum
titanium
oxide uh and agree with experiments on
sort of you know when uh as a function
of the pressure of oxygen and as a
function of the the composition of the
bulk we can get different surface
constructions and the stochiometry of
the surface reconstructions what atoms
they're made of we agreed with prior
calculations but how the atoms are
arranged we actually found more
realistic lower energy more believable
reconstruction that probably work hard
because AI can be more aggressive in
exploring these these spaces so I would
say surfaces used to be a big no no for
a for a ainal accuracy they're they're
at play now in terms of growth in terms
of reconstruction in terms of
functionalization um disorder is another
challenge that traditionally has been
hard to model in crystalling materials
right the fact that you know the crystal
itself you might have a material that is
perfectly ordered has atoms in a latis
fine but then which atoms sit on which
latis can be disordered right and again
if you're in a world where you can only
simulate tens or hundreds of atoms you
can't really access disorder because
every pattern you choose because the
unit cell is so small and it's
symmetrical turns out to be order right
there is no you can't really simulate
this order H with traditional methods
well over the last year we have put used
the same Machan potential that I told
you can do energies and forces they can
do alemy and they can interpolate
between known elements representing
disorder this is a little bit technical
but I would say one of the big Achilles
horses of material Discovery used to be
you you're constrained to making small
unit cells and small unit cells cannot
capture disorder the fact that different
atoms in a in an alloy right you're
thinking about high entropy alloy for
instance where many elements can be
distributed randomly on very on
different positions of the ltis um uh
that cannot be modeled with traditional
simulations easily it's very expensive
but it turns out these machine learning
models not only scale in size but can
play uh this alchemical trick we call
where when we want to simulate a 90 10%
alloy of you know copper and silver we
can actually cheat and simulate atoms
that are 90% silver sorry 90% copper 10%
silver and they themselves behave like a
disorder alloy and you know this this
recovers experimental trends that are
that are uh nonlinear unexpected in ways
that go beyond classical simulations and
then my last example is well all these
is nice and Dy Rafa but you know at the
end of the day materials need to be made
and well this is exactly where where all
these tools come together with robot
robotization and Automation in the lab
um what we call sort of closing the loop
or autonomous research and and I have an
example here on molecular dice but this
is something that is sort of moving
around through the field we've also done
um polymer electrolytes and different
labs to different classes of materials
you may hear more about it today um um
and at the end of the day this
um this is about like I said connecting
this Ai and computational intelligence
to actual execution in the real world
right that that top robot is was made at
MIT was in in nature in 2023 by Claus
Jensen lab that bottom robot is from
Berkeley H the top robot makes molecules
the bottom robot makes solid powders and
this is sort of happening right each of
these machines costs you know multiple
millions of dollars and takes you know
multiple years FTE uh to get set up so
this is not trivial yet and and and it's
not commoditized yet but it's happening
um so in this example we made a special
nuran Network that blends Theory an
experiment to predict Optical properties
of dice right so it's a place where we
have tens of thousands of simulations
and we have tens of thousands of
experiments so we put them together and
we make this neural network that is very
good at predicting Optical properties
this is just a small piece because then
comes the robot and like I said big
shout out to Professor Jensen because
the robot itself driven by sort of all
these pieces of AI talking to one
another achieves what we said a
generative model proposes molecules a
retrosynthesis model tells you how to
make them um an actual Master controller
calls the robot to execute the
experiments we measure the properties of
this online all prop properties that are
amable to this type of robotization
right other properties you know if you
need a synchrotron you cannot do that in
a robot right you need to go to the
synchrotron and then we update the
models and do the same Active Learning
or basent optimization that Professor
Bon just referred to which is we look at
the models and they themselves identify
the regions that combine the most
informative new experiments to run with
the most optimistic outcomes you could
get right the math of this is well
controlled um you need to decide how
much you want to balance the two but the
math of how to balance exploration and
exploitation is well understood so the
model itself decides I really don't know
what's going to happen if I do this plus
this compound looks really really
performant according to the properties
you cared about and in this particular
case we went around the M ground three
times and hundreds of molecules were
made in this collaborative
obviously science
paper I will close saying that we at
Peck and I feel excitement about AI for
science in materials you can see we
we've seen sort of we're at the third
wave was a small molecules you know in
the in the late 201 it's been proteins
you know pecking now right the main
tools were the idea that this was going
to work was put out in 2018 2019 2020
and now we're in the material design uh
Peak and you can see these startups you
can see like I said the fact that meta
they just put out a catalysis data set
and
the day before yesterday Nvidia is
making AI for chemistry where we're
definitely at this sort of pick of
interest in energy and sustainability
and I think manufacturing is the next
stop it's coming the digital twins I was
on on uh two proposals for the digital
twin but you know the ones that didn't
get it um but it's clear that it's
coming right that's the next Frontiers
okay how do we hook this not just to
scientific research but to real world
scaling up uh and I'm excited to talk
about that too and with that I'll thank
the team and hopefully this a little bit
of time for questions thank you