[MUSIC PLAYING]
MEGAN MITCHELL: Hello, and
good morning, everyone.
How are you?
Good morning.
Good afternoon.
Good evening.
I guess it really
depends on where you are.
I should qualify.
It is morning here,
in the Boston area.
And my name is Megan Mitchell.
I am the acting director of
the Jameel World Education Lab,
which is probably
familiar to many of you.
But for those of you who are
joining us for the first time,
the Jameel World Education
Lab here, at MIT,
which we refer to as J-WEL--
it's much easier on the tongue--
is the world's portal.
We consider it
the world's portal
to MIT expertise and research,
learning, experimentation
and, really, a laboratory
of educational innovation.
We collaborate with ambitious
and committed institutions
around the world.
Most of them are our members.
And hopefully, you're
joining us-- many
of you are joining us from
there-- to bring our shared
vision to life of education
designed for everyone to thrive,
which is, I hope and
believe, if you're here,
that's a mission that
resonates with you.
And we do this through
different pillars,
like our Pathways for Talent,
Architecting Learning,
Campus as a Catalyst, and that
really shapes who we work with
and how we work.
But you're here today as part
of our series in AI innovation.
And we started this
series, actually,
back in the summer,
where we heard
from our dean of digital
learning, Cynthia Breazeal.
And she spoke about the
work that she's doing
and the work happening at MIT.
But we've also explored
some of the spin-outs that
are coming out that are in the
nonprofit space that are doing
impact-driven work,
but still at scale,
and really thinking about how
to use AI to reach more learners
or to reach more learners
efficiently and effectively.
But today, we're bringing
you some folks who are--
SPEAKER: [NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
MEGAN MITCHELL: --more coming
from the corporate innovation
side.
And we will hear today from
three different panelists,
each who have prepared
presentations for you.
And they are going to share
with you the work that they've
been doing.
So first, we will hear from
Deepak Verma of EnglishHelper.
And English Helper
is really focused
on bringing English
language learning to many--
English language translation
to many different folks
around the world.
But now, they're looking
at, what can they
do in leveraging AI and
technology to expand their reach
and really broaden the already
really impactful work they're
doing.
He also serves as a partner
at ANOVA Spark Ventures.
And so he's an early
stage investor.
So really looking across
the spectrum of what's
happening in the
technology space.
He is really an innovator
across his career,
and we're excited
to hear from him.
He does have his
MBA from MIT Sloan,
and he's joining us
from Bangalore today.
Then, we will we'll turn
to Joy Dasgupta, who
is the CEO of Gyan AI, and
they're a deep tech startup,
using proprietary and
explainable AI language
model for research and
content development.
I'm interested in that
explainable qualifier there.
But their organization serves
international universities,
so I'm sure of interest
to many of you,
but publishing houses,
consulting firms, corporations,
so a lot of different
companies and the support
or different groups in the
business-to-business side
of things.
And Joy has deep
experience and played
in many different
senior leadership
roles at different
Fortune 500 companies.
And then we'll turn it over
to our final panelist, Jean
Hammond, another MBA or another
alum from the Sloan School.
And actually, someone I served
on a board with and works
diligently with MIT students
here, at here at MIT,
but also, in her
role leading what
she calls a micro-venture
capital firm, LearnLaunch,
so you can see why we
have her here today,
and invests in early stage
educational technology firms.
So really has a
great perspective
on how the ed tech landscape has
shaped and evolved over time.
But in addition to just
funding, she really
invests in the development
of those companies,
running an accelerator to
help those companies scale
and has invested in more than
86 companies around the world.
So, as you can see, a
great, great group of
panelists to give us their
perspective on what's
happening with their
companies, and here
to answer your questions.
So before we turn it over
to our first presentation--
each will do about a
15-minute presentation--
and I ask you to put your
questions in the chat, please.
We'll monitor that and
have time at the end of all
the presentations for
some moderated Q&A.
And I'll work in your
questions as well.
I'd like to introduce my
colleague, Bill Bonvillian, who
works with us here at
JWEL and has really
been the real driving force
behind this AI innovator series.
He has deep experience in the
science and technology space,
particularly looking at
it from a policy lens,
and the work that he's done
for the federal government
here in the US, particularly
serving with our Senate leaders,
working with them.
But he also ran MIT's
Washington, DC office.
So has a deep understanding
of the science and technology
and how institutions need
to be thinking about this.
But also just an incredible
contributor to the team
here at JWEL.
So, Bill, can I
turn it over to you,
please, just to say a little
bit about this, as you were?
It's your brainchild too.
BILL BONVILLIAN: Thanks, Megan.
I think today, you're
going to really enjoy--
I mean, I think there's
an underlying issue.
Why are we talking to companies?
What do they have to
do with education?
Doesn't that still
belong to educators?
But I think the answer
is that companies,
particularly smaller
firms and new startups,
they're risking their futures
on the new technologies,
and they can take a level of
risk and work in ways that
educators can't.
Companies can really play a
role in accelerating technology
adoption, while established
educational institutions,
schools, universities,
they can't take that risk,
and they don't have that
single-minded kind of focus.
So companies can really
play a useful role
in experimenting with new
technologies, which is why we
ought to talk to these folks.
What are these firms
experimenting with?
What can we expect to see?
And I'll just build a
little bit on what Megan
indicated in her introductions.
So Deepak at English
Helper is now
implementing a major AI based
digital tutoring project
to help both teachers and
students acquire English.
In other words, a
computer program that uses
AI to create
personalized learning
experiences for students.
And that's a very
important early track
for AI and probably
a principal role.
Joy Dasgupta is with Guyana AI,
which really is a services firm.
It's designed to help educators,
teachers, individual learners
and bring AI
capabilities to them.
So it can lead educators.
It can help educators.
If you're a school that
wants to start to apply AI,
Guyana AI can help you.
It also aids teachers
in developing
AI based courses and teaching
materials from course content
to video lectures.
So I could give Guyana AI all
my teaching materials, my course
readings, my lecture outlines,
and I can get back a syllabus,
lecture notes, slides.
And because it's using a
closed network of content,
it can avoid the set of
hallucination processes
that have afflicted AI.
And it's not only
for teachers, it also
affects individual learners in
designing their own AI based
learning projects.
And of course, schools
[AUDIO OUT] analyst
Joy Hammond will help
us walk through what's
happening in this world
of AI and education.
So her firm is
both an accelerator
that supports and helps
mature startup companies,
but it also is a
micro venture firm
that helps connect
them with financing
and also provide financing for
the early stages of those firms.
And Jean, who's been working
with these companies,
can tell us about what some
of the most promising firms
are doing that
she's working with.
What are the AI approaches
they're adapting for education?
And then secondly, she
can, from her vantage
point of looking at this kind of
edtech AI and education world,
give us ideas of what the
most promising approaches are
for AI and education.
So I think there's a lot we can
learn from what these firms are
up to about the
kind of new pathways
that they're trying to
create and how AI can
assist in educational missions.
MEGAN MITCHELL:
Deepak, are you all
set to share your screen and--
DEEPAK VERMA: I think I am.
MEGAN MITCHELL: Amazing.
DEEPAK VERMA: OK, great.
Well, first of
all, I just wanted
to say a big thank YOU to
Bill and the entire team
here for having
me on this panel.
It's an honor and really
looking forward to it.
And also warm hello to all
of you from around the world.
Great to connect.
Great to meet.
And with that, let's
get right to it.
So English Helper is
actually a company
that's been around for
some time, about 10 years.
And we've been focused on
the literacy challenge.
We started out
initially in India
with a product that's
really a-- think of it
as a classroom
product for students
to learn how to
pronounce and how
to build fluency in English
using their classroom textbooks.
And that product scaled to
a fairly large footprint,
as you can see on the
slide, over 100,000 schools,
25 million kids, most of them in
India, some in other countries.
But this was a
group product that
was aimed at working with a
group of students in a class.
It wasn't one to one.
In the last 10 years, while we
built scale with this product,
a few things have happened.
AI has become far more
accessible and far more
powerful.
Computational power
has increased manifold,
and now it's possible
to really think
about doing large-scale systems,
which are highly, highly
personalized.
So with that thought
in mind, we have
been building over the last
year our next-generation product
or platform that we're
rolling out currently.
It's called the Reading and
Comprehension Assistant.
And what this is it's really a
foundational literacy platform.
So it covers listening, reading,
listening, speaking, reading,
and writing.
And it works with learners from
absolute novices to experts,
and it works with
learners of all types.
So students in K-12, students
in colleges, young folks,
or even moms in India that want
to learn English so that they
can be more employable.
So we work with all of
those different groups.
And employability
is a big theme.
Some of the things that this
product does, which I think
are what makes it so
powerful, one of them
is it provides instant feedback.
So as you're speaking to the
product, it will listen to you,
and it will score
your pronunciation.
It will break down words
you're having difficulty
with into their
syllables and kind
allow you to hear the correct
pronunciation and then
your pronunciation
and practice yours
so that you can get better.
It even goes to
the phoneme level.
And all of this is with
the idea of learning
how to pronounce correctly.
But then even with passages
that it provides to you,
you answer questions,
and it's assessing,
are you really understanding
what you're reading?
So that feedback is
coming back in real time.
Another, I think, fairly
differentiating feature
about this platform is
its content agnostic.
And what I mean by that is it's
not gen AI LLM-based technology,
which is trained on large,
large amounts of content.
It's really an NLP or
computational linguistics
model, which is, A, fairly small
in terms of footprint and B,
it works on different
types of content.
And so if you provide
content for young kids,
it becomes an early
learning product.
If you provide
content for adults,
it's a product for adults.
And as a result, we bring
our content to the table.
But as we work with
partners and customers,
we're also able to
host their content
and deliver it to
their learners.
It is adaptive, and
by that, I mean,
it will adjust based
on how you're doing.
If you're having difficulty
with the materials,
it will step things down.
If you're doing really
well, it will make things
harder so that you're at the
level where you're actually
able to learn effectively.
And it has a bunch
of interactive tools
like you can listen to the
instructions and even the text
that you're supposed to read.
You can see it in your
vernacular language.
You can choose your accents.
You can slow down
the pace, et cetera,
just so that it's
a little bit more--
you can tailor it a little bit.
Each learner can tailor
it to what works for them.
And then finally, we are
aligning to various curriculum
around the world, so to
the Common Core in the US,
to the CEFR, et cetera.
So what I described to you is
these broad set of capabilities.
But then the
question becomes, how
does any specific
given learner engage?
And so what we've done
on top of the platform
is we've constructed--
call them courses,
call them journeys--
for specific outcomes.
So we have a course that
we're calling "Introduction
to Conversational Skills."
And here the idea is for
blue or gray collar workers
to develop enough
proficiency in the language
to be able to communicate,
to be able to take
an interview in English,
perhaps, to be more
confident and comfortable
in their social environment
with English.
And so this is really focused
on the conversational side,
and not so much on writing
and things like that.
We have another course that
we're calling "Introduction
to Foundational Skills,"
and this is more
of if you're familiar with CEFR,
which is the Common European
Standard Framework
for Languages,
it starts with level A1, which
is a complete novice and then
goes to A2 and B1
and B2 and C1 and C2.
And C2 is for folks
who are experts.
So think of Introduction
to Foundational Skills
as a course that takes
you from A1 to B1, B2.
And then we have an advanced
foundational skills course
that takes you from B2 to C2.
And so by the time you're done
with this across listening,
speaking, reading,
and writing, you
would be fairly proficient
in the language.
Now, I did mention that the
platform is content agnostic,
so we built a couple
of things on top of it
that are more specific
to certain use cases.
One of them is the IELTS prep.
Again, I'm not sure how many of
you are familiar with the IELTS,
but it's like a TOEFL.
It's a test that
students who are looking
to get admitted to
universities in the US
typically have to
take, and they have
to clear a certain
threshold in order
to be considered admissible.
What we're finding with
universities in the US
that we're working with
that there are many
qualified-- otherwise
qualified students
who satisfy all the
criteria for admission
but don't quite make it
on a subscore or a couple
of sub scores of the IELTS.
So this is a specific
program designed
to help students who want
to pass the IELTS exam,
practice for it, take
practice tests for it,
and then be ready to take
the actual IELTS test.
So that is the
IELTS prep course.
And then we have a category that
we're calling academic prep.
What we mean by
this is that it's
one thing to learn foundational
English, generic English,
but it's a whole
other thing if you
are looking to become a nurse
or an OR assistant or a lawyer.
You have to deal with the
language of the profession
or the language of the course
or the language of the subject.
And so the idea here is to build
specific content for learners
that are either trying
to get proficient
at the language of
a course, perhaps
in college, or from an
employability perspective
are trying to get proficient in
the language of the profession
they're getting ready for.
And so this is something
that we can add on,
and we will continue
to add on as courses
we offer for different
domains to get
learners comfortable with
domain-specific vocabularies.
So that is what I had in
terms of my prepared remarks.
Happy to pause here and interact
more in the question and answer
session.
MEGAN MITCHELL:
Fantastic, Deepak.
Excellent.
I think that's
really interesting
to see how you've
shifted or evolved
and continue to grow
the company and adapt.
And I think it will spark
some interesting questions.
But why don't we stay
on our presentations?
So we have lots of
time for questions,
and we can assimilate all
the different information.
Joy, are you ready?
JOY DASGUPTA: Hello, everybody.
My name is Joy Dasgupta.
I'm based here in Boston.
I'm the CEO of Gyan, which is
a language model company, an AI
company, and I'll tell
you a little bit about it.
I'm here to talk about
a specific product
that we have built for
the higher education
space on Gyan that is applicable
and usable by higher ed
institutions, as well as
corporate L&D departments,
to basically intelligently
discover content and auto curate
it for rapidly generating
ready-to-use courses.
So that's the focus.
We do build.
We have built many
other products
for some other
verticals as well.
That's out of scope
for this discussion.
We'll just stay focused on this.
And the target audience
for this product
is essentially
faculty instructors
who are in the business
of building courses.
However, an adjunct
and adjacent use case,
which I'll also talk about
in the course of this,
is assessments, auto assessment,
personally setting up
auto assessment for OpenText
responses, configuring it,
and then actually scoring
it when students come in
and respond to those questions.
So you know everything
that's on this slide,
but it's worth
stating one more time.
Higher ed is at an
inflection point.
It probably has
been for a while.
There are these points
that you all well know.
But I think the items here on
the left-hand side is what's key
is now and I think
into the deep future,
whatever we do or build
is going to have--
going to need to have
these attributes.
OK, I think stuff is going
to need to be flexible,
whether it's technology,
whether it's us,
whether how we
deliver training, how
we prepare for it, et cetera.
So the words that we
have come up with for--
as design inputs
into our product
is essentially
whatever we build has
to be flexible, responsible,
responsive, affordable,
adaptive, and personalized
and personalized ad quality.
And then, of course,
the operative,
the key word here is scale.
You heard from Deepak as well.
Like one of the things that
AI has enabled us to do
is scale things
that we otherwise
have to deliver in classrooms
or in face-to-face models,
et cetera.
This is beyond obviously
digital learning.
This is AI enabled.
Whoops.
So now the promise of AI.
And I'm going to talk about a
specific branch of AI, which
is large--
excuse me-- language model
based, text-based AI.
So obviously,
everybody on this call
is well familiar with
the arrival of the LLMs
back in 2022, and everything
changed after that.
ChatGPT, Anthropic,
Meta, everything--
all the very exciting
products that have come out
have created a
tremendous opportunity.
It has been backed by a
huge amount of marketing.
It has also generated
a lot of noise.
So opportunity and
confusion and what
to do with it is basically we
go out and talk to many people,
not just in higher ed, in
capital markets, in consulting,
in large corporations.
And the issue there is the
opportunity is overwhelming,
but where to start,
how to start?
And there are some
built-in challenges
with the more
popular band of AI,
the LLM based, and the key
one being that it is generally
a black box.
And it is therefore you cannot
double-click on it and get
to the heart of the analysis and
the source of where the analysis
came from.
Now, in our view,
that is a showstopper
for many use cases in higher
ed, in legal in capital markets,
in publishing.
Wherever explainability
is important,
a black box approach
to AI is problematic.
It has its uses.
It has its applications.
But there are places
where it just won't work.
So I'm here to talk to you about
an explainable language model
that we have built-in
Gyan that we have.
Then that's too much
technical stuff there.
But I'm going to talk about a
use case around it, which is how
we use that to build a course.
So just a very quick blurb on
Gyan so that you understand.
Rest of it is clearer.
Gyan basically means knowledge,
by the way, in Sanskrit.
So there are two
pieces here that
is applicable to the process
of course generation.
So first piece is we built
Gyan as a research engine.
And that is what we
apply to discover content
and to auto-curate
content quickly
from any source
anywhere, whether it
is your private
source, Gyan provided
sources, or the open internet.
So a key point here is
that you have full agency--
the instructor, the
course designer,
instructional
designer, the faculty.
You have full agency
over the content sources
that you want to target.
So Gyan will not draw
outside the lines.
Gyan will not hallucinate
because again,
just a little technical
point is Gyan's model is not
trained on data.
It is based on the rules
of the English language.
We are not using heavy duty
math to understand English.
We are using the rules
of the English language
to understand English.
So as a result, many
of the challenges
that we have with large
language models that
become a challenge
in adoption are
absent because of that
architectural difference
that we do not learn from data--
no hallucination, no IP
infringement, no black box.
You have full auditability.
There are no cut-off dates.
So when you run a query, you
get a response as of now,
whatever is there out on
the web or in your stores.
No inconsistency-- so every
time you ask Gyan a question,
you get the same answer.
Doesn't happen in some of
the big models out there.
So content discovery is
very important, obviously,
when you're trying
to generate a course.
And then there's
this auto-assessment.
So we take that
same language model
and apply it to a
student response
against fairly complex rubric.
Rubric could have items like
rate the logical progression
of this response.
Give a score for the analytical
depth of this response.
How closely is the conclusion
matching the thesis?
So we can have some
fairly complex rubric.
And you can double-click
to understand
where the score is
coming from and why
a student got a specific score.
So these two things are embedded
in this course generator
I'm about to show you.
And on this graphic on
the right is basically
saying the same point that you
have agency over the sources.
That's a very important.
And many versions of
AI that's out there,
you don't know where the
answer is coming from.
OK, you can do RAG, Retrieval
Augmented Generation.
You can provide your content.
It will try to draw inside
the box, but it will--
but it tends to always
draw outside as well.
So you can bring
your private content.
Gyan provides some content as
well, like all the preprint
servers, the archives, the bio
arcghive, chem archive, PubMed,
USPTO, et cetera.
We also have MIT
OCW preingested.
We have a whole bunch of
other OERs preingested.
So if you want to generate
a course using MIT OCW,
you can do it today right away.
And of course, the websites.
OK, so that's the backdrop.
This particular product
does these few things
that you would
expect, I suppose,
in any course
generation application.
But some of the
differences is in how
we do it, not in what we
do, because what kind of
remains constant--
so pedagogically
relevant course content.
So intelligent discovery using
our method of AI from content
everywhere, finding the most
relevant, discarding the rest.
And then auto curation--
we leverage the best
sources, MIT OCW included.
We have support for
the autonomous learner.
We also have an AI assistant
that will take you step by step,
and that's the part of the
personalization happens there.
So you are not in
a guided situation.
You're in a
self-guided situation.
Then the assessments that I
already talked to you about,
another important
module in the product.
And adaptive personalization--
OK, so here you basically--
your progress
through the course.
At a certain point,
if you are struggling,
then you take an assessment.
And the engine, looking at your
past performance and your scores
and your performance on
the specific assessment,
it is going to suggest
that you go two steps back,
or you take this
remediation program that's
somewhere else outside
of that specific course.
So it tries to catch you up
and bring you up to that point
so that then you can get the
most out of your learning.
And this final bullet here is
continuous lifelong learning.
So when we create
this course content,
the word continuous basically
means that Gyan also
keeps that course refreshed.
So say you built a course on--
I don't know-- introduction
to project management,
and there's more data.
Or let's pick a more topical
one, renewable energy, where
stuff is changing every day.
You could set an auto refresh on
your course content every month,
and you would get the latest
stuff, which of course needs
to be human adjudicated.
Somebody needs to promote
that content into the course.
But you will get a
good, rich collection
of all the new stuff that
is not in your course that
happened last month.
So it's continuously refreshed.
This is a busy slide,
but I'll just tell you,
I think it might
be important just
to share this briefly with you.
This is how it
flows-- very simple.
First, you come
in, and you provide
Gyan learning objectives.
From the learning
objectives, Gyan
is going to suggest a
bunch of learning topics.
At each point here, you can see
the instructor can intervene,
so it is human in the
loop right throughout.
So Gyan is going to suggest
a bunch of learning topics.
Instructor then says, OK,
these topics look good.
Then you trigger Gyan again.
Gyan will then go and
look at all the sources
that you have identified
and bring out content.
Instructor goes and
scans the content
and says, generally looks good.
I like it and then pushes Go.
Then Gyan from that will
generate lecture notes, reading
list, a video, which
you can, of course, then
everything you can go
in and edit of course,
before you publish it.
Assessments-- configuration
for assessment--
like what are good
questions for this course?
Set up the AI tutor and
also add to the learning
path, which learning path
is not just for this course.
Of course, it's across
a collection of courses,
so it will then incrementally
add to the learning path.
And then you finalize
the course and upload it.
OK, so that's kind of how
it works schematically.
Last thing, I'm just
going to show you what
a compiled course looks like.
So this is a
Gyan-generated course.
It's the talking head
here is an avatar.
So you've seen these.
It's good enough, not the best,
but this is what it looks like.
OK, so this is a course
on project management.
It followed that entire
pipeline that I showed you.
Yeah, where is my Play button?
I hope we can hear this.
- Project management for
information technology
management.
What is project management?
JOY DASGUPTA: So
that's the start.
Then I just go a little
further up to, let's say--
I don't know-- here.
I play again.
- --management?
Given the dynamic nature
of IT environments,
changes to project scope
requirements, or technology
are common.
JOY DASGUPTA: So what it's doing
is it took the lecture notes.
It made slides out of these,
and then we get the talking head
to read out the slides.
So all of that is automated.
You can intervene and
change and add more content,
and then the talking head
will start saying those things
as well and so on.
And I'll just show
you in the end.
There's a little summary that
happens, if I can get there,
somewhere here.
He'll try and summarize it.
- IT management is
essential for delivering
successful projects that meet
organizational objectives,
satisfy--
JOY DASGUPTA: You get the idea.
So it's not automated
end to end, obviously,
because you need human
in the loop throughout
to promote it to the next stage.
So that's, I think, all I
want to share at this point.
And of course happy to
take questions later.
Thank you.
MEGAN MITCHELL: Thank you, Joy.
I am not teaching this semester.
And I'm really
bummed that I'm not
because I think one of
the anxieties of teaching
was it was the excitement,
but also like am I capturing
all the new information?
What needs to be updated?
And having that
kind of by your side
or to start fresh and see--
just fascinating, fascinating.
So thank you very much.
And now finally, we
will turn it over
to Jean Hammond, who is the
founder of Learn Launch.
JEAN HAMMOND: All right.
Well, I'm also thrilled to be
here and very excited that JWEL
is working on these
questions because I just
think that education is
how we build the future.
And if we don't build the
future to be ready for AI,
we're not building
the right future.
Let's see.
I'm having some slide
moving trouble here.
MEGAN MITCHELL: Here we go.
JEAN HAMMOND: All right.
So really quick just to
tell you a little bit more
about Learn Launch so that you
just can visualize what we do.
So we select a very
small number of companies
to work with at a time, and then
we put them through a process
where they get to learn some
things, learn from their peers.
Of course, you always
learn more from your peers
than from the instructors.
And then put those
into their products
as they get ready for more
interaction with the market.
And so we're pretty interested
in supporting companies that
are going to build
what we would think
of as sustainable
businesses, i.e.
they're going to be something
that school systems are
interested in buying.
And every day, school
systems are buying from--
I don't know-- Pearson
and McGraw Hill.
And so they definitely
were looking
for the next big new things.
So our process is to
really have this learning
journey for the
companies and to have
them think about what is
it that they're trying
to measure in their product.
And so just as an
example, to try
to think a little bit about
the measurement of education,
do we want to measure
whether that fifth grader can
do an arithmetic
problem, or is it
more interesting
in today's world
if we can measure
at the same time
their improvement in
executive function
to take on advanced
math concepts?
So what are we trying to measure
when we're looking at things?
And for startups, of course,
you can't measure everything
you're wanting to do with
your product day one,
but over time, you're
looking for being
able to create good outputs.
So this is about
instrumenting your software
and instrumenting your system
to fit into the environment
that you're going to
deliver the product in.
And then we have an
entrepreneur in residence for AI
that focuses on how
to leverage that data.
And all of this is sort
of around our philosophy
that education systems need
to be increasingly data driven
and when some of that
data can be appropriately
automated to do that.
So really, that's sort
of our philosophy.
And then let's take
a step back and look
at the education industry.
Is it ready for AI?
And I think the big
answer is not really.
It's a very big global
market and continues
to grow as more and
more people come into
want to be a part of the
economies of their countries.
And certainly, there
were a few things
that happened when
COVID went through.
Certainly, here in the
States, we could see the--
I guess I would call it-- the
further connection of the pipes,
putting in the ability
to deliver products
to people's homes, and as well
as into the classroom digitally.
But many of the things
that were coming
through were not super
effective and were sort of based
on a rote memory learning.
So we increasingly see that
education is still going
through a digital transition.
At the same time, it's
interacting with AI,
which is, it's a big bite.
It's a big thing to
bite off all at once.
And another aspect installed
systems in education--
and remember, the bulk
of the money in education
is spent in formal education.
So that would include
private and public schools
and colleges and universities.
And there is some amount
of parents buying something
directly for their students.
But really, the bulk of the
money is in these locations.
And so if we're going
to affect education,
we probably need to
build things that
will be able to fit into
the systems that are there.
And in particular, in the US,
we have silos of information,
like say in a K-12
system that don't even
communicate to each other and
are owned by different parties.
So let's step back and think a
little bit about this relatively
slow moving industry and
where AI can come in.
It's really interesting
to see that in the first,
18 months after ChatGPT was
announced, about $280 billion
of additional spending was spent
on implementing generative AI
into businesses.
And of that, a very
tiny percent, around 2%,
went into education.
And so it's an industry
that's relatively slow moving.
Often, people are
worried about, well,
how will we be able
to use that fairly?
How will that be
affected-- affect us?
So let's think about
this a little bit.
What are some places
that we can really
do things that are different?
I think we just saw two
really phenomenal examples
of interesting ways to use AI.
And obviously, the more that
we understand the learner
and make sure that the learning
is tuned to what they already
know and what they
need to learn next,
that individualization
or personalized pathway
is valuable.
Looking for patterns--
do we actually
understand what's going
on and for our learners
in a more effective way?
And then obviously,
as we just saw,
the ability to use interactive
environments to practice
and to build on what
you already know.
And certainly, people who
have watched young kids
interact with some of these
really easy-to-use AI systems.
Hope that kids will be out there
doing inquiry-based learning
and finding the next new
thing they want to dig into.
Not sure every
youngster is thinking
about the world that way, but
it certainly a beautiful one.
It's happening.
Data silos-- again, this idea
that we can get information out.
AI is an aid to learning
materials development,
and we just saw in this
course development product.
It is going to make it much
faster to get what you need to
into people's hands.
And I loved the lifelong
learning component
of our presenter
because the idea
that you want to teach
something about what
you can see in using telescopes
to your astronomy class is fine.
But could you include what
Hubble looked at last week?
Wow, now that would
be exciting and keep
people interested and engaged.
I think there's a number of
really exciting things going on
here.
One side of that's
coming out, so K-12.
It's really about
matching learning
differences and the content.
And particularly as we're
looking at education
for the purpose of
employment, we're
seeing increasing amount
of conversation about,
how could we actually understand
the skills of the learner
and be able to map those
to the job requirements?
So we have this skills-based
hiring conversation
going on all over the
industry right now.
So let's see.
I need to watch my
time here a little bit.
I think there's some
very detailed areas that
are effective for different
parts of the education system.
And I'm going to provide
a couple examples
from our own portfolio
in the next slide that
get to a number of these
little details here.
So I've got four
companies that we've
worked with closely pulled
out here just to say how
each of them are utilizing
AI or what part of AI
they think is important
for their future.
And so I'll start
at the beginning.
So if you had asked me
when I started Learn Lunch
whether or not first and
second-grade teachers were going
to sit on the floor
of their classroom
and put logic blocks
together with their kids
to make little
microrobots, I would
have been kind of
suspicious that they
would be uncomfortable
with tech,
but that's exactly what's
happening for Robo Wunderkind.
They're not only bringing
in robots very early,
before the kids are scared.
These little
six-year-olds saying,
I'm going to be an engineer.
And, because if you bring in the
robots in fifth or sixth grade,
the kids from the advantaged
backgrounds know what to do,
and the kids from the
disadvantaged backgrounds
step back.
They don't know what to do.
They're not included.
And so that's one
of the reasons why
we're sort of excited
about the idea
that this can be
going these ways.
She's now building
in coursework to have
students by third
and fourth grade
be able to not only do some
medium-weight programming,
but also be able to, in some
cases, use some AI modules
or understand a tool called
AI as an additional way
to think about
getting things done.
And she's hoping to
build that out so
that by fifth and
sixth grade, she
has some fairly interactive
components in there.
And again, that's one of
the challenges for education
and AI is, how do we get people
Involved InScribe is working
on helping with a sense of
belonging in colleges by keeping
persistent answers to
questions that get asked over
and over again, whether they
be in student life or they
be in coursework,
helping make sure
that the right questions
are getting answered
and providing some other small
community-based supports.
Edmond is an example of the
silos of information problem
for in the US, we have
very, very heavy support
of special needs
students, but it
comes with phenomenal,
complex government regulation
and the need to
look up and find out
exactly what kind
of accommodation
is allowed for which student
on which type of activity.
And the complexity of looking
that up is almost impossible.
And so now this is not only
keeping this accommodation
database, but also providing
richer interactions
with the teacher to
provide hints as well
as collect information
of the student learning.
And Julius is using
AI, as I mentioned,
for this skills-based
view of the universe.
They're doing deep
skill analysis that's
supported by the
Department of Energy
for the different jobs
for solar installers,
or they're working with
the state of Minnesota
on training all of the
people that will manage
21 solar farms for the state.
And so they're not only
building out the courseware
by assembling courseware
based on exactly
what the learner needs to
learn from lots of sources.
They don't make much courseware.
They assemble it and provide it.
But they also have built
these really deep ways
of analyzing a per industry
skill analysis that's
maybe ahead of the
market in number
of details that can support.
I was just down at
New York EdTech Week
and saw some more
companies working
on support of building
curriculum, et cetera.
And AI is moving
very, very quickly.
So companies that
are already in market
are trying to go back and
bring additional capabilities,
automate, and enhance things
that they already had.
But also we're seeing brand new
companies come in, particularly
around things like course
development or a developed
specific course.
WOMAN: [NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
MEGAN MITCHELL: If we can,
please make sure we're muted.
JEAN HAMMOND: So this is just
a picture of all the companies
that are in our
active portfolio just
to show the diversity
of the kinds of things
that we'll be bumping
into and working with.
Education is not a single thing.
It's a complex mix of things.
So maybe just to wrap
up here, we really
have to think about how we
can bring the human inside
into the world of
an AI-mediated world
and to build great jobs
that do have a human inside
and try to figure out what
that world will look like.
I think the industry
as a whole is
in-- is in a discussion
about measuring what matters.
And so what matters?
How are we going to measure the
things that really do matter?
How can we make sure that our
assessments aren't measuring
what was needed for
1987 and instead are
measuring what is needed today?
We certainly need
to experiment with--
let's see.
This is my hope for
the education industry
that we get much
more experimental.
We just let people go
and do things that we not
have really rigid environments
because if we're bringing up
kids in rigid
environments and then
they get to the range of options
that AI hopefully will hopefully
ethically provide to us.
We're going to need
some people who
are interested in
the finding things.
We certainly can develop
more personalized pathways.
And I'm a big fan of education
being more researched.
When we go to research
what's going on in the world,
we end up in a
much deeper place.
So if what we're doing is
we're helping youngsters
set memories and
understandings that
allow critical thinking
in their brain,
then we need to understand
how that happens,
what's going on in
learning science
as well as what's going on
in the education industry.
MEGAN MITCHELL: Fantastic.
Thank you.
And thank you to all--
wow-- all of our presenters.
I think we kind of
took a deep dive
into two sets of-- two sets of
technologies or two companies
and then had a beautiful kind
of landscape look from Jean.
I think for the folks
here on the call,
there's going to be a lot of
googling and searching and doing
more research into the
different companies.
There's something I heard
throughout that I would love
to-- a string I'd
love to pull on,
and that is in
Joy's presentation,
you had kind on
one of the sides.
Education needs to be flexible,
responsive, affordable,
adaptive, adaptive.
And Jean, at the very beginning,
you kind of-- is education,
is it ready for AI?
Is the industry ready for AI?
You want to see it
be more experimental.
I think the people on
this call, the people who
show up for these types
of sessions, are there.
They're the early adopters.
They're the ones willing
to do some experiments
and try some things new.
But I from a long career in
higher education, the education
industry isn't always the
most flexible and responsive.
And so how do you think about
from your vantage point,
shifting mindsets
or equipping people
to help really leverage
this type of technology,
whether that's something
is core to your business
is sales in building
a sales funnel
and a sales pipeline,
particularly on an enterprise
side, to getting out and
getting that evidence based,
those findings that will
help change mindsets?
Or maybe there's
some other great way.
Maybe it's a
grassroots approach.
So I'm just curious, from
each of the panelists, how
you think that we can move
so many people forward
in the industry that
are a little bit less
flexible and responsive.
JEAN HAMMOND: I think that the
things that we've always known
really work in education--
learning from your peers,
being in small groups,
project-based learning,
experiential learning--
I think the more that we can
say, hey, one of the things
AI is bringing us is the ability
to bring what we've always known
work into the
environment and maybe
have less expectation
of everybody
in this group of 35
people or 25 people
are sitting in a room
together doing the same thing
at the same time.
And so probably
there's a mix of--
there's a mix of issues
going on that looks
like that if we can
help the teachers
and the instructors feel that
they're getting to do what they
always wanted to do by utilizing
some new tech, that should help.
The internet didn't
kill education.
So AI probably won't either.
DEEPAK VERMA: Yeah, I
think we have a more
kind of narrow kind of offer.
In some ways, it's
broad but narrow.
And what we're looking
for is across three
broad categories of education
or learning-- there's the K-12.
There's higher ed,
and then there's
youth, adults, et cetera.
And in each of those,
what are the glaring
problems that everybody sees,
and everybody is tackling?
And they're getting hurt by it
within the education system.
So, for example, in India,
and also in the US, I mean,
when you look at tests of
fifth graders or sixth graders
and how are they doing compared
to how they should be doing,
are they reading at
grade level, et cetera,
I mean that there is
real data around that.
And so that's what
we try to focus on.
And in some places,
we've had, I think,
a fair amount of early success.
And in some places, we've
had no movement at all.
So in higher ed, when we
focus our conversation around,
are you trying to admit
more international students,
and are you being unable to
do so because of language,
lack of ability?
Well, we can help with that.
Now, let's say you admit a
student who clears the aisles
or whatever, and joins,
and semester one happens.
Semester two, the
courses get harder.
Semester three, they
get even harder.
Now what?
And so are you seeing a drop-off
problem because some of these
folks who are not--
I mean, they've got marginal
level of language skills
encounter tough courses
with tough language.
Are they dropping out?
Well, we got a
solution for that.
And employability
is very different.
I think there's economics
that drive that system.
So it's not so hard.
I think what's hard is from
my perspective is like K-12.
I mean, those are
complex systems,
and you've got to work your way
through those complex systems.
And it's time consuming,
and it's hard.
But we're there.
We're going to keep
trying until we figure out
what the right answer is here.
JOY DASGUPTA: I
think I'll chime in
with a slightly
different perspective
because I think it's the
rate of change question.
And the world is changing.
There's nothing
we can do about it
at a rate that is accelerating.
It's not the change
is accelerating.
The rate of change
So that's a double there.
And then that's on the
receiving side of your students.
And on the other
side, the technology
is evolving even faster.
So here we are in between.
How do we prepare these children
and young adults and adults
for that, connect the dots?
So I'll give you a vendor's
perspective, our perspective.
So we are trying
to sell into this.
Just to put on my hat.
So what do we do?
OK, so everybody's
change resistant.
Adults don't change easily.
So we are looking
for early adopters.
We are looking for the
path of least resistance
to get in and make the
point and try to demonstrate
what's in it for me.
Ultimately, that's the question.
Whether you're an instructor,
faculty, dean, provost,
what's in it for me?
And of course, my
institution maybe--
whatever your expanded
sense of me is.
And so that we have to hit.
But I think the other thing
that we did-- and just
to put it out there.
So with this core
generator thing
actually was born
from this idea,
which is let's go to a
place where it's kind of--
there's nobody there.
So this is we are going to
the instructional designer
in a place where he or she
is working on Microsoft Word
and Google.
There's no major
application in this part.
So there's really no resistance.
So we can get in, and we
can show the value that this
is how you can get going.
And after that, of course,
when you get into the learning
delivery part, there's a lot
of other competing tools.
But by then, maybe we
have changed a few minds.
So net net, I think this
is a change management
problem, which is obviously
well known but hard to crack.
JEAN HAMMOND: I love
you saying going
to where there's an open space.
And maybe that's one of the
things that will come from AI
and education is that some
of the less rigid education
environments will be able
to adopt new things faster.
And we may see some of the
big new markets in education
are Latin America, and
particularly Africa,
because there's just such a huge
percent of the population that's
still under educated,
phenomenally undereducated, lots
of white space.
MEGAN MITCHELL: So beyond
the dollars and cents
or in the revenues, how
do we think about impact?
I mean, you are in an
in education space.
And yes, people often adopt
new things because of,
what's in it for me?
Like, how can I use this?
What problems does
it solve for me?
But impact is important.
And in this kind of
ever-changing and evolving
environment, the way
people think about impact
might be different.
Are there metrics
that Joy and Deepak,
you use to think
about the change,
beyond that revenue, the type
of educational impact you're
having?
Or I'll say, Jean, are there--
is a company kind of in or two
in your portfolio
that are thinking
in really interesting
ways about demonstrating
the power of the work they're
doing through particular impact
measurements and metrics?
JEAN HAMMOND: So we
had to figure this--
the answer out to this
question ourselves.
So we did some soul searching.
And what I can tell
you is, starting out,
we're a for-profit company.
We're very clear about that.
I mean, I actually
am a strong believer
that it's for-profit companies
that can sustain and scale.
And so if you want to do that,
you have to be for-profit.
Having said that, I think we
are really driven by the idea
that we can change life
trajectories of people
that we engage with and
can impart learning to.
Think about English.
You think about
foundational skills.
If I'm a little bit
better at English today
than I was yesterday, there's
more that's accessible to me.
That's more I can learn.
Perhaps I can get a better job.
And you see this in
several professions.
If you're not that
great at English,
you have a limit in terms
of how far you can go.
And then beyond that,
if you're not skilled,
you're going to get stuck.
So our view is
every learner we can
impact is going to change
that learner's trajectory
for the rest of their lives.
That's what we want to get to.
And we're doing
work, as I mentioned,
in India and in the US.
In India, we have this problem
that there are a lot of people
who want to learn,
but they can't.
They can't pay.
So what do you do?
Well, in those cases,
what we're looking at
is how do we find
funding from donors?
Or there's this program in
India, CSR, Corporate Social
Responsibility, which companies
kind of put money into.
How can we find money from
those sources to pay for this?
We're not going to do it
for free because we can't.
But how do we make
that whole system work
so that we're not
saying no to learners?
So that's impact, as you know,
from a mission perspective.
The second question is,
how do you measure it?
And I think if you think
about how our system works,
somebody comes in.
They do a placement.
We understand what
level they're at.
We provide lessons, excuse me.
And then we assess again, and
they're at a higher level.
And then we provide less.
So you can see
those trajectories.
And there are various
different curriculum standards,
and all of them specify
different levels.
And as long as we're
tracking to folks
and seeing their
journeys move forward,
I mean, the system
itself is measuring
the impact on the goal,
if that makes sense.
JEAN HAMMOND: Yes.
I think that you've
pointed to something that--
first of all, I think
changing life trajectories
is the long-term important,
and then to some extent,
we'll increase the
knowledge of humans
by our education institutions
doing research, too.
But that's what
we're here about.
But I do think there's an
interesting side going on
in AI right now because some
of the types of use of AI,
for example, for individual
personal feedback,
either as sort of a
tutor or a practice bot.
If you're running live to an
AI system, it's expensive.
And so there's some limits
to what can be done.
And again, we don't have to
have everything run live.
I mean, there's a lot of clever
ways to get around some of that.
But certainly, right
now, one of the things
that will hold back as
well as fear from the users
not understanding what they're
working with from the users.
So like some of these
products we saw today will--
as well as those holding back
things going into education--
I think the cost
will be an issue.
And so that's an aside
on the underlying desire
to get more people
more educated.
DEEPAK VERMA: If I may
just respond to one thing
that you said,
Jean, because I do
think it's an important point.
And Joy, sorry, keeping
you waiting for a bit here.
But so I think, in general,
your point is absolutely right.
I do want to make one
in full disclosure here.
A lot of our AI secret sauce
is being developed by this guy
also on this panel, Joy.
So we use Gyan
within the shelter,
and that is a very light,
very computationally light,
way compared to some of
these larger language models.
And that's what enables us to do
many of the things we're doing.
And Joy, maybe you can answer
that question some more,
but I wanted to mention
that to everybody.
JOY DASGUPTA: Thanks.
So and also, I think Jean
implied and said this also.
Like I think we are--
by being in this space and
putting our solutions out there,
I think we are part of a bigger
movement that is accelerating,
hopefully access and equity
across economic, social, global
south, et cetera, et cetera.
So that's one point
that we are part of.
I mean, we are not direct.
We are contributing in
some small way, hopefully.
And the other thing is
the point that Deepak just
made on the sustainability
side of things.
And our student
impact necessarily
is we use a very small energy
footprint as opposed to we
don't have to set up
a nuclear power plant
to train our language.
I think that's it's kind of
getting there for some of these.
So we don't use GPUs.
We use CPUs for those
who are learning this.
So that's for the movement part.
But I think at the company
level, I think we don't--
within quotes-- we don't
directly touch the students.
Our customers are institutions.
So our impact measure is--
to put it in a very
bluntly is-- so we
are trying to-- how are
we trying to impact?
OK, let's just use two threads.
Continuous learning, we talked
about and personalization.
Those are, I think, two
major vectors of impact.
I mean, think about
personalized medicine.
Think about personalized
finance, financial advising,
whatever.
So personalized learning--
that's what we do.
And our measure
of impact is, this
will sound really
crass, is like,
are we getting our
contracts renewed?
If there's a renewal
of our contract,
that means we are making a
difference to that institution.
But the point here is we don't
directly own the students.
So it's an indirect impact.
MEGAN MITCHELL: Yeah, very good.
So let's talk about--
it's a great
question in the chat
about benchmarking or
existing benchmarks or tools.
This is such a new space, and
there's so much happening.
And how does someone
who is very much
interested wants to
adopt these technologies,
listening to all of
you that you can see?
You can feel.
These are technologies
that I want to explore.
But like that trust
component in such
a evolving and emerging
space, how do people
think about building
tools or validating
that these tools that you
have and you're delivering
are worthwhile or worth
or up to the standard
that you're talking
about them being at
and can really drive
the types of change?
How is someone an informed
consumer in something
that's such a new area?
JOY DASGUPTA: It's sort of
an AI certification stamp,
MEGAN MITCHELL:
Seal of approval--
yes good housekeeping,
good AI seal of approval.
JOY DASGUPTA: I can
try to go first.
I think there's two
levels of benchmarking,
and I can talk about
the first part.
First part is the
language model itself.
And there are lots of
benchmarks out there actually,
that are put out by various
different groups, like Google,
like Microsoft.
So there's msmarco.
If you're in the medical
field, there's PubMed QA.
There's natural questions from--
I forget who.
Maybe it's from Google.
So these are large
data sets with lots
of questions on the one
side and correct answers
on the other side.
And if your model can take these
questions, look at the data set,
and answer these questions
accurately, that's the test.
OK, where do you stand
on the leaderboard?
But that's for the
language model.
That is like the
engine of your car
is still not going to give you
a sense of how the car drives.
So that's proof of the engine.
Next is proof of
the car, which is,
let's say, the course
generator, in my case
that we don't have a
benchmark for because this
is a relatively new product.
We don't know who to
compare it with necessarily,
but I think we
need to get there.
But the language model part,
there is stuff out there.
I mean, many of you
probably know that.
And you should go and
look it up, and we are--
Yan is going to publish.
We are in the process of
publishing our own benchmarks.
MEGAN MITCHELL:
Fantastic, fantastic.
DEEPAK VERMA: Yeah.
And I guess on the
education side,
what we've done in the past
with our earlier product
is done a number of
RCTs randomized studies
where products are
implemented with some students
in some classrooms
against control groups
and how they perform.
So we have all that data,
and it's very strong.
With our new-- this
whole new platform,
it's a whole new thing.
It's brand new.
We've just we've just started
giving out demo accounts,
and we'll be starting
our first pilots.
And so we're also looking
for early, not even
adopters, early experimenters
who are saying, you know,
it sounds interesting.
Let me try it and
see for myself.
And they'll bring on
10, 20, 30 learners.
We'll give it two
or three months,
and we'll see how it's going.
And then we go from there.
But I guess over time,
we'll be able to generate
real data on impact.
But as of now, it's early
days for the new product.
MEGAN MITCHELL: Amazing.
That brings us back to
the experimental approach
that Jean was talking about.
We need people that have that.
JEAN HAMMOND: But I
think in many places,
people try to measure
impact by trying
to understand what change.
The fact that this
product exists
is that this capability, and the
teachers exist, can be measured.
And so the so-called
logic models
are a way of thinking about what
are the inputs, the outputs,
and over time.
And we work with lots of
early-stage companies.
And so what we know is you
can't measure everything
that you want to do early on.
And so we sometimes think that
if a company has a product
roadmap, what they're going
to do with their product,
they should also have an
impact measurement roadmap that
goes with it, increasing
amounts of additional data
that they'll be able to access,
both from their own system,
from instrumenting
their own system,
but also from perhaps getting
the environment in which
the product is delivered, say
the school district or whatever,
to also--
to also be able
to share data out
of other parts of
the infrastructure
that's being used for education.
So do we know what
the right answer is?
No, I think we're in the middle
of a societal or worldwide
experiment to try
to figure out, well,
what is it that we're
trying to measure?
And I think that we're
trying to measure
better lives for more people.
We're trying to measure
that with equitable access.
How are we going to get there?
Let's work on it.
MEGAN MITCHELL: And OK,
so we're out of time,
but I want to ask one.
It's kind of pulling on
a question in the chat.
And so if you can just
answer really quickly.
I mean, the speed of
change, the pace of change,
the rate of change is shifting.
I mean, what's next?
Like you're already
talking about things
that feel like
we're on the edge.
We know that in two months,
three months, six months,
they're going to be new
features or additional AI tools.
Like what should
we be looking out
for just in a couple sentences?
Each of you, what's
the next horizon?
It's not even a horizon.
It's like, what's
around the next corner.
JEAN HAMMOND: Well,
I'll go first.
I think we have
to be looking out
for making sure that we build
the humans in the system.
I mean, education is social.
We learn from each
other much better
than we learn from sitting in
front of a boring old screen.
So, really, how do
we build in humans,
in the system across
all of these areas?
DEEPAK VERMA: And
answering more specifically
from my English
helper hat, we're
working on some very
interesting stuff that
will enable really proficient
users to better comprehend what
they're reading through our app.
So you think about a
nine-page research paper.
It's dense.
You guys are all from MIT.
Maybe you can read it once
and understand it fully,
but this is pretty hard.
But what we're doing
is we're building tools
to help even
advanced users really
be able to consume what they're
consuming through the app.
So ultimate aspiration is
for all of us, everyone,
to have this app in their
pocket and consume whatever
they're reading with it.
JOY DASGUPTA: And the degree
of noise is going to increase.
I think maybe that's the
basis of the question.
How do I navigate this noise?
I think maybe we can get
back to some of Jean's points
and 5 Ds on that last slide.
I think we have to get
grounded in what we want
and what we need to
do with our students
and let the tools just be
tools and not drive us.
Right now, the tail and the
dog is getting all mixed up.
So I think we just
need to be the dog.
And the future is
completely uncertain.
Nobody should even attempt
to predict it, particularly
in the AI world.
It's not possible.
Even the developers
can't predict it.
Sam Altman can't predict it.
I mean, he doesn't know.
He's surprised by the next
release of his own product.
OK, so maybe we get out of that
business and stay grounded on,
what are we trying to
accomplish here in education?
So that's maybe an
indirect answer.
MEGAN MITCHELL: That is the
perfect way to bring us back.
Like we're all what do we want
to accomplish in education?
And think of these as tools
and focus on the core mission.
So thank you all very much.
Thank you to our
audience for staying
and for allowing us to go.
Just indulge us to go just
a few minutes over so we
could get this look forward.
Thank you very much, Bill for
bringing this group together,
Joy, Deepak, Jean, for
all the great insights,
and for our folks in the
audience for your questions
and your attention, Amy has put
a link in this chat for a survey
that we would appreciate
input from our participants.
And thank you all.
This has been recorded.
We will be sharing
that on our connector.
But thank you.
Thank you.
Have a wonderful day,
evening, and rest
of the week, wherever you are.
DEEPAK VERMA: Thank
you very much.
JOY DASGUPTA: Thank you.
[MUSIC PLAYING]