thank you for joining us everyone
including our panelists today um like
you said my name is Courtney I'm a
second year in the 2-year full-time MBA
program prior to Sloan I worked in
education technology most recently at
McGraw Hill where I worked on product
development and while here at Sloan I
was able to spend the summer as a chief
of staff intern at a startup that
focuses on health education funded
hugely through mit's social impact fund
so happy to talk about funding
opportunities for those who are coming
from underfunded backgrounds and just a
little bit about my life at Sloan I'm an
active part of fly which is our first
generation club I'm co-president this
year I'm also co-president of Education
club I'm heavily involved in Pride I do
a club Sport and I'm doing the business
analytics certificate so lots of things
you can do here at SL covering a wide
variety of interests and I'd love to
pass it off to our panelists to do
introductions um name what program
you're what program you did and when you
graduated and maybe what you were doing
before Sloan and now what you're doing
after and I see Candace you're first on
my screen so I'm going to bump it to you
first sure hi my name is Candace Hines
um I was an SF MBA so I did the slown
fellows program graduated uh last year
in May of 23 um prior to coming to the
slone fellows program um I was in
healthc care operations though I did
start my career as a lawyer and in the
legal field mostly family law um I am
now working for a PE backed um uh
Dermatology and plastic surgery rollup
I'm a VP and the head of plastics
operations I'm originally from Texas um
I'm from rural Texas I'm a first gen um
on both sides of my family to go to
college and um yeah happy to be
here great we can go down the line
Daniel if you want to go
next yeah thank you uh hi everyone uh
I'm Daniel uh I am an lg23 so I
graduated last year and lgo means the
double Masters in engineering uh where I
did electrical engineering computer
science and I got my MBA simultaneously
at the same time so I was also an NBA 23
at the same time um yeah before lgo I
was doing software engineering at
Capital One and now I'm am doing product
management at meta so just all been in
the tech field um either building code
or like you know doing J tickets to
write code always been around it I've
loved that my whole time and during lgo
I did a lot of tech related things um
and yeah my relationship with fli um I'm
originally from London but my parents
were from a low-income background they
were immigrants from Ethiopia and so
I've been a big beneficiary of you know
any like Income Support uh when it comes
to education and it's always been a big
priority of me and my family so yeah I
was that's me
and I think I'm the the next in line uh
hi everyone um my name is
Elisa um I am a master of Finance
graduate also from the 23 uh program so
graduated last year um prior to that I
worked in banking back in Europe I'm
originally from
Germany and then found my way to the SV
years ago with this master's program um
similar to Daniel have been uh benefited
a lot from um anything like from
scholarships and low income support back
in Germany my parents were both U
musicians so there was a background
heavily in that music domain and nothing
much more be beyond that so um that's
why things have been uh very different
for me and um I was able to follow two
passions at MIT I did uh Finance but I
also have a huge passion for cyber
security which led to my current wall I
am right now a risk analyst in McKenzie
more specifically I'm working in the
Cyber practice supporting um or Rising
companies in their cyber risk post
posture and um yeah that's that's so far
about me and I'm passing over to
Olga hi everyone uh my name is Olga T
Gala uh MBA grad from a couple years ago
from 2021
uh prior to Sloan so I was originally
from usbekistan uh and then prior to
Sloan uh lived in Florida worked in
metals industry and in parallel to that
uh have been a reservist in US Coast
Guard now 13 years um so have enjoyed
that actually in cyber so uh similar
similar theme there to Elisa uh and now
uh I'm at BCG uh as a project leader in
our
uh principal investors private Equity
practice excited to meet
everyone amazing thank you all such a
great breath of experience tonight uh so
for our first question I'll lead into it
by saying uh I know like many of you my
parents were really encouraging me to
pursue as much higher education as
possible but had absolutely no idea what
business school was so I really came
into picking where to go uh without
familial uh input most of them said why
are you pursuing even more so I would
love to hear about why some of you
actually chose SLO and why you found
that this was the best fit for you and
kind of what decisions or what factors
went into that
decision I'm happy to talk about it a
little bit um I had a similar experience
um so I had a a first graduate degree
and I had the same experience where my
parents didn't quite know what um
graduate school really meant and what it
entailed um how where a law school even
fit into the college um experience and
so I had to sort of navigate that on my
own so whenever I I did the SF program
which is um midcareer which I I did at
42 so by then my parents were
familiarized um with uh what grad school
looked like but they had the same
reaction of why do you want another
degree um and and I I I did and I chose
Sloan in particular because it was so um
Mission based and um I I would say that
if anything it felt like my background
and a diversity of background um was
seen as an advantage and something that
I was bringing to um the school and from
everyone that I spoke with during the
admissions process prior to other
students um it it really felt like that
was an asset to me and I was bringing a
color that maybe was under repesent Ed
at the school um and I was very grateful
to be able to to have that
valued um yeah for for me uh Sloan was
or I guess it's more the MIT brand I
think that was the big ER for me um yeah
I had like African parents and they like
you know adorned you know the MIT name
in every regard but like they had no
idea what business school was
and so I think a lot of it was like me
working out what I wanted to do in my
life and also more importantly what kind
of community I wanted to keep around me
I think one thing that I learned from
being going to Sloan and doing lgo which
is the double Masters is the community
people you keep tend to be like quite
nerdy a little bit
International uh passionate about like
like the most random things like it's
like something something Tech and like
that's the community I wanted to keep
around me and that's the people I wanted
to become and so Sloan just kind of like
checked all those boxes compared to
other schools and yeah I'd like like to
say that I you know contributed to that
Community as well as you know like
obained a lot of value from those
communities so yeah that's why I chose
Stone and I wanted to add to that to
Daniel's comment on community they think
in visiting different schools and and
through the kind of the process of
selection for me Sloan stood out because
it seemed like it had the most like just
down to earth people who were who were
like Dan like passionate about something
coming from all kinds of different
diverse backgrounds but that like down
to Earth was really appealing aspect for
me
because I'm sure as you know we're on
the fly fly panel right so sometimes you
get impostor syndrome right familiar
feelings and being able to like feel
like you can fit in and just be yourself
was was really really a big deal so when
I when I walked into Sloan I talked to
you know prospective sloes and I talked
to sloes who are already there I felt
like okay like cool I don't have to you
know try to put on many many layers of
of trying to be somebody who I'm not I
can just be myself because I see all
kinds of people here and everybody's
just seemed like really nice kind and
interesting
I can also I I can only agree to what
was said already um that that hits the
nail really um what what made me choose
Sloan was actually uh because I went
there already for a semester abroad and
uh I basically came back to the campus
and I chose this because I was like for
the first time like seen as Who I Am
with all the interest I bring to the
campus and I was able to find every like
for every corner with any Niche there's
something uh you can go to and
you can't really tell from where
somebody's coming from because this
nerdiness brings in like the the DNA of
M is like what kind of interest and how
much curiosity you bring with it and not
much more it's really basically who you
are and you can really bring your full
self to to the compos
yeah absolutely so much of that
resonates with how we all feel here
today and I love that so many of you
brought up Community you're actually
beating me to the punch a little bit
that was my next series of questions I
know that um one I one of the things I
think that is so beautiful about the fly
Community both in slone and out is that
it really is a focus on lifting each
other up I know that when I talk about
my educational attainment it's not a
oneperson show I'm here because of so
many people who came before me and
supported me so I would love to hear
about uh any additional information you
have about what communities you were
part of at slan and how you got involved
in the Sloan community and especially if
you have any examples on how those
communities supported you because this
is a pretty intense experience
regardless of the program you
participate
in I can jump in on that one to open us
up I I am really really happy to be on
this p panel right now because two three
years ago so 20 about 2020 was myself
and two other sloes we founded uh fly at
Sloan and I remember I remember the
process and I remember the excitement
and kind of coming back to this kind of
point of community I remember was like
small very very small group of us there
was maybe six or seven people coming uh
doing ask me anything on socio economics
and that's kind of how we found each
other initially and connected and then
myself and two other slones like you
know what we're missing we're missing
this community and official student club
and this the amount of support um just
completely outpouring support both from
the school administration and like our
classmates that we saw immediately was
just amazing so you know coming back to
the point of like fitting in and
involvement and and being able to have
people like you but also with allies who
want to listen to your story want to be
able to support you want to be able to
relate to you and like elevate your
voice um it was it was a really really
awesome experience in that way so it's
kind of coming coming full full circle
being on this panel uh so pretty pretty
great yeah I want to follow up on the
out foring a support um I think one big
community that got to me I guess two big
communities that was to me and I guess
this panel is for prospective applicants
but like before I joined Sloan was the
blacks and business Students Association
they reached out to me before I like six
months before I got the offer and like
the day after they reached out so um
they like already had assigned me like a
mentor or someone to like support me
through the transition process to give
me advice on housing so like yeah I
think Sloan is not short on support of
this ispit like that um and the second
group is the lgo group um I can
confidently say I wouldn't have
graduated without um the support of
lgs's um just because like the work code
was like so high and so yeah I find that
like the communities that supported me
during Stone was just like I it was
something I hadn't found before even in
college and even to a degree at work now
it's like it's definitely very unique to
the school and something I like like
love with all my
heart I would also add one thing that is
it it stays also after you graduate so
I'm uh I'm Amazed by how many people um
reply that I I'm texting from the Alumni
network so now as an alumna like I'm I'm
reaching out to people across
Generations that have been at MIT a
decade ago uh but they they share the
same values very very interested in the
younger generation as well so I think
there also one advice I can give to to
anyone like it's not only when you're
studying or at grad school but it
continues to be in your back pocket
whenever you need it in your
career um I would add that the the the
best and greatest community that I got
out of the experience was my own cohort
um so the the SF program is about 110 or
so people uh we have a WhatsApp chat
that is literally all 108 of us that
graduated from the program still we're
very much in touch with each other we
travel to see each other and um uh as
Alisa was saying um we we draw on each
other for advice and
um resources still um and probably will
for a very long time but getting to know
those people um was one of the best
experiences of my life so your your
cohort and your classmates are going to
continually surprise you and how amazing
they are um but also how down to earth
and supportive and um and relatable
there's there's a lot of adversity and
um in my does a really good job sonone
does a really good job of giving you the
opportunity to showcase your background
so that you aren't compelled to just
keep it to yourself you actually share
it with people and then there it makes
relating to each other and bonding with
each other easy and of course it's a
really great group of
people absolutely SL does a really great
job of uh helping us find either smaller
cohorts or smaller groups so we can
really get to know each other even
though Sloan encompasses all these
programs and really does encourage us to
show up as our full selves which I think
is really special and I want to dig into
a little bit about how you all actually
engage with your Alumni network so Alisa
kind of building on something that you
said what uh how you engaged alumni
while you were here and after and how
you found you know community and
advancement through engaging with this
lone Alumni
network I mean I I can go first given
that I just just mentioned that and it's
a currently a big part of my life
because I'm considering like constantly
where to drive my career and um when
you're at bad school you're most exposed
to the to your cohort and maybe they
buff and then the next ones but it is as
I said like it's a like you find across
Generations a lot of people to reach out
to so I don't know exactly how I use it
there's something about to say about
like the background you bring in maybe
you have to find more advice than others
that can from a high income family
because there's some sort of compass
missing I don't know how to describe it
but sometimes you feel like there's a
corrective missing or like a clear path
is sometimes not so simple because
nobody else have have told you how to do
it there's also a lot of Advantage
because you can do it by yourself and
nobody's telling you what to do because
your parents maybe don't even know what
a business school is on the other hand
you might get lost easily so I think the
Alumni network is very helpful to to
give you some sort of like feedback or
like
if something resonates with your
interests or not and you'll find for
sure people that share that do something
you're excited about can reach out to
them that's how I do it and um I'm I'm
surprised like how many people are like
happy to share how their Journey was and
um yeah can can really recommend
that for me it um yeah I can speak maybe
to postgraduation experience it feels
like uh the community doesn't stop so
I'm in New York which is one of the
bigger sort of hubs that sends a lot of
Sony's out and it feels like there is
like a massive community of people here
like you know someone's holding a
housewarming on Saturday I just came
back from a wedding of a Sony it's like
it's a community that just like never
stops and so it has it supports me you
know both socially and like emotionally
to this day and then you know within
Sloan it was um an amazing experience to
feel like you know like Eliza said like
you feel like you have a support network
to give you advice when you don't know
what to do next and I think like during
the recruiting season that's like
especially pertinent uh when you want to
know like okay how do I pursue this
really Niche startup that I've never
heard about before but then there's a
Sony there that knows someone that knows
someone and so there's always that
connection that helps you um you know
recruit but also you know let loose a
little bit on the
weekends I have a lot of success with
the career development office um it's
got a a great platform that will help
pair you with somebody um who is either
in the field or has experience that
you're looking for they actually Avail
themselves they put themselves out on
this platform to accept um meetings with
you so that that is something that's
available to you which is phenomenal and
even if it's just like hey I'm thinking
about a startup or I'm thinking about a
career switch or something like that
they're there to um just bounce some
ideas off which is really great but I
also actually use LinkedIn constantly
and I pull up other sonies um and I've
had a 100% success rate in reaching out
to other slon um and um asking if I
could you know just tap their Network or
talk to them a little bit and um
Everybody
replies yeah I S similarly on um on my
side during during Sloan um the actual
NBA program it was really really helpful
for recruiting purposes and just kind of
getting advice getting mentorship which
a lot of the times a piece that we
really really need right because like at
Lea men we can't we're not really going
back to to our families to ask for
advice and might not have as big of a
network to to lean on to so getting
access to this huge and amazing slow
Network is a is a big big benefit and
then postgraduation I start working uh
here here at BCG and I'm in Boston
office so there's a lot of lot of sloes
around and it's been pretty awesome
because even on my day one right at work
here you walk into the room and you see
a bunch of slones and familiar faces
whether they're your year slon or prior
Year and that has been also um really
really awesome as a source of Support
also source of mentorship in my
career fantastic and so kind of winding
back to your time here on campus were
there specific resources that you found
were really helpful for you as a first
gener local income student uh or any
specific resources uh initiatives or
programs that you would recommend for
other students coming in with a similar
background uh well one big one for me I
mentioned Income Support before uh this
is gu very specific to the lgo program
but they offer a wide range of
fellowships for people who sort of can't
afford tuition and I'm like one of the
biggest beneficiaries of that like
without a doubt I couldn't have attended
business school any kind of grad school
without it and so it very much unlocked
the ability to sort of not have to
stress about tuition costs and sort of
emers myself in full stone experience um
because I'm like I was one of those
people like I couldn't go to my parents
like they can't afford it so like you
know who so it's nice to feel like I
feel supported from the lgo program
through the fellowship and I think this
extends to MIT um Sloan MBA program too
where they have a wide range of
fellowships too so um yeah income
support for me was like my biggest um
Unblocker when it comes to attending
Sloan and I felt very supported from the
program then
I would iterate what Candice was saying
about the career development office I
engag with them quite early and I'm
still in contact with my um responsible
person she's just checking in a couple
of months I'm going and um I think yeah
this is this is one of the greatest
resources that stays beyond the beyond
graduation um the program office was
really helpful um to me but also most of
my um cohort mates were um parents they
had children and so moving your entire
family across the world um finding a
place to live that is Affordable they
really tap the resources of the program
office to help guide them through it
wasn't just necessarily um you know
moving here it's it's all a new country
and a lot of things for them to have to
navigate and Boston's a busy place and
um there were a lot of resources that
they can help you so I would I get the
advice from your program office as
well yep all great advice and I'll just
add a couple sents as someone who's kind
of on the ground now um I've been really
impressed by how many paid opportunities
there are also around Sloan during the
semester there's I know pretty much
everyone I know is a TA and a research
assistant there's in semester
internships there's been a number of
opportunities for ways to kind of get
money to help you get through this
semester as well as I think Sloan has a
a culture where no we don't want anyone
to feel excluded so there are also a
number of events that are not
financially intensive um and like I said
earlier there's a social impact fund so
if you want to pursue something social
impact related over the summer there is
a stien you can apply for to help pad
that so it means that you know students
who aren't coming into Sloan with a huge
number of savings are excluded from kind
of pursuing those opportunities that
aren't able to pay you as much so there
are a couple of different things around
campus to help us feel a little bit more
like we're not inhibited by the
background and uh we got a question in
from the audience that I really really
loved and it's as a first generation
college graduate or low-income member of
the slone community how do you balance
the drive to push your limits and break
new barriers while taking the time to
celebrate and acknowledge your victories
and achievements
I know everyone is smiling because we're
all probably reflecting and thinking of
that it's a difficult that it's a
difficult thing to do um for me I I can
definitely speak for myself it's a it's
an
ongoing uh striking of a balance and the
reminders to myself to quote quote stop
and smell the roses right and and enjoy
I have a h one and a halfy old daughter
now and she is definitely helping kind
of bring that balance and pull me more
into the enjoying the the small you know
happy happy moments on uh you know as as
as you plan your life and your
achievements and your next steps to be
able to kind of pause reflect on
everything that you've done and how far
we've come and um I know all of us on
the panel and folks you know in the uh
all participants listening in I'm sure
that the path for any lwi income first
first gen student is a typically pretty
long right and there's a lot of
challenges to to overcome so I think
it's it's probably a well-deserved pause
for for most of us to look back and and
just appreciate how far we've come and
uh what we've done and the GD and
resilience that it's
taken um I don't think I balanced it
well to be honest I think like like
candidly I think it's very easy to get
caught up when your career trajectory
your money your Liv Stones your dydx is
not positive like when that gradient is
not positive you can get very much
caught up in that and feel like you're
not you know pushing your limits you not
breaking
barriers um and so you know I think I
think the times when I do double check
myself and try to be a bit more bit more
optimistic and acknowledge like where
I've succeeded is like when I speak to
like my family who are like are still
like you know like they're still like so
like like the same they're like
consistent throughout my whole life it's
like a good day to to compare how you
are now versus like how you were in the
past
and I think when they like you know
especially my dad like my dad's like oh
like you could try this you could try
that or you've changed XY Z like it's
like a very good reference point for me
and yeah I think it's a good way for me
to slow down so it's like the community
I keep around me I think allows me to
sort of see where I am and how I'm
feeling but I don't think I balance it
well like I think that's like the
truth um I'm also not sure if I balance
it well on this question really it's
it's a really good one I mean also if
you think about like there's certain
selection Biers going on the fact coming
from a low income family to already be
here that are that are the ones per
definition that are driven towards
reaching something very far um so that
makes us all very driven and I like
Daniel's point of like finding a
reference point that humbles you down
and that can be in my case like the
oldest friendships I have like the
people that know me well remind me that
maybe the starting conditions have been
different and my fear was always like it
goes up and then when is going down but
you you reach that step where you are at
at grad school so it's it's a plateau
and that's something I tell myself so
can go up but it can't go down anymore
because I bring that fear with with it
because growing up like having Financial
concerns is something that is Raising
much more than for others like others
like I want to get from Rich to Rich I
I'm like okay don't want to go back so
that's something um that I tell myself
so it's it's it's getting always better
so
yeah yeah I would um say it's gonna be
drinking through a fir hose while you're
there in in a good way because there are
so many things to do and there's so many
opportunities you can spread your
yourself a little bit thin between the
opportunities too and maybe diffuse your
impact on anyone um so you'll you have
to be judicious and you have to be
strategic and going in try to have a
plan on what you want or how much you
what you want to get specifically out of
your experience at Sloan and you can
help strategize around that by talking
to people um and you know talking to us
and messaging us and talking um uh with
the program office and things like but
uh to the original Point how do you
balance the two
things you can still be really involved
because there are a lot of special and
fun activities that the um that the
program offers and that um uh uh MIT
does in general that allows you to be
connected you're still there you're
still hanging out with your so on a
level you're still networking um but
you're actually taking some time away
and doing something fun and you know
going to one of the many activities that
they um uh set up for you so take
advantage of those because it gives you
a breather you you get to step away but
you still get to be around um people
whom you're really going to
like it's very family friendly in my
experience it was very family friendly
and so you know if you are traveling
with um a family or bring in your family
then a lot of times there's activities
for the kids
too absolutely SOS Partners kids dogs
the whole family are welcome it almost
almost every SL
event and so kind of jumping off of what
you said about how it's like drinking
from a fire hose um are there any other
things that you wish you had known about
Sloan before you started here God
everybody gave me the proper
admonishments everybody was like yeah
it's going to be too much it's a kid
candy store kind of a thing um that's
really true I wish I I understood it
fully and if I could take a second pass
at it I probably would and I would do
things a little bit differently um but I
would actually spend more time with my
with my cohort and I would get to know
even more people and I would cross over
a little bit more to the infants um and
the lgo students and really get to know
people um uh in this course and
others um I think one thing I would do
different is maybe frame my experience
differently I think I came in with the
mindset that like I'm here to Career
pivot I'm here to make friends and
that's it like I did didn't like that
was like my one track mind goal but like
in hindsight I think the way I would
frame it now is it's a lowrisk way of
trying out a bunch of things that you
like can do literally literally anything
it's you mentioned like can call you
mentioned like the social impact fund
but like one thing I regret is like not
coming in being like maybe I could do a
startup maybe I could you know leverage
the fact that MIT gives you a bunch of
free money to you start whatever like
nonsense business you want maybe not
nonsense but like any kind of business
want and so I think if I had come in
with that mindset I think I would have
been a bit more exploratory and like
similar to what Kanda said like that
could mean meeting people outside your
program it could mean a a bunch of
different things but like not being too
like goals focused but rather being like
path and journey
focused um
yeah um I agree a lot with with u what
you guys saying and
maybe to add like think about the timing
of things like if you have a one year
program or two years program or whatever
like think about like zoom out quickly
that that is what what I've would have
Tau myself like zoom out quickly with
your interest go into everything and
then there's something about like
repetition like if you find something
then then stick with it and explore it
more and more I think one of the
mistakes I was doing is like I come in
and I was like okay I'm open to
different things but I I lost myself
also because I was trying like every day
you have a decision of like 10 events or
like something is going on so have a
have a mind like have an idea of how you
make decisions do you want to try every
day something new or do you want to
stick with something you liked in the
beginning and and try to to build a
network around it and uh engage early
with Aluma Network that is something I
learned after this I should have done
this much earlier um strategically so if
you go out of that school you you have
an idea of like who is your network on
the street because it's very different
when you're not getting more on this
very nicely sympathic MIT slown umbrella
U which you take it with it but the
world is sometimes sometimes not so nice
you want to know your
people yeah I'll I'll Echo canice's
Point earlier on the relationships and
and getting to know your cohort getting
to know folks and other cohorts I think
meeting more people and then building
relationship with them and getting to
know them
beyond the first initial conversation
there's like the same kind of template
of conversation typically happens right
as long you meet new person hey what did
you do before what are you doing now
what are you planning to do like
actually kind of digging a little bit
deeper uh to understand and learn this
person um I I've done some of it I was
in in doing my two-year MBA during Co so
it was a little bit of a hiccup in our
ability to do it well but that is like
the best I think advice and the the best
way to really I think in my opinion to
to get the most um out of out of the
time it's loone is is meeting people and
really building those relationships
because the the people are your the
classmates that um you have are are
pretty amazing and and you will keep
those relationships after you
graduate absolutely great points and I'm
pulling from the chat now we have a
number of really great questions
um so an anonymous attendee I really
appreciated Olga's comment about fit and
being myself at the same time I know
schools that try to support fly students
like us aren't perfect could you be uh
as candid as possible and tell us about
some of the more difficult moments when
you were like oh I don't fited as much
as the other students from non-fi
backgrounds how did you navigate that
I
think one for me one experience uh
tended to be like around like trips and
money um I think you there are some
students who are able to just do every
single trip and they can afford it and I
definitely couldn't do that and so I
mean there was two ways I tried to
navigate it was like one was you know
trying to you know find you fun times or
like other things that got rid of that
fomo locally something that I could
afford um and the second one was like
plan the trips myself and contribute to
those communities so that I'm the one
who's aware of the fact that it's now
cost prohibitive and so those are my
strategies for doing but again it's not
perfect yeah for for me some of the
moments where you you know I felt like I
didn't fit in and it's it's the
conversations that sometimes you can't
relate to right like hey what did you
all my parents have a house in h is it
Hampton's um right or or a lot of the
hobbies that you know I didn't know how
to ski um I ended up learning later on
uh and got peer
pressured at at long which I did don't
regret but I think it's some of those
times where you're just kind of you know
you're part of the conversation but
you're can't really relate you can't
really add anything because everybody
seems to connect on that topic but you
just don't have any experience and you
feel a little bit you know awkward just
kind of like nodding or trying to stay
positive about it but uh you know you
you really you feel like you don't
belong in that in that part of the
conversation yeah I I think for me that
definitely that definitely occurs and I
I had similar experience where everybody
was going to Davos just just going to
Davos um and uh not everybody could and
and so you feel it yourself or you feel
it on behalf of others but um I'm you
know like I said I'm from rural Texas uh
my parents were laborers and so um sort
of the the
um the the pedigree or the um fine
I didn't always felt like I had or
exuded um the way that some students did
and so I felt like even in in my 40s
like I stuck out like a sore thumb um I
would say if you feel that way um own it
I would say two things just own it um
there's
something great about being your
authentic self and um if if you don't
have experience with something or a
certain situation um you'll probably
find that other people haven't as well
and but also it again it was just such
an a supportive friendly group of people
that somebody always felt it felt like
somebody was taking me under their wing
but you can also the second thing I
would say is that you can also find a
mentor whom you can be very candid with
and say like this is sort of my
background I I really feel uncomfortable
in these
situations um and try to find a mentor
who maybe has a similar background or
can relate in some way who can help
guide you through that or at least talk
you up um because like I said when I
first started this is actually a
strength of yours you're coming from a
different background with a different
Viewpoint um and that is that diversity
of thinking is so valuable in the school
and in the in the business world and in
an innovation environment so please
always just think of it as an
asset and we have maybe last maybe
second to last question but I've seen a
couple questions in the chat about
balancing kind of going from being a
full-time employee and especially when
you have family who's who relies on you
either kids or parents what is how have
you navigated the transition from you
know being able to play that role in
your family to kind of still bearing
that stress either material or emotional
uh while here it's alone
Courtney would you give the question one
more
time yeah so um the question was about
what how did you manage going from kind
of being a full-time employee kind of
bringing money in and having either kids
or parents or other family members who
rely on you financially how did you
transition from that to being at Sloan
where many of us don't have income
anymore and we're still worried about
financially supporting our family
also a big question we can maybe we can
also switch to a different one as well
um I'll just briefly touch on I have
family who financially relies on me a
bit and that's when I really pulled in
other parts of my community um Extended
relatives siblings other people to help
bear that weight and taking advantage of
some of the opportunities to make money
while here uh to supplement but also you
know having the hard conversations of
saying my ability to support the family
is Ching right now and it might not be
forever but finding you know it's it's
different for everyone finding ways to
balance that um and then there are ways
if you have children to navigate that
here with our um subsidized child care
as well um but other question is maybe
our last wrap up uh what advice do you
have for first generation students
applying maybe like a one a one sentence
kind of your One Word of Wisdom to leave
with um I can go first um I think words
of wisdom I would agree with what
Candace is saying see it as an advantage
that you can do your own path there are
no predefined paths you can you have to
own it and it's your your asset and you
you should like don't disappear Just go
with it and and find your own way and um
yeah so I I think I leave it
there I'll actually piggyback on what
Daniel said and maybe this is a little
bit less philosophical a little bit more
tactical take advantage of resources
like sandbox um it's free money for a
potential startup and um an incredible
way to gain
mentorship um because I I know I and and
several other people like we don't we
don't have familial connections that are
going to connect us with reserves to
help support an idea that we have but
something like sandbox can actually
teach you how to make those connections
um and in that way kind of change your
life forever it was an incredible
experience for me um and some of my
friends who have gone on um to Delta V
and
whatnot also be
yourself I would say tell tell your
story and be proud of
it and then ask don't be afraid to ask
for help ask anybody and everybody for
help information anything and then pay
it forward to
others um yeah I don't think I can sum
up all that by still say one word um
yeah just echoing what everyone else has
said and I guess given that this panel's
for prospective applicants I think it
would be like like Leverage your
identity whether that's being like using
a see as a superpower to tell your story
or like using it as a super power using
as a way to connect with other fli or
even other people in general to like
connect and like educate people about
what fli means and so yeah those are
that's my advice like Leverage your
identity as your super
[Music]
power
e
e e