welcome everyone um thanks for joining
us today and thanks for your interest in
MIT slones NBA program as Melissa
mentioned I'm Kelly I am part of the MBA
program Office Team um I work as a
senior associate director Focus mainly
on academics in the curriculum and I'm
also one of our uh cohort advisers for
students in the
program um so let's get started next
slide so MIT Sloan's mission is to
develop principled and Innovative
leaders who improve the world and our
goal is to give each MBA student two
years full of both the challenge and the
support that accelerates Learning and
Development and allows you to reach the
top of your potential as principled and
Innovative leaders and in the diagram
that you see here you'll see that the
student is at the center illustrating
how you sit at the center of your MBA
experience and for each student this
really looks different but no matter
what experience you come in with or what
academic and career goals you have set
for yourself what you can count on is an
education that encompasses intellectual
rigor diverse thinking and a priority on
building leadership skills and funneling
into these overlaying principles are the
MBA program pillars of innovative
Hands-On learning integrated leadership
development world renowned faculty
rewarding careers and the MIT experience
or
ecosystem so today as Melissa mentioned
we're going to focus on the classroom
learning and curriculum elements of
these pillars um the foundation for
which is our unique one semester MBA
core next
slide um an integral part of the MBA
core experience is the support system
that is embedded from day one so each
student is assigned to a cohort and a
core team on the first day of
orientation using an algorithm to
maximize diversity of perspectives on a
number of dimensions and each of the six
cohorts shown here are named after
oceans and seas each cohort has 11 core
teams with six or seven students each so
a cohorts about 70 something
students um and students work closely
with these core teams throughout all
their core courses each cohort also has
a dedicated MBA program advisor of which
I'm one and each core team is matched
with a seconde core mentor who acts as a
guide throughout your first 100 days at
loan next
Slide the MBA core is completed in your
first fall semester it's a one semester
core and it consists of Melissa if you
can
click um it consists of five full
semester courses taken with your cohort
and those courses are economics data
models and decisions or what we call DMD
Communications organization processes
and accounting and then you also take
leadership challenges for an inclusive
world or what we call lead week which
I'll share more about shortly and then
you'll have your choice of One Core
elective to take in your first fall
semester as well and you can choose
between Finance operations management
marketing or
strategy and then after that first core
semester you'll have the remaining three
semesters to tailor your cours workk to
your specific goals through SLO
electives action learning courses um
courses on Main Campus MIT even cross
registering at Harvard's professional
schools um we have a relationship with
them uh perhaps completing a certificate
or doing a semester abroad through our
small Exchange program MBA program
advisors your seconde core Mentor other
second years and faculty can all be
helpful in thinking through how to
curate your curriculum over the three
elective semesters
and then you'll see on the right side of
this slide beyond the core your
remaining degree requirements are to
complete at least 144 graduate level
elective units this averages about five
courses per semester depending on which
ones you choose um one of these
electives must be from our pre-approved
leadership elective list you'll also be
participating in Sloan intensive period
or sip week um I'll also share more on
that shortly and then then the final
degree requirements in order to graduate
with your MBA are to obtain a be average
GPA and complete the four full
semesters next
slide so lead week um is a unique thing
that was developed to create a core
educational experience for first
semester MBA students that helps
recognize that being an effective leader
requires a deep understanding of what it
means to be a human and a complex world
for three consecutive days in the middle
of October first year mbas will take a
break from regular classes and instead
they select six three-hour workshops
distributed evenly across the topics of
leadership ethics and diversity equity
and inclusion or Dei so examples of some
of this year's Workshop titles include
sports rates and gender solving the
climate crisis an on- roads climate
policy simulator
um leading through storytelling and
ethics in product design and marketing
so not only is lead week an opportunity
to hear from some amazing experts in
these kind of really interesting areas
but it gives students a chance to be in
the classroom with peers from outside of
their cohort for the first time in the
core semester and to be begin to build
those connections setting up for the
next three elective
semesters I also had mentioned the
degree requirement of slan intensive
period or sip week this requirement can
be fulfilled by completing workshops in
the spring semester which are similar in
structure to the what I just talked
about with lead week or there's a couple
other ways to complete this requirement
you can do it by participating in
certain action learning Labs TRS or
Study Tours which all occur over this
sip week in mid-march right before
spring
break next slide
I had mentioned options to customize
your curriculum and one of those is
through certificates which are open to
all Sloan degree students there are
seven certificates that you have the
option of pursuing during your time at
Sloan certificates are completely
optional but they provide a curriculum
path for the industry or functions of um
those listed here so entrepreneurship
Enterprise management Finance business
Analytics product management health care
and
sustainability students who complete the
set of requirements set forth by the
certificate will receive the certificate
in addition to their degree at
graduation and particularly for career
Changers certificates can be very
helpful in giving direction to your
course choices signaling a concentration
area to potential employers and
facilitating connections with students
who have similar career
goals next slide
um so unlike uh some possibly peer
schools MIT Sloan does not follow just
one teaching method you'll see case
studies small group projects traditional
lectures across all of our electives and
often um if not always within the same
course they they switch up the teaching
methods however if I was to name one
signature kind of teaching F method at
loan I talk about action learning
through action learning courses or we
call them Labs students apply the theory
and Concepts that they're learning in
the classroom to real business
challenges posed by external company
sponsor sponsors um in each year Sloan
faculty offer over 15 action learning
courses focusing on either a regional
area an in industry or an inter
interdisciplinary topic many of these
action learning Labs include travel to
spend time at the location of the
company sponsor but some remain local on
campus and these courses are very
popular with Sloan students because they
offer a practical opportunity to learn
how to structure and solve problems how
to collaborate effectively in a team and
how to lead through complex situations
so I've listed a few of our popular
action learning Labs here but you can
see our full roster of offerings on
Sloan's action learning web page next
slide as I mentioned at the beginning
developing principes leaders is in our
mission statement and the MIT Leadership
Center believes that this involves
pursuing Deeper Self and other awareness
at three levels individual team and
organization so the three course
elective sequence here maps to each of
these levels starting with idlab which
is built on the premise that being an
effective leader starts with
understanding yourself so traditional
CRA classroom learning Executive
coaching and informal interactions with
classmates are combined to provide an
environment for individual
transformation in this um ID lab
elective the suggested path is then to
take teams lab and conclude with leading
with impact which was formerly called
ORS lab or organization's
lab uh next
slide and then as you can imagine there
is a lot of action around Ai and the
curriculum lately and we often get asked
about what we are doing in this area at
Sloan so I wanted to highlight a little
bit of that here last summer the MBA
program introduced a new workshop for
incoming mbas led by Professor Eric so
this Workshop was designed to lay the
foundation for discovering the latest AI
Technologies and how to choose the right
tools to use for learning practical ways
to incorporate AI into your daily tasks
for understanding AI ethics and it gave
Hands-On exercises for classroom
applications um and this was something
that was offered incoming mbas as a kind
of foundational level setting Workshop
as they entered the
program a faculty we've we've had some
courses um in this area for a while but
faculty have introduced two new courses
designed to equip managers and founders
with the tools needed to excel in the
future of gen and those um this year
were gen for managers and gen lab which
is an action learning course and these
courses are a deep dive into how gen
Works its use cases and business
implications for those managing teams
all the way up to the executive level on
the technical side operations research
faculty have have designed Hands-On deep
learning this is a course focused on the
engine behind predictive and generative
AI with an emphasis on developing a deep
Hands-On understanding of how to build
the models to solve complex problems
involving the processing of unstructured
inputs so like how do we detect If a
driver is falling asleep and
unstructured outputs so how do we
summarize the content of a customer
service call
transcript next
slide and in addition to Ai and action
learning and the leadership courses that
I've just mentioned here are just a few
other courses new to Sloan's elective
offering brings this year and a
selection of others that may have been
around for a while but are consistently
popular with our
students next
slide and then finally um just carrying
on with the kind of how to curate your
academic experience in your elective
semesters we also offer several dual
degree programs and other um other
offerings so we have the LG lgo program
which is a dual degree between
engineering and MBA we have a dual
degree with Harvard Kennedy School which
combines public policy and MBA we have a
dual degree with MIT Department of urban
studies and
planning um and then we have some
students that come in with a legatum
fellowship and these students are
focused on entrepreneurship and emerging
markets and as I mentioned we have a
small Exchange program with London
Business School and Esa in Barcelona
which um allows a small number of MBA
students to do a semester abroad at
those
schools next
slide great um so I hope that this gives
you a better idea of not only the Core
Curriculum and the degree requirements
but also the many academic options and
just highlights the level of flexibility
that you have within Sloan's MBA
program and I'll close it there and I'm
happy to take any questions perfect
thanks Kelly I'm going to stop my screen
so it's easier to see we have so so so
many questions in the chat so let's get
to it um the first question for you
Kelly is in January we don't have
classes at MIT it's called IAP can you
just tell us a little bit what is I AP
and what does students do during this
time yeah um great question uh so yes so
at MIT the fall semester ends in mid
December
but the spring semester doesn't start
until the first week of February so that
January period is called IAP or
independent activities period and this
is something that's been um it's an MIT
not a Sloan uh Innovation I guess but
it's been around for a long time and the
concept behind MIT is that it gives I'm
sorry the concept behind IAP is that it
gives MIT students um a a break from the
rigorous academics so that they have
time to explore wide variety of
workshops offered by members of the MIT
community so not for credit workshops
are offered during this January period
on everything from Japanese flower
arranging to like studying regenerative
food to tours of the MIT Wright brothers
wind tunnel so that's kind of what iip
um was designed for but there are also
several of several four credit classes
that happened during IP particularly
some of the action learning courses um
travel over IAP so if you choose you can
earn some credits during IAP um and
depending on your career interest you
may be really busy with um recruiting um
on campus recruiting during that month
particularly for some finance and
Consulting roles and Tech likely um so
in short there are many things you can
do an iip you can earn credit you can do
workshops you might be recruiting but
there's nothing you're required to do
you're not required to be here and many
students just use it as a chance to
relax to visit family and just catch up
on some much needed sleep after a very
busy cor sem awesome thank you we have a
lot of questions about cross
collaboration and cross registration so
I know you can take three classes
outside of Sloan um can you share a
little bit more about how that
works yeah so um uh MBA students can
take up to three nons Sloan courses um
towards their degree requirements so up
to three courses can count towards that
144 elective unit requirement that I
mentioned nons slown means anything on
Main Campus or anything cross-registered
at Harvard um if youve perused our MIT
course catalog you'll notice that course
anything that starts with a number 15 is
considered a Sloan course it's taught by
Sloan faculty um and anything that
doesn't start with a number 15 is
considered
nonl uh you can take more than three
nonl or Harvard courses it's just that
only three will count towards those 144
um and they have to be graduate level
courses in order to count awesome thank
you so in terms of the first semester
what does the class schedule look like
or the hours um when can students be
expected to be on campus great question
so each cohort has a different um
schedule and you will learn that
schedule
uh few days before orientation when you
get your cohort assignment um but you
can expect that classes will not start
any earlier than 8:30 and won't end any
earlier than 5:00 pm unless you are
taking a certificate that offers an
evening um certificate seminar and those
meet on Monday evenings there is a lunch
block um which is free from classes
that's from 11:30 to 1 um that is when a
lot of uh Club you know guest speakers
happen um your core team meetings you
might have coffee chat scheduled during
that block so that's a block that's
protected from classes um and classes
run Monday through Thursday Fridays you
won't have any courses but you will have
um optional recitations for some of our
classes and recitations are where the TA
offers like review sessions for what you
learned in class that week
um there are two Fridays in the core
semester generally in early September
that there are required special sessions
of your core courses um and we would
share those dates uh the summer prior to
you coming great a lot of questions on
certificates so are certificates a
requirement how many of them can you do
can you still cross collaborate with
other courses if you choose to do
certificates so a lot of certificate
questions great yeah certificates are
not required they are completely
optional and like I said they're open to
um all of loan and some are even open to
um MIT graduate students as well uh they
are so there are seven certificates in
total you can complete up to two
certificates during your time in the
program um and you can cross count up to
two courses towards the requirements so
if you know managerial Finance is an
option on sustainability and the finance
certificate
then you could count that towards both
but you can only do that for two courses
um and the certificates are not it's
it's I believe the certificates are
between like 35 and 45 units to complete
a certificate so it tends to happen that
if you're generally interested in one of
those areas chances are it's not going
to be a real challenge for you to
complete the certificate units so it's
about you know less than half of your
elective units that you would Dev vote
toward the certificate so you do have
plenty of space to take courses outside
of that particular functional
area great so switching to action
learning Labs how many action learning
Labs do you think students generally
take um
I I've never actually pulled the numbers
on that I would say most students take
one during their time um some students
might take two I I
don't think I've seen a scenario where
student has been able to take more than
two but I could be wrong um but yeah I
would say the majority of our students
it's uh it's something that they place a
high priority on when they come in that
they want to take at least one action
learning lab great um can you share a
little bit more about competitions and
things that kind of happens happen
across
campus
um as yes it
so outside of academics a little bit
outside going outside um so yeah there
are uh a lot of student L clubs there
are a bunch of student L com conferences
we just wrapped up um our investment
management club uh sponsored a stock
petch competition I think it was last
week um where they invited a bunch of
schools here to do a stock pitch
competition um our clubs often our our
clubs often go like organiz themselves
and go to other competitions there is a
large MIT ecosystem of events and
centers and initiatives that you can
take advantage of um we also have a
really active significant others and
partners community so your significant
others and partners can get involved um
but I would leave that to another
webinar to talk more specifically about
the events outside of the classroom um
but it's it's very robust and it's we
say it's drinking from a fire hose right
so it's just about figuring out what
your goals are and trying to prioritize
how you spend your time based on those
goals totally yes there's a lot going on
outside the classroom um so I know we
talked a little bit about the leadership
sequence is the leadership sequence a
required set of courses that all mbas
need to take good question no so the
sequence that I showed of the ID lab
teams lab and orgs lab is a
recommendation for um mbas from the MIT
Leadership Center based on mit's
leadership philosophy um so you were not
required to take that sequence um they
are really popular courses in particular
ID lab and teams lab um you get
executive one-on-one coaching through
those courses which is a really great
benefit uh and ID lab in particular is
only open to first year mbas but it's
not required but they do meet um so
there is a requirement to take one
leadership elective those courses are on
that list and then there's also about 15
or 20 other courses on that list so
those would meet that requirement
awesome um can you touch upon how Sloan
students collaborate with like the media
lab C sales Center For Real
Estate Etc yeah um so there all of those
centers um I would say the most popular
way that Sloan students collaborate is
they all offer courses um so you can
take courses that fall under media lab
and Center For Real Estate and Cale um
and those would likely be part of that
one nons slown course limit um they all
tend to have uh speaker series and
events so if you get on their mailing
list you can um be active with them
there uh I mean depending on your
background and interest there might be
opportunities to work with faculty from
those areas on Research through a
research assistant position um
but I would say most often it's just
through taking their courses um
attending their speaker series taking
courses that bring Sloan students and
those students together um some of our
Ventures courses like fintech Ventures
or any energy Ventures tend to have um
collaborative team projects with
students from outside of Sloan who are
active in those
areas great we got a few questions of is
it possible to trans ER credits that
somebody has done before Sloan and
transfer them to the core or another
elective H good question no Sloan does
not accept transfer units um so the core
courses are required there are no
waivers for any of the core
courses great um thank you so a lot of
questions about dual degrees if you just
want to share very briefly about the
Dual degree um and how that process
works yes so our dual to be with
HKS um Melissa I'm actually not if you
are more familiar with how that
emmissions process works I'll leave that
to you I can I can totally answer this
one so many of the questions are about
like HKS and lgo so for both of these
dual degrees you have to apply for HKS
concurrently to both HKS and Sloan at
the same time in our round two and you'd
have to be admitted to both of them to
be considered and for the leaders for
Global operations you have to apply
directly to the lgo program to be
considered for both MBA and lgo and if
your application is unsuccessful for lgo
you're automatically considered for MBA
in round
two I hope that helps um all right we'll
do like one more question if that's okay
Kelly so how hard is it to get into the
elective classes that students want to
take uh if it's if you're referring to
the core electives where you have a
choice of one of the four core electives
we um you will rank your choices in the
onboarding process and then we'll assign
students based on their choice um last
year everybody was able to get their
first choice of core elective uh with
the electives um beyond the core the
three sem the remaining three semesters
we have a bidding system for slan
electives uh so you're given a certain
amount of points and you use those to
bid for the courses that you want
um and you know second year and your
advisers and everything do presentations
and share strategies on kind of how to
how bidding and and course registration
Works once you hit your elective
semesters but um I think the best
strategy is to just choose you know the
one or two courses each semester that
really are most important to you to take
and put the priority on that um for how
how you bid but yes there are some so
the bidding system um is based on
priority of graduation year so second
years would get first priority first
year would get second priority um but if
you are really serious about wanting to
get into the course and you're strategic
and how you bid um there's very high
chances that you'll be able to take that
by the time the program concludes great
all right one more Kelly um a lot of
questions on how students manage their
day-to-day activities balancing the
course work with things outside what
have you seen as an
adviser yeah so
um the core Mentor is really helpful in
this because um the core mentors meet
regularly with the core teams and since
you're working very closely with your
core team throughout all of the core
courses so the load isn't just on you
you have your core team to lean on and
the core teams are particularly designed
so that everybody comes in with
different backgrounds and expertise um
so you're almost sort of mentoring each
other in your core team as you're going
through the classes as well as having
that core mentor on top of it um but
it's calendaring is a really important
thing blocking time out for yourself and
again just understanding that yes your
goals might change from the time you
come in to the time you leave um or even
three weeks into the semester but your
program adviser can really work with you
to think about what your goals are and
then prioritize what you spend time on
in particular in your core semester um
because you don't have to do everything
that you wanted to get done at Loan in
your first semester you can choose one
or two of those things to really focus
on in your first semester and then leave
some other things for the other three
elective
semesters Perfect all right well Kelly
we got through a lot of questions I hope
everyone's questions were answered um
but if you have any questions after this
please let the admissions team know I'm
going to put the email in the chat for
you right now um we will have a few
additional webinars coming up we will
have an info session in December which
will cover the curriculum and outside of
the classroom we'll have some students
there as well in early January we're
going to do an app tips webinar so it's
all going to be about the application I
know there were a lot of questions today
about the application but we really
wanted to focus more on actually the
curriculum so I hope you'll join us for
that
um but here the email is now in the chat
and I hope everyone um enjoyed the
session and learned a lot I certainly
did Kelly so I want to thank you again
and thank you everyone for joining