And now we will start with Chris Mahi
Argetta, research scientist at the MIT
center for transportation and logistics.
Uh Chris is also director of the MIT
supply chain and global logistic
excellence logistics excellence network
or scale and his presentations survive
or thrive the future of supply chains in
a volatile world. So Chris please go
ahead.
Oh, thank you very much, Jose, for the
the kind presentation. So, it's a it's a
a big pleasure to be with you guys. So,
um and thanks again for the invitation
to the ILP, you know, like for the
invitation to to this very interesting
uh event that you put together. So, uh
now let's get started. So, there are a
lot of things happening right now in the
world and naturally you are very
overwhelmed by many of the changes that
are happening right now. So let's start
you know like deep diving a little bit
more on what is happening outside there
and why is happening and how you can
prepare yourselves. But before I move on
into these details first I would like to
speak a little bit more about what we do
at the emerging market economy logistics
lab that is the laboratory that I
represent. Basically uh the slogan that
we use is that we aim to connect the
global south hemisphere to the global
north hemisphere because most of the raw
materials and the resources that are
outside there that the mother nature has
provide are located in the global south
hemisphere but this includes not only
food as you can see in the first stream
that is regarding agri food access
models but also regarding other type of
commodities including mining including
energy oil etc etc etc. So we aim
actually to connect all of those by
providing value added services around
the world and making sure that we are
making a difference for the ones who
need the most as well. So having said
that the four streams that you see here
including agri food access models
including upstream supply chains
including global and uh transportation
and um crossber transportation and
finally what is recently called
logistics public policy making is
something that we are trying to use in
order to make what we call um ev
evidence-based and applied research
perspectives by using a bunch of
different techniques. But now let's deep
dive a little bit more on what is
important here. So when we speak about
supply chains there are like seven core
capacities that we need to bear in mind.
The first one is acquire materials you
know all the procurement that allows to
maintain the supply across the supply
chain. Second shipping and transporting
all of those materials wherever they
are. Third manufacturing them converting
them into something that is going to be
useful for human beings. Uh the fourth
one is actually to distribute them to
final consumers right but there are
other three important uh characteristics
that we need to keep in mind and these
capacities are include communication
because also the supply chains manage
something that we call information flows
we need to consider the human talent we
are focusing too much these days on
datadriven perspectives AI machine
learning but at the end the humans are
the ones making the decision and I'm
going to speak a little bit more about
it in a moment And last but not least,
we also have financial flows without the
money well and the cash. The cash is
king. We need to keep it moving across
the supply chain. So these seven
capacities are can be also considered
that they create some types of
uncertainty. If we consider acquiring
materials, if you don't have enough
suppliers, this will create some kind of
a disruption. In the second one, if you
don't have enough drivers, this can
create also a crisis. The same that if
you don't have enough containers. The
third one with manufacturing if you
don't have you know like the proper
workforce or the right number it would
be extremely difficult for you to do
everything that you do and speaking of
nearshoring French shoring offshoring
etc. So it's everything related to that
right where should where you should
locate all your different facilities and
distribution to to customers well is
what is happening right now is all the
pressure coming from panic buying you
know like shutdowns that had have been
happening here and there so and I can
continue putting many different examples
but for the sake of time I would like to
actually mention why I'm putting this in
front of you because most of the times
we are not making this simple exercise
that is capac capacity assessment. Most
of the times we tend to forget that we
need to analyze these capacities,
understand the utilization that we have
about that specific capacity, the cost
that it will take me in case that I want
to expand or stretch this capacity or
how much capital should I invest in
order to make that happen. And as I you
I always prefer to say like okay and
what is happening regarding how long
this is going to take you know or delay
in order to get this. So and how we can
face this uncertainty there is something
that we call mitigation mitigation
strategies and basically it's to reduce
the likelihood of something bad to
happen. So everything outside there the
strategies you might develop in terms of
diversifying your suppliers or making
sure that you are connecting you know
like to the right partners reliable
partners is a mitigation strategy. But
we also have something else that we call
resilience actions. The resilience
action basically aims to avoid on these
side effects of all of these potential
disruptions. But not most of the times
we are too focused on the direct effects
that the that these disruptions might
have without necessarily paying
attention to what are the indirect
effects if there is a a fire in a
particular factory or a flood. So it's
very clear that we're going to stop the
production. But what is going to happen
downstream in the supply chain or
upstream in the supply chain we need to
start paying attention to these
particular issues. So and in order to
understand I kind of slice down a little
bit like the uncertainty types we need
to bear in mind economic risk,
geopolitical risk, the technological
risk and of course we need to start
paying more and more attention to where
are all of these resources that we need
for our supply chains to for our
products located. Are they global
globally concentrated in a specific
region country? Are they located in a
specific industry or being used by a
specific industry? We need to start
paying attention to that. And in my
experience working with companies,
sometimes we pay attention to tier one
or tier two suppliers when actually the
problems happen h are happening like in
the tier four and five suppliers. So
that's something that you need to bear
in mind. So now let's talk about
something that fascinates me a lot and
is the human behavior. So I typically
provide this experiment to my students
and we typically what we do here let me
explain the experiment to you and then I
will explain the graphs that you have in
front of you. We tell the students to
define the best order size to produce a
perishable product for each of the days
across these 25 21 days. Right? So they
need to dispose the product at the end
of the day. So this means that they
cannot hold inventory. Right? And the
demand as you can imagine is random.
It's uncertain like in the real life
demand. But at the end this is a
simplification of the reality. So what
you can see here actually is with this
simple experiment we have observed
different pattern. So at the top graph
you can see the best performer and in
the bottom chart you can see the poorest
performer of that particular cohort that
we have. So we have a several elements
here. What you see here in this um
orange line is actually the demand that
was observed and as you can see it's the
same demand for both individuals. Right?
However, the way that they actually
approach the ordering behavior is
completely different. The ordering
behavior is the one that you see in
green here. So this is the near to
optimal behavior that is actually
presented with this straight line here.
And as you can see this individual is
trying to very to be very close to the
optimal you know like order here. But
the other one on the contrary again is
the green line compared to the optimal
that is this plain line or a straight
line. You see a lot of oscillation
right. And of course if you want to pay
attention to the profit that is like how
much this person was earning at the end
of each of the days. So naturally the
one that was not oscillating much was
the one who was like the best approach
possible right because that person is
not going to be paying too much money.
So what is happening here? Why why this
is important for us? All our well all
our behavior is dictated by something
very simple. Are we risk averse or risk
prone? And if you answer this very
simple question actually you will
realize that most of us we are risk
averse particularly when there is
something bad happening outside there.
So we need to make like logical
decisions and understand like what is
happening outside there. But this might
bring us you know like many different
trade-offs and then we will start paying
attention to many other things like loss
sales compared to waste comparing the
lead time versus the shelf life of the
product and then this can create like
forecasting issues or also inventory
issues. you might be ordering more than
what you need and then this can create
an unnecessary effect at the end that is
going to create issues in the whole
supply chain because the the supply
chains still depend on us and they will
keep depending on us. We are the ones
making the decisions and humans
unfortunately tend to overreact to past
realizations. We tend to consider or
follow close to the average let's say
behavior making these decisions when
actually we need to pay a little bit
more attention to what is happening to
the uncertainty but we typically don't
go with the whole visibility of to the
up to the the consumer side. So that's
why it's important to have a little bit
of visibility. So now if we extrapolate
these concepts and this human behavior
to a framework that has been known for a
long period of time that is the AAA
capabilities and what is the AAA
capabilities is agility that you are
able to reconfigure the system
quickly
adaptability means that you can make
long-term you know like changes in the
system and also you know like make sure
to adapt to changes in the long term and
alignment means that you are able to
collaborate with others and to keep an
eye on on on your suppliers on your
consumers or your customers etc. But
this is not only a race against the
clock. It's also actually to pay
attention to the fact that we are making
right decisions properly in the right
time. So most of the supply chains
according to what we have found for with
some of of our studies 85% of them have
adoption rates in agility. So they are
agile supply chains. adaptable supply
chains are only 35% of them and less
than 10% are aligned supply chains. So
what we call efficient supply chains or
resilient supply chains there are not
too many and we need to align these
three different capabilities. So for the
sake of times I decided to bring like a
one specific example that we created in
order to connect you know like the food
supply chains from Latin America to the
US you know in order to understand the
criticality of the ports. So we did that
in order to understand what was going to
be the impact of the near sharing right
with all of the efforts that you can see
here and the figures that we knew that
were growing with almost 11% of
component annual growth rate that was
expected to happen between 21 and this
year. So the opportunities for near
shuring are great right but now with all
of what is happening executive orders
and etc. So this has the accelerated and
it has it has created a little bit more
uncertainty with the tariffs than
anything else. Right? But then what we
aim to develop with this research was
actually to understand what were the
most critical ports connecting Latin
American products to the US particularly
agri food related products as I will
mention in a moment. How does this
logistics infrastructure dependency
affect the port adaptability and agility
in case of any disruption happens? And
last but not least, we also want to
understand how resilient is the current,
you know, like port ecosystem that we
have in the United States for food
imports. And then we decided to focus on
seven items that are considered from the
American food basket. Uh we are
referring to chill products and dry
products. The chilled products we
consider banana, poultry and tomatoes. I
know that the American diet is way more
than than that but we simplify it. And
then in the dry products we consider
cocoa, rice, corn and potatoes. Okay,
they don't need chilled nature, right?
So we can move on. Um so this represents
only almost 5% of the total US food
imports. But guess what? This represents
almost 70% of the imported food from
Latin America and the Caribbean. It's a
lot, right? Just these seven products
and that's why we decided to focus on
them. So what we did here basically is
we followed these fivestep methodology
to understand well first what type of
data was available there to understand
the criticality of the different
logistics facilities particularly the
ports simulate a few potential scenarios
of disruption and analyze the results.
So fortunately we were able to to
collaborate with import genius that
tracks shipping activity around the
world. We also got information from the
US census and we were able to get AIS
that is automate automatic
identification system is imagine like
the GPS for the vessels right and based
on all of this information coming from
the USDA some interviews that we did
with different uh ports and different
people through webinars etc we were able
to capture around 2.3 billion rows of
data that but out of these 2.3 trillion
bill sorry billion
rows of data. We were able to use only
these 38 let me round it up million rows
of data. So based on that we started
exploring some of the analytics behind
them to understand what were the ports
that were more important for what type
of products the trends etc. That's the
second step. And in the third step, we
started understanding what were like
what was the criticality of the ports,
how vulnerable they were in case that
they were not fully connected to the
rest of the supply chain. And we perform
some simulations as I as I mentioned to
you before. So in the second step we
were able with the help of my students
Mateo and Santiago uh and my colleague
Elena Dugongji to get these very fancy
and very you know like informative
charts to understand which ports were
the most important ones in the United
States. As you can see, Wilmington,
Delaware, uh that we discovered that is
like a paradise for tropical fruits in
the United States was massive in terms
in terms of total weight more or less
like 25% of the whole cargo for the uh
seven products that I mentioned before.
And as you can see, the weight in
general terms has been growing, right?
And we got information until 2022. So
now regarding the AIS or the GPS for the
vessels information, we got all of the
potential maritime routes and we were
able to see what was the origin, the
destination and the movement around
these different components in the
vessel. So I'm not going to speak about
the math but what we did in the third uh
you know like a step was actually to
understand how well connected the the
the particular port was how critical was
this particular port to connect to other
facilities ports or routes and how close
was to other ports in order to make sure
to reply as soon as possible if
something happened. So if you actually
pay attention to this chart, you will
realize that Philadelphia is one of the
best ports in terms of connectivity is
the best one, right? So because it's
well connected in terms of closeness is
also the best connected and in between
is that is like how critical it is you
know like to connect to other ports is
also well connected. So that's why it
was and is the the second ranket in
terms of total weight. But what happened
to Wilmington, Delaware, the paradise of
tropical fruits and vegetables. So um so
it's 25% but look at this is not so well
connected right it has issues regarding
how close it is to other ports to the
compatibility issues with other ports.
And that's how we started analyzing that
there was something happening there. So
we started paying attention to how we
can change that and we started inserting
some potential algorithms to understand
what was the potential issue. So we
brought some of these, you know, AI
applied methods in order to understand
how mature or how the ripening process
for the bananas was going to happen in
order to make sure that the bananas were
going to arrive on time to the different
ports. And then something that we
analyze is that particularly the time
and the temperature were critical to
predict the the the grade of the banana
at the very end. So something that we
discovered as well and let me come back
here for a moment is like the thickest
lines are very meaningful to connect the
different ports. Of course you cannot
see like all the connections here
between Latin America and and and and
the US but the northeast particularly is
very important for these connections.
Here we have ports like Wilmington,
Norfolk, Philadelphia, Baltimore, New
Jersey etc etc. And in the south part of
the east component we have Charleston in
South Carolina, Savannah, Georgia, etc.
And I can continue. Why is this
important? Why is this so uh relevant?
Because imagine the following. If we
simulate a disruption actually impeding
the cargo to get up to Wilmington, this
is going to create a lot of issues,
right? So we want to make sure to
understand what was like the best port
to deviate all the cargo. And we found
that Philadelphia was the best port to
debate the cargo. We created this
artificial disruption followed by New
York. But here is where it comes like
the interesting part. Why these vessels
are going to New York? It's not only
because of the capacity, it's also
because of the compatibility, the
equipment and the size of the vessels.
So this actually means that we needed to
uh to take care of how much or how
compatible this could be moved into into
different locations and to understand
how to create port ecosystems. So in
order to to go to the to the to the
final line before I give you like the
final conclusions. So we found from this
particular application that the refer
that is like the way that you connect
the re the refrigerated containers into
the into the ports was a critical
infrastructure. So this actually require
a lot of capital investment and you need
to create a lot of you know like model
and datadriven culture in your people
and a lot of scenario planning to make a
strategic decisions and this connects to
the adaptability
erh competency. The second one that we
found is like several ports should be
always considering you know like
alternative destination in case that the
first port that you're arriving fails
and then you need to divert these
vessels to other ports. So this also
make us think and double check that the
standardization on potential contingency
plans was good and to synchronize
processes to make sure that the
availability of those refer plugs or the
equipment was available as soon as
possible you know and this is regarding
agility. And the last that is the most
difficult one to get is like to create
alignment and this is actually to create
alternative destination ports with
minimum viable capacity to you know like
be able to serve efficiently the
different vessels and this implies good
communication in terms of capacities
good collaboration with other ports and
you know like the potential development.
So wrapping up here, there are many
conclusions, but it's I'm sad to tell
you that there is no one-sizefits-all
strategy to define this AAA capabilities
or actually ways to solve this, but I
invite you to keep an eye on the market
to protect your customers, to rely on
the data, to choose wisely your alleys,
particularly you know, like countries.
We tend to think about the supply chain
as potential alleys as as companies, but
it's also partner partner, you know,
like countries at the moment, you know.
So uh pay attention also to how the
supply and the demand are working
together in the supply side. Pay
attention to the procurement to the
sourcing supply chain network evolution.
Don't not only pay attention to the
snapshot that you take day by day. Water
is becoming an important part of the re
the the the resource shortage. So pay
attention to it. Geopolitical tensions
as I mentioned before demand you need to
start developing signaling related
stuff. E2 toe or end to end call supply
chains and portfolio complexity you need
to reduce it try to think how to
standardize your products and then last
thing call to action if you're
interested in knowing more how to be
part of research related to and direct
effects of disruptions on their
different scenarios or actually to the
impact of perishability uh or human
behavior in the supply chains or
actually something more exciting that is
how to combat food malnutrition and food
waste you can reach out to me. So, uh,
Jose, I'm going to stop here. So,
probably we have time for for one or two
questions probably. Yeah. One quick
question. I think, uh, is is is there
similar analysis? I know CTL of course
is extremely uh uh active and and
comprehensive. Are similar analyses done
for the um uh semiconductor supply
chain?
Yeah, there is. So naturally in the case
of the semiconductors and the chips um
there is only a couple of let's say big
big companies that one might think about
right so but this AAA uh framework can
be used elsewhere and uh to answer the
question how you can optimally use this
probably in terms of agility there is
not so much to be done but in terms of
adaptability and designing the whole
supply chain in the semiconductor
industry there is a huge opportunity
Right. But given that um Taiwan tends to
kind of centralize all the efforts,
probably the question should be more on
know how to optimally apply but how to
create you know like an alternative
supply chain for semiconductors and
understand which countries are actually
uh having or concentrating most of the
elements that you need to create a chip
you know or a semiconductor. uh and that
way you will be able actually to create
like the rest of the manufacturing, the
rest of the transportation and the seven
core capacities that I mentioned before.
Okay, great. Well, yeah, there's we
could we could be here another another
half hour easily, but um thank you so
much. And for anybody interested, of
course, uh you can also look up the
Center for Trans Transportation
Logistics at MIT. Plenty of research
there. And thank you, Chris. Uh we will
continue on.