today um going be a little bit boring
for people on the on watching later and
stuff because we're going to mostly um
be flipping things around so we're going
to use this time for quite a lot of
inclass
work um and you might need the chair
there and um try to get things um uh
getting ready for later and having
videos online um for some of the new
topics that are coming
up um before we get to to this is the
fifth week of the semester um first are
there any questions so far on problem
set
four Adam so optic you would want to two
list at the
same um let me see would I want
they no not necessarily what's what's a
part what let's let's think through
again optic O is just out it out octave
p
t transposition good I inversion and
C one of those um is very important that
you test well all of them is important
that you test with uh different length
sets but what's one of the ones that
might um might sometimes return uh true
if if the two um that the two pitch sets
are equivalent if you have this
equivalence
class cality cardinality yeah so
cardinality equivalence I it's kind of a
odd thing isn't it because it's not it's
kind of the backwards one is isn't it it
should be like
oped um duplication or something because
is specifically not saying that things
are equivalent if their cardinality is
the same it is saying two things are
equivalent if you if their what do you
want to I suppose cardinality is is that
if duplicates are removed um good so so
yeah there will be cases where um where
two pit sets will have different lengths
and um and of of things and be
equivalent
um uh oh one important thing uh um I'll
I'll do the one that I forgot to do um
that's on
inversion and
inversion
is one of these things probably like
mode or something like that that we used
way too often in music to mean too many
related but different things so I'm just
going to move that more to the center
um so what the two places that we've
been talking about inversion
are in sort of this
um do you remember this circle from C C
sharp d flat if spelling doesn't matter
D am I getting there about right yep E
flat E F now somehow I've well because
my circle is more of an egg um you know
so on and sorry I'm uh blanking
on it's been a long time since I've
written a circle of notes that is not
the circle of fifths on the board right
okay got that in order and we've thought
about this sort of axis of inversion
that you can have do you remember that
um that can Define um ways that pitches
can invert to each other we also use
inversion and so this is prime the
primary one that deit tachko is talking
about we also use inversion to mean sign
we called tonal inversion
which is to say oh yeah we did this in
class for a second right that this can
be
inverted to
this even though so because here we go
up a step here we go down a step here we
go up another step we go down a step up
a step down a step but even though the
steps are different sizes right so F to
G is what kind of Step whole step next
one whole step half and this one half
whole whole so but so in the in the
strictly
enharmonic context of inversion they
would not be the same which is the
context that Demitri Tranco is mostly
talking about in the tonal context they
would um they would be the same though
right but then there's this third part
this third very common use of the word
inversion in music that is not what
we're talking about in any way on this
problem set when John you know what that
is Chord inv chord inversion chord
inversion so right so if I have a chord
let's say a
major what is the base if I am in second
inversion e great
so you might have something like
that now here's so that's the
explanation part that's the
clarification part and now the the
critical thinking thing chord inversion
in this sense has to do with what letter
of
optic
p and there's another one so P we could
say that a c Shar e is the same as e e c
a but there's something else we need
yeah oh so we need that this o is
equivalent to this o that this octave is
the same as this octave I see everybody
shivering it's really cold in here today
isn't it right okay no I maybe it's just
me you're cold other people are cold and
I'm like up here here okay so o
and octave and
permutation um
if you have an augmented Triad there's
an interesting here let's just keep
playing we'll make a simpler augmented
Triad that you might have thought of
before then the different inversions
have to do with you can think of them as
o and P but specifically for the
augmented Triad there's another um
letter that comes into play
let's get the sound of the augmented
Triad into our
[Music]
ears what's a way that we can do let's
say a first
inversion of
this augmented
Triad yeah uh actually no just calling
out somebody go uh I I let's see yes
because we can
invert around this this point and what
are the two intervals from here to here
the same they the they are the same um
uh yes but what what are
they go major major third
and and major third because you already
said the same good sorry sometimes I I
for I forget that was prefaced with
something that we that required me to
use the C operator to um to map major
third to Major third major third right
good so it can be inversion there's
another way you can think of it yeah
Jason position transposition so if we go
up what do we have to go up a major
third so C goes up to e e goes up a
major third
to um
to g d g sharp and then G Shar goes up a
major third
to C C first it goes up a major third to
B
sharp and then what other operate what
other letter are we thinking of s s
spelling so that the the uh what do you
call it the E BP goes to C natural you
can think of all of these different
letters and different equivalence
classes as quite often depending on your
context different ways of getting to the
same answer um the hard part on the
problem set though is sometimes figuring
out if you're giv given multiple um if
you're given multiple of these letters
together you're saying that you have the
um o and P set um can you apply o and
then p and is that the same as applying
p and then
o sometimes it will be sometimes it or
some of these combinations of letters
the order won't matter and some of the
combinations of letters will open up new
possibilities that
chaining one and then the other will um
will not be sufficient for
anybody far enough on the pet to
encounter any of
those some of you have some people have
turned them
in do you remember any of the ones that
were like that
um like years ago um yeah I think
like octave permutation didn't matter
octave and permutation didn't matter
which one you did I think
that's I think that's correct yeah yep
see I I I should be thinking there's how
many combinations of there's what do you
what do you call it there's uh n Cho
five choose two right there's or five
factorial combinations but um or just
two no two to the 5ifth combinations uh
with optic but um some of a lot of them
them are never used you would never use
I don't know
um card what's something you wouldn't
use inversion without permutation quite
often or something like that yeah great
or inversion and permutation without
octave equivalence or something
fantastic I want to introduce you to um
another friend we're going to have more
as class goes on these little uh one to
two minute guest speakers and here is
somebody who
uh went through this class like
you hi I'm Sophia and I work with Mike
with music 21 in like 2016 2017 we wrote
this paper called emotion
planning called emotion painting lyric
affect musical relationship in a large
scale Lei Corpus and then idea is
there's this concept called word
painting in classical music where the
music sort of reflects what the lyrics
says so rise you will sing like rise or
fall you will sing fall and then we want
to see how prevalent that is in say folk
or popular music we had this Corpus of
around 1900 songs of folk music or
popular music and then we're able to
analyze it with music 21 what we did is
we used the natural language toolkit and
analyzed the emotion conveyed by the
lyrics and then looked at the
corresponding notes in the music um we
found a bunch of interesting things like
more emotive words that convey an
emotion are more likely to fall on
strong beat strengths like the first
beat or like the third beat on beat
whereas uh words that doesn't convey of
emotion like is and um will fall on
weaker beat strengthes and also
interesting things like words with
strong negative emotions like anger
disgust or fear tend to fall on shorter
notes
and that's what we
did so we're going to be moving on to
the concept of um Corpus and corpora um
it's a little bit and so what do we do
and statistics because the only reason
to look at a huge number of pieces is to
come up with some kind of statistical um
sort of summary or extraction or to find
things that are outliers within it and
even if you're thinking you know oh yeah
or to do deep learning stuff and you
those who have taken artificial
intelligence and deep learning classes
you'll know that um at its heart these
are all just statistics right this is
all just a whole bunch of numbers that
are being trained and extracted from
things um the Corpus I was hoping for us
to work with today I haven't been able
to get it working well enough to not
crash and um on my system and that's my
U my bad for uh not having this up um um
but I want to point out to you we're
going to be talking about uh more it's a
collection of um I think uh
2000 um
encoded uh leads a art song songs that
are sung in concerts and things
primarily by um women and uh and and
black and other minority composers um
you'll see that there are some people in
here beIN who are don't fit in any of
those categories and that was in order
to have a comparison set in there
um I don't know I'll have to ask Mark
Gotham the great researcher who was
doing this I think also he had really
hoped to get 2,000 and had a certain day
and found that he already had some bin
lying around or something but it's a
really amazing uh Corpus and I hope that
we're going to be able to work with it
later in uh the year um today being
International women's day I thought that
would be a particularly good day to work
with it but last things don't often hit
um our deadlines and we can uh we can
jump back to that
later
uh the second one that we're going to be
working with and the reason why you have
your laptops out today uh that we're
going to be working with together in
class is um part of this uh Essen folk
um music data set um and it's we're
going to be looking at the an Irish folk
music Corpus uh there's a lot of Irish
FK folk music corpora online and we'll
be uh looking at that then just to sum
up then we'll be looking at probably the
most overlooked at Corpus of all time um
but the one that's um there's a lot of
written about it and that is Johan
Sebastian box uh Corrals um the ones
that you've already been working with a
couple of them we're going to see what
happens when we work with all of them
one of the things I'm going to be asking
you to look at is one uh over the next
by next class if you can um is to start
reading an article um by Brett Arden and
David hon uh which is as you can kind of
see from the uh from the quality of the
of the scans a little bit of an old
article I think it's about 20 years old
now but it was one of the first ones to
see what happens when you take musical
features and compare them to geographic
features so like looking at um a density
contour map of melodies wherea most
phrases end on the tonic we can see that
there's a huge change from here to here
in that's Denmark up here this is
Germany uh right where the Alps began
and so we can see how um how geographic
features might change um yeah might
might change how how music goes so um
I'm going to blank that for a second I'm
going to open up a Jupiter notebook and
we're also going to unlock a few things
along the way so so hoping that we'll um
get through some of these music 21
topics as we as we
go
so we'll start by um importing an artic
of something that we've already unlocked
from music 21 import
Corpus and we'll call IRL abbreviation
for Ireland Corpus parse um we'll be
safe SN Essen f
song SL IRL see how close I can get this
to me so I'm still looking at you
oops
this topic five
great so everybody give me a quick
thumbs up if we're at this place awesome
super
um okay um
one of the things you can do anything
that you get from the Corpus just in
case you ever need to um look at it oops
sorry have an old thing um is look at
where it is in um on your hard
drive okay now somebody can hack my hard
drive um and um and so on U what kind of
thing would you expect IRL to be what
kind of object
an INT who votes for INT no
float
string want to take
a you think it's string no you don't
think what what what usually are we
working with in music
21 stream great well kind of a stream do
we think is score score score would be
most logical right in this case we're
working this is our first time working
with something bigger than a score uh
something called an opus so a collection
of scores and so um what we can do is we
can look
at at how many scores are in here so
this is a pretty small Corpus but big
enough to start doing some um statistics
on so we can do
like IRL
docor z.
show
and good deterministic it's still the
same one that I thought it would be um
and see this one of the things you'll
find if you're really interested in um
in being efficient is instead of doing
um inte into z uh what do you call it
square bracket zero and most on music 21
scores once you've done all your fil uh
streams once you've done all your
filtering you can do first and last and
all they are is um o of one um or that
that they stop finding all the scores
once they found the first one so it's a
little bit if you're into um algorithmic
optimization it can sometimes be quite a
bit faster for very long notes Okay so
what I want to know is
um this is interesting it's in 3 four um
pick
up good it does some of the things that
we expect um uh tunel pieces from folk
era to do if you begin with um what is
it a dotted eighth a dotted quarter um
missing at the beginning or added to the
pickup measure at the beginning you
expect that at the very end you also
have that so that the pickup measure and
the ending measure um usually represent
one oh is everything okay yeah go ahead
you sure of course always glad
to
so do we get it that yeah the piece
looks a little bit different the piece
looks a little bit different on yours
um hugely terribly different like
now just just a little little bit
different okay
um yeah it's I mean depending on your
version uh here's here's what it looked
like a couple years ago so it's quite a
bit smaller back then and things but
okay um
so it's in
34 is that common for Irish folk
music what would you what do you think
who has who has heard Irish musicians
play in their life for Irish music not
very many uh keep your hand up if you're
also over 21 no just kidding um because
they do usually play uh one of the
places you can hear quite often uh Irish
folk musicians play in Boston is in pubs
and things but um so rest so of people
who have heard or people who think they
might know this or um what's what's a a
time signature that you think would be
common Adam two four two4 shy 68 68 John
68 Al or I was going to say 68 68 well
one of this is one of those cool
questions where where if you have the
same answer as somebody else who still
want to hear because that starts
building up consensus somebody give me a
time signature you you don't expect to
be the highest uh the most commonly used
time signature yeah Jason 74 74 good
good okay so we have some
hypothesis what we're going to do is try
to figure out what's the most commonly
used time signature uh in this Irish
folk thing and always start with a
hypothesis because the number of times
I've seen people go ahead and um publish
things that don't um where they don't
have a a hypothesis and then they don't
realize like oh uh I printed out the
measure number divided by the number of
notes not uh you know not the time
signature um and therefore you know 137
over 14,000 probably wasn't the most
common time signature so let's start um
this was a question that came up at some
point um uh can you use are anything in
the normal python Library unlocked in
this class yes so let's import the
counter who's has who's seen counter not
everybody okay some people some people
haven't counter is just it's a very cool
um little it's just a dictionary but um
it starts off at zero when something's
not there so you don't have to say uh
when you're adding things up you can
just uh you start from from that so you
can you can you can just start adding
one to things um so I kind of like that
so let say for song in the Irish
Corpus um we can do we're going want to
get the time signature so I want you to
song.
something oops pull that up a little bit
and fill out the rest or maybe song
Maybe we don't even need to dot
something I don't know song is probably
the next
thing and you we did put um IRL scores
first up there so you know you can test
this on
one let's let's say we're only get for
Simplicity sake we're only going to be
counting the first time signature in
each song and um
and that most of the songs in this
collection I think all of them are
monophonic so uh you're only going to
have one
part where are some words you're
typing um get element by class good get
element by class or get uh there's one
one little typle get
elements plural yeah so unfortunately
there isn't a get first element thing
great anybody else having other words
that you're typing that you'd like
everyone else to
know you're all unless I tell you
otherwise like the midterm or something
you're generally allowed to talk to
people around
you Joe what's word that you've typed um
just okay
cool yeah what's um I guess we can like
yeah use
meter. okay meter. typ yeah so you'll
probably want to import meter sorry uh
if I didn't do that you can import
anything that's unlocked always so from
music 21 import meter and what's the
word that you said
meter dot time signature that that one
might be helpful
anybody else have any words that you've
been
typing fine I'm I'm going to type a
Word my word is recurse anybody type
that
word
no or
flatten anybody type that word
I'm I'm only asking for this this line
so go I'm I'm just trying to figure out
has who has gotten a time signature out
okay so some some people have uh Vincent
what you what' you type to get your time
suggestion so recurse El okay good
recurse do get Elements by
class and
anybody help what's the next thing I'm
going to
type meter. time
signature great
um anything else that I should be typing
on
that is that is this correct will TS now
be a meter. time
signature okay let's let's try let's try
this on one song since I don't know if
we have this at all so we'll call we'll
go back to the IRL do scores. first and
um what do we what was that name of that
song A lady Fair we'll call it lady um
equals IRL s scores at first um now
we'll try this lady. recurse doget
Elements by class meter. time
signature who votes this is going to get
me a time signature
who votes
not okay not sure not sure but not a
time signature you had your hand up on
not a time signature good anybody else
Vanessa you look at your
function it's a what I it's a
get yeah something that will'll get
what oops do I not
have oh sorry yes that won't return
anything if I don't put the um if I
don't put these brackets uh right
because I was trying to do it on a
function
and or oh this comes up by the way um in
your in um uh what you in problem sets
sometimes in answers the order matters
right I hadn't run the music 21 import
meter yet um just just something to keep
in mind always make sure when you're
done when you think your problem set's
done hit restart and run all and see if
it gets to the end because you might
have been solving a problem along the
way and then have oh you know in order
to solve question two I imported
something from question three but then
it's not ready when I run it so yeah so
now that we have this what
is here something called a recursive
iterator so is not a time signature how
do I get the time
signature from this we have this
anybody Hannah can index zero index
zero perfect it's um kind of like what
we did here indexing zero on a iterator
over scores but now we have something
that's indexing over the time signature
so we should be able to do this with if
I remember my
parentheses I do get used to an IDE that
fills in my parentheses for me uh which
I'm not using and I can do index zero or
I can do
first um either one this is a particular
case where first will save you a lot of
time because you're pretty sure the time
signature should be at the beginning of
the score so once you hit one stop don't
go through the whole rest of the score
looking for more time signatures if you
only want the first one good so we have
the time
signature now what we can do is this is
something we haven't seen the ratio of a
time signature the three for something
is in its ratio string there's also a
numerator denominator but this is the
one that's pretty helpful um and then
meter
counter ratio which I be doing now if I
want to count
them plus equals one good and then at
the very end let's see our meter
counter so we have had hypotheses of 34
and 68 uh I put my money on
68 and oops what I
forget oh uh IRL that scores thank
you IRL scores because the first thing
there was a metadata
so what's our winner 3 four 34 our
runner up 44
44 and then then 68 at least 68 was on
those of us were 68 the 68 crew we we
did okay on there but yeah I might have
the difference between this being sung
music versus fiddle music I don't know
we can try uh some of the other things
in there by the way with with a counter
you can also do things like meter
counter. most common three most common
and see what they are in that
order
cool so that's one of the things we can
do with um with this
Corpus let's um let's jump over to the
bach Corpus for now uh for a little bit
are there questions about this I mean
that's just the tiniest little thing we
can figure out um all the think
questions that we had before with it oh
um here let's let's actually let's do
this um let's do with the type of
experiment that um that Sophia sun was
talking about uh with position on the
beat or whatever um let's look at where
notes with accidentals
up are they most
commonly so sort of in this little
passing position in the middle of the
bar or are they more often contradicting
right at the
downbeat
hypothesis who votes for accidentals
more in the middle of the
bar good seven eight and four on the
downbeat good uh who's not
participating that didn't addap one more
time at in the at the middle of the
bar or downbeat couple down good I don't
know what the answer to this is always
just be thinking about these these
things um so let's let's do the same
type of thing we can um we'll create
another counter and we'll we'll unlock
another little thing for you um so we'll
call this what
uh
accidental we're not counting
accidentals so maybe just accidental
positions and but maybe we don't even
want to do a counter maybe let's just do
a a list so so we can run averages on
it um now we be fair to compare um well
I don't know uh where in the measure it
is maybe we want to just say we'll just
look at the 21341 so that all of our
measures are the same length except for
um hopefully the pickup measure and the
end measure are rounding errors but
maybe not you know you know because they
don't have the same length so what we
can do
is again copy and paste probably if
we're doing this more we can get this
and
instead we want to get look at every
note so there's something called uh
notes on
this or actually actually we'll we'll do
it even better we haven't imported note
yet right from music 21
import
note um because of a bad decision I made
a while back um notes also will get you
chords if there are any chords in here
and chords we will get to soon they have
to be dealt with separately so we want
to say. recourse. get Elements by class
note. note but there's another way to do
that anyone remember
what's the shortcut for recurse get
Elements by
class yeah go ahead yeah you use like
the bracket the class good so we'll put
the bracket for n in
song note. note so that will get us
every note there and how do we filter
out ones with ACD without
accidentals so try that yourself try to
figure out pretty sure that this this is
right for now yep we got a whole bunch
of notes we want to filter out once
without
accidentals oh why do we have a five
space thing that bothers
me filter out no
accidentals we're going to have some
we might not get to the buck example
because I came up with this one and it's
a neat little twist I had forgotten
about go ahead interrupt the class and
let's and ask ask that for everybody in
a loud voice what of people think about
um accidentals and the qy signature are
we counting those as accidentals no no
no okay good so we're going to have to
do some that was the wrinkle that I
thought of one of the ways you could do
is you could say oh shoot okay we're
just going to look at uh ones with in
with with C major so we can do it but
presumably sometimes you can filter down
your Corpus to get rid of some Corner
cases that might be a little bit too
hard to to deal with at least in the
first run but getting rid of everything
but C major is probably not going to
leave us with enough of a corpus
so let's temporarily
unlock a second module from music 21
import
key and first let's get the first key
signature for each um thing so we can
do uh what do how do we get the first
key signature in the piece let's assume
that for now that it doesn't switch key
signatures song. recurse
parentheses song. recurse parenthesis.
get
Elements by class or what's the simpler
way square bracket square bracket key
dot I'll tell you it's key
signature do
first so first let's filter out
everything that um so now let me let me
make a little instruction man I wish I
could edit at this part so let's let's
go back always work through one score so
we have the lady score and we'll get KS
equals lady uh was it my lady Fair um
lady key I didn't I didn't import key
yet from music
21 let's pause for a little bit and help
help me help get me get caught up and so
that anybody watching this later can get
CAU can you all come with me for a
second and I
for a
second thanks um Can can somebody tell
me what I should be putting here what um
I think we're mostly at about this line
together so uh who have I not heard from
very
much
Angelica okay so M doesn't work but I
tried to like say if the if end. pitch
accidental and if the KE signature docid
uh and then and name and sorry and um
ks. accidental
bystep n.
name good that's a pretty good start uh
I might change one thing on it anybody
else anyone have a suggestion of one
thing to change on
that so we're looking to see there is an
accidental and there is an accidental
yeah oh change name to step change name
to step so the difference between name
and step accidental by step expects a
step
C's name is c c step is start it
out nobody knows total mystery C good
step I know you knew that but just we'll
keep keep that going good so so what's
the this logic if the note pitch has an
accidental and there is an accidental
there then what um anybody feel
confident that they can code the next
line of this even if you didn't have
this then or or even just logically what
do we have what do we want to do
now if they're the same uhuh we don't
add one okay if they're the same we
don't add one good uh if n. pitch.
accidental and
equals ks. accidental by
step and do
step uh what is it something plus equals
zero we won't do anything no we can pass
um since we want to do something at this
point what how can we flip
those how can we flip it so we can add
this don't worry we'll we we'll improve
um some of the redund see in a
second if it's like this we don't want
to do anything if it's not like this
what do we want to do add one so how can
we how can we save ourselves I suppose
we can put else something plus equals
one
but I can do a a not not equal if these
are not equal
equal then we can do that so that could
work what's another another thing I can
um probably save
some save some
redundancy let's store these things at
ACC equals n. pitch.
accidental K uh
ksx
equals this when you find yourself
writing something twice in two Lin
you will probably continue to write
it and so we can do this we might even
be able to reduce this further because
python will allow you to um compare none
not equal to something else
but good does that cover all the cases
we have an accidental
we have the um axol in the key and by
the way that was great thank you for
getting us going on the right path um
and we have something that's uh and we
have a key signature accidental and so
we have an accidental on the note we
have a key signature accidental and the
two are not equal to each other so
therefore we we're going to add one to
something we'll figure out what we're
going to add something but we care about
that note right any other notes we care
about yeah what about notes where the
key signature has them sharped or
flatted but then we natural them okay
good good and the problem with the
natural is
what technically it's not an accidental
technically it's not an
accidental this is a thing that I did to
speed up so that there would be one
fewer object creation back in 2004 2005
when object creation was still something
that was slow in Python do I regret not
putting an accidental of natural on
every single note now yes I do regret
that here's a a trick that uh I've
started to do a lot since I don't really
care we'll import pitch for a
second music 21
import pitch and we'll just make one um
g u natural and I'll put it in all caps
because that means to me that I'm going
to try as much as possible never to
mutate this
so one of the things we could do now
is since none returns falsy so therefore
we continue in the or we can say The
Accidental is this one or natural and
this one is or
natural now we are always comparing
apples to or Apples to
Apples so this is just a little
programming trick and um in case you
really care about the runtime I only had
to create one extra accidental object I
think that should
work I see some confusing
yeah why can't we just have the equal
sign there's
object not compare sorry can you say a
little bit louder both for me and others
yeah like uh once we have The Accidental
and signature yep um why do we need to
have the or natural like if we're
comparing the not equals in the next
line will that not work with uh yeah so
so for what one of the reasons might be
um yeah it's true we probably
don't wait no no then then we get to
Matthew's case what what case does this
not
cover I don't see a case that this
doesn't
cover great um
so here's the case that doesn't cover um
KS again is our D major thing
accidental by step of
G is none right um n equals note. note
gsh gar 4 great next n equals note. note
G4 when I generate this it's going to
get an accidental because it needs uh
something so you're going to end up with
n do next. pitch.
accidental um oops pitch. accidental
equals pitch.
accidental natural because it will
actually have a natural sign and
then
then then this line up here next
n. pitch. accidental
tool does it equal KS accidental by step
G oops what I forget didn't I import
pitch or did
I I never ran
that I typed that but I forgot to run it
false because this is a natural an
explicit accidental of natural and this
is a none
not a none like the ones that where the
habits and go around but n o n e so
that's that's the particular case now
one of the things we never talked about
is do pitch how do accidentals compare
first we want to make sure does one
accidental flat equals
another
accidental
flat yes they do
so that's that's the reason why I put in
these um or uh where' they go or
natural so that I'm always comparing
Apples to Apples great idea yeah
duse how the example didn't we want it
to be false didn't we want it to be
false like in in the extra thing you
just wrote in the extra
thing yeah
that right
we want this one to be false because
we're in we're in D Major right G's um
accidental on G is none right so this is
none and this is a natural but the note
is still going to be a g natural it's
just one of them is represented with no
accidental and the other is represented
with The Accidental of
natural so oh you're saying having the
natural
sign so by putting the
natural so I've defined this now um ACC
equals next ends pitch. accidental or
natural what's ACC now it's a natural um
KS key signature is accidental equals KS
accidental by step
G or
natural KS accidental is now also a
natural ACC equals KS accidental is now
true the notion that um that you don't
care about the difference between a g
that has no accidental and a g that has
an accidental of natural right in this
case we do
not so
um does that does that start to clarify
things okay here here's some here some
notes let's let's always go back to
actual music that's how this that's
that's why we're confused we haven't
looked at some actual music in a little
while so we're in D Major here we have
two sharps uh Let's ignore the time
signature for now and now we have um
something like
how many how many notes Here contradict
the K the um key
signature if we look at this one one
which one dot dot that g
Shar but this hasn't what is the The
Accidental on this note is
probably
none The Accidental on this note is
almost certainly
natural and the key signatures give me
another color the
chos
of would go right here The Accidental by
step for
G is
none so in this case these two would
compare
equal but these two would
not not a very good instructor of
software engineering today sorry about
that but I'll try to get better any
other questions again we have about four
or five minutes I'd love to um try to
get a little bit further in this so I'm
going to jump back oh we have something
I never did let's just let's just make
it um in interest of time we'll we'll
say We'll create a counter and just keep
track of downbeat versus non-d downbeat
um so what we'll say
is if the accidental is not the same as
the key signature accidental then we
want then it's an interesting note so
then we want to know if it's on the
downbeat or off the downbeat what what
do y all use to figure out if something
was on the
downbeat what' you say off offset right
so if the note
offset and here is where recurse and
flat are going to be very different
right because recurses offset is with
respect
to
what the measure the measure and flatten
offset is with respect
to
what the start the start of the score
yep start of the piece start score start
yep of of whatever it is so this one we
want this
here if the offset is in 1.0 we can say
accidental positions I'm going to do
that for I don't know
downbeat plus equals 1
else accidental did I somehow not type
properly there we go dental
positions
offbeat plus equals
1 oh the other thing um that we might
want to do is eventually normalize this
for how many notes are on the downbeat
versus how many notes are on the offbeat
you all know about normalization right
you want to figure out how much more
likely is it no but but I can look at
the time and see we're not going to be
able to do all that so
um yeah so
let's I think this might work I'm
so let's look at the accidental
positions and I'm only looking at 3 four
ones you might
be anybody get something like that
Hannah you had some
results oh I did it a little differ but
I had a completely different output yep
but what but did it's it's kind of great
when we have two different people doing
different way so you have a slightly
different output did you find that
something like this in your result or um
I took the average the average like
where it appears in the meure guess uhuh
so I guess the I got was like closer to
the down be I think you got it it was a
little bit closer to the down be great
actually no it's like closer to the
middle closer to the middle
fantastic I'll give you one um one
little thing as as we do it that might
be interesting going forward um when
have time to implement this but I will
be un locking this for you right now for
n in let's just look at lady note.
note print n and n's beat
strength we'll look at this a little bit
and this tells you um here do we have
the I think somewhere I have the score
again sorry I wish I could split this
here so the first D is on the downbeat
and then we're going to go up to F
natural and the D C natural and when we
look at this oops
later we can see we have the three
pickup notes and then we have something
on the downbeat and then we have a bunch
of offbeat things yep beat strength um
is just a really really hacky thing I
threw together in probably about the
same amount of time as this thing is
here that tries to measure as a number
between Epsilon and one there is no beat
strength of zero but um how strong the
position of the note within its measure
is I cannot believe how many times I've
seen it referenced in papers now I've
used it in papers and things like that
and I uh you know now the world knows uh
that this was this terrible hack that
could probably be done much much much
better as you will realize when you do
beat strengths on triplets and things
because you can kind of see I'm doing
something about the log two of the
proportion through the measure and
therefore triplets won't work as well or
anything so I think we do something
separate for 68 so it works but um this
could be used to give you a little bit
more of a sense of the kind of problem
that Sophia sun was talking about in the
video at the beginning of the class are
certain things happen more on strong
places versus others okay can you um can
you close what you're working on for
just a second and that's also the cue
that I'm going to let you go just so I
can have uh some eyes and things so what
your the next problem set you're working
on this one but just just don't pck up
for one second is going to be looking
trying to find yourself an interesting
Corpus um whether or not you decide to
end working on a corpus study at the end
of the semester or not it's probably
good to know that we do not want to just
continue working with the bach Corrals
and the Irish folk songs and the Chinese
folk songs these three data sets are
everywhere for the rest of our lives so
we want to have that out you're going to
be asked to do that and to write up what
you find about something and you're
going to be asked to do it in teams of
two your only um condition is that you
cannot be on a team with somebody that
you did the last group problem set with
so find somebody who was not in that
problem set and do that and I I wanted
to give you some extra time for that
great um it's a little bit more on the
Sophia sun and my article online that
you can watch today or in the canvas or
later and thank you