I was in high school, I think I was a
sophomore in high school,
they bring in these consoles,
they were the TI-99s that you could
connect to a television
and they had a keyboard and
there was a program called BASIC and
that's where I programmed
my first solution of the
quadratic equation and
it just blew my mind.
So what was typical is that Argentina had
a very, very strong
public education system
going all the way from actually
pre-school, which is where
I met my wife, all the way
to finishing college
The engineering program was six years.
So I have 21 years of public free
education, it was a very
strong focus on educating yourself.
During the dictatorship it was tough, it
was assumed that if
you were Jewish you were
communist, which you know couldn't be
further from the truth in case of my
father, but you know we
would get calls at 3am in the morning
saying nasty things,
intimidation, that sort of thing.
Then we had democracy, it was great.
I studied civil engineering there and I
met my mentor Eduardo
Dvorkin, who is actually a PhD
from MIT. He's the one who inspired me to
pursue graduate studies
in the US. You know for me
what he had done and this world that he
was opening to me was
like a fantasy, I mean it was
like unreal. You know I had finished my
PhD at Caltech and I
started interviewing for jobs.
The day I said that I got an interview at
MIT, the butcher in my town
knew that I was going to MIT
to interview for a job position, everyone-
day. But there is no doubt
that the US is so special
and a place like MIT is so special. It
was very unique in
terms of opportunities.
Someone like me with my broken accent, at
some point I ended up in congress
talking to a bunch of senators about
military helmets and how they were safe
to protect against blast injuries. I got
US senators listening
to me, okay. And there is
a sort of excitement associated with it.
Then you feel that you don't
just work on things you like,
that you know you get the opportunity and
the privilege to work on
the kinds of things that
you like to do and they pay you for it.
You can make a living out of it. It's
that somebody cares.
You have something to contribute, this
country will gladly take
and value it and value you.
We are never satisfied with how we do
things. We're always revisiting what we
do. In my department,
every 10 years there is a new exercise to
revisit everything we do, from education,
you know, not take ourselves for granted.
I think that's very important.
What I respect the most about this
community right is their
commitment to excellence,
academic excellence, scholarly
excellence. But you know
this is a sort of excitement
that this place breathes
and makes it so interesting.