all right uh let's get into it um last
lecture of material before the quiz so
let's make sure we make the most of it
today we're talking about
recurrences uh recurrence is a fancy
word for saying sequence described by
induction uh so it's a sequence
um
defined
inductively and we've seen multiple
examples a great example is the
Fibonacci numbers um are there two B's
uh
Fibonacci let's pretend I spelled that
right no it's two B's and one n isn't
it are there two C's I don't know no
one's no one's helping me um doesn't
matter um defined by F0 is z
fub1 is 1 and the important part is that
FN is defined as FN minus1 plus FN minus
2 when n is at least two and this is the
part where we're describing the sequence
inductively once you know the first two
terms the next term is the sum of those
so F2 is 0 + 1 is 2 F3 is 1 + 2 is 3
then 2 + 3 is 5 3 + 5 is 8 then 13 21 34
and so on um it's just a sequence
defined inductor L that's the idea of a
recurrence and these show up all the
time when analyzing algorithms for many
of the same reasons that summations show
up when analyzing algorithms and we need
a lot of the same things out of them if
we end up with a an algorithm whose
runtime we can describe as the Fibonacci
numbers or as a similar
recurrence well that's not as useful as
it could be um a closed form would be a
lot more more helpful right um if we
could have it uh if we could find it and
indeed Fibonacci numbers do have a
closed form the nth Fibonacci number is
1/ sarek 5
Time 1 + < TK 5 / 2 to the N - 1 - < TK
5/ 22 to the
n and there's a closed form you just
take two exponentials um subtract them
divide by root 5 and you get the nth
Fibonacci number
exactly I think this is a really cool
formula also non VI how how do we
possibly go from this to that um well we
have some techniques that might work
sometimes and um other times we won't um
but certainly once we know this formula
if if we believe this formula or want to
check whether it's true now that we know
the formula we can just try the
induction and see if the induction works
out um in this case it will work out and
then you'll not only know that this is
the right formula but you'll have a
proof for it so just like with
summations if you know a closed
form um then usually it's easy to prove
it by induction so finding the closed
form is the hard part proving it is the
easy part so this guess and
check guess and
check technique that we used for sums
works just as well for
recurrences all
right um now recurrences very often show
up um especially when analyzing
recursive algorithms so let's talk about
recursive algorithms uh and show some
examples so let's start with a very
Classic Fun example called The Towers of
Hanoi so this this comes with its own
myth um it was described by Edward lucah
in
1883 he said there was a temple in anoi
that has three large pillars um I have I
have some helpers today acting as my
pillars we've got Ptown wire and
tooro um and on the leftmost pillar are
64 golden discs stacked on top of each
other getting bigger as you go down uh
and the monks there are moving the discs
around one at a time um but according to
a couple rules you're only allowed to
move one disc at a time from the top to
some other Peg and you're never allowed
to put a big box on top of a small I
mean big Golden Disc on top of a small
Golden
Disc um those are the rules one one peg
at a time so I can't pick these both up
and move them elsewhere um and always
small on top of big never the
opposite the
goal is if all the discs start over here
on the left Peg we want to get them all
to a different Peg we want to move them
all to the right Peg um by moving one
disc at a
time so let me write that down
quickly so we have let's say n
diss on left
Peg we have two other
pegs and we're going to
move one at a
time um always
keeping uh
smaller
discs on top of bigger
ones
goal all
discs on the right
Peg and as the myth goes when the monks
finish when they get all 64 discs over
to the the other
Peg the universe ends I don't know why
that's that's just the story maybe
there's a um a weight sensitive um
detonation switch over there and you
have to get all that weight on there and
then then the universe blows up it's a
myth you don't need actual answers here
um but that's the game uh and the
question is how many moves will it take
is it even possible how long does the
universe have to live do we have a year
do we have a a century um let's see if
we can figure it out let's see if we can
find an algorithm to get all of the the
discs from one side to the other are we
clear on the
game nice let's start small I always
recommend starting
small what happens if we have just one
disc and we need to move it from Ptown
to tooro how are we going to do
that is that a
hand so how how do I move a disc from
here to here according to the rules of
the game
yes you just do it yeah we're allowed to
move one disc at a time and there aren't
any bigger or smaller discs to get in
the way so you just do it in this case
um so if we're trying to move um just
dis number one from let's say Peg a to
Peg C we'll call them the pegs
ABC well you do it just by doing it you
move you move a disc uh you move dis one
from a to c great okay
um what if we have two
discs here we go how am I going to get
both of these from there to there who
can help me out yes
please small one in the middle second
one goes over here small one on the big
one absolutely perfect so if we're
trying to move discs one and two
the two smallest discs again from Peg a
to Peg c um as your colleague pointed
out um let's move first let's move dis
one from A to B then we'll move dis 2
from a to c then we'll move dis one from
B to C just as we acted out over here
next case three
boxes now
this there we go um this might take a
little little bit of planning ahead um
and the thing to remember is that at
some point we want to be able to make
this move where we take the biggest box
from the left to the right and so to do
that we need the other boxes here in the
middle so somewhere along the way we're
going to need to go from here to here of
course that's not a valid move we can't
move two boxes at once who can help me
out how are we going to do this first
part of the algorithm please
small box to the
middle we're trying to move move these
two to the
middle so here to here is our
goal small box to the
right medium box to the middle small box
on top of it perfect does that look
familiar to
anyone that's kind of exactly what we
just described for moving boxes One and
Two from one peg to another instead of
moving from the left Peg to the right
Peg we're moving from the left Peg to
the middle Peg but that's the only thing
that's changing we can use the same
algorithm to move these two boxes from
here to here in three moves now we can
do this and now we can do the same
algorithm again to move these two boxes
from here to here and if we think about
what that algorithm says it says one
2 3
let's write that one down as
well so if our goal is to
move the interval 1 through three so
boxes 1 two and three from Peg a to Peg
C well then the first thing we're going
to do is move boxes one and two from A
to
B then we're going to move box three on
its own from a to c then boxes one and
two from B to C and here when I'm saying
move two boxes at a time from one peg to
another I'm really invoking this
strategy we already know how to do it
with two boxes so let's use that as the
first part of our algorithm then make
one move then use that again does that
make
sense let's do one more example
together
okay great we have four discs we need to
move them from the left to the right um
and we're going to follow hey everyone
we're going to follow the same idea um
somewhere along the way we're going to
need to get to this
position to this
position so that we can move the bigger
box over
here and then we're going to need to
again move these three boxes together
somehow with some sequence of moves to
finish the job
and I claim we have all the tools we
need to do exactly that so step
one in fact let's write this down
first if we're trying to
move the interval from one to four so
boxes 1 2 3 and
four from a to c let's follow the same
strategy here let's put the the top
three
boxes let's move those from A to B
somehow
then we'll move box four on its own from
a to
c then we'll move boxes 1 through three
from B to
C and here where I'm saying move three
boxes from one peg to another we have an
algorithm for that it's this
algorithm yeah so let's let's see what
this looks like in practice so first
things first we're trying to move these
top three boxes from here to here um
well we have a to do that that's 1 2 3
5 six seven if we follow the algorithm
that's listed there those are the seven
moves it says to do and I want to point
out one important thing we put this one
over here back when we were just working
with three boxes we were assuming that
all of the pegs were empty that there
was nothing else to worry about other
than those three boxes but now there's a
fourth box in in the way so can we
really run our algorithm for the top
three boxes even when there's a fourth
box and yeah we can thankfully because
the fourth box will always be underneath
the fourth box doesn't affect the
movement of one through three in fact
any larger boxes don't affect the
movement of boxes 1 through three so we
can use our algorithm for three boxes
and just temporarily ignore the fact
that there's a fourth box it doesn't
matter and that's how we were able to
get here
then we're going to do this and then
again we're going to follow our our
three box strategy to get these three
over to here so that looks like one 2 3
4 5
6 seven and we've done four
boxes yes
great question how are we able to claim
that this sequence of moves especially
with more and more boxes or discs is the
optimal algorithm we've we've started
describing an algorithm to do it but is
it the best uh that's a great question
um turns out it is the best um we're not
going to prove it right now but it's not
much harder than what we've already done
um the basic idea
is at some point you have to move the
smallest at the largest box so at some
point you have to get to either this
position or this position and that and
we know how many steps that takes
assuming we're doing some proof by
induction or something so we know we
have to spend some number of steps for
the um for n minus one boxes then we
have to make a move and then we have to
put these back on top which again
takes a land slide
so with a with an induction very similar
to that you can prove that in fact this
is the optimal
algorithm
um okay but how many moves does it take
let's see if we can figure that
out um so let's let um T of n be the
number of
moves with n
Diss and we we want to figure out T of n
um somehow so here T of one if we're
just moving one disc we make one move so
T of one is one t of
two well T of two is written here it's
one two three moves if we're moving two
discs we go one two
three uh three moves how about t of
three uh well it says do the two disk
algorithm so that's T of two
then do a single
move then do the two disk algorithm
again so that's plus T of2 again so
that's 3 + 1 + 3 is
7 likewise T of
four is well you do the three disk
algorithm that's T of
three we do one move then we do the
three dis algorithm again that's another
T of three so we're looking at two t of
3 + 1 which is 14 15
and now we've exactly described the
number of moves that this algorithm uh
takes and just to really be clear about
it if we're trying to move diss one
through n so n discs together uh from
Peg a to Peg
C we're going to first
move uh the first n minus one discs from
A to
B then we're going to move uh disk n on
its own from a to c
then um the remaining n minus one diss
from B to C exactly the same strategy
we've just we've just described um and
this is going to be our general strategy
to move n diss we do our n minus one dis
algorithm then a move then our n minus
one dis algorithm again so now we've
described an algorithm by
induction and secretly that's all
recursion is we're just
inducting um
but in general the number of moves we
take is well however many moves we
needed to take for the N minus one dis
algorithm + one plus TN minus one again
so it's 2 T of n
minus1 plus
one and this is our sequence this is our
recurrence and we're getting to the
place where these are in the way so
let's move
those success
okay we've described our algorithm we've
described its runtime but like I said
earlier closed form would be so much
nicer right um I want to know how long
the universe takes with 64 discs I don't
want to have to compute 64 terms of my
sequence so what does this look like
well let's
see um we have our our numbers 1 3 7 15
2 * that + 1 is 31 then 63 then
127 uh is anyone starting to see a
pattern uh
yes uh we have a
guess T of n is 2 to the N minus 1 this
looks suspiciously like 2 4 8 16 32 64
128 um and especially since we really
are doubling every time it seems likely
that it might be related to powers of
two somehow well the good thing about
having a guess is that we know what to
do with it we check it we try to use it
to prove this formula by induction and
if it works we have the right formula
turns out it
works you can prove it with a a pretty
straightforward induction um and turns
out this is indeed the correct formula
so this is a clear example of uh what we
said about guess and check if you can
guess the formula you check it with
induction but we had to recognize that
pattern to be able to have something to
check okay but finally we can answer our
question how long does the universe have
left um we it's 64 discs so two to T of
64 that's 2 the 64 minus one
steps let's assume these uh these monks
are really strong and they can move one
disc per
second um turns out if I flip to the
correct page in my notes
um that many seconds is about um a half
trillion
years Universe has got some time
left and I find it surprising that with
just 64 discs you can get all the way up
into the trillions of years uh that's
very quick
growth
um all right any questions about towers
of Hanoi
awesome I thought the camera in the back
was a hand for a second I apologize for
that um let's move on to our next
recursive
algorithm um I promised last time that
we would talk about sorting so let's
let's talk about sorting uh and before
we get to merge sort which is um the the
fast algorithm we're going to talk about
today let's talk about a simpler
algorithm called selection sort
um the problem is you have a
list of n
numbers um and you want to arrange
them in increasing
order so your list is in whatever order
it it's in and you want to figure out
the correct increasing order so put them
in sorted
order um and the idea for selection
sort um is a very simple
one find the
smallest pull it
out repeat until
done so let's see this in action and I
have some helpers today I'm going to
need a few more
volunteers um thankfully I brought some
nice all right so we have a bunch of
helper friends and we need
to somehow put them in sorted order uh
we're going by height
here um and for selection
sort um we said find the smallest well
clearly that's Ptown here um pull them
out and then repeat okay who's the
smallest left well that's going to be
wire who's the smallest left um well
it's maybe a little less clear but let's
talk more precisely about how we're
going to find the smallest every time
and we can do this with just a just a
bunch of comparisons so let's compare
the first two uh between Ralph and wire
who's
shorter Wire yeah okay so wire is the
smallest one we've seen so far between
wire and Ptown who's shorter P toown
between these two who's shorter still p
toown
still P toown still P toown still P
toown so we got through the end of the
list Ptown is the smallest one we've
seen so Ptown is our smallest softest
roundest
boy um and that is how we are going to
find the smallest we can do that with
just n minus one
comparisons we compared the first two
then whoever won that we compared to the
third then compared that to the fourth
then the fifth and so on so n minus one
comparisons
and then you pull them out and we're
going to do it again so now with n minus
two comparisons because we have one
fewer animal up front we're going to
find that wire is the smallest then
we're going to find I think it's bubs is
the smallest um then todoro then Ralph
then Coupe get out of here um then
butternut and now we have our sorted
list how many comparisons did we have to
do to implement
that well we've already said that we did
n - one comparisons in the first
round and then the second round we had n
min-2 comparisons the third round n
minus three
comparisons down to the last round where
we had just two animals left we need one
comparison to figure out who's shorter
and then the last one is just the last
one we don't need more comparisons for
that um and we've seen this sum before
this is n minus1 * n divided by two
comparisons so this is um n^2 over two
plus change comparisons for selection
sort this is not the fast sort that was
promised this is still quadratic
runtime um it is the easiest thing like
when you have a small number of things
in front of you and you just sorry for
calling you things small number of
animals in front of you uh and you just
want to sort them like it's very easy to
just scan through find the smallest find
the smallest that's what I do by hand
but for big um for big lists for lots
and lots of numbers this is not the way
you want to
go but um a much better algorithm not
the only better algorithm but a much
better
algorithm is pretty similar to
this um and to talk about it first let's
talk about the idea of a
merch the idea is we have two sort of
lists A and
B and we
want um to combine them into a single
sorted
list um as an example um so maybe we
have these and you know that goes over
there
um there toor there we go so for example
if we have this sorted list which is
already in increasing order and this
separate sorted list that's already in
increasing order let's try to combine
them into a single sorted list and let's
just do something like selection sort
let's find the smallest and just keep
finding the smallest until we have our
answer so who's the smallest between
these two lists where do we have to
look well I I saw I saw this was that
was that an
indication all right so the beginning of
here or the beginning of here yeah the
smallest on the table is either going to
be the smallest on this side or the
smallest on this side and we know where
the smallest is because the lists are
sorted the smallest on this side is wire
the smallest on this side is Ptown we
just have to look at the first from each
of these two sorted lists and with just
one comparison we know who the shortest
is overall still Ptown
um and then we can continue um first
over here compared to the first over
here wire versus bubs I think I think
wire is smaller um now it's bubs versus
todoro um and I think bubs is smaller
this time now it's Coupe versus tooro
tooro uh Coupe versus
Ralph Ralph is
shorter um and now we get to an
interesting point where there is no
first over here anymore the side of the
table is empty um well that just means
that we're done we know this side is
already sorted and bigger than
everything else we've seen so we don't
have to do any more comparisons we just
pull them back and we're done so that's
the idea of merging two sorted lists the
algorithm says we
compare smallest in each
list um
pull out the
smallest
continue until one list
becomes
empty and we put the other
list at the
end right so we got it down to where
this list was empty this list had two
animals left um and we didn't have to do
any more work we just
we're just done with those is this
algorithm clear does it make sense why
it
works how many comparisons does it
take well each round every time we
identify um the next smallest animal
we're doing a single
comparison yeah in the worst case we're
going to have to do that for all of the
first n minus one
animals um like if it comes down to one
on the left versus one on the right then
everyone needed a comparison we only got
one freebie at the
end so worst
case um this takes less than or equal to
size of a plus size of B minus one
comparisons sound
good awesome so now that we have this
merge algorithm let's talk about merge
source
so you're given a
list with n
elements uh and we want to sort
it um this list doesn't have any
promises it it's not like half sorted or
anything like that it's just some random
list of random data we want to put it in
sorted order um and by the way let's
assume for
now that n is a power of two so we can
just keep cutting in half uh and
everything works out nicely we'll remove
that assumption later but for now we'll
just solve this for lists whose lengths
are powers of
two uh so uh the first step we are going
to sort the first and oh sorry I forgot
an important
step if n equals 1
done if you're sorting a list with just
a single element there's nothing to do
your list is already sorted so we'll
call it done otherwise we're going to
sort the first n/2
elements somehow we'll we'll get them
sorted then we will
sort the
last n /2
elements
somehow and then you merge them together
so as long as we're somehow able to sort
the first half and somehow able to sort
the second half the merge step will take
care of the
rest does this strategy make
sense cool and you might ask well how
are we going to sort the first the first
half and the last half maybe we'll use
selection sort turns out if you do that
you're still going to get quadratic
runtime that's not not the best
plan um the strategy I'm going to
propose and the way that merge sort is
described
we're going to sort the first n/2
elements using merge
sort and we're going to sort the last
two last n/2 elements
using merge
sort okay I claim I have written an
algorithm here though it might not be
obvious recursion in general is one of
those bogeyman topics it's seen is like
the bane of all computer science
students um woe unto me the end is nigh
it's the hardest hardest ever uh topic
uh and I am here to tell you it's not
some new complicated scary topic it's an
old scary top no it's an old familiar
topic um it's just induction I claim
everything we're doing here is just
going to be induction and let's talk
about what we mean by that um so let's
run through merge sword and see what it
looks like so we have our scrambled
list um which is a power of
two
which is not a power of
two which is a power of two
oops um all right last helper for the
day thank you
Charlie um now let's scramble this up
and see if we can sort them together so
here's Butternut over here
all
right so let's run through our algorithm
and see what it tells us to do so merge
sort on eight
elements so we're calling merge sort on
eight elements I'm I'm going to
abbreviate over here just to keep track
of where we are um and it says the first
thing to do is merge sort the first four
elements then merge sort the last four
elements then merge them together
so we're going to merge sort 1 through
4 and then we're going to merge sort 5
through 8 and then we're going to
merge right that's what the algorithm
tells us to do so it tells
us take these
four I did not do a good job scrambling
these did I let's let's do a little
more
um okay we'll pretend we did that um so
it tells us to merge sort the first four
elements then merge sort the last four
elements then merge them together okay
well here we're merge sorting the first
four
elements what does our algorithm tell us
to do when we're merge sorting four
elements well it
says merge sort elements one through two
then merge sort elements 3 through four
then merge them
together yeah I'm just reading the code
here and that's what it tells me to do
when I call merge sort on these four
elements so it tells me to call merge
sort on these two then call merge sort
on these two then merge these together
into a single list a single sorted list
of four elements yeah okay well what
does merge sort with two elements
mean okay um sort the first one element
sort the next one element then merge
merge sort on two
elements well sorting one and one on
their own there's nothing to do a sort a
list with one element is already sorted
so all I have to do is the merge merge
this list with that list and who's who's
shorter Ptown than bubs okay now this
list is sorted merge sort on these two
elements next um here's our you're kind
of heavy um this one over here this one
over here we get to do our merge so
who's shorter it's Coupe then it's
Charlie
so where are we again we've done this
and this now we have to merge them I'm
just following what the code says to do
um we have to merge this list with this
list okay between these two who's
shorter Ptown between these two who's
shorter bubs now one list is empty so
the other list just Falls in place and
now we have successfully called merge
sort on these four
elements let's do the same on the other
side
so split into two and
two no better not um split into one and
one merge them together toor Row
first split into one and one then merge
them back together wire then Ralph now
we have two versus two that were merging
we have wire versus todoro that's wire
we have todoro versus Ralph that's
todoro oops there we go then Ralph
versus Butternut Ralph then butternut
and now we have sorted these next four
elements as
well and the last thing we're supposed
to do is merge these four with those
four okay we've got these two it's this
we've got these two it's this these two
I think it's bubs these two todoro these
two what was it again I think it's Ralph
then these two is Coupe then
Butternut then
Charlie and so we just ran through merge
sort on these eight elements just by
following this code and it kind of
worked right we we got our answer in the
end and it worked but how can we be
confident that it's going to
work more than that how can we be
confident that we've even described an
algorithm because like how can we
describe the merge sort
algorithm using merge sort before we
finish describing merge
sort how can we know that this recursive
call to merge sort correctly sorts our
list before we've proven that merge sort
correctly sorts your lists this this is
the kind of circular thinking that makes
recursion hard to think
about but
thankfully we don't have to think about
it in that way we can think about it as
just induction we're inducting on the
size of the list that we're
sorting merge sort on one
element we know what it does and We Know
It Works it does nothing and it's
correct if there if we're sorting one
element we're good we're good merge sort
on two
elements um says we we're just doing
that one comparison like we saw this
also works merge sort on four
elements to describe merge sword on four
elements we call merge sort with two
elements then merge sort with two
elements then merge them together but by
the time we're here we already know what
it means to merge sort two elements and
we know that it does the job
correctly so these recursive
calls don't think of them as calling
back to merge sort which we haven't
finished describing yet think of them as
calling a previous incarnation of merge
sort we're calling a smaller size which
we've already constructed because we're
building them up inductively starting
from the smaller sizes and working
bigger so we know that merge sort 2
exists and is correct and we use that to
prove that merge sort 4 exists and is
correct we use that to prove that merge
sort
8 which is using merge sort 4 both its
description and its
correctness to make sure that merge sort
8 works and is
correct once we have once we know how to
merge sort eight elements we can use
that to know how to merge sort 16
elements we can use that to merge sort
32 elements so all this circular
reasoning we can break that cycle by
remembering that the recursive calls are
actually your inductive
hypothesis we're allowed to assume that
that it works for eight elements when
we're constructing and proving it for 16
elements and so on and so forth does
that idea make
sense
awesome all right um it can be helpful
to see it all at once and not with with
cute fuzzy helper friends uh so here's a
a quick animation that's just running
through the whole algorithm um and every
time has an unsorted list it's breaking
it into two halves and then by the time
they come back sorted it's doing the
merge uh so we're about to merge 5 seven
with one two looks like one is smaller
than five then two then five and seven
have no friends so they go back in um
now we're going to call merge sword on
the right half um here we're merging one
and one to get two um now we're
splitting and now we're merging back uh
0 and six now let's merge 34 with 06
looks like 01 then three then four is
the winner and then six and finally we
merge the two sorted Hales with our
familiar merge algorithm again uh next
three beats five four beats five five
beats
six then six then seven uh and that is a
quick view of merge sort with just eight
elements are there any questions on how
this algorithm
works all right still restricting to
just powers of two for now
um well how long does it take we have an
algorithm I want a
runtime uh and just like before we can
describe our runtime with a
recurrence um let's say let's call it
like M of n which is this is the um an
upper
bound on the number of
comparisons when merge sord
n
elements and we're trying to figure out
M of n for now just when N is a power of
two um and we have our algorithm it's up
here um the runtime for M of n well
we're calling the algorithm for n /2 and
we're calling it twice so 2 * m of N
/2 and then we're merging n/2 elements
with n/2 elements and that merge takes
at
most nus one more
comparisons and so M which is described
by this recurrence is an upper bound on
the number of comparisons we'll need
does this make sense how we were able to
translate this recursive algorithm into
this
recurrence um for a bound on the runtime
this isn't the exact runtime because
like we said um merge sometimes takes
fewer
comparisons um if one of the lists is
entirely smaller than the other lists
then you only need n over two
comparisons and then the other list
falls into place for free so it's going
to be somewhere between n/2 comparisons
and N minus one comparisons worst case
it's going to be n minus one and since
we're looking for an upper bound here
we'll call it n minus one okay well we
have a recurrence um we can compute some
terms and aim for a closed form see if
we can get an answer there uh and let me
write down some terms for us here's n uh
here's selection sort uh and here's
merge sort just for
comparison uh n is 1 2 4 8 16 and
32 that should be enough to find a
pattern right so for selection sort that
was the slow quadratic one um we had
zero 1 6 uh 28 120 and
496 and we already know the formula for
this that's uh n^2 - n /
2 uh for merge sort we get 0 1
17 49
129 and we don't know this formula yet
gratifying to see that it's smaller than
selection sort so this looks like an
improvement on our algorithm uh can
everyone see or is Charlie in the way
sorry about
this but looking at that I I don't
really see the pattern I can't think of
a formula that gets me those numbers
just by staring at them which brings us
to our other technique for trying to
find a closed form when we don't know
one yet um just like with sums we had
the perturbation method um when we were
trying to figure out a closed form well
here with
recurrences uh we have what we call plug
and
chug not to be confused with guess and
check whoever named these I don't like
them the names not the people they're
fine I assume um we have the plug and
chug technique which looks like the
following so roughly speaking um
substitute the
recurrence into itself so we get um
expanded and expanded versions of the
formula and look for a pattern in that
expansion let's see if we can do that
with merge
sort so we have M of n we know I'm going
to put the N minus one first this is n-1
+ 2 * m of n
/2 right that's just our our recurrence
exactly as it was um described before
but this m of n
/2 m still satisfies our recurrence so
let's apply this recurrence to n/2 and
replace this term with the recurrence
version of that so m / n is going to
equal nus1 + 2 *
n / 2 -1 + 2 * m of n
over4 so I applied our recurrence to the
input of n/2 and substituted that in
here are we clear on how I got from here
to here this is the key step um we can
expand this out a little bit um so this
is n minus one this is 2 * that is going
to be n minus 2 and then we have a 2 and
a 2 + 4 or M of n /
4 all right so we expanded it out one
step and now we have this recurrence
which still describes the same
sequence um and we can do it again let's
do it
again this is n -1 + N - 2 + 4 * all
right n over 4 -1 + 2 * m of n / 8
pretty sure I did that right we can
expand that out a little
bit uh so M of n is still equal to
nus1 plus nus 2 plus and now we have
four times this which is going to give
us n minus 4 plus there's a four and a
two we have 8 times M of n over
8 all
right and if we keep doing this we can
we can guess at the pattern we're going
to see when we expand this further and
further we can
guess that M of n is going to look like
nus1 plus nus 2 plus N - 4 + N -
plus N - 2 to the um T
-1 + 2 the T * M of n / 2
T if we expand this many times it looks
like we're going to end up with
this this was just me sort of guessing
at the formula we're going to get but
informed guessing by how this keeps
expanding
um and remember we're already assuming
that N is a power of two we're assuming
that n is 2 to the
K so what happens if we choose t =
k then M of
n would equal n -1 + N -
2 um plus N -
4 plus N - 2 to the
K-1 plus 2 the k m of n/ 2 the
K okay but 2 to the K is
n and n / 2 to the K is 1
so this term here is n * m of
yeah all right let me make sure I'm
still matching my
algebra and then from here we have we
have a sum to deal with um let's take a
look at all of these n terms how many
are there well it's 2 to the 0 up to 2
the K minus one so there should be K of
them
yes instead of
what 2 to the K so 2 to the K is n uh we
were assuming that N is a power of two
and K is that exponent um so um these
two are the same term good question so
let's see what we got how many n's did
we have we have K of
them this is K * n now let's deal with
these parts that are being
subtracted minus 1 + 2 + 4 + up to 2 the
kus1 and then this term here what was M
of one
again yeah I I see someone going like
this excellent zero yeah there's nothing
to do when when we have just one element
M of one is zero so that whole term in
fact disappears and we're just left with
this which has knen and a geometric
series
and we know formulas for geometric
series I'll spare us the the
details uh this is going to be equal
to um KN n minus 2 to the K minus
one and if we remember what K is K is
log 2 of n this is n * log 2 of n that's
this term and then this 2 to the K is
just n so minus n + one
is our
formula and we got that not by looking
at the numbers but by expanding out the
recurrence and looking for a pattern
there of course this is still just a
guess we didn't really explain why this
thing is true we would maybe want to
prove that by induction but easier
option once we have our actual guess
let's just prove this by induction once
we have our guess we can check it and
turns out this is the correct formula
there's your
check questions on that plug-and chug
method really useful method doesn't
always bear fruit um but often does and
it's a a nice tool to have in your back
pocket one bit of advice when using plug
and chug by the way is notice when I had
this n minus one and N minus 2 I didn't
combine them I could have written that
as 2 N minus 3 and then the next one
would have been what 3 n minus
7 um but it's maybe the pattern is less
clear if we did that I tried to keep
terms from the different levels of
recursion separate from each other so I
can keep track of what's coming from
each stage um so when you're doing plug
and trug try not to simplify everything
at the beginning uh it might help you
see the pattern more
readily all
right back to merge sort
finally what if n isn't a power of two
I claim the algorithm works pretty much
as described we don't really need to
change it all that much um at least we
don't have to change the idea just the
measurements uh so we're going
to sort the
first n /2 floor
elements we're going to
sort the last ceiling of n/2
elements and then merge them
together um excuse me so this notation
floor notation this means n/ two rounded
down to the nearest integer so if n was
11 we would be sorting the first five
elements and then sorting the last six
elements
and we again have two sorted lists now
with different sizes but that doesn't
matter merge doesn't care what size the
lists are we can merge them together and
this is our actual implementation of
merge sort no matter what the size
is uh and we can similarly bound its
runtime uh now M of n the run the number
of comparisons when merge sorting n
elements uh or at least an upper bound
on the number of
comparisons um well now we're
recursively calling floor of n/2 and
ceiling of N /2 and then still doing a
merge with n total elements um we can be
conservative and say the number of
comparisons is at most two
times the amount of comparisons it takes
to sort the bigger of the two
halves um if the other half is smaller
then presumably that's even fewer
comparisons um so this this recurrence
and then still
plus n minus1 for the merge at
most so this is a conservative
measurement of how many comparisons we
need in the worst case for n elements
are we okay with how we got
here
nice and now we could try the same thing
we could try to like plug and chug or
something or guess and check and see if
we can get a closed form for this
recurrence here I don't want
to um especially the the floors and SE
or the ceilings rather uh they kind of
get in the way they make it a lot harder
to do something like that um
thankfully we have yet another
tool um turns out algorithms like merge
sort um more generally what we'll call
divide and
conquer recurrences uh sorry
algorithms there are lots of divide and
conquer
algorithms um very similar to merge
merge sort that give runtime recurrences
very similar to merge sort um divide and
conquer means that usually whatever set
of data you have you're dividing it into
smaller groups there might be two there
might be multiple um you're recursively
calling your algorithm on each group
potentially possibly your groups overlap
so you need more recursive calls um and
then after you get information about
each of your subsets you somehow combine
them back together to get your answer
for the full list so merch sword is a
good example there um you'll see some
others in recitation and problem Set uh
for other divide and conquer algorithms
we're not so concerned with algorithm
design in this class um but tools that
will be used for Designing algorithms in
the future uh are very appropriate uh
and I'm I'm singling out divide and
conquer algorithms
because we have a really nice tool that
helps us analyze the runtime of divide
and conquer algorithms like this it's
called The Master
theorem
um it's called The Master theorem and it
looks like that uh it's a lot of text so
I didn't want to write it by hand um
what the heck is going on here well well
the point is the following suppose we
have a
recurrence uh so we'll call it a
divide and
conquer recurrence is going to be one
that looks like this it's going to be T
of
n equals some constant a Time T of the
ceiling of n /
B plus some function f of
n where
um a is let's see what are our
conditions a is at least one and B
is uh greater than one strictly greater
than
one and F of n is some function merge
sort certainly fits this a is 2 B is 2 F
of n is n minus
one and the master theorem says if you
have a divide and conquer recurrence
that looks like this if you check just a
a couple quick conditions on how quickly
F
grows I can use that to tell you a Theta
bound on T it's not giving me an exact
closed form it's giving me an ASM totic
bound it's going to say that t of
n um is in Theta
of something there are three cases where
the master theorem can tell you
explicitly T of n is Theta of this nice
simple
thing all right so that's the idea let's
not prove that right now but let's talk
about what the three cases mean and
where they come from uh and get some
intuition for the master
theorem okay and if we think about a
divide and conquer algorithm like this
it says well at the very top
up um we have n elements in our list um
and we're going to do some work with
recursive calls that's the a * T of
thing term but then we're going to do
some work with these n elements
themselves and that's F of n uh so we're
going to do F of n
work at this node and all the rest will
be done in sort of the children if we're
thinking about this as um the recursive
call stack C
tree um here's where we're dealing with
t of n here's where we're dealing with t
of n/
B and there are a different children in
merge sort we're splitting into two
halves we're making two recursive calls
uh in this example maybe there are three
recursive calls so a is
three uh and at each of these nodes we
are
calling F of n /
B right right and each of these is
making some recursive
calls each of these nodes uh is doing
work F of n over
b^2 then again F of n over B Cubed and
so on all the way down F
of n over B to the H however however
tall this tree
is um so each of these nodes is doing
this amount of work in itself and the
rest of the work is done
recursively how many nodes do we have at
each level well we have one node here a
nodes
here A Squared nodes
here a cubed nodes
here
um a to the H nodes here at the
bottom so we're getting more and more
sub problems but the sizes of those sub
problems are getting smaller and
smaller um to put this in context for
merge sort um at we called merge with n
elements at the very top we had two
cases where we called merge with n/ two
elements four times where we called
merge with n over four elements eight
times we called merge with n over eight
elements and so on and so on does this
idea make sense this is sort of a um a
conceptual view of all of the different
recursive calls in our device divide and
conquer
algorithm and this sum here FN * 1 plus
f n / B * a this time a squ this time a
cubed all the way down to the bottom
this is our
runtime I'm being sketchy here I'm not
dealing with the floors and ceilings
this is this is just intuition anyway um
so I'm I'm going to be a bit sloppy I
apologize in
advance um but this is conceptually our
runtime first of all how tall is this
tree what is this AG
well we're going down until well with
merge sort we're going all the way until
we get a single element we sort a single
element and that's our base case and
we're certainly not going beyond that um
well what does that say here that says n
and B to the H are equal to each
other in other words the height of the
tree is log B of
n all right and now we have the sum and
and this is our
runtime the master theorem says that
this sum often has three familiar forms
one of three familiar
forms um in the first case in case one
of the master theorem it says if FN is
Big O of this thing ignore what this
thing is if FN is Big O if FN is
small
so if F of n is
small imag imagine in the extreme case
FN is just one there's only a single
step to do at each of these
nodes well then our runtime looks like
um
1 plus a + a 2 plus a cubed
cubed plus a to the H if the fs are
insignificant compared to the
A's then our sum is basically
this um and this is a geometric series
which is basically as big as a to the H
itself up to constant factors lower
order terms we have a geometric series
formula for that but basically it's
saying if FN is
small then this last term dominates the
whole
sum right we have these two conflicting
effects where the fs are getting smaller
because the inputs are getting smaller
but the um the powers of a are getting
bigger and so case one is describing the
case where the A's grow faster than the
fs
shrink um and it turns out that in that
case the runtime is basically just a to
the H itself that t to the N is in Theta
of a to the
H which is a to the H is what a to the
log B of
n which by log rules is the same as n to
the log B of A and that's exactly the
result from case
one if the A's overpower the fs then
this last term wins and that basically
gives us our ASM totic
runtime um on the Other
Extreme if F grows fast if f is Big so
it grows really
quickly um then the F terms over here
are going to overpower the a
terms um and we end up getting the
opposite effect where this first term is
the biggest and all the rest don't
really contribute much ASM
totically so if if f is Big then the
first term in our sum dominates and we
end up getting T of n um T of n is in
Theta of
F and that is what case three says so if
F grows really fast then F alone is
where most of the work happens in terms
of our tree that means that the work we
had to do in this top node
FN that's the bulk of it and everything
else we did down here is small in
comparison all right now there's a case
three I want to keep that tree so let's
come over
here sorry there's a case two the middle
case of Master theorem that says what if
these two effects kind of balance each
other
out um um and in this
case um it's basically asking what if
all of these terms so FN * 1 FN over B *
a FN / b^ 2 * a^ 2 all of these terms in
the sum what if they're all basically
equal to each
other so in the
middle all terms of the sum are
basically equal
and so we end up getting that the
sum is well there are H terms here H+
one terms and each of the terms is
basically the same so I'm going to take
this where it's a to the H times Well n
over B to the H is one right so this is
basically well H +
one
times uh what was that last term again a
to the H * f of
one if all the terms are basically equal
then it's just the number of terms times
this last
one right um we're doing astics I don't
care about that plus one uh F of one is
a basic is a constant I don't care about
that uh so this is this ends up being
basically a to the H * H this
is Theta
of and if we remember what H was sorry
if we remember what a to the H was
that's n to the log B of A and if we
remember what H
was
um times another Factor log
B uh sorry yeah log B of
n so a to the H is this power of n h is
log of
n it's basically saying in case two if
things balance out nicely you just incur
an extra factor of log n from what you
would otherwise expect from case one
and turns out merge sort is in that
middle ground it's in case
two um because FN
here is n minus one for merge
sort uh and it's asking is
this Theta of n to the log base 2 of
two that's the condition for case 2 to
apply according to master theorem and
yeah n minus one is in Theta of n this
exponent is one so yes so we're in case
2 and this says that Master theorem of n
is Theta of n to that exponent that
exponent is one times an extra factor of
log
n so that's how we can use the master
theorem just by pattern matching on the
the shape ape of their recurrence a is 2
B is 2 FN is n minus one make sure it
satisfies the condition for case 2 and
in that case we can conclude uh that MN
is Theta of n log
n um which is the formula we found
earlier um at least when we were only
dealing with powers of two we had n log
n plus a linear term minus a linear
term and so this this matches what we
had in general it's less informative
it's only a Theta bound not an exact
formula but it still gives us what we
would expect which is
nice
um last thing I want to say about this
merge sort does have gaps uh sorry not
merge sort Master theorem does have
gaps um if you have a divide and congr
recurrence like
this um you can't always just apply
Master theorem sometimes um you have
cases that don't fall into any of the
three cases of Master theorem case one
two and three are all false U those
conditions are not valid so you can't
apply Master theorem at all so Master
theorem is not um snake oil that will
solve every problem it'll solve many
problems and in 006 in in
6121 um you'll be using it quite a bit
and you'll see how how useful it can be
in
practice final
thought um let's come back and
compare some yeah I'll just use this
compare some of our um recurrences and
the growth rates that they describe so
we had for example Fibonacci numbers uh
FN is FN minus one plus FN minus 2 uh we
had towers of Hanoi where hn was 2 h of
n minus1 + one this was Fibonacci this
was
Hanoi we have merged sort
um merge sort of n which is 2 m of n / 2
plus n minus
one and other divide and conquer
recurrences I'll use D for divide and
conquer this is a * D of n / B plus F of
N and if we take a look at what formulas
we got for these this Fibonacci this was
Theta of
um like 1.6 to the N that 1 plusun 5 all
divided by two to the N the Fibonacci
numbers grow exponentially the towers of
Hanoi grow
exponentially merch sword is very small
n log
n um and the the main difference here is
that in each of these recurrences we're
making recursive calls to smaller
terms but how quickly are those smaller
terms decreasing in merge sort every
time we make a recursive call we cut the
size in half we Cut N in
half so there are only logarithmically
many times that we can cut it in half
before we bought them out um so that's
why our our call tree over there was
only logarithmic height and so the
runtime ends up being pretty small
because there's not much of a tree to
deal with by contrast with Hanoi and
Fibonacci every time we make a recursive
call we're only subtracting one or
two and so we have to do that linearly
many times like n times before we get
down to the bottom and every time we
make this call the tree is getting
exponentially bigger it's doubling every
time we do this basically uh and that's
why in these two cases we're seeing
exponential growth because the the tree
is
huge so just thinking about this
recursive call tree which terms are
calling which other terms and how far
down does that go and how many nodes are
there
is a great way to get intuition um and a
rough idea of how quickly these things
are growing and a great reason why
divide and conquer algorithms in general
are often really good because they
bottom out
quickly that is everything I wanted to
say thank you so much um we'll see you
in recitation tomorrow and good luck
studying for your quiz