Next we have Michelle Lee from the
Zitnik lab at Harvard Medical
School. All right. Hello everyone. My
name is Michelle Lee and I'm a Burkowitz
post-docctoral research fellow at
Harvard Medical School. Thank you to the
organizers for this exciting opportunity
to share my work with you on
controllable sequence editing for
counterfactual generation. uh the
previous uh two professors gave
excellent uh primers into why how what
the space is that this work fits in. So
I will just jump right in. So let's
start with an analogy. So finish this
melody given only this single note. Now
you may say that this is an impossible
task because there are many
possibilities for what note can come
next. So what if I give you a few more
notes? Based on these four notes, can
you pick which note will come next?
Maybe picking the exact note is still
hard, but at least we can say based on
the pattern, the next note is probably
higher. Now, what pattern do we use to
deduce this? We looked at the trajectory
of the previous notes. First, there's no
change in the note. Next, the note goes
up. Then, there's no change again. So,
the best guess for the next note is
probably to go up. Indeed, that is true.
And here's the rest of the pattern. Now,
if you know how to read sheet music, you
may recognize this as the first few
notes of Twinkle, Twinkle, Little Star.
And continuing this music analogy,
what's the difference between these two
melodies? These notes look exactly the
same, but actually their identity
depends on context. As in, it's
important to recognize whether we are
interpreting the notes in the context of
the treble cleft at the top or the bass
cleft at the bottom. And not only are
the identities of these notes context
dependent, but so is the mood. Despite
the trajectories of these notes being
exactly the same, the top melody is a
very happy Twinkle, Twinkle, Little
Star, whereas the bottom melody sounds
kind of
creepy. Now, leveraging the trajectory
is not only helpful for inferring the
next note in the musical sequence, but
also the next state in the sequence of
cellular or patient profiles. Moreover,
the context such as the medication that
is prescribed at a specific time can
affect the future trajectory of the cell
or
patient. And so we introduced KFF, a
controllable sequence editing model that
can generate trajectories under any
given condition or context at any
specific time point. An example of a
condition is a certain medication that a
clinician prescribes.
Beyond conditional generation, we
hypothesize that cleft can be leveraged
for counterfactual reasoning about both
immediate and delayed effects. Suppose
we want to understand a patient's health
journey as a result of certain edits.
For example, what would the patients
trajectory look like if we gave the
purple medication in two hours?
Controllable sequence editing in
contrast to sequence editing requires
that none of the patients historical
data should change and that the model
should be able to make the edits
precisely at 2 hours. So our conditional
generation model KFFT learned temporal
concepts based on trajectories to encode
how and when certain conditions such as
medications should influence a sequence.
With these temporal concepts that
represent trajectories, KFFT is able to
selectively edit relevant time steps
while preserving unaffected portions of
the
sequence. So let's dive a little bit
deeper into KFFT's model architecture.
So KFTF manipulates sequences based on
user specified conditions and temporal
coordinates. So given a sequence, a
forecast time step and a condition
token, KFFT modifies only the relevant
portions of the sequence while
preserving unaffected elements. For
example, based on a patient's historical
lab test results, KLF generates a future
lab test trajectory conditioned on a
given treatment. Now there are two
possible tasks enabled by KLF. Immediate
sequence editing and delayed sequence
editing. Immediate sequence editing
entails predicting the immediate next
time point like
t+1. Delayed sequence editing entails
predicting a time step far into the
future like skipping directly to t+1 uh
t + 10 instead of auto reggressively
imputing the intermediate nine time
steps. Architecturally, KF has four key
components. A sequence encoder f that
extracts temporal features from
historical sequence data. a condition
adapter H that maps conditions to latent
representations, a concept encoder E
that learns temporal concepts
representing trajectory patterns over
time, and a concept decoder G that
applies these concepts to generate the
subsequent
trajectory. The inputs of the sequence
encoder is the historical data of the
cell or patient and the forecast time.
And the output of the sequence encoder
is a hidden representation of the
sequence data and a time delta
embedding. Note that the sequence
encoder can be of any type such as a
transformer architecture, XLXTM and uh
architecture or even a pre-trained time
series foundation model. The input to
the condition adapter is the condition
token from a frozen pre-trained
embedding model. And these embeddings
are passed through the adapter to
project it into a shared embedding space
with the temporal data. To account for
changes in a cell or a patient due to
both time and condition, the time delta,
the time delta and condition embeddings
are aggregated via an elementwise
summation and this new condition
embedding is aggregated with the
historical sequence embedding and the
result may optionally be projected
through a FIFO neuronet network. A gill
activation is then applied to
approximate rates of change. And these
rates of change which take values
greater than or equal to zero are the
temporal concepts representing the
trajectories of a cell or a patient. And
finally the sequence at the forecast uh
time point is predicted via element wise
multiplication with the rates of change
or temporal concepts and the latest time
point in the input sequence. And the
objective function here is hooper loss
on the predicted and ground truth
trajectories. KFF has two key
capabilities. Forecasting sequences at
any time in the future and under any
condition and generating sequences by
intervening on KFTF's learned temporal
concepts at any uh specific time point.
And we hypothesize that these
capabilities allow us to examine the
trajectories under alternative
conditions and timings of conditions.
We evaluate cleft on two real world
domains. Cellular development and
patient health. To study cellular
development, fibroblast cells derived
from mice can be artificially
reprogrammed into various other cell
states in vitro. A cell state is defined
by its gene expression. Throughout
reprogramming, a cell activates uh
transcription factor genes at different
time points to change its gene
expression, which influences its
developmental trajectory. We construct
two data sets of cellular reprogramming
experiments using the Wington OT
algorithm. Note that WOTCF is a data set
of paired trajectories of original and
counterfactual trajectories. Between
these two WOT data sets, there are about
a total of 500 uh 5,000 trajectories
with 1,480 features of coariantss that
represent the expression of 1,400 genes.
And these trajectories have an average
length of about 27 and a max length of
37. The health of a patient is often
monitored through lab tests like uh
blood sodium level, white blood cell
count, etc. The history of lab results
across multiple patient visits as well
as candidate clinical in clinical
interventions like medications can be
used to infer the most likely future
trajectory of the patient's health. We
have two patient trajectories data sets
constructed from publicly available EICU
and mimic four databases. There are over
100,000 trajectories with either 17 or
16 features of covariants that represent
the values of 17 or 16 lab tests. And
these trajectories have average lengths
of 20 and 15 and max lengths of 858 and
949.
In our first set of experiments, we
evaluate KF's performance on conditional
generation of observed cellular and
patient trajectories. We compare against
several state-of-the-art approaches
including a traditional time series
algorithm V and a pre-trained time
series foundation model called moment.
Here the yaxis is mean absolute error.
So the lower error is better. Blue bars
represent KFT models and the gray bars
are baseline models. Remember that KFFTF
can leverage any type of sequence
encoder and so here we demonstrate the
performance of KFFT with a transformer
XLSTM and a pre-trained time series
foundation model as a sequence encoder.
Notably we find that KFTbased models
perform comparably or better than their
non-cliff counterparts. This suggests
that learning trajectories through
temporal concepts can improve
conditional generation capabilities.
We additionally construct a series of
increasingly challenging data splits for
the patient data sets EICU and mimic 4.
The Xaxis shows the similarity of the
train test split. So close to zero is
akin to a random split uh where um with
very high uh train test split similarity
and close to one is the most challenging
split with low train test split
similarity. And the y-axis again is the
mean absolute error. So as you can see
the cleft models in blue show much
better generalizability than non-cliff
models especially when there is low
train test split
similarity. Now beyond evaluating KFT's
performance on conditional generation of
observed sequences we interrogate KF's
ability to simulate trajectories to
answer whatif questions. So imagine if
we could test in silicone the effects of
a candidate intervention on the cell's
gene expression or patients routine
laboratory tests at a specific time
point. For example, what medication
should I prescribe? Should I prescribe
the medication now in one year in 10
years? In the interest of time, I won't
describe the causal inference
assumptions that we make. However, I
will empirically demonstrate KFF's
performance in counterfactual
generation. To benchmark KF's ability to
generate counterfactual trajectories, we
construct a solar trajectories data set
using the Wington OT algorithm that
consists of paired trajectories in which
one is the original and the other is the
counterfactual. Specifically, these
pairs of trajectories have the exact
same historical trajectory until a
certain time step when a counterfactual
action is done. Given this historical
sequence in this counterfactual action,
the remaining trajectory is simulated
using the Wington OT algorithm. So for
this experiment, we train the model only
on original trajectories and evaluate on
counterfactual trajectories in a zeroot
manner. On the x-axis is the number of
time steps after performing the
counterfactual action. On the y-axis is
the mean absolute error. Again, as you
can see, cleft models in blue
significantly outperforms baseline
models and generating the counterfactual
trajectories in a zeroot
manner. And finally, here's a case study
where we can precisely intervene on the
predicted trajectories of patients with
type 1 diabetes to try to simulate
healthier or sicker trajectories. And
this is done directly, this is done by
directly altering the values of the
temporal concepts. If you're familiar
with uh concept bottleneck models, this
is analogous to intervening on the
values of the concept bottleneck layer.
So in the center plots, the x-axis shows
the types of patients that we compared
the intervened type 1 diabetic patients
to matched healthy patients, other
healthy patients and other type 1
diabetes patients. The yaxis is the R
squar between the trajectories of a pair
of patients. So higher R square means
higher pair Y
similarity. In the top plot, we generate
future trajectories of patients after
decreasing their glucose levels by half.
In other words, we reverse their
symptoms. We find that these intervene
trajectories look more similar to
healthy patients in the first two
columns here than to other type 1
diabetes patients in the third column,
which is what we would
expect. In the bottom plot, we do the
opposite. we generate future
trajectories of patients after doubling
their glucose levels. In other words, we
worsen their symptoms and we find that
the intervene trajectories look more
similar to other type 1 diabetic
patients in the third column than
healthy patients in the first two
columns. Again, these are expected
results.
Altogether, such findings are
particularly exciting because they
suggest that we could use Kluff to test
different clinical interventions,
timings of interventions, dosages of
medications, and even treatment
regimens. To summarize, KLF is a
controllable sequence editing approach
that can conditionally generate cellular
and patient trajectories. We demonstrate
that KFTF can additionally allow us to
simulate trajectories to answer what-if
questions about the effects of a
candidate intervention on the cell's
gene expression or a patient's routine
laboratory test at a specific time
point. On the right is a QR code to a
pre-print and please reach out if you
have any questions or suggestions. Thank
you.
[Applause]
Thank you so much. We have time for one
question. very nice
presentation
actually a long
awaiting you know model that you know in
clinics uh across the river you know in
the hospital um we need that kind that
kind of model because uh you know the
trajectory sometime we call the Hamilton
curve you know uh at certain time point
whichever you intervene you know when it
going
downhill you know the condition getting
worse uh when it going uphill uh you
just give it candy you know the patient
can get better you know it's surprising
because a trajectory is a biological
mechanism that govern the underlying
disease uh and also uh I hope you could
you know including more parameter for
instance like in oncology when you do
the infusion of the medication the We
infusion time uh is it divided into two
time or one uh bullet post or you know
how long you uh you know infuse it in
one hour or two hour does make a big
difference. Thank you.
Yeah, that's a really great suggestion
and I want to emphasize that because uh
perhaps clarify and emphasize that this
is uh the generation is done in an auto
reggressive manner and so we could
indeed simulate the length in which we
do certain interventions as well as the
certain dosage and the type of
intervention. Thank you for your
comment.
Thank you very much to all the speakers
in this session.