And this network could be all sorts of
things. I mean it could be
pipes,
roads,
um,
you know, electronic communications.
And
each edge has a capacity.
And the question is how much
um whatever can you get
get from a source to a sync.
So here we have an example.
This is a network.
This six says that only six units of
flow can pass over this edge at any
given time. This says four. This is
three. And the question is how many
units of flow can you get from S to T?
And we will call the source S and the
sync T. And these are the standard
letters that are used for them. I don't
know whether they stand for anything or
not. I mean clearly source S presumably
stands for source but I don't know why T
is a sync. Okay.
So the question is how much flow can you
get from here to here?
Um,
well,
let's try putting flow from here to
here. Does anybody see a path you could
run flow on?
Okay, this is an easy question. What is
some path from S to T?
Let's say S2
um oh my I have left out the
numbers on the nodes. So this is four
and this is five.
So S to two to four to T you could run
three units of flow along this path. So
let's put them there.
Now are there other paths you could
take?
Yeah, of course there are. You could run
two units of flow from here to here. So
that's two
to two two.
And
is this all? Well, no, because you could
run two units of flow from here
to here
to here. And we have, you know, two
units of flow already on here. So this
gives you four. You have zero units of
flow already. So this is two. You have
three units of flow here. So that gives
you five.
Now
is that the maximum?
Does anybody see any more paths?
>> Yes.
One from S. Two, three, five. Is it?
>> Yeah, you could do one from here.
Wait.
Oh, you're right. This was four. No,
wait. Yeah, this was four. But you could
run one up here. Four. You could run one
down here. One. And three.
And one up here. And one up here. And
there's still one more path you could
do, which I guess is one here, one here,
um, one here, one here, and one here. So
that's pretty complicated, but this
would be five, and this would be two,
and this would be three,
and two.
No, wait. And you could one run one run
here from four to three. So that's
there. And now we have a flow
every
the flow through every edge is less than
the capacity on that edge. So that's
good. And we have got a nine units of um
nine units of flow from here to here.
Okay. I guess I copied down the um
No, I didn't copy anything wrong. I'm
just looking at the green numbers rather
than the blue numbers. Okay. So, here is
um a flow of nine units.
So, what we're going to do later is
write down a linear program and the
solution to this linear program will be
the maximum flow. But first, I want to
talk about a cuts. So,
how could you prove
How can you prove that this flow is
maximum?
>> [clears throat]
>> Well, let's look at these three edges.
This one, this one, and that one.
There's four units of
capacity
on this edge, two units of capacity on
this edge, and three units of capacity
on that edge.
And so this defines a cut and
at most nine units of flow can cross
this cut. So that shows that nine units
of flow is maximum
cuts.
A cut is defined
as a subset of the vertices or subset
containing S but not T.
And so to make this a subset of the
vertices,
gosh,
what we do is we make the subset this
guy and this guy.
And
um maybe we should call it C.
Edges
from
C to C bar
are edges in the cut.
And let's say the capacity of an edge is
U of the edge.
So summation over E
equals I J I in C J and C bar
U of I J equals
I guess the value of cut
and it should be fairly easy that the
maximum flow
is less than or equal to the minimum cut
because if you have a flow from S to T
it must cross
every edge of the cut. So if the flow is
9 units then or rather if the cut is 9
units then
you can't have a flow larger than 9
units
and the theorem we will prove later
later theorem
the value of max flow
equals value
of minimum cut.
So you probably recognize this as being
somewhat
you know something like LP duality and
this is the primal solution
of LP and this will turn out to be the
solution
of the dual LP. P
and by the strong duality theorem of
linear program this guy equals this guy.
So the maximum flow equals the minimum
cut.
Okay. So there's a bunch of things we
have to do before we prove this theorem.
So what do we do?
First thing we do is write down the
linear program.
Does anybody have suggestions for what
the variables should be?
Yeah,
>> I guess it's like how like how many
units you like flow through each
>> through each edge. Exactly. So the
variables are going to be
x subig j that's the flow over edge
i j.
And
any suggestions for constraints?
>> Yeah. for any node not equal to SRT like
maybe the flow inwards is the flow
outwards
>> right so flow conservation I guess you
could call it
and let me write this down
um
Okay.
Okay. Summation.
Hope I'm getting this.
J such that I J is in the set of edges.
X subj.
So this is a set of things going into
node I
and a set of things going out of node I
equals um
no wait this is a set of things going
out of node I J and the set of things
going into node I and let's put a minus
sign here
so that
um K such that K I is an A. So this is a
set of things going into node I X sub K
I equals zero
because you know linear programs it's
nice to write down. So you have the
variables on the left side of the
equations and are inequalities and the
constants on the right side of the
inequalities.
And there's another set of constraints.
Can anybody figure out what it is? Yep.
>> What?
>> Yes.
>> The capacities.
>> Yeah, the capacities. We need to use the
capacities somewhere. And the you know
Xig is less than or equal to
um we call them U of J.
Okay J. and also
x i j have better than greater than
equal to zero.
And what do we want to maximize?
Okay, so what we want to do is we want
to maximize the sum of the things into
the
sync
which is node t. But actually we're
going to do this a slightly different
way. We're going to write down a
different um a new constraint summation.
Um,
oh, let's write down for all I and I
want to write down
um
K such that
KT
X sub KT
is an A. So this is all the things
going into the sync.
X sub KT is equal to
Z and we want to maximize Z.
So let's
did not leave enough room. So maximize
see.
Okay.
So that is the um
linear program
and
I have this sneaking suspicion that I
messed up a sign somewhere but
it doesn't really I mean doesn't ma I
mean this is a pro linear program which
does get the solution so it doesn't
really matter if I messed up a sign
except then when we take the duel it's
going to be
it's not going to be quite as nice.
Okay, let's just keep on going and write
down the duel. And if I got the sign
wrong, we'll fix it after that.
I want to say sign I don't I'm going to
say the sign is not wrong. This is a
perfectly good linear program for
max flow.
It's just I am, you know, a little
worried that when we take the duel,
we're going to have to flip some signs.
Okay.
So
[clears throat]
why don't I explain why don't I take the
duel now to take duel
each
equation
gives a constraint
or each inequality
no each variable gives a constraint each
constraint
gives a variable
So, we have two classes.
Well, actually, I guess we have three
classes of
equations and inequalities, but I just
want to um
use two of them. I'm going to call this
one alpha subj
and this one beta subi and this one beta
subc.
because this really is a lot like this
except um slightly different. And I
really should make this minus Z equals
Z.
Okay.
So, how do we
get the um
variables of the
how do we get the constraints of the
duel and the objective function of the
duel? Well, the objection function in
the duel is just the right hand sides of
the
right hand sides of the constraints of
the primal.
So the
so we will have minimum
Because the original L primal LP was a
maximization. We want to have a
minimization.
And the minimization
summation alpha J u of I J
subject two.
Um
okay, we're going to have a equation for
each variable.
So let's say the equation
corresponding to variable x subig j it's
just you look at all the places where
xig j appears in equation. So x subj
appears in beta subi and in alpha subj.
And we should have alpha iig j
plus beta subi minus beta subj
is greater than or equal to zero.
So it's greater than equal to because
these were positive variables. And when
we go from a maximization to a
minimization,
you're minimizing this. You want a
greater than equal to sign in your
constraints.
Okay.
Now
there is one more
um
well I guess Z was also a variable in
this
and
um
so there's an equa equing
to B and Z appears in the objective
function. So this should be greater than
or equal to one and Z also appears
in
um
well I just want to say only appears in
one equation that's beta subz. So beta
subz is greater or equal to one. No,
actually it appears in
um
Yeah.
Yeah. So this is the
duel.
>> What
>> not negative one?
Ah
because
I should have written this equation
minus and plus.
And now this left hand side is things
leading into
oh this is beta subt beta sub z I'm
sorry that was a very good question beta
subt and this thing
is
um
k
this should the
edges leading into T. And if we look
down here, edges leading into I have a
minus sign. So to make it consistent,
this has to have a minus sign. And then
this is a plus sign and
we
have beta subt greater than or equal to
one. That was a very good question and
that explains why I was worried about
the signs.
Good.
Okay.
So, what do solutions of this equation
look like?
Well,
how do you get cuts out of solutions to
this equation? Okay, and this is uh very
um
This is a rather tricky um thing.
So,
so for this we have
um
we put
we put um
numbers on the
nodes of this network.
And we want to maximize
alpha subj times the capacity
and subject to the capacity
beta i minus beta j is greater than
equal to zero.
And first I want to say you know
for optimal
alpha subig is equal to
well
either alphaig j
oh did I write forget to write down
alpha j bigger than equal to zero
because alpha subi j
was
uh
less an inequality in the
um
okay
the
constraint corresponding to al alpha i j
was an inequality so alpha j is greater
than equal to zero
and the beta sub i's are unconstrained.
For the optimal, well, you want to make
alpha subj as small as possible
subject to the constraints that alpha
subig is bigger equal to zero and alpha
sub j is bigger than beta j minus beta
i. So you might make alpha J equals
maximum of zero and beta J minus beta
subi
and the optimal.
Okay.
So we're going to put
values on the nodes and we're going to
make alpha subj for maximum zero and
beta j minus beta i. Now suppose
each
alpha j equals z or 1.
And now what we have is we have
and
I'm just going to say here
because we want to make everything as
small as possible. We'll take beta
subtal 1 and we'll take beta subs equals
zero
because
you know because if there is no
because if s
if s is one of these
if we're looking at i j where i equals s
for this then really we don't have a
beta sub i and the you know
the equations alpha i subj minus beta j
is greater than equal to zero but you
can just make everything uniform by
setting beta s equals z. So we have beta
t equal 1 beta s equals z.
So we have 0 0. Okay, I should put some
this is one
let's make this one this zero
etc.
So alpha subi j is the maximum of zero
and beta j minus beta subi. So that
means that this is going to be one. This
is going to be zero. This is going to be
one.
Um
this
is you know this would be minus one
except that's less than zero. So this
had better be zero. This is zero. This
is zero for the same reason. This is
one.
This is um
one and this is zero.
The one edges
are a cut
because the one edges are just the edges
leading out of the things nodes with
alpha
nodes with beta i equals z and to the
nodes beta i equals 1 which was our
definition of cut.
So that means that this is a cut between
um which nodes are zeros
between the green nodes and the other
nodes.
So there's one here,
one one here, and one here.
So when you add up the
you look at the
objective function, it's just the sum
over all of the
edges
in the cut times their capacity
or one for all the edges in the cut
times their capacity. So it's just the
value of the cut.
So this is
dual
objective function
value
of cut
if
beta subi is in 01.
Now here comes the trickiest part. of
this whole um thing. Why can we assume
it's the minimum cut rather than
this? In other words, why can we assume
that the optimal solution of the duel
has integer values rather than
fractional values for the variables?
look
at.
Okay, we're going to look at this graph
in another way. Graph
above
drawn
in another way.
Okay, so let's put
S
beta subs=0 on the left side
beta subt = 1 on the right side and
um
beta sub 2
beta sub3
beta sub 4 beta sub5 But
um
I want to claim I want to
I want to say that there's no reason
these beta eyes have to be in order. put
beta i's online
at value
of beta i in the optimal solution of the
duel.
[clears throat]
So if beta was 2 was equal to 2 in the
optimum solution of the duel this point
would be 0 2.
And now let's look at the edges in this
graph. And
this is
um
six.
This is
four.
This is two.
Um there's an edge three, a value three
going from
Beta 3, beta 2 to beta 4. So this is
three.
There's an edge from beta 3 to beta 4.
So that is three.
Um,
there's an edge from beta 4 to beta 5.
Wait,
there's an edge from beta 5 to beta 4,
which is this way. Two.
There's an edge from beta 4 to t. So
this is eight.
And this is two.
Um,
okay.
So,
Um,
so the claim
edges
crossing
a vertical I
form a cut.
So let's look at this edge.
Um
this vertical line this has edge two,
three and four crossing in it. And we
have beta's
Beta 1 and beta beta S and beta 2 are on
the left side. So that is just
this cut.
You have S and two on the left side of
the cut and all the other edges on the
right side of the cut. And we have four
and two and three crossing them. Now
let's try another cut.
And um I probably should use a different
color.
So
um
let's try
this cut.
Now we have five and t on the right side
and the other four edges on the left. So
what cut does that correspond to
here?
Um it's not a different color.
I'm sorry.
Let's try
making it purple.
Okay. So that
and I see I have drawn
drawn things wrong.
I left out a edge because there's an
edge from B3 to B5. So that should look
like this
because we have three going to five and
that edge had capacity four.
So the value of this cut is two.
No, wait. It's four + 8.
That's 12. And we don't count this two
edge two because it crosses the cut
backwards. And we only count edges that
cross the cut forwards. And
you know here we have
that cut is um
okay I need a purple line here. purple
line here.
No, those are the wrong
I'm sorry about that.
This is the So five and t are on the one
side of this cut. So we this this and
this edge is not cross the cut because
it crosses the cut backwards. So the
value of that cut
is
no.
So these edges are these vertices are in
the cut. So the edges are the ones that
go from something not in the cut to
something in the cut. So that's four to
t
3 to 5
and 5 to 4 is backwards edge. So the
value of that cut is 8 + 3 which is 11
which is bigger than nine. So it's not
the minimum cut but that it
I think the B beta 3 to beta 5 might
have the wrong value.
>> I think you're right. So beta 3 to beta
5 is four
and I put down three on here.
So let's see beta 3 to beta 5 three. So
this is supposed to be a three. Thank
you.
Okay. So that is um so we have a cut of
value 11
for there. So these are cuts.
Now I want to claim
The value of the dual optimum
in duel.
Well, I want to label these cuts. So,
let's label this one as
Um,
okay.
C1,
C2,
C3, C4,
C5.
And let's assume
that the betas are put down in order
because we can always renumber the
um variables so that the third variable
is the one right after the second cut.
So the value of the optimum in the dual
is equal to summation
well
summation
alpha subig j u of i j which is equal to
beta j minus beta j minus one
um
times
C sub
J minus one.
Why is that?
Well, let's look at this picture again.
So
we have alpha i subj equals maximum of
zero and beta j minus beta subi.
So,
so this is equal to summation over
forward
edges
beta j minus beta i
u of i j.
Now let's look at this edge.
This edge appears in two cuts
and its value in the first cut is beta t
minus beta 5 times the value times 8.
The value of contributing the second cut
is beta 5 minus beta 4 * 8. So adding
them up
when you sum up all the cuts you get
beta t minus beta 4 * 8
for the value this edge contributes to
the duel
which is
exactly what it's supposed to be.
Okay. So this is the trickiest part. So
should I explain it some more?
Um
so beta five. So
the cuts only come from the edges where
beta
where beta 5 is bigger than beta 4. So
this edge does not contribute anything
to the cut. If there's a cut that goes
if there's an edge that goes forward, it
contributes beta t minus beta 5 * 8 to
this cut and beta 5 minus beta 4 * 8 to
this cut. And adding those two things
up, you get beta t minus beta 4 * 8
to the total objective function of the
duel, which is just
what it's supposed to be because alpha j
is equal to beta j minus beta i.
Okay. So,
oh, wait. I think I wanted to keep that.
So,
Objective
function
of duel
is
summation beta j minus beta j minus one
c subj j minus one
right
but
summation
beta j minus beta j minus one is equal
to beta t minus beta s is equal to
because beta t was one, beta s was zero.
Let beta j minus beta j minus one equals
lambda j.
So this equals summation lambda j c j
minus one.
Okay, maybe lambda j minus one lambda j
minus one c a minus one
where
summation lambda j - 1 = 1.
This
is an average
of
values
of cuts
just by the definition of average. But
the average of a bunch of things is
bigger than the minimum of the bunch of
things. So this is greater than or equal
to the minimum
cut.
And in the optimal solution of the duel,
you take the minimum cut. You can put
zeros
on the beta subjs that are to the left
of the cut and one on the beta js to the
right of the cut. So you get the minimum
value of the cut for the solution of the
duel. So the
value of the dual substitution
is equal to the minimum cut
and we know that the value of the primal
solution is equal to the maximum flow
because that's the way we set up the LP.
So the maximum flow is equal to the
minimum cut.
Okay.
And
so the next thing I want to do, which
I'm
I don't think I'm going to quite get
through all the lecture notes today, but
what I've done today is the so far is
the thing that I really want you to
take, you know, the lesson I want you to
take home that looking at the DS and
analyzing them can give you very
interesting theorems about
um linear programs
and this is
no I want to say this is a
fundamental principle in combinatorial
optimization and um if you actually get
a linear program from somewhere
one of the first things you do is you
look at the duel you stare at it and you
say what does this mean in terms of the
actual problem you're studying. And
often
it will give you some insight into the
problem. Sometimes it won't. Sometimes
it just looks like a bunch of,
[laughter]
you know, a bunch of um
variables that you can't understand at
all.
Okay.
So,
um, I think we can erase this now.
Suppose
you have a
you have a maximum flow problem
with integer capacities.
Then
the solution is an integer
proof.
The dual solution
is a cut.
So it's
a sum
of
integers
because the capacity of the cut is the
sum of the capacities of the edges and
the capacities of the edges are
integers. So we can ask the question
does the primal
solution
also
have
I guess integer flows.
because maybe it doesn't. I mean, there
are certainly solutions where it
doesn't. I mean,
um,
you can imagine coming up with a
solution where you have, I guess, six
and a half units of flow flowing over
this edge and one and a half units
flowing over that edge. and adding up to
nine. So I guess I can't do arithmetic
but um
but you also know that all the edges
all the flows going across a cut have to
be equal to the value of that the edges
in the capacities in that cut. So you
know some edges have to be integer. So
the question is do all the edges can you
find a solution with all the edges
integers
and
the answer is yes and I don't know how
to do it easily working from the linear
program. So there's another algorithm
for
integer flows
algorithm
for
max flow
which I'm going to call augmenting paths
algorithm
and the and the idea.
Find a path.
Push as much flow
over this path as possible.
So
as much flow over this path as possible
will you know you will take the minimum
residual capacity in every edge
and the path and um that means that you
um
you know the residual capacity is always
an integer because the flows are
integers and the capacities are
integers. So that means that the whole
thing will be an integer. So let's try
this
and let's see we have a simple network.
Um
2 2 3
three. These are the capacities. Two
two. And let's put another edge from
here to here with capacity three.
And we're going to direct all the edges
to the right. So
good.
Okay. So the first step,
let's take the best path to
push flow from here to here. So let's
take three along here,
three along here, and three along here.
Okay.
Now, how much capacity remains
in the graph?
Well,
there's zero left in this edge, zero
left along this edge, and zero left
along this edge. So it looks like we
have a cut
between the left side and the right side
with
and you can't put any more flow across.
But of course you should know you should
realize that you could easily put a flow
of four on the original graph.
So um
you have to be clever
to use this algorithm.
So
how can we push more flow across this
graph?
I want to claim that we could use this
path
So this path we push it two across here.
Push two across here. And now we're
going the wrong way in the edge. But we
can do that because there's already a
flow of three across this edge. And so
to get a flow of two this way, we just
reduce this three to one.
And then we can push another flow of two
across here and another flow of two
across here.
So you can push flow across edges
backwards as long as there's
uh
there is a flow left
as long as there is as long as there's a
flow already along an edge.
[clears throat] So I want to claim
define residual
network.
Um,
if an
edge
has flow
x subj less than u of j.
The new capacity
is
U of I J minus X of J.
If an edge
has flow
x subj greater than zero.
There's an edge and residual network
with
so let's call this edge ei J
E subji with
capacity
um
x subi j.
So
what is the residual network for this
graph when we put
the flow the orange flow across it?
Well,
we have
um
well this had capacity three. So now
that edge has capacity three in the
opposite direction.
This edge has zero. So that has capacity
zero. Two two.
This edge also has capacity three and
flow three in the forward. So now we get
capacity 3 going in the backwards
direction
and this one we have capacity three in
the backwards direction. This has
capacity three in the forwards and the
capacity three in the forwards.
[clears throat]
Okay. So this is the residual network.
Okay.
And now you can see that there's a flow
of two that goes bum bum bum bum bum.
So we push this flow of two here and we
get here. I'm going to redraw this.
We get two, two,
and one going this way. And
three going this way. And two, two, and
three.
So now we have a flow from the source to
the sync with value five. And that's the
best you can do because you can see that
there's a cut of value five. With just
taking t and everything else, you can
get at most value five across this cut.
So claim
if there
is
no flow
in residual network.
So
then
there is a cut
cut in original graph.
So
if you have a value,
so I guess
I should have started this with
suppose
you have a flow
of
value
Z.
If there's no augmenting path in the
residual network, then there's a cut in
the original graph of value.
So if there's no flow in the if there's
no flow in the residual network.
Let S be
maybe C be set
of nodes you can reach
from S.
So let's say we have this
thing.
So
what nodes can you reach from S?
Actually you can't reach any nodes from
S because
this is capacity. This is at capacity.
So we could have um
made this
made this capacity four and this
capacity four. And this is still a good
flow in the residual network. And now
what nodes can we reach?
Well,
we can reach
this node.
We cannot reach this node because this
is at capacity. we can reach this node.
Oops.
And
we actually
can reach this node
because it's at capacity.
But we cannot reach this node and we
cannot reach this node. So we have a cut
here
and that corresponds to this cut here.
So every
edge
from
C to C bar,
the flow is equal to U of I J because
otherwise you could push flow from C to
C bar and every edge from C bar to C
X subig equals zero because Otherwise,
you could push extra flow backwards
along this edge.
And that says
the cut
equals
sum
c bar
u of i j equals flow.
So
if you cannot find any augmenting paths,
if you already have a partial flow,
then
you're done. You cannot get any further.
Yeah. I mean then you have you know that
is the value of the maximum flow because
you have found a minimum cut that is
equal to your flow.
So this says that
you can use the augmenting paths
algorithm
to
find max flows and
it will give you an integer flow if all
the capacities are integer which is know
what we wanted to show
and actually there's a
there's an application of this which
maybe I'm going to get through.
And this is Kunig's thurum.
Oops.
All right. And a bipartite graph.
The cardality of the maximum matching
of maximum matching
equals cardality
of minimum vertex covers.
Okay,
let's look at a graph.
So this is a bipartite graph and um
what would be a maximum matching?
Well,
I mean we clearly should put this vertex
in the matching. This vertex in the
matching. Um I guess we need another
vertex here.
Um and we can put this vertex in the
matching and this vertex in the
matching.
So the maximum
matching
equals four.
So the maximum matching is just the
maximum set of edges such that no two
share an end point.
Minimum vertex cover
set of vertices
that touch every edge.
And clearly
verdicts cover
is greater than or equal to the matching
because there must be a vertex that
touches one end point of each of the
edges of the matching. And
you don't I mean
you're not going to get less than that.
But Kodig theorem is that these two
quantities are actually equal.
And
proof
maximum flow
then cut.
Okay. So we want a flow whose
um
we want a flow whose um value is equal
to the matching. So what are we going to
do? Well, we're going to take um
s on the left and put an put an edge of
weight one to every vertex in the
matching. And now we're going to
and let's um do the same thing on the
right. We'll put a edge to the sink from
every
point on the right side of the bipartite
graph. And then and these capacities are
going to be one.
And now
let's see. Um
there
There is a max flow
with
integer
values.
And what that means is that
oh and we can let the
capacities of these middle edges be
infinity if we want.
Well, what that means is that there are
going to be some number of edges in the
middle which have weight one here.
So I want to claim that those are
clearly a maximum matching because um
you know on the right hand side
no if they one flow if there's a one
unit of flow from here to here then no
other edge could use this vertex.
So if you have a flow from here to here
then this edge
this edge is in the matching and neither
of these edges is in the matching and
similarly on the left. So the maximum
flow gives you a maximum matching
duel
is a cut
and that means that there's a cut whose
value is equal to the maximum flow and
There are going to be some edges on the
right which are cut and the some edges
on the left which are in the cut.
And
I don't think I did that right.
But um
you know if the edge is in the cut then
this vertex is in the vertex cover and
now we know that there aren't any other
paths from S to T. And that means that
we know that every vertex
every edge is covered by at least one
vertex because otherwise there would be
a path from S to T going through that
edge.
Let me see.
Um, so
let's
Okay, I did not prepare this quite
properly enough. So, this is an edge in
the cut. This, I believe, has to be an
edge in the cut. And now
And um
I can just say this is an edge in the
cut
there should be one more thing
and that means so there are three edges
in this
cut and I think that cut actually cuts
all the paths from left to right.
So, we should have
a maximum matching of only three.
And um
well, it's easy. One,
two, three.
And you can't get any more things in the
maximum matching because
you know because there's a cut.
So this is Kunix theorem and I seem to
be completely out of time. So
I will see you next time on Thursday
when we start a new topic on information
theory.