All right, let's start
from first category. Uh, advanced
diagnostics. Professor Angela Basha. She
is James Mason Craft Professor and
Professor at Department of Biological
Engineering, Material Science and Coke
Institute for Integrative Cancer
Research and the head of department of
biological engineering at MIT. She is a
expert in the field of biioaterial,
biomolecular material, organic inorganic
interface and solid state chemistry. Uh
she will speak about interesting you
know his research history today. I think
she was awarded 2024 national medal of
science and technology. Professor Angel
Bashar lead research focused on
understanding and harnessing nature's
own process in order to design
technologically important material and
device for energy and environment and
medicine. So she will present near
infrared imaging sensing probes for
imaging small size tumors. She also
found a startup for noninvasive optical
imaging system as well. So I will hand
over to Angela. So, please welcome.
Good morning. Um, it's nice to be here.
Um, I'm always excited to be here, um,
for lots of different reasons. Um, but
it's really great to interact with, um,
with people and companies that are
trying to make an impact in the world
and make an impact on people's lives.
And, um, I'm in the department of
biological engineering here at MIT and,
uh, the materials science and
engineering and the Koch Institute. But,
I'm really an inventor. Um, I've wanted
to be an inventor since I was four years
old. Um, and my my group that's what we
do. We uh we're inventors and we we like
to invent um problems and and um around
bottlenecks that we can think can make
an impact uh in the world and we work
with a lot of of partners on this. And
so um unfortunately right after this I
have to teach at 10 o'clock on the other
side of campus. So I'm going to be
running but I can come back if you want
to talk. It's the last class. I can't
bail on the students. Um but um we can
talk in in more more detail. Um and I
have way too ambitious of a slide
presentation today. Um but so I've been
fascinated um almost my entire life on
how organisms make materials. Here's an
example of an abalone shell, which is a
biomposite material. It's 98% by mass
calcium carbonate, but 2% by mass
proteins. Yet it's 3,000 times tougher
than its geologic counterpart. So I'm
going to pass this around. This is how
biology makes calcium carbonate. It made
it in the ocean. Ocean temperatures,
ocean pressures, doesn't use toxic
materials, doesn't add toxic materials
back into the environment. I'm going to
pass it this
way. Um, over here are geological
counterparts of calcium carbonate. You
might have seen this before. This is
calite, the the thermodynamically most
favored structure of calcium carbonate.
Don't drop it because it's like $150 and
it's very for me it's very valuable. But
if you look at it in the right, you can
see that it's actually optically active.
It's pretty cool. And this is the
metastable crystal structure of calcium
carbonate. And um the organisms in the
ocean pick both of those structures
simultaneously to work with um and they
control it. How many people are solid
state chemistry? Okay. Yes. Solid state
chemistry. Um so you know from if you
think about the
um phase diagram, you're usually
thinking, oh yes, temperature or
pressure. But organisms have another
very special thing which many people are
in the life sciences and biological
sciences so they know this but they can
use proteins to control crystalraphic
orientation. They can use proteins to to
make things nanocale. They can use
proteins to control optical electronic
prop well yes electronic properties. We
can use them to control electronic
properties. And so it's just amazing. So
these organisms evolved over billions of
years in the ocean to take calcium
carbonate out of the environment and
build exquisite structures. Okay. Are we
limited to that? No. So, I passed out a
periodic table for you today. Um, it's a
periodic table that I made after I got
to MIT. I wasn't here that long. It
says, "Welcome to MIT nun element, and
that's because when I got here, I felt
like I finally fit in." Um, and so it's
the periodic table on one side, and it's
the amino acids and their pKa's on the
other side because I'm fascinated
between this this interface between
biology and and um the periodic table.
How can you use those together to to
make materials? And so I'm here to talk
about ovarian cancer, but I'm going to
talk a little bit about things before
that. So um I wanted to mention uh two
of my uh collaborators, Professor Paula
Hammond in chemical engineering
institute professor and um professor
Sangita Batia. the the um the three of
us are are just dedicated to changing
the outcome of uh women living with
ovarian cancer, hopefully prevent
ovarian cancer, intercept ovarian
cancer. Um and um uh and I'll talk about
that uh that today. We're all holding
signs to say I look like an engineer.
We're part of a campaign to re um we
were part of a campaign to re um imagine
what engineers look like. I mentioned
before that organisms in the ocean have
been doing a fantastic job of making
nanomaterials for about three billion
years. Um, and they do this by uh
evolution, by controlling proteins. What
my lab did that was was different was we
said, "Okay, life has done a pretty good
job, but we think it could have done
better. What if it had the whole
periodic table to work with? What if it
wasn't limited to the ions that were
dissolved in the ocean?" And so we
developed some te technology and that's
part of what I I won the the national
medal for was can you force organisms to
work with the whole periodic table. Um
and uh you're saying no I don't think
you can and I agree with you you
probably can't force them to work with
every element on the periodic table but
can you get them to work with most
elements on the periodic table?
Absolutely. Can you get them to
genetically code it? And we've worked on
about 150 materials now that we can grow
um using biological mechanisms. We use
bacteria phages. We use proteins. We use
antibodies. We use yeast cells. Um I'll
pass around two different um batteries
that we made in my lab. These are
batteries that are genetically
engineered. Um we engineered organisms
to make the anode and the cathode wire
itself to the current collector. This
one went to the White House several
years ago for a press release. That I'll
pass that one this way. I I can't
remember. That's probably a lithium iron
phosphate battery. This is a a battery
that the technology wasn't that
difficult. We translated it to my
undergraduate teaching lab um sophomore
level and these are batteries that they
made. You're saying, "Wait a minute,
that looks just like my battery that you
know is in my um remote control or
something." Um yeah, it's the the bi the
battery, the anode, the cathode
materials are made biologically, but
then we package them as a regular
battery technology. So yeah, you can
actually work on batteries, solar cells,
fuel cells, and we've done that kind of
thing in the lab. So you can genetically
engineer simple organisms to do things
like make a make a battery. And you're
like, why would you do that? Well, one,
because it's cool. Um the the other
reason is that biology when it made that
shell, it does it at uh ocean
temperatures, ocean pressures, doesn't
use toxic materials, doesn't add toxic
materials back in the environment, just
like my cell phone, right? No. So, the
idea is can you use this these kinds of
processing to control things? And the
other key is evolution. So, through
evolution, even if you make come kind of
a not so great battery, you can evolve
it over time to try to make it better
and better. We've done that with with
many materials and I I'm not sure if I
already said we've worked with over 150
materials. So in my lab we work at the
interface between nanotechnology and
biomeaterials and I always say I've
never been accused of focusing um
because we work on energy healthcare and
the environment um and the connection
there to us is nanomaterials
um making uh nice nanomaterials um that
can um can be used for many different um
applications. And we've spun out um five
companies in my lab in different areas
anywhere from uh electronics to uh to
energy. Um uh Sision Vision I'll show
you a little data with now. It's u a
company doing um non-invasive imaging of
of lymph nodes. It's now in 15 uh
hospitals around the um around the world
actually. Um and uh other other
technologies as as well. Um this this
these are just inventions that we've
done very very recently that I don't
have time to talk about. Um but um we've
um well I can talk a little bit about
it. Okay. So um these are materials here
that we engineered. U we thought these
are going to be great battery materials.
These are really high surface area
carbons on the order of 15 or 16 um um
uh these are on the order of 15 or uh uh
16 me squared per gram. Um says 18 here.
18 meters squared per gram. We've now
grown them up to 7,000 meters squared
per gram. Very high surface area
materials. These materials we made from
batteries. They did not work for
batteries. We found out that they could
actually neutralize um really toxic
agents. We translated them to the US
Army where they used them to neutralize
chemical warfare agents sin and sarin uh
to protect uh troops. Um and um then we
actually translated those materials into
u materials that could be used for gold
mining. um and uh that were magnetic and
could be used for gold mining. And we
translated um the materials that are on
the order of 7,000 meters squared per
gram as materials to clean up forever
chemicals and other toxic chemicals in
the water. So what we try to do is just
make materials and try to fit that into
um a place where um where there's a
need. So why ovarian cancer? So, I've
become obsessed with uh ovarian cancer
um partly because of um of knowing
several women at NMIT that that died of
ovarian cancer. Um and one woman is
diagnosed in stage three or stage four
ovarian cancer every three minutes
worldwide. And my surgical uh oncologist
collaborator says that's the amount of
time it takes you to make a bagel um put
on the cream cheese and not even start
eating it yet. Woman was diagnosed with
stage three or stage four ovarian
cancer. The five-year survival rate is
um is uh 34% um at stage three, 14 uh
17% at stage four, and it's improved
very little o over the last uh last 20
years. Um and um so we um uh we we're
really concerned with this and we want
to think about how how you know what can
be done. So as you probably know there's
really no screen for ovarian cancers.
There's a large scale clinical trial um
in uh in Europe that looked at looking
at CA125 levels um and doing
transvaginal ultrasound and though they
could stage things earlier there was no
increase in survival of patients um and
um we do know that if you can find it at
at stage one um that if you have a um
um survival rate um that's much higher
about 15% of cases are are detected at
stage one. It's hard to find. It's hard
to find for a lot of reasons and we can
talk about that. So, we'd like to have a
screen um and an intervention for that.
Okay, here's the shocker and I don't
know how many people know this. I did
not know this till a couple of years
ago. So, ovarian cancer, we call ovarian
cancer, originates 85% of the time. Does
it originate from the ovaries? No, it
originates from the fallopian tubes.
It's really fallopian tube cancer. It
really starts in this tube that is
touching the um ovarian touching the
ovaries. It starts usually with a p-53
mutation and it starts to form a stick a
a precancer lesion. That precancer
lesion can be there for up to nine years
and from there it actually can start to
can start to spread and it's a different
kind of cancer. It doesn't spread
necessarily by the lymph nodes. Doesn't
necessarily spread in the blood system.
It actually sheds. It sheds into the
entrepreneurial space. That's why when a
woman is diagnosed at stage three or
stage four ovarian cancer, they don't
have one tumor. They have 10 tumors.
They have hundreds of tumors spread out
through the interparal space. And they
go through something that's called um um
they they go through reductive surgery
where the surgeon goes in, removes every
tumor that he or she can see by eye,
closes the patient up, and follows with
uh with chemotherapy. Patients become
resistant to chemotherapy and they um
most likely um relapse. And this
increases with BRCA 1 and two uh
mutations. Um so um we now know that
women that are at risk that have BRCA
one or two can have their fallopian
tubes taken out um when they're at at
the end of when they're no longer in
childbearing years. So if they're BA one
or two positive, they'll they'll have
their fallopian tubes taken out. We also
know from a um a large scale clinical
trial in Canada that women that have
their fallopian tubes which actually
have no function. They don't have a
hormonal function. Their function is to
carry the uh eggs um to the uterus um um
that if they have them taken out there's
almost zero can zero instances of
ovarian cancer. It's ovarian cancer
prevention. It's a way of preventing
preventing ovarian cancer but not all
women can do this. Um and also how does
it fit in with u a woman's desire for
reproductive uh cycle. So um we need to
um have a screening method. We need to
have an early intervention method for
for women. I want women when they go in
for their mammogram every year they go
in for ovarian cancer uh screening as
well. Um so we um when we were first
asked um to work on cancer I always tell
my students this. I didn't work on
cancer. I was happy I was working on
batteries. I had a a catalyst company. I
was doing things like that. And then the
president of MIT said, "I want you to
work on cancer." And I was like, "Oh,
well, uh, how about, you know, here's my
battery." Um, and um, and but the but
the idea was to put cancer biologists
and engineers in the same building, in
the same suite, and get them to interact
and work together. And I was very
intimidated by it, honestly, because um,
I didn't want to take up space for
someone doing more important work in
cancer because it is so important. Um,
but so I this is what I teach my
students when I'm going to run off and
teach. I actually talked to them about
this yesterday. When you're stuck and
you don't know what to do, start with
something you're really good at and then
go start with something you're very good
at and then start to branch out. So
that's what we did. I'm like I am good
at nanomaterials. Um I'm good at carbon
nano tubes. And so we started thinking
about carbon nanot tubes as not just
electrical materials or um or mechanical
materials but optical materials because
they have really interesting optical
properties in the near IR. So above a
thousand nanometers and many people in
this room basically looking at people's
um um tags I know that you already you
already know this uh kind of thing. So
we decided to look at near2 imaging for
non-invasive identification at at small
cells. So the idea is that near 2 above
1,000 nanometers and we're up to 1,000
to 1,800 nanometers you can see much
deeper. Now these devices didn't um
exist um that you couldn't buy them
commercially. That's a long story, but
my students um don't like to my students
like to build things. So, they set about
to build uh the instruments, and I'll
talk to you about them. The other thing
you need is a contrast agent. You need a
contrast agent that is fluorescent in
those wavelengths. Um and so, and that
you can modify. So, we looked, you know,
there's organic dyes. There's there are
quantum dots. They're rare earth
nanoparticles, which we spend a lot of
time in. Um these rare earth
nanoparticles here are both upconverting
and downconverting. This is an IR laser,
so you can't see it with your eye, but
you shine it on the nano particles. Um,
and they both upconvert and down convert
at the same time, which is which is
super uh uh important for us. But we can
think about these as as markers. So my
my group worked on making ultra ultra
bright um carbon nanot tubes making
plasmonic enhanced near dyes um and then
doing um up down conversion
nanoparticles for rare earth
nanoparticles looking for ovarian
cancer. Now the thing that we're really
interested in is hyperspectral imaging
for non-invasive non-instructive um and
what we really care about is how does
light interact with fallopian tubes? How
does light interact um with any organ
cell um that we're interested in? Um and
so people will know that hyperspectral
imaging has been used for
non-destructive food inspection, remote
sensing. Um but we wanted to use it for
lab label free manners to look for these
sticks or these small precancer lesions.
So we've built several instruments in
our lab. We built Dolphin which is
hyperspectral hyper diffuse imaging with
3D reconstruction with 8 cm uh detection
depth. Um we built um a um this is our
first generation instrument that was
just very um um primitive. Uh then we
built Swifty which we built with um
surgeons at MGH for real-time surgical
guided imaging to find tiny tumors
during surgery so they could surgically
plan which tumors to remove first. Oh,
I'll go back. You want to take a picture
of that? That's published. Um and um and
we found in these um with these surgical
guided imaging that if we um if we used
our near rear u ne near uh IR2 imaging
system um that we had much better
survival of patients and this is what my
surgical collaborator uh Michael Beer
told me to work on because I like I want
to prevent ovarian cancer and he said
Angie let's start with all the patients
that have ovarian cancer. let's see if
we can have them have a better outcome
through um finding tiny tumors and we
work with them on that that was a
project through the bridge project which
is a great program um and then I had a
student um a posttock
um who um who um started working started
working on looking at um vaccination and
how different vaccines and different
adgivants um affected uh lymph nodes um
and one of the things that that he
noticed is using shortwave length
infrared and uh polarization that we
could see the difference between lymph
nodes and fat or lymph nodes and muscle
they would just pop out. um and we
hadn't seen this in the literature
before and so he went and developed a a
technology I should say that we applied
to NIH twice for this and both times got
um rejected um and then we had a donor
um um part in terms and part of um um uh
of the Koch institute gave us money to
develop this this is what a lymph node
looks like under just light uh or under
microscope and this is what it looks
like under the technology because what
we've actually done is really tried to
take advantages of the differences is of
light absorption under polarization.
This is fat and this is lymph node. They
look very very same. So this we
developed this for colon cancer um
patients. So um patients that are under
having part of their colon taken out um
when they have part of their colon taken
out they take a lot of tissue out um and
they take a lot of lymph nodes out. They
have to whatever the there maybe 10
lymph nodes you need to get and send
those lymph nodes to pathology. And so
they get them first by feeling them uh
and then they put them in a a cont a
little area and then they go off to
pathology. And so we said, well, we can
actually just put them on our imaging
system and count the number of lymph
nodes, help them dissect that out and
then send them over to pathology. And so
that's the one that was rejected
multiple times by NIH, but then we
developed it on our own and this company
called Sision Vision. We got one of the
best inventions of 2023, invited to the
the White House and got a moonshot. And
now we're in 15 hospitals. So it went
from first prototype to hospitals in
three years and we've seen thousands of
patients and we've helped them we've
helped the pathologists um find lymph
nodes that they did not see during
regular palpation methods and have been
able to restage um CA patients with
cancer. Okay, so you didn't know I was
going to talk about asteroids but now
we're switching topics. But are we
really switching topics? Okay, so
there's this asteroid called asteroid
benign. You might have heard about it.
It it travels at 63,000 miles per hour
and it's about 1,673 feet across. Um,
and NASA and like a big big group of uh
of amazing researchers sent a probe to
this. It was a seven-year round trip. It
went 63 million miles at least just in
that distance. Landed moving object
landed. Took pictures, real time images
of a probe landing on an asteroid.
collected samples, rocks, sent it back.
Those rocks were were taken back and um
and brought back to the lab. I mean,
that is amazing. And it cost about 1.16
billion, which I actually think was was
not that not that bad. And yet, in 2025,
we still don't have a way of going this
deep inside of a woman's
abdomen to find a a one millimeter sized
tumor on her fallopian tubes. Okay? So
most of us are scientists and engineers
in this room. Do we think that that is
true? Do we think we can't do it or do
we think that we haven't applied enough
uh effort to figure out how to do it? Um
and so when I talk to people, they go,
"But yeah, Angie, cancer is really
really hard." I'm thinking asteroids,
yes, are are also really really hard.
And so what what we're doing is we're
putting together a group of engineers
and surgeons um working in many
different aspects of ovarian cancer. Can
we find it? Can we understand the
origins of precancer lesions, precancer
lesions? Can we intercept them? Can we
prevent them? You know, can we treat
them? Can we make them more receptive to
imunotherapies? And that's a big group.
Um, so my my uh surgical collaborator
during the pandemic, I was on a Zoom
with her. During the pandemic, I was on
a Zoom with her. I didn't know her. It
was a big Zoom. And she's talking about
when women have their fallopian tubes
taken out. Here's kind of a drawing of
it. It actually takes about five minutes
to have your fallopian tubes taken out.
Um, and I'm part of a public health
trans campaign that says when women are
under going to have like gallbladder,
appendicitis or something in their past
childbearing years, they um they should
go ahead and have their floating tubes
taken out. Takes additional five minutes
to do that and can be life-saving. But
women that are doing this for uh
prevention, if they're BRCA one or two
positive, um they they have their
fallopian tubes taken out and then
they're put in wax and they're sectioned
and about 1% of the fallopian tube is
looked at because the fallopian tube is
kind of big. I'll show you real pictures
of fallopian tubes in a minute. And she
goes, "We need a way to scan to look at
the whole fallopian tube." I'd never met
her before and I just instant messenger.
I go, "That's actually pretty easy. you
know, we can um we can we can solve
that, you know, pretty quickly if we're
using hyperspectral imaging in near
imaging. So, we she's actually one of my
best friends now. She's usually well,
she gets up at 4:30 in the morning.
She's a surgeon, but um she's um usually
one of the first people I talk to uh
every day. So, now for um patients that
are undergoing it's calledctomy, which
means they're having their fallopian
tubes taken out. They're taken out um at
John's Hopkins University where she's
head of gynecological oncology and we
have an IRB for this. Um they're sent in
organ transport media to MIT. We they're
barcoded, we c we categorize them um and
we start to image them. Um and we have a
database uh for this. Um and so we we
have we've seen over 50 patients now. We
categorize just optically all the
fallopian tubes that come in into the
lab. Um we do their biometrics their um
we we look at many different aspects of
them and you know no no two fallopian
tubes are the same and even no two
fallopian tubes in any woman are
actually the same. They have this
beautiful kind of fluffy end here that's
the one that not not physic it bumps up
against but it's not connected to this
region here not connected to to the
ovaries and this is where the p-53
mutations start and this is where the
precancer lesions start. So we do all
the biometrics of them. We look at uh
specimens from BRC patients versus
non-BRC patients and collect a lot of
data about this. We're trying to have
the biggest database of of fresh
fallopian tubes. If someone out here has
a bigger one, let me know. Um we can uh
collaborate. Um and so but people never
really so when when I go to these
meetings um and there's probably
radiologists in here, you can correct me
on this, but but they say to me, they
say fallopian tubes are really hard to
see inside of a woman. um they're really
hard to see because they look so much
like the the area around it. It's hard
to see by contrast enhanced CT. It's
hard to see by uh ultrasound, which my
my collaborator Sangita Batia is working
on new probes for that. Um and it's hard
to see um by um MRI because it looks
like the rest of the image. But if
you're looking at it under hyperspectral
image, if you scan the whole thing
between zero and 1800 nanometers
wavelength, you can find a wavelength
where floopin tubes pop out where you
can see them very very carefully. And so
we've done that. We've been
collaborating with um um pathologists at
Johns Hopkins where they are finding the
newest biomarkers for these precancer
lesions sending those we're attaching
either probes like these probes I showed
you that are fluorescent uh and looking
at that uh as well and so we make we
build these hyperspectral cubes uh at
many different wavelengths to try to
understand fallopian tubes both healthy
and non-healthy and then we start to
narrow down what wavelengths are the
best wavelengths of light for looking at
fallopian tubes. tubes, normal fallopian
tubes or um or um or ones that have um
um different kinds of
mutations. Um and here they are at
different wavelengths of light and
they're quite beautiful and they're
quite they're not invisible. Um you just
have to know how to look for them. Um I
think I already said, okay, here's the
cool thing though. After we look at
these fallopian tubes, we put them we we
fix them and we send them back to John's
Hopkins um where they we tattoo them and
they look for places that that we've
tattooed and they're able to find
regions that they did not see otherwise
and these are actually they could be
stick some of them could be stick
lesions but some of them are are
actually areas of inflammation and maybe
areas that are pre-stick lesions and so
once we have those we're working with
Krypa Veronasi another amazing inventor
he's a mechanical engineer He um you
have to look him up. His inventions are
amazing. Um we um so my friend Becky
said, "Oh, Angie can figure out how to
remove the cells." And Angie can't
figure out how to remove the cells, but
Krypa can figure out how to move the
cells. He's an expert in interfaces. So
he's developing technology to on these
these fallopian tubes from the patient
just to remove the cells from these
stick lesions, keep them viable, grow
them in so we can grow them into
organoids and study the development of
of those. um and we can culture them. We
can build patient specific organoids
based on mutations. And my friend Sanga
Batia is doing a lot of amazing work,
but she's growing fallopian tubes on a
chip um so that we can study understand
the the the mutations and the processes
along the way. H I was over ambitious in
this talk. Okay. So um we're starting to
work with uh Anantha um Chandra Quesan.
He's the dean of engineering. Besides
being a dean of engineering, he he has
done amazing development in um low power
chips. That's that's what he does. I
thought he was dean of engineering, but
no, he's actually one of the most famous
people in the world at low power chips.
Um and so um we started working together
on uh on building AI models around all
of this and machine learning because we
have this database that um is very very
unique. Um so we we um we look at our
fallopian tubes based on on probes. look
at our fellow computers based on how
they interact with light. Um we build u
models around it and now we're building
new
chips. Um where we can actually do the
um AI on chip um while we're scanning
the um the fallopian tubes. Um we've
also started saying okay can we use um
different methods of of imaging um and
segmentation to tell whether a patient
is BRCA um positive or negative um
without doing genetic analysis. And we
right now we've only been doing this for
a couple of weeks. We have about 90%
accuracy in telling if a patient is BRCA
uh positive or negative. Um we um we do
this based on on uh on slides of known
patients. Um, and I'm not going to say
too much about this, but I'm very
excited about it. So, if you're
interested in it, contact me. We've also
done the same thing to see if we can
tell if a patient has a p-53 mutation or
not. Um, and we can do that with
97.89%
accuracy. Um, the other aspect of this
is um, we work with patients. I visit
um, ovarian cancer patients in the
hospital. I visit them in clinic. Um, I
visit on panels. Um we're working with a
program that is the it's kind of turning
Henrietta Lax on the head which is not
doing um research on patients but doing
research with patients. Um and um so
we're part of a program where the
patients um interact with the surgeon
obviously they interact with um with um
the engineer they interact with the
scientists so that they actually can own
their own data. Um when our um fallopian
tubes make it um they have a bow wallet.
They look at okay they made it to MIT.
They get to look at images of their
their um their uh fallopian tubes. As we
culture their fallopian tubes and as we
make organoids and if we make a new cell
line we let them be involved in naming
the cell line um that came from their
own um uh body. And this is the um
thought of Marielle Gross. I mean not
thought it's a vision of Marielle Gross
who's at Johns Hopkins and PET. She's a
bioethicist and a um a gynecologist and
she's uh developing this um interaction
so patients can see and understand where
their biopecimens are and actually learn
about the technology that's being used
in screening it. So um we're interested
in tackling ovarian cancer um in all
these ways. I've run out of time. Uh I
want to thank you for your attention. I
know I went quickly. Um I'll try to come
back later, but I can probably take a
few questions if it's allowed.
Thank you very much Andrea. So broad the
scope of our research starting from
battery. So we take a few questions. Uh
any people questions? Yes. Hi thank you.
Um very nice talk. So I had a question
are there any biomarkers in the blood
for ovarian cancers that can be
detected? And the second question is are
those genetic mutation involved in other
type of cancer? Yes. So the answer are
um that there are um groups that are
looking um for biomarkers in uh in
ovarian cancer um but they're usually in
kind of later stage ovarian cancer. So
we're interested in u finding them much
earlier um and u my my collaborator
Senita Bates she's an expert in um
biomarkers and biomarker amplification
um and we're going back to the sticks
and pre-stick lesions looking for
biomarkers. She's developed uh an
optical uh amplification. Uh you can
look up uh her work or I can talk to you
more about it. And we want to find those
biomarkers in blood um in papsmears um
or in um um blood passes. Oh, you're in.
Yeah. Uh there was a second question. Do
you have a second question? Yeah. Yeah.
If the the mutation are involved in
other Yes. So p-53 so uh p-53 mutations.
Yes. Um BA mutations are also um in in
breast cancer as well. Um and uh p-53
mutations are in uh many kinds of
cancers. The technology we developed
because someone asked us can we do other
kinds of mutations we've done for Kas
Kas as well which um we're developing um
a optical um screen for very very early
um colon cancer as well.
Thank you.
Please use the mic so that the uh online
audience can hear. Hey, thanks Angela.
Uh two two questions. How do you keep
track of everything that's going on in
your mind? Do you write them down in a
notebook or how does that work? Here's
the key. You hire really smart people.
Um and so yeah, so I do have a
photographic memory. I had a
photographic memory when I was uh
younger. It's fading. Um but um one of
the things if you say, "Angie, what are
you good at?" I'm uh good at building
amazing teams. Um and um uh I don't
actually do any of the work myself. You
know, the students do all the work and
that's the best thing about being at MIT
is that our students are just and our
posttos are just the best. Um and um is
that bias? I guess it's bias. Sorry. Um
but um and so I meet with my teams and
my sub teams um a couple times a week.
Um and um I'm doing I'm living my dream.
Um and I only work on things I'm
interested in. That also helps. Um and
um I can't always keep the track keep
track of all the details but I do have
uh it's the team that that you build. Um
and um I'm a specialist at building good
teams. Amazing. Thank you. Just uh a
second question. Uh what percentage of
your work is commercialized by students
versus experienced entrepreneurs versus
industry partners? Yeah, I think that's
a great a great question. Um and so um
the last two companies uh Jensen um was
um um which um started out as a gene
therapy um uh company that was um spun
out by a graduate student uh of mine um
uh a team um and Yanga um and the um the
other company Sision Vision was uh spun
out by a postoc of mine um Jeremy Lee
and I showed you uh his picture. Uh my
first two companies were spun out by
myself with venture capital um and then
integrated in with with companies. Um
I'm spinning out a company right now on
high surface area carbons. I'm not sure
how that's going to work out. Um right
now I'm working with a a major mining
company where we've just done some
really cool work on rare earths. Um that
um I hope to do in collaboration with
them. So I'm I'm I'm a I want it to work
out well for my lab. Um I want to only
do things that are translatable.
um to help people or the planets. And so
what I don't want is someone to grab
something, put it on the shelf, and
never see the light of day. So I don't
have a model. Um I want to help my
students succeed. Um and I want to be um
involved uh because uh um so it's it
just it just it's different for
different ones. I've worked with uh a
lot of these ILP members that are up
here before um tech develop technologies
including I saw um one by um I saw ENI,
the Italian energy company. We developed
these um calcium carbonate based um
tiles um from yeast to grab uh excess
CO2 use paper waste paper pulp to make
tiles that was done in collaboration.
People usually come to me and say,
"Angie, I have this problem." Um, and
I'll look at the problem. I say, "First
of all, am I interested in it?" Um,
second, is it a problem that we can make
an impact in? And many of the problems
we can't. It's just not a it's not in
our our toolkit. Um, but then if it is,
then we jump on it and we try to find
partners for that.