Okay. So last time we talked about at
towards the end we talked about
sequences
and so in particular we talked about
square root of two right. a square root
of two. We could think about this if we
wanted to think about square root two on
the real line. Then we have here one and
we have two.
And we could define a sequence of
numbers where the first one is one, the
second one is 1.4,
the third is 1.4.1 4.1
and the next one is then the next digit
in square of two. So 1.4.1.4
etc.
And so so this is like a sequence of
numbers that are increasing uh and it is
square root of two where you're taking
more and more digits. Right?
So square root of two
is in some sense the limit
of this sequence.
And so precisely a sequence uh is so we
talked about that last time but let me
just remind you what that is. So a
sequence
is uh is a function
from the natural numbers. So f goes from
the natural numbers into the real
and the value at some natural number n.
the value of this function at a natural
number and this we denote usually it's a
standard notation then one denote it
like this with where the n is a
subscript okay
uh and so let's uh let's take a look at
a couple of different uh sequences. So
we told that so this here really is a
sequence. Uh another example is
um where you have a n = minus1
to the power n.
So uh so n again is is this natural
number. So this means that this sequence
a1 is equal to minus1 a2 is equal to -1
* -1. So that's one. A3 is -1 * -1
* -1.
So this is min -1 and a4 is -1
multiplied itself four times. So that's
one. Right? So this sequence here is
it's it's alternating
between the values
uh minus one and one.
So it's starting off at minus one and
then it goes to one and it goes to minus
one one minus one etc.
Okay. And so this sequence here right it
doesn't really right it's not you know
it doesn't really converge it it's not
it doesn't really have a limits right so
this here we'll make this precise in
just a minute so this sequence does not
have a limit
uh another an example of a sequence is
is a decaying sequence like this. So a n
is equal to 1 / n
right? So so a1 is equal to 1, a2 is
equal to a half, a3 is equal to a3 and
then a4 is equal to 1/4. Right? So these
numbers here are all positive. Right?
the the values of a is all all of them
are all positive and they become smaller
and smaller right
so you could write that sort of
suggestively this here is going down
like that
and so right so it seems sort of obvious
that this limit here
uh that this sequence has a limit this
here has a limit
and the limit is zero.
Okay. So now let me make the formal
definition. So so what does it mean that
a sequence is convergent?
So um a sequence
uh a n is convergent
to uh to to a. So a is another real
number
is a sequence a n is converging to a if
the following is the case.
If the following hold
uh for all epsilon
for all epsilon greater than zero
there exist
there exist an
anal
number
such that
if little n
is bigger than this natural number then
the difference between a n and the
supposed limit is bounded by epsilon.
Okay. So if you think about it, so if
you think about it on the here you have
on the real line here you have a
and so if you give me an epsilon
so then I'm looking at a here I'm
looking at an interval around a so this
is an interval here from a minus epsilon
to a plus epsilon
and the claim is that the sequence a n
is converging to a if there exists some
n. So that if n is little n is larger
than this capital n then all of these a
n lands somewhere here right all of them
a n is in this little integer for
n uh little n bigger than this capital n
right that's what it means to be
convergent right but it's like for all
epsilon so you you allowed to you know
someone else else is allowed to pick the
epsilon and then you have to prove that
there exist a capital n so that from
there on and out all of the a lie in
this little interval. Okay.
So this is what it means for a sequence
to be convergent. So we say that a n is
convergent
uh to a if this here is the case and in
that case
in that case
one also writes that uh that the limit
as n goes to infinity of a n is equal to
a
a sequence.
So if you have a sequence or a sequence
that is not convergent
uh is said to be divergent.
Okay.
And so now let me
look at an example.
Um, so suppose you're looking at
the number 0.9999
etc. Right? This number here, this is
really this number here, we really think
about this number here as one. This is
indistinguishable from one, right?
And in fact what you really think about
is that you think about that you have a
sequence
uh a where a1 is 0.9
a2 is 0.999
a3 is 0.999
A4 is equal to 0.999
9 9
etc. Right? So a n
is where you have zero point
and then nine
n times
right? If you're looking at that
sequence here, right?
Then you have that this sequence a n is
convergent
to one. So a n
this one also write that is convergent
to one like this. So a n is convergent
to one. Right? So there's various ways
of writing that is convergent. You can
write it like this. This means that it's
convergent and the limit is a. You can
write it like this. This means that the
sequence is convergent and the limit is
one. Right? Or you can write it out in
words.
Okay. Um so so this sequence I claim
that this sequence here defined like
this and this is really how you think
about this right when you think about
this number you sort of think about it
that's you know this is you know 0 9
with more and more uh numbers nines
added and the limit which is really what
this number here in itself is is one.
Okay. Now let me explain why the
sequence defined this way why this is
convergent as a limit one. Okay.
And so so now
so now of course now
you give me an epsilon. So given epsilon
given epsilon greater than zero
then I need to find a capital n so that
from there on and out the a is within
epsilon. So we need to find
to for this epsilon we need to find
capital n so that if little n is bigger
than this capital n then a n minus one
is less than epsilon right that's what
we need to do right
but for your epsilon so to do that
we need to choose this capital n.
So I'm just choosing
uh I just choose capital n. So to do
that choose
capital n such that
uh that 1 / n is less than epsilon.
Right? We can do this by the archimedian
property. Right. So this is uh so we can
find
n by the
uh such an n
and capital n by the archimedian
property
that we discussed last time.
Okay.
But now you see if you're looking at
if you take
if you now
if you now look at little n that is
bigger than capital n then you have that
one minus a n. Well, 1 minus a n
actually for all n this here is less
than
uh 1 / 10
to the power n right because like if n
is equal to 1 this is this here this is
within one10th of one and likewise this
here is in 100 of one etc. Right? So we
have this inequality. It's actually
equality in this case. This here is a
equality.
Okay. But now you see that this thing
here this is obviously 1 / 10 ^ n. It's
lesser equal to it's actually it's less
than uh n 1 / n. And so if little n is
bigger than capital n, this is therefore
less than 1 / capital n. But this here
was less than epsilon. And that's what
we needed to prove. Right?
So for the given for your given epsilon,
I specify a capital n and then we need
to prove that if little n is bigger than
that capital n, then we come within
epsilon of the limit. Okay.
Um
okay. Now let me prove a little theorem
about uh convergence sequences.
Then this is like if you will this
little lema
is like the first test for whether a
sequence is convergent.
So still
if
a end is a convergent
sequence
then
uh a n
need uh then a n is bounded.
Sorry, let me explain what I mean by
that. I mean that then the set of a n so
just explain that. So then the set
um the set a1 a2
a3
etc. This set here is bounded
Okay,
it's not enough to be bounded that to be
convergent but it is a necessary
criteria.
[Applause]
Let me just as a side remark say that
that if you're looking at the sequence a
n that we looked at just a minute ago
this here that is alternating between
minus1 and one right this is a bounded
sequence because the value there's only
two values so it's obviously bounded but
it's not convergent right so but it is a
necessary for a sequence to be
convergent is necess necessary that the
sequence of of numbers here uh is uh is
bounded for for okay so
so now let's try to prove that
so
we have so since
a n is convergent
Then there is some a so that a end in
converts to this a right
and so now I can I can just focus on one
single epsilon. So in particular
[Applause]
if we choose
epsilon to be equal to one then there
exist
then there exist capital n. So that if
little n is bigger than this capital n
then a little n minus a is less than
one. Right? This is this is that is
convergence just applied to this single
epsilon. Right?
Okay. And so now
so now so this is the first observation.
The second observation is that if we now
look at all the a that are not
considered here. So if you're looking at
the set the set
this is the first
capital a
capital n minus one a n right those are
the ones that doesn't fall in under that
this little n is bigger than the capital
n so this set here is finite
so obviously So for any finite set you
have that. So there exist
Cal
number
such that
that A N is less or equal to C for any
of these guys. Right?
For any A in this
any A in
[Applause]
uh in this finite set.
Right? So this means in other words this
means that a n is less or equal to c if
n here is between one and n minus one.
Right?
So now I look at
So now I look at uh now I want to look
at the numbers a n and um this number
here
right and I want to look at so I'm
thinking about the set
uh a absolute value
and where in here is
one up to one two etc. Right?
Well, I claim that this thing here I can
now prove that this set here is bounded
and this is just because that the first
uh n minus one those are bounded by c.
So I claim that this set here so claim
is that that uh that uh the soup
of this set
where n uh from one
over all ends
the soup of this set is uh is lesser
equal to
the max
of C and A + normal absolute value of A
+ one. So I claim that right. Now this
is clearly if you're taking the first n
minus one
then we already know that they are
bounded by c right so you just need to
worry about the one starting at capital
n right so we only need to worry about
when so this is obviously the case for
the first capital n minus one so we only
need to worry about only need
to show this
for little n
larger than capital n larger equal.
Yeah.
>> Um are you explain the max over there
why there's the absolute value of a plus
the plus one?
>> Yeah, I I would explain this and then I
I'll get to this and this is part part
of the proof. Yeah. So it it hopefully
it will be clear in a minute. If it's
not, you you should complain.
Okay. So I only need to prove that when
I'm just looking at the set here and I'm
starting at capital N, then the soup is
bounded like that.
And so then I so I'm looking at a n
but a n I can write as a end I can write
sort of in a stupid way I can write a n
as a n minus a
plus a right so I can write it like that
right
and then I can just right so I have the
sum of two things the absolute value is
less than the absolute value the sum of
the absolute values.
So I have this right.
But now you see that since little n is
bigger than this capital n this capital
n was chosen so that this here was
bounded by one. Right? So this thing
here is less than one and this here is
less than the absolute value of a.
Right?
And so we have for the whole tail
starting at capital n we have that this
thing here is bounded by one plus the
absolute value of a and for the
remaining capital n minus one those are
bounded by c right and so so together
all of this is bounded by the maximum of
these two things.
Okay.
Now the next thing I want to talk about
is that there's there's some sort of
algebraic property of limits
that is often very useful.
Um,
and I will prove there's four of these.
Um, and I will prove two of them and the
other one I will
um I will outline the proof of
>> Y.
>> So in that the soup is Oh, soup is less
than. So we we don't need to find
>> Yeah. No, you don't need to actually
find the soup, right? Yeah. And and the
reason I want to write soup and not
maximum is that of course if it's
infinite numbers, it's not clear that is
a maximum, right? So we need to use the
the terminology soup.
>> So that that max of CN
+ one is not a soup.
>> No, no, that's right. is is a bound for
the soup but but the soup presumably is
is is less
>> and one there really just one
>> and the one really to some extent could
be almost anything. Yeah, it's a it came
from the epsilon, right? But you see if
you made that epsilon smaller then then
probably the c would jump up, right?
Because that is you right because the c
was the maximum of the first n minus
one. So if you're further out then there
are more numbers that you're taking the
maximum over. So anyway yeah.
Okay. So so we want to prove some
algebraic properties
of limits.
Okay.
So, so the idea is that we take um so we
have four of these
and the first one is that you take a
sequence. So maybe I would just say
throughout a n and bn are sequences.
uh and a n is convergent to a
and bn
is convergent to b. Okay.
The first one, the first property is
that if you take a real number, sorry,
if you take a real number, C here is a
real number
and you form a new sequence
where CN is just this real number
times A N. Right? So each CN is somehow
almost like a N except that they're
multiplied by this fixed constant C. So
this here so the first one is that CN is
also convergent
uh and the limit is just C * A.
Okay.
The second one is that um that if you
take that a if you define a sequence. So
this is a different sequence that this
one. But if you define a sequence cn by
its a n the nth element is a n + bn
then this sequence is also convergent.
Cn is convergent and the limit is a + b.
So that was the second property.
[Applause]
The third property.
The third property
uh is
uh right the third property is that if
you take a product sorry so if you take
a n if you take if you define cn as a n
* bn right so this is a new sequence
then cn
is convergent and the limit is a * b and
the Last property is
that if um if the a
um are
uh all of these are different from zero.
So this here is for all n
and also you have that the limit here is
not equal to zero.
uh then
if you define a sequence to be 1 / a n
then cn here converge and the limit is
one away.
Okay.
And so I will prove sort of rigorously
the first two and I will basically tell
you how to prove the other two. But I
the first two I will kind of write out
um formally as you know as we talked
about last time how you write formal
approve whereas the what I'm going to
discuss for three and four is very very
close to a formal proof but it's more
like what you would have on a piece of
scrap There you go.
Okay. So now,
so now let's prove the first one.
So prove of one
So since
so given
epsilon greater than zero
since
so yeah so first of all of course if
this capital C
if this capital C is zero then
everything is zero So it's like trivally
the case. So we may as well assume So
may as well assume that's capital C
that capital C is not zero.
So now given epsilon greater than zero
since this sequence a n is converging to
a this means that there exist
there exist
n such that and now I'm not going to use
that epsilon you gave me that epsilon
uh I'm not going to use that epsilon in
the definition that a end is converging
to a. I'm not going to use that one, but
I'm going to use one that is closely
related. I'm going to use epsilon
divided by the norm of c. Right? Because
that's another positive fine. So you
gave me an epsilon.
I'm going to look at this number here.
That's a positive number.
And I can use that in the definition
that a n converts to a. So I'm going to
say that because a n converts to a there
exist a capital n such that if little n
is bigger than this capital n then a n
minus a
uh is less than epsilon over capital s
uh c sorry a norm of capital c right but
now I just multiply on both sides So
multiply
by
by the absolute value of capital C on
both sides.
And so if we do that then this here pops
in right it actually go in as c * a n
minus c * a
is less than epsilon and this is as long
as this n little n is bigger than that
capital n. This is exactly what we
wanted to prove. Right?
Okay. Now the second one
is
right. So the reason why I'm doing the
the first two
you see you see that those are pretty
straightforward. I mean it's not like
that it's it's not like any of these is
complicated to prove. Um the next two is
a little bit more uh I mean I wouldn't
say complicated but a little bit more
involved these two and but I want to
give you the idea because it's a kind of
a very simple but useful idea uh in
these two
so I I don't want to skip the the proof
okay so now uh we uh so we want to prove
the second property
Okay.
So we have that. So we have that a n is
converging to a and bn is converging to
b. And so again you give me an epsilon
that I have to work with. So given
epsilon
given
epsilon greater than zero
then I'm going to not again use this
epsilon in the definition that a n
converts to a and I'm not going to use
it in the definition that bn is
converging to b but I'm going to use
epsilon over two in each of them. So
since
a n converts to a there exist
there exist
a capital n and let me call it capital n
subscript a such that
if little n is bigger than this capital
n subscript a then a n minus A
is less than epsilon / 2, right?
[Applause]
And likewise,
likewise,
since um since BN converts to B, then
there exist
there exist just a capital n but and I
denote it by this this may be different
than the one coming from a the sequence
a n
such that
if little n is bigger than this capital
n subscript b then uh bn minus b is
smaller than epsilon / 2. Okay.
And so now I have to choose right. So
you gave me the epsilon and I have to
choose a capital n. I haven't chosen
that yet but I will do that now. So we
set so set
capital n equal to the maximum of these
two ends.
So you're setting it equal to the
maximum of these two. Now if little n so
then for
little n bigger than this capital n if
you're looking at a so now we want to
look at so our sequence cn was the sum
of these two right so this here was cn
so we want to prove that so we want to
look at cn minus a * b and we want to
prove that if little n is bigger than
this then this here is strictly less
than epsilon right but this thing here
is
cn was by definition a n plus bn
sorry and this was not a product it was
a sum
um minus
a + b
so but this thing here you can write as
a n minus a
plus bn minus b.
And now you can just take the absolute
value of this. It's bounded by the
absolute value of the first.
[Applause]
So plus the absolute value of the
signal,
right?
And now you see that if um if little a
uh if little a
let me keep. So if little a
sorry if little n since little n is
bigger than capital n which is bigger
than capital n of a in particular then
this thing here is less than epsilon /
two. Right? So you have that CN minus A
+ B
is less than epsilon / two that comes
from this. But you also have that
capital n is bigger equal to n subb. So
you also have that this thing here is
less than epsilon / two. Right?
So, so you have that this thing here
when little a is big n is bigger than
this capital n this thing here this
difference is strictly less than epsilon
that's what we needed to prove in order
to prove that this sequence that was a
sum of the two sequences converging to
the sum of the limits yeah
>> um we initially defined like
a less than epon what was the
justification for why we could
If we know that convers
>> right so that's right so because a n or
bn because they converge so like say a n
converts to a right then for all epsilon
you gave me the epsilon but and I'm
using that it's converging not just when
for that choice of epsilon but also even
for epsilon over two right that epsilon
if you right so you gave me the epsilon
then I'm using that is converting so I
will have to choose probably a n that is
much larger if I'm using epsilon over
two than if I use directly the epsilon
>> so it assumes that n increases like
epsilon gets smaller where
>> as epsilon gets smaller presumably you
need to choose capital n larger
>> okay so you couldn't run into a case
where we're assuming like the
convergence is like smooth as was like
oscillating about
>> right right that's right I mean so so
um right I'm just I'm using that for I'm
basically using that for all epsilon
that it wasn't just for a fixed epsilon
right and so that's why when you came
with this epsilon then I'm actually used
it for epsilon over two yeah
okay so that was the first two property
those are the the it's not like the
other one is super difficult. Uh but but
that was but those two are the most
straightforward. Let's look at the other
two.
And so right in particular because it's
like a like for the next one there's a
little trick that is useful in in
various different settings.
Um
and so so prove but but the next two I
will just outline. Okay.
So
proof
of three.
So outline.
So we need to look at a n time bn right
that's so cn is is a n * bn and we want
to compare cn with a * b
right we want to show that this thing
here if little n is sufficiently large
so given h epsilon if little n is
sufficiently large then this difference
is bounded by epsilon
but this thing here is a n bn minus a b.
Okay.
But and so the little trick is now that
in itself it's kind of difficult to
compare these two things. But the little
trick is that if you're looking at A and
B and if you sort of
by instead of comparing them directly
then comparing this with something that
is halfway between this and that then it
gets a lot easier. So what you do is
you're looking at A and B and and you
subtract A and B and then you add it
immediately again.
So this is certainly the same, right?
And now I can write this thing here as a
N. I can just concentrate on these two
first and there I can factor out a in.
So I can write that as this.
And this thing here I can factor out at
B,
right? So I can write it like that.
And now now you see this is like it
looks much more promising. This one look
like the problematic one. This one looks
like no problem at all because this is
just some fixed constant times this
difference here. This one looks a little
bit more problematic because it's not a
fixed constant, right? But we'll deal
with this in just a second. But the
first thing I can do is I just take the
absolute value of this
plus the absolute value of that.
And now I just take so so then this here
is actually the same for a product. You
can just take the product of the
absolute value.
It's the same.
Okay.
Now,
now
the next thing is that we're going to
use the theorem that we proved earlier
that since
since this sequence here
since these numbers here all of these
numbers for all when you take right when
you take the set
um when you're looking at this set
this set here since this set here is
bounded
and it's bounded because the sequence
was converging right and so we already
prove that then the the values the set
of values is a bounded set right so it's
bounded and so we can assume so there
exist
See, so that
uh A is the absolute value is bounded by
the C, right?
And so now so now I have and and um
Okay. And so now I uh have that uh CN
minus A * B.
This is what I had up there. And I'm
just using that this is now bounded by
just because these thing here are
bounded by C. I get C B N minus B plus B
over A N minus A. Right.
And now you see now it's going to follow
like so so so this here was just some
observations right and now when you come
to the proof so to prove
to prove
uh three
then given
given epsilon greater than zero.
Now we want to make sure that this thing
here is less than epsilon / two and that
this thing here is less than epsilon /
two and so I don't want to get in
trouble if this here was zero or if this
was zero. So I'm just so given epsilon
since
a n converts to a then I can um um find
now I'm basically writing out the whole
proof but a n I can find capital a n
sorry capital n a so that if little n is
bigger than capital n a
then you have that a n minus A is less
than I don't quite use that epsilon and
I don't quite use epsilon over two but I
take absolute value I multiply it like
this
okay because I don't want to have
something where if b was zero then it
really didn't make any sense what I
wrote so now there's no problem it
definitely makes sense even if b is zero
and likewise
likewise since
uh
so likewise
likewise
since since BN converts to B
then there exist
so again you you gave me a uh epsilon.
So there exist a np such that
if little n is bigger than np
then actually you have that bn
minus b
is less than epsilon again over two and
this is not quite what I use because I
don't want to be in trouble. That's c is
already non- negative because it's
bigger than these absolute value. So,
but I'm just adding one for the same
reason. And so now you see that if
little n so therefore
if little n is bigger than the maximum
of these two then both of these
inequality hold
right both of them hold and so this
means that you now have that cn minus a
* b this thing here so we had it here
this is less and C.
And then this difference here was now
assumed to be epsilon over 2
1 + c.
And likewise
this here
is bounded by
this number here times
and then this this thing here.
So epsilon
over two uh absolute value of b + one.
Okay.
And but now you see that this thing here
that's c divided by 1 + c that's bounded
by one. Right? So this thing here is
bounded by epsilon / two.
And this thing here same reason is that
this thing here is bounded by epsilon
/2.
And so the whole thing was bounded by
epsilon uh when uh when little n was
bigger than the maximum of these two. So
this in the end I I wrote out the whole
proof, right? Um in the I already posted
the lecture notes. In the lecture notes,
I didn't write out the whole proof, but
I gave the idea. So I sort of stopped
once we were here and somewhere here
after this one somewhere anyway. But you
see
okay so the
right so the next thing I want to talk
about is that if you no no I still need
uh property four and that's also useful
sorry so let let's go through that and
then then we'll come to subsequences
So I want to prove that if you take a
sequence of real numbers none of them is
zero they converge and the limit is not
zero then one over the sequence is
another convergence sequence.
Okay.
But but again just the main takeaway the
main takeaway I think from property this
third property was that this little idea
about inserting something that was
halfway between the two things you were
comparing because they weren't very easy
to compare directly and that's like a
little trick that is useful in various
places it comes up almost the same thing
one place it comes up is what's called
lightness rule that if you take two
functions and you take the product of
these two functions and you try to prove
that what is the derivative of the
product. It's exactly the same trick and
it comes up various other you know more
fancy ways.
Okay. So now let's look at let's prove
property
four.
So property form group of property form.
So we have this. So CN is 1 / a n and we
know that a n are not equal to zero and
we know that a is not equal to zero.
This here makes sense and and also 1 / a
makes sense. So we want to compare this
here with one away.
And so this thing here is 1 / a n minus
1.
And now I can put it on a common
denominator. So this is a - a n / a n *
a.
So like that
can write it like this. Right? Now
already the denominator looks very
promising because we know that this goes
to zero. Right?
And and now
but now I need to bound says so need to
bound
uh right. So need to bound we need to
bound.
So we we want to bound this here right
by epsilon when little n is sufficiently
large
the top the nominator here looks great
the denominator
maybe we're a little bit worried about
but the thing is that so we need to
bound
a n times a this here from
from below
Well, we want to bound it from below
because then when you're looking at one
over it, then that's an upper bound,
right?
And really because a here is just a
fixed number that is not zero, then it's
equivalent to proving. So it's this is
this this is equivalent
to bound
the norm of a n from below.
Remember we we don't need to bound it
from below for all a n but we need to
bound it from below for a for n
sufficiently large right
and so now you you make the trivial
observation so that a n you can write a
n as a n minus a plus a right
and so therefore uh therefore the norm
of a n is bounded by the norm of a n
minus a plus the norm of a.
Sorry, this was not the this was not
this was uh this was not how I want to
write it. I'm going to write it slightly
differently.
I'm going to write a
I'm going to do the symmetric syn thing
but I'm I'm doing it so I'm writing a n
as a min so I'm writing a as a minus a n
plus a n right
and then then if I do that then I can
just take the absolute value of a is
bounded by the absolute value of this
difference plus the absolute value of a
in right
and now I can move this here over on the
other side. So this here implies
that norm of a
minus the norm of a minus a n
is lesser equal
to this here. Right?
And now you see that this thing here is
so so now we're going to use that uh
this here was not equal to zero. So this
here is bounded away from zero.
And so now we can
we can take say a here
uh over two. So we can use this here. We
can use a norm of a over two. This is a
positive number because a was not zero.
And we can use this in the definition of
that a n. So use this. So, so use this
in the definition
of that
a converts to a right. So this means
that if you are this means that there
exist
a capital n let's call a capital n1.
It's not the final n that we want to use
but there exist a capital n1. So that if
little n is bigger than this capital n1
then actually we have that a n
a minus a n
is less than
this thing here.
Right?
But now you see that this means that
when you're looking at when you go up
here and you're looking at when you go
up to that line be before. So this is
the line from before.
Sorry this here minus this here. This
and this.
When you're looking at this line here,
well, this thing here, this here is at
most half of this. So, this thing here
is bigger than
this thing here over two, right?
And so, now you see that we have bounded
these guys from below, right?
And so now we go back up to So now we go
back up to we're looking at C minus
sorry we're looking at CN
- 1 / A.
This is this is this
up here. I'm just I'm just uh I'm just
transferring that equation down to this
board here.
So this here is a n a minus
a n
divided by and I can just take the
absolute value separately of the
denominator and the denominator a n
* a.
Okay. So, so now you see that this thing
here as long as so when
n here little n is bigger than n1
but then we have that this thing here is
at the very least the absolute value of
uh a over two. So this means that this
thing here we can now bound from from
above
like this. This is as long as you have
this inequality here and this thing this
is just a norm of a this give another
norm of a over two so the two jumps up
so it's like this thing here
right
and now you see that
now you see that this egg is just like a
constant Right? So this means that I may
have to go even further out than N1. But
if I go even further out, then I can
make this in here smaller than the given
epsilon.
Okay.
All right. So this was like the outline
if you will, but that's not at this
point there's not very much to fill in.
Right.
Okay. So now I want to talk about uh
subsequences.
And then I want to then I want to prove
a little theorem about subsequence.
So,
so I have a sequence
and uh and so I have a sequence
and then a subsequence. So I'll give you
first some examples and then I will
explain uh then I will give you the
proper definition of what a uh what a
subsequence is. So I start with
uh
this sequence from before. So this was a
sequence where a1 was minus1 a2 was one
a3 was minus1. it was alternating
between minus one and one.
And so in this case here, in this case
here, if you take
[Music]
uh this sequence, let's call it
uh
let's call it B
uh let's call it um let's use a
different index. Let's call it B K.
This is right. So k here play the same
role as n before but I want to use a
different symbol to not somehow confuse
with the n over here.
So if I take so I could take a sequence
that was like one all the time. This
here for all K.
This here would be a subsequence. This
would correspond to that you took all
the the even ones, right? That you you
just take all the even ones, right? So
this is like a sub.
You could also have another example. So
this is example one. See another example
is where you took all the odd ones.
So this here is is also a subsequence
and you could do something more
elaborate
where you take say first you take the
first two odd and then you take the next
two even. So you could have a sequence
that was like B1 is equal to minus1
B2
is equal to minus1 B3. Now it becomes
the next two even ones and then you go
back to the next two odd ones etc. Okay,
that would be another u subsequence.
Um, let me look at a few more examples.
So for instance, if
your sequence, your original sequence,
so here's another example.
If your original sequence
was just that a n was equal to n, right?
Then you could take a sequence. So then
the sequence where you just take the odd
numbers.
This here is a subsequence.
And likewise if you take all the just
the even numbers
this is also a a sequence a subsequence.
Okay.
Um but if you're looking at if you look
at say something like this where you're
taking so if you define a sequence where
it was one
one
uh one one two even like this.
This here is not a subsequence. This is
not a subsequence.
Because you have what you have done here
is that you have taken the same number
several times and it doesn't appear
several times. The value doesn't appear
several times in the original one. So
that's not allowed.
It's also not allowed to do something
like this. This here is also not a so
not a subsequence. Another thing that's
not a subsequent
when you take things out of order. So if
you do if this here was the original
sequence, if you're now looking at a
sequence that was three, two, and then
four, five. This here is etc. This here
is not a a subsequence either because
things are taken out of order. Okay.
So now what is the formal definition of
a subsequence?
So here's the formal definition.
[Music]
That's so if so you have a sequence a n
a subsequence
of a n
is where you have a map uh g
from n into n. This is a increasing map.
This is strictly increasing.
And then if you're thinking about this
thing here, right? You think about this
as a function f,
then you now could think about the
composition of these two functions.
So this thing here and maybe I would use
a different notation like this a
different uh index like this. This thing
here
BK this here is a subsequence right. So
you see that this here right when you
pick if you have a sequence like this
you know the first one could be anything
in the original one but once you have
fixed the first one you can't look back
or you can't go to this you have to the
next element have to be somewhat further
out in the sequence okay and and and
that sort of continue right
and this here is often just to indicate
that it's a subsequence of this
sequence. Then the standard notation is
a n and then another subscript.
Okay. So anyway, so of course hopefully
there's not too many subsequences of
sequences because each time it's
supposed to be another subscript.
Okay. Now there's a little theorem that
we can just prove here at the end and
that is that if you and and it's yeah
it's sometimes it's a it's a very simple
fact but it is sometimes a useful fact
and that is that if you take a sequence
so a sequence
it's a theorem
Um that's so so uh a sequence a n is
convergent
to a
if and only if
all subsequences
of a n
uh converge
to to a.
Okay. Now to prove this there's two
two things we need to prove right
because it's a if and only if statement.
So we need to prove that if it is
convergent then all subsequence are also
convergent and then we need to prove
that if all subsequence are convergent
then the original sequence is convergent
but one of the two implication is
trivial. So one of the two
implications
is trivial
and that is that namely
uh since
right so the the the map remember that
the map to define a subsequence has to
be strictly increasing, right? So that
so remember that a sequence was
a function like this.
That was a sequence, right? And a
subsequence there you have another map
that is strictly increasing
and then you're looking at the
composition. But if you take this other
map to be the identity, right? that that
the other map is like g of k is equal to
k of of course this is strictly
increasing right and if you did if you
if this hair map was the identity then
the subsequence would just be the
original sequence right so so one of the
two implication here is trivial since
a n itself
is
admittedly trivial still but it is a
subsequence.
So, so if all subsequences
converge to a well then the original
sequence since it is a subsequence
suddenly will converge right? So that
was trivial. Okay. Okay, so we not just
need to prove that if a end converts to
a then any subsequence
but this is not much more difficult
uh because you see
if you so given an epsilon
so now given epsilon
given so now so now we have so we we now
have
that a n converts to a and we're looking
at a subsequence a n and k and we want
to show
that a and k also converts to a right so
given epsilon
given epsilon greater than zero
there exist
um capital n
so that if little n is bigger than
capital n then a n minus a is less than
epsilon.
But now you see that if k is bigger than
capital n
then then what correspond to this here
is the right this is this here how to
think about it this here n k you should
really think about that this thing here
is the value of this strictly increasing
function right but this thing here is
because it's really increasing
is bigger than K. Right? So you see that
if this thing here is bigger than this,
then means that this index here is
further out than in particular the the
the capital N.
And so this means that if you have this
here, then a N k this is some
element like this but it's further out
than capital N. So this thing here
surely will also be less than epsilon
because it's fall in under here.
Okay. So that that that that
uh implication wasn't too much harder.
And that's sometimes useful
that so so like if
um yeah it's sometimes useful that
you're looking at a sequence
and um and you see that if it is
convergent that you you're looking at
you're looking at a sequence and you see
that there's a subsequence that is not
convergent or you have that there's two
different subsequence of a given
sequence that converts to different
limits. then then the original sequence
wasn't convergent either. Yeah.
>> Can you not have like a finite
subsequence of subsequence that like
doesn't get to end so hasn't arrived at
the point of convergence?
Um I mean so convergence is always
something about the tail about the end
right it's it it never care about what
happened in the beginning right so there
might be finally many ends initially
where you know things are crazy but then
from there on out
>> subsequences that we care about in this
case are those subsequences that also
>> yeah yeah so all sequences including
subsequences are infinite things, right?
Yeah. So like that's right. So because
the thing is that that you had to have
this map
uh maybe I erased it but G here has to
be a map from all the natural numbers
into N. So it means that for each
element here you get something right. So
there's really infinitely many of them.
Yeah.