okay getting complicated on it okay clip
it to the belt on the side right just
clip it right down okay good now you
have an on/off switch it'll be like you
put it on I don't touch the damn thing
everybody just talked with dr. Kovac I
don't like electronic gauges anymore I'm
just gonna move this to here all right
you know what we've done here is we've
lit an area at the podium we're going to
get a nice shot if you stay in that air
do you like to roam around a lot when
you're talking oh I'll talk right on the
phone is going to be for our tape that
microphone the air is going to see the
PA system in the house good we have your
tongue wonderful I hope it all working
good luck if it works you're the only
guy where I speak with works they
usually fit hello alright let me say
hello somehow those vocal like senior
fellows man I knew one our father maybe
we
that legacy who have you lectures since
all of the relevant information business
facts and things in this folder which I
believe has been passed out for everyone
I think rather than take any more time
on the quiet and let you hear the person
as you came here to here ladies and
gentlemen let me congratulate you first
to have in a boss who give the finest
introduction I've ever had and I've been
speaking for many years
thank you very much for being so brief
now you read as your chairman said this
fine description of mine here and I
would like to brag on one point what is
not contained is that I clear the goal
go to the National Aviation Hall of Fame
which is a pretty rare thing because I
saw bono Hine spoke here two years old
two speeches ago and he did not get it
and that's the only sense okay I'm glad
that to see so many of you interested in
a different type of engineering so in
order not to screw up completely with my
what I really want to teach you what I
want to tell you so that you learn
something from that speech I will begin
in front in Germany I was born there
which you saw under the book and before
you can be admitted or could be admitted
I don't know what it is now into an
engineering school in Germany you had
was mandatory to spend not two years but
three years of an apprenticeship
apprenticeship without pay now I
reintroduced and I will jump back and
forth several times in my talk today I
reintroduced in general ethic once I got
in charge over thousands of people and
ran a whole jet engine business
I reintroduce the apprentice system
because I felt it was mandatory and you
will hear later as we go along on my
background what I learned I think it's
mandatory that you students young men
going to college before going to college
before going to MIT get your hands dirty
I get a fail for bolts nuts tools on
everything you must get a pupil now let
me ask you a question first how many of
you have taken have worked on your car
I assume each of you as a car not a
grandpa how just raised yet how many of
you okay good how many have gone down
depose and spark looks oh boy
well that's better as I am surprised by
that I'm very glad to hear that
because I spoke in Cal Tech and in some
other places on the west coast where a
lot of boys said yes we're working on
our cars
howdy Pippi galoot below spark plugs
there was just a small number when I was
you age at that time in Germany one
person had a car out of 53 people maybe
very few cause but we were stories about
America that all American kids have
model a Ford's that was that age and
that they just turned a cow over
sideways and take the oil pan off or
start work on the bearings and crank
shafts and piston rings and valves and
and all about it and we were very
jealous of the American kids who had
this opportunity now today I don't think
many of you have looked in the oil pan
and take your open up your car and so on
anyhow you had to be an apprentice and
actually the book is correctly or your
your prospect here that two years were
mandatory but three years was
practically mandatory because up to
three years till you became a journeyman
in Germany you were not permitted to
work without supervision on any call
whether it breaks our steering range of
what it is unless you are
certified journeyman the journeyman is a
guy who had bloody fingernails some
bloody knuckles and everything busted
and had a good taste of what goes what
doesn't go I went to school I graduated
from a very small school total 650
students total capacity the oldest in
Germany but mr. Hank Oh of painkiller
cough mr. juncos of Junkers aircraft
very many famous people and successful
people graduated from that school now
here comes one little lesson the fact
that you are an MIT graduate or going to
be I think is wonderful and you will
have no trouble getting public of finest
jobs anywhere what you do with them is
another matter and I don't know if you
have a system of asking people keeping
record often what happens 10 years later
and I have a questionnaire sent to them
and they old address and say what
happened do you in ten years after you
graduated and then you can find out
whether all the things you're being
taught are really useful and practical
and necessary well I graduated and just
before graduation rate on a bulletin
board a little notice saying that twelve
young engineers are wanted in China
nationalist China that time was no
common as China but it was was up in the
hills Nash was China to maintain German
military equipment that was 1938 the end
of 38 to go over there and 39 now you
may wonder if your history is any good
and you elderly gentlemen I'm sure
remember very well the Hitler Hirohito
Mussolini axis party that while Hitler
was officially an ally of the Japanese
they love the Chinese Germany in China
were allies in World War one in ship
Germany shipped secretly the latest war
equipment to nationalist China to fight
the Japanese now that you never read
before anyone here heard it before
okay so that was a thing I wound up in
Hong Kong and it was an exciting trip to
Hong Kong because in 1939 there was a
once-a-week flight from Europe to China
one flight week took 8 days in the same
plane fully loaded
four crew members pilot copilot engineer
navigator and 12 passengers that's all
ahead big tri-motor French devotee
flying every 2 and 1/2 hours where to
make a landing in another country over
North Africa I've never seen a camel
before you Americans have seen us in
television all this brings you up to
date but in those days 1939 I never seen
a camel I never seen a black person I've
never seen a North African and we went
along down to Egypt when Egypt Iraq and
or Lebanon Lebanon in Baghdad and back
that the cross Indian cause injured in
Thailand and Burma and Indochina which
was French of those days and finally
Hong Kong and I reported in Hong Kong to
that Chinese outfit which was a secret
outfit to gather us young engineers and
take us into the interior of China now
how many of you have been to Hong Kong
oK you've seen Hong Kong skyscrapers
full of people four five six million
people in there now when I was there
150,000 people in Hong Kong of whoo
25,000 the British troops it was a very
small town with one high-rise building
of 20 storeys today it's the skyscraper
one next to the other one this
organization the chinese nationalist
organization which was supposed to
receive us and take us into the interior
had disappeared a few days before per
request of the japanese who have found
out that they're Germans on a way to
China to help the Chinese against them
they put the pressure on the British the
British caved in through the Chinese out
and here I was sitting there together
with some associates and a finest hotel
was absolutely no money which was
supposed to be paid now I could tell you
as
and our about that but this is not as
the MIT subject puts it I went into the
interior first the wall started and I
became personable of the British and for
a total of 102 Germans most of them were
residents in Hong Kong representing
mercedes-benz like our cameras various
steam engines and industrial concerns we
were all interned in Hong Kong and in
1940 where Germany made a big push
after having beaten Poland in 1939 on
France Belgium Holland Denmark and you
may recall that you gentlemen in June of
1940 things got very tough on our camp
and we were given 48 hours to quote get
the hell out of here or be interned in
Colombo in salon in India because up to
that time we were still being treated a
little kind of gentlemen because the
Chinese are those they look through the
barbed wire inside they couldn't see one
white man mistreating the other white
man that's whether those days in China a
very impossible thing well by absolute
coincidence and I want to make us much
does one the 48 hours were nearly up we
were each given a british soldier with a
fixed pilot as escort we had to pay for
him 5 horas de took us aren't wherever
we wanted to we want have the portuguese
consulate an american consulate and
wherever possibility was and i were only
few of us really tried iran in the
elevator
and the only high-rise building as I
asked for the manager of the china
national aviation corporation we all and
I say come back next Monday as I was too
late I can't do it anymore I was ready
to go back to camp and get out when I
got the elevator coming up and as I walk
in with my god the door opened and the
gentleman came up tie loose couldn't be
British the pie was loose the jacket off
hanging over so labelled fact I'm going
to take it off right now okay if you
don't mind
excuse me please
and this gentleman looked at me and
looked at that soldier and said what's
going on here
this gentleman happened to be a Mr Bond
many of you will remember born I know
pride when you remembered bond for sure
born son or the head of the FAA here
just a year ago but born was a vice
president of Penn American Airways
directing the traffic San Francisco to
Manila and now they put an extension on
madula Hong Kong and he was just there
and he saw me and then he heard my story
I couldn't speak English my wife said I
so can speak well but at least I can be
understood I hope and those day were
very difficult for me to speak English
and the guy took a time grab the phone
said surround dyers no doubt well I had
some number with no dial and said after
a while I won't hear a little bit to the
soldier get demanded 11 I talked to Kai
tuck tight tuck is the airport in Hong
Kong not anymore
as it is now now it's a long jet runway
but those there was a grass runway
little strip get in there 11 o'clock
tonight don't worry about the way no
longer the worry was of course the
British had taken my passport away
before gone so that guy took me without
a passport in the interior of China
dropped me there but had ridden me a
little card to Clare Lisa note now I
want to get an honest hand-raising of
you folks of the young folks have you
ever heard about Claire Lisa note who
has wizard
okay well amazing eyes falling harder
plate again that they snore who they had
no idea was it's no question oh it was a
captain retired from the US Army Air
Corps was hired by madam Chun guy checks
sent to Chongqing to organize the
Chinese Air Force this man in the
elevator who I didn't see for many many
years but I did see him later and he
just passed away couple years ago he had
written me a card to this captain
Chenault and said hey take a look at
that man listen or took a look at it man
and said you're an engineer and you're
probably quite capable but I can't use
you now I could use you less than a year
from now so if you
go over to the automobile place Renault
with all trucks and all passenger cars
over there with all diesel trucks you
can help China have a lot in that time
okay goodbye goodbye I went over to
Android and I learned a lot of lessons
which you should learn it was a bomber
Road you heard about the Burma Road
wasn't finished yet had be bolted
between China kun Ming and Western Union
of lower lower corner of China and Burma
the only communication which would be
there except one railroad line from
Indochina and the danger was already
that time the Japanese would occupy
Indochina and the bike stopped the road
China would be cut off because a
homologous I in between the Burma Road
goes in between a malaria my Himalayan
mountains to Burma so this man in charge
had to be a German at the French Renault
diesel immediately said would you like
to take a convoy down the Burma Road we
bring tungsten and other valuable
material which I didn't have the United
States down and we bring a bombs and
ammunition a gasoline up the Burma Road
the trucks are four-cylinder diesel
trucks and they were so overloaded that
the springs a set of leaf springs in a
car we're completely flat on the wooden
blocks were put between the chassis and
the axle because it's bringing it up so
you know effect anymore
it was just flattened out well the
territory like kun Ming where we start a
6,000 feet high and from there be
climbed of eight eight nine thousand
feet and then went down again driving a
convoy leading a convoy all Chinese and
their Chinese drivers Chinese co-drivers
the first thing we did we knocked the
doors out we took the doors I took the
windows out so that you could jump out
in case you had a job are now I don't
want to give you a long story on a ball
road but I want to tell you that at one
point we had a bearing problem one
connecting rod start hammering away in
inside an engine and I crawled
underneath it all convoy stop that was
so now no other convoy could pass there
was no other corner we had only one coin
by dawn and one coin by going up took
your pen off looked at it and I saw the
metal or remote down there and it was a
bearing rattling around in there now
where the heck you get the bearing you
wouldn't even get a bearing in United
States
I wonder they could get it in France
certainly not on the Burma Road
somewhere in the middle of knowing what
to do
Chinese spy privateer he said mister he
spoke a little tiny little English and I
spoke a little Chinese by that time
here's my hat say we're going to do the
hat he cut it we cut a strip of felt and
wrapped it around for his suggestion
aren't the bearing put the bank together
that thing was running up and down a
Burma Road with that hat in there okay
here you cheap engineers and all experts
on everything you'll see that some very
good idea of an uneducated Chinese boy
who does had a good fearful situation
could cut the hat pull around and up
went the next problem ahead was a
village was up on top of one of the high
points and we stopped the overnight to
eat to sleep on a bamboo cot and next
morning I couldn't start the Angels
altitude was too high so what to do now
you learn another thing you begin to
learn all kind of things without go to
MIT or German engineering school or
somewhere I learned from then on one
engine we got started luckily who then
pulled every truck till it goes down and
then let it roll down gain speed and
start the engine
alright so this is my experience on the
Boomer wound I could tell you a lot more
of what's going on there then came the
day when my neighbor and those days we
didn't live in a Chinese town we had
foreigners had to live outside in a very
modern little village in Kunming my
neighbor was smoked and he grabbed me
morning on December the 8th 1941 I was
just going over to a place where I had
started a garage of my own the Chinese
had never seen a white man
rarely work in a garage now they are
cause they only the governor had a car
his wife at a car his concubines he had
three of them had cause the police chief
Etta called the military and a couple
bankers and to foreign embassies
embassies they all came to duman's
karachi got bigger they are going to
hired one man another man another man
finally i had two dozen men and i
photographs of it and i visited that
garage a couple months a couple years
ago we were in china it is still there
and there now you repair cause what they
do
we needed a spring leaf another springs
one big one at a little shorter one sort
of a loop sort of one that's a set of
Springs for the british ambassador
we couldn't get a spring leaf but we had
a round iron rod long rod and I had a
Chinese tall six-foot-something
blacksmith who had a little fight foot
something
wife take busted little baby all their
nursing right along aligned as well all
standard down there standard procedure
and she operated a hand pump to get the
fire going charcoal fire and a fifty
gasoline barrel hazard thing heated and
he took that rod and he did that rod
justice section about a foot of it and I
said okay now and she took the baby
dumped it down in the corner grab the
sledgehammer and with a round swing with
a round swing and I mean around swing
was prohibited in Germany I don't know
how it is here in America I didn't even
know all it's an England but there was a
round swing was dangerous the hammer
could fly away down there but she swung
and they cam it piece by piece heat it
again he did it again he'd again another
section a leaf out of it curled the eyes
and we had to spring except it wasn't
hot how we went on hard the spring we
had no idea what the degree of hardness
should be or what it should be but we've
all told to do our little business in
this trough and the trough was for was
urine the guy he to the whole spring and
then dumped it in a little bit a little
more beam on little wall and dumped the
whole thing is it okay
believe it or not that spring was
running
to earth when I was including until I
joined apply tires it was running all
right
the many many examples I can give you
how you can help yourself as some
ingenuity with some feel for the
situation a man had no theory no
theoretical knowledge the vendor said he
just did it ok I joined the Flying
Tigers p40 Curtis corners now p-40s when
a 1937 plane opposition was Japanese
zero we had a lot of bombers overhead we
had zeros overhead who had bombed before
the flight Tigers arrived the city and
electric works and whatever we had there
that tried to hit my garage to well here
was the first example of me learning
American technique
I got a handbook of an Ellison engine
1,050 horsepower driving a three-bladed
propeller and the Curtis ride wasn't all
plane but other solid clean armored
plating self-sealing fuel tanks - 30
caliber machine guns firing through the
propeller hub for 50 calibers in the
wings so an initial plane we had they
were a hundred oven shipped to China now
I tell you one thing which you won't
believe and you never heard fulfilled
did you know that the United States had
planned a preemptive strike on Japan
prior to Bravo all right
Croesus my wife's name down there I have
that folder the this page of the
newspaper in a book which is a new book
as odd which gives the fact that the
United States knowing the Japanese would
have to attack the United States because
they were all completely they had normal
fuel we boycotted numbers iron we
boycott understeer we did many things
from we caused them to do it they were
power was done in anyway I don't want to
defend a Japanese one dog bit but we
know an attack was going to come not
necessarily all the way down a why we
thought Guam or Kwajalein or some of
these places would get hit not all the
way get an aircraft carrier down in a
long range
getting Japanese planes
Hawaii we had planned several months
earlier and to Flying Tigers with us
fighter squadrons three of them which
were sent over already in a dissipation
of three more squadrons of bomber
squadrons who were stuck in Australia
for some red tape reason when the war
started so the United States had planned
to hit Japan before Japan could hit us
in Hawaii and that is a fact you look at
if you don't believe it well I hope you
get the book down there my wife up there
later has the name of the book down they
would say just came out and let's handle
it huh
she's sleeping okay all right here we
here we go here we where p-40s
with a V engine 12 solos spark plugs
inside spark plug from both sides on the
bank spark plugs on the outside pretty
good machines very heavy
the whole plane weight 8,000 pounds had
2,000 horsepower to drive it and we have
a propeller governor I don't know if you
know it of appellate governor's a
propeller has not only blades but they
rotate not only this way of course but
they rotate on takeoff a different angle
and when they cruise or when they climb
so they're just a few degrees of
rotation so a governor the governor is
the gadget which is held on by four nuts
against four studs built into the V and
I have lesson one for you here when you
design something but you think is
practical later you better think of how
it's going to be used and talk to people
who use it and not just sit at an
air-conditioned office as you're going
to have you understand and have it
thinking of a nice engine hanging on the
crane and worried maybe even going to
working on that engine or looking at
that engine this engine is hot as hell
when it comes back from the mission and
the pilot says hey I got a propeller
governor problem quickly fix it
they're Japs on the way already 20
minutes following us later you better
get in there take four nuts loose get a
new governor on quickly put it together
get that
plane ready to fly again or the subject
beam bomb or being straight no idea what
practicality meant they installed that
nice governor when it's nice and cool
and good hand light and skiing could be
little light here and little more
business this way you can headed an
airplane in Seoul sitting on a military
runway there in China somewhere and it
was useless I'll tell you another one
which is the same style the p40 which is
that airplay talked about head of course
a tail wheel like all these planes in
those days had meant no nearly all the
plates so everybody took off a gain
speed as a game speed had lifted its
tail toll as horizontal gain more speed
till they had a ninety five hundred
miles now and then it could lift up and
take off they had a lot of gravel in
China in sand because we had no asphalt
runways there was no asphalt that didn't
exist in China all the runways that we
built was ten thousand women and I'm not
exaggerating over ten thousand chopping
away on stones make them smaller make
them smaller and have a real fine layer
on top and then they were two hundred
men on a big V pulling a stone roll over
the runway down there to press it down
but the problem was it was still a
little grabber left and that gravel
well I skip one play now let's go to
what's more the p40 inlet as a plane got
up because of the dirt they had
installed filters on a site of the inlet
of the engine and the aerodynamics of
that filter which was sucking air into
the engine worked real fine at first on
the ground but as a plane game speed and
the tail got up suddenly the air foil
there stream broke and went back and
rear and the engine immediately suffered
and couldn't get enough pressure enough
take off down there can you follow that
I don't know if I made that play enough
but all I want to tell you that great
ideas can be done can be had can be
executed on the ground everybody thinks
is fine they ran the engine on the
ground all works beautiful now we have a
filter now we keep the little gravel out
and what half
later the airplane couldn't even take
off we lost many an airplane later which
could not again enough power in
available runway taken off with that Don
Phil Dean till I as a master sergeant I
could never get a commission being an
enemy alien at that point of our still
enemy alien set and put out an order
signed by general Chennault no more you
so filters leave the filters out and let
the way engine way out if you have to
but at least take off that plane take up
for runway now came the other thing I
was going to mention before then two
years later we got more modern planes
armored North American p-51 streamlined
ready for the wall more power
British engines in their rolls-royce
engines congratulations whether British
gentlemen it is know yet that are they
okay congratulate you the hell of a good
engine down there two-stage supercharger
we loved it except you had a different
yeah you had a different ignition system
on the right side on the left side now
that was more complicated but you know I
can never talk about that later but
anyhow there was that p-51 streamliners
could be long range with the inlet air
inlet not anymore on the side on front
but behind the pilot below the pilot
seat was Inlet and again the same misery
existed the propeller shaft and through
little bit of rocks into the inlet which
was uneasy play now in Europe that
wasn't happen in America they wouldn't
have you had a smooth runway jazz I
could sweep it at the head people hand
sweeper the prisoner's dude and so on
but in China it was impossible and the
only way to fix all the leaks which then
the result of later from underneath the
aircraft they're hit by liberal rocks
was when I came through on Thanksgiving
Day 1943 we made a very great surprise
rate on the Japanese or long-range they
didn't know the people if you want that
come we didn't know either till the
night before and I bought some from the
Chinese some bicycles that put bicycle
spokes into it put the nuts on the other
side and at least I could fly the
missions are one of most successful miss
milray at 64 enemy aircraft destroyed
and not a single loss and anything that
was that was a good deal okay one more
thing
by China I was just about four months in
a regular US Army Air Corps not anymore
the Flying Tigers they were discontinued
in 42 per contract and I stayed in per
special provision Secretary of War
Stimson gave general Chennault
permission he became a general in the
meantime to keep me in the military and
I was very proud of it I got paid not
only Master Sergeant pay I got overseas
pea got flying pay it was just a great
great entertainment for me the whole
thing when a few months after this
happened to North had me cold in his
office and said no one I got a job for
you I said well I am busy as can be and
he could see my black hands and all the
covers and said I need a Japanese zero
flying by flown by American pilots we
got to put a zero to get a final what a
dumb thing does it flies higher than we
do by several thousand feet it flies
faster by 50 miles per hour
it flies further by 8,000 miles distance
further it does many many things we have
never thought the Japanese were able to
do we only knew of Japanese toys which
break and rust you know you old folks
remember that but nothing that they
build an aircraft which was absolutely
superior to any Germans built at that
time even the Spitfire I hate to say at
that point zero was superior at that
particular point if you can afford what
they could have what they thought they
could afford but couldn't afford namely
the loss of a pilot episode the reason
why the zero was so good was a I found
out after I put the first jabbsi row
together from shut down pieces as was
done in 19 February 1943 I was finished
with it I got sick as hell in a process
but anyhow the plane was brought over to
enure I went with it and I got orders
from general Arnold to take the plane
apart and separate to the United States
and then go back to over to the United
States and put it together again and
sell war bonds over there but this was
done after American pilots flew the zero
against other American planes flown by
American pilots to find out what
technique what fighting technique could
be used with that superior plane we
point out one
japanese pilots have no parachutes
parachute weighs 40 pounds something
like that japanese plane 2 has no armor
plating protection like all plane set
japanese planes had no self-sealing fuel
tanks they used all the fuel capacity to
put fuel and not to put fuel protective
or leakage protective supplement and so
on so again a lot of things we learned
there at that time and the new war
memorandum came out which was
distributed in South Pacific also came
as a result of having a zero namely
never dogfight with the Japanese zero
only make a pass at him from high
altitude this was only when he had to
fly low to escort his bombers who were
no damn good but he do header as head of
a company I'm and so Americans had a
chance to make a pass at a zero then
dive away and dive away and come on
climbed back again the other way and
make another pass it okay incidentally
during the rest of the war the Japanese
didn't improve the aircraft but very
very little
they lost had lost all their good pilots
in the first two years of the war and
from 1943-44 it was really no more real
battle against the Japanese air force we
had all the modern planes we had the
modern bombers then finally we had a
nuclear bomb okay now I was supposed to
speak about one hour so we have another
half I'm just halfway through that's
exactly what happened the war was over I
had gone to the United States I had been
transferred into the OSS some of you may
have heard about that
that was the intelligence for the CIA is
today was it OSS during the war and
there I had I met the commanding general
white Bill Donovan who had passed away a
few years ago but just now book was
written about him and he helped me
decide by God we'll go to make an office
out of you and you don't have to go to
China anymore and whatever it takes
we'll do well after two three months in
the United States during which time I
met my charming wife said there which
was the only good thing really happened
over here so but she was not my wife
that time I mean she was wife after that
after the war I asked for return to
China I sent a telegram to Donald
to say dear general America is beautiful
but please can be back to China so I
came back to China still a mother's
heart is still an enemy alien and in May
of 45 I received a telegram from this
young lady saying very simple bill
introduced in Congress to make you
citizen congratulations
Clarisse that was Anna and what indeed
happened is a general Donovan pulled his
rank and his influence and Congress
passed a special law that I never have
resided the United States became an
American citizen and I was told only two
times all together that was done once as
Winston Churchill at the segment was
Gardner so I became a soon and when I
came back talked to the wall
I joined Douglas Aircraft research in
Santa Monica California there we worked
I worked on afterburners now you know
and after Bernays a jet engine in front
then comes if you want additional swash
for military plane to go supersonic and
afterburner that was in those days
responsibility of the airplane builder
now there's part of the engine builder
because it really is integrated with the
engine pratt whitney General Electric
whoever else makes engine slows voice we
all have afterburners following the
engine as part of the engine builders
responsibility okay
and it wasn't was interesting
fascinating my girlfriend lived in
Connecticut but was usually overseas in
South America and Europe somewhere and I
was just doing well when I got a
telegram from Shanghai China all the
loudspeaker system of Douglas Aircraft
from General Samoyed starting an airline
you want to come back like to have you a
special project engineer so he gave me a
salary figure which was a multiple of
what I made a Douglas tax free and
everything whole trip paid free matter
of fact he asked me to be one of the
crew members of 24 war-surplus commerce'
46 big twin-engine transports he bought
to fly from a why over to China which it
was illegal to fly a twin-engine
propeller plane over the Pacific Ocean
but snow couldn't tell us what was rule
or not a rule he bought 24
planes put 24 crews together and
everyday day of the day after day one
after the other planes left in all 24
planes right safely in China after
landing on Johnson Ireland and Guam on
Kwajalein and Manila and Hong Kong or
Kent on on Kent on to Shanghai just
before we left
my wife had returned or my girlfriend
had returned I told her I'm going to
China and you said you like China and
everything you like of China you have
the first chance to see it now yourself
cool let's get married that we take
right off we got married we looked
elihpa book yellow pages and on the
beach in Santa Monica for a judge for
Saturday he said where are you kids we
said we had the beach he said well you
hurry up for another half now have you
got a witness I know we don't have a
witness say okay bring my son along so
we got married she went on a troopship
to Shanghai with our dog with a born in
Berlin Germany but she had bought along
I flew to Ally Hawaii overall his hot
rod and I met her and Shanghai at the
dock in 1947 now I can tell you a long
story now make it in two sentences or
three sentences because you want to go
to jet engines the three sentence where
when the whole the Communists came back
by that time Japan was defeated the
Communists came in the communist
communist from the north
pushed us further south further south
finally the airline had to leave
Shanghai it would have kept on canned on
Hong Kong from there to Taiwan and at
that point my wife said I have enough of
it I she said I said I'd enough of it we
both had enough of it we had gone home
Holly went home that time was no regular
airline service yet that time there was
no shipping service yet unless you're
the military and believe it or not
you're looking at the only man and
they're certain the only woman who ever
together with a dog in a Jeep drove from
the Orient to the Mediterranean Sea with
automap except National Geographic that
big that was Asia our Europe was a
little bit hanging in the corner today
we had no map but there was a red line
on that map
it says Ganga scan made that trip that's
a truth we have no idea where we get
gastly we had no idea we get food where
we go to sleep all I knew
let's get awfully cotan of Kansas Tana
winter and so we left in October with
Royal Air Force jeeps I bought three
real warrior for Jeeps
all put together because one of the good
body one of the good engine wants
something else I made a good edge out of
it and we drove 10,000 miles we carried
with us a great overload four-wheel
drive and I learned a lot but you could
use to later the four-wheel drive is
great but if you have that heavy loader
like we had like 52 gallons of gasoline
which means 10 jerry cans gasoline at
the own tankful already six seven
hundred pounds right there and winter
clothes and summer clothes there's no
change the tools and everything it's we
had a range of about a thousand match
well I can tell you a lot about that
trip and I'm sure you would like to hear
a lot about it but I promised dr. Kolb
we're going to jet engines I came back
to the biote around from Tehran I know
is no more challenge there were roads
again at least mark road somewhere else
for roads going over the Mount all the
way to Iraq Baghdad but Baghdad to the
Royal Kingdom of Jordan Jordan to
Jerusalem open to them to Tel Aviv and
from there back to the United States we
saw the Jeep to the American potter's
company in Jerusalem for the same money
I paid for Hong Kong and enterin I wrote
a letter to brother Whitney and a letter
to General Electric who I know both will
make jet engines I didn't know the rest
of them was on the East Coast and then
I'm coming back in about three months
and I'm looking for a job so DiSanto
pride wouldn't have answered General
Electric the Nance either but I called
John electric it happened to be the
person that yes you are the guy with a
pretty stamps yes I they are aware of
the pretty stamps well we made your
letter to Lynn Massachusetts
Lynn Massachusetts makes jet engines for
GE and you call them I called them to
say oh yeah we're waiting for you come
right up and we came right up the
following day they interviewed me and
hired me on the spot
310 that time was weird $50 a month I
was a said don't tell anyone that's so
much money but don't tell anyone and I
started on tests that the best thing you
can do when you leave here with your
degree is to get
into a company in a subject Oh which
makes gadgetry whatever you like whether
it's aircraft engines or airplanes or
electronics whatever it is get on test
on test you find out what goes haywire
and I was lucky that the big boss of the
outfit here in Lynn Massachusetts knew a
damn foreigner came in now and he's here
any other mentos impact on Flying Tigers
and everything else he made me report to
him every morning at 8 o clock shop what
went wrong in the past 24 hours on the
jet engine development and those days we
switched over from a scientifical I 16
and I 40 which we copied from the
British into an axial flow engine which
we copied from the Germans just let's
face it no one said it in a book but
it's an exact copy of the engine which
drove the Messerschmitt 262 it's a
little log compressor but the same idea
long combustion system little bit better
a little higher temperature a little
better turbine or better materials
because the Germans had no good material
of course had to cool the hollow turbine
buckets which operated at 1400 to 1500
degree Fahrenheit which has already
grown dog red if you do that and they
had to cool it in order to keep them
together
we had better material we had molybdenum
we had all kind of other things and so
we built the first engine which was
called the TG 180 forget about the
number the next one was TG 190 we put in
mass production that was G's number the
actual military mobile j-47 we both
37,000 j-47 engines just in time for the
Korean War
every f-86 which was now a jet plane was
part by j-47 the b-47 bomber six engines
all six j-47 unelected a forty sevens B
36 bombers which had four big Pratt
Whitney engines ran very well we added
in order one a little better with 4G jet
engines two and a each wingtip and so we
were suddenly in the business till they
get them until the Korean War was over
and the engines were kind of obsolete
the pressure ratio was five to one
in about twelve stages and there was the
end of it but at that time I had been
transferred from the testing into
running the research laboratory somebody
picked me up and said look that Don
thing is sitting here it's the biggest
in the world Pratt Whitney claims they
were to build a bigger one we need
something to test components like
compressors full-scale high altitude
evacuated was big suction pumps to get
the altitude up to 60,000 feet 70,000
feet up to hundred thousand feet
altitude with air speeds at that time
subsonic not yet supersonic but we all
intended to go supersonic of course
ultimately so we ought to have
supersonic capability and all together
it was a very fascinating a job for
compressors turbines and combustion
systems and I had a chance since I now
was in charge of the laboratory
following orders of the engineers was
MIT degrees and whatever else ahead on
their following orders what to do but to
carry out and tell my wife and she would
loves about it it was more difficult to
operate the research laboratory than the
equipment I want to test I tell you that
right now
to run as massive equipment cooled by
4,000 gallon of ocean waters per minute
which we suck into cooled of fresh water
and the fresh water circulating through
exhaust and so on to cool the
temperature down to minus 60 - 70 and to
dry the air otherwise all the
instruments get a little bit of snow on
top down there and freeze up and to do
this I could tell you a long story
just running laboratory but in the
process as we try to get the pressure
ratio which all our theoretical people
say boy if you could go to ten to one
instead of five to one or twelve to one
boy what we could do nice plug that a
compressor and I said why the hell don't
they rotate the first few stationary
veins which are always ahead of a
rotating one now you all know I assume
what is you have a state of Ain a row of
Stata veins and then a rotor and then
another state obeyed another rotor
another state of Ain another rotor stage
all put together to build up pressure
which builds up on a negative side of
the state of Ain let's say well if we
rotate those and as a speed goes up but
I got a patent
to make a long story short every engine
you fly today has that variable status
system six stages variable summit five
stages some four stages but I got a
patent and suddenly I got a big name at
general acting and the next thing what
happened is that my boss called the big
boss vice president of General Electric
and a secretary our secretary 12 of us
had one secretary said the big boss
horse talked to you and I thought she
was kidding I didn't want to go and
after I said you damn well better go I'm
not kidding you so I did go over
shivering and he said sit down here I
sat down I said I understand you're
bitching about our engines that they are
hard to maintain they are not one and as
well as they should you could do better
I said yes I made some comments he said
ok we're going to have a competition now
remember that another lesson competition
internally don't wait for the outside
internally another team of whatever you
design how does I need different you'll
find out the other guys have some good
ideas too we had to a competition with
two teams one variable status like I had
won water and another one put another
rotor in front of the one water so there
were two different rotors like the pod
woody engine all heads and since Pratt
wouldn t already was running a dual
water engine we thought well we'll be so
far behind at that point and the
decision was made to go variables theta
today we have everything we have the
whole world has now operating the
russians and pratt whitney variable
status and we added another rotor to the
whole thing like pride we needed to so
we all have practically identical
engines for supersonic flight and so on
so i got eight tons on this one new
engine which was called j79 and again we
hit a just right if you call it hitting
it right when a war was it vietnamese
war starting 62 63 64 67 69 71 72 every
phantom fighter to j79 every f-104
starfighter YG's every night you can go
down line 79s are all over and they're
nato the whole NATO Air Force's all but
England England Edward
but everybody else the Germans the Danes
the Italians everyone built j7i on the
license over there this engine grew and
pressure ratio up to twelve to one with
the single rotor in variable status
which was called the big progress right
there one single shaft all these three
bearings one in front one in the middle
and one in the rear instead of five
bearings and seven bearings are bearing
each bearing you know what a bearing is
right the ball bearing or what a roll of
a each bearing eat seals and need
lubrication system and lead to scavenge
system it just sounds simple to put a
bearing it but you put a bearing it
which has lubrication or constantly
running through it and scavenge it up
and seal the air from getting in and so
on you have a heck of a lot more
difficult things to do than when you
draw on a map here is that a hurricane
but there's no very kid I just say that
because dr. Kobler was nice enough to
show me all the few things he has
planned to do was some of you fellas who
are his students the lesson learned
there is talk with the people who use
the engine who use your product I became
a big shot at that time I was a vice
president of a company I became in
charge of a total division of the total
aircraft is aware 22,000 people at that
time go to 25,000 people go up to 30,000
people 32,000 people became a huge
organization and under me where another
group of six vice presidents and then
we'll other in levels the typical seven
level organization you know I would
never get the truth up what's really
going on from the bottom to the top it's
impossible you learn it I hope you
remember that now I said it and you
bring it up again talk to people who use
a machine and talk to your service
people out in the field and talk to the
image manufactured people what is
difficult so that you get the real truth
to it and what the only way to do it is
I pulled out a serviceman and he'll
report to me directly now part of the
quality control man had report to me
directly and I had 14 people reported me
including one professional SEO
now he was a Navy captain retired and I
had it with me
the other saw a puss and he was a nasty
guy and I say you know Schmitt the right
thing for you is to be natural be I want
you to take every decision any one
decision I want to make and I were in a
democratic organization
I had 51 percent of the vote so there
was no problem there I said you'll go
over it
hostile try to find a father now I often
correct it what I wanted to do as a
consequence of his talk something I did
I didn't have to do that but I just want
to tell you if you ever have management
that you will have a generation from now
and you're 40 years old 45 years old
you're running organization and you let
people remember that that old bald guy
down there who talked and told you to
get quality customer service and visit
the customer yourself talk to them on a
phone if necessary call no way Norwegian
airline SES call the Tahitian Airways
which operates all angels today today
Jon Electric is the largest jet edge of
an effect on the world we have 42,000
people primarily my engines which I
design in those days it takes 20 years
from the day you decide to build an
engine 10 years to get it to test and
run it right at another 10 years before
you begin to make money because the
first price you have to put on it you're
going to lose money on every engine the
more engine you sell the more money you
lose and that then takes a while until
it slowly comes up the cost gets cheaper
and cheaper and lowered lowered you find
an easier way to make buckets you don't
machine them anymore
turbo bucket you cast it which is much
simpler or you castables in dimensions
of about 20,000 of an inch and you get
it down to where you really begin making
money today again at General Electric
there's no secret you read a stock
report of your energy stock it is a most
money-making group of General Electric
products between refrigerators and
freezers and light bulbs and general
general motors electric motors I mean
and whatever it is the jet engines make
the most money and of course Pratt
Whitney now will be out to trying to
catch an electric and rolls-royce
crying again but I hope the people in my
place whom I left behind will keep on
feeling insecure last lesson feel
insecure don't ever feel secure whether
you ride a motorcycle like I did to work
or whether you ski or whether you design
and think well or if your pride wedding
are held unlikely we'll never make it
I'm sure that's what they thought I
assume so that's what they thought but
they would GE made it because it takes a
while in which they lost management and
they lost some good people and good
people retired plan when you lost a hell
of a bunch of very very good people who
retired I know that and I always grew up
now I hope that when we're going up to
we're going to stay we're a bright-eyed
bushy-tailed on top but I'm not sure but
feel insecure don't ever think you
haven't made till you I'm better and
sleep I tell you that that that's one
thing you drive home a motorcycle lady
gets open to the car door and you hit
the right side to hit that open car door
for two-door car and boy you going right
over the radio I got a big hole of my
left like I tell you that so lot of
things can happen but just feel insecure
now it is exactly three minutes before
one hour now would you like to ask some
questions or any particular area would
you like to hear four questions
I want to make three remarks first
pregnant engineers we talked about
having the effect of changing away the
world becomes and I think our speaker
today has taken part in that chain
transportation has changed and I hope it
never changed back to what was the
second thing is I want to repeat the
advice that he gave that is you've got
to get out and get a moment there's just
no substitute talking to you
the guy with the skinned knuckles it's
all different than the real world and if
you're going to be a work with with
equipment you got to do that the third
is there is a book which is in the
library I'm told that the only language
you can buy it in right now is Chinese
or German it's called urban the German
if you want to read about this trip from
from China the Tel Aviv and I assure you
that it's worth the effort to get it to
read it now when take a couple minutes
for those of you that want to leave it
have carpools or whatever and then with
your permission we'll have a few
questions tonight it like thank you very
much for listening and thank you very
much for your comment I appreciate
are there questions that may I make a
comment not based on your comments but
that you don't get a wrong impression
that an engineer doesn't have to do
engineer work you are on the right
profession I think there's no more
exciting job than engineering job and
you do need the aerodynamic knowledge
and you need the mechanical strength but
you also need specifications that's one
thing I forgot to say specifications
besides walking around you've got to
have good specs on their specs which are
reasonable which are proper like how
much of a material strength sorry
designed to 85% 90% 92% or whatever the
case this is all very very important
later in the field on a wall that poor
soldier with a piece or bullet going
through the blades that blade will break
right off if it's designed to a limit
like that and there are many many of
these examples where a material fall
flaw may be locally there which normally
wouldn't make a piece fail but it failed
because you designed it too close to the
limit so a good specification is worth a
lot why we do it
oh because it was so big even al is a
big plant two miles long we bought it
from curtiss-wright war surplus and
updated it and the highway gone by in
case you ever go there is Newman way I
don't know if you saw it they named it
after I was a I didn't even know about
it they named the highway Newman way but
it is for big engines we make in small
angels here military and commercial and
big engines in Cincinnati you're going
to Inlet or one of these big commercial
engines down there it's eight it's so oh
you're up to eight feet and we had one
the engine for the supersonic transport
which President Kennedy wanted and after
he passed away Congress cancelled it
right away and I think it did the right
thing of incidentally at this point but
the engine was a huge engine with 70,000
pounds faster
1961 we ran it we ran 35 engines and so
we had to do the big facilities and big
test cells and so on all right okay
very briefly I love the day of you know
that we had a nuclear-powered aircraft
engine running anyone knows all right so
they are okay with nausea I'm surprised
in other places they had known about it
I was put in charge of mechanical design
of that nuclear powered engine in 1951
I've just been three years with General
Electric and not a nuclear part of it
but an engine which could run both on
chemical fuel on nuclear fuel and on a
mixture of both so in other words take
off a nuke on regular fuel till you up
to altitude then switch over to nuclear
power that thing can fly three times
around the world as long as there's food
for the crew if the engine lasts that
long but that that's another matter but
anyhow we got orders from the military
build a much bigger nuclear engine and
that was cancer to 1960 when aerial
refueling became a standard technique
no not at all there are 3000 German
officers and men in China helping the
Chinese against the Japanese right
throughout the war but the Germans
didn't like the Japanese actually the
people didn't like the Japanese if you
have state injury Oh will you've been
doing it maybe god knows what you're
gonna do you'll be shot Oh nuts not I
don't know that you never do that or
idea
hey all let me tell you tell you this
engineers I was caught up in the service
on August 1 1937 when they had total
draft coming in all engineering students
and all medical students who
automatically deferred they knew the war
was coming they needed all the engineers
to build in a massive thing but look if
I may just add one more thing in this
matter in the six years you can keep
talking till they leave in six years of
hitlerism but all horrible things he did
he dead was able to produce an
incredible amount of weaponry from
submarines to battleships to
88-millimeter and aircraft to jet
engines to everything else and you have
to give him credit but he didn't do that
himself manufacture of people did it
against his will but he delayed the
development of jet engines I know that
as a fact at the German book with just I
gave my last talk I gave a damn per hour
and there someone gave me a fake German
book about German fighter aircraft how
Hitler deliberately ordered the delay or
the stopping of working on jet engines
on German jet engine because it would
water down the effort on the other thing
same as pratt whitney and cutters right
had been told not to work on jet engines
during world war ii and they left it up
to Westinghouse and General Electric
because we were the two electrical
turbine manufacturers and familiar with
it but they didn't want to weaken the
effort of Pratt Whitney Engen Electric
was our good luck that has happened this
way but but that's the way it went
yeah
no it was a solar Lee a and P aircraft
nuclear propulsion program gen electric
goes top-secret it was at the even
airplane on the other end completely
fenced in and covered up and is that
right
we'll see while you kept the ticket all
right I never read about it I think
that's a short day and I read about it
I'm very good yeah yeah well hi anyhow
I'm glad to see you here I good the
high-bypass engine all right that was
another thing
the British led the way there they had
an 8/10 bypass ratio engine the the one
on the the convoy on a cover the weather
convoy and I built the first one was two
and a half bypass ratio made happen out
it because the company wouldn't give me
all the money I wanted so they added it
to the rear I added it to the rear