Okay. So, here are our two godfathers of
biology and medicines, our keynote
speakers that um make you know frame the
arc of biology and medicines um that
this this symposium is really about. And
now I'm going to close and we'll um
introduce um our first keynote speaker
George Church. The first thing that came
to my mind was visionary frontier in
V12.
Um the definition is act of exploring
and advancing into new territories
whether in thought technology or society
by being an creative insightful and
forward-looking approach that is you in
my opinion. The second thought that came
to my mind and I ran it by your cousin
is the Swiss army knife of biology.
you have done um you have been a
trailblazing leader in the very
interfunction field and we spoke about
this earlier. I was in your office 10
years ago um and you have not only
inspired me but an enormous amount of
your trainees in the entire field to try
out new things and develop creatively
technologies as we go.
You have um been ahead of us nearly at
every given turn, George. You
co-invented next generation sequencing,
making the human genome project possible
and laying the foundation for what we
now take for granted in genomics. You
founded the personal genome project,
daring to imagine a future where
individuals could share actually their
genomes to accelerate science. That's
not far. Um, you have pioneered
multiplex genome engineering, not just
editing one gene, but thousands in
parallel. Your lab was among the first
to drive forward crisper technology,
developing base editors and other tools
that now are making it into the clinic
and that transform how we think about
rewriting genomes. You have really never
shied away at least from my perspective
from auditious questions from encoding
digital data and DNA to the extinction
to new frontiers in human health and
longevity. I think you have over more
than 600 publications, 150 patents,
started up more than 50 biotechn biotech
companies, many of those in the B2F
space and whole generations of trainees
who now lead labs and um startups and
companies across the world. So this
impact is multiplexed far beyond any
single achievement. and you're part of
the Academy of Science, the N the
National Academy of Science, National
Academy of Engineering, and so many more
awards that will take an entire hour to
just introduce you. I am um incredibly
grateful that you have accepted our
invite to give a keynote today to open
our bar to function symposium. And I'm
just going to give the stage over to
you, George. Thank you.
Yes, it's uh my great pleasure to be
back. Uh again, uh I want to talk
uh just like our previous speaker, I
have gotten over a
unknown but not COVID and not uh flu A
and B. Uh and it makes me a little bit
disappointed that I don't know the name
of that virus because we definitely have
the technology to do it. And I similarly
will show my disappointment. We haven't
sequenced everybody on the planet uh
yet. But anyway, there's there's lots of
positive news in this talk as well.
Okay. So, I want to talk about machine
learning AI in in particular combined
with multiplex libraries. We call this
ML squared and that uh and you'll see
why it the combination is far more
powerful than anything separately. I
think this audience in particular would
know that. And I want to focus on new
therapies. We're going in some cases
straight to new therapies without full
understanding of what we're doing. I
will admit that in the same sense that
we started vaccination back in the 1700s
before we knew that much about immuno
immunology and viology.
Okay, this is where we are. And I will
uh furthermore state some of my genetic
problems uh uh dyslexia
uh um serpena um respiratory issues and
um and narcolepsy. And this is I'm in
good company here with Thomas Edison
here hanging out with the president of
the United States back then. And uh and
and but my point of the slide is not uh
is not that. It's it's that a lot of
times what we find are simple mandelian
traits are not are not reflected in the
population. There are um you know low
penetrance and complex modifiers and so
to a certain extent almost everything um
almost every trait disease or not is
complicated. Um and yeah see all these
genes were were looked at simultaneously
in this paper which I recommend.
So, so there'll be three examples. One
will be sleep, one will be height and
one more. And then this is uh this is
one of the most wellstudied uh traits as
you all know because it's collected in a
lot of G-W was studies on other things.
And this is an intermediate point quite
a few years ago, you know, showing 9,500
snips. Um but the important thing here
is again that the the therapies don't
necessarily res uh correspond to fixing
the snip or fixing the gene that the
snip is in. It very often is something
quite different. And in fact there there
uh over half a dozen different uh
therapies that involve growth hormone
that have to do with this polygenic um I
won't call it disease. It's it's a
trait. uh but there are nevertheless
medical treatments for it.
They aren't related necessarily to the
the alals that cause them. And the final
one is aging. Age related diseases are
going to kill 90% of us probably. And uh
and there and it's and it's very
complicated. Um but I think it's well
within our range and and with
exponential technologies that we'll be
discussing in a second. Um it looks like
it's happening faster and faster. Here's
a nice study from my not from my lab but
from my colleague Vadim Kadesv who I
collaborate and on centinarians and the
story wasn't that there's one key
regulator gene that that we just had to
figure out for aging. It's more that
there's a depletion of uh you know
serious loss of function germline
mutations that may not be um super so
serious depending on how many doses you
have but contribute to age related
disease
and then so this this is all building up
to these three examples of function
building up to an argument I'm making
that that um that whole whole genome
sequencing is something that can be
applied at various times during one's
life and And the goal there is
prevention, not necessarily figuring out
mechanism and so forth. Um, and Orchid
Health, for example, is um, one of one
of my companies that does whole genome
sequencing on every single in vitro
fertilization embryo that goes through
the clinic. So, that's a it's a new tool
that can um
can prevent uh problems with pregnancy
and problems with newborns.
Um Molina just mentioned the personal
genome project. This is something that
that we've been advocating since 2005.
This um um
uh it's it's it's still an unusual
project. I don't know whether it's still
unique but but the idea was to do both
genome sequencing with full medical
records and multiomics
not deidentified specifically consented
for fully open integrated and even
commercial use. A lot of a lot of the
resources we have in the genomics
community do not uh do not allow
commercial use as a default state and
and as a consequence of that consenting
mechanism we were approved by the um
NIST and FDA for genome bottle. Um two
of our two of our trios are now fully
sequenced um just recently um thanks to
the TDT consortium and so forth. They
have a cube 100. That's a fairly rare
quality level of 1 in 10 billion. Um,
and it's just because they happen to be
hanging out in this open project that
they were selected. Uh, one Ashkanazi
trio and one Hanchinese trio. Um,
critical assessment of genome
interpretation, genome project, right,
which is still just taking off recently.
Um, the encode project horses various
sorts. uh three and four um structure of
nuclei and various stem cell banks and
and even some companies again because we
didn't forbid commercial use by in the
consenting mechanism.
Anyway, well every everything I'll
mention about uh uh transition
translation into commercial use starts
with this personal genome project as the
source of the biomedical materials. Um
so we'll talk about just quickly about
where all of you know where we are on
analytic and synthetic. Synthetic is
mostly what I do but we did uh so this
has been improving faster than Moore's
law for you know since the the u
since uh the 80s or before and it went
it jumped up a little bit. I would say
this mostly due to multiplexing
uh and uh and even synthesis it
continues. We're making libraries in the
order of 10 to the 17th yet. They're not
fully utilized yet, but they're they're
um and and we we introduced this the um
these multiplex chip synthesis in 2004,
and it really wasn't picked up on by
groups outside of our collaborators here
at the Broad and and uh at Harvard
Medical School in general
for about a decade. Um then nanopore
sequencing you all know this and uh
fluorescent microscopy sequencing which
is sometimes called fluorescent nextgen
sequencing and it ble bled over as a
single fiberblast cell that which each
of the the the GATC forc color is is
recited as a as a barcode um indicating
the RNA type but we've you know we
worked with uh complete genomics now MGI
um with aluminina with 10x genomics
which is now spatial omix um which gives
us 3D um DNA RNA protein at resolutions
up to 20 nmters and actually we just
published one at 2 nanometer resolution
with turf microscopy
okay so gene therapies in Asia um
I'm interested in affordable
technologies both now the reading
genomes is 20 million times cheaper and
considerably higher quality. Um but uh
what about therapies and especially gene
therapies? When I entered gene therapy
field many years ago, I was concerned
that I might not be able to do or we may
not be able to do for gene therapies
what we did for gene sequencing because
it was it has gone up by 10 eightfold in
eight years. Um that's opposite
direction. So, it's now $4 million a
dose. And it and it's not just gene
therapies. It's it's orphan drugs in
general. It's great that we have the
orphan drug act that allows us to
finally target these rare diseases, but
it has this problem which I have argued
for years and and I think recently was
validated is they have um it's related
to market size. So most most of these
diseases have hundreds of people that
benefit
and the research and development and
clinical trial costs are fairly fixed
and the denominator is just too low to
get a a a good price. But if you get in
if you get to the denominators in the
billions of people as was the case for
for co 19 uh 6.5 billion people um
took it uh the these form these were
formulated as gene therapies either as
viral or or lipid nanoparticle messenger
RNA but then the price came down to $30
a dose and I think that's going to be
true for everything that that fix those
it's either a common disease or can be
formulated
approached as a common disease and the
other big one which I've already
mentioned age related diseases so I'm
going to focus in on that a bit um we
know quite a bit so it's sort of have to
be full there's a lot of ignorance about
about the biochemistry of of age related
diseases there a lot known and the key
of synthetic biology and and engineering
in general is um to get started on it
while we're still half ignorant Um and
so this is just a simple cartoon with
the extracellular matrix on at the top,
the lipid billayer and the cytoplasm and
it's all signaling and organels
especially the organal nucleus and and
some of our favorite actors in here like
OSK which are the Yamanaka factors and
um and then we picked uh out of we did
48 gene therapies and by we I mean uh
Noah Davidson who I'll mention again in
a moment um 48 gene therapy
simultaneously as a postto. I was amazed
at how quickly that went. And then we
check picked a set of three subsets
fibroblast growth factor 21 uh TGF beta
2 receptor um
soluble form so not the natural form and
then alpha cloth or ATF we'll call that
for short and OSK for these three in
nucleus. So these these were picked to
be secreted. We knew that you could
transfer some youthfulness via blood
from young animals to to old animals.
Uh, and we just took a guess that these
three since they were secreted and they
pass this gene therapy test that I'll
show you just a moment. And we wanted
them to be expressed in livers, which is
one of the easier things to do. And we
want them to be tested not with
biomarkers or gene aging clocks but with
um with age related disease models. So
uh one is uh the uh
high high caloric western diet uh for
these mice where they get about double
their size. And then these are these are
the various combinations of these three
genes. We're delivering them separately
in independent AAV vectors and and you
can see it's focused especially on the
red and the pink uh which which are
doing well in both the obesity and um
diabetes models and also in the um in
this kidney uh obstruction model where
it starts out with a normal kidney and
and then recovers. Um so
we took this um Noah here uh took this
into uh
uh pre-clinical and toward uh clinical
trials now from both human and dogs uh
for example mitro valal disease. You can
see the various uh indications we're
following here have relatively little to
do with each other other than that they
have they're all age related diseases
and uh we use both the ATF triple
combinations is triple gene therapy and
OSK
um OSK is supposed to is thought to work
in the nucleus and the ATF are thought
to work through secretion but um
uh I think they may both work by
rejuvenate uh rejuvenating the liver.
So, um,
we don't typically go to the FDA with
the I mean these are we're in
discussions with the FDA, but as age
related diseases, a specific age related
disease as I showed in the previous
slides, not longevity, not aging
reversal, any of that. Uh, because they
don't consider that a disease and even
if they did, it's it's much longer
clinical trials than we want to do. So
um but nevertheless we do on occasion
take uh the pre-clinical trials and let
them go on and turn it into a lifespan
trial. Again this is not for the FDA.
This is just for publication purposes.
And this was published in cellular
reprogramming. And here we have this
triple gene therapy. And I should
mention I think since aging is
complicated enough there may be some
magic bullet single gene single small
molecule or even but we think it's a
case for polyarm pharmacy where we get
have to get all of the whack-a-ole done
at once or nearly at once. So anyway,
this is a triple therapy uh of the
Yamanaka uh reprogramming factors and we
we applied the dose very late in life of
these animals at the point where half of
them were dying um under good laboratory
conditions are dying of old age and we
nevertheless get this um big improvement
where blue is the experimental and black
is the control uh animals. So about 50%
extension of life from this midpoint of
death. So
um so let's let's talk about the role of
machine learning and all in all the
things I've been talking about in I'm
going to frame it in terms of uh
delivery but it it applies to almost
everything else we do as well and have
been doing for years. Here we're looking
at tissue tropisms, immune reaction, um
pharmacocinetics, phicodnamics
doing it rodent and in primate models
you see in the next slide. And these are
some of the um new um vectors uh aav
vectors that we've developed with their
code names here. And they they are
either for brain or specific for neurons
um muscle and so on. And here is where
we look through every possible
combination of um every possible amino
acid substitution at every position
along the capsid. Um
and uh
this the capsid here is about 738 amino
acids and then so and then we went to
higher levels in not just single amino
acid changes but but multiple up to 28
at a time. Now obviously you know that
the common notori blows up when you're
about three or four at a time especially
if you're letting them be anywhere in
the 738
aminoes but I'll show you how that I'm
sorry in that one uh I I think you all
intuitively know that red means that
it's much stronger than wild type and
blue might mean much weaker and uh and
and it's and the winners of the mutants
that win are are in different places for
the different tissues. So, I'll show you
specific example here. We're comparing
it to what was the very best in the
field at the time. It was everybody's
go-to for for brain and neural delivery.
Um, and we um we use this combination of
machine learning and multiplex libraries
to inject. We went straight to primates.
We did not do in vitro or yeast display
or mouse or anything. We went straight
to two different primate species and
injected a million different designs. So
these are all designed by machine
learning. They were not randomized by
PCR or anything any other random thing.
Every single one of the million was
designed which me and you'll see in the
next slide exactly what the consequence
is uh or but here the consequence we're
focusing on is 100 times better than the
previous best at targeting the brain.
You can see these are
uh allegedly at the same um intensity
um before the the the previous winner
and this new one called BCAP 1 or HD9
and uh we deargeted the liver 10fold.
Now deargeting the liver is quite
important. You want to keep the dosage
as low as possible. And if if a lot of
the material is going to be sequestered
in the liver, you both lose it from
where you want to target, but it's also
um
um a chance of having toxicity in the
liver. So that deargeting was important.
And so the way that we got these these
large libraries and the reason we use
machine learning to design them is that
when we don't use machine learning or
use poor models, we get a difficulty
where this is the the percent changes in
the in the uh we looked at a domain of
28 amino acids in this early experiment.
Um asking how how heavily we can bombard
it. The last slide I showed we could
change one at a time all over 738 amino
acids. Here we picked the surface of
domain of 28 amino acids and we had
trouble getting three or four amino
acids at a time without breaking it. So
it didn't work as a virus asset at all.
If we use logistic regression, some
other neural network methods, we could
get out to 26 27 28 all 28 at once and
not just an example but a whole library
that were that radically changed. We
hope that that sort of radical change
without breaking the virus would allow
us to get the new tissues and that's how
we got the new tissues. And I just want
to mention this is not limited to cap
viral capsules. It's limit it's it can
apply to all sorts of other categories
of of therapeutics and delivery methods.
So for example, proteins are a main one.
Um and here we didn't want to have a big
bulky capsid or nucleic acid hanging off
of it as a barcode. We had in the
previous one we had the benefit in the
previous one that that's natural for
AAV. Here we wanted a short peptide
which we call M codes and we could and
we made thousands of these. Now this
just shows 96 of them and shows how
clean we we co- co-developed co- machine
learning uh and and large library made
pairs of binders and uh barcodes. And
you can see there's almost no off
diagonal binding um in this um in this
combination of binders and barcodes. Um
here's a blowup showing this really dark
along the diagonal and and target. And
this is we've used this in a nonprofit
E11 bio which is doing a conneto uh at
about 100 times higher efficiency than
ever before. And that will allow us to
do mouse and human brain connectivity.
But mainly we're using it for these
tissue specific medicines where proteins
have the same story that I told you in
the last slide about um viral capsules.
And here's an example of you know the
protein equivalent what I was talking
about before for the brain um both
studies protein and caps were brain.
Here we're using a humanized mouse with
a human transferin receptor in the
brain. And we get a 10-fold enrichment
of the winner relative for the average
um
um protein uh in this set. And and in
each case, we use multiple barcodes for
the same protein. Make sure it's not
some barcode artifact. And what we find
in vitro is very different from what we
find in vivo. So we tend to do it in
vivo as close to human as possible.
either human eyes, mouse or primate.
And so this ML squared I think is
general. It's it's been the foundation
of almost all our recent startups from
my my lab. I've already mentioned Dino
Therapeutics with Eric and Manifold
thanks to Pierce and Gleb. Um Jura has
written this preprint which I encourage
you to read. It's it's we haven't done
much with it in terms of screening but
we have um synthesized in the 17th
designs without randomization
uh without
much randomization. Helix Nano Laya.ai
AI is a local company that's focused not
just on uh biotech but in science in
general and it's and one by one we're
going through fields where we'll pick at
you know an achievement of one of our
colleague companies and fields that we
know relatively little about and try to
exceed them you know so for example
good-hearted competition with Madna
which is a sibling company
um and then finally and I really want to
open this up for questions
uh setting aside enough time for that.
Um
uh we just want to end on these cell and
organ therapies. Um so
um you all know that there's a human
cell atlas and and a fantastic uh
resources on transcription for a variety
of different tissues, single cell
sequencing and so forth. We wanted to
figure out uh the regulatory. So
variance the function a lot of the
variants are regulatory either cis or
trans. And we'd like to figure out the
code that have that affects such
profound things of developmental uh and
tissue specific nature expression and so
forth. And and here is
we we made a a nearly comprehensive
transcription factor library. Um and we
we made in the first paper which is in
nature biotech thanks to Alex and Paris
300 different recipes and and some and
we characterize them by trans
transcription heat maps like this one
and we weren't
we would get some that looked synonymous
and and uh even though and these were
all single transcription factors. Most
of what we've done since then has been
two or more multiple transcription
factors required to get the tissue of of
interest. But we would get 10 different
solutions for endothelial cells. So this
is a broad category. We all know that
there's different very big differences
between endothelial cells in the brain
and the livers for example. But lumping
them together is 10 different recipes.
10 different recipes for neurons. Again,
there's great diversity with within that
category and in different recipes for
fiberglass. And we got we found to our
surprise and delight that about we came
to get used to that these recipes would
be 98% conversion in 4 days. Even though
when we started on this the standard was
to try to emulate what happens during
natural development where where it takes
hundreds of days to get through all the
developmental phases going through all
the different progenitors and it seemed
like that should be the goal and we
being synthetic
um were willing to take whatever we
could get. I think there are certain
advantages to doing it quickly and at
high efficiency.
Uh anyway, this this nature biotech
turned into this company GC Therapeutics
which has a couple of things moving into
clinical trials including
um
uh liodenderite precursor cells. These
these uh liytes are responsible for the
white matter which constitutes about uh
40% of your brain where where things
have to go fast and it wraps a certain
number of times around an axon with
myelin and demyelinating diseases
typically autoimmune diseases uh create
havoc with this and if you bring in
freshender sites they're going to
suffer the same fate although we
engineered these iligodender sites to
not only restore the myelin but also be
resistant at the cytoine uh uh
strategies uh for um autoimmunity in the
future. So this is one of the things
that we're doing. This second example
not from GZ therapeutics but from two
graduate students recent graduate
students from my lab who are interested
in developing ovarian follicles from uh
human stem cells and this is because uh
uh these going to be par uh dozens of
painful hormones as part of the IVF
process. We reduced the number and uh of
the of these injections reducing the the
cost by three-fold in the pain. The
oytes were immature. The eggs needed
maturation. We developed an IPS derived
granulosis cells. These are very much
like the support structure that happens
in ovarian follicles in vivo. And um
fast forward to the present, we're in
phase three clinical trials. As far as
we know, it's the first IPS-based
therapy um with FDA approval to to enter
phase three clinical trials. Somehow we
it's a very crowded field IPS based
therapies. We jump to the front in in
part because this is just maturing eggs.
It's not doing more than that.
Now that's that's how we can get tissues
fairly sophisticated tissues like
ovarian follicles. Um but when we want
really complicated organs and we're
focusing initially on kidney, liver and
heart um
we need something we need something
better than human so far. This may
change than human stem cell derived. And
for that we we go to a developmental
system that's very close to human in
size physiology and and then this has
been known for years. We didn't invent
this. In fact we were invited when when
uh three of the pioneers of the
xenotransplantation field read our
crisper paper. invited us to work on
this and and Luhan Yang who was a
graduate student posttock and co-founder
of eugenesis with me uh took this on as
a challenge and and we were very we're
all very grateful that she did. Um
there's hundreds of thousands of people
on dialysis that would love to be off
dialysis
even if it means having part of their
body be from a pig. Um and and one of
the things that the FDA was most
concerned about was that these patients,
all transplant patients except identical
twins uh are have uh immune suppressants
as part of the protocol. And uh every
pig organ produces lots of retrovirus
more than more than most mammals. And
each of these is we've we and others
have shown that will infect uh human
cells and then replicate in the human
cells and infect other cells. An immune
suppressed patient is a setup for uh
evolution uh of a zonotic virus and I
think we are all sick of zonotic viruses
uh and don't want to create a new one.
Um, so anyway, so we knocked them out
and it turned out it was very easy to do
with plain vanilla crisper. Um, we did
that many years ago and we've done it
many times since then in multiple
different pig strains. Um, we did three
knockouts. These were incredibly fast
acting rejections. These were not your
ordinary humanto human rejection. These
were u sugars. Um, and then we put in
seven trans gene. humanize the blood
compliment, the blood clotting, the
innate immunity and inflammation, the
seven human trans genes.
Um,
and we uh I'll show you the patient in
just a moment, but I wanted to say that
we're not just responding to the
incredible shortage of organs. We are uh
looking forward to enhancements of
various sorts uh including uh you know
DNA damage u immunity pathogens cancer
scessence all of which have precedence
in both natural variation and in
synthetic biology and I'm just going to
show you this uh the one which we both
worry about and are encouraged by it's
very interesting and it's has to do with
variance and function um is these are
human specific pathogens there's a large
number of parasites, bacteria and
viruses.
Um but then there are also some subset
which are present shared with humans and
pigs and uh we need to worry about these
and the ones previous slide uh depending
on whether it's a whole organism thing
uh or a cellular level um we may not
have to worry about all of these.
And this is uh uh a video hopefully of
uh Tim Andrews who's now been eight
months off of diialysis with this uh pig
kidney from from uh that I've been
describing. Um thanks to these surgeons.
Let's see if Oh, there we go. Um so
that's the the pig kidney being
transferred over. Uh he's been 8 months.
We have another patient who has uh was
treated in in June. This is him very uh
excited about um about being off
dialysis
and I just want to open up for just
broad discussion plenty of time uh but I
want to thank all the members of the
personal genome project. These are we
have we had for a while annual meetings
of the not just of the scientists and
the engineers and the physicians but the
patients as well which is something that
was afforded by the fact that we are not
the identified
um and then I also want to thank my this
is my alumni this is not my actual lab
size this is alumni meeting okay so uh
open up for questions
What an impressive talk covering so many
aspects relevant to VF George. It's
phenomenal. Are there questions in the
audience?
Don't be shy. Engage.
I can start. Um so you're spending this
arc from the personal genome
project over longevity which clearly is
the most common disease of all if you
want so to rare disease indications that
are genetically anchored. Um each of
these pillars with enormous track
records of advancing it to the clinic.
How do they interface? How do you draw
conclusions from personal genome data
for predicting longevity targets and
identifying those that will be likely
having an impact in patients?
>> Yeah. So,
so even though I've been a strong
advocate for personalized medicine since
before it was called that, um
I also feel that there's a lot of common
diseases that are better treated as if
they were diseases of our species rather
than of individuals and aid and I think
a lot of age- related diseases will fall
into that category like you can
you can redefine a lot of common
diseases as age- related diseases. Not
all of them, but but many of them. And
so it uh and I also feel that that baked
into the personal genome project before
it even started was the idea that a lot
of these diseases were avoidable um but
preventable by uh genetic counseling.
And even though I have
advocated uh gene therapies for rare
diseases, I've also pointed out
continuously that there is a more
cost-effective way to do it long term as
we go forward. Um
which is to get the entire population
sequenced. Um it is now definitely cost
effective to do that. Um I I estimate
there's a 10-fold return on investment
uh
uh if we did that uh mainly due to uh
carrier uh screening of very serious
mandelian diseases may affect 3 to 5% of
the population but that 3 to 5% cost
millions of dollars per patient not to
mention loss of of um anxiety for the
whole family and community. So, um, why
we haven't done that yet. I mean, the
price point has been there for many
years now. It's a there's some kind of
social, uh, thing going on. Um, and it's
not just social stigma or anything
simple. It's u has to do with econ
health economics and and other things,
but I think it will happen soon. Um, so
that's the personal side. And then the
other side is using PGP resources to
help develop things for common diseases.
>> Yeah, great.
No questions after such a talk. Casper,
I have I have many more. I can keep
going.
>> Thanks a lot, George. Super inspiring as
always. I was just you made an off-hand
comment uh that I hope I understood
correctly about longevity being more
complex and polygenic which is probably
true than other diseases as I understood
it at least and I was just wondering why
you think longevity in terms of treating
it might be more difficult to treat than
schizophrenia or height I mean we're not
trying to treat height I guess but you
know just why would that be more complex
do you think
>> I think the question uh is uh you
whether I think why do I think uh
longevity be harder than schizophrenia
and other complex diseases. And I think
I misspoke. I actually think that
longevity may be that that all of them
are easier than they look. Um it doesn't
mean that we're going to solve it
tomorrow. I'm not making specific
predictions of when, but I think we have
now exponential technologies. We're
becoming more and more accustomed to
doing multiplex editing um and doing,
you know, population in a dish, G-W was
in a dish and all these things. I um and
I think a lot of the solutions we'll
come up with are not just reversal of a
mutation. It's thinking out of the box
as to what how the whole system works.
Um and uh so no, I don't think longevity
is necessarily hard. I don't want to
misrepresent it as being too easy
either. I mean, it's just it's just
plain old science and we're going to get
it done hopefully before you and I die.
Romania,
that was a it was a beautiful talk. It
gives a a lot of hope for the future. I
wanted to kind of focus on a piece at
the end where you're talking about
specifically uh uh going after, you
know, like the pig kidneys, the
engineered pig kidneys. I have a bunch
of people in my life who have chronic
kidney disease and I'm want and and one
of them who is basically at the point of
needing a dialysis and a transplant
doesn't want it because he is basically
saying I would rather die than feel the
than have to take imunosuppressants
every day. So kind of pulling forward
from where we currently are at with the
whole xenotransplantation concept. How
just as like a like a pulse check, how
far do you feel like we are from getting
to a point where you get transplanted an
organ that you know is likely been grown
in in another animal or in a vat, but
then you know it is it is matched to you
immunologically and you don't need
long-term uh immune management.
>> Right. Absolutely terrific question. Um
I think most of the patients that I've
run into and heard about uh would far
prefer to have immunosuppressants than
dialysis. Dialysis is associated with
brain fog and almost as soon as you
leave the diialysis clinic you start
your start body starts building up
toxins and so on. Um that nevertheless
our immediate goal now that we think
that we have something that will work
for getting patients off of dialysis is
to get them off of immunosuppressants as
well. And one of the I I mean I can't
tell you what the answer is yet because
I don't know but but one of the things
we're trying is to we I said we humanize
these with seven genes. We're going to
try to crank that up to 10,000 genes.
And it's not going to be simple because
there's all kinds of interactions that
are species specific, but it's it'll be
an interesting challenge. And this is
how we learn about biology uh is by
trying to do something uh with a very
specific goal in mind and allows us
sometimes to take um shortcut. Um so
that's one thing. The other thing is
we're looking at tolerance. Uh so
there's there there are some tolerance
um experiments that look promising um
and um and all of the tricks that are
being used for allergenic uh cell
therapies
um might be applicable to Zeno as well.
In fact, I think we mutually reinforce
each other that people that are doing
allergenic rather than are saying, well,
if they can do zeno, we can do
allergenic
modulo the the uh imunosuppressants. So
anyway, I think there's a few pathways
and we're going as fast as we can on
each of those. I completely agree immune
suppressence is the next thing to do.
Yeah. Or get rid of.
>> We have a question back there.
Hello, thank you so much for your time.
So I just wanted to ask because I'm
curious about your thoughts. So as you
discussed AI and machine learning have
shown a lot of promise in improving the
drug development process over the past
you know decade and even you know even
different applications before that. So
I'm curious, what do you think are the
current limitations in AI and machine
learning applications in drug
development that can and most likely
will be improved in the next few or five
years,
>> right? So there's uh there many
limitations uh that are seem to be
falling away quickly. Uh there's a
little bit of hype uh that we need to be
cautious of. Excuse
me. And uh you know I would say the um
uh there are two kinds of categories of
where you can apply AI if if you want to
make a dichotomy here. One one is where
you're observing something that's that's
so big you can't reproduce it in the
laboratory. And then there's set of
things that are easy to reproduce and
maybe even make libraries of millions
and billions in the li in the laboratory
that are faithfully represent some
aspect of mechanism or disease or
therapy. Um you know examples of big
things or things that you can you can
see in populations for example are um
but things that you can do in lab which
I focused on here even the lab could
involve primates humanized primates and
so forth. I think that AI is limited by
data uh and especially so in um in h in
uh human biology
and one of the things that Laya is doing
differently than I wouldn't say all but
most AI company most AI companies are um
scraping the internet including PubMed
and and all sorts of very deep resources
but most of those resources were not
designed with AI in mind even though AI
is very flexible it's not infinitely
flexible just like human minds are not
infinitely flexible and anyway so as an
alternative just scraping the internet
and PubMed um we're developing these big
data sets in house um recognizing that
almost every new technology that comes
online can almost immediately redo the
last two years of work in its field um
um or I'm sorry last infinity uh in its
field in about two years or less and So,
um I think that's going to be
that is the main problem and it's and
with a very obvious solution.
>> There's a question back there just
applauding your statement that data are
needed to improve AI and models.
>> Hey George, uh yeah, thanks for the
great summary of all the amazing
technology you brought into this world
together with your lab. It's phenomenal.
Um my question is about some of the data
you showed on the longevity. So um you
prolonged I believe it was dogs
lifespan. Um do they also also health uh
age healthier because I guess the the
goal would be to live longer but not to
be sick for longer.
>> Yeah it's a great question. That is our
goal is not is I is you know reversal of
aging age related is certainly at a
cellular level the the Yamanaka factors
do reverse aging. I mean that's that's
for sure. Um we are that particular
experiment you're referring to were the
three of the Yamanaka factors OS and K.
Uh
the
uh the dosing was done very late in
life. So they were very old and I don't
think there was a well doumented
reversal of those um traits. Um
it's it's the the field is still young.
I'm not and you should not be
discouraged at this point encouraged
that we got them to live a little bit
longer. And there and there are multiple
other experiments I could go on I could
give an entire talk on work from many uh
labs that are suddenly getting these uh
survival curves that are going off far
to the to the right.
>> Great. Sorry you have to ask over the
break. Um we have to cut it off now.
Other than could you give the V2F
community one sentences of what you
encourage us to think about in embark on
>> unprepared uh but uh uh I would say a AI
especially coupled with with large
libraries um to the extent you can do it
in um humanized as close to human as
possible we've even used deedent models
where we have humans that whose uh
surviving family have given permission
for the their body to be used science.
That's as close that's really as close
as you can get without putting a human
at risk. So humanized primates and
deedants I think uh are key component
for but you want to get as much data as
possible out of each of those
experiments. It shouldn't just be a one
dose, one drug per
>> Yeah.
>> Because primates and humans are
extremely uh precious um resources. So
we try to get at least a million
different uh drugs and multiple data
points per drug in in each of those
precious uh samples. Thank you.
>> Great George. Thank you so much. Um
thanks everyone. This was a wonderful
first session.