Okay, next speaker we move on to third
category the Nobel drug delivery system.
Speaker is Dr. Jacob Witten and Jacob
Witten is a postto fellow at professor
Daniel Anderson's lab at co institute
for integrant cancer research. So his
talk today is advanced in deep don
particle for messenger RNA delivery and
focus on ionizable lipid designed by
using neural network. So Jacob, please.
Thanks. Thanks everybody for coming. I'm
excited to talk to you today about my
work on uh developing better gene
therapies with AI. Um so just to start
off, you know, uh I'm going to be
focusing on developing development of
genetic medicines. I'm going to be
showing a lot of data in the lung. And
here's really the reason why is that
genetic medicine in particular uh could
address a a ton of critically unmet
needs in lung disease. And so that
includes things like rare genetic
monogenic diseases like cystic fibrosis
or primary silary diskynesia that
affects tens of thousands of patients
worldwide as well as more complex but
also more common diseases some of the
leading causes of death and morbidity in
the world including asthma, COPD, lung
cancer and adopathic pulmonary fibrosis
that affect millions or even hundreds of
millions of people. And in all of these
cases, we have a really straightforward
sense in in a lot of context just due to
our really extensive knowledge of
disease mechanisms and the genetics of
different disease of how we might go
about treating or preventing or curing
these diseases if we could deliver the
right genes to the lung in particular
the lung epithelium. And one of the nice
things features of the lung epithelium
is that it's relatively straightforward
to deliver high doses specifically to
the lung epithelium via inhalation
particularly a process called
nebulization where patients will inhale
a mist containing your medicine and
it'll go directly to the lungs. And so
when you get this nice local delivery
directly to the lungs, you get a you get
a high dose in the particular organ of
interest. uh and uh but then you get a
low systemic delivery so you don't have
to worry nearly as much about the
systemic side effects and systemic
toxicity that you can see when you give
something like an introvenous uh gene
therapy. So this is really what we're
going to be targeting. Although a lot of
the techniques that I'm going to talk
about can really apply to many different
tissues and I will show a little bit of
data related to intramuscular delivery
for something like an intramuscular
vaccine. But anyway, so we have all
these diseases. We have all this sense
of the genetics of how we might modulate
the genetics via delivery of some kind
of gene and that would treat the disease
if we could actually go ahead and
deliver the gene to the lung epithelium.
And this turns out to be much more
difficult than was initially thought. So
um just to give a sense here of the
difficulty of the problem. So the CFTR
gene disco was discovered in 1989 as the
uh cause mutations in CFTR cause cystic
fibrosis. And to give a sense of the
expectations around this time and the
excitement when the CFTR gene was
discovered. We have this great quote
here that the expectation was all you
needed was to get a little bit of CFTR
to act in the lungs and hey press so
you'd have a Nobel Prize. Now, avid
followers of the Nobel Prize may notice
that there has not been a Nobel Prize
for gene therapy for CF. Um, and it
turns out it's a much more difficult
problem than it initially appeared. So,
uh, initial efforts focused on
delivering healthy CFTR to the lung to
get CFTR expressed using an adenoviral
vector after about eight years of
clinical trials. These were abandoned
due to basically no efficacy. Uh,
likewise, people tried adino associated
viral vectors for about eight years and
abandoned it. although those efforts
have recently restarted and we're
hopeful in the field that those are
going to go forward. Uh likewise, people
tried nonviral delivery of CFTR
expressing DNA via liposomes. Again,
after about 20 years, these showed uh
either very limited or no efficacy. And
so these trials were were abandoned. And
more recently there's been a lot more of
excite a lot more excitement around mRNA
uh lipid nanop particles much more about
which shortly and uh have a lot of
promise for delivery to the lung
epithelium for treatment of these
different diseases. Now of course mrna
lmpps also are not just useful in the
lung. The vast majority of you you know
me included have probably gotten uh
either the fizer or beyond uh fiser
beyond or madna mrna vaccines for covid.
So you know we know that these things
work clinically and we know you know
that the they can be really useful and
really help patients. So this is really
the focus of my work is around lip and
nanoparticles trying to push lip and
nanoparticles forward as much as
possible in this uh but all throughout
the body particularly focusing on this
lung delivery space and so I thought I'd
first say you know what is a lipid
nanoparticle they're the most clinically
advanced nonviral gene delivery system
right with the mRNA vaccines and so
they're comprised of uh r well
subnucleic acid typically RNA mRNA in
particular uh mixed with an ethanol
phase that contains various lipids. So
it contains helper lipids, things like
uh ethanol uh things like cholesterol
and a phospholipid and a pegolated lipid
as well as kind of the secret sauce of a
lipid nanoparticle the ionizable lipid.
Now what happens is when you mix these
two phases together using some kind of
micrfluidic mixing system, you get a
nanoparticle. These nanoparticles have
to be stable in the lung mucous layer or
in serum or what have you and then get
taken up by cells in a process called
endoccytosis at which point uh they the
nanoparticles need to break out of the
endoome that's called endooal escape and
the nanoparticle can then disassemble
the RNA can be translated into whatever
therapeutic or antigenic protein you're
interested in. Now I promise much more
about ionizable lipids. So these, you
know, as as the name kind of suggests,
these are lipids that have an ionizable
head group and a lipid tail. Um, and
they're really critically important for
encapsulating the nucleic acid as well
as for achieving endooal escape and
uptake in the cell type of interest. And
so for a particular application, you
really need to exquisitely tune the
chemistry of these ionizable lipids in
order to non-toxically deliver to your
cell types of interest. This is an
incredibly difficult problem, but
ionizable lipids have shown a lot of
promise for being able to do this. So,
just to give an example here, this is
SM102, the ionizable lipid found in the
Madna vaccine. And I'm just going to
highlight here the ionizable head group,
which has a tertiary amine. This will
become positively charged at low pH,
such as the pH uh of the endoome after
endooal acidification. This helps with
triggering endooal escape as well as a
lipid tail. And the precise uh chemistry
and structure of the lipid tail is going
to determine how effective endooal
escape is. So it's critically important.
And so the question really becomes how
do we find the right ionizable lipid for
each task. So SM102 is exceptionally
good as an intramuscular vaccine. That's
why it's you know approved for the the
COVID vaccine. But it turns out that
it's not quite as good at delivery to
the lung epithelium. We're going to need
to look for different chemistries there.
And so the Anderson lab uses a variety
of kind of high throughput screening and
rational design approaches to find
ionizable lipids for particular tasks.
But here I want to focus on the work
that we've been doing around AI for
design of ionizable lipids. So you know
AI as we probably all know is really
revolutionizing the life sciences. The
Nobel Prize for uh in in chemistry I
believe last year was given to uh deep
mind and the Baker lab for uh protein
structure analysis type of tasks. things
like using alpha fold for protein
structure prediction or using RF
diffusion for protein structure
generation. But this is not the only
place where AI has been really useful.
So for example uh people have used a a
machine learning paradigm called message
passing neural networks to design
antibiotics in silico that can attack uh
antibiotic resistant bacteria. And so
just in a in a general sense what it
takes to use AI to do something in in
the life sciences or really anything is
you need two things. You need a machine
machine learning architecture. This can
be you know a giant set of transformers
like is used in um in you know AI like
chat GPT or or quad or so on. Uh or and
you also need a large quantity of
training data and this is really why
protein structure analysis is advanced
so far. We have the protein data bank
which has hundreds of thousands of uh
structures of proteins that we can train
a model to predict as well as huge
amounts of things like multiple uh uh
multiple sequence alignments and so on
that give information about structural
relationships between related proteins.
But when we don't have protein datab
bank we can still do our best to find
data sets and I'll talk about uh the
approach they took to to get those data
sets.
And so the um so the approach that I
took to design ionizable lipids uh is
something that I call lion or lipid
optimization using neural networks. And
so I said I needed two things. You need
training data and a model architecture.
So the model architecture is based on
something called the the the thing I
mentioned earlier called a message
passing neural network. And so what
happens here is you take the ionizable
lipid chemical structure. This can be
represented mathematically as a graph.
There's kind of a natural way to encode
the graph um as a vector. This is that
message passing uh neural network or
also known as a graphical neural network
sort of equivalent here. And this gets
mixed with various uh metadata about the
task that's trying to be accomplished
with an LNP formulation parameters. I'm
not going to go into the details uh too
much there though I'm happy to ask
answer questions. The so anyway the
output of the MPNN gets mixed with this
metadata put into a feed for neural
network and it outputs a predicted
delivery. So what you then do is once
you have a trained Lion model you rank
possible ionizable lipids. So you say,
"Okay, model, I'm going to make a an LNP
with this particular ionizable lipid or
that ionizable lipid, which is going to
have better delivery." And so the model
will will just rank uh different lipids,
and then you can take the ones that the
model likes the most, synthesize them,
and test them for delivery. Now, there's
our model architecture. I said, you
know, you need model architecture, you
need data. So here I uh it turns out
that you can actually scrape a ton of
literature from the data. those actually
never intended to be used for machine
learning, but we could nevertheless
adapt it as training data for machine
learning. So some that the Anderson lab
as well as other labs love to do is
screen large libraries of ionizable
lipids for mRNA delivery. So just to
take an example here, this is a library
uh sorry for the small text. I guess
I'll just voice it over. Um that was uh
many different ionizable lipids
generated with a three component
reaction between an amine, isocyanide
and a ketone. It's a nice high yield
predictable reaction. And so if you take
about 10 of each component, you get 10
by 10 by 10 or a thousand different
ionizable lipids. You can screen. What
they did was they screened all of them
for mRNA delivery in this case the
helila cells. And so this is just a heat
map of red is better delivery, blue is
worse delivery. And so we basically have
a thousand data points here. And you can
use this directly to say okay, which is
the best cyanizable lipid out of this
set. Or you can do what I did which is
take this data and use this training
data for uh for the lion model. And so
then what I did was I go to the
literature and I just find as many
papers as I can basically publish heat
maps scrape that data. Each different
paper here is is is a is a different
data set and then you just feed it all
into the lion model. Um and now you have
a fully nicely trained model. Okay. So
now we have our model and now we would
like to not just you know see how it
looks in silicon in a computer. We want
to actually make new things in the
world. Um and so uh I went uh worked
with a another chemist in the lab I
adjust Raji who came up with this uh
beautiful four component lipid synthesis
scheme again sort of ooi reaction base
with a ketone caroxilic acid amine and
isocyanide. These again react in a nice
predictable way and you get a gigantic
combinatorial explosion of possible
lipids that could be synthesized. Right?
So with about 50 of each component
commercially available, that's 50 to the
fourth different ionizable lipids that
could be synthesized. So a lot of
different options. And so here what I
did was I narrowed all those options
down. So I started with about 1.6
million candidate structures that could
in principle be synthesized with pretty
straightforward commercially available
components. Um and then narrowed that
down to 33 which I then screened in vivo
for intramuscular mRNA delivery just as
a nice simple uh pre-screening assay.
And then after a little bit more
optimization, which uh I'm not going to
bore you with the precise details here,
we ended up with these three key
structures, FO32, FO35, and EB66 that
were identified by
Lion. And so, first thing I wanted to
do, you know, I will get to the
respiratory tract, I promise. First
thing I wanted to do was just see how
these things look for intramuscular mRNA
delivery. This is kind of a nice thing
to do to look at how these uh how these
things might do for an intramuscular
mRNA vaccine. Um and so the data that
I'm going to be showing you for the next
few slides is luminescence data. So just
to describe a little bit what what I'm
talking about here, uh what happens is
you take mRNA encoding firefly
luciferase. This is the gene that makes
fireflies glow. And so you put it
package that in L&PS inject it
intramuscularly. Six hours later you
basically just see how much they're the
mice are glowing. And more glowing means
more luciferase protein was made which
means better transfaction. So higher
numbers are better in the data that I'm
going to be showing you here. And so
this is an example of what the raw data
looks like. You can just image these
mice live and they kind of will light
up. Red is lighting up more better
delivery. And so here I'm going to be
showing FO32 in blue and FO35 in red
comparing to solid circle controls. So
for example here I'm showing the madna
co vaccine formulation SM102 over here
on the right. and FO32 and FO35 are both
outperforming SM102 as well as this
highly potent preclinical benchmark that
we love to use in the Anderson lab
called CKK12. And this holds true across
four different orders of magnitude. FO32
and FO35 are consistently outperforming
uh at least matching or usually
outperforming the two different controls
that we were able to throw at and EB66
has also been quite potent as well.
Okay, so you know I promised respiratory
tract. Let's get to that. So first thing
I did was looked at intraasal delivery.
This is sort of a model of what you
would do as um an intraasal vaccine. So
intraasal vaccines could potentially be
really good at generating sterilizing
immunity against viruses, be much better
at generating herd immunity. Um and so
you get uh less in the way of
breakthrough infections and that would
be really helpful uh for you know new
viral pandemics for example. Um so here
you have the mice inhale the nanop
particles basically into their nose
while anesthetized and then their noses
light up as you can see here. And then
when we quantify the data, we see that f
of 32 and 35 match or even maybe
slightly exceed every solid circle
control that we're able to throw at it.
And this includes the two controls I've
talked about as well as one that we
published on last year as being
specifically good for intraasal
delivery. So we're really exceptionally
potent here. And the next thing we
wanted to do was look at deep lung
delivery. So here we did oroaringial
installation where the mice inhale the
L&P basically into their deep lungs. And
so it's the same deal here. The lungs
light up. I'm showing representative
images of Xvivo lungs lighting up uh
with luciferase signal as well as seeing
that FO32 is outperforming every control
that we're able to throw at it whether
it's our standard set of controls or
L&PS that have been specifically
published for lung delivery by a factor
of anywhere between three and 10. So
this is really um really exciting. Um
and again FO35 is basically matching
matching our our best control. Um and
the next thing we wanted to do was look
at nebulize delivery to mice. So, as I
mentioned, nebulization, where you kind
of make a mist that the patient will
inhale in, is a really nice, gentle way
to deliver to actual human patient
lungs. They can do this at home with
home nebulizers. In this case, we're
nebulizing to mice. And here, what we're
seeing is ZO32 is able to match 11717.
This is a lipid I'll mention it briefly
in a little bit a little more uh that we
published on a couple years ago as again
being very specifically good for
nebulize delivery being state-of-the-art
for nebulization having very good
stabilization properties to the
nebulization process. So this again is
is really exciting showing that we're
able to match or exceed the
state-of-the-art and in basically every
test that we're able to throw at these
nanoparticles. Now one question that you
might be asking is what is lion actually
doing right? So, are we just making
minor tweaks to stuff that we already
know works, or are we potentially making
really new nanoparticles with new kinds
of chemistry that people might not have
thought of testing before uh before the
AI model basically suggested that? And
so to kind of answer that question, I
want to show some of the structures of
either FDA approved in the case of the
Madna or Fiser vaccines or al-Nam's MC3
lipid or highly advanced clinical uh
lipids. This is LP1 from Intellia and A9
from Achuatas. And the important thing
here is that these all have very very
similar chemical structures. In fact, I
believe some that I don't quote me on
this, but I believe some of them might
be suing each other over how similar
they are. Um, so don't quote me on that.
I'm not 100% sure. Um so uh the the
important thing here is that these these
have basically uh very classic kind of
branched tails in a very straightforward
way that's known to help with endooal
escape. They tend to be either
completely saturated or have just a
couple uh cy double
bonds. Um and basically what they have
is these different lipids are variation
on this kind of branch tail branchtail
theme shot through Esther is the
occasional cy double bond and otherwise
saturated. And so the lipids here that
were designed by AI are actually really
radically different in terms of their
structure. So FO32 for example has an
alkine group which again you won't see
in these in these lipid in these really
advanced preclinical lipids or clinical
lipids I should say. And as well as FO35
and EB66 have these tarpine tails that
are really radically different from
anything that you see either in the
training set or in these kind of uh
clinical benchmarks. And so what what's
happening here is Lion is actually
picking out these really radically
different chemical structures, showing
that there's regions of chemical space
that had not been explored before, but
nevertheless are able to yield really
potent ionizing lipids, really potent
mrna delivery. So what I've shown you so
far is we can make mouse lungs light up,
right? But there's a couple of questions
here that are really important. Number
one, mice are notorious for not being
people. Uh many things work in mice that
turn out not to work when you scale the
people. And number two, it doesn't
really answer the question of what cells
are being transfected. And so to to get
at this question, I first want to just
back up a little bit and give you a
sense of what I mean when I'm going to
be talking about what cells are
transfected. Just a brief a brief point
on lung anatomy. So the lung is kind of
this fractally branching structure where
when you breathe in, air flows through
this fractal structure and into alvoli
where gas exchange occurs. And so the
lungs a little bit can be thought of as
like two organs that to oversimplify
somewhat where you've got the conducting
airways
um where air flows through and then the
respiratory airways with the alvoli
where gas exchange occurs and these are
very structurally and functionally
distinct. And so the conducting airways
this is where air passed through. This
is where you get mucous secretion. So
it's a major site of disease for uh for
things like cystic fibrosis, chronic
bronchitis, a major site for asthma.
Importantly, mice are exceptionally poor
models of the conducting airways. They
lack a lot of the physiology that a
human airway is going to have. The
industry standard here for studying
conducting airways is actually ferrets.
Um, now in the respiratory airways, uh
this is where gas exchange occurs.
You've got pulmonary surfactant and
alvolar macrofasages. So very different
from uh from the presence of mucus. It's
a major site of disease for things like
pulmonary fibrosis, alvolar proteinosis,
also a major site for asthma. And and
there's more diseases as well. And the
important thing here is while mice are
somewhat better models of alvoli I think
than they are for conducting airways
once again ferrets are a really really
good industry standard for pre-clinical
studies for studying the
alvoli. So we wanted to get at what our
nanoparticles are doing number one in
these sub regions of the lung and number
two in a more relevant model than mice.
And so to do this we collaborated with
University of Iowa which has these
beautiful reporter ferret models for
studying this kind of problem. And so
these are ferrets where every cell
expresses TD tomato so they're red. If
you deliver a pro if you uh get activity
of creep recominase it rearranges the
genome uh so that these cells instead of
expressing TD tomato now express GFP. So
transfected cells turn from red to
green. So the way this works is uh we
administer via microspayer LNP
encapsulating CRM mRNA and then two
weeks later we image the ferret lungs to
see what cells have been transfected in
other in other words what cells have
turned green and so here this is the
kind of whole lobe images um of ferrets
that have been transfected with
different LMPs and so we've got this
IR11717 that I mentioned before as being
really good for nebulize delivery here
we're not nebulizing but we wanted to
see what it could do in in a micros
sprayer as Well, as well as our two AI
designed lipids, FO32 and FO35. And so
now let's zoom in and see what these
things are actually doing. Um, so all
three L&PS, it turns out, are able to
transfect alvoli. So these kind of what
we're seeing here in these zoomed in
images is these kind of diffuse
squiggles that are turning green. The
diffuse squiggles, for lack of a better
way to put it, are what alvoli looks
like on histologology here. And we're
able to turn them green. So that's nice.
The next thing we want to look at is the
conducting airway epithelium. you know
the site of disease for a lot of mucco
obstructive diseases and what we see
here is really interesting. So, uh,
basically here what a conducting airway
looks like is a little kind of black
blob where air would be flowing into the
screen essentially and then the rim is
the conducting airway epithelium that we
want to transfect and it's basically
undetectable. And we can also just look
at the the trachea where it's the same
kind of thing just bigger. Um, and we're
basically unable to to detect
transfected lung epithelia um in the
conducting airways with the 11717 which
is interesting because it hit conducting
airways just fine in mice. again
reinforcing mice are not going to cut it
for this uh organ system. But FO32 and
FO35 are able to really robustly
transfect both the trachea and smaller
conducting airways as you can see from
the zoomed in images of these kind of
rims of these uh black blobs turning uh
green. And one really interesting
observation we were able to make is that
FO35 uniquely is able to transfect sub
mucosal glands. So sub mucosal glands
are very important for airway
homeostasis. um they secrete mucus, they
secrete amn microbial peptides for many
different diseases. These are the cells
that you really desperately uh need to
transfect if you want to have a
therapeutic impact on um on these
diseases. Something like cystic fibrosis
for example. So this is really exciting
to see. Um now ferrets are really great
but uh uh much like mice are not humans,
ferrets are still not quite humans. So
then we wanted to see what these things
could do in human cells. And so to to
look at this because we can't just treat
a human quite yet, uh we grew uh air
liquid interface cultures. And when you
grow an airquid interface culture with
the appropriate media media using
bronchial epithelial cells, you can
generate something that looks very
invivo- like. So this is just an example
H& stain of an ALI culture that I grew
um where you can see dense silation on
top and something called a
pseudoratified epithelium very similar
physiologically to an actual stain of a
human trachea that you can see below.
And so we're really able to reproduce
the physiology of the conducting
airways. And so here in collaboration uh
with BEu which has a IPSC derived uh
cystic fibrosis uh air liquid interface
uh uh bronchilithelial culture model. um
we were able to transfect these ALI
cultures with Mcherry mRNA and turn a
lot of the cells red which means you
know we can uh transfect humanlike lung
tissue and you can kind you can also
kind of zoom in with confocal microscopy
and see things like siliated cells being
really robustly transfected um you can
we can also do this with primary humor
and airway cultures as we did
collaboration with the uh the CF found
cystic fibrosis foundation and here
we're able to see uh at our highest dose
transffection of about 4% of cells which
doesn't sound like much, but it's
actually very difficult to even get any
uh any detectable transfaction at all.
So 4% of cells is actually quite robust
for a single dose of these particularly
really really difficult airway cultures
to transfect. And that we can also look
at things like cell types. So here we're
able to transfect secretary cells which
is really useful for uh in particular
here for for for CF um but is also
useful for all sorts of other diseases.
Um and so to conclude here, you know,
I'm uh I I think this hopefully shows
that we can really use AI to get a new
chemical space um you know, in terms of
ioniz that that we can actually do
really really important and really
really advanced pre-clinical work with
the lipids that AI is designing. Um and
with that I would like to thank uh my
adviser Dan and Bob and uh my
collaborators Rajie Manon and Sandra
Bartley in particular. Um and I'm happy
to take some questions. Thank you very
much. There you go. for questions.
Thank you.
Hi. Uh thank you for the talk. It was
really interesting and I really
appreciate it. Uh especially slide 13
which is where my question was about the
IP landscape. Um I am generally very
excited about L&PS and whenever I see
exciting uh data for especially invivo
reprogramming I want to try and include
that in our you know our workflow.
Um the issue I do come back to is the IP
landscape. So I think you are correct.
Last I checked uh Madna, Fizer and Alen
Lam are all suing each other and uh I'm
I'm an organic chemist formally trained
and those structures are very similar.
So it's going to be a long battle. Um,
so what I was wondering is could you is
is it feasible to
use published IP or a published patents
as a training set data to guide the AI
models away from murky I'll call it
murky IP space right now since it's
still in the courts. Yeah. Would that
bias it too much I guess? Yeah. So
there's two things that you could do. So
thing number one you can try to scrape
that data because they often actually
publish activity data in their patents.
So, I've thought about scraping these.
It turns out to be really difficult to
scrape. Like, I think with every new
update and, you know, GPT3, 44, quad 2,
3, 4, or whatever, I hope that finally
it's going to be good enough to scrape
to to scrape those patents to give me
more training data because I think
there's probably at least as much
training data in the patent literature
um as there is in in the kind of
peer-reviewed literature. The second
question of can you steer away from
patent space, you know, is a good one
that I haven't thought about too much. I
I I don't know why you couldn't because
it would be relatively straightforward
as you're kind of doing your incilico
screen of activity to also just do a
similarity score to everything found in
the literature if again you could decode
those structures which current image
analysis is very bad at turning images
of structures into like a smile string
that can be further processed. So
there's kind of just technical
limitations there that if I had either a
giant army of undergrads or GPT7 I could
probably handle but I have neither right
now. Thank you.
Question.
Uh, hi. Uh, I was wondering if I
understood correctly. The model is
maximizing potency. I was wondering if
there's challenges with safety or
stability that can be messed up when the
potency is fixed by AI because it
doesn't seem like there's a And if I may
ask a second one
um I can wait. I I actually forgot my
second one. Okay. So So you asked two
questions. One about safety, one about
stability. So think about stability. You
know, if you're predicting activity,
being unstable is probably bad for
activity. So I expect that's kind of
wrapped up in there. But you know if
you're talking about things like
manufacturability or like kind of
stibility during shipment yeah that's
like a little bit of an unknown. These
problems generally can be solved if with
enough kind of like figuring out like
the exact optimal synthesis parameters.
The question about safety is also a
really important one because um you know
when you're doing endooal escape you're
fundamentally destabilizing membranes
and this is a dangerous thing to be
doing and so you often see more potent
lipids tend to be a little bit more
toxic and you know there's a sense to to
which the relevant question is not how
potent are you but how large is your
therapeutic window even if the lipid is
not very potent. If it's completely
non-toxic you could drink it like water
it doesn't matter so much if it's less
potent. Um so you know we haven't seen
like this is
like one thing to say is there really
isn't data to train a model on this kind
of thing. So we can't really train a
model on therapeutic window you um
number two we have not actually seen
significantly different toxicity between
this the these lipids and any other
lipids. So as of now I would say that's
like a gap but we haven't actually
observed it empirically being a
particular issue. Um if we had huge
amounts of safety data that would be
great but but but we don't. Um but these
lipids do seem perfectly safe as best we
can tell. Now I remember my second
question. Um so you know we just saw
Mona and Verex clinical
trial showing some tolerability issue
and this has been ongoing for any
inhalation any delivery to long for few
decades now. How much better is good
enough? Like you're increasing potency
and you're saying, "Okay, this is going
to be three times better, five times
better." But can we somehow make a guess
of how much better is good enough? Do we
need thousand times better or maybe five
times better? So I'm going to be really
interested in the data that both that
that Vertex Arcturus and Recode who
should all be publishing results this
year if not this half of this year are
showing in terms of measurement of
transfaction as well as 4D molecular
therapeutics and AEV company that's
that's doing nebulized trials. The short
answer is I don't know. There's a lot of
complexities around the biology of of CF
that make this difficult. So for
example, they may be getting very potent
transffection, but they're not getting
transffection this rare cell type called
the pulmonary ionosite. And so that
maybe is distorting chloride transport
in a way that attenuates uh kind of
clinical benefit. Or maybe they'll show
a clinical benefit and we're actually
there. Like it's very hard to say
without that kind of data. Um
uh and and it also may vary by by by
disease. Um
uh sorry your question is just how much
better do we need to do? Yeah. Um and
then but then but then also regarding
tolerability there's been some recent
results out uh that I think have been
really exciting on the tolerability
front understanding the effect of
membrane rupture on uh the induction of
inflammation and how you can attenuate
that. So for example uh the use of uh
galactin inhibitor called thiod
thiodalacttoside has has now been I
guess in a preprint has been shown to
really reduce but a printer that that I
trust that looks like solid data has
been shown to really reduce inflammation
driven by LMPS. So the toxicity is
really now starting to be zeroed in on
and there's going to be ways to reduce
it. So I don't think this this this
stuff with uh the like the effect of um
glectins following membrane uh rupture
that may be a major component of the
safety concerns and it also may be
fixable with these inhibition inhibition
of glection glectin or with selection of
ionizable lipids that use this different
uh membrane repair path called escort.
So there's starting to be a lot more
known about safety concerns and how to
actually assay them in vitro and in vivo
and how we can avoid them with ionizable
lipid design. Thank you. Last one
question. Oh, thanks. I had a related
question. Uh so this is really
interesting and again you seem you know
very focused on on where you're going to
get to select based on the delivery
method itself but one really key
challenge in drug delivery is actually
specificity of the delivery itself. So
I'm curious if you've thought about for
this model or for future work, how can
you focus on on specificity of delivery
to different tissues without having to
do very specific drug delivery like like
in the case of inhalation here? Uh so
you're talking about more are you
talking about kind of subtypes in the
lung like slead celus being able to like
introvenous delivery? Yeah, introvenous
delivery for targeted drug delivery. So
IV delivery um you know I've I've
thought about it uh on the AI side
there's not that much can be said
because we're a little bit data poor. I
actually think uh if the person from
Medicine Therapeutics is here they may
disagree but they're not sharing their
data set unfortunately. Uh but they have
some incredible data that that I've seen
in other talks. So stay tuned for that.
Um but you know in terms of organ
targeting right now it's uh more about
screening. There's a little bit of
rational design that can be done to tune
uh delivery between the liver and the
spleen and the lung. But a lot of what's
being done IV is more around rational
design with like antibbody or peptide uh
or small molecule conjugates to try to
target particular cells. So there's a
lot of interest for example in targeting
tea cells with CD3 or CD5 antibodies or
whatever else. So I would say uh for IV
you know hitting the liver is relatively
straightforward because the liver is
just a sink for all nanoparticles for
more uh for rare tissues and more
difficult tissues stem cells tea cells
whatever else this right now I would say
the most promising work is being done
with with antibbody conjugates um but
you do need to you do need to have the
right anti the right ionizable lipid for
a particular conjugate it's not
necessarily 100% % plug and play.
Thank you very much, Jacob.