Episode
10. Go combinatorial.
What if the technologies we need to
solve the big challenges we face ahead
already been invented? How would you
know? I open this series of videos with
one idea. There are about 40 years of
technology sitting in the shelf waiting
to be discovered by a new breed of
innovators. We are sitting on a gold
mine of underutilized technologies. That
is scores of technologies conceived with
some purpose in mind that did not
materialize as impact in time and now
languish on the metaphorical shelf. Let
me tell you how I came to appreciate
these using an analogy with grilling.
Do you grill your burgers or your
vegetables with the lid of the grill
open or closed? There's a difference
between those two options. Do you close
the lid and wait about 5 minutes until
they're just a turn away from done? Or
do you leave the lid open and admire the
cooking for 15 minutes? Closing the lid
makes all the difference. It recycles
and recombines the heat. Engineers call
that a feedback loop. The more heat you
reuse, the sooner you'll get to enjoy
the juicy burger or vegetable. and the
less energy you will waste. Now that you
have seen the rest of these videos, you
probably know where I'm going with this
analogy. In the old mindset, each
technology had one use and problems
could only be solved one way. Then they
were discarded. Discarding ideas is like
cooking with the lid open. Most of the
potential innovations like the heat in
the analogy go to waste. In the new
mindset, we have options. You can
repurpose technologies. It is like
cooking with the lid closed. We recycle
and recombine technologies and we stand
to accelerate the rate at which we
explore and understand problems. I first
hinted at some of these ideas in a
concept paper published in epsilon
theory and more recently in a response
to the National Science Foundation
request for information. This has
important implications for how you run
an innovation department for science and
technology agencies for investment firms
and for up andcoming innovators and
tinkerers. Imagine if we could bring
this same thinking to solve the
challenges we care about. Climate
change, inequality, education. It's
easy. The cooker is like a problem
solved. The more we ready technology for
reuse, the likelier it is to be employed
usefully to solve problems. And the more
we make those technologies available,
the more we stand to take advantage of
our own diversity of purpose. We are
sitting at top a gold mine. We've barely
scratched the surface of how to usefully
employ technologies already invented.
[Music]