Welcome, everyone.
Thank you for joining us
for our open conversation
with neuropsychologist and
lifelong learner, Bia Adams.
Today, we'll talk about
the ways in which curiosity
and continuous learning can
transform personal growth
and mental well-being.
I'm Curt Newton, Director
of MIT OpenCourseWare.
OpenCourseWare is a
free and open collection
of materials from
thousands of MIT courses
covering the entire
MIT curriculum.
We create new
opportunities for millions
of learners and educators,
share open education resources
from MIT, and help lead a
global revolution in free access
to knowledge.
This is the third event in
the Open Conversation series
which focuses on how
open learning can
empower people to improve
their lives, communities,
and the world.
Our guest today is Bia Adams.
Bia has been on a fascinating
and inspiring journey.
From an initial degree and
work in clinical and behavioral
psychology, to dance with
the London Contemporary Dance
School and the Royal Ballet,
and then back to psychology,
extending into computational
neuroscience and related fields
with MIT Open
Learning resources.
Thank you, Bia, for
joining us today.
There's so much to get
to explore and share.
Really looking forward to it.
So, if we might begin with
your wonderful accomplishments,
academic and in
personal pursuits, Beah,
would you please
share with us some
of the themes and
throughlines in your career
and your personal growth
and how curiosity has
played a role in this journey?
Hi, Curt.
Hi, everyone.
Thank you for having me.
I'm so excited to
finally be here.
Yeah, a few things about myself.
I'm a neuropsychologist,
as you said,
and I'm a former
professional dancer.
I'm also a lifelong
learning-- my career has
been built across
diverse experiences,
but I think I've always
retained an interest
in lifelong learning.
I like to say that if money
and jobs were not concepts,
I would happily be
a forever student.
I started dancing when I
was four, four and a half,
but I thought-- my
mum thought would
be just a few lessons
of ballet turned
into many years of dancing.
I spent most of my
childhood and teens dancing,
then I studied psychology,
clinical and cognitive.
I worked as a psychologist
for a few years.
Then in my mid-20s, I went
on an extended sabbatical
because I wanted to
explore dance a bit more
and I wanted to
perform a bit more.
So this time, I studied
contemporary dance
in London Contemporary
Dance School,
and I performed for a few years.
I also explored with
other movement practices.
I managed to get a
black belt in aikido.
I started skateboarding,
longboarding,
which, of course, led
to quite a few injuries.
Due to those, and also because
I really developed an interest
in the neuroscience
part of psychology,
I went back to psychology
and I resumed my studies,
and I eventually specialized
in medical neuroscience
and started working as a
neuropsychologist, which
is what I do now.
I still dance, albeit
not professionally,
but I do it regularly
and with much joy.
I discovered MIT OpenCourses
in 2022, it was, yes.
And I completed several
from various fields.
And I'm planning to actually
approach more in next year.
Other than that,
I'm multilingual.
I grew up speaking
several languages,
and then acquired more.
One of my project--
I mean, every five years I try
to approach a new language,
and I'm doing that
at the moment.
I find much--
I'm drawn, I'm curious
about how new languages work
and how structure
arises out of them.
Also, this year,
I finished writing
my first book of fiction,
to be released next year.
It's called Humans
After All, and if you
watch my online spaces, you will
see excerpts from it already,
and hopefully the
final result next year.
Yeah, you asked me
about curiosity.
I think curiosity has been
there throughout my development.
I've always been
drawn by movement
and interested in
movement, how it arises.
How our bodies move, why we
are able to do things and why
we are not able to do things.
So I think-- when I
started doing ballet,
I was drawn-- curiosity helped
me dissect movement, understand
technique, understand
timing, how
movement relates to music,
another big interest of mine.
Then also that the expression,
the possibilities of expression
that arise out of dignity,
not just the series of steps.
So what I didn't know
then, but I appreciate now
as a psychologist, is
that this curiosity I
had activated the dopaminergic
system in the brain, the reward
system.
That's something which
makes you go after things,
it opens the door to learning.
And it also makes you a bit
more cognitively flexible
so that you can
adapt to learning,
and through the connections
that the dopaminergic system has
with the hippocampus, to
consolidate what you've learned.
So I didn't know then
that I was actually
priming my brain for deep
learning without even
knowing what deep learning was.
Later on when I transitioned
to neuroscience,
I think curiosity served
almost a protective--
almost had a protective
role because instead
of interpreting this
change as change in career,
almost in identity,
I looked at it
as an opportunity to
explore something new,
explore something meaningful.
And I think that's
important in periods
when you that we
associate with identity.
I was a dancer, and then
I became a scientist.
So instead of interpreting
this change as a threat,
I try to look at it through
the eyes of the explorer.
What could come out of this?
And I think that reframes
uncertainty and reframes
ambiguity, which our brains are
not very good at tolerating.
Does that answer your question?
Yeah, yeah.
That spirit of exploration is so
fundamental to what we can get
up to, and it's-- thank
you for sharing that path.
Yeah.
I mean, I would
share that what we've
learned about the people who
use MIT OpenCourseWare more
broadly from around
the world, they're
coming from a lot of
different positions.
Some of them are enrolled
students, some of them
are educators
trying to figure out
how to teach more effectively.
Many of them are just
curious, independent learners.
And what we've heard from
everyone across the board,
that the number one
reason why they're
coming to these resources
is because they have
this fundamental curiosity.
And there's often other
reasons beyond that,
but it's just really interesting
that that force is out there
so widely reflected, and you've
definitely been living it,
so thank you, yeah.
Well, curiosity, if we
look at the way curiosity
arises in the brain, I think
that will probably just answer
your curiosity and your
question a bit more.
We become more curious when our
brains detect an information
gap.
When we sense that there's
something we don't know,
but we could know; that there's
something we don't fully
understand, but we
could understand;
and when the brain
detects this gap,
it sets in motion the
same dopaminergic system
I mentioned earlier
that, in turn,
prepares the
neurochemical milieu,
the dopamine required
to create the motivation
to go out there, seek
the missing information,
and close the gap.
And it's exactly this
exploratory behavior
that we mentioned earlier.
So most-- I'm quite confident
that a lot of learners
already have some knowledge
from certain fields,
but there's that
information gap.
That's something they wish they
would know more of and more
from, and that once they find
the platform, once they find
the source of knowledge,
they seize it because that's
what the brain does.
They have all the support,
the neurobiological support
to do that.
Yeah.
And it never stops.
Those questions, that
sense of, oh, here's a gap,
here's a new thing,
we certainly feel
that when we're young all the
time, but also, it never stops.
And so to be able
to support people
at every age of life, continuing
to explore that stuff, as you've
been doing, feels just really,
really important and useful,
yeah.
It's self-replenishing,
I would say.
It never stops-- once you find
an answer to one question,
another one arises.
So I totally agree.
And that's actually an
important thing to note.
Curiosity and motivation,
they're not personality traits.
You're not born with
them and they stay rigid
for the rest of their life.
They are practice.
They are tools and
facets of one's behavior
that need constant practice.
And the more you practice, the
more will come out of them.
So yeah, I agree.
Yeah, yeah.
I wonder if you have
a perspective on how
living a life of curiosity
supports one's broader
sense of well-being and
connection in the world.
Through your own
experience or the work that
you're doing with people,
what have you seen about that?
Well, curiosity, per se, the
act of engaging curiosity
and motivation to engage in
new pursuits-- and mind you,
when I say learning, the
curiosity to learn something new
and the motivation to
learn something new,
I don't mean just
abstract stuff.
Actually, it's preferred, from
a neuroscientific point of view,
for it to be multimodal.
Cognitive, motor,
social, emotional,
because it recruits
more areas of the brain,
going by the same principle
of lose it or use it--
or use it or lose it.
So maintaining a curious
approach to life,
maintaining curiosity in
engaging with new learning
material, with
lifelong learning,
has quite a few benefits, and
mainly why it is important.
It's because it literally
changes the brain.
It drives what we
call neuroplasticity.
Neuroplasticity is
the brain's ability
to change itself in
response to experience,
in response to new learning.
So curiosity-- applied
curiosity in new learning
rewires the brain to
form new circuits.
You allow for neurogenesis,
the formation of--
the genesis of new
neurons in some areas
of the brain, particularly
the hippocampus.
It also acts as a
protective buffer
against age-related
cognitive decline.
It slows down-- it lowers
the incidence of dementia.
Let us not forget
the social benefits
that come with being curious
and engaging in new pursuits
with others.
Just the act of doing
something with others,
of proving oneself to be
capable of being competent,
the feeling of self-efficacy, of
mastery, they build confidence.
And all these things are proven
to reduce symptoms of anxiety
and depression and isolation.
Also, when you see a
curiosity, neuroscience
shows us that when
curiosity is high, yeah,
our brains switch from networks
that preferentially process
threat to networks that
allow for exploration
for curious approach, for
going out and exploring
one's territory.
That also goes hand-in-hand
with-- let's call
it cognitive flexibility.
With the ability to
reappraise a situation
not in terms of threat, but
in terms of exploration.
So maintaining this
mindset of what else--
how else could I
look at a situation?
What else is there to
find out about this?
How can I look at this from
a different perspective?
Or then, what else is there
that I feel I could know,
but I don't?
I don't yet understand,
but I know I could?
The missing puzzle,
how do I find it?
The brain loves puzzles.
The fact that a sense of
curiosity, it helps us,
like I said before, reframe
uncertainty, but it also--
it also puts us in a
situation where we also
become more resilient.
We allow for the
brain's instances
of cognitive reappraisal
and reframing of a situation
to work so that we have
a better stress response.
The less-- the better
decision-making.
The impact of stress
on emotional circuits
in the limbic system is reduced.
So curiosity is not just
learning new material,
it actually impacts mental
health and resilience long-term.
Yeah.
I love hearing that reflection.
We at OpenCourseWare,
at Open Learning,
we hear from so many
people around the world
that they've been able to
make use of our resources
when they are living in
various disrupted situations
in their lives.
I mean, lives are complicated,
and having these materials
shared openly and freely
with the world, clearly
people's lives have
some stresses in them.
But they're able to tap
into some foundational,
I guess, curiosities to,
despite or working through,
with resilience,
those disruptions,
continue to keep learning.
And we love hearing the
stories reporting back
about how they continue to
be able to keep learning.
People-- I'm remembering--
at OpenCourseWare,
we have this Chalk
Radio podcast,
and we just did a
series of hearing
from learners around the world.
Specifically, we heard a story
from a person named Lotfullah
in Afghanistan who was
living in a situation
where-- could not count
on having internet access
from day to day,
from hour to hour,
and all sorts of
other disruptions.
But were able to make
use of the materials
that we've shared
to keep learning
and how just vitally
useful that that was.
We hear those stories
again and again.
So it does seem to switch
something for people,
and really glad that we
can help support that.
Yeah.
And it's the
occurrence of what you
said, is supported by very
clearly defined structures
in the brain.
And again, it's,
again, the midbrain,
the dopaminergic
subsystem in the midbrain,
mainly the ventral tegmental
area and the nucleus accumbens,
which allow for this
sense of purpose,
for this sense of the micro-wins
of maybe understanding it
doesn't have to be the big
goal and the big monster.
It can be the small gremlin
that you finally tame
and you learn how to deal with,
but it's those micro-wins, those
that feeling of process that
I may not have understood
the full thing, but at
least I've got this much,
I mastered this much,
and maybe tomorrow, I'll
make sense of the next
bit, and next week I'll
make this make sense
of the next bit.
And that gives a
sense of progress,
but also of purpose, of
goal-directed behavior, which,
in times of hardship, in
times of duress and distress,
is what keeps you going.
And it could be as little as--
I said, it doesn't
have to be abstract.
It can be learning how
to play a new instrument
or learning how to-- that's
not a small thing-- learning
how to code.
I've actually approached
Ana Bell's code--
AI and computer science course,
so it reminds me of that.
So, yeah, maybe it has
even a stronger impact
on people who go
through difficult times
because, again, it
gives you that something
to look forward to.
That's something to
mobilize your resources
towards which is so
important in staving off--
in staunching symptoms
of hopelessness, which
are very closely
linked with depression,
and crippling anxiety.
So yeah, I completely
agree with you.
Yeah.
Yeah, what I'm hearing
in your description
is this process of building
confidence bit by bit, too.
You start from a place
of realizing, hey,
there's something
that I don't know
that I'm curious about and
building that confidence.
That confidence can be really
infectious in a good way, yeah?
Yeah.
No, you're spot-on.
Now that I told
you, I'm learning--
I'm approaching
foreign languages,
and I was saying to my friend,
when I sit down to relearn--
I call it relearning Hebrew
because I sort of knew something
from before, and I'm drawn to
it because it forces my brain
to do things counterintuitively.
The same way I experienced
with when I started aikido,
it's against the way
my brain would do it.
Not only is it a right
to left, but it's
a whole different
grammar structure.
So it puts me in a
situation of discomfort.
So I'm sometimes overwhelmed.
I don't know whether I'll
be able to make sense of it,
but the micro--
there are micro-wins.
If I manage to
understand this much,
then the next day I'll sit
down and say, OK, let's see
what happens--
let's see what happens today.
Let's see what I
make sense of today.
So I become a bit more
confident because it's
yet another small milestone
that I've conquered.
I'm this much closer to
something which I don't even
know where it is in
time and in space,
but I become more confident.
And that takes me back to when
I retrained in neuropsychology.
I remember I had to learn
a lot of neuroanatomy,
neurophysiology, diagnostics.
And it was-- oftentimes,
it was quite intimidating,
it was overwhelming.
But even those small
win of understanding
how cranial nerves work,
or finding the acronym
to remember something, or
nailing a small differential
diagnosis, that not
only did it make
me happy through the
same reward circuitry,
but it boosted my motivation,
the big M word, to carry on.
So it actually kept me on track.
Otherwise, perhaps I
would have given up
if I looked at this whole
chunk as, oh God, here's
the big monster.
So I agree with you,
building confidence slowly
is definitely
something that we see
with lifelong learners, people
who engage in lifelong learning.
Yeah, yeah.
This brings to mind stories that
we hear from so many people,
especially older learners.
I think there's a
way in which we're
conditioned as older
people to think
we're supposed to know stuff.
Yeah.
And that moving into
that space of not knowing
can be uncomfortable, but
we hear from so many people,
I studied this
subject back in school
and it didn't make sense
to me, and suddenly,
thank you, OpenCourseWare,
for instance,
for giving me this
alternate explanation.
Suddenly now I understand,
I've recovered that sense of,
yeah, I can come back to this
and take another try at it,
and just how
transformative that can
be for people no matter what
stage in life they're at.
Absolutely.
It also-- I would like to
say this tongue-in-cheek,
that it stops you--
it prevents one
from taking oneself
too seriously.
Keeping humble.
A lot of us,
especially if there's
something we become
good at, hopefully, we
tend to think that we know the
answers to all the questions
or what we know is
enough, but it's always
good to have this reality
check that there's something
there we don't know or there may
be another way to look at it.
And that, again, takes us
back to cognitive flexibility.
It's something that tends to--
because of how brain
function declines
physiologically,
cognitive flexibility,
fluidity of thinking and
of appraising reality
and what's being internalized
as knowledge is a bit lost.
So working on that wiring
through lifelong learning,
through complex work,
through, like you said,
learning new things or
revisiting new things
through mentally
stimulating hobbies,
it allows for the looseness of
that circuitry to be maintained.
And also for the distance
from yourself that sometimes
is needed to just be
able to learn new things
and to look at the world
with different eyes.
It's a humble thing to be
able to do that later in life.
Yeah.
Do you ever have people who
have learned about your story
say something like, I just
don't know how I would have time
to learn all of these things.
How do you find the time?
How do you create that space?
I get that in the sauna, I
get that at work, I get that--
I get that.
And my answer is,
how do you know--
and I actually
get that question.
My answer is usually,
well, I'm old,
so I've had time to
do all those things.
That's usually my go-to
get-out-of-jail-free card.
I usually say, well, I'm old,
I've been around since forever.
I've had time to
do these things.
But then maybe the more complex,
less tongue-in-cheek answer
would be I really
enjoyed what I did.
I never-- even now,
people say, well, why do
you swim five days a week?
I'm like, I actually
enjoy doing it.
It's not something--
it's not an ordeal.
Most of the things
I've done I've
done because I was
really drawn to them.
So for me, it's a joy.
This is joy.
I mean, there are clearly things
that I would rather not do
and they're there just
to maintain something.
Having to do strength in
order to maintain flexibility.
But I actually-- like you
said, it's self-replenishing,
it's self-perpetuating.
Like now, I can't stop
learning this foreign language.
Actually, I wake up
and I think, maybe
I want to make sense of that.
So I think it's
just-- it's something
that I was encouraged to do.
Also, I had good parental
encouragement growing up,
and luckily I had the
context and the environment
to pursue some interests.
And I maintained, like
I said, this practice.
I maintained the curiosity
and the motivation, and also
the discipline, which deserves
another conversation altogether,
to do these things.
And then, to
complete the answer,
they've brought me enough
reward to keep me going.
It was not something I did
just for the sake of doing.
I got a lot out of it
enough to keep going.
Yeah.
Curious to hear a little bit
more maybe about your sense
of the social aspects of
being a lifelong learner.
In addition to all the
things that we individually
are drawn into, how have
you experienced in your life
sharing it with other
people or bringing
other people into these
journeys, and things
you might want to
share with share
with our viewers about that?
Well, you hit the
nail on the head,
it's like you read my mind.
I actually meant to bring
this into the conversation.
And maybe part of it I
discuss a fiction context
in this book I've
finished writing, how
important the social dimension
of learning is in general,
and also how important
it's been for me.
And how intrinsic it is to
sometimes just stay on track
and to maintain the
motivation to keep going.
And it's something which
is perhaps slightly waning
in the modern world.
The act of learning with others,
the act of sharing knowledge
with others--
we're in this together.
As hard as it gets, we're
learning this together,
or we're learning
from each other,
to me, has been very important.
Although, in terms of
personality, maybe,
I actually prefer,
especially when
it comes to abstract
knowledge, to learn alone.
But then I like to share.
I like to have somebody to
have shared reflection with.
And it also helps
with accountability.
I remember-- it could
be a discussion forum,
but learning with
somebody else--
a study buddy, right?
Preferably a human
study buddy helps with--
I've already mentioned
accountability comprehension
and sharing understanding
of material.
But what it also does, I've
noticed, especially when you
study something which
is hard, and there
are obstacles along
the way and fatigue
rears its ugly head,
having a study buddy
helps with eliminating
or reducing
the sense of isolation
that can come out
of months and months of
being engaged in hard study.
And sometimes it's
that sense of isolation
that can halt progress.
So to me, it's been important
to have somebody to--
when it came to
academic pursuits,
it was important
to have somebody
to even meet and have a
conversation about tomorrow's
exam or what had to be studied.
I was lucky to have a
good friend in university
and I'm forever grateful to
her for being my study buddy--
human study buddy.
And when it comes to other types
of learning, of course, just
sharing the fact
that-- let me show you
how I learned to play guitar,
or you show me this dance piece
and I'll try to copy you, it
creates a sense of cohesion,
and also a sense of mastery.
Like I've mentioned before,
a sense of efficacy.
I'm showing you that
I'm good at this.
I'm showing you that I'm
competent enough to do this.
And then there's the feedback
that comes back to me
and I feel competent.
Through those same social
reward and the circuitry
that supports it is
back-mirrored to me,
and in turn, I feel
more competent,
that's extremely important.
And again, it helps with
resilience, with grit.
So social learning, I
couldn't encourage it more.
And I think learning, per
se-- we've already said,
all the-- we've already
outlined the benefits,
the lifelong benefits that
come with just being engaged
in learning, but
there's also the aspect
of-- if we were to visualize
this, a sort of visual vignette,
have this learning window
or door, let's call it,
and you have curiosity
and motivation
which help you take the
first steps through.
Good job, I didn't say window.
So you take the first step
through the learning door.
And then you have the
discipline and the rigor
and the structure which
keep you on track.
But then I think you also
need a sense of community
to anchor you into something
which hopefully will
become larger than yourself.
So I couldn't stress more the
benefits of social learning
and just doing it
with other humans.
Yeah.
Thanks, thanks.
Yeah, it makes me think of
MIT's motto, Mind and Hand.
There's the learning part of
it, the intellectual part of it.
But the hand part, the doing,
in particular, I think,
has this way of just bringing
other people into the process.
We demonstrate the things that
we're learning through the hand,
through the activities
out in the world.
We're creating opportunities
to engage with other people.
I know in my personal life,
I've been on a learning journey
for over a decade
about climate change
and how to respond to these
intersecting challenges
and the things that it
calls me into to share
my learnings have
to do with how do we
show up for civic
engagement as a citizen?
How to get engaged there.
So there's this
continuous feedback loop
between learning new things
and showing up in social spaces
to both demonstrate
what I've learned,
but also ask those questions
that are still ringing that
lead me into the next thing.
I'll also note, it's not
part of MIT's official motto,
but informally, Mind,
Hand, and Heart, showing up
for all of with our full selves
is really important part of it
as well.
I think of the heart part
of it is very connected
with that feeling of curiosity.
What is it that spark
or that small flame
that opens up as
the heart piece.
So, yeah, just a joy riffing
on that for a moment, yeah.
Yeah.
Yeah-- no, I totally agree.
And I absolutely
love MIT's motto.
Maybe I mentioned earlier, this
aspect of embodied cognition.
And I touched on it
briefly earlier when I--
and when I mentioned
multimodal learning and just
learning through all modalities,
which is actually preferred.
The brain likes that because
it recruits more areas.
It allocates more resources
from various bits.
And it's also-- it's been quite
the buzzword in the last few
years, embodied
cognition, and how--
because there's both
top-down regulation
of processes and bottom-up.
It's not just the brain
dictating everything
into the body.
It actually-- what happens and
how emotion and behavior arises
is both top-down and bottom-up.
What comes through
the senses, what
comes from the outside
going all the way up
into the higher instances of
the brain, and top-down as well.
So I'm happy you touched
on that because it's linked
with, as I said, this buzzword.
Yeah.
Embodied cognition.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And if I may, reflecting on
the social aspect of this,
we're so grateful
for all of the people
who are watching our livestream
right now and who registered.
And we got so many questions
from people about the broader
themes that we'd be
talking about today.
Maybe I'll turn some
of our attention
to what we've heard from
those questions here.
I think we've got over 100
questions that were submitted,
and our team has done
some valiant work
trying to group these into
some themes that people out
in the world are
wondering about,
especially around curiosity.
So, here's this first one.
Do you think curiosity
is a learnable skill?
And if so, what strategies might
help individuals and communities
to develop and reinforce
and carry it forward?
Curiosity, we've said, is--
let me think about the question.
So is curiosity learnable?
Or can it be developed, maybe?
Can it be enhanced, right?
So straight off
the bat, there are
no chemical--
pharmacological stimulants
that could enhance or
create curiosity, at least
not in a healthy way.
But there are cognitive
and emotional conditions
that we could create
to enhance curiosity.
Well, this question,
actually a very good one,
takes me back to what
we mentioned earlier,
about curiosity arising when the
brain detects this information
gap.
So why do we become curious?
Because we know that there's
something we don't yet know
or we can't yet do or we don't
yet understand, but we could.
So the brain sets in motion
its tried-and-tested ways
to make us motivated to go
out there and find the missing
piece in the puzzle.
So how could we
create the context
in which curiosity piques?
I've noticed, both in
dance and neuroscience,
that-- but mainly neuroscience
has confirmed this,
that the human brain likes,
and at the same time,
hates incomplete puzzles.
And that's tied in with
the information gap.
When the brain detects that
there's a missing puzzle,
it will increase motivation
to go out there and find it.
We like to find
the missing gaps.
So sometimes if we frame
the learning material
and the question in
such a way that we
sense that there's
something we don't yet know,
our brains will do
what needs to be
done to put us in the situation
where we can go out and find
the missing piece.
So that's usually a strategy.
Then novelty.
Novelty is-- bringing new
things into our reality,
into our environment
can spike curiosity.
The brain loves novelty.
New perspectives, new ways of
looking at the world, new tools.
New tools are great.
Like, how do I use this?
New angles into a problem.
That's what-- novelty
spikes curiosity.
Also, that gets me
thinking about something
that a friend of mine
mentioned the other day, Tim.
He said that he feels more
curious and more motivated to do
things and also performs
better when he feels free,
or I would say--
I would say autonomous.
Yeah, and just to get
my disclaimer in early,
by autonomous, I don't
mean anarchy by autonomy.
I mean the freedom to explore,
to sometimes choose the question
rather than engaging in the
type of learning where you just
have to learn a given
material all the time.
The sense of agency,
the sense of,
I'm the one who does
the exploration,
and sometimes, if we
don't choose the answer,
we at least choose the question.
Also feeling the sense of
sometimes feeling safe,
maybe that's the word,
and I will explain.
The sense of that low stake.
Not always engaging in a
high-stakes environment.
Not that the environment--
it's not that they're bad
and they're not conducive
to progress or mastery
or competence, but because
the constant involvement
in a high-stake, slightly
threatening environment
dampens curiosity.
As we've said before,
curiosity spikes
when the brain shifts from
threat perception networks
to exploratory networks.
So sometimes feeling a bit
looser, a bit more comfortable
in an environment
with lower stakes
can set off
exploratory behavior.
If we're constantly engaged
in learning activities that
titillate the brain's
defense mechanisms,
we tend to become less
curious, and then motivation
goes down a bit.
So to answer the question, look
for puzzles, incomplete puzzles.
Novelty, autonomy to explore.
And then find environments
where you feel looser,
not constantly judged,
not constantly evaluated
and stuck labels on.
I think that helps with
long-term sustainment and--
sustainment and
enhancing of curiosity,
and the motivation
to back it up.
Yeah, good.
Yeah.
It leads me to another
set of questions
we got from some folks,
which I will summarize,
is while we've been singing
curiosity's praises,
are there ways in which
one might be too curious?
Are there ways
that we might want
to think about
managing that curiosity
to particular ends versus just
welcoming it with open arms--
OK, that's an interesting
question, becoming too curious,
as in dabbling into an
excessive number of interests.
Yeah, well, I think
we can interpret it--
you were talking about novelty
and how novelty is-- the brain
loves novelty.
I assume--
No, you're right.
The brain-- yeah.
No, you're totally right.
The brain loves
novelty, but if there's
one thing that the brain can't
do, as much as we would like
to think that and as much
biohackers promise us,
the brain can't process
unlimited input.
Yeah.
Right?
Cognitive fatigue
is a real thing,
and it's mainly due to the
prefrontal cortex, which
sits just here
below the forehead,
being metabolically extremely
costly, and fatigues easily,
and performance goes down.
So if becoming too curious
about too many things
at one specific time leads
to cognitive overload,
then you have a problem
because there's mental clutter.
You won't see clearly.
You won't see as clearly.
The brain's analytical
instances won't
be as well-equipped
to, one, comprehend
and make sense of
what's being learned.
To also evaluate evidence.
If it's something that requires
seeking truth or figuring out
whether trying to
make sense of things,
that mental clutter,
that prefrontal fatigue,
prefrontal fatigue actually--
the prefrontal cortex fatigues
because for two reasons.
One, when multitasking;
and two, when
having to switch between
sources of information.
So being too
curious, as in being
a bit jumpy and
frivolous about what
you allow your
attention to go towards,
if that leads to
cognitive overwhelm,
then those analytical
instances of the brain
won't do their job as well.
Yeah, so you need to filter,
you need to curate, and then
to focus and
concentrate just to keep
cognitive fatigue and cognitive
overload from happening.
So I would say that is a caveat.
Plus, you just don't have
enough attentional power.
It's mainly an issue
of computation, mainly.
It's just brain limitation.
But when one maintains enough
distance to become their own
filter and curator, then
hopefully it will get distilled
to what actually deserves your
attention and what doesn't.
Yeah.
This makes me think of
this interesting balance
that we have found ourselves in
with OpenCourseWare and our MITx
free online open
courses, that there's
a way in which the information
system online is now
really good at feeding that
wish for dopamine hits,
and the novelty continuous.
And on the other
hand, there might
be things that are out in
the world that are just
like too big to take on.
Require too much persistence.
But by sharing materials
like OpenCourseWare does,
here's materials framed
within, say, a course in which
they were taught, but here's
the materials openly for you
to make your way through.
There's enough of a
container that you
can match your
persistence at the moment
to track your way through.
It's like the best of
both worlds, if you will.
It's like--
Yeah, I completely agree.
All of this stuff to feed
your curiosity, but just
containerd enough to
walk you through it.
That's what--
And that also restores a
bit of agency, if you like.
You're the one
who chooses what's
internalized instead of
everything coming towards you
and being a bit overwhelming.
I had that issue--
I remember when I approached
MIT courses, I thought, oh God,
what do I do?
I want to do everything.
And then I had that, and I
had the immunology course,
and I had Patrick Winston--
I had the AI course, and then I
had the mind and machine course.
But I noticed that the structure
in which they're presented,
and then the
individual structure
of the individual
courses, actually
helped me tone down that
initial anxiety, and I was like,
OK, hang on, I can
find my way through it,
so it wasn't that overwhelming.
Yeah.
It's a helpful feature to not
have a defined end date where
you have to finish it all by.
Yeah.
We got some other questions
about the shifting information,
content landscape
out in the world,
and between, say,
all the shows that we
can stream online and short-form
videos that social media is
pushing out.
What role do you think
ongoing-basis platforms
like MIT Open Learning can
play in fostering, supporting,
stewarding that sort of
ability for deeper learning?
This is kind of building
on what we've just
been talking about,
but maybe anything more
to think about there with--
Opportunities for deep
learning, you mean?
Yeah, deeper learning
beyond the short-form stuff
or the pure entertainment
stuff, yeah.
Well, I think the crux is--
maybe sounds a bit
elitist, the quality of it.
The rigor.
The fact that it's not
something you can-- it's not--
I mean, it is entertaining
and it's definitely rewarding,
but it's not something you
can just brush the surface of.
It's not something that can
be-- you can just take a look at
and you dive in and
out of this course
and then you move on to another.
It takes a certain amount of
engagement, depth of engagement.
Does this answer your question?
Yeah, yeah.
It's something that,
again, takes me
back to what we
were saying earlier
about the protective
effects of lifelong learning
and its implications on your
mental health and well-being
and resilience.
And there are maybe
two things to note.
The benefits we outlined
are dose-dependent
and also cumulative.
You don't derive
the same benefits
if you dab in and
out of interests,
and you don't do
it in a sustained
type of rigorous engagement.
And I think, at least the
courses I've completed
and the ones I'm looking
at now, don't really
allow for that type of
entertainment-led involvement.
You have to apply yourself.
And again, without
that threat that
can arise rise from--
to high stakes,
like you said,
you pace yourself,
and there are micro-wins,
and it comes with sheets,
and you can do the
exercises, and then
you can do-- you can read
the-- you do the assignments.
And it sort of requires
a certain level of depth
from the learner in
terms of engagement
that underpins a deep
learning and the benefits that
come with that.
That's what I think.
That's what I've noticed.
Yeah, good.
Yeah, and in conversations
with colleagues around here,
we are talking
increasingly about how
to complement that depth with
the right forms of engagement,
to have things be MIT good
without, right off the bat,
having them all be
so hard academically.
Colleagues over
at the MIT Museum
who were talking about this
concept of depth-on-demand,
where you meet people with
really engaging things
to pique their curiosity, but
then be able to flow through
and follow through with that.
It feels a really
important set of things
to be developing over
time, and I look forward
to us being able to get
into that more and more.
I think hard-- the hardness,
difficulty, is something
that people go for,
at least myself,
and when I looked
at these courses,
I was actually quite
happy that they're hard,
that I didn't understand.
Because-- and it's
normal, I think,
for periods of
overwhelm and doubt
and fatigue to occur
because the courses
are so difficult
and so rigorous.
But again, if we look at it from
a neuroscientific perspective,
it's that level of challenge
and that limbic friction,
we call it, that friction, that
sense of, I'm a bit overwhelmed
and I'm a bit scared, but it's
exactly that sense of challenge
that drives
neuroplasticity, and that
then helps with the
motivation to stay on track.
So I'm sure that other
people will agree,
the reason why we
approach these courses is
that they were excellent.
Exquisite in terms of the
quality of the material
and how they're taught, but
also because they're just
in that Goldilocks
zone of difficulty.
If something is too easy,
the brain gets bored.
If something is too
hard, then those defense
mechanisms I mentioned
earlier are titillated
and the desire to keep
going is dampened.
But I think they're
perfectly poised
on that angle of the Goldilocks
zone of just above that level
of competence and maybe a
bit higher for motivation
to keep you going.
So I was happy that they're
hard, and some of them
were so hard that I
have chunks of them
that I couldn't approach fully.
Professor Allen Adams's
quantum mechanics one, my God,
I got to the harmonic
oscillator bit, I
still-- even now, I have
shivers down my spine
and it took me quite a
while to work my way out
of that jungle in murky waters.
But I had a human study
buddy, and I was, I think,
disciplined enough
to keep going.
So yeah, I like the fact
that they're a bit harder
than my muscles can fight.
OK.
Well, that material will
always be there for you,
so you can keep
coming back to it.
Yeah.
So I think we're about
to draw to a close.
Maybe I'll pose
this very briefly,
one last question from our
audience about, I don't know,
any thoughts on cultural
or organizational practices
that might help foster
this sort of environment.
For me, for instance,
that raises something
that we're very
committed to, which
is this sense of knowledge
as a public good.
That this knowledge
being out there
and shared freely with
the world and supporting
that is a really important
cultural practice that
sets the stage for
people such as yourself
to have access to
these materials.
And if any brief thought
on a cultural practice
that you would like
to see supported more
to help foster this
sort of curiosity,
I'd love to hear about it.
The first thing
that comes to mind,
and maybe not the most
relevant one, is linked--
is connected to what I said
earlier, the sense of safety.
Yeah.
The sense of low stakes.
The sense of looseness
and autonomy.
The not always having
to do something
for some extrinsic good.
The sense of, I'm doing
this not because I'm judged
and not because there's
always a job down the line
and I have to
complete this course,
otherwise I won't keep the job.
And I have to complete this
program in order accede
to a better job and whatnot,
to sometimes keep it low-stakes
and not with either a
hatchet above one's head
or with an immediate goal,
which is maybe not even related
to the main interest
in the first place,
but to allow for curiosity
and supporting motivation
to arise naturally.
To allow for more
looseness in people
to move and choose
their areas of interest,
and then pursue it in
a less judgmental way.
Just people feeling more
supported and lifted--
I'm using dance terms--
rather than constantly
evaluated and pushed in a,
do this so you can grab
the other type of way.
Does that make sense?
Yes, it sure does.
I think that's a wonderful
way to wrap the conversation.
May we all find these
safe, inviting spaces
to engage in learning in
just that sort of way.
Yeah.
I really appreciate that.
All right.
Well, this has been a
wonderful conversation, Bia.
So glad that you've been able
to share your experiences
and your perspectives
and insights with us.
Your drive to help others and
yourself is inspirational.
So, thank you to
everyone who's tuned in
and joined this conversation.
We welcome you to keep
learning with MITx, with MIT
OpenCourseWare, and
with MIT Open Learning.
We also welcome you
to support our work
by sharing our resources with
your friends, colleagues,
and families, sharing your
experiences and your stories
of how you've used these
free resources with us,
share those stories with us.
And if you're in a
position to do so,
please do consider
donating to support
our efforts and the
thousands of people who use
our free resources every day.
And until our next
open conversation,
I wish you a fond
farewell, and thanks again,
Bia, for joining us today.