[Music]
The National Football League is the most
profitable important football
organization in America. Football's the
most profitable sport in the country.
Advertising is incredibly valuable in
football games. Now, the NFL is 32
teams, essentially 32 businesses
competing in a literal sense with each
other. And there's a huge incentive to
collude. What the NFL does is they only
sell the TV rights for the league, which
causes a cartel. They're saying, "If you
want to broadcast football, you got to
come to us and we're going to charge a
super high price." In 1957, the Supreme
Court ruled that this was
anti-competitive. And they couldn't do
it. And the NFL will make $40 billion
this year off their collusive cartel.
Why? Because Congress stepped in and
said, "Well, we're going to actually
exempt football from our nation's
antitrust laws."
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learnmit.edu.
[Music]