[Music]
being part of the MIT Space Systems
laboratory provides incredible
opportunities I don't think there's very
many places that you can actually work
to send your algorithms and control
schemes to space to test to be able to
interact with International Space
Station it's a remarkable opportunities
Space Systems it encompasses any field
of science or engineering that you can
think of we work with computers with
mechanics with thermal engineering
propulsion we specialize but we can't
ignore or leave out any of the
subsystems you always have something new
you didn't challenging to work on even
if you've done something once but the
next time you do it it's a it's a little
bit different and the environment in
space is not one that's really I mean
easy to work with so there's always new
problems to solve and I think that's
what you know I love about it the most
the Department of aeronautics and
Astronautics at MIT is in the School of
Engineering and here we really cover two
bases one is airplanes Aeronautics as
well as spacecraft so what I like to
think of is we're engineering but we
defy gravity you can work with the
International Space Station you can
build and fly your own UAVs you work
with astronauts they really come out of
their education now with a full
experience of impacting the aerospace
field the MIT space laboratory is in the
Department of aeronautics and
Astronautics and we really focus on the
space side we are the expert laboratory
in systems engineering putting all these
complex systems together and teaching
students what that means and how to make
them work ultimately in space we give
students here the opportunity to be
hands-on in the hardware to the
breakfast project where they're gonna
send out hardware to an asteroid through
space for two-and-a-half years to Speers
where they're gonna send their hardware
up on station these students are getting
to work with the leaders in the
aerospace industry on real hardware say
the art technology with education is
something we really need to marry and we
do that to our capstone class where
students get to design new technology
that surprisingly actually we've been
able to fly in orbit on station and
to interplanetary missions we started
this concept at a time truly innovative
the first ones to ever do it
cdio conceived design implement operate
we began that in 1999 since then we've
done the class about ten times and at
least four of them have gone to space
you get to experience what it's really
like on a real high profile NASA mission
you have to meet all those requirements
that the other instruments have to meet
and so that whole experience is really
invaluable in teaching you what real
aerospace engineering is like my
involvement with the projects that we
have here at the SSL goes all the way
from hard work level actually crimping
cables screwing on satellite parts all
the way up to writing code for it
from the start I've been working with
developing algorithms that we can test
our architecture in space we interact
with the astronauts live over video feed
and they unpackage our software load
into the system and run our tests being
able to be a part of what is the whole
picture gonna look like how are we going
to develop the architecture meet
requirements and I think these are
really important skills I need to be
developed and I think I can take into my
future career we as a lab have three
main focus areas on the one side we work
with computer models of how to develop
space mission then we do a lot of ground
test best we build things in the ground
that we test in the laboratory a proof
of concept can they work the third step
is things that go to space for example
our sphere satellites that are aboard
International Space Station what spheres
is is it is a testament MIT decided to
use the space station not to test a
complete mission but to create a testing
environment to do microgravity research
in space
mit has operated over ninety test
sessions doing research that goes from
what we call formation flight having
satellites moved together in a
coordinated fashion making two
satellites talk to each other
autonomously doing things like tether
formation when there's a string between
a satellites and they're flying together
keeping that tether under tension the
streets program began at the MIT
statistics laboratory as a class in 1999
in 2006 it got up to the space station
in 2010 NASA and the DoD made the
spheres part of the ISS National
Laboratory making it truly a facility
for everybody began MIT access is an
x-ray instrument that's on the
osiris-rex spacecraft the Cyrus Rex
spacecraft is going to explore this
asteroid Bennu nASA has put a little bit
of money aside and said let's see if
universities can come up with a good
instrument idea and we started
developing the rexes instrument back in
2012 breakfast is going to look at the
asteroid in the x-ray regime and tell us
what the asteroid is made out of so does
it have iron sulfur or magnesium in the
regolith which is the dirt that's on the
outside of the asteroid I start on a
rexis when rexis was part of the
undergrad capstone class and really the
experience that I got in that class was
so exciting that I decided to continue
on on rexis Rothman masters and now my
PhD work on the rexes project students
did everything we designed rexis we
designed a test program we implemented a
test program we physically built the
hardware as well as contributing to the
scientific analysis of our data as an
x-ray spectrometer it will be the first
instrument to get a look at the x-ray
spectra that comes off the asteroid
which gives us a unique insight into the
elemental composition
asteroid and so we're getting data that
no one's ever gotten before the spheres
program is educated several thousand
students from all the way as young as
eleven years old
we made a competition that is based on
the students programming a player for an
autonomous satellite the best players in
simulation get to send their code up to
the space station students can say I can
send things to space I can send my
software to space Space Systems lab in
star lab or in a nice sweet spot we work
on missions that are small enough where
where we can hold them all in our in our
hands and in our heads but they're
impactful and they fly it's constantly
humbling to be around faculty members
that are really excellent what they do
whether they're NASA Chief Technologist
or former secretaries of the Air Force
just be able to learn from these people
day to day make aero-astro at MIT what
it is all my life when I was a kid or
throughout undergrad I was thought of
MIT as being like this super cool place
and which cutting-edge research was done
now that I'm here I can actually feel
that your research can have a tremendous
impact
you