Okay. So today we are going to turn from
the consumer side of the story to the
producer side of the story. Once again
in the first lecture we talked about
supply and demand curves. The last few
lectures we developed where demand
curves come from. Now we're develop
where supply curves come from. So we're
going to flip and explain where supply
curves come from.
So, and to do so, we're going to start
by talking about production
functions. Now, we all know
what firms, what consumers want. They
want to figure out the bundle of goods
that makes them as well off as possible
given their budget constraint. What do
firms want?
Firms want to maximize their profits. So
just like consumers want to maximize
their utility, firms want to maximize
their profits. And firm profits will
depend so they want to maximize
profits. And profits will depend on
three things. They'll depend on consumer
demand.
They'll depend on the cost of
production and they will depend on
competition. Now the first two, the
first and the third are things which are
largely out of the firm's control. Not
totally out of the firm's control. We'll
come back to how things like advertising
might affect demand and how things like
monopolies might affect competition. But
in the standard model, view them as sort
of out of the firm's control. Take them
as given. What the firm controls is the
cost of production. That's what they can
that's what's under their
control. So from the firm's
perspective, maximizing profits is the
same as minimizing costs.
Okay, the way to maximize profits is to
minimize costs and that's how the firm
produces as efficiently as possible by
minimizing
costs. Okay, once again in the real
world there's complications but in the
model and what'll explain most the real
world we just say
firms their goal is to minimize
costs. Now to understand how to minimize
costs we have to understand where a
firm's costs come from.
understand that we have to understand
what firms actually
do. So in this course, firms are simply
black boxes for much of the course.
They're simply boxes where inputs go in
and outputs come out and in the middle
is something called a production
function. Okay, that production function
is the magic that makes is the magic of
the firm. Okay. And technically what a
production function is, what a
production function is, it's a
description of what is technically
feasible for the firm to produce. Okay,
that's their production function. What
is technically feasible for them to
produce.
Okay. And essentially what this
production function does is it takes as
inputs two things. Takes as inputs uh
factors of production. It takes factors
of
production what we call factors of
production. I'll come back to what those
are in a
minute. Takes factors of production. It
puts it through a production
function which is a black box will
express as a mathematical function and
out comes a production of goods and
services. Okay. And that's the way we
model the supply
side. So what are these factors of
production? These factors of production
are what we call inputs into the
production process. The
inputs into production are of two types.
To make life easy, once again, obviously
in the real world there's a million
types of inputs in a production. But to
make life easy, we'll start with a model
with two types of inputs in a
production.
Labor and
capital. Labor and
capital. Okay. Labor. It's clear what
labor is. It's the amount of hours that
people work at your firm.
Okay. So, labor is literally how many
hours are devoted towards work uh at
your
firm. Hours are
provided by
individuals in the labor market. So now
people on the other side of the equation
instead of people wanting pizza and
cookies, now people are inputs into
production because they produce the
labor. So people produce labor. they
work at your firm and the price they
demand for that labor is the
wage. That is the price that they demand
for their labor. Where does the wage
come from? We'll talk about that in a
few lectures. Right now, we're going to
take the wage as given. Just in previous
lectures, we took the price of cookies
and the price of pizza as
given. And we'll tell you later where
they come from. Now, we're just going to
take the wage as given. I'll tell you
later where that comes from. By
proceeding in steps, we make it feasible
to model this in a in a reasonable way.
Okay, capital is more confusing. Okay,
capital is more confusing. This is
basically think of it as everything else
that goes in production. The machines,
the buildings, the land you build on.
Think of it roughly as machines. Think
of this black box as being workers and
machines come together to produce
something. The workers we call labor.
Labor. The machines we call
capital. And the price of capital we're
going to call the rental
rate. In other words, think of whatever
you use in production as rented. You
rent a machine. You rent a building.
Okay? In substance, workers, the wage is
the price you pay to rent an hour of a
worker's time, right? That's the way.
It's what the wage is. The price for
renting an hour of a worker's time. And
the rental rate is the price for renting
a unit of
capital. Okay. Now, later on we'll talk
about where that comes from, the fact
that firms actually own machines, etc.
But for now, this makes it easy and
allows for a parallel analysis between
workers and machines. They're both
things you
rent. Okay.
Now the production function is a
function
Q that
basically converts I'm sorry it's a
function f I'm sorry it's a function f
that converts labor and capital into
outputs. So the production function f
converts labor and capital into output
just like utility function. And once
again there's going to be enormous
parallels to the consumer theory. That's
what I drilled into you developing the
intuition of consumer theory. That same
intuition is going to carry over here to
producer theory. So just like the
utility function is a mathematical
representation of how goods turn into
happiness, the production function which
in some sense easy to understand is a
mathematical representation of how
inputs turn to outputs. Sort of easy to
understand. Utility function is a vague
thing. A production function is a
technology. We all know that. Okay, it's
the 20 007 contest. You've got some
inputs and you produce an output.
Okay, so production function is just the
technology that translates the inputs to
the
outputs. Let me highlight one thing.
Little Q I'm going to distinguish here
and if I get this wrong, you can catch
me. Little Q refers to a specific firm.
Big Q refers to the market. So I did my
supply and demand curves where I had big
Q. That refers to the whole market.
Little Q refers to a given firm within
the market. Okay? and we'll go over that
throughout. Okay. Now, these
inputs can be what we call
variable or
fixed. And what do we mean by what do we
mean by that? A varial input is an input
that can be easily
changed. A fixed input is one that is
hard to change at least in the near
term.
So the key distinction between whether
an input is variable or fixed is whether
you're talking about the short
run or the long
run. The short run is
defined as a period of time over which
only some good some inputs are variable
and others are fixed.
The long run is defined as a period of
time of which all inputs are
variable. That's it. That's the
definition. I'm not going to tell you
the short run is six months and three
days and four hours and long runs past
that. I can't tell you that. I can't
tell you what they represent except
theoretically. Theoretically, we define
the short run as a period of time which
some inputs are fixed and some are
variable. The long run is a period of
time over which everything's variable.
Think of the short run as days and the
long run as decades and sort of where in
between days and decades things lay in
depends. Okay. So what we are going to
do is we are going to assume that labor
is variable and capital is
fixed. That is labor is something you
can adjust at any point in time. You can
always fire somebody and hire someone
the next day. Okay. Now, in reality,
that's difficult, but in in theory, you
can. Capital is harder to change. You
got to build a new machine. You got to
build a new building, etc. That's slower
to change. So, we're going to call labor
the variable input and capital the fixed
input. So, in the short
run, we get that labor will be variable
and capital will be
fixed. But in the long run, they're both
variable. Now, of course, once again, in
reality, this isn't so distinct. This
isn't so clean. You can't just fire
workers right away and replace them the
next day, especially in this labor
market with a lot of labor shortage. And
you can build machines pretty quickly.
Okay, so the short run long run
distinction is obviously not perfect,
but it allows us to essentially
distinguish the the concept of things
you can change quickly versus things you
can't. Okay, let me pause there. There's
a lot of definitions questions about
that. Yeah.
No Q. No, it should not. Q Q is a Q
could be L plus K. That would be a
particular form of F. But just like you
can't tell me what form my utility
function is, I can't tell you what form
your production function is. This is
some rich function of how you translate
L and K to Q. So if Q is just L plus K,
that would be a predictable production
function, which would imply that another
unit of labor, another unit of capital
deliver. But what if a machine is five
times as good as a worker? Then it' be
L+ 5K. What if what if the effect of
machines and workers varies based on how
many machines and workers you have? Then
it's a richer function. So just like
utility isn't just cookies plus slices,
it's some function of cookies and
slices. Production is some function of
labor and capital. All right, good
question. Other
questions? Okay, so now let's talk about
the short run. Let's talk about shortrun
production. And how do we think about a
firm's shortrun production
decisions? How do we think about a
decisions? Well, in the short run,
capital's fixed. So, we can write our
production function as Q= F of L and K
bar. Capital's fixed in the short run.
Okay, that's definitional.
So what the firm is trying to ask is
look I can't change the machines I have
that's fixed in the future I could
change it but for my decision today I've
gone to work today September 20th I
showed up at work I have a decision to
make today which is how many workers do
I want today well the key input that
decision is going to be the marginal
product of
labor which is how valuable is the next
worker in terms of delivering output
which is going to be DQ
DL that is what is the marginal effect
of the next worker. Remember this course
always works on marginal decisions. What
is the marginal effect of the next
worker on output
produced?
Okay, we are going to
assume that in the relevant range
dqdl is
negative that is we are going to assume
diminishing marginal
products. This does not mean diminishing
total product. This does not mean once
again like with consumers more is
generally better. More workers are
better. But each worker given fixed
capital adds less to
output. Okay. Now this is hard to think
about and harder than it's easier with
pizza slices to have this intuition but
same intuition as pizza slices. So let's
do an example illustrates it. Let's
think about digging a hole. You want to
dig a hole and you have one piece of
capital, a
shovel. And that can't be changed in the
short run. All you can change is how
many people you have working on digging
the hole. So you hire the first person
and they're digging. You hire a second
person, you clearly you'll get faster,
more productive digging. But will it be
twice as fast? Well, maybe if you can
get them to if you can get them to
alternate shifts. One more 12, one to
other 12. How about the third worker?
Will be three times as fast? Maybe, but
probably not. By the time you're the
hundth worker, there's only one shovel.
What are they going to do? They're sort
of sitting around. You can rotate them
really quickly. And you're certainly
better off with a 100 workers than with
90 workers because you can rotate it
more quickly. But clearly the hundth
worker is not as valuable as the second
worker in terms of digging that
hole. So the idea of diminished marginal
product is given that you only have one
shovel, giving you fixed capital, each
additional worker does less and less
good. Okay, it's not quite as simple as
an intuition as diminishing margin
utility, which I think is sort of na
natural, but the and and you know it's
not always true. Like I said, you can
imagine the second worker might be as
good as the first worker, but in
general, each additional worker will add
less and less value if they're working
with the same number of
machines. Okay? Now, in the long run,
you could take more advantage. You could
add wheelbarrows and more shovels, and
you could add sorts of capital and then
make each worker more productive. But in
in the short run, with only one piece of
capital, that one shovel, there is uh
nothing else you can do. Yeah.
I'm sorry. Yeah, I'm sorry. It's
diminishing. Shouldn't say negative.
It's diminishing. My bad. It's
diminishing. My bad. It's not negative.
It's diminishing. Sorry about that. So,
we have diminishing marginal product. DQ
square or DL square is negative, but
DQDL is positive. Each additional worker
adds value. Add less and less and less.
Thank you for catching
that. Okay, other questions.
So diminishing marginal product in the
short run. That's all we're really going
to say about the short run. The more
interesting case is the long run. So now
let's talk about long run
production. The long run's more
interesting because now you can vary
both capital and labor. So now the
problem's going to look just like the
consumer choice problem. Consumer
choice, we never said you couldn't
affect number of pizza. You can only
change cookies. That's what I've just
done here. I've said you can't change
pizza, you can only change cookies. And
just as in that case, given a fixed
amount of pizza, each additional cookie
does less and less. Okay? Now, we're
going to vary both. And guess what?
We're going to choose a familiar form
for the production function. Let's
assume Q equals the square root of L*
K. Let's assume Q equals the square root
of L* K. familiar form but once again a
useful form in this context just as it
was in consumer
theory and let's go to figure
51 this
illustrates a set of combinations of K
and L which deliver the same amount of
Q look familiar it should look familiar
these look like indifference curves but
in this context we call them Isoquants
because we like making up cool words.
Isoquants. An isoquant is the
combination of K and L that delivers the
same
output. So all the features of
indifference curves that we liked apply
to
isoquants. Okay. Further out is
better. They slope down. They don't
cross. Okay. And basically what it's
saying
is it's about opportunity cost. That
basically as you have more capital for a
given for a given amount of money you
want to spend and less labor that's
going to affect how much you produce. If
it if the amount you produce stays
constant, you switch capital and labor.
You stay in the same isoquant. If you
can produce more, you move out to a
higher
isoquant.
Okay. Now here's a good question. It
relates to the earlier question was
asked about K plus
L. What determines the shape of these
isoquants. What determines their shape?
What underlying sort of notion? It's a
hard question. See if anyone's the
intuition. When are when are these
isoquants going to
be more bendy and when are they going to
be when are they going to be straighter
and when are they going to be more bent?
What's going to determine
that? Yeah.
Exactly. It's going to depend on the
substitutability of the different
inputs. The more
substitutable, the straighter is the
isoquant. The less substitutable, the
more bent is the isoquant. So for
example, let's look at figure
52A. Here we have the production
function that was that was suggested
earlier. I like to think it's a
production function between this is one
where goods are perfectly substitutable.
Okay, I think it's a production function
between Harvard graduates and Beanie
Babies. Okay, perfectly nothing on that.
Come on guys, work with me here. Okay,
this is the this perfectly
substitutable. Okay, and bas No, no,
don't mean to offend the Harvard the
Harvard students in the class, they're
smart. They came over here to take
classes, so they're exempted. Okay, but
basically the idea is these inputs are
perfectly
substitutable. So it doesn't matter if
you have a unit of labor capital as long
as you have just matters the total
number of units you have in that term as
your production that would lead to these
straight downward sloping
isoquants. On the other hand, consider
something like figure 52B on the other
side of the
page. These would be nonsubstitutable
inputs so that the production function
is Q equals the min of X and Y. For
example, think of these like cereal and
cereal boxes. Okay? Doesn't matter how
much for every amount of cereal you got,
you got to have a box. If you only have
one box, it doesn't matter how much
cereal you have, it's just going to sit
there. Okay? You need more boxes. Okay?
So, just like the indifference curves
for this case were left shoe, right
shoe. This is you think of serial serial
boxes things which are
nonsubstitutable. They can't substitute
for each other at all. And in that case
you get these squared uh squared
isoquants.
Okay, questions about that uh
intuition. So it's the degree of
substitutability which determines the
shape of these isoquants. more
generally just we'll generally be in
between as I said nothing's ever at the
extremes we'll generally be in between
these two cases and we'll have an
isoquant that looks like figure
53 and along that isoquant we have the
slope which is the
marginal the marginal rate of technical
substitution just to really mess you up
with consumers your margin rate
substitution margin rate of
transformation MRS and MRT now I'm going
to have MRTS okay which is the margin
rate of technical
substitution okay that is the margin
rate of technical substitution is the
rate at which effectively you can trade
off labor and capital to produce the
same quantity of
good so and essentially we can relate
this just as we can relate the MRS to
margin utilities yeah I'm sorry go ahead
Roger of technical
substitution margin of technical
substitution. Remember when we developed
the margin rate of substitution I used a
little proof to show you how it relates
to margin utilities. We can use the same
proof here which is let's ask let's ask
what happens you have a marginal
increase in labor and a marginal
decrease in capital so that you stay on
the same line. Okay. Well, we know the
So, we're asking where DL time MPL, the
marginal product of
labor, plus DK time MPK, just as a
marginal product of labor, there's a
marginal product of
capital. Okay, same intuition. It's
diminishing. One worker each additional
shovel does less and less good. Okay,
same concept there. That's equal to zero
along that indifference curve. It's an
incremental step along that indifference
curve. So solving this, this says that
this the slope of that indifference
curve DK
DL okay is equal to the
MRTS which is equal to
minus
MPL over
MPK. The slope of the indifference curve
is minus MPL over MK APK. Once again,
looks should look familiar from consumer
theory. Okay, it's the ratio of the
marginal products that determines the
slope of the indifference curve.
Okay. So for
example, let's take our production
function we're using here, which is uh
square root of L * K. That's our
production function. Okay. Let's solve
for the marginal rate of technical
substitution. Well, we know what's the
marginal product of labor. The marginal
product of labor is the
derivative of this production
function with respect to
L. Okay, take the der of that production
function with respect to L and you get
0.5 * K over square root of K *
L. The marginal product of capital is
the derivative of this production
function with respect to
K. You take that derivative, you get 0.5
*
L over K *
L. So that the marginal rate of
technical substitution is the ratio of
these two the opposite ratio which
equals minus K over L.
In this case once again I don't want to
confuse people this is the this is for
for this production function that's a
marginary touchal substitution just like
for this utility function I got a
particular margin of substitution okay
that is I'm just showing you how to
develop it for a given production
function and that gives you something
like figure
53 okay figure 53 shows you the marginal
rate technical substitution for this
production function and you can see that
at for example a point like A you have
an MRTS of
minus4. That means that you have very
little labor and a lot of capital. That
means you give up four units of capital
to get one more worker. Why? Because
marginal products are diminishing. When
you've got four shovels and one worker,
you'd happily give up shovels to get
more workers. Okay? So, you want to move
to the right. Likewise, at point C,
you've got four workers and one shovel.
that's doing you no good. You'd happily
give up a worker to get a shovel. So you
want to move to the
left. Okay, so basically um that is how
we end up with with this marginal rate
of technical substitution. Okay,
questions about
that? Okay, once again parallel to
consumer
theory. Now, now I'm going to talk about
two things which are are not parallel to
consumer theory. Let me just say by way
of introduction, producer theory is one
step harder than consumer theory. It's
all the fun stuff for consumer theory
plus one additional step. Okay? And
we'll talk about that step starting uh
two lectures from now. But for right
now, it's parallel consumer theory. But
here's a couple of wrinkles that arise
in the context of production that you
don't get in the context of
consumption. The first wrinkle is what
we
call returns to scale.
returns to
scale.
Okay, returns to scale are the notion of
what
happens when I increase all inputs
proportionally. It's not sort of an
interesting question for consumer
theory, but it's interesting producer
theory because I want to say what
happens if the firm gets bigger. When
you say in your mind, what happens when
a firm gets bigger? You're thinking what
happens when it just when everything
increases, when all inputs increase
proportionally is our notion of how a
firm gets bigger.
And so that's what we call return to
scale. Scale is basically when you scale
up everything or scale down everything
equally.
So the question is how does output
respond? For example, it could be that
when you double inputs, you double
outputs. It could be that f of 2 L comma
2 k equals 2 * f of l k.
We'll call this a constant
returnsto-scale production
function. Double output, double inputs,
double outputs. Sort of a natural
intuition, but it doesn't have to be the
case. Indeed,
typically we assume firms have we call
diminishing returns to scale. Decreasing
returns to scale. I'm sorry. Decreasing
returns to scale where f of 2 L comma 2k
is less than 2 * f of l and k. That is
when you double inputs, you get less
than twice as much
outputs. Why is that? Well, think about
the idea that basically uh if you you're
still trying to dig a hole. There's one
guy with one shovel. You got two guys
with two shovels. They're in each
other's way. they can't quite work as
efficiently as one guy with one shovel
because you're still trying to dig one
hole. Okay? So, it's a decrease in
return to scale doubling the enterprise
or if you go to four guys with four
shovels, they're definitely going to be
just be way. They have to sit around for
a while. So, doubling the enterprise
doesn't double production. Of course, we
can also consider cases of increasing
returns to scale where f of 2L con
2k is greater than 2 * f of l and
k. Increase in returns to
scale that would might arise through
something like the fact that when the
firm gets bigger, it can specialize
more. So maybe as a firm gets bigger and
bigger, it can get better and better at
what it does and production can become
more and more efficient.
Okay. So these this is an important
concept because basically this is how we
think about economies growing. This is
the core of any model of economic
growth. If you take macroeconomics about
economic growth the core of any model of
economic growth is what is the returns
to scale for the
economy. Typically economists do not
believe that there's everywhere and
always increasing returns to scale. We
typically believe returns to scale may
increase initially as you specialize the
firm but eventually have to decrease.
And the reason we believe that or at
least believed that was that if there
was always and forever increasing
returns to scale, how many firms would
there be in the
economy? One. Because it could always
just do better by getting bigger and
bigger and bigger. Now, it turns out for
search engines, maybe that's not such a
bad description. We'll see in the trial
that's going on now where Google may get
broken up. So it may be that increasing
returns to scale may last longer than we
thought as economists but typically we
think of firms as maybe initially having
increasing return insurance to scale and
then eventually as they mature having
decreasing returns to
scale. Okay, questions about
that. Yeah.
Well, I'm going to get to that in a
second. Not necessarily. And I'm going
to get I'm going to get to that in one
second.
Okay, I want to because we haven't
talked about innovation yet and that's a
missing piece of this that I want to
turn to next. But other questions? So
I'm going to turn to last before I do I
just want to review where we are. So
basically just like we have utility
function and production function it
translates your inputs into your
outputs. In the short run labor's fixed,
capital's not this is just the only
reason I tell you short run case is to
develop the intuition of diminishing
marginal products. The ancient case the
long run was where it's just like
consumer theory. You're just like
consumer theory. You're trading off
pizza pizza and cookies to make you
happy. Here you're trading off labor and
capital to make a good. Okay. And it's
the same mathematics we saw
before. All
right. And likewise, just as we had
marginal rates of substitution
determining the slope of the difference
curve, we have these marginal rates of
technical substitution determining the
slope of the isoquant.
Now let me come to the question here and
talk about a last topic which is
productivity. One of the most exciting
topics in economics is thinking about
productivity. Okay. One of the most
famous and the idea of productivity
comes actually from a very famous
application from
1798 of the idea of uh decreasing
returns to scale or diminishing marginal
product. Thomas Malfus was a very I
think probably pretty depressed
philosopher given all the stuff he wrote
uh back in the
1700s and he said look think about the
production of
agriculture there's essentially two
inputs there's people and land the
people harvest the land he said in the
the difference between capital and land
is land is always fixed even in the long
run there's only so much land we got the
earth unless we go colonize another
planet which I don't think he was
thinking about back then there's a fixed
amount of land so that means that the
marginal product of labor must be
everywhere
diminishing that means that
eventually we're going to starve there's
only so much land as population grows
each worker's producing less and less
and less on the same amount of land and
eventually we starve through the
principle diminished marginal product he
didn't put it that way but that was
intuition basically a fixed amount of
land ever growing population each worker
produces less and less and less until
you can't feed yourself until you
produce less than actually needed to
feed yourself and people start to die
off. So Mthus actually said that there
would be cycle the world would be would
be marked by cycles of starvation that
essentially population would grow we'd
be unable to lose enough food. We'd all
a bunch of us would die off then we'd
have a small enough population we'd have
marginal product of labor that could
support production and we go back to
producing food again till we all died
off again. really not a very happy uh
picture of the
future. Now, since Mthus wrote that
book, the world population increased
roughly a
thousand%. Okay, roughly a thousand%
increase in world population and we are
fatter than
ever. Okay, so what did Mthus get wrong?
I mean, not there's not starvation and
let me be clear, there's horrible
problem starvation around the world.
Although let me also be clear the famous
economist of Marchen effectively won the
nob Nobel prize for an important
observation which is that there's never
been a famine in a
democracy. So we think about famines and
starvation all over the world. Remember
that's a political failure not
technological failure. There's never
been a famine in democracy. Famines only
happen when corrupt governments uh don't
spread the food they need to the people
who need to get it. So fundamentally we
have enough food despite the fact
population has gone up 10 times. gone up
a thousand% sorry 100 times. So what is
it? What's happened? What's changed?
What did Mthus mix miss? Yeah.
Technology. Mus the fact that we are
missing a key component of how we write
down our production function. We because
there's actually productivity
improvements in agriculture. What were
they? Well,
fertilizers, machines,
um basically in the long run we have and
eventually uh disease resistant seeds,
better land management practices. He
missed all the changes. He was right
that the amount of land is fixed, but he
missed the fact that the way we used
land will get more and more productive
over time. He missed all the technology
that was going to come. He missed the
productivity improvements that we were
going to
see. Okay.
actually world food consumption per
capita is actually up since 1950 despite
the fact that world population has
grown. So what this says is really we
should really think about writing
production functions as Q uh equals A
time F of L and K where A is a
productivity factor.
Okay, basically there's an extra piece
which makes the world more
productive. Okay, this is not just true
in
agriculture. Let's think of one of the
most famous examples which is car
production. Okay, basically before the
1900s, cars were made like other
customized goods. A single person or a
couple people make it together. And then
Henry Ford introduced the assembly line
where basically you had interchangeable
parts and you had a conveyor belt or
assembly line where people could just
specialize in putting this this screwing
this bolt in over and over and over
again and they could do it much faster
and they could specialize in it. Now
this seems pretty obvious at the time
but it was very pretty obvious now. It's
pretty radical at the time. He actually
cut the car cost of car production in
half almost
overnight. That was a massive
productivity improvement. the same
number of workers could produce many
more many same number of workers and
same number of machines you can produce
many many more
cars. Okay. Now, but this innovation
didn't just end with Henry Ford. Okay.
Um the Indian company Tata produces the
Nano which is a $2,500 car. How is the
Nano so cheap? Well, it's basically much
lighter than other cars. It's much
smaller, but they do things like putting
the wheels way out on the edge instead
of under the car to create more room for
people to sit in. Okay? And they
minimize the parts that are used to make
it easy to exchange and easier to
repair. Innovation is going on. And of
course, we're seeing perhaps most one of
the most major innovations in our in
automobile industry in decades, which is
the electrification of the automobile
fleet. And if you don't think Tesla's
more innovative than an old Ford, you
haven't seen a Tesla, okay? despite what
we think about Elon Musk. It's a pretty
cool car. Okay. So, basically we are
seeing continuous continuous um uh
productivity improvements and that's
what the standard model
misses. Okay. is that basically now this
has
become a really important area in
economics because ultimately a or
product improvements become one of the
key determinants for countries in their
standard of
living. Okay. So with standard of living
think of it as how much stuff do we get
to consume per person? Think of it as
our standard of living. How much stuff
do we have per person? Okay. What's
going to determine that? three things.
How hard we
work, how many machines we
have, and how productive we are with
those
inputs. Those are three things that'll
determine how much stuff we have. What's
great about productivity is these two
are expensive. Working harder is costly.
You got to work harder. It sucks.
Capital, you got to build a machine. You
need to use stuff to build a machine.
Productivity, boom, you got more. A
brilliant idea and suddenly, boom, you
got more stuff for everyone.
So productivity is is the magic that
makes economic growth happen almost
costlessly. Okay? And as a result,
productivity is the central determinant
of our standard of
living. And it turns out productivity
has changed. From World War II until
about
1973, US productivity grew at about 2
and a half% a year. What that meant was
working just as hard with just as many
machines, we could each consume two and
a half% more stuff every single
year, just magically through the growth
in productivity. Okay. However, from
1973 until the 1990s, that fell to less
than 1% a year, which meant if we wanted
more stuff, we had to work harder, get
more machines.
Now one question people were asking was
basically you know the IT revolution
started in the late 80s but productivity
didn't increase people were saying well
where's the IT revolution there's a
great saying saying you can see the IT
revolution everywhere in life except the
productivity numbers but then suddenly
there was a boom from the mid 90s to the
mid 2000s productivity jumped up again
we thought aha the IT revolution is here
productivity rose to about 2.3% a year
but after 2005 it stopped and
productivity is back down again to a
little more than 1% a
year. So, we're basically not really
growing. We're not really innovating and
developing and allow our standard of
living to grow as fast as it used
to.
Okay, this raises three key questions.
The first question
is, you know, why why not long lasting
effects of ET of it
ET? Why did the IT revolution sort of
cause this brief burst and then
eventually kind of wear
off? Is it because basically all our
innovation is watching Tik Tok and not
in making stuff? I don't know. But
that's sort of one question we have,
which is why is this incredible? You
guys have no idea how different life is
now than it was 25 years ago in terms of
the internet and everything you have,
but somehow we're not that much more
productive as an economy. The question
is why
not? The second question this
raises is where does productivity come
from? Where does what's the where does A
come from?
And here this is a rich field of study
because I said it was free. It's not
free. It's not magical. Productivity is
through real things. In the case of
Henry Ford is through a brilliant
insight. So one place A comes from is
education. As we educate people and make
them smarter, make them more creative,
they'll think of cool new
ideas. Okay. Productivity comes from
firm research and development.
As firms do research and development,
stuff that many of you may go on and do
with your
lives, okay, they think up new
ideas, okay, and they develop new
products. It also comes from public
research and
development like the National Science
Foundation. Some of you may have may may
eventually get funding from the National
SC may already have or may eventually
get funding from the National Science
Foundation for educations. The National
Science Foundation funds a lot of
research. The National Institutes of
Health fund a lot of research. This
turns out to be particularly critical
because that's a lot of the basic
research that gets done. Firms do what
we often call applied research. They
take basic ideas and turn them into
products. But the basic research is
often funded by government. And so
that's where that comes from. So
basically it there are things we can do
as society to increase our productivity.
We don't just sit back and let it
happen. Having more educated population,
more investments in R&D, the research
and development by the way is R&D. Those
can really make a difference in terms of
how fast we
grow. Third
question, third
point. How should we spend
productivity? And here's what I mean by
that. Imagine you have a cool new idea
that can make things more efficient.
Take Henry Ford's idea. He could do two
things with that. One is he could make
more cars. Two is he give people more
time off. Right? If A goes up, you can
reduce L and end up with the same amount
of
output. There's no reason an increase in
A has to go into more Q. An increase in
A could go into less L, which people
like. They like time off. One thing
we'll learn in this class, the hardest
thing I teach in this class at MIT, the
single hardest thing is in the real
world, people actually don't like work.
And we find this hard to believe, guys,
but in the real world, people would
rather not be at work than at work.
Okay? And basically people would rather
say well gee if you can make cars
quicker why am I why am I working so
hard and the answer is we don't know you
know there's no clear question about how
to spend productivity indeed the US and
Europe have made radically different
choices on this front decades since
World War II where productivity has
risen the US has largely put that into
more
goods Europe has largely put a lot of it
into more leisure so a starting worker
in Europe gets six weeks off a starting
worker in the US gets two weeks off.
Basically, people in Europe work from
about 25 to 60 and then stop. People in
the US work from like 20 to to 65. We
work a lot more hours per week. The US
has decided we want lot well, it's been
decided, I don't want to say necessarily
a conscious decision, but our society is
one which evolved to be that all the
productive improvements go into more
stuff. Whereas in Europe, a lot of it
goes into more time off. What's the
better thing to have? Good question.
Okay. When I was young, I probably
thought stuff. Now that I'm older, I
might think time off. Okay, but that's
something we need to be conscious of
that our society that societies can take
different paths. The pandemic may have
shook this up in the US. The pandemic
was the first chance that people had to
actually be at home and say, "Wait a
second, maybe I don't want to work that
hard." And there was a huge reduction in
labor supply after the pandemic. A lot
of people retired early. People aren't
working as hard. People want to be in
better jobs. People want to work from
home. So the pandemic really shook
things up in terms of people maybe
starting to value their leisure uh more
than maybe they did before. Okay, so
that's the third
question. The
fourth
is who gets
a that is which group in society
benefits from more productive
economy.
Okay. So basically
um if you look at the period from World
War II till
1973 the average US income grew by 2 and
a half% a year because of productivity.
It turns out pretty much every group in
society saw that increase. The poorest
people saw their incomes go up about two
and a half% a year. The richest people
saw their incomes go up to about two and
a half% a year. Since the mid1 1970s
that has changed
radically. Since the mid1 1970s
virtually all of the benefit of
increased productivity has gone to gone
to the richest members of society, the
people that own the capital and not to
the
workers. Okay. Basically, if you look at
the purchasing power of a typical wage
today, it's not much higher than what
you could buy with that wage in
1980. That is and we're the wage itself
is higher, but goods cost more. We'll
come back and talk more about inflation
and things. The bottom line is the
average worker can't buy that much more
stuff than they could in
1980. Meanwhile, the wealthiest have
gotten incredibly wealthy. Um the share
of wealth uh in the US um the share of
income controlled by the top 1% of
people in the US uh was uh 26% in
1989. Uh and it's 35% today.
Even more in 2021
uh in the coming back from the pandemic
in the year you know in the year after
the pandemic as we readjusted to life
the top 1% of earners saw their incomes
increase by
9% while everyone else saw their incomes
decrease. So the top 1% of earners were
the only group that actually saw their
income increase. Everyone else saw
income decrease because inflation aid
into people's wages.
The bottom line is we also a doesn't
magically go to everyone. Okay, it's not
like a more productive economy so
everyone benefits. That's determined by
a set of decisions made by individual
actors in the economy and by the
government. And that's what we'll talk
about later semester is how does the
government think about those decisions
or how do we think as society about how
to spend the extra resources we get when
the economy gets more productive. Okay.
Okay. And that comes to the topic of
economic fairness which we won't spend
nearly enough time on but we will come
back to towards the end of the semester.
Okay. Questions about
that? All right. Why don't we stop there
and uh there's there's no section
Friday, right? No section Friday.
Remember the first problem set is due
next Friday and the section you go to
next Friday is the one you're going to
stay in for the semester. Okay. Thank
you.