There are hundreds of millions of people
in the world with type 2 diabetes and
obesity and the numbers are expected to
rise. A big part of the mission of the
Novonautics Foundation is to increase
prevention and treatment of cardium
metabolic disease. So in Denmark we have
a strong tradition for research in
cardiumabolic disease and connecting
this to the broad institute which is
really good at conducting uh research at
scale. This is uh a really powerful
partnership. The Nova Norris Foundation
Center at the Broad Institute is a
center that has a unique architecture
that connects competences in the Danish
life science ecosystem with competences
at the Broad Institute to understand the
genetic mechanisms underlying type 2
diabetes and obesity. Type 2 diabetes is
a highly heterogeneous disorder. So by
understanding individual subtypes early
on, we are aiming to be able to
intervene and eventually cure diabetes
by identifying the biology that
underlies these individual subtypes of
of type 2 diabetes. Together with
Molina, uh my lab and her lab are
looking at how genetic variance
influence the risk of diabetes. The way
we're doing uh this is u measuring or
looking at an sites. So um fat cells in
the body. So rather than dissecting an
individual genetic risk locus one step
at a time typically taking years we have
implemented an edible site or fat cell
model derived from thousands of patients
over from the MGB um um bioank and we
developed ways of reading out biology at
scale resulting in an immense amount of
data. The expertise of my lab is that we
are very interested in uh making and
developing AI models that can integrate
various different types of biological
data. We are then trying to find
patterns that try to explain why a
genetic variant is influencing your risk
of uh type two diabetes. We also
collaborate with people. I and I think
that's really important. I've had
several PhD students from my lab that
have uh visited abroad and also Molina's
lab and a major benefit of uh being part
of the Novon Foundation Center at the
Broad. It's kind of like you know having
another home or another workplace where
people really care about you. We always
say that if you're part of this center
you're in the bridge building business.
We really just fully onboarded the
Danishbased scientists into the Broad
Institute as part of this collaboration.
Molina and Simon's collaboration is a
perfect exemplar for what's happening
across the entire center. We see an
incredible amount of opportunities to
take the discoveries that we're
currently making and then bringing them
to patient populations in Denmark and
elsewhere. What excites me the most
about the new Foundation Center at the
Broad is the great connections that have
been built, the excitement that's in the
center, the excellent science that is
being produced and hopefully the ability
to move towards better treatment of
cardabolic disease in the future.
[Music]