Thanks so much for having me and uh hey
everyone, thanks so much for joining us
today. My name is JQ. I guess my
government name is Jonathan. I go by my
initials. Uh wanted to rebranded high
school. There's too many Johns and
Jacks. So JQ was the way to go and it
rhymes with GQ. So it worked out
perfectly. Um so yeah, I am now a
secondyear MBA. I graduate next May. Um
my former career was in the government.
So I worked for the Department of
Defense. And this past summer I was in
defense tech. So I worked at a defense
tech startup. And what I really wanted
to get out of my MBA experience was to
really be able to pivot away from the
government side and better understand
how that private sector worked out. And
I feel that I have had a lot of great
tools and a lot of opportunities both
interacting with classmates and then
professors and then doing certain
conferences and the like and that's been
really useful for me um to develop on my
own and then also to build that network
with other individuals
I think. Yeah. Yeah. And then I guess on
the side what I'm also a part of, I am
the current co-president of the
Asian-American Alliance. We have a very
robust community of other affinity
groups. We also have different clubs
that focus on industry. So on top of the
Asian-American Alliance, I'm also part
of the global security tech club. Um and
then um there's also additional other
clubs. So like a big focus of other
individuals could be like tech and then
also um PM individuals. I guess that's
kind of my intro and if the panelists
are ready, Terrell, do you want me to
start with their introductions? Give
them a chance to speak.
>> Yeah, for sure. Go ahead.
>> Awesome. Why don't we start with Katie?
Katie and I actually over overlapped a
year. So Katie, why don't you give us
your intro, your name, your program,
your year, and what we were doing before
and after Sloan.
>> Now, can you hear me? Um, hi everyone.
My name is Katie Dao. I just graduated
um in this past spring. I was part of
the regular full-time MBA program. So,
two years before Sloan, I worked in life
sciences consulting and um I'm now in a
rotational program at a biotech.
Is that everything I was supposed to
say?
>> Thanks, Katie. How about we go to MK or
Manit?
>> Hi, everyone. Uh my name is Manit. I uh
did the Sloan fellows MBA program which
is one-year accelerated program. Uh
before Sloan I was in industry uh in
aerospace on the manufacturing side and
post Sloan I have been in consulting uh
still attached to aerospace industry but
now more focused uh on PE sector. Glad
to be here.
>> Thanks so much Mik. Greg.
Hi
>> everyone. I'm Greg Kim. Uh, I was an MBA
from the graduating class of 2018, which
means I applied 10 years ago, as someone
pointed out to me, unfortunately, a
couple weeks ago. Um, before school, I
was in IT consulting. Um, focused mainly
in the healthcare and education space.
And after school, I bounced around a few
places in like sort of the esports and
sports industry, including Riot Games,
Madison Square Garden, and now Oak.
Thanks, Greg. And then Elizabeth, I
don't know if you were granted the
panelists function. I think so. Right.
>> I just joined. Okay, cool. Um, hi
everyone. My name is Elizabeth How. I
graduated in 2022.
Um, I was part of the LJGO program. I
started before or before, um, joining
Sloan, I was a software engineer at
Wayfair for a couple of years. And then
after that, after school, I moved into
Johnson and Johnson
um working in the data strategy, data
engineering, the general data space. So
um I'm with their contact lens business
based outside of Jacksonville, Florida.
And um yeah, getting I've been doing
data engineering, data strategy, some
cloud computing, and we're getting into
a little bit of of Gen AI stuff now as
well.
Thanks Elizabeth and thank you all for
your intros. As you guys can see, it's a
fairly diverse um group of individuals
we have for our panel and again this is
focused on you know with uh the club
that we were all a part of and it's cool
to see that you can interact with people
from different programs. So the LGOS's
FM SFMBAs and there are certain classes
and certificates that you can take where
you can learn from those experiences. So
with that, just kind of want to start
with the first question. We'll go with
Greg and then we can go with Elizabeth
and then I'll go
actually let's just go with the the
other order. So that's easier.
Elizabeth, you can start first. Uh the
question is why do you choose Sloan?
>> Sure. Um I've always known that I wanted
to do an MBA at some point in my life as
a even as a software engineer. I felt
like maybe that wasn't what I wanted to
do forever. I didn't want to code
forever and to get into more of the
business space. I just felt like my
undergrad was too technical and I needed
some more business education. Um, with
that being said, I still really enjoyed
the technical aspect. So, I started
looking around to see if there were they
had dual degree programs out there
offered by um the top MBA schools. So
MIT came up actually um as one of my top
options. I visited um the campus. I was
already living in Cambridge so that
helped. Um but
having met Sloan, I also did other
visited other schools to see um the
culture and do some tours, join some
online and in person admission events
and just felt like the people that I met
with Sloan
um like I I could see myself here and it
had a good blend of the kind of
technical a little bit nerdy um
background with like a very downto-
earthth and nice culture which I didn't
always feel at other schools. So I felt
like my personality, my background and
my interests mixed really well with with
what Sloan is is for as well.
>> Great. Thanks Elizabeth.
>> Yeah. Um for me well I'll start with
YMBBA and then I'll quickly switch to
YO. the YMBA I think you know getting my
professional career start in consulting
like I mentioned I was in the healthcare
and education space really great
learning experience developed a really
great toolkit was kind of bored out of
my mind so I wanted to do something with
my career that was more exciting or I
was more passionate about so that was
why MBA and then why Sloan I think two
reasons one you know at my firm there
happened to be a few Sloan alumni who I
really looked up to uh one of my direct
managers was a Sloan um So there was
sort of like a I knew alums in the space
I I knew alums from the school uh that I
looked up to. And the second one which
is kind of a cheap answer is like Sloan
is unique in that we we have the Sloan
Sports Analytics Conference and that was
something I knew I wanted to be a part
of sort of since college when I read
about in the New York Times. So uh
coming to Sloan for for an MBA was sort
of full circle to to all of those
things.
>> Yeah. conferences were also what got me
uh involved with like Sloan hearing
about it. There's the national security
conference that I was able to attend
even before I joined Sloan officially.
So yeah, it's a great point MK or Manit.
>> Sure. So for me um similar to Elizabeth,
uh I have a technical background. I I'm
a material science engineer. So MIT is I
see it as a Mecca of uh uh engineers for
engineer for engineers. So it was a
natural um attraction affinity to the
school and I um by the time I was
looking into MBA programs I was uh a
decent amount into my career. So I
wanted to look at programs that are more
towards executive MBA and uh Sloan
Fellows is a unique program because it
is an executive MBA but it's a full year
uh full-time uh one year full-time. So
you're you are actually stepping away
from your career, taking a break and
kind of resetting. So I like that aspect
of it. And then thirdly, I was al
already in Boston. And I I had visited
other campuses, but it it was either
like they're uh too big or in a too
small of a town. So Boston already felt
like home and it was just a comfortable
transition.
>> Yeah. Thanks, man. Yeah, I can
definitely speak to just like the
different amounts of skill sets that I
mentioned earlier. I mean, even the
greater undergraduate community too in
general, graduates, PhD students. I've
taken some classes with those
individuals and just learned a lot and
everyone's trying to build something
together, have that passion, which is
awesome, Katie.
>> Yeah. Um, I think I echo a lot of what
everyone else said. Um, so I won't
repeat it too much, but um, one thing I
will say is I I think a few of us have
technical backgrounds. I also had a
technical undergrad degree and so I did
want business I did want to get an MBA
to get a business degree, but you
definitely don't have to have a
technical background to come at to MIT.
Some of my friends were journalists,
like English majors, things like that.
So don't let that intimidate you. Um,
just because quite a few of us have
technical backgrounds. Um but yeah, I so
I I wanted to learn more about business.
I wanted to get um I wanted to pivot out
of consulting so was looking at business
schools. Um and yeah, again echo a lot
of what other folks said, but I really
loved kind of the innovative culture of
MIT and of Sloan. Um you know, there's
so many people working on like really
interesting things, trying to solve
really interesting problems. So that was
a big plus for me. Additionally, being
interested in healthcare and life
sciences. Um the Cambridge area is
obviously extremely strong. There's tons
of small biotechs. Um obviously lots of
research going on at MIT. So it felt
like a good fit for me industry-wise.
And then last thing I'll say is that I
really liked the class size of Sloan.
Um, so Sloan is a little bit of a
smaller class size than a lot of other
similar schools. Um, and I really
appreciated that because, you know,
roughly 400 people, and this is for the
regular MBA program, but roughly 400
people, you can kind of get to know most
of them. Maybe not, you're not best
friends with every single one of them,
but it felt like a very manageable class
size, and I really liked that.
>> Yeah, thanks, Katie. Yeah, definitely
really appreciate that. right now,
especially as I've made like more of my
friends in the second year, I can really
get to really hear their thoughts
outside of some of the um you know, what
I was used to in undergrad. Um all
right, so for the next question, I'll
start with Greg and then we'll go with
Elizabeth and then Manita and Katie and
it'll be focused on the community at
Sloan. So just describe it for us what
your experiences were, pros, no cons, no
cons,
>> no cons. Um I think I think everyone's
going to say this, but I think it was
super collaborative. Um, I'll be honest,
like I came into an MBA program
expecting
sort of what you may from what I hear
get at some other schools like a type A
super competitive environment just there
to network. But like I think one of the
biggest things that quickly surprised me
about Sloan was just how how
collaborative everyone was and that like
you know I made friends for life at
school. Uh I wasn't necessarily
expecting to, but um just hitting the
ground running our first core semester,
getting to know everyone in my core team
and my section like I you know I made
fast friends very quickly and they've
stayed my friends since school and like
sure the networking elements really
helpful but um I sort of really
appreciated how all my classmates and I
one banded together to get through some
of the coursework but two just like you
know just being in Boston together for
those two years. Um, I definitely would
not trade that for anything. So, um,
yeah, I think really supportive and
collaborative. That's how I describe it.
>> Thanks, Greg.
>> I Yeah, I don't remember.
>> Sorry, I Elizabeth. Okay.
>> Okay. Um, definitely echo what Greg
said. Very collaborative
um, ex um, culture at Sloan. um first
core semester, a lot of the work you do
is with your core team and so a lot of
the projects are team projects um if not
most of them. And
my experience is a little bit different
first few semesters just because I
actually said yes to Sloan the week
before the country shut down in 2020.
So, the first semester was a little bit
more a little bit different, but but MIT
definitely tried to still give us the
inperson experience, which we did get,
we just couldn't like all 400 of us
couldn't have been on campus at the same
time. Um, but even though maybe a lot of
the traditional more um get to know you
in person networking experiences weren't
um available to us right away, I think
we were all very creative in coming up
with different ways to get to know each
other. Um so smaller um dinners, people
had like online cookbook clubs where
where people who liked to cook would
would join Zoom at the same time and
each week somebody would pick a dish
they wanted to teach everybody how to do
and send the ingredients beforehand. So
I think um class-wise it's very
collaborative. People are very friendly.
It's very innovative. And I think that
also um goes to show even in like the co
pandemic how we were able to work with
the situation that we were handed with
and still um
come out lifelong friends and get the
the work done and
yeah I think it was pretty much
everything that I expected and more. Um,
so yeah, there are honestly no cons from
my end. I was very happy with with the
decision with going to Sloan.
>> Thanks, Elizabeth. Elizabeth Manique.
>> Uh, I would say again this is
incremental. Um,
I was very pleasantly surprised by uh
everyone's humility. I think um coming
in of course everybody is very well
accomplished and uh you know we we
that's the first thing generally we
project especially in this kind of
environment with a very uh prestigious
school very competitive admissions
process. Um, but it was really great
once you start working together and you
know you get past all of that. It was
just uh really pleasant to find out that
people are so smart and they're experts
in whatever area they work in or they're
coming from, but they're still very
humble and they're very um if very
helpful, collaborative, if you have any
questions, you know, they'll they will
go out of their way to help each other
out. So,
what I would say about the community.
>> Absolutely, Katie.
>> Yeah. No, I mean I agree with everyone
everything that's been said. Definitely
a culture of Sloan's helping Sloan. Um I
also think just uh a really passionate
community. Everyone is like really
excited about the things they're working
on or the clubs that they're helping
lead. And I just found it to be like a a
really invigorating community um where I
could just learn so much from other
people and everyone is always willing to
yeah take the time to help you and give
you feedback on you know whatever you
might be working on and things like
that. So yeah really really great strong
um community.
>> Thanks Katie and thanks everyone. Yeah
love it and I'm still appreciating it
right now. I mean today is a big club
fest day. So that's where all of the new
students get to interact with all the
different clubs they can be a part of.
So there's that club culture. There's
also just that general sense as Katie
was talking about like Sloan is helping
Sloan. And we'll go into a question
later on about the alumni community. Um
but there's I'm sure there's some
anecdotes that people have to share
about that. But for our next question,
we're going to ask um we're going to
start with Manite on just how were you
involved in the community at Sloan?
So for uh I'd say for SF MBA program
it's a little bit tricky because we are
we're there for a very short amount of
time. Um
but we I think we still made the most of
it. Uh in terms of community of course
you have clubs, conferences, people have
already mentioned that but a big part of
your community is going to be your your
classmates, your cohort, your core teams
and things that you plan with them. So
um outside of the of the the structured
uh environment I'd say like you find um
there are hackathons that you can find
people of your same interest connect
with them uh through hackathons through
clubs uh you also as you learn more
about each other um you connect on
things so we like did lot of hiking
trips around um there al also tres that
you can do uh and if you're doing any
certification you get to participate in
those tracks. Um and then one thing
that's very memorable for me is that um
there are these C c functions that that
get hosted through clubs and our cohort
we did our like our own version of C
function where we in uh had the whole
cohort do different cultural themes. So
we had like a um um what is it like an
Indian indo um Southeast Asian night. We
had a Japanese night. So we did all
these different cultural events and it
was just really great to immerse in
other people's culture and learn more
about uh their traditions.
>> Thanks Manate. I hope Katie so she
doesn't have to regurgitate everyone's
statements.
Thank you, JQ. Um, yes, on campus,
there's lots to join on campus. Um, so
for me, I was uh I was one of the
co-presidents of the yarn, which is
Sloan's um kind of storytelling
organization, but it's essentially it's
this really awesome um event. It's
basically happens almost every month
where uh four Sloanies will get up and
they'll kind of talk about their life
story for 20 minutes in front of um
roughly 200 people, 300 people, whoever
wants to show up that night. Um but it's
this really awesome experience to
connect with your fellow Sloonies and
kind of like get to know them um a bit
better and help just understand the
different walks of life that people come
from. So I was co-president of that. So
that took up a lot of my time. Um but I
was also involved in the helping run the
healthcare conference which was fun but
a lot of work. Um as folks mentioned
conferences are a really big thing and
they are a tough but rewarding
experience. It's really um it's a really
cool experience and a big accomplishment
to say that you helped put one of those
on and like bring together really
interesting speakers and come up with
interesting panels and just put a whole
operation on.
And then I was also part of the
Asian-American Alliance board with JQ um
which was also a really really wonderful
experience, a really great way to
connect with fellow Asian and
Asian-American Sloanies. and we put on
several different events, some of them
being like the C functions like Manique
mentioned. Um, and then I think one of
the highlights also of kind of my like
club involvement was I um kind of held
like a a panel for um you know different
Asian and Asian-American Sloan to talk
about their experiences and just kind of
share with the broader Sloan population
of you know what are things that the a
that Asians and Asian-Americans go
through just in in the world and in the
day-to-day. Um, so that was a really
cool experience to kind of think about
the questions that we wanted to ask and
the different elements of the
Asian-American experience that we wanted
to showcase to kind of the broader
broader Sloan population. Yeah, that was
a little bit of what I was involved in.
>> Can attest to Katie's involvement. And
then she also was the chief merch
officer and she helped us create this
sweater which all the students
areounding over right now. So, good job,
Katie.
All right, Elizabeth.
How were you involved um in the
community?
>> Sure. So, being in the LJGO program,
there are certain committees within the
program that are all run by students on
top of the the Sloan clubs that kind of
circle around the
requirements we also have in our
program. So I was um one of the
co-chairs of the internship committee
which helps
filter through all of the so in the LJGO
program it's a 24-month full-time
two-year program where one of your
semesters so full six months you're
actually off with a company doing a six
month internship and so um all of these
companies that propose projects need to
come through MIT and the students groom
through them to see depending on which
engineering major you are and what
project it is what majors can do it.
Anyways, I was on that internship
committee. Um I also my first year I
worked on the the sports analytics
conference which was
like like folks mentioned a lot of work
but very rewarding. Um it was the first
time it was online again. So different
challenges that we had to work through
than previous years, but um it was it
was fun either way and got to meet a lot
of people and make connections that I
otherwise probably wouldn't have. Um, I
went on a lot of tres, as many as I
could, um, because I really like
traveling and I, a lot of these trees
are planned by students from these
different countries. And so, um, going
on these trucks gave me a way of
experiencing a country that that people
from that country want like to put
together for you and like do the local
things, but also some of the the
traditional like touristy things. It was
a good blend of that, but also I think
what was really cool is on the Israel
track there were there was a lot of like
learning that I wouldn't have gotten.
They had speakers, they had like
um people from the local community come
come talk to us and we even had like a
panel. So I think it was a good blend of
learning and and fun with a lot of good
friends and meeting new friends.
Um what else did I do? I think I went to
a lot of C functions. That's also a lot
of fun and a a good way to experience
different cultures, different clubs. Um,
but yeah, I think that was that was most
of what I did.
Yep.
>> Thanks, Elizabeth. Yeah, the C functions
were the culture functions. So, it's
where the affinity clubs, all the
affinity clubs host kind of a event
where they kind of showcase their
culture, be it through food, be it
through dance. Um, and yeah, those are
so much fun. Um, I think our first one
is next week with the Hispanic Business
Club. Um, and yeah, for the sports
analytics conference, fingers crossed
for Caitlyn Clark and Tom Brady. I mean,
you never know.
>> I'm just pointing that out there. I just
hope. Who knows,
>> Greg?
>> Yeah, that's a good segue. Um, so, so I
was that my crowning achievement at
Stone was working on the sports
conference. Um, I was co-lead my second
year and that was the year we were lucky
enough to bring in President Barack
Obama. So, not quite Caitlin Clark, but
maybe close. Um, so that that consumed
my life. uh pretty much all of second
year. Uh happily so um the first year I
was also involved. I just kind of did
like the esports panel and like we did a
Super Smash Brothers tournament which
was kind of funny. Um so that that was
like my main extracurricular and I think
you know some people do a broad range of
stuff. Some people really focus in on
like the one they really care about. Um
I would say the latter path is sort of
what I did when I was at school. Um
otherwise community-wise I think like I
kind of alluded to it. I had a really
great experience my first year with my
ocean and my core team. Not everyone
does, but we were a pretty tight-knit
group. Um I don't know if they do it
anymore, but there used to be like a
Sloan Olympics thing, which is basically
like a small field day. Um we won that
our first fall. We're obnoxious and came
back as a team in the spring, which most
people don't do. And we also did it our
second year as like a second year Baltic
Ocean team, which was really obnoxious.
Uh but it was a lot of fun for all of
us. So, um, yeah, pretty much like the
conference and just just hanging out
with my close friends, you know, I think
Boston's both Boston's a great town when
you have a community around you and
Sloan gives you that. So, just, you
know, being able to hang out all over
Cambridge or people's houses, um, you're
just like grabbing dinner together, just
like playing board games at someone's
house. Um, those are some of the like my
best memories at Sloan. So, I would say
like those are the kind of the two
things. Uh, two ways I most engage with
the community.
>> Thanks, Greg. Yeah, listen to all your
reflections makes me really privileged
to still be at school and really
>> goes by fast.
>> Goes by really fast.
>> That office quote where it's like, I
wish I knew I was in the good times when
I'm in them. So, good good reminder.
Thanks, guys. We're going to do one more
question. We'll pass over the Q&A to I
think if that makes sense um the last 20
minutes or so. All right, this final
question is how have you engaged with
the alumni network either as a student
uh and since graduating?
So, we'll go with um let's see, we'll
give Katie another shot. Katie, all you.
>> My answer will probably be the shortest
because I've only been out of school for
um like three months, so I am a fresh
alum. Um but yeah, I mean I so I live in
New York now. there's super strong alum
representation in New York. And I'm I
think I'm hanging out with Sloan people
at least once or twice a week. Um so
that's kind of I I can't really speak to
too much further than that because I
haven't like had to network for a new
job or anything yet. But um no, I I
think I mean actually I'll take a step
back. When I was recruiting and looking
for my internships and my jobs, I will
say that the alum network was very
responsive. like pretty much anyone I
would reach out to on LinkedIn would
respond to me and respond to me pretty
quickly um and just want to be as
helpful as possible. So yeah, I think
the the alum network is is quite strong,
but I'm a fresh alum, so I'll hand it
over to the others.
>> Thanks, Katie. Oops. Uh let's see.
Elizabeth, why don't you go next?
>> Sure. Um
agree with what Katie said. The alum
network is is definitely strong. Being
in Jacksonville, Florida, there isn't a
huge Sloan presence here, but um I've
stayed connected with actually some of
the alums that I connected with while I
was still in school, either through like
while I was doing my my six-month LJGO
internship. I did a ton of networking
then because outside of work, there
wasn't like homework to do. So I stayed
in touch with them and I
the el the LJL program puts together a
alumni conference every year. So right
out of school I went to the the first
the conference for for that year. I
haven't been back since because work got
busy. But I think those are just um
examples of how um the alums continue to
stay connected and um with my friends. I
still meet up with them whenever I go to
Boston. A lot of them stay in Boston. So
that's sort of like peer-to-peer
connections with with alums, but kind of
more upward wise. Um agree with what
Katie said. People are always super
responsive. I've been to panels or um
meetings with alums where they literally
said, "I will hire you just because you
graduated from here and we went through
the same experiences." Um which is
something I've never heard before and
I've heard it from multiple people. So I
think the fact that
um we all went through the same
experiences and um the alums know what
education we got through through the the
program gives them enough belief in our
in our abilities to be able to take up
um jobs that we're interested in in in
their space and develop into it even if
we didn't necessarily have the skills um
at the very beginning. Um
yeah, I think overall the alumni
community has has been very strong. Um
I think our and then I guess through
me as an alum now I've had people reach
out to me on LinkedIn as well interested
in exploring applying to MIT and also
like why would you apply to a dual
degree program? um kind of wanting to
know more about the experiences and
walking through their their story to see
if if the program is a good fit. Do they
want to go the full-time MBA or do they
want um something like the LJGO program
where you get a degree in the in
engineering and a degree in M in your
MBA all in two years. It is more school
work for sure, but um if it's something
that you're interested in, it is it is
worth the work.
>> Thanks, Elizabeth. Rick, how about you?
>> Yeah, I would say like the the network's
both like there when you need it, but
it's also there when you don't, right?
Like I think Sloan's helping Sloan is a
very real thing. I think anytime
um I've been considering new
opportunities or my peers have like it's
really easy to just link like link up
with any other alum on uh any other alum
like through LinkedIn or or just through
your own personal network and someone's
always willing to lend a helping hand.
Um I would say the most frequent way
manifests itself is just like with my
peer group, right? Just like having the
group chat, right? Like um the other day
like one of my analysts was bothering me
so I was just like I just like hopped on
WhatsApp like hey guys like how do you
guys handle this kind of thing right or
or how do you deal with these situations
or you know when it's time to have comp
conversations like how are you
navigating these things I think just
like just having that group of people
who share that set of experiences. It
also so happens that a bunch of people
in my group chat are Asian-American, so
like I think that helps too. But just
like being able to like have those
shared experiences and background, know
someone's coming from a similar place
even if they're in a different industry
or something like I think that's been a
huge plus and it's just kind of like a
great day-to-day relief. Um, and also
like now, you know, my I I work for like
a sponsorship agency part of our
company. So, like when we're doing
business sales, like I actually like
have a network of people who are like
mid-level senior at a bunch of companies
now that like I can try to get in touch
with to help our sales people try to
actually sell some sports sponsorship.
So, it's had a little bit more practical
value in the last couple years too,
which I didn't necessarily expect. So,
both formally and informally, I think
it's it's it's a really tight-knit
community.
>> Awesome. Thanks, Greg. Manit.
>> Yeah. um resonate with each uh point
everybody made. Um it's great. I mean
I've been keeping in touch or tapping
into the alumni network uh for any you
know if you want to get any perspective
on industry or want to understand uh
something in gather some insights on a
particular industry. It has been great.
It has been great for warm intros. Uh so
um you know I've reached out to people
uh whom I know and then they have
offered to connect me to three or four
other people and warm introductions are
always um more responsive than cold. Um
other than that I would say they're uh
another great asset to have when you're
traveling. So I'm in I'm still in like
these uh big WhatsApp groups and if
somebody is going to be in a city they
just post it like hey going to be in
London these days is anybody around and
people are usually very responsive and
you know even though you have may have
not gone to the same program or the not
overlapped at all but just because
you're associated with the with the
school people will show up to meet you
like complete strangers but you still
have something woman.
>> Thanks, Minnie. Thanks, guys. So, we're
going to go into some Q&A from the
attendees. Terrell, do you want me to
take this or do you want to? I'm happy
to.
>> Take it away, JQ.
>> Awesome. So, we're going to start with
Elizabeth. Someone had a question
specific for the LJGO, but while she's
answering that question, I want you guys
all for the next question just like your
best memory or like the most rewarding
experience of Sloan for you. So, for
Elizabeth, we're going to start with
LJGO specifically. Um, how' the LJL
experience compare with the with your
MBA counterparts? Specifically, did you
find that you missed out on networking
opportunities or had less time to engage
with the MBA class because of your MS
requirements?
Um short answer is yes. You do have less
time to do maybe some of the other um
MBA activities like I wasn't as involved
as as Katie or a lot of people were in
in Sloan clubs um because of the
engineering classes but I chose to take
more engineering classes slightly more
engineering classes than required. I
think people can choose to tailor their
experience to just the minimal
requirements and take the rest of your
classes all within Sloan. Um or do half
and half or somebody in my class did a
minimal Sloan requirements and all
engineering otherwise. Um, so short
answer is yes, but I think you can
tailor it to to be more Sloan focused if
you wanted to. And also just a caveat
that my experience was during COVID and
so a lot of the large group activities
that you normally we normally would have
gone to as a whole cohort wasn't
available to us. So it was also more
more effort on the individual to to
schedule these smaller gettogethers to
get to know groups and instead of like
five oceans normally we had eight my
year. So they added some rivers and
called them oceans anyway. So I was part
of the Amazon River and they had other
rivers as well. So each cohort was also
smaller.
um which makes it easier to get to know
your co your cohort but also not not
that easy to get to know the whole class
when you're not on campus at the same
time. But going back to the normal
experience, I definitely had classmates
who who were way more involved on the
MBA side and wouldn't say that that they
missed out on too much because of their
their engineering requirements. Um
within the engineering courses, you can
also choose to take easier classes or
harder classes. So I think it's very
very much still even though there are
additional academic requirements there
are ways that you can tailor it to your
need.
>> Thanks Elizabeth. So now I'll allow you
some time to think about your your best
memory most rewarding experience.
Manique are you ready?
Yeah, I I don't know if I will be ready,
but I'm just like scrolling through my
down the memory lane to pick one because
it is so difficult. Um, I'm going to go
with like a celebrity shock type of
experience. Um and this is again like
there's so many experiences to pick from
but Indraui was a guest speaker on uh
campus and uh she was in um the Samberg
conference room upstairs. Um, and I
remember like I mean
given her accomplishments and just how
uh uh well celebrated of a CEO she has
been and a board member um you know
you're I was sitting in the first row
and I remember like being that close. I
I'm usually not a fan of people, but it
was just like, wow, this is amazing that
you're you get to be in presence of such
a great personality and actually have
the opportunity to ask questions, you
know, even after the talk, have
one-on-one conversations. So, I think
just um it the school providing that
opportunity and having these celebrity
type people on campus is awesome.
Thanks, Manatee. Katie, you're gonna go
last. Well, actually, Elizabeth will go
last. Greg, how about you?
>> Um, for me, aside from the conference,
um, I think it was like I think it was
the payoff of second year spring. This
probably isn't the right topic for an
admissions panel, but I think just like
being able to spend time with all my
friends like going all over the place
essentially once like you know all the
like most of the work was done and I had
the job offer like that was when I
really got to I think enjoy my time at
school and connect with my classmates
most like like literally the week after
the sports conference I just like
grabbed my four closest friends like
you're coming with me to Disney World
and we just like skipped class and went
to Disney World for like four days. Um,
but but I think it was all those little
moments. Like I think it was it was
doing that. It was going on like a New
Zealand study tour. It was like going on
a trip with my friends to Europe for
graduation. Like I think the classroom
stuff was great. The network I built was
great, but this the my favorite moments
were all on my classmates for sure.
>> Thanks, Greg. Katie.
>> Yeah. Um, having just gone through
second year spring, I can definitely
definitely agree with Greg. It's uh
really chaotic but really fun and a lot
of like really good bonding and memories
um with friends. Um, but for me, I would
say probably my like proudest memory
from Sloan was doing a yarn, which is
like kind of what I described earlier.
Um, of like getting getting up in front
of 200 of my classmates and just talking
about my life for 20 minutes. Um, which
for me was like an extremely rewarding
experience because like going into the
MBA, going into the MBA, if you had
asked me if I would ever do one, I would
have been like a million% no. like you
could not force me to I would not want
to go in front of that many people and
just like be vulnerable. Um but like
being Asian-American and like there's
you know I obviously it's generalities
and you know stereotypes but I
definitely um struggled with like being
quiet and not using my voice enough and
that was a lot of the feedback that I
got coming into the MBA. And so it was
definitely something that I really
wanted to push on and work on and and
grow in. And so yeah, doing the yarn was
kind of like a culmination of all of
that and something that I very proud of
myself for doing.
>> Thanks Katie Elizabeth.
>> My
maybe because I'm also further away from
from from being in school. My my first
um thought when you asked the question
was also trip related with my
classmates. It was also towards the end
of of our time there. Um it was a trip
to Argentina where our first flight got
cancelled and we were running around the
airport trying to rebook ourselves to to
go to Argentina. And it kind of just
running through the airport with my
classmates and like it felt like an
amazing race moment where everybody was
like running from terminal to terminal
trying to get a flight that would get us
there as soon as possible. And then and
then yeah, just just small moments that
make up the whole whole story that end
up being bits and pieces of of memory
that you take with take with you
forever. I think is is
like what's what stuck with me when you
first asked the question. But of course
like the classroom was was great and
um but all of all of those things kind
of build together to into the different
relationships that we that you have that
you end up um making memories with these
different people that that stick with
you and and take going forward.
>> Thanks, Elizabeth. All right. So, we
have a question for Manit focused on the
SFMBA. So, we're going to do that next,
but uh in the background as our last
question, we'll close out with um a
question for everyone on how the
Asian-American community has at Sloan
has helped you with like your career
progression or how it's helped you along
the way. So, Manique, for you with the
SFMBA program, there's like kind of two
questions. Um but so the SFMBA is known
to leave no fell behind. Um and they are
asking specifically how much support
would you say you have received from
your fellows in moving through career
switch post SFMBA and what kind of
support was that? They mentioned that
they have a background in aerospace. So
they're interested in also uh switching
I believe and then also speaking to the
fact of the one-year program versus the
two-year program if you're able to
provide a succinct answer there.
>> I'll do my best. Um yeah, so as far as
support, I would say a lot of support.
So as I was um entering the program, I
knew what I wanted to get out of and
what my path was going to be post MBA,
but I was um you know, you you meet
people from different walks of life and
different experiences, industries. And
it was really good to learn more about
different industries, not just from the
outside, but actually understand what a
a day in the life of um a consultant or
a day in the life of a um a PE analyst
would be like. So I think it was very
helpful to know the the true picture and
even after the program um just
connecting to the alumni as I was going
through the recruitment process to like
make the right connections was very
helpful. So definitely like we uh live
behind.
Um as far as the second part was about
what was it other than the support
>> the one and two years.
>> Okay. The one one to two years. Uh yeah.
So I
one year definitely feels very short and
at the end of one year we were all like
oh where did it was just blink of an eye
and here we are at graduation. So
definitely 2 years would have felt a lot
better because there's not there's
you're you're doing your program and
then there's loan but then there's MIT
so you want to experience all of it and
it's just juggling a lot of different
priorities. Um, it would have been nice
to do the two-year program, but then uh
you just have to know what what your
what works best for you because one year
also allows you to go back into uh
workforce like after one year you're not
away from your career for two years. Uh
so I it it's it's a balance. Um, if I
could if I could have made everything
work with the two-year, perhaps I would
have chosen that. But it is what it is.
>> Hey, if it was going to be five years
for two years of tuition, I'd do it.
>> Yeah, there you go. Exactly.
>> All right, Greg, you spoke a little bit
about um how you are in WhatsApp groups
with uh your fellow Asian-American
Sloan. Can you speak a little bit to how
that community at Sloan has helped you?
>> Yeah, I think I mean I think that's more
like
>> Yeah, I think that's more natural social
evolution, not like Sloan helping me.
Um, but I would say like I think in that
regard I I think you know my career is a
bit off the beaten path, right? Like I
went into this video game thing for a
couple years. I came back to traditional
sports and there weren't there aren't
exactly a lot of Sloan alumni in my
space that are Asian-American. So it for
me I think it hasn't been as helpful in
that regard. that the way I think it has
been helpful is kind of like I alluded
to earlier from like a peer-to-peer
experience, right? Like there's I like I
just like have the sounding board of of
my friends. Um you kind of have like all
your friends is like a barometer for for
you know how you're approaching your
career. You're helping them solve their
questions which is like gives you more
perspective uh on like the challenges
that you face. I you know I think in the
same way just as like with any strong
educational institution like most of
your learning happens not in the
classroom but from your peers and I I
think in that way um just like the
Asian-Americans who happen to be my
closest friends have been like you know
immense in in my like personal
development and like in some of the ways
I approached my career. So, uh, I think
in that way, uh, I think both
Asian-Americans in Sloan and the broader
Sloan community are, um, you have been a
powerful thing.
>> Thanks, Greg, Katie.
>> Yeah, I mean, um, I think I'm lucky that
some of my close friends who are
Asian-American were also ines.
So, um, we were able to like take
classes together and like work on
project teams together. And then as we
were going through like recruiting and
like negotiating our offers and things
like that, it was really great to be
able to just like bounce
ideas, bounce questions off each other,
just like understand what they were
going through. Um, and actually some of
those people like I got to know through
the AsianAmerican Alliance and through
like the Asian-American Alliance events
and ski trip and things like that. So, I
probably would have known them through
the classes we had taken, but I don't
think I would have been as close to
them. So, I feel like I was very lucky
in that sense.
>> Thanks, Katie. Elizabeth,
>> sure. Um, similar to what Greg and Katie
already shared, a lot of it um
are a lot of the how has being part of
the community helped. Um, while I was at
Sloan, I think something that stood out
to me is is like being
having maybe similar cultural
backgrounds and understanding um our
upbringing being and like Katie shared
before too, like coming into school
knowing maybe we were known as more shy
people or soft-spoken
that it is something that we wanted to
work on or even as an Asian-American
woman noticing that often often times we
say sorry when it is not necessary. Um
during school I remember that was
something that a lot of us wanted to
work on. And so in just daily life and
conversation when somebody says it when
it was not needed that we would call
each other out on it and and through
time you you start noticing that you
start doing it less. And so I think that
is just I think something interesting
with the with the shared um experiences
and um through the friendship and
openness and just people being very very
open and opening open to be vulnerable
with each other was was definitely
um something that I think was very
refreshing and and
memorable that
still to to this day we we share similar
similarly even though we're in different
industries with with my friends like
what we're going through our challenges
and how we might navigate through
different situations
and
and it's always a learning experience as
well as a just sometimes a nice nice um
set of ears to to vent to.
Yeah, definitely. Thanks, Elizabeth.
Manise, close us out.
>> Sure. Uh, so I'd say I mean, Sloan and
MIT in general is a very diverse place.
So, I think it it provides us the a
platform or the ability to connect with
a lot of our identities. So, we're we're
like Elizabeth mentioned, we're uh we're
woman, we have a certain way, and we're
Asian-American, and we're other things.
We are technical background people. So
it just you you find uh because it's
such a diverse community uh in all
aspects not just in our physical
attributes or backgrounds in many
aspects that you it allows you to find
others that that are similar in that and
just uh be yourself be your natural self
u while you're going through this
transformational experience.