think uh okay yeah an area we've been uh
doing research on for uh for the past
few years which is the orbital carrying
capacity and space sustainability
implications now this this topic has
implications for Space Traffic
management orbital debris and so I'll
cover a lot of those as well so before I
get there I want to talk about my
research group uh here at MIT and the
areas that we cover uh so these are the
four sort of groupings of areas we
definitely cover a lot of topics um in
our work at MIT so space sustainability
has been a key uh Focus area we actually
started working on this back in 2018 um
before this really came to the Limelight
with NASA's renewed focus on Space
sustainability and some of the new
international efforts on Space
sustainability uh we do a lot of work in
understanding space weather in
particular the effects of space weather
on on orbit assets satellites um and how
satellites are impacted by space weather
Space Traffic management is becoming
more and more important we've done a lot
of work on coordinating large satellite
constellations and understanding the
Space Traffic management constraints
when you have constellations that are
occupying nearby orbits and finally my
group is is well known for space
situational awareness and fundamental
astrodynamics so in that topic area
we're really focused on uh understanding
what's on orbit the algorithms and
processes for taking observational data
and converting that into an a detailed
understanding of the objects that are on
orbit and we also do fundamental
astrodynamics which is the fun stuff so
the applied math of orbital mechanics
here's a picture of my group uh we have
about seven students for posts uh spread
across these these four areas so with
that I want to motivate the talk for
today with this with this uh movie and
essentially what you're seeing here are
some projected and some that have become
reality of the future Space Traffic that
we're expecting over the next uh 10 to
30 years so for example a low earth
orbit population has more than doubled a
lot of that has to do with the starlink
constellation that at the moment is
above 7,000 satellites in orbit uh
beyond that there are other
constellations that want to uh basically
access similar commercial opportunities
to starlink such as Kyper constellation
and other uh constellations such as one
web and um Boeing and their
constellation so this picture is looking
fairly crowded there's going to be a lot
of activity up there
and we're going to be operating in lowth
orbit at a a level of satellite activity
that we've never seen before so this is
hopefully a a promising future but is
causing some concerns and some of those
concerns we've known about for a while
here's Hollywood's take on the orbital
debris problem of course this is the um
um the movie uh that Hollywood created
uh to discuss the Kesler effect so this
is the Gravity movie and a lot of the
details here in that in that uh sequence
are not physically uh are not physically
um accurate but the idea that orbital
debris might become an issue and might
threaten um crude space flight um is
actually a re a real um risk so there's
an effect that we know in the community
called the Kesler effect where
potentially in the future we might have
the density of debris in low of orbit
reach a critical point and once it
reaches that critical point collisions
are going to lead to subsequent
collisions and we might have this
catastrophic Cascade in low earth orbit
and that could render u space activities
potentially infeasible or more or less
just very difficult um so we want to
kind of prevent this future in lowth
orbit and so governments are concerned
about these space sustainability issues
so we had recently NASA release a space
sustainability strategy volume one um
and NASA's planned to release subsequent
uh documents on Space sustainability and
there efforts but also the FCC has
issued the first fine for a debris event
so um dish uh satellite network was
fined about
$150,000 for a debris generation event
FCC also changed some of the rules
around orbital debris in particular NASA
had this precedent this rule that uh
they expected owner operators to remove
defunct satellites within 25 years of
mission um end and so FCC has updated
that recently from 25 years to 5 years
um a lot of these rules a lot of these
efforts and that's not just in the US um
there's an effort in the UK focus on
Space sustainability and Issa has
established a zero debris Charter where
they're hoping that companies sign on to
this Charter and um basically agree to
generate zero debris or uh work towards
that goal so governments want to do
something before it's too late but the
issue that we're seeing within our group
and uh more broadly is that there aren't
hard numbers
and there there aren't hard physics
behind some of these initiatives so what
we hope to do and what I want to share
with you today is we've been developing
this tool at MIT called mocat and mocat
stands for the MIT orbital Capacity
Analysis tool and we hope to change that
we hope to put hard numbers Behind these
calculations and some hard physics for
example the 5-year
rule um it's still unclear like what the
physical
um uh result there um that motivates
that five-year Rule and a lot of this is
really um the governments want to do
something they're concerned and they're
trying to get ahead of the problem so
one of the the efforts that we took on
at MIT is we've released this open
source orbital capacity tool made that
available to the public and so one of
the concerns that we saw is that there
are various um orbital debris modeling
tools out there they exist but a lot of
them are closed source and they're
difficult to replicate and so the issue
with that is this can lead to a muddle
debate where operators are not sure of
whether or not they are going to lead to
a more sustainable lowth orbit or you
know whether or not they should believe
the results coming out of these closed
Source tools so one of the efforts that
we took on at MIT is to develop an open
source tool where all of the assumptions
in our approach can be uh scrutinized
and basically anyone can see what what
assumptions we're using and our tool um
was a large software project and in
essence has the same capability as some
of these tools that are um owned and
operated by uh Nations so at the oecd
meeting last year uh we we released this
tool this is the oecd space forum and
mocad really has two components and I'll
talk about both of them today one
component is is this link here and if
you want you can um on your laptop or on
your phone actually go and download it
right now and if you go to this link you
can actually run the simulations of of
one of our tools uh so these two links
one is the mocat uh MC tool Theon Carlo
tool the other one is a sour syc
modeling tool so that's one of the
efforts that we're taking on at MIT and
here's some of the results that we get
from some of these tools so for example
on the left is a simulation with no
future launches so what we're seeing in
a simulation is what if we um stop
launching new satellites so our space
economy basically disappears and um the
things that are up there are up there
they're not going to be disposed of uh
what does the environment look like and
even under this scenario and it's it's
hard to see uh the red are debris and
the blue BL and the green are um intact
payloads but if you wait till this uh
movie starts over you can see there's a
lot of green initially and what happens
is we're not launching any additional
satellites so all of those green intact
payloads because of natural um decay of
their orbits are going to deorbit fairly
quickly but what's also going to happen
is that all the debris that's up there
is going to generate all of the
subsequent collisions and it's going to
grow over time so if we stop launching
today we're still going to see a growth
of space debris over time but but an
important part that we're um sort of
trying to highlight with our work is
it's it's really critical to know where
that growth and debris is going to
happen because that's going to affect
the solution that you use to solve this
problem and on the right here what we're
showing is if you take all of these
future plan constellations under FCC
filings of what uh companies and owner
operators intend to do and we model that
forward this is what the space debris
population looks like and see here you
can see that initially um it really
starts with the same simulation as the
left initially there's not that many
Green Dots but dramatically the number
of these Green Dots increases because of
the Space Traffic that I discussed
before and then after this space traffic
gets fairly green soon after we see a
very large growth in orbital debris
because this increased Space Traffic
means that there's going to be more
space activity and more debris
generation events but the the thing I
want to highlight here is two twofold
one these simulations the the pixels
that we're showing for active satellite
and orbital debris they're exaggerated
obviously right so they're exaggerated
so you could see them um so we want a a
disclaimer they're not to scale of what
the sizes of the satellites are the
other thing is it really depends on the
altitude it depends on the location and
what I hope to do with this talk is
really uh tease out all of those nuances
for you okay so let's start from square
one that's the end result that we're
going to get to and then in square one
what are the multiple factors that
constrain orbital capacity why can't we
operate an infinite number of satellites
in LOF orbit what constrains the problem
well here are some of them and I think
this list is pretty exhaustive I might
be missing one or two but I think this
is a pretty good list uh there are about
six factors in in our in our opinion
that constrains this um orbital activity
on the left we have Spectrum there's not
an unlimited um Spectrum for the
satellites to broadcast signals from
space of course there might be some
Technical Solutions that you can use um
to come around that um light pollution
so we've heard if anyone's following um
a lot of this in in the media we've
heard that telescopes are uh becoming
inundated with uh light pollution from
starlink so that's an issue so the more
satellites we launch in lowth orbit and
in particular their reflectivity it
could affect our groundbase
observatories and then Ali mentioned
this um earlier but admissions so for
example if we're mostly making
satellites out of aluminum which is the
case and those satellites are going to
deorbit at a fairly High rate if we're
launching uh 2,000 satellites per year
with a mission life of 5 years you can
do the numbers that's a that's about a
thousand uh the orbits that we're going
to see per year thousand satellites
coming back in the atmosphere that's
going to deposit a lot of aluminum and
on the right they're volume constraints
these satellites can occupy the same
space right so they they have some
volume constraints their operational
constraints as well as the numbers grow
dramatically there are going to be more
collision avoidance Maneuvers and
someone's going to have to play the
traffic cop if the numbers get really
really large this can be become
something that an individual person
can't do so managing the maneuvers of
7,000 satellites which starlink
currently does can't be done manually it
has to be done automatically and we know
that starlink does that automatic
collision avoidance and then finally the
long-term environmental constraints so
these are all the issues and they they
bind over capacity in in different ways
our group we focus on are the issues on
the right there's work being done at MIT
on the issues on the left um Dan
Hastings and his group is working on
admissions uh Carrie Cy and her group
are working on light pollution and um Ed
Crawley and his group are working on
Spectrum so I I feel like confidently
saying that a lot of these topics are
covered at MIT but my group specifically
we just focus on these three so let's
talk about those three topics um and and
I like to think about those three in in
these two ways on the right there's this
term that we've coined recently we call
it intrinsic capacity really what you
want to think about this this term as is
the Space Traffic management issues so
we know that even if we knew perfectly
where all the satellites were we still
have to avoid collisions we need to make
sure that those satellites in their
orbits don't intersect what happens
naturally on orbit is because of the
pertubations some of them atmospheric
pertubations some of them gravitational
perations the orbits are not perfectly
maintained they Decay over time and if
you don't uh perform collision avoidance
Maneuvers that can lead to collisions so
there's this intrinsic capacity issue
that we focus on in our group and if
you've ever heard of the mathematical
problem the sphere packing problem in
mathematics um essentially like how many
spheres can you fit in a volume think
about this as an orbit packing problem
you have these spheres which are the
keep out regions for satellites that are
orbiting under the laws of kar and
Newton and we want to understand how
many of those spheres can we uh safely
operate in lowth orbit but this picture
is very pristine and doesn't include
orbital debris in order for us to
include orbital debris we have to model
all of these probabilistic events of
course operators don't want to generate
debris their goal is not to gener
generate debris but we can't Design
Systems with a zero probability of
failure there's going to be a non-zero
probability that these systems are going
to fail and maybe operate in an
unintended way and those could lead to
debris and in terms of doing this
calculation on the right we have to do
it in the probabilistic fashion which is
um what are the probabilities that we're
going to have uh satellites St failed
and what are the probabilities that
those satellites are going to generate
debris we in some cases you might have
explosions batteries on board explode um
launch Vehicles explode we really don't
design them to do that but they do do
that with some small probability and so
these are really two different ways of
thinking about orbital capacity and the
binding one from our work we've shown
that this really is a binding uh orbital
cap capacity notion this is what's
limiting us this random debris
generation but the one on the left also
limits us as you if you go to and you
look at the FCC filings there are a lot
of really popular orbits so starlink
occupies the 550 kilm orbit and that's
for a reason and the reason for that is
if you go any lower you need a lot of
satellites to ensure that you have the
the right number of satellites overhead
right if you go any higher then you're
well outside of the atmosphere so your
debris uh concerns get and Amplified so
there's this goil log zone of where
satellites want to operate and in that
zone you really care about
this all right so what what how do we
model this probabilistic uh Behavior so
one of the one of these models is called
a sore sync model and it it might be
very familiar to something that you've
already seen so if you've ever seen
results from an epidemiological model
such as the models that we had during
covid that were modeling disease and
infected individuals and these are
populationbased models um if you've ever
seen seen any of the results of these
models U this is essentially what a
sourc model does it tries to model the
various populations on orbit um here's a
very simple model which is two
populations intact objects so you can
think about intact objects as intact
satellites that might be derel or might
be active and then debris and there are
sources and syns for these two
populations the sources for intact
objects are the things that might Decay
from a shell above it or might be
launched into that shell and the sinks
are the natural decay of those intact
objects due to atmospheric perturbations
as they uh re-enter in the atmosphere
and burn up in our upper atmosphere and
then obviously the source for debris are
collisions of intact objects and maybe
collisions of orbital debris within with
themselves um there's also a source from
Decay from above and a snc as the
orbital debris decays From Below in
essence you can model this Behavior with
a very s simple um ordinary differential
equation that looks something like this
of course this differential equation is
going to have multiple species on the
right what I'm showing you is if we
model these sources and syns we can look
for points where the sources and sync
balance the amount of things that
deorbit because of the natural um Decay
effect balances what we're adding up
there from collisions from accidents and
if we look for these natural balancing
points we can find these system
equilibrium and that's what I'm showing
you here on the graph and the notion of
orbital capacity that we uh work on at
MIT is where are the system equilibrium
and how do we utilize them to basically
operate um a in the space environment so
that's a sourc model on the other side
there are these Moni Carlo models what
are Moni Carlo models they essentially
try to model each individual object and
by each individual object I mean the
debris the active satellites the rocket
bodies and they model all of their
properties they model the sizes the mass
the areas of these objects and how these
objects interact when they Collide so
you want to think about these models is
having uh an a particular satellite on a
particular orbit and that satellite is
going to collide with a particular piece
of debris the issue with these kind of
models is That Is Random right so that
process of satellites colliding with
debris um happen with some probability
so in order for us to get a behavior of
the environment we have to run Monte
Carlo simulations and in essence what
that is is we're repeating the
simulation over and over again with
these random uh fluctuations
of for example this time that rocket
body explodes and generates 10,000 of
pieces of debris and in that simulation
it doesn't and as you can see with the
different curves here of these different
man Carlo simulations you see that the
actual trajectory of the growth and
number of objects looks fairly random
but what we want to know is what's the
distribution of that and what are the
mean values and that's what we uh talk
about as the environment's
evolution and you can think about these
models are sitting on two ends of a
spectrum from more complicated models to
more simple models on the left Spectrum
you have Source Inc models which are
simpler and on the right side of the
spectrum we have more complex models um
such as Monte Carlo the things that you
can do with Source sync models are
things like optimization so for example
I can optimize the environment if I put
one of these models inside of an
optimization code I might need to
evaluate that model 10,000 times for me
to find an optimal solution so it needs
to be fast it needs to be able to run
fast and I need to be able to simulate
thousands and thousands of simulations
on the right I have a very high fidelity
model but these models require
supercomputers so in order for us to
simulate the thousands of objects going
to be on orbit today and also simulate
the millions of total objects that we
expect in the next 20 to 30 years we
really do need to run these models on
our supercomputer here at MIT um and
push and push the boundary of the number
of objects that we can include in a
simulation like
this okay so if we look at a source sync
model and we do some calculations that
if anyone's interested in the details of
this calculation I didn't want to bore
folks with too many equations uh just
ask me but I'll I'll I'll tell you at at
a very simple level what the details are
so what I did with this what we did with
this work is we basically looked at a
source sync model and we looked for all
of these equilibrium points so we wanted
to find when is the environment at a
homo homeostasis equilibrium where the
objects that we're launching balance out
these objects that are naturally
decaying and we can keep the environment
at this equilibrium okay so where are
those equilibrium and not only do we do
that but we also optimize for the
equilibria that allow us to operate the
most satellites on orbit so the maximum
number of satellites that we can operate
yet keeping this equilibrium condition
and this is what the curve looks like
and it's is expected we expected this
behavior that we can operate uh the
solution are these black points the
orange points are the FCC filings so our
optim our optimized solution look like
the are these black points and then this
is where the future demand is this is
where people have said I want to go to
that orbit I want to go to that orbit
that's the future demand and we get this
behavior that we expected we can fit a
lot more satellites at lower altitudes
and the reason for that is that the
atmosphere is thicker there and it's
much more forg forgiven uh due to
Collision so if you have a collision
there the resident time that that uh
debris is on orbit is fairly short so at
200 km if there's a collision the debris
is only going to be up there for a few
weeks if we get up to let's say 800 km
and there's a collision it could be up
there for 200 years 150 years so it's
less forgiving so we get this very
characteristic behavior that we can fit
a lot more things in lth orbert and we
can't fit that many in high higher
orbits but if we start looking at where
folks want to go we see that there's
these very popular regions like I said
earlier around the 550 let's say to 700
km region this particular point is where
uh Kyper their constellation is is being
proposed to go and there's also a
Chinese constellation that's going to go
at that altitude and I think one of the
SpaceX um shells will be at this
altitude as well and you can see it's
fairly close to this capacity the other
notion that I want to point out is um
these equilibria and this is something
that came out of our work there are a
lot of these potential equilibria but
some of those equilibria are actually
not preferred because they result in
many many collisions so for example in
some of these ium cases and I'll show
some results later we have uh up to 10
20% of satellites per year suffering a
collision and being defunct per year but
yet the environment is still at an
equilibrium you might ask why how is
that even possible well it's possible
because as long as those collisions are
happening at lower orbits the atmosphere
cleans it up naturally but if those
collisions are happening at anything at
800 to 1,000 kilm we're in big trouble
so you could have a lot a lot of
collisions down here and you're okay but
we have to ask the question is that even
a future we want to live in where lth
orbit becomes this uh aluminum churning
environment of just constant collisions
and so that brings up a a sort of a
policy level question what risk level do
we want to operate in um and anyone that
operates in that environment is going to
inherit that risk but here's a really
interesting property about orbital
capacity that we've also discovered if
we look at the optimal solution so let's
say this is we want to launch at 550
let's say this is the current shell 550
and we look at the optimal solution so
the capacity of 550 is this blue curve
and then we look at the demand and for
example let's say at 550 starlink wants
to launch a th000 more satellites than
the optimal solution can we accommodate
that demand turns out we can and here is
here's an explanation of the physics of
how this works so how do we accommodate
theand that's nonoptimal essentially
what we have to do is in the Shell below
it reduce the capacity so our
accommodated population is this orange
so in order to accommodate a greater
number at this current shell and the
shell below it we have to reduce the
capacity in the Shell above it we have
to reduce the capacity and why is that
the case the reason why that's the case
is because if I operate more satellites
than optimal at this shell that means
I'm going to generate more debris at
that shell that debris is going to go
somewhere it's going to Decay and rain
down in the Shell below it if it rains
down to that shell below it that that
means it's going to be more debris in
that shell so that shell has to reduce
its capacity to accommodate this
additional debris and the fact that I
have more satellites in this shell means
that I can operate less satellites above
it because I have a lower capacity for
debris transitioning from this shell to
below it so basically this notion of
capacity is non-local if I if I um want
to accommodate a certain Behavior at a
certain altitude it's going to affect
nearby
altitudes and then this is the the
notion that I discussed earlier about uh
um about uh the risk level so for
example here what I'm showing is I'm
showing the orbital capacity as a
function of number of satellites and on
the horizontal axis I'm varying my
acceptable risk and what I what I do
with each one of these points is I
calculate the optimal capacity and
really what this shows that capacity is
not a single number it's in reality it's
a risk capacity manifold it depends on
how much risk we're willing to accept
and it turns out that we have quite a
high number number of equilibrial
solution that we can operate in but some
of these equilibrial solution are at
fairly high risk this is 45% failure
rates due to collisions um talking to
owner operators they want to be more
down to the 1% even lower so this is
what we're comfortable with
nowadays um but if we're not careful we
could lead to a future that we're up
here all right so I want to talk a lot
of that work was on Source sync modeling
I want to talk about the work that we've
done on on the Monte Carl side which are
these high fidelity simulat
so for example these are all the mon
Carlo solutions that the major space
agencies and their support um have
developed so NASA has Legend Isa has
Delta Aerospace has Adept the UK space
agency has damage and so the way that
these models are used is the agencies
analyze different policies and they want
to understand what the debris
environment is going to look like in the
future the issue with these models that
they're all closed Source because of
restrictions such as itar and other
restrictions um some of these agencies
don't want to relas release the code and
the assumptions that have gone into this
model so that motivated us at MIT to
develop our own and so this is why we
developed the mocat as our model and
here's where mocat stands so not only do
we have an open source model but we've
been able to push the envelope in terms
of the state-of-the-art so if we look at
the maximum population that can be
handled with this model and the way that
I'm I'm um plotting this is just looking
at the literature so for each point on
this graph there's a reference there's a
paper that's been published so they've
published in the literature of what NASA
Legend and Delta can do they can get up
to the hundreds of thousands of objects
which is actually pretty good but the
issue is if we model the future Space
Traffic we're not going to be in this
regime we're going to be more in this
regime so mocad is really one of the
first models to be able to push into the
tens of millions of objects which is
what we're actually going to see with
the future traffic so none of these
models have been able to run the future
traffic simulation because this of this
limitation and our model was the first
to do that so what are these mon Carlo
models look like so for example these
two points that I'm showing here are two
satellites that might be in the mon
Carlo model they Collide they generate a
debris cloud and then all each of these
points we calculate what's the
probability that these uh pieces of
debris are going to collide and if they
do Collide we have a breakup model that
simulates the collision and the
explosion and then we simulate that
forward so that's essentially what's
going on inside of these mon Carlo
models there's a lot of complicated
things that are going on but the output
of the Mante Carlo model are these
simulations
here's a simulation that's going to take
a little bit of time to explain but
really explains what's going on in the
mon Cara model so what I'm showing you
here is a collision that happened at
this
altitude now this is a very uh typical
plot that we we use in Space Traffic
management and space debris research
which is called the gabber plot and what
I'm plotting is I'm plotting two points
I'm plotting the Pary point and the apog
point so for example here's the Pary
point and then the apog point for that
object would be there and then here is
the parag point for some objects down
here and the apy point would be there
parag point or is the closest point that
that satellite gets to the Earth the AP
points the furthest away if the
satellite is in a circular orbit that
means that the radius of the satellite
is constant per and AP equal so these
are two circular orbits per and AP equal
that collided notice that they generate
debris that are not circular the parag
and apog points are not equal so this
Collision is generating Ecentric objects
it's kicking up objects into higher
altitude which is a problem it's also
kicking objects into lower altitudes
which is okay but the problem is that
these objects are also going into higher
altitudes and if you look at the size
distribution uh 50 cm down to 1 cm these
um smaller objects have high area to
mass ratios so these smaller objects are
actually deorbiting quite quickly but
some of these larger objects can stay up
there uh fairly long in the environment
and that's because their area to mass
ratios are low so you can see that this
is the deorbiting uh sort of behavior
you can see the objects start to deorbit
but there's a lot of objects that are
deorbiting very slowly this is a 30-year
simulation of a collision at 1200 km and
then so if we do the no future launch
case where we don't have any launches
this is what the future environment
looks like so if there's no launches
basically um you see star link down here
a lot of satellites and then after some
while the starlink the orbits but we
don't see this growth of debris down
here really where the debris starts
growing are altitudes above 700 km
because we're outside of the atmosphere
so if you talk about where the
problematic regions are are these higher
altitudes and you can see that even if
we stop launching the amount of debris
at about 800 km is going to grow and
this simulation all other models that I
mentioned earlier can do simulations
like this but the simulations that they
can't do are simulations like this that
we were able to do uh with our approach
so this is the Mega constellation future
what what we're modeling here is the FCC
filings and all of the satellites that
are being proposed to be launched such
as starlink gen one Gen 2 uh spin launch
has a constellation one web Boeing and
they're going at these different
altitudes and they're also staging their
launches they're not just going to all
launch at once they're going to launch
over time so we can model that uh
launching over time and then what we see
in our simulations if we model this
future is that the amount of objects in
our catalog gets into the tens of
millions 20 million objects and this is
one reason why some of the other state
of the the art Solutions can't handle
it's because they really can't get into
the millions of objects but one thing
that we've been concerned about is star
link they're gen one versus gen two Gen
2 has about 30,000 satellites gen one is
about 7,000 so folks have been very
concerned about that we're not seeing
much of a difference in the growth in
the the Bri population between gen one
and gen two and so why is that the case
the reason that's the case is that gen
two is actually uh putting a lot of
satellites at very low altitudes and
there's a reason for this so you know
Gen 2 wants to connect to your smart
phone uh they want to provide uh direct
cell phone connection I think right now
there's some of that in um some of your
smartphones that if you have an
emergency you can connect to a satellite
but in the future the hope is that
satellites could augment our ground
Network where you don't have coverage
and so they want to launch a lot of
satellites at lower altitudes and these
satellites will deorbit actually uh the
debris generated due to these satellites
will deorbit fairly quickly at these
higher altitudes um there's still some
debris that's there you can see this
banding pattern what this banding
pattern is is the space weather 11year
cycle so as we have high space weather
activity more space debris de orbits
when we have low space weather activity
the space debris stays up there longer
so we see this banding pattern and this
is happening at the starlink orbits it's
not fairly dramatic but the dramatic
growth when you see this exponential
growth in in debris is actually
happening at these higher altitudes
these higher altitudes are the problem
areas the numbers might not be as large
but the resident time of debris can be
hundreds of years if not uh greater so
I'm just going back to the simulation
this is the exact same data that I
showed at the beginning that's why the
simulation looks so red but if you zoom
in further and you look at the altitude
banding you could see that a lot of the
debris is actually being generated at
these higher altitudes so it's a much
more nuanced picture than um you know
the simple simulation shows we really do
need to focus at where which altitudes
are the problematic areas I do want to
leave off um with one final topic which
is uh the iceberg in the room which is
the lethal non-trackable population
these are objects that are up there that
are space cataloging um can't track but
they can potentially destroy or kill a
satellite these are objects from um
diameters of 5 cm so think about like a
um a softball to things that are 1 cm so
if that hits a satellite it will
absolutely destroy the satellite but
they are close to untrackable so if we
look at that population what's the
effect of the lethal NRA aable
population so there's two types of
collisions that I'm showing you here one
is non-catastrophic and one is
catastrophic a non-catastrophic
collision it's like you can imagine a
bullet flying through a satellite I shot
a bullet at the satellite it passes
right through it kills a satellite it
destroys their onboard computer but
generates very minimal fragments because
it just passes right through a
catastrophic Collision is a collision
that has enough energy that it disiner
the satellites when they when that
Collision happens the satellite breaks
up into thousands of pieces it turns out
that the lethal non trable population as
we include more and more of them we go
in smaller and smaller sizes will
generate more and more non-catastrophic
collisions but not a lot of catastrophic
collisions until till we get to this
point and we see an e in the curve and
essentially what's happening there is
this lethal nont trable population is
destroying satellites um but not gener
generating a ton of debris but that
deric satellite that's been uh basically
uh made non-operable
is now on orbit and that satellite can
potentially collide with other derik
satellites or active satellites and
generate these catastrophic collisions
so that's the issue with lethal
non-trackable they really change our
postm mission disposal rate and the risk
level that we have on orbit um so I want
to make sure we have enough time for
questions so um just a quick note on
this what we did here is we looked at
smaller and smaller lethal non-trackable
and the effect that we see is that space
weather becomes a more dramatic effect
on the lethal non-trackable population
and I did want to just touch on what
we're doing in terms of policy one of
the pieces of work that we're doing is
on the side of adaptive adaptive
governance so we've been working with
NASA on figuring out how these tools can
be used with policy and one of the
approaches that we're working on is this
idea of adaptive governance where um
instead of having fixed capacity levels
or fixed regulatory uh quotas what we
want to do is be more adaptive to events
and use our models to understand where
can we place new misss and in in in
essence do that as as a response to the
environment as opposed to having fixed
quotas and fixed
rules and so um actually I want to end
by summarizing so I've shown a lot of
work and one of the the threads in our
work is we really want to move from this
qualitative discussion to a quantitative
discussion currently there's no shared
definition of orbital capacity in the
limits and that's going to limit
agreement amongst Nations among amongst
operators permission guidelines which is
kind of what we're using now is
insufficient to ensure Leo
sustainability and the more important
point that we've come across is there
are various modeling approaches that
exist but they're mostly closed source
which makes them difficult to replicate
and can model the debate so in terms of
space sustainability we really think we
got to go to an open- Source uh
transparent uh Paradigm and then finally
these concerns can be weaponized both
from a a a nation state perspective and
also a commercial perspective to uh
produce regulatory Market exclusion we
don't want that so as much as we can we
want to go to a physics based
calculation where these discussions are
not weaponized so with that I think we
have maybe a minute or two for some
[Applause]
questions question
there was an issue earlier I think with
the
mic better hi Martin beum from GSA um I
wonder is in my head I'm thinking that
there's a failure mode that's more
Cascade more
catastrophic than I got the sense from
from what you presented like one you
know one failure hits three others hits
others is there a sense of that sort of
failing there is and they happen at
higher altitudes so that's definitely
there this Kessler effect and I can show
you one graph um without getting super
technical um this graph here so if you
look at this graph here and you look at
this these equilibrium point right
there's an unstable one and a stable one
at this point what happens is the two
equilibrium points converge and they
become complex there's no equilibrium
any point above this point is Kesler
right but the thing is at low altitudes
there's plenty of equilibria so the
number we have to get to at low
altitudes can be in the
millions but it depends on the altitude
if you get high enough you get to a
th000 kilometers that's what we're
seeing that some of those altitudes are
probably above that Tipping Point
because if we stop launching today the
debris is still going to grow so yeah
it's
there another
location okay thank you very much thank
you
[Applause]