All right, let's get started. Welcome
everyone. Uh so excited to kickstart the
semester with the first robotics seminar
of the fall with Professor Trevor Daryl.
Uh I'll be introducing the speaker and
then uh I'll pass on the mic to him. Uh
so Professor Daryl is on the faculty of
the CS and E divisions of the ECS
department at UC Berkeley. He founded
and co-leads the Berkeley uh artificial
intelligence lab or the bear lab, the
Berkeley deep drive or BDD industrial
consortia and the bear comments program.
Daryl's group develops algorithms for
large scale perceptual learning
including object and activity
recognition and detection for a variety
of applications including autonomous
vehicles, media search, and multimodal
interaction with robots and mobile
devices. His areas of interest include
computer vision, machine learning, and
multimodal natural language processing.
And we're so excited to hear from you,
Trevor. Take it away.
>> Cool. I think this will work. Um,
thanks, Sandrea, for the wonderful
introduction. Uh, it's great to be here
and be in this new building, in this new
auditorium. I've uh uh great to see all
the new infrastructure at Berkeley, at
at Berkeley, at MIT. Uh, we have
wonderful new buildings, too. Um uh and
it's this is a fun talk to give. I'm
really excited about everything that's
happening in vision and language and
robotics uh and also to give this uh u
talk at MIT. Um and there's a structure
uh to my talk. I'm going to actually
spend the first part talking a little
bit about philosophy uh and what does it
mean to be vision uh and language and
robotics and which dominates the other.
Uh hopefully I'll provoke some MIT
people in the room. We'll see if that
happens or not. And then maybe most
useful will be some of the new tools and
tricks that I'll talk about that uh
we've been building uh Berkeley that I
think are driving new capabilities for
robotics that are really exciting. Uh
and then last I'll tell you the
direction that my lab is uh betting on
for the future uh which is sort of
trying to uh blend the um paradigm of
largecale uh pre-training with uh
bottomup structure from traditional
computer vision and computer graphics.
Uh sort of a 4D conjecture. But first
let's talk about philosophy and let's
you know really get to the heart of the
triggering you know what what who you
know existential angst of what is
robotics and does like uh uh does vision
a subset of robotics or is robotics a
subset of vision right which uh which is
it which contains the other right um
we've seen so much now uh so many so
many vision people are actually moving
to robotics it's kind of crazy. Uh, and
uh, why is this happening? Why are like
all the computer vision people suddenly
becoming roboticists? Uh, is it because
robotics has all the unsolved problems?
You know, data at scales solve vision,
so let's go see if data at scale solves
robotics. Um, is it because vision
people want scary demos like we want,
you know, humanoids stomping around our
lab, looking anonymous, creating the
fear in our funders just like the
roboticists? Uh, or I I just gave this
talk at RSS as a keynote and I was like,
or you guys still have conferences that
fit in one room and this is amazing. I
this is like ECCV was uh, you know, less
than 10 years ago and I loved it and and
I like the I like the sense of
community. Um
uh it and at that conference there was a
distinct sense of worry. The day before
I gave my keynote, there was a panel on
the future of RSS and one and and uh and
they were conjuring up future visions
and one of the future visions was why
IRA was acquired by CVPR and RSS was
acquired by Nurips, right? Is are vision
and ML going to just dominate robotics
in the future? There's no just like they
maybe did for computer vision uh and
NLP. Um uh or conversely will I argue
that um uh you know vision is just a you
know uh contained within robotics right
robotics is actually the larger problem.
Well, what do you think? This is uh the
beautiful image of a state-of-the-art
humanoid robot humanoid robot, right?
This is currently the future in 2025.
Everyone's diving into humanoid
robotics. Um uh I wonder how many people
actually recognize this image. There's
only one person in the room for sure who
maybe two who actually know where this
image came from. And and so hold your
comment for a second. You know, is this
in fact it looks to me like it just came
out of a Genai midjourney renderer of
what what was the prompt? Humanoid robot
2025.
No, this is actually the cover of a
book. Anybody aside from professors in
the room know what the book was?
By a famous MIT professor, Bertld Horn.
This is in fact the textbook that I
learned computer vision from. so many
decades ago and this was what we called
robot vision clearly for humanoids or in
the direction of humanoids far far away
I don't think anyone this was like
science fiction back then uh and machine
vision then clearly didn't have anything
to do with robotics the way we would
call it robotics today right that this
is the syllabus from I guess 20 2004
this is all just like meat and potatoes
computer vision no humanoid robot out of
control yet. This is called robot
vision. So, so what happened? Uh, you
know, vision was part of robotics way
back in the day, back in the day when I
was originally trained. Um, but it all
changed just around the turn of the
millennium when social media and the
internet redefined it. Uh, and and in
some sense redefined it usefully. uh
without the internet we wouldn't have
had all the progress in machine learning
and computer vision both imageet and
common crawl and the resulting vision
and language models that they uh led to
um but now maybe we're seeing everything
come back together which I think is a
useful thing the unification of vision
and language and robotics and and I'm
pretty happy about that so so I wouldn't
worry too much which one sub you know
contains the other subsumes the other I
think it's all the same thing and the
and the core challenges
of each sub field are still quite
apparent um so that's one first you know
bit of philosophy that that I wanted to
deliver don't worry about which is which
um the second bit of philosophy I wanted
to uh discuss is um actually somewhat
inspired by a lot of the conversations
I've had with Phil Solo over the years
we've each independently and thinking of
these ideas. Um, and it's before we even
get into the nitty-gritty of multimodal
models, let's just imagine
what to actually blind model see. What
is what is a texton model see? Are you
know can blind models just a regular LLM
text LLM that's never seen pixels? Is it
visually grounded?
Well, if you had asked me this like
three years ago, I would have been like,
"Nope." Uh, like I don't I don't know
what you're talking about. Grounded. I
know what grounded meant. Grounded is
like a language person's term to say it
is something connected to a real signal
in the real world like a robot, right?
And these LLMs, they might have been
really cool back in 2022. They were like
amazing at textual trans translation and
reasoning. And like while there were
some vision people who were really anti-
vision especially at Berke anti-
language especially at Berkeley um you
know even they would admit that language
was useful to define tasks like you know
you don't want to refer to category
number 25 you'd rather refer to orange
ball um but they're not grounded in any
real way you know we then would refer to
some Chinese room or stochastic parrot
arguments that I I won't go into in
detail but then surprisingly over Over
the last three years, my view has
changed. And it started and so apologies
for this detour into language for a
while if this is a robotics uh seminar,
but you might find it interesting. It
started off with a bunch of my students
co-advised by uh the colleagues you see
there um who were interested in
multimodality in parsing. and they were
all excited by a recent series of
award-winning papers in EMNLP and ACL
and conferences like that which had
shown that when you're trying to solve
parsing tasks, it turned out that having
pixels as a feature just dramatically
improved the performance over all the
previous methods, the traditional um NLP
methods. And you can see why it's cool
to think that like perception of the
world could help even in a task like
like parsing like do we know whether the
cat is on the table or the cup is on the
table or both. It turns out prior about
the world are useful and you could get
those through pixels. Um and so my
students knew a good thing when they saw
it. They all these other award-winning
papers they got on the hunt for another
award-winning paper and they said what
we can do we can bring more powerful
features. We can bring LLM embeddings.
clearly everything will get better. It
did. They were very happy until they
actually looked closely at the results
and they actually saw that once you
added semantic features like these
features that were coming out of BERT
and then eventually more powerful models
actually just the semantic features
alone the text features alone blew away
the vision features or in fact adding
the vision feature back didn't even help
uh hurt. So that was weird. It kind of
was a real like for a person who's
interested in multimodal models kind of
hurt. I I like I I want my pixels to to
matter. And here they started not to
matter. Oh well, maybe that's just this
one little thing. Except it wasn't. Um
as I'll show you in the next few slides,
the next project that we went down in
this direction um was a little bit of
accidental result. We were trying to
make diffusion models back in the day.
Okay, this was about two or three years
ago. Not not be as as um I should just
say suck as much as they did right back
then. Diffusion models, state-of-the-art
models often really didn't do attribute
binding very well. They would like you
asked for an orange dog, it would throw
some orange object in the scene, but no,
not even a dog. They were very poor on
spatial relations. Um they would have a
hard time with attribute binding and and
gender in this example. they would just
never dress the woman in in blue, always
in red. Um, and so on and so forth. And
so this was a problem. And one of my
students actually in a class project
very quickly found of he's like, "Wait a
minute. I I I see that even LLM can
sometimes talk about the world and know
what's bound with which. What maybe I
could just combine those two things."
And it he turns out like actually just
conjuring
a prompt from an LLM could really help a
diffusion model that was generating
pixels. Now the diffusion model had been
trained on tons of pixels, but the LLM
has never seen a pixel. It's only seen
text
and and it's outputting some structure
which turns out to be very similar to
what I would call a scene graph. Um, and
so this is a first in a series of papers
from 2023. You can see there are called
LLM grounded diffusion where we
basically showed that you could take an
LLM and very lightly prompt it to
generate structures that were scene
graphs and then you could condition
diffusion models on those scene graphs
and get much more high fidelity um,
generations. Now current obviously this
was two years ago. This field's moving
fast. By now these enormous models have
been trained on this and certainly you
don't need this hack to make current
models succeed. Um but we we were
state-of-the-art for a couple weeks or
days or months. Um and uh and now it's
still an interesting point is to look
back and say wait a minute that's
evidence that the texton model kind of
could generate a scene graph which again
three years ago if you'd given me a
checklist or if I was defining the word
grounding in front of a class I'd be
like nope grounding you know texton
models aren't grounded don't know about
scene graphs they don't know that planes
are in the sky they don't know that
boats are in the ocean they don't know
what the texture of the ocean looks like
so on and so forth of course I could get
into details about how you take a scene
graph as conditioning to improve a
diffusion model. There are a lot of
papers on that out there, including the
one that we published. But once you do
that, it it all gets uh better. So
suddenly we would have attribute binding
just by adding this conditioning that
came from a texton model. Um which now I
have to conclude kind of does know about
scene graphs. somehow from all the text
it's read, it understands how to reason
about the world and generate uh
women dressed in blue. Uh and it also
worked for video. Again, this was pre
Neo and pre all the latest ones. So, the
state-of-the-art models were incredibly
bad and ours were just way less bad. But
the art models couldn't even put one
object on top of another or make the
thing fly in the right direction or this
was its Pikachu and you know didn't
really look like a Pikachu. Um and so
our uh just a simple combination of a
model that had never seen a pixel and
models that could generate pixels but
didn't understand uh structure uh seemed
to give a lot of leverage. So now I'm
concluding that these textonly LLMs know
about scene layouts and they know about
motion graphs. And so uh it makes me
really question what does what kind of
visual perception is already in an LLM?
Uh and um and so what you know of course
I can't go too far right like
po human pose and pose tracking that's a
computer visions person computer vision
person problem. you know, we're never
going to have that the the you know, if
you talk to Aliosha at Berkeley, he's
like ah he doesn't know about stepping
upstairs and it doesn't know about one
hand touching the other interacting,
but or does it? And so the very last
paper in this series is uh something we
published uh I think at CDPR this past
summer um but it's been out on archive
for a year uh which um actually asked
that question. Do textonly LLMs know
about human pose interactions in a way
that can usefully improve perception of
human pose over conventional computer
vision baselines. And I wouldn't be
showing this slide if it weren't the
case. And after the fact, it's not
surprising to me at all. Like
traditional computer vision folks and
probably even traditional roboticists
would be like, "How do I estimate human
pose? I well I got to do some sort of uh
structure structure and multiv- view
reconstruction. I probably have human
prior uh shape prior. Um maybe multi
cameras. I'm going to collect a data
set. I'm going to go read Michael
Black's papers. I'm going to He's I'm
going to have people in a dome. Great.
So, let's start putting pairs of people
in a dome. I think there's one of those
at CMU and one of those in Michael's
lab. And great. Let's collect How many
times have I put a a bride and groom in
those? Probably zero or a small number.
So there aren't even data sets to go
learn from traditionally. And so once I
say all that, it doesn't surprise me
anymore to realize actually if you go
read a lot of text, you're going to find
a lot of descriptions about human pose
and how people interact. So maybe these
texton models actually do know a little
bit about interaction of body pose and
certain configur certain actions and
multi-person configurations. And that's
what we showed in this recent um CVPR
paper. Um here we're using an LLM, but
there are ablations with LLMs. Um to see
that just using a a VLM alone can get
you a significant amount of signal. It
can tell you some important constraints
or what to pay attention to. And you can
then add that to a traditional uh uh
pose estimator which will get more
accurate uh multi-party pose and contact
and information like that. So if you're
interested in that the paper was called
pose priors from language models um and
uh it's on archive and uh I believe it's
CVPR.
So that's kind of rounding out the
philosophy part of of today which is
first of all don't worry vision language
and robotics it's all the same. we're
all going to be competing with each
other and um and that's probably a good
thing and it's historically consistent
to return to our roots and and actually
you can poo poo language models and but
we don't even it's very hard to prove
what they can't do and so it I'm more
convinced by experimental evidence than
argument uh about the power of different
kinds of models out there and there's a
lot of signal in some of these text
models
that common sense knowledge and
knowledge about what I would have said
uh is grounding uh than I previously
expected. Maybe I've convinced you as
well. So that's cool. That's philosophy.
Um now I'm going to spend the next maybe
20 minutes uh telling you about just
cool stuff. Cool stuff that's hopefully
useful to roboticists, definitely useful
for our robotics projects. And it's
gonna kind of be on this continuum
of trying to make VLMs uh and VAS either
more robust
um able to work at higher resolution
um uh and then pushing towards some of
the major paradigms of learning and
control either world modeling in the
first in the first instance in
datadriven imagination or um behavior
cloning uh with explicit reconstruction
of 3D structure and um human motion and
that'll be video mimic before I close
with a sort of 4D pre-training uh and
some of our work called Star Trek uh and
Armor. Uh so this will be a little bit
of of a kind of set of spotlights and
whichever one you're interested in feel
free to ask me a question or read the
paper. Um once you start using these
models, I just said the power of these
models is how strong these priors are
because the textonly models seem to
already know a lot. As soon as you do
that, you start noticing and then
worrying about hallucination because
these the text prior are so strong,
they'll just start to make stuff up. Or
it's not even making it up. It's quite
reasonable that there's a refrigerator
in the kitchen, right? There probably
is. It's just not in that image. And
when we're talking about an image
caption, we usually want stuff that's in
the actual there's some pixels to
support that, right? Or at least we
could that could how how we define this
problem. Um and and so you want to try
and find places where the prior is
dominating the the pixels, the
observation. Uh and perhaps you want to
undo that. Uh here I'm intentionally
giving you a very small image. So you're
probably suffering just like a VLM with
a 225x 225 uh you know encoded feature
and the boy is sharing his umbrella with
what? With a dog, right? Isn't that what
always happens? Except if you really
look closely, it's not uh a dog. Um and
it's not uh um uh uh yeah. So um and
these models can you can ask it after
the fact. Sorry I'm missing a slide
here. Um so uh it the first pass through
the VLM would say the boy is sharing his
his umbrella with a dog but it's
actually not a dog. It's a cat. Um and
then if you after the fact say well kind
VLM are you sure? Even just asking the
same VLM are you sure that that's
actually a cat? It'll probably say, "Oh,
wait. Sorry, kind sir. Uh, no. I I was I
was so wrong. I humbly request you let
me correct myself. That's actually
obviously a cat and a Frisbee or
something like that." Um, so the same
model actually can notice that it's
wrong even when it generated something
that's correct. That motivated us to try
and find an inline architecture which
could on the fly as it's generating
tokens generate confidence tokens that
say wait am I sure about what I just
said and when I'm not sure backtrack
until I am sure and and regenerate. So
um we'd like to do that and and it's
inspired by some of the ideas that were
called retrospective uh thinking. Oh,
here's the slide that I was uh um
thinking about. Uh no, so never mind.
So, so we build this architecture called
reverse where we generate tokens. In
this case, perhaps we generate uh an uh
incorrect token. The boy is sharing his
umbrella with a girl. Um, and we would
like the model to then immediately say,
"Wait a minute, that I have low
confidence about that." And I should
backtrack uh and keep backtracking until
I generate a token which appears
confident and I know it's confident
because it generates a token that says
it's confident. So, so this is kind of
magical. I've defined the goal. How do
we actually build that? Well, we
actually turns out once you describe
this idea, you can actually build it in
a straightforward way just by
constructing a training set that has
that property and training a model to do
it. That was sort of surprising to me.
Um so
the key idea is to go out and collect
have data tag the noun phrases in the
data and of course in the ground truth
data we tag the noun phrases with
something that says this is confident
because it is confident.
uh and we go out and construct negative
data where we change the noun phrase to
be something that's not in the image and
we label that as an unconfident or
incorrect uh object. And we can do this
for a variety of different things. You
can change the number of baseball
players in a baseball image. You can
change the style of an object, for
example, in this airplane image. You can
change a fact like the author in the in
the of the book. Uh, and so now I have a
data set where when things are wrong,
the model says it's wrong. And when
things are right, the model says it's
right. And I can then fine-tune a model
with this structure. And lo and behold,
the model will generalize. And now when
it's not quite sure, it'll actually tell
us it's unconfident about this. And then
we can train we can then at inference
time as something is generated we can
monitor the likelihood that the next
token that's going to be produced is
that unconfident token.
And whenever it suddenly pops up to be
high, we can say let's skip that and try
again and generate a different token.
And suddenly it generates a token that
then the next token is not going to be
the unconfident token. It's going to be
the confident token and keep going. And
you can either use rejection sampling or
query writing. Um, and it works in a lot
of good uh useful cases where otherwise
models would have hallucinated. Um, and
you can trade off the expressivity
versus groundedness. Um, and we also
have some extensions of this to u
robotics. And um when you um ask for
something that's not there, the model
should um be aware that the object's not
there and u backtrack to something else.
I'm going to skip over that in the
interest of time.
Um so if you're interested in that in
more detail, uh check out uh this uh
paper. The algorithm is called reverse
and the title is generate but verify
reducing visual hallucination in vision
language models with retrospective
resampling. Uh and I think the robotics
extension is going to be on archive soon
if it's not already. So that's one cool
thing like I think reducing
hallucinations gets us um a significant
way towards acceptance of these classes
of of VLMs in um real hard problems like
in real robotics problems. Uh another
thing we probably need to do is not be
limited to relatively narrow views of
the world. I think like my earliest work
in robotics was building depth cameras
for uh robotic sensors, robotic systems.
Um, and we knew you need to have lots of
pixels to get accurate information. And
if you're looking out at the world, we'd
like to not just be limited to 224 x
224. Let's we should probably be able to
take 4K by 4K or 8K by 8K. Uh, this is
work led by my student by Fangg Xi as
part of a collaboration with Nvidia. Um,
and I don't probably have to uh convince
you that it's going to be hard to brute
force scale your way to this. Like, even
if you believe in data space scale,
let's eventually these exponential
things catch up with you. If my if I'm
trying to scale to 4K by 4K and I want
to ask questions about little details in
the scene, like what's the name of that
sailboat? First of all, you're not going
to be able to answer the question that
low res. And if you try and just brute
force run it at high- res or you've got
some robotic scene and you want to, you
know, count how many um protrusions
there are from an object that you need
to manipulate. Um well, clearly we're
not going to do this with brute force.
And clearly anyone who's been around
vision for more than a few decades
knows, well, come on, think about how
every other vision biological vision
system solves this problem or how we've
been thinking about it for decades in
computer vision. We should be attending
to the things that matter, looking at
them at higher resolution and processing
them. Except that's hard to integrate
with our that it just sounds like I
bought a whole bag of inductive bias
that nobody wanted to have. And so that
that hasn't been fashionable lately. And
we already know what attention means.
Attention is the cross attention of a
transformer that's fully connected to
everything, right? Um but here I want to
have a different kind of attention. I I
want to attend to attention. So I want
to actually have computer vision or
human uh psychopysics style perception
and say let's figure out where I should
look so that I can actually have higher
resolution. Um and yet do this all in a
data driven end toend way based on
transformers. Um so there's a lot of
data. I won't go into this in the
interest of time in this talk, but it's
not hard to go out and construct very
overly annotated uh images at high
resolution with detailed descriptions
all over the place. Uh and once you have
that to train a model that basically can
have multi-resolution tokens. So, I can
have low resolution tokens that are
essentially 224 x24, but I can also chip
up my image and send the the um 4K 4K
image into almost the same uh encoder
and get high resolution tokens
corresponding to sub regions. Uh, and
now the game is which of those should I
decode? I can't put them all into I
can't train with all of them. That gets
that explosion of complexity.
Uh, uh I want to discover which are the
ones that are salient
either for this image or for the task
the prompt and selectively decode those
and put them into uh uh into an
inference paths. Uh and so this is the
figure that I like the most that
summarizes this VA HD model um with the
sort of PS3 architecture which takes an
image at low resolution. Those are the
tokens uh on the left, the kind of cyan
green tokens and some text question or
query. And then it decides based on all
of that where to look and it generates a
token that then goes out and causes
other tokens to be put into the decoding
stream. These highresolution orange
tokens, right? So we now have an
integrated architecture that's endtoend
trainable that um you generates a token.
It's actually similar to the previous
idea. This we have a a retrospect token
that or a confident unconfident token
that decides whether or not to
backtrack. Here I'm generating a token
that decides what other tokens to to
insert into this stream. It's kind of
like a rag architecture um but it's in a
course defi you know multi-resolution
perception uh architecture and this
scales uh elegantly and has the desired
properties that you would like. I'll
refer you to the paper to look in detail
at these uh results. Um and I'll just
show you this video which I think is one
of the Nvidia is interested in
autonomous driving. And you know you
might want to ask questions about the
driving environment. So you're you're
racing down the road. You want to ask a
question about the exit upcoming. You
need to read what's on the sign. And you
know if you use a baseline system the
baseline system either is operating at
too low resolution and can't see you
know can't figure out the answer to the
question until it's too late or it's
running too slow and it can figure it
out but also too late. Only with this
kind of architecture can you operate at
a super high resolution and do so uh
efficiently.
So that's cool. I think we have two
ideas now that really push forward VLMs
for the for real world tasks like
robotics task reducing hallucinations
running at high resolution. Um now let's
move on to sort of what are the dominant
paradigms of vision for robotics and
I'll show you actually three different
ideas. Uh the first being world models,
the second being kind of explicit like
behavior cloning in detail. uh and then
this 40 pre-training future. Um so this
is a CVPR paper uh I think won a best
runner up for some for best uh student
paper or something I can't remember just
a spotlight I apologize if I overclaimed
there um navigation world models led by
Amir Bar and uh collaboration with Meta
and Yan Lun and others
um and I think this is like you know
this world model story is somewhat
controversial um but I also think it's
interesting and it scales it's a real
scaling hypothe hypothesis it's saying
we're building these models diffusion
models that can predict images and they
can predict images conditioned on
previous images in time and now that I
can do that how far can I push this if I
train it on just images of this in video
of this room can I then predict what an
arbitrary viewpoint of this room looks
like without doing slam without doing
any explicit 3D reconstruction no nerfs
um but just like train a model to
predict the next view conditioned on an
action. Um, and increasingly we're we're
seeing that we can do that. And further,
if I can condition on an action, I can
now, you know, do MPC or the equivalent,
roll out multiple futures, decide which
future looks like the one that I want,
and take that action and then keep
going. Um, and uh, don't worry, I'm not
going to say this is solved or the only
way to do robotics, but I do think it's
exciting to see the the progress that's
being made. And um, I think eventually
these models will converge with some of
the other ideas, but here's where the
state-of-the-art is. Um, obviously this
world, this condition video model as
world model idea has been out there for
quite a while. Um and uh the sort of
dreamer architecture popularized it uh
recently. Um and we train a model to
predict predict the next frame of a
video conditioned on an action uh
navigation action and a time point uh
and train that just from from data uh of
either closed worlds or open worlds. So
we then give it a start image and a goal
image and we see can the model
hallucinate into the world and decide
what actions to take to get to uh a goal
image. And if it's a relatively simple
environment like a fixed room, it's
actually it works pretty well. uh and
it's a you know probably you could solve
this with slam but it's interesting you
can solve this purely with a datadriven
uh architecture uh as well. What makes
it feasible right now because otherwise
it would have been just like incredibly
computationally prohibitive
uh is to not to train a diffusion
transform a typical diffusion
transformer on video where we're like
sampling a new uh denoising a new image
sample based on the previous um frames.
But to do it in an architecture that's
only conditioned on the past um only
fully conditioned on the current frame
uh and linearly conditioned on all the
previous frames. So that's uh that's
important. There's a lot of data we can
train from. Here's the illustration of
this diffusion process where each frame
is denoised. That would have been the
the prior baseline method. In our new uh
attent uh attention in our CDT the
architecture is only fully is only
quadratic on the current image and it's
linear in the number of frames for the
previous image and that you know makes
it scale much more favorably than the
than the prior diffusion transformer for
this kind of thing.
Um, so this model can follow
trajectories in known environments.
That's pretty cool.
Uh, I mean some of the visualization,
it's not photorealistic perfect. Uh, and
I don't think we have any, we're not
reporting evidence yet that you can do
very precise manipulation or anything
like that. But it's interesting to see
how well it works and how that it also
works in unknown environments, right?
like you actually can totally
hallucinate what it would look like if I
move to the right here. And who knows if
that's a what it should look like
because this is all imagined, but it
gives you something
uh kind of crazy. So this is sort of at
the boundary of real robotics and
hallucination. Um you can use it for
planning and navigation as I said with
MPC and rollouts and those results are
are in the paper. Um, and I think I this
is probably obvious. You can use MPC and
uh or architectures like this Nomad
architecture from 2024 and just use the
hallucinated rollouts. Now, this is all
in known worlds and pick the one that
looks closest to the goal and get
state-of-the-art performance on uh c
current challenges.
Okay, so the takeaway from from this are
generative world models, conditional
diffusion transformers, computationally
efficient. So you can train this and
scale this uh and um this without having
explicit structure learning to act in
the world.
So the last of these sort of um nuggets
is
if you were if you don't like world
models, you probably like this. So, I'm
going to give you both bets, whoever,
you know, uh, we're we're doing all the
work at Berkeley right now. Um, this is
much more a computer vision person's
robotics, humanoid robotics talk. This
is like I'm going to watch humans move
in the world. I'm going to watch and
recover the structure of the world and
I'm going to learn how to act in the
world just purely through passive
observation
um by constructing that world and a
simulated environment with reward and
training robotic humanoid policy from
watching how people act, right? Uh
obviously a vision person argues that
it's easier to do data collection by
watching the world than explicitly going
out and trying to collect data. And um
and also you can collect data naturally
uh through um you know by just watching.
And so here is a kind of result we have
by watching Berkeley students wander
through the environment. We and maybe
they're a little bit drunk. I don't
know. We get we get hum we get robots
that also mimic them and walk through
the environment. uh and we call this
particular algorithm or the we call the
um capability that this particular
algorithm
uh provides contextual control because
as you'll see as I go through the
following slides, we're training a model
conditioned on the specific environment.
So it's going to be conditioned on the
3D structure of those stairs. It's going
to have observed human beings walking
around. And so it's kind of the opposite
of what many people in humanoid robotics
are doing right now, which is to try and
construct a single policy that can work
anywhere. Actually, in the the results
in this paper that's just been released,
I think it'll be presented at Coral uh
next month. We're training a policy just
for this specific environment. Condition
on observations for that environment. As
the robot walks around, it's going to do
whatever people did in that spot. So, I
think in a moment this robot's going to
go back and sit on that bench because
that's what if a person was at the
bench, it would sit down. And this was
all learned just by watching people
moving in this environment.
Uh there's no control. Well, there's the
right now the person's just saying what
joystick controlling what direction to
go and whatever direction it goes, it
does the action that's natural for that
location in the environment.
Uh,
and so how do we do this? We do this by
tracking uh all the things that we can
track. We can watch people move in the
environment, multiple people as well,
watch how they interact with each other.
uh we can reconstruct the environment uh
and then we in the environment train a
simulated uh uh robot to act in the
appropriate way at that spot being as
consistent with the observed human
behavior as possible. We call this video
mimic. This is sort of a highle snapshot
of the whole thing. It's driven purely
by moninocular video input. We have um
from Anju Kanazawa's lab uh 3D
reconstructions of human bodies over
time. This is a collaboration with
Anju's lab, Peter Beiel's lab, my lab
and Jendra's lab. A lot of students
getting together to bring this to
reality. Very exciting work. And we of
course track the pose. We recover the 3D
reconstruction of the environment. We
align those two. uh we retarget the
human motion onto a robotic uh form
factor um and then uh can render what
the robot looks like if it was mimicking
the human behavior and then we can train
a policy to match that model given the
act given the simulated uh observations
that the real robot will see uh at
inference time. So this video kind of
gives you the sort of sums up everything
that's happening in one shot,
reconstructing the reconstructing the
world, reconstructing the motion of a
person retargeted to the humanoid robot
form, and then simulating what the
sensors on the humanoid robot can see.
And now we're going to train a policy
based on those sensors to cause the
robot to behave as close as the person
did in the real world. Uh and we have um
uh the variety of um uh uh policy
learning strategies here um um you know
pre-training with just the mocap and
then doing geometry aware tracking and
distilling with the root motion and
finally fine-tuning with RL on all of
those observations. Uh and so here's
again some results of walking around
indoors in the uh bear lab building up
and down the stairs and up and down the
stairs of the Bankro Library uh at
Berkeley. Um you know I think you look
at results like this and it looks
amazing and cool how much we have also
still how much there is left to be done.
Uh, and also as I said, these results
are for a specific environment. And
obviously, we're going to have to figure
out how to train a policy that
automatically generalizes to any
environment as a either a mixture of
these policies or by distilling them
into a super policy. And for that, I
would say just stay tuned for the
future. Uh, Arthur, Hongac, David, and
and Junhi were the lead um uh uh
students on this project. amazing work.
Okay, so in the last 10 or so minutes,
um
let me push a little bit farther. I
think the two things that I just the two
kind of paradigms I just uh showed you
our latest results on the kind of model
based world model based approach
uh and the sort of full 3D
reconstruction behavior cloning
approach. They're both they're like
extremes. It's cool that we have
state-of-the-art results in both, but
they also kind of feel a little bit
limiting to me. They're they're they're
either too general in one sense or too
constrained in another. And so I'd like
to propose something that's a little bit
in the middle. And I'm going to call it
the 4D pre-training uh hypothesis or
conjecture or bet. Um, and first I'm
going to do a little bit of history
again back into the past and we see the
the progression of uh training of
robotic visual learning models. Actually
this early work that uh Peter uh and I
with Chelsea and uh Sergey uh pioneered
back in 2015 one of the first like deep
networks that was end to end trainable.
And actually one of the small facts that
I think led to this model success that
might be overlooked by some is it
actually wasn't the the reason this
model I think worked was it was actually
estimating trajectories in a sense I'll
get back we didn't call them
trajectories back then but there was an
argmax function in that model that made
it trainable with small amounts of data
otherwise if you look back like how
could you have trained a model there
with the with the posity of data that
you had turns out that the architecture
there found the peaks of distributions
and and really returned them over time
and that that'll turn out to be relevant
I think as I look to the future. Then
people removed that from the
architecture and tried to train more
general approaches for pre-training with
some success um including mass
autoenccoder style models which echo our
also our previous work uh that Deepo Pak
led on uh context encoders um and these
started to be used for general
pre-training representations
um and of course now using transformer
uh representations both for encoders and
for LLMs.
and we kind of arrive at the
state-of-the-art. And in terms of pixel
processing,
the the brute force approaches on pixels
still seem to have a tough time scaling
as efficiently as text scales. I haven't
seen that emergent video model. I mean,
maybe the latest kind of Neo and Genie
and VO and all those models. I guess the
jury is still out on some of those, but
um for most of the models out there and
certainly all the open models, we we
haven't seen pre-training just on pixel
features be easy, you know, except maybe
at, you know, the most
um biggest corporate scales. We'll see.
We'll see. And the jury is still out on
that. And that's because I think all of
the work we've been doing has been just
too focused on texture.
envision. Uh, and I'll hearken back to
the past, the tradition of computer
vision, and say these pixel features,
either 2D or 3D, ignore the most
important problem in computer vision.
Actually, they ignore the three most
important problems in computer vision,
which again, I wonder if any of the
old-timers in the room know what I'm
referring to. Actually, was a CMU phrase
from our friend Teo Kennady, who would
say, "What's the most important problem
in computer vision?" Well, the most
important problem is correspondence.
Does anybody know what the second most
important problem is?
>> That's right. And the third is also like
real estate. So, um, again, this was a
phrase I heard when I was a grad student
or uh, and I'm going to say they're I
think arguably also the three most
important ones in robotics. Uh, and we
sort of have been missing that except to
the extent that we're pre-training on
trajectories or building models that
pre-train trajectories.
And um and so that's what I'm sort of
excited about right now is to find ways
to use this datadriven pre-training
model uh because I like models that
don't have too much inductive bias that
are task independent um and don't have
too many quirky parts and interfaces and
can be somewhat endto-end trained. But I
don't want to be beholden just to a
pixel. I want to try and have
trajectories. Uh obviously if we can go
all the way to objects I'd be happy too.
Maybe eventually we get there. We've you
sort of tried that. And
so right now I like this idea of a
particle based trajectory. So we want to
find um models that can pay attention to
how things are moving over time and
learn from that. Because if you have
these particlebased representations,
if you can figure if you can somehow get
them from the video, you're very very
close to state in many robotic tasks.
Like if I need to figure out how to move
this uh
AV clicker and put it over here into
this holder, I mean, that's a pretty
hard task if I'm just doing from pixels
and texture. But if I tell you the you
know front and end key point of this and
I tell you the two key points here kind
of almost any learning algorithm can get
me from here to there u by servoing or
search or something. Um and it does seem
we're getting very close in computer
vision to having a kind of bottomup just
getting that from the pixels. These are
like results from just moninocular video
which can do 3D optic flow or 3D optic
flow plus correspondence over a long
range correspondence that we call 4D
vision. This is one paper that u uh
Shenan Wang uh and and Anju's group uh
pioneered. There are a bunch of other
similar techniques at the bottom. And
I'll briefly mention one of the latest
versions that some of my students also
helped Anju's group with called Star
Trek. I think that is just the code has
just been released quite recently. Uh
lots of great collaborators on this
paper. Um and and basically we're
solving the full monocular 3D
reconstruction correspondence track
everything over time uh largely in a
feed forward process uh with suitable
training data and okay cool. Sometimes
PowerPoint blows up here because these
videos are so large but it seemed to
blow up and then catch its breath and
come back to life. So that was nice. Um
uh so you can see the scenes being
aligned and reconstructed uh and we both
get reconstruction over time but also an
implicit representation. So every point
is aligned back to the 3D coordinate
system implied by the first frame and
every point it then has correspondence
throughout the whole video. So you know
where every point is in 3D
and it and its identity. Uh and that's
uh cool. So,
was cool until PowerPoint died. So,
let's try if I can get it back.
Good. Got through it there. Um, so this
Star Trek u algorithm is sort of in a
series that originates from Duster and
Monster. Many of you will be familiar
with those terms, but basically it's
this new class of methods that's doing
feed forward reconstruction from
multiple views um and um kind of working
very well. So I think this class of
architecture can drive particle based
representations that I'm going to argue
are the cool way to do pre-training. And
maybe I'll mostly talk about the second
paper here called armor. And so we want
to basically take these representations
that I call 4D representations
uh which are 3D plus time
uh and just pre-train on those the same
way we were pre-training on pixels. Uh
we're going to essentially do MAE style
uh reconstructions and predict the
future. And and that's this paper we
presented at ICML this year called Armor
pre-training autogressive robotic models
with 40 representations. And the basic
punch line here, I think I think we've
we've solved a few things. We've
certainly not solved most of the
problems in the space. I think this is
just the first kind of um assault on the
beach head, if you will, of this in this
direction, and more will be coming soon.
Um but the basic idea of this result is
you've all probably seen people
pre-train on EGO 4D and use those
representations to drive um large
robotic models or VALAs. Uh we've done
that in the past, too. Here we basically
did the same thing, but instead of doing
it on the pixels from Ego 4D, we trained
it on the 4D representations from Ego
4D. And so naturally now, not only do I
see the texture of the hand, but I
actually have the 3D and 4D structure of
the hand as it moves through the world.
And predicting those trajectories, I
argue, is really close to the task. for
example, if you're trying to have an
endeeace mimic the human action in a
kitchen. And those are the early results
that we have that just training on ego
40 alone without substantial in-domain
robotic data. If you use these 40
representations, you get a pretty nice
result. As you can see in our paper, if
you if you uh look at the results in
detail there, I only have one or two
minutes left, so I'm not going to go
through all of this. I'll just spotlight
the overall architecture which is a uh
you know transformerbased
auto reggressive decoder that's trying
to predict the next trajectory element
in this 4D sequence given the image
input and other things like text prompts
and and whatnot and this is a LLM
languagebased model I think you could
sorry this is not an LLM uh
extend this also to such models and
that's one of the things that we're
working on in the future Um and the
results uh comparing um to baseline
methods including MVP and Octo and
OpenVLA are in our uh ICML paper. Uh
with that, I'm gonna wind down with uh
like 90 seconds left and just say I hope
I've given you this argument about the
4D future uh and sort of a middle ground
between extreme reconstruction and
behavior cloning that I showed you in
video mimic or pure datadriven world
models. Um these VALAs really are
useful. You can make them run at high
resolution and deh hallucinate them if
you're worried about those two things.
And as we come to this unified
perspective that we're all doing the
same thing in AI, whether it's vision or
language or robotics and haptics should
definitely play a role. I didn't get a
chance to mention any of that, but it's
uh you know, a lot of TED's pioneering
work I think is going to be very
relevant there. That's another modality
that is in the mix. Um you know, we need
to always remember that the the
knowledge and the data can come from
anywhere. And right now, since there's
so much text, even these blind models
know a lot. And I wonder how much in the
text already knows what a gel site will
sense. And I'll ask that over coffee
with Ted later on and see if he has an
opinion. Uh with that, I think I will
close. Uh and thank you for your time.
Thank you, Trevor. Do we have any
questions from the audience?
Oh yeah, thank you so much for the talk.
I just had a question about the deh
hallucination thing. So you mentioned
that there would be confidence tokens
that are generated. So is it more likely
for them to generate more confident
tokens or is it like uh it's very
equally likely that it generates like a
low confidence token versus a high
confidence token. So is there anything
in on that front because if it's trying
to if it just generates unconfident
tokens then that's kind of
>> well it generates a token uh based on
the general the model the prior implicit
in the model and then it generates a
token that essentially is the check
pass. It's like
>> right
>> it's another token that gets to you know
it's like in that example where you let
the whole you generate the whole string
and you say wait a minute was there
actually a dog and the model can somehow
figure out on a second pass that there
wasn't a dog the generation of this
extra token allows the model to have a
second look at what it just did and
apparently that gives it more signal and
the confidence of that token or the
likelihood of that token being generated
as CN versus un um is powerful enough to
let you decide to backtrack and try
again until you get something that the
model both generates and confirms
>> as in a token sequence. Did I ask could
I ask? Okay. So I meant so there's no
current uh at least in that
implementation where the confident
tokens like let's say there's a token
which is actually very it should be very
confident in or it's actually more
accurate. So there's no way that it
would actually uh generate that as
opposed to something which it is
actually uh low confidence.
>> Well I mean it will eventually get there
because it will reject uh until it gets
there. Yeah. Yeah, I think the whole
point of this is we haven't figured that
out yet. I mean, of course, I think
future work could be, well, why don't I
take all this data to retrain the model?
Maybe it'll get better.
>> Yeah, sure.
>> It's probably the next paper in the
series.
>> Okay. Uh hopefully I'll see it. Thank
you so much.
>> Or you can do it.
>> Okay. Thank you so much. Uh maybe I'll
take one more question.
Hey, thanks for the great talk. Um, my
question was uh from the very last
slide. I was hoping that the middle
ground between the completely datadriven
world models versus um database world
models would be something like where we
use uh slam plus diffusion models in
conjunction to together because um for
example in a start track the example
that you showed where the train moves
away there is a hole in the map there
and which could be filled with diffusion
model which you have already proven at
the beginning of the slides that if you
provide structure to any generative
model it produces very good results.
So what are your thoughts on that? Yeah,
I think that's if I'm mapping your
question correctly onto the following
question of I mean diffusion models at
scale, especially the very powerful ones
that are coming out may be implicitly
reconstructing 4D representations
internally. Um there might be an
alternate pathway to this pre-trained
future. Um and so I think we have a few
projects on trying to introspect or
distill internal structures out of
diffusion models and they that might
also be a way to get to this kind of
representation of the story but we don't
have any results on that yet. So I think
it's still TBD and be interested to hear
of other people who are trying similar
things.
>> Great. Thank you.
>> Okay. Uh that's all the time we have for
questions. So, let's thank the speaker
again.