Today we're going to talk about
peerguided learning at scale. Um the
thing I asked you to do for today was to
write a little bit in your learning
journal about um one of your hobbies
that you use online resources to learn
from. Um, so just get in groups of
three, um, and spend the first few
minutes talking to each other about what
kinds of, uh, hobbies you have and what
kind of online learning you do in those
hobbies. Does that make sense? Ready?
Go.
All right, come on back. Great
condition. So, first of all, Omar should
show us his camera. Do you want to talk
about um, so I I I talked about
photography? Like I spend an unhealthy
amount of time on YouTube like with
photography tutorials. And so this
camera is a 50-y old camera and I had no
idea um how to even begin looking for
one. And like these last three weeks
I've been looking because I want to run
a CPW event um for uh admits on how to
use an SLR camera. Isn't that cool? So I
don't know like this is in really great
condition and I was like on eBay for
hours but I you know watched YouTube
tutorials was reading on like Reddit
forums, photography forums, DP review,
pedopixel like on what to look out for
and before that like learning how to
actually take photos. Um was all done
through YouTube. It was selftaught. I
started off with a phone and then I
slowly built up um my toolbox once I had
the knowledge and yeah now I'm like the
photo editor for the tech. I stuff for
yearbook and now I do a lot of stuff for
photography and now I'm actually
teaching others. Um I recently actually
just interviewed up here this I
interviewed for to teach a digital
photography course although due to time
conflicts I won't be able to do that. Um
but I did interview and I um was about
to go on the other side of that um
learning experience.
Camera's rad. I just got it um before my
last class. So like I need to go to a
camera shop just to make sure it works.
um which I'll be doing after this class.
A photo of that. I want a photo a photo
of Omar with his new camera taken with a
contemporary.
Yeah. I I I mean those Polaroid cameras
became much more widely accessible
probably when I was in grade school.
Like they were pretty common and then
and then there was sort of a revival in
the last few years. So like my daughter
has a Polaroid camera. I don't think
it's called. We call them Polaroid
cameras because they probably have some
different term now of instant camera or
something like that. Um, anybody have a
completely different hobby from Omar
where you could tell a very similar kind
of story about learning
or I guess like you know similar sort of
story of learning is like you know
through YouTube right like I want to or
I'm like starting to learn how to like
play guitar and bass and stuff. Um, but
the thing with YouTube is it's like we
talk about like algorithm guided
learning or whatever, but like it kind
of almost feels like YouTube's sort of
an algorithm kind of guided learning in
a way or like I feel like the YouTube
algorithm really sort of drives my
interests or like diverts my interests
into different things at different
periods of time. Like on a weekby- week
beek basis, I can be interested in
something completely different than what
I was interested in last week. So, it
feels like I like I'm just sort of
moving through a bunch of like different
hobbies and because I feel like I'm at
the whim of the YouTube algorithm
sometimes. Oh, yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
People Yeah. Yeah. No, I think people
feel that way with lots of uh kind of
technologies that do some kind of
aggregation. Pinterest for people who do
crafty kinds of things. Tik Tok for
people who follow media and stuff like
that. Yeah. Good. What other what other
hobbies do you talk about or what other
sort of learn like informal learning
strategies seem important and
interesting or things that you were
talking about in your groups?
Yeah. Awesome. I'll say like on a less I
guess handson like level. Um, I like use
like similar resources like YouTube and
stuff like that for like a lot of like
collecting knowledge for like things
that I'm interested in like fashion for
example because a lot of a lot of it is
like you know like like in New York
fashion week for example it's like these
very condensed times right where like
it's all happening and a lot of people
follow very closely but if you're an MIT
student you're probably like I can't
feeling
But like then you can like watch
highlights from it and like actual like
critics commentary on them and like kind
of see like what that's doing both
socially and also like from an artistic
sense. Yeah. Do you use Pinterest or
anything for sort of collecting your um
I'm I've I had a social media
problem YouTube so now I've kind of just
continued into YouTube and stuff but I I
do get to I guess reflect on it because
I'm doing costume designs and stuff. Oh,
cool. Yeah. My my my daughter is big
into aesthetics of various kinds, craft
things or design things. And Pinterest
is like a big part of how she like she
does the same kind of combing that you
does, but she's deliberate about taking
things that she likes and storing them
and categorizing them and trying to make
sense of them and things like
that. Yeah. Dana. And then I was just
going to say like just like another
medium outside of like watching videos
is just like online like so mine is like
cooking. So like recipes and just like
articles. Um, and then also like mine
was like a little bit of TikTok just in
like the one minute video of like you
can cook this and it like isn't a
professional chef showing you how to do
it was cool to see that like oh like I
can relate to that person so I can do
it. Um, what what what are your favorite
sort of recipe media or cooking media?
Like how do you So I've only perfected
one singular dish. Um, and it's
scallops. Um, which is like a relatively
hard thing, but like I'm scared to cook
a chicken because I'm gonna give myself
salmonilla a scallop.
Yeah. So, my family joke is you only
going to eat scallops for this. You're
like, "Yeah, they're pretty good.
They're healthy. Might be too many heavy
metals if you do that your whole life or
something like that." But yeah. Yeah. I
don't know if bottom feeders are what
you should do for your whole life, but
that seems like seems like a good start.
How about you, Armon? Uh I do mention
this in our group but what came out from
people talking like a lot of people
relate is number file uh stream blue one
brown this video I just put them in what
is this it's a maths video they just
tell you cool math stuff
it's called number file number file
street blue on brown those kind of
videos so sometimes you learn that there
is fractional dimension and you just be
watching what that means And I watch
those, too. So, they're really
interested. Um, yeah. Who's who's the
guy who came here a couple years ago for
a graduation or convocation or
something? Mark. Hm. Mark Robber. Mark
Robber. Yep. Yeah. Yeah. He's sort of
science YouTuber. Guy named Veritasium
does uh does things like that too. Yeah.
Yeah. Enormously uh popular and
successful and things like that. Um I
play a lot of computer games and I my
life sort of overlaps. I don't know.
computer games are like a couple of
years older than me, but not by much. I
mean, definitely some of my earliest
memories are um games that would have
been played off of like a cassette reel
rather than any kind of rotary disc or
or something like that. Um but another
distinctive memory is that uh one of the
first categories of games were these
textbased games where you had to sort of
enter prompts into a parser like open
mailbox, go left, go right, walk in, you
know, pick up key, put key and lock,
those kinds of things. So, a lot of what
you're doing Yeah. Come on in. um was
kind of guessing like uh you know what
what was the what was the right key term
to put in to um to engage things and so
actually a lot of these games Infocom
was a company that sold a lot of them.
Um the game companies would also publish
a book and the book would have uh the
answers to a whole bunch of things or
like solution sets in invisible ink and
so you had like a little uh um pen that
came with it. And so when you decided
that you had given up trying for
yourself, you would uh you would cover
the invisible ink with this pen that
would reveal the sort of next clue and
help you go on and so forth. Um and uh
but now you know essentially every video
game it like they almost instantly are
created with a wiki that has you know
every item in the game and what they do
and where they go. Um a Reddit forum for
conversation. um more recently Discord
um pages, you know, that actually, you
know, for smaller games can be kind of
surprisingly intimate where you, you
know, you really do feel like you're
just like chatting with the guy who made
the game. Um even if you know, there may
not be responding to you directly, but
they're certainly like responding to
people that are there around with you
and things like that, YouTube channels
or all these kinds of things. Um yeah, I
think there I think there's all kinds of
ways. There ve there are very few
people I think left in theorked world
who don't have some kind of encounter
with this sort of informal learning. Um
I I I think you know just an enormous
number of people in a very short period
of time. I mean obviously there have
always been people who do DIY kinds of
things and stuff like that but the
degree to which online resources has
shaped those learning interactions um is
a profound change over the last uh
decade or two. The uh um and I think it
I think it reminds us to do a few things
that are useful. One is to um is to
conceptualize learning really broadly.
Um, you know, a lot of times that we
think of learning, we sort of we pin it
down in education, K12 education,
college, things like that, but that's
that's a relatively small part of
people's lives. Um, people are learning
all throughout their lives all the time.
Um, people are developing new skills for
work. They're developing new skills
around their interests. They're they're
they're pursuing passions. They're doing
whatever else. And so think I think it's
very helpful when thinking about online
learning to be really open um to all
these kinds of things. And then you know
I I would say if there's a core argument
in peerg guided learning at scale it's
that these technologies have been so
profound in changing the ways that we
pursue learning outside of school and
schools have proven to be institutions
that are just remarkably resistant um to
these forms of learning as well. Well,
my hunch is most of you don't have an
experience where you feel like, yeah,
the kind of learning that I did in my
eighth grade physics class was really
just like the kind of learning that I
did to learn photography or something
like that. Um, there's something about
schools um and the design and
organization of schools that makes it
really hard for these kinds of learning
environments to make their way in. Um, I
think a lot of what I want to share with
you today are some of the most
substantial efforts particularly in
higher education to figure out how some
of these approaches to um peer-guided
learning at scale could make their way
into formal institutions. Um I the ideas
that I am presenting to you when I you
know if I was talking about them 10
years ago I would have positioned them
more as these are very viable ways in
which at least higher education maybe a
number of forms of education might
substantially change in the next five or
10 years. Um and I think I will I'm more
likely to present you them today as an
interesting dead end. um as a set of
things that people were trying putting a
lot of effort behind putting a lot of
design behind and and really didn't have
um much impact in how especially higher
education Kate in how in how formal
education of all kinds are organized um
you know studying things that flop is is
good we're going to come back to this a
few different times studying things that
flop is really important to figure out
um why things work if you just study uh
things that work um you actually don't
know why they work you know the
characteristics I have, but but there's
lots of things that are in common
between things that work and things that
don't work. Um, and so that's what we'll
uh we'll delve into some today. Um,
maybe I'll talk for a little bit and
then see what kind of thoughts you have.
All right, so we are I think we did the
Rainbow Loom story. We talked about this
the other the other day. This is, you
know, one I think iconic moment of, you
know, the creation of a new craft
generates um these these new kinds of
communities. Um, this was from 2013. You
know, low tech but high in creativity.
The Rainbow Loom has kids hooked,
spending hours after school and on
weekends making bracelets, weaving
together small, colorful rubber bands on
a simple plastic loom. Um, and all of
the um the narrative around Rainbow Loom
was, man, look, we finally got kids off
their phones. Like, we finally got kids
in the real world connecting to one
another. You know, this is I think 2013
that this is published right before
Christmas. Um, but of course the kids
were were on their phones the whole time
that they were playing with Rainbow
Loom. And so this is Ashley and Steph um
who are these two girls, you know, who
have 200, you know, a quarter of a
million people subscribed to. Oh, this
is Yeah. How to make a Rainbow Loom
Starburst bracelet. When whenever I
recorded this um 30 million views, um
probably 10 times as many that were on
the official Rainbow Loom um Starburst
page that somehow these uh these two
kids had um captivated. I I don't know.
It's hard to say that it was millions of
people because it actually could have
been like a couple hundred thousand
people each watch this like 10 or 20
times because it's super hard to make
one of these bracelets. Um but uh um you
know I think a a compelling example of
how network learning was you know and
and and something like this if you're my
age you know looking at this in 2013
it's it's really hard to imagine
something similar happening in 1990 or
something like that. Like if someone had
invented a new kind of craft you would
have like had to go to a craft store.
You would have had to join a club. be
able to go to classes. There have to be
a college club or something like that.
Um there wouldn't, you know, I I mean,
you know, maybe PBS would put on a
television show about it. You'd have,
you know, you could imagine like the Bob
Ross of Rainbow Loom or something like
that. Um but uh you know, um very hard
to imagine the same kind of highly
decentralized
um uh mechanism by which learners
connect themselves to each other. I
think one of the things I'm going to ask
you to um read for an upcoming week, I
can't remember, it's next week. Um uh
but this uh piece by Ivon Illich called
Deschooling Society um I think it's
written in the 1960s. Um and he he
almost exactly with like the very dawn
of computing and he predicts learning
networks that that emerge like this. Um
he says you know one day I mean he has a
funny way of describing he says well you
know one day there's going to be a bunch
of learners um who write down the things
they're interested in learning on punch
cards because that's what computers at
the time and there's going to be a bunch
of experts who share their interests on
punch cards and the computers are going
to connect these punch cards together um
and get people teaching and learning
from one another and like we it turned
out we had YouTube rather than punch
cards but um it was a pretty similar
kind of phenomenon um there are you know
in in the in the 20 in the early 2010s,
there were some people who were
particularly enthusiastic about the
fact, you know, so one thing about
Rainbow Loom you could say is something
like, well, all right, so some kids
figured out how to make plastic
bracelets. That's okay. Um, but there
are people who achieve like elite levels
of performance in a variety of different
disciplines and domains by following the
same kinds of practices that the Rainbow
Kids, Rainbow Kids were using. So, this
is a guy named Julius Jgo who, as I
recall, won a silver medal in the
Olympics. Um, he was from Kenya and he
was a javelin thrower. There are no
field athletes in Kenya. They're all
track runners. Um, and for whatever
reason, Julius Diego got it in his head
like, I'm going to be a javelin thrower.
Um, and uh, you know, I mean, here, you
know, my coach is me and the YouTube
videos. Um, and he became an elite, you
know, globally recognized ath. I mean,
there's a there's a there's a moment
where this tips. there's a moment where
he goes to um a track and field
competition um you know he doesn't
really have a coach and he throws a
javelin pretty far and some people
notice him and kind of take him under
his wing and stuff like that. So it's
not you know it's it's not just YouTube
videos that get you entirely to um being
the second best javelin thrower in the
world. Um but uh but going quite a long
way you know there's there's echoes of
this of the story that I told you before
of uh um Batush the boy genius of Ulan
Batar the the kid who sort of discovered
in Mongolia um through MITx and things
like this the idea that these could have
these profound democratizing effects
like you don't you know you don't have
to be um in in a country that has a
really big track and field
infrastructure um to be able to become a
great athlete. You can do it anywhere
because we have YouTube now.
Um, so in I I was working for Harvard X
in 2013. Um,
uh, maybe I, you know, maybe I'll pause
to tell this story, too. Well, I don't
know what the right order is now that
I'm inspired by it, but um there was
this term massive open online courses
and it actually was not originally
applied to the courses that came out of
Corsera um and edex and MITx and Udacity
and things like that. There were a group
of Canadian educators who 2008, 2009,
2010, 2011 started building theseworked
courses. Um, some of the I'll go more
into the details of the network courses,
but you would basically kind of create
an online learning environment, have
people create blogs, connect on Twitter,
form social network connections with one
another and sort of all be studying the
same thing at the same time. Sometimes
some of the people would be getting
credit from some institution and other
people would not be getting credit. They
were all kind of openly being involved.
You know, a few thousand people,
probably the largest of these, um,
signing up. And so there was actually a
reporter who when um Edex and Corsera
got started was trying to figure out
what these things should be called. Um
and somebody said like well these
Canadian guys have these things called
massive open online courses. Um and the
name stuck but it stuck to describe
something very very different. Um, one
of the things that we recognized early
on is that is that in the early days of
people doing the massive open online
courses that came out of Harvard and MIT
is many of them were not just using the
course materials that were being
provided on these platforms, but they
were using all kinds of other things.
So, you'd ask people and they're like,
you know, um, yeah, well, we're
searching for all kinds of things that
show up. We're reading like the
Wikipedia entries about the things that
show up in these classes. We're buying
additional books that are around them.
Um, we're looking for those books on
Google books. We're joining Facebook
groups of people who are studying these
courses together and things like that.
Um, and so the the the the barriers
between these sort of instructorg guided
learning at scale, these like highly
structured learning management system
kinds of things and the sort of informal
world of people messing around on
YouTube learning about stuff um sort of
uh smooshed together. probably a bunch
of you have some kind of experience of
that in your classes too. I mean
presumably all of you like are like when
you don't understand something in class
you're looking up online videos about it
or you don't like the lecture and you
know probably mostly in your technical
classes you watch it from some other
place. I don't know do any of you join
groups or like find communities of
people who are good at at solving
problems and the things that you're
interested in.
One thing about being an MIT student is
you can go on OCW if you miss a lecture
or you don't understand the lecture you
want to explain in a different way from
a different professor just watch that
same lecture which I've done before for
some of my more technical classes. Yep.
So yeah, so you can rewatch sort of past
things. Some professors are sort of
pretty explicit about that. You know,
they'll be like, "Well, this is my
lecture, but like somebody else filmed,
you know, roughly the same course four
years ago, and so you can watch all
those things." Um, how many of your
classes still use Piaza or some kind of
discussion forum sort of things? Um, are
the are the Piaza forms ever
insufficient and then you go to Stack
Overflow or to some other kind of maybe
for your coding classes and things like
that? I would say Piaza has like a weird
social dynamic in itself. No, I want
that now. Tell me more.
I think it's like um I mean like
obviously you can both do like anonymous
questions and non-anmous question but
usually it seems like you know it it
really depends
on a little bit on like who's really
using it and also how responsive the
faculty and stuff are and how they
choose to respond because that I have
been in a in quite a few classes where
like
log on and then it's like yes I had that
question and they're like oh sorry we
boarded the question weird but then I've
also been quite a few classes where it's
like they're asking this like super
highlevel question about the lecture and
then it kind of sets that expectation
for the class especially if it's a
larger class of like oh like my like
quotequote dumb questions not going to
be answered yeah it's not going to be
kind of respected or things like that
yeah you know And um I mean because
these things are social in nature, I bet
a lot of those things can be determined
pretty early on by the actions of a
couple of people. Um when we were
studying Massive Women online courses,
one of the things we found in the
discussion forums, the largest threads,
the most upvoted kinds of things were
almost always amongst the very first
topics cho like posted. So, so it wasn't
like the forums were surfacing um like
it wasn't like there was lots of ideas
and the most interesting or important of
those ideas were surfacing at the top.
It was like somebody jumped in there
first and then people started talking
about those things, you know. Um and you
could imagine you could imagine an
alternate timeline of the exact same
course you're in where the first two
people to co post happen to just be
people who are like I don't understand
this really basic thing. Will someone
explain it again? And the forums have
sort of a whole different uh character
to them. I mean to some extent I think
of computer programming in particular as
a field that depends upon this kind of
informal learning that b like that
basically no one knows enough about
programming languages and how they
operate and how they solve problems and
so you you essentially can't do that
profession if you can't figure out how
to navigate all the online resources all
online communities and things like that.
And unusually um you can you can be pro
be promoted and thrive in those
communities through your participation
in some of these kind of informal
learning networks. You know you can be
really active I mean in creating open
source projects or just be a really
active contributor to Stack Overflow or
other kinds of communities like that get
recognized for your contributions and
have that translate into other kinds of
opportunities. So um the boundaries
between um there there are ways that I
think these informal learning
environments and formal learning
environments the boundaries can permeate
even if as we'll keep talking about like
just trying to take the whole informal
peer guided learning infrastructure and
bring it into schools seems not to to
work pretty well.
Um uh you know I think one of the
actually one of the most compelling
reasons for integrating technology into
people's school learning at all is the
idea that actually for most of your
lives the kind of learning that you do
will look more like the learning around
your hobbies than it does look like the
learning in your classes. You know in in
the next couple of years some of you
will keep taking classes for a long long
time but most of you will probably stop
um or take them only infrequently. You
will probably however continue um to
participate in these online learning
communities. To me it raises really
interesting questions like you know what
responsibility does a school have for
helping people become really good um you
know at learning cooking through playing
with recipes the way Dana described or
or learning photography um through
online forums or music through uh online
videos in the way that that Jiren and
Omar described. like what what would
what would a K12 education look like if
someone left school and they were like,
I'm totally prepared to teach myself
stuff by engaging these online
communities because I've had a bunch of
practice in those sorts of things. What
would a what would a college education
look like if it was good at that? I feel
like that's like such an interesting
point because I like think back to a
conversation I had with my mom where she
like grew up and was out of college or
out of high school like right before the
like really dawn of like computer
classes in high school and middle school
and like in middle school so like
rudimentary to us we like learn how to
use an Excel sheet and like just learn
how to like Google things um and like a
lot of just like the super basic skills
like how to type on a computer a
computer like keyboard that she doesn't
know how to do and it almost seems like
the next generation will like leave
computer classes like knowing how to
navigate these sites and like then all
the stuff that I had to learn on my own
like maybe I'm asking my kids like where
did you learn that and they're just like
in school. Um there was a phrase that
was used for a number of years that was
called digital native. Um the idea maybe
maybe a more common you know phrase that
you'll hear probably in the next few
years will be something like AI native.
um the idea that like what's the
difference between having to learn
something by by having it come into you
into your into your life versus like
having it be something that you kind of
grow up with all the time. There's
actually a bunch of good evidence that
in fact that digital natives that young
people are actually not that much better
at using technology especially learning
things than older folks. Um you know
young people in schools are usually
pretty good at doing certain kinds of
technology mediated things but the
things that are most helpful for
learning they're often no better at than
sort of anybody else. Um although I'
I've always liked the idea you know one
of the things that comes along with the
idea of immigration of digital natives
and so digital immigrants and digital
natives is that uh um you know second
generation immigrants are always taking
on new responsibilities for teaching
their first generation parents about
things you know you like you you grow up
in a country and you learn the language
you learn the culture you know other
kinds of things that you sort of have to
explain to your parents so there's
something kind of nice about um that
metaphor carrying over
um something that I know state of
Massachusetts is doing is um I don't
know if I completely agree with it um
blending computer science and computer
literacy together. I do think that
teaching computer literacy is of utmost
importance. Um I credit a lot of my um
computer literacy to my seventh grade
seventh and eighth grade technology
teacher. Um you know the link that I use
now was created back in seventh grade.
use is the very same account and he was
the one who got me um I think I
mentioned the typing lessons like the
beginning of the class that's where I
learned how to type um that's where I
learned how to um create a portfolio
create an online website um do like
individual kind of research and like
create a project on something that I'm
interested about um and I think creating
projects on something that's is like
personal to someone within a K through
12 um lesson is really important for
teaching them how to like conduct
research
take notes and uh come up with
conclusions on what they've um gone up
and looked for online. And a constant
challenge educators have is what new
things are actually worth investing
additional discretionary time in. I
mean, there were, you know, plenty of
folks 10 years ago who said, man, it's
incredibly important. Every high
schooler should complete a MOO. MOUKs
are going to be absolutely essential to
how people learn and finish higher
education in the future. If you can't do
a MOO, you're really going to be left
out. It's like, well, maybe not so much.
turned like a LinkedIn profile however
many years later still seems like a
pretty handy thing to have. There is no
reason 10 years ago that you could it's
very easy to imagine a world where
LinkedIn got replaced by something else
entirely and mukes were super important
like in 2013 the success paths of those
things were not at all predictable. Um
uh educators are super anxious about I I
just gave it Aaron came to this
conference with me. I gave a talk to a
bunch of educators about AI and
education on Monday. Um and there's a
ton of anxiety about like how important
are these things? What what do we not
need? Does it make sense to teach kids
the same way to search anymore? If you
know, AI agents are just going to answer
our questions for us or do we is it more
important to be able to do that because
the AI agents are going to say nonsense
to us? Um all these all these kinds of
things. Yeah. Ty, in that Oh, sorry. In
that regard, like do you consider AI a
form of like peer learning because it's
been trained on pure community like
stack overflow, all these other things.
Question. Oh, so my first thing about AI
um uh I was giving a talk with Jim Waldo
um who's the who was the chief technical
officer at Harvard. He's a neat guy um
because he got he got a PhD in
philosophy about 40 years ago then went
and worked at Oracle, helped write Java.
If you have an Android phone, you're
probably running his code on it. Um and
then he came back um and now he does
policy stuff and he's sort of a
philosopher again, but he's like AI what
do you AI is what we call computing
technologies that are new and we don't
understand very well. Um, and 10 years
from now, they won't be called AI
anymore. Um, and so, uh, you know, like
are generative pre-trained transformers
peer communication? Well, you know,
maybe, um, you know, if like what do I,
what do I think? What do I think a
peer-guided network is? Um, a learner
enters a network with a wide range of
learning resources that are generated by
previously all human agents. Um, could
an a, you know, could a generative
pre-trained transformer generate a
useful learning sequence? Seems
plausible. Um, you know, I I I remain
not entirely convinced. I I actually
what somebody came up to me and was like
like we're like we have a startup where
we're creating online classes by having
AI create the classes. And I was like,
that just sounds like a terrible idea.
In part because there's just such a huge
surfet of classes. Like there's so many
things out there and they're really not
unfortunately that expensive to develop.
Um like why do you mean machines to do
them? Um
uh I have a I have a colleague uh
um Carolyn Ros who worked with chat bots
for decades. Um
uh and and she actually she's has
convinced me to be very skeptical of
interactions of individuals with chat
bots. Um like I don't know how many of
you in the last week spent more than an
hour talking to a
chatbot. Zero, maybe one. Um I just
don't think people like it that much. Um
she really thought that where they could
be powerful is jumping in in the
conversations between two people. Um
that you just have peers talking to each
other. So you're on this discussion
forum and you're going back and forth or
other things like that and then a bot
comes in and sort of helps you um ask an
interesting question. Get like oh look
somebody over here has a different
perspective on that. Let me connect you
to that. and so you can talk and things
like that. Um, but yeah, it totally I I
think I think it totally seems plausible
that a peer guided learning environment
could include, you know, artificial
agents that are doing things that humans
had previously been doing.
Yeah, I guess to like both your points
of like a interaction, I I would say um
um an interesting aspect of that
especially in terms of like what can be
a credible source for learning and stuff
like that. So, I think in California, or
at least the the the part of California
I was in for a while, we did have like a
middle school little like a week-l long
program that every kid had to do that
was like, "Oh, you're 13. Here, make an
email and here's how you Google stuff."
Um, and like recently with um the new
Google AI feature that kind of
summarizes answers for you. Now, I was
like thinking about like um how does
that
change kind of those levels of
instructions? Because sometimes I look
up things and I see the summary and I'm
like I don't know what the answer is but
I know it's not
that and I and I go deeper. But like
let's say if I'm a middle schooler and
it's like well I don't learn this or I'm
a high schooler that took that class in
middle school and it's like well now I'm
not sure or I take Bard's word for good.
Yeah. Yeah. No, a hu a huge problem with
GPT generated text is that it's probably
much more useful for experts than for
noviceses. Um, so if you're an if you
know you ask a GPT to make eight things
and and two of them are cool and six of
them are nonsense or the opposite, an
expert can tell the difference and be
like, "Oh, that was an idea I didn't
have before." But a novice can't. A
novice just looks and be like, "Okay,
these are eight ideas. They all seem
plausible and they're confidently stated
and things like that." It's a huge
problem that educators are going to have
to wrestle with um in the in the years
ahead.
Um it's, you know, the kind of class
that you're describing, um if if it were
to be taught 10 years ago, a big thing
that educators were thinking about at
the time was how are people going to
navigate a social web? Um so, um when
when the web was first developed, we'll
get into this a little bit more, it was
pretty hard for people to contribute to
it. Um you had to know a little bit
about FTP, you had to know a little bit
about HTML, a couple other things like
that. They weren't like super hard, but
there was a relatively small portion of
the population that added content to the
internet. Um, and there were suite of
technologies that got bundled and called
web 2.0. Um, which said, okay, we're
going to make it much easier for anybody
to type things online. You can all start
a blog. You can all start a micro blog.
You can all make a simple website. You
don't have to know how to code to do any
of these things. Um, we're gonna we're
going to use user interfaces to take
away all that sort of programming
expertise that's necessary. And so
people thought, "Wow, you know, I bet
our lives are going to and you know,
young people's lives." If you, you know,
if you were teaching 11 year olds, 12
year olds in 2013, you thought, man, a
major thing they're going to have to do
is how to connect and network with each
other. We have to have them create their
LinkedIn page um so that they know how
to social network with each other. We
have to have them um, you know,
participate in online dialogues. We have
to have them think about what are
responsible ways of representing
themselves. Um people talk a lot about
their digital footprint um and other
kinds of things like that. Um you know
today a 13-year-old is entering a web
environment in which there are lots of
parts of social media which are
collapsing. Um that uh um you know just
as an example actually I was I went to
the guy who ran this conference on
Monday and well it was kind of so there
were usually this conference get 100 or
150 people show up. It was about AI.
They had 240 people show up and 70 folks
were on the wait list. Um, tons and tons
of interest from educators. And I and I
went to the guy who runs it, Tom
Driscoll, and says, "What do you think
these teachers are interested in? Like
what are you like, what do they want to
know? Why are they here?" Um, and he's
like, "You know what? I don't know." Um,
10 years ago, they would have had blogs.
They would have, you know, participated
in forums. They would have joined
Facebook groups. they would have sort of
like um uh they had there were many many
more ways that educators were
proactively um contributing their ideas
to the web. Maybe not all of them. Maybe
it was you know 10% of them or 20% of
the time but enough of them that you
could kind of get the pulse of a whole
community. Um which he felt like and I
agree you really can't do anymore. Um
some of that is that there was there was
a moment in web 2.0 know in which people
believed that the infrastructure of the
web might be really quite open and quite
owned um or controlled by individual
people um that there could be a world
where people create their own websites,
they create their own blogs, they host
their own accounts and things like that.
Um and uh you know I don't know when
some of these things starting around
2015 2016 people started describing um
the web we lost a kind of a kind of
moment in which social media took a turn
um uh you know so these are the kinds of
things that like I don't know I was
playing around with in 2004 2007 any of
you have a live journal blog as one of
the early sort of blogging sites people
like create their own space and hosting
it this was a wordpress.com blog of my
wife and I you know, writing little
stories about us, going on adventures
and things like that. Um, posting
pictures, hosting it ourselves. Um, and
essentially Facebook came and sort of
demolished all this. Um, and said, you
know what, like you don't need to host
your own blog. You don't need to um, you
know, you don't need to like figure out
an FTP server to upload your own
pictures or use a picture interface.
Like we're going to create an interface
there. people participate in a lot of
the same kind of practices on Facebook
of writing little stories on the trips
they do and posting pictures and stuff
like that. But all of a sudden it was
all controlled by Mark Zuckerberg. Um
this was a quote from David Weinberger.
In many ways Facebook fulfilled the
dream of blogging but like not exactly
like like everybody was online but they
weren't in spaces that they owned, had
control over, had some familiarity with.
Um and then um we'll talk about some of
this as it goes along. Um, I think there
was a there was a moment in which
participation in a broad online life
felt much less toxic and draining and
vulnerability inspiring as it does right
now. Um uh you know I mean if if there
are there if you're a teacher who's
working in a state which has recently
passed a divisive concepts law um or
other things like that regulating the
kinds of topics you can talk about and
things like that like all of that has a
sort of chilling effect um you know not
I mean not to mention just the the ways
in which you know the social media
services Facebook Twitter other kinds of
things we use have sort of degraded um
in their conversations over time um uh
you This is what David Weinberger said.
The bloggers field did not scale. Um
like like there you know some people
created their own blogs but not
everyone. Um and then Facebook came in
and many people who created blogs like
I'll just post to Facebook. A lot of
those people have like moved over to
Substack now or other kinds of things
like that but but systems that they
don't control. Um there is I think a
parallel to that story that happened in
higher education. Um so in the early
days um when the web was first made
available broadly to schools which also
h you know happens to overlap with my
life. So I I think in 1993 Dartmouth
College is the first college to give um
every incoming student an email address.
I think in
1994 very quickly many many other
colleges had done that. By the time I
graduated high school but certainly by
the time I was into college in 1996 um I
had an email address. everybody else
would have had an email address. That
would have been, you know, um pretty
pretty universal and standard. Um but
this is what university web pages looked
like at the time. Um MIT still has some
of these kinds of things. Has anybody
ever been to somebody's tilda space? You
know,
www.mmit.eduilda jri or something like
that. Who do you um Oh man, the 1806
professor. What's what's his
forgetting? Um the one who just retired
Gil String. Good. Perfect. Great. Others
that people can think of who have these
things? So, um um so some things that
you'll notice about the Well, I don't
know. What do you just looking at these
pictures? What do you notice about these
things? What strikes you about them?
There were some giggles before, which I
think is appropriate.
Like everything is
okay. So, you know, not a lot of font
diversity. What else?
There's no advertisements. Yeah. Good.
No, these are so so these were not
created like with Wix or something like
that where in exchange for making a
website you have to put a bar of
advertisements at the bottom or
something like that. So somebody
actually made these pages. They're all
personal homepages. Other things that
strike you?
The backgrounds. What about the
backgrounds?
Um it's certainly of like I don't know.
I I feel like I I personally associate
them with a very specific time period.
Okay, good. It's like this is natural.
They they have they have a '9s aesthetic
to them. Yeah. I would say maybe it is
like partially just like the quality of
like like let's say a pattern or
something you can put on or like now we
have a lot of templates that make sure
it's like aesthetically consistent. This
is pre-CAva. We're not we're not uh Ken,
what were you going to observe? Oh, I
was about to say about the templates
like they're not all using the exact
same uh template and similar formatting.
They're not all using the exact same
template in similar formatting. I think
that that is actually quite important.
Um there are some good things that
templates do of make things looking um
uh aesthetic. Um but they standardize in
a way. They they put things in the same
way. People at universities do really
really different kinds of things. That
might be important. Other observations
about these? It's very speromorphic. Um,
like there's buttons on the the bottom
left one with like icons that you don't
see as often. And I want to say the
background, especially the bottom left,
reminds me of a a physical wallpaper.
Uhhuh. Um, which is like a principle. Do
you want to define skuorphism for us?
Skeorphism is
like the most famous example. It's
probably like iOS 6 where you have all
these buttons and like reflections that
sort of try to mimic real life. And
that's like what skuomorphism is trying
to mimic real life. And then when we
transition to iOS 7, you removed a lot
of that dimension and it became a lot
more simplistic and and symbolic. A lot
of the early note-taking apps would have
a background like a yellow legal pad or
or like a spiral binding on the side or
something like that and you're like,
"Brother, we could put the we don't need
the lines. Like the cursor will do that
for you." Um but um people wanted to
make some kind of connection between
what they saw be you know what they saw
in the physical world and what this new
digital thing was trying to do.
Skeumorphism shows up in that book
somewhere. I can't remember now where I
wrote about it but um um yeah I mean
obviously these pictures are just
outstanding. Um
uh just like people had kind of like a
cool
idiosyncratic
um personalized kind of a bane in the
butt to organize sort of blogosphere
that existed that Facebook just came and
sort of demolished and homogenized and
standardized and pulled out of the
control of individual people's spaces
and into this sort of corporate space.
Um, you could say that Blackboard did
something very very similar to campus
web pages. Um, that learning management
systems came along um and they said,
"We're gonna standardize it all." Um,
you you don't have you don't have to
create your own page anymore. Like
Blackboard will create your own faculty
page, create your own course page. Um,
and that's going to come with some kind
of benefits of standardization. It's
going to make it a lot easier for
people, but it's but it's also going to
get rid of um some of the kind of
wonderful
idiosyncrasies um of these things. And
it's going to mean that there's a
corporate entity who is who is not
accountable who's accountable to their
shareholders and not accountable to the
same values that we might have as a
university, which is deciding what those
things look like. Much like when we move
all of our blogs onto Facebook, um you
don't even you're not even accountable
to shareholders. are just accountable to
whatever Mark thinks you know people
should be doing in Facebook. Um yeah, in
many ways Blackboard fulfilled the dream
of the university till the spaces did
not scale. I believe the problem could
have been solved but then Blackboard
happened. Um why would Blackboard
happen? Um these are the instructions
for Sunni onion about how you would go
about creating one of your tilda space
pages. you know, log into AAD, create a
directory, change to this directory,
create HTML documents, um, HTML
developers jumpstation, you know, set
pro equals w file namex. You can like
you read about a page of this stuff and
you're like, "Yeah, I can see why a lot
of people, you know, like why launching
a Blackboard page might be uh might be
fine." Um,
uh, uh, this is what the um, what is
this
blackboard? I don't I don't remember
what uh learning management system this
was. Maybe it's Canvas. It's not Canvas.
I don't I can't remember what it is now.
This is the this is the very first
version of a sort of a version of this
course um that I taught 10 years ago. Um
and this is the this is the page that
the that the system generated for me um
when I first created the class. So it
comes with a bunch of these sort of st
not not this stuff that I added but
syllabus class sessions other resources
assignments collaborate information
reserves list search this site lecture
video um it makes a set of assumptions
about what my course is um it says you
know this is what the standard format of
this learning experience should be um
but maybe that's not at all what I want
it certainly doesn't make a lot you know
if I had if I had taught this class
about this was in an education school if
I had made this class about education
technology ology about um the experience
of indigenous kids learning on
reservations about um I don't know the
uh um global education policy um
intermediate statistics it all would
have been the exact same format um they
would have given the same sort of
standardized creation for this which
just in lots of you know it makes sense
in some kind of ways and it's bonkers in
other kinds of ways our courses are
super different why should all of our
courses have the same template why
should we all be sort of subtly
invisibly squished into teaching our
courses the same way um by by these
kinds of structures. Um and of course
there's all kinds of physical analoges
to this too. Um the the way we design
environments shapes the learning
experiences um that happen in the I just
read a beautiful sentence of this which
is you know something like um it was
something like buildings have agenda for
their occupants. um the way that spaces
are created, like it doesn't tell you
what to do, but it certainly guides you.
You know, you walk into a room like this
um and you have some thoughts about the
kind of learning that's going to happen
in that space. Like, well, you're all
going to be facing in the same
direction. Probably not going to be
talking to a whole each other a whole
lot um in that space. There's some, you
know, you're going to be writing with
certain kinds of physical materials. If
you try to use a laptop on those, uh,
you know, square square tables, you'll
have a hard time, you know, there's no
room for power cords or other kinds of
things like this. Um this is actually
one of the most famous examples in elite
private education in the United States.
Um which is uh um there were um uh
donors to the the Philips exit school
who were really concerned um that that
essentially there's too much
instructionism and not enough
constructionism. They wouldn't have said
it the exact same way, but they would
have said something along those lines.
Too much sitting passive listening, not
enough sort of engaged conversation. Um
and so a a bunch of donors uh got
together um and they said in every
classroom we're going to pull out all of
the chairs that look like this and we're
going to put in these tables called
Harkness tables. Um some of the features
of Harkness tables are that you need to
be able to fit everybody in the class
sort of in an oval around the table. Um
the tables are so large that they
usually have to be like built in
different pieces and then shipped into
the room and then assembled inside the
room. um they're incredibly heavy, but
they um they they make it so there is no
front of the room. Um they they and and
they, you know, at Philips exit at other
kinds of independent schools, they put
these tables in every classroom. Um they
put them in the English classrooms, they
put them in the history classrooms, but
they put them in the math classrooms,
they put them in the science classrooms.
Um and the intention was to to change
the physical space in order to create
certain kinds of learning environments
and certain kinds of interactions there
and there. Now, of course, um you can
give a math lecture in a room like this,
but it's but it's hard to lecture for 52
minutes, you know, if you're standing
here and half the kids either have their
backs to you or have to, you know,
rotate around or other kinds of things
like that. Um it's it's designed to make
people do that. So you can sort of think
about like what are the you know h what
are what you know what uh what agenda
does this online space have for its
occupants? Um what is it that a can that
a sort of generic canvas classroom tells
instructors and students that they're
supposed to do?
Um the you can look at these links
later, but these are two of the folks
who um as as as Blackboard was sort of
sweeping higher education were uh um uh
amongst the most active in trying to
have these conversations. There was a
book um that was written about them uh
and some other people called Edupunks um
and uh trying to make connection between
the the punk movement and music um you
know very sort of like countercultural
do-it-yourself
um you know uh kind of stand up to the
man sort of thing um and folks like the
Reverend Jim Groom um and Alan Cogdon
living you know they have they have
these monikers because if you were
participating in social networks you
create handles for those kinds of things
but also Reverend Jim Groom was a bit a
profit of such things.
Um so what what these systems really
allow um is a certain kind of
coordination. Um it becomes very very
easy to say all the faculty are going to
have a page. Um you're all going to
create at the same time. It's going to
be automatically generated for you at
the beginning of the semester. Even if
you don't like computers, we're still
going to be able to make you do it
because it's not that hard. Um but there
are a couple of characteristics of it
that I think are not so good. I've
talked mostly about the sort of stamped
piece of it. Um
uh there's there's a way in which um the
control of all of the learning artifacts
is with the institution and not the
people. Um, so imagine imagine an
infrastructure for um online learning
and higher education where you didn't
put all the stuff on someone else's web
page, you put it on your own web page.
Like what if when you went to do
homework, you went to do writing, you
went to ask questions, it didn't show up
on the school's Canvas site, which you
don't care about, but it was on your
site in some kind of way. It was in some
sort of space that you controlled. And
then the thing that was always craziest
to me about these sites is that we
delete them every 18 months. Um, you
know, it's a it's a strange thing to go
to students and be like, "Please pour in
um your best, most thoughtful, most
interesting words, ideas." Um, oh, and
by the way, nine months from now,
they're going to be automatically
deleted. Um, that's a that's a sort of
strange feature to me of a of an online
learning environment. Um,
uh, so so me and other folks for a while
were really interested in like, well,
what would an alternative to this look
like? um what would be what would be
something um that was not Blackboard
that was not Canvas um that still could
have coordination um but it would let it
would have some of these characteristics
that the sort of web 2.0 open web
movement had like it let students own
their own stuff um it helped them
develop some technology proficiency. It
connected people um to each other and to
their work. It didn't just like hoover
up your stuff, churn it through, grade
it, and delete it, but it would be like
something that you owned and cared about
for a while. Um,
uh, those are ice cream sandwiches. Um,
uh, yeah. Good. Yeah. So, it's a good
it's a good picture. It, you know, it
definitely evokes some of these kinds of
pictures. Like some of these kinds of
pictures sort of ended up on like
professor Twitter handles in the 2013.
Um, I didn't make that picture. I had
one semester um where I don't know some
students just were like enjoying class
and they sent me a whole bunch of p I
don't know how quickly can I find these
things.
Um there's one of
me.
Uh are these going to be on here?
Um. H there's a few. There's like this
one. This one. Oh, no. That's a real
one. Justin is LeBron James. A little
little dicey to be doing this one these
days. I don't You probably wouldn't uh
you probably wouldn't put white Justin
into a black body anymore, but uh back
in the day. Um yeah, I don't for one day
for class uh I think something terrible
had happened in the world and I made
them ice cream sandwiches one day for
class and so they uh um they made that
picture there.
It was for
a we're get we're getting to the real
issues
now. I think that I went to the
International Society and Technology and
Education conference and they basically
grabbed a bunch of random people and
took them to a photo shoot to generate
their own stock photos. Um they they
want they wanted to have a whole set of
stock photos that were from the
membership of this organization. And so
it was just like I don't think I was
holding any I think I I mean I like you
could imagine this is like generic
invitation to kind of thing. Um, but
that's where all that came from.
Um, is is this worth your learning time?
Hard to say, but it's pretty fun. Okay,
this you should remember a little bit.
Um, this is another this is another
branch of um uh of constructionism. You
know, these ideas just repeat
themselves. They get reinvented over and
over again. um these two Canadian
educators, people who sort of founded
the 2007208 original mass of open online
courses and they had this idea called
connectivism. Um and they said, you
know, part of the problem with learning
theory is that it thinks that learning
happens and knowledge exists inside
people's heads. But learning and
knowledge really exists between people
more than exists within people. Um
there's a famous line which is which you
probably all would agree with in some
way that the smartest person in the room
is the room. Um that like the collective
capacity of people is where kind of the
heart of art intelligence is like
connectivism almost went further and
said like maybe the only intelligence in
the room is the room. Um maybe your
knowledge your understanding like
doesn't exist without social convention
like language um like culture other
kinds of things like that. Um so this
was so this was at first an educational
philosophy. Um may you know may maybe it
was a maybe it was an epistemology maybe
it was a philosophy of knowledge but
then it got translated into these
pedagogical ideas. Um and the
pedagogical ideas were say what if you
defined courses where their primary
value was creating connections between
people and ideas. Um uh one of one of
the things Stephen D said about this
which you'll find it very connected to
situated learning um he says you know
like if you become a physicist what
happens um well like you read physics
papers and you follow new ideas in
physics and you figure out where
physicists talk to each other and like
where the physics lounge is um and which
physics conferences to go to I don't
know what music physicists like what
television shows they find funny all
these kinds of things like that is as
much a part of becoming a physicist as
learning formulas and theories and
knowledge and things like that. What if
we had educational systems that took
that really seriously? Like the job of a
physics class is not just to have you,
you know, be able to learn some formulas
about Newton's three laws, but to
connect to other physicists. That's kind
of that's kind of a cool idea. Um, uh,
Ste, one of the most radical things
Steven DS ever said, he said something
along the lines of, "In my class, the
content is McGuffin." Um, a mcguffin is
the thing in a movie that's not really
important that drives the plot forward.
Um, it's the briefcase that gets
switched in the beginning which helps
two people fall in love with each other
or something like that. Um, the mcguffin
is the thing that you're sort of chasing
to make the plot move forward. This is a
radical statement for an educator. The
content is a mcguffin. The thing that I
told you the class is about as a trick.
The real part of the class is getting
you connected to each other, to things
that you're interested in, to other
kinds of expertise is a very radical set
of ideas. Um, and there are a lot of
people who are sort of um profoundly
influenced by them. Um, and people
trying to say like, yeah, well, what
what could some like genuine alternative
architecture to canvas um that embraced
some of these ideas of the open web, of
web 2.0, of connectism, what might it
look like? Um, and so this no longer
exists. I don't I don't think either of
those links are live anymore. Um, but
this is what the website for this class,
um, or an earlier version of this class
used to look like. Um, and here's how
the infrastructure of it worked. Um, at
the beginning of class, um, folks were
assigned to create spaces where they
would do the work of this class. Um, so
you wouldn't have a learning journal.
You wouldn't have like a Canvas
discussion page or something like that.
Go make your own blog. Go make your own
Tumblr page. Go make your own Twitter
feed. Go make your own Flickr page. Make
all kinds of other things like that. Um,
and do all of the work for this class in
your own space. Now, one problem with
that is that nobody can find that stuff
anymore. Now, it's all sort of on other
people's things. But that's a solvable
problem. Um, because we're going to
build this thing called the syndication
bus. Um and the syndication bus is gonna
depend on this technology which how many
of you are familiar with real simple
syndication. Is that something that you
like you like vaguely know exists? So
again 10 or 15 years ago um this was
considered like an essential part of the
web and there are many people would have
told you like this is the future of of
how people will find things. So before
um you know Jiren was telling us before
about the YouTube algorithm kind of
controlling what he watches and what he
finds and things like that. An
alternative to that was you subscribe to
a series of feeds. Um so you would like
find all the bloggers that you like or
all the video bloggers you like or
whatever else. You would choose their
feeds and then you would have you know
one really popular technology was called
Google Reader which just gave you the
things that came out of those feeds. So
instead of instead of being sort of like
bounced around by an algorithm to things
that people think are popular,
interesting and things like that um you
sort of have more control over that. So
basically what we did um was everyone
would create their own online space and
then we would use this signification bus
to aggregate all those things. So
effectively um we would oh there
um there's an animation there that's
missing. Um, we would make a copy of
each of these pieces and we would pull
the copy into the syndication bus. So,
you owned your own thing, but we would
use RSS to grab one copy of those
things. Um, and then we would aggregate
them in different kinds of ways. Um, so,
um, imagine if every time you wrote in
your learning journal, you didn't just
write in your own Google Slides, um, but
you wrote on a blog, um, anybody could
subscribe to that blog, but the course
subscribed to the blog. um and sort of
hoovered all of those things up into one
space. Um you could also um teach people
other ways of aggregating things like
anytime in any of the spaces that you're
working you share something that we
might be interested tag it with T509
massive. Um and then what gets populated
in this sort of syndication bust Twitter
channel is like all the tweets that
people have that are about T509 massive.
Um there were
uh the then um when you showed up on the
homepage I as the instructor would pick
a few of these things. So there was a
section called the spotlight where I
would sort of go through all the stuff
that people were generating every week
and pick a few things that I thought
were like particularly interesting,
particularly important, particularly
funny, stuff like that, and sort of show
them to people to feature them.
Um and then uh that's probably kind of
less important. Um, but then there were
other spaces, you know, we I could
create spaces that were about a
particular assignment. Um, you could
say, "Okay, everybody is working on your
Oh, oh, I want to tell you about how I
graded the class, but I could say,
"Everybody create your rubric." Um, and
then pull all of those things together,
you know, like have a kind of rubric hub
that everybody could see those things.
And then we had a space, I think it was
called the fire hose or something like
that. Um, where it was everything that
was coming in. Um there were probably 50
or 60 people who took this version of
the class and so there was no way that
everybody was going to read everything
that everyone else did but like a part
of class every week was finding out um
who are you connected with who are you
finding interesting who are you learning
from like oh you four were English
teachers before you came in like this
class like you should beworked with each
other moreover you should beworked to
other English teachers um the things
that you're generating like if you're
putting a bunch of work into this class
why just have it sit in a, you know, in
a discussion form that no one's ever
going to see again, like put it in this
space where you can share with other
people and stuff like that. Um,
uh,
one, you know, if you if you if you if
you take this idea, um, of letting
people choose how they want to share who
they want to connect with sort of
seriously, the more and more you get to
this idea of like there, you know,
there's no right way to do this. Um,
you're all coming into this class with
different goals. Maybe some of you, you
know, really want to connect with other
edtech companies and are interested in
being a founder or working for a
startup. Maybe some of you want to go
into education research. Maybe some want
to go into teaching. Why should you all
have the same criteria for what you're
writing about or what you're sharing?
Why don't you just tell me what it is
that you want to learn about? Why don't
you tell me what your goals are for this
kind of communication? Um and so people
would create uh their own rubrics about
um you know essentially like you tell me
what your blog is supposed to do
supposed to accomplish. I think at one
point um you know there was a part of
the assignment which you had to say like
describe how your writing is going to
benefit you and your learning, how your
writing is going to benefit the other
people in this class and how your
writing might plausibly benefit some
other community somewhere else that
you're connected to in some kind of way.
This was a professional I taught this at
the Harvard Graduate School of
Education. So people were sort of for
the most part already coming in with
with some kind of professional
communities from outside to to network.
Um and
um and there were there were lots of
other people um who were doing this kind
of thing. Um this was a course called
connected courses which was basically
teaching people across higher education
how you would go about creating these
courses. Um, but people built them in
anthropology. You know, probably one of
the most famous ones, which I think
still has a bunch of stuff which exists,
um, is called DS 106, digital
storytelling 106, um, which was a course
offered, um, at the University of Mary
Washington, but like essentially
syndicated to a bunch of other
universities and also built in such a
way I still, you can probably still go
to ds 106.org right now. Um, and uh, it
was mostly about creative assignments.
Um, they had a uh they had a feature
called the daily create where you know
some if you took this class four days a
week, you were supposed to do a daily
create. It might be something like my
favorite one was uh um pull out your
keychain and make a short video where
you tell the story of your keychain. Um
where does each key come from? What does
it mean to you? Other kinds of things
like that. Um sort of figuring out how
to make their way across the web.
Um so I told you this was a story
essentially of a failed enterprise. Um
you won't f like clearly I'm not
teaching like this anymore. Um you won't
find many other classes. You'll find
you'll find you know the ideas kind of
out there percolating in different
spaces. Um uh but like probably doesn't
really exist. Um why did it fail?
Probably two big reasons. Um one that
we'll keep coming back to which I've
termed the curse of the familiar which
is it's just weird. Um, it's different.
It's unusual. It takes a bunch of time
to learn. On the one hand, I think
people who are participating in these
classes were like, "Ah man, I learned a
lot of stuff about blogging, about using
Twitter, about connecting with other
people, about social networking." But
like, you know, my guy the, you know,
the the class was intermediate
statistics. Like like that's not what
you were supposed to be learning in this
thing. Um there were a handful of
universities that built a sort of
collaborative infrastructure around this
stuff in the hopes that you could drive
down some of the complexity. So this guy
Jim Groom built a company called Reclaim
Hosting um which tried to make it really
like universities could sign up to make
it really easy for every student in the
school to start a blog and then you like
teach them all about blogging a little
bit and then maybe you could get away
from discussion forums and have people
do more so of their short form writing
on blogs. Um maybe there are some people
out there that are still trying it but
uh but not that much. Um and then
um uh another huge challenge with asking
people to write publicly uh is that we
are not all equally vulnerable to the
consequences of um having our writing be
read. Anybody recognize this person? Um
she's a woman named uh Anita Sarassian
um who uh um had a website called
Feminist Frequency which uh um was sort
of one of one of the initial spaces that
was related to um what became Gamergate.
Um she uh she made a bunch of videos
basically about sort of anti-feminist
themes in video games like how uh um how
like you know there's always a princess
that needs to be saved and the princess
doesn't actually have to like doesn't
get to have her own character and things
like that. Um and uh just you know piled
on ruthlessly um by by all kinds of
people you know especially people who
who saw gaming as a hobby who didn't
want these tropes changed. Um, and so
you know, people get doxed and swatted
and all kinds of Are you all familiar
with Gamergate? Is that a phrase? Okay.
Um, so I don't even remember what year
this was now, but uh um I don't know. We
should in the media studies department,
we should be teaching a class called
Gamergate. It was it was kind of um it
seemed ludicrous at the time, but it was
uh it was a sort of way of you know
organizing groups of people to
effectively suppress communication from
sort of subalter perspectives from
people who are trying to say different
kinds of things. Um, so yeah, anyway,
for me as like a pretty privileged white
dude like blogging my way through the
world is relatively safe and relatively
straightforward, but you know, if I have
50 or 60 students in my class, they're
all going to be coming from different
perspectives and they're all going to be
sort of inequitably vulnerable um to
writing something which catches the
attention in negative ways of big crowds
um or offends people or messes up their
relationship or other kinds of things. I
mean, what part of what you want to do
in writing in a class is let people be
experimental and try on ideas that they
don't agree with yet or don't understand
yet, you know, and in when I was doing
this in 2013, that felt like a little
bit risky, maybe like yeah, I could I
could imagine someone might like take
down a post that they, you know, decide
wasn't well worded or disagree with
things like that. Um, in 2024, it seems
substantially um more risky. Not not I
would say not just because um of
heightened sensitivities um but because
you know because actors in society have
learned how to
um how to how to broadcast messages that
appear online in various kinds of places
um and to use them to generate outrage
and drive traffic and and those kinds of
things.
Um, oh, this was the company, uh,
Reclaim Hosting. Um, and they're, uh,
somebody should Google Reclaim Hosting
and see if they're they're still, um,
uh, known for education was a was a
project that was basically it was sort
of trying to take like everything that I
just described and figure out like how
do you make a really simple front end
for it so it's not hard for people to
build, but it still lets people own
stuff. um it still lets people sort of
you know be the be the owner of their
own means of production.
Um but it's something that I think will
um this was you know by far the most
exciting part of teaching these courses
was realizing that people were still
using this infrastructure in various
kinds of ways years after the course
ended. So I think I taught this course
in 2013 and still in 2015 people were
posting on their blogs connecting with
each other like you know I don't know
the equivalent of that would be like you
know if you're in 1806 now and it has a
piaza forum what if three years from now
you were inspired to like hop back in
there and
still like good god I would never do
such a thing but part you know you
wouldn't do such a thing because you
don't own it and it's not yours and you
can't take it in the direction that
you're interested in. But if we, you
know, in higher education, if we gave
you an infrastructure that you had some
control over, um, you might be
substantially more, I mean, at least the
students at the time were, um, were were
interested in in continuing to pursue
these kinds of, uh, these kinds of
learning experiences.
Um but I would but I would say the sort
of the the the degree to which people
feel much more individual threat about
sharing things um online especially in
really sort of open spaces. Um and just
the like difficulty of the ramp up time
of building all this infrastructure has
made it like more or less um an
interesting dead end and something kind
of fun to learn from and explore. It
probably also illustrates um more of
what you'll read about. This is like an
effort in higher education that
basically foundered. Um you'll read
about other kinds of things that sort of
foundered in different ways in K12 or
the challenge to make them not founder
for next week. Like there's all this
amazing learning that happens um in
people's informal learning experiences.
How do we why is it so hard to bring
those practices into school
environments? What is the nature of
school environments um that makes it
difficult for that to happen?
Um good. What qu maybe I think that's
where I got to the end. what questions
do folks have or what um um my question
is um what place kind of does um like
kind of online community building
without the presence of like instructors
have in this
yeah if it was if if this worked
um because you owned your own piece of
writing you know I'm teaching this class
at a professional school um you might
find that actually what motivates you
most to write these assignments is that
you've found a bunch of other sixth
grade science teachers that are reading
your blog posts and you sort of
increasingly care less that you know
Justin the instructor of this class is
reading your stuff and more like hey I'm
getting my ideas out there and
connecting more with other earth science
teachers. Um and that I think for a lot
of you know when it was most successful
that for people just felt like work that
was super real and urgent. Um you know
the the other thing is most of the thing
I don't know um when people got
responses it it there there wasn't a
whole lot of there's probably some but
there wasn't a whole lot of like you are
required to reply to at least two people
um kinds of things. Um there was a lot
of you know when like people would write
blog posts but they would write blog
posts that sort of tagged or or posted
back to someone else's post. So it was
just kind of like a natural um uh
conversation that was that was happening
and unfolding like where it was most
successful
um what you felt like as an instructor
is you were you were just like put
putting putting some fuel for this fire
to burn on its own. you were just like,
you know, here check out these things
like, you know, and then but then people
would take them in the directions that
they were most interested and excited
about. Does that answer your
question other thoughts or things that
how does this play into the Google doc
that runs this course? Huh? Yeah. So,
well, some of it is I uh probably
probably the main lingering piece um is
that it's a is that it's a pain in the
ass to show my Canvas site to someone
else. And one of the main things that I
want to do is, you know, I don't know,
in in in my career of teaching is be
able to like quickly to explain to other
people how I teach. Um, so one, you
know, one of the best things about
having the whole course live on a Google
doc is, you know, any new professor
who's just starting teaching edtech and
society, it's like here's a whole
course, you know, take it and c I mean,
they're probably taking it and like
shoving it bit by bit into Canvas, which
I've done periodically for some things.
Um, that any of you, you know, who want
to sign up for my, you know, future
people who are interested in this class,
you know, syllabus is there. You, you
know, I mean, it's even got it's even
got the revision history. You can now
see, nobody does that, but you can now
see what we did. I mean in I I would
also say earlier versions of that like
when the web was sort of more active in
this way, you know, I would like over
the summer I would post like here are
all the changes that I made to my
syllabus and like circulated around to
hashtags or other networks of people
that were active in those conversations
and people would definitely jump in to
the syllabus um and through and add
comments and be like oh you this new
book just came out or these new
resources came out and things like that.
I mean it existed as a for for a period
of time a much more sort of social
document. Um again when when yeah there
were a lot of you know educators
especially people interested in online
learning and education technology who
were pretty active in those kinds of
communities. Um and so you could do
stuff like that. Now it's mostly just a
legacy of you know editing that thing is
so much easier than editing canvas. Um
anytime I want to change something in
canvas I have to do it in three places
and click 15 buttons like Google doc I
just edit. Um good. So that was a little
bit in uh some of these ideas of peer
guided learning in higher education.
We'll see some more of them. Um, in K12,
I think you're going to read some stuff
from Mimito and uh
um what else did I make you do for next
time? And and Mitch Resnik um about
Scratch, which is Scratch is probably
the um most successful peer-guided
learning environment which has made its
way into K12 schools. Although one of
the things that we'll learn is that uh
when it gets there it kind of gets uh
schoolified in ways that are horrific to
the people who made it. But uh more to
follow when they discuss that uh on
Monday. Great. Have a wonderful uh rest
of your week and weekend and I will see
you next week.