[Music]
In my sophomore year, I walked onto the
crew team and it completely changed my
life. Having that outlet
for stress helps me enjoy both parts of
my life, both the athletic and the
academic side a lot
more. We kind of all push each other to
become the fastest boats that we can be.
But at the same time, in order to become
the best versions of ourselves, we have
to be supportive of each other
throughout the
way. The entire crew just rowing as one
person. You're all moving at the exact
same time. The ores are clicking in
exactly the same
[Music]
rhythm. That is just such an incredibly
magical moment that I've never
experienced anywhere else. For more MIT
moments from MIT Open Learning, like,
subscribe, or