He is a uh principal investigator in MIT
pro probabilistic computing project. He
is going to explore
uh probabilistic computing approach
alternative to deep learning to build
machines that can learn and think with
people. Let's welcome
uh Minka. I'm sorry. It's okay. Thank
you. Hi
everybody. Very happy to be here. Now,
maybe like some of you, I grew up loving
science fiction that prominently
featured AI. There was a vision that we
could somehow have artificial
agents who were embodying some of the
highest human ideals. you know, not just
that they were rational, but
superhumanly informed and helpful. And
even AI villains, uh, like here I'm
showing Lieutenant Commander Data's evil
twin lore, could at least be counted on
to be rationally self-interested.
But the place we are today in this early
emergence of probabistic computing and
AI, still very much the beginning, is we
have systems that fail to live up to the
basic norms of rationality that science
fiction and also cognitive science have
been exploring for a long
time. In highstakes deployments from
some of the world's best AI companies,
where engineers have worked hard to
prevent failure, it so far hasn't been
possible.
I think it's helpful to reflect on the
quality of the failure modes that we're
seeing from machine learning
systems. Some of you may have
experienced failure modes like this in
your own
vehicle, but I think it's important to
reflect on the analogy to human
intelligence that's causing us to
chuckle here. If a human driver was
seeing a sequence of fluctuating
hallucinations, we might not want them
behind the wheel, especially if they
didn't think anything was wrong. Right?
There's no alarm bells going off in the
Tesla's cabin.
And in fact uh this has led to uh this
kind of failure mode has led to both
significant fatalities and as one of the
cost drivers in the autonomous vehicle
industry. You know the the mistakes that
these systems make are mistakes that
would not be made by uh even a human
child behind the wheel if they were
sober and paying
attention.
Um so let's dig a little bit deeper.
What's really going on with these kinds
of failure modes of machine learning? In
fact, you can see the same kinds of
errors in classic games of strategy. So,
many of you may know that the world's
best go players today are AI systems.
But you may not know that there's simple
camouflage that you can teach a human
amateur, an amateur who's beaten by
human pros and soundly beaten by Go AI
players normally. But the go the go AIs
cannot see through that camouflage. So,
an amateur like me, having learned the
camouflage, will beat superhuman Go
players. The Go AI can't see the
configuration in front of its face, much
like the Tesla can't see the overturned
bus. So, what's really going on? What's
the gap between rationality at the core
of intelligence and today's
AI? The roots are in the discipline of
machine learning and the enormous power
it's brought to scaling AI, but also the
cracks in that theory. So we've been
building larger and larger end toend
train neural networks using enormous
advances in parallel compute uh GPUs,
TPUs, deep learning stacks like PyTorch,
Jacks and TensorFlow which automate the
math of deep learning and massive data
sets including the common crawl, large
simulations and sticky product loops
designed us to keep us feeding the
machine learning systems the data they
need. then training them end to end to
try to produce these
systems. But I have to
acknowledge as someone who uh teaches
machine learning methods on occasion
here that we don't entirely understand
how these machine learning systems are
working. There's something alchemical
about
it and that raises the question, what
better technological foundations are
needed to deliver on the dreams of
rationality and AI?
At MIT and especially at the Seagull
family quest for intelligence, we've
been pursuing a different approach.
We're building engineered rational by
design AI that constructs world models
that are coherent and used rationally by
construction where let's say the sensory
information about a room like this is
parsed into a hierarchical multiscale
symbolic model that coheres with both
our common sense unlike the entangled
representations inside a neural network
and also with the world is revealed by
science which validates the intuitive
perception that at some level there are
objects in space out there, not just
activations uh in some
transformer. Now, in fact, even human
children robustly develop generalizable
world models. There's a slightly
troubling genre on YouTube of uh
children and non-human primates, it
turns out, uh driving golf carts. And
while one might question the judgment
calls of all of the primates involved in
making these videos, um, we would be
shocked if they couldn't see the road in
front of them, right? If they failed the
way that the Teslas did. And of course,
there's deep biological reasons for
this. The ability to construct robust,
rational models of the world is an
evolutionarily ancient necessity.
Even small fish swimming around needed
to see their prey and accurately locate
them in three dimensions without
hallucination so that they could eat
enough to survive and
reproduce. You know, without robust
rational perception, it's unclear that
the evolutionary ratchet could even have
gotten started. Now, when you hear the
narrative that what deep learning is
doing is evolutionary scale compute, I
think it's actually worth considering
how much less efficient and effective
than evolution it actually is. Now,
that's not to say that deep learning
methods don't have a role to play, a
crucial tool in the broader probabistic
computing toolkit for scaling software
and inference far beyond the scales
we're used to today. But at MIT, we see
it located within a broader framework of
toolkits for engineering rational by
design AI that crucially have to exploit
scale parallel compute in many of the
same ways deep learning did, but to go
beyond it by applying it to modular,
interpretable, and in some cases
symbolic and engineered representations.
And our research moonshots at the Quest
for intelligence are pursuing that
program using modular learning from
human scale data. So learning much more
like the efficiency that you and I learn
and using comparisons, quantitative
comparisons between AI systems and human
behavior in comparable
worlds. And the key technical innovation
enabling us to scale this approach is an
emerging field called proistic
programming which unifies the symbolic,
probabilistic and neural or
differentiable approaches to
computation.
So many of us may be familiar with the
power of the symbolic and neural
components. In fact, compilers like
TensorFlow and PyTorch and Jax are
really paralyzing symbolic
representation frameworks for
differentiable or neural computation.
Right? You don't train neural nets using
neural nets. You train them using
symbolic programs that manage the
parallelism. Um, but of course there's a
much broader sphere of methods that are
needed for rationality, including
decision theory, the ability to weigh
risk and reward, to make guesses given
incomplete information. And it turns out
those can be integrated with the
symbolic and the
differentiable. And over the years, uh,
we've sort of been climbing up the
ladders of scale with this approach. Um,
so I've been working in this area for
about 20 years. uh but it's really only
in the last few years we turned an
inflection point and started early
projects with Google to demonstrate
scale time series forecasting and 3D
scene perception using this approach uh
dduplicating and linking and cleaning
databases with millions of records like
the US Medicare physicians registry um
and there have been a number of startup
companies that have become part of the
business intelligence industry so far
and then a new one in gaming uh started
recently uh that have been
commercializing this approach and so
feel free to talk to me about uh the
spectrum of industry applications for
people who are
interested. Just to make sure we have a
concrete view of probabistic programming
here, what you're seeing is data
streaming in one point at a time. And on
the right, you're seeing the symbolic
source code for a probabistic model
that's being edited by two probabistic
programs working together. One that
defines a space of possible models and
then the other one that explores that
space guessing and testing against each
data point incrementally. Here is
probabic program building a map in real
time of one of uh from data from one of
the floors in the computer science and
AI lab at
MIT. Probleistic programs can detect and
correct errors and hallucinations in
neural net object detectors like you're
seeing here. Uh so for example, you
know, we know that it's unphysical to
have a bottle floating sideways in
midair and that fails to explain the
actual image of the bottle. The neural
net can't handle that, but the
probabistic program
can. And inside the box, crucially, are
representations and inference processes,
which unlike the entangled weights of
transformers, we understand and can
engineer. Now, the pendulum swings often
by decade in computer science. And in
this moment, this approach might seem to
be out of favor. But for people who were
around at the beginning of deep
learning, I just want to invite you to
consider how foreign the idea of
learning representations was at scale
just 10 or 15 years ago. And then what
happened as parallel compute was
unlocked in service of that hypothesis.
Well, I think we may be at a similar
moment for representations that have
been rationally engineered. Here you can
see there's a graphics model inside the
system and the system's exploring small
edits that you could imagine making
yourself with a graphics engine editor
just way faster than you could do by
hand. And ultimately that's how the
system's fitting 3D models to data. And
in fact it turns out this approach is
just beginning to scale to open world
video. So here I'm showing real RGB
in-depth video captured from an iPad uh
by my wonderful student George who did a
lot of this research most recently along
with Nashad and a stochastic
reconstruction in terms of an
explainable Gausian representation where
the resolution is automatically
adjusting as the objects move closer or
farther from the camera.
Uh and at the Quest for intelligence
we've been building larger scale models
of human perception based on
representations like this. So consider
the fact that our eyes and perceptual
systems can connect the dots from sparse
patterns where neural nets can may not
be able to see
anything. These are some of the
capacities we think rationally
engineered representations will unlock
in
perception. But what about expert
systems and databases? Maybe that's a
topic of interest to some of you here
from industry. A couple of my startups
over the years have worked in this area.
Well, here I'm showing four different
databases and I'm showing real data in
one color and synthetic data from
learned probabistic programs in another
color. And so what you can see is we can
learn probabistic models from data that
accurately capture not just the main
effects but the heterogeneity in the
tails but also the error bars and the
inferial uncertainty that's associated
with rigorous reasoning from
data. And this leads to an interesting
project. Would it be possible to build a
model of the global human population
that uses probabistic inference to join
across massive disperate data sources
that don't share primary keys? A common
asset to accelerate research and
clinical
trials. This kind of thing can't really
be done with deep learning because we
need to be able to audit what
information flows through different
parts of the model and we need to be
able to quantify uncertainty where data
is sparse. But with probabistic
programs, we have the technical
foundations that are needed to do that.
And if you think about the sparity of
this kind of data where there aren't
primary keys, that's what I'm showing
here on the slide, you can see that LLMs
and tool use don't solve the problem.
You somehow need a model that fills in
all the gaps in the actual data we have
and reasons in a coherent, rigorously
grounded, probabilistically calibrated
way. And we need to be able to talk to
it in English. So one of the systems we
built recently maps from English claims
or queries like show age and gender for
people who are Democrat voters to parse
trees which can parse out different
meanings of the phrase right does
democrat voter mean registered democrats
or people who identify as Democrats just
for
example or let's take an application
that many of us may have uh some family
experience for a family member just gets
an unfortunate diagnosis and now we want
to know okay what are what what's the
person's likely
prognosis. Well, with this kind of
approach, we can get automated
uncertainty calibrated prognosis even in
realms where the data is sparse. Like
for example, many cancer patients are
older than most clinical trial
populations in cancer. So there's a
challenging statistical inference to do
off sample to be able to deliver a
capability like
this. And at the Quest for Intelligence,
we're also using the same approach to
try to reverse engineer much more
foundational aspects of human common
sense. Our ability to ground language
and models of the world or um as in work
by my wonderful student Shen, our
ability to generate behavior that helps
other people, machines that really learn
and think with us. So here you can see a
famous video from developmental
psychology where this adult is doing
some kind of puzzling thing and this
toddler spontaneously generates very
helpful
behavior even though the adult was
clearly failing to achieve their
goals. And uh my student Shen and others
have been working on applying this kind
of approach to make much better natural
language assistance and to resolve some
of the safety challenges we're starting
to encounter uh with increasingly common
agents that we might not want to entrust
let's say to make credit card
transactions on our
behalf. So Shen has done work that's
already been tested in virtual worlds
and one of the next phases is to try to
bring it into the real
one. Okay. So zooming out over the last
many decades actually all scale compute
has been increasingly probabilistic from
networks to the early web and data
science to modern neural network
systems. But what if we could start to
pursue aworked modular rational scaling
route for AI where the components were
designed rather than relying entirely on
learning? Maybe there would there would
be a way to do it without necessarily
centralizing so much uh within just a
few AI
labs. Okay. Um uh thank you. Um all this
work was done in collaboration with many
wonderful students and engineers. Um uh
anyway I'm happy to take some is is
there time for
questions? Maybe not. Okay. Thank
you question. Okay. Great.
Great. So, one question, can we truly
achieve predicting position and velocity
simultaneously using a single camera
akin to having stereoscopic vision?
Yeah, it's a beautiful question. Um,
yeah, so the quest for intelligence is
working on this in its perceptual
intelligence mission, both trying to
build models of humans ability to do
this and also use that as the basis for
more capable machine perception systems.
And one of the hypotheses we're testing
which I showed you some early results
from is engineered representations as
compared to learn transformers. Um so
yeah that's exactly the one of the types
of questions we think is current. And
I'll say more generally by the way since
this is an industry audience. The quest
for intelligence is engaging with
corporate member companies. My lab has
done that quite frequently over the
years to field test early versions of
these capabilities and help to discover
where the differential edges really are
with pure deep learning systems versus
what are the cases like in our language
understanding work where we use hybrids
of probabistic programming and deep
learning and we're actually
experimenting with both um using open
source platforms that have been
developed here at MIT. So that's a way
where some of your questions could get
tested maybe with a little more vigor uh
than uh just the discussion we can have
here.
Okay. World models are said to be
essential for the practical use of
humanoid robots. What do you see as the
main possibilities and challenges in
their real world implementation? Yeah,
great question.
Um,
well, okay, I think the possibilities
are fairly easy to imagine in broad
terms if we could really have robots
that had world models with the
incredible scale and flexibility of our
own world models.
So I think one challenge, one question
is will deep learning really be able to
produce such world models merely by
adding more data and compute or maybe
even also inference time compute or will
those scaling
curves prove economically prohibitive.
Second challenge for the thesis we're
presenting is how will we scale up
engineered rational representations that
can be much more data efficient to have
broad
coverage. So we have some interesting
early evidence that it's possible to
scale engineered rational
representations much farther than people
thought even just a couple years ago and
I think testing that out will be one of
the main activities of the quest for
intelligence and also industry partners
over the coming years.
Thank you very much.