I'm Cara Miller and I'm Rob Stoner and
this is what if it
[Music]
works from the MIT energy initiative
this is what if it works a podcast
looking at the energy solutions for
climate change I'm Cara Miller you might
know me from the public radio program
Innovation Hub which I hosted I now
write the big idea column for the Boston
Globe and I'm Robert Stoner the
president of the Kendall Square project
and former director of the MIT energy
initiative and today we're going to talk
about how science can give rise to
companies and how we can only fully
achieve our societal goals if those
companies and governments can work
together but first a little story to
illustrate this sort of Journey in the
1970s and ' 80s three scientists started
doing work that would ultimately de
decades later earned them a Nobel Prize
their work was with a very unstable
element an element that easily catches
on fire lithium but what they discovered
was this you can make a battery with
lithium a battery that as it turned out
had some commercial uses what uses Well
that took a bit of time to figure out I
think initially they're like thinking of
cell phones or thinking of little stuff
right even getting to work at all but by
about 2000 it became apparent that
actually you could make a car that used
a lithium ion battery and it would be
way better than a golf cart using lead
asid batteries for sure that's Bill
Green the director of the MIT energy
initiative and a chemical engineering
professor at MIT so people started to
think oh maybe this is a real thing and
some companies started manufacturing
them and you could buy them but the
performance was not as good as the
gasoline cars the cost was much higher
and so it was just a little niche thing
and not too long after it became clear
that yeah maybe you could use these
batteries for cars an American company
started that would eventually use
lithium ion batteries to power its
electric cars the company was founded in
2003 by two Engineers Mark tarpening and
Martin eard but they would eventually
leave and one of its most prolific
fundraisers Elon Musk ultimately became
its
CEO right around the time that musk
became CEO of Tesla in 2008 the US
Department of energy gave the company
nearly half a billion dollars in loans
to scale up this whole electric vehicle
thing you know the government hadn't
decided that this is what's going to
happen and it wasn't clear because
nobody knew what the real prices were
going to be in the future but anyway
they gave it a try and the Tesla example
worked out well also in China some
companies did a nice job making some
nice electric vehicles and once those
vehicles in the last decade those
vehicles started coming out and people
saw wow these actually do perform well
they do have good reliability
maintenance costs aren't too high and
this actually looks like it's really
going to happen and then you can see
once they get mass produced the costs
start going down because the engineers
figure out more and more clever ways to
manufacture them the supply chain gets
to be better for all everything needed
and so that's why by 2019 we actually
had a thing green says this is where the
rubber meets the road so to speak it
took a long some time about four decades
between the time that chemists realized
that you could use a form of lithium in
a battery and the time when you and I
started seeing a lot of Teslas and so
maybe more than 40 years from invention
to the full scale deployment that really
affects the climate that's the way it is
right now so I think you know everyone
involved we want it to happen faster
right we needed to be faster to meet our
Net Zero targets and so have to figure
out how can we make the steps faster all
the way on the chain that green thinks
is the work ahead of us that is the work
of the energy transition the move
towards cleaner sources of energy how do
we bring scientists and universities and
governments and Industry together to
make a 40-year process a little or maybe
a lot faster I think there's like a
systemic issue that at the beginning you
need a lot of different scientists and
Engineers trying to make the discoveries
and trying to find the manifestations of
them that really have a chance
to be practical affordable attractive to
people and then you need a lot of people
to work in the startup companies and
this in the early stages of a business
to develop it further and further to get
it to be really good and then you need
at some point there has to be a
consensus that this is what we're doing
and then the government policy will come
and really support the widespread
deployment because all sudden you scale
from you know millions and tens of
millions of dollars kind of scale to
hundreds of billions scale to make a
full scale deployment that's going to
affect the climate so that's really
massive investment decisions and so you
need to have very low risk on those big
decisions so you need the government to
be involved to sort of support the thing
coming in it has to be well demonstrated
people have to show that they like it so
it's really going to be a real Market
but once you reach that point things can
happen pretty fast because the big
investors then will come in because they
see oh there's a guaranteed way to make
some money and here's a side note we're
in a global race to produce cleaner
technology
faster and better you could say that's a
win-win for everybody but there are
downsides to the US falling behind which
might be happening in the realm of
electric
vehicles chines were willing to spend
real money on it I we all owe kind of a
debt to the Chinese government of taking
the early risk because it was not clear
when they started investing that it was
really going to work that well and going
to be attractive but they made a big bet
that that was going to happen I would
say that actually we similarly we owe
the German government a lot of kudos for
the development of solar cells they gave
a really big subsidy for photo voltaics
and that led to the development of
gigantic industry also mostly in China
but fundamentally that was being
supported by the German government to do
it and it came to the benefit of
everybody in the world that we now we
all have cheap solar sales and we're
going to need to come up with Greener
Alternatives for lots of industrial
processes like making cement and steel
and all the other things that make our
lives look the way they do but what if
China ends up scaling up all those
Technologies like they've done with
electric vehicles and solar cells Bill
Green says that might not be an optimal
solution I think as a researcher it's
super beneficial if there's
Manufacturing in your field in your
country so then you naturally have
people in your country who are working
on manufacturing stuff and if you're
trying to make an innovation that's
related to that manufacturing you can
have good Communications with the people
make the manufacturing and so I think
it's a shame that the foldable take
business all went to China I don't know
exactly the whole story about how that
happened but I think it was it's really
unfortunate because in the US we
actually had a lot of the key
researchers and we still do have a lot
of the key researchers in F Vol TX
having Manufacturing in the US means
that budding scientists and Engineers
can work more closely with companies
they can intern they can have speakers
from the companies come to their classes
in essence proximity matters and says
green no matter the country government
matters a lot if you just have the free
market it is not going to happen very
very slowly because fossil fuels are
cheap and there's no reason just
economically there's no reason to move
away from them it's completely because
we're trying to protect the climate
stabilize the climate that we're going
to do it therefore it's it's got to be
government regulation subsidies tax
have got to be driving it and government
investment research too normally when we
we have something that I don't know a
new um a new cell phone we don't feel
it's the government's role to play much
of a part in there they might have
actually supported some basic research
that led to some new kind of chip or
something but fundamentally it's mostly
the free market and it just moves at the
pace that the free market moves at and
how some people can make some money and
that's and and it works out for us
because we all get these nice cell
phones right but in this particular case
every year of delay is more years with
billions of tons of CO2 accumulating in
the atmosphere and the climate
changing and so it's it's a societal
need to move faster and so just working
the old way is not really appropriate
for the for this kind of innovation so
so yay for government yay for the
international you know CO2 reduction
process Paris agreement but you're
sitting here running an industrial
Consortium at MIT one that I used to run
it talk a little bit about how you see
its role and the RO of Industry yeah so
a very key part of this is at the end
there's somebody who's doing the
gigantic deployment at the hundreds of
billions of dollars scale to really make
climate impact that somebody is going to
be a company it's not going to be the
government providing you electricity or
selling you a car right somebody there's
going to be some gigantic Corporation
that's providing
reliably the new good that you get
that's now clean and working out all the
The Kinks that how to do that and so the
companies are definitely going to be
involved by the end and the MIT energy
initiative point of view is that we
should start from the beginning get the
companies involved helping to provide
some of the funding for the research
paying attention to the research as it's
going and starting to see early if
suppose we have somebody wants to do a
startup company maybe the big company
wants to keep in eye on it maybe they
want to make a small investment in it
then they might be ready to to take it
over and and scale it up when the thing
is really ready and I think that that's
a way we can help the whole thing along
also the students at MIT most of them
are going to go work for these companies
that are making these Innovations and so
it makes perfect sense for the companies
to be interested in the development of
their future Workforce and it makes
perfect sense for the MIT students to
want to try internships and try to check
check out these companies and see if
they want to work for them and so I
think there's like multiple reasons why
we should be working together on it and
the companies are trying you know at
least some of the companies are really
trying to make their best plan for how
they're going to do the transition they
have some amount of R&D capacity inside
the companies but most of them don't
have R&D capacity like MIT does and so
we can really help them with with pieces
where they don't have internal strength
or is a double check on their own
internal r&t and so I think there a lot
of ways that MIT can be beneficial to
them and of course the companies be
beneficial to MIT they help us to keep
focusing on problems that are real not
just academic problems but problems that
are really potentially going to have
real impact on the world and they can
provide some of the funding to make it
happen and so I think there's like a lot
of mutual benefit from working together
all right I have a couple questions one
is just about the role of big companies
so we talked about the role of
government in terms of like funding a
lab and getting the science started but
then you know we talked about the on
musk saying well this is kind of a small
company but going to fund this Factory
to see some Teslas roll off the line
here and what they look like and people
drive them and so on but it sounds like
you're saying but then when you get to
this point where you've
got something that you need to really
roll out at scale it's going to be an
apple or a Toyota or you know X on
mobile or whatever that's going to that
has billions of dollars and like the and
networks all over the world to be able
to actually do this yes yeah yeah
definitely okay so then this leads me to
my second question which is people who
run those companies are judged I mean
stocks trade every day you know all
those companies that I talked about are
traded um so you know they are focused
on quarterly earnings and earnings calls
and it seems to me that when you talk
even if you could compress a 45-year
Time transition like with EVS to 20
years or 15 years or whatever I mean you
you wouldn't be around as a CEO for
three years if you didn't produce so how
do you think how do people who run these
companies think about long time frames
when I mean their jobs are like on the
line all the time yeah this is really
difficult right the incentive structure
in many parts of our economy and in this
particular one are like often mismatched
with what the society really wants and I
see it with the companies I interact
with um that
some of the companies have decided
forget it I'm just going to run for the
maximum profit today I'm going to kill
my R&D Department I'm not going to worry
about the future and I'm just going to
run the assets I have today and maximize
the amount of money I get from them and
buy back the stock or whatever I can do
to make my stock option longterm people
this is the oil and gas industry well
oil and gas but not just oil and gas I
think all over and inside oil gas
there's a split so actually most of the
companies don't have R&D anymore and
basically that's the way they're
operating that're just're running down
our assets I think if you go to Coal
companies it's even more like this um
they don't they don't have research and
development to think like what is a new
product going to be right they basically
decide they're just going to cash out
the company when coal is no longer
nobody wants to buy coal anymore they're
going to close the company okay you're G
to stop exploring they'll drill till
they can drill or they'll mine till they
can not mine anymore and then they're
done okay they're done right and then
you know and they're just basically
cashing out the company and that's
that's one strategy but then there's
other companies the ones that come to
MIT to support research they typically
are still running R&D arms their idea is
we're going to still be a viable company
after our main product is no longer
bought by anybody and so we're going to
have a plan B plan a is we're making a
lot of money now it satisfies our
shareholders background plan is we're
making the plan B so that when we can't
do it that way we're going to have a new
product and we're going to still make a
lot of money with our new product and
we're going to be the supplier and we're
taking advantage that we have this huge
organization knows how to do gigantic
projects has a lot of cap a lot of cash
flow has a lot of Engineers and we think
that in the future there's going to be a
need for big projects that use a lot of
cash flow and need a lot of Engineers
and so we'll be ready to be the supplier
for that and they're trying to explore
like how can we actually monetize our
capacity our abilities that we have in
the company but instead of selling Oil
we're going to sell CO2 sequestration or
we're going to sell hydrogen or you you
know they have a lot of different ideas
of what they want to do and um and the
different companies are all making
different decisions about this because
partly as you said the CEO incentives
are not that well aligned with the
long-term stuff so it's almost like that
the cios make their own decision kind of
free actually from the stakeholder
pressures because most of the
shareholders just care about they get
the dividend and the stock price goes up
right but a lot of the CEOs feel some
obligation to keep the company together
as a viable concern they're proud of
their company they have a lot of their
friends or employees there and they want
it to be a Running Company and and they
want uh they have grandchildren too and
they want the climate problem to be
solved and so a bunch of them are
putting money into trying to find how
that can
happen those companies have a lot of
capacity so if they really do it they
can be very very beneficial at speeding
up the timelines you know the the the
deployment if you had to start from a
startup I have a little startup if my
little startup with it six employees has
to somehow replace you know 10 billion
tons of CO2 per year it's like there's
no way right it's like you know we're
struggling just to raise $10 million I
had to raise a hundred billion that's
like a completely different thing right
and so um if we had to wait for me it's
going to be more than 40 years before my
small company can solve the the world's
problems but the big companies if one of
the big companies decides oh I can see I
can make some money doing this
environmentally beneficial thing they
can scale it like in one year to you
know gigantic scale that that a small
company could almost never do and so I
think I think we have to hope that some
of the big companies are really going to
do that it's also important that that in
the US we have most of the companies are
shareholder controlled but around the
world a lot of the energy companies are
actually controlled by the governments
that they're located in and the
governments have a very complicated set
of
stakeholders and they their citizens
many of them want climate change to be
on the agenda and so those companies
face a different pressures um and so in
in some countries the same company that
drills for oil is also the same company
that puts in the Solar Vol photovoltaics
it's putting in the electric vehicle
Chargers they're putting in the
windmills they're doing the whole thing
the the government says you're our
Energy company do everything we want and
and that's what they're doing and I
think putting all the companies together
in one pot and thinking they're all the
same I think is really not accurate at
all yeah I think that's a really good
point but among those companies whose
whose capital budgets are stressed
because they're being pushed into these
other areas the BPS and the shells the
Ecco
patrols their exploration budgets are
declining yes and so there sort of
facing a future in which they can't be
oil and gas companies
anymore is that because is that because
like of well they have to acquire
somebody
else's Assets in order to be able to
continue producing because they'll
eventually exhaust their their proven
resources it's just that's just because
they're getting to the end of how much
oil is in those Wells yeah they spend a
lot of money every year looking for more
and figuring out ways to get at oil that
maybe at depth or maybe under the under
under a part of the ocean that's
inaccessible or the North uh in areas
that are inaccessible trying to figure
out how to get it you're quite right I
mean in some of these companies there's
certain amount of research going on
still that pushes those those boundaries
but in others there's retrenchment on
the one hand it's you know yay yay for
renewable energies and the energy
transition on the other hand it's like
oh my God we could get to a point where
we either don't have enough of those
things to continue running the economy
as we run it now and we Face higher
prices and maybe a big economic
downturn or something's going to have to
happen on the renewable side to enable
transition actually the very tricky
thing of the transition is that we all
want to still have transportation we all
want to still be able to get an airplane
and go for a vacation we all want
electricity come in our house and so
that's actually a higher want than our
want for a clean climate right and so
however we do the energy transition it
has to continue to reliably provide all
those services that everybody relies on
and in fact you could kill people if if
you screw it up you know if all a sudden
you ban the trucks and nobody can bring
the food from the farms you could have a
famine it's a lot of bad things could
happen this makes it super tricky
because it's like we have to maintain
the exist existing fossil fuel based uh
infrastructure and at the same time
build the new infrastructure that's
going to replace it and then of course
from the point of view people who own
the different things the economic pros
and cons can be wildly crazy right that
you know that the from the point of view
of the consumers of electricity in
Illinois you really might want to have a
lot of solar cells they have plenty of
land there and you can put a lot of phot
voltaics out it might be really great
for cleaning up the environment but then
the utilities might also own Some Coal
power plants and they're like oh my
goodness
we're we're losing our Capital asset we
have to spend all this extra Capital by
these solar cells and so they're like
well then we want to raise the rates but
then the the citizens of Illinois might
say wow I don't want to pay so much
money for electricity so there's like a
lot of conflicts and I think it's the
companies are have internal conflicts
between the incumbent technology and
bringing the new one and each of us as
consumers have a conflict between that
we're basically using fossil fuel
technology now and we want to make sure
we keep on getting the goods that we
want but also want the transition to
happen the only way we can conquer this
is we have to do it together as a
collective action that a society has to
say this is what we're doing we're going
to make regulations and taxes to make
sure that we satisfy all these needs of
maintaining the services that we need
and at the same time cleaning them up
and providing the the resources needed
to make that really happen if we just
say it's going to happen and we don't
actually put the resources in it's not
really going to happen it's just a
statement and and if we make regulations
that shut things down before we have the
replacement there's going to be like
[Music]
chaos so Bill you you had talked before
about this but in many ways you know you
kind of bring together uh companies and
Academia and people in government and
you talked about the need for a higher
level of urgency than we had when we
were going through the EV transition do
you really sense that people have that
level of urgency or maybe it needs to be
even higher I think the political will
actually I saw polling from Republican
party people that the political will on
both sides of the aisle in the United
States is in favor of cleaning up the
climate and if you go around the world
that's why all the countries support the
Paris agreement even a bunch of
countries that you know autocrats in
charge they still signed on because they
know their citizens really want the
climate to be stabilized right and also
they see the problems they're going to
have famines they're going to have
floods they're going to have all kinds
of trouble so they can see like it's
really better for our country to to
support the Paris agreement so there's
agreement at that level I think it's
when you get down to the nitty-gritty of
you know who's paying exactly for this
and how inconvenient is for me um that
then you you'll have people start to
resist and and for people who lose their
jobs it's even more extreme right if you
say well sorry the coal mines are closed
um all the people in the coal mining
town are going to be really mad right
and so we have to figure out how do we
you know help to compensate people how
to to cover how to make this the whole
transition work but I think the same we
have the same problem in Many Things Not
Just Energy so housing is a big thing
for Boston area right if you talk to
anybody for for the US I would say
housing shortage is really c yeah so
from one point of view you can say I
think if you ask people do you think we
should have more housing the rent should
be lower I think it'd be like 90% of
people say yes right then you say okay
will you allow the lot on the corner
there to become an apartment building
instead of being a couple small houses
and most people in the town say no it's
be ugly I hate apartment buildings right
okay so it's it's the same kind of thing
it's like that the we agree in principle
that there's a problem and we need to
address it but then when people propose
specific
Solutions uh people have resistance and
I think in the energy space where you
see it a lot is about cost so that if
the replacement is cheap enough we're
cool with it so no I didn't hear anybody
really complain about the switch of from
incandescent light bulbs to LED light
bulbs you have to be like a crank to
complain about that there were some
cranks there were some cranks okay there
always are I mean um uh but you know if
if you go to EVS now you hear people a
little bit more resistant part of it is
that the EVS are more expensive right
now and and it's going to take some
public money to put in public Chargers
and stuff like that but uh I think that
that as the price of the EVS go down
you're going to see people that today
would say I'll never buy an EV if the EV
is $5,000 cheaper and you and you don't
have to BU pay for gas then I think a
lot of people might say ah I guess I'll
you know I said I wasn't going to buy an
EV but I think I'm G to buy it now right
so I think the price is a key part and
it's the same thing why we have the coal
power plants is 100% an economic thing
right and and so if we can get the
prices of the new technologies to be
close enough then it's much easier to
convince people to go along with the
change and so you know the engineers and
the and the industry guys have a lot of
work to do to try to get the
Technologies to be affordable reliable
practical not annoying to use um so then
then the society will say okay that
sounds great and then once the society
says it's fine then the government
Regulators are happy to come in and make
it and require it because it's like uh
it's requiring what people want anyway
yeah I mean there these heroic things
that that are going to happen in the
future I think you know things like
fusion and you know I'm I'm all for them
and it's exciting and very much worth
funding but if you can delay that time
until we absolutely need them and until
we need to start spending money on
adaptation that is you
know changing changing where people live
changing you know
coastlines enormous expenditures that
we're going to have to make if you can
delay that uh it it's a much much
cheaper much safer transition and so you
know I'm really much in favor of of
doing more I think toward incremental
very near term things than I think
probably probably we're we're doing
right now yeah if you were you know
optimistically thinking here's how I
would script this scenario of who needs
to work together and how they need to do
it what would happen well it's not
happening like right this second okay so
I think there's a separation we have
some technologies that are really ready
and it's it's all about doing the
deployment and working out some details
about the regulations and so you know
photovoltaics and windmills for
electricity is really ready okay and
it's but it's like you know it's like
zoning and permits for power lines and
you know and details about who's going
to how exactly we're going to handle the
uh intermittency of the electrical power
so there there's definitely things to
work on there but it's like it's like
more like you just put some money on it
you say this is the policy we're doing
it it could really happen more solar
cells more windmills and I think the EV
is it's very much like that too it's
like the EV deployment we're doing now
is going to work great for people who
have their own garage or their own
driveway and they can put their own
charger in and that's I think we're
already on the way that that's just
going to happen and you don't have to do
anything but if we want to get them in
for all the apartment buildings and
condos and we want to you know help
people who can't afford the capital cost
and we're going to make sure enough
Chargers are on the highway so people
are happy to use them that that that's
some more money is gonna be needed and
it's GNA you know so there's like a A
Part B of the EV roll out but again it's
like we know what to do it's like just
getting people to do it right then
there's other ones like are those people
in the government or are those people in
companies well if the companies have to
do it the government if they set the
regulation the incentives right up the
the the free market will do it because
the technology exists but if they don't
do it the companies are not in a
business to make a loss they're not
gonna they're not going to do it so you
can see with the charger companies right
now that the the setup doesn't really
encourage them they don't make any money
on Chargers and therefore they're not
putting any more Chargers in and it's
like somehow they've got to the
rules so that somebody can make some
money running the Chargers and then
they'll put them in okay now partly it's
like as more EVS come in there'll be
more demand for the Chargers and that
will help them make some money but I
think it's probably needs some
examination about what the rules are for
the Chargers to make it work and
similarly for apartment buildings you
have to figure out what the heck the
rules are about who puts a charger in
the parking lot and uh I I have no idea
but
it's legislature or the Town Council
whoever's in charge of it's got to start
working on it because it's going to be
like on your doorstep you know four
years from now and ideally you have the
solution already worked out and you've
already discussed it with all the
neighbors and it's all ready to go and
if you don't it could be 10 years in the
courts but then we have other
Technologies we we don't have solutions
for so I'm working right now on ethylene
um trying to figure out how we can
replace the process that we use to make
ethylene so there's many materials that
we use high temperature heat right now
to make them so cement steel certain
types of plastics a a bunch of things
and right now we don't really have a
comparably cost solution for providing
that heat so right now people do it with
natural gas or with coal it's super
cheap to provide high temperature heat
burning some coal burning some natural
gas but if you're going to switch to
some other way all the ways we have
right now are too expensive or or
considerably more expensive so you'd
have to use very strong government
regulation to force people to switch or
we have to invent technology that's more
affordable so that's one where we're at
still at the point where the engineers
have to figure out like do we have a
real solution here that can work um can
we demonstrate it convince the industry
that this is going to work and then if
you can convince them you get some demos
then the government might feel like I
can impose the regulation you have to do
it but if it's not demonstrated they're
not going to force the industry to
change um so I think we have a split and
and you can look through all the
different Technologies of where we are
and some of them really need University
Research at the the scientists some of
them need some Engineers maybe maybe
University maybe National Lab maybe some
company guys but better coordination
better funding to really push it along
um and uh so I'm I'm very optimistic
about the ones where we already have the
technology in hand and um some of the
other Technologies I can see that we're
making good progress and I'm optimistic
about them and there's some of them
where we just need a lot more work to
get there this problem is being
approached systematically I mean just
for the benefit of our listeners I mean
it's not sort of
hopeless I was wondering that when you
said like oh we need a lot of heat to
make steel and so on um are like
scientists all over the place um have
they been sort of deployed to deal with
this or is it just like well if you're
interested go go check it out but you
know so so in steel for example the the
companies are super interested okay um
and so they're they have their is
working like crazy to try to find it
like a lot of Steel banking companies
are still in Europe and they got very
strict regulations coming down the pike
and they got to do something so they're
really motivated and we have University
researchers who see it but there's a lot
more obscure industrial processes that
don't have a big constituency for them
that are all still going to need
attention um they need cheerleaders to
be like how about this industrial
process can we make it better yeah
exactly and they need you know some
funding stream to support them to work
on it often you need the industry to be
involved to even teach you about the
process you know what you're really
working on and we you know at Mighty
we've done some of that but I think
there's a lot more opportunities for
doing that part of it is we need the
connections with the right companies and
the companies had to be motivated to
work on that process some of it we need
to teach the government people about the
different processes so they'll they'll
decide to make some funding streams
available to work on them but but I
think it's it's it's possible to do it
it's not and and the big ones of Steel
and cement for example they two of the
biggest there's already quite big
efforts I think for steel people have a
pretty good idea how to do it I'm not so
sure about the story about cement but
they're they're definitely working in
the lab at MIT on it and there's some
startup companies trying to do it people
want it to be simple you know they want
the silver bullet and it's going to
solve all the problems and I'm sorry
it's just that's not the way the world
is the world's complicated and you know
it's our economy is complicated there's
a ton of companies and a ton of people
doing different jobs all over the world
and basically almost every company and
every job and every person is being
affected by this change and of course
it's complicated and so I think I think
we should just embrace it it is
complicated and we have a lot of smart
people to work on it and we just need to
you know smooth things out and make that
that work more efficient so we can make
it not 40 years but make it 20 years and
then I think we in good
shape the world is complicated but we're
here to explain it to you Bill Green is
the director of the MIT energy
initiative he's a chemical engineering
professor at MIT Bill thank you so much
thank you it's been a pleasure thanks
[Music]
Bill what if it works is a production of
the MIT energy initiative if you like
the show please leave us a review or
invite a friend to listen and remember
to subscribe on Apple podcast Spotify or
wherever you get your
podcast you can find an archive of every
episode all of our show notes and a lot
more at energy . mit.edu
podcasts and you can learn more about
the work of the energy initiative and
the energy transition at energy. mit.edu
our original podcast artwork is by
zeitler Design special thanks to all the
people at Mighty and MIT who make this
show possible I'm Cara Miller and I'm
Rob Stoner thanks for listening
[Music]