Okay. So last time uh we uh we talked
about
um in particular we talked about two
things. We talked about the cushy
uh convergence here.
So the cushy convergence theorem says
that any any cushy sequence
uh is convergent.
Right? So this is one thing we talked
quite a bit about last time. uh and we
proved it but we proved it assuming
another theorem. So we showed it the
proof
proof used
the also bas
now now
the person bias theorem. So that's the
following.
So this is the following theorem
that say that any bounded
any bounded
sequence
A end has a convergent subsequence
and let's call it a and k. Okay, that
was the balsano vra theorem. So using
this remember the cushi convergence
theorem the proof then went like this
that if you take a cushi sequence then
it was easy to prove that it was bounded
then you use the balsano vasium to say
that now the sequence is bounded it's a
sequence the sequence is bounded so it
has a convergent subsequence so you have
and the limit you would then want to
prove that the limit is actually a limit
That's for the whole sequence right
that's what we did right
now but we didn't prove the balsano vess
theorem so let's try to pro prove it now
so proof of the bzano vos
so let me try to explain the idea
So you have a sequence a n
and a n is bounded. Let's just say it
doesn't matter but let's say that a n
lie in the interval from 0 to one.
It could be any other bounded interval
but but let's just say it's 0 to one.
Then the idea is that you we want to
prove that a n we want to so the idea is
that we want to find
want to find
um a subsequence
A and K
and two other sequences.
A sorry B K and C K. And these two other
sequences has a property that if you
have here
A and K then the B's lie below
the they lie below the A and K and the
C's
lies above it.
So, so the sequence the subsequence
that we will find is going to be
squeezed between two other sequences.
So, so right. So, a and k
is squeezed
between two other sequences.
And the thing about the other sequences
is that they are much nicer
because so why are they much nicer? The
BKS
are monotum
increasing
and the CK
are monotum decreasing.
Okay.
So, so you have that. So the picture is
sort of that the that the bees the bees
are always moving in this directions.
The C's here this is the B's they you
know as as K get larger they're moving
to the right and the C case are moving
to the left and these guys
A and K
they will be squeezed between these two
right? So if you're looking at a later
one right h so this is like one and now
imagine that you take a later uh uh in
the subsequence
sorry let me indicate it here a n say l
and l is now further out in the
subsequence
then this is going to be lying between b
L and CL
but these here this here will lie you
know the B L because it's further out in
subsequence it would lie to the right of
the so here will be BK it would be BK
would be to the left and CK would be to
the right of this right so you see that
these here are coming together they're
coming together like this and the the
the a no the the a the subsequent is
going to be squeezed in smaller and
smaller interval right and that's going
to force it to converge right and the
the point here is that because this here
is increasing
and they always lie between the ones
that go below this automatically means
that the B case will always be less than
than the first
C
and and this C case will always be
bigger than the first
uh B and so this is a more a sequence
that go up but it's bounded so it has a
limit so BK
is converging to something
the CKS are going down but they're
bounded from uniformly bounded from
below so they will also be converging
converging,
right? But now they're coming closer
together, right? They're coming closer
and closer together. This is converging
to that and this is converted to this.
So that's going to imply that B is equal
to C.
Okay, that's the idea. Yeah, sorry.
>> They they only they
will uh they they will be uh they will
have sorry the B
K will be less or equal to B K + one and
the C K
will uh be uh big or equal to CK + one.
>> So so it's not strict it's like
inequality like this.
>> Yeah that's right. But the thing is also
that they are going to that the
difference. So the CK is lying above the
BK. Right? So this here is positive.
This is
and we prove that this here is bounded
by two. It was actually going to be
equal to we actually prove that this
here is equal to um to one minus like
this and you see this here goes to zero.
So you're right that uh if they didn't
come together we couldn't conclude
things but they will come together this
will guarantee. So how do we do this?
That's the idea. How do we do this?
Well,
and again I'm just I'm just doing 0 to
one, but it but the same argument work
for any other interval. It's only like
it will look it will look simpler if I
do it from 0 to one. Uh but it's not
there's nothing essential I'm using
about. So here is your starting interval
from 0 to one.
We want to construct a subsequence and
we want to not only what do we want to
construct a subsequence but we also want
to construct the sequence BK and the
sequence CK right so let me find let me
define B1 b1 is just going to be zero
c1 is going to be one
and then uh a n1 that's the subsequence
the first element is subsequence I just
take it to be the first element in
sequence okay so now of course we have
trivially that we have that b1 which is
zero
this is lesser equal to a1 because it
lie in this interval lesser or equal to
c1 which is one Okay.
Now then you divide it into two
intervals here. So the second step is
that you take the interval from 0 to
one.
You divide it into two halves. Right? So
you have between zero and a half and a
half and one. The whole sequence lie in
this interval.
So this means that there are either
infinitely many here or infinitely many
there. Right? Let's say that infinitely
many of the a lie in this interval.
Okay? So then we're going to
forward we were going to just focus on
this interval and on sub intervals of
this. Okay. So the we need we have
defined a1
a now we want to define and b1 and c1
then so now assume again assume
that infinite many
lie in this interval right so then we
make um we a n2 the second element in a
subsequence
we let it be the next element after a1
that is in this smaller interval right
so this here is the second element
in the original sequence
[Applause]
that lies
in the interval from 0 to a half.
Okay,
that's a n2, right? We don't want to
have a1 again, right? We need another
element because it's otherwise it's not
going to be a subsequence. You can't
pick a pick the A1 we already I mean it
could be the same value but it's it will
have to come from a different subscript.
Okay. Now B2
is then just going to be the left end
point of this interval. So this is again
zero and C2
is going to be the right end point of
this interval we're now focusing on. So
that's a half.
Now
uh so now to the next. So now how do we
construct the third element in the
subsequence
and the corresponding
B's and C's.
Okay. The thing is that and here you
have to be a little bit careful because
now we we we we
assumed that there was infinitely many
elements in the sequence that lie in
this smaller interval. You are going to
only from here on out you're going to
only look at those infinitely many.
You're not going to care about you know
so this may be the fifth the seventh the
15th element in the original sequence.
You're not going to worry about what
lies here, right? And so now you divide
this one here into two halves. This
interval between zero and a half, you
divide it into two halves.
And so so now imagine you have then the
picture here. Here you have zero. Here
you have uh a half.
And then you divide it into this
interval from zero to half. You divide
it into
two equally
large intervals. So
now
we already we're just focusing on the
infinitely many of the original sequence
that lie here. But of those infinitely
many either infinite many lie here or
infinitely many lie there. Right?
Let's say that that there's only
finitely many here. Say but there are
infinitely many here. Right? So if
there's infinitely many in this interval
here, then from here on out, you would
only focus on those infinite many. And
the next element would be right we know
that uh right the next element would be
the next element after the the one you
pick to be the second element in the
subsequence
that would lie in this in this
subsequence. Right? So we define a3
is now the next element. So a N3
this is now this element that lies in in
in this interval here right and then B
B3 is then going to be 1 / 4 and B uh
sorry and C3
is going to be the right uh end point of
this interval 1 over 4 one over two
Right?
And then you continue, right? Then you
continue this way. So let me just make
sure that it's totally clear. Let me
just go over how how we did it.
Right? So, so just because I want to be
careful that you, you know, once you, so
we started with the interval from 0 to
one, the first element you just pick in
the subsequence that was just the first
element in the original sequence and the
B1 was just the left endpoint here. So
that was zero. C1 was the right endpoint
that was one.
Now you divide it into two and one of
the two half potentially of course both
of the two half could have infinite many
elements in the original sequence. You
just focus on one of the two half that
have infinite elements, right? If
they're both fine, but you just take one
of them, right?
And so from here on out, we're just
going to focus on those infinitely many.
And then you're going to pick the next
one after the the A1 that lies in that
interval you're focusing on. That's the
second element in a subsequence. And the
B's will always be the left end point of
the interval. The C's will be the right
end point of the interval.
Then when you do the third element, then
you have to remember that you were
looking at infinitely many. And so now
it's like you're looking at you divide
this interval into two.
And now either this one here or that one
here has infinite many, right? and you
pick whatever it is. I mean, I guess we
we assumed it was this interval.
And then the next element after the the
two first you picked in the original
sequence, the next element that lies in
this that's going to be your third
element of the sequence. And then still
the B's will be then of this interval
you're focusing on would be the left end
point and the C the right end point.
Right? If you do that, you see each time
you're halfing it. So it means well it
first of all it means that the that the
bees are going to be increasing right
because it's always right each time you
divide into a half and it's always and
but it's like the interval you focus on
previously you divide into a half like
this and then you either you pick either
this point or that point right and this
here was the previous one right so the
bees will always be increasing
Likewise, the C's will be a decreasing
sequence.
And you also see
that the difference between CK say CK +
1 minus B K + one that the difference
here, right? But the difference is going
to be like half of the length of the
previous interval, right? So the
difference here is going to be 1/2. it's
actually going to be 12
uh and then B C
minus BK.
So you're getting this form right and so
and now if you just use that you're
starting with if you're just using that
the aridium. So when so you get this
recursive formula here
and you also have that c uh 1 minus b1
this is the length of the original
interval right because b1 was zero c1
was one so this is one
and so you're just putting this in and
so you get the formula that c k minus bk
K is equal to 2 to the uh 1 minus K.
So you're getting this formula here.
This just come from this recursive
formula and how this starts right. See
this give you this. Okay. And so you see
that the length of these interval
becomes smaller and smaller. Again the
sequence BK is increasing the CK is
decreasing. So this means that this here
is converging to some B. This here is
converging to some C. And because the
difference between these goes to zero.
Then the B must be equal to C.
Right?
and and so this will prove that the
limit that you construct because the the
this is going to be squeezed
you have this property that if you're
looking at a k and even uh sorry a n k
and even a uh n l
that this thing here. This here will by
construction will lie between these two
but all the later ones will also lie in
this interval. Right? So this here will
also lie in this interval
CK as long as L here is bigger equal to
K.
Right?
And so you see that this thing here this
thing here will because this here is
converging
to B and this is actually now we prove
that this converts to the same number B.
So this means that these guys here that
is squeezed between these two other
sequence will also converge
to B. Okay. So that's a vol.
Okay. Another key concept is um in this
class is the concept of a series.
Um
and
and so so this is the concept of a
series.
U and so a series is like as follows
that suppose you have so let
a n be a sequence
from a sequence you can form another
sequence and you can form another
sequence the following way that s so we
form
another sequence
And that is that uh s1 and we call this
other sequence sn another sequence sn
and uh and the sequence is defined as
follows that s_ub_1 is a1
s_ub_2 is a1 + a2
s3 3
is uh a1 + a2 + a3.
Um, S4 is where you summing the first
four element in this in the original
sequence
and and then you write sorry this is
first four element and then you write
the nth element you write it just as a
sum where I equals to one say to N of
the AIS.
So, so if you have a a sequence then you
can form another sequence
and this is this we denote by s and this
here is this here is so we really so
this here other sequence if a sequence
is of this form then you call it a
series so so uh so sn here so but sn is
just a sequence this here is called is
said to be
a series.
Okay.
Now um let's let's go to the most so I'm
sure m probably everybody have heard
about that's a kind of one of the famous
Greek paradoxes is this with I mean they
have various different forms is this
with one form of it is with Achilles and
the turtle where the turtle is getting a
head start of Achilles and the paradox
is that because the turtle have a head
start, then Achilles can never catch up
with the turtle even though the turtle
is moving incredibly slowly because in
order to catch up with the turtle then
Achilles first have have to go um half
of the distance that the turtle have
gone and then once you have done that he
have to go half of the distance that he
that the turtle now have traveled etc
and so this go on infinitely long and
Therefore, he can never catch up with
the turtle. There's various other
version of this, right? But that and
that's exactly a series and like and
this is also like the most important
series is what's called the geometric
series.
So the geometric series.
So this is a you know the most important
uh series and it's the most important
because it's kind of a non-trivial
series that can be used to determine
whether other series or whether these
other for other sums whether these uh
this sequence sn whether it converges or
not. So the geometric series is the
following that C you take some number C
and then you are summing uh this number
but to a power so you're looking at
where you have some power say from zero
to n
right so this means that um so this is
SN so it mean that s uh s zero uh this
is just where you have
where you have uh by C to the power zero
by definition is one and s1 is then when
you're summing
c to the power z plus c to ^ 1. So
that's just uh 1 + c and s_ub_2 is then
uh s_ub_2 is then
[Applause]
s_2 is then uh c 0 + c1
+ c². So that's just 1 + uh c + uh c²,
right? Etc.
So that's a geometric series where it's
just a number and each time you multiply
that number by itself the end time and
then you're adding it to the previous.
So that's the geometric series. Okay.
And now and the reason why this is uh
important is that this is very useful to
determine whether other series are
convergent or not because you can
compare it. You can compare other series
with the geometric series
and the geometric series is easy to
determine whether it's convergent or
not. And so this is because of the
following little calculation here. Let's
suppose I'm looking at some summing here
from zero to N of C to the power I
and now I multiply this with C. Right?
So then this here would just be where
I'm summing here. You see if I multiply
by C I can move that C inside and then
the first time it's really right. So you
can write this thing here. So let me
just write it out. So this is C and then
it's 1 + C + C 2 + CQ
etc like that up to C uh N.
And if you multiply by C then of course
this is just C + C ^2 + C cub up to
uh C to the N + one. Okay.
And so this means that if you take this
thing here, so if you take if you're
looking at this sum from zero to n of CI
and now you multiply by 1 minus C,
right? Then this here is the same as
this here is the same as
just one times this. So let me just
write it out. This is what this just
give you the in original series. So this
gives you this up to CN. That's when we
multiply the one in when we multiply it
by minus C then we get this thing here
with a minus sign. So we're getting
minus C. Um so I can write like this
like that.
But now you see that there's a lot of
cancellation, right? This thing here
cancel
with this here. The next one would
cancel with this. This here would cancel
with the second last, right? And so you
were only left with this one here and
that one here. But the this one here
comes in with a minus sign. So this is 1
minus c to the n + one.
Okay. So we have this little formula
have this little formula say that if you
take uh if you take 1 minus c and you
sum from i = z
to n ci
right this is what we did here then
you're getting 1 - 1 - c to the n + one.
Okay.
So now of course if c if c is one let's
wait with figuring it out but assume
that c here is not equal to one
then I can write this here
as that this sum here i = z to n ci I
can just divide here by this here on
both sides. So I get this thing here
1 minus C. So I have this formula here
assuming that C is not equal to one. So
I can divide by 1 minus C.
And now you see that um so now we can
now from this here we can determine so
we can prove a little theorem.
So that the geometric series so this is
geometric series convergence
convergence.
Right?
Remember that this this thing here. So a
series here. So maybe I should just
emphasize that over here.
So if you write down a series, so again
a series is always that you're starting
with a sequence like this and then you
form this other sequence sn where you're
summing the first
um the first n you know I guess in this
case now I'm starting from zero so then
it would be n plus one elements
like this
and and and and sometimes one also just
write for the series one write it as
as this where one
uh one write like this here
but uh but really what you're thinking
about is this sequence here and so but
you you sort of with a slight abuse of
notation you write this here for a
series but what you're thinking about is
this sequence And so a series is
convergent.
It is convergent.
Uh just means
that the sequence
sn is convergent.
Okay. So it just means that that that
this sequence sn is convergent
and the and the and the sum and the
limit
of the sequence series
this is just the limit
um is the limit
of the sn
That's called that is usually denoted
denoted
by by by this uh by this infinite sum
a sorry this was I
ai like that right so so you see there's
a little bit of abuse of notation
that one one talk about a series and one
typically write it like this. What one
really mean is that one think about this
sequence here and then if it's
convergent this just means that these Sn
converge
and the limit the limit but the limit
you would also write as this. So in a
way this symbol here is used for two
different things. it's used for the
series and if the series is convergent
it's also used for the limit. Okay, this
is like standard. So,
okay. So, now let's come back to the
geometric series, right? So, again the
geometric series were that you take some
C
and then you form this series here
C I I = Z to infinity. It's it's of
course important where you start. I mean
it's the convergence is not important
but the what the limit is depends on
where you start. Okay. So so this is a
geometric series and we have that if um
if see here so we have now the following
that um that the geometric series
series
is convergent
if
if C here in absolute value is less than
one
uh and uh and divergent otherwise
if as the absolute value of C is bigger
to one.
Okay. So, so this is the claim that okay
and so this is and and so this is a
claim and and in fact um
right and and in fact so one more thing
is that that
so moreover
If uh if C
is less than one then the limit so so so
then the claim is that it's convergent
then the limit
is uh one one minus 2. This here has a
limit and so we write this here as the
this infin.
Okay. Now let's just try to prove this.
So let me first do and we have we almost
there already.
So the thing is
that
Right. So let's first look at the case
uh assume
C in absolute value it's less than
strictly less than one. Well, then we
have already proven that Sn is so sn
I = 0 to N CI and we have already proven
that this here is 1 minus CN + 1 over 1
- C right and this makes sense C is
strictly norm is strictly less than one
so in particular C is not one right so
this here is is fine but now you see
that If you take something with norm
strictly less than one, then just
because CN + one, the norm of this here,
well, if you take a something and you
multiply it by another, so so if you
take two numbers a and b and you take
the absolute value of the product,
that's the same as the product of the
absolute values,
right? So, so this means that if you
take C to the power n + one, so if you
take C and you multiply it by self, n +
one time, this is the same as the
absolute value times to raised to the
power n plus one, right? And so now you
see that because this c has absolute
value less than one, strictly less than
one, then as n go to infinity, this here
converts to zero. Right? So this means
that as n go to infinity this thing here
right converge this here goes to zero.
So just by the algebraic rules for
limits right this thing here is going to
converge to one minus C over one like
that right
so you see that in the case where the
where C in absolute value is strictly
less than one then we have now proven
that the geometric series is convergent
and in fact we have even which is really
nice and and sort of unusual for a
series. I mean, usually you cannot
actually determine what the limit is,
but in this case, we could, right? But
we still need to figure out why is it
not convergent if C
is um the absolute value of C is bigger
or equal to one.
And so here's an easy thing.
I mean, but you could also kind of I
mean, yeah. So, here's an easy thing
that if you're looking at C, sorry, SN +
1 minus SN,
right?
Well, SN + one or SN say this here was
just right. This here was just C to the
power zero up to C to the power n S N +
one
is where you do the same stuff. You're
adding these guys,
but then you have to add one more,
right? So this means that this
difference here is really C to the N +
one, right?
But now I could look at the absolute
value of this difference.
This is this
but this is the same again as C to the
power n + one.
But you see if C here is the absolute
value is bigger equal to one then this
thing here then this thing here so if
the absolute value here is bigger equal
to one then this thing here must be big
or equal to one right remember that if a
sequence is convergent if a sequence is
convergent then it is a cushy sequence
it's a cushy sequence that if you go
sufficiently far out then from there on
and out everything bunch very very close
together but you see here not even two
consecutive is bunching together because
independent on how far out how large n
is the difference is always at least one
right so this is not even a cus I mean
this well I mean it's actually
equivalent of course but it's not a cus
sequence it sort of failed like the most
basic thing with consecutive ones
does not even lie close together. So
this proved this uh this theorem about
the geometric convergence the geometric
series convergence.
Okay. So now so this is like
the most important example of a
sequence. Um
maybe the second most important
is what's called the harmonic series.
So harmonic series
and but the harmonic series is
unfortunately not a series that is
convergent. So the harmonic series is
the following. So I again I'm writing it
I'm using this abusive notation
that I'm writing the series as like a
infinite sum but this infinite sum you
know but it's not a convergent series.
So the infinite sum doesn't really make
sense. So so this is the here I have to
start because I'm dividing by n. So I'm
starting by one with one. So this here
is called the harmonic sh.
Okay. and and um and there's there's
various so for series
and for series there's like a sort of
bunch of things bunch of tests that are
useful to determine whether a series is
converging or not right and but there's
but and and the ones and we'll talk
about these tests I talk a little bit
about later in this lecture I'll talk
about some of the tests but not all of
them and and we will later talk about
more the test that is particular useful
in this case it's what's called the
integral test but I won't talk about
that today
um but instead I will show you a very
simple proof of why this here
is not convergent
so uh so so here's a theorem
The harmonic series
is a divergence. It's not conver it's
diverg.
Okay. And so in fact what we will prove
is the following
that we will show that if you're looking
at so n is an integer. If you're looking
at at so this is this is like so this is
like a right this is only some of the
you know you only hit for this here you
only hit some of the um element in the
sequence right so this is where I'm
summing again from i = 1 to 2 n to 2 to
the n minus one n is an integer of 1 I
right so I want to prove that these guys
here
if if the original sequence has been
convergent then of course any
subsequence would also be convergent and
we're going to prove that this thing
here is big or equal to n /2 so I claim
that we have this so this is a claim
that you have this But if you have this
thing here, you see that then the se
this subsequence here is unbounded.
Right? So of course the original
harmonic series is not convergent.
Right? So let's try to prove this. And
again you know this is not um this is
just like a simple proof of that very
simple minor proof that the harmonic
series is divergent
but but there are you know more
you know once we learn about the
integral test and so on there are other
in a way better ways of doing it.
So let me try to prove this. So I want
to prove the claim
prove of of the claim.
So I'm going to prove it by so I just
prove so so I want to establish this for
all n and I'm going to prove it first
when um when n
is equal to one. Right? So let's show
this for n equal to one.
So for n= to one
well then the claim here means that um
right so 2 to the one that's two so this
is this is s1 right right because two to
the one is 2 minus one so this is one so
I claim that so so I want to prove that
s1 is bigger equal to a
want to show
but of course S1 here S1 is just one
over one so it's actually that's
definitely fine okay so this is so it's
for so we we so so we want to prove the
claim and the claim is okay so claim is
okay
for n = 1. Okay. So now I want to prove
it. So I want to assume so assume
the claim
is correct
for for N and we want to prove it for
want to show it
to show the claim
for
for the next one, right? And so I I have
that. So we we have we assume
that s2 n
minus one that this is bigger than n /2
and then I want to look at uh s 2 n + 1
-1. Okay, how can I write this thing
here? So I'm summing, right? This here
is a sum of the one over I where I do it
up to this thing here. But I can think
about that as a sum of the one where I
do up to this here
and then then I have to sorry sum the
rest also. So this is I = to 2 n to 2 n
+ 1
2 n sorry + 1 - 1
like this of 1 / i right
but now you see
I want to bound it from below
right so I
So if you sort of continue this line
then by assumption this thing here is
bounded by n /2 right this thing here
right I'm summing right I'm summing two
n numbers right from here to here there
are two n numbers
right
and uh and so it's two n numbers and if
I take the smallest of those two
numbers, right? If I take the smallest
of these guys and I multiply by 2 n,
then that's definitely a lower bound. So
let's try to do this. So I say 2 n 2 to
the n and then the smallest, but the
smallest is the last one. So the
smallest is 1 / 2 to the n + one
minus one, right?
But this thing here, right, is of course
obviously bigger than so n / two. This
thing here, well, this is 2 to the n.
But this thing here, if I divide by a
larger number, and the larger number is
just this here, then I get something
even smaller. So I would have 1 / 2 to
the n + one, right?
But now you see that this thing here
cancel with these guys here. And so
you're getting that this is n / 2 + a
half. And so this is n + one / two. And
that's exactly the claim for n + one.
Right? So we proven that if it was true
for n then it's also true for n + one.
And we remember to check that the
beginning was also okay.
Okay, so that's the harmonic series. So
you see that the harmonic series is
divergent.
Now
um the harmonic series is of course an
example of something else.
Namely that
if you're looking at so when you're
looking at a series
the first thing you look at typically is
Okay. So,
let me just have a side here. So,
if you give me a series,
you know, it doesn't really matter where
I mean it
it doesn't matter very much where it's
the for for whether a series is
convergent. It doesn't matter where you
start because this is just adding
something to it. It will matter where
you start for the limit but not whether
or not the sequence series is
converging. But if you give me a limit
the first thing I always check is that
this so first so so for a series
always check
if a n goes to zero or not.
And why? Because if you give me a
series, this the the the question about
a series is always whether it's
converging or not. Right? And again,
just like we did, if you're looking at
Sn
say minus SN minus one, this is where
I'm looking at two consecutive things,
right? But if I'm looking at this
difference here, the difference here,
this is where I'm summing up to the a n
minus one. Here I'm summing up to the a
n. So the difference here is a n. And if
the sequence just like we saw, if the
sequence of the series sorry is
convergent, it means that this sequence
here is convergent. But it means that it
has to be a cruise sequence that things
have to bunch together. But that two
consecutive bunchs together or not is
determined whether a n goes to zero or
not. So if a n does not go to zero, you
already done, right? There's no reason
to continue. It's already clear that
this if a end does not go to zero, you
can just say it it doesn't converge
because a end doesn't go to zero. So
there's no reason to start with any kind
of test or anything any sort of uh good
ideas.
Um okay so so that was just a side
remark. The other thing is that for the
the harmonic series is uh you know so
this of course failed this test
but but it also is an example of
something where you're taking a so
suppose you take a so you have a
sequence a n
and and then you're forming the series
this here. Now, if all of the a
suppose that all of the a ends are non-
negative, right? Then if you're looking
at sn
+ one, you can think about sn + one as
where you're summing
the first
n elements and then you're adding
the n plus one elements. Right? So this
here you can think about as sn
plus a n + one. And so of course if you
have if all of these elements is non-
negative this means that this here is
non- negative. So this thing here is
bigger than Sn. So you see that if all
of the element a is non negative then
this sequence sn is monotone. So in this
case here if you have this this imply
that this sn
is mono increasing right. And so now to
say whether this in if you have this to
determine whether this series here is
convergent or not it's just a matter of
proving whether you know to determine
whether this this
sequence is bounded or not. Right? So
you just need to find a bound.
Okay. So this naturally leads to looking
at what's called absolute convergence.
So this is something stronger than
convergence.
And for many things for many although
not all
there's a particular test that deals
with it with uh where you don't have
both things or where you don't have the
stronger property. So for many things
you are you have absolute convergence.
Um okay and um
so let me try to so absolute conver.
So again you have a um a series here.
This series here is set to be absolute
convergence or converge absolutely. So
converge
absolutely
if if the co the series where you slap
absolute values on them. If this thing
here
converge
right?
So if this so we say that this here
converts absolutely if this here
converge. Okay. Now
uh so I claim that uh that absolute
convergence is stronger than
convergence.
So, so absolute
convergence
implies
uh convergence.
This is a theorem.
But it's not the other way around,
right? So if you have what's called the
So here an example
and and we haven't yet proved that it's
converging, but we'll do that in some
later lecture.
So um so here's an example.
If you're looking at the series minus
one to the power n / n n n n n n n n n n
n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n n
n n n n n n n n n n n = 1 to infinity.
This here you see this is if if this
hair just had been one then it had been
the harmonic series. This here series is
it's also kind of like a famous series.
It's called the alternating
alternating harmonic series.
And it's alternating alternating mean
that the sign of it is alternating
right. So the sign of this a element it
keep changing from guess in this case
the first one is negative the next one
is positive. So it go back and forth
between uh uh back and forth uh around
zero. to a harmonic series.
And this series is convergent
is convergent
but not absolutely convergent.
Why? Because the the if you slap
absolute value sign you get the
harmonics is and we already know that
this is not convergent but not
absolutely converted.
Okay.
So this is the alternating harmonic
series. Okay. Now let's try to prove
that uh absolute convergence implies
convergence.
And so I'm going to look at so I take
two series. So I have SN that's my
original series a I = Z to N like that.
And then I take the one where I slap
absolute value sign and I denote it with
a bar.
So I = to zero 2 N of A.
And then I make a little observation
and the observation is
that if I take
if I'm looking at
SN and SM
so just think about at N here is larger
than N.
Then you can think about this thing here
as this thing here is just where you're
summing from m + one
n up to a n right that's this difference
right
but if you take absolute value on this
absolute value on that well that's a
that's of of course less or equal to
right where you're taking absolute value
on each individual one
like that.
But this thing here is just this is just
right this thing here is just for the
the other series. this is it's the same
sort of difference
and and here actually I don't need to
take absolute value but I could take
absolute value but this is already non
negative
and so you see that so so you make this
little observation but now we know that
if it is absolutely convergent then this
sequence here converge so this means
that in particular it's equivalent to
saying that it's a cushy sequence and so
this means that things if you are
sufficiently far out these things here
have bunched together epsilon together
if you are bigger than some capital n
but now this inequality say that these
things here bunch together so you see
that that if this is convergent
then it's a cy sequence but this means
that this here is a cy sequence so it
means that there are vision series was
converged.
Okay. Um
and so now let's look at one more
example and then then we'll talk about
some of the tests.
Um
yeah. So let's look at so we we we saw
that the harmonic series is divergent.
Um
so we saw that the harmonic series is
divergent
but let's what about
right I mean and what about so this is
another thing you could do right so
maybe the most important
series is the geometric series after
that you can debate a little bit which
series is the most important and but
these here is some other candidates for
that. Um, so I'm looking at now the sum
here n = 0 to infinity.
Uh, and I'm looking at
uh 1 / n squares. But you could do it
more generally where you raise it to
some power. Right? If that power was
one, you got the alternating, you got
the harmonic series. But I'm now I'm
just looking at a specific power two.
Okay.
And so I claim that that this series
here this here is um this here is um I
mean this one doesn't really have a name
but it is a key series. And so I claim
that this here is convergence. So this
is
now
You observe that the a n in this case
this is just 1 / n^2 right and these
here are non- negative. So all we need
to do is so we just need to prove. So
this is when the a ends are non negative
all you need to prove is that that the
sequence you just need to prove need to
show
that the SN which is where you're
summing here
I = uh you can't you shouldn't sum from
zero sum from one I = to uh one to n
that you will need to prove that these
here are bounded
and this is because the a
ends are non negative.
Okay. So now the idea here is that um I
mean again this is not
um this is not necessarily how I would
do it but um if but this the advantage
with this here is that it doesn't use
anything fancy. I mean it's not like the
the the way later on you would do it
will you would use the integral test but
we haven't talked about this integral
test yet. So you can do it very simple
mindedly.
And so the claim here is that
um that um that you want to compare.
So we want to we want to make a
following claim
uh that um
that um that if you're looking at s to
the 2 n + one sorry f to the 2 n. So
it's just similar to what we did before.
If we want to prove we want to prove
that this thing here uh for this uh
series that this is less than the sum
here from i uh equal to uh zero to n of
12 to the power i. So we'll put n minus
one.
So we claim this thing here.
Now you see that so we claim that we
have this inequality for all in right
but um this thing here we already know
that this here is a geometric series
series
with C = to a half so it's convergent
and you see this thing here is a subsequ
sequence
but it's a subsequence because this here
is convergent. This here is this here is
yeah right this here is bounded by
something fixed right so it means that
this subsequence here is bounded
but the original series was a mono
increasing sequence. So if a subsequence
is bounded then the original sequence is
bounded and and so convergent right. So
we just need to prove we just need to
give a bound like this and the bound
here you get is but we already
determined that this here is less or
equal to one over 1 minus c. C is a
half. So this is like this. So this here
is a half. So this whole thing here is
two.
So this here would be bounded by two.
Right? Okay. So now we want to prove so
we want to prove this claim here. So if
we can prove this claim then we have
that the series this series here is
convergent.
Okay. So now let's let's let's try to do
that. So when
n is equal to one so we we do it again
in the same way.
This is called by induction. We do it
for first for
for n = 1 for n = 1 it is a claim that s
right if n is equal to one this is 2
minus one that's one so it's a claim
that this thing here
is uh is bigger equals is lesser equal
to
and now it's when n is equal to one it's
just this is you're just summing over
one thing. It's just one thing and it is
a half to the power zero and that's one.
So for n= 1, this is what we need to
show.
Okay.
But now let's see
for n equal to one. Well, this here is
indeed one. So that's okay, right?
So this is okay.
So now assume
assume that s ^ 2n -1 is bounded by this
i = 0 to n -1 of 12 to the power i.
Right? So assume this and we want to
prove the same thing but for n + one. So
want to show
the same inequality
for
n + one. Okay.
So let me do that.
[Applause]
So I'm looking at s 2 n + 1 -1.
So s 2n + 1 - one I can write as where
I'm summing the first 2 n minus one
and then I'm I'm summing
and then plus and then I'm what I'm
summing from I equ= to 2 n to uh up to 2
n + 1 - one
right and then it's 1 / i^ 2
now in this case remember before we
wanted to prove that something was
divergent
So we wanted to give a lower bound. In
this case we want to give a upper bound.
So when we do this we think about what
is the instead of what is the smallest
we think about what is the largest of
these numbers but that's the first one
right and there are again just like
before there are two n many of them. So
this thing here is lesser equal to s2 n
minus one. Sorry. Yeah, like this. And
then there are two n many they're all
non negative. And this is and the first
one is the largest.
So 1 / 2 n
squared like this, right?
And so you see that this thing here is
so now we can fill in the assumption. We
were assuming that this here was less
than this.
So this is the sum from
i =0 to n -1 of 12 to the power i
and uh the this thing here but the
square kills that one and you're still
left with one over 2n
but you see this is of course exactly
the next one in the series. So this is I
= 0 to N of a half to the power I like
that right and that's indeed this is
like the induction step right this is
what's called the induction step so this
is so it's true also so if it's true for
n the claim then it's also true for n
plus one
Okay.
So now uh so now um let me I have just
four minutes left. There's a little bit
more uh in I already posted the lecture
notes uh and um and there's a bit more
here I want to talk about.
So I want to talk about some of the
tests but we we'll talk about that more
next time also. So to determine
whether another series
a series is converging
converge
uh then
there are a number of tests
and then of the the key
uh the key point is to use the right
test. So uh I will just talk about so I
just mentioned some of the tests but we
won't anyway go through all of them you
know so maybe I can't go through any of
them. So there's a comparison test,
there's a ratio test,
there's root test,
and there's also the one I talked about
several times, the integral test.
And then there's even one called the
alternate series test.
[Applause]
Okay, now maybe I can just talk about
the the comparison test. That's in a way
the simplest of.
And so the comparison test is
that you're looking at two series. So
you have these two series here
and you have this other series here.
And the comparison tests say that if you
have a n bigger equal to zero less or
equal to bn. So if you have this and
and the B and this series here
converge
then then the corresponding thing with
the A in
will also converge.
and and this this this is the simplest
version of the comparison test and this
is in a way used in two ways right so
you often you have a series and maybe it
could be a super complicated series
and uh but you see some kind of path in
and so you can compare it with a much
simpler series that perhaps you already
know whether it's converging right and
so if you can compare it with something
else and you know that that converge
then you conclude that that that a end
series is converging. It's also
sometimes used that you want to
determine whether this series here is
converging but you can you actually you
can easily kind of compare it with some
other series where you have this
relationship here and this one you
already know is divergent right so it's
used in both ways when it's used to both
determine that a series is convergent
and it's also used to determine that the
series is divergent okay so there's a
little bit more about test on the in the
lecture notes. Um but we will anyway
talk about it more next time. Yeah.
>> Question about like the intuition of
this like
>> Yeah.
Right. Right. Right. So so so that's
right. So
so so
right. So that's so that sort of thing
is I mean this last one show you that
the geometric series is one that is that
sort of come up often as a kind of
comparison in a way when how you get it
different for different people obviously
you don't start with a claim you sort of
looking at the first few things and you
see a pattern basically but it's not I
mean you know this is not the way you
want to really you know later on you
know I would never prove any kind of
convergence like this you know there's a
a there's a way of comparing it with the
so the idea is let me just tell you but
of course the lecture is over but but
there is um so the integral test is that
you're looking at so you're looking at a
series and if you have a series of non-
negative numbers you can think about
that the series is like the area below.
If this here is if this is think about
this here as a1 and this is maybe a2
then you can think about the sum as the
sum of the areas like this and so the
integral of test is that you comparing
it with some curve and the area that
lies below it then it's like much more
clear right the other one is like where
you have to do it case by case right
that's not you know here there's a kind
of general idea So it's nice in this
particular case. I'm not sure it's you
know what I mean. I mean you had to look
at the first few things and see if you
see a pattern, right? And of course you
don't start with a claim, right? That's
like the end. When you when you actually
have a claim, then you already know
what's going on.