what I want to share is sort of the long
road that we've been on to get close to
a major effort on digital twins that I
think will take place in the future and
the real motivation I think of for
digital twins is in semiconductor
manufacturing is to create the platform
that will enable us to harness and apply
AI to improve semiconductor
manufacturing so I'll give you some
examples but I thought it would be
important first to sort of explain a
little what we mean by a digital twin
but before that you need to know and
remember the obvious what is the purpose
of semiconductor processing equipment
what is the purpose of semiconductor
manufacturing and that's
to transform some starting wafer into a
wafer with functional integrated
circuits on it right and so the way we
do this is processing through hundreds
of unit processes
that not only achieve that wafer State
change but also have to deal with
generating an environment around the
wafer uh controlling the equipment and
the Machine controlling and interacting
with the facility uh and to do all of
that in the face of enormous numbers of
uncontrollable uh parameters and
variations so the purpose is simply
achieving these wafer State changes so
the purpose of a semiconductor digital
twin is to better support that
manufacturing and all of the associated
tasks to make that happen so the
conceptual components of a digital twin
are first a representation of those
States like the wafer state that we're
trying to transform the plant the
equipment or facility what is the state
of the equipment and tools and what is
the state of the process the environment
or generating around the wafer to cause
that wafer State change a second key
component is models of the in in a
digital twin and these are models
especially about how those States evolve
or how we want them to evolve okay and
then finally those work together
together with
communication uh data exchange and
actions uh with the physical entity in
order to carry out many different kinds
of tasks so the twin and a key idea here
is the pairing of that physical entity
and the virtual
entity so what are some of the key tasks
I mean the the core task again is that
wafer State change but in order to
achieve that we hope a digital twin will
better support our tasks at the unit
process level for example rum by run or
realtime control support anomaly
detection fault detection and
classification recipe synthesis and
optimization and by the way you can
already see oh I'm going to need pretty
sophisticated models for that I'd really
like to have more intelligence in all of
these tasks I'd like to enable AI
assistance for all of these tasks
similarly there's tasks at the equipment
level predictive maintenance diagnosis
equipment design and of course at the
facility or full flow level like yield
Improvement yield prediction throughput
and scheduling optimization uh
optimizing the consumables for better
sustainability Fab layout and
design so where do we need digital twins
semiconductor manufacturing certainly in
the wafer Fab but the vision is a bit
larger we also need that in advanced
packaging that's rapidly transforming a
lot of the industry and of course
assembly and
test we also need digital twins for
Education and
Training right so not everybody has an
mit. Nano in their backyard we're
blessed with that and can use that
physical entity for Education and
Training but the workforce needs for
this larger semiconductor industry in
the future is going to need virtual
versions of that also in order to be
able to educate train and build the
skills of existing uh Workforce force
that we're going to need to transform
and bring into the semiconductor
domain so digital twins could have a
Major Impact I think it's fairly obvious
to think about operational uh
efficiencies but it's also potentially
transformative in
R&D that is again what we imagine is if
you have a digital twin with access to
data models representations and all of
the infrastructure to support that
that's a platform form for AI and
machine learning enabled tasks in both
manufacturing and
R&D and a key part of that vision is if
I've got virtual twins of Fab processes
that I've got say in an R&D Fab that
enables the translation and transfer of
that to scale
manufacturing not just by uh you know
transferring the the uh the the basic
recipe but also all of the models and
everything else that go with it in order
to make it
scalable so you might ask well why don't
we already have a full set of digital
semiconductor digital twins if they're
so valuable and it's interesting because
I think we've been kind of edging up to
this for at least 30 years or more in
fact at MIT we tried about 30 years ago
um we had a substantial DARPA funded
program on computer AED fabrication so
this was before the digital twin phrase
was around but the key ideas were very
very similar we were looking at building
some infrastructure to support computer
AED maybe not AI aided at the time
computer aided fabrication uh including
representation layers data access and
data representation sort of Standards to
enable a whole host of applic ations
scheduling at the plant level design
support fabrication support equipment
control uh and and so forth and so there
was a lot of really interesting ideas
from the time including language
representations of process flows so this
is a little example of a a a pfr process
flow representation for one little ramp
up step uh on on a
furnace what's fascinating to me now is
this a language
representation what do large language
models do they translate from one
representation to another they
manipulate and understand so I think
some of these ideas from 30 years ago
are going to be very important now with
the new technologies available to be
able to uh uh uh employ and harness some
of these AI Technologies so we had Cafe
30 35 years ago it was difficult ult
however to scale with the existing
technology uh of the time and what has
happened over the last 30 years is not
an integrated system an integrated
digital twin framework but instead many
many point Solutions each solution maybe
it's a runby run controller or maybe
it's a scheduling task each and every
one of these has its own data
representation its own models and
modeling methodology and its own sort of
customized for that specific spefic task
so there is still now today a lot of
these Point Solutions um but there's a
large cost in time that's required in
order to bring one of those in and
deploy them for each task and
application and indeed in many Fabs it's
only really worth it if it fixes a
crisis so uh that cost is large and
difficult uh we need to find ways to uh
improve that
so one of the aspects I'm going to share
with you is some of the the lessons that
I've learned along the way on working on
some of these kinds of Point Solutions
myself uh uh this is a bit of my journey
towards digital Twins and I'm not going
to go through Bullet by pullet here but
suffice it to say lots of interesting
projects with great students and
Industry collaborations on process
modeling process control and more
recently uh the employment of machine
learning methods uh to some of these
tasks but again I think we're at a
really interesting stage because the
technology enablers have advanced we've
got much better sensor and data ability
to access and store enormous amounts of
data that we didn't have 30 years ago of
course we've got much more powerful
compute
capability and of course we've got the
explosion the new modeling methods we're
in the age of Ai and machine
learning in order to get to employing
those uh new enablers we do need to make
it easier to develop digital twins to
deploy them to be able to interplay with
other digital Twins and these are going
to require looking back at those
components of a digital twin and
thinking carefully about shared
underlying software data system and
security uh infrastructure but also get
back to shared standards if you will on
what the data representations will be
and a apis or standard means to access
that data and to access and support
models and I think we're also going to
need some wisdom based on the experience
over the accumulated uh years and so
what I thought I'd do is give you some
insight on a few of the key lessons that
I've learned in working on precursors to
digital TN many of those uh uh Point
Solutions so here's the first lesson
models that we employ must adapt and
update and I think this is fairly
obvious if you think back to one of the
core Point
Solutions um often employed in
semiconductor manufacturing you have
controllers uh uh of the equipment
that's changing the state of the wafer
so for example here's some uh work we
did on a runby run controller for
chemical mechanical polishing CMP is
essentially you rub the surface of the
wafer against a uh polymeric polishing
pad it's sort of like high-tech sanding
uh wet sanding with a a slurry with
particles in it and you might imagine
and you'd be right that your intuition
about sanding like a a block of wood
apply so for example if I polish faster
the removal rate goes up or if I press
hard the removal rate goes up but at the
bottom here is a plot that shows over
350 Wafers that removal rate changes in
the equipment as the polishing pad and
other aspects of the equipment State uh
uh wear or change and so the solution is
simply a feedback control many of us are
Engineers right this sounds like a
control problem a feedback problem and
in fact model-based control and enables
you to have a model like that model in
the middle a very simple low order
polinomial model and if I can update
that model to track the state of the
tool then I know what the right pressure
and downforce and uh uh uh rotation rate
and so on should be in order to achieve
the goal right so with careful tracking
of the state
that is to say I've got a model that is
my digital twin of this part of the
equipment in process if that keeps
twinned and up to dat with the tool then
I can make the right the right
decisions by the way this this is a
little fun kind of Point here we often
think of neural network models as uh
something that I would do to model say
maybe that removal rate as a function of
the process conditions but also so
neural network or Ai and machine
learning models can also be helpful in
other aspects for example in that
feedback control I was just describing
we want to track the state of the
equipment but I got to be careful not to
adapt my model too much because then I
might be adapting to noise and in fact
there's an optimal set of weights for
how fast you update the model that
depend fundamentally on the rate of
drift or the
Noise Okay so so one could for example
and here's some work that uh that we did
to learn what the optimal weights
are we have a little neural network here
that learns what the optimal weights are
to use with a very simple almost linear
model fun
fact this is from paper 28 years ago so
we were doing a little bit of AI in
semiconductor manufacturing for a long
time
this same idea of model update applies
any place where you're building a model
that has uh empirical dependencies so
for example this is some work with
SanDisk on chip stack memory packaging
the basic idea is uh you get your supply
of chips each chip having about a
thousand e test parameters from a wafer
uh manufacturer and based on an e test
program you just pick out the known good
dies that you're going to want to stack
in four or eight or 16 chip stacks and
package the problem is that e test
program is not perfect there's actually
some lurking die that look like they're
going to be good but at the end of the
line when you Finly test the packaged
device some of those chip sacks don't
work and so the idea here would be can
we add a machine learning based
classifier that complements and sits on
top of the E test program to better
predict which D are going to survive at
the end so we did that uh using about
six or eight weeks of uh of of die data
you can build a really good model that
actually does improve improve the
yield however what we found out is that
model was only good for about a week two
weeks later it's not as accurate anymore
three weeks later it's almost not
helpful anymore so once again the lesson
there was that classifier decays so I
need a feedback loop I need an online
learning to keep track of the subtle
correlations that are happening that
cause D On's package to be good uh or or
bad so again the key this is just
showing a little bit of some of the
yield uh benefit um from this this kind
of an example
so the key lesson there is the core
digital twins idea of synchronization
between the physical and virtual entity
is really
important a second key lesson is
variability and uncertainty models are
crucial here's some work that we did to
model that CMP process again account for
variations that are inherent that are
caused by layout pattern density
variation and in fact if you run those
kinds of semiempirical models You can
predict what the surface Heights will be
and this is crucial for identifying
problem areas for example that little
lower right corner there is going to
poish
imperfectly so the methodology in this
case is not just physics-based models
but in fact semi-empirical models that
you tune based on standard test vehicles
uh so one of our contributions here uh
is a the MIT semitech 854 mask set that
continues to be used uh to this day uh
to help characterize and and model CMP
processes and that semi-physical model
can be tuned to that specific process
and consumable set even if you don't
know and we still don't know to the day
to this day all of the nanoscale
physical dependencies in the that uh
occur in
CMP another great opportunity once you
have models that include variability is
you can employ branches of AI
methodologies including basian
optimization that I think you may hear a
little bit more about uh today um that
explore the space very
efficiently figuring out what the next
experiment should be to run in order to
both learn and uh uh get towards your
goal so here's a little example of work
we've uh done with Applied Materials to
try to speed up the ion implant tune
when you change to a new recipe or
remploy an old recipe after the
equipment has drifted and the basic idea
is
unfortunately uh things do change a
little bit the beam shape changes a
little bit with equipment aging and an
unadjusted implant profile across the
wafer is pretty non-uniform so what do
you do well the practice is you run a
few test Wafers make some measurements
tune up the equipment what we did here
was again use this basian optimization
to rapidly learn beam
shapes and accounting for uncertainty I
find what the next tuning run should be
such that with only typically one or two
tuning runs you get a very good uniform
profile so reducing from the sort of uh
standard operating procedure cutting the
number of uh tuning runs needed by half
or more so that lesson is digital twins
are going to need to address variation
and uncertainty uh uh quantification for
various
tasks uh the next lesson is pretty
intuitive standards and Frameworks are
hard uh um they are needed but they're
going to require a lot of uh thought uh
about what to standardize in order to
achieve the goals of interoperability
integration and so on and here one of
the early lessons and I'm actually
pointing back to the beginning here in
some of the cafe work is a conceptual
model or a conceptual framework where
what you really ought to be
standardizing on are the data
representations not on the
transformation models okay so the key
representations about those states that
the digital twin will need to represent
and then the models that tell how to
transform between those States and the
last lesson is sort of closely connected
to that
that we're going to need many many
different kinds of models to solve the
wide variety of tasks that we talked
about and a key point here is you're
never going to be able to standardize on
these models and in fact you want to
have a platform that will enable us to
explore all the way from abob nisho very
first principles numerically uh based
you know the partial differential
equation-based very compute intensive
kinds of models that capture a lot of
the physics to the full range of very
empirical functional models for example
that very simple polinomial model that
you can can use for runby run control of
CMP but there's lots of room in between
for all kinds of other models in
particular those that um uh are going to
be needed for twins or surrogate models
for some of the tasks that are AI based
so we're going to see a lot more neural
network kinds of models or physics
informed neural network kinds of models
that interplay uh with each other so the
road ahead I think is we're now getting
close to where we can actually
contemplate having full digital twins
Full flow digital twins sequences of all
of the twins for each of the unit
processes each of the unit Metrology
steps and to enable that you're going to
need shared standard data
representations support for that wide
range of models and the
interoperability to uh support a wide uh
range of different
tasks uh the road ahead I think is also
going to be very much enabled by uh
collaborations from the federal
government from state government and the
industry uh the road ahead will include
a brand new Chips manufacturing USA
Institute focused on these uh digital
Twins and just yesterday uh uh the U
announcement came from nist of that new
digital twins Institute it'll be managed
by the SRC uh and headquartered in North
Carolina and I think that's going to be
a very exciting platform and next step
we now have the underlying Technologies
to enable the digital twins capability
that were not previously possible great
exciting time and opportunity we can
learn from all of those Point Solutions
but the new manufacturing USA Institute
will help us build critical mass shared
Frameworks ecosystem Development Across
many of the players
and continue uh as R was talking about
uh Foster deeper industry and University
interactions in research and education
so I think digital twins are going to be
a great enabler for the future of the
semiconductor industry and going to be
kind of a bridge in a different way to
employing the AI technology not just
generating the AI technology uh for the
betterment and advancement uh and next
steps in the uh semiconductor industry
so thank you
uh thank you very much proper boning um
given we have uh only 10 minutes maybe
I'll be around yeah or you can have a
quick question quick answer um is
possible here po one question before I
take a break as someone at mmt on The
Cutting Edge of research in the area
what is your most Pro more provocative
vision of the future in digital twinning
if longstanding hurdles are overcome
what's beyond practical DTS well I I I
think one of the the visions that we
actually thought about exploring but
really wasn't possible decades ago
is truly flexible semiconductor
manufacturing okay right
now you get a pdk and it's a fixed
manufacturing process and that's
wonderful for enabling you know digital
integrated circuits that are are are
built using standard transistors right
but what if you had digital twins with
models of each of those individual unit
steps and ways and
intelligence be able to chain those
together in new ways those those steps
but with confidence that you think those
steps would actually work and
interplay that would be a a potential
GameChanger now you could start to
really customize all of your Fab
processes with confidence and who knows
what kind of new device product uh uh uh
system micro system ideas might might
come out of that so that's a big dream
but I think digital twins would
absolutely be necessary to achieve that
all right yeah thank you very much Prof
bony let's give a
PL um