Episode
7: Lessons from a Real Garage.
Everyone loves the Innovation Origin
Stories that begin in garages or dorms.
Hullet Packard's garage is so famous.
It's an official historical site with a
plaque. So, let me advance that you do
not need a garage or garage culture.
You'll see what I mean in a few minutes.
Apple 2 has a garage origin story. It's
in the Steve Jobs biopic. In 1976, the
story goes, two Steves showed a
prototype to investors in a garage. They
had just sold 10 prototype motherboards
to a local store and they were ready to
make it a business. Some of the
investors later described the Steves as
smelly hippies. And one of the Steves
later explained that the garage was just
where they hung out because they had no
money for anything else. They did the
work elsewhere. This is such a great
origin story for what's become the most
valuable company ever that past this
point we're ready to believe whatever.
Here is when I typically ask my audience
which may at different times include
investors, corporations or students to
guess how much money they would have put
in the project themselves had they been
able to see the prototype in the garage.
They end up telling me a number between
a,000 and $100,000.
I believe most of them respond
automatically with what they've heard.
Angel investors typically invest. When I
remind them that the story happened in
1976, they typically drop a zero.
So, let's see what the Steieves got in
1976 and how it compares with what we
think today the company needs to start
going. After a few conversations with
different people in their network, the
Steves met Mike Marcula. Marula had
retired from Intel, a multi-millionaire.
He was an engineer by training and had
worked as a marketing manager. So he
understood technology and understood
business development. So the story goes
like this. In 1976,
Mike Marcula saw the prototype the
Steves had assembled. He then invested
$92,000 of his own capital and secured a
$250,000 credit line for the business.
Together, the Steves and Marula went on
to raise more money, and they raised an
additional $1 million in the next 6
months. They built a company, chased
after revenue, and Apple computers is
the result.
You can get a fuller account of this
story from a variety of sources. What I
find interesting about it is that it is
reproducible. What makes this story
interesting to me isn't that some of it
happened in a garage, but how Marcula
empowered the Steves and what he ended
up needing as proof before committing to
the project. Let me give you a sense of
perspective. The nearly $1.5 million
that Marula Jobs and Wnik raised in 1976
would have paid then for the salaries of
about 75 engineers. In 2024, it would
take about 20 million to afford that
many salaries in California. A
modern-day Marula would have to seed the
garage project with about $2 million
today to emulate what Mike Marula did in
1976.
And yet in 2024, the winner of your
average monthsl long pitch contest might
get at best $50,000.
That is the gap between how we've been
thinking about innovation lately and how
we used to think about innovation.
That is the mindset gap before us. Every
time I share this Apple origin story
with people, someone will come and tell
me that they don't know how to get $2
million from an investor and they'll ask
me whether it is realistic to expect
that amount. And my answer to them and
to you, if that's your question, is the
same. This happened. Maybe you should
actually make it your point not to
accept money from anybody that gives you
any less because what this story tells
you is how much money it takes to build
truly a company. And maybe you cannot do
it with just $50,000 at the time. It
takes a mindset shift to realize that
the investors you want are the ones that
are capable of that kind of an
investment and to be strong enough to
kind of move away from the investments
that are much smaller that might not get
you to actually demonstrate your great
idea. There's two sides to this story.
There's the first part of it in which
the Steves had managed to produce a new
kind of motherboard that no one had
produced before and had managed to sell
10 units of it to people in their
community. That required no investment.
It required no business plan. It
required no pitch. It required no
entrepreneurial contest. They were just
able to go and do it. Then there's the
second part of the story which is one in
which they realize they have a business
to build. Not a startup, a business. And
then they go out for investors. Then the
question is which kind of investor
should you choose? Or if you're an
investor, what kind of an entrepreneur
should you choose? Should you go with
someone that's ready to start with just
50k or should you hope to find an
investor that understands that the price
at the end is a company that's self-
sustaining.
In that last case, you want to go with
an investor that's capable to put of
putting enough money from the beginning
so you can worry about the one thing
that matters. Build the business. You
can get started with what you have, but
you cannot demonstrate a multi-million
dollar business stringing ideas along
pennies at a time, much less build one.
You'll have to get real. And you'll have
to find people intent on getting real,
too. And that's true whether you are an
investor or the tinkerer with a garage.
[Music]