okay so we are going to dive in today
and talk about uh where demand curves
come from the motivation for the last
couple lectures was that we showed you a
demand curve and a supply curve and I
promised I tell you what the basis for
those demand Supply curves are the last
two lectures we started building that
basis and today we'll show you where
demand curves actually come from so
let's actually derive let's start by
actually deriving a demand curve okay so
deriving a demand
curve okay so
um basically theand curve as we said in
the first lecture is the relationship
between from the price charged for a
good and the consumer's desired quantity
of the good so what we'll do is return
to the example before and show you where
that comes from so remember the example
before remember we utility function
which was the square root of s * C
slices times cookies okay we had a
budget constraint which was Y is equal
to the price of slices times the number
of slices plus the price of cookies
times the number of cookies and we
assume to start that y was 24 the price
of slices was four and and the price of
cookies was
two okay so how do we derive a demand
curve Step
One is we solve for we solve for optimal
consumption solve for for SAR C star
stop solve for the the optimal
consumption pair how do we do that well
as we said last time constrained
optimization are the point where you can
the highest difference curves you can
reach given your budget constraint leads
you to set
mrss equal to
mrrt that's the tangency condition
that's the point where you're as well
off as possible remember it's marginal
thinking in economics it's the next unit
you want to consume pizza and cookies
until the next unit makes you as happy
as the price the market charges how
happy does it make you well that's your
margin rate of substitution that's minus
s over C what is the market charge well
that's minus the price ratio which is
minus a
half okay so basically we derived that
last time or uh yes we derived that two
times ago that is the constrained
optimization now we then or last time
now but we go to the next step now which
is would say well what does that imply
for optimal slices and cookies well we
just plug that into the budget
constraint we have we have this equation
which is one equation in in uh two
unknowns we also this equation which is
that
24 equals 4S + 2
C so now we have two equations and two
unknowns okay we know how to do that
okay and we solve that we get that c
star equals 6 and S star equals 3 we
just solve those two equations and two
unknowns and then we get
C star is six n s star is
three okay so that is
Illustrated in the top panel of figure
one uh in the future let's not make it
so compressed more I'm I'm okay with
killing a few more trees to make sure
our fine students don't have to hurt
their Vision okay so basically that is
if you look at in figure 41 at the very
top you look at budget constraint one
okay that is our original budget
constraint we just had you and the
tangency the Alum point is at Point a
you want six cookies and three slices of
pizza okay this is reviewing what we did
before questions about that though
because this is some math you're G have
to do over and over and over again till
you're sick of it questions about
that okay so now let's ask what happens
if the price of cookies
changes what happens if the price of
cookies Rises to Rises to three so let's
say the price of
cookies goes from two to
three well the new slope of the budget
constraint is now instead of minus one2
it's minus 1/3 so un optimization
problem is set Min - s over c equal to
minus 13 not minus
one2 your budget constraint is now
24 = 4S + 3 C
once you have two equations in two
unknowns you've solved that and you get
that c star equals 4 SAR equals
3 okay yeah question speak up so
everyone can hear
you oh uh negative s over C I'm sorry
what is your
question is it
negative uh did I do that wrong
yes you're right my bad neg3 over4 I
should never do that with look at my
notes good catch neg3 over4 okay so you
solve that and you end up getting the
optimum of cookies is four Optimum slice
of pizza is three that is point B on the
top
diagram how did we get there well
mathematically I showed you subject to
one mathematical mistake I showed you
how to get there graphically how do we
get there well we draw the new budget
constraint
bc2 okay and we find the tangency
between the indifference curve and that
new budget constraint bc2 offers a
smaller opportunity set as we discussed
last time so you'll end up with fewer
Goods you have a smaller opportunity set
and you do you end up with the same
amount of pizza but with fewer
cookies likewise what if the price of
cookies fell to 4/3 what if the price of
cookies
went from 2 to
4/3 well once again you could do the
math and you'll find that basically when
you do that you're going to want three
slices and nine
cookies and graphically you can see that
that's a outward shift in the budget
constraint to
bc3 that's the rightmost budget
constraint your indifference curve is
tangent with that budget constraint at
nine cookies and three slices
pizza so what's happening here we are
shifting the price of cookies and
showing you based on tools you've
learned how that impacts how many
cookies you want how many slices you
want in other words we're drawing the
demand curve look at the translation
from the top figure to the bottom figure
the bottom figure has on it cookies on
the x- axis and the price of cookies on
the y- axis well that's a demand curve
we've just drawn it I've just shown you
for three different prices of cookies
how many different cookies you
want so we are we have now derived the
domain curve we derived the domain curve
by op by optimizing your utility at
different prices and finding which
quantity you want at each of those
different prices and that's the demain
curve it's the quantity you want at each
price so that's where the demain curve
comes
from okay yeah
number
of great point someone noticed and that
as we varied the price of cookies the
number of slice of pie did not change
that is not a general law that is a
specific feature of this utility
function in general when you change one
price both Goods will change what's nice
one reason we use this convenient
utility function is has some nice
mathematical properties and one is it
makes life easy by having the slice of
pizza stay the same the price so
essentially what we're saying here is
that we have for pizza we have what we
call a flat price consumption curve okay
which is BAS a cross price consumption
curve which is basically when the price
of one good changes the demand for the
other good doesn't change and that's
just a feature of this particular
utility function but it's not
General
okay now in fact you could yeah go
ahead the margin exactly so I I skipped
a step which is defining the mrss I
defined that last time or two time I
don't remember two times ago I think the
mrss is remember the the M negative of
the ratio of the Marge utility of
cookies to Mar utility of pizza okay and
that's minus that so so what the way we
got this we did two lectures ago we
basically uh uh took the derivative of
the utility function first with respect
to cookies then with respect to Pizza we
got the two different margin utilities
and then we took the ratio that gives
the margin rate of substitution all
right good question good to clarify
where that came from so this is building
on the work we did two lectures
ago other
questions okay so that is where demand
curves come from fun exercise at home do
the same exercise changing the price of
pizza do the reverse exercise you will
find as well there's a flat there's no
effect the number of cookies but you
will find effect on the number of slices
of pizza and you can show how that will
how that'll vary okay now now that we
know what demand curves are I want to
talk about what do they look like let's
talk about the
shape of demand curves what drives what
they look
like okay and what drives what demand
curves look like is going to be what we
call the elasticity of
demand okay the elasticity of
demand Epsilon is going to be the
percentage change in quantity Delta Q
over Q per percentage change in price or
a continuous time DQ
DP and basically we're gonna we're going
to generally work in discrete space but
the math you can do continuously I I
write it both ways because you're G to
the examples we'll use will sort of do
in discrete space it's a little easier
to see it but basically it's the
derivative of the quantity with respect
to the price it's the percentage change
in quantity with respect to price okay
so approximately equals approximately
equals the
derivative okay so basically that is the
elasticity of demand this tells you how
responsive people's demand is to the
price they have to
pay once again I find it very useful to
fix ideas in this class to think about
extreme cases that never exist in
reality but can help you understand the
intuition so let's look at figure
42 figure 42 would be a case of
perfectly inelastic demand that that
would be
Ada equals z that we call perfectly
inelastic demand that's a vertical
demand
curve in this case demand does not
respond to
prices okay can anyone think of a good
that even could come close to a
perfectly in AAS demand or feature even
features of a good yeah like
what gas gas would be well it's you're
right in the sense
it's a very interesting example in the
sense it's sort of inelastic because
like you got to get to work on the other
hand there's a bus there's your bike you
could walk you could buy a new car so
it's not perfectly an elastic but it's
it's somewhat what else
yeah water would be something uh but
once again not perfectly because like
you can drink Coke you can drink juice
you can drink other things you're on the
right track yeah insulin is the classic
example we use okay there's no
substitute when you're having diabetic
you know when your diabetic trauma for
insulin uh you will not say you know
it's a buck more I'm just going to die
okay uh it is uh we think it's fairly
now it's not perfectly nothing's
perfectly in elastic at some point if
insulin was a million dollars you might
just not buy it because you can't afford
it but it's certainly locally
inelastic okay so that be an example of
kind of but once again these are great
examples of things which the examples
we're given are Goods which should be
somewhat inelastic but not perfectly
okay likewise in figure 43
we consider a good with perfectly
elastic demand which is Epsilon equals
negative
Infinity perfectly elastic demand that
is any infinite tmal change in price
causes an infinite change in
quantity once again doesn't exist in
reality but what types of goods would
have very very very elastic
demand
yeah luxury goods would have elastic
demand because basically you know you
don't really need them them what
else
yeah yeah so McDonald's versus Burger
King okay now we may have our
preferences but the bottom line is
McDonald's charged twice as much as
Burger King for a burger everyone just
go to Burger King okay basically it's
there is it's there there's a point at
which uh there're so and essentially
what is a
question oh no we're we're good examples
but here's the key
feature that differentiates elasticity
it's
substitutability Goods with no
substitutes are not
elastic Goods with lots of substitutes
are very elastic that's why I
immediately respond to gas by talking
about all the that's so embedded in my
brain that when someone brought off gas
what did I go to I went to all the
substitutes because more substitutes
there are the more elastic the good is
okay so basically you that's essentially
how to think about elasticity think
about
substitutability okay the degree of
substitutability is the degree of
elasticity and obviously everything in
the world is going to lie between these
two extremes there's nothing in the
world that's ever purely inelastic and
purely elastic but things are going to
lie between these two extremes and the
where they lie will be a function of how
substitutable they
are okay questions about
that now let me make a point that we are
going to um in this class um uh once
again be cheating a little bit about uh
linear versus nonlinear demand curves a
constant elasticity demand curve would
have to be
nonlinear you should if you don't see
that right away it's something you
should go home and think about a
constant elasticity but we're going to
we're going to talk about curves we're
going to talk about one elasticity and
draw linear curves so once again just
think is very local approximations so
it's approximately right okay so don't
get too thrown off by the nonlinear
linear part of this stuff and once it's
unclear
ask
yeah no it's it's it it's the it's the
elasticity it's how much a change
incremental change in price changes
quantity okay so now now let's talk
about another topic which is we've
talked we remember we talked about what
moves budget constraints we talked about
prices changing income changing so let's
talk about what happens when to demand
curves when income
changes income and demand
curves okay so now let's go to figure
44 once again we start at Point
a that is our original setup with the
budget strength 24 equal 4S + 2 C and
the utility function unal square root of
c and that gets a solution at Point
a okay now imagine that your income
rises from $24 to
$32 nothing else has changed your
preference is the same price is the same
but your income has risen from $24 to
$32 well in that case the
optimization is now you're still you're
you're still setting minus s over C
to a price ratio okay you're still
setting s over C to the price ratio
minus one2 that hasn't changed because
the price ratio hasn't changed and your
preferen haven't changed what's changed
is the second equation which your bud
rate is now 32 equals 4S plus 2
C so the tangency condition hasn't
changed which change R goes up is the
budget constraint and we solve for that
you'll now see you get that c star
equals 8 and SAR equals
4 so you changed your consumption but
not because price have changed you're
richer you want more that is exactly
what we see in at point
B point B shows remember when your
income goes up there's a parallel shift
outward in the budget constraint income
goes up parallel shift outward in the
budget constraint you still want to find
the tangency that tangency is still
going to solve this condition because
prices and preferences have haven't
changed it's just going to be a higher
quantity and that's what happens at
point
B same tangency at a higher quantity
likewise at Point C we show what happens
if your income Falls to
$16 then you want less pizza and fewer
fewer less pizza and fewer cookies four
cookies and two
slices what is that lead us to that
leads us to a relationship now between
your income
and the quantity demanded and that
relationship is shown in the second
panel of figure 44 we call this the
angle
curve the angle curve which is the name
for the relationship between income and
quantity demanded and you can draw an
angle curve for S and an angle curve for
C here we're drawing the angle curve for
C okay and the Ang the angle curve the
slope of the angle curve is what we call
the in elasticity of demand or
gamma which is Delta Q over Q over Delta
y over y or approximately DQ
Dy okay so
basically this is instead of how does
demand change with price which is the
demand curve this is how does demand
change with income or what we call the
angle curve
Okay so
now and we're going to come in a few
minutes about why this is important but
let's talk about the properties of
gamma okay gamma is much more
interesting than Epsilon Epsilon you
know some negative number zero to minus
infinity gamma can have a much larger
range in fact gamma is usually greater
than zero in fact when gamma is greater
than zero we call them normal
Goods normal Goods goods are Goods where
gamma is greater than
zero but gamma does not have to be
greater than zero well Epsilon has to be
less than or equal to zero gamma does
not gamma could actually be less than
zero does anyone know how that could
happen how could it happen that you get
richer and want less of something what's
an example yeah it's what's what's
called inferior good okay but give an
example
right right exactly so as you get richer
you want to get rid of things that you
only eating because they were cheap
what's an example of that yeah Ramen is
the example of that Ramen is the
ultimate inferior good no one wants to
eat ramen I realize there's fancy Ramen
restrant but you know nobody should go
there okay people want to eat R people
eat ramen because it's cheap okay no in
all seriousness it is sort of amazing
that Ramen is become sort of a
restaurant food after all you know it is
in other countries I realize but most
consumption of ramen is done by she pack
it to the supermarket okay as you get
richer you consume less Ramen you might
not consume zero you might still like it
but you're not need it five days a week
like when you're starving you know
entrepreneur trying to make your own
business okay so Ram is example of an
inferior good a good that as you get
richer you have less of it because
basically you're only eating it because
it was
cheap okay now even within normal Goods
we have a distinction which is within
normal Goods we distinguish between two
things which gamma greater than one and
Gamma less than
one what do you think we call Goods with
gamma greater than one versus gamma less
than one and this relates to examples
that were given
before yeah or which
one greater than one so basically luxury
goods are where as your income Rises the
percent of your income spent on the good
goes up let's be very clear as your gun
Rises you consume more of everything
generally
but it's how does the budget share
change do you spend more and more of
your budget on that good as you get
richer and that's what we call a luxury
good so a classic luxury good would be
eating at restaurants when you're
poor you have to buy you have to make
your own dinners because eating
restaurants too expensive as you get
richer a larger and larger share of your
budget will be consumed by eating at
restaurants okay that's a luxury good
what about Gamma less than one what we
call that
anyone got any ideas gamma less than one
yeah what
then no GI and good is well that we'll
come back to that gamma you're you're
one step ahead gamma less than one
simpler than that so if these are
luxuries what are
these
Necessities sorry for the small
writing Necessities these are Goods
where as your income goes up you don't
have less of them Ramen is an inferior
good you literally have less Ramen but
this is like eating at home eating at
home you don't necessarily you don't eat
spend less on eating at home as you get
richer but you might spend a lower share
or this could be clothes or this could
be
rent things where if I get rich you get
a nicer apartment but if you get really
rich you know when you're poor your
apartment's 60% of your income when
you're rich it's going to fall yeah
more than zero exactly exactly it's less
than one but more than zero that's a
great Point these are both greater than
one this is less than one but greater
than zero if it's less than zero it's
inferior so that's the interesting
distinction between necessity inferior
let me explain this very clear inferior
is it's very unclear I mean inferior is
as your income goes up you literally
have less of it necessity as your income
goes up you have more of it but it goes
but it rises F slower than your income
so rent is the perfect example richer
people have nicer Apartments than poorer
people but richer people spend a smaller
share of their budget on apartments than
do poor
people okay it's a necessity richer
people have nicer watches than poor
people and it's a rising share of their
budget as they get richer because they
don't have a nice watch when they're
poor and as they get rich they buy nicer
and nicer
watches okay
yeah we're going to do that in one
minute other questions
okay these are The Primitives that allow
us to go on to do um the fun the the
sort of fundamental goal of this lecture
which is to get into
behind the mechanics of what happens
when you change prices did everyone get
this can I put this
up okay what happens what's the
mechanics of what happens when you
change
prices now you said you say John you
just showed what happens when you change
prices the price goes up people want
less of it the price goes down people
want more of it you derive the demand
curve let us go a half hour early and I
say no I will not let you go a half hour
early because there's actually a very
important underlying mechanics going on
when the price changes and this
mechanics is largely not so relevant for
most Goods we do but for some Goods who
delay the semester to be critical and
that's why it's important to understand
the mechanics and this is um basically
the fact that when a price changes when
a price changes so this calls mechanics
of a price
change when a price changes two things
happen simultaneously you may not
realize it but actually when a price
changes two things
happen the first is what we call the
substitution
effect the substitution effect which is
when relative prices change you want to
shift away from the good that's gotten
relatively expensive towards the good
that's gotten less
expensive that's the substitution effect
you say yeah that makes sense that's a
price change but the second one is the
income
effect which is when a price changes
you're also effectively richer or poorer
and that also affects your
demand so when a price changes two
things happen Goods become
differentially attractive and you're
richer or poor and both things drive
your response to that price change and
it turns out understanding the
difference between them will end up
being critical for a number of things
we'll do this semester and that's why
I'm bothering telling you so
okay so let to understand this we're
going to go through one of the more
complicated examples of this class so
that's why I'm leaving time with time
for it we're going to talk about
decomposing a price change into an
income and substitution effect and then
I get we're going to do the math of this
in section or did we yeah we'll do the
mathematics of this in section it's hard
enough I'll do the graphics here and the
intuition the math will be covered in
section okay so now let's go back to our
classic example we start at Point a
we're on original budget constraint one
so this is figure four five look at bc1
that's original budget constraint and
our indifference curve is tangent at
Point a so as we've said a number of
times this sem this lecture we choose
six cookies and three pizzas that's our
base
case now imagine that the price of
cookies rises from $2 to
$3 well we know what happens we solve
for that already earlier this lecture
when the price cookies rise from $2 $3
we know you move from point A to point
C you move from consuming six cookies
and three slices of pizza of four
cookies and three slice of pizza we
already solve for that great you already
know that why aren't we done
we are done because that's composed of
two effects a substitution effect and
income effect how do we measure these
well the way we do it
graphically is we say the substitution
effect is technically
defined as the change in the quantity
purchased holding utility constant so
it's Delta
Q at
ubar holding your utility
constant how would you change change
your mix of
goods how do we measure that we measure
by drawing an imaginary budget
constraint BC Prime this isn't a real
budget constraints imaginary and we find
the point and what is BC Prime BC Prime
has two features first of all it is
parallel to the new budget
constraint it's parallel to the new it's
got the new price ratios the slope of
the new budget constraint of BC Prime is
the same as bc2 so minus 3/4 right that
was the uh the slope was uh yeah minus
3/4 okay so the new budget constraint
has a slope of minus 3/4s but it is
tangent to the original indifference
curve the one that contains point
a so once again how do we measure the
substitution effect we measure it by
drawing a new budget constraint
imaginary budget
constraint that is parallel to the new
budget constraint it it's the new price
ratio minus 3/4 instead of minus a half
but tangent to the old indifference
curve and think about what that's doing
we're showing you the change in qu
quantity you get at a constant utility
how do we keep utility constant we stay
in the same indifference curve so by
staying in the same indifference curve
we're holding utility constant and we're
showing you that even with utility
constant you would want fewer cookies
why would you want why would you want
fewer cookies you'd move from six
cookies to 4.89 cookies why because
cookies have gotten more expensive Rel
to Pizza
that's the pure substance doesn't matter
you're rich or poor it's just cookies
have got more expensive you want fewer
of
them it's easy understand if we go
directly to the second
effect okay if we go directly to the
second effect okay which is um oh well
no actually let me do one thing first I
want to First prove to
you that the substitution effect is
always
negative the substitution effect is
negative okay so to prove that so
graphically we can prove that by just
noting that if you're on the same
indifference
curve and you're tangent to a steeper
budget
constraint you must be to the left right
if I'm the same IND different Square the
bud straight steepen I must be to the
left of the original point so it's got
to be a negative
effect
mathematically think of this in Five
Steps step one the substitution effect
puts you at the tangency of the
difference curve in
prices we know at that
tangency that mu C over muu s
equals PC over PS I just canceled the
negatives okay we know those are equal
at any tangency we know those are equal
at every
tangency we know that this has gone up
price of cookies has gone up Rel to
pizza slices right once again jump in if
anything's not
clear if that goes up what has to happen
this has to go up they have to be equal
the right side went up so the left side
has to go up how do you make the
marginal utility ratio go up how do you
make it so that the ratio marginal of
cookies the marginality of slices goes
up what do you do how can you
operationalize that
well how do you make the numerator
higher how do you make the Marge utility
of cookies
bigger
yeah yeah remember Marge utilities are
negative function of quantity I said
they're confusing the fewer cookies you
have the more each cookie is
worth if you have fewer cookies that
means you have to have more slices if
you have more slices what does that do
to the marginality of slices it lowers
it so by shifting from cookies to slices
you lower the r you rate I'm sorry you
raise the ratio margin utilities you
raise the numerator and lower the
denominator through that
shift so you therefore say that if
you're going to be tangent and you're
going have a higher price ratio you
must have fewer cookies and more slices
by definition and that's the proof that
substitution effects are
negative okay questions about that
if the price goes up
Absolutely I'll tell you that in a
minute but this if the price goes
up
okay other questions it's a good
question good clarification okay now
let's go to the second effect the income
effect the income effect is say is
measuring the change the effect of the
the Delta
quantity due to income effectively
Rising
what do you mean income Rises your
income hasn't changed
here why is income effectively risen why
are you effectively Rich I'm sorry um
sorry the income is Fallen my bad your
income's effectively fallen in this case
why are you effectively
poor now your income hasn't changed why
effectively poor
yeah yeah your opportunity set has been
constricted so your income itself hasn't
fallen but your resources have what you
can buy with that income has fallen
you're effectively
poor so it's not really that why is
Fallen it's sort of why over sort of the
composite price you know the the price
level has fallen why over the price
levels Fallen the overall price level in
society's increased pizza's the same
cookies are up so your effective income
is Fallen your real income is
Fallen okay you're effectively poor what
does that mean if you're effectively
poor what's going to happen
well what does that depend on that
depends
on
this that's why I bother telling you so
I'm a big Dr Seuss fan okay basically if
it's a normal
good and the and your income goes down
what will you do you'll have less of it
but if it's an inferior good and income
goes down what will you do you'll have
more of it so while the substitution
effect can be signed the income effect
cannot the in effect cannot be signed
because it depends on whether it's a
normal or inferior
good
okay in the case we're showing here in
figure four five this is a normal good
so the income effect works in tandem
with the substitution effect the
substitution effect you want so you want
fewer cookies for two reasons let's
here's the intuition here's the key
intuition you want fewer cookies for two
reasons first cookies are a worse deal
you have the opportunity cost of cookies
has
risen second you're effectively poorer
your opportunity set is constricted and
cookies are normal good so for those two
reasons you want fewer
cookies but what if cookies were an
inferior good then the graph would look
like figure
46 the graph like figure 46 in this case
the substitution effect would go one way
but the income effect would go the other
way and the net would be
unclear now we've drawn figure 46 such
that the demand for cookie still Falls
but you don't have to draw it that
way okay so the key thing is the
substitution effect has to be the
opposite of the sign of the price change
negative but let's be clear it's good
clarification Subs effect has to be the
opposite of the sign of the price change
the income effect does not think effect
depends on whether it's a normal or
inferior
good this is pretty confusing so I find
it's useful to um to actually uh think
about well let's let's actually rush
through figure 4 six let's what figure
46 is because it's not this I I I rush
you figure 46 let's go back figure 46 is
no longer pizza and cookies figure 46 is
now steak and potatoes okay because
pizza and cookies are both normal Goods
potatoes is the classic inferior
good right poor people especially back
in the day used to have to eat potatoes
because they were cheap to grow and very
filling and steak was
unaffordable but basically as you get
richer you want fewer potatoes and more
steak okay especially an Agricultural
Society okay so let's say originally
people are at
bc1 where the price of steak is $5 the
price of potatoes a
dollar the price of steak is $5 the
price of potato is a dollar and let's
say their income is $25 so in this
example incomes
25 the price of a stake
is five and the price of
potatoes is
one okay so the budget constraint looks
like
bc1 you can have for $25 you can have 25
potatoes or five
steaks and let's say your preferences
are such that you end up at Point a you
choose to have three and a half steaks
and seven and a half potatoes okay once
again I just got that through the magic
we showed you last time this is
constrained optimization I'm not writing
down the utility function I'm just going
right to the results but you know how to
get there
now let's say that things change and the
price of potatoes rise to $3 a
pound steak is still five bucks a pound
potatoes are now $3 a pound now what
happens is your budget strange shifts
into
bc2 your budget constraint is pivoted in
massively so now you still have five
Stakes of all you want is stake but you
can only have 8.3 potatoes on your $25
of income new budget screen is bc2
what happens well let's look at the
income and substitution effects the
substitution effect we get by drawing an
imaginary budget constraint BC Prime
what are the features of BC prime it is
parallel to the new budget
constraint but tangent to the old
indifference curve and so that puts us
at point B so substitution effect lowers
our demand for for
potatoes from 7 and2 to four we knew had
to lower it subst effect is
unambiguously signed the price went up
so you got to have few of them that's
unambiguous the income effect however
goes the other way because potatoes are
inferior in other words now that you're
so poor now potatoes so expensive you
don't have money for steak anymore so
you gotta have more potatoes it's ironic
right but basically potatoes getting
expensive has made you poor when you're
poor you got to have more
potatoes okay and so the income effect
goes the other way because potatoes are
an inferior good effect takes you back
from wanting four potatoes up to wanting
five potatoes so the net effect if we
didn't income substitution would we just
see well with your demand curve would
just say oh well you know demand curve
slop down it's you know we get a higher
price leads to fewer potatoes but we
miss the fact that the substitution
effects are going opposite
directions okay questions about that
example
yeah they're all price going there's the
price of potatoes going up to three from
I'm sorry the price of potatoes went
from one to
three okay Price p went from one to
three that led to a substition effect
that we know which way it goes when a
price goes up you want less of something
the substitution effect but an income
effect that went the other way now that
leads the natural question can you
actually get an income effect for an
inferior good that ends up bigger than
the substitution effect that is Could
you actually get get demand curves to
not slope down think about what would
happen if the income effect was so big
that it pushed you past the original
point it pushed you to the right past
the original intersection well that
would imply something funky that would
imply demand curve slope down demand
curve slope up instead of sloping down
then apply demand curve slope up that
would say higher prices make you want
more of something which violates what we
the very first lecture of this class we
said domain curves slop
down but it's possible theoretically
that you can get what's called a gfin
good a gfin good is a good where the
income effect the good is so
inferior that the income effect
dominates the substitution effect you
end up with a wrong signed relationship
between price and demand you actually
get that a higher price leads to more
demand or an upward sloping demand
curve now can that happen well I like to
I like the name GF and because it rhymes
with Griffin and Griffins are
imaginary okay GI and goods are also
largely imaginary it's a great
theoretical concept but they don't
really exist
yeah a VIN Goods is a different Vin
that's a totally different concept
that's that's the concept that basically
you want more when the price is up
because you care about your social
standing uh but that's that's sort of a
behavioral economics thing we'll come
back to that talk behav it's not a
standard economics
effect so GI and goods really don't
exist um the classic example people
often have had was well gee when the
price of
potatoes um went up uh in Ireland cuz
the potato blight people ended up
consuming more potatoes so potato
consumption went up per person in
Ireland when the price of potatoes went
up during the potato blight people said
aha potatoes are a GI and good but
here's what they got wrong here's where
empirical economics is fun they missed
the fact that what other effect did the
potato blight have it chased all the
people who could afford it out of
Ireland the only people who left were
super poor so yeah so yeah on average
potatoes per person went up but it
wasn't that each person consume more
it's just people who didn't consume many
potatoes left all people left were just
huge potato consumers so if you look at
the data you see potatoes per capita
went up it's a given good what you're
missing is the Capas are
different each person eat more potatoes
it's just the non-p poat eaters left
people left with The Potato Eaters and
that's why empirical economics is fun
because it can help explain these kind
of anomalies so where does this leave us
let's draw let's draw a chart here to
explain this all okay so this let's
imagine we're going to have here the
price
change the price change we're going to
have the substitution
effect the income
effect and the net
effect okay and we're going to start
with normal
Goods we're start with normal Goods so
with normal Goods if the price goes up
like I just showed you
the subs effect must be negative must be
the opposite of the price
change the income
effect if it's a normal good must also
be
negative therefore on net you get a
higher price leads to lower
demand likewise if the price goes down
this is what this good this good
question was highlighting I was just
looking a price going up well in that
case the substitution effect let's think
about the
intuition if the price of cookies went
down we have just lowered the
opportunity cost of having
cookies therefore we're going to want
more cookies and fewer Pizza through the
substitution effect so therefore the
substitution effect will be positive if
the price goes down the income effect
will also be positive why why the income
effect be positive if the price of
cookies goes
down why the income effect be positive
yeah
you're effectively richer you can buy
more cookies with the same money since
you're richer you want more normal Goods
cookies are normal good you want more
cookies so this goes
up now what's more interesting is what
if these goods were inferior what if
cookies were
inferior so now when the price goes
up what happens to substitution effect
through Subs effect is demand it goes
down as this gentleman helpfully pointed
it goes down why because we know the
sign of substitution effects they're
always the opposite of the price change
no mystery there price goes up
substitution effects are Subs effect
drives demand down price goes down
substitution effect um I'm sorry goes up
yeah right PR price goes up Subs effect
drives demand down price goes down
substitute effect drives demand up those
never change so here if the price goes
down substitute effect will be positive
those don't change what changes is the
income effect if it's an inferior good
if it's an inferior
good now when the price goes up okay
when the price goes up you want more of
it and when the price goes down you want
less of it so the net is
unclear okay so once again if goods are
normal then demand curves look like them
you know then basically there's no this
this seems if goods are normal it seems
like I just wasted 20 minutes to your
time right because if goods are normal
it's like well look yeah they build on
each other but we end up in the same
place in the imaginary B strs imaginary
anyway so who cares the answer is I'll
tell you why we care in three or four Le
in about six
lectures because it turns out when you
make your decisions about how hard
you're going to work or how much you're
going to save income sub effects are
going to start to work against each
other this case is only really
interesting if the income affects if
it's an inferior good and then you can
get some interesting things although
practice we don't really have gi and
goods but in theory at least you can get
interesting
things okay questions about
that okay one other announcement please
don't go um I really love that you guys
come after lecture and ask me questions
that's awesome I just do have to say on
Mondays I have to sort of book out of
here fairly quickly uh so don't feel
dissed I do have office hours and if you
can't make the office hours just email
me I have I'm in the office lots of
times just email and we can talk thanks