So um right so to one of the things I
want to focus on today and we'll get to
this in just a minute is uh how to write
a proof. So this is going to be
uh
how to write uh a mathematical proof.
So how how do you write a proof as
opposed to you know how do you think
about uh why something should be true,
right? And so this is like one of the
important topics for this uh course. So
uh you know overall I mean there's a lot
of uh important concepts that we will
talk about right but some of the general
things that we learn is how to prove
something but also how to write a proper
mathematical proof right and those
things are a little bit different and
we'll talk about this in a minute.
Uh I also want to say that so on the
course information the last page of the
course several people were asking about
this on the last page of course
animation
there is uh there is right so there's a
notes there's a notes for the class that
I write uh and I typically I try to
write them in advance a couple of days
in advance and then I try to go over it
the day uh also to make sure to find
tbooks and things like that. So that is
more readable. Uh so if I were you, I
would first read the lecture notes that
I post after the lectures. Uh and then
there's also on the last page of the
course information there is uh and I try
to do this in advance but it's a little
bit difficult to do it in advance. So uh
it say the the date and it say the
material some keywords from the lecture
uh on that date. So I over the weekend I
posted for the two lectures for this
week
but then I go back I will try to go
back. So I actually went back this
morning and changed some of it from the
second lecture so that it fits more and
I think I will only uh I give references
there to the book but and initially I
was thinking giving both references to
Ruden and to the main textbook.
I think it's probably just uh maybe it's
I mean I think it's probably smarter
just to give it from the main textbook.
Okay. But I and uh Rudin is a great book
um you know this was a book uh that was
that was um that was created here long
time ago and it it is like a classic in
the subject. It's a great book. It's
more formal than the other book. So the
other book is a little bit more
accessible.
Uh, and so that's why we're using that.
But but actually Rudin is a fantastic
book. If if it was just myself,
uh, I would just I think Ruden is hard
to beat. But but but the other one is is
more accessible and so it might actually
be better the first time you learn it.
And but so I think from here on out, so
I deleted the references I had to root
in. I think I would just give references
to the main textbook
uh and and but but you know I certainly
encourage you to look at root and also I
also encourage you to look at chapters
that we will skip uh but there's also
things that that we initially skip and
then we come back to
but but again you know you should and
it's like the when I list the things
that we will cover in the lecture in
advance it's only sort of approximation
right so um once I write lecture it
might be slightly different
okay so um so we had uh so last time we
talked about the theorem we didn't prove
it that the real is a complete
uh order field,
right? And so in particular, it was an
order set uh that was uh also a field
and it was complete, right? And so
again, complete meant so if you had a
subset a here, which was a subset of of
R,
then uh A is bounded.
It's bounded from above.
[Applause]
Uh if there exist
uh m in uh r such that
for all
uh a in a
a here is less equal to m. So,
and then if that's the case, then we say
that and M here
is set to be
uh an upper bound.
Likewise, might likewise
uh if um if a here is a subset of r
uh uh then we say that
that uh a is bounded from below.
If there exist
uh little m in in R such that
uh m here is less than a for all Okay.
Okay.
So, this is upper and lower bounds.
Okay. And several people ask on on Piaza
they ask um you know they were a little
unclear about
um you know where does this M capital M
where does this have to be in what set
does it have to be? And likewise for
this little M, right? And so let me try
to give you some example and I try to do
that on P, but let me just uh just
because several people were asking about
it, let me just say again. So that this
capital M when you have it like this,
this capital M does not need to be in
the set, right? A is bounded. So here's
an example.
If you're looking at the set 0 one. So
this is the interval. This is the
interval but it does not contain zero
and it does not contain one but it
contain everything in between zero and
one.
This one here is bounded. So this if
this here is a and we think about a here
as a subset of r
then a is bounded
and so one usually say it's bounded if
it's it's it's both from above and
below.
All right. So if one just say that it's
bounded then one means that it's bound
from above and below
it's bounded
and uh right and so because like bounded
from above
about because you can just you have that
if x here is in this interval then of
course x is lesser or equal to one right
in fact it's strictly less than one
Right?
But you see this set here, there is no
element in the set that is an upper
bound for this set, right? The upper
bound is outside the set, but it is an
all of our and that's that's fine,
right? An upper bound uh is will
typically just be in a larger set. And
the same with uh with
with lower bound.
Now these this kind everything on this
board except this theorem but you know
this in terms of ordered sets right has
nothing to do you know it's just much
more general than R. So if you take if S
here is an ordered set
and A here is a subset
it's a subset.
So it's a ordered set. So so it it's a
set with an ordering. And if a here is a
subset of s
then again we can say that uh a is
bounded from above.
If um if uh there exist
m again m does not have to be an a
but it can be just in the larger set so
that such that
for all
a in a it's lesser equal to m
Right? So this is just this is like the
definition in general being bounded
above if you have a order set and you
have a subset. Right? And now just to
illustrate it. So typically we're going
to think about where the set is with a
usual ordering and you have a subset of
it and you talk about whether it's
bounded from above or below.
But of course, you could also do it in
in a more general setting like this,
right? And so here's an example
that if you look at which maybe is
counterintuitive,
but if you take if s here is
is the half line. So it's it's all the
real numbers
between
uh say zero and infinity.
Um
and um
and then uh you would have a here is a
subset
zero to one.
Right?
Now a here and the ordering. So this is
this is of course a subset of r but you
should forget about r. I mean you know
you know the ordering from r but forget
about it because this is now what you
think about the set s right?
And so if you're looking at A as a
subset of this then A here A is bounded
from above.
Right? Why? This is just because for all
a in in a you have that A here is
strictly less than one. So one here is
an upper bound for A. Right? But now
think about does this set here has a
lower bound, right?
Well, a lower bound have to be inside
this set S, right? Because we're
thinking about this here as a subset of
this ordered set. We don't think about
it as a subset of the real line. But if
you think about it as a subset of this
set here, then there is no lower bound,
right? because zero is not in this set
and no negative numbers in this set. So
this here so and this seems maybe a
little bit counterintuitive but a is not
is not
bounded from below
as a subset of
of s. Obviously it is bounded from below
if you were thinking about it as a
subset of real real line. But if you
think about it as a subset of S, it's
not bounded from below.
Okay. So
[Applause]
another person was asking the infinite
and minus infinity those are not uh real
numbers. Okay.
>> Yeah.
try.
>> Uh
uh if it's not directly stated that if
that it's not directly stated that
there's a set S
uh and then it has to be a subset of
that set, right? then it would be
assumed that is a yeah a of course you
welcome to to ask on pat is you know I
don't have the homework here but but but
I would say that you're safe if it's if
it's not stated directly what the larger
set is then you can assume it's are
because we're going to concentrate
mostly on our this is another
distinction between Ruden and and this
book that is the main textbook ruden is
more abstract than the main textbook we
are using
in particular. Um you know the this the
main textbook here and I'll do the same
in my lectures is that a lot of things
are motivated from R and then you
abstract afterwards. So whereas ruden
starts with abstraction and then it
specializes to R and and of course
there's you know there's an argument for
maybe starting with a familiar and then
abstract instead of doing the other way
around.
Okay so
right and so for a whether it's just a
order set I mean just in general so so
remember that completeness
So completeness. So this is when you
have a order set.
So if you have a order set and a here is
a subset
uh of s that is bounded from above
from above.
uh then if this if it is complete if S
is complete. So if
S is complete
then any subset that is bounded from
above
uh has a has a least upper bound. Then
uh then a has a list
upper bound.
Okay. And that least upper bounds is
denoted by the soup
of a. Right? So, so this thing here it
has the property
that uh that a is lesser equal to m for
all
uh a in a and also if
m_1 is another upper bound
upper bound
for a
then
uh m is less or equal to m.
So that's a least ups
and the same thing is so similarly
when we have a order set and we have a
set if it's complete and if we have
uh
if uh a here
is bound from below Boom.
Then uh then
uh infair
of A is the least up is the
the largest the greatest
uh lower bound
for A right. So this again means that
this number here little M. So M here is
lesser equal to A for all
A in A.
And if M1 here is another lower bound.
then uh m1 here is less or equal to m.
So this is the symmetric property.
And so again r the reals uh is complete.
So whenever you take a bounded subset of
the real so if it's bounded that means
that it's bounded from above and below
then it has a least upper bound and a
greatest lower bound. Okay. And those
are are denoted by soup and if right and
and in general soup and in are not in
the set itself in the set a right
I mean they could be but in general they
wouldn't be. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> That's as right. Uh so
uh no so so if you're looking at this
set here right
so suppose that this here is is the set
um
uh
uh s then and if you take a here is a
subset of s and a here is bounded from
let's say that a there is bounded from
below,
right? If it's bounded from below,
you know, then it couldn't be this set
here.
This here is not bounded from below,
right? So, it sort of means that if it's
bounded from below, then a here could
not have numbers that was approaching
zero.
Right? And so actually if it is bounded
from below,
if it's a subset of this and it's
bounded from below, then actually it
would have a least lower bound lower
bound, right? You should mean
so it is it is I mean I'm not going to
prove anything is complete or not
complete but but it's pretty convincing
that it is actually complete.
Um in this sense there's an other sense
that is not complete but but anyway in
this sense it is complete. Yeah. No it's
it's it's a little bit uh it can be
confusing. Later on we'll talk about
maybe some other notion of completeness
and then it's not complete but but this
notion it is complete.
Okay. So, so
um the the the next thing I want to get
to is this with how to write a
mathematical proof. Okay. And so and and
again
I mean that's a super important thing to
learn in this class.
Uh and and it's not just a
it's not just a
a formal thing.
Uh I mean, you know, it Yeah. I mean, it
may seem like a formal thing, you know,
why bother with that? Uh uh but it's
really really useful and the more
complicated things become, the more
useful it is.
And so um so I want to illustrate this
with how to write a mathematical proof.
So I going going to illustrate this. So,
so we will illustrate it
by by uh proving again by by by uh by
writing a
a formal proof
of time
square root of two
is a real number.
So I want to write a a I want to you
know so last time we talked about that
square root of two was a real number and
but that what we when we proved it it
was more like we talked about the idea
and so and so then the question is so if
you have like you imagine you have a
piece of scrap paper what we did last
time was what you would be writing on
the scrap paper. So I want to talk about
you know if you were handing it in or
showing it to something somebody then
you wouldn't do that
uh you would do what we do now and but
it doesn't necessarily make for a great
a formal proof doesn't necessarily make
for a great lecture because it's kind of
formal.
So, so, so let me try to explain how you
should should write this. And again,
this is a very simple example.
Um, but hopefully it will give you an
idea of what to do. And again, this is a
really important part of this class that
you know you you're bound to use in many
other classes later on.
Okay. So let's first talk about what was
square root of two. So square root of
two this here was a number and it was
given by that it has a property that
it's positive and when you square it
then you get two right that was what
square root of two was.
Now
um
so we again so we want to prove so this
is the theorem. So theorem
square root of two is a real number.
So I know maybe I should write it more
formally. there exist
alpha greater than zero. Uh
there's alpha in r with
alpha greater than zero and alpha
squared is equal to two. Okay.
Now we look at the set
uh A.
The set A is the numbers uh the it's the
uh X
such that X is positive
uh and
uh X²
is lesser equal to two.
Yeah. So x here and so now I was
specialized to the real numbers. So that
was why I didn't actually write it but
but you're right. Certainly can't hurt.
Uh okay. So that's the theorem and so
now we try to write a formal proof.
Uh observe first
that
um a here is non empty
since
one is in a right one is positive and
when you square one you get one so this
is definitely less or equal to two so a
here is non
Um uh next observe
that
uh a here
is bounded is bounded from above.
In general, by the way, when you write a
proof, then you then you really only try
to establish the properties that you
need because otherwise it's confusing.
If you establish all kind of other
property that is not needed, that just
makes it confusing. So it's bounded from
above
and this is just because
um since
since uh two is an upper bound
for
okay
now the next thing here. So now we have
a non- empty bounded subset. So we set
so set alpha equal to the soup of a
and we we want to prove want to show
that alpha is positive and alpha squ is
equal to 2.
[Applause]
Well,
right by definition the way we defined
uh
the way we defined a all the elements in
a were positive. So by definition
uh uh uh zero is a lower bound.
So so you for sure have that zero here
is less or equal to well it's actually I
mean even one is a lower bound. So, so
uh we can also just say that one since
one is a lower bound since since one
here is in a you also have that this
alpha here must be bigger equal to one
because it was supposed to be an upper
bound for a. So in particular
now um
and so we have that alpha is less than
one and it's the least upper bound and
two was an upper bound. So you are to
have this
since uh maybe I should write if you
write write it with this uh since since
one is an a we have
that one here lesser equal to alpha.
Uh
and
since
alpha is the least of a bound
and true is an upper bound.
We have
that alpha is less than equal to two.
Okay. Now remember I mean we're going to
do it exactly like we did last time but
we're just going to write it down uh in
a proper way as a proof. Right? So
remember that last time we then divided
the proof into two steps.
Uh the first step was uh so part one.
So, so, so now, so all we need to prove,
maybe I'll just say that all we need to
prove
to show
is that alpha square is equal to two,
right? Because we already have it as
positive now because it's bigger than
one, right?
And so there was two parts to this to
step one and step two or step part one
and part two.
The first part was so part one we will
show
that uh alpha squared
is less or equal to
uh two
and so we prove this. So
assume not
uh we will show that that leads
that. Um
this
leads to
a contradiction
to that alpha is the least upper bound
for
I mean I'm writing everything out here
right just to illustrate is right as you
get more and more familiar with this
right then the structure is the same but
you know some of these steps will seem
almost too trivial and that's probably
fine right but of course it's always
good to air on more details than fewer
details
okay so so this is what we want to do so
so we assume not so assume
so assume
that alpha squared is strictly bigger
than two. Right?
Then and this is where it sort of
deviate more from how we did it last
time
and that's why you know what we did last
time is really what you want to have on
on the scrap paper. I mean that's what
we did last time was like the idea and
then once you see the idea then you try
to write it as a formal proof like what
we do now
and so so so assume not
set
h equal to so I'm going to set h equ= to
alpha^ 2 - 2 over 4 alpha.
Okay. Right. Obviously, if this was like
the first time you would do it, you
wouldn't just come up with this sort of
thing, right? I mean, this is coming
from the scrap paper that you have,
right? You're setting h equal to that.
And then you observe
you observe that since since uh
since alpha here is bigger than one and
uh alpha squared is bigger than two.
Since that right then the nominator here
is positive and the denominator is
positive. So h here is positive right?
You also have that you also have that h
is um
uh
uh right you also have automatically
that uh that h is maybe we don't need
that. Let's see if we need that.
Uh okay. So now uh you def set
uh alpha 1 equal to uh alpha
minus h.
And what I want to prove is so we want
to show
that uh alpha here alpha 1 is an upper
bound
for a.
So I want to prove that this is an upper
bound for a the first thing I want to do
if it's an upper bounds it does need to
be need to be positive. So let's check
that.
So um so since
uh since
so since
we already have that h was positive so
this here was h was positive alpha^ 2 -
over 4 alpha.
Right? This thing here is less or equal
to I can even forget about the two. So I
can write it as alpha squar over 4
alpha. And so this here is I can just
divide by alpha. So I get alpha over 4.
So I have since we have that h here is
less than alpha over 4 then
uh alpha 1
is uh is bigger than
uh is bigger equal to 3/4
of uh of alpha right
because I'm subtracting at most alpha
over 4 and so there's still 3/4 of alpha
left right so I have This in particular,
this thing here, it's actually bigger
than 3 over 4, but I just need it to be
positive.
So, it's positive. So,
so alpha over alpha 1 is positive.
Now, I'm looking at alpha 1 squared,
right?
And so alpha 1^ 2 is uh is equal to
alpha minus h
squared.
So this here is equal to alpha^ 2 + h^ 2
- 2 alpha h.
Okay.
And this thing here is less or equal to
uh alpha squared.
Uh here h here is uh h is uh so now I
like to say that h is lesser equal to
one.
Uh actually I'm going to use that it's
less than a half. And why is that the
case? It's actually
uh alpha itself. We already know that
alpha was less than two. So you have
that this thing here is less or equal to
2 over 4. So this is equal to a half.
Right?
Um so now uh now I have that
um now I have that this thing here is
less than
um then plus
um here I can here I I just use that
it's less than
uh this thing here by this here I just I
think it's fine to just use uh h here I
could use h over two. Maybe I'll use h
over two. So one of the h I just replace
by a half that is an upper bound and the
other one uh I just keep right.
So I have that and then minus 2 alpha h.
But if you multiply alpha
by h then it's disappear in the
denominator. So you're getting minus 2
and then you're getting uh alpha squared
- 2 over uh 4
right and so here you get this here
becomes uh alpha squared
uh plus and here I'm just writing in and
I think it's at the moment we're sort of
overkilling it here. Um, and so I can
replace this one here. So, uh, right,
let me just write it in. Alpha 2 - 2
over, uh, 2 * 4 * alpha, right?
And this thing here is alpha 2 - 2 / 2.
This two cancel with one of those two.
So, this is what I have.
Uh and so now I get
that uh this thing here
is so
so I get that this thing here is uh um
uh
we adding it here. So this thing here is
uh alpha squared. So, let's just let me
just bring these two together. Let me u
let me just maybe I'll just uh combine
all of these. I don't think I need it
this well.
Um
um right. So, if I if I combine these
two here, I think I'm fine with just
having a a two here. H four, sorry,
instead of the two. So if I if I do that
then I get alpha squared
maybe I should just bring it on the
common denominator. So this here this
alpha sorry I'm get rid of I'm just I'm
replacing I'm bounding this from above
by alpha squar plus
and I'm going to I'm going to just make
it easy for myself. So I think it's fine
to just uh use that alpha is bounded by
one and then you can just bound it by
alpha squared minus 2 uh over 4
uh and uh and this in here is uh is
alpha squared
minus 2 over 2 right here again I'm just
using that alpha was bigger equal to
one. Uh and um right and then I I just
actually ignore this true right. So this
is definitely an upper bound.
And so now you see that this thing here
is equal to alpha squared. This thing
here you can think about this thing
here. You can write this in here if you
will as alpha^ 2 + alpha^ 2 - 2 over 4 -
2 alpha^ 2 - 2 over over 4.
And so what you get is that it's alpha^
2 minus alpha^ 2 - 2 over 4.
Right? And this thing here is now this
thing here is positive right because
alpha square was strictly bigger than
two. This is positive. So this is
strictly less than alpha square right.
And so this here would also which is
still right. This is
right. So this thing here is also an
upper bound. Uh, sorry. Sorry. Oh, I
need to Oh, sorry.
Okay. So, I have this.
No, no, sorry about that.
Okay. So, yeah. No, I I sorry. I um
Okay, let let's go over this again.
Sorry.
So what I'm trying to prove here I'm
trying to write down the formal I mean
that that's a problem that it got so
formal that that I was now in. So what
I'm trying to prove here is that I want
to say this part one is that alpha
squared
is lesser equal to to one. Right? This
is what less equal to two. That's what I
want to prove. Right? This is part one,
right? And so I assume not so I assume
that alpha square was strictly bigger
than two, right? If alpha square was
strictly bigger than two, here you have
zero. Here you have alpha and now we
define this alpha zero.
Alpha zero was to the left so to speak
of alpha because it was subtracting a
little bit
and what I want to show is that this
alpha zero I want to show that this
alpha zero is also an upper bound so I
want to prove that this square here is
also bigger than two that's what I want
to prove right
so I want to find I want to to find a
lower bound B and that lower bound
should be two. Right? So this is not
exactly what I wanted to do. Okay? So
let's just go through it here. Sorry. So
this here was correct and this here is
for really for the second part.
Uh
okay.
So we define it like this.
And now I say that this thing here
is bigger equal to
But I want to bound it from below. And
so then I can ignore the h squ. So it's
bigger than because that's positive just
bigger than alpha^ 2 - 2 alpha h. Right?
And this thing here is so this is equal
to alpha squar minus 2 alpha. I fill in
what h was. This here was h
right
and uh and uh then you see that this
here cancel with that and this here and
you're getting that you're getting alpha
squared
uh uh this is this alpha squar minus
uh alpha^ 2 - 2 / 2
And this thing here is equal to this is
equal to alpha squared over two. This is
subtracting that and then you're adding
right you're adding one. So this is what
it is right alpha we have already proven
that alpha here was bigger equal to one.
So, so using so this here is bigger
equal to I claim that this here is
bigger equal to two using
that
alpha is uh bigger equal to one right
and so you see that alpha one that is a
smaller number because you're
subtracting a positive number from alpha
that is also an upper bound right. So
this is contradicting. So this
contradict and then one often writes uh
one often writes this symbol here. This
is a standard symbol that means this is
a contradiction. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Then you get two. But that's fine.
I just needed to show I all I needed to
do was I needed to prove
that I I I I have that. So So you see
that I have that I'm assuming that this
thing here is strictly positive and then
I define alpha 1 but alpha 1 is strictly
less than alpha. Right? And then I have
that alpha squar alpha squar alpha 1
squared is bigger equal to two. This
here means that alpha 1 is also an upper
bound. This is strictly less than alpha.
This was supposed to be the least upper
bound. That's a contradiction. Right?
And so you see I fell into the trap. I
was doing it so formally that I lost
track of what I was doing. So I was
actually in a process of proving the I
mean that's a danger with but but the
formal proof is is much easier to read
afterwards, right? And so you see the
difference here with a formal proof was
last time we we sort of did a little
calculation and then we try to figure
out what should this H be and then it
sort of came at the end. Right? But but
when you write down the formal proof
then you would sort of upfront you would
already have done that little
calculation and you would up front say
what h was supposed to be and then you
kind of run through the argument. Right.
Yeah.
>> Sorry.
>> Uh um here. So
uh if I'm I'm I mean of course alpha is
much bigger than one but I'm just using
we already we I'm only need here that
alpha is bigger equal to one to say that
this thing here is bigger equal to two
>> sorry
>> this is right this is alpha so the the
inequality here is that alpha 1 2 is
bigger equal to two and I'm using that
alpha
at this stage here to conclude this
inequality. I'm using
uh sorry no no you're right yeah sorry
about that you're right I'm using that
alpha no I'm not using that I'm using
that alpha squared is bigger equal to
two yeah sorry that was what you meant
yeah saying you
okay so that was uh why that was a
formal proof of uh parts one and then
there's part um
part two so the other inequality
So, how do we do that?
And and and when you write this,
when you write this, it's always good to
try to explain
um
what you're going to do and in in in
this case what is going to be the
contradiction. So let's try to prove
part two and hopefully we get it
straight this time. So so part two so I
want to show that um so we have so part
one was establishing that alpha squar
was lesser
equal to true. Now we want to prove so
part two
uh uh want to show
that alpha squar is bigger equal to two.
And so
uh again we're proving this
we will show this by contradiction.
So
assume
that
alpha squared is strictly less than two.
Right?
And now it it's it's it's you know it's
it's I think it's helpful. Well, you
don't necessarily have to do it, but I
think it's helpful if you say um maybe
it's too, you know, too long, but it's
at least helpful to think about uh where
is the contradiction coming from. So, if
alpha square is less than two,
uh in so I I will say it, you don't
necessarily have to write it, but indeed
we will show
that if this is the case
is the case
then they exist.
uh there exist some numbers alpha 2
bigger than alpha such that
alpha 2 squared is also less than
two.
Contradicting
that alpha is an upper bound
for for for the set A we defined. Okay,
that's what we will prove. Okay.
And so we want to find a a a real number
that is larger than this
but still uh but still uh the square is
still less than two. Okay.
And so in this case I'm going to
so so
now we sort of do the you know the
structure is going to be the same.
you know, we had this little scrap paper
where we sort of outline the argument
and figure out what H had to be. And so
I'm going to use this H. So, so we're
going to again maybe I'll just erase
this here so we don't get confused with
the first part and the second part.
Okay.
[Applause]
Okay. So,
so I'm going to set
h again. I'm going to define it very
similar to what I did before, but now I
have to remember that I'm assuming that
alpha squar is less than two. So I
define h to be 2 minus alpha squar over
4 alpha.
Okay, this is how I define it.
uh and then I what I'm interested in is
so I have here zero I have this that is
supposed to be the upper bound but I
want to prove that that really isn't an
upper bound that's an element in in my
set A and so this is this alpha 2 so I'm
defy so I'm setting
set this and alpha 2 equal to alpha plus
h
this here was just to illustrate you
shouldn't you don't necessarily have to
include that
okay and I want to show you we want to
show
I think it's good idea to write what you
want to show in particular if I really
had written that before uh then I
wouldn't have been in trouble right
because I was trying to prove something
else uh so you want to prove that alpha
squared here
is also less than two. Right?
So this is this is so so we already have
that alpha here
uh is is positive.
It's
um it's bigger than one. So uh so this
number here this here we already know is
bigger than alpha. Okay.
And so if I can prove that so this here
is so this bigger than alpha if I can
prove that the square is less than two
then alpha here alpha here sorry would
not be an upper bound right there's
another element in the set uh a that is
bigger. Okay.
So I want to prove that. So now I'm
looking at alpha
2 squared. So that is alpha plus h.
Right? That's how I define alpha 2 and I
square it.
And if I do that then I get alpha
squared plus h 2
uh plus
um 2 h
uh alpha right
and I now uh so now I want an upper
bound right and so we already have that
alpha is this one here h is you see that
h is in this case here. So h is is equal
to 2 - alpha^ 2 over 4 alpha. Alpha is
bigger equal to one. This here the
denominator is bounded by two. So again
it's 2 over 4. So this is bounded by a
half.
So h is positive
and we have that h is positive and h is
less than half.
And so now uh I this here I can bound I
can bound trivially by just using that h
is bounded by one. So I get this plus h
+ 2
uh and then h * alpha again or 2 h
alpha. This is right when you multiply
this by two alpha then the alpha cancel
out and the two cancel with one of these
uh with
two in this form. So you're getting 2
minus alpha squar over two.
Okay. And so now I get that this thing
here is bounded by so h here
h is also
a
a very rough bound for h is so using
sorry
so using so I have that and now using
that h here is equal = to alpha 2 -
alpha^ 2 / 2 / 4 alpha which is less
than
uh 2 - alpha^ 2 over 2 since
alpha here is bigger than one
right so I have that right so using that
we have
that alpha 2^ squared is less or equal
to let me just write that line I'm just
now filling in alpha squared to the h
here I'm using this inequality here 2 -
alpha^ 2 / 2 and then I have the same
thing again
and so you see that this here it's this
here times 2 so this is just alpha^ 2us
- 2 + 2 -
uh alpha square
and and this inequality here was one of
these inequality I should have replaced
by a strict inequality. This because h
is positive and is strictly less than
one. So this here is actually a strict
inequality. So this here is a strict
inequality.
Okay. But now you see that this thing
here the alpha cancel out and you're
getting two right so you have that alpha
2 squared is strictly less than two
that's what we wanted to prove right and
this this this
gives
that
alpha 2 is also in a and yet
alpha 2 was bigger bigger than alpha.
And this is the desired contradiction.
Okay. So again, you know, we already did
this last time, but but the the point
here is that how do you write down a
formal proof, right? And a formal proof
in this case is that you try very
clearly in this case it was divided into
two steps. So you you you you try to
divide it into the two steps and then
maybe you have a a last line that say
that you know part one part one
and part two together
show
that alpha squ is equal to two. uh
completing the proof,
right? And again, the point here was
that so we already knew how to prove
this, but like how do you write down a
formal proof, right? And so in in in for
this proof, it was divided into these
two steps. So you try to write each step
separately.
They were both both of the two steps was
proven by contradiction.
And so you would say up front you would
say that you're going to prove it by
contradiction.
And then of course there would be you
would you know it the statement that you
want to prove since you're proving it by
contradiction you would assume the
negation
and then I think if you can and it
doesn't fill too much I think it's very
helpful to write what you are trying how
you are trying to get the contradiction
right that's what I tried here right and
then but and then you see then the big
difference from when we were trying to
figure out how to prove it is that you
now go ahead and you just define
you define the things. You define H and
alpha 2, right? That sort of seems to
come out of nowhere
and then you establish the property that
you want to prove that that leads to the
contradiction. Okay, that's sort of the
structure.
Are there any questions to this?
Yeah.
>> So,
>> right. So, we're using a few things.
We're using um I mean and and and uh
we're using a few thing uh we're using
that is ordered that is ordered. We're
also using uh something about that is a
ordered field. And why? because we're
using something well we're using
something about multiplication to at all
define square root right and also we're
using something about that one is bigger
than zero right
uh and um
and then
um and then so we're using and then
we're also using of course completeness
in order to define this least upper
bound right so we're using a bunch of
these things, right? But of course, if
you have
Yeah. I mean, uh I mean, if you're
asking when I mean and that's not really
I mean you know uh at this stage I mean
like very very soon um in one of the
next few lectures
things will be in the real numbers. I
mean we're not going to work on general
fields and we're not going to yeah I
mean general fields this is not part of
the subject but you but of course it's
interesting to ask
and you see and and I think that's your
point is like when can you define
something like a square root of two in a
field something like that and and
there's a lot of things you're
absolutely right that there's a lot of
these things that was just sort of
general property but maybe we shouldn't
get too much into
the so I wanted to there's a few more
things I was hoping to do. So I also
wanted to just talk about the
Archimedian property again. And so I
wanted to again you know just outline
uh how to write a formal proof and again
and the reason of course why I'm
illustrating how to write a form the for
the writing a formal proof is an
important part of this class
and and I'm obviously uh using the syncs
that we already proved last time just so
so that you can kind of focus on how to
not not the proof not the statements why
the statement should be true but just
how to write it. Um and so let's
let's talk about the Archimedian
property
and so the Archimedian property just
saying that so this is the theorem
that the natural numbers
is not bounded from above. Right?
That's one way of formulating it. Right?
You could also say like we did last time
that whenever you take a real there's a
larger uh natural number than that real,
right? This but that's the same.
Okay. So now how do we prove this?
So again here we're thinking about
things as being subset of R. We always
you know when when we don't really
mention it then we always think about it
as being subset of R.
And so we uh we pro we will show this by
contradiction.
by contradiction.
So suppose
alpha is an upper bound
for the natural numbers.
Well, uh we can assume
after replacing
uh alpha by by soup of a. We can assume
that alpha
is the least up about
Right. So, and now uh and and then then
I think it's nice again uh to to write
where the contradiction is coming from.
So,
so
we'll show
We will get the desired contradiction
by showing
that's uh that that's alpha minus one
is also
an upper bound
contradicting
that alpha was the least of
okay and So now uh since
since uh alpha so so so this is what we
want to prove that and since
alpha is an upper bound
for all
natural numbers.
Uh if you add one to the natural number,
this is also this here is also a natural
number, right? N + one is also a natural
number. So n + one must be lesser equal
to this upper bound, right?
But this implies
that n subtracting one on both side
implies that n is less or equal to alpha
minus one. And this which holds for all
n
are all natural numbers. So,
alpha minus one is also an upper one.
Okay. And that's and this is this is the
right this this proof gives you this the
side contradiction.
Okay. So that's how you would write
that.
Let me um talk a little bit about
sequences and we so this will be a big
topic. Uh so sequences
so well first so we talked about that a
little bit. So if you look at at the So
how do we think about
of of square root two uh on the on the
real line I mean so the way to think
about square root of two is what we did
here that it's this positive thing so
that the square is two right but if you
want to place two on the real line
then uh you could sing about it as one
as a limit of a sequence. If you take
one and then the one is less than 1.4
which is less than 1.4
[Music]
one
which is less than 1.414
etc.
Right? And so this here is a
sequence. I'll be make that precise in
just a minute. But it's a an increasing
sequence of numbers. And the limit the
limit is square2. Right? So if you
plug it two in on the calculator, it
will bring out a lot of digits, right?
And these are the first digits and it
will continue on. And that's how you
think about uh square root of two. If
you want to think about it on the real
line
and so we want to and so square two is
going to be the limit of these and we
need to make this precise and we also
need to make precise what really a
sequence is.
So a sequence
so a sequence
of real numbers.
This is a map.
It's a function from the natural numbers
into R.
So for each natural number you get a
real number and and so right so a
function
it is you know a function is is defined
by the value at different points. So
this thing here but if it but if you
want to think about it as a sequence
then it's common to denote it to denote
this here like that. So this is how one
typically write a sequence where instead
of the you know what the the argument is
this what what this is inside a bracket
you write it as a subscript. Okay.
So this is a sequence
and so uh and so in in the case over
there if you're thinking about a1 say to
be equal to 1 a2 to be equal to 1.4 4 83
and now I'm thinking about the sequence
here as I'm thinking about square root
of two and I take the number of you know
the subscript here I'm just taking the
number of digits in square root two so
now I need three digits here I needed
two one 41
a4 is 1.414 4 1 4 etc. Right? And so
so then you have so then a n here is a
sequence
of real numbers
and it's actually increasing that the
sequence a n is less than a n + one. we
have this property
and uh and we want to talk about next
time we want to talk about uh uh what
does a limit mean?
What is a limit?
And and so uh square root of two indeed
will be the limit of this sequence and
the limit you write like this sometimes
as n goes to infinity of a n.
But we'll talk about this next time.
Okay.