Hello everyone. I'm John Hart from the
mechanical engineering department and I
have the privilege of chairing this next
session on manufacturing. And as I was
sitting at the back preparing, I
realized this is a bit of a full- circle
moment because uh while I was doing my
masters and PhD in mechanical
engineering here, I transitioned between
degrees from focusing on machine design,
precision engineering to an unexpected
focus on nanomaterials, which led me to
spend long days with a first generation
iPod hidden in my clean room suit uh in
the MTL, the precursor to MIT Nano. and
the convergence of those two topics
shaped the first decade or so of my
faculty career. Uh so after I give some
introductory remarks uh I'll introduce
our outstanding speakers who will also
span the spectrum of manufacturing
uh in some ways from the inside MIT
perspective and also from the outside
MIT perspective or what we like to see
MIT's impact in manufacturing to be
beyond the borders of our campus.
I
came to MIT about
12 years ago. There we go. And and since
then, I've seen an incredible growth in
manufacturing across campus. We've
already heard some outstanding remarks
connecting manufacturing to health and
life sciences and in the opening by
Vladimir and Sally before that. Uh but
along with the growth of manufacturing
across disciplines at MIT, it really is
in MIT's DNA. We have manufacturing in
all engineering departments in
humanities and social sciences of course
in management and operations. And MIT's
dedication to manufacturing part of its
industrial inspiration and mind and hand
ethos uh is not only about
technology
research and education but it's also
about understanding the landscape of
manufacturing domestically and globally.
And it's about getting people out of
campus,
our graduates who are budding
enthusiasts of manufacturing and when
the opportunity presents itself,
starting and scaling new companies.
So collecting these like terms so to
say, we're very proud that alongside
I'm sorry I don't think the the remote
is working but if you can advance next
slide. alongside heels and the other
strategic initiatives we launched MIT
launched in May the MIT initiative for
new manufacturing or INM uh and uh I'm
have the privilege of being one of the
faculty co-directors along with
professor Suzanne Berger and professor
Chris Love Suzanne an institute
professor of political science and Chris
a professor of chemical engineering an
expert in biio manufacturing and
Rick Lockach dean of the Sloan school
and Paula Hammond institute professor
and executive vice prohost are the
co-chairs of our steering committee. And
the INM by definition is one of these
strategic initiatives has broad goals.
Goals to unite MIT in manufacturing and
support research, education, and
partnerships to improve manufacturing in
the US and across the world. Uh we're
just getting started. We've only uh been
live for about six months. Uh but we uh
have defined four crosscutting themes
that define MIT's work across campus and
with its partners. Reimagining
manufacturing technologies and systems.
Elevating the productivity and
experience of manufacturing, which
really speaks to the human nature of
manufacturing and how work and worker
productivity are key to the frontier.
Scaling new manufacturing, working
internally and externally with young
companies and old companies to uh
understand and help them go from one to
many, the true beauty of of what makes
manufacturing magical and mysterious and
transforming the manufacturing base.
speaking to working with uh not just big
companies but small and medium
enterprises particularly from the
workforce uh education side as as John
Lou will speak in particular in a little
while we've identified several program
areas uh areas of focus activity
supporting research in manufacturing
across MIT both in technology domains
and crosscutting themes focusing on
deployment uh uh taking MIT's work
outside of campus us through workforce
training through visiting small and
medium enterprises and so on. uh
alongside of those a deep focus on
education and workforce uh on campus and
beyond supporting new laboratories as we
raise funding and build programs uh
around campus including a partnership
we've already established with MIT nano
in the area of 3D printing we're
engaging industry through a consortium
of large companies and we are uh
ideulating programs in collaboration
with the trust center despond center and
others to focus on manufacturing
entrepreneurship
the INM started by an organic process a
community that we gathered to say, "Hey,
hey, how broad and how important is
manufacturing? How exciting is is it to
our community?" And this has included uh
early efforts on workforce training like
manufacturing academy piloted in the
Birkers in Western Massachusetts. A
series of amazing distinguished speakers
like Mo Morris Chang uh October of two
years ago uh who filled 10250 and has
such an incredible story to tell about
his career in the semiconductor
industry. And as I mentioned, uh,
efforts, uh, particularly here supported
by the Masttec collaborative, uh, to,
uh, put new manufacturing equipment at
MIT, uh, specifically in a in a lab
provided in partnership with MIT Nano on
the fifth floor and some space in
mechanical engineering aside of our
other manufacturing courses. And we're
also proud to have seven founding
industry members of our consortium. The
uh, industry consortium is only one part
of the initiative, but a key part. uh
and we're engaging closely with those
companies and open to uh new
introductions at at any time. Uh and
last but not least, more of a note for
our onampus audience. Uh we have just
opened up a call for INM's first set of
seed research projects here focused on
AI and automation for manufacturing.
It's a top interest of our industry
members, which is the source of funding
supporting this seed call. And while
we'll have hopefully many calls for
proposals that stretch across all the
different domains I highlighted, this
one is focused on a set of topics uh uh
related to AI and automation. Uh if you
uh are interested, please see our
website or go to inm.edu edu and and
click the tab on request for proposals
and we'll be about to we'll be able to
fund seven to 10 projects uh both as
research projects and demonstration
projects to help translate capabilities
already developed on campus into
industry contexts. So with that let me
transition to our uh set of speakers uh
leading off uh will be Dan Orurin who's
a MIT PhD. I first met him when he was
finishing up his PhD and thinking about
starting the company that is incredibly
exciting called Radiant Technologies. Uh
after Dan, we'll hear from Professor Liz
Reynolds, a professor of practice in uh
the department of urban studies and
planning, but her expertise stretches
far beyond just being a professor at
MIT, including a key role in the in the
White House in the Biden administration.
uh and John Louu, principal research
scientist in mechanical engineering who
will speak about uh his innovative work
and innovative deployment of new
pedagogy for manufacturing workforce
education. Uh each will have a a brief
presentation with some slides and then I
think we'll have time for a panel
discussion and any questions that you
submit through the pigeon hole back
there. So Dan, please uh please come on
up.
So, I'm here to tell you a little bit
about Ardiant Technologies. And just to
give you a little bit of context here,
what we're all about is that we think 3D
nanop fabrication is what's going to
fully unlock the potential of optics and
photonics.
And you know that all started with some
very simple questions quite some time
ago about what actually is necessary in
order to do first principles 3D nanop
fabrication that is not just practical
but pragmatic and which can scale.
So this has brought us to where we are
now where we're building the world's
first 3D 3D nanoptics and photonics
foundry. And we're able to pattern any
arbitrary geometry. We're able to do
that with deeply subwavelength
resolution. And not only that, but we
can control gradients of material and
achieve things like gradients of
refractive index. And most importantly,
we're able to do it with materials that
are compatible with existing foundry
technologies.
Now, further into the future, you can
even imagine using this technique to do
multimaterial. We've shown it's possible
to do conductors, semiconductors, and
dialectrics all at once. But in
practice, none of this actually matters
because there did not exist a way to do
3D nanop fabrication fast enough. So of
course uh we also had to go and invent
that um here at MIT with Peter so
something called uh line scan temporally
focused to photon lithography which is a
big mouthful but the point is here that
this allows you to instead of scanning a
single point pattern entire planes and
that means you can go fast enough for
this to be economically feasible and
make millions of components per year per
customer.
And with that we've shown we can make
everything from lenses for coupling
imaging and relaying to things like
filters for MX demox and compute as well
as 3D wave guides and reflectors for
routing as well as MX and demox.
But that's just these subcomponents
really. This is a transition one that
looks a lot like what happened with the
transistor where we went from soldering
these parts together to then creating
entire integrated systems out of them.
But being able to do that for free space
optics and photonics.
So that's a little bit about the
company. But you know it wasn't such a
simple path to get here. I actually
started out as an artist and
photographer. Um I ran a printmaking
business and an art business sort of
exploring what's possible with sculpting
light. And it just so happened that one
of my best friends had started here at
MIT. And over some beers at the miracle
of science, we realized we could combine
these very old photographic printmaking
technologies with new tools from
neuroscience. And that's where this all
started essentially. You know, we tried
some stuff in lab. We got adopt I got
adopted by a professor at Bdon became a
technician, a master student and then
got a PhD, published in science
magazine. uh then spun this out uh via
the activate fellowship which supports
uh scientists to bring their ideas and
research to market. Uh and then even
then you know it was still early there
was scientific risk left to be dealt
with. So we raised money from the
government through SBIRS. We then took
that and we showed we could make
highquality optical materials. And with
that out of the way we were able to go
raise our seed round. We won a DARPA
program and with that DARPA program
we've been able to grow to now 30
people. We have a facility here in
Waltham where we're now building the
world's first 3D
fabrication foundry. And that's where we
are today. And finally, customers are
taking us seriously. We're doing
development deals with them. And
hopefully in a few years we'll have a
scaled manufacturing facility that'll
allow us to make millions of components
for AI hyperscalers. Specifically, the
beach head that we found is in
connectors for data centers. This is a
major issue just shifting from using
copper to connect chips and things
within racks together to using light.
But further in the future, what we
imagine is actually being able to shift
the substrate for computation completely
away or partially away from electrons to
photons and enable new kinds of sensors
that allow embodied intelligence to
essentially navigate and understand our
world. So with that, I'll uh let the
other folks come up and thank you very
much.
Great. Um well, good morning everyone.
It's a real pleasure to be here and
particularly with uh uh old and dear
colleagues from many years working on
the topic of advanced manufacturing and
um and policy etc. My name is Liz
Reynolds and um as John alluded, I have
been involved in advanced manufacturing
topics at MIT for uh over a decade now.
But what's been interesting in the last
five years or so is to um see how much
this topic has become uh critical not
just in the US but around the world and
uh the the movement the sort of
headwinds and tailwinds that are working
right now in rebuilding uh advanced
manufacturing bases and
re-industrializing is really quite
fascinating. And I think we could all
probably say the next 5 to 10 years will
be the most dynamic time that we've been
in uh when it comes to thinking about
advanced manufacturing and society more
broadly. So I'm just going to take I'm
just sort of doing a third a 60,000 ft
view on what's been going on. And I
apologize for this parochial view which
is a US- ccentric view. uh I did work
for the Biden administration and I am uh
you know grounded in in in some of the
views on that front but they are
evolving as I'll I'll talk about and um
and hopefully this also sets the stage
for what John is going to say. So let me
first by just talking about what what
are the motivators behind this movement
in what many have been calling sort of
the next industrial revolution. And I
think I'm I'm going to list four here
and we'll talk more broadly I think
about others uh throughout the day but
um people can first uh first and
foremost I think it was the global
pandemic that essentially uh highlighted
all the vulnerabilities in the US
economy visav manufacturing and
resilience in our supply chains
domestically uh and even uh and also
globally um but whether it was from um
personal protective equipment to
semiconductors everyone's quite aware of
that we had significant challenges for
the country and they affected not just
national security but economic security
which now it's really hard to say where
does one start and where does one finish
but for semiconductors uh many will
remember that when we had the shortage
um of semiconductors at the in 2021 uh
the auto industry uh essentially shut
down and that directly affected uh
inflation that year by a third and so
you're seeing this inter interaction of
the of the issues that were both for
national security purposes but also
economic security purpose is a real
problem. um climate change uh we you
know climate change now tends to be
discussed in in terms of economic sec uh
sorry energy security uh but we have
increasing threats um uh due to climate
change but we're also seeing as the
demands from AI increase and from
increasing manufacturing centers as well
that companies are thinking about energy
security in a different way and that
requires integrating both their
manufacturing and their uh data
requirements in space in sort of uh
places. Do we have enough uh energy? Do
we have enough water? Do we have enough
uh you know uh capabilities re basically
to drive our industrial um industrial or
re-industrialization.
Third, the geopolitical landscape. Of
course, we've seen with uh Russia's
invasion of Ukraine and other conflicts
first and foremost a real stress on the
US defense industrial base. you know,
challenges to actually supplying enough
ammunition, uh, legacy systems that are
not, uh, you know, rising to the
challenge. And then, of course, the
tension that's been growing with China
over both military, uh, challenges, but
also technological challenges. And, and
there's data now to suggest that the US
has fallen behind China in many critical
areas. Um, finally, inequality. This is
I think at the core of a lot of our um
challenges sort of socially around uh
democracy. It's not just happening in
the US, it's happening everywhere. But
economic populism is often grounded in
economic insecurity. And so the advance
the manufacturing agenda actually has
been you know an area where people feel
there is an opportunity for expanding
middle class jobs etc. But that's that
in in my mind is also a motivator for a
lot of the policy we've been seeing.
So, I want to talk a little bit about uh
MIT's response. Um, I don't know if I'd
call it a I I think I'd call it a
response to a lot of what's going on,
which is we um uh Simon Johnson and I a
couple years ago started a priority
technologies uh seminar and the idea
here was that what we see is a real
convergence of um technological
development uh you know frontier
technology uh innovation going on uh
both at the firm and national level and
policy uh interests and these are
converging to sort of try and meet this
moment of national and economic security
challenges for the US. And so we've
developed a seminar. We've had a number
of our faculty present on areas where
they are leaning in to a tech the
technology development but also where
there's significant policy implications.
What does it mean for the country for uh
the US and also um you know around the
world to move forward and to advance in
these particular areas. Of course,
semiconductor is one of the key areas
since we've seen um uh the challenge and
then the introduction of the chips act
by the bid administration a few years
ago. Um and I think they also these
these six areas which reflect in some
ways foundational technologies like uh
critical minerals and semiconductors or
foundational areas really in the
upstream value chain to frontier
technologies biio manufacturing quantum
to some of the downstream um important
work in advanced manufacturing and and
drones really as a case study. This is
not of course a exhaustive list but a a
list that is evocative of what the
challenges are for the country in
combining both our innovation ecosystem
with our industrial ecosystem uh and how
do those two interact. I think drones
are a great example of that where
obviously uh very dependent on uh
critical mineral supply on um
semiconductors on advanced manufacturing
technologies and on the ability to
actually make drones at scale. Uh right
now in the US we make about 100,000 a
year that needs to be expanded to about
a million plus a year. And how are we
going to do that? Where are we going to
do that? Th those are important
questions right now. And just to
highlight a couple of the crosscutting
themes, uh workforce, which John will be
talking about, comes up all the time
across each one of these critical areas
about does the US have both at a
technician level and at a higher
education level the workforce it needs.
Um and I feel Vlad has been leading the
charge on what universities need to be
doing uh and could be doing to help uh
educate the next generation. uh supply
chains and manufacturing as I mentioned
without a supply uh secure supply chain
uh we the US is really vulnerable in a
lot of these areas and we have to be
looking ahead in that area we're we're
quite behind of course in critical
minerals uh but as you look at quantum
for example how do we build in uh
resilience across not just the country
but uh with allies and partners scale up
and demand pull this issue of uh and we
heard it earlier with some of the
panelists but how are companies um like
Dan's
making the move from the lab to and
prototypes to the pilot you know
production to demonstration to
commercialization uh the US capital
markets has not historically been well
organized for that kind of support
particularly in growth in growth capital
so what are we seeing there and what's
the role of government uh and the
federal government to provide some of
that demand uh early on small and
mediumsiz firms we have a challenge with
adopting new technology uh not just the
invention of the technology but the
adoption of the technology which has
always been a challenge or is perhaps
part of the the technology life cycle
which uh you know often takes about 30
years for to to really play out and then
finally R&D and I think this is
particularly important given what we see
in the country right now is without that
continued support by uh the federal
government which goes to universities
and elsewhere um we will have challenges
breaking through uh into new
technologies ies will have challenges uh
leapfrogging in existing places. So the
R&D is a critical part of the US
innovation ecosystem. So this is a book
coming out next spring. Um and I think
that the it's really helpful uh and the
lessons that come out of this can can
really inform directions going forward
for the US and and beyond. But let me
just take a quick moment to talk about
this industrial strategy that I think we
are now fully part of in the US. And
again, as I mentioned before, what we
see is that industrial strategy and
policy usually steps in when we see
markets are not responding to what we
need sort of through a national security
lens or an economic security lens. Um
that became clear with the B
administration with on semiconductors on
critical minerals on our defense
industrial base places where we need a
government to step in. And what's
interesting is to see that in this
current administration, we're seeing
likewise uh an agreement and a an
investment in some of these areas. A a
focus on resilience, a focus on
re-industrialization, a focus on uh
foreign direct investment as a priority.
Um but also some a focus on America
first, which brings its own um you know
challenges.
And I just wanted to highlight I think
people may be familiar but some of these
are really kind of interesting new
directions that the US government is
taking which is very active steps in um
investing in companies to uh strengthen
our supply chains and perhaps you know
create what some might call national
champions which has pros and cons. Uh
but the MP materials deal where the
Biden administration had invested in MP
materials now you know DoD uh largest
stakeholder uh very actively trying to
build and create um opportunities or CA
capabilities and magnet manufacturing.
the Intel deal, uh, grants that were
given by the B administration, now
equity investments, um, now an equity
stake, um, and, uh, the the deal with
Nvidia, which, um, you know, which was,
uh, counter to the national security
interest that the B administration had
outlined, uh, also just very novel ways
in which the co the government is moving
forward. Nepon steel again trying to
secure domestic production capabilities
uh, long term.
So continuity and divergence. I'm just
going to talk um a bit uh in terms of
the continuity between the last
administration and this administration.
US policy very a lot of similarities in
terms of the focus on industries again
critical minerals semiconductors uh and
I'll I'll the semiconductor piece I
think for this group might be uh
particularly interesting as we know
there's been a lot of investment in
building cap capabilities for frontier
manufacturing in the country but uh but
right now what we're seeing also is a
pulling back on some of the R&D
investments uh some of the uh
investments in packaging capabilities
and creating more of a broad uh fund for
supporting you know many different types
of projects and companies. Um there's a
an agreement that really internationally
the World Trade Organization policies
have not served the country well. Uh
unfair trade practices that that people
want to you know change that that model.
Um and then the response to China, we
can debate about the use of tariffs and
how they're used, but certainly this
idea that the US needs to be
strengthening its relationship visav
technological development with China.
And then differences uh I won't go into
these in great detail, but I think
people probably, you know, are aware of
the tariff um tariffs now that are
broad-based and I think are creating a
headwind for US manufacturing right now
in terms of increasing the intermediate
costs of a lot of manufacturing. uh the
administration is sort of picking
winners. It's not to say that these
companies aren't worthy of investment,
but it's not ha doesn't have the
competitive process that you might see
to help you know build industries uh
that are globally competitive. Um it's
also focused on FDI. And then um I think
it's fair to say that there is an
undermining given the UN investment uh
challenges that we're seeing or the
pulling back of investment from a lot of
the national agencies in science and
technology that will have challenges for
the country uh long term. So to that let
me just say um the broader implications
I'll just close on a couple thoughts uh
that hopefully are food for discussion.
Um I think that there we have concerns
now about what are the long-term um
impacts on US leadership and technology
and science if our R&D engine is
compromised. That was discussed I think
maybe touched upon in the last panel but
a real issue there. Um we are also
seeing uh I think allies and partners
turning in other directions in terms of
their investments and their
partnerships. uh a risk of US
isolationism and and greater
protectionism that will be a problematic
limited state capacity and that uh we
are seeing both a reduction in in um in
workforce today uh particularly um in
the federal government lack of capacity
really to deliver on some of the agenda
items that I mentioned earlier for the
for manufacturing um and more of a focus
on deals, one-on-one deals with
different companies. Um, and I like to
say everything's on the table all the
time that there's a lot of uh dynamic
engagement right now in um in all that's
going on in trying to rebuild the
industrial base in the US. Uh I'm happy
I would say in the semiconductor space I
think there has there's more uh there's
more continuity. There's less uh um
pulling back on some of the investments
that have been made. But uh investing in
the R&D piece is critical and it's
unclear what that's going to look like
going forward. So with that, I'll uh
I'll stop and hand over to John. Thank
you.
Okay.
Hello everyone. I'm John Leu. Uh I teach
in uh the mechanical engineering
department here and I lead a group in
learning engineering. Uh so what I want
to talk about is you know these are the
kinds of headlines that certainly catch
might have caught your eyes certainly
catch my eyes. For example, Apple about
half a year ago announced 500 billion
dollars to expand manufacturing
operations in the US and then last month
changed that number to 600. Uh usually
these numbers are across you know one
two decades. This number is across four
years. Um GNOVA is making huge
investments. Uh Rivian just announced
last week that they're breaking ground
in their $5 billion plant. These are not
just one-offs as well. There's actually
a ton of different $1 billion projects.
This graphic just came out a few months
ago. Uh all the $1 billion projects
happening uh breaking ground across the
US and they all come of course with
hundreds and thousands of of jobs. Uh
also not just one you know sites here
and there. Uh if you take a look um at
uh um what are manufacturing firms
actually struggling with though? I mean
certainly a lot of very positive
investment into it. Uh this is these are
quarterly surveys uh done by National
Association of Manufacturing. Basically
what's your top pain point? Is it you
know business? Is it uh uh you know the
economy and sales what I want to point
out is that the gray has been rising and
in fact other than a slow small gap in
COVID it's really been at the top for
the past few years. What's gray? Uh gray
is attracting and retaining a quality
workforce and so gray has been king for
the past four or five years.
And it's not just showing up in employer
perceptions. Uh it's also in our
demographic data as well. So what you're
seeing in the red is demographics of the
manufacturing workforce about 20 years
ago. Uh and what you're seeing on the
horizontal axis again is age. So there's
been a massive shift of age to the
right. Right? So blue is where we're at
now in the recent years. Manufacturing
workforce now uh Bureau of Labor of
Statistics uh basically estimates about
25% over 55 and above. So essentially
what we're seeing is a very very large
that that peak there a huge wave of
retirements in the next decade. Um and
so uh this story in the US is not just a
US uh story. You'll hear this and I was
just in Europe uh recently. They're also
struggling with a similar issue. India
also wants to grow out their
manufacturing workforce. We have
projects there as well. And so uh these
are some of the questions I'm really
interested in asking. Possibilities for
new good jobs. How are requirements
changing? How do we prepare industries
and people for them? uh new systems and
tools to develop how we and transform
how we learn and how we work in STEM and
then finally what kinds of fundamental
knowledge do we have to uncover about
how humans work and learn uh in these
kinds of industries. Uh so uh you know
two years two years ago we were three
people uh now this is a picture just
from a few weeks ago really people from
the background three kinds of
backgrounds in my group human machine
computer interaction XR um learning
sciences education uh and then straight
up mechanical engineering manufacturing
that's kind of the three uh kind of
buckets of knowledge that we generally
draw from. Uh so what I want to do now
is kind of look through or kind of give
you a survey of some of the projects uh
that we've been able to do and and
hopefully they'll be relevant to this
audience. The first one is all all the
way on the system side. So we when we
think about advanced manufacturing uh I
have a premise or a hypothesis that hey
we believe there's something that's
holding people back in the workforce and
that is there's a kind of a a gap
between what technicians do and know and
what engineers do and know. In fact,
when we've interviewed now scores of
firms, we kind of hear a mantra like,
"Hey, I wish engineers had hands-on
skills." Ah, but I wish technicians had
analytical skills. And we believe that
in order to adopt and integrate new
technologies, these new technologies are
are all connected. So, you can't just
bring in uh a new machine and expect
that to work. It has upstream and
downstream effects. Uh technologies like
IoT or robotics or many of the digital
technologies as well. And so the
question is, you know, what kind of
worker really needs to be able to do
this? We started to ask a few years ago,
maybe we're thinking about this in this
wrong way. Perhaps we really need a new
worker type. And so this project, which
we've now published uh last year in
National Academyy's policyfacing journal
uh is about proposing a new type of
worker for to help firms move into
advanced manufacturing. I'm calling this
worker the technologist. uh and what
we're doing essentially is creating a
bridge to collaborate both with the
technicians who know the uh processes
and the equipment very well and the uh
engineers who are making decisions on
the level of of of design all the way to
systems and operations. And so this is
uh essentially we're taking and drawing
from the core of curriculum that we
teach here at MIT, the masters of
engineering and advanced manufacturing
design and adapting it for a new
audience. folks without university
degrees, folks who are assemblers,
operators, technicians on the factory
floor. Uh so far we've been targeting
aerospace defense, marine industrial
base, but now we're in conversations
with applied material, Samsung uh
thinking about how do we uh bridge over
to the semiconductor industry. Um, I'm
pleased to share we're just about to
finish round one, uh, phase one funding
from the DoD and we just were awarded a
$5.5 million grant to disseminate to six
sites in New England targeting against
the aerospace defense marine industrial
base. Uh so uh the six sites, you know,
two in Rhode Island, three in
Massachusetts, uh uh one in Connecticut,
even though the numbers are small, we're
just looking, we're promising to educate
about 180 technologists over the next
few years, but we ended up receiving
letters of support from senators from
all three states primarily because of
the potential economic impact that it
would have on states and helping
industries regain competitiveness. So
that's an example of the kinds of work
that we do on whole manufacturing
workforce systems or workforce training
systems. Now I want to spend a little
bit of time just highlighting uh some of
the kind of individual when we think
about individuals learning how kind what
kinds of technologies might we be able
to develop to support that kind of
learning as well. Okay, so here's an
example. Obviously, a lot of work in VR
training these days. We have a paper
coming out where we're benchmarking. Uh,
a lot of that VR training, especially
targeting towards manufacturing, turns
out. Uh, I can I can I can say kind of
one of the key takeaways. We don't
believe that a lot of this is informed
by learning theories and learning
sciences. So, what we're trying to do is
to try to push up against the space.
Hey, how do the learning theories and
learning sciences from education inform
the design of these environments? So,
we've now developed a kind of a demo
environment where now you can learn by
making mistakes and making meaning of
your decisions and choices where the
environment is open-ended instead of a
lot of what we see in the commercial
space which is scripted and linear and
doesn't allow for errors. Once you're
able to do that, then of course it
brings up the questions of okay, how do
systems work with humans to make meaning
uh or to make best the the errors and
mistakes that we all know are really
important to learning. And the second
part is I believe you know one of the
largest uh barriers to adoption for XR
is the just the high cost of developing
these experiences. And so how do we make
developing XR like using PowerPoint so
that teachers can make their own
experiences in the future. Um another
example of uh a project that we have is
hey we teach engineering design and
manufacturing DFM in mech by having
students take up our products all the
time. That's great, but you know, how do
we actually scale that kind of pedagogy?
Augmented reality is a really
interesting way because it's physically
in contextualized. It's also scalable
and you know, you can publish it on
things like Apple Store and Google Play.
So, we've now been able to do that uh
over a number of different uh iterations
of an online course. And now we're
moving towards how do we gamify the
learning? How do we bring in game- based
analytics to hopefully identify, hey,
are there patterns that noviceses might
approach disassembly and making, you
know, sense uh sensemaking of these
different features and connecting them
to design principles versus how experts
might approach uh that kind of activity.
Uh and then this is one of the newer uh
lines of work and given that I know we
have mastec folks in the in the audience
uh part part of this was funded by the
mastc grant uh for advanced
manufacturing where uh Hollywood has
been now in the space for about four or
five years where they're developing next
generation green screen technology. So
on the left what you're seeing is
snippets from behind the scenes of the
the production of Mandalorian. I don't
know raise of hands any any fans of Star
Wars here? Okay, good. Fantastic. So
that was the first iteration of virtual
what we call virtual production. Now
basically taking highdensity LED panels
and turning that into the actual
environment. So now when the talent
points at a mountain, it's really there.
It takes away a lot of the
post-production costs and it fronts it
up so that now you can engage with it in
a real-time way. It brings scalability
and photo realism at at a at a different
level. So what you're seeing here on the
right is we're finally developing the
space here at MIT. in building 35 again
partially enabled by support from
masttec and now what we can do is how do
we develop these beautiful videos and
enable next generation STEM learning so
if you're interested in that happy to
talk about it but that's that's a new
project in our group and then finally
we're really interested in like how do
we scale both the learning a lot of our
labs are incredibly expensive in the
equipment and also often underutilized
like maybe it's only being used one or
two hours in the day could we open that
kind of up so we have some work now in
enabling tele operations or developing
tele operations for students to be able
to access really really high-end
equipment from a distance and actually
we have now collaboration with
University of Cambridge and UK uh to do
some tele operations uh across different
tasks in manufacturing. So that just
gives you a sense of the kinds of work
that we're doing now in our in our group
to be able to enable uh uh next
generation learning and work in
manufacturing.
All right. Thank you.
Thank you, John, Liz, and Dan for your
remarks and s such an immense range of
topics that all connect to the substrate
of manufacturing and what it takes to
get ideas out of the lab or the early
stage
to scale and and all of the surrounding
factors. So we have some time for short
discussion and then the iPad we'll
probably have some some questions that
we'll try to tackle at the end. Let me
start with you Liz. I think at the start
of your remarks you said something like
the next 5 to 10 years will be the most
dynamic time in manufacturing. Can you
say more why why you feel that way?
>> You you want me
you want me to defend uh something I
said? I I don't doubt it. But
>> my assertion um well I think that that
is uh I I say that for a couple reasons.
one I think just technologically uh
people who are if you look across uh
every field um really that it's touching
manufacturing that we're seeing these
advances that were not even there you
know 5 or 10 years ago whether that's in
robotics or 3D printing or now with AI
what the transformation is going to be
there so there's a technological motion
that now makes it possible to be doing
things that we weren't actually
potentially doing in the US before and
now we're seeing that um and we're
seeing it globally, right? Um it's not
and and so that on top of some of the
other things I said. So for example, now
with supply chains, people are saying we
invested in uh our primal our primary
goal was efficiency in the last couple
decades for a lot of the offshoring of
manufacturing. Um and now people are
stepping back and saying, you know, we
have to also think about resilience on
these supply chains. And so what does
that look like? um uh and part of that
is um some is domestic you know
increased production but actually it's
about strengthening global supply chains
everywhere and it's redundancy and its
regionalization and it's also AI with
predictive um you know optimization and
things like that so I think that's going
on and then we have this uh world order
shifting world order uh which we see
happening in terms of uh manufacturing
and priorities uh and sort of alliances
a China US tension um and what does that
mean? What are the implications for the
rest of the world I think um are are are
quite you know quite prevalent. Um and
so I see like there and then you have a
policy piece in which the government
neoliberal models that said you know
we're just going to leave it to the
market are being pushed to the wayside.
Uh and they have been for a long time in
uh in other countries in Asia certainly
but now we're seeing every country uh
lean in to their investments in
semiconductor uh production in uh more
resilient critical u supply chains for
critical minerals which will have a
manufacturing implication. So that um
you know that also just brings us into a
time where that everything is it's a
very dynamic time. We all of the models
that we were built on in the last couple
decades are really being um you know uh
sort of upended I think.
>> Thank you. And we certainly see in the
the companies we work with uh the the
interest in in rapid change and these
kind of you know pressures internal
external pressures that are causing
reconsideration
and and also an in my opinion an
interesting ja position maybe not
entirely that between the the companies
you know that are building new capacity
right take John you had a screenshot
about Rivian and Rivian's new factory
clean sheet right they and design it
fully digitally from the bottom up
versus say an established company that
has to plum new technology into its
existing operations. And some similar
challenges, some some some different
challenges. Uh and that leads me to you
Dan. So when when we first met, I
remember your technology is kind of
magical, right? If I remember right,
it's making something at, you know, a
larger scale, not a huge scale, and then
shrinking it down to achieve 3D
patterning. Is that is that right?
>> That was what we did.
>> Okay. And that's a lot of what happened
at MIT. But then, you know, you go out,
you talk to the marketplace, and you
hear what they actually need, right? Um,
and what we learned when we did that is
that actually some of the biggest issues
in the semiconductor industry is just
getting things in and out of the chip,
right? And this is the case for
electronics, but it's even more so the
case for photonics. And so having a
material that you could co-package with
these things in order to connect stuff
together had become and honestly always
was, it's just worse now, the biggest
pain point in the industry. So we
actually switched to not shrinking
things and using a scaffold material
that is consisted of glass so that it
was compatible with these semiconductor
processes. And that was a really
critical transition and a pivot that
we're very happy to have made.
>> Awesome. And building on that, can you
talk more about the challenges you faced
or you challenges you anticipate facing
as you scale?
>> Well, there's a long list of things. Uh,
but you know, as a scientist, it's not
sort of these really hard problems you
think about in science that worry me.
It's sort of these like fiddly
engineering problems of how do you glue
things together a million times? How do
you position things with submicron
tolerance over and over and over again?
How do you make sure that your laser is
stable and putting out what you think
it's putting out day in and day out? So,
I mean, these are the challenges you
start to encounter when you're thinking
about scaling up for manufacturing,
which of course at these, you know,
research stages are are not so critical.
>> And I'm sure leading the company, you've
thought about workforce and maybe the
things beyond what you thought of doing
your research. What are some of the
workforce challenges or what talent have
you had to find?
>> The the technologist thing is something
that um really speaks to me, right? Uh
so when we're looking for talent, you
know, the company is primarily not US
citizens, right? That says something
about the workforce that we have here.
That's not by choice necessarily. That's
just what talent we have access to. Uh
but then you have to go out and you have
to find people who you you know are
willing to take on more of the
technician type role and things in
between like this technologist type
role. And what we're finding is we don't
find that in very many places. The way
in which we've plumbed our educational
system is just not fit to have both
hands-on skills and this sort of
analytical and creative thinking to
solve these problems. Um
>> you can send someone to my program.
Well, but there are schools that are
very good at this and we should be using
those as uh examples um and maybe put
trade programs together uh for that. Uh
University of Wateroo is a crazy wealth
of talent of people who have done co-ops
at multiple different companies. So even
in their second year in undergraduate
they can come in and start essentially
doing all the things that we would
expect out of somebody quite frankly
with who's doing a PhD here at MIT and
oftentimes even better they have even
more hands-on skills and that says
something right there's something about
the way we educate people where we have
failed to really get them to do hands-on
problem solving to an extent that is
really important for these types of
manufacturing. ing um problems.
>> So, John, now I want to ask you this the
scaling question in a in a couple ways.
Incredible impact already with the
technologist program. Like true
congratulations, but
180 in in a few years. What what if I
come to you and say, "No, I want
180,000."
>> How would you do it?
>> Uh so, we we designed this to scale. uh
and and I would say this for on on a few
levels. One is that the the content that
we've developed, it's meant to be done
in a hybrid fashion. So there's part of
it that's online and then there's part
of it that's meant to do on the in a
hands-on lab. And so this is why we are
partnering with schools as as you saw in
the sites. You know, there's technology
centers in New England, there's
community colleges in the region that uh
we're working with because not you know,
skilled technical workforce and this is
one of the big differences. they don't
often uh relocate for a job like we
knowledge workers do but skilled
technical workforce don't they stay
within the region so in order to upskill
a region you really have to work with
the regional partners there and so in
order to get a rural Massachusetts we
need an education site there and so in
terms of John's uh question I'd answer
this on on two levels one the
technologist program if we're talking
about that it is uh meant to scale
broadly uh right so once we have this
blueprint with the six sites now we have
a full package where any education site
uh in the US or really outside who wants
to be able to do it can take up this
package, send their folks to us for
their instructors to be trained and then
they can launch techamp in their own
site and and a lot of the the lectures
and the the simulations are online
already and so sites can pick that up.
We don't want to move away from the site
nature though uh because of the regional
uh connection uh a lot of these sites
are embedded with real relationships
with their employers many ofmemes for
example that Liz was talking about. And
then the second thing is, you know,
these folks, they're really hands-on,
right? So, we have to be able to offer
those hands-on labs. The second part is,
and this is why I'm so excited about the
the XR work that some of you in the
audience are engaged with, you know,
that that we're certainly supporting,
uh, is that, you know, I don't think the
technology is there yet, but there's a
lot of ways to scale hands-on learning
in ways that are scalable and
intelligent that I'm really excited
about in the next 3 to 5 years that, you
know, right now are still stuck in
traditional modes of small cohorts, you
know, one one instructor to 10. You have
to be in the space uh, right now. And
and this is why, you know, I have
schools coming to me saying, you know,
we have a weight list of 200 to 300
students every single year. We're
turning away students from the trades
because we can't get the capacity up.
And so, how do we work with those
schools who are already in the space uh
to be able to increase their capacity to
get to the young folks or the incumbent
workers or those who are undermployed
who are interested in careers in
manufacturing?
Yeah, I would just add I know uh John
speaks to this as well, but um the other
part of this is uh is the pipeline is
how we're attracting the next generation
into this field because uh wages in
manufacturing have not uh necessarily
kept up. We've lost a lot of the wage
premium we've had in the past. So for uh
to attract the next generation, we're
going to have to also see I think you
know if we can increase the productivity
of these firms, they can pay higher
wages. They uh we hopefully can attract
the next generation. But there's a lot
of competition. If you look in
Massachusetts, um you know, kids coming
out of high school uh have a lot of
options and it's um it's incumbent upon
sort of the ecosystem broadly to to try
and bring that next generation in. I
think that's a a good example of the
kind of the marriage between technology
adoption, productivity, and workforce
like with wages, right? All you really
have to tackle this from a lot of
different aspects otherwise firms can't
pay enough, they can't get the right
skills, they can't move into advanced
modes of manufacturing. Absolutely.
>> And John, I know you're thinking about
AI these days and how AI can be
incorporated meaningfully in in
education and and learning. May maybe
paint paint us a picture of 2030.
How do you feel an MIT student will be
using AI in learning or how a
technologist a budding technologist
might be interacting with the platform
in a way that's you know not not yet
possible.
>> Yeah. So I I actually was just this
morning talking to Sanjay I think a lot
of us know Sanjay Sarma who's you know
former VP of open learning and also in
manufacturing about this. So uh I would
be really interested uh you know if for
even for the MIT student population if
we could move towards you know what is
the future of humanto human interaction
for learning. Again I think even from a
faculty perspective a lot of times we
kind of delegate the teaching and
learning to our TAs or to recitation
courses. Um, I think there's potentially
a real way to recapture the one-on-one
tutoring that has still that still, you
know, really is hard to compete against
if you can think about a new paradigm,
which is the teacher or the faculty as a
high-end coach. Like if you think about
you know an NBA athlete sitting down
with their uh you know a coach or a
trainer usually there's a session where
they're bringing out highlevel analytics
and covering the past week's performance
and then thinking about a plan for the
next week. Right now we not we don't do
that in education because it's so kind
of costly for a faculty to spend that
time. Imagine, you know, another
generation of AI plus analytics to be
able to inform a faculty on, hey, what
is the students progression in the past
2 to three years and now in my 10-15
minutes, we can really make that a very
worthwhile experience when I'm crafting
a a learning plan for you in the next
week that we're working on together. And
so that would obviously, you know,
require a new generation of AI plus
learning, but there we're not scaling
out AI to become less personal. It's
actually recapturing the human nature of
uh humanto human learning.
>> I also want to emphasize that a big part
of it should always be getting people
out of the classroom. So much learning
does not happen in the classroom. And
you know, you start to encounter the
hairy problems in the real world, right?
And that's the sooner you can get people
doing that at a younger age, building,
trying things, failing. And you know, in
reality, this is kind of old as dirt,
right? apprenticeships, we should take
those types of things really really
seriously and that's just a form of
mentorship, right? Yeah. So, uh we
should really think about how do we
bring that in a more meaningful way into
all of our educational institutions.
>> It's a great point.
>> Yeah, great point. And one hope I have
is this
>> kind of symbiosis between the digital
and the physical can make learning more
of a continuum and a par things in
parallel rather than you know maybe
spend four years at a university and
then go work and and maybe like you
mentioned Waterlue there'll be more
universities with co-op programs. We see
Northeastern, especially mechanical
engineering across the river, incredible
co-op program and such capable students
graduating already as as experienced
engineers. So, so to your point def
definitely
now I would take us in a totally
different direction Dan
foundaries vertical integration did you
allude to you know and and share what
you what what you're comfortable with
like a radiant will will be the foundry
of the future for these kinds of
technologies or do you think of
different how do you think of like that
business model that
>> this is a very complicated question you
know the the semiconductor supply chain
you know
>> I hesitate to say I understand it right.
I'm just learning even it takes years to
even begin to get the map of what's
really happening there. And more than
that, different companies are vertically
integrated to different amounts. So
maybe some I'm talking to, you know,
Google and they vertically integrate
down to here, but they also work a with
a supplier that's, you know, in this
window and they work with an OSAT that's
in this window and it's it's a real
mess. Um but that's also an opportunity
in a way to do this sort of vertical
integration when you're going a little
bit back to the drawing board. Uh
and you sort of have to do this to some
extent, right? You know, if you want to
really do 3D nanop fabrication, you
know, you have to solve the holistic
problem. There's a chicken and egg
problem there. You know, you need the
materials platform, you need the
lithography. You now have this design
space that nobody has ever operated in.
So you now need the tools to design and
you then need to educate the market on
what's possible in that space right and
and that's very very complicated
to give you a more concrete thing where
things insert really really well it's
actually in advanced packaging right so
this is sort of one of the places we're
finding there's a huge amount of pain
right now and essentially you know when
it's all inside the foundry that's well
and good but then it starts to get very
messy So as much as you can, if you can
take those advanced packaging steps in
the semiconductor industry and turn them
into something that looks more like a
foundry process, you get a really big
win. Thank you. And I can imagine while
there's big challenges, however much you
decide to own, that also is a big part
of the moat, right? This is why
manufacturing is hard. It's the
knowledge of how to convert the, you
know, the design into the physical
product.
>> Absolutely. And I think business model
is actually a big part of it, right? You
know, if we were a tool company, we
couldn't solve this problem. If we were
a materials company, we couldn't solve
this problem. If we were a fabulous
company, we couldn't solve this problem.
You know, you have to be all of these
things when you're going from zero to
one.
>> Thank you. Well, we just have a few
minutes left. I shouldn't ignore the
iPad because we have some questions from
from the audience. Uh,
John, one of the audience members wants
to hear about the Star Wars VR and how
that relates to industrially relevant
skills. It's not the highest votes, but
I think it's a really cool question.
>> Okay. Um, so, uh, uh, I'll give you an
example. Um, so I would love to use this
like, so, so I teach 8. I I don't know
if this is an MIT person, uh, you know,
I teach the yo-yo course, you know, kind
of manufacturing for junior seniors. uh
this this term we were totally
oversubscribed uh and one of the large
limitations that we have is factory
tours like we're not able uh I can only
fit one factory tour in because we have
to fit it within you know class time and
then how do we uh transport you know a
whole bus load of folks and can
factories even take 70 students everyone
is telling me no they're only going to
take 10 and then some of them you know
have restrictions and and whatnot and
then when we're there we're we're kind
of at the uh kind of at the mercy of the
host we might be seeing the process, you
know, 20 ft away. Uh, and you know,
we're kind of just listening to what the
factory tour, you know, guide is saying.
They might not even be an engineer and
and then the process might not even be
active at the time. I would love to be
able to like imagine if I had a factory
and I could take students around and
show them a process and say, "Hey, you
know, this part is incorrect. How do we
do root cause analysis?" And like we can
do anything we want to this factory. We
can pause it. We can rewind it. We can
go back to a particular place. Come with
me. You know, all none of that is
possible in a real factory. All of that
is possible if I have a virtual factory
that I can film myself walking around in
a factory and do whatever I want with
the factory. That's just one example. Uh
I mean I think you know the mechanics
faculty are really interested in like
hey stress strain fields are really
complex 3D and when I'm lecturing I'm
just like trying to take 2D uh
cross-sections. How do I lecture around
this? Well, I'd love to like walk
through the field and do so. Or we have
a physics faculty now working with us.
Like she wants to rotate ENM fields for
802. She wants to rotate and like rotate
ENM fields and talk about it, zoom in
and zoom out, walk through it kind of
like I don't know if some of you grew up
with the magic school bus, you know, but
you're kind of like you're kind of going
through things and you're pointing out
different features in a particular
place. Um, that could all be possible
now with lectures, video lectures that
we could do. some of it for
manufacturing but you know potentially
for all STEM at MIT. So those are just
some examples.
>> Can we have a 3D virtual tour of MIT
Nano?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Vladimir, let's make it
happen.
>> Okay.
>> Already in the future.
>> I will say one thing. MIT used to have
this amazing program called hacking
manufacturing where they took PhD
students and dropped them in factories
in China and then they messed around and
saw what they could do with the
manufacturing lines. And you know I
would love to see more of that.
>> I had no idea. I got to find out about
that.
>> Yeah, that's cool.
>> All right, that's a great way to end.
Thank you again so much and thanks
everyone for listening.