In my group, we study and develop
materials to make nuclear power safer.
If you want to do a neat demo, we can
actually make some stainless steel from
scratch and fire up the arc melter. Uh,
yes, I definitely want to do that.
So, we have a few projects in this lab.
One of them is to produce what I call
the fuel cladding of the future. At
Fukushima, the fuel got so hot that it
boiled the surrounding water into steam,
which reacted with the zirconium in the
fuel rods. When zirconium reacts with
steam, it also makes hydrogen gas. And
it's the hydrogen gas that exploded.
We're developing new combinations of
zirconium and stainless steel that don't
react with steam to make hydrogen. This
is a zirconium steam oxidation facility.
We take different alloys of zirconium
cut into little pieces, then put them
through hanging on a bunch of strings in
this chamber right here, and then send
in steam at 400° C to simulate what
would happen in a nuclear reactor in an
accident condition. For more MIT moments
from MIT Open Learning, like, subscribe,
or
[Music]