Uh our special guest today is Dr. Ellen
Stoofan, under secretary for science and
research at the Smithsonian Institution.
Uh the lecture is made possible by a
bequest of the late Major Lester
Gardner, a member of the MIT class of
1898.
Uh the lecturesship is earmarked for
annual presentations on aeronautical
history. Obviously, it's been broadened
since then. Over the years, we've been
honored by luminaries in the field,
including Igor Sikosski, Jimmy Doodel,
Von Brill, and Neil Armstrong. Recent
speakers were Gwen Shotwell, and Charles
Balden.
A remarkable individual, Major Gardner
played not one but two critical roles in
the advancement of aviation in the early
years of the 20th century. First with
the encouragement of Grover Loning and
Jerome Hunac and Glenn Martin, Major
Gardner organized the Gardener
Publishing Company publishing aviation
who's who in American aeronautics the
rubber age and later aviation
aeronautical engineering which was the
predecessor of aviation week which many
of us like to read. In addition, Major
Gardner was among the founders of the
Institute of Aeronautical Sciences,
which later became the Institute of
Aerospace Sciences, which was one of the
progenitors of the American Institute of
Aeronautics and Astronautics, AIAA,
which is the professional society
associated with the field. An air
officer in World War I, Major Gardner
was a recipient of numerous aeronautical
awards, including the Daniel Guggenheim
Medal in 1947,
given for outstanding achievement in
advancing aeronautics, particularly for
his conception organization, Institute
for Aeronautical Sciences. With this as
background, let's turn our attention to
our speaker today, Dr. Ellen Stoofan,
Under Secretary for Science and Research
at the Smithsonian Institution. uh in
which job she oversees the science
museums and science research centers as
well as Smithsonian libraries and
archives, office of international
relations, Smithsonian scholarly press
and scientific diving program with 25
years experience in space
administration, planetary science. Dr.
Stove has focused on the Smithsonian's
collective scientific initiatives,
commitment to research, addressing
current issues such as biodiversity,
climate change, global health, search
for life in our solar system beyond. As
the former chief scientist of NASA, Dr.
Stoofan served as principal advisor to
administrator science programs to
strategic planning helping guide the
development of long range plans to send
humans to Mars and developing strategies
for NASA to support commercial activity
in LEO. She hold masters she holds
masters and doctorate degrees in
geological sciences from Brown
University, bachelor's degrees from the
college of William and Mary. She has
received the presidential early career
award for science and engineers, the
NASA student service medal and the
explorers club lol Thomas award. Without
further ado, uh allow me to welcome Dr.
Ellen Stoofan the 2021 Lester D. Gardner
lecture. Let me turn it over to you.
>> Thank you uh so much and uh it is such
an honor to be here and of course all
those things at NASA I I did only with
the permission of my uh boss Dr. Newman
here. Uh let's see.
I was just saying after years of a year
of Zoom, I can actually share my screen.
Okay. As I said, um you know, thank you.
It's such an honor to be here today. Um
and I I thought that um given the um
excitement at least in the planetary
science community certainly but I think
in the broader community also um going
on of the last month's landing of the
Perseverance lander and the about to be
flight of um Ingenuity which uh uh uh
Dava has right behind her there. She
joined me on Mars. Um, you know, I
thought it would be interesting to
really talk about this issue of
exploring planetary surfaces with robots
and humans. Um, for those who are close
to the space program, you know that
oftentimes there's been a discussion as
though uh robotic exploration of the
solar system and human exploration of
the solar system are two things that are
opposed to each other or in conflict.
Why do we need to send humans? Um
there's always been um especially there
has been a thread in the planetary
science community sort of oh anti- um
human exploration. Um and I think we've
moved beyond that. But I think it's
really interesting to step really far
back and look at the at how we explore
planetary surfaces. And I'm going to go
through a couple different examples
today and how we use different
technologies
um to get the science that we need. And
I'm just going to argue that humans are
actually just one of those technologies,
one of those skill sets that are
available to us as we try to answer uh
really big scientific questions.
I also um have to apologize that I have
a hard cut off um right at 3:00 because
I have to go um give another talk. So I
want to apologize, but I'm going to try
to um finish well in advance to a answer
uh questions.
I thought it would be interesting to
start with um this slide which is
actually an artist rendition of the
exoplanet some of the exoplanets that
were discovered by the Kepler mission
because today I'm really going to focus
on solar system exploration but one of
the things I really want to emphasize is
is the fact that we've discovered these
uh thousands of exoplanets obviously
with with the recent numbers really
jumping up with the results from the
transiting exoplanet survey satellite
that this is putting our solar system
into a much needed and much broader
context. I think this makes this whole
question of how we explore planetary
surfaces interesting especially as we
move into the era of the James Web Space
Telescope as we think about larger and
larger telescopes. We're going to be
starting to use um astro astro
astronomical techniques to do planetary
science, which of course we did in the
beginning of planetary science. And
we'll be circling back around to that
again as we start really trying to get
at exoplanets. How earthlike are they?
What are the processes that that we see
uh taking place? Um
okay,
there we go. Um okay, but back to our
solar system. So obviously it's been 60
years that we've been um exploring our
solar system and during that time
obviously NASA has amazingly been able
to visit and in many cases revisit all
of the bodies in our own solar system
and given that I'm talking with Alan
Stern in my next uh appointment after
this one I have to mention of course um
including Pluto or quiper belt objects
we have also explored um beyond just the
major planets of our solar system and of
course series and comets and asteroids.
So, a really comprehensive exploration
and I'll be pointing out in a couple
different places this has actually
really differed from the uh exploration
plans and approaches that have been used
by other countries. Um, and I'll be
talking about Venus and Mars today.
Obviously, those were um the planets
that were most studied by the then
Soviet Union, now Russia. um which to
chose to rather than do sort of the
expansive uh reconnaissance of the solar
system that the United States did in
instead chose to focus on on just a few
bodies.
But I'm also going to argue that as
we've gone out and tried to answer
scientific questions, it's been a
function of of both what technologies do
we have available to us um to go and
answer scientific questions and then of
course how much funding is available to
actually go ahead and implement those
missions because obviously as a
scientist if we had all the money in the
world I would be everywhere with some of
the most advanced techniques. possible,
but there's only so much money.
Technology is only ever at a certain
state. So, we balance those things and
come up with priorities. And this has
now been uh as most of you know um put
into routine through the national
academyy's decadal surveys which lays
out uh 10-year plan recommendations that
they give to NASA and NASA balances
those recommendations against its budget
and and sets out priorities of what
exploration uh can be accomplished.
And as we bring in human exploration,
that brings in way other motivations for
why we explore. Um my uh many of us are
are good friends with um John Grunfeld
and he put it I think better than most
people have. Um he would say we would
explore for fear, greed, and knowledge.
And the knowledge part is the the part
I'm going to focus on today. Um the fear
part he he said was the uh the
geopolitical you know we're trying to
we're trying to show uh superiority as
we did in Apollo in the cold war to say
we have technological superiority. So
that's sort of the fear. Um greed is
obviously the era that we're moving into
right now. Are there actually commercial
reasons that drive exploration forward?
I think many of us feel it's a little
early for that. Um but but still that is
a motivator for why we might move into
the solar system. Um and and then
there's the whole inspiration piece. But
today I'm really going to focus on what
drives us forward in a scientific sense
and how do those questions become more
complex as we move and we learn which
then modifies the questions and then
again we have to have technology and
funding um catch up to allow us to
actually implement those plans. Um,
let's see.
I also want to point out that one of the
things we've certainly learned as um as
we've gained more and more knowledge um
and as we've been able as I I said said
in the first slide showing the Kepler
exoplanets
um that we always have to be really
cautious as we frame questions and move
outward because we
not only live in a single solar system
that we now know differs greatly from
many many of the solar systems we've
been able to observe but we're also
exploring our solar system at a point in
time and I really have loved this slide
that Don Brownley put together um
because all of these are the earth you
have the early earth with a magma ocean
you have the blue earth dominated by by
seno bacteria you have ice covered
snowball earth so you really have to
think we're not only investigating our
solar system as a unique place in the
universe, we're actually also getting it
at a certain point in time. And so as we
frame scientific questions, we have to
be really thoughtful about the fact um
that the time in which we are exploring
it is is not representative of the
entire history of that solar system. And
that obviously becomes really critical
as we go to places like Venus and Mars
that we know have gone like the Earth
through pretty radical changes
throughout their history. And so when
we're trying to answer scientific
questions, a lot of the times we're
trying to grab an understanding of
something that happened billions of
years before and therefore those
questions are quite hard to answer. Um
this is another reason why I'm so
excited. You know, most people are
looking for that blue planet Earth 2.0.
I want to find that really cool magma
ocean planet because you know my whole
career people are like oh yeah the magma
ocean planet and then we do this and
you're like can we go back to that magma
ocean planet really cool and the thought
that with as we develop more and more
powerful telescopes we're going to
actually be able to study examples of
these around our galaxy I think in other
solar systems I think is incredibly
exciting.
I thought it would be interesting and
obviously this is something we all know
quite well as we think about this
question of when do we use robots? How
do we change how we explore a planet
historically? How do we decide when to
go to do humans to go through how we
normally and how historically we have
explored the solar system? As all of you
well know, we started with flyby
missions. Whether it's a Pioneer, a
Mariner, a Voyager, uh those are the
easiest technologically. That's
certainly why we started out with them.
To get into orbit around a body is hard.
It was a technology we didn't have. So,
we started with flybys. or we were
trying to do something like the
reconnaissance of the outer solar
system, the Grand Tour mission, where we
know because of a unique lineup of the
planets with Voyager that we could grab
a whole bunch of planetary systems out
in the outer solar system with one um
mission, one mission, two spacecraft.
So, we choose a flyby mission partially
because it was a technology reason, but
then partially because it's
reconnaissance. It's easy to do. It
might suit a specific situation. But
then pretty quickly we want to get into
orbit. Why do we want to get into orbit?
Obviously sustained look at a planetary
surface, much better knowledge of the
gravity field so that we can understand
the interior of a planet uh and
obviously looking at change over a
planet with time. We get that global
view, the global data sets that then
actually help us figure out if we want
to land on the surface, where are we
going to go? because we only can land in
one place normally and we want to make
sure if we're spending all this money
that we're landing in the right place.
So using an orbiter we gather huge data
sets to try to understand where best to
land on a planetary surface. Um first
steps are always a robotic lander
usually without mobility because they're
easier to do. um you have a specific set
of tech of scientific questions usually
a combination of measurements of an
atmosphere if there is one a surface um
trying to understand the basic chemistry
uh is normally how we stand out all the
way to more simpler static landers like
an insight lander on Mars um that's
trying to answer a really specific
question for which you need a static
lander you have a seismometer you want
to go you want to sit on the surface you
don't want to move um so you go back to
that static lander
But as your questions become more
complex, as you understand the geology
of a surface, being in one place is not
good enough. You need mobility. Uh and
then your choice of mobility obviously
depends on your destination.
uh whether it's ground mobility or
aerial mobility and that is also driven
by the geology because if you go to a
place and I'll come back to this in a
minute as we go to Venus if your
geologic units are tens to hundreds of
kilometers across a rover is really
difficult because you're going to have
to go really far distances um before you
actually get to answer the questions
you're trying to answer. So in a case
like that, you really want aerial
mobility where you can get from point A
to point B and they're far apart much
more rapidly. Sample return is usually
obviously the next if it's
technologically feasible because as you
well know we can't repeat uh ground
laboratories um on a planet. We can do
really well. Um but the best
laboratories are still located here on
this planet. and then a human lander.
And whether your human is the vehicle
for sample return as it was with with
Apollo or whether humans are are are
doing a function beyond that is is
something uh we can discuss. And
obviously the moon is going to be the
typical sequence of how this happened.
It started with flybys, both pioneer and
luna missions, impactors in the case of
the moon because that was an easy thing
to do and get you some good data. um
Luna, the Rangers, the Surveyor program.
Russians called all their ma missions
Luna. So pretty much you say Luna, you
you're talking about one of these
missions. And then obviously surface
mobility, uh robotic in the case of the
Luna missions with the Luna, uh and S
then sample return with one of the later
Luna missions and obviously the the US
went to to surface mobility and sample
return with humans um during the Apollo
mission.
Uh and just to iterate again, even
though science was not driving the
Apollo program by any stretch of the
imagination, um it was definitely
geopolitical conflict as we all know.
Nevertheless, you still had to follow
that similar sequence of exploration
because you needed the knowledge in
order to be able to conduct uh safe uh
human operations. So you were not going
to be able to land on the surface and
move around unless you had had flyby
missions, orbiters, landers, this
sequence because you needed to gain the
knowledge to understand that it was
actually safe to conduct human
operations. So those surveyor missions
were really critical in understanding
the surface density, understanding safe
landing sites for Apollo. And so that
same sequence of um of exploration and
actually in this case um you there was
amazing science that came out of it. It
wasn't driven by the science but you
needed the knowledge to actually help
move the technology forward uh to get to
where we need to go. And that sequence
especially I think Apollo also really
illustrates
um that it's technology ready readiness
driven right we also started with simple
missions the missions got more complex
uh we learned to land on a planetary
surface we learned to take back off of a
planetary surface and we couldn't do
those things until we had developed the
technologies in order to be able to do
them. you needed the driver, the science
driver, but then you also needed the
technological capability to actually go
ahead and implement uh the mission that
you were trying to do.
Um so today I'm just going to visit the
similar sequence with some of my
favorite places um in the solar system.
You know, I can never resist um talking
about Titan down there in the uh lower
right. Um I'll visit Earth very briefly
at the end. Um, I'll start out with
Venus there in the upper left, uh, and
come around to Mars, which obviously has
the most complexity, um, and I think
some of the most interesting, um,
stories. Now, Venus is is particularly
interesting, I think, um, long a target
of exploration by the Soviet Union, and
that's Vanera 14, uh, down there, a
surface image from Vanera 14 at the
bottom of the slide. Um, and as as you
well know, Venus is a particularly
fascinating target in this solar system
and now especially even more so in the
in the context of exoplanets because
here you have this planet that's about
the same size as Earth. Uh, it's made
of, we think because of similar
densities, made of probably largely the
same materials as the Earth. It should
only be 10 to 20 degrees centigrade
hotter than the Earth because of its
proximity to the Sun. Um, and yet it's
gone through this very different um,
evolution,
losing an oceans's worth of water
probably about three and a half uh to
maybe four billion years ago. Uh,
dominated by volcanic activity is a
typical uh, Venuian surface that you see
at the top center. Uh, these are Mellin
data that you see at the top, Mellan
radar data and Mellin topographic and
radar data on the globe at the left. So
again, an Earth-sized planet, but a very
very different evolutionary
path. Uh lack of a magnetic field. Um uh
just an absolutely fascinating planet.
We started in this case exploring Venus
uh in a similar sequence. First we had
flyby missions, then we had orbiters um
in the case of the US Pioneer Venus and
and then the Mellan mission.
uh and in the case of the Russians, a
large number of missions including a
large number of surface landers as well
as the Vanera 1516 uh radar orbiter. Uh
and then they also had a balloon
mission. So adding that mobility uh
piece with the Vega balloons um down to
the surface. The US has uh long
investigated
going back to Venus um with several
different kinds of missions. one of
which is a static lander for that um
seismology uh investigation. Very hard
to do because you need to keep a
seismometer alive for at least probably
three to six months. You really want it
to last for a couple years uh so that
you can catch not just one quake quake
but a large number of quakes and a large
enough one that it actually sets up
resonances in the entire planet so that
you can get a deep interior structure of
the planet. Part of the mystery of
understanding why Venus went down this
very different uh evolutionary path than
Earth did is really to get a detailed
interior map. But as we all know, it is
500° centigrade on the surface of Venus.
Um so it is very hard to operate uh
surface landers. As most of you probably
know, the Vanera landers actually burned
up from the out inside out because they
were so well insulated from the Venujian
atmosphere that the electronics inside
could not vent. So they actually
overheated from the inside only lasting
a few hours on the surface.
But we have these hugely significant
questions for Venus like are these rough
bright areas you see in the center of
Venus. Those are called tessra. They're
continentlike regions. And if they have
granitic rock that would tell you that
Venus indeed held a lot of water and and
held water in its interior early in its
history. So the composition of these
regions is really critical. So we have
to think about what would our ideal next
mission to Venus be. Uh there have been
a couple orbiters uh both from Japan and
from Europe uh that have gone to Venus
mostly studying the Venujian atmosphere
which has a whole series I'm a surface
geologist you can tell. Oh yeah the
atmosphere. Um, so we've had two
missions that have really focused on the
atmosphere uh since Mellin, which Mellin
ended in 94. So really long time ago.
I'm obviously a little bitter about
this. Um, and we have not been back to
the surface of Venus to address any of
these huge questions that Malan unveiled
about why Venus went down this different
evolutionary path. In this current
discovery round, there are actually uh
two missions being uh proposed. Uh one
of which is a surface uh probe lander
that would last for a couple hours, get
surface chemistry and atmospheric
chemistry. And the other one is an
orbiter mission uh that would get um
near infrared. You can see through some
of the windows in the atmosphere and get
some of the surface chemistry. for
example, would be capable of detecting
erupting volcanoes
um and would also get much higher
resolution topography which would help
us answer some of these questions. Full
disclosure, I am a I'm a collaborator on
that mission called Veraritoss. So,
there are missions to get back and we've
long looked at at at mobility for Venus
mostly in balloons. Um because with a
balloon you could go up to higher levels
in the atmosphere uh where it's cooler,
cool your electronics down uh use the
super rotation to move uh and then lower
back down to the surface where it's hot,
you know, do some surface chemistry, pop
back up higher where it's cooler again.
Unfortunately, those are fairly complex
missions that would require technology
development, might require high
temperature electronics. Um, and
therefore, the science is there. We know
what questions, we know what we want to
do, but the funding and the technology
are both lagging behind. Um, so Venus is
a really frustrating place, but because
because of these high temperatures, um,
really expansive exploration of the
surface, which is what we see at Mars,
is needed at Venus, but the technology
is holding us back in a way that doesn't
allow us to do it affordably.
Now, I'm going to go I clearly like
extreme places because I'm going from
Venus, which is very hot, uh, to Titan,
which is about 90° Kelvin on the
surface. Um and Titan again follows one
of these typical progressions. First
really studied by the Voyager spacecraft
in flyby mode of the Shatternian system.
Um one of the largest moons in the solar
system and as you can see from the
Cassini image uh obviously the next
following a flyby we had the orbiter
mission to the Saturnian system of
Cassini. Um Titan is the only uh body in
the solar system with a substantial
atmosphere mostly nitrogen like ours. uh
and uh Jonathan Lenin and Sushi Lata put
together a great uh paper talking about
the fact that methane has this whole
cycle where it's being released from the
subsurface goes up into the atmosphere
is uh photochemically
uh split apart but you also have this
whole cycle where it actually rains
methane and ethane on Titan. There's a
whole hydraologic cycle with hydro
hydraology being uh replaced by
hydrocarbons. Um so a really fascinating
place and the only other place in the
solar system where we actually have um
open bodies of liquid in this case seas
and rivers of liquid methane and ethane
exchanging gas with the atmosphere and
potentially places to go to understand
the limits um of life in in our solar
system. So really interesting place.
So even though uh Cassini was actually
an interesting mission because it
combined being an orbiter with actually
having a surface probe so that you got
down to the surface with the Huygens's
mission. But clearly with the discovery
of these bodies of open liquid um on
Titan the the seas of Titan which are
predominantly located at the northern uh
the northern pole quickly became an
object of study for potential future
exploration.
So I spent about five years working on a
proposal for NASA called the Titan Mari
Explorer. It's an artist conception you
see at the at the uh right and on the
left is a map of Lijia Mari which is one
of the larger seas on Titan where you
could fit as you see the dash line in
kind of the center of the sea. Um that's
the landing ellipse arrow ellipse. So
you can actually fit um landing a probe
right directly into the sea which would
then float on the surface. Um and those
are just uh Monte Carlo simulations of
some of the paths uh that the lander
would take. The floating probe uh based
on wind models uh for uh Titan those uh
windy green lines uh and and the little
uh rose diagrams are just the elevation
of the surface to say how far would you
be able to see to the horizon.
So this mission is a particularly
interesting example of technology
readiness
uh allowing us or not allowing us to go
do a more in-depth ex uh exploration of
a planetary surface. The question was
pretty clear right only open bodies of
liquid in the solar system so high
priority target not to mention
exploration of the limits of life in our
solar system. Does life require water uh
to evolve or does it just require a
liquid? Could liquid methane and ethane
uh serve that role? So very interesting
astrobiology target along with this
uniqueness of of a hydraologic like
cycle.
But the problem is you have to live for
a very long time um in order to explore
this in in a very cold environment. So
at the time NASA came forward with a a
program uh for what they called
government furnished equipment which was
a technology test of an advanced
sterling radioisotope cooler uh which
used plutonium to create a hot side and
a cool cycle to drive a sterling uh
engine to provide the power. This is
perfect for Titan because the waste heat
from the ASRG would actually keep the
temperature inside the probe. um at at
sort of close to earth ambient
temperatures. So you wouldn't have to do
any exotic um sealing of the capsule. It
would just stay nice and kind of toasty
uh inside allowing us to use
conventional electronics and survive on
the surface of Titan. Um the problem is
the advanced sterling radioisotope
generators were not at a high enough
state of technological readiness to
actually be put on a spacecraft mission
and sent across the solar system. Um so
in the end NASA actually abandoned the
program um for a while of even working
on the ASRGs because they were having
such trouble getting the technology
readiness level up much beyond a TRL4
a and so in this case it was a really
frustrating example the science is there
the funding was almost there but the
technology actually wasn't ready this
you can do this mission um on solar but
it's obviously on and batteries but it's
obviously very hard. Um, and
conventional um, RTGs are make it less
optimal. So, you really needed a
technology solution to help you out with
this and it didn't happen. So, that's
really sad, but luckily for me, we're
still going back to Titan and for
everyone, not just me. Luckily for
everyone. Uh, so you work with what you
can, right? There are still lots of
compelling science questions for Titan.
Um and so uh this is Zibby Turtles
Dragonfly mission which was selected a
few years ago. Um it's an octacopter
that will uh land on Titan uh I think in
I think right now the date is 33. Um
and explore the equatorial zone where we
get intermittent rain. So there are
surfaces that get wet and get dry and
there are areas that we think are dried
out areas where there had pre previously
been standing liquids. So again, not
probably, in my opinion, quite as good
of a target as those seas at the North
Pole, but really still able to address
some of these outstanding
astrobiological questions for Titan and
using mobility in a different way. You
know, in the lakes, we were actually
using just the the wind moving the probe
around on the lake surface, but in this
case, we could actually use aerial
mobility because the Titan atmosphere is
so dense and cover actually pretty far
distances and explore a lot of different
geological terrains from the dunes that
you see here in this artist conception
all the way to an impact crater uh
that's a little further on its on its uh
journey.
I want to spend uh uh the last part
obviously talking about this place uh
Mars um that you see behind me and on
the screen. Um and Mars is obviously,
you know, as we look at the path of
exploration, um I find the Mars story to
be a particularly fascinating one
because again, you have this very
similar progression, right? We went from
orbital missions, uh we refined the
science questions, we landed on the
surface, we then developed mobility, and
right now we're looking at moving into
an era of of sample return and human
exploration. So following very much this
kind of uh cookbook that we laid out
with the moon, we've been doing the same
thing with Mars, but laid out over a
much much longer time period. And the
length of that time period, I'm going to
argue, has to do with not just funding
and technology, but also has to actually
do with the science and how we progress
the science forward. So most of you know
obviously Mars along a target of
fascination because of these dried up
rivereds that you can see that was are
uh pointed out seen in the mariner data
fly by m early flyby missions but then
of course uh well mapped um by the
Viking mission with its two orbiters and
two landers on the surface and because
we got this amazing Viking data set of
Mars we've been able to with subsequent
orbiters but also subsequent landers
get down to the surface and then use
mobility to try to answer more and more
sophisticated
uh questions.
But with the Viking lander, which is
over on the far right, we also stumbled
in a way that I think is particularly
interesting because obviously as as most
of you know, one of the prime questions
that Viking was trying to answer was the
question we're still trying to answer is
did life evolve on Mars? And I think a
lot of you know the story that um my dad
worked for NASA. I was at the Viking
launches. I was 14 years old to date
myself. and Carl Sean and Jerry Soffen
were there and they were giving talks
about why we were exploring Mars and
looking for life. And I said, "Wow,
that's really cool. I'm going to be a
planetary geologist and do that, too."
And that's what I've done. And here we
still are talking about was there life
on Mars? How are we going to try to
figure this out? But obviously, as you
well know, the Viking lander experiment
used the science that we had at the time
and our understanding of life to design
an experiment to search for life that
was just fundamentally flawed based on
Mars and what we now know about Mars. We
were never going to get a positive
result from the Viking lander
experiment. putting putting water and
nutrient-rich uh mixing that with a soil
at the top of Mars surface is not going
to do anything for you because of the
fact that the top surface of Mars is so
heavily radiated full of things like
perchlorates. But we didn't have enough
information to design that experiment in
the way. So it wasn't that those people
were doing anything wrong. They designed
the experiment to answer the science
question with the information they had
at the time. But of course, there was a
feeling that when they got a negative
result to the life experiment on Viking,
that there was a lot lack of interest
from NASA and the scientific community,
not really from the scientists, but
certainly from the broader public. Oh,
there's no life on Mars. It's just
another dead planet. Why go back? Um and
as time has gone on that did have a
partially cause a pause along with
funding issues of exploring Mars. But
then as we got more sophisticated
realized and understood Mars better, we
designed more and more complex missions
to Mars that really followed this
premise of trying to understand the
first thing you have to do is step back
and try to understand the habitability.
And obviously one of the things that um
that Curiosity
uh has done for us and this is obviously
a shot of Gail Crater from the Curiosity
lander. Those beautiful beautiful layers
of rock that we know many of them were
laid down in water. This issue that
water did persist for very long periods
of time on Mars and that we know that
habitable environments existed. We also
have gotten much more sophisticated
about what would it take to actually
find life on Mars. Um, and this is from
a a NASA astrobiology website called the
ladder of life that I particularly like
because it really gets to this issue of
how do you design a scientific
experiment to actually try to answer the
question you're trying to answer? And
you think that's trivial. Any of us who
are scientists or engineers know that's
not trivial. It is really hard to make
sure you're designing your instrument to
really get at the answer when you might
not actually know what the answer looks
like. And obviously there is now over
the last uh well it's not obvious over
the last 5 to 10 years increasingly
interesting study by astrobiologists
around the concept of life as we don't
know it. because this ladder of life
which is basically how we go about
searching for life uh in our solar
system and then beyond does really is
really based on earth life. So we look
for biomolecule components, we look for
functional molecules like DNA or RNA,
we're looking for metabolism and then
ultimately Darwinian evolution when we
search or design an experiment to search
for life. the scientific community is
having increasingly interesting
conversations about how do you search
for life as we don't know it. Um and
obviously some of these things still
hold.
So, as we go into a new site on Mars
with Perseverance, and this is Jazerero
Crater, uh, where the Perseverance
lander is now sitting, a really good
example of how that orbital data, and
you know, I sort of presented on that
early slide this how we explore
planetary surfaces, this kind of linear
progression. But of course, it's not. We
need increasingly sophisticated um
orbiters to get ground data that helps
us then decide and refine where we send
landed missions. And in this case, these
colors on this are from orbital data
telling us there are clays on the
surface in this uh delta region on Mars.
Uh that would be an environment, the
type of environment in which life could
originate. Hence the choice of that for
the perseverance uh landing. And of
course, here is Perseverance itself
being lowered down uh onto the surface
um of Mars um having on it a series of
experiments
uh different instrument tools that will
help us get closer to this question of
did life evolve on Mars? Um and of
course, one of the really fun things uh
about uh this is this is an image. I
think it's it it's uh one that just came
down I think yesterday of uh the
Ingenuity helicopter. So now combining
not just uh mobility on the surface as a
rover but also bringing aerial mobility
along and I was I have been not joking
all along the Ingenuity helicopter as
most of you know has a piece of the
right flyer fabric on it and I keep
saying that future astronauts have to go
pick Ingenuity up and bring it back so
that we can put it next to the right
flyer in the Air and Space Museum uh at
some point in the future. Sorry, I set
an alarm so that I would stop talking.
Um, so I think this will be a really and
we're all looking forward to Ingenuity's
first flight next week, but this idea of
bringing along a recon tool to allow you
to better scope out where the rover is
going to go next, I think is a really
good example of of robotic tools.
Obviously, the other interesting thing
about the Perseverance mission is it's
going to lead to that next step of
sample return that we've only done uh on
another planetary body at the moon.
We've obviously done it uh for both uh
asteroids
um and for uh deep space particles, but
we really are looking and obviously
other countries have also done it for
comets, but really looking forward to
seeing the implementation of the Mars
sample return mission um that is now
notional for the uh late uh 2020s. Um,
but the problem is obviously even with
these really wonderful cache samples
from uh Perseverance, they're still
going to be really limited. Um, and the
problem is, as we all know, is that if
life evolved on Mars, which we think
there's good scientific reason to think
that it would have. What we really want
to know is to what degree of complexity
did it get? How widespread was it? How
varied was it? And one small sample is
not going to answer that. And so to me,
the only way you're ever going to answer
these really complicated questions about
the evolution of life on Mars is by
sending humans. Um because it is this
question of not just looking at one
rock, but looking at thousands of rocks,
not just moving around one crater, but
moving around many regions of Mars. Um
and so being able to have humans on the
surface is actually uh the best way to
move this forward.
But Mars is really hard. Humans are
always going to rely on robots in order
to be able to function on Mars. Whether
it's from orbital data, uh whether it's
from reconnaissance tools like uh like
small helicopters that can do recon. Um
and in particular also, I would argue um
from things like artificial intelligence
that are going to help humans make
decisions, especially when they're well
out of signal uh any kind of immediate
signal contrast um from Earth. So really
important to send humans but also really
important not to underestimate
uh the difficulty in actually getting
humans to Mars.
But I think um just to close and then
I'd love to take questions.
Um when we explore planetary surfaces
our our ultimate aim is always to get
back to try to understand how planets
work with the ultimate goal of really
trying to understand how does the earth
work. Um and and these questions have
become even more critical when we look
at things uh like climate change and say
we really need to understand how
climates evolve and change on other
planets. We really want to understand
how life evolves and changes and
possibly goes extinct on other planets.
Uh and and I think the earth is also a
really good example of the fact that we
best explore and we do the best science
when we have humans and robots working
together. And and it's to me always been
a false argument of trying to choose
between humans and and robots. And
instead we should really think about
what question are you trying to answer?
What is the best tool? And humans are a
tool in our toolbox and how do we move
the science forward by choosing the
appropriate tool and how do we keep pu
pushing technology forward as our as our
uh questions become more and more
complex. So uh thank you and I will stop
there.
>> So Dr. Stoven, thank you very much for a
fascinating talk that laid out both the
the technological things we got to do as
well as the scientific questions. You
know there are some on this Zoom call
who are technologists actually studying
the advancement of technology. Maybe
they'll take some lessons from what you
said there. So let let's open it up to
questions. Can you please uh if you have
a question put up your hand which is in
the reactions
uh and I will call upon uh you
questions anybody
Jeff Hoffman. So Jeff do you know
anything about Mars?
>> Well yeah
>> just a little bit.
>> Our our Moxy experiment is going to
provide some of that 20 show us how to
provide that 20 tons of oxygen. But just
two comments. The first on you know
related to humans and robots just to
make sure everybody appreciates that
right now it takes hundreds of people to
operate one little robot on Mars which
which really is kind of amazing when
when you think about it in terms of the
relative efficiency of human and robotic
exploration.
Um, and the second thing uh that that
I've I've always tried to talk to my
roboticist friends is,
you know, right now we operate uh
Perseverance and and all the Mars rovers
and everything, you know, so
conservatively because there's only one
of them and, you know, unlike the Hubble
telescope, we can't go and fix it if it
breaks. So, so we're extremely limited
in what we're willing to do. Imagine if
you as a roboticist could be on Mars
with your robots and able to fix them if
they break and also reconfigure them if
they're, you know, new experiments
become available. and um and and so I
think that's the real future of human
robotic cooperation is is is having
people in the same working area at the
same time in places that humans can get
to. Obviously, there's always going to
be places that only we can send robots
to. But anyway, thanks thanks very much
for your talk. Yeah, and Jeeoff, those
are really good points. And I I used to
make use the example I think it took the
opportunity rover about eight nine years
to go 26
uh miles. So I always say, you know, a
human most many humans probably you, not
me, you know, can can run a marathon in
in a number of hours and yet you had
this rover that it took eight years to
go that far. And and I think human
mobility um as you say, risk aversion is
a big deal. Um and and it's frustrating
to me now with perseverance you're like
have we gone anywhere yet and you're
just you know not that we wouldn't be
very cautious with humans that we send
also but and I think that human and
robotics robots together is really
critical for example there are zones on
Mars that right now the scientific
community has said that humans should
not go there because there still could
be accident life on Mars there's zones
where we think there is water close to
the surface uh a and therefore humans
shouldn't go there from both sides
contamination. You know, we don't want
to come contaminate Mars life. We don't
want to uh get COVID like you know some
kind of um pandemic disease from Mars
life which I am actually not worried
about but some people obviously are
concerned about it. And so the idea that
humans could approach zones where we
think that water was close to the
surface, send robots in to find out if
that's true or not, send robots in to
actually assess it, see if there is um
some extent life, um is a really
critical one. So that humans and robots
working together is totally the way
we're going to explore Mars in the
future. Um and I think most of us who
lived through this versus debate have
always been very frustrated. Why are we
arguing about this? It's it's kind of,
you know, not a not a useful argument.
>> Okay. Thank you. So, David Newman.
>> Hi, Ellen. Thank you. That was an
incredible talk. Really enjoyed it. Um,
looking for students hands. Oh, good.
One's coming up. So, I'm going to be
quick so we can try to get you more, but
um trying to channel maybe a a question
or tea up something for you to comment
on on behalf of a lot of our students
that are watching too. Uh first thank
you for uh chairing the um transition
for for NASA. That was I know an amazing
amount amount of work and effort. Uh so
thank you so much for doing that.
Maybe what one or two pieces of advice
would you give the the new NASA
leadership team coming on board um to
help with our lunar? We'll just keep it
the question to what's your what maybe
some words of wisdom for um exploring
the moon and Mars in the immediate
future.
>> Um I'm not supposed to talk about
anything that happened during the
transition. So I have to be care but I'm
very I you know I have lots of opinions.
So I have to be careful how I answer it.
So
you know if you look historically so
this is a whole another subject you know
talk too um you know or hopefully I hope
you guys have had one of these talks if
not we you should get one um on this
whole issue of of the politics and I
think the last you know especially 20
years have been super interesting as
we've done this moon versus mar you know
what became a moon versus Mars kind of
discussion um and I think it was
particularly interesting obviously over
end of Clinton, uh I guess through the
Bushes, um Obama, Trump, um now to Biden
of what is where are we going with human
exploration? What is the target? And and
frankly, when I first got to NASA under
under Obama, I had someone say to me,
"Oh, the destination actually doesn't
matter." And I'm like, "No, actually,
the destination does matter. It matters.
It matters to me as a scientist, but I
think it matters to everyone. You just
can't plan human exploration and not
care where you're going. Um, and so I do
think for NASA as you look at at it
being changed from its purpose being
changed sort of every four to eight
years for human exploration combined
with a lack of resources
um and very high expectations
makes it very hard for the agency to
succeed. Um and I think the challenge
for the and the opportunity
for the incoming administration is going
to be the um emphasis on
uh balancing presence in low earth orbit
>> with again stop pitting things against
each other as we worked on David. It's
not moon versus Mars, it's moon to Mars.
Um, and so this continuity of of
purpose,
um, that we actually started joking
about the transition team, I think we
heard it from every single person we
talked to. Continuity of purpose. I
think that continuity of purpose is
really important for NASA and it doesn't
matter what administrations you're
talking about, what parties, you've got
to let NASA have some continuity of
purpose or we're not going anywhere.
>> Okay. Thank you. So George, there's a
question from a student.
>> Thank you Dan. Thank you Ellen very much
for your talk. Um I I'm a PhD student in
the engineering systems lab. I work with
Professor Dec and also with Professor
Hoffman and I'm kind of following up on
Jeff's question about humans and robots
on on planetary surfaces.
Um so it's interesting that uh there has
been this gap of about seven eight and
then 10 years between different
generations of Roberts Pathfinder in 96
per spirit and opportunity 2003
curiosity 2011 and then perseverance
2021 so the gap is about 7 to 10 years
and it's actually slightly increasing as
we're going along. So um maybe the the
other use of humans is not that they are
faster scientists and better scientists
but that the cycle of evolution of
robots can accelerate when humans are on
planets with robots and I wonder what
your thoughts are on that.
>> You know I think that's a really good
point because frankly that seven to 10
years that you're seeing it is actually
a pretty typical cycle for for NASA
flagship missions. you can afford to do
a flagship or a multi-billion dollar
mission
about once a decade um and that's come
out of the decadals and NASA is often in
the planetary science division and
because after the um famous ALH841
there became a Mars program line in the
budget so there was a little more money
so they could sometimes squeeze two
flagships in in the in in a decade one
Mars and one maybe to the outer solar
system
But but this is where that funding
piece, right, becomes really critical.
And then frankly, it's it's compounded
with a risk aversion, right? Because
then you're thinking, this is my only
chance to go to Mars in this decade. I
know it's going to cost me billions of
dollars. So, do I want to really have a
next generation rover or am I just going
to take more or less a carbon copy of
the Curiosity rover because it worked
and do it again? So all of a sudden you
also get this risk aversion to pushing
technology development because you're
you know this is my this is my chance to
go to Mars in the decade. I'm not taking
any risk. And so I really do think that
if you saw humans going to Mars the
investment in in the robotic
technologies would go up because as you
say humans are going to need these tools
to work with. The human exploration
program tends to be better funded than
the planetary exploration program. And I
think there's going to be a demand,
right? Because now humans are going to
really need these robotic tools. And I
think it's going to lead to this much
better robots and humans. And for me,
that's exciting because that means way
more science. And so I I think we're
going to move into a really exciting
point, whereas right now we really are
limited by this kind of pace of
available budget flagship a decade kind
of um situation.
>> All right. It's 3:00. So, thank you very
much.
>> Uh, let's let's thank her again.
>> Thank you. This was really fun. I'm
really sorry. I could I could talk to
you guys all day. I'm really sorry.
>> Thank Thank you, Joyce, for what you did
in setting this up. And thank you all
for attending. I'll let
>> Can you
All right. Thanks everybody. Sorry I
have to run.
>> Byebye.
>> Thank you.