Okay. So today we're doing linear
programming and we are um
yeah going to basically do a very I
think a four or five
lecture um
unit on linear programming and linear
programming is one of the big
I guess engines behind optimization
and to show how important it is um Well,
when I started working in
1986,
there were a bunch of linear programming
um you know tools on the market and
Robert Bixby in 1987 founded a company
and wrote Clex which was the um by far
the best linear programming tool on the
market and he charged uh immense amount
for it and a lot of people bought it and
he retire and he sold his company 10
years later for I don't know4 or $50
million
and um you know and IBM recently bought
the company that he sold it to for $180
million so it's big business
and very important
okay
just yeah so what is linear programming
So I'm going to give two examples of
problems you might want to solve with
linear programming and
um
then we will continue with other things.
So what is linear programming? It's
essentially
optimize
either minimize
or maximize
a linear function
subject to linear constraints.
And we'll start with a diet model.
And um
so this is actually taken straight from
the lecture notes and I think
given the um
given the costs I think it only works if
you're feeding mice. So, let's say you
have some mice
um
and their nutritional requirements.
They need a certain amount of starch.
Um and there are two grains you can give
them. Grain one and grain two. And
they need eight
units of starch,
15 units of protein, and seven units of
vitamins.
And grain one contains five,
four, and two, and costs um
60 cents.
And
grain two costs contains seven, two, and
one, and costs
35.
And the question is how cheaply can you
feed the mice and satisfy their
nutritional requirements.
So what we do with linear programming is
we
need
to write down
a model.
And how do you write down a model? You
choose variables.
write
objective function and constraints
and then you feed your linear program to
a linear programming package and it will
give you the answer. So any suggestions
as to what the variables should be.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. How much of each grain? So let's
let x1
amount of grain one
and x2 be the amount of grain two.
And now we want to write down an
adjective function. So we either need to
minimize or maximize something. So what
do we want to minimize
the cost? So
let's write it down here. Minimize.
I guess it's
60 x1 + 35 x2.
And what are the constraints? Well, the
constraints are that they get enough
starch, get enough proteins, and get
enough vitamin. So that would be
And what we do when we write down linear
programs is we say subject
to
I believe we say subject two. Let's see
if
yeah subject to
before we write down all the
constraints.
So
subject two and now we need some things.
So we need
5 * the grain 1 + 7 * grain 2 has to be
at least 8.
So 5 x1 + 7 x2 is greater than or equal
to 8.
And 4x1 + 2 x2 is greater than or equal
to 15.
And finally
2x1 + x2 is greater than equal to 7
and I'm not going to solve it in part
because it has an utterly trivial answer
and also
we're not going to actually tell you how
to solve linear programmings. in this
class.
Um there's something called the simplex
method and I will you know give you a
very rough overview of how the simplex
method works at some point. But actually
explaining exactly how the details work
is something first you'll probably never
need because there are tons of linear
programming packages and you can you
know just download one from the internet
and use that. And second,
it's, you know, it's explaining how it
works is somewhat interesting, but it's
also rather tedious and there are lots
of little um technicalities you have to
go through. So I don't really want to do
that.
So um
so that is linear program.
Oh wait,
I just realized there are two
constraints I did not write down. Does
anybody can anybody tell me what they
are?
Yes.
>> Negative.
>> Non- negativity. Yeah. So, x1 greater
than or two x1 greater than or equal to
zero and x2 greater than equal to zero.
And these are non- negativity
constraints.
Non
negativity constraints.
And they're actually handled a little
bit differently than most constraints
in um
are often handled a little differently
from most constraints in linear
programming.
Okay.
Okay. And now I'm going to come up with
a another example.
Okay. So, let's say you're having a bake
sale
and there are two things you know how to
bake. Let's say you know how to bake
cookies.
and we'll simplify the ingredient list.
Don't, you know, don't go home and use
this ingredient list for real cookies.
So,
um, eggs
we need one, sugar,
we need two cups, and flour,
we need one cup, no, one and 1/2 cups.
And then you also know how to bake
meringues.
And for those you need three eggs,
you need one cup of sugar. And you don't
need any flour.
And you can sell
a batch of meringues
for $20.
And you can sell a batch of cookies
So the first thing we need to do is
write down our variables. So what
variables would you use?
Yeah.
>> No. Yes.
>> Like how many cookies and how many,
>> right? How many batches of cookies and
how many batches of meringue? So um
let's say x1
is the number of batches
of cookies
and x2 is a number of batches
of merangues.
And what do we have? Well,
you want to maximize the amount of
money. So, you want to maximize
um so our notes call the things you're
maximizing or minimizing Z. And
um
much of the time you don't actually need
to
not much of the time you don't actually
need to write down Z in your linear
program. But there are sometimes when
it's very useful to have a variable name
for the thing you're maximizing. So
we'll use it. Um, well, you don't want
to run out of eggs. So, that means that
the number of batches of cookies, x1
* 1 + 3 *
x2
had better be less than or equal to the
total number of eggs you have,
which I didn't tell you what how many
eggs you had.
Okay.
So, let's say we have nine eggs,
um,
eight cups of sugar,
and 15 cups
flour.
So, x1 + 3x2 is less than equal to 9.
And 2x1 + x2
is less than or equal to 8. And there's
another one. 1.5 * x3 x1
is less than or equal to 15.
And of course we have x1 greater than
equal to 0 and x2 greater than equal to
zero.
And one nice thing you can do with
linear programs if there's not very many
variables and not very many um
constraints is you can actually draw the
feasible region on the plane. So
I think I need to give you some notation
before I go ahead. Um
with drawing this
notation.
A feasible solution
is not necessarily optimal is a
is a point.
Let's say x1 through xn are our
variables or x1 x2
through
um
I'm looking see if the notes
okay let's say x k
bit satis The size of the constraints.
[applause]
An optimal solution
is a feasible solution that optimizes
our objective function.
>> [groaning]
>> So,
okay.
So what does the feasible region look
like? Well, let's write it down. Let's
say this is x1 and this is x2
and we have x1 well we have 2 x1 + x2 is
less than equal to 8 which means we have
the point 8 up here and the point 4 down
here and we have the linear region
there.
So that's our first
constraint.
Second constraint is x1 + 3 x2 is less
than equal of 9. So now let's
put 9 here
three here. And our second constraint
will be everything under
this.
And the third constraint is 1.5x1 is
less than equal to 15 which means x1 is
less than or equal to 10 which means the
third constraint
is
everything to the left of this line.
So you can see that this third
constraint is completely
meaningless because anything that
satisfies the first two constraints must
satisfy the third one.
And the actual feasible reason is this
region
and the intersection of the first two
constraints.
Okay.
I think before I need to say anything
more, I should say something about
the standard form and the canonical form
for linear programming programs.
Because
so
the notes
form.
So maximum
Z is equal to
cranspose.
These are our constraints. No, this is
our not constraints. This is our
objective function X.
So here
I guess
cranspose
is the vector 2020
um
ax
equals b
and x greater or equal to zero.
canonical form
maximum
and it's nearly the same cranspose
x
a sub x less than equal to b
x greater than or equal to zero
Thurm.
any
um linear program can be put
into
well either standard
or canonical
form.
So how do we do this?
Okay. So there are some easier one. So
suppose our objective function
suppose
objective function is minimize
3x + 5 3x1 + 5 x2. How would you turn
that into a maximization problem?
>> Yes. negative.
>> Yeah, exactly. Stick a negative on it.
Maximize - 3x1 - 5x2.
Okay.
Um
suppose you
have
unconstrained variable
X subi
can be either positive or negative.
Maybe I should just tell you the answer
to this because it's not quite as
obvious as the last one.
Okay.
So replace
x i with
x sub i + - x sub i minus
x sub i + is greater than equal to zero.
x sub i minus is greater than equal to
zero.
So whenever you have
so I mean
doesn't matter whether x i is positive
or negative there's also ways some x i
plus and some x i minus which will give
you any value of x subi
and now these are non- negative
variables
Okay. So, there's two more cases I
should talk about. Um,
and they are a little bit more
complicated than this.
Um
suppose
So let's look up here. So canonical form
all the constraints are inequalities.
Standard form all the constraints are
equalities. So to go back and forth
between canonical form or standard form
or just to put an arbitrary linear
program in canonical form we need to
turn inequalities into equalities and
vice versa. So suppose we have
have
um
x1 + 3 x2 less than equal to 9
x1 x2 greater than equal to zero. How do
we make this in a How do we make this
inequality?
Any suggestions?
>> Yes,
>> you can add another variable. you add
another variable. Very good. What we add
do is we add something that's called a
slack variable
and we get x1 + 3 x2 + s
is equal to 9
with s greater than or equal to zero.
And if we have x1 + 3 x2
greater than equal to 9, we would add
something called a surplus variable.
x1 + 3x2
- x = 9 s greater than zero.
And the last thing is we do we need to
do is we need to say how to turn
any inequal equalities into
inequalities.
And that is actually again pretty easy.
So if we have x1
+ 3 x2 = 9,
we can turn that into x1 + 3 x2
greater than or equal to 9 and x1 + 3 x2
less than or equal to 9.
So anything that satisfies this
satisfies that. And now if you don't
like if you want to put your thing in
canonical form, you need to get rid of
all the greater than equal to signs. But
that's easy. Then you just say - x1 -
3x2 is less than equal to - 9.
And this is canonical form.
So why do we need to worry about
canonical form and standard form?
Well,
standard form
use
in simplex method.
So the simplex method is one of the
standard ways of solving linear programs
and we're not going to go into it but as
I said I will sketch you the basic ideas
for it at some point and we use use this
in duality
and
duality is one of the most important
um
I guess aspects of linear program. Well,
another very important aspect of linear
program is that there's efficient method
of solving them. But as I said, we're
not going to um explain that very in
very much detail because,
you know, if you're, you know, a ma an
applied mathematician employed at some
company, you never actually solve linear
programming by hand. You
you use whatever tool you have
available, which is probably CLEX, if
it's a company that solves a ton of
different linear programs. And um
that's
you know you don't need to know what's
underneath the hood in CLEX but
if you are an applied mathematician you
really do need to know how to use
duality and I we will explain duality in
this course. [clears throat]
So,
um,
So let's write down a theorem.
Every
linear program
that has a solution
and optimal solution
has an optimal
optimal
basic
feasible solution.
Okay. So what is a basic feasible
solution? Well, the easiest way to
explain is
by looking at this diagram. Of course,
you know, real linear programs, this
diagram isn't planer. It's n-dimensional
and impossible to draw on a blackboard,
but
the basic idea is the same. So the basic
the
the basic feasible solutions
are basically the intersection
are the
extreme points of the feasible region.
So these are basic feasible
solutions
and the theorem is that one of these is
optimal.
So why are they called basic feasible
solutions?
Well, to explain that, I think I need to
go into
um standard form and put this linear
proto in standard form.
The above LP in standard form
is
um
maximize
Z = 20 X1 + 20 X2.
Um
subject two
um x1 + 3 x2 less than equal to 9
x2
or rather
plus s1. This is our slack variable. And
now we need 2 x1
plus x2.
And now we need a different slack
variable for the second equation. You
need a slack variable for each equation.
When you're doing this and finally
15x1.5x1
is less than equal to 15.
So that would be plus S3
equals 50.
So a basis Here
basis is a linearly independent
set of columns.
So
let's just take
um
this one.
Okay. So that is x1
plus s1
= 9.
2x1 + s2
s2 =
and 1.5 x1 + x3.
Actually,
we're just picking these three columns.
So, we leave this one. So, that is equal
to
15.
And for every basis there's a solution
because this is just uh
you know an a a matrix times a vector
equals a vector.
I mean it's just uh
set of linear equations with k
equations and k variables. So it has a
solution.
Um,
and I guess this solution would be x1 =
10. And now you could use this to get S2
equals
that's 20 + S2 = 8 - 12 and
S1 = -1.
So you can see that this
basis
is not
feasible solution.
because it violates the
um non- negativity constraints.
But
every linear program has a feasible
solution which the feasible points here
correspond
to the
extreme points of the feasible region.
And the optimal one is the one 20 x1 +
20 x2
that is furthest in the direction of the
vector which is the objective function.
And what does the linear programming
what does the simplex algorithm do?
Well, what the simplex algorithm does is
it starts at
one basic feasible solution, which in
this case you would use 0 0 and it walks
along the edges
until
and it chooses an edge which improves
the objective function every time. And
there's always an edge that improves the
objective function unless you're
actually at the optimum. So that just
walks along the edges until it reaches
the optimum.
So is this an efficient algorithm?
Well,
this is a little bit of um
you know, history which
we're not going to um
you know, we're not going to test you
on, but you know, this was Donsig's
simplex algorithm just to walk along the
edges and he proposed it. It worked
really well in practice, but pretty much
for any
I mean, you need some way of choosing
which edge you're going to walk along.
And pretty much for any way of choosing
which edge you want to walk along,
people could come up with a counter
example which it took exponentially many
steps along the edges.
So
it works really well in practice. In the
worst case,
nobody could,
you know, nobody could prove that it
worked really well.
And
this lasted until
Dan Spielman and um Tang, Dan Spielman
was a professor at MIT at the time,
invented a new technique called smooth
analysis that says that it works really
well almost all the time.
So
that is probably all we're going to say
on the simplex algorithm.
Okay.
So now I want to talk about duality
and we're going to use this
linear program as a
you know as an example. And actually
as you can see from that diagram we
could just get rid of this constraint.
it doesn't make any difference and just
look at these first two constraints.
So what we're going to do is we're going
to ask how can we find a lower bound on
the optimum and how can we find an upper
bound on the optimum
and then we will show that
these two bounds actually will end up
being equal
under some conditions. So lower bound
any feasible solution
solution
gives a lower bound.
So let's take a feasible solution for
that one. Um how about x1 = x2 = 2. That
satisfies all the constraints.
X1 = X2 = 2
and um
does that 2 + 6 is 8 and 4 + 2 is 6 and
those are satisfied
and the objective function
is 20 * 2 + 20 * 2 is equal to 80.
So that is one way you could do this.
And I should say that for this linear
program, even though I've called them
batches, you have to assume that you can
use fractional numbers for x1 and x2.
Otherwise, you get an integer program
and not a linear program. And those are
much more complicated.
Okay, so any feasible solution gives you
a lower bound. How about an upper bound?
So
let's I'm going to write down something.
20 x1 + x2,
okay,
is certainly less than 20 x1 + 3 x2,
right? Because we have
well because x2 is positive. And now we
have x1 + 3x2 is less than equal to 9.
So this is less than or equal to 20 * 9
= 180.
And we can do the same thing for the
second um constraint.
20 x1 + x2 is less than equal to 20
*
2x1
+ x2 is less than or equal to 160.
So these are both good upper bounds and
this is a good lower bound. Can we do
better?
Okay, let's do better.
Let's add this and this.
We have
two. Let's see. We have 3x1
+ 4x2.
[applause]
So we're adding these two constraints.
It's less than or equal to 17
and you know we have 203.
Oh,
x1 + x2 is
less than or equal to 20/3 * 3x1 + 4 x2
is less than or equal to 20/3
* 17 which is equal to um 113 and the
third.
Okay,
so we got a much better upper bound by
adding these two constraints.
So what happens if we find the best sum
of these constraints?
How does it look?
Okay. So I want to go about this more
systematically so we can find the dual
linear program. Every linear program has
a dual linear program and we want to do
this. So we have
and
you know the way we
the way we will do this is we will
assume that the linear program is
canonical
in canonical form for the time being and
luckily this linear program just happens
to be in canonical form.
So how do we do this? Well,
what we want to do is we want a
combination of
a combination
of these
constraints
which will let us give a best upper
bound possible. So let's say we have y1
* our first constraint x1 + 3x2 is less
than equal to 9
and y 2 * our second constraint
um that's 2x1 + x2 is less than or equal
to
>> [applause]
>> And now
we want
this combination
to be less than
or equal to.
All right.
We want 20 x1 + x2 to be bigger than to
be less than or equal to our
combination. So we want the combination
to be bigger than or equal to
20 x1 + 20 x2. So that tells us that y1
* 1 + y 2 * 2
had better be bigger than 20.
And 3 y1 + y 2
is also bigger than or equal to 20.
So suppose we found y's like this. What
would we have?
We would have
y1
x1.
Okay, I want it. Y1 + 2 Y 2
X1 +
3 Y1 + Y 3 Y1 + Y2
X2
is greater than or equal to 20 x1 + 20
x2.
So this
would be our things and this is in turn
less than or equal to
I want to say 9 y1 + 8 y 2
y 2
So to get the best bound on 20 x1 + 20
x2, we need to minimize 9 y1 + 8 y2. So
we want to minimize
9 y1 + 8 y 2 subject to
um
y1 + 2 y2 greater than equal to 20.
>> [applause]
>> and 3 y1 + y2
+ y2 greater than equal to 20
and y1 y2 greater than equal to zero. So
why y1 y2 greater than equal to 0? Well,
I mean, if y 2 was less than zero, then
when we add these equalities up, we
have,
you know,
the less than or equal to if y2 was less
than or equal to zero, the less than
equal to sign would turn into a greater
than equal to sign and adding these
inequalities up would not make any
sense. So, we need the yi is greater
than equal to zero.
So what did we what did we get here?
What is this thing?
It's another linear program. So this is
the dual
linear program.
And now I want to write down
I want to write down the dual linear
program for an arbitrary program in
um canonical form
and then we will
show the theorem of weak duality.
But maybe I want to um
maybe I want to solve these linear
problems first.
So
x1
Okay=
3 x2 = 2.
This is a feasible point.
X1 = 3. X 2 = 2. That's 3 + 2 * 3 is
less than equal to 9. And 6 + 2 is less
than equal to 8. So this is a feasible
point. And objective function is 20 * 5
= 100.
Now let's solve this one.
Okay, I did not write down the solution
here. But there is a solution to this
linear program. So the objective
function is also 100.
And um
you know the dual program gave you an
upper bound and the feasible point in
the dual program gives you an upper
bound. A feasible point in the primal
program gives you a lower bound. So
because this 100 is equal to that 100
then
we are we know that the answer is 100.
So let's try y1 = 4, y 2 = 8.
4 + 16 is 20. 12 + 8 is 20. and
9 * 4 + 8 * 8 is equal to 100.
So here is a feasible point for the dual
program which also gives the optimum
objective value.
Okay.
So,
canonical
form
duel.
Okay. Well, the primal
was maximize
z= c transpose x
sub subject to a x
less than equal to b and x greater than
zero.
>> [clears throat]
>> Well, the duel
turns out to be minimize
y I'm sorry w equals
b transpose y
subject to a transpose
y is greater than equal to c y greater
than equal to zero.
And you can see why this is maybe by
looking at this example. Um
[clears throat]
when we did this example, we had you
know the original linear program
had the matrix A 1 3 2 1.
This now has the matrix A equals 1 2 3
1. And this two came from the
A I J A12
thing a um a 21
um entry of A and now it's the A12 entry
of the new A. So this is just this
matrix is just the transpose of the
original.
The right hand sides are just the
original um objective function and the
new objective function is just the right
hand sides of these inequalities.
So [clears throat]
um we have
a transpose
instead of a the objective function gets
turned into the right hand side of the
constraints and the right hand side of
the constraints gets turned into the new
objective function.
Okay.
Okay. So now I will prove something
called weak duality.
Durham
weak
duality.
If x is a feasible solution of the
primal
with objective
function
um
z= cranspose
x
And y is a feasible solution
of dual
objective function
w equals
b transpose
Y [sighs]
and then
Z is less than group W.
So any feasible solution of the primal
is less than any feasible solution of
the duel.
Okay. There's also something called
strong duality
which we're not going to have a chance
to prove today. We will do that next
time. But I'm going to tell you what it
is and then we'll get the proof of weak
duality.
So strong duality is really
I want to say this is
one of the great um
one of the most important you know
theorems in cominatorial optimization
strong duality
the
If the optimum
Z star is finite
so is W star
and Z star is equal to W star.
So weak duality says that for any
feasible solution
the
value for the
primal is lesser through the value for
the dual. Strong duality says that
if the you know if the optimal values
are finite then they are equal.
Okay. So how do we prove weak duality?
So we have Z equals
proof
of
weak
duality.
We have Z
equals
cranspose X.
Recall
a transpose y was greater than equal to
c. So that's one of our
constra that's our constraints of the
duel. So what we're going to do is we're
going to plug this into here and we get
um
cranspose X is less than or equal to
A transpose Y
transpose X which is equal to Y
transpose A
And now
well
do we have something about
ax there? Up there we have ax less or
equal to b. So let's plug that into
here. And that's less than equal to
yrpose b. And what was yrpose b?
um y transpose b.
Well,
that's just actually the transpose of b
transpose y transpose
and branspose y
was w.
So this
uh
this is w because w is a scalar. So
transposing it doesn't make any
difference. So that says that Z
is less than equal to this thing which
is less included this thing which is
equal to W. So Z is less than W.
Okay, there's two more things I want to
do today.
Although [clears throat]
I'm not entirely sure we'll get by more
than one of them.
The duel
of the duel is the primal
and really I think probably all of you
were expecting this to be true.
So [clears throat]
um
the primal
is the maximum
Z= Crpose X
such that or subject to sorry A X is
less than or equal to B and X greater
than equal to zero.
Now the dual
is minimum
of W = B transpose Y
subject to
A transpose Y greater than equal to C Y
greater than equal to zero.
So before we can go on, we want to put
the duel in the canonical form because I
haven't told you how to take dus of
anything that's not in the canonical
form. So one way you can take duels of
an arbitrary pro linear program is first
put into canonical form and then take
the duel. Another way is to
go back and look at the proof and figure
out the formula for taking the duel of
an arbitrary linear program. And we'll
do that next time.
So, but let's put this in
canonical form. So, how do we turn a
uh minimization into a maximization? We
saw this already. We just take the
negative. So, we need to
So, what we need to do is we need to
maximize
minus brpose y
subject to
yeah
well
this inequality is the wrong way around
for um
a canonical form. So let's
take the negative of it. Subject to
minus a transpose
y is less than equal to minus c
and y greater than or equal to zero.
So this is the canonical form. So all we
do is we um
we want to take the transpose of a
and
put this up here. So
the duel is
minus
crpose
x
um
subject
to
okay we need to take the transpose of
this that gives us a minus a
x is greater than or equal to
um minus b.
But now if we just take the negative of
this and the negative of this we get
back to the original thing maximize z=
cranspose x such that ax is less than
equal to b rather than minus ax is
greater than minus b and x greater than
equal to zero.
So the transpose of the transpose is the
dual which
no makes
which justifies the name or the sorry
the duel of the duel is the primal which
justifies the name duel.
Okay,
I have four minutes left and I don't
know if I can say anything reasonable in
four minutes. Are there any questions
about this?
Okay. So, one thing
you do when you're first see a linear
program, if you're doing research, is
take the duel and stare at it and see if
it makes any sense intuitively. There
are lots of linear programs where if you
take the duel and you stare at it, it
makes sense intuitively and you
understand why the duel is an upper
bound on the optimum of the primal.
There are also lots of other linear
programs when you get it, you take the
duel, you stare at it, and you scratch
your head and you say, why is this a
bound on the primal? And I mean, you
know it is because it's the duel, but
it's not intuitively obvious.
So, um,
and you know, some of those if you stare
at it for longer, you understand what's
going on. And some of them you can stare
at it for as long as you want and you
probably still won't understand. So, um,
we're going to see illustrations of I
think after the
after the quiz
or maybe before the quiz.
Yeah, we will see illustrations of
this kind
no of
primal program making intuitive sense
and then the dual
makes also intuitively sense and
is clearly an upper bound on the primal.
So you're going to see that in um I
guess zero sum games and in um probably
max flow.
Okay. So I will see everybody on
Thursday and we will talk more about
linear programs and duels
and I will put out a homework tonight
which I think will be due next Tuesday.