and it is a great pleasure to end this
year seminar series having do Dr sorry
I'm standing in front of you Dr Arch
Raja here with us today from Lawrence
Berkeley National
Laboratory uh Dr Raja completed her PhD
in chemical physics from Columbia
University after spending a year as a
postto and applied physics department at
Stanford University she joined the Cav
energy and nanoscience Institute at UC
Berkeley as a heising Simon's fellow in
July 2019 she became a staff scientist
at the Imaging and manipulation of Nano
structures facility at the molecular
Foundry and in 2024 she became an
Affiliated faculty member of the Cav
energy and nanoscience Institute uh Dr
Raja has received many awards in
recognition of her research
contributions amongst which are the lbnl
director's award for exceptional
achievement in early scientific career
early career lab directed research
development award and she was also
recognized as part of the 2019 rising
stars in physics cohort so it's a great
pleasure to have you here with us uh
arch before I hand it over just a
reminder of course for you in the room
you can just ask your questions directly
we also have audience who listening
online you can uh typee your uh
questions through the Q&A option that's
available to you and I'm going to help
moderate so with that please help me
welcome Arch and thanks for joining
[Applause]
us thank you for for the kind
introduction and thank you for having me
over and uh all of you online and here
spending your afternoon with me to learn
about what we've been up to these past
few years so uh I'm Arch Raja from uh
Lawrence Berkeley National Lab I work in
that building that's the molecular
Foundry and uh we uh have all kinds of
research going on and I specifically
work in the Imaging and manipulation of
Nano structures facility and uh I'll be
talking to you about how we've been
controlling atomically thin layers uh to
do uh cool uh science uh a little bit
about The Foundry and uh this morning um
Professor bullich kindly gave me a
little bit of a history and also a tour
of MIT Nano and it's very much sort of
in the spirit um of MIT Nano so it's a
nanoscience um Research Center there are
five such centers uh run by the
department of energy in different
National Labs we are the ones in uh
Berkeley and kind of the goal of these
centers is to democratize science if you
have a good idea you can come work with
us
um and we have um all kinds of equipment
and Theory uh resources for this and uh
something that I'd like to emphasize is
that we're a knowledge-based user
facility so you're not just coming to us
to you know push buttons on equipment
but really work with us to uh develop a
project and these user proposals can be
up to a year long you can just think of
it like a professional collaboration
where you know before you send a sample
to the other group you'll write a little
couple of paragraphs and say you know
this is what we want out of that
collaboration um so our uh so the we
have like weekly Optics lab group
meetings so this is an example of one
you know there's my group but um most of
the people in that uh room are are users
who are really engaged they even if they
go back to their home institutions they
join us for these meetings and um you
know Innovation really uh uh happens
when everyone gets together and I think
this is really the spirit here at MIT
Nano as well and um I'm happy to say
that you know these sort of weekly
meetings that started in Co have
persisted and we kind of cross-pollinate
uh ideas across disciplines here so um
sort of um uh talking about uh nanoscale
science uh let's go back to you know why
we're working in this scale at all um
the beauty of making different kinds of
molecules you can really control the
functionality you know atom by atom but
uh as you all know very well uh with one
of the noble laurates uh close by that
you can extend this idea before you hit
sort of the macroscopic physics or
chemistry limits there's the scale of
science where you can maybe tune the
physical dimensions of the material not
change the material but get completely
uh different properties much like the
way you think of you know particle in a
box you're mimicking it now at the Nano
scale by making Quantum dots of
different sizes uh but something as we
make these nanoscale objects smaller and
smaller for example today's Talk's all
going to be atomically thin
semiconductors which are essentially a
molecule thick the interactions with the
local environment become increasingly um
sort of important and maybe um we can
utilize those interactions to get
interesting properties so this is just
an example of a solvatochromic effect
for the Chemists in the audience you
know it's the same molecule put in
different solvents you're getting
different colors so kind of a contrast
to that you know often uh uh portrayed
colors of the quantum dot so how do you
think of it in the solid state version
is that if you have a layer you know a
periodic crystal that's just an atomic
sheet uh uh thick or a molecule thick
you have all your lines of force going
out of your material and the non-local
effect so the properties of what your
electrons exodons or other carriers and
other quasi particles are doing in these
materials is now going to be very
sensitive to not just the atoms in your
material but the ones around it and uh
in the past um we've shown that you can
in fact change the band gap of the same
material by changing its local
environment um this is an example where
we have a monol layer of a 2d
semiconductor and we put another
material on top and using Optics we read
out the band band Gap and um and this is
a demonstration of like um an inplane
hetr structure but it's the same
material throughout just the environment
has changed a consequence of this sort
of the is also that you're very
sensitive to disorder of the local
environment and um we also come up to
understand that there's a new type of
disorder called dialectric
disorder that can happen just by you
know all different kinds of schuts
around when you make your atomically
thin layer um and uh what we've uh shown
in the past is that you know different
kind of particles have different
sensitivities to it so your free
carriers would be more sensitive and
then your bound carriers would be less
sensitive but still some
sensitive and um one of the things that
we were able to show is that if you were
to make this environment somewhat
uniform you can improve a lot of
macroscopic properties um for example
this is an example where we showed that
when you have an as prepared atomically
thin layer and I'll talk about how we're
preparing those in a second um your uh
diffusivity or how fast your um
excitations move in your sample can be
like up to 30 times slower when you put
them in a very uniform uh environment
now how do you create this sort of
interesting environments um a very
common way to do it at the 2D limit and
there are lots of experts in the local
neighborhood here who can stack these 2D
um uh layers on top of each other to
create different local environments and
the cool thing is that you don't have to
worry about uh outof plane bonding or
epitaxy so long as you're dealing with
these um vanderwal Slayers which are
essentially just Bound in the plane and
no dangling bonds out of plane you also
have an additional degree of Freedom
which is the in plane rotation uh which
is demonstrated over there and we'll
talk quite a bit about it um in this
talk uh I also want to acknowledge uh
similarly there are lots of groups um
again also uh many groups at MIT who are
excelling at growing these structures
chemically as well and creating all
kinds of cool hetr structures um but for
the most part of this St
or almost all of the stock all the
structures we're going to be dealing
with are the ones that are prepared sort
of artisanally by peeling a larger
Crystal into very thin layers and then
assembling them using polymer stamps on
top of each other to you know get our
desired uh stack of
Interest now in the whole about 10 years
ago uh gim and Gregor wrote this um
perspective on how basically this is
like nanoscale Lego and over the past
decade what we also come to appreciate
is that there's a lot of stuff going on
between the Lego Lego blocks it's almost
like Plumbing between the Lego if you
want to imagine it and this
understanding what the orbitals are
doing across these layers is going to be
a big part of especially I would say the
first half of this uh talk and it's also
a really good segue into what got me
personally interested and a lot of
people like me interested in this field
because what happens when you peel these
2D semiconductors layer by layer is that
these interlayer orbital hybridization
changes and then all of a sudden you
have cool properties at the monol layer
limit so we have uh this is just to say
that we have a little perspective out
where we discuss uh kind of this
importance of hybridization effects
across the layers and there's a lot of
um opto Electronics uh or applications
that really depend on this phenomena as
well
so this is really going back to the
start so I started my PhD around the
time when these two papers came out that
worked with really old material so mos2
is the material that I'm going to talk
about here um and in the rest of the
talk it'll be WS2 but variety of
transition metal diogenites kind of
follow the same principle so it's a it's
a generally applicable picture here so
mos2 WS2 there have been like reviews on
you know the opto electronic properties
of these materials back in the ' 70s so
why did it become so interesting um say
around
2010 it's because uh people started
applying the technique of um mechanical
exfoliation where they take a piece of
Scotch tape or polymer and peel these
layers by layer and then they saw
something very interesting happen at the
monolayer limit so just to orient
ourselves the green uh Dots here are the
transition metals and the orange are the
Cal calogen so it's m Mo and S on either
side and it's stacked on top of each
other we're looking at it from the
side now the band structure
corresponding to that is like so here so
the highest occupied bands or the veence
band and the conduction band up here or
the lowest unoccupied uh orbitals uh
there's an offset in k space that means
you need a vibration to actually couple
this um transition uh and it's an
indirect Gap semiconductor the same
picture I've kind of trying to cartoon
it out here in uh in orbital picture so
as you go to the center of the brillan
zone you have more like outter plane
orbitals like P orbitals DZ s and as you
go to the edges you have more of the
transition metal D XY Etc uh that are
contributing to the uh edges of the bill
one zone so as you go layer by layer PE
layer by layer you have Quantum
confinement effects kicking in in the
out of plane Direction and so you're
going to start increasing the Gap
associated with all of these outer plane
orbitals like at the gamma point or in
between here
and at some point and with and that
point is the monol limit this indirect
Gap becomes larger than the direct gap
which is at the K point and so you
transition to a direct Gap
semiconductor now why is that
interesting because direct Gap
semiconductors are bright you don't need
this extra vibration or phone on to you
know enable the transition up or down
and this is a picture it's an optical
image you're looking at these this just
you know it's just a 20x image on a
microscope it's by I and that already
should tell you about the extraordinary
light matter coupling because you're
seeing something that's a just a
molecule thick here sitting on a
substrate with holes and then there's
fewu layers now if you were to excited
electrically or optically this is the
light emission that you see so the light
emission from the monol layers orders a
magnitude brighter than uh the few
layers and you already see the effects
of the local environment here so this uh
the parts sitting on the hole are
emitting brighter so this work done in
both Tony Hines and Fang Wong's group
that kind of got the the feel interested
in these Monier uh limit
semiconductors and uh an important thing
that you know uh that we'll use uh
throughout the talk the word is exons
and what are exons they're electron
whole pairs that abound to each other
and you can create them when you shine
uh the semiconductor with light or
excite them electrically so when you
knock an electron out of the conduct
veence band into the conduction band you
leave a hole behind and it kind of
they're attracted to each other like a
hydrogen atom now uh the physics of two
2D exiton so just like the way you solve
for a hydrogen atom was um kind of
solved analytically by Natalia rova
followed by leonet kelish um uh back in
the day and then you know afterwards
closer to you know our time people have
done like microscopic models explaining
the exons in actual materials here like
perovskites py materials and so on uh
why why are we interested in these exons
so what uh we found is that these just
like the hydrogen atom you have excited
ridberg States like 1s 2s 3s and so on
you can measure those in the exons and
what those measurements uh implied was
these exons are bound by almost half an
EV uh so half an electron volt so room
temperature is about 25 Mill electron
volt so these are very robust even you
know well beyond room temperature and
for your reference bulk semiconductors
are about you know tens of meev so now
we're going to play with these exons in
the next um for the rest of the talk um
the first part is going to be uh about
how we break this exiton up across a 2d
Junction so you have a donor and
acceptor semiconductor and we break this
exiton up and in the second part we're
going to talk about how we localize some
of these exons using this intralayer
twist and in the third part we really go
into the you know Micron or macro scale
uh where we talk about moving these
exitrons around in the plane of the a
semiconductor so if you have a junction
of uh two semiconductors on top of each
other so the top layer is um say wsc2
sitting on WS2 um again same sort of
band structure as the mos2 initially uh
uh described with some uh modifications
but for the most part they direct Gap
and one of them is U slightly um
staggered from the other actually quite
a bit staggered it's a few hundred me
and if you were to excite the lower Gap
semiconductor so that's the donor the
electron from that would rather move
into the acceptor uh layer now uh again
over the past decade a lot has been done
with just characterizing charge transfer
in these systems and it's sort of well
accepted that the charge transfer
happens incredibly fast within the
resolution of most stable top you know
optic systems um and there's a number of
references that I'm citing here and the
data and I'm showing you is from a
transient absorption measurement where
you're just tracking the bleach of the
exonic feature now the question that
hasn't been resolved um uh is where is
all that excess energy going you have
300 meev you're dumping somewhere in
that system and the other part is
obviously the vibrations are playing
some role in this what exactly are they
doing uh and finally why is it also so
robust um
so along with you know this
understanding that charge transfer
happens super fast there's a parallel
body of literature in thermal transport
that says these are just terrible
thermal conductors you cannot transfer
heat across these Junctions they're as
bad as air cuz you imagine right you're
peeling layer by layer and then you're
assembling there's all kinds of stuff in
between and it's so what thermal
transport you measure whether it's like
um x-ray defraction techniques with time
resolution or Ramen thermometry you
measure something that is very close to
the thermal conductance of air so you
have these two things you you have Ultra
fast charge transfer and you have poor
thermal transfer and uh in fact there
have been papers that have you know
exploited this poor thermal transport to
make highly anisotropic like thermal uh
conductance and so on this is an example
of an application from um another group
uh so what we decided to do was this we
I'm I started my research group and boom
co happened so I became a user of a lot
of the facilities around me and it
turned out um that was the first year
they were willing to open up the
ultrafast Electron defraction Beam line
for an experiment and they were also
willing to let me put a sample that they
would typically have not been cuz it's
it was um it has not been tested out in
such a measurement it's a tiny sample
with a large beam and so on but we were
very fortunate they were willing to take
a chance on us and we uh essentially
said we're going to put this hetr
structure in your in your um time
resolved setup where they come in with a
fcond laser to excite your sample but
instead of your typical Optical probe
and say transient absorption you come in
with an bunch of electrons that's being
generated elsewhere and these are Mega
electron volt electrons so they're very
highly energetic so uh they they you can
see many orders of defraction um in this
system and what we observe is this
beautiful diagram here so you're seeing
like the defraction peaks of all the
different he hexagonal layers so there's
WS2 WS2 and HB an encapsulating and
you're going order by order so the order
is in the in the parenthesis there now
what is our observable here why are we
even doing this experiment is because
this intensity is going to tell you uh
what temperature your system is at so
you're literally going to be able to
track temperature of every monolayer
here so if you imagine what is heat your
atoms are jiggling around so in this
defraction peak uh as the atoms jiggle
around the brag Peak itself the
intensity goes down as things heat up
and the extra um intensity is actually
dumped in the uh diffuse scattering and
uh if the mean Square displacement is uh
connected to the intensity like so and
we can literally uh measure this in this
experiment so let's do the Baseline
experiment to just confirm that the
thermal transport sucks which is we put
aluminium on top and we uh we just
excite just the aluminium and watch the
heat flow through so this is our um
observation so you're measuring Del
Delta I over I as a function of hundreds
of
PS um and these are different orders of
defraction that I'm plotting and with
some Theory you can convert it to
temperature and uh what we're seeing is
a quantitative measure of temperature at
the uh anstrom scale with PC
resolution and so if you convert that
picture into temperature so what you see
is that your wse2 starts heating up uh
but the WS2 never really thermalizes
even out to nanocs
and if you were to fit this with a Fier
heat diffusion model you can extract an
interfacial conductance which is as low
as what others have measured using other
techniques so no surprises here now
let's track the energy transport after
photo exitation so we come in with the
laser we excite only the wsc2 cuz that's
lower
Gap and now we watch what happens notice
the x-axis is now just few picoc seconds
no longer hundreds of picoc seconds kind
of within a couple of PCS the wsc2 and
the WS2
thermalize and uh you if you were this
highly non-e equilibrium situation but
you can parameterize this just to get a
handle on if it were if you could use
the word capit conductance here or
interfacial conductance here it would be
ridiculously high it would be like three
orders of magnitude higher as much as
you know say some metallic interfaces
and then watch how it cools it also
concurrently cools over the nanoscale um
um time you know resolution that we have
so it's very clear from the previous
slide that you know the previous
mechanism cannot explain this data so it
cannot be just
phons uh just to put it in perspective
if you only had phons it's as bad as I
know Diamond uh interfaces and then if
you were to um parameterize the
conductance out with the free I mean
sort of the photo exited carriers you
have super high interfacial
conduction so the picture boils down to
the fact that you actually do have have
this interlayer uh hybridization which
now enables you to have a sort of a
phonon um electron um coupled mechanism
where from your K point which is the
point where I'm exciting it it will go
into this elevator state or a portal
that will take you to the next level
with very sort of very easily because it
doesn't matter at what angle you are or
what um uh this uh you know p orbital DZ
Square orbital hybridization that I
talked to you about at the beginning of
the talk that's fairly robust and even
if you're assembling it by hand that
hybridization is what is going to help
you with now moving the electrons from
one layer to the
other and um our Theory collaborators
calculated this in sort of a firy golden
um rule kind of uh picture where they
start with one state to the other and
they can uh make these plots where they
tell you if you were to start at the K
point Point here which is the star here
uh after 30 Picos seconds where do you
end up and this is just um you know
spots of uh the brighter the spot the
higher probability it'll end up there
and this is basically the region around
the Lambda Valley and they can do the
same um you know for the other layer as
well and just this 30 ftoc time scale it
kind of checks out with measurements
that have been done with like line um
just from Linewood broadening or time
resoled
arpis uh and so let's look at this uh
picture now in theory you can do a lot
of cool things you can also split it up
into acoustic phonons Optical phonons uh
layer by layer so and they've done it
now in the other layer where you start
from the Lambda Valley and where do you
end up you actually do end up mostly at
the K valy it would appear so in the end
you know the to explain the sort of
bidirectional um um phonon uh transport
or heating after photo exitation you
need to invoke this state that's
hybridized across these layers which is
insensitive to twist or to um the fact
that you just assembled it um and uh our
observation is consistent with also the
uh charge transfer time scales of 100 uh
fto
seconds now just to summarize um we've
been able to now investigate what's
happening during this Ultra fast uh
charge transfer process to that 300 M of
energy that you're kind of Distributing
in your sample while you do this Ultra
fast charge transfer and the mechanism
identifies uh the role of uh this
interval hybridized or inter layer sorry
hybridized states that enables this uh
transfer and it's a very distinct
mechanism because if you were to look at
just dialectric dialectric metal metal
metal dialectric or metal semiconductor
You' invoke some version of the phonon
going through or the electron tunneling
through you know electron dissipating
phonons and they uh they go through
instead whereas here it's truly a
coupled electron phonon mechanism that's
enabling this um charge transfer there
are lots of things that have not you
know been solved in in this um
experiment um we could in principle if
you had better samples identify the
diffuse scattering and actually watch
those parts of the brillan Zone light up
where the phone on are uh going uh this
has been done in like bulk samples uh
but not in these atomically thin uh
layers um and then there might be ways
to tune this Lambda Valley and tune the
thermal transport so I can imagine that
being pretty useful to you know devices
uh where you can control how much your
um uh uh thermal transport is is and
also where it's happening using maybe
strain and other things there are few
different knobs here that um we could
have been tuning uh as well so uh before
I go to the next part I want to
acknowledge you know everyone who was
involved cuz this was a pretty big team
effort to get this done especially in
the pandemic um so our beamline folks um
uh our group um collaborators uh and and
and the the especially the theory
collaborators so so far everything that
I talked about was you know we have this
WS2 on top of wsc2 and we don't care
about the twist we're just looking at
how we can break apart the exaton that
you create in one of the
layers um now for a second if you were
to align them
uh you realize it has about 4% ltis
mismatch and it would take like 26 unit
cells of WS2 to match 25 and you get you
can create a super cell um which will
now repeat over and over again and at
different angles such super stells still
exist but they're much
smaller uh why are we uh now interested
in going at 0 degrees if you ask is
there at around again um 2019 2020 there
were lots of papers that said we're
seeing signature es of uh new
excitations due to this um kind of uh
alignment of the uh Mor pattern the mor
patterns basically the super lce that
you're creating by uh stacking these two
layers so a number of um papers that
look at uh photoluminescence uh em uh so
you're just looking at the emission and
you see new Peaks and say you attributed
to this um and there was also a paper uh
with time resolved arpus which suggested
maybe these are localized so they see
like a kpace
localization um but of course it would
have been very nice to see it in real
space and uh that's what we started
hunting for uh and this and the system
we chose was one uh the same one that we
had a lot of experience with uh and if
you were to look at the absorption so
the reflectance contrast um at this
ultra thin limit for all practical
purposes you can think of it like UVA
absorption so what you're seeing here
are peaks of the WSC 2 peaks of the WS2
the two different semiconductor layers
and this is what it looks like at a
large twist Angle now if you align these
layers what uh Fang Wang's group on
campus in in UC Berkeley found is that
you're um if you look at the lowest uh
Exon Peak it actually splits into Three
Peaks um and we picked this system
because if we really want to do a hypers
spectral map within one Mor unit cell um
there techniques that are immediately
available like electron energy loss
spectroscopy and uh absorption which is
basically like measuring a dialectric
function and that's what eels has been
used to do you know for many years so if
you look at uh our experiment again it's
just like um light spectroscopy except
that now we're using the uh inelastic
scattering of electrons and sending that
to um uh spectrometer so we stuck our um
hetra structure in uh the Team One
microscope at the national Center of
electron microscopy so NM is part of the
molecular Foundry so it's the seventh
floor of our Foundry we like to say it's
just in the next building and uh so we
come in and you get two things one is
just as your electron scatter off your
um nuclei you get structural information
which is in over here in that uh anulus
and then the energy that's uh sort of
the inelastically scattered electrons we
collect them and send it in into a
spectrometer um so the dialectric
function um is what we are ultimately
after because that's what the absorption
Spectrum gives us right and the
scattering of an electron off your
material you can split it up into
different parts you know there stuff
related to the normalization You Know
sample related there's the angle at
which you're collecting but a big chunk
of it is related to the IM AR part of
the dialectric function which is related
to absorption directly to that
reflectance contrast that was I showed
you in the previous slide now in
principle if all goes well we can try to
do a hyperspectral map but now with a05
nanometer prob so that's what we are
after so there are a number of
experimental challenges um so in in the
temm at least back then you don't have a
cryostat to do this measurement we do
need to go to cold temperatures because
your exiton lines get sharper you can do
cleaner
experiments uh and that just makes life
easier and also damage to your sample um
as many people who do cryo know is
reduced uh a lot as well we're talking
about super thin materials here these
electrons can the high energy electrons
literally knock atoms off these if
you're not careful so we don't have
cryostats but you have a bucket of
nitrogen and um you know you can measure
within the time it evaporates so it's a
bit of a hero experiment um though I
have to state that now we are installing
an actual cryostat and I'll probably be
able to tell you in a year how it all
goes um another important sort of
technological advance that enabled this
measurement was around the time I joined
The Foundry they also got this direct
electron detector so they able to
measure every electron you know with
high Precision very little uh
noise um and finally the monochromation
so you photons it's easy to monochromate
electrons a lot harder uh and we got
about you know 1
me so it's pretty broad it's very Broad
and you'll still see that you don't
always need the perfect set of
experimental conditions to if you choose
your phenomena correctly so that's kind
of the lesson from this experiment and
I'd be very remiss if I didn't
acknowledge sandya and Peter sandya Sara
was a postar now faculty in um ASU in
Arizona State and Peter Aria's uh staff
scientist at NM uh they were really
willing to collaborate with us on our
not so clean samples and really iterate
with us what we get beam time or you
know electron time once a month and we
kind of iterate it over you know a year
in Co to get to where we are and my
group Daria and uh was a visiting
student on this scgsr program uh many of
you if you're interested in this just
let me know I can tell you more about it
she spent um a few months in my group
and my postto yonas so they would make
the samples on an aperture on just a
silicon aperture and so that the
electron micr scopists don't have any
confusion where to land so there's only
one hole that's the only place the
electrons are going to go through and um
so the and a really important part that
um many times is missed is how important
sample preparation is for such an
experiment so like for example we
designed this aperture so that it's easy
to find the sample even in an optical
microscope folks know how hard it is
sometimes to find the layers you want so
imagine now at the Nano scale um and a
very important characterization we have
to do before we stick it in is called
second harmonic generation and that it's
like doing x-ray crystallography but
just on your Micron scale in your sample
these monol layers are conveniently they
lack cental symmetry so you get these
nice polar plots uh these kind of flower
plots and that tell you about exactly
how you've aligned your two layers um
you as you're aligning them on the
polymer stamp you know you the student
or post dog makes a guess okay this
looks roughly zero we put it in but it
could be UH 60 um and sag or second
harmonic generation is a coherent
process so if it were zero or 60 you'd
get you know if it can constructively or
destructively interfere and this is
something we determine a PR and this
actually fairly hard to do in the
electron microscope if you haven't done
it um you know
earlier so this is the you know the the
hero experiment so we um have all of the
um Spectra stacked here so in Gray is
Optical Spectra taken in our Optical cry
super sharp you can monochromate your
photons really well right and overlaid
in color are all the Spectra we get in
the eels um uh Spectrum so it's broad
because your monochromation is only 130
meev but it's satisfying to see that if
you were to broaden the the very sharp
Peaks we have it roughly matches uh the
eels uh
Peak uh now a little interlude on
structure before we get back to those
eel speaks so this is where our Theory
collaborators come in and what they said
is actually okay everyone talks of these
things as Lego blocks you just stack
them on top of each other but you know
what if you were stacked AA which is if
your calans were just sitting on top of
each other over here where my um laser
pointer is if say your sulfur and your
selenium are on top of each other it's
eclipsed right and thermodynamically
that's un less favorable than if it were
staggered in these B stacking situations
where it's just energetically not
hitting up against another atom or the
static hindrance is not there so if you
were to just relax this structure it's
no longer just a simple Lego but it's
reconstructing and uh you can see that
you know just if you did the structure
you should be able to see a difference
is what they said and so we went in and
you can also simulate you know what your
um structure should look like with and
without uh the relaxation so if there
was no relaxation so let's just focus on
D here okay before we get to the other
ones say there was no relaxation
everything was super rigid what are you
seeing in the in the structural image
what you're seeing is uh the interaction
of the electron with the nuclei and if
you have a column of nuclei and and if
you're if you more nuclei in one column
in this method um in ADF you get a
brighter signal so that's what you see
so the a a regions you anticipate it to
be brighter and the B regions to be a
bit duller because the net kind of
nuclear Mass through that is lower and
you should but then the size of that
spot should roughly be the same if you
were to um look at our experimental data
out at F what you see is that's not what
you see you see that the super bright
spots are significantly smaller than the
the less bright spots and qualitatively
it matches with this kind of relaxation
picture that we have so again uh going
beyond the Lego picture here so now
let's get back to uh what our um main
goal was which was to try and do this
hyperspectral Imaging of this Mor exiton
cuz there's a suggestion that you could
localize them like you know basically
create little quantum dot like States in
them um so I'm stitching together four
unit cells so you have this bright spot
here which is the AA spot and then you
have the b s sites here that are uh and
then you go back to a so let's um look
at the Spectra uh from the eel
spectrometer um at these three different
spots so this is what you see so at the
a aite you measure a lot more oscillator
strength than what you measure at the B
sites so it doesn't matter that our
monochromation was not that great I
think this was enough to make the
suggestion that you have localized
oscillator strength at the at one of
these sites so if you almost think about
it it reminded me um a lot about say
traditional Quantum Wells where you
might have like face segregation or you
know um alloy segregation which leads to
like localized emission so if you think
about what's happening here is that you
have a super ltis of exaton in an ideal
sample so we're presenting average data
in an ideal sample you have a super lus
of exonic States if you were to fix the
hole at the a site and plot the electron
cloud what our Theory collaborators
would show is a picture like this
where the electron density just like
drops off rapidly as you go to the other
sides so they can you know create a
picture in theory of what such a super
lce looks like um and we can create our
picture with from experiment kind of
smear it the same amount and um
basically what you're what we're showing
is that um if you're you're localizing
your exitation at these AA sites where
uh you have your cogens lined up and uh
the o later strength um you know is is
localized there and in principle if you
had a perfect sample you could have like
a u super lus of these exonic states
which are cool for a variety of
applications so one thing that's in
progress is of course we wanted to see
all the three Mor exiton Peaks and also
try to understand you know more about
the heterogeneity in the system so we've
been doing different types of ramen and
also um spectroscopy in a temm out at
oakd where they have like 10 meev
resolution and we've also had samples
where some samples are non-reconstructed
some samples are
reconstructed and U we really this is
sort of unpublished you know data that's
um where we're trying to understand uh
you know really the heterogeneity in
this system and we're seeing some
differences between the reconstructed
and non-reconstructed samples and their
Optical
signatures uh so let me um acknowledge
uh everyone here uh to whom uh you know
um who made this happen before I go to
my very final part which is again same
material systems WS2 wsc2 I'm not
changing anything so hopefully uh you're
uh up for a little bit more uh uh
science uh just the last lap here so we
have this Mor um system right where you
have the um luses on top of each other
the WS2 and
wsc2 uh of course you like in the first
part I told you there's charge transfer
also happening in the system and that
happens but when you have the ltis is
aligned the electron in the hole
actually stay Bound for much longer and
now you can try to do little tricks with
this um this is no longer an archive
sorry this is um just published this uh
middle of this year um and you know it's
the same principle right you have the um
electron jumping to the other layer but
when you have them aligned they can
stick together for longer and then they
can also emit as an interlayer exiton so
this is just to show you what a typical
sample looks like um you have the two
layers sitting on top of each other
encapsulated in um boron nitride which
passivates and protects it and in this
overlapping region all your monolayer
emission is quenched but you have a
completely new Peak that appears at a
different wavelength that's related to
this inter layer um exiton and uh we
studied what happened happens to this
interlayer exiton in this Mo potential
that we showed you before um and I'll
just quickly go over some of the results
um uh the experimental setup is uh
something that you know um like
Professor Tales group is an expert in
very familiar with uh or uh uh Professor
SCH schoen's group uh you know we just
have regular Optical setup defraction
limited spot and we come in with visible
exitation we collect the pl and then we
walk watching what happens to the pl as
um we ex U um we excited and so the spot
spreads and that's a handle on the
diffusion or the transport of your
exitation and then we collect it on like
an image we monochromate to a
spectrometer we also measure uh Lifetime
and move move around uh the sample okay
so this is what the experiment is just
to reorient
you and um you know we did a temperature
depend in measurement because we thought
now you have this you know Mor potential
this egg boox like potential that you're
living in um it should be like a AR
renous process you have an activated
process for diffusion and then you
suppress diffusion uh once you're below
some temperature but uh you know uh
there are few different things that we
saw so first we measure just the
diffusion length from these images on
the camera and then we measure the
lifetime which just drops uh
continuously doesn't matter whether it's
0 60 inrease um and then if you were
to plot the
diffusivity uh what you see as you um
you know for the most part above 100
Kelvin it behaves like an activated
process um but then below 100 Kelvin
things kind of start to Plateau out to
like a non you know not so small number
so it's diffusing still really well even
down to cryogenic
temperatures um and we couldn't explain
why this was happening you know you're
still in the mor potential why shouldn't
it just like stop moving U but have a
Remnant
diffusivity um and for that we uh worked
with um johanes lishner group at
Imperial where they you know created
this Mor hopping potential for us you
know fitted fitted it closely with our
experimentally extracted values just
from the arenus part
um and uh to cut a long story short what
they say is now the more a um material
has very interesting mechanical
properties it can host new kinds of
phonons just because you're kind of tra
locked locking two materials together
which have a 4% lattice mismatch your
lattice is constantly moving even at low
temperatures because you have these
ultra low Shear modes that come about in
these materials that wouldn't have
existed if you didn't have this Mor and
if you were to do a kind of an MD
snapshot molecular Dynamics so
simulation where you take a snapshot of
the veilance band and the conduction
band over
time they literally show that moving and
so they say the mechanism for this
diffusion possibly is this so we have we
don't have it's not um we don't have the
what do you call the we haven't caught
it red red-handed so to speak but this
is a proposal of what could be happening
because these are the you know new modes
that exist down to uh low cryogenic
temperatures and typically diffusion um
needs like phonons to assist in its
motion except in this case they're
assisting in a different way not
directly scattering of the exiton but
literally the the lce is
dynamic um so just to uh summarize so we
you know looked at this WS2 wsc2
heterojunction uh two semiconductors on
top of each other really looked at from
the atom scale and then all the way out
to like the diffusion of energy or exons
in this case uh which Carri the energy
in the 2D
landscape um and let me uh acknowledge
everyone who was involved in this work
as well um and finally yeah so I think
we we did all of it in good time with
time to spare for questions so um thank
you so much for your attention and of
course if you want to talk to me about
uh working with us either as a user or
joining the group just reach out to me
come talk with me at the reception email
me but I'll leave this out here for
questions thank you so much much for
your attention thank
[Applause]
you we have some time for questions any
questions in the audience and for
whoever is listening online please feel
free to uh type her questions and Kelly
can you help me moderate if there's a
question any questions from the
audience okay I'll start with one can
you comment more I guess I have two
questions I'll start with one more on
the implications of this sheer mode
phonons that you talked about maybe just
describe it in a little bit more depth
and uh what exactly it implies and you
mentioned also you haven't
experimentally yet been able to identify
is there a path towards that right so
the um ultra low frequency modes they
anticipate it to happen you know like at
an me or
less uh and it's basically that you have
um they call it a phas on it's just
another uh it's like words they take
from the Quasi Crystal literature but
basically because you have this Mor
pattern on top you can um describe the
interlayer motion and and that leads to
a new phonon kind of mode which is
related to this interlayer here now the
ways to identify it I think from the
selection rules what I understand the
ideal kind of measurement might have
been like brillan scattering but to do
brillan scattering on small samples is
quite challenging
um an other way to maybe look for it
would have been probably maybe the ultra
fast electron defraction maybe we would
see signatures of it there so I think
it's just at this window where we see
low fre so we've done a lot of low
frequency Ramen on this but our
holographic filters and all of those
things go down to only about 10 wave
numbers and that's not anywhere close to
where these modes are so that's one of
the reasons we've not been able to
measure them the reason we invoke that
explanation is because we don't have any
other good reason why there's even
diffusion um down to you know even below
30 Kelvin yeah great thank
you jumping on that um I I I also found
the persistent diffusivity at low
temperature to be really interesting and
the low frequency Shear modes are are
are an interesting hypothesis could you
could you not also have a resonant
dipole mediated aiton transfer process
where the electron in the hole aren't
physically moving but they could be you
know if if you imagine these localized
Moray States as Quantum dots you know
you could have recombination at one site
and then that uh that field excite
another electron hole pair and that
would manifest as a parent ex transport
um so I think uh the recombination so
let me think about this so you're saying
that the interlay Exton would recombine
and then or or virtual You' create like
a virtual Photon which which would then
be created as another type of as you're
as you're saying that I'm I'm realizing
the oscillator strength would be an
issue yeah yeah so the oscillator
strength is like I think it's even been
measured um in Ton's group recently um
maybe even five orders of magnitude
lower so I think that's that's where the
yeah cuz the vertical dipole you're all
um you're not only separated vertically
you know this uh by space but also like
laterally a little bit so yeah you just
have very low oscillator strength compar
to the a exiton so in principle you
could say you can absorb you know in
plane but then the dipoles are
completely orthogonal
so the one with the high oscillator
strength is just an orthogonal yeah so I
think that's that's that absolutely
rules that out
yeah but there might be some other so I
have to say there's been a there's a lot
more activity on the theory side going
on you know um probably when folks like
your collaborators like Mage and others
are also thinking about this because the
way I've been describing things so far
by the way I mean it it's um it's kind
of like a first order thing if you think
about charge transfer from one layer to
the other the ideal way to discuss it
would be that you start with an exiton
and you end with an exiton not about
like it's breaking up and going and I
think that formalism as it develops I
think will give us more insight think of
it in the firmy Golden Rule not as an
electron hopping from one state to
another but think of you start with an
intra layer exiton as your initial State
and an inter layer exiton as your final
state so I think that will tell us more
maybe there's a way that can have more
resonant transport I I I I right now I
don't have a
way to justify that as being a plausible
mechanism
yeah any other questions from the room
sorry okay so I think um there's a
question online asking about what new
structures might be possible next with
these layers and what sort of
applications might you might you
envision yeah uh um I think um you know
the face space is like really large
because I literally talked to you about
two semiconducting
layers if you look at the Periodic Table
of 2D materials now you have like super
conductors magnets semiconducting
magnets there's a whole variety of
insulators and um you can stack any of
these guys on top of each other um I'm
um you know I'm very uh excited for what
the new structures can be U I think but
the main challenge is just um our
throughput I would say and trying to
assemble these so another space to watch
out for is just the synthetic part like
how people are able to grow um on the
application side um you know if you
think about the oscillator strength or
light matter coupling of these Atomic
lethan layers um this single sheet of
semiconductor at its fundamental
resonance can absorb like 20% and 30% of
light so you know an obvious space where
you know whether it's light emission or
light absorption any devices that use
that that would be um an obvious space
for
applications um the other thing that um
I haven't touched upon as much is that
these are also very much tunable by
things like substrate engineering or
strain you know strained silicon you
know enables a lot of our technology
right like this is something that is uh
should be explored in these as well and
people have cre a lot of quantum
emitters in these so yeah the Space is
really large for sensing or emission
yeah thank you um any last questions
from the audience if not please help me
thank archa again thank you arch for a
great
talk there will be a reception until
4:30 here so please do stay back talk to
Dr Raja she'll be here for another 303
minutes and thank you all for joining us
see you in
2025 for