the next company we are proud to
introduce is Civic
Atlas Civic Atlas is AI powered tool for
tracking building permits and Zoning
cases and and ultimately development
activity John Divine is the CEO and
founder of Civic Atlas John has over a
decade of experience specializing in
that insection of GIS real estate and
software development John holds a
Masters in City Planning degree from MIT
where he was a research assistant at the
MIT Civ
data Design Lab and the MIT Urban risk
lab welcome to John who's presenting
Civic
Atlas thanks Trisha um my name is John
um as Trisha mentioned I'm an urban
planner and the founder and CEO of Civic
Atlas we're an AI powered platform for
tracking Urban Development Across the
United
States prior to my time at MIT I spent
10 years working as an urban planner in
Dallas Texas and along the way I found
out that it's really hard to keep track
of Urban Development um you see here all
this lovely paperwork on the right um
these are zoning cases in Dallas a
really important source of information
about new development and I was having
to spend tens of hours each week reading
these manually copy and pasting the
results into spreadsheets and mapping it
in GIS um today if you actually want to
understand the building supply pipeline
of a city you have to do exactly this
manual process gather data from building
per permits planning commissions public
meeting agendas and then map it all in
GIS very few organizations can afford to
spend all this time doing this um and
the consequence is that America doesn't
really know what it's
building over the past 20 years Civic
technologists have started working on
solutions to this unfortunately almost
all the tools out there only work for
one city at a time and they still rely
on someone manually entering data um or
for local governments to keep really
clean well-maintained apis which is Out
Of Reach for a lot of smaller or rural
municipalities um the exciting thing is
that new technologies specifically large
language models mean that an automated
more standardized approach is now
possible at Civic Atlas we've been
building an allpurpose workflow where we
can go into any City regardless of how
they store data around peris res zoning
cases and integrate it to give you a
clear picture of the building supply
pipeline we start with web scrapers that
pull raw public records straight from G
websites we then use llms and
traditional ETL methods to take data
from those 100 page PDFs and put into
Json um a white weight flexible format
um that most web apps can work with we
then use large language models to enrich
location information where needed and
then we can geocode it um through apis
like Google Maps um a lot of the time
zoning cases don't even have addresses
they have weird legally as phrases
um you know at the intersection of
Lovers Lane and and mocking bir Drive um
but LMS are great at taking that and
turning into something that apis can
understand we then pull this data from
every different city in the US put it
into one clean web app and we can make
it just as clean intuitive and user
friendly um as apps like Zillow Airbnb
or Google
Maps this past November we launched our
first beta in Dallas uh we built a
real-time map of every billing permit
and planning case in the city uh you can
try this out for free at Civic gas.net
um without spending a dollar on
Advertising we got over 80 Enterprise
signups um and really exciting positive
local news coverage as you'd expect most
of our users are based in real estate um
but we also have major retailers
Architects um community members
neighborhood associations academics
there's a lot of different people that
want information about building that
just don't have access to it um with
existing tools
today um highlighting a couple of our
major success stories um one of our
users is Crow Holdings they're a major
real estate investor and developer in
Dallas and they use us to track the
multif family housing Supply um they say
that having a good understanding of
upcoming development is hugely
significant for determining the
profitability of their Investments
existing softwares don't do a good job
of this and so we help them invest much
more effectively than their competitors
Vision Plus is an Architecture Firm that
advises developers on how to build new
projects in
Dallas as they go through a complex
zoning in a titon process it's important
for them to find examples of other
developments they got City approval
right now this is really difficult you
got to spend a lot of time going through
those PDFs but we make it really fast
for them to find comparable projects
this helps them reduce project delays
get new housing built faster um and
build trust with
communities um lastly kind of a fun
exciting use um is the Dallas Free Press
they're a local newspaper um and as you
may be aware a lot of local media has
lost the funding to have reporters
follow City Hall closely um we sort of
act as a force multiplier for their
reporting team helping them track real
estate cases that otherwise they
wouldn't afford to cover um and this
gets trusted information out to the
public and kind of builds a sense of
community knowledge and Trust about
uping
development our next step is to take all
this raw data and start turning it into
statistics and highle analytics um we'll
be able to have people compare any
custom geography across the country
things like zip codes census tracks and
see exactly what's getting built and how
it varies across
jurisdictions we can also layer in
demographic psychographic and Census
Data um and start doing Predictive
Analytics on where we can expect
development to happen um right now we're
looking for a large Enterprise pilot
partner to help us figure out what these
data points are most valuable and how
how can we combine it with your own
proprietary data to give you really
powerful tailored
insights um we're open to Partners in
any industry um a couple obvious
candidates to us would be retail where
we could help out with site selection
and predictive inventory analytics
commercial real estate for that market
intelligence use case mentioned earlier
um and then governments um we can use
this data to help Drive policy analysis
um and create tools for public data
transparency um my name is John um and
have to open things up for Q&A
excellent thank you so much John real
exciting stuff that you're you're doing
there with Civic Atlas few questions for
you um so you spoke about a little bit
but could you just uh expand are you
limited to any specific geography and
and why or why not yeah so uh we are not
limited to any specific geography um our
workflow can work um regardless of
country regardless of State we're
getting started in Texas um just as an
active real estate market it's a great
time Market but we can deploy this
technology anywhere fantastic and can
you use AI to summarize specific zoning
cases how does that work yeah so
thankfully a lot of these newer models
have context Windows long enough that
they can actually analyze these entire
100 page complex PDFs um so it's on a
road map to start generating kind of
clear concise summaries um of these huge
complex legal
documents fantastic and the next
question question we have for you is can
you use this approach for other public
records so um proposed City legislation
for example yeah yeah we we are not
limited to building permits and Zoning
cases um we've got a request to start
looking at city council meeting agendas
and other public minutes um whatever
would be useful to to Partners um we can
integrate into the system fantastic well
John thank you once again for joining us
today and learning more about Civic
Atlas appreciate it thank you okay