the MIT energy initiative presents MIT
spin-off tachar processes waste biomass
to reduce Airborne emissions written by
Katherine M
O'Neal to prepare fields for planting
Farmers the world over often burn corn
stocks rice husks hay straw and other
waste Left Behind from the previous
harvest in many places the practice
creates huge seasonal clouds of smog
contributing to air pollution that kills
7 million people globally a year
according to the World Health
Organization annually $120 billion worth
of crop and Forest residues are burned
in the open worldwide a major waste of
resources in an energy starved world
says Kevin Kung sm13 phd1 17 Kung is
working to transform this waste biomass
into marketable products and capitalize
on a billion dooll Global Market through
his MIT spin-off company tachar founded
in 2015 takar developed smallscale
lowcost portable equipment to convert
waste biomass into solid fuel using a
variety of thermochemical treatments
including one known as oxygen lean
taction the technology emerged from
kung's PhD project in the lap of ammed
gonium the Ronald C crane 1972 professor
of mechanical
engineering biomass fuels including wood
Pete and animal dung are a major source
of carbon emission
but billions of people rely on such
fuels for cooking Heating and other
household needs currently burning
biomass generates 10% of the primary
energy used worldwide and the process is
used largely in rural energy poor
communities we're not going to change
that overnight there are places with no
other sources of energy godiam says what
takach Char's technology provides is a
way to use biomass more cleanly and
efficiently by concentrating the fuel
and eliminating contaminants such as
moisture and dirt thus creating a clean
burning fuel one that generates less
smoke in rural communities where biomass
is used extensively as a primary energy
source taction will address air
pollution headon gonium says
thermochemical treatment densifies
biomass at elevated temperatures
converting plant materials that are
typically loose wet and bulky into
compact charcoal centralized processing
plants exist but collection and
transportation present major barriers to
utilization Kung says
takar solution moves processing into the
field to date takar has worked with
about 5,500 Farmers to process 9,000
metric tons of crops takar estimates
this technology has the potential to
reduce carbon dioxide equivalent
emissions by gigatons per year at scale
carbon dioxide equivalent is a measure
used to gauge global warming potential
in recognition in 2021 takar won the
first ever Earth shot prize in the Clean
Air category a 1 million pound prize
funded by Prince William and Princess
Kate's Royal
Foundation roots in
Kenya as Kung tells the story takar
emerged from a class project that took
him to Kenya which explains the
company's name a combination of takataka
which means trash and Swahili and Char
for the charcoal end product it was 2011
and Kung was at MIT as a biological
engineering grad student focused on
cancer research but MIT gives students
big latitude for exploration and I took
courses outside my department he says in
Spring 2011 he signed up for a class
known as
15966 Global Health delivery lab in the
MIT Sloan School of
Management the class brought Kung to
Kenia to work with a non-governmental
organization in nairobi's kibber the
largest urban slum in Africa we
interviewed slum households for their
views on health and that's when I
noticed the charcoal problem Kung says
the problem as Kung describes it was
that charcoal was everywhere in cabara
piled up outside traded by the road and
used the primary fuel even indoors its
creation contributed to deforestation
and it smoke presented a serious health
hazard eager to address this challenge
Kung secured Fellowship support from the
MIT International Development initiative
and the Priscilla King gray Public
Service Center to conduct more research
in Kenya in 2012 he formed takar as a
team and received seed money from the
MIT ID AS Global challenge MIT legatum
Center and daab to produce charcoal from
household organic waste this work also
led to a fertilizer company sopi
Organics that Kung founded in 2016 with
the help of MIT ideas but that is
another
story meanwhile Kong had another top
priority finding a topic for his PhD
dissertation back at MIT he met
Alexander slokum the Walter M May and a
Hazel May professor of mechanical
engineer in who on a long walk and talk
along the Charles River suggested he
turn his Kenya work into a thesis slum
connected him with Robert Stoner deputy
director for Science and Technology at
the it energy initiative Mighty and
founding director of mighty's tataa
Center for technology and design Stoner
in turn introduced Kung to gonum who
became his PhD adviser while slok and
Stoner joined his doctoral
committee roots and MIT
lab gon's telling of the atar Story
begins not surprisingly in the lab back
in 2010 he had a master student
interested in renewable energy and he
suggested the student investigate
biomass that student Richard Bates 10
sm12
phd6 began exploring the science of
converting biomass to more clean burning
charcoal through taction most taction
also known as low temperature paralysis
systems use external heating sources but
the lab's goal gum explained ples was to
develop an efficient self-sustained
reactor that would generate fewer
emissions we needed to understand the
chemistry and physics of the process and
develop fundamental scaling models
before going to the lab to build the
device he says by the time Kung joined
the lab in 2013 gonan was working with
the Tata center to identify Technologies
suitable for developing countries and
largely based on renewable energy Kung
was able to secure a Tata fellowship and
building on basis research developed the
small scale practical device for biomass
thermochemical conversion in the field
that launched tachar this device which
was patented by MIT with inventor Kung
gonium Stoner MIT research scientist
Santos Shambo and slokum is
self-contained and scalable it burns a
little of the biomass to generate Heat
this heat bakes the rest of the biomass
releasing gases the system then
introduces air to enable these gases to
combust which burns off the volatiles
and generates more heat keeping the
thermochemical reaction going the trick
is how to introduce the right amount of
air at the right location to sustain the
process gonium explains if you put in
more air that will burn the biomass if
you put in less there won't be enough
heat to produce the charcoal that will
stop the reaction about 10% of the
biomass is used as fuel to support the
reaction Kung says adding that 90% is
densified into a form that's easier to
handle and utilize he notes that the the
research received financial support from
the Abdul Latif Jam water and Food
Systems lab and the despond center for
technological innovation both at MIT
sunel Thung another postto and gonium
lab participated in the effort to scale
up the technology at the MIT bats lab no
relation to Richard Bates the charcoal
produce is more valuable per ton and
easier to transport and sell than
biomass reducing Transportation costs by
2/3 and giving Farmers an additional
income opportunity
and an incentive not to burn
agricultural waste Kung says there's
more income for farmers and you get
better air
quality roots in
India when Kung became a Tata fellow he
joined a program founded to take on the
biggest challenges of the developing
world with a focus on India according to
Stoner Tata fellows including Kung
typically visit India twice a year and
spend 6 to8 weeks meeting stakeholders
in Industry the government and in
communities to G perspective on their
areas of study a unique part of Tata is
that you're considering the ecosystem as
a whole says Kung who interviewed
hundreds of small holder Farmers met
with truck drivers and visited existing
biomass processing plants during his
tataa trips to India along the way he
also connected with Indian engineer
videt Mohan who became takach Char's
co-founder it was very important for
Kevin to be there walking about
experimenting and interviewing Farmers
Stoner says he learned about the lives
of
farmers these experiences helped
instilling Kung an appreciation for
small farmers that still drives him
today as takar rolls out its first pilot
programs Tinkers with the technology
grows his team now up to 10 and
Endeavors to build a revenue stream so
while takatar has gotten a lot of
attention in accolades from the idea's
award to the Earth shot prize Kung says
what motivates him is the prospect of
improving people's lives the dream he
says is to EMP power communities to help
both the planet and themselves we're
excited about the environmental justice
perspective he says our work brings
production and carbon removal or
avoidance to rural communities providing
them with a way to convert waste make
money and reduce air pollution