So um today we're going to cover an
introduction to time series analysis and
time series analysis is really a very
sort of powerful meth methodology in
statistics
um and especially uh powerful when it
comes to modeling uh financial markets.
So I hope you'll find this introduction
engaging and motivating. Um so let's
talk about time series. Uh we basically
have notation indicating a stochcastic
process where x corresponds to the value
of the process at time t
and the time periods t can be discrete.
This is most commonly what we'll work
with. Uh but it can also correspond to a
continuous time interval. And so uh we
can imagine basically time periods u uh
time indexed by uh positive numbers from
zero. And in terms of modeling such a
time series um we want to be able to
specify the probability model for any
collection of time point values. So when
we say let's specify a probability model
for a time series then that corresponds
to being able to specify the joint
density
of any set of points. Here we have m
different time points.
This generalizes to all cases of m and
uh such a subset of the values of the
process are uh a finite dimensional uh
set of values and so we'll have finite
dimensional distributions for xt.
Now, uh, importantly, we'll want to
consider time series that are strictly
stationary.
And a strictly stationary time series is
one for which the distribution of any
set of time points
um is equal to the distribution of the
same time points shifted by a constant.
So if we're looking at
the index of time and we have xt um if
we look at say four points here
t1 t2 t3 t4 then the distribution of the
values at these time points will be the
same as the distribution if we shift
these time points all by the same
amount. toao. So t2 plus toao and so
forth. So we basically have that in this
window
and in this window
the distribution of outcomes is the
same. So what does that mean? Well, that
means that if there's a mean value
in this period, then it's the same mean
value in this other period as well as
all possible periods. So we basically
have
a probability model
that is constrained in terms of the
level being horizontal
and the amount of spread about that
level is constant.
Now with statistics we like to estimate
parameters.
Parameters like a sample mean are very
easy to estimate. We get a sample of
values and estimate the population mean
with the sample mean. And so we're may
be familiar with estimating constants
and estimating means of populations is
is a you know trivial example example of
that. With stationary time series, we
want to consider
perhaps a transform of our time series
to a stationary scale and then there
will be parameters of that distribution
that we can estimate and we can estimate
them because
the distribution is the same basically
across the whole range. So there's some
hope that we'll be able to uh specify
parameters
uh consistently and with high precision.
Now um
uh a less strict
um stationerity condition is called
covariant stationerity.
And with covariant stationerity,
we're looking just at the first and
second order sort of expectations
of the time series values. So the mean
value of xt
will be a constant mu for all t
and the variance of xt
will also not depend on the time t. it
will be stationary or constant over the
time range and the co-variance
of values that are tow units apart will
have a co-variance that simply is a
function of how far apart the time
points are. So
here um you know we're looking basically
at sort of a mean level mu and maybe
plus or minus the square root of the
variance of xt
uh being
the lower and upper
levels here. And then if we're
interested in looking at how correlated
different time values are then if we
consider
say t and t plus toao I guess
and we also consider another t prime and
t prime plus toao
over here. Then when we have
realizations of the process, they're
going to be staying within
a few standard deviations of the mean
and the correlation between values at
different time points will be the same
if the distance the the time period
between those time points are the same.
So
so those that's covariant stationerity.
Now with such uh time series that are
co-variance stationary then we can look
at the autocorrelation function
and the correlation between xt and xt
plus toao is the covariance between the
two
divided by the square root of the
product of the variances. So these are
familiar formulas generally for
correlations and we call them
autocorrelations because we're looking
at the correlation of a time series with
itself
and so we have row of t is the
autocorrelation.
Now let's take a look at some uh
financial time series. Uh let's begin
with just looking at the S&P 500 index.
So this is the
uh value of the 500 major stocks in the
US equity market. And this is from I
think 2011 to 2020 plus. And you can see
how this over that period of time
trended up with some dramatic uh drops
due to co
and with such a time series
um it's clearly not stationary
because it's trending over time. If we
looked at different bands of years, they
have different means. And so we really
cannot uh consider this scaling of the
index to be uh stationary or coariant
stationary.
And what ends up happening with many
many financial time series is that we
consider
the time series YT say to correspond to
a random walk model on the log scale.
So if we were to look at
taking the log of the series
and
look at the increments of that
this is the log return
of yt.
Then
the value of yt
is going to be an initial value y knot
times the exponential of the sum of
these log returns.
And we can relate these log returns
to the uh percent returns on a
fractional scale.
This is log of 1 + rt
where rt is equal to yt minus ytus one
over uh yt minus one.
Um
so what will commonly be the case is
that this sequence of log returns is
coariant stationary.
And so what I'd like to do next is to
look at some time series plots of
different financial time series and see
whether this transformation
uh to log returns seems to make the
series appear stationary.
So here's the S&P 500 index. Um these
graphs here actually update the graph
from before to uh the end of uh
September.
And
if we change initially the
absolute price to the log of the price,
um you'll notice that sort of an
exponential growth tends to transform to
a linear growth on the log scale.
And
that comment is uh representing the fact
that the lower panel follows more of a
straight line path than the upper panel
which has perhaps some exponential
curvature to it. Now if we look at the
uh monthly log returns,
we can see that
those monthly
increments on the log scale
have basically a flat time series
process. And so it's rather consistent
with this, you know, movement across
a level that in this case is close to
zero um with constant variance. Now with
this data, we might consider looking at
the distribution of these log returns
and see whether they're consistent with
a normal model just as a benchmark
example that we might use. And here's
the uh uh fitted normal curve to the
data. And
you know, would you say that this is a
good fit to the data?
Do I see any nods or shakes? I think you
had a shake.
>> Um it looks like relative weight like it
falls like
>> right. Yeah. And so um the true height
is basically uh the realized values that
are close to the mean and the normal fit
is sort of underestimating those values
that are close and complementing that
the tails of the distribution maybe are
underestimating the magnitude of the
tails as well. And so this property is a
property that is called lepto kurtosis
and which means sort of slender. Uh
lepto is Greek for slender. Um and then
so let's take a look at what happens if
we look at weekly returns.
Okay, with weekly returns
we get an again a series that appears to
be fairly flat.
The volatility though looks like it
maybe isn't stable. So the variation of
the uh time series at different time
points may not be constant. It certainly
was extreme during the COVID crisis
um as evident here. And here's again the
normal curve which has the s the same
properties noted before. And then here's
the daily log returns.
So looking at a higher frequency
measurements, we again get this property
of sort of a stability in the mean, but
maybe not a stability or stationerity in
the variance.
And again, the normal model doesn't look
like it's uh appropriate. and it
captures a a center and a spread, but
uh seems to be far off near the mean and
far away. Okay, let's take a look at
Amazon stock. So, we're just going to
look at the same plots here. Uh you'll
notice that the absolute price has a
rather um notable exponential growth in
it. Um when we take the log scale we
have this plot and what's really
important to see is whether the sort of
variability in the time series is
constant
or not. And when before taking the logs
we have a really narrow variation of the
price series com at the beginning
compared with the end. But on the log
scale, the variation is is more
comparable. So that's actually a good
thing to have. We still have a trend in
the series. And taking the
differences in the log values
makes this series
stationary or at least appear
stationary. And here's the uh log
returns on a monthly frequency.
And uh here's the uh histogram of those
log returns and the normal fit. It's
perhaps doing a slightly better job uh
than for the S&P 500. It's not clear. Um
here is the weekly frequency time
series. Again, um the top panel does
look like it's consistent with a
stationary series in terms of the
properties we've highlighted so far and
the Gaussian distribution seems to be
fitting a bit better.
Um if we look at the daily log returns
then uh we have um this sort of
leptoccurtosis
appearing in this uh histogram of daily
returns. And in looking at the time
series of the daily returns
um it looks like there are some
significant spikes
that are not really sort of consistent
with the rest of the series. So maybe uh
you know that feature is something that
we would want to incorporate into our
models.
Well, here's
getting away from the uh equity markets.
This is looking at the crude oil futures
contract.
And with the crude oil futures contract
um
this
future um it trades I think at the
Chicago Merkantile Exchange. Um it
actually has a
dramatic feature that the value of the
contract went negative in 2020
which was a shock to financial markets
especially uh brokers and traders in
those contracts. You can imagine if you
had a hundred contracts of crude oil
on the day you woke up and the price was
negative, you basically owed your broker
a hundred times that negative value. And
uh brokers actually sometimes were
unable to tell you what your position
was because their systems didn't allow
for negative prices. um if we try to
take the log of the series and look at
the differences with these negative
values that's actually a huge problem
but nonetheless uh let's see I did graph
these um which essentially will sort of
exclude those days when there were
negative values for the contract and
looking at this here's the monthly log
returns. So this is excluding the
negative uh price periods
um on a monthly basis, on a weekly
basis,
and on a daily basis. And so what's
really important here is just how
looking at different financial time
series with the same framework
of log logging the series if it's
positive and looking at increments on
the log scale which correspond to
percentage changes. um the data
generally is transformed or often is
transformed to a stationary scale. Um
yet another example is looking at the
yields
of the uh 10-year uh US Treasury.
Um, and so the top panel shows
it's called price, but it's really the
yield uh in percentage terms of 10-year
government bonds. And so you can see it
started above 3% dropped down to less
than 1% following the COVID crisis and
then was rising ever since.
And if we look at the uh
price or the yield changes on the log
scale, we get this plot which isn't too
different um and in its appearance. But
then if we look at the uh changes in log
on uh u changes in log uh the increments
in log which are log returns in sort of
mathematical definition. Log returns are
not really the right terminology for the
percentage changes in yield but we'll
basically be using the same terminology
as before. One can see that we basically
get a distribution of increments
steps in the random walk on the log
scale that
are unimodal and symmetric.
And as we consider
higher frequency, here's weekly and
here's daily, it's actually doing a
better job perhaps using a normal model
for this uh transformed series than for
the uh equity market series. So, so with
these cases, uh the same
manipulations of the data, taking logs,
looking at log returns corresponds to
transforming the series to
a random walk process.
And with random walk processes
um we can think of the sum from zero to
t of or it's capital t say of x subt
and call this maybe s subt.
Um
in modeling
the random walk by this sum um there
will be many different models we can
consider for this. The simplest model
would be one where these x's the steps
are
identically distributed and independent.
So it's like a pure random walk.
um and uh more complicated models uh
will
consider ST um or the XTS to be
dependent upon each other. So what we'd
like to do then is let's see as we um
let's see here
if we think of this autocorrelation
function the correlation
between
x's
that are toao units of time apart
um we can actually calculate
autocorrelations
for
each of the series we just looked at.
And so here is the autocorrelation
function of the monthly log returns on
the S&P 500.
And one can see that there actually was
a large negative autocorrelation for one
month apart.
and the other autocorrelations varied
around this blue range.
And what's important with
autocorrelations
um if we have a time series
uh xt
t equaling 1 2 up to capital t and then
we consider the uh sample
autocorrelation
at lag K.
Then this is an estimate of the
correlation between XT and XT + K.
And we call this RK.
And I'll maybe put a hat on it to
indicate that this is estimated from the
sample.
It turns out that this is
approximately
distributed
as a normal
with
a mean or I guess okay a normal with the
row k the true autocorrelation
and a variance that's one over t minus
k.
So if we
look at
these bands, these bands correspond to
sort of the region of sample
autocorrelations
that are consistent with a zero
true autocorrelation.
So if we want to if we want to test a
null hypothesis that row k is equal to
zero,
we can say reject
if
r hat k
is greater than 1.96
times the square of 1 / t minus k.
applying a normal model for that return
distribution. So we basically have um
for the r hat k where we have a row k
here we have a bell-shaped curve with a
standard deviation
square root of 1 over t minus k and if
we consider row k equal to zero then we
do the rejection if it's outside these
bands. Now um
the uh let's take a look at how these
autocorrelations vary as we vary the
frequency. Here's the uh weekly
frequency
for the computation of log returns. And
we have this pattern where perhaps there
are some
significant negative autocorrelations
at say uh five weeks apart.
Um, and
what would you say is a property of
a time series that has negative
autocorrelations
say of order at lag five. What does that
really
mean in terms of what you would expect?
Yes. Sort
>> of mean reversion.
>> Mean rever. Yes. Exactly. So the
negative autocorrelations
are consistent perhaps with mean
reversion. So that means that
if you know the price changes are too
high they'll revert back or if they're
too low they'll revert back. And um
let's see also on these graphs are
partial autocorrelations which we'll
discuss later.
Um but uh partial
autocorrelations are correlations at a
given lag after accommodating
the dependence on lower order lags.
We'll see that what how that works out
uh in the case study later. But let's
take a look at just these other series.
Um, so here's the daily series uh with
the S&P 500. And so you can see, oh,
there's actually some reasonable strong
autocorrelations.
Here's Amazon stock.
I'm not sure why it doesn't have the
band on the lower side. Uh
but it um it basically is symmetrical
with that blue band where the
correlation is consistent with zero
autocorrelation.
Um here's the weekly, here's the daily.
So, so interestingly, Amazon stock
doesn't seem to have any significant
autocorrelations regardless of the
frequency. Here's the um crude oil
future.
You can see that with the crude oil
future in on a weekly basis, we have a
negative autocorrelation at uh two weeks
and then a positive autocorrelation at
three weeks. So there's some interesting
uh patterns that perhaps can be
exploited.
And here's daily. Uh again, one can see
the rather significant autocorrelations
at the low lag values.
And let's see with the treasury
yields looking at the autocorrelations
and how the log yield changes one can
see that there is some strong time
dependence at the weekly basis as well
as that the daily basis.
Now
let's see the this discussion of
autocorrelations
is
a very important one in uh time series
modeling
and I just want to
um highlight how if we have a time
series
and we have a we fit a time series
model.
And so we compute say y t t = 1 to t.
Then um the residual
series
from
this fit of the time series model is the
set of errors
which are yt minus y t
and
you know we can just write yt is equal
to y t plus epsilon or error t.
Um a good model.
So the model
is good
if
the ETSs
basically
have
mean zero
constant variance
are uncorrelated.
with each other. And so the these
assumptions um are basically assumptions
of a white noise process.
So if our model
basically
predicts up to this
residual process which is unpredictable
has mean zero constant variance is
uncorrelated. There's no information
left in the residual series and so we
can use the autocorrelation
of the
residual series.
We can use the autocorrelation function
of the error series to test
if
the uh
model is good basically.
And a good model
will be a model that has captured all of
the time dependent information in it.
And
the uh
predictions from these or forecasts from
this model are ones we have confidence
in. And so there's actually another
assumption here which is that um
let's see it's um if the epsilon t are
normal or gaussian
then this gives uh good predictions
and by predictions I'm thinking of not
point forecasts of a series but a
prediction interval and how wide should
that prediction interval be depending
upon the variability.
Um so so if when we work with time
series we're actually are
going to work often with
autocorrelations
of residuals to see um whether there's
any time dependence in the series. And
if we um
what what's rather interesting to note
is that
one can fix a single correlation
lag and use that to test whether the
data are consistent with a zero
autocorrelation of a fixed lag. We can
also
use sets of lags and test whether the
whole set is equal to zero or not. And
so um
let's see let me just write it over
here. So um if say row one equals row 2
equals
row k
is equal to zero
then
r hat j
which is distributed as normal zero
roughly 1 / t
um for j equaling one to to uh A
r hat j 2 * t
is approximately
the square of a normal 01 which is a kai
squared 1
random variable.
And if we look at the sum of t r hat j^
2 from 1 to k this will be approximately
a ki squared distribution with k degrees
of freedom. And so we can then we can
reject
the uh null hypothesis.
If
this test statistic I'll call it well
actually I'll call it BP because it's
actually called the box pierce test if
BP
is large
say larger than
a critical value C star which where this
is determined by the ki squared
distribution.
And so this is actually called the box
pierce test.
And um so
we'll actually uh be very interested in
autocorrelations of the original series
but then autocorrelations of the
residual series. And whenever we have a
model where the residual series still
has significant autocorrelations in it,
then we're really not done yet. We
really need to continue.
Okay.
So we have
now the next topic is a really sort of
extraordinary theorem.
um the W representation theorem
and
with
stationary processes that are
co-variance stationary
then it turns out that any covariant
stationary process can be decomposed
into
a VT process which is linearly
deterministic.
So it's that means that
basically the current value is a linear
combination of past values
and ST is a moving average process
where we have these ADA T's which are
white noise
and our ST process is just a weighted
sum of those white noise terms.
And
the white noise terms are also
uncorrelated with the linearly
deterministic process.
So
let's see when I first learned of this
theorem I was um
had an issue with well what is a
linearly deterministic process? So, can
anyone suggest what a linearly
deterministic process is
or or could be or an example of one.
So we have VT
is linear
the deterministic.
So we have VT. So if we observe VT over
a sequence of time points,
will for what patterns of VT will that
determine
the VT process into the future?
Can you think of any?
So if vt
is equal to mu
plus say cosine
of theta t
then this thing will just move up and
down and we can actually determine
that cosine function from enough values
of vt. Yes. So does that mean like any
any periodic process would be linearly
determined?
>> Yes. Any Yeah. And um it's interesting
uh
to know that I th those of you who may
have studied harmonic analysis
um
could come across the u
result that if we have say different
period different cosine or s functions
and take sums of those
then that will also be a linearly
predictable process.
And so if you look at summing signs of
different frequencies which basically
corresponds to forier series that are
flat um then uh those are linearly
predictable.
Um
so so that's
the VT process that we
should be aware of. Um but what's really
interesting is that the variation about
that deterministic process the ST
process um can be
expressed as a moving average process
and this
u representation holds for any covariant
stationary time series. Now for any
coariant stationary time series
um let's see
with the covariance
stationary
process
st
um we have basically that mu is equal to
the expected value of st sort of sigma
squar which is the variance of st.
This is constant over time. This is
constant over time. And the co-variance
of xt xt plus toao
is equal to gamma of toao
uh for all t.
So
any coariant stationary process
can be represented as this moving
average
of white noise process.
And so well how would we
use this Wolves representation theorem?
Well, if we have a time series XT that
we want to specify a coariant stationary
time series model to it, well, the first
thing we would do perhaps is sort of
drend
the series XT so that it has a constant
mean level. So if we had a
linear trend or a quadratic trend, we
would subtract that out. So xt is a
series that uh looks like it has a flat
path. And then we could initialize
a parameter P indicating the past
number of observations
that explain the linearly deterministic
term.
And we can then
project our time series XT onto the
space spanned by the lags,
the P lags.
and then look at the errors about that
projection.
So here we can think of having the time
series values y1 to yn
and we can project those onto the lags
of the y values. So for the first sort
of p rows we actually need to go back in
time. So that means we have to start not
from the beginning of our time series
but maybe p units ahead and then we can
apply ordinary le squares to define the
projection
matrix onto those lagged values. And
then we have this projected residual.
And what we would want is that this
projected residual
um would if it's a stationary time
series, we could use time series
methods. We'll learn about how to
specify a moving average model to these
uh series and get estimates of the size
and also estimates of the white noise
terms.
And with this
step, we then
can evaluate whether our residuals
um are orthogonal to lagged values for
lags greater than pback.
So these residuals
should not have any dependence on
lags of y that are further back than p.
If if not if if there is if those are
not orthogonal then we should increase
p. Um, and then we want to look at
whether the ADAT's in our moving average
model, whether those are consistent with
white noise or not.
And so if they are, we're good. But if
if not then we need to consider sort of
changing the specification of the moving
average model and perhaps adding other
variables such as deterministic
variables that could be useful in the
projections. But what this demonstrates
is how this theory can
in sort of the abstract be applied to
real world data. And um
so uh you know as we increase P the
number of lags we use for the projection
um we end up getting a limiting value
as P gets large. Um that this sort of is
capturing the uh
linearly predictable uh part of the
series. the VTS. Um, but this assumption
basically requires
if we let P grow arbitrarily large, we
probably want to make sure that P over N
uh goes to zero. so that we're
estimating P parameters
with
a number of points that
is large relative to P.
Um
so this is just a way of thinking about
how uh
we might approach our modeling effort
exploiting the wool decomposition.
But um what's what's really important
here is that
any covariant stationary model
has a representation as this moving
average process of white noise.
So that's a fairly powerful result. It
says that once we have transformed our
data to a scale that where coariant
stationerity is appropriate then we can
restrict ourselves to the class of
moving average processes. And what we'll
see is that there are alternatives to
moving average processes called auto
reggressions that are very closely
related to uh moving average processes.
Yes.
>> Um so I guess my question is why do you
need to specify covarian stationerity
for um the the uh the representation
theorem?
>> Okay. Um the uh well with the
representation. Okay.
Okay. Um let's see where is it? Here you
know it's fine. Here here it is. Okay,
basically if if we consider this process
ST which has some set of weights SI
times white noise ADA T's then if these
conditions are satisfied for the size so
the sum they're squares summable
you know finite then this process ST t
is going to be covariant stationary.
It'll have finite mean and variance
that's constant and the covariances will
also be constant over increments of know
any lag. What's what's powerful is that
this representation
can be used for any coariant stationary
model.
So this is coariant stationary
but any coariant stationary model has
this kind of representation.
Yeah sure.
And of course you know um
coariant stationerity is a nice
assumption. It may not be satisfied. So
you need to you know have more complex
models. But it's good to know when you
have these uh assumptions satisfied that
this is the representation.
All right. So we next want to introduce
you to this operator called a lag
operator or a backshift operator.
And uh because I call it a lag operator,
I label it L. And so L
operates on a time series XT and just
shifts the time index back one period.
So we're thinking of discrete time
series with integer values of t and um
the lag
operating on xt shifts the time units
back one period. And we can think of L
to the zero power
doing the identity.
L1
one power of L shifts back once. If we
apply L twice or L squ this shifts back
two periods and of course if we apply it
N times then we shift back N periods.
And so with these lag operators, we can
think of inverses of those operators as
well and sort of consider sort of
shifting the time series forward if that
were useful. And so when we think of the
w representation
um we can express it as the sum of the
moving average process
and the linearly deterministic process
vt. And we can represent the uh moving
average process as a polomial
of the lag operators possibly of
infinite order that is multiplying the
um ad t's.
Now
a a useful um sort of application of
this uh moving average representation is
that if we think about how was
the value of the process at time t
affected by the white noise process ada
j lags ago.
Then
the partial derivative of XT with
respect to that J lag back white noise
term is given by SI J. So when pi j is
large in magnitude that means that the
current value of x is dependent on the j
lag of the white noise
and
with a representation of the xt series
by uh this uh pi function if one sort of
graphs the pi function over lags.
So let me do it over here. So if we look
at SI J as a function of J
and have
we might have weights J that vary
positive and negative. And so if this
were the case,
it would indicate in this graph that the
impact of
the white noise sort of three periods
ago has a significant impact on X now.
So it can capture sort of delayed
responses of the time series XT to the
white noise terms. And if we look at the
long range
impact of A to J or sorry the long range
yeah impact of uh
the uh
or the cumulative response of XT
basically corresponds um
to the uh sum
of the size
and so there's basically a long run
cumulative response of XT to the uh to a
given
a T. Um so this is the long run
cumulative response to uh the white
noise terms. Now what's interesting
about
the uh s of l process
so if we have s of l is equal to the sum
u from zero to infinity of s j l to the
j
um
it's possible that this operator is
invertible able
and
if it's invertible there exists
an inverse operator
with coefficients pi star and the
product of these two polomials is simply
equal to the identity
and
if that's the case
that an inverse of the PI of L operator
exists. Then we can
write our model for the stationary
process
as being equivalent to
applying the inverse operator to both
sides. And so we get an inverse operator
which is a polomial lags operating on xt
is equal to the a to t. So this
corresponds
to actually an auto reggression model
that um has white noise terms.
And so
when this exists this is the format of
that. And what we'd like to do is
um show you how this works with some
different examples. Right now it's
perhaps a bit abstract but when we look
at the special cases of an auto
reggressive order one model um many of
these terms will become clear. Now um
we can introduce with this notation of
lags and polomial lag operators the um
ARMA PQ models where ARMA stands for
auto reggressive
and MA stands for moving average models
and the P corresponds to the order of
the auto reggressive and the Q
corresponds to the order of the moving
average. We can think of our time series
XT being a sum of terms, auto
reggressive terms on the top row and
then the second row corresponds to
moving average terms of the white noise.
So notice in the top row we have xt
and actually if you look at that
equation if we sort of take xt minus mu
this turns out to be equal to v1
xt -1 minus mu plus v2
and so forth. So these are lag terms of
the mean adjusted x's and then we have
the next row is the sum of the white
noise terms at time t t t t t t t t t t
t t t t t t t t t t t t t t t t t t t t
t t t t t t t t t t t minus one up to t
minus q. So, ARMA PQ models are a
parsimmonious case of time series models
where we just have P auto reggressive
parameters F1 to FP and Q moving average
parameters theta 1 to theta Q.
And if we write
the if we group all the terms with x's
on the left hand side and all the terms
with the adas on the right hand side we
then get this f of l operator* xt minus
f is equal to theta of l a t
and
the w decomposition
of this
arma model is to multiply this arma
equation on both sides by the inverse of
f of l.
And so mu plus s of l a t is the w uh
decomposition
representation of the of the process.
So let's look at
um auto reggressive
models.
So we'll assume that there's no moving
average term. So we have the f of l
operator
operating on xt minus mu is equal to the
white noise.
And so that model basically says that XT
is a linear combination of the P lags of
XT plus white noise.
So this is a regression model for our
time series XT using predictor variables
the lags of this time series. And if we
take expectations of both sides,
we basically get mu
the constant
expectation of the coariant stationary
process is equal to C plus the sum of FJ
times mu, the expectation of each of the
lags
plus zero. And so C turns out to equal
mu * V of 1.
So u
we have that uh representation of the
constant term.
Now
what's
important with time series models is
whether the time series model
is stationary or not.
And
it turns out that for an auto
reggressive model with parameters f1 to
fp
that if we look at what's called this
characteristic equation
1 minus v1 z
minus v2 z ^ 2 up to pp z to the p
power.
If we consider the roots of that
polomial
then well if we have roots lambda 1 to
lambda p
then
f of l has to be the product of these
terms. each of these terms,
each of these factors are equal to zero
when sort of z equals
uh lambda 1.
So if z equals lambda 1 then the first
term is zero. If z equals the p
root lambda p then this last factor is
zero. So this is a representation of
this peace order polomial
in terms of its roots
and the condition for stationerity is
that all of these roots have to lie
outside the unit circle
in the complex plane.
And so um
if we look at one of these roots
fix just lambda as a root then if we
take the inverse of this factor
it has this geometric
sum expression
of 1 + 1 over lambda l + 1 over lambda^
2 l^2 and so forth.
And so it's basically an infinite order
polomial
in lags.
Um and the coefficients are one over
lambda to the i power.
So if these lambdas are bigger than one
in magnitude
then the inverse of those
the reciprocal of those is uh smaller
than one in magnitude. So these terms
will die down
with a limiting value of zero
and that's necessary for this
representation
to
be appropriate.
So we get a co-variance stationary
sum of lagged errors
uh lagged white noise terms um with this
uh representation. So the f inverse of L
is actually the product
of P of these
reciprocals.
And so the condition that each of those
reciprocals or or each of those terms is
defined by lambda js that are bigger
than one in magnitude
makes their geometric series expression
converge. If the lambdas
were inside the unit circle the
magnitude then when we multiply them
together square them they get bigger and
bigger.
Okay. Um
so let's take a look at what this
works out to be just for an auto
reggressive process with p equal to 1.
with P equal to 1, our characteristic
equation is simply 1 minus V Z = Z. And
so the root of that is clearly 1 over
FE.
And so the a the p= 1 auto reggressive
model is going to be coariant stationary
if and only if the magnitude of fee is
smaller than one or equivalently
its inverse magnitude is greater than
one.
And so we end up having these first and
second moments and these co-variances
which are very easy to compute.
And you know this will probably be an
homework exercise problem. But with the
first order auto reggression model, we
have a constant mean, a constant
variance, which is sigma squar over 1
minus v
time sigma squared. And uh the
co-variances
basically are the variance
times f to the j power. So with an
autocorrelation
uh the fee is the first
order autocorrelation and fee to the J
is the J order autocorrelation.
Okay. Now if f is
um
between or minus one and one or for fee
between zero and one the process
uh exhibits exponential mean reversion
and when fee is negative
but no larger than negative one in
magnitude then it exhibits some
oscillating exponential mean reversion.
But when f equals 1, then the wool
decomposition does not exist and the
process
is a simple random walk which is
non-stationary
and when fee is greater than one then
the process is explosive.
So uh in financial markets there these
first order auto reggressive models
actually are used quite frequently with
interest rates where there's maybe a
constant long-term interest rate level
and there's variation about that. This
olbeck process corresponds to the first
order auto reggressive process.
um
with these other series um these are
financial
or time series and financial markets
where the level of the series is
expected to be stable over time. So
perhaps interest rate spreads would be
modeled as being stable or stationary.
real exchange rates perhaps or valuation
ratios. Um so so these models arise in
these uh application areas. Now to fit
um an auto reggressive process
um
and we could simply just fit a linear
regression
model with p lags of the series as uh
explanatory variables. But what's rather
interesting to know is this approach
called ule uh solving ule walker
equations. If we take our model
equation,
that first equation line, we have the
mean deviation
of XT is equal to a linear combination
of FJ times the J lag deviation from U.
There's a typo there. That second
uh F2 should have an XT minus 2. Um then
if we multiply both sides of this model
equation by Xt minus J minus mu
then we basically for each term we're
adding XT minus J minus mu as a factor
and then take expectations of that we
have our J
lag auto covariance
and it's equal to
the F1 * the J minus1
lag autocariance
plus F2 * the J minus 2 lag and so forth
and if
the J is equal to zero then we also have
a sigma squared term where we're looking
at um basically that that well that term
comes comes in. So um so we basically
have equations
a system of equations
if we vary J
and so if we consider J equal to one to
P we get a system of P linear equations
in the FJS
and this is our U walker equations gamma
one is equal to the first row of the
matrix times the vector of fees and so
forth.
And with the properties of the
autocovariances,
they are symmetrical.
So we can actually use these to uh
make the computations of of the
matrices. And when we use this Ule
Walker approach to estimate the
parameters,
we're actually using a sort of method of
moments principle for estimating the
auto reggressive model parameters.
Method of moments is a principle in
statistical estimation where we
basically equate sample moments and the
population moments and solve for what
population parameter values match the
sample moments.
Now uh we can do a similar analysis of
moving average models. So here we have a
Qth order moving average model
represented by a polomial theta of L of
order Q in terms of powers of L. And um
the properties of this process
can be studied. And one thing we might
want to do is invert this moving average
model into an auto reggressive model
by basically modeling multiplying the
model equation on both sides by the
inverse of the theta of L operator.
And so if we do that um then we
basically have an auto reggressive
representation
of the moving average order Q model.
And if you calculate
simple
second order properties of this moving
average process, well the mean is simply
mu.
The right hand side of the equation is
just
weighted sums of adas which have mean
zero. And so the expectation of the left
hand side is simply equal to mu. And if
we look at the variance of xt
um it basically is the variance of the
weighted sum of the adas.
And it turns out to have this simple
form
with co-variances of the series
with moving average processes. If we
look at time increments J that are
longer than the Q order, then there's no
overlap of white noise terms
in XT and XT plus J. And so their
co-variance is going to be zero. When
there is overlap then we get this
formula.
Okay. Uh so next
um we want to uh deal with how we can
accommodate non-stationerity and time
series. So far we've just assumed
examples and models like auto
reggressive and moving average models
where this series is stationary.
There will be cases when our time series
is not stationary
and
differencing the series
will generally render a series to a
stationary uh transformation.
And so
if we consider
first order differencing
we have
let's see here if we do deltayt
equaling 1 - l yt
= yt
minus l yt
which is yt minus yt minus one. Okay,
this is first order differences.
If we
apply the
first difference of this, we end up
getting yt - yt -1
- yt -1 - ytus 2.
And this turns out to be equal to yt - 2
ytus1
+ ytus 2.
And there could be kith order
differencing, but in practice we'll only
generally use first or second order
differencing. And what's really neat
about differencing is that first order
differencing
will eliminate a linear trend in the
series.
Basically, if we have a linear trend,
then the difference will just be a
constant difference.
And the second order difference is
appropriate
if there is a sort of quadratic
um trend in the series and second order
differencing will eliminate that
quadratic trend. So we'll finish there
for today. But this issue of modeling
differences of the series
or second differences of the series as
stationary corresponds to having time
series models that are looking at the
dynamics of the slope of the time series
or
which is like the first derivative or
the second derivative
and assuming that those are perhaps
constant level and constant variability.
So, so those mathematical features end
up now being very intuitive uhly applied
actually with with different cases.
Okay, we'll finish there for today.