hello and welcome to energy reads your
source for a handpicked audio articles
on the latest energy news from
MIT my name is Kelly Travers and I've
been the one reading to you today we're
doing something a little different
instead of reading one of our recently
released articles we will be teasing
several that are upcoming and have yet
to be published if you're familiar with
the MIT energy initiative or Mighty as
we call ourselves you may know that we
publish a magazine called Energy Futures
twice a year in addition to reading you
the news I'm also our magazine managing
editor sorry for the lowkey flex there
but it puts me in a position to say that
I'm very excited with absolutely no bias
to share with you some of the cool
stories we have coming out soon in our
next
issue let me set the stage by sharing
that in May 2022 Mighty completed a
three-year study that explored how
energy storage techn can be harnessed to
decarbonize our Global Energy Systems
what is so cool about storage is that it
allows us to really take advantage of
renewable energy sources that we refer
to as variable meaning they aren't
always available so when the Sun is up
and doing its thing or the wind is
blowing storage makes it possible to you
guessed it store the energy collected at
those times so it can be used once the
sun is set and the wind has died down so
then you can do things like charge
whatever it is you're using to listen to
this podcast for
instance building on the completion of
our energy storage study the research
articles in this issue of Energy Futures
focus a lot on different storage and
battery
technologies in one article we introduce
a new modeling framework that can help
guide the development of flow batteries
these are electrochemical devices that
can store hundreds of megawatt hours of
energy which would be really beneficial
for large scale long duration
electricity storage especially on a
future grid dominated by intermittent
solar and wind power generators current
flow batteries rely on vadium which is
an energy storage material that's
expensive and not always readily
available investigators worldwide are
exploring a variety of other less
expensive more abundant options to
replace vadium and using their modeling
framework the MIT researchers calculated
the total cost of some of those options
considering operating expenses as well
as initial Capital costs the results
show that in many cases the low Capital
costs may be more than offset by high
operating costs over the lifetime of the
battery such results can help Focus
today's disperate efforts on designs
with the most promise which will help
speed
development in another article we share
the work of an MIT team seeking to lower
the high cost of making lithium ion
batteries they do this by using
combustion but not for burning coal or
oil they they realized that much of the
cost of making a lithium ion battery can
be traced to the manufacturing materials
used to make the cathode which is one of
its two electrodes the team developed a
system that under carefully controlled
conditions uses combusting Flames to
produce not polluting foot but rather
valuable materials including some that
are critical in the manufacturer of
lithium ion batteries their system
promises to be simpler much quicker less
expensive and far less energy intensive
than the conventional me now used and
most importantly it does this without
sacrificing battery
performance this issue of Energy Futures
also highlights some of the cool stuff
going on in our education department I
am particularly excited about an
interview we did with mighty's Director
of Education Ana Danielson she and her
team lead energy education at MIT they
have been developing a robust
educational toolkit not just for
undergraduate and graduate students at
MIT but also for online Learners around
the world and high school students who
want to contribute to a world powered by
Clean Energy a big piece of mighty's
educational programming is preparing
Learners to take an active role in
climate action it does this in part by
really emphasizing practice and
experience in addition to giving the
students the knowledge skills and
courage to be ready to jump into action
one thing AA said that really stood out
to me was that if Done Right education
is an energy transition
accelerator we profile one student who
really seems to embody this idea syus
Horowitz is currently a senior at MIT
majoring in mechanical engineering and
minoring in energy studies and
environment and sustainability the
article Dives straight into one of
silas's projects taking us right to the
edge of a marsh where they are tinkering
with a blue and black robot about the
size and shape of a shoe box and studded
with lights and mini propellers this
remotely operated vehicle or ROV is an
underwater drone destined to collect
water s from beneath a sheet of Arctic
ice it will be employed to measure
carbon dioxide and methane in the water
in the summer of 2022 the Rover was
successfully deployed on a field run in
the Canadian High
Arctic in another profile we meet
Michael Howland he is an assistant
professor of civil and environmental
engineering and MIT he is working to get
more electricity out of renewable energy
systems and to prepare young scientists
and Engineers with the training and
tools they need to tackle climate change
mitigation
he also does a lot of work with wind
energy and recently he and his team
developed a model that predicts the
power produced by each individual
turbine on a wind farm based on the
physics of the Wind Farm as a whole he
used this model to improve Wind Farm
efficiency by misaligning some of the
upwind turbines in certain conditions
the downwind units experience less wake
turbulence this increased the overall
energy output of the wind farm by as
much as 1 to 3% without requiring any
additional costs so crazy fact if a 1.2%
energy increase was applied to the
world's existing wind farms it would be
the equivalent of adding more than
3,600 new wind turbines that's enough to
power about 3 million
homes this issue of Energy Futures also
digs into two programs geared towards
high school
students the first is climate action
through education also known as Kate
this program is developing climate
change curriculum for youth in high
schools so what's particularly cool
about K is that it's creating
climate-based lessons for a range of
disciplines Beyond just science from
math to history to language arts
Christopher kidle who is leading this
project and among his many titles is
mighty's deputy director for policy told
us we will be honest about the threats
posed by climate change but also give
students a sense of agency that they can
do something about this and for the many
teachers especially non-science teachers
starved for knowledge and background
material Kate offers resources to give
them confidence to implement our
curriculum the curriculum is rolling out
in Pilot form soon in more than a dozen
Massachusetts high schools and
eventually in high schools across the
United States in another article we
learn about a group of Massachusetts
high school students who joined MIT
Professor Ariel first in her lab over
the summer to build lowcost fuel cells
with a seemingly bizarre collection of
materials shrink eating inks a
children's toy popular in the 1980s
carbon based materials nail polish and
some smelly bacteria the students
received quite literally a trial by fire
introduction to the scientific method at
one point one of their experimental
electrodes actually burst into flames
other results though proved more
promising okay so on that explosive note
I think that might be enough spoilers
for now I hope you'll keep listening to
energy reads and I look forward to
reading these stories to you in full
when we release this next issue of
Energy Futures thank you for
listening and that's our wrap