Our final speaker today is Brian Leu, a
PhD candidate at MIT's Operations
Research Center. Before MIT, Brian was a
data and applied scientists at Microsoft
and he brings a strong technical lens to
today's conversation. Brian will discuss
a research collaboration between HSI and
Amwell Silvercloud utilizing health
analytics to enhance engagement and
effectiveness. Take it away, Brian.
>> Uh, cool.
>> So, yeah, thanks everyone. And then, um,
I'll just be quickly talking about kind
of some of the more in detailed research
that we're doing in this collaboration.
And this is joint work with, uh, Petro,
who's also a PhD student in the OC, and
with our adviser, uh, Professor Rupul
Munder, who's associate professor at the
operations research and statistics group
at Sloan.
So um what we're kind of interested in
our collaboration is kind of developing
models to better explore patient
behavior on the silvercloud platform.
And one thing kind of from the start we
noticed with silvercloud is that we they
gave us uh very rich data. So we have
patient demographics we have information
about the supporters even usage logs
kind of timestamp data points every time
a uh patient even interacts with their
platform as well as feedback. So we're
actually very excited to receive this
kind of like large uh amount of real
world data that we can kind of apply to
several methods that we have been
developing uh to analyze.
So kind of uh at the high level what
we're interested in uh modeling or
predicting is first patient outcomes. So
uh a patient enters the platform, they
complete uh modules and they leave the
platform and then we kind of have a
start and an end score. And um from this
we can kind of determine how much the
patient improves, whether there's
reliable improvement uh both for their
uh silvercloud programs for anxiety and
for depression.
And we're also also interested in
looking at patient engagement. So this
is kind of whether or not they complete
the program. Some patients they start
the program, they abandon. And also kind
of how often do they use the program? So
like the duration that they spend per
session and how that progresses through
uh through their time with SilverCloud.
And one kind of goal we have uh like
overarching goal is we're not interested
in just making models to predict these
outcomes or engagement metrics. Well,
we're also interested in understanding
what various factors whether it's on the
silvercloud side, the patient side
contribute towards these types of
patient behaviors such as uh successful
treatment outcomes.
So this is actually what we found kind
of very early on in our collaboration is
that it's it's a very difficult uh like
process right um you have a lot of data
uh for patient outcomes the kind of
signal is very noisy and what we ended
up doing is we actually determined that
we need really like uh complex like
state-of-the-art machine learning models
such as like boosted tree ensembles to
get models that perform well. Now while
these models perform well they're
actually very complicated and difficult
to interpret.
So kind of uh the models we use just
like uh for example like one of our
favorite models are like uh gradient
boosted decision trees and these
basically just generate a bunch of
decision trees to form a complex model
that predicts um predicts a prediction
target. And just kind of a sample of
what we're looking at here is uh on this
picture this is just like a sample of
500 500 tree boosting ensemble. And this
is actually kind of a small smallest
model by like most uh modern machine
learning standards. And even from this
it's like almost impossible to determine
looking at this model what's going on.
So this model is very useful for making
predictions. However, for actually
understanding what's in the data, this
model is not so great.
And in kind of the field of like
interpretability in machine learning,
this is a pretty well-known trade-off.
You have like your modern ML methods
like random forests, gradient boosted
trees, your like modern foundation
models, language models, they're
excellent at making predictions.
However, they're actually very poor at
kind of revealing patterns in the data.
Versus a lot of the classical methods
such as like decision trees, linear
regression, these models are a lot
simpler. They're easier to understand.
You can kind of determine what's going
on. However, in terms of prediction
prediction accuracy, they perform very
poorly. So, what we kind of do for our
research is we develop methods that kind
of explore this trade-off. We try to get
uh like we kind of start with high
performing models like random forests
and trees and we see we can extract
models that are simpler but still
perform well and still however um you
can look at these simple models and
determine more useful insights about the
data. So this is kind of a sample of
like the relevant research we've been
doing in the past few years on this
field.
So um I'll just kind of conclude with a
quick demonstration on kind of what we
did with the silvercloud data is we are
interested in for example in predicting
uh whether or not patients exhibit
reliable improvement for uh anxiety
treatment. And we start with this model
large model. This is the large tree that
performs well. And we compress this
model into a much smaller distilled
model. And from this model we can
actually get interesting insights about
the data. So one key point is going from
the full model to the compact model we
actually get very very similar
performance. And this is actually a new
method that we developed that's
currently under review. And the
extracted model is small enough to be uh
examined by hand. So in this extracted
model every single uh kind of structure
here is a rule. It's like a single
sentence that describes what's going on
in the data. And you can look at and
examine each of these rules to get an
idea of what factors in um impact
successful treatment outcomes.
Cool. So I think uh that's uh coming up
about time. So yeah, happy to take any
questions.
>> Um thank thanks Brian. Um, I suspect
that some folks may be really interested
in this and some folks may have not ever
seen this before, but um, this is the
kind of work we do here at MIT and it's
very exciting. So can you talk a little
bit when you're when you're doing this
and you ended up with your 12 rules um
or in any other part of this can you
share a little bit of a of something of
a s what surprised you about the
research you were doing here and and
what did you do next when you you know
ran into such a surprise?
Uh one one thing that I think was uh
pretty interesting was I think at first
uh when we just like started uh fitting
models it actually even with kind of
like the modern ML methods we had
trouble getting good predictive
performance and it required a lot of
like kind of um almost like manually
like engineering features from the data.
So we looked at a lot of things like for
every single like patient who's assigned
a supporter, how many other patients the
supporter has like supporter workload
experience and it was actually quite a
surprise to see that those actually had
a influence on like um patient outcomes.
So like how how experienced the
supporters were and things like that.
>> So that actually has a lot of practical
potentially practical implications and
that um that you can work on with with
Anel and and the uh ML Silver Cloud
team.
>> Yeah. Yeah, definitely.
>> All right. Well, I am looking at the
time and we seem to have filled an hour.
So, I'm going to turn it back over to um
to Jim.