Hello and welcome to Today I Learned:
Climate from the Massachusetts Institute
of Technology. I'm Laur Hesse Fisher.
If you're like many of our listeners,
you might be wondering: okay, so the CO2 from
burning fossil fuels is warming the planet,
right? So why haven't we just gotten rid
of all of these fossil fuels already? Well,
we live in a world that's currently dependent
on fossil fuels, yet a lot of that dependence is
invisible to us. So we collaborated with TABLE,
an international coalition of universities that
helps the public understand our food system. Their
recent podcast miniseries is called Fuel to Fork,
and it explores all the many ways that
fossil fuels are involved in putting food
on our plates. And today we are going to get a
glimpse into the hard work that is happening to
eliminate pollution from the food system, and
in doing so explore the very real ways that
our food now depends on fossil fuels. Even to
produce the simplest thing, like a tortilla
chip. I love tortilla chips. In fact I had some
on the weekend and they were very tasty. That's
Jennifer Clapp. I'm a professor and Canada
Research Chair in global food security and
sustainability at the University of Waterloo
in Canada. I'm also a member of IPES-Food,
which is the international panel of experts on
sustainable food systems. She's here to help
us follow the journey of a tortilla chip from farm
to grocery store, taking note of all the ways that
fossil fuels are used along the way. So let's get
started. Well tortilla chips, have relatively few
ingredients. They're made of corn, or in the rest
of the world it's called maize. Here in the US we
have over 90 million acres of corn fields. If that
were a state, it would be the fifth largest, just
barely behind Montana. And if you took a drive
through this great state of corn, the first thing
you might notice above the vast waving expanses
of green are the machines that tend the corn from
planting to harvest. Farm machinery typically
runs on diesel fuel. And that's the machinery
used to plow the fields, drill the seeds, spread
the fertilizer, spread the pesticides, spread the
herbicides. Also for harvesting crops big machines
are used, you know, combine harvesters and other
kinds of machines that thresh the grain. It's
probably no surprise that these great machines
require fuel to run. But what about the quieter
parts of a corn farm, like the barns? Corn has a
lot of moisture in it. It's a heavy crop, and
to store it properly it needs to be dried. And
farmers typically use giant fans in a barn to dry
out the corn, and typically heat those barns with
propane fuel. The two things that we've mentioned
so far, the farming machinery and drying the crop,
make up about half of the fossil energy use on
a typical corn farm. There's one last big chunk
of emissions that we're going to come back to a
little bit later in this episode. For now though,
we're packing up our corn for sale. Commodities
like corn do travel around a fair bit. If it's
trucked it's typically using diesel fuel, and
also if it's shipped it's definitely using oil.
Those fossil fuels get our dried corn to a
factory where it will be turned into masa,
the delicious dough that makes a tortilla.
And what it involves is soaking and simmering,
like cooking, these dried kernels of corn for up
to 12 hours. That process is called wet milling.
For our tortilla chips, this is almost the end of
the line. The masa from the wet mill is ready to
be shaped and baked and fried. Other corn products
will keep passing through more screens and
grinders and dryers and fermenters on their way
to becoming things like cornstarch and corn syrup,
and even the ethanol that we add to gasoline.
There isn't good recent data on this, but back
in 2001 the US Energy Information Administration
did a study of corn wet mills and found that they
used 15% of all of the energy in, not just corn,
but the entire US food industry. So that gives you
a sense of just how energy consumptive it is. When
you hear about ultra processed foods, this is what
it means. The ingredients go through a whole bunch
of machines to break them down to their proteins
and fibers and oils and such. It tends to use
a lot of fossil fuels, and be less healthy for
us too. With our tortilla chips the last machine
would be the fryer that makes them nice and crispy
and snackable. But there's one more step
before they're shipped to the grocery store,
and that's packaging. In my local community I
can buy corn chips that come in a paper bag,
which really makes me happy. But most corn chips
that you're going to find in a grocery store shelf
are packaged in plastic. And that plastic is made
of—do you know? It's oil! Yeah, our food system
doesn't rely on fossil fuels just for energy. Tons
of stuff, packaging, farm equipment, is also made
of fossil fuels. You might have seen large sheets
of plastic covering farm fields that sort of keep
in moisture and keep temperatures warm in the
soil, or covering a greenhouse. Herbicides,
pesticides: they're all fossil fuel sort of
oil based chemicals. So when we think about
fossil fuels on the farm, they're just, they're
everywhere. Remember earlier when we found that
the farming and drying machinery added up to about
half of a farm's fossil energy use? Well, most of
the remaining half comes from just one of those
fossil fuel-based chemicals alone. The fertilizer
use is probably the biggest use of fossil energy
when we're talking about growing corn. For as long
as there's been farming, people have been adding
fertilizers like manure and wood ash to soil to
revitalize it. These products really started
to be used much more frequently after around
the 1840s, when scientific developments led to an
understanding about the importance of nitrogen,
phosphorus and potassium as key nutrients that
plants need for better plant growth. Phosphorus
and potash are actually today typically mined
from the earth and processed to make fertilizers.
But the third nutrient, nitrogen, is trickier.
There's no nitrogen rock that we can mine. On the
other hand, there is one very abundant source
of nitrogen very close to hand. It's in the
air that we're breathing. Earth's atmosphere is
almost 80% nitrogen gas. And scientists knew that
nitrogen was in the air. They just didn't know
how to capture it and make it into a physical,
usable form that could be applied to soil. And
then, in the early 1900s, two German chemists,
Fritz Haber and Carl Bosch, figured it
out. If you react nitrogen with hydrogen,
they mix to make NH3, also known as ammonia.
And this became the main ingredient for modern
fertilizers. The catch is that the hydrogen comes
from yet another fossil fuel: natural gas. So the
Haber-Bosch process really changed everything,
because people didn't have to worry about where
the nitrogen was going to come from to fertilize
crops. And the use of synthetic nitrogen increased
massively. And what that's meant is that more
crops can be grown, more land around the world
can be cultivated for agriculture, because the
nutrients can be continually replenished. And on
that land humans are supplying a regular stream of
nitrogen, provided mostly by natural gas. Where,
unfortunately, it continues to impact the
climate in yet another way. There's been a
tendency to over-apply fertilizer, just kind of
like an insurance policy that farmers want to be
sure that they're putting enough on the field to
ensure plant growth. But not all nitrogen that's
put down in the field is taken up by the plant.
And then soil microbes eat up the nitrogen, and it
converts it into a gas called nitrous oxide, which
is more damaging than carbon dioxide when we're
talking about climate change. And corn uses a lot
of fertilizer, so it has a lot of nitrous oxide
emissions. Fertilizer is by far the biggest
way that humans create nitrous oxide,
this highly climate-warming gas. If you add both
the manufacturing process and the nitrous oxide,
fertilizer has the same impact on the climate as
a major country. In fact, it contributes as much
to climate change each year as Japan does, which
is the world's seventh largest climate polluter,
So all in all the fertilizer industry is pretty
significant. Okay, so what do we do about all
this? You might ask, is it even possible to have
our tortilla chips without the climate pollution?
Can I imagine a fossil fuel free bag of corn
chips? I think in this current world that we
live in that's hard to imagine, given all of the
places in the whole production process that have
relied on and continue to rely on fossil energy.
Let's take farming machinery for a moment. You
might say, well, couldn't we just run these
machines on electricity, like switching a gas
powered car for an electric car? And yeah, we
probably could. But it's not straightforward,
because a tractor has to have a lot of horsepower,
especially for plowing, especially for these
sort of harvesting and threshing activities. That
means that an electric tractor would need to hold
a lot of energy in its battery. For the heaviest
equipment, like combine harvesters, the industry
is still waiting on more powerful motors and
batteries to hit the market, and to be affordable.
But don't throw up your hands. There is a lot we
can do right now. Like in the drying barns, which
can be heated electrically, and the wet mills that
can switch to clean power sources. Or what about
the problem of over-applying nitrogen? That's
no good for anybody who cares about our climate,
but it's also especially bad for the people who
are buying all of this fertilizer that just ends
up being wasted. Because it's a big cost for
farmers. And the big companies are all investing
in digital technology that can analyze the type
of soil and its fertility, and then provide advice
to farmers that you should only put this much
fertilizer in this part of your field, maybe you
want to use a little bit more in that part of
your field. There are also these things called
slow-release fertilizers, which are coated in a
slow-dissolving plastic so that all the nitrogen
doesn't get dumped on the field at once. Or,
could we produce the nitrogen that our corn needs
without using natural gas? There are emerging
processes that use clean electricity instead,
or even engineered microbes in the soil. All of
these ideas are being actively pursued right now,
and also studied to see what kinds of unintended
effects might arise if we start doing things like
treating our soils with plastics, or using a lot
of energy for AI-powered digital farming tools. So
in this episode, we wanted to highlight the often
hidden fossil fuel use in our food system. But
we also wanted to highlight the often invisible
solutions that are happening. Because as more and
more of get activated and equipped to tackle this
issue, researchers, innovators, investors, and
folks working across the food system get creative,
and solutions like these become possible. So it's
a big ask to say, okay, throw that model out the
window and start scratch with something else. But
there are models of other things that can work,
such as agroecology, which is using nature's own
processes to provide the fertilization of of soils
by growing different crops next to each other.
It's a big change. And so it's not going to happen
overnight. But I I always think about the fact
that the way that we ended up with the agriculture
we have today took about 200 years. Farmers did
adopt synthetic fertilizers. They did adopt
hybrid seeds. You know, all of the aspects that
we think of as conventional farming today were
at one point new technologies. So we shouldn't
think necessarily that farmers are going to be
resistant to change. But that change has to be
tangible for them in terms of the benefits, and
it has to be easy, and it has to be affordable.
And that's harder than just saying, keep the
fossil fuels in the ground. But in the end,
this hard, steady work is what it's going to
take to have a clean economy that offers us a
good living and the things that we need. And even
the things that we like, like a bag of chips.
That is our show. But if you're interested
in learning more about fossil fuels in the
food system, I invite you to check out the
entire Fuel to Fork miniseries from TABLE,
in collaboration with IPES-Food and the Global
Alliance for the Future of Food. Just look up
Fuel to Fork wherever you get your podcasts.
And hey, you can also look up TILclimate there
and follow us. There are a lot more episodes to
brush up on your climate knowledge and satisfy
your climate curiosity. Or get in touch and ask
us your climate change questions. Email us at
tilclimate.mit.edu, or leave us a voicemail
at 617 253 3566. TILclimate is the climate
change podcast of the Massachusetts Institute
of Technology. Aaron Krol is our writer and
executive producer. David Lishansky is our
audio producer. Michelle Harris is our fact
checker. Grace Sawin is our student production
assistant. The music is by Blue Dot sessions.
And I'm your host and senior editor Laur
Hesse Fisher. A big thanks to Professor
Jennifer clapp for speaking with us, and to you,
our listeners. Keep up your climate curiosity.