good morning afternoon evening everyone
depending on where you are in the world
um so my name is Karen Jang I am a
faculty member at the operations
Management Group at slong uh you see
here kind of a very brief F of myself I
actually I grew up in h China and I did
my ma undergrad and master's degrees in
chinua University which I always stroke
is the MIT in
China and then uh I came to the US and
did my pH D at Stanford University uh in
management science and engineering then
after that I was fortunate enough to
join the faculty of slung and um and
I've been here since
2011 um so my my research is broadly
related to sustainability issues in
Global Supply chains and uh in the past
um decade in particular I have focused
uh in particular on um food and Global
and and food and agricultureal system
globally and really the overarching goal
of of my research in this area is how we
can think about innovating the systems
um with technology incentive design as
well as behavioral interventions to
promote both environmental and social
sustainability um and and I think that
you know it goes without saying why food
and agricultural systems are important
to us because food is such a fundamental
need for all all of us uh but just to
you know uh illustr rate uh that
importance and highlight that importance
with some numbers here um you
know uh the global demand for safe and
nutritious food is is you know ever
growing and and this is also coupled
with the challenge that in at least some
parts of the world uh productivity may
it has been declining because of uh
climate
challenges um uh you know food um the
food system is related to two of the
most pressing challenges in the world
one is hunger and the other is poverty
uh and this is especially true when we
think about a large portion of this uh
system intersect with uh developing
nations uh where a lot of the uh small
holder producers are the main uh
producers of food uh now of course the
the food system uh has a huge uh impact
on you know Environ mental
sustainability uh it occupies a
significant portion of our land and use
a significant uh part of the water
globally and also contribute
substantially to greenhouse gas
emissions uh finally uh there's also
significant Public Health uh relation
between the food system and um and and
public health uh in the sense that you
know uh a lot of uh a large portion of
population actually suffer from uh food
contamination and um um pathogens Etc uh
in you know in in the food
system um
so um to give you an overview uh this is
kind of the overarching goal of my
research uh again focusing on the global
EOS systems how we can use uh
Technologies uh incentives as well as
behavioral uh interventions to improve
the efficiency of the systems the
sustainability as well as the social
welfare of the systems so far I've been
look at uh multiple topics under this
overarching goal uh all the way from
Upstream production and resource uh
optimization to the middle part in terms
of how we design markets and Supply
chains as well as to the downstream how
do we ensure food access and reduce food
waste um oops sorry I did something
wrong with my with my okay I'm back all
right so oh I'm not back I guess okay um
and and uh in the process of doing this
research uh I'm I am um I'm you know a
believer of underground collaboration
and this is collaborating with a whole
spectrum of organizations from private
organizations companies startups
nonprofits to you know public
organization such as governments and um
think tanks and and also academic
institutions particularly those in the
ground uh of the regions where my
research projects
are so what I wanted to do uh today is
to share with you a few examples of uh
these projects to give you a sense of
what kind of uh questions we uh we try
to answer and what kind of tools that we
use in answering those questions uh the
first example is a collaboration with
the state government uh of kataka in
India and focusing on on uh a digital
reform of the state where they build a
digital agricultureal platform to unify
trades across uh over 160 agricultural
markets uh throughout the state and um
the idea of this platform is really by
integrating historically isolated
markets and also to digitize transaction
processes this could potentially
increase competition on the buyer side
uh improve Market channels for and
Market access for farmers who are
oftentimes confined to their own local
regions and also increase price
transparency to um potentially address
issues such as uh collusion uh on the
buyer side um we did two things uh with
this uh with with the state government
of cantica one is uh we first perform a
very rigorous impact assessment for the
government to really demonstrate whether
uh establishing such a platform can
significantly improve Farmers welfare
and Farmers income and um and this
requires us to uh you know perform uh
Advanced econometrics analysis and
statistical analysis on large scale um
price and uh quantity data that we can
get from uh from the platform and our
results show that uh actually the impact
of such a platform on Farmer income uh
is not uni is not uniform across
different Commodities there are some
Commodities farmers benefit
significantly as you can see here the
313 uh Commodities with the green bar
but then for other
Commodities um the the platform has
actually not yielded a significant price
Improvement for the farmers and by
analyzing the potential supply chain and
operational reasons behind um these um
these uh supply chain operational
processes behind uh these Commodities we
find that uh this could potentially
related to Limited in Market competition
and and the platform has not signif
sufficiently address those issues and
does a lack of impact and so what we did
next as a as a followup is that we work
with the government to completely
redesign the auction used on this uh on
the platform for these Commodities um
with the goal of further increasing
competition among the Traders among the
buyers and then we work with the
government to launch a a uh pilot
implementation in one of the major
markets for lenos and uh the graph show
here demonstrates that the pilot
actually led to a very significant uh
price Improvement and profit gain for
over 20,000 Farmers that participate in
the market where the new auction
mechanism was
implemented so uh this is one of the
examples earlier examples um that that
we look at uh basically how platform Des
design and and price and the price
Discovery processes on this platform can
be designed to um increase the impact of
such
platform as a next example this is a
current ongoing project in Indonesia and
this is in collaboration with a uh
private company pam pam which is a
platform company as well as a local
academic institution ipb University
specializing agricultural uh
Technologies and the idea of this this
project is uh to design
incentives to promote sustainable
practice adoption by small holders um so
so far um uh many of these uh um you
know projects for promoting sustainable
practices by small holder farmers are
only confined within very small scale
pilots and Regional pilots and
short-term uh pilot with transient
benefits and so there's the question of
how can we design incentives to enable
scalable long-term and consist
consistent uh consistent um uh adoption
of these practices and so what we did is
that we started by um interacting with
the relevant stakeholders to understand
you know what are some of the challenges
that they face and that that prevent
these um uh practices from being
consistently adopted and based on that
Insight we develop a model to compare
two mainstream uh incentive design uh
which is termed offsetting in setting
incentives um yeah the the the high
level result from the from the model is
such that um in setting incentive is is
a a less popular incentive that's only
starting to emerge in practice however
for our analysis shows that it can
actually help to balance trade-off
between productivity and sustainability
adoption much better compared to the
more mainstream offsetting incentive and
as a result it can be more cost
effective uh to ensure long-term
adoption of sustainable practices by
small holders and given this modeling
inside then we go to the field we
actually develop a simulation experiment
um and recruited over 200 Farmers to
participate in this experiment to
observe their decisions when they are
exposed to these two different kinds of
incentives and you can see here some
pictures of us in the field interacting
with Indonesian uh oil pal farmers as
well as the interface of the simulation
game that the farmers uh make decisions
in and and the results suggest that is
is is consistent with our modeling
prediction where um the in setting
incentive essentially can promote more
consistent compliance than the
offsetting incentive uh we are currently
actually discussing with a number of
corporate organiz corporates uh to
design potential fi uh randomized
control trials to really evaluate the
impact Act of uh these two incentives uh
in in actual you know farming
decisions so very quickly one last
example that I wanted to share is
another uh project that we recently
worked on and this focused on Ghana
subsaharan country and in this project
we look at the problem of uh fot waste
as well as food security essentially the
idea is that there's a large amount of
food being wasted in the production
process of food supply chains and yet at
the same time we know that food
insecurity and hunger are major issues
in these developing countries so uh the
the the overarching goal is how we can
design lowcost scalable behavor
interventions to reduce foot waste in
the production processes and in
particular we focus on restaurant
kitchens uh this project is is uh we are
in collaboration with a number of um
academic Partners uh as as well as the
local Ghana tourism authority to uh
basically design uh different kinds of
intervention messages that either uh
highlight public um interest or private
interest so public will be uh public
interest will be related to saying if we
can save uh we can if we can reduce food
waste then the reduced foot waste could
be used to feed more people the private
interest intervention is more related to
how reducing fot waste can improve uh
can induce cost savings by The Man by
the restaurants and as a result more
sustainable employment by the workers in
the
kitchen um we uh collaborate with our
local Partners to engage 71 restaurants
and run a few randomized control trial
across these restaurants over three
weeks uh and this is a map of all the
restaurants that were part you know um
engaged in the experiment um and what we
found is that in fact private interest
intervention can be over twice as as
effective as public interest
interventions um and the impact that we
can measure from uh this three-week
experiment is such that using these
interventions to reduce food waste can
have a significant societal impact uh
just looking at the restaurants in a
that that we involve in the experiment
or in the study the total foot waste
avoided because of the use of these
interventions could already feed 5,000
people in the country and so we believe
that this is another you know um project
that can have a quite significant
societal impact so to conclude uh I
would just want to highlight that uh I
have quite actively and consistently
engaged andan students in my project and
these students contribute in and
particip in a number of different ways
and different types of analysis ranging
from statistical machine learning
analysis to optimization and also I
think you know because of my interest in
you know field workor as well as
behavioral interventions a lot of times
these students also engage in designing
experiments implementing experiments in
the field as well as analyzing the data
from these experiments