hello open course Weare Learners this is
Professor cber talking to you and I just
wanted to say a little bit about why the
next two classes are not to be found um
on this site MIT and the music
department was very fortunate to be able
to hire a new professor in computation
music that semester and one of the
things that we value as a department is
people's ability to be good teachers so
as part of their interview U the
candidates came and took over one of the
classes to uh teach the content of the
class and a little bit of their
Specialties too and two of those classes
were um that were used were this class
21 M
383 both of the Cates I can say did
amazing work and I wish I could share
them their videos with you but we have a
feeling that it's already stressful
enough to be doing a job interview and
to have your teaching being evaluated by
people in the room uh and then to know
that whatever things you did in an
unfamiliar classroom with unfamiliar
students would also be put out online uh
it's just a little bit too much so these
too ask too much to ask so these videos
are not available I want to say a little
bit though what was in each of
them the first class was the
continuation of our series on music
cognition and computation and how
computers can Aid the process of
understanding how the brain processes
music and also how historically and I
think in the
future uh insights from music cognition
have improved the things that we do on
the computer uh the most important uh
example of this is Carol Crum hansel's
um probe
tone uh experiments uh in understanding
musical expectation in scales and keys
and these experiments which helped you
understand how each note plays in our
ability to understand what key we're in
at this point underlies a quite a number
of algorithms being used today by
computers to automatically detect the
keys of compositions and this includes
music 21's default analyze key method
and this is why the assignments on
understanding uh key
analysis went hand inand with the
section on cognition
the lecture also covered and gave the
opportunity to discuss some of the
experiments reported by David hon in his
book sweet anticipation of which the
students were assigned to do
readings I would encourage as a
substitute for the content of this
lecture for you to look deeply at this
book
by a prominent U music cognition and
expert and also one of the Breakthrough
founders of our field of computational
Music Theory musicology David
hiron doing so I think would give a good
sense of the majority of what was
contained in the
lecture beyond what uh the candidate
spoke about her own particular
expertise the second guest lecturer
covered the topic of the history of
algorithmic composition from its
Beginnings even before the computer
until today and this lecture
covered the main reading for this week
which is on the iliac
Suite uh the one of the first pieces to
be composed by computers using
algorithms and to generate notes and
continuing up till to today with
advances in AI such as the music
Transformer by Anna Hong at Google and
other uh other new developments one of
the reasons why it's so important to
look
at music algorithmic music composition
in sort of a broader historical scope is
it's too easy to get hung up on the
particular problem that we have today
where we're getting closer and closer to
having the computer produce musical
scores that sound like other
compositions like by particular
composers and to work on that problem
without asking well why why should we
care why do we want the computer to
compose a new piece in the style of
Johan Sebastian Bach unless by chance
you've already heard every piece by Bach
and you're just bored and you need more
which most of us haven't explored what's
actually out
there
instead by looking back at the earliest
history when having a computer actually
write music at that level of
sophistication was so far from being
possible and looking at what people
wanted to do with the computer it helps
to answer questions how can the computer
be used to to come up with ideas or take
ideas that I have that will take too
long for me to generate on my own and
make that part more efficient how can it
be a tool to help me be a better human
composer or just better
human so the class went through some of
the earliest algorithmic compositions
from Guido of areto a monk living in the
11th century through Mozart's musical
dice games up until the ilak suite and
then
beyond some of what's covered in this
class also appears in the various videos
that accompany this class that weren't
shown to students this year but uh are
available for
you and other aspects touched on the
guest speaker particular expertise which
was very valuable to be brought in
anybody else teaching this class would
bring in her his own Specialties that
would be make that class different from
mine and nobody should teach this class
exactly the same way I would teach it or
have taught it so that gives a little
bit of a nutshell of what's happening
the students then went on to write their
own algorithms to to generate
compositions algorithmically and they
did a very good job of avoiding the
problem of trying to get the computer to
do something that we already do better
that we are not interested really in the
computer's
output
and that we just would only want to
listen to if we knew a human created and
instead they went beyond that and
created piece of music that were
interesting in themselves and that no
human would ever choose to
write in addition to the two classes
that job candidates uh covered two other
classes at around this time needed to
be uh removed and the contents pushed
into other classes because MIT was in
the process of
proposing to the full faculty a new
master's program two new Master's
programs in in music technology and
computation and it happened that these
uh proposals had to happen at the same
time as this class and so a little bit
of time was lost on that I'm hoping that
if you've been interested in this class
and want to go forward you might look
into these programs which I assume will
be live at the time that these videos
are
released I think that this is all that
I'm going to be able to provide
especially for the open courseware
audience in this class except at the
very end where I have a little message
for you that I recorded at the time
thank you