[Music]
hello everyone and welcome back to uh
this introductory lecture series for the
data science Challenge and this lecture
is going to cover uh technology so in
the previous lecture you saw um this
introductory material on te- cells and
how they fight cancer and become
exhausted and so what we really need are
Technologies to actually measure the te-
cells characterize what they're doing
and learn how we can change those States
and that's really where the technology
comes in in this lecture what we're
really going to be focusing on to begin
with is measuring a gene expression in
single cells and so this is broken down
into sort of three areas one is
revisiting gene expression programs then
talking about how we're going to measure
those gene expression programs in single
cells and then how we're going to do
perturbations to cells and measure gene
expression programs in those
cells so uh gene expression programs so
to remind you all um genes are um you
know the f Al units of heredity uh in
all organisms and they're passed down to
us from our parents and genes contain
information that specifies um all our
physical traits such as you know our
height or our eye color and also
biological traits such as how we respond
to different diseases and genes are
written in DNA and using this four base
code of AD thyine cytosine and guanine
or ATC and G so in each of our cells uh
genetic information flows from DNA to
RNA to protein so remember our genes are
encoded in DNA and then this DNA can be
copied or transcribed into an RNA
molecule and then that RNA molecule can
be translated into a protein and it's
these proteins that are really giving
the cells the different functional
capacities uh that they have across
these different tissue types and so the
genes and uh which genes are expressed
are controlled by Gene regulation and
Gene regulation is to lead to um
different genes and proteins being
expressed creating this functional
diversity we see across the cells and uh
in gene regulation we have gene
expression programs and these programs
are groups of genes that are expressed
together or turned on together during a
biological process so when a biological
process gets turned on RNA and protein
need to be made so you need more of an
RNA and more of a protein in order to
carry out that process and so that's
this idea of a gene being turned on and
RNA being made and protein translated so
by measuring the levels of RNA we can
learn what genes have been turned on or
off in a cell and that tells us uh what
the cell is really up to so to recap
each cell type and state is encoded by a
different gene expression program
different sets of genes and by measuring
the levels of the RNA we can learn what
genes have been turned on and are
defining that program so now let's
connect what we learned about gene
expression program
to the t- cell states that we uh
previously discussed in the first
introductory lecture so to remind you uh
the t- cell States in in cancer are
going from this progenitor state to this
affector state and finally this terminal
exhausted State and uh these states
differ in their ability to kill uh
cancer cells where the progenitor States
and the affector states are strong at
killing tumor whereas the terminally
exhaust state is very weak at killing
tumors and this this ability kill tumors
is really uh defined by the gene
expression programs in those cell States
so each state has a different gene
expression program and now let's just
look at a few of the genes that Define
uh those gene expression programs for
each t- cell state so for instance in
the progenitor T cells we see a
expression very high expression of this
Gene tcf7 and we know that tcf7 is
important for maintaining the progenitor
t- cell state so when we see High
expression of tcf7 in a Cell uh we know
that that gene expression program is
really defining or kind of indicating to
us that this is a progenitor t- cell
likewise uh in the affector te- cells uh
we see high levels of expression of prf1
um this is a gene that's important for
forming pores On Target cancer cells
that lead to the death of the cancer
cell so that's a gene that we already
know is important for the affector kind
of t- cell killing activity so when we
see high expression of prf1 high
expression meaning High numbers of RNA
molecules we know that that t cell is in
the affector state and then finally we
have the terminal exhausted T Cell state
where we have high expression of the
gene pdcd1 now pdcd1 we've actually seen
before in the previous lecture pdcd1
encodes the protein pd1 and this is a
target of immune checkpoint blockade and
the pdcd1 gene that encodes pd1 it gets
engaged and it leads to the t- cell uh
killing activ being inhibited and so the
cells lose their ability to kill Target
cancer cells so when we see A- celling
the gene pdcd1 at high levels we know
that that's likely a t- cell that's in
the terminal exhausted
state so um this is just these are just
a few of the genes that Define the gene
expression programs for each of the t-
cell States however um in reality gene
expression programs are defined by tens
to hundreds of genes not just two genes
alone so we really need technologies
where we can measure the expression of
genes where we can look at how much RNA
is being made for each gene and
quantitatively measure that and we can
use those measurements to exhaustively
define the gene expression programs for
each of the t- cell States so we'll talk
about what those Technologies are so
that's the first problem we want to
discuss and the second problem is once
we have a good understanding of the gene
expression programs in the in the t-
cell States we would really like to um
perturb these cells and by perturb I
mean apply a genetic change to this t-
cell such that we shift the distribution
of t- cell states to favor progenitor
and affector States however there's many
genetic perturbations that one could
make in te- cells so in our genomes
there are 20,000 genes roughly and in
theory then you could make 20,000
perturbations however that's way too
many to characterize experimentally in
the lab so we need to think of how we uh
tackle such a problem
[Music]