you ask AI to show you a vision of a
sustainable future where materials and
energy flows are balanced this is an example
of what you get I specified Boston and you can
tell because if you notice on the road there are
cars driving in opposite directions in the in the
same path with human bikers so so we know it's
authentic but what jumps out to you about this
image is the greenery covering every building
absorbing carbon dioxide from the atmosphere we
never see this even though it's kind of consistent
with every image we've ever seen about the future
of sustainable cities and sustainable human life
what's notably absent are solar panels solar
panels which are typically vast arrays that I used
to dream about as a high school student wishing
to come to MIT and finding those solar panels on
the side of the highways in my drive many of you
probably passed those on your way here today that
Vision has become reality but I'm going to tell
you in a few minutes that it's actually breaking
some of our sustainability systems goals we want
our solar panels to be embedded in the material
infrastructure and if you take nothing else home
from this image is that we're actually very far
from changing the way that we manage our energy
and materials flows there is a huge materials
burden associated with the transition to a more
sustainable economy um and that brings major
challenges that were poised to advance if we're
going to meet the 2040 sustainable energy goals we
need to extract four times the amount of material
we have ever extracted on planet Earth this is ex
exclusive of our steel and concrete needs this is
just copper and manganese Cobalt and base metals
that we're trying to use largely for our energy
infrastructure our grid distribution and our
Batteries Now the unfortunate reality is that
in order to get those Metals out of the ground
we need to build mines on this scale this is the
grasberg mine it's on the order of 2,000 m across
and over 500 M deep those Road cuts that you see
the lines on the inside of the cavern those are
driven on by tractors whose tires are three or
four times as tall as I am now any of you who's
ever tried to power something with a battery knows
that there's no battery on planet Earth that gets
you to the bottom of this mine and back out with
a load of or on it you'd run dead in the first
leg that beholden you to fossil fuel only fossil
fuel gets you to the bottom of this pit and back
out and it's that precise problem and related ones
that means that all of our renewable energy goals
tie us to carbon dioxide emissions we are beholden
to carbon dioxide emissions until we rethink
this problem and we rethink our materials demands
associated with energy and energy production you
can see this into intergovernmental panel for
climate changes predictions for our carbon dioxide
emissions that r line is the most likely scenario
with the orange um drip lines around it projecting
the uncertainty but what you notice is that we're
actually not going to be very successful at
decarbonizing and in fact meeting these two
degre c curves requires that we be pulling carbon
dioxide out of the atmosphere and at astronomical
scale so if you note that green line that's the 2°
C scenario um actually requires us to be removing
on the order of 13 billion metric tons of carbon
dioxide annually by 2050 now 13 billion metric
tons is larger than the coal and oil and gas
Industries combined and they had 200 years to
do it we've got to start doing this within the
next couple of decades it's an astronomically
different approach to doing things in addition to
decarbonizing our energy source and fortunately
for you there are some great innovators today who
are going to tell us a few of the strategies that
we can get to do this first you're going to hear
about dematerializing our energy production it's a
really exciting Innovation out of blad bullit's
lab so you'll finally get to hear him talk to
you about his science and engineering Innovations
then we're going to hear from Antoine alinor about
how to more sustainably use the materials that we
have already extracted let's not dig those pits or
let's dig them in fundamentally different ways so
that we can be more efficient about our materials
processing and finally you'll hear from Rafa
Gomez bombelli Who's going to tell you a little
bit about how we might use advances in artificial
intelligence to better design materials a priori
and I'm hoping he'll tell you a little bit about
the work he's been doing in carbon dioxide removal
material Innovation which as I mentioned is
critically needed to spawn an industry that
doesn't exist within decades now how many of you
have been able to see this beautiful piece of land
behind the MIT Nano building okay a few of you
but not enough later today when you're walking
around campus go behind the MIT Nano building
and you'll find this beautiful um piece of land
that used to be the MIT junkyard you'd go there if
you wanted to find bits of an engine which we all
do we go different places for that now um this is
named uh kindly by Vlad as the improbability walk
it's named in honor of Millie dressle house the
queen of carbon Nano science and there are two
reasons for that name one is that Millie used to
U Mentor her students on walks she was known as a
as a great and supportive mentor and she would
take them on walks during these discussions so
this walk is specifically for that practice and
for that reflection second improbability because
Millie used to say that her journey to being MIT
Professor was as improbable a journey as any other
she was the daughter of Polish immigrants who grew
up in the Bronx and made her way to be Institute
professor at MIT one of the first winners of the
national medal of Science and many others uh we
were fortunate to learn from her now the reason
that I this up here is that that challenge that
I just described to you is improbable but it's not
impossible and I'm excited today to welcome Vlad
bovich Antoine alinor and Rafa Gomez bombelli
to the stage to hear the next few talks which
we'll discuss after thank you all right um
it's indeed a big challenge to figure out
how to decarbonize the planet um in so many ways
one way to provide you energy is to drill a hole
pull the oil out of the well and burn it and
if you do that you can use every molecule that
you extract and from it gain about two three four
electron volts of energy per molecule once as you
turn it into carbon dioxide and consequently start
causing issues for the planet what we have thought
of is to ask another question what if I can take
that molecule I have extracted in the form of oil
out of the ground and what if that molecule can
over and over and over again very say molecule
give me the energy I need how would that work
well it would work if you take that molecule
and actually incorporate it as a tin film that you
do not burn but because it happens to be very dark
meaning it absorbs light very efficiently it can
be used inside a solar structure layer an active
layer of a solar cell every molecule we right now
burn in our gasoline engines could be turned into
a solar molecule and if such that film of oilbased
material can absorb a photon and give you one to
two electron volts of energy not once not twice
but millions of times and the only reason why
it would stop is because there is a probability
that eventually after a million times of exciting
and pulling out the charge out of that molecule
you will eventually break a bond and that Bond
consequently will cause that particular molecule
not to be quite as effective as it used to be in
making the sunlight turned into electricity
carbon based materials that we extract right
now and we do not need to add additional ones
could be turned today into carbon based solar
structures and indeed if you look at those solar
structures there is an opportunity to ask well
what should those solar structures sit on well
how about carbon how about carbon-based Fabrics
that again can be extruded made out of that very
same oil the same petrochemicals that you right
now spend once pull them out burn them you're
done with them right now today if we change the
Paradigm the value of every one of those molecules
goes up by a factor of a few million because every
one of them can be that much more effective in
actually making an active structure that could
never be previously done the goal what I want to
show you in the next few slides is indeed examples
of doing just that here's a picture of a solar
cell here is a solar cell that's in that picture
it's a piece of fabric that happens to have
electrodes on it active layers on it and if you
apply two electrodes here and here and C you know
connect it to something while Shining Light on it
you will indeed generate electricity it changes
the Paradigm of what a solar cell could be and
as a result reshapes the way we think of how to
deploy such solar cells it turns out that the cost
of a solar electricity is not in the cost of the
solar panel that's the cheapest part of the system
what cost you two-thirds of the money sometimes
more is installing that particular system on
your roof wiring it ensuring it's electrically
safe because all of it is done in the field by
a person who needs to climb on a roof and wire
or electrically connect without Burning Down The
House the set of panels if all of that can be done
in a factory where you start with a fabric you add
to it some solar material and make it as big as
you want you need not need to wire it anymore all
you need to do is climb on the roof staple it to
the roof and through that generate a Deployable
solar cell that simply plugs into your home it
could change a paradigm quite significantly the
other part of it is is we have enough installers
to actually install all the solar cells that we
want today if I gave you all the solar cells
the world needs to power itself today how long
would it take us to actually install them and
deploy them the answer is a very very long time
simply the amount of electricians and those who
need to pour concrete and put aluminum framing
on your roof that's a huge amount of extra
work that we simply don't have the labor for
If instead I can make you the laborer because you
went to Home Depot got yourself a carpet unrolled
it on your roof stapled it and plugged it on
the side of the house dramatically increases
the number of Labor Force we have to deploy and
provide the solar deployment in the way we want it
but the key to it is no wiring needed on your roof
the key to it is unrolling a very light format
solar structure and indeed that is the vision that
we aimed for the Silicon solar c as we know it has
looked like it looks today since 1970s essentially
since it was invented the ones that were installed
on the roof of Jimmy Carter's White House looked
pretty much the same as the ones that you can buy
today and install on your own roof that is not
progress that is simply making technology better
and better by efficiency but the efficiency will
not give us the cost reductions that we need it
will give us a little bit we are at about 20%
efficient cells we might be able to one day
get 25 30% efficient cells commercially available
one and a half time Improvement or you can reduce
the weight 100 times and consequently avoid the
wiring avoid installation cost dramatically and
through that reduce the cost of what would
it take to truly make an active structure
that could be Deployable starting back in 2011
we worked with Professor Karen gleon in chemical
engineering to use her chemically deposited
calent bonded polymers conductive ones on top
of pieces of paper to serve as a substrate on top
of which to re evaporated carbon based molecules
similar to the ones that are in your cell phones
and are used for your organic LED displays oh and
by the way oleds have been now around for 20
years they've been commercially utilized for
over a decade they are stable they can be used for
million hours it turns out halflife carbon based
solar materials can be similarly stable even
more stable and should be able to be used for
even longer time it's easier to make a solar
cell than a display and yet we make displays
readily why do I say it's easier to make a solar
cell well because displays everyone looks at
and you want every one of your pixels to work for
a solar cell if I have a pixel or two section that
doesn't quite work no one notices the yields are a
lot more tolerant to actual large area deployment
and hence imagining ways of deploying them through
high throughput manufacturing unrolling them like
this or at MIT Nano here's a coating of a thin
film of material these are not carbon based the
ones I'm showing you print here although this can
be carbon based as well these are so called per
guides also an extremely inexpensive readily
available material these are options right in
thinking how do we redefine what solar technology
looks like and we have asked questions and what
would be the ultimate reduction in weight one
can imagine we made back few years back an a
solar cell that is so light that it can sit on top
of a soap bubble six watts per gram of solar cell
that's remarkable amount of energy production with
one little caveat which is it's only two microns
thick as a device and hence if you pick it up and
you don't handle it very nicely you'll break it so
we've realized well maybe that technology though
can be added onto a piece of fabric after all my
shirt doesn't rip very easily and if I add to it
a solar cell that solar cell would be protected by
the fabric underneath and yet fabric is light
and breathable and so we came up with this a
method by which we can peel off a three Micron
substrate off of a piece of plastic why do we
start with a piece of plastic I need something
to grow my extremely thin solar cell that will
sit on these three microns on top of and so you
can imagine chemically Vapor depositing the three
Micron substrate adding to it the active layers
the bottom electrodes the top electrodes and then
transferring that onto a piece of fabric gluing
it with another four microns of glue to make an
active structure that when you shine light on you
will be able to get a dramatic amount of power
out of it as needed after all at the end you will
make a structure that weighs about 1 gram and is
about 50 microns in thickness about the thickness
of a human hair all for the sake of deployment
being extremely rapid and you utilization of
materials being extremely reduced but keeping
the part that matters the part that will absorb
light and give you the electricity you need thank
you ask my colleague Elenor to join us next
all right it's a pleasure to be here today
um I'm going to talk very very quickly in 11
minutes about a adventure that started 4 4,000
years ago uh that is about Metallurgy that is
about in that case copper and precious metal
recycling or recovery um and I'm going to try to
convey the idea that we perhaps need to change
the chemical basis of our ability to recycle and
extract Metals in the context that was very well
presented before by desire um something you may
not know if you are a producer producer or user
of silver nickel manganese Cobalt Platinum um the
recycling of those elements that are very you very
heavily used in modern Electronics um is actually
completely tied to primary production the tide
might be on the price point because you're always
competing with the price point of primary precious
metal production but also comes in the recycling
today the main facility that's going to recycle
your electronic waste will end up being a copper
smelter if you don't have copper smelter in your
country you're going to have a hard time recycling
electronic waste because the most of the value in
the electronic waste are the copper and the silver
now don't worry about the chart here it's just
designed to be very impressive uh it's showing the
amount of energy that is going on to recycle the
silver that is coming from your electronic waste
you can see how long it takes for the silver to
come out of that supply chain and even when it
comes out it usually comes out with gold a little
bit of selenium and torium which means you need
now to invest in another facility which economy
depends on the four elements that I just mentioned
now don't worry none of you are doing this most
of the time you're shipping it abroad and you're
waiting for somebody else to do that but of course
the amount of energy and environmental impact
of each of the box that you see here is actually
responsible for some of the sustainability
challenge that you've heard in the introduction
now um in my group and many people around here
at MIT including with the climate project are
trying to think about using electricity with the
assumptions that electricity can be made without
greenhouse gases emission and with a mitigated
environmental impact now if this is the case right
if electricity is cleaning off and of course its
price is good enough then most likely all of the
materials challenges that we're talking about will
be handled by electrochemistry and electrolysis
now here is an example of a large scale 60 million
tons per year electrolysis a manufacturing process
which makes aluminum yes the aluminum you're
using today is made 100% by electrolysis and
yet it cost I think $2 per kilogram so we
know that using electricity at large scale
for materials extraction and separation is cost
effective and it's supporting the economy and
Society we live in now there are few technical
details on that slide um is the fact that you
don't want to separate the two compartments
of your electrolysis reactor you may have done
water electrolysis if you have not done so it's
pretty straightforward to do in your own kitchen
if you want but if you do water electrolysis
you know you have an anodic product you see the
oxygen gas coming out and then you see the famous
hydrogen you know the expensive hydrogen coming
on the other electrode and these two things
have to happen but if you have a separator in
the middle you have to pay for the energy cost of
going through the separator and immediately this
is not cost effective for most of the commodity
metal production now there are other factors that
are chemistry related there are factors related
to manufacturing this needs to be a continuous
process you need to constantly purchase electrical
power and dissipate that electrical power
as current in order to make the metal or recycled
and get your metal back now there is a wisdom in
electrochemistry and electrolysis at scale which
says you should not do any pre-treatment to your
feet stock that is something where there are
discussions aluminum has the Bayer process
which transforms boide into pure alumina aluminum
oxide this aluminize 99.99% aluminum oxide right
so that's a lot of pre-treatment that allows this
technology to work how to do that is what I want
to share with you today for other methods what
we're doing in the lab is using Earth so geology
shows us that for example if you look in the
Earth crust where you have copper and the precious
metals you have a natural separation between the
oxide and the sulfides this separation between the
oxides and the sulfides allows you to get today
your ore to get copper for example this is an
example here you may remember remember from high
school the pyite calop pyite which is goldish and
at the bottom you see the silicate which is quartz
which is basically youran component so we know by
Nature that if you achieve certain conditions you
can separate chemically the precious and valuable
Metals copper iron and sulfides versus deoxide
now once you do that your entire chemistry is
upside down again I'm not going to dwell too much
on this but this is telling you that everything
you know about ox side chemistry or waterbased
chemistry is completely upside down once you
do sulfide and sulfur based chemistry so that's
that's the graph on the right here where you see
that uranium is now very easy to make silver is
much easier than copper iron is easier than copper
and so on and so forth and that's what we've done
in the lab in the lab we've basically developed
a technique to transform any feed stock either
a mix of ew or perhaps certain alloid or even
minerals or waste from existing facility and
we're basically substituting the sulfur with
the oxygen so that we can then use this
separation that I discussed before now
we've done this here for the battery material
you may know that the nickel manganese Cobalt
batteries are oxides and there is a challenge
to try to recover the lithium versus the Cobalt
and the rest of it it depends on the market
value and here we've shown that we can use
sulfur to selectively Target the nickel and
the Cobalt and leave behind the manganese and
the lithium as salt that you can dissolve and
we do that using sulfur and the processes that
you're showing that is shown here now how do
you now recover the Yellow Part which is the
sulfide versus the Pink part you can use for
example physical separation now suddenly we go
back to the very small scale perhaps even nanoc
scale interaction to figure out in what condition
can you liberate the sulfides with the valuable
Metals versus the non valuable oxides or sulfates
once you've done that you have to go toward
the metal you have to do electrolysis we have
developed a unique technology molten sulfide
electrolyses where no oxygen is involved in the
system what you get at the anode the positive
electrode is the sulfur yes the same sulfur
from the previous slide which we paid for is now
recovered by electrolysis while in the meantime
at the cathode that's the bottom electrode that
you see here we are making the liquid copper but
we've also done it for other elements like ranium
and um and and all of the precious metals above
copper this is an illustration of the recovery
of the elemental sulfur so it can of become a
material circularity problem we are initially
consuming sulfur to get rid of the oxygen but
at some point we can regenerate some of those
sulfur by electrolysis and you can recognize
your your famous yellow material that is
this Elemental sulfur now we heard about
scaling up how to do that at bigger scale uh
we've been fortunate to do that with support
of the federal government here is a 5 kgr
per day capacity reactor where we can do
any transformation of a mix into sulfides
so example of utilization include the rare
earth you may have heard about the magnet big
problem how we're going to get the rare earth
we can separate them and sidiz them on the on
the right reactor and then on the left reactor
we have the electris cell where we make metals
from sulfide at a scale of about 2 kg per day
capacity now here is a picture of the outcome
of the electrolysis at 300 G per hour scale
you can see the liquid Copper at the bottom on
the top you have the sulfide electrolyte and
we have shown that this concept can be applied
for the selective recovery of anything that is
less stable than copper again this is important
in the context of silver or gold recovery but
also MIP denum uranium and perhaps The Rare
Earth because now we can selectively design
the process such that we recover first the
most precious and valuable metals and then
we go after the copper and then perhaps we
go after the iron now we are trying at MIT
in order to really demonstrate the viability of
this we are trying to build a ton one ton 1,000
kilogram scale capability I think you follow the
track right we start at you know 10 milligrams
we do one gram we do 10 gram we do 100 grams the
typical path forward is to do a startup after that
you can talk to me about this experience I've
done it for 15 years now we've decided that we
should go to the Thousand kilogram first before
we can really t and collaborate further with the
with the market of Finance so with this you have
my contact here and I'll be happy to stay later
to answer any any questions thank you for your
[Applause] attention I I this I used to have a
question here but you know if you have a question
as a title then the answer is no so I have my
answers AI for chemistry and materials we're
getting there um and I think I don't need you
know Des that was that was a killer introduction
I I really loved it um so I don't need to say
it again sustainability and decarbonization go
through new materials Technologies and you've seen
it takes decades since something works in the lab
it's like oh this work this idea has legs until
it makes it to Market and it's used by millions
of people takes approximately 20 years so when
we look at the 2050 objectives they're actually
the 2030 objectives because we need kind of need
to lock in a lot of the science 20 years ahead of
of scaling it up um and at the same time we've all
experienced something that's been transformational
in our day-to-day lives at sort of you know five
to 10 year scale like it's been 10 years in
alphago right like I don't know if you were a go
player this this whole world blew up and it hasn't
been 10 years it's been barely 10 years since then
um and then over the last three to four we've seen
image generation right we thought you needed to be
sort of artistically talented Ed to produce some
images turns out the distribution of images was
surprisingly easy to learn right a computer could
learn how an image looks like from a text prompt
in a way that was completely unexpected five 10
years ago and then there's been this big big win
in the Sciences with Alpha fall I mean we've seen
it right two Nobel prizes in The Sciences went to
AI one sort of to the AI technology in general
and one to AI for protein exu prediction right
and then you know if you're a scientist I am
never writing a cover letter again I'm going
to just ch GPT you know I've got my uh this is
a high temperature super conductor an impossible
thing maybe I've got my cover letter prepared
uh to send to a journal if we ever discover this
thing so what does this mean for materials right
like you've heard it we need materials how how do
we get these tools and point them to the sort of
societal systemic challenges that that are ahead
of of us and um this could look like batteries
this could look like electrolyzers this could
look like renewable Plastics this could look like
decarbonization Technologies um what's different
what's the same we're never going to have the same
amounts of data right there is no way this the
models the foundational models that we have access
to today have been trained on all of the internet
all of the text and all of the images that were
ever taken even if they were copyrighted we we'
already run out of data for for those models in
The Sciences we don't have access to that scale of
data and that's typically Silo you know Dow data
is not going to be accessible to me uh if I work
at dupon anymore right so all all this subtlety
about data is very pervasive and I would postulate
that we kind of know the rules of the game and and
in the case of you know Professor Alor you just
saw thermodynamics that's written in in in stone
right like compared to that the rest of physics
is stamp collecting in the words of rather for so
how do we exploit that right such that when we do
AI on chemistry and materials we get to exploit
this sort of fundamental understanding of the
rules and uh there's one more ler it's like okay
somehow we need to coule our ability to evaluate
hypothesis right like AI you know you ask CH GPT
you know when I drop an apple do you think it will
go down or up and it can give you a sense of what
he thinks it will happen in the Sciences that's
half of the job right coming up with a hypothesis
is half of the job that happens virtually and then
you need to test the hypothesis and that needs
to happen in the real world right experiments
need to be done data needs to be collected to
inform your understanding of the world the way
we traditionally do experiments is not the the
most helpful way for the AI Paradigm to thrive
and this is what we saw the big win Alpha fall
protein structure prediction that was predicated
on a carefully curated data set of 100,000 protein
structures or 200,000 protein structures that have
taken decades and and sort of tens of millions
of dollars to collect so when the data is there
AI can definitely shine but typically we need
sort of these more data intensive pipelines that
produce hundreds of experiments and and explore
um millions of parameters search spaces and again
how do we miss how do match that with the kind
of conversation that Professor L was saying 100
gr you know a ton a thousand tons how do how
would we interplate that with the creativity
and scale of AI so I would say things that are
ready to go that are happening today if you have
structured Property Data Machan model has changed
how we go from the structure of a material or the
structure of a protein you're going to he about
nanom medicines this has completely changed over
the last 5 to 10 years and one of the reasons
is like AI Works in that space structur property
relationships are functions that machine learning
can totally totally learn so given enough data
what is enough data it's probably more than
a thousand data points right if I have more
than a thousand pairs of this x goes to this y a
machine learning model can do it for molecules for
crystals or or for proteins as we've seen AI can
predict how to make stuffff right that's that's
kind of very important too because it's not enough
to say well this material could have very good
properties based on the model I just train now I
need to know how to make it um and making is a you
know an interplay of thermodynamics and physics
driven driving forces and uh recipes and uh
cooking in a way that that's very datadriven so AI
can go read the papers process the literature and
learn how to predict the synthesis of something
from precursors that are commercially available
through a series of steps this can be molecules
or materials there is enough evidence out there
that you can have an AI process the literature and
like a student learn how to propose new synthesis
for a material based on the synthesis of similar
materials that have made before and lately with
the with the outcome of uh of large language
models we've seen this orchestration of pieces
this coming and going has become a lot more
smooth right so we can have an AI that has a
piece has an agent that reads papers I have an
agent that um runs a physics based calculation
to get some thermodynamic parameters that may
be very important and has another agent that
goes and produces a synthesis plan and maybe has
an agent that interfaces an instrument and takes
a measurement so we've seen these orchestration
papers um and these stration examples come up as
as things that AI can do for us and uh something
that is very dear to me and relates to the sort
of astronaut on a horse riding on the moon is
that AI can propose new designs right that's
called inverse design that's called generative AI
um this has been demonstrated for molecules this
has been demonstrated for proteins I don't know if
you've heard but there is a protein design company
they raised a billion dollar a series meaning that
you know some people are are willing to put their
money where their mouth is in in protein design
and it's work to for molecular for Atomic crystals
like how do we arrange atoms to make a material
that does something what has not happened quite
yet well AI doesn't do anything in the physical
world someone needs to do something at a milligram
at a gram at a kilogram at a ton scale this this
hasn't happened yet yet right the connection of AI
with this very meaningful technological transition
hasn't occurred right AI cannot convince human
beings to change what they're doing AI cannot
physically act upon the world yet so if we want
that to happen there's a next layer of value
creation very much along the lines that that
uh Professor Alor mention in their own in their
own work and then AI doesn't have any context we
typically train from a inputs to produce B outputs
all this context of our competitors are already
doing that this is you know somebody else has
this patent we cannot trust the supply chain for
selenium in our own processes all those things
would need to be put into the model explicitly
right AI cannot decide what's important AI doesn't
have a context for how the world Works in general
so because um I got about a minute left I would
say we've done the uh the beauty of AI tools
and computation is that very agnostic so these
are things that can be deployed systematically
across materials classes and applications so
this is uh CO2 capture so can we do better than
current Technologies this is this gray band is
how strongly current molecules bind to CO2 this
is good enough for flu gas because there is so
much CO2 that you know being okay at binding is
enough you capture most of it because it's very
concentrated if you want to do direct a capture
you need to bind more strongly than the current
molecules for the economics of of carbon capture
to be effective so of all the molecules an AI
could dream which are the ones that kind of make
sense well we need to be more strong than this
gray bars well it turns out this family don't work
this families work and before we make a single
compound we have a sense for like what's even
doable what's even possible now which of these are
expensive enough well that's another layer of uh
of computation I got 10 second left so I would
just say this is a material class that Professor
Plata and I both like zeolites they're used for
cracking they're used for Doo if you drive a
diesel car same game we can use AI to explore
the combinatorial space of how to make them
uh and with this I will thank our sponsors thanks
the team and thank you so much folks for for your
time right up to the stage andan and VD please
join us on stage for a conversation um we have
about 15 minutes I believe before the the end
of the session um I like to say that there are
many high privileges of being an MIT Professor
um being able to train some of the best students
in the world uh being able to get other MIT
professors to talk to me um and of course
interacting with people like you who are advancing
the frontiers of Science and Technology in your
day-to-day lives we are really excited to engage
with you this morning we welcome your questions
and the discussion um and and we'll go ahead and
jump right in so I'll be keeping an eye on the
audience for for any questions um from the room
but I also have a few myself and um it's hard to
know where to start actually you all um had such
lovely context to share I think um I'm going to
start at the top uh Vlad I find it interesting
that you rely so heavily on carbon structures is
unsurprising Right giving the focus of your work
um human life also evolved to use car structures
in in so many differential ways um what is your
sense of this term decarbonization and how do you
kind of think differently about about this and and
what we actually need to be doing to refocus our
efforts well U I'll start by simply saying one
thing I really wish I told you at the beginning
uh on the side screens there is a QR code you
can scan it and you can type your questions and
then the questions would also appear for us for
the sessions and sessions to come pigeon hole is
the method by which we can also get additional
questions no literally right in front of me no I
wish I have actually repeated it my apologies for
not doing that to ask you a questionary and it is
incredible to me to recognize that we do have the
abundance of carbon and yet the only way we use it
is either to eat it to make ourselves or to burn
it um and in the electronics domains uh Millie
dressle house was one of the Pioneers who have
instructed us that if carbon takes certain forms
it can actually give you electrical performance
Optical performance that we couldn't have expected
uh or at least we were not spending enough time
on um the field of organic Electronics as first
pioneered through the Practical use of A40 billion
old olet industry really validated that uh there
are more active electronic surfaces in a form
of carbon based organic LEDs than of any other
material out there silicon backplane maybe is the
only other one that you can claim is there but
there is more more amorphous organic being laid
down than crystalline silicons has been laid down
area wise and that gives us an opportunity to
ask well for devices that do work on electronic
principles but don't require an extreme speed is
it possible to utilize carbon based materials to
do what they do best which is absorb light and
then from there on convert that light into slow
moving slowish moving electricity but plenty fast
to be able to be utilized for everyday use um I am
very excited about carbon I do think that anything
that's in the Earth's crust today easy to reach is
the material we should touch and hence address
your question on are we going to be in this
Perpetual catch22 of needing to and spend a lot
more energy to decarbonize the planet as we want
it yes thank you um I failed to point out earlier
that uh Vlad is a founder of three companies uh
Antoine I think I think is on the verge or or I
don't know are we allowed to say um and um but
also worked in industry and for a mining industry
before coming returning to MIT as did Rafa so the
reason that I point that out is that these are
folks who consider real constraints of of Economic
and um and application space so feel free to push
hard on them as you're formulating your questions
because they can handle it um many professors
live in the distant future we try to live in the
the near-term impact of as well as imagining and
ideating that future so uh to that point I want to
bring up the concept of biom materials momentarily
so Rafa nicely highlighted the advances that
have been made in understanding predicting and
describing protein folding structures you know
when I think about my bones and I think about what
this building is made of and my skin and what my
fabric is made of again all formulations of carbon
and carbon storage what is limiting manufacturer
as you showed in some of your videos from being
able to access the WID space of biomaterials and
and all of you might have something to to add
to this question so maybe Rafa I'll start with
you yeah I mean I think the design space of biom
materials is has been proven sort of completely
expressive right there's lots of things the same
building blocks can be put together to make sort
of functional enzymes and collagen right so
we can get mechanical properties we can get
electronic properties we can get catalysis out of
biomaterials right the most effective electroly
um is the photosystem too it's an enzyme so I
would say the language of biomaterials can express
lots of function including structure the thing
that's missing is that we don't have economic
control of atomic Arrangements in the way nature
does right the cost of making proteins the cost
of making this highly engineer Nano structures
the way life does is uh is just very high so as
of right now you can make medicines mostly right
because medicines can have sort of higher costs
there is there's a lot of price that one can put
into a medicine um but many other applications
are limited not by the potential of biomaterials
but by the cost structures and I think there is
a lot of room over there to sort of industrialize
um synthetic biology and biomaterials in general
it's it's more I think the the potentials there
the execution I think will need a will need
technology that that doesn't exist today
yeah thank you and could you just comment
briefly on the role of robots you mentioned
you know AI can't actually go and do in the
physical world do you see robots as being able
to tackle this challenge yes so this is this is
a great question because theoretically there
is no reason why armies of grad students and
technicians couldn't embody AI you could imagine
just like you know there was a guy moving the
chess pces H when the AI suggests chess moves
uh we could do that for the sciences and have
armies of students doing things in The Labb turns
out that's not how humans like to work right with
we expect the AI Revolution for AI to do the
minial tasks and us keep doing the more abstracted
tasks not the other way around um and then human
reproducibility you know when when you're doing
sort of all these repeated laborious intensive
experiments um reproducibility is an issue and in
these two things robots are tireless right they
they will operate consistently they won't lose
motivations for instance negative data is very
depressing you do experiments nothing works that's
very depressing to a human being it's critical
to have negative data to to train models um so
in that sense uh the ability of robots to like I
said work tirelessly and extremely reproducibly
even if they're not faster than humans the
tolerances are much much better than human
reproducibility right we've seen I'm sure you've
seen examples in your labs when two students you
know one of them I don't know keeps the blinds
open one of then keeps the blinds closed and the
results don't line up for weeks until somebody
realizes if everything's put into a repeatable
process with a robot so I think that's what a lot
of these sort of AI power science will most likely
be enabled by or or cycled through Automation in
the lab yeah thank you um I I want to just move uh
right before we jump into the questions from the
audience Antoine I wanted to ask about scale and
so it's really clear to see how you know robots
and AI help us accelerate Discovery and augment
our own capab abilities um I I I really like the
line that you used I think it was you know we go
to the Earth and we learn from the earth um when
we talk about planetary scale that is needed here
uh just to put it into perspective people I just
want to throw some numbers out there the the whole
Plastics economy is around 400 million metric
tons we think of that as a big huge um term that
is small compared to the 51 billion metric tons
of carbon dioxide emissions and that is small
compared to the reservoir of carbon that is in
the atmosphere on the order of 800 uh billion
metric tons what you're doing with materials
processing has to be done at enormous scale I
just wanted to give you a moment to to comment on
what the next steps are it's you know you said ton
scale ton per what unit time and and what's the
timeline um to getting to kind of meeting some
important fraction of human material needs yeah
this this is an important question so the the
Paradigm that are out there for metal extraction
today are based mostly on carbon hydrocarbon
and gas solid reactions mostly and these things
we can do them at very large scale like a blast
furnace and all these high scale reactor if we're
thinking about electrochemical methods we might
rethink a little bit the logic of high volume
because electrochemistry is a Surface phenomena
and as such you would imagine developing reactors
unit reactors which one of them would make make
maybe 10,000 ton per year so it's like two order
of magnitude smaller than the existing operation
but you would multiply them very much like a solar
array of of solar generation is a multiple of cell
put next to each other we have to do the same
thing but I think the scale has to be you know
thousand times bigger than the bonus scale you
can do for sale for solar generation for example
so that's the Hope right now is we're discovering
that in order to allow companies to be comfortable
with those Technologies you need to show them
like a module in a mod modle that is operating
continuously for several days and weeks and
months so that we can achieve what we heard about
manufacturing because ultimately materials and
metals production is a manufacturing process as
well the metal that is coming out as very unique
structure chemical composition and even physical
features that if you don't achieve this you're
not making steel or you're not making copper yeah
yeah and I just want to highlight there these area
requirements and volumetric requirements are enorm
because of the surface area requirements of
electrochemistry this is where nanomaterials
are incredibly exciting because you can take
surface large surface areas and Shrink them
down you know to to the size of a coffee cup and
hold them in your hand as Vlad nicely showed us so
there's a unique role I think for nanomaterials
to enable novel electrochemical cell deployment
um and then the rest is is just multiplication
so we can handle that all right um there's some
very exciting uh uh questions uh coming down the
line uh and and there's a hand in the room but
I I want to make sure we have time to address
this one that has a lot of votes um Hanuman are
you in the room who submitted the would you mind
reading your question sure I guess the question I
guess had to do with with AI data access you had
mentioned that it's currently accessed everything
on the public available internet but you said
there's Silo data by individual companies but
uh I can see that there's a disincentivize for
those companies to just all of a sudden give
everybody access to their data how can we expand
that access while still maintaining IP well it
it's a extremely timely problem and actually
for instance we've come back with Publishers
Publishers used to be okay with automated access
to their papers to their scientific literature
and they're now holding it close to their chest
so we kind of moved in the wrong direction with
Publishers because they realize there's a lot of
potential value that maybe they don't know how to
capture but somebody else could so we've gone a
little bit in the wrong direction with scientific
literature over the last two years there's
good examples in drag discovery particularly
some some consortia in Europe where things are a
little bit more toped down sometimes um and using
tools um what's called homomorphic encryption
which are computational tools this is an area
of research of computational tools that allow you
to still train machine learning models but on an
encrypted data that can't be decoded back to the
actual molecular structure that you're protecting
right so everybody could train on sort of this
Federated data sets but uh the models people don't
have visibility to the actual sort of data because
it's been encrypted in a way that still allows you
to do machine learning but doesn't allow you to
know what the what the data is so there are some
examples around you know Federated learning ER
consorti potentially pre-competitive research and
homomorphic encryption but this is a place where
sort of policy and uh economic interests of the
companies are are sort of aligning right now there
is no solve problem it's not just a technical
problem uh and it's been worked out there is no
singular answer yeah I F that back on everyone in
the room to take that one home with them and it's
a really it's a really great question and start
to think differently remember how crazy we all
thought Jeff Bezos was when he was going to ship
us all our stuff for a hundred bucks a year and we
thought this man's going to lose money but he got
us all hooked on that right what can come by by
liberating data um there's probably a lot to be
had there okay so when uh I'm gonna a question
to Vlad deployment cost of solar panels driven
by install rather than manufacturing what part
of that is physical install versus electrical
safety um and as your solution mitigates the
physical cost it's it's a great question I I
guess I would answer it in U parabs I'm going to
give you just a few examples to kind of consider
one of them is the cost of a prefabricated home is
half the cost of a home you built on site you can
say a lot of money by asking to build yourself a
prefab um why is that because of everything that
needs to be done to make things just right is so
much easier being done inside the factory than
outside the factory result of it is that rather
than installing your solar cells on your roof and
wiring them on your roof pre-wiring them prior to
deployment would be particularly powerful but the
only problem is that today's panels weigh 25 kilos
50 pounds a piece 50 pounds is the limit of what
a laborer should be asked to lift and as a result
we limit ourselves to that size one by 2 m not 20
by 10 m that we could do if we could reduce
the weight of the solar cell dramatically so
the opportunity in redesigning the deployment
would be dramatic second part is it turns out
that everything in the world cost just about the
same per kilo now that's a very strong statement
and of course you can always come up with a way
to challenge me on it I'd love to have longer
discussions on it but the cost of items depends
on the number of synthetic steps that you go
through if you need to synthesize a very complex
molecule that's going to be a very expensive one
because it's going to take many synthetic steps
and indeed the cost of objects scales with a
number of synthetic steps avoiding the amount of
matter you need to use will reduce your costs as
well so combine the installation Paradigm uh when
it comes to prefab versus not combine it with the
reduction of cost and what's the right number to
State in the overall reduction well I'll wave my
hands and say it's going to be three times cheaper
to install a solar cell if it's light uh compared
to the way we do it right now am I correct on
that number it very much depends on a whole
bunch of details but I know that I'll need to use
a lot less aluminum in order to reinforce my home
and I'll be able to use a lot less concrete
to prevent wind from blowing my solar cells
away because that's the other thing we fight with
the solar installation plus I'm going to open up
areas we right now cannot which is Warehouse roofs
that are not loadbearing and capable of carrying
silicon solar cells but certainly would be
available in millions of Acres quantities to take
on extremely lightweight cells thank you other
I saw a hand in the audience yes please andur
so so is there any way to find
out I so yeah I mean we're back to the sort of
Nano level control that life has over matter
that we can you can barely replicate so I would
say that's because every cell is much smaller and
energy efficient than individual pieces of a chip
right like I think it's we're going back to the
sort of atomic control that nature has over
is that that we don't necessarily have over
manufacturing I think it's it's another side
of the same coin I I I guess I would you know
you're asking a very deep question that could
be answered in a number of different ways we
certainly do not operate our brains at the speed
that the chips operate their brains that we also
happen to have a cooling system in the form of
liquid that computers don't and have avoided it
to avoid shorts uh but that would also speed us up
and reduce the amount of energy needed there are
solutions that indeed we are working towards and
our colleagues at Lincoln laboratory later today
will tell you a few stories on how to speed up
and reduce the energy of computation AI requires
a tremendous amount of energy because we choose to
use the cloud we are choosing to spend a lot more
energy than we should right because every time
that you send something to the cloud and receive
it back you're using so many more turnovers of
chips than it would if you just happen to do
all the work on your local computer your phone so
there are choices we are making right now to live
the lifestyle we do that correlates to the excess
energy consumption we have but we also wish for
Chad GPT to write our uh introductory letters and
if we stopped wishing that yeah we use less energy
but we'll be less productive so energy is needed
for the productivity gains that Society wishes uh
can we speed it up absolutely uh today's ships
can be about 100 times less energy consuming as
compared to what they are we just need to reinvent
them from scratch and you'll hear some of those
stories yeah that's a really nice um summary it's
really fundamentally different from the way that
we've been been thinking and using them so far um
I want to uh turn so I've lost the order switched
on me I I Antoine I'd like to turn to you and
ask is the a question from the audience is the
process for metal recycling broad enough to apply
to General unnown feeds um as in a one siiz fits
most or is it actually necessary to know exactly
what materials you're looking to to recover in
the extraction process yeah this is uh this is
an important Point um again this is all driven
ultimately by the Purity and the recovery of the
valuable things that you get from your Stream So
if you don't know what's in your stream you're
not going to be able to optimize the technology
now that's a manufacturing statement very well
known in terms of Technology themselves we are
putting these materials in conditions that are
unknown I think it goes back to can we predict
the thermodynamics in those conditions the
answer is no and as such it is possible that
certain feed talk because of the presence of
minor impurities might ultimately become more
favorable than other feed stock in order to get
the maximum recovery and selectivity so the answer
is that the principles apply generally to any fet
stock that industry mining waste manufacturer or
waste generator might have but of course the
the the devil will be in the details and you
can only get access to those details once you
have enough material to be processed I want to
illustrate this with impurity right if you have
1% of silver in your stream and 99% of the rest is
not silver how long is it going to take us in our
laboratory to show you what happened to the silver
atoms how many grams of silver do I need
to make until I can see them and say yes
this is marketable silver for the London Metal
Exchange and and and in that sense it's going
to be tied back to whatever fit stock you're
giving us and it is quite clear that some of
them might be more commercially interesting than
others even though down the line the economy of
scale will make even the less profitable one at
some point profitable yeah um okay so I'm gonna
um pivot us for a second because I've I've heard
it as a theme in a few different questions that
are asked um but it's not been stated explicitly
and the the statement that i' I'd like to throw
on the table is that e e economics and prosperity
are very tightly tied to CO2 equivalent emissions
and as countries transition to being more postr
excuse me um what is the word I'm looking for
as prosperous thank you I haven't had enough
coffee this morning so um as countries are
engaging in that transition they're inevitably
relying on Old Technologies not necessarily leap
rocking to what we know is the best this comes out
as a theme in cloud computing and the use of that
for artificial intelligence calculations it comes
to us as a theme in our materials um Recycling and
and Recovery uh and comes to us as a theme as
we think about how to meet the energy demands
of those growing societies um Can Can you comment
for a minute about how you imagine us having that
sustained economic growth as we try to transition
societies around the planet um without the carbon
based emissions or equivalents associated with
energy production so I guess I'll uh highlight the
energy initiative work that was done a few years
ago through the Tata center where the mission
was can you frugally engineered technology that
can be adapted by the other people in the world
Beyond us living in a very comfortable environment
where we are today if everyone in the world tried
to live at the energy intensity of us in United
States we would not be able to contain we would
not be able to support 8 billion people we would
be able to support only one billion people at the
level intensity of consumption of energy as we
have right now and so can we frugally engineer
an option for the rest of the world and the
answer is with that our work has been driven
by coming up with a much more easily Deployable
solar cell to me I think a individual there are
billion of them who have no Road leading to their
Village really doesn't care what's the efficiency
of the solar cell that they are carrying on
their back to Power their Village I think the
only question they have is how many trips do
I need to make to get enough energy to power
my Village and there giving you more watts per
kilogram me meaning giving your solar cell doesn't
perform optimally like Silicon would but weighs
100 times less is a value to them that will allow
them to go ahead and deploy it much more readily
the challenge though of today is that still they
do not have the batteries they will opt for
lead acid battery in order to store that energy
and hence although we have some solutions there
need more we need to be able to deploy more and
hence yes the well-being of an individual in the
country directly relates to the per capita energy
use human development index the way United Nations
will label it so give me more energy and I'll be
more prosperous right but give me more energy I'll
be emitting more CO2 as well uh come up with a
lightweight or indeed Deployable technology that
can easily be adapted because it's doesn't cost
very much by many that becomes something that
of course will win over the others yeah so you
highlighted in your response the value proposition
to the individual the service that they're looking
for from that energy not so much kind of agnostic
to where it's coming from and then to use what's
available and I think that's really interesting
how we provide that service I'm wondering if we
could hear from antoana RAF on your responses to
this this notion I'm trying to think when when
these things come up I was try to to sort of think
what are examples where this has worked before
like are there instances where societies have S of
liap frog the bad decisions that we learn were bad
and and I think you know it might be a a testament
to you know other issues like the competition with
China but I would say electric vehicles in China
it's true that the grid has a lot more cold in
China than than we would maybe aspire to but
electrification of Transportation has sort of
happened at a pace that it hasn't happened here
right like so I would say that's an example where
a where a society has maybe leap frogged internal
combustion engines and straight up going to uh to
electrified cars at a faster paace that us sort
of early adopters have um and then you know maybe
Boston's you know we have the first Subway in the
in the world right so we have one of the oldest
and worst looking Subways in the world so maybe
it's one of those places where early adopters are
locked in in h what are ultimately bad choices but
you're committed now so I think electrification of
the vehicle Fleet in China will be an example of
of lip frogging a little bit I don't know if if
you folks have can come out with other examples
Antoine I I wanted to ask you specifically as you
think about materials and energy flows is there
a way for you that you think about using AI to
solve these really complex global scale problems
not necessarily I don't know about the global
problems but for sure the materials processing
industry was the first one to use AI because we
make steel at 30 cents per kilogram at 1 billion
tons per year so there's no more places where we
have data all the time and we optimize constantly
all the processes to make sure sure we can improve
now how is it going to help for completely new
technology will be dependent on the sensors and
the quality of the technology we deploy okay um
I'm going to take one we're we're technically
out of time but I want to finish with one final
thought from each of the speakers um and then I'm
going to give you a little bit of homework because
you've come to MIT and that's it's a requirement
so um as you leave today I want you to go home
into your industries and think about one thing
that you can do to advance sustainability the
constraints are that it has to be done within
the next 3 months so it's a thing that you can do
within the next three months small definitive uh
finite take it home and uh and it needs to advance
uh sustainability initiatives in your specific
role so achievable today send send an email make
a phone call propose a solution something that
you've been thinking about I'm going to give you
30 seconds to write it down as I'm turning to my
colleagues for their closing thoughts we're going
to count to 30 everybody we can do it one two okay
I should see you all
writing okay you're committed to it now it's
it's in writing um the last question that was
on the screen at the end is what do we need from
our industrial Partners so as I've given you all
homework we're now putting some some homework on
our plate to go out and and Shake three hands for
for the mission um what do we need as academic
scientists working with our industrial Partners
yeah I think what are the real world important
problems at scale right sometimes it's it's a
very especially for for computational science like
what is you know should we doing doox for diesel
or doox for ammonia combustion like it's what
what are sort of the big strategic needs and I
think those are often times not you know there's
no paper saying and this is the most important
thing in our industry right now um so those types
of sort of pointers of where where do we point all
these tools right how do we translate how we make
the effort of translating uh these agnostic tools
into real impact in your industries that's very
hard for us to know so I would say that's that
type of guidance is extremely helpful and and I
expect useful uh two things I think I've seen the
question about what do you need to know about our
waste and our materials produced in manufacturing
that is is definitely something you should bring
up to us so that we can verify whether or not
our approach makes sense for those materials but
then the second aspect is your supply chain right
where do you buy it from in what form what are
the specifications of the things you're buying
that you're using in your manufacturing which
then makes the waste because there are some gems
here there might be ways that our technology
might work very well for 5,000 ton 10,000 ton
but if you don't tell us we will not find it uh
engag us uh this is not a one-way Street where we
get rules from you we solve the problem we pass
you the answer back uh the more we talk to each
other the more we'll be able to make ideas that
Blossom beyond what either us or industry can go
ahead and do on their own human friction leads to
Innovation let's generate more and more reasons
to be together and consequently come to these
events become members of various organizations we
are invite us to come over so we can go and tell
you stories that the best best way we think that
could be done it is this event and events like
this that are indeed designed to hopefully give
us a reason why we exist as academics we're not
just here to train amazing people who will then
change the world we are here to also generate
the best ideas but those ideas are particularly
powerful if we get your input and get you as a
partner as we develop them yeah so thank you for
co- innovating with us this morning um this
is great advice to take forward as you move
through the rest of the sessions today thank
you again to my speaker Che thank you that's