good afternoon
so with been studying properties of
stable equilibrium
States relations that can be extracted
from the fundamental
relation of any
system and therefore if the system is
for example a substance of a pure
substance or mixtures of
substances um yes it is a lot of um
math and mathematical manipulations and
today we'll have a little more of that
uh then we we we stop about the
mathematics at least for this part uh
but I wanted
to to stress the fact that
we are extracting a lot of U information
out of just the idea that there exists a
fundamental relation for stable
equilibrium States from which we can
extract
properties uh and it's precisely the
mathematical M manipulations that is not
just by itself but with proper physical
interpretation and that's the important
aspect it's not just the mathematics
it's also to interpret the mathematics
and then see what the useful part of it
is it's from this that you can extract a
lot of
information uh for example in
um in
economics manipulations of this
sort have earned uh the Nobel Prize to
Paul Samuelson who was a professor here
with MIT uh because you realize that
essentially also in economics don't ask
me what part of Economics but in any
case in economics there are functions
like that that can be manipulated by the
tools that we are developing from which
you can extract a lot of information
about uh economics in that
case so uh mathematics is a powerful uh
uh
tool and way of that allows you to think
straight so all right yes we've done the
Leandra transform and uh we have applied
it to derive uh uh the elal free energy
the Gibs free energy the
enthalpy and also this Oiler free
energy that uh
will return to to to also today and uh
and the next
time also we develop this Max
coming from the second this the the
reciprocity of the second order
derivatives of the various
functions today I want to introduce uh
quickly or in the review quickly if
you've seen it already the this um other
tool which is the Jacobian
determinants uh so if you have a system
of two uh
functions and you take the Matrix in
which you put all the the partial
derivatives in that fashion the
determinant of that Matrix is called the
Jacobian determinant The Matrix is the
Jacobian and the determinant of the of
the Jacobian is we call it
the uh Jacobian anyway just for short
and we use this uh symbol which
resembles a partial because somehow it's
it's a partial of a vector of of
functions with respect to a vector of
the uh independent
variables and it has these properties
which you can infer easily by uh the
properties of determinants you exchange
a row exchange a column you exchange the
sign uh and uh so you can easily prove
these
relations you can also notice that if
one of the functions like for example
G is the uh is the is the simple
function gals
y
then uh the second row is just the
derivative of y with respect to X since
Y and X are independent variables that's
zero and this the derivative of y with
respect to Y is one okay so that's zero
and one which leaves for the determinant
just this term here which is the partial
derivative of of f with respect to
X so this is a a useful identity because
you can pass from partial derivatives
that maybe you want to
evaluate to an equivalent Jacobian and
then we will see that we can manipulate
that uh
further of course if also f is equal to
X then this the is
becomes simply the entity I mean
one okay the other theorem about zius is
that if you consider a function of a
single variable and you invert the
function so you have f is a function of
X and you invert it as X as a function
of F you know that the derivative of
this inverted function is equal to the
inverse of the derivative of the
original
function and the equivalent for a system
of uh um uh two functions of two
variables is that
the uh
Jacobian of the inverted
system when you solve the system this
system of equations to put in evidence X
and Y is a function on F of f and g so
you change the independent
variables uh and so you invert well the
uh Jacobian of the invert system is
equal to the inverse of the Jacobian of
the original
system and that also shows shows that if
you prove if you um choose the function
g y as
before gals y as before you can uh prove
by this relation the fact that the uh
inverse I mean the partial derivative
of the inverse with respect to F at fix
Y is equal to the inverse of the
original partial
derivative so
formally you see this is uh X over y a
constant y let's read it Loosely well
you can just uh put uh it uh consider
the DX and the Dy consider it as a
fraction and put it under a the
denominator and you get this function
and uh it is fair in other words it
proves that you can do that easy uh
manipulation all right and the other
item is that if you have a function f of
x so X is your independent variable but
but suppose you want to represent your
independent variable as a in parametric
form so you have so X is a function of
another uh variable say a x of a so you
substitute in the function and so you
have a function of a function this is a
function of a now a has become the
independent
variable so the chain rule for
derivatives says for for single
variables that the derivative of f
respect to a is the derivative of s with
respect to x times the derivative of x
with respect to a okay the
equivalent for our system of two
variables uh so when you change your
system f and g uh in instead of as a
function of X and Y but is a function of
a and b so the X and Y are in turn
functions of a and
b um then you have a situation similar
to that and the derivative actually the
Jacobian of S and G with respect to the
new
variables you can is equal
to uh the Jacobian with respect to the
old variables times the Jacobian of the
new Vari of the old variables with
respect to the old
one and
formally you can
uh write this result suppose you delete
these two so you view
this result is simply the Jacobian of f
with respect to
a so you write it this way and then you
have empty spaces here where you can put
anything that cancels out so for example
you can put the Jacobian of XY with
respect to XY which is equal to one the
identity we just proved it
before and
th uh the formal manipulation becomes uh
uh easy now because uh then you
interpret this one as the Jacobian of f
with respect to XY and this is as the
Jacobian of XY with respect to
a
okay let's give an example that brings
us to a a a useful uh relation useful
identity for two properties that are uh
among the list that we have seen are
measurable so
take the
S determinant the determinant of the S
relation of the S Matrix of the
fundamental relation with respect to
entropy and volume so it's the Matrix of
the second order derivatives of energy
with respect to entropy and
volume now since
these second derivatives are derivatives
of for example we remember that the
derivative the first derivative of e
with respect to S is the temperature you
can also write them in this way
in terms of
the conjugate
variables temperature for entropy minus
the pressure for
volume okay so this is just uh applying
those
definitions and then here you recognize
that apart from the minus sign here that
can be uh taken to outside of the
determinant this is just the Coban of
temperature and pressure versus uh with
respect to S
snv so now let's do this trick of
Shifting the denominator leing the empty
spaces and let's put here whatever we
want so I'll do it in two ways I put
SNP here and
there okay and then I have I notice that
I have chosen my uh I make it make my my
choice so
that uh in each of these determinant I
mean
Jacobian there is a repeated U uh
pressure above and
below so that is the derivative of of t
with respect to S at constant
p and this other side has s which is
repeated
so that is the derivative of p with
respect to V at constant
s then if you look
up and I have let me remind it
here uh we Define the heat capacity at
constant uh pressure a few days ago and
and that was defined as the derivative
of the enthalpy with respect to
temperature at p
but if you look at how the enal the
differential for the enthalpy is if you
keep p and N constant DH is equal to
TDs so you can substitute the DH with
the TDS
here at constant pnn so CP or actually
you see here that the derivative of s
with respect to T at constant p is CP
over t
this derivative is therefore the inverse
of CP over
T why the inverse because we just Pro
that uh uh this derivative here is equal
to uh the inverse of its uh reciprocal
so to
speak also this other one we can
recognize as one of the properties that
we have defined or
almost by it's it's
the it's the derivative of V with
respect to pressure with the minus in
front so it's the
compressibility actually the other day
we defined the isothermal
compressibility so when you compress a
material at constant temperature but you
could also compress it at constant
entropy that defines the isentropic
compressibility and so here you
recognize the inverse of the isentropic
compressibility okay so first result is
that that this uh since the determinant
of the H determin of the H Matrix has uh
to be non negative by the conditions of
stability that we have uh already proved
we have this
inequality but that's not the main um
object here I want to do now the same
but by substituting here in the empty
spaces another pair of
variables again in such a way that
numerator and denominator have one same
variable like here the temperature and
here the
volume then this becomes the partial of
p with respect to volume at constant
temperature and this becomes a partial
of t with respect to s set constant V
and by the
same definitions that we just reviewed
you can show that this is equal to T
over the heat capacity at constant
volume and this other is and this other
is uh one over the volume times the
isothermal compressibility also this
group must be greater than or equal to
zero but
since they came from the manipulation of
the same
stuff these groups must also be equal to
one
another and that by eliminating tnv
which sort of cancel when you if you
equate that to to
this you obtain this result that the
ratio of the heat
capacities constant pressure and volume
is equal to the ratio of the
compressibilities
temperature over entropy constant
entropy temperature versus constant uh
entropy for example if you
remember like for
air uh or for
a diatomic um
gas
ER CP how much is CP over
CV anybody
remembers for air
it's
1.4 it it is a
75th 7 over
5 okay so that
means that also the ratio of these
compressibilities is 1
over4 we will see uh uh in a while that
this gives us this has some importance
in in a practical application which is
uh the airs Springs that are used in
many
uh transport U device I mean Transport
Systems Like Trains uh trucks and cars
and so on and even
bicycles uh airs Springs okay
so but before we get to that uh let's
keep going with um another
uh relation that uh we can
prove by again using the properties of
jacobians and here is
a the situation in which you have a
surface for example a function of X Y
and Z equal Zer represents a surface
that you can represent in three
dimensions XYZ so
okay of course you can uh view that
surface from various points of view by
choosing what your base reference frame
is and what the independent variable is
so you can represent that uh surface
also in these three alternative
ways X is a function of X and why now
you see what I'm saying if I uh if I
have this
uh surface here
which is f of x y zal
z uh I can represent it for suppose this
is X Y and
Z okay so this is
also for every X and Y I have a value of
Z so I can view it as a function of X of
Z as a function of X and Y but I can
also view it also uh from here I fix X I
fix Z and that gives me a
y so that's y function of uh Z and x and
so on okay so these are alternative ways
of representing in in thermodynamics the
typical surface that is treated this way
is the pvt relation so the the equation
of
state that particular
equation uh that for a class of States
like single phase
States uh is equivalent to the uh
fundamental
relation and U and so it's useful
because it's in terms of easily measur
measurable properties like volume
temperature and
pressure
okay all right so here we do what do we
do we take take essentially ratios of
stuff that are equal to
one or actually say minus
one so say x
z uh and ZX the denominator by the
properties of determinants that's equal
to minus one if if I switch one uh one
column it changes
sign okay so I write this which are
easy identities then I rearrange them in
a in an in a more interesting way so
that again I have the same variable uh
numerator and denominator so for example
this is the partial of X with respect to
Y at constant Z this is the partial of X
with respect I'm sorry y with respect to
Z at constant X and this is partial of Z
respect to x constant
Y which is written here
and if you multiply minus one three
times you get minus one so this is
called the cyc cyclic relation and if
you apply it to
the uh pvt relation equation of State
here is what you
get and for example you could you could
apply it you remember that the one of
the Maxwell relations that we said could
be useful to measure entropy because it
has it gives a entropy
changes that you can measure by
measuring volume changes pressure
changes temperature changes at constant
temperature at constant volume so this
is somehow uh the basis of a an
instrument that you could call an
entropy
meter well by applying this cyclic
relation and I'm not going to the
details but I'll let you uh show
that um you prove that this derivative
is equal to the ratio of alpha p over
Capa T so it's the
um isobaric coefficient of expansion
Alpha over the isothermal
compressibility of your
material for example for a
gas I mean if I can write
the ideal gas
relation you can view that as a as a v
as a function of T and
P and
N right so it's
nrt over
P so it's easy to compute for example
Alpha
p Alpha p is 1 / V the derivative of V
with respect to
T at constant pressure so it's how much
the uh uh the
expansion for a given U increasing
temperature all right so it's one / V
the derivative of V of V with respect to
T is easy it's
NR over
p and if you use that again this is 1 /
T Capa
T is
minus 1 / V the derivative of V with
respect to P at constant
T all right we can also do that
derivative uh the derivative of this
with respect to p
is
minus
nrt / p ^
2 I apply that
again and the minus goes away with the
minus one V goes away I'm left with one
/
P so Alpha and Kappa for ideal gases are
relatively simple
and uh um and so this gives that that
derivative here is equal to P /
T okay for a
gas there is
another interesting
relation that you can prove
not so easily but relatively uh
straightforward by
using uh
the
jacobians it's the Mayer relation which
relates CP CV Alpha p and Capa
te and of course temperature and
volume and here you see this is just the
definition of CP
we write this derivative in terms of a
Jacobian with the with the property that
is kept constant repeated numerator and
do denominator then we shift leave the
empty space and then we search and now
the CH the choice of what to put there
is sort of a smart you have to have some
uh just trial and error or some
experience on how to choose
it but here if you for example we choose
to to to select T and
V the second one has a repeated um
variable numerator denominator so it is
a partial derivative and again we find
that it's related to Capa T the first
determinant has four different variables
so we write it here in terms of its
definition and then these various
entries can be recognized as
those properties for example this is CV
over
T
um this we just prove this Alpha over
Kappa
T this is the same because of the
symmetry of um of the S determinant and
or because of the max relations which is
the same and this is one over Capa T so
now you compute the determinant you get
that you place it here
and out comes to my
relation okay yeah so what what's the my
relation for a
gas what's the relation between c c
CP and CV for a for
gas no
what the
water how about
R the gas
constant
usually you don't do heat
capacities uh we we uh we you we do
specific Heats so that's CP small C is
Capital C over
n and uh CV small C heat
capacity I'm sorry specific heat is the
CV over
n and then the relation my relation is
that CP equals CV plus the gas constant
but let's prove it because we said that
U uh we have it there so we have we have
to compute V
uh what is it the VT Alpha
squ over Capa
T all right which is this term here
which is the difference between the two
capacitors so Alpha so that's
VT uh Alpha is 1 / T so got T squ
here and Kappa is one over P so I got a
p there
so that goes with that and hopefully
since PV is equal to an
nrt divided by T gives
NR I see a lot of rust in your minds
about about previous thermal that's
okay
uh all right
so done
with these properties I want to go back
to the subject of available
energy you remember what we've done
um I forget now if it was the previous
lecture or the one
before
um available
energy this is the setup in which I have
a system and a
reservoir and they undergo a a weight
process and we know that if the process
the weight process is
reversible uh we can
extract uh the maximum amount of energy
when the system ends in a in a mutual
equilibrium state with the environment
with the rest
work here is instead we are going to
adopt two different states two arbitrary
States so initial and
final and you ask yourself well if my
system has to go from A1 to
A2 and it has available the interaction
with the this thermal
Reservoir what is the maximum weight
lifted it can
do or if it cannot lift the weight
what is the minimum weight
lowering that is required so as to
achieve that
change and we have seen that um all any
I mean this class of problems what's the
maximum work what's the minimum
work are always solved by writing an
energy balance
an entropy
balance and also inserting as much as we
know about the properties of the systems
involved in this case we have a
reservoir for which we know the
fundamental relation is this linear
relationship between energy and
entropy and by the
way uh usually in
uh often I mean in in uh especially in
in the
physics language what we call thermal
Reservoir it's called The Heat
buff okay now you realize that uh we
defined uh uh the heat interaction so
that keep from a to
me uh so that
uh
the okay so that if you are I want how
much entropy is
transferred you get it because the ratio
between energy and entropy uh
transferred in a heat interaction is
equal to the temperature at which that
transfer
occurs
okay now the
reservoir you can write the fundamental
relation for the reservoir
uh this
way so you
see the why they call it heat buff
because the uh heat Reservoir is ready
to provide a heat interaction if you
extract energy at its
temperature uh then it provides also the
entropy and in in the right ratio so
that you have a heat interaction at the
temperature of the
reservoir so it's a heat buff in the
sense that it can provide uh heat I mean
so that's at least
justifies that's the reading of the ter
that's the my justification of that
language it is not a reservoir of heat
though in a in the sense that
heat is not a a form of energy it is a
form of energy
transfer you cannot store heat you store
energy okay you transfer energy in the
form of heat when you have an
interaction of that
form so the language is is important and
lose language is okay if you understand
what you're doing if it is too loose and
if you
assign to this language uh two popular
meaning then you get a lot of
confusion this is
why
I one of our objectives here is to try
to be as careful as possible with the
language and by the way uh my
um sincere congratulations for how good
you're doing in your uh
homeworks
okay
so the the
work that you by solving this system of
equations we already said that we we
find an expression for the
work which is uh H which is a term
related to irreversibility entropy
produced by irreversibility which is not
there if the process is reversible and
that's typically the best you can do
whether you have to spend energy or
produce uh um mechanical energy
uh you get the best always when you do
it uh reversibly so if you have to
extract energy if you can extract energy
you extract the max you should do the
reversable process if you have to spend
energy in order to obtain uh a change of
state for example heating up uh some
water it's a a task that requires uh
spending energy you can ask yourself
what is the minimum uh uh work that you
need to spend in order to heat up that
uh that water
and if you do
that uh maybe when we do uh next time
the review on aies uh we
uh
we will'll see our efficient certain
ways we have to heat up
water
uh
okay now the maximum the reversible work
is the difference between the available
energies of the two uh states of your
system it's also the
difference in this availability function
gamma that is energy minus entropy
multiplied by the temperature of the
resare well called the availab canonical
AV availability function and that we
have seen that uh if you try to um
represented
graphically it acquires an absolute
minimum uh at the state in which a
system is in mutual equilibrium with the
reservoir so uh we by by exploiting this
this idea that this is a
minimum uh
we we extract information about for
example the
uh concavity of the
fundamental relation
By
devising changes so you start from this
uh Mutual equilibrium State and you move
anywhere else in uh an available one of
the possible states of your system a
wherever you
move gamma must
increase and so for example we chose uh
particular changes and we prove that uh
with those particular changes just you
can find that
uh the second differential of the
energy with respect to V and so fixed
sorry fixed then and V the second
differential so the concavity here is
positive you can do it also from the
other point of view so we say you find
that the second differential of s with
respect to uh at fixed vnn is negative
okay
now yeah we also apply that to prove uh
uh
but for example that the specific I mean
the heat capacities are uh non-
negative and we
proved the first part this is just the
first part of the of the theorem by CH
Brown today we'll uh we'll do also a
second part which is
um even more
interesting so the first part was any
way that um if you if you perturb your
the state of your system which is
initially in mutual equilibrium with the
res you put it off the mutual
equilibrium by for example giving energy
the system will
react uh by increasing its temperature
and the temperature as we know is the
escaping tendency for energy so it
increases its willingness to give away
energy and since the reservoir is there
uh it is It prepares uh the increasing
in temperature
prepares uh the for the for a heat
interaction in which the system gives
energy to the
thereby
contrasting the change with which you
took it away from equilibrium it tries
to spontaneously return to equilibrium
by increasing its
temperature so that's one thing all
right so to to see a little
more uh let's broaden our
class or category of systems that we
call thermal reservoirs or say heat
Buffs because in practice we often have
also uh
reservoirs that are variable
volume
often the atmosphere where we live the
Environ is the environment and it's
something that would accept a change in
volume uh
uh
without if you if if if the changeing
volume is reasonably small and also the
changes in
energy are reasonably small uh you can
add or subtract the volume and energy to
the environment without changing its
temperature and
pressure so if the system is large
enough like the air uh in the
environment of of a town or the the the
water in the sea or in the lake or in a
river with respect to if it is if it is
large enough with respect to the amounts
of energies entropies and volume that
you exchange then you may consider that
as a as a thermal r word so A system
that maintains
fixed uh values of the temperature and
the pressure in this case we
consider system which has variable
volume but still the amounts are
fixed okay then the fundamental relation
for a system is also um
linear except that
now okay before we had the uh energy
entropy and this is the temperature
TR now if we add volume as a possibility
to change then okay let's see make to
this
then okay then we have an equation of
uh of the plane
of which the slopes are
TR when you take the slope at constant V
and minus P when you take the slope at
constant uh
s so this is equation of a of a plane
and that's the fundamental relation for
that thermal Reservoir at variable
volume so we ask the same question now
okay what
if I'm changing state for my
system but it exchanges volume what it
exchanges volume with the
reservoir so maybe the system changes s
the
volume and where does it take that
volume from the
reservoir or where does it give it to
the
reservoir you want to ask the maximum
work or the minimum work requirement for
doing that change well energy balance
entropy balance fundamental relation for
the reservoir and here you also have to
do a volume balance because you have an
additional variable that has to be kept
uh fixed for the composite
system the overall volume is
concerned in order to have no other
effect external
effects like in a weight
process okay
so when you do the Sol when you solve
this problem
by eliminating the variables that um
relate to the
resir here's the
result it's almost like before except
that there is now an extra term here
which is PR times the difference in
volume of your system and again it's a
reversible term minus
a term related to
irreversibility the reversible term can
be seen as the difference in two
um
properties you could consider this as a
definition of another property that we
still call for short of names um
available energy with respect to that
particular Reservoir in that variable
volume it's it's like the one
before plus this additional P * Delta
V and also this one if you as you notice
may be written as a
difference in an availability function e
minus TRS plus P
RV which we're going to call uh just
with the name capital c
and we may notice
that this is
not it looks like but it's not the GS
free
energy except when the system is in
mutual equilibrium in the state of
mutual equilibrium with the
environment in that case TR is also the
temperature of your system a and
therefore this is the Gibs free energy
whereas uh in any other
state this TR this PR may not
be the uh temperature of your system
a and actually if the state is not an
equilibrium State the temp the system a
might not even have a temperature
defined actually it does not if it is
not stable equilibrium yet this
availability function is
defined and it gives
you these answers to questions of
minimum or maximum uh work to do or to
uh to
obtain yes exactly with the same
procedure that we have done to
obtain
these conditions for the
stability you can do it also here now I
since I have several variables it's not
uh I'm sorry let me go back one moment
here
okay so you you should think of a
similar procedure only in a
three-dimensional setup in which you
start from a mutual equilibrium state
and you
move away from it and then you apply the
condition that gamma must
increase if you move away now whereas
here you could move
away only on the e s
plane in the new uh setup where also the
Val volume is CH is uh is is is can be
changed yes you can move
at constant uh V or constant e or but
you can also move in any other direction
so you have more
choices and whatever choice you make you
still have to have this property to
uh uh
increase so here I let you if you're
interested watch the
details I choose a a uh for example to
move by changing the entropy and the
volume keeping keeping the N fixed and
it turns out that when you compute the
change in the variable Fe it is exactly
equal to a half the second differential
of
e uh and therefore you prove that this
is greater than equal to
zero or if I choose instead to change
the energy and volume and therefore and
to move along the stable equilibrium
State curve so that the entropy is
determined by the fundamental relation
then Delta V becomes equal to minus the
second differential of the
entropy and since that must be greater
than zero it it gives again that
d2s is at fixed n now this
d2s now
if you want to represent
it it's not just the second
derivative
uh because you
see when we have D d2s at constant V and
N this was equal to the second
derivative of s with respect to
e times the e s
but this other
d2s at constant n only you can vary both
e and s
then uh it's given by d2s with respect
to
e^2 time e
squar plus twice the second derivative
of s with respect to e and with respect
to V times d e
DV plus the second with respect to
V twice times DV squ so it's a quadratic
form which you can express also in terms
of the uh in in in this form uh like
using matrices D
DV here you put the S determinant which
is the determinant made up of the second
derivatives okay and this is
equal and then you multiply this by this
other Vector made up of two
elements D and DV if you do matrix
multiplication of of this let's be more
uh elegant here uh you get the above
result
okay and the fact that this has to be
negative for arbitrary so this has to
be uh negative for arbitrary choice of
your vector D DV which
means no matter what direction you want
to move uh uh
this has to be
negative that requires that the Matrix
inside be no negative
definite and the Matrix is non negative
definite
when I me I mean sorry sorry non
positive non so it's it's negative
semide definite okay so when is a matrix
uh let's start with positive when is a
matrix positive
definite I have a matrix a 1 one
a12 and let's make it symmetric
okay so
this if it is positive semide
definite the diagonal entries must be
non-
negative the
determinant must be non- negative so a 1
1 a22 minus
a12 squared because it's a
symmetric must be greater than equal to
zero you want to make it uh uh if the
Matrix instead of
being positive semi-definite is negative
semi-definite so this is less than or
equal to
so the
entries on the diagonal should
be non NE non
positive how about the
determinant should I change the
sign not for a 2X two
Matrix because you see also
the more uh fundamental way uh property
of of a non negative uh of a a nonos
of of a negative semide definite Matrix
is that it's igen values are
all
negative so it means let's say let's
call them Lambda so Lambda 1 is less
than zero Lambda 2 is less than zero
and for a 2x2 matrix the
determinant is equal to the product of
the two L values so this is also equal
to Lambda 1 time Lambda 2 so if you
multiply two negative numbers you get a
positive number and so you
get the determinant is greater than zero
If instead you you add a 3 by 3x3 Matrix
then you have three negative numbers
that multiplied give the determinant in
that
case with an odd number of uh entries uh
negative time negative time negative
makes Nega right so the determinant of
of of the uh
semi uh of a negative semide definite
Matrix is positive for odd number of uh
rows and columns and uh negative for uh
what did it say positive for even number
and negative for odd
number
okay we need that in a short
while here oh yeah let me just uh
go back to like
a a simple
um
question
about all right suppose you
have you have vacuum so you have a
piston you have a a
container in which you manage to have
nothing vacuum vacuum means no particles
nothing
okay so the question
is is that a
situation and this vacuum is in a uh in
an environment which I can
model as a reservoir
at pressure
PR yeah also temperature TR but uh the
temperature doesn't play much over Ro
here so it's like I have this container
in the environment here man I manage to
make
vacuum what's the minimum work required
to make that
vacuum or if I have that vacuum can I do
something useful can I lift the weight
what's the maximum uh
lift well let's
apply this formula
here assume that we do things the best
thermodynamic way so that means without
generating entropy by
irreversibility and suppose I want my
initial state state one
okay so let me say that I started with
my piston down below
here and now so this is my say State one
and this is my state
two and I
pull here I have the
pressure of the
environment so if I pull
how much work do I have to do I have to
the if you look at the piston on one
side you have zero pressure because
nothing here on the other side you have
PR so if you if the the
volume change is vs2 minus
V1 you can view that as
a that's let's call X this
uh the loc let's call Z the location of
the of the weight I'm sorry of the
piston and let's call Little a the area
of the
Piston
so the
force that you have to apply is equal
to the pressure times which is force per
unit area times the area so that's the
force the
work is
f time
x Force I'm sorry
Z
right uh so that's p
r time a
z but a z is the volume so that's p r *
V but actually it's V2 minus V1 because
uh this is V2 and this is V1 is equal to
zero in in our case
so it seems that the
work that you need to spend B in order
to go from one to two in a reversible
way is equal to
that which is written
here except that
now it has the wrong
sign because this represents the work
with the arrow out
instead we are spend if we change the
direction of the the arrow so me say
that this is the work that I need to
spend
okay and of course this I could also
write at the same
thing by changing the arrow if I change
the arrow I change also the
sign
okay so essentially the the the the
minimum work to required to produce the
vacuum is equal to the pressure of the
environment times the volume of that
vacuum that's an easy result we could
have I mean we actually got to that
result without all the complicated uh
long story that we are telling
but that's just
to uh show what uh the consistency of
this relation we what we what we know
so now let's think of another kind of uh
Reservoir which again can be uh
typically is a typical model of the a
environment or the or or some natural uh
environment so here is a particular
Reservoir that can exchange through a
semi perable membrane only one type of
substance with your
system we may we may call it the an
osmotic Reservoir or a thermal Reservoir
or we just not don't give any
names but just Define it uh uh by just
these words all
right you run the same machine machery
energy balance entropy balance now you
also have to make a balance for the
amounts of constituents of the kind of
substance that can be uh
transferred for example you
can you may be
interested in U you know some people are
devising uh devising um methods or or U
uh plants that want to extract CO2 from
the
atmosphere right so you want to ask well
what's the minimum amount of work I need
to spend if I want to uh extract CO2
from the
atmosphere because that minimum defines
the
target defines also the way in which you
determine the efficiency the second low
efficiency of that uh particular uh
equipment and it's a question very
similar to this one because one
way one way to do
that uh not saying it's the reversible
way but I'm saying that one way to do it
is first you do
vacuum and
then you open
up the permeability of the Piston to C
just
CO2 and so CO2 will fill this
region and you'll have just CO2 because
the other parts the other mean O oxygen
and nitrogen cannot go through uh this
particular semi-permeable membrane and
that way you have
separated so one way is produce vacuum
and we know how much it work it requires
use a semi-perm membrane and there you
have your your uh CO2 your CO2
eventually will reach Mutual equilibrium
with the reservoir and
uh
uh so if you at that stage I have
blocked my piston cannot go up and down
and I change Reservoir instead of having
a reservoir at variable volume
I have a reservoir at uh that can
exchange that so at constant chemical
potential of that substance
CO2
okay uh the final state will be that
instead of vacuum I will just have CO2
pure let's say that this will have a
chemical potential that we will
call MU
I and it will have a pressure that
corresponds to what we
defined when they are in mutual
equilibrium equality of chemical
potentials defines the partial
pressure so the CO2 will be at the
partial pressure that it has in air
viewed as a
mixture okay
this second part of the process from
when I after I made vacuum and I stop
the piston and I open the pory uh the
second part of the process is
spontaneous because
initially you are in non equilibrium
State because here you have no CO2
whereas in order for a equilibrium you
need to have chemical potentials to be
equal so this is an irreversible process
there will be entropy produced by
reversibility so this is not the best
way to do it you could also evaluate how
much is the efficiency if you could
compare it with what's the minimum work
that is required and the minimum work
that is
required is given
here by this formula here I'm Sorry by
this formula
here so there is again another
um available energy
function I'm sorry available energy
property for this particular kind of
osmotic
reservoirs the difference of which tells
you the minimum or the maximum
works for producing or or exploiting and
the situation
so we'll return later on uh to this
question of minimum work for separating
a substance from uh from from say the
atmosphere
here this combination that appears in
the expression for this new version of
the available energy namely e minus TRS
minus the chemical potential
times the amount of that substance that
is can cross between the system and the
reservoir we may give it a name or not
simply an availability
function maybe we could call it osmotic
availability function maybe we could use
this letter or another letter uh it's
just a matter of
choice as for for the other availability
functions this also is
minimum so also from this one you can
derive by the
same method as before same
procedure conditions for stability of
equilibrium for the second differential
of the energy now it will be like uh uh
this is but not with volume but with NI
I uh that substitutes and that's the
uh the the the expression for this
second order
differentials and finally we could have
a grand situation okay so Grand
Reservoir
um with which
you can your system can exchange
anything it
wants amounts volume energy and
entropy
okay so you have to run again the same
Machinery energy balance entropy balance
fundamental relation for the
reservoir notice that PO in the previous
case maybe I didn't emphasize it enough
but what changes from Reservoir to
Reservoir is the
expression for the fundamental relation
see these uh terms are
new peculiar to this
Reservoir that acts as a reservoir not
only for exchanges of energy and entropy
but also for if you change volume it
doesn't change the pressure if you
change the amounts it doesn't change the
chemical
potentials and then you have to uh
remember also to do the
volume balance and the balance balances
for all of the amounts of the various
constituents that are
conserved now chemical reactions
here again eliminate
the terms that relate to
the reservoir and you get this
expression which is a
another generalization of the available
energy with respect to this completely
open uh Reservoir and uh it's
um this is the available energy the
expression which can also be written as
a difference in two
values so the the work the maximum or
minum the reversible work is the
difference in the values of this new
availability function which I like to
call Oiler availability function for the
reason I already explained uh the other
time and that will be also clear uh
later
on so this e minus TRS plus PV minus mu
RN this availability function is defined
for all states equilibrium and non-e
equilibrium when your system is
in
uh neutal equilibrium so so it is in the
state at temperature TR pressure PR and
with the chemical potential so complete
equilibrium between system and
Reservoir then this availability
function we corresponds to that
characteristic function that we called
the
oiler free energy
that I just reviewed at the beginning of
today
okay and from this
one this
also is
minimum at Mutual
equilibrium and you can do the same
again
uh to EXT ract
conditions for stability this
time this
expression D2 e is with respect not to
just two variables so this
Matrix uh the S Matrix will not be just
2 by two but will be uh 2 + r because y
also also can change all the
constituents and if the our constituents
is like a 2X two 2+ R by 2+ R so it's
this Matrix that we have already
anticipated a while
ago and uh this therefore
proves uh I mean here the details here
prove in more detail
also these expression that we had
anticipated but you can also choose
since now you you are you think that you
are in a in a the mutual equilibrium
State and then you can move your
State uh in various
directions and one
way is that
you choose another
state
that has still has the same temperature
pressure of your reservo but you change
the
amount so you choose to move away from
Mutual
equilibrium because the conditions for
Mutual equilibrium with res is not only
now that it can exchange not only energy
but also amounts it's not only the
temperature equality it's also the
pressure equality for the volume change
and the chemical potentials or chemical
potential so I can move away from Mutual
equilibrium while keeping some of the
mutual equilibrium conditions satisfied
like same temperature and same pressure
and moving only the
amounts if you do that and move along uh
the stable equilibrium State surface
constant temperature and
pressure uh the condition that Delta uh
that that uh this um
Oiler uh availability
function must increase along that
path turns out to be the change in this
variable
side is uh equal to the second
differential of the Gibs free
energy you you can prove it by
remembering that the
the Gibs V energy is e minus s minus TR
and here TR and PR remain remain
constant so it it remains
defined so this proves that um the
Gibs free
energy as a minimum if you move so the
second differential is non negative yes
it's is non negative h if you move at
con if you change the composition at
constant
tnp if you keep only temperature fixed
and change the volume instead of keeping
the pressure constant you get a similar
relation this is not the givs free
energy it's the elol free
energy at constant t
okay so remember that we have seen
the that from these conditions here we
obtain first part of the brown
principle
now
yes another little piece of math sorry
about
that uh
but that will get us to the second part
of the chatellier brown principle so it
is which is a more General uh
statement
which requires a little um uh brush
up or maybe first time you see
math
uh so let's say we have a function
for of two variables I put also the the
other Z here just to say that the z's
are going to be constant so I have
several variables but I
keep a constant all except two of them
which are X and
Y and then for example I have that
function I can write the
differential so that's the partial of a
with respect to X
time DX times the partial of a with
respect to y * d y I'm going to use the
notation comma X for partial with
respect to X which is often used like in
fluid mechanics so maybe you've seen it
already or
elsewhere and for example comma X is the
second derivative with respect to X
twice uh comma XY is the derivative of
uh with respect to X and with respect to
Y
okay so this is the partial derivative
with respect to
X and here's the full Glory of uh the um
representation of that
derivatives uh where where the subs as
you remember mean the other variables
of the original function that you're
taking the deriv the partial derivative
of okay
good then we
have like we've seen there for d2s
here's
D2 of this variable
a can think of s but it could be also
others like the gifts fre energy or or
the elos free energy or whatever you
need
and this is the quadratic
form
that represents the explicit
form of the
uh second or
differential okay so now that we have a
quadratic
form the trick is to put it in the
so-called canonical form because you see
this quadratic
form has a square here a square there
and then it has a product DX
Dy this isn't doesn't have a a definite
sign
but let's try to rewrite this quadratic
form into a form in which you have
something
squared and uh Dy squared so a
combination of DX and Dy proper
combinate if you choose a proper
combination of DX and D
y uh and this is the proper combination
I already built in the the answer so you
if you want to check it you just
substitute if you if you take this
expression and work it out you will
prove to yourself that it's equivalent
to that
one and this ratio this coefficient here
is the ratio
of uh the second derivative with respect
to XY and divided by the second
derivative respect to
xx and then you find if you substitute
by comparison you find that what you
need to put in front of the Dy squ is
this Lambda which is not sorry that I
used Lambda here it's not the a
values but this
Lambda is given by this
expression again terms of the
original you can do it in this way where
in your summation you get you keep the
square of the Y squared or you can do it
also in this other way this is another
canonical form in which you keep the X
squar they
are two equivalent
ways of course here the Lambda is
different than the Lambda X is given by
this
one okay
now do I have more
space
now let's look at
uh
suppose that our function a is such that
it's uh second differential must be
positive okay
so positive
means that this Matrix is positive
definite or semide
definite and as as we remember yeah I
took away the wrong so if we
remember uh positive definite for a
matrix imply
all these things are
positive or non
negative so we have to have that
axx is greater than
zero and in fact here that's what I have
written
axx is greater than zero it's greater
than something else is greater than zero
and also a y I is greater than
zero
but here we have written also something
more strong than
that we have written that a XX or a y y
is greater than
Lambda let's
see
um the
Lambda uh
Tai yeah I can write it
there
um see for example Lambda
y let me rewrite it uh this way uh it
has that the
denominator a xx
squ and at the denominate I'm sorry at
the yeah denominator there and numerator
a XX time
a y
y minus a
XY
squar that is the
determinant of the S
Matrix that
numerator
so since the Matrix is positive the
numerator is positive the denominator is
positive so this is also
positive
okay so Lambda so this explains why
Lambda uh you can do that for y but also
for
x uh the lambdas are also non
negative and now you can also see here y
Lambda uh for example Lambda
Y is smaller than a y y because you look
look here this is lamb this is a and
then you subtract something
positive so if if you from a you
subtract something positive it means
that Lambda is smaller than a i a y
y
okay all right so this is the
mathematics that uh
stands uh that supports that stands
behind the um the next the The Brown
principle that we're going to do in a
second of course you can do exactly the
same that I've done here
for uh positive semide definite you can
also do it for negative
sem okay
these
steps help understanding uh
the various steps on the previous
uh
slide and
uh the bottom line is is here you can uh
um rewrite that aou
X it it this is equal to the
partial of ax which is the conjugate
potential to variable uh uh X so
um yeah so suppose suppose our function
is
S and
S is a function of energy and so s e e
which is the equivalent so our functions
is the entropy and X variable is the
energy
so s e e means partial of s with respect
to e twice but since the partial of s
with respect to
e is 1 / t
Okay so this is equivalent also to the
the you can write it
as s comma e which is the inverse of the
temperature the gain comma
e and of course you can do also the
other uh like that so this is the
meaning of partial of the a comma X
again comma X done at constant
y the point is
that uh by doing this math here that I
want to skip
uh I have uh um I prove that the Lambda
also the lambdas can be written as
partials of um this potential so on the
first derivative respect to X but not
while keeping y constant y but but while
keeping constant the other
potential conjugated to
Y okay
so what changes in these two terms is
what is kept constant here I keep
constant y here I say I keep I keep
constant the potential conjugated to
Y and that's the
key to
uh to the the Practical uh consequences
of these mathematics
so for
example let's change once more variable
so that we you get uh a more confused
but we just have five minutes so it's
okay uh so we start from a function
E from this fundamental relation this
form of the fundamental
relation keep the end fixed and look at
what happens by applying what we've just
seen
this is the train of inequalities that
is implied by one of the forms by this
form and by the second form is written
here you can do the
substitutions uh you see I put here what
the variable X Y is what a subx a sub y
called the temperature and the pressure
in our case and here is a
result now by the way by looking at
these derivatives you find all friends
and you can see that for example you can
rewrite this as
CP is greater than or equal to CV which
is greater than equal to zero or that
one the compressibility constant
temperature is greater than a
compressibility at constant
entropy okay
so what's the
reading that the chatel brown
does so what's the difference here
between V the what is what is the
difference between these two derivatives
is what is kept
constant I change the entropy and
measure what temperature change
occurs uh when I keep volume or when I
keep uh pressure
fixed you see
volume
is the original variable pressure is the
conjugated potential it has to do with
the tendency to escape uh to to to gain
volume so minus pressure is the tendency
to yield
volume so the the idea is that you know
that the interpretation of these
derivatives being positive is that the
system uh reacts if you move it away
from the mutual equilibrium state from
of the
environment uh you add some entropy for
example it will increase its temperature
this is
positive so as to increase its uh
uh tendency
to return energy to contrast your change
by giving energy giving energy away to
your environment so the system responds
by trying to uh spontaneously
reestablish
equilibrium but it does more
so if you do it at constant volume than
if you do it at constant pressure so the
reaction of the system is
stronger uh
if if what so what's the difference the
difference is that
here the system as as a smaller reaction
if you
keep keeping the pressure constant means
means keeping your
system uh in equilibrium with your res
at least as for the condition that
requires pressure equality so you're not
touching that condition for Mutual
equilibrium you're touching also some
something else so if you if you do it
there the system says all right well
after all you're you're moving me away
but not so much so its reaction is
softer if you move it away so that also
its pressure changes and therefore like
you do when you keep the volume constant
uh then it will U it will uh in in
increase uh not
only so essentially you are
touching two conditions of Mutual
equilibrium touching equality of
temperature and touching equality of
pressure and therefore the system reacts
stronger wants more to come back to
equilibrium this is the uh this is the
um uh the idea and since I wanted
to to give me two more minutes I wanted
to uh show you the uh
application
here you know uh this is an air spring
so it's like a piston with air
inside and it acts like a standard uh
mechanical spring you can compute the
spring
constant and you here are the details
it's kind of easy um mechanical
engineering so to
speak uh so the cake this uh K is the K
the the spring constant that
relates the increasing uh reaction or
force of your spring to a change in its
uh
compression and this is also similar
situation it this acts as a
spring and you can
compute uh DF over DX
and uh if you do go down here you see
it's related to how much the area little
a of the Piston the
volume and this thing as a denominator
is the
compressibility so you could have U so
if you act your
spring while keeping the temperature
constant so if your spring uh is in
contact with the th
were and therefore it has the time to
exchange energy to remain in mutual
equilibrium which typically is when you
push it but push it slow enough so that
the system has time to uh exchange heat
with the environment and remain in
equilibrium then you get one spring
constant If instead you push a spring
fast like when the car goes on on a on a
bump
uh that the system doesn't have time to
exchange energy or or heat and the
entropy remains
constant so that's the
isothermal uh compress I'm sorry the
isentropic compressibility that
appears and so you see that the ratio of
these two compress of these two uh spray
constants
is
equal to CP over C CV which for air is
1.4 we just
reviewed so that means that U if you act
on the spring fast you get the spring
constant that is 40% higher than if you
act on the spring
slow
okay and these devices if you look up
air Springs you see that there are uh
it's an enormous business because as I
said trains uh buses bicycles cars use
spring constants combined also with The
Dumping system to give you uh like um
suspension systems that are uh allowed
to absorb vibrations and make it uh more
uh
comfortable Okay so sorry if I went a
little bit uh late