Good afternoon. Uh my name is David
Martin. I'm a first need to connect
this.
>> Yep. Another program director here at uh
uh corporate relations and uh uh while
Har's getting set up, I have the honor
to be uh introducing him this afternoon.
So Hari Balakrishnan is the Fujitsu
professor of computer science at MIT and
a director of MIT's center for wireless
networks and mobile computing. His
research is inworked computer systems
with current interests in networking,
sensing and perception for sensor
equipped mobile devices connected to
cloud or edge services running in data
centers. He has made many highly cited
contributions to mobile and sensor
computing, internet transport and
routing, overlay networks and P2P
systems and data management. And today
his presentation is titled Gala in AI
for autonomous system design and optim
optimization. So join me in welcoming
Hari Abalakrishnan.
[applause]
>> Thanks.
>> Okay,
it's working. Is mic on? Great. Good
afternoon everybody. Um so what I'd like
to talk to you about is a line of
research that our group has been working
on for about a little over 18 months or
two years but actually builds on about a
decade's work uh worth of work in our
lab u the networks and mobile systems
group um which is uh a lot of this work
has been actually led by my colleague
Mohammed Alizad um uh working with me
and several of our students uh uh Joseph
Puya Ponta Arash and Kimya
So um let's get into it.
All right. So here's the big picture of
um what I'm going to talk about. If you
look at AI today, especially generative
AI um technologies and things related to
inference,
whether they're based on LLMs or not
LLMs, the pace at which AI model
advancements are happening outpaces the
pace at which the systems that deliver
these AI applications are being
innovated upon. And while there's been a
lot of advances in modeling, systems
really are the lifeblood of AI. If you
didn't have computing systems based on
GPUs and fast networks um and other
compute engines uh working at very high
speed and efficiency uh you end up with
not being able to take advantage of all
of the impressive advances in the models
and we've talked to a number of
companies and many of them have started
dedicating squads of experts to AI
infrastructure and this is true for the
big companies but it's also true for
companies that have started to have
deployed their own models often in the
cloud and there's very little support
given to those engineers and these
engineers end up spending a lot of time
on making AI more efficient and it's
expensive. Uh GPUs are expensive and uh
often uh it's hard to get hands get your
hands on GPUs as well. So what we've
been doing in this work is trying to
pioneer a new era of highly autonomous
infrastructure which allows for these
systems uh these complex distributed
computing systems to be uh adaptive to
changing workloads and changing hardware
um and uh changing user needs.
Self-improves by observing what it's
doing, what's happening to the data in
the system. And because these systems
are pretty complicated, we feel like
it's reached the edge of human comping
and human comprehension to understand
how to design and optimize these
systems. Uh it turns out it's
architected by AI itself. And our
initial mode here is to view the AI as a
collaborator to the human engineer or
the human designer. Um but actually over
time we think for some of these very
complicated problems, we would end up
with the AI making decisions um and
updating even production code. And
that's part of the vision. It's not it's
not real yet. So the types of results
that we've been observing are that we
can deliver continuous system
optimizations
because the workload keeps changing you
know um and I'll show lots of examples
of this uh about one or two orders of
magnitude 10 to 100 times faster than
experts. It takes uh hours to produce
these optimizations and improvements uh
in a continuous way. uh whereas it would
take weeks of time uh for an expert or a
squad of experts to produce these types
of optimizations.
So here here's some uh evidence for AI
outpacing its system infrastructure. So
you know TensorFlow which today is sort
of people have stopped using it because
I think Google recently announced that
they're really not going to be
supporting it anymore. It's about 10
years old. um that was uh that came
about in 2016 and when the first um LLM
based systems were starting to get
deployed they deployed it on these
inference servers that were built on
TensorFlow which is really not a good
match for these types of problems. Um
and this has been evolved later on this
was named uh renamed to Triton which
I'll come back to because today we used
um people use Triton which is uh an open
source projects uh led by largely by
Nvidia um to um uh to deploy these these
nonLM based systems but there's been
about a two or three year gap in terms
of the infrastructure and then when chat
GPT came about um there was really huge
memory footprint they grew very very um
aggressive very very quickly. Uh it's an
auto reggressive model and there wasn't
the system infrastructure that was
available. We had these GPUs but there
was not really much software to support
this and and the first types of systems
that allowed us to do something
reasonable was this open source project
out of Berkeley VLM which is now
probably the de facto most popular way
to support LLM based applications. In
fact, even companies that have large
language model deployments, many of them
are kind of based or folks off of VLM
and uh it took about two years of a gap
and it continues to get uh uh innovated
upon. Uh SG lang was another system that
came about two years after this uh model
advancement.
And if you look at the commercial world
in terms of a lot of these projects are
actually open source. Uh the ways in
which these GPU clusters for large
language models get managed is you know
you have NVIDIA Dynamo uh AI bricks from
from bite dance um and VLM production
stack is the system that you would run
to orchestrate all of these GPU
software. So you have these engines that
are running things like VLM or uh other
individual engine LLM inferences and
then you need something to manage and
coordinate this cluster of GPUs whether
it be two GPUs or 8 GPUs or you know
thousands of GPUs and we'll talk about
this. The GPUs are extremely complicated
engines. They're highly parallel
machines of their own and uh there's
lots of ways in which one could uh go
wrong and we've talked to some
companies. they bought these GPUs or
they lease them um in in GPU clouds and
they're running at utilization of 10 or
15% because uh they need that for the
peak but they don't know how to manage
these GPUs um efficiently and wastes a
lot of money.
Now our research was not didn't start
based on these observations about AI
inference. It started with a different
observation. Um
we notice that when we look at students
who join our group um in our lab, it
takes about two to two and a half years
to teach a student how to think the way
we do. We work on a large number of
different distributed and uh distributed
systems. And uh there's particular ways
we think about it. At the end of the
day, all these distributed systems are
big networks of cues with caching and
pipelining and parallel machines. And it
just so happens you can configure them
and you can you know kind of connect
them in lots of different ways and you
know essentially infinite number of
ways. And it takes two to two and a half
years to teach students how to be
productive in in research. And this is
not just true of our group. We've talked
to other professors and other um um
people in companies when undergraduates
join after and then it takes them two to
three years to get up to speed in
understanding how to design complex
computer systems. So almost like I
wouldn't say as a joke but almost as a
off-the- cuff remark I mentioned to my
colleague Mohammad Ali Zadi that you
know I wonder what it'll take for us to
teach an AI not train an AI this
foundational models have already been
built and they come with three things
which are exactly the same three things
that our undergraduate students come
come with. They know how to do um kind
of analytics and math kind of read
spreadsheets or look at data and analyze
this data. They understand how to
summarize documents and understand
documents. You can ask them questions.
They know how to read and they know how
to write code and they know how to
comprehend code which is staggeringly
impressive. But if you look at it,
that's exactly the three same skills
that students come into our group after
their undergraduate degree. Yes, they've
learned some computer science. They've
learned all the stuff, but they don't
learn how we should be designing uh
highly complex computer systems. So, I
just said like I wonder what it would
take to do this. And he's crazy. So he
went about starting to teach an AI how
to do this. So he built a prototype and
very quickly came up with some results
and then all of us most of us in our
group jumped onto this and then we
started looking at real problems to to
solve. So our mission here in this
project uh is to reimagine system design
and optimization with AI. So today it's
a fairly rare specialty especially for
these very complicated systems. uh and
there are some companies with a large
number of engineers who know how to do
this like Google but most companies
don't have this type of capability it's
quite painfully slow even at large
companies and frankly it's capped by
human time and human intuition and
you'll see this with some examples but
these AI systems now have read every
possible paper that's been written on
this topic and no human being has done
that so they're actually kind of able to
apply that knowledge if you teach it the
right way if you if you guide it the the
right way. So what we'd like instead is
to think about design in terms of hours
and then you tune in minutes and as the
workload changes you're continuously
adapting to each use case and the lesson
here which I'll get to at the end again
is that to try to be highly specialized
to what's actually happening rather than
to build highly generic systems.
So we started going about building a PhD
level AI. So this the the aim of the
research was can we build an AI that
could act like a junior PhD student in
you know maybe with two or three years
of experience uh or a mid-career PhD
student or equivalently an engineer and
so what do the what do we do as system
design what do system designers do well
we look at a lot of data we don't really
have we have some intuition but we look
at a lot of data we conduct a lot of
experiments and we use that data and
then we look at documentation of systems
we read papers
and we look at code. We might actually
reach out to some optimizers and solvers
and so on. But this workflow,
you could build an AI to do lots of
things. Our goal was to build a workflow
for a group of systems designers that's
almost exactly the same as how human
beings operate. So we have researcher
agents, we have engineer agents, we have
supervisor or adviser agents. And I'll
show you an example where most of the
time the supervisor is doing nothing
except every once in a while it's going
to come up with some uh with questions.
And we've done this in a way that's
pretty interesting. The supervisor agent
has access to the knowledge but it never
proposes an idea. It asks questions. It
asks for things that are being missed.
And so this has been amazing as an
effort for us because we've been able to
mimic the way human small human teams
three four people work. And we've been
able to get an AI to do some pretty
interesting things. So what this AI
agentic system does is it does modeling,
it does some analysis.
Most importantly, it constructs
experiments which is really what we do
as humans. And the key is to construct a
small number of experiments. If you put
this into a system like an LLM and you
ask it to solve a single problem, it
will conduct 4,000 to 5,000 experiments
which just takes too long and takes
costs too much money. So instead we come
up with something that takes maybe about
10 to 20 experiments. And by contrast,
human beings when applied to this these
problems we find take a 100 experiments.
And partly that's because human beings
first of all it takes them more time to
construct the experiment and do the
system experiment but they also make
mistakes. And shockingly the AI may have
a wrong idea but it doesn't make a
mistake implementing the wrong idea. Um
whereas humans with with an idea right
or wrong they have bugs in their code
much because the way this is structured
is not inventing massive amounts of
code. It's taking existing software and
making kind of fine-tuned changes to it.
The most interesting thing about it that
really got us all excited and I'll show
you this um and hope I convey excitement
is that this thing has invented
algorithms. It's invented uh today five
or six new algorithms for managing
resources and at least three of them are
publishable in conferences. And so
that's what's got us excited about this
this system.
Now the intuition for our system is
built on a re a decade of research on
AIdriven systems in my group. A lot of
this was led by uh my colleague uh
Mohammad Ali Zade. But um over 10 years
ago I worked with one of my students
who's now a professor at Stanford Keith
Winstein on a system called Remy which
applied uh a version of reinforcement
learning to automatically invent new
congestion control protocols for the
internet things like you know that are
implemented in TCP. Um data center
scheduling. uh Mohammad and his students
worked on data center scheduling uh
using machine learning and the insight
here was very similar to the type of
insight used in Alph Go which was that
thing from deep mind that was pretty
impressive. So he observed that the way
in which you have to pack jobs within a
big cluster is multi-resource and
multi-dimensional because you have uh
CPUs, you have storage, you have memory
and it's not a single resource
optimization. So he framed it as kind of
a game in the first version that they
built. um where there were simulations
being done and it was almost like you
have you make a decision and then new
jobs come in and then you make a
decision so you could view it as a
two-player game and what you're trying
to do is like Tetris you're trying to
pack the most number of jobs into your
into your cluster. So there's a a long
string of this work that has been done.
But what we also observed from this work
um was that almost every single one of
them it was all based on reinforcement
learning. And almost every single one of
them required simulation which is fine
but
in the end it was pretty fragile. And
the reason it was fragile is two
reasons. One is that with reinforcement
learning what you come up with is a
neural policy. You come up with a neural
network as a policy. And
when you run this, you might have a huge
amount of training data. You do all the
most rigorous experiments. The simulator
is it's very difficult to build a
simulator that's exactly faithful to the
environment in which you're operating.
There's all sorts of implementation
artifacts. And with reinforcement
learning producing a neural policy, a
you end up with a neural policy that
human beings don't understand. So people
are really afraid to put into some
production system because they don't
know what's happening. and B when you
get new data or the environment changes
these policies these algorithms all many
of our papers almost all of them are
pretty fragile they don't perform well
and they don't keel over like in a
graceful way uh they fail badly when
they optimize they optimize really well
when they fail they fail really badly
so we were stuck you know it's
disappointing because we published all
these papers the results look great and
nobody uses this in a production system.
The difference happened for us with the
when when LLMs came along and not
because of their ability to code but
because of their ability to think in
terms of natural language and express
their thinking to us. You can ask for
chain of thought. You can ask for how it
how it's reasoning. And what we've done
instead is to generalize this approach.
So we're not interested in optimizing a
specific system. We're interested in
optimizing
pretty much any distributed computing
system and we can do that with uh large
language models as one of the components
and then I'll show you some of the other
components. So I'm going to do this with
an example first and then we'll
generalize. So we looked at the problem
of serving an LLM workload. So this is
like chat, GPT, perplexity, anthropic,
all of these things. you know, requests
come in to uh to an API server to a set
of API servers and they dispatch them to
these GPUs and the GPUs done do a bunch
of computing and they get the results
back and you know users are you know
they engage with the with the dialogue
and every one of these distributed
systems has something called a request
router which is how do you request how
do you route these or distribute these
requests among GPUs in an inference
cluster and this is a pretty difficult
problem. Um firstly for two reasons
mainly two reasons. The first one is
that the workloads are very very
complicated and changing. You have you
know when you use chat GPT you type in
something and that's a prompt. These
prompts you could think of it as tokens
that come into the system and then you
have output tokens whatever the answer
it's producing. It's very difficult to
predict how much work a given query is
going to take. You might send in a big
document, lots of tokens and you might
ask a very simple question of that and
it takes almost no resources to produce
the answer. You might send a big PDF and
ask what's the title very little
computation small number of output
tokens or you might send a small amount
of information in your prompt and then
the thing goes about thinking and
reasoning and it takes like five minutes
and it comes back with this huge answer.
So it's very difficult to predict and
one of the main resources that um get
consumed here is memory in the GPU. The
second reason this is problematic is you
don't get to send one request at a time
to a GPU. These GPUs are themselves
parallel machines. So each GPU you can
get to send some number of requests. And
to first order what gates the number of
requests is the amount of memory that
the GPU consumes. Problem is you don't
know how much memory u a future request
is going to consume. So you don't quite
know what to do. So what do existing
systems do? What they do is they come up
with some generic policy. They do
roundrobin, you know, just like in the
grocery store, you just like whatever
you send it to the next each request
comes in, you send it to the next GPU in
sequence. And some of the systems have
something slightly more sophisticated
called LLQ or least loaded Q. And least
loaded Q is what you would imagine. You
know, you have a Q in front of every
GPU, you send it to the least loaded
queue. If you don't know anything about
the workload, that's what you do. So, we
ran this on a whole series of workloads
and this is one of them. uh it's a
somewhat challenging workload which uses
chatting and you know those reasoning
models and this is a benchmark shared
GPT plus reasoning and you we run it at
somewhat high load on a 256 node uh GPU
cluster running the VLM uh open source
inference engine on this llama model and
we measure the slowdown which is the
mean latency for a request. You send a
request and you get a response back. We
measure the time um and you divide that
by the best possible latency which is
the delay you would get to respond to
that request when there's no load on the
system and what we find is it's between
35 and 50 plus about 50 for the
roundroin policy and 35 for LLQ. Now if
you worked in the sort of distributed
cluster management area, it's possible
to design not with GPUs but with
standard CPUs, it's possible to design
things where no matter what the workload
is, you can be pretty clever and design
things with a slowdown of like a factor
of three or four. A slowdown of 35 to 50
is quite quite substantial.
So the first thing we did was um as we
started thinking about an AI wanting to
solve this problem um we have a human
expert and in fact um Mohammmed my
colleague is one of the world's experts
on this worked on this these types of
problems in routing and scheduling and
um resource management in systems for
over 20 years. So um he decided to work
on this problem and about two weeks of
work and over a 100 experiments he
designed for this workload a scheduling
algorithm a request starting algorithm
that had a slowdown of about two a
factor of two or three and took him
about over two weeks to do this
problems like this and others our AI GIA
is able to solve in two hours and it
does it with a small number of
simulations and it does it more
importantly if you look at his
algorithm's algorithm and GIA they
actually end up using the same insight
but the GIA algorithm is more robust and
better than what our human expert in
this problem produced and we've seen
this now in multiple examples that I'll
show you as we go along. So again I'm
not saying yet that this replaces people
because it's not yet at that point but
it's at the point where it's giving us
really good ideas on how to think about
systems. So it is really a good
collaborator and it's at the point now
where almost all of the students in our
group are using the tool and they're
they're modifying the tool for their own
purposes and uh I'm teaching a graduate
networking class this semester and uh
one of the things that we're doing
Mohammed and I are doing in our class is
we we have all these student projects
that people are supposed to work on and
one of the things for them this semester
is more than half of the groups we have
about 60 plus students more than half of
the groups I believe are have been asked
to take any problem in computer systems
and networking that they've seen either
in the class or outside and use this
agentic system to see what they get out
of it and the students are super excited
about being able to use that to to come
up with good insight. So I'm hyper
confident that this is going to lead to
new ideas and new publishable work uh
where we presumably have to make the AI
uh certainly a co-author if not a lead
author.
Okay, so now the first thing you might
ask is how good are just existing LLMs?
These are absolutely impressive. So you
could go to like a reasoning model like
03 or 40 or something like that. You
could say, "Hey, I'm going to give you a
very detailed system prompt. I'm going
to tell you, here's all the information.
Just put it in the G LM and ask for it
to come up with an answer." And what we
find that they're kind of okay, but the
human expert though, this is the score
is sort of you think of it as the a
score that's inverse of the of the delay
for this workload. the what the metric
you're trying to optimize the better
scores are on the right and what you
find is you can the LLM does better than
LLQ and the reason it's a distribution
is the LLM is allowed to come up with
lots of algorithms because every time
you give it you change the temperature a
little bit you give a little it'll come
up with a new algorithm you tell it oh
this algorithm didn't work and it'll
tell you oh you're absolutely right it
didn't work here's a new algorithm
you've you've seen the you've seen the
drill and you can adjust the temperature
and have it come up with new algorithms
so there a distribution of scores and
you find it's a little bit LLQ but far
worse than what the human expert has
produced.
So we've done it differently. It's not a
black box sending into an LLM. It's a
system where it goes in with a
simulator. And for any complex problem,
we either create a simulator or you have
a test bed. And what these agents have
been taught, there's a supervisor agent,
there's a researcher agent, etc. They've
been taught to think about computer
systems. So we've taught them almost the
way in which we've taught we teach our
students with example. We teach them
principles like measure two levels
deeper than you than your high level
metric and we teach it to ask questions
about the data. We teach it to be
consistent you know ask about
consistency questions about the data and
we've taught it how to design new
experiments and there's a difference
here. So there are systems now that are
super exciting out there called alpha
evolve from Google if you've seen alpha
evolve. Um there's fun search which was
the previous version of it. This is an
extremely hot area. But they all come up
with a new idea. But the way they all
come up with a new idea is they morph
the code. So the way these things work
is you come up with some existing piece
of software. Maybe you have two ideas.
You say here's my two ideas and then it
runs the experiment. And at all the
points in time it's creating a database
of programs which is some code for some
algorithm and a score. And to mutate the
code it uses a sort of genetic
programming approach. it mutates and
comes up with a new algorithm by kind of
taking the code taking the code the
codes that have good scores and starts
tweaking it and it throws out the ones
with bad scores. The problem is this is
not how human experts think. This is not
how any human thinks about systems
design. They're not looking at the code
and trying to code monkey around to
figure out the next thing. They're
thinking in terms of conceptual ideas.
They're thinking in terms of the design
and the measurement. So they should be
thinking the code's important but the
architecture the understanding of the
system is also important and the
principles are much more important. So
we've done it differently and we also
think that a single agent coming up with
things doesn't really work. We've built
something that has multiple agents
collaborating and they have different
specialized goals. The goal of the
supervisor is vetting and questioning
and forcing a chain of thought. So it's
a different architecture and it's not
rooted in code. It's rooted in kind of
design and documents and then it goes in
and changes the code and comes up.
There's a lot of measurement that
happens. So I'll show you a demo of how
this works for the same LLM problem. So
you give it a prompt that looks like
this and this is a screenshot of a a
video. So the user prompt basically is
design a request scheduleuler to
minimize average latency. Now you could
do other metrics. Uh people have things
like time to first token which is a
metric because you're sitting there you
want to get the answer quickly if you're
sitting behind. Some people also look at
something called tapot which is time per
output token which is the time between
different tokens on the output. So it
makes you feel like you're getting a
response as chat GPT is producing the
response. There's lots of metrics but we
just look at the entire request which is
actually a good metric for things like
coding agents or things where you have
an agentic system. So you know just
getting a partial result is not very
useful in an agentic system. So anyway
this is one of the metrics. So you don't
have to give it a lot of detail. You
give it the highle architecture and then
you say that use the simulator. So we've
built a simulator for distributed large
language models. Um and for other
systems we have an approach to build
simulators using causal simulation uh
which is a long line of papers. But we
can either work with simulators or we
could work with actual test bed um code.
So you don't have to give it a lot of
details. You give it the high level
architecture and then you give it the
task. You optimize the global
scheduleuler and here's the benchmark
that you have to run and then you have
to specify some guard rails. One of the
things that these AI systems are pretty
good at is cheating. So for example, if
you ask it to optimize a metric and you
give it the workload, give it the
simulator, they the first versions of
this, they're very good at kind of
running the simulator, getting the
result, and then coming up with an idea
that'll only work on that workload. They
basically cheat. It's not that
different, I think, from if you allowed
like humans to say you want to win a
metric, and you give it the workload.
Well, it's going to cheat on that
workload. So you specify the guardrails
to prevent it from cheating. And when
you specify it tightly, it says you're
not allowed to modify this. You're not
allowed to look at the number of output
tokens. Like if you look at the output
tokens, it optimizes it immediately. So
you specify the guard, which was a
lesson. It like if it can cheat, it
absolutely cheats. Um so
we have also asked it to understand the
code first and you'll see that when it
starts working, this is what the
trajectory looks like in this system. I
forgot to say the system is called GIA.
GIA u comes from gal cells which are
support tissues for neurons in the
brain. So in the same way we would like
ga as a system to support human uh
engineers or the human brain. So it
starts looking at this and it starts to
navigate files because it's been taught
to do this exactly the way a human being
would do it. It's given some documents,
it reads the documents and then it's
doing like Unix commands and shell
commands. It has access to a shell. It
has access to sandbox. It's doing pretty
much what a human engineer would do
because that's what it's been taught to
do and then it starts running some stuff
and you know it's really good at being
told how to do it. So it runs its first
LLQ baseline the least loaded queue and
on this workload it finds that the mean
response time is the mean latency is 40
seconds. So it keeps chugging along and
now it produces its first attempt. And
this was super exciting to us because
what it does is it looks at all this.
And by the way, by this time it's
already taken 45 steps. It's about 5 or
10 minutes in. Um, and it says, you
can't read this too well, but it says
this file contains and it does it
exactly as it's been taught. It's been
taught to make small changes,
incremental changes, not to do some big
thing. So it comes out and this is so
amazing. It produces these comments that
are so humanlike. This file contains a
very with like puts a star on very small
amount because it's been told to produce
a very small amount of improvement in
the beginning contains a very small
amount of logic that tries to pick a
replica that will lead to lower overall
latency than and then it becomes
arrogant. It immediately starts calling
this LLQ naive which is very similar. It
says this is a naive LLQ and where it's
picking this up who knows it's probably
from some literature or some code
somewhere else. Then the naive algorithm
which by the way is not actually super
naive. It just happens to not work here.
The key observation is that LQ not only
looks at the number of requests while
ignoring how big those requests are and
how much GPU memory they currently
occupy. This is completely the way we
want human. And by the way, the AI has
not been trained on this problem because
it's going to be applied to all these
other problems. It's been trained on
distributed systems. It has not been it
doesn't know anything about this
problem. It's just thinking the way
we've been uh we've taught it to think.
And it's very gratifying. It's like you
see a student and it runs the first
experiment or they run the first
experiment. I don't know the pronoun for
these LL for these AIs and it produces
an answer which isn't that much better
but you know it's impressive. It
produced one algorithm and it worked. It
didn't it didn't break. It actually
worked and we were super excited. So now
it kind of chugs along and it starts
searching. It hasn't actually done
anything. all these algorithms that it's
searching for and you can see the code
that it oh sorry you can see the code
that it let me uh get back here
I think I was over here yeah all the
code that it's produces in as the search
continues it's they're reasonable ideas
but none of them is actually working you
can see that these trajectories it's
printing out these uh it's plotting
these points um as it go along goes
along and it kind of doesn't really
achieve anything um and At this point,
what's going to happen,
it's been taught to run a bunch of
things. If it doesn't make any progress,
it's been taught to now present its
thinking. It's like now it's going and
meeting its supervisor. And it says,
I've carefully explored multiple design
directions. Memory aware load balancing,
prompt length bucketing, shortest prompt
first. These are all interesting
algorithms. They've never been published
in the context of these LLMs. In fact,
one of these algorithms is from job
scheduling in factories. Another is from
internet um you know like RSVP those
protocols for admission control. It's
tried something. It's tried prompt link
bucketing which is and then memory aware
load balance. It's tried all these
things like it's got from the train
model and then it goes rather than
continuing to iterate blindly. I'm going
to step by step back. It's been taught
to do this in systems profile the
baseline more rigorously and derive a
quantitative model of where time is
actually spent. Is it queuing versus
execution? Is it preeemptions? Is it GPU
memory pressure? This is super humanlike
in what it's actually doing. And the
super, you didn't see this, but the
supervisor goes agreed, which is kind of
what supervisors often do. Um, so um,
and again, that's also been taught. You
either agree, you disagree, or you ask
questions. So that's it's it's very
controlled in terms of what the
supervisor um really does. So now it's
starting to measure things. It doesn't
know anything about this problem, but
it's being taught to measure multiple
levels deeper. So it now instruments
everything it can in the simulator. It
says here's the request simulator 7,300.
The average latency is 40 seconds.
Here's the 95th percentile. It's like
very humanlike. And then it starts
looking at lower level numbers. Plots
the memory utilization. And then it
plots this total number of restarts
which is shown at the bottom. This turns
out to be very key because everybody who
was presented this problem on request
routing assumes this is a load balancing
problem because anytime you have a
request router, you like find the thing
with the least load and you send it
there.
This took Mohammad about a week to
figure out that this is not a load
balancing problem. What's happening is
that on this workload, the memory, the
mean memory utilization is about 90%.
And the P95 is 99.8%.
The memory is kind of being used.
This is not a load balance problem. It
took the human expert who's he's amazing
on these problems. It took him almost a
week to figure this out. This thing got
it in about an hour. And what it really
is is a restart. What a restart is is
the following. You send a job to a GPU.
You send multiple jobs to a GPU and it's
processing it and then it's decoding. So
you might have sent a 50 token input
like small number of characters and it's
producing 10,000 bytes of output and it
runs out of memory. Now when something
runs out of memory in the GPU, what
these engines do is they got to pick
something and stop that stop it. So what
LLM does, it picks the youngest job, the
one that's been in the system the least
amount of time in the parallel execution
and just says I'm going to suspend you.
it leaves it on the engine. So it frees
up memory and then when it restarts
there's no storage to keep track of all
the state that was what was consuming
it. So you restart the whole job. So the
number of restarts is 26%. And this will
turn out to be pretty important because
the whole thing comes down to these
restarts which are essentially you do
all this work and then it's wasted work.
So anyway, there's still going to be
quite a ways to go before we come up
with something new because even Mohammed
took a week after this insight to come
up with something. So now it says nearly
half the latency is pure queuing at the
globe. All these inferences it's coming
up with based on data. Now all the
replicas are driven to almost 100%
memory. To cut latency, we must keep
prompt load prompts prompt loads prompt
loads balanced to avoid replicas hitting
100%. And shorten the global queue,
which is a just sort of a stupid
statement. Of course, you need to
shorten the global queue. That's the
whole point. That's where the latency
is. But at least it's observing these
things.
So then advisor, you missed it. It said,
"Sounds good. Proceed." Which is another
great supervisor uh thing. It's it's
easy to be a professor. Um so [laughter]
so then it starts to do this and it
tries some ideas which actually make it
worse. But one of the things that we've
taught it is if it becomes worse, don't
immediately stop. Understand why it's
becoming worse. So it continues to do
this thing and it's trying lots of
things and actually you see here that
what it's doing and this is a place
where the advisers are finally going to
contribute something on let me just go
back a bit so it runs this and it says
I've run all these algorithms
memory head room it comes up with
beautiful names for these things size
affinity batching I've evaluated all of
the stuff I'm short of this improvement
that you want basically I'm at the same
level I'm 3% % better which is probably
useless and I'm going to continue to
iterate on schedulers and at this point
finally the supervisor has had enough
and it says it seem it doesn't propose
anything it says this is exactly what
we've taught it just ask questions it
seems we've been unable to reduce the
number of restarts why is that is there
something structurally wrong about our
approach that's making it difficult to
limit the number of restarts now when a
question is asked this thing has been
taught to do chain of thought reasoning
So it spits out a boatload of
information and then the supervisor is
going to start discussing this with it.
So the boatload of information it says
why do they persist VLM's preempt on
growth behavior. It alloc allocates just
enough blocks and then comes up with
this example a 50 token prompt that
later decodes 1,5 by the way it's
measured one example and says the 50
token prompt that gave me 1500 will
eventually need 1500 over 16 94 extra
blocks. We cannot foresee this growth.
So an apparently safe decision can
trigger a preeemption. So it found one
example like this and it actually found
an insight which by the way a human
might not have obtained um easily and it
kind of gave you this insight and then
it says that what we need is to come up
with a scheduleuler where we don't know
the decode growth. Decode is the number
of output tokens that you have to
produce. Um and then it says what could
cut restarts
and this is where like this idea of
networking of doing admission control
starts to come into play. What it's
going to do is come up with an insight
that tries to reserve some headroom per
replica. So it's not going to push the
memory to 100%.
So it has a conclusion and the
supervisor is brilliant at this point.
It says proceed. Um so continue um and
then it invents this algorithm that when
we saw it we were really blown away. It
and comes up with a beautiful name for
the algorithm called headroom admission
h global scheduleul harra. What it says
is eliminate most preeemption. So it's
aiming now to not worry about this
highle metric. It's tried all these
ideas. It never cut the restarts and it
says I'm not going to worry about this
latency metric that you want me to. I am
just going to come up with the best way
to cut restarts. and says what I'm going
to do is I'm going to monitor my
workload recent amount of whatever work
is coming I'm going to look at the
number of decode tokens which is the
output tokens and I know the number of
input tokens they're called prefill
tokens in LLM jargon so I'm going to
have this ratio of decode to prefill if
the number of output tokens to the
number of input tokens measured in
recent workload is higher than a
threshold and if the memory with safety
fraction is if the amount of memory is
used is above ove a certain threshold
then I'm going to hold on to the job.
I'm not going to send it. Okay. So I got
these two parameters and it's also been
taught by the way whenever you come up
with a proposal and you think that
there's um some u you don't know how to
tune it come up with two two or more
parameters that you can trade off and
ideally come up with two parameters that
you can trade off between in order to
get the result that you want. So, it
does this
and it actually is going to run it and
the first time it runs it, it actually
becomes worse,
but it's been taught not to not to give
up on it. And uh let me see if I can
show you what it found.
Uh
what it'll do is it runs it and the
number of restarts that it found found
is only seven. But now it says I found a
parameter and I can trade off between
the parameters and it starts trading off
between these. You can see that it
changes these values of the uh let me go
back a bit. It's changing the values of
the uh prefill and decode u the the the
ratio and the safety margin and it
finally breaks through this 40 secondond
barrier. It comes up with something
that's about 30 seconds. But it's also
been taught to compose ideas. So what it
also has been taught is you've done
other ideas before and one of the ideas
it did before was the shortest remaining
time first or shortest job scheduling
which is from factory scheduling when
you have a set of variable job length
jobs you put the shortest jobs first and
the mean latency goes down that didn't
work before because it was running out
of memory but now it goes back and
composes that idea because it's been
taught to not throw away old ideas that
may work so it's been taught to compose
it comes back and composes it and it
actually comes back and produces
something That's about 22 seconds which
matches the time of the human expert
except it did it in 20 simulations in
two hours versus uh over a 100
simulation and two weeks because the
human being gets tired and has to go to
the guy has to sleep. I mean you know he
runs out of ideas. This thing just
continues to continues to crank.
Now oops let me go to the next slide
here. the algorithm it discovers at the
end and implements
it's also been taught to be very compact
and clean. This is the original code. Um
it's got basically it's added these two
key lines and there's a little bit more
somewhere else but these are the two key
lines. It's been taught to have very
understandable, very comprehensible,
very explainable outputs. So this first
idea is to prioritize smaller requests
and the second idea is the submission
control and it writes this in a very
compact way. you can teach it to to uh
provide explanations for it. So this is
not a blackbox neural policy. It's
intended really whether or not somebody
uses this algorithm. The point is the
insight becomes completely obvious to to
people. And that's just one of many
optimizations. Uh we had it go and do a
better batuler. It improved by 21
seconds. By this time mama then my
students had given up. They they wanted
to use the tool. Nobody wants to invent
this on their own. Like let me use the
tool. Let me teach the tool to come up
with something. And then we had it build
an autoscaler when the workload varies.
And when we do all of this together for
these types of workloads, we find we can
provide the same latency guarantees with
40% fewer GPU resources.
Uh we did another use case recently from
a company that um is a nonlm based
transformer model. This is not about
LLMs at all. This runs on the Triton
server. It's doing um some sort of
ranking thing. uh we don't really
understand the know the application and
the original algorithm with the queries
per second or requests per second uh was
this for different uh 90th percentiles
of latencies and they wanted a 20
millisecond latency uh for the 90th
percentile we're able to provide um a
10x higher throughput for the same
latency guarantee as the original system
so again that's another very interesting
result completely different system again
the GIA AI has not been taught anything
about that system it's been taught about
system design. So there's two
differentiators. The first is this
verification playground. It could be in
simulation or a test bed and it
instruments everything and it's been
taught to measure and the other is this
multi-agentic framework with these
supervisors and these engineers and it's
really white box approach not this
blackbox approach. It's rooted in
systems reasoning not the use of LLMs
blindly. So in other words, we are
teaching the things that it should be
looking at uh the principles it should
be looking at. So I'll skip some of
this. Uh if there's something you take
away from here, I think that it is the
specialization is a key to unlocking
performance. As the workload changes, as
the environment changes, you want your
systems to adapt and continually change.
And that is something that this type of
AI uh can enable.
So I I'll leave on this note that AI for
AI I think it's time and just like these
tools for CAD like magic and spice and
so on led to this era of exponential
improvement because what you would do is
you would have these tools that would
run on computers and you would use them
to simulate the next generation of
faster computers which then got built
and then those faster computers would
allow you to build even more complicated
hardware systems with simulation. We
think that the way to get truly
exponential improvements is in something
like this. Um so uh this has been pretty
exciting. So our research side uh we've
recently started a company with this
because people got really excited about
this. It's uh venture funded and the
company's focus is on AI systems for uh
using GEA for AI. But our research at
MIT continues in things unrelated to AI
applications. So if you could apply this
to other computer systems problems, they
could be in wireless, they could be in
um um distributed systems design etc. So
that's where we are. If you u have any
questions or any comments, I can take
them now or you can reach me by email.
Thank you.
[applause] Are
>> you going to be able to maybe the the uh
networking session which is right after
the next talk?
>> Sure. I think I can if people want to
ask questions then I can offer that.
>> Um I have to leave at three.
>> Okay. All right.
Anyway, um like to thank uh uh Hari for
a great talk today. Um if we could
probably take one question if somebody
had something that they were dying to
ask.
>> All right. Go ahead.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Go ahead.
>> Go ahead. So uh very very enjoyable.
Was everything done through the language
modality or did you actually have any
sort of uh any sort of policy that was
parameterized by a neural net or did you
apply reinforcement learning as an
overlay either overall for the iteration
or even once it found some parameters
that it wanted to tune or was even that
tuning done via text to the LLM?
>> In this work we didn't use RL at all. uh
although internally LLMs use RL to get
better and better on things we u did not
use RL in this at all uh uh and our
policies are not neural in nature
although I think there will be problems
where your idea would be useful I'm sure
>> so fantastic work I I really like this
ju can you step like step back above the
kind of system design
>> domain what's this telling us about how
we use the language abilities LLMs in
systems generally because it seems to be
like you know using the systems to argue
in natural language against each other
and to debate internally in the system
is a very different design approach
applicable.
>> That's a good question. I I have only a
superficial answer. I think that our
goal here was to design this thing the
way humans the way we work. So you just
mimic that because we don't think it
needs to get thrown away. We don't think
it needs to get replaced because one of
the things we have at the end is we want
a human agent to be sitting in this mix.
A human to also be sitting right now
this is much more autonomous. So we've
designed like that. So I don't have a
good answer to your question but how do
we think about systems like the last
thing you look at is the code to figure
out how to optimize something. So you're
arguing and making these decisions based
on documents, based on design, based on
pictures and based on analytics. You're
measuring and experimenting. So we've
taught this thing to when in doubt
conduct the experiment and be um ri be
judicious about the next experiment you
conduct. The next experiment you conduct
should not be based on taking pieces of
code and morphing them but instead based
on some understanding of what's going on
underneath in the system. So I think
what it's telling us I I feel like what
it's telling us is the way humans have
been doing this is actually pretty good.
It's just that I think these problems
are too difficult. They're too
complicated. Uh we don't know enough of
the literature and the amount of
literature on this is phenomenal. this
thing knows everything. Uh we don't none
of us knows. Half the papers it's used
in this I've never even heard of. And so
it's telling us that uh that and then
the ability to um kind of reason on
these models is freaking impressive.
Thank you. Yeah.
>> Thank you very much.
>> Thank you. [applause]