The following content is provided under
a Creative Common License. Your support
will help MIT Open Courseware continue
to offer high-quality educational
resources for free. To make a donation
or view additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT Open
Courseware at ocw.mmit.edu.
>> Okay. Uh let's see some of the
administrative stuff. First of all, um
Wednesday's our play test. So it's an
internal play test. you'll learn to play
with each other's games. Uh which means
chances are you're going to get in about
enough time to play one person's game
and enough time for you for that group
to play your game. So, we're just going
to just basically pair teams. Uh
hopefully I think we have 14. So, I
think that works out just right. But,
uh, one thing I would certainly
recommend before going on to Wednesday's
class is making sure that you've had a
chance to play test with at least
someone who's not in your group. Uh, and
the reason for this, what you want to be
keeping an eye out for are rules that
you've already agreed on in your team,
but might have forgotten to write down
somewhere. Um, I want the rules written
down. Uh, they don't necessarily need
need to look great. Uh, type is awesome
because they're easy to read, but uh,
and and they're easy to revise later.
Um, it's not actually a requirement, but
you got to have them written down. You
should be able to just put it in front
of person. I would suggest actually
making a couple of Xes uh if you want to
you come in early uh on Wednesday. Uh
I'll I'll I'll activate the gambit
Xerox. You just make a couple of copies
so that the entire the entire group of
four people who's going to be testing
your game can just read all the rules at
the same time while you're explaining it
to them. Um, for the most um, if you're
in a situation where you already have
rules that you think could be understood
without explaining, I would suggest not
explaining at all. Just give them the
rules and see what they make of it. But
it's going to be very informative that
that way. Not every single team may be
in that situation. You may not have that
much confidence in this point. If you
think you've gotten all your rules
written down, but you don't you just
kind of not feel a little not quite so
confident that everything's in there, do
it anyway. Just don't explain it. Give
it to them. See what they're having
problems with and explain it. Um it'll
still be informative. you still be able
to get that data point of what should we
have written down as a clarification uh
as a complete omission you know uh what
needs to be rewarded uh before the game
actually starts um but uh I do fully
recognize that there may be certain
teams that do not have a set of rules
that's that comprehensive yet in the end
you want to get your play testing time
so you know it's going to take half an
hour for somebody to understand your
game just by reading your rules, then
you do want to try to cut that down
eventually before you submit your your
your game. You want to be in a situation
where someone can understand your entire
game quickly by reading the rules.
>> Um, when you're play testing and timing,
>> we weren't sure, we didn't remember, we
didn't read carefully enough, the what
is the maximum time that the game has to
take and does that include setup from a
complete novice or does that include,
you know, do you Are you allowed to
explain the rules and have totally
experienced players go at it? And once
experienced players go at it, it has to
take a certain amount of time. How how
does it
>> It was supposed to be for novice
players, but you know, I'm just going to
check the actual uh uh syllabus.
>> So, we have to be able to explain the
entire game, run through the entire
playthrough and all that in 10 minutes.
>> That that one I wasn't sure. I think
it's actually only a play through, but I
but give me a sec. I'm going to look it
up.
>> That'd be great.
>> I'm pretty sure it says 10 minutes. 10
to 20. Five 10 minutes of 10. Yeah. 5 10
minutes including setup and play.
>> Including setup and
>> but does that include excluding
>> not necessarily
>> it should include read.
>> It should not
>> it should not 10 minutes is way too
short a time to read and understand and
play a game.
>> Yeah, let me just verify that
about it.
>> Our game takes like two minutes to play
at the moment.
the news.
>> It can take very short time. It can take
really long for creating a deck that has
more information written on each card.
I'll just take time to write it. So that
that way the right lesson
card.
>> So I uh it's true. It doesn't say 10
minutes. Uh that that that take it you
need to be able to play and understand
the game in 10 minutes. So, I'm going to
say setup and play has to be 10 minutes.
So, it's like every time you reset the
game and you play to the end, that
should take that should be under 10
minutes. If it takes longer than that to
understand the game, that's fine. But,
frankly, if it takes more than 10
minutes for someone to understand your
games, you have a problem. Uh, and the
problem isn't going to be one that's
going to affect your grade. is going to
be one that you can use the processes in
this class to iterate on to improve your
game to the point where it doesn't take
that long to understand because the game
reading the rules should not take longer
to think
there are games like that but try not to
make those games uh at least not as
precise
uh so I would say aim for the the
explanate the explaining of the rules to
also take within 10 minutes right now
I'm not quite sure uh it might be okay
if the actual explanation require
requires someone who's actually an
expert in the game to explain it. By the
end of this assignment, you should be
definitely getting to the point where
you don't even need that. Just a new
player with your rules should be able to
understand and play your game in 10
minutes. It could it could involve
discussion of an entire group of new
players. Like, you know, you got four
people, you say four card game, you have
four people and you're all looking at
the room simultaneously and the queen
says, uh, why does it say so and so? And
somebody else who has never played a
game before answers that. That's fine.
And that's actually how a lot of people
play. Um, sometimes people put in quick
start rules on this is this is all you
need to know to play your first round of
of cards and that actually helps a lot
of people get started, you know. Uh, and
then they're like kind of picking up the
other
>> lowers the activation energy.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Um, and in the end more
people play your game. That's that's
that's a good that's a good thing.
Um, so that's on Wednesday. Everyone
please come on time uh because every
minute that we and uh waiting for
someone to show up feeds into that and
full teams don't show up actually. Who's
who's designing a game that has to be
played by four players?
>> So there are some differenc
Okay.
>> All right. Not bad. Cool. All right. So
So even show
>> Okay. Um
>> All right. So that's preparation for
Wednesday. Now, um I do kind of want to
apologize for Friday's lecture. I was on
I was on a lot of meds. Uh you may or
may not have noticed I was having
splitting headache and it was not the
best lecture that I've given in my
entire teaching career. In fact, it was
probably the worst lecture I've given in
my entire
>> I didn't. Well, oh
wait,
um, it occurred to me that there might
actually be a better way to sort of get
some of those concepts across other than
me yammering for 3 hours. Uh, and what
I'd like to do is revisit some of them,
but actually do um do do a bit of an of
an activity. I have never done this
before. Uh, so this is not tested. You
guys are the first iteration of
>> I feel
>> uh
>> but basically what we're going to do is
I'm going to go through these terms
again, explain it one more time. You
guys, you know, can ask me for
clarifications or anything and then
each, you know, group of about I think
two people. Uh we're going to pick a
game that somebody that pretty much
everyone in the class should sort of
know. They may not know the exact rules,
but they'll sort of know game. um and
sort of analyze that game across these
different uh these different axes. And
the idea of that is that if you get used
to this, then you can do that same thing
to your own game. And that may shed
light on how your game is balanced, how
your game is balanced, especially
between chance and skills, which is
really the topic of um of this class.
but also you know questions of you know
is our game doing what we want people uh
want our game to be doing. So that's
that's the general outline. Um, so, uh,
so there's one more thing I want to
mention before I go right into that.
And, uh, and I think and Jason actually
brought up a point at the end of, uh,
last Friday was that, uh, he noticed
that our two end robots, Mr. Robboto and
Badass Mofo 600,
>> 6010, I believe.
>> Yeah, 610. It was upgraded version.
He started at 608
>> and then there's a couple iterations on
Saturday.
>> Um, one of them was purely deterministic
>> but horrendously complex in the sense
that uh horrendously complex not in the
sense that it was difficult to explain
what it was doing but difficult to
predict what it was going to do. Um you
know this this was the one that jumped
that had that that it will start its
turn order based on the number of hit
points that it had you know which
>> and take the number of moves based also
number of hit points it had
>> right so it's you know entirely
algorithmic you know it's just it's just
following its rules every single time um
the other one was pretty much random
right I mean who that was Mr. robot
which had a die roll every every round.
Uh and it just did something perfect
>> and and we ended up with the closest
fight of that day. I think you know um
and and that kind of does drive home the
point that you know at some point of
time you can get complexity through
purely deterministic rules
>> that frankly is as hard to predict as uh
pure as pure randomness.
>> A card game is like that.
>> Your card game is something like that.
But the nice thing about that is that if
you have deterministic, you can see why
it happened. You can see why. Wow. That
I I I didn't expect that to happen, but
I can see why that happened. Uh because
>> so he was going to win.
>> He was so sure he was going to win.
>> Yeah.
>> But then we Yeah.
>> Did not turn out as such.
>> So, you know, that's that's that's
that's a desirable trait. It's a lot
better than just saying, "Well, it's a
die roll." I mean the nice thing about
uh about virals is that it does take it
out of your control.
In fact it's it's kind of designed to
make it not skill-based and as a result
of that you give people who are lagging
who are having a harder time playing the
the game and entirely unskill based way
of catching up. Uh which is awesome um
if that's what you're going for. And
then the other one is you know if it's
if you just make it deterministic but
complex enough so the behavior is just
hard to predict but logical once it
actually happens then you know you kind
of get the same result and it all
balances out. Obviously Dals are really
easy to implement. Uh it's difficult to
actually come up with rules that
deterministically give you the kind of
complex behavior that you're looking
for. Um but it's a nice thing to go for.
Of course, to get that complexity,
sometimes you need so many rules that
people just kind kind of get bored. It's
like, wow, this is really complicated.
I'm not sure whether I can figure out
what the next step is going to be. And
then you just give up. That's kind of
the downside of, you know, really
complex determination behavior. Um,
but you know, it's it's it's neat that
that that that you kind of saw both of
those playing off each other and you saw
kind of them behaving in pretty much
unpredictable ways and yet giving nicely
balanced results. So they're both really
really valuable tools.
Um, so now I'm going to be actually
deeply deeply plagiarizing from Salem
and from uh KB Salem and Eric Zimmerman
uh from uh Rules of Play, which is that
one of those big thick books I brought
in on the first day. Um I'm not making
you read it because I find that book
takes three pages to explain what could
have been explained in one which is why
I have why I have a whole bunch of
summaries in here. Uh but uh I am going
but but what what that book does do is
give you very very concrete terms that
are pretty well accepted um if not
necessarily among game designers among
people of various expert domains. Uh and
I've got some of those over there for
people for you to refer to. Um I touched
a little bit on information theory on on
Monday. that model of you know uh how a
signal goes from an uh someone who wants
to send it through a transmitter goes
through some sort of channel is received
through some sort of receiver to to a
person and and I talk if that
transmitter if the if a person want if
if the person who wants to send a signal
it's actually the game the game state uh
and is transferring information to a
player who needs to get information
about what's going on in the game um in
order to make a decision
uh then you can see how this applies to
game design. And in between you have
noise. You you you you have the thing
that prevents you from knowing exactly
what the game state is. And um and there
are c there are certain words that are
associated with with with that level of
of uncertainty. I mean uncertainty and
certainty are two are two words that
they suggest to begin with. Um
so
just one second.
So um so you know the uncertainty
includes both the
the the
your inability to know what's going to
happen next due to chance or due to
really complex behavior uh as you saw in
both of the robots. Uh it's just the
degree to which uh how much the game uh
all the different states the game could
take either maybe in the next turn or
throughout the entire play of the game.
Um
and uh and in information theory they
actually also use the word information
almost interchangeably. Uh unfortunately
this gets kind of confusion uh kind of
confusing because people don't actually
use the word information in that sense
in day-to-day life. And if and in fact
I'm going to propose a different way of
looking at it that also uses the word
information in a completely different
way. So I'm actually going to stop using
uh the word information for now. I'm
just going to call uh call it
uncertainty which is pretty much all the
different things that could happen in
the game you know uh either in the next
turn or or throughout the the game.
Certainty is the is the degree to which
you know uh you have knowledge about
what could have happened. you know, a
chess board pieces could be configured
in any position, but one move after the
opening, there's only a small set that
it could possibly that that that that
that uh that could possibly happen,
right? I mean, it's probably on the
order of only one side is moving for the
first time. Any one of the pawns could
move
>> 20
>> 20 Yeah, the knights could move. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> So, you know, there's only 20 20
different possible things. So, you know,
that's kind of the degree the degree of
certainty that you have among all the
different states, all the uncertainty of
this chessboard, you you are certain
that it's going to be limited to this
chunk. Um
and um
and your your your knowledge of what
that ratio
uh is of how much you know could be
happening based on what you know of the
game rules based on your experience of
the game uh based on uh your skill in
the game uh to the states that the game
could possibly take uh is called risk.
So um you can think of you can flip you
can flip it the other way around and say
that if the uncertainty of the first
turn is is you know 20 different moves
you know but you're certain that you
know the guy that you're that that that
oh say say I'm the opening player I'm
playing white and I really only know how
to make three of those openings
effective you know so I'm I I then then
then I then and if that person and the
person that I'm playing against knows
that really I only know three openings
really I only know two um you know then
then that person's degree of of risk is
kind of limited to the range of
possibilities that branch out of that
two out of 20
um so that's one way that you can sort
of describe risk um let me see whether
there's a more technical term that I can
describe that with the patient
So um so one thing that I want uh the
that I want you to think about later um
actually for for for the analysis that
we're going to to um to to do you I want
groups of two 4 6 8 10 12 14 15 mostly
groups two and one group of three. Um
actually one
actually let's just do groups of three.
It would be easier that way. Um and uh
and to think about you know pick a game
first that that you think that you can
probably mention in this class without
having to explain to everybody else
exactly how this game is played. Uh you
know uh it could be a computer game, it
could be a war game, it could be a card
game, something fairly wrong there. Um,
and I want you to think about okay in
you know what are the things that uh
what what what are all the variables
that you need to know in this game you
know uh do it in fairly simple terms you
know if you're doing something like a
game of uh cosmic encounter or something
then you know that's that you can say
that every single race has a unique
power without explaining to me every
single power uh and which is I think
they're likeundred different races in
the game. So that was cosplaying
encounter.
>> Oh, it's fun.
You will get a chance to play later this
this semester. So cool. Um let's see. Uh
so think think about what are all the
variables that you got to keep track of.
That's kind of the degree of
uncertainty. That's the amount of
information that could be in the system
in a way that Shannon and we were you
you you use it. That's all the different
range of possibilities, all the
different things you got to keep track.
What do you know for sure as a single
player in this game? Um, you know, what
do you know at your first turn and what,
you know, what what sort of information
do you tend to pick up along the way? Um
Um,
let's see. Yeah. So, so let's start with
that. We got, you know, just five
minutes. It doesn't have to be an
exhaustive list. So, let's split in just
groups of three.
the first activity and we're going to be
visiting every single one of
>> through all these different lenses. So
I'm just going to start actually now and
you know uh and if we ran out of time to
do some uh uh uh this we can always do
it after class and we can talk about it
u but we're going to go through all of
them so I'm going to speak to this uh
starting with this team and moving all
the way over just talk about
>> Sure. So, we decided to go for Scrabble.
And so, in terms of variables, you have
the individual individual tiles. Their
tiles are uncertain. Yours are fairly
certain. The ones on the board are
certain because they're faced. So,
>> um
>> the ones that have been placed, you
mean?
>> Yes.
>> Yes. Another variable. Well, we're not I
guess the variable is the bonus squares
on the board.
>> Uh you can think of them as even though
they're fixed on the board, they're
variable in terms of as more tiles get
played, some of them become open and
some of them become closed, and you
don't know which ones are going to be
open and closed.
>> True. True. Um, also yes. Uh, yeah. All
right. Uh, so that's that's that's
something as you don't know how that's
going to to turn out during the middle
thing. So, one thing that's interesting
about word games, especially Scrabble
and crossword puzzles in general is that
a lot of them uh rely on the fact that
uh lang the English language in
particular is actually pretty redundant.
you can take about 50% of the letters
out from a word uh this fairly long word
and you can still figure out what it
means. Uh that works really well for
crossbow puzzles uh because you know you
get something like 25% of words you can
actually still figure out word what it
means especially if you got a clue. Um
but uh uh for Scrabble it also means
that it's now possible for you to make
uh connections between disperate uh
disperate characters. you can find a
word that's going to fit that. Um cuz
part of the problem uh actually um that
hasn't played words with friends.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Okay. So, my brother,
>> it's online scramble basically, right?
You know. Oh, yeah.
>> Um
>> the same folks who made Worlds with
Friends made a game called Worlds with
Pirates.
>> And um and I I have a screenshot here of
a game I was playing yesterday. And uh
basically you have you have few way
fewer letters. You have H A R a lot of
Rs
and exclamation mark.
>> So the number of letters that you can
get uh uh the quantity of the letters
that you get are the same as the
scrabble but the range of different
letters that you can get is way lower,
which means there actually a lot less
less uncertainties. Um,
and because the because the game has so
much um because this language, this
parent language has so much uh uh uh I I
I I want to be very careful to use the
right word here.
>> Uh is it true?
>> So my so If I'm using the right word
here, the word that this is actually a
very non-redundant language because a r
is is a word a r r is a different word
both of which are valid. Um so there's
actually very little redundancy. uh you
know it's like I see eight R and I think
that could be any number of words
and as a result you notice that my that
this this this game of words with
pirates it results in an incredibly
dense world because I can fill in
whereas you can't do that with scrabble
scramble spaces go empty uh and get
locked out because you know unless you
have an incredible knowledge of scrabble
dictionary for the most
um you don't know those exploits that
are going to let you slice in an extra
character because most people's
knowledge of English
>> doesn't happen again.
>> So anyway, I thought that was
specifically useful for for illustration
at this point. Okay, so Scrabble. All
right, cool. Um next game.
>> So, uh we did go fish. So I mean some of
the of information we had were like
every player's hand and the um pile of
cards in the middle that you can
>> uh
uncertainty
>> being what cards the other player has
and the channel that comes out it is
them asking what cards they want and you
asking
>> them for cards, right? And there's noise
because just because they're asking for
a certain card can kind of imply what
they have in their hand, but doesn't
necessarily tell you what don't have,
>> right? It only tells you what they don't
have in their hands. Sometimes it tells
you what they don't have in their hands.
Sometimes it they they give you a card
and I forget the rules. Do you have if
you have multiple threes and someone
says, "Got any threes?"
>> You give all three.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Okay. So, so, so you
>> Why would you have three threes? Why
don't you just put a pair down?
>> Yeah. That would just be dumb.
>> I mean, you're a bad player.
>> Yeah.
>> But for the most part, you know, in in
in that game, um that's your one channel
finding out what the state of the game
is. Uh the game state is what everybody
has has at hand.
>> Cool. Cool. Cool.
>> Uh Mario Kart.
>> Mhm.
>> Sweet.
>> Yeah. There's a lot of there's a lot of
uncertain a lot of things to keep track
of. So the things that you can't
possibly keep track of but that are
really important to the game are uh you
know what's what's going to come up when
you hit an item block and what items
people around you have. So you might
think it's safe to like bump another
player, but if they have three green
shells, they can activate that then and
blast you out of the map. Um
>> another one is like what position you're
in because if you're first place, you
know, the blue shell hits you. So it's
also what position you're in, what
position people are in, stuff like that,
>> right? So,
>> so the probability of being hit by a
blue shell is way higher when you're
number one.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. So, you gather information through
your visual range, which is also a
function of basically where you are in
the map.
>> And so, the information you're getting
about other players,
>> uh, depends on where you are. And
interestingly, you know, if they're
immediately in front of you, you have a
lot more information than if they're
behind you, you have a lot more
information than if they're way far away
from you,
>> right? Because if they're behind you or
they're way far away from you, you don't
know what what weapons they've got
equipped for you. for instance, you
generally know what position other
people are in,
>> but that's all you got, you know. Uh so
that's that's some uh
>> and then there's different paths and
levels. So you might think there's
someone in the same position as you, but
they're not at the same point because
they take a different branch. And then
there's also the varying capabilities of
different cars. So in Mario Kart 64, if
you take Bowser and you're playing and
there's Toad, you can ram into Toad and
Toad will go like flying.
>> Bowser.
>> Yeah.
So many one element of risk uh that you
get in uh in uh Mario Kart is that the
kinds of weapons that you get are pretty
much weighted based on where you are in
the game. If you are at the back, you
get all the awesome weapons because the
game
>> you get a star like Disney Racer on
PlayStation was way more weighted than
that.
>> Sure, there are more obvious versions of
of this. I think Super Monkey Ball does
this too actually. Um, when you're right
in the front, I think all you get are
bananas. Is that is that that the only
>> in parts?
>> Mostly bananas and like one green shell.
>> Yeah,
>> that's pretty much it.
>> You get you get a file jump,
>> but also the fake mystery box.
>> Yeah.
>> And then halfway through uh and halfway
games, the waiting is I'm going to guess
roughly linear. So the basic idea is of
one of the things about risk is that
every time you take up a new weapon, you
you are basically taking a gamble about
what you're going to get. If you're
already holding a weapon,
>> yeah,
>> sometimes you can choose to discard that
to pick up something new. And I believe
later iteration you carry two weapons or
something like that. Um so you know
that's one element of of risk, right?
What do I know? I know what I've got.
You know what what what else do I know?
I know what position I I'm in. And I
know that if I run into this box right
now and I got rid of what I had, I could
pick up a cooler weapon,
there's a probability associated with
that. And you know, and that's the other
risk. You know, it's like you kind of
it's it's like a one way to think of it
is that it is a certain outcome with a
certain probability associated. You are
going to get away with it. It might be
crap.
>> You only really gain a sense of hardware
though from like experience
>> playing with it. Yeah, it's one of those
things where your certainty of this game
goes out west the more you play. Yeah.
>> Cool. Thanks.
>> So we beat Monopoly.
>> Sure.
>> So
uh so Monopoly basically u what's
certain is who owns what property
essentially and it's technically certain
how much money everyone has though
keeping track of all that information on
a term basis can be difficult. So there
is a little bit of relative uncertainty
just due to the quantity of information
there
>> and uh yes you gain uncertainties. It's
actually Monopoly has very different
opening and end games essentially. Um
towards the start of the game there's a
lot of uncertainty about how other
players are going to value property that
you give up. As Bowen was telling me I
wasn't even aware of this in Monopoly
when you decide not to purchase a
property it actually goes up to auction.
Yeah,
>> that's like most people that
>> and it's an open auction and so you
don't know what other people's
valuations are. So each time you bid,
you're taking a risk
>> if you don't actually want that price.
>> That makes the game actually more
interesting.
>> Oh yeah.
>> It turns out it turns out the game is
not that much more interesting
>> even when you even when you have the the
option system.
>> We will get to
>> still pretty boring.
you see my degenerate strategies. We
will get to that.
It's the end of the game. Basically,
it's also a lot of uncertainty about
what players are going to be, well,
these aren't part of the rules, but
whether they're going to be willing to
trade with you, whether you can, you
know, do things like manage to get into
jail so you can stop landing on people's
properties, kind of thing. Chances, of
course, another level of uncertainty
there. So,
>> yeah. Uh it it's weird about the risk
associated with an auction because
>> you kind of know
the sort of
especially in the early game you have a
vague idea of how much people could
possibly bid on this, right? You know,
it's like not not more than the amount
of money that they have or needing a
mortgage or something that they have
just to get the cash for an auction. But
it's um but it's it's it's one of those
things that you know would fatty bill.
Uh so it's true.
Okay. All right.
>> So we chose chess
and so
chess has this no uncertainty in the
game because the if I would say any
uncertainty it would be you don't know
what your opponent is going to do. Mhm.
>> So you have to make a move assuming that
he's going to do something he can do
something completely different.
>> And as well as like risk in the game,
>> the only risk is also not knowing what
your opponent's going to do. So he could
do a series of moves which causes you to
be in situation where you have to lose
piece.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, that's pretty much it.
>> No, no, that's that that's cool. Um, I
would argue that not knowing what your
player is capable of is deep
uncertainty. And in fact, it's it's it's
a huge amount of of of uncertainty in
game. It's true that, you know, the way
how the pieces move are and where the p
the pieces are placed, you know,
everyone knows that. Uh, everyone want
to get a mixed one. It's a game of
perfect information. The game state is
low noise. you know, you you you know
exactly what's going in the game unless
you're playing with like a 5-year-old
who doesn't put the piece right down in
the square, you know. Um
>> so I guess something where it'd be a lot
more a lot more noise for the game would
be if you're playing something like
speed test because then it's like oh you
just have to think fast and
>> sure it's a lot harder to realize what's
going on.
>> Yeah, that that is true because then now
now you're limited by your own cognitive
u bandwidth, right? you know, uh, so
that's true, but it it doesn't change
the amount of uncertainty in the game.
The uncertainty on the game really is
your opponent and what's in that
person's head, uh, you know, the
knowledge of of openings and knowledge
of different moves, whether that player
has seen something that you haven't
seen, uh, or, you know, those of counter
that that that you always annoying.
>> Always annoying. You get the impression
that they know exactly how to counter
what you're doing and you're kind of
floating like,
>> right, right, right. Sometimes you're
counting on them to do something and
then you don't. It's like, well, did you
do that? I would have done that.
>> I think it's like golf where you have to
pretend like you really look like
poker.
>> Um, okay. So, so you know that that's
one way to look at your your game. What
do you know? What do you don't uh don't
don't know. What's the probability that
you uh what's what's the probability of
certainty that you know something? Um,
and of course I'm not not as you what as
as a game designer you're thinking what
do your players know? What your players
not know? What can your players do? A
reasoned a reasonable guess of what
likelihood something is going to happen
um or something is going to be true. You
know, it's like, okay, I don't know how
what cars that person has, but I but
there's an 80% probability that that
person has jacks of higher off the of
the of the the trump because that person
bid on that trump. That's that that
that's a fairly good good guess. Um
lowrisk guess. Okay. Now, now we're
going to the other schema which is the
information systems. Um now I talked a
little bit about perfect and Imperfect
information. Perfect information games.
You know games state. Everyone knows
game state. No player does not know game
state. Um imperfect information. Okay,
there's something that you don't know.
Maybe it's you know card games in
particular because cards have two sides.
You know that's cards are t typically
used to hold back the perfect
information. Anyone play strategy
in perfect information any you know
every single piece. There's nothing
random in the entire game. There are no
dy rolls, you know, there are no random
shuffles.
>> Well, the other guy chooses to
click where he places his pieces. It can
be perceived as random to you.
>> Can be perceived as random. It is true.
It is. But it I mean but but but but uh
let's get really uh uh specific about
termin is that it's actually uncertain.
It's not actually random. It is a
decision made by not play by rules. Um
so yeah. So actually one objectively
like it is not random. It is perceived
as random. Uh it's perceived as
effectively right because really the
person could have put his pieces
anywhere within I think the first two
rows or something like that. Um
so so so um how however that's that's
kind of a blood tool. This is game and
game of perfect information or imperfect
information. That's a yes no question.
doesn't really tell you that much about
your your
your asking okay what is actually random
and what is not actually uh random but
may be perceived as that slightly better
question you know uh because you can
think okay if if I as a player I know
that's not random but it could be
anything
uh because of what the other player has
done I'm going to treat it as random I
might as well do all and when you're
designing for that player you are you
are doing all your calculations just
taking it as random
Um
there might be um uh there is a game
theorist not game theorist a game
studies uh uh scholar named Cia Pierce
who works over at Georgia Tech and her
proposal is that u a more useful range
of questions to ask would be what's
known to all players you know and in
game of perfect information everything's
known to all players uh what's only
known to one player what's known to the
game you know is like uh especially for
a computer game computer knows game
knows a lot more about game state. But
that sometimes that even comes down to
rules. So if you've ever done boss
battles in something like Metroid or
Castlevania for instance, there are
rules of which every that every single
boss is going to react to anything that
you do. Maybe it's based on time. Maybe
it's just a sequence of actions or like
the robots that you like the AI giant
robot that you guys programmed uh in
person. You don't know those rules going
into the game. that's those doesn't
prevent you from playing the game. And
in fact, part of the fun is figuring out
what that rules is, figuring out what
the pattern is against. Um, so that's an
example of the thing that's known to the
game. Other things that are known to the
game are
um
actually now maybe that's not that's not
a good example because randomly
generated stuff like there is a shuffle
deck. Uh shuffled decks are kind of one
of those things where it's a little bit
unclear uh about what whether the game
knows what's in that stack. It's true
that you shuffled it. So, it's randomly
generated, but once you've shuffled it,
it is now in a fixed order. Uh so the
game knows what order that that that
message even though it was initially
randomly generated. It's not like
randomly generated every single turn
like a di. Um but you know, it's a good
question to ask. you know, uh even if
it's not an easy question to answer,
it's a good question to ask what's known
to the game but not known to the rest of
players and what's just randomly
generated. You know, it's like, you
know, even if the game had a brain, they
would have no idea what this game's ter
because it's a freaking title. Um, so
use those games again. Every single one
of those games they're talking about
what's what's known to all players,
what's known to one player, what's known
to the game, and what's just randomly
generated. Go.
Okay.
Every single game detail
should we just do?
>> So we changed again poker Texas Holdm
now. So no longer in chess and so
it's kind of it's imperfect information
because you know what's in your hand,
you know what's out on the board, but
you have no idea what everyone anyone
else has. They can try and tricky. So
it's maybe perceived. It's perceived
knowledge. So uh like let's say they
play a large bet. It's perceived that
they must have a good hand, but it's not
necessarily
accurate. So it's it's not really an
objective based. However, it is
subjective. Whenever you finally show
your hands, then it's either you want
one or you lost. It's not really up for
debate.
>> So I guess it could also be uh whether
you know like again with chess how you
what what the other player knows whether
uh the other players know like
conventional poker conventions for
>> for folding or not.
>> Mhm.
Okay. Um
let's see other things. Other things
that a lot of uh Korean especially poker
uh there that is known to all players
will be things like what are the number
of kings in the deck you know what are
number uh you know what are what are the
forces and what are all different hands
that that that you could make and what
are the point values. So that's just one
example of things that need to be known
by all players. Well, that the
assumption that all players know that.
Sometimes all players don't know all
>> like memorizing the probabilities is a
huge
>> really big players know the objective
probabilities of a given hand.
>> Yeah, actually a lot of casinos they let
you bring in a card with the
probabilities. You can
>> really
>> I'm surprised that they let you do that.
Okay. All right.
>> I guess I guess blackjack.
>> I'm pretty sure blackjack too you can
bring in cards with numbers on. So, you
know, um you know that the the themes
that are known to the game would be, of
course, you know, shuffle order. Uh
I guess this happens more in blackjack
where you've got like five decks all
shuffled together and you know, you
know, there are certain number of kings
in and they're in there somewhere. So,
if all the kings get played out, you're
going to have no more kings left in
there and then you can you can you can
sort of do do computations from them. Um
and uh one thing I want to clarify about
objective and proceed. Um objective
doesn't necessarily mean that any one
player knows whether this is good or
bad. Uh the idea is that if if there was
a third party observer who was not
playing the game and knew all of game
state, you know, look into the deck to
look into the hands, you know, uh knows
what's coming up or a computer running
the game that that person that computer
will know to the the extent to where
something is good or bad. So if you get
a hand, you know, um probabilistically
you can sort of tell, well, this is a
pretty darn good hand or this is this is
already probabilistically crappy.
>> I got cheap enough suits.
>> It might be good for that game, right?
It might it might be just like I I don't
care, you know, but it might be good if
nobody else has anything, you know, but
uh
>> probability you're not going to have it.
>> Yeah, but but pro probabilistically you
want to win that. That's why you have
pro players saying things like right up
until this point I was winning, you
know, and then you know and then you
lost the entire game. But it's like
probabilistically they were doing
everything right. And and actually
that's a lot of professional players
have those strategies to uh to say well
they were doing everything right. Sure
they they lost the hand but to them they
were winning they were winning
everywhere up up to the point where they
fold. Uh okay next game
Monopoly game let's run through the all
players one player game etc.
>> Uh all players know the board state. So
the people that are owners of any of the
properties and what's still owned by the
bank. Um
everybody so
every given player knows the amount of
money that they have and also what
valuation they place on all of their
properties which is not known to other
people except kind of incidentally
through their actions. Uh the game knows
the state of the community chance and
sorry community chance and chance decks,
right?
>> And then there's randomly generated die
rolls.
>> Die rolls.
>> I I I I'm forgetting whether uh Monopoly
requires you to show your bankroll
clearly.
>> I think so.
>> If you want to know how much money
someone else has,
>> they have to tell you.
>> It would be interesting to look up and
see uh what the actual. Cool. All right.
So popular
>> good marketing.
>> It's very shallow.
>> So it's really it's really familiar. I
know I've so I asked friends of mine who
have to play Monopoly but don't like to
play for instance settlers. And um a lot
of it is really you don't have to think
too much about it. It's just an excuse
to sit around and talk with people. Um
there's there's um not that much that
kind of distinguishes somebody who's
like a incredibly good player from an
incredibly bad player. It's has that bit
of that any given Sunday feel to it. So
you always have an opportunity to win
there can be dramatic swings of faith
and all that kind of thing.
>> So it's kind of like adult candy
can you just go through the motions.
>> Yeah. But I mean, I also have friends
who are like avid Monopoly players and I
really believe that there's a deep skill
to playing Monopoly, but I'm yet to be
convinced.
>> There is a strategy. I'm not sure it is
a skill.
>> Okay. All right. Cool. Thanks.
>> We need Mario.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Sticking with
the game.
>> So, except for a couple of special
stages in general, players are aware of
their welcome position other players um
during the race. We assume everyone
knows the maps. You play them. So, we
assume everyone knows the maps.
You're not sure if you know what other
people like what their special powerups
are and you can like look at the screen
and see what they have.
>> Yeah. So, if you're playing against
other humans, there are situations where
you definitely know what they have. I
don't think
>> it's a strategy.
>> In Mario Kart DS, you know all your
opponent's items.
>> Yeah, that's true. That's lame.
>> Suddenly on a on a simultaneous
multiplayer game where your screen is
divided into four or two.
>> Yeah. You know what your opponent has
and designers have to take that into
account.
>> Same thing for Halo, right?
>> Yeah. Talking about just said it. You
said counteract.
>> Yeah. Um and let's see what else. Uh so
there's um you perceive it as kind, I
guess, completely random, especially if
you don't pay much attention to it, but
it's more like weighted random what
items you get. And so that's something
that you might figure out as you go
along that actually as you're further up
uh you you get worse items. I in fact
it's a good strategy in that game to
remain second place for most of the race
and then and then go to first. You don't
really want to be in first place.
>> Now the game knows those probability
rates.
>> The game definitely knows that. The game
also knows who's going to get hit by a
red shell for example when you launch
it. It's not entirely clear to me as a
player when there's multiple people in
front of me who's going to pick
>> um when I shoot a green shell be back
behind me.
You know, the game knows what's going
on. I I know. Is that in my field of
view? I might hear it. I might hear the
result. I might not.
>> The game definitely understands the
physics way better than any human player
could possibly.
>> Yeah. Yeah. For sure. For sure.
>> Yeah.
>> The game knows all the players positions
and abilities, but it doesn't know what
they're going to do or how they're going
to interact with each other. It also
doesn't presumably actually know uh what
items are coming up.
>> Oh, and then another thing is as players
you can learn the patterns of some of
the of the hazards and and and be able
to be able to predict which way to go
depending on when you where how you know
a certain
>> that's like knowing a map, right? That's
like knowing.
>> Yeah. What if any of them are random?
Actually,
>> depends.
>> Some of them are random. But uh one
thing to keep in mind about randomly
generated computers obviously uh well
maybe not it's not obvious but uh
computers actually have a real tough
time generating really random numbers.
>> It's a pseudo random
>> is they could that's why they're called
pseudo random. Uh so so to some extent
the computer knows but it's trying
really really hard not to know that
coming up but it's really really useful
if you ever go into game design uh for
digital games uh to use that to your
advantage because you can use that to
reproduce problematic situations. Uh
it's like yeah random number generator
that we have absolute control over uh
and you use that to uh to your advantage
when you're trying to find bugs.
>> Cool. Thanks. Um, so just remind we did
go fish. So I mean clearly every player
knows what's in his hand, knows what
pairs have been played thus far, knows
how many cards people have and stuff
like that. Um,
>> generally people should know what cards
have been given from one player to
another player. They might have
forgotten that. Um
sometimes there's a situation where uh
most of the players don't know which
pairs can be possibly made at a given
point.
>> Sometimes one player may know that
because he might have one card that
someone else gave their card to somebody
else
>> or something like this. But the game
definitely knows this.
>> Um also the order of the deck is random.
>> Yeah.
>> At least right at the beginning first.
Yeah.
>> Cool. So for Scrabble, all the players
know the pieces on the board. They all
know the letter frequencies.
>> They don't know what tiles you're going
to get next. The bag is random graph.
>> What does everyone know the dictionary
though? Like the dictionary knows it.
>> I mean that that's the knowledge that is
both available to one player and to the
game. Technically the game has official
Scrabble dictionary. uh if you're
playing a digital version then they're
probably using it. Uh you're playing
against your family, they probably don't
accept, you know, certain two letter
words
in the dictionary.
>> Um
>> we also don't know like what the other
players have like,
>> right? So one person only knows like
what they have, but then like the other
three aren't really. But then again,
towards the end of the game, we
discussed how if you're playing with two
people, you can probabilistically figure
out what they
>> or figure out what you're going to get
next when you draw.
>> It's also more likely for you to figure
out as as the game goes on and piles get
clear, what letters will never come up.
>> At pro at pro levels of Scrabble, they
do know exactly what final steps, right?
There's a there's like a certain point
that you get to at which point Scrabble
players just know what's left and work
out kind of all the possible.
>> At that point, do you just like keep
letters that are more likely to work
with what's in the bag? Like how does
how do you use that to your advantage?
>> After all the files drawn, you know,
>> yeah, you're trying to prevent them from
using the letters that they've got. Uh
but if you uh most scramble boards uh
although I don't know if all scramble
boards have this they actually show the
frequency in which a number of uh the
number of letters the number of tiles
for any given letter are in there. So
it's actually expected that you're going
to take this into account. It's like oh
four you know there are only four hes or
something like that and they're all out.
All right there's none coming down.
>> Random other Scrabble facts. found out a
lot about Scrabble when I was reading
about computational Scrabble planes.
Apparently in Scrabble tournaments,
people like they have a chess clock
system, right, for making sure it
doesn't go over time. And apparently
people set aside like half their time to
playing the end game of Scrabble,
>> which is the point at which at which
there's basically full information
>> and then you're just sitting there out
like
what the best sequence of play is to
beat your opponent and it becomes like
chess.
How much time do you get on the test?
>> I don't even remember.
>> So yeah, high level Scrabble is
completely different from the Scrabble
when you play. It's crazy.
>> I'd love to find a video.
>> Okay. All right. Uh still got some time.
Great. Uh let's talk about cybernetics.
um cybernetics are you know given that I
kind of invented at MIT uh is something
that you probably encountered and I' we
mentioned this a few times the whole
idea of feedback I want to break this
down a little bit though uh because
um feedback works uh the the official
sense of feedbacks in the sort of theory
of cybernetic systems as written by
Robert weer back in the 40s I think um
is that there is a sensor something
which measures
what the system is doing. There is a
comp there's a comparator which is
in his era was a machine and in our era
is probably a rule a logic a statement
uh you know you know that that that that
compares this against some sort of uh
set value or some sort of rule and
decides to take action um and activate
and you can think of this this way all
as you know your sensor is the variable
that you're looking at or a certain
collection of variables that you're
looking at. So, what are you looking at?
A comparator is a rule that you're
comparing against. Uh, you know, it's um
I'm trying to pick a game that no one
has mentioned here so far
uh that has a good feedback system.
Say, um I I I played a version of cops
and robbers as a kid where every time
you c you the cop caught a robber, the
robber would have to go into a jail area
and couldn't get out of it. to someone
tagged him, someone from the robber team
tag them. Uh, and the basic idea is that
the fewer people there are in a field,
assuming they are playing in a fixed
space. The more robbers there are in a
jail, the easier it is for a robber to
run uh uh actually because they have
more freedom. Sure, there are more cops
to any given robber so they can do uh
kind of flanking,
but one of the variables that we're
looking at are how many people are
currently in jail. Um and uh and an
activator is basically what's the rule
or what's the game dynamic that comes
into play. So that's kind of interesting
thing about the cops and robbers uh
situation. I want to have more space to
run when all my buddies are in jail, but
there are a lot more cops going after me
and that actually uh means that it's
easier for them to flank me even though
I have more space to run. So those are
both a negative and a positive uh
feedback system. more space to run is
actually a negative feedback system. it
uh and how you tell the difference is is
it stabilizing to my state or is it
cumulative to my state uh if if it's
stabilizing which means you know I'm
doing badly my team is doing badly but
this is now giving me an edge uh or I'm
doing really well and this is really
crappy um Mario Kart has tons of these
um those are negative feedback those
those are things that basically reduce
the the uh the gap between the best and
and the people who were doing well,
people doing well. Positive feedback is
accumulated. They're doing well, they're
going to do even better. So, the cops
have got everybody but one and now it's
five to one game. You know, the cops
have a that that's a positive feedback
system because now now they can do
tactics as opposed to everyone going
after someone. Um
uh and and you have these two feedback
loops kind of working together. There
are tons of these in games. uh and games
aren't really the kinds of closed
systems that cybernet that cybernetics
was actually originally designed to
handle. Um in fact very few systems are
actually closed systems in that way and
games are actually better than most. Um
but let's but let's talk about you know
uh what's in all of the games we're
talking about. What are some of some of
the negative feedback loops? What are
some of the positive feedback loops?
Mario Kart team, you've got way too
easy.
>> Think of someone the game. you think of
some of the games.
>> Yeah, that's what I didn't know that the
AI automatically go faster if there's a
huge gap.
>> That's more than just a Mario Kart
actually. It does a lot of racing games.
>> Also, when if you're playing like the
Grand Prix, there's always three
computers that are always better than
everyone else and then all the rest of
them. So, they will always be the ones
that are in the top four like they're in
the top always.
>> But Mario Kart, think of different game,
but let's take a look. Go through all
the games. Uh
>> uh sure. Think about chess. Actually,
chess and white actually be an
interesting one for
>> No, but shot chess we take a shot after
shot.
>> Yes.
>> That gets too easy.
>> Well, it depends on Well, take it can be
negative feedback, but there's also the
method positive feedback. It depends on
how you play.
>> Yeah. Winner takes any drinking game
pretty much.
>> Yeah.
>> It depends on what your goals are,
right?
Shot chest. Shot chest. You can have it
that whenever you take a piece, you have
to drink that piece. But then there's
also whenever you take a piece, the
opponent has to drink the piece.
>> So that means so it can either be
negative or positive feedback depending
on how you play.
>> Yeah. But but but let's pick a version
of the game.
>> Uh ideally pick the same game, but if
it's too boring, pick something else.
The same criteria.
Okay. So, uh let's start
from somewhere in the middle, which I
think is this right here.
>> So, we took a pretty easy one, but it's
pretty like mathematical feedback. We we
did war. Okay. Statistically, if you're
winning, every time you win, you're
lowering the value of your cards.
>> You get the average value of your deck.
>> Yeah. So, mathematically,
positive feedback loop, right? Right.
Right. Lowering the fact that you're
getting more cards. Negative the fact
that you're lowering the average value
within your deck.
>> So which which makes it harder for you
to keep winning.
>> Exactly.
>> Okay.
>> So that's just negative feedback. Any
positive feedback loop?
>> There's a small positive feedback loop
in so far as you can't win unless you
get all the cards. So thus winning hands
gets you more cards gets you closer to
winning.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, the more cards you have, the
closer you're at winning. That's like
saying any game with points, the more
points you get, you're closer to winning
their positive.
>> Yeah,
>> I guess those cards
>> logically, but it's kind of
>> Well, the only other one is if you if
you have a war,
>> then you win those three extra cards and
depending on what they are could be
positive, negative.
>> Okay, great.
>> Which way should we go? This this way.
>> We switch to settlers. a bunch of
feedback loops.
>> Um, obviously like the more points you
get, assuming those points are like
cities and settlements and the more
resources you're going to get in the
future and those points you can build.
So like eventually one player just has
so much stuff can do whatever they want
to positive, right?
>> Yeah. Um, there's also negative feedback
like the sensor is the relative prices
of resources. the more one resource is
worth in time in comparison to the other
ones, the more people try to build on
that resource brick
>> and the less that resource would be
worth in the future. So
>> the long term they tend to balance out
instead of having one go randomly out of
control.
>> Think about that one. That's
interesting.
>> Yeah.
>> Also like the more
this isn't exactly feedback, but like
the more the better you're doing, the
less likely people are going to try to
Yeah, that's that's that's that that in
my opinion is the biggest negative
feedback loop in the entire game. If
you're in the league, everyone hates
you.
>> You're not actually making any progress
in the game.
>> Okay. There's also um if if you have a
bunch of resources like if you have a
bunch of cities on like a resource and
so like if someone draws a six and you
end up getting like six resources from a
tile then that's higher probability that
if someone draws or rolls a seven the
>> so I guess that's negative feedback too.
the welling the servant and losing your
cards mechanic is very much a negative
feedback like I'm so rich now I'm not so
rich you know and people who are kind of
poor says I still got the same number
same that's that that's negative
feedback um a couple of things about
negative feedback u uh to to keep in
mind is that uh negative feedback does
tend to make games last longer it it
sort of staves out the ending of the
game because obviously the difference
between the people in the lead and
people not in the lead are narrowed to
the point that sometimes folks are back
in contention again and uh positive
feedback tends to make things end
sooner. Um
uh oh. Um
okay. All right. I'll get
>> um so in Scrabble, the main one that we
came up with was that if you play a long
word, you get a lot of points, but you
and you also get a lot of tiles, which
gives you opportunity to the next turn
play more points or get like
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah.
>> There's also that the more tiles you
play, the less tiles there are
available. So that's kind of It's both
positive and negative. That was
>> immunity and yeah, it becomes kind of a
negative feedback loop because you may
just end up with fewer times.
>> That's true.
>> Any other negative?
>> We try to make it into a show.
>> Okay. That's that's let's that's put off
that discussion.
>> Yeah. Every time you play a bigger word,
it's easier for someone else to play a
word off of that.
That's
>> um that's an interesting thing because
um that's actually a counter example to
to to
a point that was that was made by Eric
Zimmerman because he argues that
positive feedback actually magnifies
early successes and negative feedback
tends to magnify late ones just like in
the Mario Kart example. It's great to be
the second place, right? Because you
know if you do a late a late game
success that propels you in the first
place just as the game ends. Uh whereas
uh uh some of the examples that we've
been hearing on public feedback, uh you
know, if you manage to be the first one
to build a city in settlers, you know,
uh that tends to perpetuate your success
for the rest of the game. Uh the game
isn't quite as predictable as that, but
you know, it's it's it's it's designed
that way at least. Um but in but that's
that's a very very good example of the
you know you got this negative feedback
loop near the end of the game where uh
where you have a success by playing all
of your tiles but the bag is almost
empty. So now you are not getting not
only are you not getting an advantage
that early that late game success isn't
translating into any kind of uh of of
significant advantage later on. Still,
you know, it's uh it's as a general
rule, if you are dealing with a limited
resource like tiles, uh then you know,
you do have this situation where a
positive feedback gain a positive
feedback loop is kind of amplifying
early successes
and negative feedback loops make late
successes more powerful.
>> So, we're basically with a starcraft. I
think with the starcraft
the some of the This positive feedback
is that the more worker you build and
then the more you can get the mirror.
>> The more workers you build, the more
cash you get, the more cash you get, the
more workers you can build.
>> That's the another positive feedback
loop is the the more that you destroy
like you conquer your opponents, the
harder it is for them to build up and
defend against you. Well, it the easier
it is for you to beat them. On the other
hand, you want your feedback.
>> Oh, then
>> I think the positive feedback just like
emphasize a lot of early game strategy.
>> So, a negative feedback loop in
Starcraft would be the faster you the
more you expand your territories, the
harder is for you to defend because
you're spreading out your resources and
the more friends you have. So the easier
it is for your opponents to attack you.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. We were having that little
discussion earlier and finding finding
other negative people nukes was kind of
tricky. Actually,
>> another one that we I thought of was the
the more the more uh research that you
do, the less resources you have for
building units or workers and such. And
so you have to decide. I mean, you'll
power up your units, but you may have
less to actually build those units.
But probably not really. It's that's a
very small negative loop.
>> I think another negative is like the
more troops you have like the less like
attention you can give to all each of
them. So like hard
>> less effectively.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. The more the more different
screens you got to you got to keep your
eye on basically.
>> That's the thing that's the great thing
about the the control one. So one go
here two go here.
So, one thing about team games though is
there's a huge positive feedback if
you're doing four or 3B 3D and you take
out one of them and it's like so many so
much easier.
>> Yes.
>> It's just harder than 3B2.
>> Then you have a bunch of risk cuz what
happens if you try taking out taking out
one person, but then you fail and now
you're weak, but then they have a lot
more. There
>> is risk.
>> Yeah. So there's an interesting
comparison with Warcraft 3 which did
have negative feedback loop where if
your army gets past a certain size then
it costs more you kind of get taxed
income.
>> Um yeah I don't know if you guys know
about this. Yeah. Basically think think
like Starcraft but then you have a food
count but once you get past a certain
food count then each of your peons
brings in less gold from the farm sorry
from the gold mine. And it gets even
worse the more troops you get. So you're
kind of
>> punished for being too far ahead.
>> There's a very clear negative feedback.
>> I This isn't a
strict negative feedback loop, but it's
interesting to look at uh the resource
management. Um basically
investing in
units that bring in more resources or
investing in other units that do
fighting are all different positive
feedback loops. And you can view not
investing as negative feedback loops in
those areas. Although that's really not
completely true.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I'm not sure if you're
giving me trying to say that negative
feedback, but you're right. They are
different positive feedback loops. They
work very differently. You know, winning
a battle makes it easier for you to win
later battles,
>> but winning a uh but building more
workers makes it easier for you to build
more units. So
>> uh kind of a not apparent uh positive
feedback is the starcraft uh upgrading
attack power by just once
greatly increases its efficiency because
now two attacks will take down four
three attacks. I
>> I don't want to get into that much
detail.
>> Very important. So I just went
>> super key.
>> I was I was going to say crunch you can
have bigger workforce but every turn you
have to pay for that. So you get more
money if you work pay for that negative
feedback.
>> Yeah. That's that's that's that that's a
key.
>> Turns out in monopoly if you have a lot
of money or stuff which people then land
on which gives you more money.
weird. That's that's
>> top secret secret strategy winning
Monopoly is to buy lots of stuff and
then have people land on it so you can
get more money. So actually but so this
has just one little uh negative feedback
into well actually two for uh
>> income tax
>> that's the income tax and like the
>> and
like several thousand hotels
actual governments like that too right
>> so so
>> it's patent out of real life but then
again so is the whole of Monopoly game
the whole Monopoly game is about real
life land ownership monopolies Atlantic
City, I believe.
>> Yeah.
>> Atlantic City.
>> So, yeah. Uh, and and that gives us a
good segue into degenerate strategies.
Yeah. Right.
>> No.
>> Sorry. Okay.
>> All right. So, so I'll go into that a
little bit, but uh maybe I'll get I'll
get into that on Wednesday, but on
Wednesday, we're going to focus that
mostly on your uh on play testing the
game. If we have no time for anything
else, we are play testing your game. Uh,
and so bringing the games, bringing your
cards, make sure your cards are ready
before class. Don't like frantically
writing stuff. Uh, try not to be
changing stuff right up to
after class. Sometimes you might be feel
pressured into that. Um, try to be ready
before class starts. Uh, and try to show
up at a right beginning of class because
it will really really suck if you finish
play testing. If you finish play testing
someone else's game and that team
doesn't have enough time to play test
yours, okay? and it may happen and that
will suck. So, let's try to start that
uh right on time by this Wednesday.
>> Thank you.