Yeah. So, we're sort of in the last part
of the class now and I've been
reflecting on what what to do together.
Um and uh I asked everybody for for some
input, a little survey about what topics
to do and how much detail to do.
Um there was no consensus in the survey
of of what people wanted to do. Um
but I've decided I would like to do for
a couple of weeks uh talk about some
applications of projection theory in
other areas. Um and then in the last
couple weeks try to talk about at least
the some of the main ideas in the proof
of the sharp projection theorem.
Um
yeah so we recently had been doing uh
Burgans's projection theorem and the
burganc cat's projection theorem in
finite fields and um we so
feeling that that we really had to work
pretty hard for those things and it was
striking that we had to work pretty hard
just to get this like very small uh
improvement um and um so in some of what
we'll do in the rest of the class I I
will try to show that that that small
improvement is really valuable
Um
okay. Um so the yeah so the so so the
the plan for the rest of the class is
for for about one week we'll talk about
random walks on groups and then for
about one week we'll talk about
homogeneous dynamics. Um and then at the
end we'll talk about the sharp
projection theorem.
Okay. Um
um cool. And also in the last few
classes I felt that we were um doing
some very technical things and and and
uh um sometimes a little bit of a
struggle. Um so for for today what I
want to do is to give I hope a very
friendly induct in introduction to
random walks on groups and then um next
week on Tuesday to explain how
projection theory helps to figure out
some interesting things.
Okay.
[Applause]
So talk about
random walks
of groups.
All right. So suppose that G is a finite
group
and then mu is a probability measure on
G. So I'll think of it
as a function on G
which is non- negative and sums to one.
Okay. So if you have a probability
measure like this, you can do a random
walk where at each step of the random
walk, you pick an element of G by this
probability and then you move by that
element. So here's how the random walk
works.
So you start somewhere
say at G0 then you sample
a step h from mu
and the next guy g1 is g 0 * h.
So that's one step of the random walk
and then you can keep doing this.
Okay. And um so if you do take K steps
of the random walk then that will be
there will be some probability
distribution of where you end up after k
steps and the main question about one
main question about random walks is how
evenly distributed is that probability
distribution.
Um so
question
how evenly
distributed
is uh the random walk after k steps.
Okay. And we'll make we'll make this
more precise in a moment.
All right. So,
so we um it is helpful to describe this
random walk using uh convolution.
Okay, so convolution on a group looks
like this. We have two functions f_sub_1
and f_sub_2 on this group. And then if I
convolve them with each other
and I evaluate that at g, that's the sum
g1 * g2 = g. f of g1 f_sub_1 of g1
f_sub_2 of g2.
That's the sum over all the g1 and g2
that multiply to g of of this.
Okay. Um and then for mu we can make an
operator and t mu of f is just f
convolved with mu. And this operator
basically describes this random walk.
So let's say how they're related. So
suppose I were to take t mu and apply it
to the delta function at g knot and
evaluate that at some g.
Um
okay. So let's let's see what's a good
way to write this.
Um so that's the sum. Um actually let me
look at how I wrote it in my notes. I
tried writing this a few ways and then I
decided there was a good way to write
it.
Right? Yeah. Let's write it this way.
So suppose I want to evaluate this at g*
h. So that's the sum over g1 * g2 = g *
h of delta function at g of g1 time mu
of g2.
All right. So the only way that this sum
can be not zero is if g1 is g0.
So there's only one term in this sum.
So this um g 0 * g2 is g 0 * h of mu of
g2.
There's only one term and it's the term
where g2 is h.
Okay. So this thing is the probability
distribution of one step of the random
walk. The probability if I started at g
that I end up at g* h is mu of h. That's
the definition of my random walk. So
this operator is performing one step of
the random walker. And therefore if I
take t mu to the k of delta g0 that's uh
like k steps of the random walk
starting at g.
Okay.
Um actually let me say this I could say
this better.
So this is the probability
that a random walk is at g
after k steps.
Okay. So now we can take this question
how evenly distributed is the random
walk. We can write that as a precise
question about this. I'll call it
question one.
So I'd like to estimate
okay t mu to the k of delta g0. So this
is the actual probability distribution.
And if the probability was completely
even over the whole group, it would be
one over the size of the group
everywhere. So I'm going to see how
close it is to that by measuring the
norm of this difference. So I like to
estimate that. Okay. And L2 is helpful
but also perhaps a little arbitrary. You
could also put other norms. So could put
or L infinity or maybe some other norm.
Okay. So this is the kind of question
about random walks on groups that we are
going to try to understand.
All right. So um to understand this it
is helpful to notice that this is a
linear operator. This t- mu is a linear
operator. It's basically a matrix. And
it's helpful to think about that um in
terms of matrix ideas like the singular
values and singular vectors of this
matrix.
So t mu plus a linear operator
and we're going to study
singular values and singular vectors
of t.
Okay. So there is um
one um simple singular value which is or
value I guess that t mu of one is one.
>> Yeah.
>> Are singular values and singular vectors
just the same as values and values.
>> Um they are closely related. Um
so let me do a quick review of singular
values and values. Right.
Um,
so if you have a a matrix and you think
about what it does to the unit ball, it
will turn the unit ball into an
ellipsoid.
Um and the principal axes of this
ellipsoid are the singular values sigma
sigma 2.
Okay. And then um
uh so if we look at the pre-im images of
these things those will be the singular
vectors.
So well depending on the matrix they
could be pointing any which way but
maybe that's um v2
and that is v1.
Okay. And they will always be so we'll
have um
uh
so the the vi or orthonormal
and the size of mvi
is sigma.
Um
and the mvi are also worth are also
orthogonal. Those
are the singular vectors.
Okay. Now they are not generally igen
vectors in the sense that mvi will not
usually be a multiple of vi. Uh but they
are closely related to them. Um the vi
are the igen vectors
of m star or m m star I guess. Um
and the uh sigma i squared are the igen
values of m star mic
mm star.
Um
so in particular this biggest uh this
biggest singular vector measures the
operator norm of the matrix which is
that the the um so these are these are
ordered like this and um
MV
is at most sigma 1
Okay, so the reason we're talking about
singular values is we're going to care
about stuff like this. And
this is naturally associated with
singular values. If m is not symmetric,
it's not necessarily the same as talking
about values.
Okay.
Um,
okay. So, if we take this tu of the
function one, the constant function,
we'll just get one because this t- mu is
is like an averaging operator.
We're averaging t. So, t mu of f at g is
the average value at of g at some other
places around g that are dictated by mu.
So t mu of one is one.
Okay. And um now it's uh okay. So so
that implies that the that the the Okay.
So I'll do a little lema.
The the the largest singular value.
Yeah. Okay. So little lema is that t mu
of f and l2 is at most f and l2 and this
is sharp because of this example.
They could be they could be equal.
Okay.
Okay. So proving this will help us think
a little bit about what convolution
means. Um so t mu of f is f convolved
with mu
g here.
So that's the sum g1 g2 = g f of g1 mu
of g2.
And I'd like to think of this as a sum
over g2. So it's the sum over g2 because
I'm thinking of it that way. I can bring
the mu of g2 out front and then what I
have left is f of g1 which is g * g2
inverse
and I want to think of this as a linear
combination of a bunch of different
functions of g.
Okay, let's give them a name. So this
function of g is sort of f but but we
first did this thing and I want I want
you to think of it as taking f and then
shifting it using the group. So it's the
right translation by g2 of f of g is
defined to be this thing here.
So we could plug that in. Um and this
shifting operation doesn't change the
norm of g. So, RG2 of F in L2 is the
same as F in R2.
Ah, I've been mentioning L2. What? Yeah,
I should say.
Okay, let me pause for a second. I
should have said something before.
[Applause]
Okay, so when we have these functions on
G, we're going to measure their norm.
Um, and if I have f L2 of G, this is
going to be some G and G, f of gum
squared to the 12. Or I could take an
inner product, the inner product of
f_sub_1 and f_sub_2 is the sum g and g,
f_sub_1 of g, f_sub_2 of g to that. So
the functions on g are I hope we're
spaced with this with this natural
measure. Okay. Um so then if I take a
function and I
translate it or do this right
translation um it just sort of permutes
the value so it doesn't change this
thing.
Okay. So now if we look at our t mu of f
um
um I have this
yeah
I'm interested in the norm of t mu of f.
This is the norm of the sum on G2 mu of
G2
R subg2 of F.
It's a linear combination of these
functions which are all translates of F.
And L2 is a norm. It obeys the triangle
inequality. So this is less than the sum
on G2 mu of G2
RG2 of F and L2. All of these have the
same norm.
which is the L2 norm of F and the L2
norm and then this adds up to one. So
this is just the L2 norm of F.
Okay,
so this is a basic fact about averaging
operators. Um and
to understand whether the random walk is
mixing things up, we have to care about
how it behaves on the space orthogonal
to one. And the first observation is
that it preserves the space orthogonal
to one. So let's give that space a name.
Say L2 of G KN is the set of F and L2 of
G.
So that
sum G and G of F of G is zero. This is
saying that f is orthogonal to the
constant function.
Okay. So another simple lema is that our
operator t mu actually takes this space
to itself. So it takes the constant
function to itself and it takes the
perpendicular space to itself which will
imply that the constant function is one
of the singular vectors of the of of
this operator.
Okay. So proof
um uh
so I want to understand the sum g and g
of t team muf of g. Going to imagine
that the sum of f of g is zero. And I
want to see if that's still true. All
right. So that's the sum g and g sum g1
* g2 equals g. f of g1 mu of g2.
And if you think about what we're
summing over, we're just summing over G1
and G2.
So this is the sum over G1 and G2 of F
of G1, mu of G2. And now that factors.
So this is one. And if F was in L2 of
GN, this would be zero.
This is
so f if f is an l2 of g not then so t mu
of f will be
okay Oh,
[Applause]
all right. So, so we've seen that um
t mu of one is one and t mu takes l2 of
g kn to itself.
So this is the largest singular value
we've seen and um and then here there's
something else. So let's say sigma one
of t mu.
So, so this this one could I'll call it
sigma kn of t mu. Somehow in this
setting the one is sort of trivial and
everything else will depend on the trace
of mu. So sigma 1 of t mu is the largest
singular value
of of this part.
Okay.
All right. So question two is going to
be to estimate that
estimate sigma one of t and these two
questions are related to each other. Um
this thing helps to understand um how I
mean helps a lot to understand how this
operator behaves and and to and to
answer question one. So let me put up a
simple proposition how question two is
related to question one.
So proposition if you look at that thing
t mu to the k delta function g minus 1 /
g in l2 this is bounded by sigma 1 of t
mu to the k.
Okay so proof.
So we want to see what t mu to the k
does to a delta function at a point.
Let's take this delta function at a
point and t mu splits up the constant
function is an igen function and then
and then then the the the things with
mean zero. So let's split up this delta
function. So the the
constant part of it is like this and
then we have this.
So the reason we split it up that way is
that this part which in the beginning of
the class we could have we would have
called like the high part of this um so
I guess I'll do that that's in L2 of G 0
mean zero part okay now what happens
when we apply this operator well this
operator takes constants to constants
uh it's the identity on the constant
part um and so I take t mu to the k
delta g kn
this part will say stay stay like one
over one over I'll take the left hand
side and then if I subtract that it will
disappear so what I'll be left with is t
mu to the k on
this uh high part of the delta g not
okay how big is that well this part
lives in this space so we can bound the
size of this thing using the uh singular
vector. Um and so so
I get t mu
to the k
of delta g high
two that's bounded by
sigma 1 of t mu to the k
times delta g high2
Okay. And now it's it's also now
straightforward to check that this is
smaller than one.
Okay.
So uh it's an application um
if we were able to arrange that sigma 1
t mu to the k was less than 1 over 100
times the size of g
um then well this l2 norm would be less
than one over 100 times the size of g
and so in particular the l infinity norm
would be less than one over 100 times
the size of g. So then I would say that
for every g um
t mu k delta g of g minus one over the
size of g would be smaller than 1 over
100 times the size of g. That would tell
us say that this function is pretty
close to this constant function within
1%. So that random walk would now have
mixed uh pretty thoroughly.
Okay, great. So if we can get our hands
on sigma 1 of t mu, then we can figure
out how long it takes this random walk
to mix evenly.
Cool.
Okay.
So now let me mention tell you an
interesting example of a particular
group and a particular mu where there's
a cool estimate for this
So we are going to mostly focus or maybe
only focus on the group SL2 of FP
and um could pick many different
measures for a random walk but one nice
one which has been studied is to take
the set A to be so f so first of all um
if A is a subset of G. There's a natural
measure on A which is the uniform
measure. So measure on A which is one
over the cardality of A times the sum A
and A of delta A.
Okay. Um okay. So there's a nice set A
inside of here which was studied by
Selberg. A Selberg.
Uh
well okay which is relevant to a theorem
of Selberg. P set his third differently.
But
so there are four elements in this set.
Um and these are generators of the group
SL2FP. There are many ways you could
choose generators for this group, but
this is probably the simplest way.
Um
and okay and now I can state a theorem.
So theorem one exists a positive c I
think one one over 100 should be fine.
Um so that
for every p prime if you take a selberg
and sl2 of fp you make a random walk. Um
and so in this setting let me write t a
for t sub mu sub a.
um then
sigma 1 of ta is less than 1 minus c. So
uniformly for all primes.
So if this is say 99 over 100 then you
can just read off uh you know high
powers of this are bounded by something
and you can plug that into the
discussion over here. So it says that
that random walk mixes extremely fast.
Yeah.
>> How does sigma one behave kind of as it
over time? Does it converge to sub or
oscillate a lot?
>> Um so the question is how does sigma 1
of ta behave um as as the prime varies?
I do not know the answer to that
question.
Um so I should say so let me say that
this was this is a correlary of a
theorem of Selberg
from the late 50s
um and Selberg act's actual theorem is
about the first igen value of the
lelassian on a hyperbolic surface which
is associated to this group
and you can go back and forth. With
modern technology, it's considered not
very difficult to go back and forth
between a bound for the igen value of
the surface and a bound here. Uh but
when you do go back and forth, you will
screw up the constants.
Um Selberg's theorem was that the first
igen value of that surface was at least
316s
and that's probably not the right
answer. And he conjectured that it
should be a quarter.
Um so for his actual problem there was
there is a beautiful conjecture about
what happens as p goes to infinity which
is that the values should converge to a
quarter
um for this I'm not sure
okay cool
okay so bounds like this are also
related to uh expand standard graphs,
isoparametric inequalities in graphs and
I thought I would also show that um and
um so it it shows that well okay so so
let me explain that. So we can we can if
you have a set of of generators inside
of a group we can use that to make a
graph called a kaly graph.
[Applause]
And this mixing inequality
can be thought of or implies some
interesting geometric features of the
graph.
So um
expansion
in graphs.
Okay. So if G is a finite group
then A is a set of generators
and I guess that to have a graph maybe
we should say that is a symmetric set of
generators. I don't know if that's
important. Yeah, let's leave it.
Um
then we'll have a kaly graph kaly graph
of GA. This is a graph.
The vertices
are G and G. And a pair G1, G2
um is an edge
if and only if um G2 is G1 * A or vice
versa.
Um yeah, so I guess we should have it
symmetric. Um G2= G1 * A where A is in
A.
Okay. And the random walk we've been
imagining is basically the random walk
on this graph. You start at a vertex and
you move randomly to a neighboring along
the edges. Yeah.
>> How do you identify SL2 of a finite
field with a hyperbolic surface?
>> Um yeah, I I I will Okay, we'll talk
about the connection to hyperbolic
geometry a little later when we talk
about the proof of this theorem, but
let's do it then.
Yeah. Okay.
Um
okay so that's the kaly graph
um
and in this graph if I have subsets s
and t inside of the vertices e of s and
t the edges from s to t that's going to
be the set of g1 g2 and s cross t so
that g1 g2 is an edge
a set of edges from fast.
Okay. So, proposition
if we have CGA is above then the number
of edges from S to S complement. So, S
is going to be a subset of the vertices.
number of these edges is at least one
minus sigma 1 of TA
times
a * S * S complement over G.
Okay, so let's digest this a little bit.
Um so what does this expression mean?
Well, there are S.
This is the this is how many points
there are in the set S. From each of
those points, there are a edges coming
out. So, this is how many edges there
are that are leaving points at S.
How many of them do we think end up in S
complement? Well, we don't really know,
but as a reference point,
everything was sort of random. The
fraction of edges that ended up in S
complement might be S complement over G.
So this expression here would be the
typical number of edges from S to S
complement if we had a random graph
where each vertex was in this many
edges.
Okay. And then we're going to say that
the actual number of edges is at least
some fraction of that.
If sigma 1 of TA were one, this would be
a trivial inequality. It's bigger than
zero. But if sigma 1 is is smaller than
one, then this is a non-trivial
inequality. and it says that the number
of edges is a certain a definite
fraction of what you would see in the
random model.
Okay, so let's prove this or at least
give a proof sketch.
So the key point is that we can describe
this quantity using this operator TA and
then it becomes not so surprising that
the singular value of TA is relevant.
How do you do it? The number of edges
from S to S complement is the inner
product is inner product of TA of the
characteristic function of S with the
characteristic function of S complement
and there's a factor of a in front. This
is a normalization. If if TA had been
just TA is an averaging operator, but we
didn't really want to average. We wanted
to count edges. So there's an extra
factor.
Okay. Does this look plausible to
people? Should we write this?
Let's write this out a little bit.
So t a1s
of g
is 1 / a sum a and a
of uh
um
s of g
a inverse.
So that's the definition of the of the
convolution.
Um
so we we so then when we take this inner
product we're going to have the um sum g
and g
1 / a sum a
1 s of g a inverse one s complement of
So we will only be counting
uh we'll be counting G's that are in S
complement but GA inverse is an S and
that's an edge that starts in S and goes
to S complnt.
So S S complement
over here we have G. Over here we have
GA inverse and those are connected by an
edge. That's the thing that we're
counting.
Okay, this double sum here means we're
counting all of the going through all
the edges, but we're only counting an
edge if it goes from S to S complement.
And we have this, which we didn't really
want, which is why we multiplied by this
over here.
Okay, good.
Okay, so now remember that this operator
uh sort of splits we it takes the
constant functions to the constant
functions and it takes the mean zero
functions to the mean zero functions. So
we should split everybody in sight into
a constant part and a mean zero part.
So we split
1 s is s over g that's the constant part
plus 1 s minus s over g. So this I'll
call it 1 s high and it lives in l2 g0.
Okay. Do the same thing for s
complement. So now the number of edges
from S to S complement
that is A times
um okay we'll have TA of the constant
parts so that's SG s complement G
plus A times the high frequency high
frequency parts uh the non the mean zero
parts um TA of 1s high
one as complement.
Okay. So let's call this zero and this
is the high part or the let's call this
the constant part and this is the high
part.
Okay. So the rest of it is just a
computation and I won't do the algebra
carefully but if you do the constant
part you get this as SS complement over
G. The constant part exactly tracks what
would happen if all the edges were
random. Okay. And then for the high part
of course we won't compute it exactly
because we have to know what the
operator TA is. But we can bound it by
the um by the norm of TA sigma 1 of TA
times 1 S high in L2
times 1 S complement high in L2.
Okay. And then those things are
straightforward to compute those L2
norms. And if you work if you compute
them you get that this is a this is I'll
put the sigma one out front.
And then it's the same thing a s S
complement over G.
Okay. So the true answer is the constant
term plus the high term which is like an
error term and whose size is at most
this. And if sigma 1 is strictly less
than one then the error term is strictly
smaller than the constant term. So
something will be left over and that's
the inequality.
Okay, so let me make a little remark.
Um, if S is smaller than G over two,
then S complement is bigger than G
over2. So this is more or less without
loss of generality. You know, if you
switch the roles of S and S complement,
but it means S complement is at least G
over2, which means that this whole
fraction has order of one. So then we
get that the number of edges from S to S
complement is at least half sigma 1 of
TA
A time S. So it's at least uh a definite
fraction of all of the possible edges
that it could be living leaving us.
Okay. So this property here is called
being an expander graph
because if you take a set that's less
than half of the graph and then you add
to it all of the edges that are leaving
it then it will get significantly
bigger. It will expand. So it's called
an expander graph.
Okay.
Okay. Cool.
Um so so this proposition shows
that if this sigma one is strictly less
than one it's something like in Selber's
theorem then the edges in the graph
behave in this way that it's an expanded
graph.
Okay, cool.
Okay, now so Selberg did not state his
theorem in this way. So this is slightly
ahistorical, but Selberg's theorem plus
things that are not very difficult in
hindsight show that this kaly graph of
SL2FP is an expander graph and it is in
a sense the first Zelberg didn't quite
say this but in a sense this was the
first proof that any graph was an
expander graph. Um, expander graphs were
officially defined in 1970 by Pinsker
and something pretty close by Koma Garf
and Bars in the 60s and all of those
people realized that um random graphs
were expander graphs.
Um,
yeah. So I maybe many people have seen
but it's really a remarkable thing. So,
so just for comparison, like a simple
graph that we might think of that we can
easily visualize would be like a like an
n byn grid and that kind of graph is not
an expander at all. So an n byn grid has
n squared vertices but you can cut it in
half with a vertical line and you only
cut n edges. So the number of edges so s
and s complement are each about half of
the graph. The number of edges between
them is is much smaller than s. Um so
these are very large graphs but the
number of edges it takes to cut it in
half is comparable to all of the edges
and um it most graphs are like that but
before people realized it it was
surprising and counterintuitive that any
graphs were like that and it's very
significant fact in many domains of math
and science.
Okay.
Uh okay, let me pause there and
questions about about Selberg's theorem
and this setup mixing and expansion.
>> The point of a generators is just so
that it's connected.
>> Yes, that's right. So um so the question
is uh is what what is the point of a
being generators?
[Applause]
So if a did not generate the group then
this graph would be disconnected and
then it wouldn't mix at all. Um so make
a remark
suppose that A is in a finite group and
that H
the so the the subgroup
generated by A is H which is a proper
subgroup.
Okay. So then if we take TA and we apply
it to the characteristic function of
this subgroup since all of these guys
are in the subgroup we would just stay
in the subgroup. So this would be 1 H.
Okay. And um and that implies with a
teeny bit of work that sigma 1 of TA
would be one.
Right? So, okay, one thing we could see
is that no matter how many times we
repeat this operation, we will never mix
over the whole group because we'll never
get out of H. And so, based on what
we've seen before, um, this should be
one.
Yeah.
>> Just make a big does it just make the
graph more
likely to be an expander?
>> Yeah. So, the question is, if we make a
big, is the graph more likely to be an
expander? Um
perhaps if we so we could we could take
a big and then it would um so we're so
we're allowed to take a big and um we
will talk in a little bit about what
what we can say if we just know that a
is big what does that tell us about
sigma of ta we'll we'll talk about that
right
okay so another remark I wanted to make
is that the first proof of this theorem
was very difficult so the first proof
depended on. So it had some interesting
analysis related to hyperbolic geometry
but then it depended on the remon
hypothesis for curves over finite
fields.
So that's a you know a beautiful and
important theorem but if you wanted to
include the whole proof of that then the
proof of this theorem is effectively
several hundred pages long and has a lot
of algebraic geometry. Um and in around
the early 1990s, Sarnac and Shuer gave a
much simpler proof.
Uh which is the proof that we'll talk
about.
Okay.
Okay. Okay. So in the rest of the class
I will start to describe the uh proof by
Sarn and and Shuer um uh and and
introduce the first the first key idea.
All right.
Okay. Um
so first idea
this idea has to do with the
representation theory
of the group SL2FP
it's a proposition
okay so if we have a representation so a
representation is a group homorphism
to uh this is a unitary representation
so to the unitary group in D dimensions.
So this is a representation
need a group homorphism
um and okay and let me so there there's
the trivial representation where
everything goes to the identity but let
me say it is a non-trivial
representation
um then actually d needs to be quite big
d is at least p + 1 over
Okay,
so before we prove this theorem, let's
try to put it in context by trying to
think about group representations.
Um, where would we find a group
representation?
Okay, well SL2FP acts on itself. So it
acts on the space that we started with
L2 of G. So, so any so any group G
acts on L2 G by the action that we sort
of wrote down. You take a function and
you like shift the space under it.
Okay, that action is not trivial. So the
only only the constant functions are
fixed. So that's a non-trivial action.
And the dimension of this space is the
cardality of G. So for this group that
would be about P cubed.
So cardality of SL2
FP.
Okay. Um
what else? Well, if you have a subgroup
of G,
H is a subgroup
of G. Then um G acts
on G mod H and so it acts
acts on this as a set and so it acts on
L2 of G mod H by a unitary
representation and so the dimension
of L2 of GH
is the cardality of G mod which is the
cardality of G divided by the cardality
of H.
Okay, so let's think of some subgroups
of SL2FP.
Think of there's the diagonal subgroup
looks like this.
The size of the diagonal subgroup is
around P. There's the unipotent subgroup
looks like this. Size of the unipotent
subgroup is P.
And you could sort of mix these
together. So there's the upper
triangular subgroup. Uh but we already
used the letter U. So I'm going to call
this B for Burell. Uh so I'll write it A
A inverse T.
That's a subgroup. And the size of the
upper triangle subgroup is around P^
squ. So that's the biggest one that we
have come up with here. And if you plug
this in here, uh so if you take SL2FP,
that's around P. And so this is uh the
right order of magnitude.
Okay. And this is an interesting fact
about this group which is extremely
different from a billion groups. So for
for an aelion group uh every irreducible
representation is onedimensional. So
there are lots and lots of
representations where D is one. But for
SL2FP life is very different. All of
them have very large dimension.
Okay.
So let's prove this theorem.
Uh so I had heard about this theorem
years ago and I always assumed that to
prove this theorem one had to study a
lot of representation theory and I was a
little intimidated by it. Uh but then I
read the proof as I was getting ready to
teach this class and actually it it
doesn't require anything that's outside
of uh you know a good a good
undergraduate algebra curriculum
and it's quite elegant.
All right. So here's the proof. Um,
so we're going to focus on this matrix
for a little while and try to figure out
what the representation does with this
matrix.
So let's suppose for now
that row of this matrix is not just the
identity.
Um,
actually let me let me say it in a
different order. So let's say so U is
that matrix and V is this matrix which
is very similar to U and we'll make the
remark that so exercise this point I
won't include the details U and V
generate
SL2
okay if you play around a little bit you
you can see this all right so therefore
if we have a non-trivial representation
these cannot both go to the identity.
So row is non-trivial.
So either row of u or row of v is not
the identity. And u and v are so similar
to each other it doesn't really matter
which one. So I'm going to say
essentially without loss of generality
row of u is not the identity.
All right. Now let's think about row of
u. Um
there's something quite special about
this matrix which is um
um that it is conjugate
to powers of itself.
Let me write that down. So suppose take
a diagonal matrix A a inverse. I put
this matrix in the middle
and then I want to conjugate it. So now
I put on the other side the inverse.
Right? So this is the conjugate of my
matrix U.
Okay.
So I multiply this by this. Uh I
multiply the top row by a and the bottom
row by a inverse. So I get a a z a
inverse. And then I still have this guy.
Now when I multiply these matrices
together, I multiply the left column by
a inverse and the right column by a.
The diagonals cancel, but I get one 01
a.
Okay.
So see that u is conjugate
to
u to the power a squ
and this is for any a
right.
So that is a special and really
interesting feature of this element of
my group.
And so now I have a representation and
row of u is conjugate to row of u of a 2
which is row of u to the a 2. So now I
have a matrix I have a unitary matrix
and it is conjugate to a big power of
itself.
Okay, in the world of matrices, it's not
so easy to get that to happen. So, this
group has a has an interesting property
that has an element which is conjugate
to many different powers of itself.
And in matrices, it's not so easy to
find a matrix which is conjugate to many
different powers of itself.
Why? because
uh uh- because of how the igen values
behave.
So
okay. So so now let's think about IGEN
values.
[Applause]
Okay.
So
row of U is U of D is a matrix.
And if row of u is conjugate to row of u
to the a^2
then that tells us that the igen values
the spectrum of row of u is the same as
the igen values of row of u to the a^ 2.
Two conjugate matrices have the same
igen values.
But if you take a matrix and raise it to
a power, the igen values are all raised
to a power. So this is the igen values
of row of u to the a 2.
Okay.
Okay. So for instance, you could take a
to be two and it tells you if you have
an igen value of row of u you raise it
to the fourth power that will also be an
igen value of row of u. And you can keep
doing that. And it's not just four. We
have many choices for a squ.
Okay. So let's think about what the igen
values of row of u may be like. So study
values of row of u. So this is an an
amazing fact about them. And there's a
more pedestrian fact that we should also
observe. We know that u to the p is the
identity.
And therefore
row of u to the p is the identity. So
then if lambda is an igen value of row
of u then we get that lambda to the p is
the is one. Okay. So the igen values of
row of u they're all p roots of unity.
Um
right so we get the following. If lambda
is an igen value of row of u then lambda
to the p is one and lambda to the a 2 is
also an igen value of row of u.
Okay.
So
um since lambda to the p is one, we only
care about a^2 mod p. So could put mod p
there.
Um and um
there are p min -1 / 2 quadratic
residues
mod p.
So this a^ squ mod p. It could be any
quadratic residue mod p. There are p
minus one over two of them. And if you
take a p of unity and you raise it to a
power it's between one and p you'll
you'll change it. So so lambda is a
primitive. So if lambda is not one
then lambda is a primitive p root of
unity
and that tells us that the lambda to the
a^ 2 mod p are all distinct
for the p minus one over two quadratic
reserves.
Okay, so we now have seen that that
there are an awful lot of different igen
values which can only happen if the
matrix is in a large dimension.
So that gives us that d is at least p +
1 / 2.
Okay, actually I so how do we know that
row of u has a not an igen value that's
not one? Well, if all the igen values
were one, then row of u you you could is
conjugate to a matrix with ones on the
diagonals and some upper triangular
stuff. And if you raise that to a power,
you'll never get the identity. Um
an exercise. So there's a little a
little something where exercise.
If um the igen values of row of u are
exactly the set one
and
row of u to the p = 1 then row of u is
the identity
I I'll leave the matrix details.
Okay.
So all the representations of SL2 are
really big. Why does that matter?
Let's do another proposition.
So proposition two
you take sigma 1 of t mu. So mu is a
measure on
probability measure on SL2 FP.
Then sigma 1 of this guy if you square
it and you multiply by D +1 / 2 that is
at most the size of SL2FP
times mu L2.
Simplifying the algebra a little bit,
sigma 1 of t mu^2 is smaller than around
1 over p^2
time mu l2.
Okay.
All right. So we come back to the
question from earlier in the class. How
are singular values related to igen
values?
So sigma i of t mu
squared is lambda i of t mu t mu star.
It's the ien value of this matrix.
And the key observation is that the igen
spaces of this matrix have a g action on
them. And except for the constant
functions the igen spaces are not
trivial. Here's the key
spaces
of t mu t mu star have a g action
and except for
the constant functions. So the constant
functions are an igen space of t mu tu
star but all the other ones it's a
non-trivial action.
Let's suppose that for a moment and see
why it's helpful and then we can think
more carefully about what exactly are
the igen spaces.
Um.
All right.
Um
Okay.
Um so that tells us that sig each sigma
i
has a multiplicity
which is at least d + 1 / 2.
So you have and we really care about the
biggest one, this biggest singular
vector. There's not just one biggest
singular vector, but there's a a whole
singular subspace of a big dimension and
all of those vectors have have this
large singular value.
Okay. So now another uh fact from linear
algebra is that if you add up the
singular values squared of a of a matrix
with multiplicity
that is the Hilbert Schmidt norm of the
matrix. So it's the sum of the entries
of the matrix.
Uh
so this is a matrix where the rows and
columns are indexed by our group G. So
it has an entry G1 G2 and it's the sum
of the entries squared.
Does this look familiar to people from
linear algebra?
Okay. Okay. Now the entries of our
matrix we can read off. It's the sum g1
g2
mu of something like g1 g2 inverse. This
might not be exactly right but it's the
right idea.
>> Uh that's that's the entry and then
we're squaring it.
Um and so that's the size of the group
times the sum of mu of g^2.
Okay, so that's the right hand side
and over here we're counting with
multiplicity and the multiplicity is
always large. So this is at least d + 1
/ 2 * sigma 1 of t mu^ 2
So there's an important difference
between the sigma 1 and the sigma 0. The
sigma 0 went with the constant functions
that lives in a space of dimension one.
But anybody else lives in a big
dimensional space. And so this uh counts
get gets counted many times. Um and and
that changes the playing field.
Um, what is D?
>> What is D? Sorry. D is P. Sorry.
Thank you.
Okay. Is it right up there? Yeah. So, D
is the dimension of the representation,
but um that's why I put it, but it's a
it was just a mistake. It's supposed to
be P+ one over two.
So what needs to be spelled out more
carefully?
I think we should just spell out a
little more carefully why the spaces
have this G action.
Okay, so first of all, what is T mu
star? Let's say mu star of g is just mu
of g inverse. And if you write down the
definition of the adjint and play around
a little bit, you'll see that t mu star
is just t of u star convoling with you.
So t mu t mu star of that is just you
take f you convolve it with mu star and
then you convolve it with mu. So it's t
of uh mu convolve with mu star.
Okay so our oper our operator is still
just a convolution operator just
convolving by something slightly
different. And now we want to see that
convolution
uh commutes with the some symmetries of
of g.
Um okay so our convolution has been
defined to be on the right and so I
think it's supposed to commute with the
symmetries of of f on the left. So let's
say f the left action of g on f of h is
f of
g inverse h.
I want to say that uh convolution
commutes with this action. So I want to
say claim
that for for any measure new
if I take T new of left action G of F
this is left action G T new of F.
Okay, cross my finger that I wrote
everything correctly so that this is
true.
uh t new of left action g of f at some
um
let's say I evaluate that at x.
So the I'm going to convolve this
function with new. So it's lgf convolved
with new at x. So it's the sum x1 x2 = x
lf of x1
new of x2.
So that's the sum x1 x2 = x f of g
inverse x1
new of x2.
All right. So the product of these two
guys is g inverse x.
So really the product x1 tilda time x2
tilda is g inverse x
um f of x1 tilda new of x2 tilda.
So that is t new of f evaluated at g
inverse x.
So that's lg of t new of f x
probably can see that I'm not a very
algebraically minded person. I think
there's probably a high sort of more
highbrow proof of this. So something
about acting on the left commutes with
acting on the right.
Okay. So,
so the group
commutes the group acts on functions and
that action commutes with this. So, if
you have an igen space of this, the
group will act on it.
So if t new of f is lambda f then t new
of lgf
will be lg t new of f which is lg of
lambda f which is lambda lg of f.
So LG so G
acts on V lambda the space.
Okay. So that fleshes out
this.
[Applause]
Okay.
Cool. So um let's do a quick application
of this to see what we have learned
about mixing.
So remember that we already know that
this thing is bounded by one and it's
not at all clear whether this is bigger
or smaller than one. It depends upon mu.
Um if this is bigger than one then this
is kind of useless. But if this is
smaller than one then it gives us some
new information.
Okay,
one question about proposition 2.
>> Yeah.
>> Does it require the existence of a
representation of degree P + 1 /2?
>> Uh not exactly. I mean this oper this
operator here has spaces
>> and we know that the group acts on them.
So therefore there are representations
of this group.
Okay.
So application.
So suppose a is a subset of SL2FP.
It doesn't have to be a Selberg just any
subset. And remember that mu of A is the
uniform measure on A.
Okay. So what is mu of a L2 squared?
Well, we square the amplitude of 1 / a^2
and then we add it up and we'll get a
contribution from a points. So we get
one over the cardality of a
right. So if we just plug in our our uh
estimate, proposition two
tells us that sigma 1 of ta squared is
bounded by um
p ^2.
Whoops,
I did that wrong. That's not good.
This is about p cub. This is about p.
Okay, good. So it's bounded by p ^2 over
a.
So we can see
that if a is significantly bigger than p
^2 then sigma 1 of ta is less than one.
So a is 10 p ^2 or even better p 2 plus
epsilon
then sigma 1 is quite a bit less than
one and so this this walk this random
walk will mix. Great.
Um in particular corlary of that is that
if H is a proper subgroup
of SL2FP
so we saw earlier take a proper subgroup
and you you walk you just stay in the
subgroup it won't mix at all sigma 1
would be one um then H has size which is
smaller than around P ^2
and we saw earlier that there is a
subgroup of size about P^2. So this is
sharp.
Okay. So this addresses the question
that was raised earlier. The set A may
be large. If you just know the size of
A, can you say whether it mixes or not?
Um this is essentially a sharp answer to
that question. If A is significantly
bigger than P^2, then the random walk
does mix. And if a is smaller than p ^2,
a could live in a subgroup and the
random walk may not mix.
This whole phenomenon is is is quite
different from what would happen in a
commutive group. Um in a commutive
group, you could take very large subsets
and still nothing might mix. Um
partly because the commutive group might
have very large subgroups, but even if
it doesn't, it wouldn't work.
Yeah.
Cool.
Okay, so that's all very interesting,
but it doesn't look very close to this
theorem yet because this is theorem says
that we get mixing if our subset has
size larger than P ^2 and this is a
subset of size four. So we will have to
think some more uh about how to do this
and we will talk about that uh next
time.