And our second speaker and is he there
he is okay is Ben Kleinstever
colleague of mine at Massachusetts
General Hospital Center for Genomic
Medicine. Uh and he's going to be
talking about you know what I think was
science fiction about a decade ago but
now seems very real and very salient. So
take it away Ben.
>> All right. Wonderful. Thanks for the
invitation to Molina uh to come speak at
the symposium. It's been really
interesting to to learn from all of you
in a field that's a little adjacent to
my own. So bear with me as I tell you
something a little tangential to what
you've been talking about so far today,
but more about the variant to medicine
or variant to therapeutics approach.
Um some quick disclosures, none of which
are uh relevant to what I'll tell you
today.
Uh and first of course just
acknowledging the folks in my group uh
who I have the pleasure of showing you
their data today and telling you their
stories. So obviously very grateful to
work with these um talented and and
really motivated trainees.
So what I hope to tell you today is a
story that's 10 years in the making. How
do we go from genetic diagnosis of uh
specific mutations, non-inherited but
sort of uh either inherited or
non-inherited mutations uh and draw on a
toolbox of genome editing technologies
to rapidly treat uh individual
mutations?
um and can we think about ways to scale
this and do this more rapidly for
patients and then if I have time at the
end I'll tell you uh how we're thinking
about other technologies that would
allow us to leap beyond sort of one
patient at a time uh but now think about
treating thousands at a time for even
rare diseases.
So I think as you all know genome
editing technologies have given us a
really unprecedented ability to go and
pick at individual letters in our three
billion bases of DNA in our genomes. And
I won't belabor this slide for the sake
of time but just the pie chart beside
the the cartoon here I think is really
important to frame how we think about
genome editing from a technology
development perspective. Um and this is
just showing the different types of
genetic lesions that cause human
disease. So from single letter mutations
to small deletions or large copy um
gains or losses uh what this really
means is that we need a diversity of
tools to go and think about correcting
all kinds of different genetic disease.
So for the sake of the first maybe 15
minutes that I'll tell you I'm going to
focus on tools that allow us to make
single letter changes to the genome. And
these are really acutely actionable in
the clinic because the tools to correct
these types of mutations are quite
efficient and quite precise given the
tremendous development of techn these
technologies called base editors over
the last decade or so.
So I'll tell you quickly about base
editors. So they were developed here at
the broad institute by David Lu's lab.
Um these are a really amazing technology
that are built on a crisper cast 9
enzyme chassis. The crispercast enzymes
role in a base editing reaction is to
locate a target site to bind it and to
expose a small part of singlestranded
DNA. So um here we're trying to expose a
few letters in a a target site to make
that accessible for an enzyatic process.
The second part of a base editor is the
diaminise domain. And this is the really
key function of a base editor where now
when we have this single strand of DNA
exposed the diaminise can go and perform
some chemistry on these individual
letters. Uh so if you're trying to
convert an A to a G, this happens
through adinine dam oops adinine
damination
um to innine and then through subsequent
repair we get a G in place upon removal
of the inosine. So this is one flavor of
several different types of base editors
that have been developed. Uh the two
major classes are called adinine base
editors and cytosine base editors. And
these essentially give you the ability
to make a to g or c to t changes.
And this is of course again important as
we think about correcting um human
pathogenic mutations where between these
two classes of base editors we can now
in principle address more than 60% of
known single letter mutations.
But there's a big challenge for
implementing base editors to correct
pathogenic mutations. And this uh is
dependent on a simple property of
crisper proteins called the pam. So a
cast 9 protein to find its target site
has to recognize a short sequence called
a PAM. For the commonly used castine
protein, this is just two guanine
nucleotides. So this occurs pretty
frequently. And the position of this is
quite important because the PAM has to
be at a certain distance away from your
edit that you want to make so that you
can basically place the diaminise over
top of this single stranded DNA. So what
this means when you go to use a base
editor is that there's an a window of
editing efficiency and we call this a
base editor edit window and we have to
have a pam at the right distance
upstream to put the diaminise over top
of our edit of interest.
A second key consideration here is that
the edit window is a couple bases wide.
So we also want to avoid editing
unintended bases nearby uh because this
can result in what we call bystander
editing. So if you want to edit this A,
you may not want to edit this other A
that could be directly adjacent to it or
maybe a few bases away. So there are a
few strategies to try and mitigate uh
the editing of bystander bases and one
of which is of course just choosing a
different guide RNA and positioning the
target site by a different bioues.
Okay. So uh but again the bottom line
here is to be able to base edit
efficiently and to correct pathogenic
mutations we have to have PAMS in the
right spot and if you had a pathogenic
mutation shown here in this diagram and
no PAMS in the right position we
wouldn't be able to perform that base
edit.
So this really has been an opportunity
for my lab and others to go and take
these amazing proteins that came out of
nature and use methods called protein
engineering to build a really rich
toolbox of cast 9 proteins that now give
us the precision to place base editors
wherever we would like.
So a few years ago we came up with one
potential solution to this problem where
again if you're using the naturally
occurring crisper cast proteins you have
a bunch of blind spots where you can't
base edit. We engineered what we called
a PAMless version of cast 9 called spry.
Uh where that essentially without
requiring a pam anymore, we could place
the base editor anywhere across the
genome. This now gave us the ability to
perform base edits at nearly any base of
the genome using a single castine
protein.
This protein's been useful to us and
others for lots of other applications
beyond base editing. So here just
highlighting one example where we've
used this enzyme as a nucleus in vitro
to digest DNA in place of restriction
enzymes. Um Russell Walton in my group
was the person who engineered this
protein. He's now doing his PhD here at
the Broad. This is a picture of Russell
holding a tube of sprry that is now sold
by NEB. I think he was the first
customer to to buy this excitedly and is
still waiting for his 3-cent royalty. Um
so I think that's one of again many
potential uses of a pamless cast 9
protein. Uh we and others have gone on
to use enzymes like sprry hooked up to
um base editors and and to prime editors
for therapeutics and pre-clinical
applications and now with my colleague
succeeded raven at the NH even in a
clinical trial to treat a primary immune
deficiency.
Um but one of the potential issues of
using a pamless enzyme is that uh by
design we've allowed this enzyme to
access the whole genome to give us the
precision to edit anywhere. So we have
these big boosts in targeting range. But
a potential consequence here is that
we've lost some specificity. So with
wild type cast 9, it requires a PAM. It
can only access part of the genome. That
creates issues for being able to to edit
any specific base. But that by some ways
makes the enzyme somewhat specific
because it can't access much of the
genome and it may encounter fewer
offtargets.
But with a pamless enzyme and this is a
vast oversimplification of of a cartoon
here um it in theory has access to the
entire genome. So it can encounter more
theoretical potential offtarget sites.
Uh and we and others have actually shown
that when you use a pamless enzyme the
rates of offtarget editing can increase.
And it turns out actually our goal when
we were building the spry protein
actually was not to do this all along.
We were trying to do something else. And
the simplest evolutionary trajectory
that we found to get to this phenotype
of not requiring uh to changing a PAM
was uh we kept making the enzyme lose
its PAM preference. What we were trying
to do actually was instead of removing
the PAM, we were trying to make lots of
different proteins that had different
PAM requirements because then each
individual protein would be safe because
it would still be restricted to a subset
of the genome. But if we engineered
enough of these proteins, we would have
the same comprehensive genome targeting
as you would get with a Pamless protein.
So an example that would look something
like this where instead of building one
enzyme to edit anywhere, our goal
originally was to build many enzymes
that had really specific PAM
requirements and then you could draw
from this toolbox of enzymes for any
given editing application.
So when I started my lab seven years
ago, our one of our really key goals was
to learn enough about what controlled
how cast 9 reads its PAM to get to the
point where we could develop a model
where we could go and now predict a new
enzyme for any given sequence of
interest. Uh I'm going to simplify seven
years of research in two slides. So to
do this, we had to first build some
assays to uh more scalably characterize
crisper proteins. Uh before we built
this assay, poor Russell would sit in
the cold room and purify proteins one at
a time. Uh but by developing this assay
where we could now screen proteins 100
or 400 at a time in different types of
um 96 well plate plastic wear, we could
think about profiling thousands of
proteins to gain enough data to train
machine learning models. So uh when
Rachel joined my lab during COVID for
her rotation project, we thought this
would be sort of a simple thing to do.
It ended up being her entire 5-year
thesis project. Uh but what we wanted to
do was learn enough about the
relationship between the amino acid
sequence of cast 9 and its PAM
requirement. And if we could do this
across enough proteins, could we then
begin to predict new proteins bespoke
for a specific genetic use cases?
So saying that again a different way,
what Rachel then did was basically
create large libraries of castine
proteins, deeply characterize their
properties using this assay that Russell
built. And by screening and
characterizing over a thousand cast 9
proteins, Rachel could then take that
data and uh uh train a machine learning
model based on the input of amino acid
sequence and also the PAM profiles and
then begin to think about creating a
model where if we wanted to uh design a
protein that could target a specific
sequence, could we then draw from this
toolbox of 64 million cast 9 proteins
and predict really efficient and
specific enzymes from that set?
So here's one potential example uh of
how uh this model would perform. So I
have these animations backwards. I
apologize. So what we did with Luca
Panella's lab at MGH was design a
website where someone could go and input
their uh parameters of the crisper
protein that they would want. So for
instance in this case here for uh this
redopsin p23h mutation that causes
autoomal dominant blindness we need a
really specific type of crispercast
enzyme. On the mutant alil we have an
ngtg pam and on the wild type alil we
have an nggg pam. The canonical
crispercast protein would be really good
at recognizing the wild type alil but
really bad at recognizing the mutant al.
So this is essentially backwards of what
we would want to treat this genetic
disease because we want to be able to
knock out the mutant alil and leave the
wild type alone.
So what we can now do is we can go into
this Pamela uh prediction model using
the simple web interface. We can input
these design parameters like maximizing
efficiency on an NGTG PAM and minimizing
efficiency on NGGG and then have the
model spit out two or 10 different cast
proteins that we can go and test in a
cell model.
So this is what we did. So we created a
HEC 293 model uh that encoded this
genetic mutation. uh forgive the um
genetics of HEC293 cells where we have
two copies of the mutant alil and one
copy of the wild type al. If we use the
wild type cast 9 protein spcast 9, what
we found as expected is that the wild
type cast 9 protein is very effective at
knocking out the wild type al because it
can recognize ng but it can't recognize
ngtg. So this is really not what we
want. We want to leave the wild type
alil alone.
If we take our PAM relaxed enzyme that I
told you about a few slides ago that can
recognize sort of the whole genome, it
can recognize in theory both of these
alals equally. That's exactly what we
observe. We saw editing both on the NG
wild type AL and the NGT mutant al. But
now taking one of the Pamela predicted
enzymes, what we found was a reversal in
the biology of cast 9 where we preserved
now um the wild type AL. We left it
alone because this new enzyme can't
target NG and we observed really
substantial editing on the mutant alil
because we're able to design a protein
that could access this new NGT space.
So this is one of many potential
examples where you can now use this
model to go and predict specific enzymes
for individual use cases. Um and again
this was built on many years of our
learnings about the biology of cast 9
and building the right assays to create
training data. now to the point where we
have a model that can go and predict
bespoke cast 9 proteins for individual
genetic sequences.
Um the end result here is that we have
really a massive toolbox of crispercast
enzymes that are individually safe. Um
they tend to be much more efficient than
PAM relaxed enzymes because they uh
aren't searching the whole genome for
their targets and together we have
enough of them now that we do still have
the ability to target the genome with
high versatility.
Um, we've shown that these enzymes
behave really nicely as base editors for
single letter changes um and across
other types of editing platforms like
prime editors and other next generation
genome editing tools.
So now I'll show you an example of where
we can now implement this uh type of uh
prediction and implementation approach
uh clinically.
So actually first I'll just again frame
this problem. So where we started in
sort of 2012 with wild type crisper cast
9 proteins like spcast 9 is this was an
amazing tool that allowed us to access
some of the genome. Uh and now we have
many different types of pam variant cast
9 proteins that uh allow us to access
access the genome with really incredible
versatility with a single protein like
spry or now in many cases like for
therapeutics we have these Pamela
designed enzymes or other rationally
designed enzymes from my lab. They give
us the ability to have the same
targeting range as one would with SPRY
uh but now each enzyme being much um
safer and much more efficient. Uh I do
think there are lots of really
interesting use cases for each type of
uh protein. Um having one enzyme that
can do lots of things is really amazing
for the type of work that we've heard a
lot about today for functional genomics
and doing really dense tiling screens of
regulatory elements and even protein
coding sequences. Uh but in my world
where we're more concerned about
therapeutics, we really do want sort of
the the best athlete. We want an enzyme
that's efficient and safe uh and uh
versatile.
So here's one specific example uh where
we can sort of rapidly now implement
this pipeline to predict these bespoke
proteins. So Kieran Musenure, who
trained here at MGH, but now runs a
research lab at the University of
Pennsylvania, emailed me last summer
essentially saying that they have this
really sick infant who has a a metabolic
disease, a mutation in the CPS1 gene, um
causing a ura cycle disorder, and that
they'd already screened some of our PAM
laxed enzymes for base editing and found
that they could achieve reasonable
levels of editing. uh but just wondered
before they pulled the trigger on
manufacturing this uh mRNA to treat this
patient, did we have something that was
maybe more efficient and safer?
So I went and looked at this specific
sequence that uh this infant had. He
actually inherited two mutations in this
gene. Uh this one was actually the most
correctable by base editing. So this was
the the better target. And when we look
at this genetic mutation here, this is
the A that we need to convert back to a
G to remove the stop codon and restore
the natural glutamine codon here. How
one then approaches this is we would
look for adinine base editors because
these make a tog edits. And then we
could design some target sites for this
crispercast base editor that would
position the edit window over top of
this admin. It may be a little difficult
to see, but here I'm showing the PAMS of
these target sites, and you'll see there
are no NGS at the right spot upstream.
So, we have to use either a PAMLaxed
enzyme or some of these uh more designed
custom proteins that we've built
recently.
So, Kieran's lab had tested uh these
pamlaxed enzymes like SPG and Spry, and
they found that some of them combined
with certain guide RNAs could achieve
levels of editing that in theory would
be beneficial to this patient.
Um but again coming back to this
question you know did we have something
that was safer uh although the the
pamless enzymes did work in this case
could we use something from this uh
toolbox of proteins to make this edit
with fewer offtarget risks.
So here we have this amazing uh
opportunity to test all these enzymes
that we've built over the years where
Kieran's group had already tested the
Pamlax proteins and now we could go and
predict a bespoke protein from our
Pamela model and even at the same time
maybe test some other enzymes that we'd
been engineering in the lab uh over the
last six years. So these sort of
rationally engineered human-designed
proteins.
Um okay so here's some of the data that
went into this. So again the initial
result that Kieran had sent me were
using the PAM relaxed enzyme with this
specific guide RNA achieving the the
therapeutic threshold in their early
test. So I got this email from him at
like 3:00 a.m. He had just Kieran had
analyzed the NGS data um himself. uh the
Pamela enzyme, we had just sent him one
prediction from our model compared to
two of these manually engineered enzymes
that we'd been building for five years
and found that all three of these
proteins outperformed the PAM relaxed
enzyme to correct this genetic mutation.
And when we further stress tested these
enzymes by making the diaminise a little
bit weaker to make it safer so that it
wouldn't have as many offtarget edits on
RNA, what we found is that the the
Pamela designed enzyme here outperformed
the Pamless enzyme and also these two
other rationally engineered proteins. So
saying that a different way actually the
the ML designed protein really
outperformed the human engineered
proteins that we've been building for
years. This isn't always the case, but
in this specific example, it was. Um, so
having the the fortune of a toolbox now
allows us to really identify these
efficacious and safe enzymes.
So this was just the start of a really
remarkable story that I'm sure many of
you heard about, have heard about uh
this treatment, uh, this really amazing
timeline for baby KJ. Um, getting the
diagnosis really within a few days after
birth. Uh Kieran's lab developed this
patient specific cell line. We sent them
some editors to try. They rapidly tried
that within I think about 10 days. They
already had results. Um quickly
generated a mouse model and did some
experiments in non-human primates. All
in about a six-month time frame to begin
dosing a baby KJ with a first low dose
of this therapy.
Um I'll point you to the the paper that
came out in the New England Journal that
really deeply describes the story.
Again, this was led by Kieran Musenuru
and Becca Erenss Nicholas at UPEN. We
played a small role in designing the the
protein chassis that went into this
therapeutic. The bottom line here is
that this young boy who had a
devastating metabolic disease that 50%
of patients with these mutations die in
the first year of life um now can
consume a normal protein diet uh and has
returned home with his family. So, lots
was written about this in May when this
uh story first broke in the New York
Times and all kind of other media
outlets. Uh if you've got 10 minutes
tonight, go on to just Google Upen Baby
KJ video and there's a 10-minute video
that really nicely describes um all the
amazing discoveries and collaboration
that led to the development of this
therapeutic. Um
this is something that I think is you
know really motivating for our field and
really inspirational that we can go from
diagnosis to treatment in 6 months now.
Um really customized base editor for
this patient's mutation.
Um I will also shout out one of my other
colleagues at the NIH Succeed Raven
who's leading many clinical trials using
these engineered crisper cast proteins
for base editing for inborn errors of
immunity. um three different ongoing
trials for different flavors of primary
immune deficiencies. Um two have already
enrolled patients and showing promise
and others uh recently dosed. So I think
here again just highlighting the really
immense potential of uh pairing base
editors with these customized crisper
cast proteins uh to get medicines into
patients that we know should be
beneficial because essentially we're
just converting back to a wild type
genome and doing our best as we can to
avoid offtarget edits.
I have no idea. Do I have five more
minutes? Five more minutes. Okay. So I
think to to frame where we've come um
you know we have now this really
tremendous toolbox of crispercast
proteins that allow us to think about
going from diagnosis to treatment in a
matter of months. Um we'd like to do
this quicker, right? So 6 months is okay
for some diseases, but for others it's
still really not fast enough. So how do
we think about even accelerating this
timeline even quicker?
So uh here for most rare diseases one of
the problems is that many patients
present with different genetic mutations
um very rare where there's an enriched
mutation that every individual would
have like in cle cell disease. So um
this is usually the situation where
we've found that uh we can diagnose
identify and develop a a base editor and
a guide RNA for a few mutations in a
gene. But to do this for tens or
hundreds or thousands of different
patients for the same disease, there are
many different potential challenges here
for scale. Um some of which are
scientific, some of which are
regulatory. I think all of these aspects
are being solved right now. Um, some of
the bigger challenges just are
financial. It still costs millions of
dollars and months of time to develop
these bespoke base editing treatments
for different patients. So, how do we
think about solving some of these
problems? In my lab, we're working on
methods to make this process quicker
where we can now make as much of this
predictable as possible. Um, where we
can have a set of off-the-shelf base
editors and predict which guide RNA one
would use to go and treat that genetic
mutation.
U but another approach would be to think
of different ways of editing. So instead
of going to correct individual
mutations, can we develop technologies
where we would insert specific cDNAs
that would correct these mutations at
the endogenous locus for an an
individual gene? And if we could develop
these types of pan mutation editors, we
could treat all patients within a
disease class uh with one editing
modality. So this would be widely
applicable across lots of patients.
Um, so there have been lots of ways that
have been proposed in the terms of
genome editing technologies to do this
and two of the major enzymes that would
allow us to insert DNA into the genome
are called recombinases and transposees.
Um, for the sake of time I'll just do
this pretty quickly and saying that both
of these types these classes of enzymes
require double stranded DNA donors and
this is just how they evolved in nature.
they uh by necessity have to utilize
double stranded DNA as a donor to insert
that cargo into the genome. Uh but this
creates an issue. So most primary human
cell types in mice and humans don't like
double stranded DNA. This triggers our
innate immune response uh usually
leading to cell death depending on the
cell type that you're working in. Um so
showing this differently in an
experiment in neonatal mice if you
inject PBS they're perfectly happy. Um
if we inject double stranded DNA at
different doses into mice, we see this
really profound activation of sting,
phosphorolated sting uh because seagass
will recognize double stranded DNA and
initiate this uh interferon cascade.
Um in adult mice, this is even more
profound where um in untreated or in PBS
treated mice, there's obviously no
activation of sting. Uh but in double
stranded DNA treated mice, we see this
really uh essentially every hippatocite
in the liver will light up. Um and this
of course leads to pretty rapid cell
death uh and animal death in mice. Uh so
because all of these promising platforms
for large sequence integration require
double stranded DNA donors, this issue
of innate immunity essentially rules out
all of these enzymes for large sequence
insertion because they all require
double stranded DNA donors. So we
wondered if we could get away from this
type of donor format so that we could
think about large sequence insertion for
therapeutic purposes. So double stranded
DNA is seagassp provoking. Uh we know uh
based on recent evidence in the field
that circular singlestranded DNA is
immunasive. It's not detectable by
seagass. Got one minute I can do this.
Um it's not detectable by seagass
because there's no double stranded
portion. Um the problem here though is
that this now is not functional with re
combinases because we've removed the
doublest stranded DNA um substrate.
So we wondered could we make only a
small region of this DNA donor
doublestranded um such that the
reaccombase could still recognize it but
now the vast majority of this donor DNA
molecule remains evasive to seagass. Um
so this would be immune evasive as a
molecule but still recognizable by
recombinases.
So there's a lot of data that underlies
this, but I'll just show you the the
take-home message here is that when we
use the doublest stranded DNA like I
showed you a few slides ago, we see this
really profound activation of sting. But
when we use this chimeic molecule with
only a short double stranded region,
this remains immune stealth. We don't
activate um seagass or sting.
So we've gone on to show that this u
different type of DNA donor format is
actually functional with all different
types of large sequence insertion
technologies. uh we've done this in lots
of different cultured human cell types.
We've done this in primary human cells
and also now in vivo in mice.
Um so this gives us a lot of optimism
about large sequence insertion as pan
mutation editing approaches moving
forward because we now have an a DNA
donor format type that is able to evade
immune detection. Um, these types of
donors are compatible with all of our
favorite types of enzymes that we use to
insert large sequences into the genome.
And this now, I think, removes one of
the major barriers that was really
prohibiting the uh these pan mutation
editing approaches from being functional
in vivo or in most primary human cell
types.
Um, so this work was actually led by
Connor, a graduate student in the time
at the lab, who's now just temporarily
doing a short posttock. Um, Joe and
Devid and many others in the group have
played a key role. um other folks at
Full Circle Therapeutics and other labs
at MGH and at um MGB who played really
key roles in the the invivo aspects of
this work as well.
So to summarize, I think we've come
really far in the last decade uh from
being able to diagnose mutations uh to
now being able to develop these really
rapid customizable treatments for
patients in a matter of months. Uh I'm
extremely optimistic that we can really
compress those timelines even further
given that the FDA has signaled a lot of
interest in in playing an active role in
in how they change their regulatory
mindset and getting these treatments
into patients quicker as well. Um,
beyond the mutation specific editing, I
showed you how we've thought about
removing one of the key barriers for
large sequence insertion that will all
also now allow us to think about these
pan mutation editing approaches where we
could develop one editing treatment for
all patients in a a class of genetic
disease. So with that, I'll I'll show a
cartoon of the lab and again just really
grateful for their efforts and very
thankful for all the funders that have
enabled us to do this work. Thank you
for letting me tell you something
different.
Incredible work. Few questions. One or
two
>> here.
>> That was a that was a really amazing
talk as as someone whose partner has a
rare rare disease that is uh not really
on the
>> uh not really in any clinical trials
right now. It's just it's really cool to
hear something hopeful. Um, in terms of
the part at the end where you're talking
about using a, you know, partially DSDNA
as a payload, how big of a do you have,
and I don't know if you have a sense of
this, but how big of a thing could you
potentially replace like an Exxon or
like do you have a sense of the payload
size?
>> Yeah, so we've tested cDNA anywhere from
2 KB or 1 KB on the lower end up to 6 or
7 KB. Uh, recombinases are actually
really agnostic in most senses of in the
cargo that they insert. So they're not
like some technologies where the bigger
you make the cargo like homology
directed repair with crisper cast
nucleases where the the size of
insertion makes the efficiency lower.
They're generally agnostic of the the
cargo size up to a certain point. And I
think there it just becomes a matter of
delivering the the donor into cells that
becomes the bottleneck rather than the
enzyme itself. So um I think most cDNAs
are under 5 kb. I think it's like 90% of
cDNAs of genes are under five kilobases
and that's well within the remmit of
these types of approaches.
>> So So just to kind of continue then I'll
hand it to someone else but you'd be
thinking about so you'd be thinking
about dropping in a a a full cDNA
directly or would you be thinking about
like replacing an exxon that is you know
the exxon in question that has like a
missense or nonsense mutation just
trying to get a feel for method there.
>> Yeah. So, so here I think if you're
using something like a recombinase and
you're trying to insert at the
endogenous locus, the ideal strategy
would be to insert the full cDNA and in
some cases maybe an intron if needed for
the correct expression of a gene and
then having a a polya sequence. So you
basically turn off the native gene
downstream and you'd only express the
corrective cDNA and by doing this at the
endogenous locus you'd express it at the
the normal levels.
>> Thank you very much.
>> All right, last question. Go ahead,
Molina. Last question for you.
>> What? Very quick. I mean, breakthrough
work. It's really phenomenal to um hear
it over and over again. I love it. I
have one question. Actually, I might
have missed that part. Is your model to
design picking up or predicting
bystander effects of the editors?
>> Yeah. So, uh I don't know if there's
great models yet. So, Manda Arbab here
did her PhD with David Lou. they
developed a um a prediction method
called behive and that helps you
nominate guide RNAs that one could use
but um I think there's no great
consensus I think it's sort of trial by
you know try and see what you get and
what we've learned actually for a lot of
the primary deficiencies is that um we
have good cell models to test the impact
of a bystander edit because it shouldn't
be that if you have a bystander you
can't use this clinically I think we
have to learn what the impact is and in
some cases actually the bystander edit
has been beneficial. We don't know
whether that's because it's changing the
function of the protein or it's changing
expression of the protein, but I think
this is something the field will learn a
lot more about as we get more of these
um approaches into the clinic.
>> Awesome.