welcome everyone and thank you all for
being here um on behalf of women atro
and equity and biom Medicine we're
thrilled to have Dr Nasha chway here
with us today to talk about racial
disparities in cancer research Nasha CH
PhD is an assistant professor at The
Institute for molecular medicine at the
fight Institute for medical research in
2014 she received her PhD in
computational biology from while Cornell
medicine in New York
she then went on to complete her
post-doctoral training at The Institute
for systems biology in
2019 with the late Dr Ilia shmulovich in
cancer integrative genomic analysis and
biomarker Discovery Dr CH analyzes
patient derived data sets in order to
understand the risk for cancer
development and progression how tumors
respond to treatment and how to better
predict effective treatment regimens to
improve cancer outcomes a particular
focus of her work is an understanding
the biological basis for cancer Health
disparities experienced by understudied
populations particularly those of
African descent and with an eye toward
informing better interventions that will
lead to Equitable Health outcomes thank
you all for being
here thank you for that wonderful
introduction Ro uh good afternoon to
everybody uh this afternoon we're going
to have a a discussion uh a provocative
discussion about a topic that is close
to my heart um and to the heart of many
people and we set up the session this
afternoon I'm going to give a short
overview talk of this area of uh cancer
disparities so it's a quick overview
talk um just introducing Concepts and
the general motivating the problem and
then Dr Alicia uh Dr um Martin and I are
going to have uh a chat a Fireside cat
it's rather cool here in Boston this
afternoon uh we have the chairs but not
the fire uh but hopefully we'll bring
the fire with the discussion and of
course we'll at that point open it up
for discussion uh to the room um okay
and so to get started I thought we' just
um start with a definition okay cancer
Health disparities are differences in
disease measures between population
groups so you can consider the measures
as incident or prevalence or mortality
morbidity Etc as listed on the slide and
we typically when you hear cancer
disparities it's easy to jump
immediately to racial and ethnic
disparities but I want to highlight at
this juncture that there are many
population groups who
experience
um uh outcomes that are not positive
compared to other groups that are
defined on many axes of how they
self-identify so that includes by
socioeconomic status or by um uh their
uh individuals with disability or how
individuals identify by their sexual or
gender identity so I don't want to us to
leave this room this afternoon uh
believing only that people of racial and
ethnic uh minorities in the US are the
only ones who experience disparities
there are inequities in many population
groups across the board in cancer and so
I want us to keep that in mind
um my group studies racial and ethnic
disparities and these are well
documented and have persistent for a
long time so this is data from the
NCI program which uh epidemiological
surveillance database where we're
looking here at mortality age adjusted
mortality from 2000 to
2019 by race and ethnicity so how people
self-identify and we can see that
although in general mortality in due to
cancer across different sites is going
down uh that um there are still
persistent differences if we look here
at the end of the graph here when this
last data was collected in
2019 that mortality uh is higher in
certain groups that identify for example
here non-hispanic groups have the
highest
mortality in cancer across the board in
the US
um just so that we are not singularly
focused on the US we also see just
abundant Global variation in cancer
incidents and mortality
globally um this data is looking at the
annualized rate of change in terms of
cancer incidents over the same sort of
10 10 years as we looked at in the in
the previous data and we're seeing a
recent Trend where we seeing in low and
middle inome countries a rapid increase
in cancer
incidents uh that is projected to be
very very high over the next 30 to 50
years according to un who data so this
problem of differences in in cancer
outcomes and incidents is predicted to
be an even major public challenge Public
Health Challenge
worldwide if we
consider the income levels of different
countries across the globe we see that
the estimated new cancer cases uh those
rates are different according to the
whether or not the countries are
classified as High High um HDI so sort
of their socioeconomic development index
so high HDI countries versus low HDI
countries basically poorer countries are
expected to have a much larger incident
of are projected to have much larger
incident of cancer so if you consider
some of these um factors driving
disparities across groups whether it's
by socioeconomic status how people
self-identify by racial ethnicity where
people live Etc the issue of cancer
Health disparities is not Germain or
unique to the US but is projected to be
a significant Global issue facing us
over the coming
years so what do we know drives and
causes this disparities so there are
several buckets of factors that are
known to contribute so environmental
factors are some of among some of the
most quoted for example are exposures to
um environmental toxins air quality
Transportation where we live the places
where we live contribute to a disease
risk that instinctively makes sense to
us uh behavioral factors such as our
diet our our level of EX ize um our
adherence to health behaviors that
contribute to our overall health social
factors including health literacy the
level of Education our income as well as
our ability to access health care and
then individual cultures we see
differences in incidents and mortality
in different places all those places
have different localized cultures and
different beliefs that contribute to
their health outcomes psychological
factors like stress have been reported
to be associated with cancer incidents
and outcomes and certainly for many of
us in the room who've come to this
problem uh being interested in
biological and genetic determinants of
of of disparities in
cancer when you see these factors listed
like this it's difficult to think of a
framework to put it all together with so
the aacr has this organizing framework
they recently published in their cancer
disparities report that looks at how
these factors interact together in a
framework that is driven Upstream by uh
structural factors in the US such as
racism uh which lead to structural
inequities and societal
injustices which acting through all
these factors jointly contributes to
cancer inequities and disparities across
the cancer Continuum so when we refer to
the cancer Continuum as you know risk
early detection cancer development
treatment treatment outcomes and
survivorship um my particular area of
focus and interest in is in the
biological and genetic factors uh and so
we've come at this from this sort of EP
lens of racial and ethnic disparities in
cancer but I've also told you that I'm
interested in the biologic and genetic
drivers so there's a little bit of in
congruence here because I'm interested
in a biologic and genetic aspect of
disparities but it's defined by a social
construct so I'm going to take a little
bit of a segue here to talk about the
social
constructs of race and
ethnicity um so race is defined by um as
a category of humankind that shares
distinct physical traits or ethnicity by
how groups identify according to Common
sort of racial National tribal uh or
religious background so it's how people
self-identify based on uh where they
come from what they believe about thems
it's not an inherently
biological uh variable in the US these
are typically uh taken from
standardized um variables from say the
sense from the US government om Office
of Management and budget uh from the
Census uh where we tend to get a lot of
these data from the health systems or uh
ethn Unity where we have two categories
in the US Hispanic or Latino Or nonh
Hispanic or
Latino so in thinking about disparities
many of us have started to consider that
we want to understand how people are
related to each other biologically
perhaps a better lens to look at this
through is one of genetic ancestry so we
can take the genetic data from
individuals in our studies and infer
genetic ancestry based on reference
population um and look at how similar
those individuals we're studying are are
to reference po uh individuals in a
reference database and use this ref uh
reference genetic ancestry or genetic
similarity as the basis of grouping
people together and then determining how
that relates to various cancer
phenotypes and so my group um
particularly studies um ancestry
affecting cancer and uses that as a
foundational framework organizing
principle to look at how the social
environmental and lifestyle exposure
interact with our underlying ancestry
related genetics and biology and uh
manifest as cancer disparities in in in
the
phenotypes um the basis of this work
which I don't have time to go through
this Mo this afternoon is some of our
earlier work some of work I did as a
postu with people some of the
investigators who are here at the broad
is um
when here in the tcga atlas in the pan
cancer Atlas phase in
20189 thereabouts we did exactly this we
inferred genetic ancestry from the
germline data in the tcga cohort and
then we looked at how that ancestry
correlated with uh somatic phenotypes in
cancer so here for example this is work
led by uh Gian Kang who's now at mskcc
where she showed here for example that
uh somatic alteration frequencies in
particular genes in pan cancer Atlas we
saw elevated mutations somatic
alteration frequencies in these three
genes and then specific alteration
frequencies in kidney cancer and vhl
pbm1 and bladder cancer and uh a couple
of other genes specific to East Asian
ancestry so there is a basis of seeing
Mo molecular traits so sematic
alterations at various levels of
biological organization whether it's
somatic mutations expression um gene
expression alterations that are related
to ancestry cancer uh that could play a
role in manifesting in in our
investigating in our investigations of
ancestry related traits driving uh
cancer phenotypes in disparities related
work what is confusing is that um in
this work both concepts of race and
ancestry play a role and feed into the
health status and I found this schematic
by Tim rebik to be particularly
insightful because both our racial and
ethnic identity and our ancestry have
distinct and interrelated impacts on
health status so in essence the
underlying ancestry relates to biologic
iCal attributes that contribute to the
genomic architecture of an individual at
Birth and those biological int
attributes that are in uh influenced by
inherited
genetics and the lifetime
exposures uh uh elicited on our epig
genome jointly contributes to our health
status right but our lifetime exposure
and our experiences over the course of
our lifetime which contribute to us
developing cancer are also impacted by
our race ethnicity because they
influence where we live what we eat who
we interact with and our lived
experience of the world that's
translated into a biology via say for
example epigenetic mechanisms so it's
actually quite a gnarly ball of yarn to
uncouple and un twist really to to tease
apart the relative impact of ancestry
race ethnicity in driving different
cancer phenotypes um that can contribute
to disparities and so the organizing
principle of my lab is to um uh analyze
a computational biologist is to analyze
molecular profiling data sets multiomic
profiling data sets from cancer cohorts
to try and infer prognostic markers or
predict clinically useful end points
through a race of race ethnicity and
ancestry and determine sort of the
biological and genetic factors that
contributes to cancer Health disparities
so this is our current mission statement
as a lab uh we ask questions like what
are the genetic and molecular features
that drive cancer disparities uh does
this lead us to a mechanistic
understanding of cancer
disparities uh and can we build better
models for prediction and ultimately can
we identify novel therapeutic targets
uh that's the end goal I'm going to give
an example of a cancer type we work on
today uh for the in the interest of time
endometrial cancer is one of the tumor
types we're focused on it's particularly
interesting to me and um um going to
give a call to action for those of us
who are here and if you're online please
come work on inom metrial cancer
everybody it is a rising Global epidemic
which somehow no one seems to have heard
about um incidence and mortality of
endometrial cancer uterine cancers
broadly is rising across the board so we
have incidence data here and mortality
data on the right you can see that the
prevalence seems to be higher in higher
income countries although we see uh for
example here that mortality is also
generally high in low-income countries
uh but it's the uh rate data shows in a
steeper increase in low-income countries
I'm not not showing that data here early
work from uh people who are here
including G GS and andry CHC established
that um we have pathological
classification so classic histology like
endometroid subtypes or non- endomet
subtype by
histology and tumor grading associated
with particular somatic alterations like
tp53 mutations and establish a molecular
classification taxonomy as well which
lately has been integrated into clinical
treatment guidelines as of um a recent
release of the Figo classification in
this disease but what's particularly
concerning whereas other cancer types
the incidents and mortality is
decreasing slowly over time so we're
making progress for some reason in
endometrial cancers the opposite uh even
when we can when we adjust our
epidemiological estimates by rates of
hysterctomy in this
disease we see we are seeing that the
incidence rates uh for endometrial
cancer on the
rise and not
unsurprisingly the incidents and
mortality rates are increasing at an
even steeper Pace in women who
self-identify as black so the women who
black women have the steepest increase
in incidents of mortality and that tend
to get get the more most aggressive
molecular subtypes or molecular
histological subtypes that have uh less
treatment options that we don't
understand the Genesis of okay so one of
our research question is what's driving
this disparity in aggressive disease
presentation and uh like
many uh examples we lack the cohorts
that are rationally and ethnically
diverse that have have data that's
collected across all these domains that
we know are drivers of disparities so we
know what the problem is we know what
kind of data we need and we know who we
need it from but we don't have it okay
so that's where we are
today uh and so I present to you what
we're currently doing and where we'd
like to go so we got to start somewhere
we can't just sit around and say we
don't have anything so we can't do
anything so the first thing we're trying
is to leverage existing clinical
sequencing data we have uh I work at a
hospital we see patients and so we've uh
we're looking at retrospective cases uh
we're in a large metropolitan area of
New York greater New York Metro one of
the most diverse areas in in the country
and so uh here we have a cohort over the
last the defined area the last 10 years
it's around of people who were seen in
our Hospital who met the inclusion
criteria who also got clinical genome
sequencing done um in that cohort we're
seeing around 30% African ancestry
individuals we look at them by
hystological subtype we look at them
through ancestry and we try to correlate
these and try to understand if we see an
enrichment of specific mutations or
characteristics of their tumors uh with
ancestry Etc and then we're also uh
applying because we're part of the
hospital for access to their historic
historical residential uh addresses to
to be able to do geoc coding and then
use population or census data to get
access say to their income and use
indices of their socioeconomic status
population level indices to estimate
sort of their uh area level metrics of
of of of access or socio economic status
but we know from uh studies that were
shown so for example this was a new New
England
New New England Journal of Medicine
article that showed for example that uh
one of our most popular clinical genome
sequencing companies over 80% of the
people that have tested to this point
which was September
2022 were of European ancestry
so um we can do what we can do with what
we have but it's not going to be
sufficient we also leveraging this
institutional catchment area we're in
we're partnering with other local New
York area hospitals to build resources
like this New York polyethnic 1,000
cohort uh where the goal is
intentionally recruit um historically
excluded populations into these cancer
genome sequencing cohorts of which one
of them is for endometrial cancer the
pilot data is here where we show that
the vast majority of individuals that
were recruited in the study of African
antry and then a subset of this Cod is
endometrial cancer we're currently
analyzing that data now not authorized
to talk about it exactly and show you
but we're making significant progress
and help hope to have that data out um
later this year but the cohort size is
on the order of 100
also we can also do something with
what's available right now and so we're
also trying to take advantage of
population biobanks that are available
right so we have all of us um it's one
of those resources that actually has
genetic socioeconomic environmental
clinical all these different drivers of
disparity uh type data that's there and
so we've started working um industrious
ly I would say my team is uh on defining
case control cohorts in all of us people
with cancer with endometrial cancer
admittedly the case count is low
depending on how strict you are with
your case definition anywhere on the
order of 400 to 1,000 but if you
consider that the tcga cods our own
institutional cohorts are in that realm
this almost doubles the number of uh
germline in metrial cancers that are in
the in the public domain and then here
we're defining Concepts that are both
genetic and social determinance data
we're using the survey data as well as
clinically abstracted data from the EMR
and building uh integrated uh um machine
learning models to predict endometrial
cancer status ultimately we want to
predict risk we want to build risk
models uh but we're still it's still
early days for us here I would
say these three paths I would say are an
imperfect solution because these data
were not collected fit for purpose and
so I think what's on the horizon for us
that's the most exciting is being part
of the recently funded cancer Grand
Challenge team the uh the cancer
iniquities team titled team sambai
societal ancestry and molecular biology
analysis of inequities um very excited
about this work this work is being led
by Dr Melissa Davis at moha school of
medicine basically from everything I've
told you so far it's centering um the
African ancestry African diaspora and
then looking through all through putting
that at the center of the lens and
looking at all these aspects that we
know Drive disparities in a fit for
purpose way uh the planned recruitment
for this project
is the US the UK and sites throughout
Africa uh germline tumor normal match
sequencing RNA SE long read any sort of
state-of-the-art technology in the right
population with the right study design
with all the right um known risk
factors uh straight from the jump but
this is a five-year project so um we're
what 3 months in so very exciting but uh
this just goes to show that in solving
and tackling a complex problem like this
we have to start from somewhere so we
start with where we are but we know
where we need to go and projects like
this are where we where things really
need to go intentional study design
intentional recruitment in the right
target
populations and so in essence um we want
to focus on peas ing apart the
biological and genetic determinance of
disparities asking the right questions
and that's it in a nutshell looking
forward to our conversation we cannot do
this work alone I want to acknowledge my
group who working very hard we have an
army of collaborators that we're working
with um all the sources of funding
support and today I especially want to
acknowledge somebody very important to
me my postdoctoral mental passed away um
earlier this year uh it's particularly
impacting me this week because um the
memorial simposium celebrating his
life's work and his contribution to
scientist this weekend on Saturday and I
put that um Link in there uh there will
be a uh the Symposium will be streamed
live as well it's on Saturday uh so
thank you for your attention
[Applause]
my M have been with you forward to
having
pleas thank you Nasha for your
presentation um we're now going to move
on to a firesight chat
portion um with Dr Alicia Martin our
very own she is an assistant
investigator at the analytics and
translational genetics unit at MGH an
assistant professor at Harvard Medical
school and an associate member at the
broen city um affiliated with the
Stanley Center for psychiatric research
on the medical and population genetics
program as a population of statistical
geneticists her research examines the
role of human history in shaping Global
genetic and phenotypic diversity given
vast eurocentric study biases she
investigates the general
generalizability oh my goodness
generalizability of knowledge gained
from large scale genetic studies across
globally diverse populations she's
particularly focused on ensuring that
the translation of genetic Technologies
via penic risk does not exacerbate
Health disparities induced by those
study biases towards this end she is
developing statistical methods Community
Resources vir genomics and research
capacity for multi-ancestry studies
particularly in
underrepresented
populations take away
thank thank you for giving the
opportunity to have a conversation with
such an esteemed lovely call here um and
thank you so much for all of your work
on these disparities I think they're so
incredibly challenging to disentangle so
hard to understand um want to start also
with my condolences for the loss of your
Mentor I'm sure that that is a huge loss
in in the field
um I want to kind of start big picture
and thinking about these disparities and
having this chat with you because you're
interested in the biological you're
interested in the genetics so you're
interested in the mechanism but it's
really hard to start at that level when
there's so much ins sconed in our
society and in how you know structural
racism is impacting disparities
including through access to healthare so
first I want to start with um how do the
disparities that you're describing and
that you're researching relate to who
can get care how easily can they get
care and also related to trust in
mainstream medicine
all right um thank you um uh before I
answer the question I also want to thank
you for your work in this field I think
um in getting to this field and tackling
some of this work reading some of your
early work on um CH and and and
representation there was also insightful
in in in US thinking about what we think
about and and getting to where we are as
well
um I think uh fundamentally
speaking who I think that slide from the
um
NM perspective was very telling right so
we've done all this work in the genomic
field to figure out the cancer drivers
so we're going to find all the drivers
and find what's mutated and then find a
targeted uh treatment and and administer
Precision oncology but we have this
fundamental issue where um most some
people aren't even getting the test okay
and so even if there is a drug they
can't get it um uh I trained on the you
know on the side of the analysis and
identifying the mutations and getting to
what drugs we need to make against which
which targets and I I didn't fully
consider the ramifications of what if
somebody didn't get the test uh and so
now that we're here um I'm having to
really take the time to educate myself
about these issues and consider the
wider ranging impact of that and I think
it comes uh it comes back to a question
a discussion we having earlier here
today uh with colleagues that I don't
feel like I'm an expert in Access issues
and you know who Etc but as a practicing
scientist I have to be informed and I
have to be aware of the science we're
doing has an impact in society and so
being more mindful about communicating
what we do outside of my realm outside
of my genomics colleagues uh talking to
people um I think at the recent aacr
disparities meeting uh it became clear
that a platform for um Advocate Patient
Advocates and advocacy in general for
scientists is important because that
message needs to go out to these
communities so that people understand
what it is we're doing what what genetic
testing means what it what it means so
that it becomes part of everyday
language part of the everyday lexicon so
that if you're in your physician asks
you to be part of a
study um it's it's not something um I
believe a patient advocate called it um
you know you're not you're not a guinea
pig in a study right to be part of a
clinical trial or so there is um there
is some responsibility on as a scientist
to Advocate a little bit and to
communicate our science more widely so
that uh what we
do it has has a wider impact and uh
influences legislation which in turn
will lead to changes in who has access
what gets paid for and and then who is
repres
ultimately absolutely I feel like it's a
cycle that we all need to kind of play a
role in especially as scientists
understanding the data on the
communication angle um you know science
communication to marginalized groups is
very important so on that
topic beyond the analytical work that
your group is doing you mentioned vested
interest in the science communication
piece what is your lab doing and Beyond
the scope of the analyses to try to sort
of bring everybody along and make sure
that people don't feel like guinea pigs
when it comes to such a massive kind of
life or death kind of decision as what
kind of treatment you get yeah
admittedly um I don't know that we have
formal things we're doing as a lab and
as the lab head that falls directly on
me I
am a shy
person believe it or not so I'm like as
soon as these lights go off I'd like to
run out that door um it's it's hard and
um I've been thinking of uh getting
maybe more formal
training uh or actually yeah seeking out
maybe more formal training and building
even just a five minute Spiel a one
minute Spiel that I can use to to to to
to communicate these things um I would
like to be better at social media I've
reached out to our social media
department and they have every
institution has resources right where um
our our Communications team have
professionals you know we we we are
professionals at this we have
professionals at that who can actually
help you you can meet with them explain
what you do and they can help you create
packages um I have a younger sister who
is much more facile at technology than I
am and she schedules her social media
posts and stuff I was like oh looking
over her shoulder like oh could you
could you help me do that cuz the other
thing I'll say is oh I don't have time
and then she's like well you could
schedule the post I was like oh is that
a thing okay so um I think yeah bringing
more intentionality to it is is
definitely something do that point I
mean also to your credit this is
something that you want to do but as
with many folks in this room I'm sure we
don't have time for all the things that
we would necessarily like to do and
there are Communications experts and
their advocacy groups and playing a role
at liasing between these communication
experts and advocacy groups seems like
something we might consider as
scientists who deeply understand the
data and deeply understand some of these
bases of disparities um is that
something you might consider in the
future for sure
awesome um I wanted to come back to this
idea of the environment so it's you know
such a big topic right we're all very
curious and excited about the
environment and and I'm coming sort of
from like a bit of a gwos perspective
where like we're
doing massive genomic studies all the
time um but to the points on some of
your slides some of these types of omix
data don't require hundreds of thousands
of people to be particularly meaningful
to patients so I'm curious about um some
of the like cancer risk projects that
you're contemplating and that you're
working on and particularly in low and
middle inome countries where scaling
multiomic data maybe a particular
challenge um what are you thinking about
the utility of some of these omix data
to play a role in both understanding the
like molecular profiling nature of
cancer but also to potentially Bridge a
gap with our understanding of the
environment and social determinance of
health and maybe trying to build some
causal models that can we can use as a
framework to try to understand how these
different pieces all kind of fit
together
excuse me I'll um I'll give you a sec to
to think about that and just get some
water but
um for example we're helping build
biomarkers from proteomic data on the
basis of smoking which is obviously a
big risk factor for lung cancer for
example are you thinking about these
kinds of things where are you excited
about the field going on the cancer
disparities
topic sorry yes you're
good no this is an exciting uh the
exciting Point set of point to bring out
especially on the issue of scale right
because we can't all be part of these
large consortia that have a billion
dollars to do 20,000 samples right and I
think this goes back a little bit to
what I was saying about practicality
like what can we do today we all have a
collaborator who has some number of
samples and so the question is what can
we do with what we have right now and
how can that help and and I really like
this example you gave about smoking
right um I think the other ohms like
expression proteome metabolome uh
potentially have informative information
there that uh really gets at biomarkers
really gets at uh doing something
getting to a place where you could
design a low cost test or screening
diagnostic uh very quickly
uh and so things like that are very
exciting I did my PhD in DNA methylation
based subtyping in cancer and DNA
methylation will always be my first love
and I've been doing a lot of thinking
lately about um reading a lot too about
uh the epig genome as a mechanism of
embedding of environmental exposures and
thinking a lot too about genetic
regulation of DNA methylation and so
tring ulating across those um some
there's some thought been given by other
people of building metalation risk
scores as indicators of the general
environmental
exposure uh signature as well so sort of
a fingerprint of where you've been and
how it's been going so there's lots of
little areas like that that you could
probably get started pretty
quickly one thing too I like about the
EP genome is that you're using DNA and
um with all Logistics and
fixation uh that has you know the
potential to stay a bit more stable over
time and across conditions which might
be a challenge in some type of
environment so there's there are some
room there uh for exciting developments
definitely and one of the areas that you
were talking about was an endometrial
cancer this sort of explosion and
prevalence that we might expect during
the um next few decades and I'm
wondering if there is a good
understanding of what the exposures are
that are potentially going to lead to
that explosion and whether there are
some omix data that might help um tag
those because that's an interesting and
exciting area I think the biggest risk
factor that people the biggest um driver
of that rise is uh obesity uh and other
metabolic syndrome and so just like in
general in the world everything related
or you know triangulating with the
Obesity epidemic in the world is is is
converging there um and then there is
hormonal exposures as well of of two big
things that are also potentially easy to
measure um there is potential to
intervene uh but I think it's feels
wrong to sit here and say oh yeah
obesity is easy to tackle because if was
we would have gotten there already you
know yeah similarly on the hormonal side
I'm sure there are some hormone blockers
but I'm sure also that impacts a whole
system not just a single component of
your risk I think one of the challenges
in endometrial cancer that it's
relatively understudied right and so
what we thought for example uh there was
like type one type two this one is
homono driven this one is not it turns
out that it's not quite that's
simplified or that uh one or the other
and there of course it's always a
Continuum uh and so just having more
directed attention and more rigorous
study will will will be important
awesome well I'm looking forward to
seeing your role in that um kind of the
general question again zooming out that
we were kind of discussing is where do
you start with your research you're
exploring such a massive space and what
what determines which questions you want
to be really going after for example
some genes have known cancer drivers
associated with them do you start by
looking at those drivers and in those
specific cancers or do you take kind of
an unbiased approach and if so
how maybe that's a tough question it's
it is a pretty tough question um it
depends it depends on the project it
depends on the focus and so um when I
started my lab I think it also depends
where you are in your career right so
some projects are longer term investment
right so you start you you want to take
an unbiased approach and you plan the
study well and it takes how long it
takes right and uh some projects are
student driven and they have to graduate
in two years so you design a project
where you've um got a a fair idea of
where it's going and the it's an interim
objective to the longer term objective
so you're more focused you want you have
a specific hypothesis about a particular
pathway and that project is constrained
to that pathway so then um uh then that
that's what determines whether you focus
on specific genes or specific
Pathways
um you so I'm I'm looking at the
presenter screen it's still showing my
mentor and one thing he always used to
say was um let the science lead you so I
think I I should stop
talking that sounds like wise advice for
all of us
yeah
um I want to turn to sort of a question
that's kind of near and dear to my
research and our shared interests which
is um the topic of ancestry so you I
think gave like a really nice outline of
the delineations between race ethnicity
and ancestry so I just wanted to start
with when researchers are studying
cancer disparities whether that be in
incidents or
mortality do they use just to reiterate
ancestry or self-identified race or
ethnicity I would say they use
self-identified race or
ethnicity particularly if it's
epidemiological data uh because of how
that data was collected
historically uh so for example the
surveillance database that's maintained
by the National Cancer Institute
um the surveillance database that
maintains that data collects that data
uh using self-identified race um
self-identified rcio ethnicity yeah and
I guess that's something that you can
easily get from a cancer patient walking
in the door without a whole genome
sequence or without genetic data already
generated so when you're doing cancer
genomic
analysis are you
using ancestry or using race or using
ethnicity or some combination of
these I would say in looking at it from
An ancestry perspective is fairly
new
um I
think I'm trying to remember when I
start when I first started seeing papers
looking at it from their perspective but
I think for a long time in cancer
genomics we looked at the cohort as you
know this cohort as this tumor type and
these mutations and didn't consider
necessarily racial
ethnicity
[Music]
um yeah and then um for a long time then
when people who studied disparities
would compare mutations they would
compare the rate of mutations between
groups defined by self-identified race
or
ethnicity then people started asking
what's why would you what is the
rationale of for expecting
differences from groups that are defined
by self identity self-identification so
then it's like oh right if it's a social
construct can you expect that you'd see
differences in mutation then if you see
differences in mutation by those groups
that are defined by socially defined
variables is it that is it the social
definition or what's genetically similar
between those two be those two groups so
that's I think how sort of it converged
to oh maybe we should Define the groups
by genetic ancestry then if we see
differences then we can we can know that
these differences are genetically D
driven right I guess you have like a bit
of a chicken and egg kind of problem
when you're trying to understand and
tease apart these disparities because if
you're doing a germline genetic study
differences in a Le frequency that
you're identifying you want to make sure
that you're controlling for ancestry
however if you're then looking at driver
mutation differences maybe that differs
as a consequence of a whole lived
experience and maybe that's a little bit
more social so at some level I see
utility and having both of these when
trying to understand and study
disparities as they relate to the genome
whether it be germ lineer somatic in
this context oh yeah I don't know if we
have the kind of time to delve into it
but I've been thinking about this and
maybe you're the right person to to to
because in a g was right you add all
your ad mixture coefficients rate to
control for the effect of
ancestry um to find Snips linked to your
trait but what if your trait is
inherently ancestry it or okay h no your
trait is the disease but you can so you
can take two approaches right you can do
the GS in each group independently but
then you're losing power because you
don't have that many samples from the
non-european ancestry group yeah there's
there's a lot to do the part yeah that's
a tricky one when you so for the gws you
want to make sure that you're accounting
for ancestry to ensure that you know any
IL like effect on the disease is larger
in say cases compared to controls versus
background
expectation but then when you're getting
to what what's what is the driver of
some of these cancer differences and
you're bringing in all of these social
and environmental contributions
structural racism Access to Health Care
obesity hormonal regulation all of or
hormone
exposures there's so much there that can
also influence does someone get cancer
in the first place so bringing these two
things together both of them are
impacting The genome in some way right
so I've seen so some strategies people
started to employ for example but it
it's also circular so let me put it this
way you can say for example use a PRS to
control for the genetic effect right if
you have a PRS that works well across
all groups defined by ancestry you can
add that to your model to ask given that
you have this genetic background do
these social effects have play a role in
contributing to the
disease that's that's makes a lot of
sense one approach uh in endometrial
cancer there's been one very big
G um I I I'm unsure where's the camera I
am unsure whether that PRS Works equally
well across all
groups well I think you and I could talk
about this topic all day um but to
broaden the conversation so other folks
in the room I know will be also really
interested I want to also talk a little
bit bit about the all of us uh work that
you're doing particularly because that's
such an amazing biobank that's us-wide
and it also is intended to boost
representation from traditionally
underrepresented groups in biomedical
research um so how much information is
encoded in all of us that is useful for
us to dig into trying to understand some
of the root causes of cancer disparities
I think as designed uh all of us is one
of those unique resources that is
optimally designed to help us to tease
apart some of the questions we have
about disparities uh in general about
diseases in general uh for cancer it's
it works well it has one small drawback
in that there we don't have too much
genome sequencing but we do have
germline sequencing data there and then
we have all the social and some
environmental data and then we have all
the clinical data from that you can
extract from emrs and wonder if there
are going to be future researchers that
are like this is a gap we need to fill
we're going to go sequence those tumors
too right I'm I'm I'm not sure in the
road map if the tumor samples were
collected but that would if that was
there then it would be it would be yeah
gold mine I would certainly sign up for
ex
definitely um what else in the all of us
sort of data would be amazing to have
when I know for example from working
with biobanks that cancer registry
information can be a little limited
including with things like stage and
histology and that sort of thing yeah
definitely I think for for cancer
utility having more of the pathology
type information would be ideal so
having more uh his uh pathology
confirmed histology staging and then an
easier way to get Survival and update on
Survival outcomes would be like icing on
the cake nice so good to have but you've
got a starting point already right great
um kind of on that topic since all of us
has whole genome sequencing data what
information can you learn about
someone's likelihood of having cancer
what type of cancer they might have from
their whole genome sequencing data
germine data alone and then relatedly
what other pieces of information would
be really valuable to have from if if
you just had the home whole genome data
alone uh you could not determine whether
a person had cancer or not but you could
determine the risk of having cancer uh
based on uh triangulating the whole
genome data with uh known with databases
with known pathogenic germline variants
especially those in highly
penetrant uh uh germline uh cancer
predisposition genes uh so for example
again I'm just going to use endometrial
cancer today I do know about other
cancer types um we have cancer
predisposition syndromes like uh um the
Lynch syndrome which um predisposes you
to endometrial and colon cancer so you
have a defined set of genes that you
know pathogenic varant and these genes
leads to high uh likelihood of getting
endometrial colon cancer um we can also
uh again estimate the likelihood of
developing that that Tuma type using a
PRS a a polyenic risk score for that uh
for that for different cancer types um
um we can um what else can we do oh we
can look at the structural variation
data that would be very um very
important to look at it at sort of large
scale uh duplication or uh structural
alterations in the genome though those
would be very very telling and
predictive but the I think the power the
ultimate power of all of us comes from
having multiple streams of different
types of data to to to to to work with
and also um this series is sort of co-
co-run by the equity and biom Medicine
series and also is being you know set up
by women at Broad and so I want to turn
a little bit to some Career Development
question because of course you're
running a lab you're working on cancer
disparities your career trajectory seems
like one that's fairly inspirational so
can you tell us a little bit about the
lab that you've built and what you look
for in a team and any sort of career
advice that you can lend to folks in the
room right um so I've had my lab for uh
two years 8 months 4 days three
hours two yeah two and a half years give
or take um and um it's it's I love it I
I really love it I love my group um uh I
think there are many things that one
could do with the PhD this is one of
them
um I love uh I I I love the work we do
it's hard sometimes it's fun sometimes
it's a lot of things um and so uh I come
from a background of team sports so when
I was building my team I really thought
about how uh a lot about those
principles of how everyone on the team
team we're all working to one goal we
want to win uh whatever you know how you
define win publish the papers eradicate
cancer um um Advance our careers
individually and collectively uh but not
everyone uh is is is the same because if
we're all the same like let's take for
example a basketball team if we were all
tall then nobody could shoot or if if we
were all dribbling the ball up then
nobody could get the rebound so it's you
know it's really been so far the first
few people who've joined the team they
are not all the exact same phenotype and
so I think there's been strength in
numbers in that way and that we don't
have a single person who can do we don't
have any single copy of the same
person that makes a lot of sense um I
guess building on that
you know what advice do you have for
trainees who are going out and are
thinking about what their next steps are
be that from a postback position or
having done their PHD what comes next
that was at least personally like a
pretty existential kind of moment of
self-reflection and it was really
challenging and so I'm wondering how you
came to your position how challenging it
was to get to your position and do you
have advice for those that might be
thinking about what their next steps are
in indeed it was I identify with that as
well it was extremely challenging and uh
it took a pandemic uh to bring the level
of the self-examination that determined
my course um so the first piece of
advice I always give is to spend a
significant amount of time in
self-reflection to decide what makes
sense for you there's a lot of advice
that's going to be handed out to you
about what makes sense to other people
what they would do uh what feels good
for them what's right for their life
which might not be right for your life
the second thing is to talk to people so
having the right team of mentors not one
person you could have a primary Mentor a
secondary Mentor but talk to as many
people as possible you can have one
question that you ask the say everyone
that you talk to and different questions
you ask to different people to try and
get sort of a 360 Dee perspective on the
issue um and then I think there's some
level of serendipity to what happens as
well where you are and um and then there
is um just some encouragement for
somebody who's out there who's in this
place because there was a time where I
would say I was really like I don't know
where I'm going I don't know where this
is going to be and now I guess 3 years
down the road I'm sitting on the stage
I'm apparently giving an expert talk I
got a grant from the
ni and so if you had asked me these
questions three years ago I might not
have been as perky about it because I
was in a place where I thought I'm not
sure this next step is exactly where
this is going so I just want to
encourage other people that at that
moment it might not feel like things are
going to turn out but just keep
persevering you might just be in that
last last dark space just before things
turn bright
and so I just want to yeah encourage
somebody out there today great on the
optimistic note of perseverance I think
we're at
time inly that great uh so thank you so
much for such an Illuminating wonderful
conversation it's been such a wonderful
opportunity to meet you I really
appreciate
[Applause]
it for