With school back in session here at MIT,
some of the brightest minds in the world
are here starting their school year
aiming for their degrees in arguably the
most competitive academic environment in
America, if not the world at large.
These are some serious high achievers in
and out of the classroom we're talking
about here. Amongst the prospective
engineers, scientists, and
mathematicians on this campus with a
high achievement mindset includes grad
student Abby Lee from Canada. Lee,
always a high energy, high determination
kid for as long as memory serves, is
currently pursuing her master's degree
here on campus in the aerospace
engineering department. An athlete
throughout her high school and
undergraduate years, Lee had taken to
endurance sports. Currently a member of
the triathlon club here on campus, Lee
has set her sights on competing on more
triathlons.
So, when I got here, it was kind of like
that fresh start. What do I want to do?
What have I been missing in undergrad?
and I noticed that MIT has a triathlon
club and I loved the Olympic triathon I
did probably about six years ago now and
so I said okay let's join the triathlon
club and see where it takes me and I'd
known what an iron man was pretty much
my whole life um there was someone from
my undergrad who had set a world record
as well in Iron Man's and so it was kind
of in the back of my mind that it was
this really hard thing to do um maybe I
should start with a marathon that was
also going in my brain um but more and
more I talked about it with some of my
friends as a joke like hey What if I
just like tried to do this? Um, trained
a bit more with the club and kind of
dove straight into, you know, the life
of a triathlete.
>> If studying and experimenting her way
towards her master's degree in literal
out of thisworld work wasn't enough,
there's one more place that the name
Abby Lee may very well land. The
Guinness Book of World Records. Her goal
to become one of the first and the
youngest woman to compete in an Iron Man
triathlon on all six inhabited
continents. Iron Man triathlons are some
of the hardest in the world.
>> I think I try and ignore as much of the
outside world as I can. You know, I've
trained as much as I can. You know, like
maybe I could have trained more in one
or two sessions, but that's I can't go
back in time. I've already done that.
We're already at the start line. So, I
try and just think like, okay, what do I
need to focus on now uh in this race to
get me to that finish line? Keeping my
heart rate down, you know, enjoying the
scenery. I've gotten to travel the world
through, you know, this this world
record attempt. And so I kind of get to
see Spain and see Brazil and all of
these places I've never seen before. So
trying to absorb that a little bit, keep
the nerves down and, you know, keep
pushing. There are some moments
throughout this journey so far that have
been really, really hard. Um, I think
I've learned a lot about what I'm
capable of and that's been eye opening
for sure and really rewarding, but also
just trying to push myself through it
because at the end of the day, this is
something I really want to do and and
I'm going to have to be the number one
person driving that.
>> Aby's determination to hit her goals and
then some has been something that has
stuck with her since childhood according
to her mother, Sharon.
>> Um, never stop Abby. I think that's a
big huge thing with Abby. If she thinks
she can do it, she's going to do it. And
that's determination from probably six,
seven years of age, nothing has stopped
her. So I think that with sport and
school, she is a high achiever. Nothing
stops her. No one stops her. Any
challenge doesn't stop.
>> Paige Forester, Aby's lab partner,
workout buddy, and close friend, says
that that drive is infectious.
>> I mean, honestly, it's been like so
inspiring. I feel like Abby is like one
of, you know, your friends, like they're
supposed to be your peers, but I think
it's really important that you look up
to them and like Abby is somebody that I
just admire so much. Um, like at the end
of the day, like when you really think
about what she's doing, it's amazing.
Um, but like dayto-day, like getting to
work out with her, she's probably my
favorite person to work out with because
she's crazy and she'll do anything that
I ask her to. Um, like if I propose a
150 mi ride, she's like, "Yeah, let's do
it. Like, let's go right now." Um, but
actually like more importantly than
that, I think Abby is like one of the
few people I know that is super humble.
So if she's like the best at something,
if she's not the best at something,
she's always like open about that and
that will actually talk about it. And I
really appreciate that because I never
feel with her like there's any
competition between us. Like I just love
to work out with her because um we're
just like proud of each other. So like
when we are in the pool or we're on the
bike like we're just hyping each other
up the whole time. And that's actually
true. like I I don't I don't find that
with um people. I feel like Aby's just
really unique in that sense. So, she's I
love working out with her. She's
awesome.
>> With this global goal, she is halfway
home. Three down, three to go. So far,
Lee has taken to the Iron Man course in
South Africa back in March of 2025,
Brazil in June of 2025, and Spain the
following month. The European leg was an
especially difficult race for her as
fatigue and a possible stomach bug
started to set in.
And so that race, hardest day of my
life. Um, and I was grinding from
kilometer 25 onwards to finish that
race. So to put that in perspective, my
body was begging me for a nap. And I
still had to tell it, you have 155 more
kilometers on the bike and then you have
to go run a marathon and you have to
meet these cut off times or you this
won't be a certified race. So it was a
lot of just mentally pushing myself,
reminding myself that today is
temporary. um you know, if I can just
get to this finish line, I don't have to
be back in Spain again. I don't have to
do that European race again. Um it was
really rewarding to cross the finish
line, but toughest moment of my life for
sure.
>> So, what's next for Abby Lee? Three more
Iron Man triathlons on the docket,
including one in October of 2025, the
Iron Man World Championships in Kona,
Hawaii. Before she heads west, she needs
a big piece of the triathlon puzzle, a
triathlon bike. My biggest barrier right
now actually is I don't have a bike.
So, I flew to Brazil with a used bike,
but it was about a $1,200 triathlon
bike. I was super super excited to get
to use it and it arrived broken. Um, and
that was a killer. In Brazil, I had
scrambled to get there. There was some
travel hiccups and I opened the box and
the bike was broken and I didn't know
what to do. And thankfully the
Brazilians some of the nicest people
I've ever met and four people were like,
"What size are you? We'll lend you a
bike." Like it just was such a
demonstration of how incredible this
community is. Um, and I just felt so
supportive. So, I did get to borrow a
bike and then I had to rent one for
Spain, but I don't currently have a bike
to train on. I'm a grad student, so I'm
trying my best to accomplish this all
off of my siphon, which is not super
forgiving. Um, definitely great, but not
not maybe where I need it to be for
this. So, trying to budget for that
bike, but I I don't have something to
train on now. Maybe I'll rent for Kona.
Um, but that's the biggest hiccup for
me. Trying to get onto a TT like
triathlon bike before that race and and
get the feel for it, maybe get it fit
for me is huge.
>> For Abby Lee, a student, an engineer,
and a triathlete, the sky or really
anything certainly isn't the limit.
>> Was it a scary watch? Was it scary
watching it for three of them already?
Yes. and Spain was not fun to have to
hear what she had to go through. But I
think when she came through the other
end of that and said nothing in her life
will be that hard, I truly believe it.
Mind over matter is what got Abby
through it and that'll get her through
that. Once she steps foot onto the
starting line, the time for training is
over and it's all about the race at hand
for Abby Lee. With three more Iron Man
triathlons to go, the path will not be
easy. But with the support of the
friends, family, and classmates cheering
her on near and far, success has already
been achieved.
>> So, of course, I would like to say the
MIT community has already done so much.
I think just surrounding myself with so
many brilliant and like-minded
individuals has been huge. Just the MIT
tri club, my friends, my labmates are
some of the most driven people I've ever
met, and it's infectious. And that's
been really great to see. In terms of
the the community itself, if anyone
knows, you know, great resources for
Iron Man, places to to find that
equipment, places to find the fuel that
I'll need for those races, and anyone
who's open to make partnerships, like
that's definitely something I'm looking
towards. And just trying to have fun
with it and seeing who I can inspire
along the way. You know, I always hear
from people, "Oh my gosh, you did an
Iron Man. That's incredible. I'd never
be able to do that. I don't run." But I
didn't run either. I didn't bike. My
first road bike ever I bought in
September from the MIT police auction
cuz I couldn't afford anything else. And
so I'm hoping to show people it's maybe
not about being the best at what you're
doing, but just trying just getting out
there. And so, you know, if the MIT
community has anyone who's looking for
for some inspiration on getting started
and just really trying your best and
setting lofty goals and not being afraid
to fail, I'd say like come chat with me.
I'd love to help. If you would like to
help Abby in her Iron Man triathlon
journey, visit her website for more
details. You can also follow her
progress towards the Guinness Book of
World Records on her Instagram as well.
[Music]