uh so the new topic we'll focus on today
is uncertainty and how you make
decisions under
uncertainty now the reason it's sort of
embarrassing we've taken this long to
get to it is most decisions in life are
made under uncertainty so consider for
example your decision to study for the
Final in this
course if you knew exactly which
proportion of the final com would come
from which lecture you could study them
in those proportions or figure out what
you knew best and not and you'd have a
clear studying plan but you don't know
that I do but you don't so basically
you've got to figure out in an uncertain
world where you're not sure what's going
to be on the final how should you
allocate your time to
study okay that is a decision under
uncertainty
if the forecast had a 50% chance of rain
today you have to decide whether to
carry an umbrella you know the benefit
is your you're protective it's wet the
disadvantage is you might lose it and
it's a pain to carry it around that's a
decision under
uncertainty as you grow up uncertainties
multiply and multiply whether to buy a
house or rent whether to get health
insurance what kind of life insurance to
buy everything becomes larger and more
uncertain As you move into adult life
and so we need if we're going to have a
realistic model of people making
decisions we need a model that allows
for decision- making under
uncertainty and that's what we'll spend
today's lecture on now once again while
this is late in the course and we're
compartmentalizing you'll be able to see
how you can take this model and incord
it into the other things we're
doing okay indeed one thing we strive
for in the final is to get you to apply
Concepts across different lectures so a
lot of things we'll talk about making
under certainty will immediately tie
back to some of the things we learned in
consumer Theory you should be able to
see how those things fit
together okay so to understand this
let's start by me offering you a bet
okay and the bet I'm going to offer you
is
heads you get
$125 tails you pay me
$100 okay that's the bet now without
thinking what the Professor wants to
hear just gut instinct how many of you
take that
bet okay so that's about the proportion
I always get that's about maybe 20% of
the class takes the bet so let's think
about that decision about whether to
take the bet or not well a natural place
to start is to compute the BET's
expected value expected value is simply
the probability that you win
times the payout so the probability win
times the
value if you
win plus the probability that you
lose times the
value if you lose well for this bet the
expected
value is 50% I mean I I guess I should
have specified I'm an honest guy it's
unweighted coin but I presume you guys
assume that 50% times winning
$125 plus
50% times losing $100 or an expected
value of$
12250 it's a positive expected value bet
or what we call in economics a more than
fair bet a fair bet is one with an
expected value of zero this is a more
than fair bet
okay so the defition of fair bet is zero
expected value so this bet by definition
is a more than fair bet but when I
offered you this bet most of you didn't
want to take it now I don't think it's
that you can't do this math in your head
I think it's that you're
human okay and
humans have a feature of their decision-
making that we call risk
aversion risk
aversion risk verion means that
individuals value each dollar of winning
less than they devalue each dollar of
losing they're made less Happy by each
dollar of winning than they than they're
made sad by each dollar of losing and
the reason is actually pretty clear when
we go back to Consumer Theory and to do
this we're going to turn to a new tool
which is going to be expected utility
Theory so a new tool which is expected
utility Theory
the way I expect utility the is going to
work is we're going to rewrite this
equation but not in terms of dollar
values but rather in terms of what
matters which is utility utility is not
about dollars it's about utility so how
do we rewrite this expect utility Well
we'd say look the expected utility of a
gamble is a probability that you
win times your utility if you
win plus the probability that you lose
times your utility if you
lose now if utility functions were
linear I hope you can see this would be
the same as expected
value if utility function was a linear F
proper linear function of your money so
give expected value but in fact utility
functions aren't linear we typically
consider utility functions being concave
that is we typically assume diminishing
marginal product of consumption
okay we typically assume uh or
diminishing Marge utility of consumption
or diminishing marginal rates of
substitution going back to Consumer
Theory okay and the what that yields
naturally without any new math is risk
aversion someone who has a concave
utility or diminishing margin utility of
consumption will naturally be risk
averse why is that well
intuitively it's because if you're if
you have a concave utility function each
additional dollar makes you less happy
than losing a dollar makes you
sad okay and that yields naturally risk
aversion so let's go through Let's do an
example let's use our typical utility
function form which utility is square
root of consumption a one argument
utility function make life super easy
all you care about consumption utility
square of consumption okay and let's say
that c0 is 100 so u0 equals 10 you start
with
100 and you end up with 10 now let's
calculate the expected utility of the
gamble I offered you the expected
utility of the have few would be a 50%
chance
that you win well if you
win someone raise their hand and tell me
what's your utility if you
win yeah 15 how'd you get
that you you want 100 you want you
started with 100 you want 125 so it's a
square root of
225 or 15 that's exactly
right what is your utility
if what is your utility if you
lose what is your utility if you lose
yeah zero it's 0.5 times the square root
of zero you started with 100 you lose
100 so it's half of 15 plus 0o or
7.5 so you expect utility is lower you
started with 10 it fell to 7.5
I offered you a more than fair bet and
you didn't take
it simply because youve diminishing
margin utility of consumption I'll come
back to why some people might have taken
it but the reason most people don't take
that bet is simply because the property
that we all derived as natural feature
of utility back in lecture two which is
diminishing Marge utility of consumption
okay I find a great way to see this as
graphical so let's go to figure 20-1
which I find a little confusing but
ultimately helpful so let's take our
time on this figure 21 is a different
figure we've ever seen before on the
xaxis your wealth or your consumption in
this case you sort of consume your
wealth okay on the y- axis we're just
graphing your udal okay once again we
don't care about the level of oodles we
only care about the relationships
between different decisions and how they
affect your
oodles okay so for example you IM you
originally start at Point a
you have
$100 that translates to utility of 10 10
util now I've given you a choice between
a gamble with a 50% chance at ending up
at zero and a 50% chance of ending up at
point
B well if you value that you just say
well a 50% chance of each means that I
end up at Point c i take 50% of point a
I say 50% of zero 50% of point B and at
Point C which is below point
a because of the concavity utility
function because by going up towards 225
it gets
flatter so I don't get nearly as much
but when I go down towards zero it gets
steeper so I'm really sad about losing
Zero sucks 225 is good but like is it
you know that's great but I'm not nearly
as happy when know 125 I say I'm having
nothing to eat this
week so because of of the concavity
utility
function okay you don't want a bet even
though it's more than fair even though
it's a bet that's more than fair you
still don't want
it once again no new assumptions here no
new
math this is just using the property of
diminishing Marg utility of consumption
questions about
that okay what if utility function a
different form what if utility function
instead of the form of um utility of
square root of C what if utility
function of the form
um uh actually no let me let me let me
cover something else first so what you
see like I said you're better off at
Point a than Point C that's why I choose
not to take the gamble indeed here's a
fascinating fact you would imagine I
came to you and I said look I'm your
boss you're going to take this gamble
unless you pay me not to so change the
framing I say to you're going to take
this G gble unless you pay me not to
someone can anyone in do the math and
tell me how much they'd be willing to
pay me with this utility function not to
take this
gamble can everyone figure out how much
they be willing to pay me not to take
this
gamble well
yeah what's
that uh no not quite but let
let's keep going think about it so let
let's work out the math of this okay you
basically are saying you're I'm asking
you what payment to me plus the gamble
leaves you back at this original
point so if you take the gamble that's
as if your consumption if you take that
gamble if you look at the answers here
on the graph you look at Point C and go
to the
left that gamble leaves you at the same
level of Happiness as having
$56.25
yeah exactly that gamble leaves you at
the same level of half 56 so therefore
you're willing to pay
$43.75 to avoid that
gamble because by paying that you end up
by paying that by by because if you pay
me because if if if you pay me $43.75
and take the gamble it leaves you in
different not taking the gamble can
people see that think about that for a
second it's
stunning I've offered you a more than
fair
Gamble and yet you're willing to pay me
almost half your wealth to get out of
it it's pretty amazing right that is the
power of concavity of utility functions
you are so sad at
zero the you'll give up half your wealth
to avoid a 50% chance of ending up
there okay
another way to see this how much would
the winning payoff have to be to get you
to take the
gamble someone tell me that how much
would the win if lose 100 win X how big
is X before you take the
gamble
yeah four how' you get
400 trying to get to you're trying to
have your um utility be 10 before and
after so if it's half of four the square
of 400 is 20 and then half 20 is 10 so
then if you have add that the um
expected value that's going to remain is
10 uh that's exactly like one wrinkle
it's 300 not 400 why because you start
with 100 oh yeah so you're right you
want 400 in that square root but but you
don't uh but but you start with 100 okay
so the point is so another way to think
of this is literally this is how crazy
you bet I have to offer you to take it
literally tails you lose a 100 heads you
in
300 okay so that is a really
massive Fair bet I have to give you to
take it and that's the key lesson in
this lecture everything we talk about in
this lecture and next lecture is all
driven by one simple thing it sucks to
go to zero okay and the closer you get
to zero that is an enormous make you
enormously sadder than getting above
where you are today makes you
happier and I don't think that's
unreasonable okay as a way to think
about the
world okay now let's do some extensions
and applications of this model before we
get to through some extensions and
applications to talk about why this
model can
explain lots of things in the world why
adding this wrinkle essentially remember
what I said about modeling the first
first lecture we start with the simplest
possible model and then add wrinkles to
allow to explain more things here's a
wrinkle this making our modeling
harder okay but it's can explain a lot
more things by doing so so for example
let's change this to instead of utility
me square root of C let's say utility is
0.1 time
C that's
utility so once again you start with C
0al
100 u0 equals
10 but now if I offer you that gamble do
you take it what's your expecting
utility well there's a 50% chance you
win times uh 0.1 *
225 and the 15 CH you lose 0.5 * 0.1
Time
Zero what is that
it's 12 and a half it's I'm sorry it's
not 12 and a half it's uh if you do that
it's 11 and a
quarter so this
equals which is greater than 10 so you
do take the
BET why do you take the bet in this case
and not in the previous
case
yeah exactly it's linear so all you care
about expected value the expected value
is positive you're
done
okay now what if we had a different
utility
function what if we had a utility
function and we see that in figure 20-2
I'm sorry this shows we call this risk
neutrality so you're no longer risk
averse with linear functions you are
risk neutral you just do expected value
you don't care about the risk just
taking expected value and that's shown
here that basically look I start at 10
this bet leaves me at Point C which
11.25 so I'm better off so with concave
functions you get risk
aversion and unwilling to take Fair
Bets with risk
neutrality with with I'm sorry with
linear utility you get risk neutrality
and sort of an indifference towards risk
but of course there's also a third case
which is what if your utility function
was of the form um what if utility
function was of the form
uh uh oh yeah what if function was the
form utility equals
c^2
over uh utility equals c^2 over
1000 utility equals c s over a 100000 I
chose this particular function because
once again c0 = 100
u = 10 that's why I chose that function
same starting point it makes it easier
to start from the same point but now
let's ask what happens with this
function what's the expect utility the
gamble the expect utility
0.5 time um uh 0.5 times if you win
that's 225 sared over a
100000 plus 0.5 times if you lose which
is zero
what is the value of that it's
25.3 you are really happy to take this
gamble you've increased utility why
figure 20-3 utility is now
convex this is what we call a risk
loving individual they're no longer risk
averse not even risk neutral they're
risk-loving they are made happier by
taking risk that yields a convex utility
function okay in in that case you are
much better off at Point C than point a
because in this case it's you don't have
diminishing marity consumption you have
increasing Marge utility of consumption
so going getting a dollar richer makes
you happier than getting a dollar poor
makes you
sad now this is really uh unreasonable
as a description of people in general
but it's not unreasonable description of
some people in some places maybe
risk-loving and if you're risk-loving
you will take an unfair Gamble
in this case imagine I said heads you
win 75 tails you lose
100 that is an unfair bet that's a
negative expected value bet yet this
person would still take
it they would get an expect utility from
that of
15.3 they can expect you if so if I said
heads 75 you get 75 tails you pay me 100
so it's a negative expected value of 12.
yet with this utility function that
person will take that bet because it
yields an expected utility of
15.3 so if you're risk loving you'll
even take unfair
gambles indeed it goes further than that
you will pay me for the opportunity to
take an unfair
gamble risk leving implies that
literally if I'm walking along and say
well I you know I might offer you this
deal you know if you're really nice you
know you you know I might have this
unfair bet you'll pay me to take the
unfair bet because it makes you happy to
take that risk
now you prefer a fair bet obviously more
is better but you prefer an unfair bet
to not taking a
bet okay questions about
that so that's the
basics okay let me do one more
extension which is very interesting let
me ask another question once again gut
reaction just give me the answer your
gut let's say that I changed the example
which is if you win you get
$12.50 if you lose you pay me $10 how
many people take that
bet okay this always happens too now
you're all being a little inconsistent
because many more of you should take
that bet why is
that why
yeah it's what it's worth less money
it's the same divided by 10 but why it's
being worth less money make you more
want to take it as a risk averse
individual
[Music]
last1 exactly think about this concave
utility function back in figure
20-1 think about what happens as you
shrink the gamble to shrink the gamble
towards the initial
Point what happens the function becomes
locally
linear so in fact the smaller the gamble
the less concave effectively is your
decision- making and once you're linear
you only care about expected value so
indeed in the what I just said if I just
did that gamble I gave you guys and put
it on our original risk averse utility
function the expect utility of that
gamble was 0.5 times the square root of
um the square root of
uh uh
11250 plus 0.5
* theun of 100us 10 or
90 and if you add that you actually get
10.05 Which is higher than your initial
expect
utility this is very
important what matters is not the size
of the
gamble what matters is the size of the
gamble relative to your
resources risk aversion is
relative okay what matters is not the
size of the gamble stand of the gamble
Rel to your resources Bill Gates and you
feel differently about a $100
gamble okay so basically and that's
because as the gamble gets small Rel to
your initial wealth utility function
becomes locally linear and you become
risk
neutral it's a very very important
Insight you should be able to see this
actually I can tell you a couple things
you should be able see the same
Insight uh answers a um a couple of
other a couple of other
questions what so what this says is as
the gamble get basically the bottom line
is as the gamble gets small or as your
initial wealth gets bigger you become
more risk-neutral that's the key lesson
okay any questions about
that
yeah uh because we never care about the
only care about comparing decisions note
I always said well it's 10.05 bigger
than 10 that's all I care about I never
said anything about interpreting
10.05 I just said is it bigger than 10
or smaller than 10 the key thing is we
always compare cardinal values but it's
only the relative implication that
matters what is comparing values when
you calculate utility calculate a value
it's just that value in a vacuum is
meaningless it's only meaningful
relative to an alternative Choice with a
different utility value and that's how
you Val them does that make sense
ah excellent point that is that's a
great Point expect utility theory is
making a particular assumption about how
we combine utility different
states you could imagine in fact when
you get to higher order Theory it's a
great question there's other kinds of
models people use for expect utility
that don't make this simple linear
combination assumption and you talked
about one reason that assumption may not
be great it's in approximations because
it sub that we're combining Cardinal
things we it's a cardinal sin we're
combining things that we said we really
shouldn't be combining that's a great
point it works very well in 99% of cases
but there are cases where you get um uh
Pro paradoxes with this model and to
explain them you need more complicated
models great Point other questions okay
now let's go on and talk about a couple
of applications let's start by talking
about
insurance okay insurance is big business
in the US US consumers spend about 10%
of GDP or over two trillion dollars a
year on
insurance health
insurance life
insurance accident
insurance insurance against fire or
theft Etc Auto Insurance
insurance is Big Business and it's
literally 10% of our GDP is Insurance
why do they do this I mean that's a huge
amount of money for this product more
than many many other sectors in the
economy why is that true well to
understand that let's go through an
example suppose that you're a 25y old
and I'll explain why in a second why I'm
being gendered in a second you're
25-year-old single male here in
Cambridge Okay the reason I picked male
is because basically a 25y old single
malale is Invincible the only risk to
bad health is getting hit by a car was
women can get pregnant and that's
another risk to their health so let's
pick a male who basically the only thing
that could cause medical expenditures
would be get hit by a car which
unfortunately is a real risk in
Cambridge okay so imagine that um you
have a situation where your income is
$40,000 a year that's your initial
income $40,000 a
year okay and let's say that there's a
1%
chance that you get hit by a car every
year higher than we'd like but probably
not unreasonable for Cambridge okay and
if you get hit you end up with a
hospital
bill of
$330,000 that's your hospital bill if
you get
hit so how would you evaluate and I'm
going to come along and offer you
insurance and what that insurance is
going to do is pay
the way insurance is going to work is
you're going to pay me a certain amount
no matter what happens if you get hit or
not but if you get hit I pay your
medical bill so let's be clear Insurance
you pay no matter what if you get hit or
don't get hit you pay me an insurance
premium a certain amount of money we
call that the premium so you pay me a
premium whether you get hit or not in
return if you get hit I pay your medical
bill okay well let's ask how much should
someone be willing to spend
for insurance what what is the amount
they willing to pay well imagine your
utility function is square root of C as
we've been working with square Ro of C
so your expected
utility is what happens if you do get
hit well if you do get hit there's a
0.01
chance of what that utility is a square
root of what well you still earn your
income I'm assuming you don't lose your
job you still earn your 40,000
and you still pay your insurance premium
no matter what let's call that
X but you don't have any medical bill if
I'm sorry this is if you if you don't
have insurance if you don't have
insurance and then I'm sorry if you
don't have insurance you pay 40,000
minus the 30,000 medical bill this is
the no this is the no insurance case
Okay expected utility no
insurance there's a 0.1 chance that you
end up with 40,000 inome 30,000 medical
bills there's 99%
chance that you end up with the square
root of
40,000
okay okay and that is an expect utility
of
$199 that's your expect utility if you
don't buy
insurance if you do buy
insurance expect utility yes Insurance
there's a 0.01 chance that you get your
40,000
minus the insurance premium X we're
going to come to what x is but you don't
pay your medical
bill and if you don't get hit by the car
you actually get the same thing
40,000 minus X so literally this is just
of 40,000 minus
X so now we can
ask what is the price you'd be willing
to pay for insurance
against getting hit by a car and the
answer is we answer that by setting your
expected utility equal with or without
insurance so your expected utility with
insurance is the square root of 40,000
time
x 40K minus X you expect utility without
insurance is
$199 so this is one equation one unknown
40,000 40K - x = 199 and you solve that
and you get that X =
3.99 you will pay
$399 let's be clear the reason you will
is because that's a premium that equates
your well-being in the state with or
without the
accident
okay think about that number for a
second relative to what the insurance is
worth
what's the in what's the expected value
of this
insurance what's the expected value of
the insurance you're
buying what's expected yeah $300 there's
a one there's a 1% chance that they pay
pay you
$30,000 so you are paying three you are
willing to pay
$3.99 for insurance with an expected
value of 300 why because is your risk
averse you are happy to pay more just
like you're unhappy to take a
gamble that's fair you're happy to buy
insurance that's not
fair because this is the opposite of
gambling insurance is the opposite of
gambling so just as a risk averse person
will take a gamble won't take a gamble
that's fair they're they're willing to
buy insurance even if it's unfair and we
call this extra $99
the risk premium so the extra 99 we call
the risk
premium how much are individuals willing
to pay to avoid through Insurance to
avoid bearing
risk
okay this is a striking fact and it's
consistent with the fact that insurance
is big big big business in
America it's consistent with that
because risk averse individual ual will
pay um to have
insurance now I would like you to take
do as an exercise to show yourself that
the following things are true
a as the size of the loss Rises holding
income constant the risk premium
Rises B holding the loss constant as
your income Rises the risk premium Falls
both of those things simply follow from
the intuition we've developed in
gambling basically the more you become
the more the the gamble is is irrelevant
Rel to your income the less you care and
the less you're willing to take do
unfair things like take an actual unfair
bet or Bay pay a risk
premium okay questions about
that that's it now you're right these
are making certain mathematical
assumptions but the idea that people
want to risk premium is just comes the
magn to this risk premum will depend on
what you assume about the form of the
expect utility function or the utility
function itself but the Notions as a
risk pre will always be true with risk
averse individuals
yeah complicating the model do people or
we want to talk about people um if you
like Incorporated the fact that if you
are paying for insurance that's
preventing you from buying something
else does that change how much oh no no
that's that's it that's Incorporated
it's Square to see so by definition if I
buy insurance I can't buy something else
right that's Incorporated
here okay now that's one application
let's talk about another application
let's talk about the
lottery the lottery in the United States
is a total ripoff the expected value of
a lottery ticket of every dollar you
spend on the lottery in the US is 50
Cents it's a massively unfair bet yet
it's also massively popular and a major
source of revenue for states is state
lotteries
why is that how can you have a situation
where you have um a popular unfair bet
now there's four theories for why this
is Theory
one is people are risk
loving they play the lottery because
they're risk loving how can you use
something I just talked about 37 seconds
ago disprove that theory how can you
disprove the fact that people are risk
loving
how can you say Americans are clearly
not risk loving they spend 1.5 they
spend $2 trillion on insurance they're
clearly not risk loving so that theory
goes out the
window okay the second
theory is a little more subtle which is
that people are both risk Avers and risk
loving and to see this we go to figure
we go to figure 20-4 of what what's
called fredman Savage preferences you
don't need to know that that's just what
they're
called this is our preferences to help
to explain riddles like this and here
those preferences look they're
preferences where they start concave and
then become
convex so the way this works is follow
along with me imagine as a small 5050
gamble between W1 and
W3 for that small gamble people clearly
don't want to take it they are worse off
with the gamble at point B than the
utility of B Star so the same logic
before people won't take that small
gamble now imagine a giant
gamble oh I'm sorry now imagine G from
W3 to
W5 well for that gamble they become risk
loving they're H they're more than happy
to take that gamble even though it's
5050 it's above the
utility so now imagine a Gamble from W1
to
W5 if you do a giant gamble people might
end up RIS looking risk loving so it
could be yeah they're risk averse over
small things but they love those big
gambles and that's why they play the
lottery why is that empirically
false why is an empirically false
description of the lottery because 99%
of the money made in the lottery is not
on Mega Millions it's on scratch tickets
which are you gamble for
$100 okay so people are in the range
where they're at the bottom of this
function if that theory was true we'd
see lotteries but only Mega Millions you
wouldn't see little lotteries and you
do so that's how we empirically prove
this theories and
right okay the third and fourth
theories are in subsets to flip sides of
each
other and the third theory is that this
is
entertainment and this comes to how we
go further in micrograms 1401 imagine
that I put in utility function not just
consumption but the thrill of scratching
something off the scill of the thrill of
seeing gee maybe I won money and maybe
it's worth a dollar to you just a th
chance even though you know you'll
probably lose maybe in utility function
is the thrill you get from that there's
nothing wrong or IL legitim about that
just the way you write down the utility
function so many people just gamble
because they find it entertaining and
the The Thrill is in the utility
function the problem is there's another
theory which is that people are
uninformed
or just making
mistakes which is not that they get
utility Jo from but they just don't
understand what they're doing they don't
understand what a bad deal it is or if
they do understand they just don't think
it through properly and they're making a
mistake okay now we can't really we both
these are true to some
extent why does it matter which one is
true well it matters enormously if we
think the truth is one of these it
matters enormously which one it is
primarily and why is that because it
drives what the government should
do if this is the correct view
government should support lotteries it's
a great way to make money it's what we
call voluntary taxation if people like
gambling then why let the private sector
make the money the government can make
the money by setting up a lottery so if
that's true we should be encouraging
state lotteries if this is true we
should be discouraging them the
government is sanctioning people to make
bad decisions that's not the role of a
government is not to set up more
opportunities people make bad
decisions so it terms out it matters
enormously for government policy which
of these are right matters enormously
which of these are right because
basically it depends on is this a
voluntary tax or government encourag
mistakes and we don't
know but the stakes are huge in some
low-income communities people spend I
kid you not up to 20% of income on the
lottery these are huge Stakes for many
people's lives this is a very important
question to be thinking about okay
questions about
that okay one last topic I want to cover
and this is going to be a lead into what
we're going to cover after Thanksgiving
so you have to think about this and sort
of put it in your head and Che it over
for for a week and a half okay which is
the problem of information asymmetry
information
asymmetry what do I mean by that well
let's go back to our insurance fact I
said that insurance is Big Business 10%
of
GDP you know what you know what else
amounts to about six or s% of
GDP government provided
insurance that is not only do people
spend $2 something trillion dollars on
private Insurance the government spends
almost another $2 trillion on public
Insurance well you might say wait a
second how could that make sense people
want Insurance they're buying it what's
the government doing in this
business why should there be a
government role people just buying they
want insurance they should buy it some
people risk ofers they buy it some
people aren't they don't what's the
government doing with it and the reason
is because private people buy too little
private
insurance not cuz they're not not
because they're not risk averse but
because of an information
asymmetry because some parties have
information that others do not and that
can cause a failure of insurance
markets and to see that let's go to the
best example the classic example the
example that won the Nobel Prize for
George acof which is the ex the lemons
problem acof set up the following
problem and the the lemon's problem is
basically the Insight that information
asymmetry can cause market failure
remember if markets don't fail the
government's just piss off okay
government is only useful if markets
fail okay and acrofs insight was that
information asymmetry much like Monopoly
or other things we'll talk about can
create a market failure how does it do
so let's go through a simple example uh
imagine the world of George George
Jackoff was writing in back in the 1970s
where when you bought a used car there
was no Carfax there was none of that
stuff you had no idea what had happened
to the car when you bought a used car
when I was young you were just sort of
basically taking a gamble how good was
the car okay so imagine that um so so
imagine that um uh I have a 10-year-old
car that I keep in pristine shape and
let's say that that is worth
$5,000 so the value to to John the value
of the card of John is
$5,000 okay that's what everyone says a
good car in good shape is worth and
let's say I'm going to sell to Andrew
and let's say the value of the car to
Andrew is
$6,000 for a pristine car he's will to
pay
$6,000 this is a welfare improving
transaction it makes Andrew happier than
it makes me sad I am happy to sell it at
5,000 he's happy to buy it at $6,000
there's $1,000 of consumer surplus
created by the this transaction should
happen now but imagine that Andrew also
knows that most 10-year-old cars are
crappy they're not kept in good
condition and he knows that on average
if you buy a 10-year-old car you'll have
to put in $2,000 of repairs to make it
run so Andrew doesn't know that my car
is not crappy I can tell them it's
pristine I could show them things it's
like whatever you could have got an
accident I have no idea I don't have
Carfax Carfax says what's the internet
no that exists okay he said I don't know
all I know is if I buy a 10-year-old car
my value is 6,000 minus the $2,000 I
expect to put in to fix it so I'm not
buying your
car the market has failed a transaction
that make both parties better off has
not happened why because information
asymmetry imagine now in today's world
imagine we have perfect information
about how good a car is then there's no
more information symmetry in today's
world I could show them the Carfax and
everything and say look it's pristine
they'd say great I know have to put
$2,000 in let's do
it but without that information he
doesn't do it the information asymmetry
is that I know how good the car is but
he
doesn't and the fact that different
parties of different information just by
itself can cause an entire Market to
collapse okay this is very important
this is incredibly deep Insight one of
the deepest insights in all economics
okay that basically a market where
nothing else is wrong no Monopoly
nothing else is wrong just the fact that
the buyer and seller have different
information could cause the market to
collapse here the market is just one
sale but you can expand it to Market see
how it could collapse okay and the
intuition is with perfect information
this transaction would happen without
perfect information it doesn't therefore
the information asymmetry has caused a
market failure questions about that
now let's think for a second about how
that applies to
Insurance Andrew's got his insurance
company Andrew Co I walk in I'm like hey
I'm John I want Insurance he's like why
like are you a sky dier do you engage in
Risky sexual behavior why aren't you buy
insurance through MIT or someone else
I'm worried I'm worried that there's a
problem that we're going to call adverse
selection
I'm worried that there's adverse
election that is the set of people the
people who come to me to want to buy
insurance are only the people who really
need it and I'm going to lose money if I
sell them
Insurance the information asymmetry is
on the other foot now now the buyer
knows more than the seller does in the
car example the seller knew more than
the buyer did now with insurance the
buyer knows more than the seller does
but it's the same
problem if Andrew knew that in fact I'm
a I'm a clean living non- skydiving guy
okay okay then he'd be happy to sell me
Insurance say you know let's say I come
and I say I'm willing to pay $3.99 he
says great I make $99 in
profit but since he doesn't know that
he's worried the fact of coming in means
I'm someone runs in the middle of the
street W Mars gets hit a lot so he's
going to lose money if he gets gives me
Insurance therefore he won't insure me
even
though societyd be better off he'd be if
he had full information' be happy to
insure me because it partial information
he won't that's a market failure the
reason government provides insurance is
because that market failure leads to
underinsurance that market failure leads
people who could have insurance at a
fair price not getting
it what we'll talk about after
Thanksgiving is how the government
specifically addresses that market
failure through things like mandates
taxes subsidies Single Payer coverage
we'll talk about that and how the
government addresses those market
failures through government policy