our next speaker Professor Rafael gas
Bomar I hope the pronounce is right uh
who is a associate professor in MIT
Department of Material Science and
Engineering he's interested in fing
machine learning and atom atomistic
simulations for Designing materials and
their transformation now let's welcome
Rafael thank
you yes
yeah5 they're running this like
clockwork and thanks so much for for
coming uh I go by Rafa like the like a
tennis player and um uh like like it was
said at the at the introduction uh my
work groups at the sort of interface of
AI and and first principles um and the
reason why this is important is because
it takes about 20 years for a material
to make it to Market from the time
somebody has an idea at the lab it's
like oh this gooey substance could be
good for um uh for posted notes until
something is actually produced at scale
in the market it the typical number that
people use is 20 years um and for our
net Z objectives in 2050 we pretty much
have five six more years to invent the
technologies that will scale up by the
time we need a net zero we've determined
that we will be at a net zero economy
um and a lot of the problems and the
solutions around the energy and
sustainability go around materials
Innovations there is obviously going to
be you know Arbitrage about uh buying
electricity today and selling it
tomorrow there there are Technical
Solutions that are not just about
materials but materials are going to be
critical obviously for energy storage
and batteries right lithium ion
batteries do not really scale to a great
scale or it's going to be challenging to
store all the electricity that we need
in lithium ion batteries the way they
look right now energy energy conversion
right we want more solar can we make
solar that is not as expensive as
silicon um can we make better polymers
for windmill blades so I don't know if
you follow this but the offshore
windmills have been complicated because
the materials are not as tough as they
could be can we make cheaper magnets for
these windmills right so it's all these
questions that are intimately tied uh TI
to to materials Innovations Plastics
what do we do with with plastics right
we make a 100 million tons of
polyethylene every year um well the
solution through that has to go through
materials
Innovations in parallel to the sort of
urgent needs we've seen a class of
Technology explode over the last decade
or over the last five years right things
that used to
be exclusive to humans and really really
hard turn out to be not that hard
anymore right it's been over almost a
decade since Alpha ago when you know
this game that was supposed to be
combinatorially much harder than chess
and and intractable for computers for a
100 years turned out to be solvable with
a new class of Technology right with
deep learning or machine learning in
general and we've seen this apply to a
number of of places right we've seen um
like I said the sort of rule based games
solved with reinforcement learning maybe
7 years ago we've obviously seen all the
Winds of Machine Vision if you got a
nest camera right tells you the postman
the post person showed up with a package
that's all Machine Vision and that
technology has been sort of part of our
lives for now maybe five years and then
over the last two or three llms right
we've all seen and the success of uh
obviously chat GPT and similar
Technologies in producing sort of
humanlike text and and then in the
Sciences there's been sort of one big
wind has been Alpha right you remember
maybe four or five years ago this
problem of protein structure prediction
figuring out what geometry a protein is
going to have just based on its sequence
on the physics based side it's like a
really interactable problem it requires
computation at a scale that we we
couldn't sort of
really aspire to to deploy and it turns
out it was a very learnable problem that
it wasn't really that hard and with a
100,000 instances of training examples
it was actually learnable so all of
these have something in common right
they been a combination of gpus that's
what you know Nvidia is one of the most
valuable companies in the world um uh
just data right although we've kind of
run out of data for llms because they've
already read every word that has ever
been written so maybe some of those are
already CT and then algorithms right
just algorithmic Innovation and I for
instance I am never going to write a
cover letter again in my life right got
this cover letter prepared in case we
ever discover a high temperature
superconductor I already have GPT right
to me the the cover letter now can I ask
GPT to find me the super conductor
that's that's the harder part that's the
thing that's very different about our
world right like how do we deploy these
Technologies for chemistry and and
materials Innovations could that could
be any of these things right it could be
carbon capture right we need to sack
carbon out of the air we need need
batteries like I said we need more
sustainable Plastics um and this has
some qualitative differences from some
of the other victories um the first one
is that typically we only want a match
to Human Performance for most of the
other tasks right we want images as good
as as an artist would draw you know we
want contracts as good as a lawyer would
would write uh but here we kind of want
to do better than the best human has
ever done in history right because
otherwise we you know you know you'll
invent things once um so we want to do
better than the best scientist has ever
done which is kind of a shift um and it
has sort of this outof
distribution extrapolation challenge
that is really hard for machine learning
right we're asking the machine learning
model to do something that is by
definition outside of the training data
outside of the way we trained it because
we're asking it to invent completely
Noble things um and we postulate and
this is not necessarily A a proven
hypothesis that the fact that in the
Sciences we have rules should help right
the fact that you know maybe your
companies do physics based simulations
maybe you do you know finite elements
maybe you do fluid dynamics right in
many places we know the laws of physics
in a way that should help our models and
a big example of this would be climate
modeling right we don't do any climate
modeling but climate modeling is
something that has really succeeded over
the last three two three years um
through a combination of understanding
the way the physics works and utilizing
lots of experimental data um to drive
things forward so in the chemistry and
Material Science space we we only get to
deploy um machine learning or to utilize
machine learning if we live sort of in a
more data intensive Paradigm right at
the end of the day um the traditional
scientific
approach So-Cal edisonian approach would
be this on the left here
where the framework is a human decides
what the space of options would be right
and that's typically in the hundreds of
thousands right when when experimental
scientists show up in their Labs today
they you know the thing the set of
things they could be doing that day it's
typically in the hundreds or thousands
of ideas it's not in the millions or
billions of ideas um and then they
select based on their understanding of
the world the literature they've read
their internal model of the world
handful of experiments which take a
couple of days to run so this cycle
these data pipes are kind of narrow
right and then the outcomes are sort of
two three new data points a day which
are just very well digested by a human
being right we're very good at operating
in low modes in low data modes right
that's something we've done cognitively
very well so AI is not really going to
change this part of the world if if you
really produce new data at sort of a
throughput of a couple a day you don't
need a deep Lear anymore right or our
deep learning model won't be a
Difference Maker right because our human
intuition is very good on the other side
of the pipe and this is of this new
paradigm that has emerged over the last
few years is ways to generate more data
over larger design spaces like well a
computer a million options 100 million
options that's really not that difficult
problem for a computer today Pharma
companies and again I don't know if
there are any here um they purchase new
comp compounds from virtual catalogs
from a company called enamine or others
like them which have a list of 1.5
billion compounds you could buy for them
from them and you put your lit machine
learning model running over the list of
compounds these folks make and order the
ones that could work for you um so in
this new paradigm we have broader search
spaces we try to create data in bigger
chunks at a given time and the loop gets
closed not through human intuition but
through a computer right through Active
Learning um uh and in general um in
chemistry and materials there is a
hierarchy of how much data we can make
at every instance right so typically um
at the base of the pyramid we can deploy
statistical machine learning models over
millions and billions of options right
this people call this virtual screening
we can totally screen Millions hundreds
of millions of compounds with a neural
network or with a machine learning model
so this ual space we can screen you know
at gigantic scales um maybe we can use
sort of more trust worthy simulations
right depending on your field you could
sort of screen with a neural network in
climate modeling and then run a few
models forward with
actual physics based simulations or
finite element simulations um and then
we need to make stuff and depending
where in the world you see this is this
is the where the materials world is very
different from other places
because if you want chat GPT to write
contracts you only need to worry that
the contracts are good but there is
no change of um uh platform you know the
contract is a digital object that gets
sent over email as a PDF file so CH GPT
can actuate in the real world directly
right in materials we kind of need to
make stuff right and then we need to
make it to see if it works and then we
need to scale it up to deploy it into
into the market right and these two
things we will talk more about this but
this is critical um so there is making
which is kind of harder than simulating
and then there is characterizing and
measuring the quality of what you've
made for the performance metrics that
you want to hit for your Target product
profiles like is this thing good enough
and and that typically is the most time
consuming part right so different places
different Industries and different um
products have sort of different widths
but in general this cycle um of of how
much data we produce is hierarchical
like this and in my group we've done a
number of these um I won't I won't spend
too much time describing sort of our own
detailed research but we've deployed
these types of things for polymers for
for lithium batteries for organic
Electronics we've done organic light
emitting diodes uh we've done nanoporous
Catal I have some slides on on those you
have time we're doing recyclable
polymers for windmill blades so in
general this hierarchy of running some
some Physics based simulations over some
design space making them work together
with machine learning models such that
we can save ourselves simulation time
even and then bring in domain experts as
the translation entity right that that
will translate computational designs
into actual sort of materials that that
will be tested right and and every time
we narrow down the face space of things
we could do and have this communicate
with one another this this should look
tiny on your screens um the data
infrastructure that we built is like
tens of thousands of lines of code in
order to store all of these to automate
to have these Digital Data pipes there's
a lot of infrastructure that needs to be
built um maybe there will be questions
later about sort of what is the balance
between digitizing old data and
digitizing new data um I've typically
been on the camp of digitizing new data
digitizing old data until llms was a
nightmare with llms maybe there is there
is a a low overhead way of going back
and and salvaging all data and research
in augmented generation in rag but until
today leverage in all data was was just
too expensive
um so more concretely right what are
places where AI is being deployed today
sort of at the interface of research or
or um very aggressive early adopters in
the in Industry well deep learning
models machine learning models can
definitely predict what a material what
a molecule will do from its structure
this I I just mention this when I talked
about this enamine company for drag
Discovery right so going back for you
know
2015 for the first instances 20 for
molecules 2018 for the first instances
for
for crystals maybe a little bit later in
the early 2020s for proteins uh and this
is a generative example over the last
sort of five to 10 years the community
has made deep learning models that are
just very good at looking at matter so
for whatever arrangement of atoms if I
have enough training data in the right
space I can make a machine learning
model that would tell me this is good
this is bad and and that's Pharma
companies do this all the time today
right so you you train a model on your
you know binding examples from a highr
puras and now you have a binding
predictor that would apply to new
compounds that you want to buy or make
right and or to admit um or this would
apply to polymers for lithium ion
batteries or to crystals for
ferroelectric material so in general um
over the last sort of 5 to 10 years the
community has made good deep learning
models that given a structure will
assign the label
of what it's going to do as long as
there is enough data um AI can predict
how to make stuff okay um we call in
chemistry we call this retrosynthesis
which is if you wanted this compound
these are the precursors you were going
to have to buy and these are the ways
you would put them together um this goes
back the idea of trying to do this with
computers goes back to the 60s to Cory
who worked you know at a school that
shall not be named over right over there
um uh and and this has been a a dream of
the organic chemistry community and
again it's been commoditized now many
companies will provide retrosynthesis
software as a service where you say well
I want to make this compound you call
their their their API you call their web
and then they send you back well then
you should buy these precursors and make
these chemistries in this way right so
this is this is something is not perfect
nothing everything could be perfected
but it works and has been around for
this this example for instance from
Marvin segler who's now at Microsoft is
six years old now so this is like I said
this been productized um and this is the
case also for for
materials materials are a little bit
behind because the chemists have all
agreed about how to report the way they
make stuff all chemical reactions are
WRAT in the same way m materials
chemistry material synthesis procedures
are written in a completely different
way right like so if you know if you
shake and Cal sign or you do Soul gel
right there is infinite combinations
that don't have a standard onology
meaning that the only way of
processing syn material synthesis data
has been going to the literature and
reading papers because the data is
unstructured and again llms have really
changed this over the last three years
it's been possible to go to the
literature and ask an llm to read the
papers and organize the material
synthesis data such that then you can
predict how to make new materials based
on the recipes of existing materials
right so again llms have have power the
extraction and then other classes of
models can predict how to make M you
know an oxide or how to make a a
catalyst based or a metal organic
framework based on on the on the
literature
and then just in the last couple of
years uh LMS have sort of taken a bigger
role in what we can say sort of
orchestrating or or agentic workflows
where you know in addition to sort of
doing this individual task that I said
you know you can go read the literature
or we can predict what a material will
do um the orchestration of what to do
when can also be run by a by an NM right
so these are a couple of examples I
apologize here to to my Budd Gabe gz
this is in nature now but I'm citing the
the preprint but this disc go in nature
at the end of 2023 um and this is a a
particular paper for a for a llm that
again reads the
literature decides whether you need to
change your reagents um and produces
synthesis recipes sort of autonomously
right the the orchestration of which
model to call when is something that is
is happening right now and then you know
there it says gener ative AI right there
what does what does sort of material
Discovery have to do with generative AI
well they're kind of one and the same
thing from our perspective if if you
notice I mention machine learning models
that go from structure to property or
from material to synthesis but really
what we want to do is go from the
property I want to maybe the structure
that will produce it or from the
material that I want to the synthesis
from the properties that I want to the
synthesis that would make a material
with those properties right what I want
is to inverse the sign ideally the
product people will come to me with a
Target product profile and say well we
want some nanoporous material that would
absorb CO2 in this pressure and
temperature and it costs less than a
dollar a kilogram right and then I just
put that into the LM and it tells me
well then you need to buy these
precursors and put them in the oven for
two days um that's a generative task
right instead of going from a known
structure to the properties we expect it
will have we go from the properties we
want to a material that could have them
and that's a it's a much harder task
because there may be many answers if you
want something trivial there might be
many answers and if you want something
impossible like my high temperature
superconductor there might be no answer
whatsoever also and the model needs to
know how to do this um U the idea of
trying to do this in chemistry goes back
about eight years from the first
examples and people have kept going at
it and there is a gilon improvements
over that original work um and there is
a big ecosystem of AI for chemistry
companies that have utilized or or
productize generative AI for small
molecules interestingly um AI for small
molecules even though it got very
exciting there's a lot of small
molecules you could make and and people
have been thinking about sort of AI for
chemistry for a long time so it seem
like a natural match um proteins which
seemed harder originally have overtaking
small molecules and they turn out to be
easier for you know based on and the
reason I believe is because
proteins all form a family they all come
from the same
distribution biology and life and
evolution have created a common language
that covers all of proteins so it turns
out those were were easier functions to
learn just like go was easier to learn
than self-driving cars um proteins
turned out to be learnable in a way that
has exploded over the last you know
three four years um so generative models
for proteins really work and they say if
you want a protein that binds this other
Target like that then you need to you
know arrange this amino acids in a
sequence and you can make those in a um
uh Express those uh
as a nucleic acid and then translate
them and you know these companies I have
a list later I don't know if you've
heard during this space cidra raised a
billion dollars a series no this is not
an MIT startup um it raised a billion
dollars a series recently to do that um
so like I said the inverse design maybe
a little bit technical but in general
the same tools that produce you know
pictures of an astronaut riding a horse
on the surface of the Moon from a prpt
from a prompt could produce a blue low
cost stable molecule to put in the LED
display on my phone we just need to you
know train them on different data and
structure them in a different way
because the thing we're producing here
are pixels and the thing we're producing
in this model is ideally atomic
structure or even better just the
synthesis recipe just tell me what to
buy right like don't even tell me what
the molecule looks like just tell me
what I need to make um um so that sounds
amazing you know
and what's what's not working right like
what's what what is it really sort of
what what are the boundaries right now
well there's a lot of things AI cannot
do in chemistry and materials um I have
them listed there I can sort of give a
little color but deciding what's
important it's all about context right
at the end of the day a lot of this have
to do with sort of the rest of the
context and AI cannot decide whether
it's better to to make a sustainable
plastic or a recycling system for
existing Plastics that's that's you know
there is technoeconomic there is a moral
there is a market opportunity there is
time to pass like all these things live
outside the training data and the way
machine learning models think so that's
our responsibility right like we we are
the ones that need to Define very clear
objective function so what is the Target
in the most structured well defined
possible way that I want to pursue
otherwise the models will cheat they
will cheat all the time and just give
you the most obvious solution or or the
easiest solution um if if the question
is unspecified um I don't know what your
companies exactly have encountered here
but in general creative humans don't
like to be told what to do by a
computer um and this is a big impedance
matching when things need to be realized
in the real world right in the physical
World objects need to made be made
chemistry needs to happen in a lab um so
the conduit for this AI creativity is
human beings that are extremely skilled
and deep thinkers who would rather
explore their own hypothesis than a
computer's hypothesis and this seems
trivial but it's held back the field
because well the AI has high tolerance
for false positives right something you
thought was a great idea turns out to be
a bad idea the computer doesn't care
right like well will it learns it's good
data it keep going it's kind of Soul
crashing to have false negatives all the
time in the lab right so in general the
the computer human interface around AI
for for materials and science is not a
solved problem uh and then this this
goes back to a point that I keep
referring to like the AI doesn't make
anything right and there is two layers
of making in materials and chemistry
there's the first layer of just making a
tiny amount so we can see if the thing
works which is one barrier
and an in Pharma too and then there's a
second of making a ton of it or many
many tons of it to put it in in whatever
your Market is right you're making
Catalyst you know some of these big
catalysts in in petrochemistry they load
20 tons or 50 tons of catalyst in a
single time the scaling is completely
outside of of what AI can think about
and then and you've seen this with with
GPT these models don't really know when
they're really really wrong right like
there's you can go out of domain you
train your model on on oxides and you
ask it about Alloys about metallic
Alloys instead of ceramic oxides and
it's catastrophic but the model won't
tell you it's catastrophic we just give
you random numbers um so what's what's
the happening today at the research
level what is sort of the the solution
to some of these things well what we
call this the execution Gap uh and how
are folks taking this on with autonomous
Labs or programmable labs right that's
how the AI the scientific intelligence
gets hooked into enacting science not
just thinking about science but doing
science and that's with a lab that can
be accessed through code and there's
been examples for a few years this is
sort of growing and growing these are
two examples from last year um this is
from from the other camp this a west
coast exampler of Berkeley and this is
from my my dear collaborator um uh Claus
Jensen here at MIT chemical engineering
we contributed AI to this but we didn't
contribute the robot right making this
requires mechanical engineers it
requires you know Machining pieces it
requires control people
so making the AI actuate the real world
turns out to be not really an AI problem
at all and a automation um and sort of
chemistry or materials or synthesis or
processing problem altoe now in this
particular example we were able to hook
all the pieces in the space of dice
molecules of a certain color so this
wasn't phal compounds but it was
chemical compounds uh with a desired
color we were able
to create a programmable lab that has
moving pieces and can make chemistry
happen on its own and the AI tools to
design molecules with generative AI
predict how to make them with
retrosynthesis and access to the
literature to recover literature
information predict their properties
with property prediction models like the
graph neural networks I mentioned
earlier quantify uncertainty to know how
to make the itself
better with rounds of
learning uh and drive the whole cycle
through and through three or four times
autonomously I mean it's autonomous in
the sense that most of the when it works
it runs on its own if run out of solvent
somebody gets a text message that they
need to go replace the solvent so it's
autonomous in its normal operation but
obviously requires a human supervisor
but not necessarily a co-pilot so here
we are we're we're in a place where more
data is better right llms worked because
they could read of all the internet and
all the copyrighted information out
there uh scientific journals are are on
to us uh and on to this practice
practices and they're not letting people
read papers right they know they hold a
lot of value uh but somehow we need to
integrate all of these data sets and all
these modalities and try to achieve as
much sort of scientific
reasoning um as we can I I was making
some changes here
um uh at the last minute this is the
slide that I brought over so sorry it's
misformed but I I suspected you folks
were going to uh to care about this this
is what I was mention is sort of about
this time these waves of things we've
seen we saw small molecule drugs almost
hit a peak there's some clinical trial
results coming back I don't know if
you're following the field but recursion
has three or four clinical outcomes
coming out this year so it's kind of
it's
uh
H we're going to get our grades back in
in the small molecule drugs but we
already took the exam right like the ex
Britain we're just waiting for the
greates uh protein drugs happening right
now and the material
is is sort of you know a lot of
big AI names have attached their names
or their their activities to material
design and sustainability work over the
last you know three to six months so it
has sort of a Time urgency and and an
excitement to it um so with this I think
I have 52 seconds left so I'll just
thank the team thanks our sponsors and
thank you so much for your time Fox
[Applause]
yes so there's a number of written
questions it seems like what all the
questions will be written
yes yeah so the first question says uh
the whether we can go from model to
Theory um being that being uh analyzing
models using other models extracting
knowledge or are machine learning and
Theory just too different um I didn't
want to bore this community with details
I believe machine learning and Theory
simulations are kind of the same thing
um so sorry if this is this is what you
wanted to spend some time on I'm sorry
we we I'm sure we get more chances to
talk in our lives uh my personal belief
on my group's whole research area is
that there is a
Continuum of computation that goes from
places where you know all the physics
and all the theory if you're making you
know planes uh you pretty much don't
need machine learning right we know the
equations that govern the way planes
work um to Alpha which is completely
black box it doesn't really use any of
the physics that we know and anything in
between so there's a whole spectrum of
places and you know Microsoft is doing
this Google is doing this where you
inject machine learning into simulations
that you like but you make them faster
or you make them more efficient or more
accurate or you inject more physics
understanding into machine learning to
make the models more efficient or learn
with less data there is something called
equivariance which is having machine
learning models obey the same symmetry
as the real world so you know if you've
got an arrow and you rotate your own
position the arrow will rotate with you
and machine models don't do that by
default if you rotate the reference
point the arrow still points in the old
in the old Direction unless the models
are equivariant and well that turns out
to help a lot to learn so tasks but not
others so yes I I do believe in that
very big
time uh yeah are we so the first one
I'll just go by votes and try to be fast
are we going to be able to generate
enzymes that can catalyze reaction that
will help remediation and detoxification
at scale um I think the qu the answer is
Big Time yes on the technical part so I
think enzyme design is a subset of
protein design um and that's just going
to work you know we have we can we can
express enzymes we can measure the
activity in a Clos Loop we can fine-tune
models that we train on General protein
task so I think this Loop of enzyme
Discovery is most likely to work whether
this would be economical to actually do
remediation out there is a much harder
question and today AI won't help us
answer that question technoeconomic
analysis and and sort of market analysis
um AI won't do that for us but enzymes
are very expensive so most likely the
the first answer the answer to that
question was yes whether that will
actually be useful in the real world is
maybe
not would you have examples where
visualization and computation help
people explore complex tradeoffs using
these methods yes this a very good one
thank you uh
so actually we're used to very good
human computer
interfaces in general you know when you
log in into your bank app or you go
shopping in Amazon The Experience the
way you interact with data has been
curated by being really experts for many
many years um so in that sense there's a
lot to learn from the way people
interact with data uh from those fields
um in general this is a place where we
my group have invested many cycles which
is distilling and Mining
AI outputs such that they can be handed
off to a or passed on to a human being
that can get you know excited about what
thei is producing not overwhelmed about
sort of the stream of of nonsense right
if you let an AI model on its own it
most likely going to produce a stream of
nonsense so distill down compress apply
all the filters whether AI or or rule
base but in general yes that's a place
where we've we've done I think we've
spent a lot of work
and all the projects that end up making
something and you know we we file a
pattern on a catalyst or we make a cool
polymer that maybe can you know be a
product all go through distilling data
mining visualizing such that a human
being can pick up the the the Baton and
actually make something and tell us
things back because then it's like well
somebody presented this at a conference
last year it's not a new IP right wasn't
a so or this molecule you know it's too
expensive why because this
retrosynthesis recipe this thing is
proposing uses platinum and we cannot
afford the platinum in this material
right so it's not only as showing uh
data mining AI predictions for human
beings but human beings being able to
give actionable feedback back into the
models let's see if we can do a couple
more uh what is the best practice or
state-of-the-art to apply AI for
starting a new project on materials
design
so I would say I have a slide here of
this this might be I skipped it because
I was running a little bit fast
and this is my experience when things
have worked so maybe it would be sort of
the answer to this is like that in our
experience it needs to be something that
you've measured before it seems hard to
deploy AI on making something you've
never made or thought about before so
typically the B being able to measure
knowing what the space looks like having
some uh literature data to pre-train on
that really helps actually in our
experience having the model read all the
literature before we start doing
anything that seems really useful and
then there needs to be some mechanism to
create new data these cycles of learning
they are a huge bottom leg because the
model will obviously have gaps and you
know especially in the context of this
big data Paradigm I was talking about we
need a lot of data to patch those gaps
um so typically we need some mechanism
for active learning and cycling so I
would say I don't know if it's exactly
best practices as a as a
uh rule that I propose to you but it's
definitely a experience that we've had
um that sort of this this is the common
denominator of of success
here is large scale automated synthesis
and testing really needed Oram more
simulation and AI leverage to converse
design finite element static Dynamics um
I
think yes it's like inclusive or H so
both are true the handoff of one to
another
is a again a place where humans can make
decisions typically when when I give a
slightly more technical talk I have
three examples of work we've done that
has the bullets that you know the common
denominators that showed before and one
of them there were no robots whatsoever
the AI predictions were filtered down
passed on to human beings who then use
their expertise could be convinced that
this was a a good idea that it was worth
their time that it align with their
creativity that they have enough agency
to so it use a lot of AI a lot of
physics that we trusted we could be very
predictive because we really know the
lose of the game we could be very
quantitative and very predictive the
models would extrap at well right
physics extrapolates much better than AI
right the physics based models by
definition are are made to generalize
machinary models struggle to generalize
so typically in our experience the more
physics we have the less it needs to be
a robot doing experiments because we
kind of automate all the simulations and
distill down really good ideas if things
are more black box and we don't have a
lot
of physics base or scientific support
and we're just trying things um that's
kind of hard for for human beings you
know there's not that many cycles of
just trying things that you can do with
human beings so typically the less we
know about the nature of the problem the
more we rely on large scale experimental
efforts that could be done by humans
right like if you have a grad student
technicians that can do five experiments
a day for you know 300 days a year
that's enough data right so the question
is what's the sort of you know what are
the reproducibility motivation cost
tradeoffs between human and robotized
experimentation so maybe we have time
for one
more um oh yeah what's the state of
multimodal understanding in chemistry
and materials and what do we foresee as
initiatives in this
regard so it's about to happen so it's
going to happen hasn't happened yet we
really haven't seen a lot of multimodal
training and typically in chemistry the
typical modality is a lot of chemical
structures and the properties so it's
just one modality um and then all the
synthesis story we were just describing
right where you can have sort of how to
make stuff so I think these haven't
really been orchestrated yet I think
will likely happen structure to property
synthesis to structure I think those two
you know if you know I don't know if
it's going to be berley I don't know if
it's going to be us I don't know if it's
going to be a company um but these two
things will get orchestrated
alongside large language models reading
the literature right the only blocking
element for large language models really
in the literature is licenses from the
from the Publishers right everything
else is sort of technically trivial so I
think it's coming um I think the lab
part of this will be a couple more years
I think coordinating this with Machine
Vision to know how to you know pour a
liquid so you can shake it
that's going to be a little bit longer
so I would say digital multimodal yes
physical
actionable lab multimodal will take a
little bit longer and I think we're up
to time so thank you very much folks for
your time thank you thank you