all right welcome back to 61200 today we
continue our theme of probability as we
will continue to do for the next few
lectures um first uh recap from last
class and last recitation uh key concept
we'll be using today is conditional
probability remember this notation is
the probability of event a occurring
given that you already know that b
occurred which is like if you imagine
this entire Blackboard as the space as
the sample space all the possibilities
of what could happen and we have events
a is some subset of that space b is some
subset of that space what the vertical
Bar B means restricting to conditioning
on b means focusing on just this red
subset of where B is and just think
about the probability of a happening
relative to those events instead of
think the probability of a happening
relative to all events and you can
compute that as the probability of this
intersection uh divided by the
probability of B so we're just focusing
in assuming B already happened then this
is becomes our entire sample space that
we can restrict to okay and then we can
use that for example to compute
probabilities of events so this was law
of total probability probability of an
event a is uh if you pick your favorite
event e sort of like a proof by cases
you get to choose any event e you want
that's whatever's most convenient then
you can compute compute probability of a
using by splitting into two cases one
where e occurs and one where e does not
occur so you take the probability that
the E occurs you multiply it by the
probability that a occurs given e and
you do the same for not e and because uh
e and not e are by definition disjoint
events exactly one of them happens this
uh works out you have the uh the product
rule here between these events and the
sum rule between these events I think
easiest to see in this tree um I tend to
draw my trees vertically you can draw
them horizontally whatever uh we have uh
event e occurring or not occurring and
then separately we have event a or not a
occurring and any of these could happen
in any combination when we write down a
tree usually we write on the edges
conditional probabilities at the
beginning there's no condition so it's
just probability of e on one side and
probability of not e on the other
side uh but then usually on this Branch
we write what's the probability of a
given that e occurred and on this Branch
what's the probability that not a
occurred given that e occurred this
whole branch is that e occurred and then
we care about given that we got here
what's the probability of a happening
what's the probability of not a
happening and similarly on the other
side what's the probability of a and not
a happening given that e didn't happen
that's those are all the cases um and
then you can compute the probability of
each of these individual situations by
taking the product of these
probabilities down the path um that's
what we have shown in the past and so in
particular if you want to compute the
probability of a a is these two nodes
together these are the two a branches
and so that is this product plus this
product by construction everything here
is disjoint and so you can just add the
probabilities up and you get get this
law okay we may use it today
uh today I want to talk about a related
concept which is Independence so today
is Independence Day not starring Will
Smith or any other modern versions of
Independence Day um and the the tagline
for Independence Day back in the 90s I
was alive back then uh it says the
question of whether or not we are alone
in the universe has been answered you
know are we are we independent from the
rest of the universe or are we dependent
it turns out the answer is uh we're
independent if and only if probability
of a given a b is probability of a
that's sorry spoilers for the movie but
that's that's what you get by the end so
that's our mathematical definition of a
is
independent of
B if probability of a given
B uh probability of a conditioned on B
is is just the probability of a again so
in other words conditioning on B does
not affect the probability of a with the
condition without the condition you get
the same thing um we have to also say or
the probability of b equals
zero uh for this annoying technical
reason which I forgot to mention up here
probability of a given B is not defined
when probability of B is zero because
then you get a division by zero error we
don't like those so uh I don't even know
what this means
when B when the probability of B is zero
so we need to say whether we're
independent in that case and we
are so it turns out the empty event
where no which never happens is
independent of everything also the full
event which always happens is
independent of
everything uh so this is a way to
measure uh whether two things are
independent uh meaning whether the
outcome or like whether a happened
whether B happened has any impact on
whether a will happen that's intuitively
what this means and it's a useful
concept here isong page an example uh
that gives you some intuition about why
the Monty Hall problem comes out the way
it does so let's
do Monty
Hall um I'm G to Define two
events one is door one
uh has a
prize so I forget the door names that uh
brinmore used so I'm just going to call
them door number one two and three just
like in the game
show uh
and I don't have fancy colored boxes
okay I'm I'm not going to repeat the
whole analysis of Monty Hall but I just
want you to think about these two events
so event a is that door one has the
price we know without anything else this
happens with onethird probability uh
event B is that door two is revealed to
not have the prize after player after
the player chooses door one okay this is
a bit of a mouthful but let's just
suppose uh that the player starts by
choosing door number one uh in the
analysis we did we had a uniform random
choice of choosing all three doors it
doesn't actually matter which door you
choose because everything else is random
it's fine if you always choose door one
but whe whether it's random whether it's
deterministic let's just suppose the
player the player chooses door
one and event B is Will door number two
be
revealed uh to not have the
press okay and now my question is is
event a and event B uh are they
independent from each other and I claim
that they
are
uh and the way we can determine that is
by Computing these two probabilities
probability of a and probability of a
given B now probability of a we know
is uh
1/3 right with that this is just does
door one half prize that's uniform
random so uh oneir for that and so for
this to be independent it better be the
case that uh probability of a given B is
also
1/3 and if you think about it uh that is
one of the things we computed um because
what we computed was what's the
probability of
switching uh the switching rule winning
so we're supposing here the player chose
door
one and so if in the switching strategy
they will switch to uh in in conditioned
on b means that player the player chose
door one and door two was revealed not
to have the prize and so we would switch
to door three and we worked out that the
winning probability if you in the
switching strategy was 2/3 so that means
the probability that door one has the
prize must be 1/3 because the
probability that door three three has
the priz is 2/3 and 1 - 2/3 is 1/3 so
indeed these are equal and the events
are independent and while I don't claim
this is super intuitive yet um I mean if
you stare it's like you stare at it for
an hour and then it's intuitive so it's
not especially intuitive but I think
while before we saw you can just compute
everything and find the answer um I
think this does give a little intuition
the idea is that revealing door two to
not have the prize doesn't tell you
anything about whether door one has the
price and that's intuitively why
switching is good because you've reduced
down to two uh possibilities instead of
just instead of three if you stick to a
uh it will be as if you were no doors
were revealed right if you suppose you
pick door number one at the beginning
and you uh decide I'm just going to stay
no matter what then whatever information
they show you doesn't tell you anything
about uh uh whether door one will have
the price and that's that's what this is
confirming that that vague feeling that
might be true uh this shows that indeed
this information being revealed tells
you nothing about whether a will happen
or whether a happened I guess uh the
probabilities are the same either way
and so this gives you some intuition for
why uh the monteal problem came out the
way it
did still you should compute things but
the goal by the end of this class is
you'll have at least some intuition
about probability and hopefully it will
be the correct one
here's another situation to think about
suppose you have two events A and B
which are disjoint so they're two
subsets of the sample space and they
don't have any elements in common so we
normally write this as a intersect B is
the empty
set then are they independent well uh
let's just compute these probabilities
probability of a I don't know how to
compute but probability of a given B
that I know how to compute I zoom into B
and I see how many A's are in there and
zero there's no a inside B uh in other
words the
probability here probability of a
intersect B is zero because there's no
intersection so whatever the denominator
is is zero okay and uh so this means
they are not
independent typically
uh unless uh some exceptional cases
happen
namely uh I guess it could be that a is
also the empty set there's nothing in a
then probability of a um equals this
thing probability of a given
B uh and the other situation is uh
probability of B is
zero because that's another situation
where we just have independence by
definition okay so disjoint events are
not independent uh the intuition here is
if I tell you that b happened you know
very well a did not happen because we
assume these are disjoint events okay
another example is uh
subsets let's suppose which way is
easier B is a subset of
a so a is the big thing and B is nestled
inside then I want to know uh what is
the probability of a given
B well if I zoom into B it looks in
completely a all of this is included
inside a and so this probability is
one and so this is another situation
where uh A and B are not
independent unless some very special
cases
happen uh namely
it could be uh a is everything a always
occurs probability of a equals 1 um or
again it could be probability of b
equals
zero so if B is just nothing then uh
they're independent just by definition
if a is everything then uh yeah
restricting to B it's still everything
question why don't we say dependent it's
a good question uh I believe
traditionally not not independent we
could just say dependent uh I guess I
don't know what dependent means I guess
you could try to Define dependence like
amount of dependence and maybe
statisticians do that but in our worlds
we generally just Define independent and
then there's the converse and we call it
non-independent I agree it's weird you
could maybe think of it as dependent
but pretty sure it's not standard
all right uh let me tell you some more
ways of course the in you take two
events they're probably dependent in
some sense uh Independence is kind of
the special thing and it's what we are
going to focus on is detecting when when
an event is
independent so let me tell you some ways
to other ways to compute it so we can
use this definition and compute it uh
but it's It's oddly asymmetric right we
talked about the probability of a given
B what if it's easier to compute the
probability of B given a for example or
something else uh there's another nice
characterization which I'm going to call
the product rule we've already seen a
product rule with inclusion exclusion
but
um here's another one
so an event a is independent of another
event B if and only if probability of a
intersect B is the product of the
probabilities okay this is what
you this is what makes sense I guess in
some sense if uh naively if you try to
if you want to think about the
probability of of an intersection what's
in other words the probability of one
event happening and another event
happening naively that would be the
product and Independence is exactly when
you can do this if you're independent
this is true if you're not independent
this is false so it this is some sense
why we care about
independence uh and yeah let me get
another chalk
here and it's effectively what we're
using in when I was saying oh uh the
probability of this event happening is
the probability of this thing happening
times the the probability of this thing
happening conditioned on this one that
that multiplication is is okay partly
because I mean in particular because
event e is independent of a given e in
some sense I guess this is not properly
an event but you can think of it that
way all right let's prove this theorem
uh by
cases so
case
one what I'd like to branch on is is the
probability of b equal to zero because
it's just annoying to work with this
definition there's a special case b
equals zero okay so that turns out to be
the natural case breakdown case two is
going to be probability B is not zero
okay so uh when B probability of b
equals z we know uh that a is
independent of
B that's part of the
definition so now uh so this part is
true so for this if and only if to be
true we better make sure the probability
of a intersect B is equal to that
product okay but then this number is
zero so this product is zero so what we
really want is that the probability of a
intersect B is zero and indeed
probability of a intersect B is at most
probability of
B why because this set is contained in
this set and probability is monotone if
you take a smaller set it contains all
the elements of this set then this
probability will be less than equal to
that uh and probability B is zero by
assumption uh and so it's also equal to
probability of a Time probability of B I
guess I'm also using that uh
probabilities are non- negative and so
I've sandwiched this probability between
Z and zero which means it equals
zero uh it's both less than or greater
than or equal to zero so equal zero and
so we're done with that case Okay
probability be not equal to zero is the
more interesting case because that's
when we get to work with this formula
probability of a given B is equal to
probability of a so that's the
definition of independence so write
Independence if and only if probability
of a given b equals probability of
a okay so now we have
some uh computation to
do let's see we also have a formula for
probability of a given B up here that's
the definition so let's plug that in
probability of a intersect B divided by
probability of
B okay so this is equal to that this is
equal to that so these two things are
equal and now on this equation I'd just
like I see probability of a here I see
probability of B on the denominator here
I'd like to multiply both sides by
probability of B and I get uh this is a
equivalent to probability of a Time
probability of
b equals probability of a intercept
B which is exactly what I wanted to
prove that's so I'm
done uh crucially here though I'm using
in order to multiply both sides by
probability of B and to get an if and
only if it's crucial that this is not
zero if you multiply both sides of a
formula by zero you don't get a very
interesting formula and you don't get an
if and only if so but once I assume that
probability is not zero then I can
actually do the multiplication and uh
and I get a useful statement and this is
true so I get the cancellation I wanted
otherwise I get zero over zero okay so
uh this tells us a different way to
determine Independence right we could
compute this thing and this thing uh or
we can compute this thing and this thing
uh and if they're equal it's the same
thing as that condition being true
notably uh this definition or this
condition sometimes this is the
definition of independence you might see
both uh they're they're equivalent so
you could use either one this definition
is symmetric in A and B if I swap A and
B I get exactly the same thing right a
intersect B is the same as B intersect a
probability of a times probability of B
is the same thing as probability of B
times probability of a so uh I no longer
have to say a is independent of B I can
just say A and B are independent without
worrying about
uh which one's first so
corollary
uh independent
of is a symmetric
relation a is independent of B if and
only if B is independent of a so I'll
just talk about A and B being
independent for from now on this
definition is not obviously symmetric
but now that you know that these are
interchangeable if it's easier to
compute probability of B given a you can
do that as well you can do probability
of B given a equals probability of B
that's just as good as checking this
one not obvious from that definition but
through this transformation it becomes
obvious all
right let's uh let's do some more
interesting examples
and let's start
with flipping to Independent Fair
coins okay now that you know what
Independence means we're going to be
using it a lot uh in particular just as
an
assumption uh a lot of probability
problems are not well defined unless you
specify as part of the statement that uh
two random events are independent from
each other you already saw this in your
problem set we wanted all of the errors
that the bots made to be independent
from each other meaning uh whether one
thing happens does not influence the
outcome of the other so a simple example
of this where you this is a reasonable
assumption is you have two coins uh I
don't use physical money anymore but
imagine you have two coins and you flip
them whether this one comes out heads
and whether this one comes out heads
should be independent of each other
unless you I don't know glue the two
coins together then they're very
dependent I used it
dependent um so usually when we're
saying we're going to flip a bunch of
coins we need to specify are they
somehow linked together maybe I don't
know they have some quantum entanglement
and whether one comes out heads
influences the other or they're
physically attached or something like
that but normally we think of the case
where the coins are all dependent okay
so we're going to use Independence also
as an assumption in the problem
statement and that
specifies uh in some sense what your
sample space should be then there's
another assumption here which is fair
that means that they come out 50% heads
50%
Tails so
um sample
space is uh heads and tails squared so
heads and tails cross heads and tails uh
the the set of pairs heads Tails heads
Tails
um or X Y where X and Y are in H or T I
forget whether we've squared sets before
but that's the
meaning just like the cross product of
two of them um and so there's like a
there's the first coin and the second
coin this is an ordered pair and they're
each equally likely the assumption that
they're independent
tells us they should be uh all all of
these outcomes are equally likely or the
assumption that they're independent and
fair makes them all equally likely I
guess all right so let's do this more
precisely let's say a is the
event uh that the first
coin uh comes out
heads El
is uh and let's let B be the event
that the second coin comes out
hits okay
um I would like to claim that these two
events are independent from each other
not just by assumption but by Computing
according to either of these formulas
okay so let's let's do that so we fully
understand situation I'm going to draw
tree
here so this is the first first
coin and this is the second
coin each one can be heads or
tails okay and because we're assuming
fair this should be probability half
this should be probability half also
here the probability of each of these
coin flips being header taals given the
previous one uh it doesn't matter that
the first one happen so uh we just write
a half half on all of these
edges okay so now I want to
say let's
say
probability of B given a this is going
to be a little bit circular because
we're using Independence both as an
assumption and the thing we're Computing
but we should be used to drawing these
kinds of diagrams under this implicit
Independence assumption by now we are
told this the number we write here is
the probability of this thing happening
given that this one happened okay so
probability of B given a uh so this this
was um a
is this Edge right I guess this node is
event a in some sense a is that the
first coin flip was a heads so
probability of B given a is exactly the
probability written on this Edge because
this would be uh B given a that
event a happened and then B happened
or I guess the maybe the edge is more is
thought of this way this is more like a
intersect B that they both happened okay
but however you slice it probability of
B given a is a half that's what we
defined the probability of the second
coin being a heads given that the first
one is also a heads shouldn't matter is
a half and on the other hand the
probability
of second coin being heads by itself is
a half so yes it's independent I may say
okay not a very exciting example let's
uh slightly more exciting is that uh
let's say first
coin uh heads
probability is
p and
second
coin uh heads
probability is q
so I invest in some weighted coins it's
probability of P that the first one
comes up heads probability of Q the
second one comes up heads maybe p and Q
are equal to half or maybe there's
something
else uh then still I get for example uh
I don't know the probability that A and
B happens is going to be P *
Q it's hard to do this without
assumption that these are independent
events but this is this is how we've
been Computing things and that's also
probability of
a product with probability B
okay not very exciting let's make this
interesting and Define some events that
are not just a function of one coin but
in fact depend on the entire sample
space so I'm going to go back to this
example and define s to be the event
that uh I guess I should write a and b
are
independent here and a and b are
independent
here okay but now I'm going to write an
event that's not so obvious
uh the S event is going to be that the
coin flips come out the same either both
heads or both
Tails okay this clearly involves both
coin flips so you might think that s and
a say are dependent on each other
intuitively they are but according to
this definition they are
independent that's the claim so let's
compute it um I claim the easy one is to
compute probability of s given
a so in this diagram a is that we're
here uh that we flipped ahead so far and
now I want to know the probability that
the coins come out the same well
condition on a being a heads that's the
same as the probability of uh the second
coin being
heads right so this is just uh the
probability of B
which is not quite what I wanted we
wanted it to be probability of s I guess
but it is equal to the probability of b
um which is a
half by
assumption on the other hand we want to
know is the probability of s the same
thing well probability of s is uh
corresponds to this
node and this
node right this is the head's heads case
this is the Tail's tails
case uh we know the probability of this
is a quarter because it's 12 * 1/2 and
the probability of this is also a
quarter 12 * 1/2 we know all of these
are equally likely a quarter and so
probability of s is the sum of those
two uh this is quarter plus a quarter
also known as a half and so these two
things are
equal so you can think of this as a
betting game suppose uh I ask you to bet
on whether uh two coins are are going to
come out the same or different and
they're Fair independent coins so I'm
going to flip them and you get a dollar
if they're the same and you lose a
dollar if they're different or something
like that um if I flip the first coin
and it comes out heads that doesn't tell
you anything uh you're still going to
have a half half probability of winning
when the second flip happens right uh
doing the first flip does not tell you
anything about whether the second flip
is going to be the same as the first one
because it's still equally likely to be
equal or not equal that's what this is
formalizing okay but until you compute
it I would say this is not exactly
obvious all right let's do the same
thing so here
uh A and S are
independent let's try the same thing
with unfair
coins suppose we have uh parties p and Q
and we have S is the event that the
coins come out the same now things are
not so
easy
uh
so what's the probability that they come
out the
same maybe I should draw this tree again
for the not same ca for the unfair case
so we've got heads tails for the first
coin
so this is probability P this is
probability 1 minus p and then we've got
heads and tails for the second
coin which we're assuming now is
probability q and one minus
Q independent of what happened
before okay and still s is this plus
this
and so we just take these products and
add them up so probability of s
probability of heads Heads maybe I'll
write it out uh probability of heads
Heads plus the probability of Tails
Tails uh the first one is p * Q so the
probability of getting the first heads
is p the probability of getting second
heads is q and by assumption these are
independent so I can take their
product uh and the other one is 1 P * 1
- q and now I just get some ugly algebra
this is like 2 p q minus P minus Q + 1 I
think Check
Yes okay uh on the other hand let's try
uh probability of s given a this one is
actually easy because uh this is saying
okay we condition here's a we condition
on there being a heads in the first step
what's the probability that the same
well that's the same as the probability
that the second coin comes up heads as
well and so that's exactly
Q so uh these things are going to be
independent so I guess uh s and a are
independent if and only if uh 2 PQ
Min - P - Q + 1 = Q in other words uh 2
p q - P - 2 Q + 1 =
0 and this happens to factor I don't
claim this is obvious but it is the same
as uh
2 Q minus 1 pus 1 = 0
and so uh there's two there's two ways
to for this to be true one is that P
equals one in other words the first coin
always comes up heads I would call that
a one-sided coin or you can make them by
manufacturing coin that's heads on both
sides that's a two-sided coin but really
only one side or uh Q is a
half so if Q is a Fair coin
sorry if if the second coin is a Fair
coin then s and a are independent of
each other and so uh this tells us that
uh what we found here which was that s
and a were independent of each other
really needs that the coins are fair
fair coins and one-sided coins are the
only situation where uh this s event uh
here that the coins come out the same is
independent of the first or second coin
so if we were playing this gambling game
with unfair coins and you knew p andq
and I told you that the first one came
out heads that actually uh tells you
something about whether you're more or
less likely to uh for the next coin to
match it because then matching is no
longer uh symmetric all right so lots of
examples of coin flipping um maybe it
gives you some intuition for some
examples that are independent and some
that are dependent why do we care about
nfir coins uh well one fun uh fact is
that normal coins are not fair they're
more likely to come up the same
orientation that you flip that you
started in then they are to flip over
and there's a nice physics model by perc
diaconus and others uh from back in 2007
that uh computes that for normal coin
flips uh you should get uh about 51%
chance of staying on the same side so if
you play this game with somebody and you
make money
uh please thank us um there's there's
this thing called procession coins when
you flip them vigorously as they say uh
they tend to also spin in this way which
does not cause them to flip over and so
they spend more time a little more time
uh face original versus face upside down
and that gives you a slightly higher
chance uh on the right is a is a machine
that always flips the coin the same
number of flips and so it always
produces the same result that's cheating
uh this theoretical model was recently
verified experimentally for
350,000 real coin flips uh by these 50
authors this was like an online Internet
collaboration uh just completed last
late last year um and uh they compute
maybe not 51% but
50.8% is the thing that they get or
somewhere between 50.6 and 50.9 so it
confirms this this intuition although it
does depend somewhat which currency you
use and uh who you are different
flippers have a different style in
flipping and so your personal
probability may be different from this
one so keep that in mind uh there are a
zillion videos uh online of these like
12-hour marathons just so you know for
verifiable science where you can watch
people flipping coins and typing in the
result and flipping coin type in the
result and anyway that
is uh you can watch this for the next 12
hours or we could go back to lecture um
all right
so some more Concepts uh Independence
between two events is kind of cool but
what if we have more than two
events we do this all the time in this
class we talk about uh I don't know
whether two vertices in a graph are
connected and then we want to know well
what about what if the we want the whole
graph to be connected what if we want
all the the vertices in the graph to be
connected for that it was enough to do
things pairwise we said well if every
pair vertic sees there's a path then
then that's a connected graph that
turned out to be the right answer for
graph connectivity with probability it's
much more annoying so uh one thing you
might Define is what we call pairwise
Independence so uh I guess let's suppose
I have
events um E1
through en n then I'll call them
pairwise independent if
uh for all I and
J uh between one and
N uh
with I not equal to
J um
EI
and EJ are
independent okay of course EI and EI are
not independent that's the it's one of
the overlapping cases uh so EI is not
going to be independent from itself but
it should be independent from all the
others okay this would be the natural
pairwise
definition on the other hand we have a
stronger notion called Mutual
Independence this is more annoying to
verify but it's probably what you
actually want and it says not only if I
take any two events they're independent
from each other but if I take any subset
of of events it's independent from any
one event you could also compare subsets
to subsets that doesn't turn out to
matter so what matters is uh if you fix
any event EI so e uh I is between one
and
n and I take another set set J it's a
subset of the elements from one to
n uh except it should not have I because
we don't want to compare EI to
itself then we want
EI to be
independent
from
uh the
intersection of the
ejs so I forget whether you've seen this
notation you've seen big Sigma for sums
you've seen big Pi for products
this is big uh big intersection for
intersection I guess we ran out of
clever idea clever Greek letters uh so
this is just the intersection of EJ uh
for all Little J and Big
J so we want each event EI to be
independent from the intersection of any
subset of the other events this is uh a
pain to verify for lots of events let's
just think about it for three events for
a little bit so there's on the one hand
we have pair wise Pence where you just
compare E1 versus E2 E2 versus E3 and E1
versus E3 and here uh you do that but
then you also compare like E1 versus the
intersection of E2 and E3 and you
compare uh E2 versus the intersection of
E1 and E3 and you compare E3 with the
intersection of E1 and
E2 okay so twice as much work uh you
check this Independence definition and
you get your answer uh let us do uh an
example maybe first some
motivation let's do some
forensics okay suppose you are at a
murder scene and you find nine pieces of
evidence that's a lot of evidence it's
probably not realistic but let's uh for
sake of example uh say you find nine
markers
that a uh that are consistent with a
particular suspect being at the scene of
the crime uh DNA
whatever uh and let's say Mi is the
event that a randomly chosen
human matches marker I
oh yeah I should tell you another
version of mutual Independence which is
useful uh so
equivalently this is the product rule
form uh for any J that's a subset of one
up to
n uh the probability of the intersection
of EJ
for J in Big J is equal to the product
of the probabilities of the individual
events J and Big J okay this is the
natural generalization of
uh what we had for the product rule for
Independence between two
events okay so back to forensics we have
uh suppose we have a bunch of these
events and for each one we compute we
know their probabil because we know
taken lots of surveys or whatever let's
say the probability of each
Mi uh is equal to 10% 10% chance that
you match this particular marker for
each marker just for Simplicity so say
it's the same for all of them in reality
it would be different so uh You' now
what we care about uh supposing that so
this is just assuming like sampling a
random human uh maybe in the area I
don't know let's say All Humans we're
fair or something we have no prior
assumption then um what we care about is
the probability that all of these come
out as matching our particular human
that we have in mind so we have a
suspect and now we want to take the
intersection of all those events we want
to and suppose that human matches all of
those markers now we want to know what's
the probability that that happen for a
random human and you would like to say
this is 1 10 9 one and billion chance so
there's only like six people who could
match uh but that's only true if these
events are mutually
independent it's actually true if and
only if the events are mutually
independent this is the definition a
definition of mutual Independence well
okay so mutual Independence is a little
stronger it says not only the
intersection of all nine events uh is
the product probability is the product
of the probabilities but also for any
subset of those nine events so that's
crucial uh we don't need that for this
example this example we only care about
the intersection of all nine but if you
want to prove that something is mutually
independent you need to check all of the
events intersected together and also
different subsets of them intersected
together so keep that in mind on problem
sets let's do uh a more interesting
example uh where this matters
okay back to coin
flipping the source of all examples
today uh let's say we
flip three
mutually
independent
coins Fair coins
so we're going to State Independence as
an assumption this is again this is now
saying that the coins are not related
any way they're each flipped completely
separately from each other no impact uh
from one to the
other according to that definition say
but now I'm going to Define some events
that are interesting so a is going to be
uh the event that uh the
first and second
coins come out the same
when you flip
them uh event B is going to be the event
that the second and third coins come out
the
same and event C is going to be the
event that the third and first coins
come out the
same are these events
independent I don't think it's
obvious so we
compute all right let's start with par
wise
Independence let's think about uh say
the probability of a intersect B versus
the product of the probab ities of A and
B so we I mean we did this if you were
strict to just a for example let's let's
start with probability of
a probability of a only depends on the
first and second coins so this is
exactly an example we saw before where
we just flipped two independent coins
and we had this s was the event that the
coins are the same so that's probability
of s that's going to
be2 okay so probability of a a over here
sorry for the relabeling this is just
like probability of s before and so it's
12 okay probability of each of these
events is individually 1/2 so what we
would like is for the intersection of
two of them to be probability a quarter
right 1 half
times2 so let's see if it
is all right now we have to actually
look at the problem so a is the event
that the first and second coins are the
same B is the event that the second and
third coins are the same so this is like
uh this is like coin 1 equals coin 2 and
this is like coin 2 equals coin 3 so if
they're if both of those things happen
if C1 equals C2 and C2 equal C3 uh the
the intersection here is um C1 = C2 =
C3 right
so uh in other words this is the
probability of heads heads
Heads uh I guess I'll WR as a set oh boy
too many too many brackets I'm gonna
have all three types of brackets this is
exciting probability gets square
brackets then set gets curly braces then
an ordered pair gets round parentheses
I'm happy they're all distinct makes it
so much clearer
all right so
this this braced quantity in the middle
here is an event remember events are
just sets over the S subsets of the
sample space so it's a set of possible
samples so uh a intersect B is the same
thing as all the coins being the same
that means headsets heads or tails Tails
Tails okay so that probability we could
rewrite this of course as the
probability of headsets heads I'm going
to Omit some parents here just for
Simplicity plus the prob of tals tals
tals because these are different samples
they are dint from each other and so we
can use the sum rule uh and the
probability of each of those events is
1/8 right it's 1/ half to the power
three it's 1 12 * 1 12 * 1/2 because
each of them is uh independent so this
is 1/8 plus
1/8 which is
one4 and that's what we uh not we
wanted that's funny I make a mistake I
did I
did oh no that's what I wanted right
sorry this probability is a what I
wanted was this for to equal not
probability of a but probability of a
times probability of
B uh these were each a
half and so their product is a quarter
and so that matches so these are
pairwise independent
okay I only computed it for a intersect
B but you should also in principle do it
for B intersect C and A intersect C all
the pairs uh but by symmetry if you
think about this the right way those
will all come out the same okay I'll
just wave my hands at that uh but what
about Mutual Independence so these three
events are mutually in or pairwise
independent but they are not mutually
independent let's prove that or let's
compute that
for that we care
about
uh we could do probability of
intersection I claim it's a little
easier to think about this probability
the probability of C given a intersect B
because we just thought a lot about what
a intersect b means it turns out to be
equivalent to saying that the three
coins are the same
so now what is the probability of C
given that the three coins are the
same prob C says the third coin and the
first coin are the
same so what's this
probability one
yeah remember this this notation means
compute the probability of this event
zooming in the special case where a
intersect B is true so that in the S the
sample space has eight possible spots
it's like a it's like a
cube I guess each axis is heads or tails
there's also a back back face
here uh and what we're saying here is um
a intersect B is just the two extremes
heads heads Heads Tails Tails Tails
maybe you're used to the cube and this
is familiar that they're opposite
Corners like this maybe not um and so if
we zoom into just those two places and
we want to evaluate well what's the CH
what are the chances that coin 2 equals
coin 3 or actually what was it no third
first and third coins it doesn't matter
right what are the chances that the
first coin and the third coin are the
same in these two scenarios well 100%
it's guaranteed if you already know that
all three coins are the same which is
what we figured out a intersect b means
then of course the first and third coins
are the
same okay uh whereas the probability of
C from the without any condition is
1/4
one
half sorry uh just like probability of a
here that was the s that we computed
before so these are different from each
other uh so uh not mutually
independent so this is kind of an
interesting example where you have
pairwise
Independence but not full Independence
not not triple wise Independence and
there's only three events so that's the
most you could hope for uh in computer
science these things actually matter
when you do algorithms and like hashing
in particular it matters how much
Independence you have some hash
functions are pawise independent or
maybe three wise independent or five
wise independent all these things are
important Concepts in hashing for
example but we won't we talking about
that here that's the next class six 121
all
right finally we have well one or two
more interesting
examples okay um big one is the birthday
Paradox or you might call it the
birthday principle but I like I like
living in a contradiction so we'll keep
it as a paradox
it's not a paradox it's just a a
surprising fun fact something where
intuition
and uh does not match
mathematics uh so the the Paradox is
that if you sample a bunch of people and
measure their birthdays you're a lot
more likely that you might expect to get
them to uh to have two people with the
same birthday okay let's call them
Birthday Twins okay if you're actually
Twins then you have the same birthday
pretty almost certainly unless you span
midnight uh but uh are there any twins
in the audience or like both of you are
here okay I didn't think so so then I'm
going to assume that your birthdays are
all independent from each other I think
twins are pretty much the only way to
get dependence um and I'm going to
assume
that you're equally likely to be on all
days and uh that's less true in reality
uh but the the effect of the birthday
Paradox will only be stronger if you
have a non-uniform distribution like we
do in
reality uh
so
um given what you already know in this
class in
particular uh the pigeon hole principle
or the Pidgey hole principle if you're a
Pokemon fan um what how how many how
many people do I need to take in order
to guarantee that I have a duplicate
birthday some Birthday
Twins you remember all the way back to
the pige and H principle
yeah 366 for a 365 day year which is
which uh so D here let for example could
be
365 325 how many days are in a year
all right
um so in general if Nal D +
1 uh then we get guaranteed
duplicate and of course if it's bigger
also and the surprising thing is that
probabilistically so this is for worst
case Behavior I mean if I had n equals D
could be each of you has their own
birthday each person in their own
birthday uh pigeon hole um but that's
very unlikely it turns out and we're
going to about to compute How likely it
is so maybe we can do uh an
experiment uh which is I'm going to see
whether anyone here has the same any two
people have the same birthday if you're
willing to raise your hand so please pay
attention because I want to go through
days really fast so let's start with
August
the most common month so okay among the
August people how many on August
1 August
2nd August
3rd August 4th August 5th August
6th August
7th August
8th August
9 August 10 10 just one August 11 1
August 12th
oh two all right August 11th two August
11th yay we did it didn't even have to
get through August it's because we have
quite a few people here um I don't know
maybe a 100 so uh turns
out for D equals 365 let's assume no
leap years uh
if okay so we had like a 100 people I'm
going to going to warm you up with 23
people 23 people is where the
probability is just barely greater than
50% that there's uh two people so big
difference from
365 uh n equal 30 the probability goes
up to
70% n equal
60 the probability goes up
to 97
% oh
99%
99.4% okay very high uh n equals
100 and he guesses how many
nines
five
six six nines a holy grail of 6 69 97%
it's a lot of nines okay so uh the
probability grows
exponentially uh but in particular this
break even point is surprisingly low uh
23 versus 365 it's a little bigger than
the square root it's like 1.2 time the
square root of 365 is about
23 uh so that's the surprise the Paradox
let's compute it
it's actually similar to something we
computed before in a combinatoric
setting which was the uh how many dollar
bills where uh there are how many dollar
bills are there where none of the digits
in the serial number uh were duplicate
right so we computed that way back when
I'm going to do a similar thing here
similar trick uh let me first set up the
sample
space this is like coin flipping but
more like rolling I suppose you have n
people each of them rolls a desided die
so that means the sample space is just
the set of tpls uh do I want to call it
D no let's call it B for birthday B1 up
to
BN uh
where each bi is between one and D let's
say let's number our days one to D and
this is a curly
brace uh the event that we care
about is getting duplicate birthdays so
this is uh so I'm going to call this s
so what we are interested in is uh the
set of tupal
birthdays where
um there are some two indices I and J
where b i equals
BJ right that's the duplicate birthday
that's the Birthday Twins
this happens with high probability and
is very annoying to compute the
probability of uh but there's this one
trick which you may recall from the uh
when we were looking at serial numbers
on dollar bills let's think about the
complement event so if we look at e
bar this is the set of birthday tupal
where there are no
duplicates that's easier to figure out
so we want to say for all I not equal to
J bi does not equal
BJ okay this is easier to think about as
a process if we think of this going back
to like generalized product rule uh how
we want to know how many different ways
are there to do this where the first
birthday that I choose it could be
anyone I don't care there's D different
possibilities for the birth first
birthday that I choose then uh the next
birthday I choose there's D minus one
options if I want to avoid
duplication okay then the next birthday
there's D minus two options hope play
this is old hat by now you're used to
generalized product rule and uh hard
part is knowing when to stop this is
going to be D
minus n + one I think should be the
right sure yeah this is
generalized product rule
this is the number of
ways and we're assuming that each Tuple
of birthdays is equally likely this was
our assumption everything is independent
and
uniform uh so what we need to do is take
the number of ways this happens and
divide it by the entire size of the
sample space divide it by the size of s
okay so I'm going to divide
this
by uh and this is going to give me the
probability of e bar
here the probability of getting no
duplicate birthdays is the number of
ways to get no duplicate birthdays
divided by the number of different ways
to get birthdays period and that is
just this is the non-generalized product
role how many what is the size of s
here yeah D to the N thank you it's
either n to the D or D to the N you got
to think for a while it's like yeah D to
the N there's D ways for this D ways for
this D ways so it's just the product of
n D's the product of D * D * d n * so
I'm going to write that as D * D * D
times uh D there's exactly n terms
upstairs and there's also n terms
downstairs okay so now I have this
crazy ratio between into products I just
just need to compute it okay this is a
bit annoying um but one big Insight so
this thing is equal
to uh instead of taking this product and
this product separately and dividing
them I could instead take this ratio and
multiply it by this ratio and multiply
it by this ratio and so on right that's
that's why I wrote out this D to the n
as a bunch of D's so I could take them
uh element by element so this is going
to be equal to the product from IAL 1 to
d
d uh of n
sorry there's n different terms each of
them is of the form D minus I over D and
I have an index error so I need to start
at zero and end at n minus
one okay that will give me the right
thing on top top I start with D minus 0
I end with d minus
nus1 okay so this ugly formula actually
gets pretty
clean okay now is when uh it's hard to
evaluate but there's this great fact uh
okay so first I'm going to rewrite this
as uh
product as one this D over D is one and
then we have an i over d in the second
half okay this um turns out to be nice
because uh one - x is less than e to the
minus x e here is Oilers
constant two
roughly and a little bigger than two and
uh if you look at the tailor expansion
of e to the minus X which is something
you may know from calculus it starts
with 1 - x and it's like plus x^2 - x
cub whatever maybe some denominators
there too but 1 - x is actually um well
approximated by eus x uh and it so it's
approximately equal for X
small and if you think about what x is
here uh it's a probability it's less
than one so that's pretty small and so
this will actually be a pretty good
approximation we're going to replace 1 -
x with eus X and then this product will
be easy to evaluate easier
so this going to be
e to the minus I over
D
okay uh sorry not equal this is going to
be less than so it's a good
approximation when X is small but it's
always less than because the next term
is positive at least for x non-
negative it's going to be less than and
so if we get an upper bound remember uh
we're evaluating here the probability of
ebar ebar is like our error case the bad
case we want to show is unlikely so if
we can upper bound the probability of
the bad thing happening that gives us a
lower bound on the good thing happening
uh good thing being uh Birthday
Twins okay we're almost
done with briday
Paradox so uh the cool thing here is we
have a product of
exponentials you may recall that if you
have I don't know e to the X time e to
the Y this is equal to e to x +
y right so if we're this is taking a
product of two exponentials is the
exponential of the sum and more
generally if you take n the product of n
exponentials that will be the same as
the exponential of the sum of those N
Things so this is equal to e to the
sum I didn't leave myself in a room e to
the sum i = 0 to n minus
one
ofus I overd I
guess maybe I should put the minus out
here it's a little
cleaner okay uh and I can
parenthesize like
this over
D because this D does not depend on I so
the sum of I over D is the of is the
same as the sum of I all over D I've
still got this minus F front and this is
our good friend arithmetic sum the
Triangular numbers it's indexed a little
funny usually we think one up to n which
is n * n plus 1 over two uh this is 0 up
to n minus one zero of course doesn't
matter uh so it's really one up to n
minus one so this is going to be e to
Theus uh n * n
-1/
2 and then the whole thing's over D so
we end up with a D in the
denominator okay so this was the
probability that there are no duplicate
birthday and you can see uh it goes down
exponentially this is remember e to the
X is one e to the minus X is 1 over e to
the X
so so the denominator here is increasing
exponentially as we increase
n and the big thing is and so that's why
you get so many nines very quickly out
here but if we're interested in this
crossover point where we get 50/50
chance that there's a duplicate birthday
versus not which is interesting the big
thing that matters is that we have n squ
up here there's a minus n but the big
part is n s and this if we invert it
this is where we're going to get a
square root Behavior so uh let's
suppose uh that this
probability is equal to a half or
roughly equal to a half when does that
happen uh we did some approximation here
with this less than so this isn't going
to be exactly right but it's close uh we
want this exponential
to equal two right so we want e to the N
nus1 over 2D sorry move the E down here
this is all in the
exponent we want this to be equal to two
that's when one over it will equal a
half okay so we take logs of both sides
that's like n * nus1 over
2D equals lwn 2 natural
log uh so we maybe move this over we get
n *
nus1 =
2D L 2 and at this point I'm going to
wave my hands a little bit and say this
minus one doesn't matter too much and so
basically this is a square root so it's
going to be n is roughly the square root
of 2D lwn 2 and so there's this there's
this constant term which is square < TK
of 2 L 2 this is about 1.1
77 so this is about
1.2 to the square root of D this is what
I claimed before if you take 1.2 * the
sare OT of 365 you get approximately
23 if you compute it exactly you get
23 so kind of neat uh in general if you
have D days you need about square root
of D people to get a duplicate this has
all sorts of implications in computer
science
usually in the context of hash tables if
you're trying to if you're randomly
placing people into uh locations pigeon
holes I suppose uh it's once you have
square root of n or square root of D
different people you're likely to get
two that happen to cohabitate unless uh
you know if you choose them
uniformly uh so for example if
you're if you're a cryptographer and
you're signing your
emails uh you would
you want to guarantee that you don't
have uh two emails that have the same
signature because if you did uh someone
who's receiving them and checking the
signatures can't distinguish between the
two emails so that tells you You' like
the set of possible signatures on your
emails to be at least the square of the
number of possible emails you could
write so this gives you a lower bound on
how big cryptographic signatures need to
be in order to be safe just in terms of
whether they're
duplications uh or your
Dropbox and you're trying to sync files
from one computer to another and you
want to compute some hash on the files
on both sides to see do I need to
retransfer this file did it change on
either side it better be that the space
of possible hashes is at least the
square of the number of possible files
otherwise uh you're going to get
accidental uh hash
matches all
right a little more time so let me tell
you about
one uh independent concept um not
particularly related to Independence but
related to conditional
probability which
is gambler's
fallacy gambler's fallacy is it can be
phrased many ways uh but let's talk
about coins because that's that's what
we're doing uh let's
say you do 10 coin
flips and they all come out
heads and I want to
know what's the
probability that the next coin
flip is also heads
what's the
answer uh sorry Fair coin I should
say give you a Fair coin each flip is
independent from the other
flips what are the chances that the 11th
flip is
heads a half I should hope
so uh if you're a
probabilist or if you're a student in
61200 uh the answer is one
half if you're a
gambler probably an addicted Gambler I
mean this is a statement
about human psychology who knows they
say
uh less than a half because I'm due for
a tals don't you
think right you imagine they imagine
that uh hyp hypothetical Gambler
imagines that the coin has memory it
remembers all those heads it got and
when you flip it the next time now
finally it's going to be tals but no
probability is actually a half Gambler
the F this this is something that's
actually false Gambler believes oh
finally I'm due for taals very unlikely
that the next coin is Tails you know I
haven't seen an earthquake in the last
100 years very unlikely I'll see one
this year I mean that may be true but it
also may not be true depends on your
prior probabilities about earthquake
models all right uh and if I tell you
it's a fair coin then you know it's not
true it has to be exactly a half every
single time it's actually pretty likely
to get a bunch of heads in a row now
it's not that likely to get 10 coin
flips in a row that's one in a thousand
roughly um so probabilist just just says
wow one in a thousand cool well probably
the next one is a half okay uh there's a
third type of person which I'll call the
basian and they would say uh maybe it's
bigger than a half maybe you lied to me
and the coin is not fair that's the
other interpretation and if this if you
if you flipped a coin 10 coin 10 flips
maybe it's not enough but 11 or 12 then
you start thinking hm I think there's
something weird about this coin then you
want to inspect the coin see if it's
heads on both sides or whatever so uh
you can formalize this a little bit
using the law of total probability
combined with Bas rule uh in the
following
way I'm going to write this a little
informally but uh the probability of a
head conditioned on getting 10 heads
previously you can split it into two
parts and say uh I'm just going to think
of a simple model either the coin is
really fair or you're cheater and the
coin is heads on both sides those are
the only two possibilities for this
model of course you could consider a
more General model and there's a whole
world about
this so
uh I'm going to call these two scenarios
cheat and
fair and hopefully this equation is
relatively
uh obvious just it's a
mouthful okay everything here is
conditioned on H to the 10 so you can
kind of ignore that part because that's
we're assuming throughout that we have
10 coin flips starting as heads okay and
now two scenarios it could be your
cheating or it could be your fair and
these are disjoint scenarios uh so I can
split things up according to law of
total probability is the probability of
cheat times uh the same thing
conditioned on cheating in addition or
probability of Fair times the
probability of the same thing
conditioning on Fair in addition to what
I conditioned on before so everything's
conditioned on H 10 so you can write
this out and we actually know what these
are they look ugly
the probability of heads with a cheating
coin that is heads on both sides that's
one okay so it's one times the
probability of
cheating of there being a cheat here uh
given H to the 10
plus this probability probability of
heads on with a Fair coin that we know
is a
half times probability of you're using a
Fair coin given that I've seen 10 heads
now these two coin quantities that's you
need more modeling to understand what it
what the chances are to that I'm using a
cheating coin uh given that I saw H 10
heads but you can compute it and so now
you can actually quantify how much
bigger than a half in this particular
model of cheating uh what's the chances
that the next coin flip will be hits but
so fun example and that's all for
today enjoy your Independence Day