Today we'll be diving into some of the
most exciting research happening at MIT
material sciences. how new understanding
of structural processes at the nano
scale allows to control structure and
function at the micros macro scale and
how that understanding
can lead to new performance materials.
So we'll be hearing about several use
cases which demonstrate the strength of
this bottomup approach in solving
industrial problems. We're going to have
three presentations. Each presentation
is 35 minutes. So it's relatively short.
Um but I asked each presenter to leave a
couple of minutes at the end for
questions.
Um unfortunately we only can do
questions for the live audience here.
Those who are following us virtually
can't ask unfortunately
but um I'll make sure to repeat the
question so it will be heard by those
who follow us who follow the live
stream.
Um, we'll wrap up at 1 p.m. and go for
lunch.