Now we'll hear from Chair Van Astrand
who has since I believe May 2023 chaired
the Massachusetts Department of Public
Utilities.
>> Thank you.
Thanks everybody.
So, I really appreciate the opportunity
to be here. Um, as Andrew mentioned,
I've been chair of the commission coming
up on almost two years, May of 2023. Um,
and one of the things I inherited was
what was a pending proceeding in
Massachusetts called the future of gas
proceeding where we issued an order
that's very relevant to what we've been
talking about today. I wanted to provide
a little bit of know I had to learn when
I got here and I I I was a law professor
in West West Virginia University. You
can imagine the kind of the culture
shock of going from a coal state to a
wonderful blue state pursuing a really
aggressive clean energy targets. But
that provides the framework for what
we're trying to do at the at the
Department of Public Utilities and how
network geothermal potentially fits into
that whole message um whole initiative.
So what's what's the statutory
framework? What are we doing? And then a
little bit about the current
demonstration projects, but I think you
probably heard a lot about those
already. So one of the things is the
global warming solutions act of 2008. So
we're going to be net zero by 2050 and
then later on the another subsequent
climate bill says we're going to
establish sector specific emissions
reduction targets for 2025 and 2030. So
that was the clean energy and climate
plan of June of 2022. And this is just
an excerpt from that plan. You can see
um sort of starting off in 1990 and then
to the far right is 2030. The four
various sectors and you can see the
building sector. You can see that
reduction that we need to achieve by
2030. And this is that the the down
below just excerpts that building
sector. So that's kind of that's what
we're striving for in terms of how does
this network geothermal fit into how
does this um the transition the natural
gas industry? What are we trying to
accomplish? It's really trying to
achieve those goals. They're now statuto
the global warming solution act and the
fact that the CECP the clean energy and
climate plan established these sub
sector targets. So pretty much says
residential got to get from 15.3 down to
7.8 and for commercial and the total
percent reduction 47% reduction. And so
that's what we're trying to achieve.
That's that's basically I see my job as
a as a regulator is these policy
decisions have been made by the
legislature. my job is to imple
implement them and try to make that make
that happen. Um so the statutory
framework I think is Ania talked about
this somewhat already but sort of where
where network geothermal comes in. So
the 2021 climate bill expressly allowed
um the gas utilities to propose these
these pilot scale projects. Another
piece that came in the following year
and you may hear be hearing a lot about
um GSAP or gas system enhancement plans
um the gas utilities in Massachusetts
are spending a lot of money every year
to address what is referred to in the
statute as leakprone pipes. So back in
2014, the gas leaks act was passed that
basically provided preferential rate
recovery for costs incurred by the gas
utilities to to repair or address
leakprone pipe. The notion is these are
safety issues. They're risk issues.
Obviously, we have a lot of old
infrastructure in Massachusetts. So that
expedited rate recovery um sort of
removes one of the tools that we have as
regulators which is called regulatory
lag that typically a utility will spend
the money and then it won't recover in
rates for a while could be a year or two
years but that gap provides an incentive
for cost containment. Well, what the gas
leaks act did in 2014 was pretty much
say you file your gas system enhancement
plan with the DPU in October of 31st. we
have six months to go over it and then
May one you begin recovering those costs
in rates. So it provides this expedited
rate treatment to to um address the
leakprone pipe and then so it's very
controversial. We had a GEP working
group that met through a lot of 2023 to
figure out that gas leaks act having
been passed in 2014 focusing primarily
on the safety issue and the risk issue.
Then we have the climate bill that says,
well, we need to achieve these
greenhouse gas reductions. Do we need to
revisit the gas leaks act in light of
the the new focus on reducing greenhouse
gas emissions? And so there's a lot a
lot of work is revisiting that. We
currently have those filings in front of
us. We'll be issuing orders in April,
April 30th with respect to gas system
enhancement plans beginning on May 1.
But a big thing and how network
geothermal fits into this is the 2022
climate bill. I think Ania might have
mentioned this but we can basically one
means of addressing the leakprone pipe
rather than just replacing it with more
gas pipe is to replace it with a utility
scale non-emitting renewable thermal
energy infrastructure aka geothermal
network. So that is a that is a big
benefit in terms of um we're trying to
avoid potentially stranded investment by
continuing to replace gas pipes with gas
pipes that going to last 50 or 60 years.
This says well when you're spending that
money on your GEP plan you can actually
use a thermal energy network would be
one way of addressing the leakprone pipe
and avoiding that stranded cost by just
putting more natural gas infrastructure
into the ground. As Ania mentioned, the
2024 climate bill um actually makes it
specific that a gas company is allowed
to get in the business of of creating
these thermal energy networks. Um and I
also mentioned um we're trying to
address this obligation to serve very
controversial in the states but it's
basically as as you can see from Ania's
chart if if you have a a comp a customer
who does not want to give up their gas
how can you make the case we're going to
substitute this network geothermal for
their for your gas very controversial.
So, they took a shot at addressing the
obligation to serve um at least with
respect to new hookups by allowing the
consideration of adequate substitutes.
In other words, you might not have a
right to gas service if they're adequate
substitutes. They're non- gas
substitutes. Um but we're still working
our way through this. Um and then that
eligible infrastructure investment in
these G GE programs is not just
replacement and also includes
retirement, which means we can actually
take out the pipe. One way of addressing
the leak prone pipe is just remove the
leak prone pipe because you're going to
convert you're going to put customers to
elect electrification electrified
solutions whether it's ground source
heat pumps or air source heat pumps.
So when I got here in May of 2023 I
inherited this docket. It had been
started in October of 2020 and I think
the record had closed in October of
2022.
I thought I think we need to probably
issue an order in this in this docket.
But it was um basically um what is going
to be the pathway for the natural gas
utilities? How do we achieve these
greenhouse gas reduction targets which
the global warming solutions act and the
2021 climate bill require us to achieve?
And so we issued this order uh basically
ident setting forth this regulatory
framework and what we basically landed
on was electrification is going to be
the primary pathway and that's airsource
heat pumps ground source heat pumps
which includes the geothermal energy
networks and the way I described what we
did in that order was basically point
out to this clean energy back the clean
energy framework that I had in the first
couple of slides. We just want to put
the LDC's, the local gas distribution
utilities on a pathway to achieve net
zero by 2050. And so part of that is is
in a couple months, April 1, each LDC
has to file a climate compliance plan.
In other words, show that you are on a
pathway that's going to get you to net
zero by 2050. You're going to achieve
those those sub limits that I had that
on that other slide. The other big thing
we did in 2080 was um put the burden on
the LDC, the local gas distribution
companies. Before you make any
additional investment in natural gas
distribution infrastructure, show that
you considered a non- gas pipeline
alternative. And that could be it could
be energy efficiency, it could be
electric air source heat pump, ground
source heat pump, network geothermal,
but basically we want to avoid stranded
costs. We want to avoid putting
additional pipe in the ground. So that
was a big element and right now the the
the natural gas distribution companies,
they're all working together. They're
going to be filing with us an agreed
upon natural um non- gas pipeline and
NPA framework and because we need to
start applying that as as they're coming
in and asking for new additional
investment. Did have you consider the an
NPA that non- gas pipeline alternative?
And then the other thing I think they
can Ian mentioned um so March one
roughly a year from now then we're
requiring each LDC to file a target
electrification project. In other words
try to take out a decommission a portion
of a gas service territory in favor of
of air source heat pump ground source
heat pump electric or network
geothermal. Um you have to work with
your applicable electric distribution
company because in Massachusetts we have
some utilities that are both gas and
electric. Sometimes Eversource provides
the electric and National Grid provides
the gas. You got to come in together.
Um, National Grid actually filed a
target electrification demonstration
proposal in December of 2024 for the
towns of Lminster and Winthrop where
they're going to try to decommission
part of the gas service territory in
favor of electrification. But that's
going to be a big part of um sort of how
we manage this this this gas transition
is the climate compliance plans and the
role that these that these um
demonstration projects are going to play
and that's where the obligation to serve
piece is so challenging because when you
look at the chart that Ania had you know
all it takes is one one customer who
says I don't want to give up my gas and
you're not able to take out that you're
not able to decommission the pipe and
the number and the numbers just don't
work all that well if you can't
decommission the pipe. type. So that's
why states are struggling with how can
we how can we substitute um the
basically a another means of providing
the essential service of heat instead of
instead of natural gas.
So, one of the things that um it's it's
helpful along the lines of of of NEO's
discussion of the demonstration projects
because the 2021 climate bill
specifically authorizes the gas
companies to file with us demonstration
projects proposals and and it it lays
out some criteria. So when we look at
these demonstration projects when
Framingham comes in, whenever source
comes in with the Framingham project and
National Grid comes in for the Lel and
and Franklin Fields projects, these are
the criteria that we are going to apply
and in determining the rate treatment,
the rate recovery of those of those
costs. Um pretty straightforward. Must
have reasonable likelihood of
facilitating substantial reductions.
That goes back to achieving those
greenhouse gas limits. We don't want you
don't want you to blend in hydrogen and
RNG and we need to use a third party
evaluation. And then we consider the
reasonleness of the size, scope and
scale. In other words, do the benefits
justify the proposed cost. And another
key element is the calculation of
benefits must include the calculations
of the social value of greenhouse gas
emissions reduction. That's going to be
a good way of when you're looking at
those costs and benefits that you're
going to put a price on carbon,
basically the carbon that you're
avoiding by taking out that natural gas
infrastructure and replacing it with
with something else. So, real briefly, I
think you're going to hear a lot about
the Framingham project that Eversource
has done. There's a phase two that was
awarded a preliminary grant, I think, by
the Department of Energy, which is
caught up in all this stuff that's going
on in Washington DC right now. Um, n so
that was approved in the in the
Eversource rate case from from 2020,
DPU19120.
And then National Grid had a separate
proceeding where this is before I got
here, of course, but authorizing up to
15.6 million for four network geothermal
projects. the first of which was in l
and I think national good has announced
that they are they are terminating that
project um I think just the level of
participation wasn't as wasn't as great
the numbers didn't didn't work very well
but they've also filed for the Franklin
field apartments with the Boston Housing
Authority and so that's that project is
is moving forward and then we'll be
looking like I say we'll be applying
those criteria then we consider the rate
recovery treatment of these of these
demonstration projects so with that I'm
happy to answer questions Sir,
whatever.