hi I'm Marcy black and um I got all all
three degrees at MIT so it's good to be
back home um did you know that
biomanufacturing over half of it is
dedicated to purifying out unwanted
impurities in the process and these
impurities can be toxic in even very
dilute quantities this leads to
unnecessary delays and costs in bringing
drugs and Therapeutics to Mar Market I
founded a co-founded Advanced silicon
group to help lower the barriers for
Diagnostics so that everyone has access
to good
Healthcare So currently the biofarma
manufacturing industry measures protein
using a technique called an Eliza
technique now Liza can sufficiently
measure the proteins but it's far from
ideal it's time consuming it takes about
4 hours of skilled labor time and it's
expensive it costs about $400 per test
and only measure one protein per test
we're developing a small silicon chip
that can do this 15 times faster and 15
times lower cost the end user will
simply put a drop of solution onto the
chip rinse it and then place it into our
handheld testing system to measure the
protein concentration of
Interest so this Market as I mentioned
for protein sensing is very large um and
there's a lot of pain points in the
market right now so there's a lot of
people developing new technology to try
to fill this Market need we do three
things different the first thing we do
is we do an electrical measurement
electrical measurements are are less
expensive than Optical um and if you
want to do a quantitative measurement
you really need to convert it to
electrical anyways in the end and also
electrical we we really good at
measuring very small signals with
electrical measurements so it can be
more sensitive the second thing we do
different is we use silicon and and as
you'll learn tomorrow um silicon has a
wide body of knowledge behind it um this
allows us to make use of this knowledge
and pack many different different tests
onto the same chip so we can measure
many different protein concentrations in
the same
test we can Multiplex also because we're
silicon compatible we can scale up to
manufacturing very easily and increase
the throughput pretty much as as much as
we want um the oh in addition because
and silicon we can make it very small
and the cost of biosensing is dominated
by the antibody or the or the aptamer
that's used to detect the the protein um
and since we're going small we can make
it low cost because we can use less
antibody the third thing we do different
is we use Nano structures or nanowires
and these have a very high surface area
to volume ratio that makes them very
sensitive to their environment and can
lead to very sensitive detection
so I already mentioned the Liza where
we're faster and cheaper um but there's
another uh protein test that's common
that I bet everyone is used and that's a
like a covid test a rapid antigen test
um those are useful but they have a
limit in how low a detection they can do
and also doing quantitative measurements
is difficult with those types of tests
so our sensor will combine the vantages
of both of these without the
disadvantage um and there's a lot of
markets for doing protein sensing a
pretty much any type of measurement that
you need that would be needs to be
sensitive multiplexed Rapid or low cost
our sensor might be a good fit for um
we're currently focused on the biofarma
manufacturing but we also have Partners
in other areas as well so for example
we're working with a company growing
nerve tissue and they want to use our
sensor to measure for biomarkers to tell
how well the the nerve tissue is growing
um we're also working with a company uh
in India the cave Krishna Institute to
help them measure tubercul dormant Tu
tuberculosis in their patients and we're
also collaborating with several biofarma
companies uh Boston bib in the Boston
area and also another large biofarma
company both of which are interested in
using our sensor for measuring host cell
proteins and this is the most important
slide of the deck um we're here because
we're looking for partners we're looking
for people to uh scale up semiconductor
manufacturing with to to develop
antibodies or optimar with us custom
electrical testing biomedical device
design and biom manufacturers but also
anyone who could use a test a protein
test that's lowcost Multiplex and Rapid
um I have a couple of my uh a couple of
our amazing Engineers are here we have a
a booth and I welcome you to come visit
us and please join me in lowering the
barriers for Diagnostics so that
everyone has access to good Healthcare
thank
you thank you Mery