so thank you all for joining today's
seminar it's a pleasure to have
Professor shabari uh dos with us here
today from Penn State
University so Professor dos is the
professor of engineering uh in the
department of engineering science and
mechanics and has many other affiliation
within uh Penn State University he
joined uh Penn State in
2016 and prior to that was a
post-doctoral research scholar and den
an assistant research scientist at argon
National Laboratory his group is focused
on 2D microelectronics for monolithic 3D
integration biion inspired sensing
neuromorphic Computing and heartb birth
security some of which today to we're
going to learn about we're very excited
uh and Professor Doss has received
Awards including the young investigator
award from the United States Air Force
office of scientific research as well as
the National Science Foundation career
award so with that um feel free to ask
questions throughout whoever is
listening to us online please type your
questions I will moderate on your behalf
and ask the questions uh thank you for
joining us and we're very excited to
listen to your talk
thank you forage for the nice
introduction uh it's a pleasure to be
here and uh talking to all of you about
our uh some of our most recent work on
uh as you can see from the title the AI
for 2D materials and 2D materials for Ai
and I will see you know a reason for me
to come up with this particular uh title
but before I go into the technical part
of the talk uh maybe a little bit about
myself um uh I did my um all my
schooling uh back in India uh I grown up
in a town called Kolkata which is in the
eastern part of India uh then I did my
undergraduate also from India in jadur
University in electronics and
telecommunication before coming to the
United States to do my PhD from puru uh
and after that I spent couple of years
in the Argon National Lab as a
postdoctoral scholar and as an assistant
scientist and then I kind of joined pen
as a tenure track faculty I have been
there for almost 8 and a half years now
um I would also like to acknowledge all
my funding agencies uh uh and uh
definitely all my students who are doing
all the hard work uh uh and really an
amazing group of you know motivated
students who uh you know kind of are the
main pillar of you know whatever uh
success that comes to the group um so my
group has the focus of looking into
neuromorphic or brain inspired Computing
uh that's like you know one of the
fundamental principle that drives our
group and we use mostly 2D materials for
that uh although a lot of principles
that we are using can be also applied to
oxide based transistors and even you
know paros materials but our Focus has
been 2D materials and I will tell you
you know some of the key advantages of
2D materials so uh we also look into you
know specific C found in animal brains I
will give you a couple of examples today
so we designed this brain inspired
circuits so and you know more recently
we have started looking into 3D
integration with the you know uh the
idea that you know brain ultimately is a
three-dimensional structure and if we
can do computation in the
three-dimensional architecture you know
it can actually bring a lot of Energy
Efficiency uh to to the uh Computing and
then finally you know we also look into
machine learning uh of course one of our
idea is to make the next generation of
artificial neural network deep neural
networks energy efficient because
they're not at the sustainable path but
we also use their power in order to kind
of mitigate some of the challenges with
the 2D materials and that is the part I
call you know the AI for 2D materials
and today's talk will actually start
with that aspect how do we use the AI to
kind of uh uh enhance the performance uh
of a 2d material based sensor in this
case we call it a graphine tongue uh
which is used for you know you know kind
of robust chemical analysis of course
the tongue doesn't look like this this
is again AI generated by Chad GPT um the
tongue looks much simpler and not that
uh exciting over there this is like
simple graphine transistors you know
very small you know even smaller than
probably a quarter uh uh and we use this
particular you know graphine device for
a specific application uh which is you
know related to you know really food
because food is a very complex chemical
you know if you think about the juices
you know the milk you know whatever we
eat is actually a very complex chemical
so analyzing those chemicals using this
platform gives us a little bit
confidence about the power of both
machine learning and the hardware piece
that we are
developing now when it comes to food you
know I think the inspiration comes from
you know the best sensor out there for
food which is probably our tongue right
and the tongue is kind of quite
interesting because if you think about
the test receptors in the tongue there
are only five different types of test
receptors which can broadly categorize
you know sweet shower you know bitter
Umami which is a taste of meat and salty
right but if you think about the tongue
in general we can figure out the
difference between a chocolate cake and
a cheesecake both being sweet right or
you know if you train your tongue then
it can also differentiate between very
shuttle differences between different
types of wine right so so although our
test receptors the hardware piece is
very limited the gustatory cortex is
actually pretty elaborate which helps us
to kind of get you know more ideas about
you know similar types of
chemical one more important thing you
know what we kind of got very motivated
about is the fact that you know in the
animal kingdom no two tongues are
identical you know I think my tongue and
your tongue are completely different but
if we are given a pork or a chicken to
eat both of us if we are meat eater
we'll be able to tell what is a pork and
what is a meat right so in spite of
differences between the tongues which is
the variation from from one device to
the other one Hardware piece to the
other we can categorize the same you
know thing that we are eating and this
is kind of going to be very important
going forward because most of the
nanomaterial based sensors do not really
make it to the commercialization because
of this problem of variation right
device to device cycle to cycle so the
question is since the nature can do it
can we adopt the same principle for our
chemi sensors as well now there is one
more important piece about the tongue
right the question is whether human
beings have the best tongue or not what
differentiate you know two different
tongues in the Kingdom Animal Kingdom so
the five types of test receptor is
common across all the tongues but there
are also number of test receptors that
matters and if you look into a chicken
the chicken has got only 25 total test
receptors although there are like all
five types okay so five of each so this
is not the best tongue of course the
chicken only feds on very limited kind
of food right the the cat has
400 the dog has got
2,000 human has got 10,000 but the
question is are we the best tongue out
there and the answer is no the best
tongue is actually a catfish the catfish
has got 200,000 test receptors and its
entire body is actually test receptor
and what it allows it to do is to find
out very small changes in the underwater
aquatic environment to find a predatory
action you you know because aquatic
environment is chemically extremely
chaotic and yet it can get a very high
sensitivity and selectivity because of
the large number of test receptors it
has got which is nothing but having a
lot of information from the same
environment so more test receptors
allows you to collect you know more
information so now we kind of look into
the same principle and design our
graphine based electronic tongue which
is simple graphine transistors and one
thing which is quite interesting about
graphine is once you put a liquid on top
of this graphine there is this electric
double layer that forms at the interface
and that carries the chemical signature
of the species that you're putting on
top and that then get translated into
the IV characteristics of graphine I'm
pretty sure that you have all seen this
kind of graphine
characteristics uh and then as I will
tell you you know we use this entire
machine learning in order to kind of
analyze this entire IV characteristics
to identify different chemicals now let
me state to the problem with this
graphine chemi sensor so here I have a
single graphine device and we do pH
sensing and you can see wonderful nice
results for each pH the characteristics
is distinct and therefore we can say
that we have made a amazing pH sensor
okay and this work has been going on for
a long time you know but the problem in
next day you know if you measure the
same device okay the device
characteristics has drifted a little bit
so your sensitivity has now gone down
and if you measured it with a acoss
multiple different sensors that you have
fabricated you have even more device to
device variation and now you can see
that between ph45 and six everything
appears to be the same so if I give an
unknown solution right and if you
measure it you measure a direct point
you won't be able to tell whether it is
ph4 or five so we lost our sensitivity
to the fact that there's a lot of device
to device cycle to cycle manufacturing
to manufacturing variation the question
is now how can we mitigate that now one
question we could ask is that should we
look into the direct point you know as
our indicator of a change in the
chemical solution or should we look into
some of the other parameters there's a
huge list of parameters that you can
extract right the minimum current the
maximum current the onoff ratio because
it's a transistor so you can really
extract a lot of information but even if
I do that and look into you know how
each of this parameter kind of changes
as a function of you know all this
device to device variation I can
probably go ahead and rank them and I
can find that oh okay V has the rank
five but ID is rank one and you know
that's good but then even with the first
rank you know figure of Merit I don't
get to 100% accuracy because it is still
drifting okay now what we could do is we
could do some very simple machine
learning where we say that okay instead
of looking into one parameter at a time
why don't we combine you know three
different quantities let's say the top
three and there you see that you know
you get you know clustering of the data
this is K nearest never algorithm and
you get to you know almost 100% accuracy
once you get you know five different
parameters that you look into at the
same time but the question is you know
here all these parameters that we are
extracting are based on human derived
knowledge right but are we the best to
you know extract information from you
know a data set so what we did is you
know we kind of thought about instead of
you know extracting this D Point minimum
current ourselves why don't we give the
entire IV characteristics to the
convolution neural network which is
generally very good in order to
features and then see you know whether
it can classify the different PHS or not
and you can see immediately the accuracy
goes to 98% without us going into all
this elaborate exercise of finding out
which are the best figure of merits
right and this is in spite of having
those device to device and sensor to
sensor and time to time cycle to cycle
variation right so now this is all good
but when the question that we ask is
that okay we all know artificial neural
network or black boxes they perform very
well but we never know why do they
perform very well so then we looked into
things called these shapely features to
identify which part of the graphine
characteristics the network is focusing
on in order to really do such an amazing
job in terms of being a pH sensor and
what we found is that if you can compare
you know the ph4 you see that these blue
regions are all activated for ph4 while
other regions are activated for
different pH values which means that the
network is not looking into a single
parameter but into a part of this IV
characteristics in a very shuttle manner
because the weight for each of these
point is different and there is no
mathematical definition of you know how
do I describe a part of these
characteristics and this is precisely
why the network works so much better
because it looks into very shuttle
changes in the IV characteristics which
is beyond mathematical description right
so we get a very high accuracy because
of you know this this interesting aspect
and you can do is you can actually take
you know three4 chip train it the device
on those and then test it on a
completely newly fabricated chip and
still you get very high accuracy number
which means that you know you don't have
to make billions of chips and on each
chip you have to do separate training
right then then it will not be
commercializable so that's also very
good that you can do the training uh uh
on a different chip and then testing on
the other then we thought about okay pH
is a very simple topic right because the
pH gives you really observable changes
in the IV characteristics but what about
milk and adulterating it with water
because when you adulterate milk with
water the PH does not change so if you
have a pH sensor you will not be able to
detect adulteration of milk but then
what we did is we did the same principle
we measured a lot of device with
different milk adulteration percentage
and then you know train the machine
learning model and look at the accuracy
of it being telling you what is the
adulteration percentage now adulation
percentage is not really a
classification problem it's more of a
regression problem because you don't
know whether you will be adult rating
with 10% or 20% or 3. 5% of water and
then we also trained a regression based
model and we found that still it gives
you an accuracy within 2 to 3% of milk
adulteration right the same principle
and you can actually expand it to you
know different Coke of coffee you know
milk and one thing you notice is that
it's the same exact Raffine device
without any functionalization because
generally when we try to develop a
sensor for milk we need to know what in
milk makes it milk and then go ahead and
functionalize your graphine device or
what in Coke makes it Coke and
functionalize we are not functionalizing
this we are simply collecting a lot of
data from many different graphine
sensors and then training the model and
telling them this is scog versus this is
uh you know zero sugar versus Pepsi
right because these are chemically very
similar right and yet the network is
able to learn and
distinguish and does a very very good
job in there okay and then we look into
even more deeper problems let's say for
example different fruit juices and as
they degrade over time because now it is
just not the juice but also the
different bacterial or fungi activity
because the the reason a juice degrade
is different for different juices right
orange juice May degrade because of
oxidation processes but you know
pineapple juice May degress because
there might be more fungi activity
happening so if you really need to know
whether a juice is two day old or three
day old first you need to know the the
chemistry that goes on in degrading that
fruit juice and then try to kind of
Target that particular molecule and then
figure out whether it is degraded or not
we are not doing anything like that we
are simply collecting data from
different juices over different days and
training the machine learning model we
use a different types of network
architecture and then it can tell you
you know whether what juice it is and
also you know how old it is right so
this is where I feel like the power of
artificial neural network can really
mitigate a lot of real life problem with
all the Nano sensors that we are
developing because now I don't really
need to make the perfect sensor I can
deal with imperfection by taking help
from this neural network right this is
the part where I kind of say that AI can
be useful for 2D material so now I will
switch gear so this is the AI for 2D
material if you're interested you can
you know go and read our paper we just
published this a few months back uh now
I'm going to 2D materials for AI right
and in this context as I told you that
you know we are uh not only looking into
synapses and neurons that's how you know
the basic abstract of artificial neural
network is but we are focusing on the
unique architecture found in different
animal brains because these animals are
really very good in sensory computation
and I'm going to give you couple of
example the first example is this Locust
uh and Locust you know fly in a swarm
and a single swarm can consist up to a
million Locust they all fly together but
never collide with each other right so
they are really naturally avoiding
Collision so therefore we can really and
and there's a single neuron in the brain
of the Locust which is called this
lobula giant movement detector neuron
which actually helps it to avoid
Collision right so a single neuron is
avoiding collision and that's what makes
it extremely energy efficient right and
we have flying drones autonomous cars we
have you know uh collision avoidance
systems today but they're very bulky
energy and efficient so can we learn
from Locust and design something for
collision avoidance so now let's see you
know what the Locust does in order to
avoid Collision so it has a compound eye
you can see that those photo receptor
cells so whenever an object approaches
the Locust eye it uses two kind of
stimulus one is the angular projection
which is Theta which increases as the
object comes closer and the other is the
angular velocity which is Theta Prime
which is just the differential of the
same information now this D now this
lgmd neuron has got two branches as you
can see the blue dendritic branch takes
the angular velocity information and
creates an Exciter response which means
that as the object comes closer the
response increases which is quite
natural but what the Red dritic Branch
does is quite interesting because it
takes the angular projection information
which also increases as the object comes
closer but it creates an inhibitory
response look at the red curve so the
response goes down as the object comes
closer and that is counterintuitive you
know why would a response go down when
something is about to collide with you
then what the lgmd neuron does it kind
of multiplies the two and creates a non-
monoton firing sequence where the firing
frequency becomes maximum right before
the Collision is going to take place and
that gives the Locust enough time to fly
out in a different direction right so
you can see it's a very simple
architecture so we thought about okay
why don't we go and simply you know
mimic this architecture so we kind of
did that and I'm going to go through
this so we created this inhibitory
module excitory module and the Escape
module using our 2D material based
devices so so let's say for example we
have a car and the car is approaching
your sensor and as the car comes closer
the intensity of the headlight that is
you know falling on the sensor is going
to increase and you can see over here if
the car is moving faster then the
intensity go high earlier if the cars
are moving slower the intensity will go
higher later right but this information
alone is not good enough for you to
avoid Collision because it's a monotonic
information so what we do is we actually
used a circuit which is kind of inspired
by the locus but walks in a very
different principle so this if you can
recollect it's a inverter okay which
means that you know if if your input is
low the output is high and if your
output is high the input is low it's
just an inverter and generally a seos
inverter will not respond to light if
you shine light on a simos inverter it
will remain the same right as long as
you're not changing the biasing
condition to that inverter but now this
inverter is very special because it has
got this mos2 transistor in the bottom
right and this mos2 transistor re
responds to light and whenever you shine
light on this MOS it's a direct band Gap
material you have photogenerated
carriers electron hold Pairs and then
this holes get strapped into the
underlying oxide and that changes the
threshold voltage of the mos2 transistor
now as the threshold voltage of this
lower transistor is changing so will be
the inverter response you know in a
static condition just by Shining Light
the inverter response keeps changing and
as you keep shining it the invert you
know you can see that the response is
going towards the left so after some
time the state of the inverter changes
from high to low as a threshold
crossovers so this is almost very simp
similar to an inhibitory response
although the light intensity is
increasing the response of your device
is initially high and later low and
based on how fast the car is appearing
or approaching you get a earlier versus
a late response so now we have created
the inhibition we still have to create
the Exciter response so how do we do
that you just cascet two inverters the
inverse of a inverse will give you now
it's a buffer circuit and if you shine
light on the same thing now it will
create an excit response where the
response is low initially and eventually
becomes high as the light comes closer
and closer so now I got both inhibition
and excitation the final job is to
multiply the two and that's easy I
simply use an and gate because and gate
is a logical multiplier and if I do that
I get the spike and the spike happens
earlier for a faster moving car and
later for a slower moving car so it's
kind of using the same algorithm that
the Locust uses but designing it using
all solid St devices using in sensor
Computing capability to get to very low
Power Collision of ir system right so
that's one example where we can actually
learn from nature now let's look into
the second example the second example
going from Vision to hearing so here we
are looking into know burn o because
this is one of the uh you know you know
burn o hunts in complete darkness so it
relies not on his eyes but on its
hearing capability to find a
you know or or even I mean escape from
the Predators um but you know the reason
you know it can localize sound with the
Precision of almost 1 to 3 degree and I
do not know I mean I kind of got excited
about our years after you know learning
about barow is that know why do we have
two years why not one for hearing you
know and one thing that is true about
having two years is that you know
whenever a sound approaches from a
particular direction it reaches the 2
years with a certain time Gap you know
for example if the sound is coming from
right it will reach your right ear first
and the left ear later so there's a
finite time difference between the time
reaching your two years now the problem
is this time difference is generally of
the order of hundreds of microc for bar
which is a smaller head to maybe a
millisecond for elephant which has a
bigger head right because the velocity
of sound is pretty fast right and our
head is too small so now you're are
trying to solve you know this temporal
problem which is in hundreds of microc
using neurons which can only fire every
few millisecond right that's a very
difficult computational problem to solve
so how do we do it you actually convert
or use a neural architecture that
converts the temporal information into a
spatial map so how does it do it it has
this you know uh organization of neurons
it uses two types of neuron these red
neurons are called The Coincidence
neuron you know they kind of fire every
time they receive the information from
the top and bottom neuron at the same
time while the black ones are called the
delay neurons they simply convert the
acustic information into electrical
spikes and brings it to the uh you know
the delay neuron so let's look into this
demonstration now let's say for example
the sound is coming from Straight Ahead
it will reach both ears at the same time
and it will propagate the same distance
and The Coincidence will occur at the
middle but if the sound comes from the
right side then it will reach the right
ear first there will be longer
propagation in the branch below and
shorter in the top and therefore the
coincidence will happen at a different
location so so just by knowing where did
The Coincidence took place you can tell
which direction the sound came from
right it's a very interesting
architecture to do sound localization we
actually went ahead and did that but in
this particular case we use a special
transistor uh which we call a split GED
transistor uh which does not have only
one gate but it has multiple Gates and
there is a small gap between the gates
and you can see there are you know many
gates in this transistor so what happens
is that you know this transistor could
only be turned off
if you have the voltages applied to the
same color gate at the same time so the
top and bottom electrodes work as a
coincidence neuron okay but at the same
time you can see there is a small gap
between these top and bottom electrodes
which means you can never completely
turn off the transistor right because
there's a small gap which is not under
gate
control so but you can see that for the
blue one I can turn it off better
compared to the green one because of the
fringing electric field right so what
happens is that you know whenever you
get the spikes at the same top and
bottom neuron there is a drop in the
current right but the magnitude of the
drop depends upon which color this
coincidence took place so this is almost
like a mixed signal device which does
digital computation in the vertical
Direction and analog computation in the
horizontal direction to mimic the
architecture found in the bar O's brain
and with that we can now get to you know
very high High Precision in these
devices okay we can get down to almost
like you know 0.01 degree precision and
we are also not restricted to acustic
wave you can use the entire
electromagnetic you know radiation
spectrum because you just need the right
transducer to convert that into
electrical spikes and then use the
architecture for
detecting so this is another example now
I will uh switch gear a little bit so we
do a lot of these animals you know for
example we look into octopus for
multisensory integration if you're
interested you can look into this paper
uh we also look into you know uh
dragonfly for probabilistic computing
you know we have done a lot of work
using 2D materials to get you know all
these goian characteristics you know
stochastic Computing you know uh and and
in in many computational problem we
don't need an accurate solution and
approximate solution is good enough and
that is something you know Nature has
already figured out even before Bas came
out with the base theorem uh so we kind
of mimic those principles in these kind
of devices um uh but in the for the last
part of my talk and I'm going to focus
more about the the future of computing
you and why 2D material is something
that we are using for the future of
computing and trying to do all the
neuromorphic with 2D material I mean
which we all know that we are
transitioning from finfit technology
very soon into gate rollar around and
eventually to C fet or you know Nano
sheet technology and the main idea
behind that is that you need to have
better gate electrostatics more gate you
put around your transistor the better
your transistor performance will become
so you not only make the transistor uh
you know oxide very thin but you also
try to put it you know gate all around
but in order to do that you also need to
have the channel being very thin right
and you cannot really make silicon too
thin because of the fact that the
mobility of silicon kind of goes down
the drain when you make it you know a
monol layer or 1 nanometer thick you
can't even have a manufacturable
technique to make 1 nanometer silicon
although very recently in iedm uh I
think they were demonstration showing
that 1.5 nanometer of silicon films can
be made so so our competition gets
tougher but we are not going to use the
hope with the 2D material but the idea
is that the 2D material can offer you
much higher Mobility numbers so the
trans or better transport in the channel
at the similar thickness you know which
your silicon or any bulk material cannot
provide So eventually if you think about
2D material that the ultimate choice for
any
transistor now uh even if you kind of
make the transistor very very small
ultimately you're going to be limited by
the lithography tools right I mean you
cannot make a transistor which is you
know two or 3 nanometer in length that's
not going to be possible with the to
graphy Tool so so ultimately at the end
of the day you have to start doing you
know 3D integration uh because you have
to start stacking devices on top of each
other if you really need to get more
transistor in the same footprint so 3D
integration is probably the ultimate way
to reinstate M law and I think in might
Professor Kims group is working a lot on
this 3D integration uh now this is very
difficult to do with silicon logic
because of the fact that at the back end
I cannot really get high performance
silicon uh and therefore I lose you know
know all the wonderful quality that the
Silicon provides uh U although this is
something that has already happened for
the memory industry because for the
memory silicon is just a readout Channel
I don't really care about the high
performance from those memory devices so
you can really stack these uh and this
is something that is not possible
currently with you know silicon
technology or it's going to be extremely
expensive but the 2D material gives you
an opportunity to do the 3D integration
because you can really you know either
you know grow these 2D materials on a
different wafer and keep transfer ing
them and making transistors so we really
not bound to the substrate uh and that
is literally what we are kind of
exploiting uh and then I think 3D
integration as I told you is just not to
make more transistor you can also start
putting different functionalities in
every layer right from sensing storage
logic and that way you can mitigate this
Von bottleneck or you know this memory
wall problem of shuttling data between
you know different sensors and uh
compute units which kind of cost a lot
of energy so 3D integration is good for
both more more as well as more than mod
application and U although you know
industry is looking into a different way
of doing this uh heterogeneous
integration using packaging technology
they're putting different chiplets
together using interposer uh but
eventually to have the highest density
of interconnection you have to go
monolithic 3D integration because of the
fact that when you do through silicon VR
the VR Dimension can only be you know T
of micrometer maybe down to a micrometer
but when you do it in a monolithic
manner you can really have uh the VR as
small small as your transistor
interconnects and that's why you know
monolithic integration is the best way
of getting highest transistor
interconnectivity which is the key for
3D integration so this is something that
we are doing at pen State we are working
with two types of 2D material our focus
is currently on for the channel we are
working on N type mos2 and ptype tungen
selenide these are right now grown on
sap substrate at 800 to 1,000
Centigrade epit uh we get very good
quality 2D material over 2in w
very soon we're going to have capability
of doing it on the 4in Wafers and then
we go ahead and transfer this material
using this pmma assisted uh uh transfer
process which still requires more
optimization but the the end story is
that we can actually start making you
know thousands and thousands of devices
to start looking into their uniformity
yield you know and variation from
devices to devices so so this is our
first you know we kind of published this
paper last year where we were able to
for the first time demonstrate you know
monolithic integration of you know 2D
transition s here you are seeing a chip
which has 30,000 transistors in two
tiers each in each tier has got 30,000
transistors the total number is 60,000
we were able to also scale these devices
down to channel length of 45 nanometer
we can go down to 20 nanometer it's just
the eeld kind of goes down with the
shorter Channel than devices and we
don't even stop at only stacking two
tiers of devices we can stack three
tiers of transistors on top of each
other and and you can see the clear
Advantage the transistor footprint
Remains the Same while I'm you know
simply increasing the number of
transistors I kind of stack them on top
of each other and as I told you now you
can connect your transistors in the
bottom and the top tier by the VR which
is sitting right next to the transistor
right that's the key advantage of doing
uh 3D integration in a monolithic manner
uh we actually measured a lot of
transistors these are 10,000 transistors
in tier one uh and you can see the
distribution of these devices across the
wafer performances in this type of
devices were not as high uh towards the
end of the stock I will talk about some
of the high performance transistors that
we have made uh these are tier one
transistors this is tier 2 transistors
what I'm saying is that the 2D material
is maturing to scale right we can
actually now demonstrate large area
large number of
transistors uh these are scale devices
scale devices show more variation so we
need to have a lot of improvement in our
lithography in order to get to you know
scaled devices with more
uniformity um and these are some
cross-sectional TM images showing you
know MOS all the three tiers these are
the tier one tier 2 tier three devices
for the nmos but we can also do it with
tungsten selenide and then it is a pmos
device right so we have both nmos and
pmos stacked in three tiers so that's
the first uh round of our demonstration
and remember each of these device also
has a memory integrated with them
because we are having this flash kind of
you know memory architecture where we
have alumina halfa alumina where the
small band Gap material can charge
straps uh uh sandwich between two large
band Gap material when you apply
voltages so these are all in memory
Computing uh capable you know devices so
uh you can see the memory ratio memory
retention and to some extent also the
memory endurance in these devices right
and these devices I told you earlier are
also you know sensitive to light so you
can also use them as photo sensor so now
you have integrated logic sensing and
Computing in all these 30,000
transistors which are there you know
across you know these different years so
that is really you know both transistor
scaling as well as functionality scaling
now moving forward I mean I also like to
thank for of my students because this
was not trivial at all because the total
number of lithography step that it
required was actually 38 you know and
doing this number of lithography St in
an academic environment and making sure
everything works is uh really
non-trivial you know we can I can simply
say we putting transistors on top of
each other but it is not trivial and a
lot of you actually do this every day so
you will be able to appreciate it
more uh so now next step is that okay so
now we have got uh uh uh unipolar
transistors stacked on top of together
can we do seos capability so we found
that tungsten C is a very interesting
material because if you put nickel
contact and if you do alumina capping
you get a very nice n type
characteristics from tonson selenite but
if you change it to padium as the
contact and haia as a capping layer then
you get a very nice P type
characteristic so now I have both n and
p characteristics from the same material
so can't we start building you know 3D
seos capabilities so here is our first
demonstration of of a 3D CS now we are
going Beyond inverter we are trying to
make more complex circuits in this case
an nand gate which has two nmos
transistors in the tier one and then
they're connected through this VR to the
two top transistors which are P type in
tier 2 so now we can start looking into
really the advantage of 3D integration
and you can see over here that the VR is
connecting transistor to transistor this
is something you cannot do with through
silicon via technology or heterogeneous
integration right so the main advantage
of 3D kind of shows up over here so and
you can see each transistor also has
this memory so it's like inmemory
compute capability with you know 3D
SOS uh and then you know we also
demonstrated other kinds of logic gates
one thing I would mention the yield of
this uh logic gates were pretty poor
okay only 10% to 20% of this logic gets
actually worked but they worked uh so
this was the first demonstration of a
you know 3D seos capability uh and as I
told you that you know I mean industry
is taking this heterogeneous integration
aspect and today they have been able to
achieve you know the VR pitch of 1
micrometer uh after so many years of
investment uh uh and the in this IO
density is a key parameter that's going
to be benchmarking you know going
forward for the 3D and you can see even
in an academic environment or first
generation or these are not even gen
zero devices maybe gen minus one devices
can achieve you know integration density
which can compete with you know the the
uh 3D packaging technology so that's the
advantage of Monolithic 3D inte
integration and then as I told you right
this doesn't have to stop in only you
know seos transistors we can actually
now Place graphine devices on the top
tier which could be good for chem
sensing application and mos2 devices in
the bottom tier for logic so you can now
do near sensor Computing so here is a
chip which has you know graphine
transistors on top and mos2 transistors
in the bottom you can see look at the
cross-sectional TM uh and you can see
that the graphine devices are sitting
right on top of your mos2 transistor so
you can really do now you know in sensor
on near sensor compute uh with this chip
we did a very quick demonstration we put
a liquid droplet and as a droplet
evaporates you know the concentration of
salt in the droplet changes that changes
the response of the graphine device in
an analog Manner and then we took that
analog information and digitized this
using some mos2 based comparator circuit
so very simple application but you can
see the potential of you know
integrating heterogenous material now in
this 3D
stack um so that was you know another
example this also so we I think we just
published uh two months back and then
again it doesn't have to only restrict
to just 2D material as I was telling at
the very beginning of my talk you can
also start stacking you know 2D and 3D
materials you know like for example a
lot of work that you know my
collaborator Professor Jalan is doing at
University of Minnesota has to do with
Paro Sky's material and he is able to
grow this using this hybrid MB technique
on a sacrificial layer which is latis
matched so therefore you get a very good
quality of sto film but now you can
dissolve olve that stonum oxide in water
and you can create a nanomembrane of
this peroxides so now you can start
taking this peroxide material and start
stacking them with the 2D material and
in that way enable newer functionality
so in this kind of a device we found
that we have something called incipient
fero electricity U where you get this
counterclockwise estasis in the uh mos2
gated by stto we got some you know polar
order from the second harmonic
generation measurement but one thing
which was not very good was you know the
tension was very poor because an f f you
should have two polarization state that
are stable but because it's an incipient
ferroelectric material you know it kind
of depolarizes very quickly but what we
found is that you know this material
when you cool it down to low temperature
you know the memory state becomes
extremely stable so we went out to 100
Kelvin and even 15 Kelvin and we found
that it could be a very good alternative
for cryogenic memory because in you
cryogenic condition you know charge St
memories may not work as well and for a
lot of quantum applications you will
need you know cryogenic memory devices
so we went down to 15 Kelvin and we
found that this device is actually an
excellent memory device at low
temperature with you know good long-term
retention uh uh switching speed is less
than 20 nond reasonably fast uh and you
can also store you know almost 64
discrete States in a single device it's
almost like you know five bit to six bit
of memory stored in a single device so
so that's also another interesting area
that I think is going to be absolutely
you know interesting going forward so
you can climb kind of see you know the
importance of 3D integration you know
and what we have been able to accomplish
so far now I will you know for the last
uh 10 minutes I'm going to talk a little
bit about high performance devices
because all the devices I showed you so
far are pretty you know low in
performance right I mean tens of
micrograms of current to hundreds of
micrograms of current so and I'm talking
about know replacing silicon with this
2D material so you can see that the
requirement for the high performance
devic is that you need to need to have a
more than a milliamp micrometer on State
current for both n and p and your
parasitic capacitance has to be low
because parastic capacitance has been a
under uh you know studied Topic in the
2D community and then one more important
thing is that the low power application
requires your supply voltage to be less
than 1 volt your off current has to be
zero or low at VG equal to zero and that
is something you know not really
addressed in the 2D Community we will
see a l large onoff ratio but the
devices gets turned off for a very you
know negative VG for the nfed and very
positive voltage for the pfed okay so
and if you have that you can never
design circuit okay so circuit designer
will never be interested in 2D material
so that's going to be very important of
course you need to reduce device to
device variation otherwise you cannot
make circuits either so we have started
looking into this so This are our most
recent results on mos2 uh I think right
now there's a consensus that antimon is
the best contact material for uh 2D
materials I mean b month is also very
good here we using gold and that's why
we don't reach as high performance as
like milliamps per micrometer but we get
to consistently 300 micr per micrometer
on 1,000 devices right so large number
of devices now we have been able to get
to very high on State current and we
have been able to reduce the off current
at VG equal to zero the onoff ratio
always existed with the 2D material but
what we could not do is to bring down
the off current to low values at VG
equal to zero so we were able to do that
with doing some growth optimization and
you can kind of see that the device to
device variation has also gone down
quite a
bit and then you know you can do all
this uh uh statistical plot and you can
see that you know the threshold voltage
variation is actually quite quite low
and if you compare it with the existing
silicon technology it is getting there
it's still not there I will show you
some more slides on that and then when
you compare it you know this is a plot I
wanted to draw your attention two that
you see I mean many devices show very
high on State current but they cannot
turn off their device at VG equal to
zero because the right corner for you to
be in this extreme right hand plot is
the you know upper uh left hand corner
right because you need to have both high
on current and large onoff Ratio or low
off current at VG equal to zero and that
is something that has not been really
achieved okay you can get high on
current but you cannot turn off this
device so threshold engineering becomes
extremely important but you can see that
you know we have been able to get to the
corner where tsmc and Intel are I mean
tsmc in is still a little bit better
than us okay and our champion device get
up to almost like 300 microns for
micrometer current so that is nfet now
what has been struggling in the
community for quite a bit is a p fet
right P fet performances have been even
poorer but we have now been able to
achieve similar performing P fet so our
pfet currents are also now of the order
of 250 to 300 micr per micrometer and we
have been able to do that with you know
something we are using called the anod
doing so we have defect passivation
because defect was actually really
creating a lot of problem with stun and
selenite with anod doping we able to
passivate the selenium vacancies and we
able to get to very high performance
device to device variation is also quite
low um and you can see that even for the
pfed the pets are off at VG equal to
zero because that's what I need to make
circuits and again when you compare comp
it with all the other literature now you
can see that you know I mean uh this is
probably the best result in literature
for the p fet uh because we get both
very high on current as well as large
onoff ratio right so now we have both
the high performance n MOS and pmos with
the right threshold voltage so now we
can start moving into making more
reasonable circuits so we have started
now building uh using pdks so now we are
using the layout design that you will
use for a particular technology node so
we are using right now 200 nanometer 192
nanom technology node and we are now
designing all the circuits like nand n
and you can see they work all with 3vt
and here I'd also like to mention that
because a lot of people are looking into
oxides your gate voltage is generally 20
volts 30 volts remember our vdd has to
be low for both The Source drain voltage
as well as the gate voltage unless you
do that your circuits are not going to
work right so you also need to scale the
oxides so all the data that I showed you
were with uot numbers of 2.3 nanometer
so we have been using you know 10
nanometer or 5 nanometer halfam oxide
and we are able to get down to really
you know low voltage operation of this
transistor and that is why we can now
make the circuits operate so these are
nand and Norgate zor gate you know which
requires more transistors uh
multiplexers uh D flip flops because you
do not only need you know combinatorial
circuits you also need sequential
circuits right for you know to design a
computer so we can make D flip flog we
can also make srams right these are the
very basic component of a uh building a
computer using 2D material so now we
have all the basic component so what
lefts to be done is to make the
computer so here is the first
demonstration of a 2d cosos computer
which has all the sequential and
combination real circuits you have D
flip flog arithmetic logic unit and we
are using a single instruction set
computer
this is the ultimate version of a risk
processor risk processor is reduceed
instruction set processor if you go down
to one instruction right U uh you can do
all operation it just takes longer time
okay and we are also designing it for
one bit this is not a 32-bit computer
right I mean that will be too much so we
design this entire computer so here is
this entire computer over here which has
72 nmos and 72 pses you can see the pmos
and nmos sitting right next to each
other right now uh because we can you
know transfer them and make all these
devices on ultra thin
oxides and this actually works okay so
we can actually make a single
instruction set computer work and here
are the you know the uh timing diagrams
of this 2dcos computer this is the first
demonstration of a 2dcos computer uh but
then we fail in something and this is
what I wanted to you know highlight this
uh look at the speed of these devices
they're working at hundreds of microc I
don't think Intel anybody will be
interested if the speed is so poor right
but then you know why are we limited on
speed we are not limited on the speed
from a fundamental device point of view
we are restricted by the parasitic
capacitances which our community has not
really paid a lot of attention to okay
we have a lot of you know measurement
capacit big pads you know that we are
using for measuring these devices so we
thought about okay uh that we figured
out so what about you know we do some
you know modeling of the devices so uh
this is the industry standard you know
BC bulk model which was developed by
Chang mingu right from UC Berkeley and
the industry uses this model so any new
transistor technology you should be able
to match it to this Bim bulk model and
you can see that our experimental
characteristics matches very well with
the Bim bul once we have it we can start
doing spice simulation right because
then that will tell me you know if I
were to reduce all my parasitic
capacitances what will be my projected
performance and we found that if you can
get down to a F2 farad of capacitance
your speed actually becomes T of PC
right so today we are not limited
anymore by the transistor performance
but by the parasitics so 2D is catching
up with the Silicon even in terms of the
circuit it's just that we have to now
take care of this aspect and we did it
for all the different logic gates uh and
then eventually we thought about okay
why don't we compare this uh 2D single
instruction computer made out of 2D
material with silicon finfet right so
kind of used the most advanced silicon 7
nanometer you know pdk and you know all
the BCM bulk model for that and you can
kind of see this these SS TT and FF are
just simply we take the slowest nmos and
slowest pmos from our 2D and FF means
you know fastest C and fastest nmos from
our 2D and the TT is the typical one
which is the median value and you can
see that the 2D instruction computer is
only 10x worse than the most advanced
silicon finfet devices and remember our
devices are still 200 nanom to 100
nanometer Channel length our eots are
still not 1 nanometer so we really have
a lot of room to improve our 2D
performance and really get to the
performance of silicon devices so we are
not too far and we are only 10 years
into real exploration of 2D materials
especially the actual exploration has
probably started in last three four
years right so there's a lot of Promise
in 2D material and that's why we are
using 2D for doing all these St with
that I would probably end you know these
are all our Publications so uh the the
2D computer paper just got accepted
earlier this week in nature as well so
I'm very happy that that is going to
come out uh uh but if you're interested
uh uh you can look into these papers but
I think you can see our main philosophy
is to go towards 3D integration with
high performance and low power 2D
devices and maybe also bring into the
mix you know some of these 3D nanom
membranes to develop you know new
paradigm of sensing Computing and
storage which is inspired by you know
biological brains animal brains uh to
really satisfy the need for both more
more and more than more with that I
would like to thank you and I will be
happy to take any
questions thanks for a great
talk thanks a lot so we have time maybe
10 minutes for questions so any
questions from the audience while I'll
look
online hello uh absolutely inspiring
talk I want to change my research field
um I guess so uh when you present it it
looks so simple but I guess how how
robust and how much knowledge do you
need from a theory and from the AI side
like were you able to train up a
graduate student or did they have to
almost have a completely separate skill
set to be able to integrate within your
group and do these calculations uh I I
think one thing which is important is to
have you know diverse range of graduate
students so I think some of my graduate
students do have a little bit of
background in machine learning uh and
then you know are also students who have
more you know more senior students who
have background in mostly the device
aspect but I think this kind of a
marriage is very important uh for them
to do the projects like this so so I
mean is that your question I mean what
kind of expertise you need in order to
do this thing I mean uh would you would
you need um a more expert group to be
able to like let's say I collected that
data would I need an expert group to be
able to apply that uh ma learning model
or do you think it's got to a point
where an amateur could I think machine
learning models are probably the easiest
part in this uh entire thing I would say
because you know I mean they're all
available you know you know you can
really I mean today any undergraduate
that comes out can write all this python
code they probably know this thing
better than even me you know I mean but
I'm saying the developing expertise in
this kind of machine learning that we
are doing probably doesn't uh require a
lot of background in machine what you
need is a lot of vision for what you
want to do with this data
you know for example when we thought
about I mean there's a lot of followup
work we are doing in this graphine
sensor work right where we're trying to
identify uh can you you know train a
machine with the existing data on some
contaminant with some known solution and
get the graphine device of the machine
learning model to learn the signature of
the contaminant and then test it in a
completely unknown solution right so
these kind of problems I think which
were almost
unimaginable you know 5 years back are
now possible with the advancement in the
AI part because all these models were
not as much available back then so
there's a power of this machine learning
tools or all this chat GPD and whatever
Evolution has happened is can now drive
or mitigate a lot of challenge that we
Face generally with this 2D material or
in general nanomaterial Community is
what my feeling is so we want to bring
that expertise in this field which
already exist and pretty welld
developed awesome thank you
so one question from our online audience
considering the potential for large area
synthesis which 2D materials do you
believe offer the greatest potential for
immediate or near-term impact in
electronics and sensors and on that
topic can you maybe also comment a
little bit more on the processing you
did to the 2D material to get to your
computer again no excellent question I
think U uh well there are so many 2D
material so at pen State we have uh made
sure we focus on couple because if you
start focusing on 10 different 20
different 2D materials become then you
are completely defocused so we have
identified mos2 because it's probably
one of the most it's probably the
easiest one to grow uh it has a lot of
you know air stability uh it's very easy
to work with so there therefore there's
a lot of optimization that has gone into
you know developing mos2 as the end type
2D material it's also much easier to
make end type contact to mos2 so mos2
becomes a Natural Choice P fet still is
a long-standing uh challenge in the
field so very recently we have got some
exciting results with tungsten selenide
there are other candidates like moly
selenide mide tellides are more
difficult to grow and also not very
stable because they tend to oxidize so
selenide strikes a balance between the
stability how easily it can be grown and
then you can do some doping technique to
get to highp Fed performance so that's
why we have focused on these two
material but you know I mean tomorrow
somebody may come up with a very new
material so recently there's a paper I
think in nature materials about bisat
oxyselenide that material also seems
like promising because that has a native
oxide which is very high quality these
2D materials don't have a native oxide
like this silicon right So eventually we
have to also think about integrating
gate dialectric so that remains a
challenge all the data that I have
showed you over here are back gated
transistors eventually the computer has
to be made using topg transistors top
gate will require you to have a very
good dialectric on the top and basil you
know I mean the nucleation on this 2D
material is going to be tough so you
have to innovate over there how to get a
very high quality dialectric as a top
gate uh we want to minimize defect in
this tuning material but if you
eliminate all defects then you also
cannot nucleate very well on the uh on
the basil plane of this 2D material so
there has to be a lot of work that has
to go in in order to also optimize that
we're also looking into a lot of uh 2D
dialectric because then they can be put
right on top of the the 2D materials
with a good
interface uh so there's a lot of
optimization that has gone into to get
to this stage but I think there's still
lot more engineering challenges remains
to be solved thank you any other
questions um as graphine Purity
increases do you foresee uh like n&p dop
or dopes uh graphine as a option for p&n
type oh I think graphine is definitely
not a choice at all
uh because it doesn't have a band Gap so
I cannot turn off my transistors right
so even
doped uh you can dope it doping will
change the threshold the direct point
right the doping is not going to open up
a band Gap so unless I open up a band
Gap in graphine I mean graphine is uh
mostly not very useful for transistor
application it's very good for sensing
though thank
you uh I was curious about the electron
mobility of 2D materials as you stack up
this uh structures to into 3D and you is
it is it really the mos2 type of uh
material that uh improves the electron
mobility
and would you need to I guess another
way of asking how would you deal with
the terminal profile of a 3D mos2 and
how you would cool it down you know yeah
I think excellent question so Mobility
numbers right now what we get is of the
order of 10 to 20 in mos2 and I think
similar number for wsc2 theoretically
projected numbers are higher so we
should probably be able to get there as
we reduce the number of sulfur vacancies
in this films and have to reduce the
grain boundaries and things like that so
Mobility is probably as long as I get to
100 I'm happy because you know once you
make the devices too small Mobility
doesn't matter that much anyways what
matters is the contact resistance and
the on current so as long as I have a
low contact resistance in a scale device
I should be able to get to high
performance and then when it comes to
the thermal management that's an
excellent question I mean we are
struggling to manage the heat in a 2d
chip so in a 3D chip the thermal
management is going to be even worse so
there's a lot of interest in looking
into you know heat spreaders right so
innovation in materials which can at
least spread the heat if you cannot
completely eliminate it uh or you know
you do some kind of a design where you
do not really have a lot of hot spots so
your transistor or the architecture
design can be some uh Innovation can
come over there um so but that managing
the heat in a 3 tdic is going to be an
emerging
topic thank you for your talk and my
question is during the talk you
mentioned that the yield of the devic is
10 to 20% do you have any idea how to
improve no I think the yield of the
devices is high so I think mos2 devices
we can get to very high yield you know
sometimes even 100% yield when we are
trying to do this more complex circuits
in a 3D architecture then the yield goes
down and I think this is something you
know I mean we are in Academia so as you
know I mean we Face a lot of challenges
you know because we transfer the
material sometimes the transfer doesn't
go very well is the fact that you know
these 3D Fabrications are uh not only
easy but also very expensive so you
cannot just go and simply repeat it just
to get a 100% yield right so I think the
proof of concept we demonstrate that it
can be done and then I think once it
goes to the industry level I think the
yield problem should be able to be
manage thank
you let's thank our speaker again for a
wonderful full talk