good morning everybody Welcome to the
mpg primer
today um just a reminder that we are
looking for the next MPG co-chair so
someone to stand alongside me next year
help pick speakers help pick topics help
run the show um if you're interested
there's a QR code you can nominate
yourself or also someone that might be
you think would be good for the job
this is a thank you Kevin in the
back he does a lot of work in the behind
the scenes of the mpg and today is his
last day so let's give him a thank you
last day
Applause today we're supposed to have
Max Holbrook talk about
epigenetics um and something came up in
um Yan who with 13 hours ago spilled in
the spot so uh saved the day so you guys
could all be here learn some science and
eat some great food um so thank you
again so so
much yenu is a PhD candidate in Jason
ber Roos lab in the stem cell and
regenerative biology department at
Harvard he's also affiliate member here
at the Bro Institute prior to his
Graduate Studies he received his
Bachelor of Science and biology from
tingua University in China and broadly
his uh interest in rare Gene regulation
aging and computational biology um and
today he's going to share um some
epigenetic insights from a new paper
they just published uh tracking protein
binding to Sis regulatory elements with
print please ask questions along the way
there's two microphones set up in the
middle or you could also raise your hand
and I'll run over to you so thank
you uh can everyone hear
me okay awesome um so thank you all for
coming here this this early uh and uh
I'm very happy to be here today uh my
name is Yen and I want to share with you
a very recent story published by our lab
uh where we developed a new technology
more precisely a more a new
computational method called print that
allows you to track The Binding of
regulatory proteins in C regory elements
across the genome with single cell
attack seek so I want to start by
talking about the genome we know that
the human genome is very big but only a
very very small portion around 1%
actually encod for proteins so the
coding region is actually a tiny portion
of the genome and the rest of the genome
is actually non-coding and then within
the non-coding genome we have in human
genome around a million regulatory
elements such as promoters and enhancers
and these elements are actually uh
playing a very big role regulating the
expression of genes depending on which
genes are expressed in which cells so as
a result it has become one of the
central questions of modern day U
genomics and you know even biology to
study how the AC activities and
functions of promoters and enhancers are
regulated and I think to this is a
really broad question so really to start
think about uh to answer this I think
it's important to think about what
happens on the molecular level we know
that the majority of the genome is
actually very inaccessible chatin
meaning that they are very Compact and
they're you know packed with
nisms but these small regions like the
uh not sure if I can see M curser uh
these promoters and enhancers when
they're active they look different
because if you zoom into one of these
regions you see of course you have ncms
on two sides of the region but you also
have in the middle a nucleis free region
usually devoid of
nucleis and this region is much more
open than the the rest of the The genome
and just because there's new nucleis
there now you can have transission
factors uh
comb and then uh when you have the right
combination of transition factors they
recruit uh the in poies and I want to
emphasize here that uh every
transmission Factor only buy a very
small subset of all of the uh C regory
elements and then every C regory element
is only Bound by a specific selective uh
combination of TFS so it is this
combinatorial and selective Bing that
eventually determines the expression of
our genes I also want to emphasize the
size of things okay this regulatory
elements so let's say a one promoter
enhancer is usually around a few hundred
base pairs wide
every nucleis will occupy the space of
around 150 base part of DNA you know
from ranging from 100 to 200 and TFS are
so much smaller transission factors
usually bind 10 to 20 base parts of DNA
and ares are slightly
larger so as you can see that
every every C is in fact like an intra
molecular machine right with all of
these parts working together to
determine this function so something
that we been wondering in the lab is
what is The Binding dynamics of all of
these factors how do they dynamically
work together to determine the function
of the C and I want to give a special
highlight to these little guys here so
transtion factors we know that transtion
factors are truly the master Regulators
of self fate and function they're so
important we know that with the overe
expression just a few TFS we can
actually convert one sulfate completely
to another sufate so for example if you
over Express uh the these four TFS the
yamanaka factors can convert a fiber
blast to induced plent stem cell or if
you over Express these three TFS in the
bottom you can convert a fiber blast to
a heart muscle cell a cardom monoy so
it's very cool and as we know that they
also play a big role in disease
Development A lot of times you see
disregulation of TF driving the
progression of disease and of course
during natural development n
differentiation uh you also see TFS
everywhere so in our lab we really like
to use use the hematopoetic system as
the model system uh just because you you
can see from the hematop stem cells here
uh to the progenitor cells in the middle
and to the more differentiated cells on
the bottom there are so many self fate
decision points and almost every one of
them is governed by a specific set of
TFS so you can see TFS are everywhere
and they're so important in biology so
as a result for decades people have
really wanted to figure out where HTF
binds which findinding size are in the
genome and what Target genes they
regulate and although people have been
trying this for decades as it turn out
even up until today if you want to
systematically map The Binding of every
TF in the genome it is still very
challenging so people have developed you
know a bunch of different methods to
solve this problem uh chipstick is
considered to be the gold standard of uh
a mapping TF binding basically you use a
antibody against your TF to pull down
the TF along with the genomic DNA that's
Bound by the TF and you sequence that
part of the DNA and you know uh which
regions of the G genome are bound um but
as you can imagine every TF requires a
different antibody and then not every TF
is a good antibody so this this method
although it's very accurate it
definitely lowers the number of TF you
can study usually you can only do a few
TFS at a
time another way to map transmission
Factor binding site is through
computation methods and uh just to give
you one example we know that uh
transmission factors when they buy to
the genome they recognize a specific DNA
sequence every TF recognize a different
uh DNA sequence we call it the TF
recognition Motif or just short for TF
Motif and then we also know that TFS
mostly bind to open regions of the
genome like the active promoters and
enhancers so a thing that people have
been doing is that they scan the DNA
sequence in those promoters and
enhancers for the presence of those
motifs and they say oh this is a
promoter I scan a DNA sequence I found
oh there's a recognition Motif by this
TF so it's probably Bound by this TF and
as you can imagine this is lower
accuracy because in fact a lot of the
places with the TF multif are actually
not bound by the TF uh and uh but this
eventually allows you to study a higher
number of TFS uh so as you can see the
the need for the field is actually to
develop a new method that can give you
both accur mapping but also allows you
to study a much larger number of
transmission
factors so that's actually the central
goal of our project we want to develop a
technology to accurately map the The
genome wi binding of a very large number
of transission factors ideally hundreds
or even a more than a thousands and we
know the TFS have interplay with u with
nucleis so we also want to be able to
map The Binding of nucleis at the same
time in the genome so how do we do this
uh we decided to use a taxic
footprinting uh and let me just explain
a little bit how this works so for those
who are not familiar with a taxic a
taxic is a method to measure uh
chromatine accessibility basically to
figure out which parts of the chromatine
uh are uh open and accessible and we do
this by treating chromatine with an
enzyme called uh tn5 which is a
transposes what TMI does is that TMI
will cut chromatine to create double St
brakes and liate sequencing adapters at
the same time to the end of the cuts and
then the enzyme has a really nice
property that it only goes to the open
regions of the CHR like the promoters
and enhancer and cut those regions and
then for the rest of the genome it
doesn't really cut so when you sequence
the ends of the the resulting fragments
and map them back to the genome you get
a track like this so this track
represents the cutting density and you
can see that for the majority of the
genome for example like this region you
get very low cutting Den because they're
packed with nucle and the enzyme is
having a hard time cutting it but you
see very small parts of the genome like
this one this one this one having very
high cutting density because they're
open regions without nucleis and enzym
is having a good time cutting them so
this is a taxi you can see basically
what it tells you is where the promoters
are and where the enhancers are in the
genome so with fopr we use the same
experiment same data but look at it at a
much higher resolution so what we do is
that we would zoom in into each one of
those regions like I said There usually
a few hundred base pair wide and we
quantify this cutting at single base
pair resolution and then when you do
that you'll realize within every
so-called open region uh The Cutting is
not uniform you get ups and downs and
then you'll see that the positions that
are bound by uh DNA binding proteins
like TFS just because the protein
sitting on DNA it's protecting that
short stretch of DNA from enzimatic
cutting so for example this part if you
see the cursor uh this part underneath
the TF is protected so it's showing a
lower than expected cutting density
compared to the two flanks and then you
will see a valley like a like a dip in
your signal and it kind of looks like
when you step onto the stand you leave a
footprint right so we call this a method
footprinting and call the shape like
that value the footprint of the DNA
binding TF um and then the data is very
noisy but if you have a good statistical
model you can actually detect or
evaluate how significant this depletion
of cutting is and then you can give
every position a footprint score and
then you will see that the positions
with higher scores represent The Binding
of an object physically protecting that
piece of DNA and like we said before
every TF recognize a pretty specific DNA
sequence TF Motif so once you know
there's something bound here you can
examine the DNA sequence underneath and
say oh now I know this is more likely
Bound by this TF and not that TF so you
can assign each footprint to a specific
Tif and uh if this works uh it would
allow us to accurately track the bun of
both nucleis and a lot of different TFS
with one single axic
experiment so we uh started the project
and uh try to figure out how to do this
and realize one thing that's very
interesting was that uh imagine you have
a toxic data set you see all of those uh
open regions you zoom into one of them
and what you see is that the footprints
really come in various different sizes
just because the objects are different
sizes theisms uh for example like this
one oops the nucs are very big like I
said it covers around 150 base pairs of
DNA so it would leave a very wide
footprint but the transmiss factors they
only binds like 10 to 20 base parts of
DNA so leave a very narrow footprint and
what we realize is that uh you can
actually detect The Binding of all of
these different objects
simultaneously uh just by scanning
through different window sizes when you
run foot
printing for example if you use a very
large window to detect the center versus
two flanks depletion of cutting and you
scan it through the this whole region
you will see the signal the footprint
signal of a large object here and a
object here uh corresponding to the
nisms but when you scan through this
region with a very narrow window uh like
this one you will specifically pick up
the signal of a small object filtering
out the larger objects so you can do
this you know across a whole range of
different window sizes and we call this
multikill for printing because it allows
you to separately detect the The Binding
of uh objects with different sizes so
when you stack the results together you
can get a map like this where on the
x-axis you see the genomic locations of
each object on the y- AIS you see the
physical size of the object and the
higher up you go on the y- axis when you
see a signal the bigger the object so
essentially uh what this gives you is
something almost like a you know
molecular level microscope that allows
you to uh resolve the local organization
of chromatine you will see a big thing
here a middle thing here and a smaller
thing here so um does this really work
we first the first thing we tested was
simulated data uh so what we did was
that very simple we simulated Footprints
of objects with different sizes and
different shapes uh in the computer uh
and this of course will be much cleaner
than real data and then we run that
multiscale foot printing approach here
and you will get a result like this so
remember x- axis is where the objects
are Y axis shows the size and you
clearly see that with a very small
object like this one you will only
detect signal very low on the y- axis
using the the very narrow windows with a
very big object uh you will see signal
much higher up on the y- axis because
you're using the bigger windows and you
can even see that if your footprint is
having a weird shape you see a very
distinct pattern and this almost says
that the the footprint the multiscale
footprint pattern can be used as a
fingerprint of like how the DNA and the
protein
interacts and we're really encouraged by
the results so we decided to you know
test this on real data so we test it on
um a taxi data from a cell line hg2 and
just to show you one example region uh
this is a promoter uh around 800 base
pairs uh in this cancer cell line and
here on the multiscale pattern you can
see in the middle you have uh you have a
a footprint that's very low on the y
axis meaning that it's a small thing and
on two sides you see two very um strong
Footprints much higher on the y- axis
meaning that they're big big things so
if you align this to the reference
genome you realize the center object is
right on top of a ctcf motif at the
center of a ctcf chip SE Peak meaning
that is very likely to be a ctcf by name
and two things on the two sides are
aligning perfectly with hism chip data
meaning that they are nucs so you can
already see that it res resolves the
local organization of chitine that you
get big things and small things and we
explore this uh a lot and realize the
objects with different sizes different
shapes or even different binding string
all leave very distinct footprint so
it's like every object has its own
fingerprint in this pattern and also
very interestingly I really really want
to emphasize is that a lot of TFS don't
leave Footprints so either because they
bind the in too transiently were too
weakly that don't really protect DNA
Enough From The Cutting and they're
invisible TF we don't see them in our
data so when when I first saw this I was
really frustrated uh but later I'll tell
you how we found out a way to map The
Binding of the invisible TFS through a
rather unexpected uh
approach so another question that we
were wondering at the at the time was
that now that we can detect The Binding
of these different proteins what is the
genomic syntax governing their
organization in other words we always
say everything you need is written in
the DNA sequence does the DNA how much
does the DNA sequence determine where
the nucleis are where the proteins are
and we try to answer this question by
actually doing something very
straightforward which is to train a deep
learning model that uses only DNA
sequence as the input and try to ask the
model to predict Lo the local multiscale
footprint patterns basically saying can
you just by looking at the DNA sequence
predict where the nisms are where the
the TFS are if this model can even be
trained or like have some performance
that means there's useful information to
learn from DNA right uh so we try this
and it worked surprisingly well so I
will show you one example result uh here
this is one promoter in the same s line
and then on the top you see the observe
the footprints from a tax seek you see
uh one nucleis uh
here uh and another nucleis uh here and
then in the middle you see one two three
I guess I can use this cursor it's
better uh you can see one TF 2 TF 3 TF 4
TF 5 TF some so the TFS are in between
the nisms and then uh this region is not
was not included in the training set so
the model has not seen this region
during training but once the model is
trained on other regions of the uh the
genome and then you just give the model
the DNA sequence within this region and
ask it what where do you think the the
objects are the model will predict uh
the pattern in the bottom on the bottom
where it will say I think there's a nism
here I think there's a nism here exactly
matching the actual observed pattern and
the model actually knows where the the
TFS will be like one two three four five
so that was really remarkable and kind
of surprising to us uh but the coolest
thing is not to make the predictions
because you know we already have the
footprints from the observe data the
most exciting opportunity was to
actually ask the model to explain how it
was making the prediction you can ask
the model how which parts of the
sequences you're looking at to make
these predictions and then we do this by
calculating something called a sequence
attribution score for each base pair
basically it's a score that evaluates
the importance or the contribution of
each base pair to the final prediction
if a base is very important you'll have
a high score uh so if you do that for
the whole region uh the mod you'll get a
track like this so this is a track of
the score and you will see that the
model is actually not using oh sorry the
model is not using every single base
pair to make prediction it is actually
prioritizing to use you know these
spaces these spaces these spaces to make
predictions and if you look at what
those short stretches of DNA are they
are actually exactly TF binding motives
so for some reason the model through
learning is be is able to capture um the
TF the arrangement of TF motifs and use
them to predict where the objects are
and and uh even cooler thing is that
instead of looking at the whole region
you can of course focus on specific
objects so let's say uh this footprint
Alpha uh comparing to chips we know that
Alpha is on top of a ctcf binding size
so this is very likely
ctcf uh if you ask the model how are you
predicting that there will be a
footprint there at Alpha the model says
for this one I'm just looking at these
baces which is exactly the ctcf motif uh
looking at the motif I know there will
be a TF which is kind of trivial but uh
what's interesting is that for footprint
beta if you ask the model how are you
predicting Forint beta uh the model will
say oh Forint beta you know we know that
it's uh on top of the n22 uh bing side
the model says I'm looking at the nf22
motif but also this motif of nfyb next
to nf22 I'm using both of them to
predict the binding uh the presence of
this footprint and that's very
interesting because fyb is one of those
and in this case one of those invisible
TFS if you look at the observed or the
predicted there's no a visible footprint
here so meaning that nyb itself probably
binds DNA not strongly enough to leave a
footprint but the model has seen enough
sequence footprint dependency like
relationships it is able to capture that
this Motif has a dependency with this
nearby visible footprint and it's thus
able to uh kind of like capture the the
finding event of f b and then uh
similarly you can also ask the model how
predicting the presence of this nucleis
the model will say for this nucleis I'm
using this sequence this nfyb binding
site and this Nerf one binding site uh
this Motif to predict and that's also
really interesting because this Motif is
like 400 base pairs away from the
nucleis so the model is capturing some
long range dependency between the
objects in the same
region and then um
as you can see that we keep saying that
oh the model keep picks up these short
DNA uh sequences that are actually the
TF motifs and we think they could be
really Bound by the TF but we don't
really like at the time we didn't know
whether that was true are these
positions with the high scores really
Bound by TFS we really need to uh
Benchmark against ground truth data of
TF binding which is chipseek so
something you can do is that let's say
ask a quick question how how are how is
your model predicting where the
nucleosomes are how is the model
predicting where the nucleosomes are
yeah because all of the transcription
factors are based on sequence right
right but is
predicting where the nucleus that means
the nucleis the positioning of the nucis
is sequence dependent oh yeah because
like the I I think the our our
understanding of this process is that
where the nism is it's actually shaped
by both where the TFS are and of course
you cannot see this thing here but like
the nucis remodelers but where the nucis
remodel are is still to some extent like
related to where the TFS are so uh
basically uh we've seen this in in some
examples where uh you know the model
looks at certain TF binding sides and
then it knows the nucis should be
exactly these many base pairs away from
those TFS and in silico you can you know
in the computer you can change your
sequence by moving this TF to the side
like to the left or to the right we're
upating the TF and the model if you do
that the model give it a slightly
different prediction we say the mo now
the nucleis would move to the side where
the nucleis would disappear so that
means that there's a dependency between
where the TFS are and where the nucleis
are and I think that is to some extent
know like certain TFS really like to
bind um at a certain distance to nucleis
some are like right next to the nism
some are like at a certain distance uh
and I think but but I really need to
emphasize that the model is learning um
correlation so whether this is the nucis
is determine where the TFS are what the
TFS are determined with the nule like
the causality is still needs to be
established through
experiments uh so uh we really want to
know whether the sites highlighted by
the sequence attribution scores are
really Bound by the TFS so something you
can do is that let's say you have a TF
you're interested in uh you have its
Motif you scan it through the whole
genome and you'll see a lot of motif uh
sites and then when you compare when you
overlap with chipseek you realize a lot
of the sites have chips signal so they
are bound sites a lot of sites with the
motif but they don't have chip signal
meaning that they're Unbound multi site
they're not really used by the TF and we
did that and if you compare the sites
that are bound and Unbound if you look
at their sequence attribution scores uh
you see something like this so for
example on the left you see atf3
and then every so this he map every row
is a individual Motif s all the sides on
the left have chip signal and you can
see that uh the color here represents
the sequence attribution scores so you
can see the bound sides really do have
much higher sequence attribution scores
the model knows that they are bound and
then the Unbound SES overall they don't
have chip and they also have very uh
much lower uh sequence attribution
scores so for some reason although all
of these sites have a motif the model
was able able to by looking at nearby
sequence context figure out which sites
are used by the TF which sites are not
used by the TF so this gives you a very
good TF findinding predictor and then I
also want to highlight y1 because y1 is
one of those invisible TFS you
absolutely don't see its footprint at
least in your data but just by learning
the dependency with nearby uh visible
objects the model is able to figure out
that these Motif sides are bound and
these Motif sides are Unbound and then
we realize that you can do a simple
transformation to convert the sequence
attribution scores to a final TF binding
score and that TF binding score will
give you a really nice prediction of
which sites are bound by which TFS so
data Benchmark using a larger set of
chipstick data compared to the previous
methods developed in the past 10 to
20ish years uh to predict TF finding and
then you can see that the method on the
right is our method it's definitely
showing improved accuracy in predicting
TF using chipseek as ground truth so
this gives us a really nice TF binding
predictor and we were really encouraged
by the results and now we're thinking
can we apply this to actually track the
Dynamics of TF binding through a real
biological process for example
differentiation and here I want to say
that it is such a nice opportunity to be
able to footprint with a taxi because a
taxic is uniquely adapted into single
cell platforms there are so many single
cell axic methods uh compared to you
know DNA seek and m& seek so the unique
opportunity here is that you can with a
single cell attack data run for printing
for every single cell type or every
single cell State and you can compare
the differences so let me just show you
one example uh in our lab we generated
this um human bone marrow sharti data
which which is basically multi-m of both
a taxic and RC in the same individual
cells and we sequence around 900,000
cells so you can see the map on the left
and then we covered most of the major
cell types in hematop poises you can see
here are the hematop stem cells and they
can differentiate into the RR lineage
the B cell lineage uh the myoid lineage
and covering most of the major cell
types so what you can do here is that
you can let's say take all of these
let's say a few thousand cells in the HC
State aggregate their data so you get a
very deep track of the The Cutting
density it can run fo Printing and the
de learning model on it to figure out
where the TFS are where the nisms are
and then you take a little step forward
like here you aggregate all of these
cells and then you do the same thing you
get the TF binding pattern and take one
step forward one step forward you can do
this iteratively and eventually you'll
be able to figure out the TF binding and
nucleis binding pattern across all of
the different cell States so to show you
what the results might look like uh this
is showing one promoter the GM pe1
promoter P1 itself expresses also a
transition Factor here every row is a
cell state so you can think of it as a
tiny group of cells you know in a little
corner In This U map and we have 1,000
different cell States generated uh
sampled from that um data set so you get
1,000
rows every column is a single base pair
so we're showing the 800 base pair uh
region within that promoter and then the
color in the heat map in the middle
shows the pred TF finding score so if
you see a red area that means that
position is bound by a TF and then if
you see blue that means this position is
not bound so what you see immediately is
that even in this same region you get
several different distinct patterns of T
binding across the cell types right so
for example if you look at the myoid
cells the Milo cells is where this Gene
is very highly expressed you see
multiple TFS Bound in here like every
red stripe is a TF the strongest stripe
with strongest predicted TF binding is
in fact P1 itself so it turns out that
this Gene expresses a TF the TF comes
back and binds its own promoter to form
an auto regulation Loop and if you look
at another cell type cells um you lose
all of this binding but you gain binding
here which is not bound in the M cell
you gain binding here if you look what
it is it is scatter one and it's
actually very well known that P the spi1
G and gatan Gene fight with each other
their enemies uh during
differentiation if P if spi1 wins the
cells going to myoid and if Gan wins the
cells going to erythroid so you can see
this enemy of spi1 coming here and
inhibiting its own enemy repressing its
expression and it's interesting if you
look at the bar on the right which is
the overall accessibility like the total
number of cutting you see within this
region uh you can see that all of these
details will be lost if you just do uh
if you just calculate accessibility so
essentially this TF patterns cannot be
detected uh by doing the traditional way
of analyzing attack data which is
calling the Peaks you know promoters and
enhancers and just counting how many uh
reads you have in those
regions so uh like we mentioned before
instead of looking at all of the cell
States you can of course also just focus
on one specific lineage let's say the
eror L
and now you can take the pseuds or like
the small cell groups from the beginning
of differentiation to the end and align
them sort them through pseudo time and
then you get something like this so here
I'm showing one enhancer that's very
important for regulating hemoglobin
genes the H3 uh enhancer and then from
top to bottom you still get different
cell States but ranging from the stem
cells to middle of the lineage to more
later like differentiated cells and
again I'm showing a 00 base pair region
so you can see that the color represent
the TF finding score you can see that um
the TFS start from very low binding and
they gradually gain binding during
differentiation some TFS gain binding
much later like this one you know it's
starts to bind much later on but there
are also TFS that start binding very
early like this one very early during
differentiation you can see binding and
the Rd TFS are actually G one and T one
which are exactly the master Regulators
of eor differentiation
and like I mentioned before when you do
the multiscale you not only get the TFS
but you also get the nisms right so you
can try to see where the nisms are bound
in this region across differentiation
and you get a map like this so here you
can see that at the beginning of
differentiation you get you know kind of
fuzzy patterns of nisms and this Center
region is not really nucleis free uh but
during differentiation you start to get
more face nucleis like more well
positioned nucleis one two and three and
then as the cells differentiate the
nisms actually move around like this
nucis uh moves to the right this nucis
moves to the left and they increase the
space in the middle so they you're
getting a bigger and bigger nism free
region in the middle and that allows for
more TF to be bound so this actually you
know you can see how AC is established
step by step across differentiation and
we thought that was like a really cool
opportunity and additionally we also
want to see whether this method can be
applied to disease like can you get a
healthy sample a disease sample call
where the footprints are and then
compare them to see which TFS have
changed during disease and then uh our
lab is very interesed in aging so we did
this in the Aging context where we get
uh hetic stem cells from Young mice and
old mice and we we did uh 10x volum on
it and then uh called Footprints using
our method and R the de model and this
is our data set you can see you have the
stem cells here the different iate into
some of the downstream lineages but if
we only focus on the stem cells you see
that the young cells are here the old
cells are here so they really take
different cell states in the state space
and we ran the previous analysis we
mentioned so I'm not going to go over
those right now but I want to highlight
something that we haven't mentioned
before which is to identify the novo TF
motives so if you still remember we said
uh when we asked the model to explain
its prediction you can get this track of
sequence important scores and even
without knowing you know without having
a previously defined Motif database you
can just look at this track and say oh I
think I know this is very likely a TF
Motif because it's highlighted this is
very likely a TF Motif and then you can
score use the TF binding score to
compare is this Motif more bound or less
Bound in the disease store healthy uh
cell States and then you will know which
TF go up during uh aging and which TF
going down during aging and then when do
this you will see that you know this
this plot shows like the which TFS go up
which TFS which motifs go down you see a
lot of changes during aging and when you
call that denal Motif some of them when
you compare to a known Motif database
they can be very well matched to a
previously known Motif so you know what
it is so for example we know uh AP1 TFS
like false and then RS G they go up dur
aging and then we see some TS like y11
Nerf one they go down during aging but
also see a lot of motifs like this motif
number eight here I'm not sure you can
see this this motif number eight here uh
we see this Motif being picked up by the
model and it its binding goes up during
aging but it doesn't really match any
known Motif in The Motif database so
we're like is could this be a new TF
that nobody knows about then you know
that's having a completely new Motif and
we looked into this and realized that
was not the case what what's happening
is that these unknown motifs are
actually composite motifs so they're
consisting of multiple know motifs you
know concatenated together so for
example these motifs all go up dur aging
and then you can see that for example
this top one is actually ad Motif and a
rank Motif combined together then this
one is also add some runks but the runks
is flipped in the other strand and then
you also see a lot of like s add timer
motives G at timer motives s motives so
it seems like the Deep learning model is
picking up the Partnerships between TFS
when they bind but at the time we didn't
really know is this you know really
physiological partnership between TFS do
they actually
interact uh and interestingly we looked
into literature and found that some of
these composite motifs are supported by
uh structural data like Crystal
structures or crowm structures and then
for example this motif number 10 matches
exactly the DNA sequence used in this
structure this is you can found it in uh
you can find it in pdb and you can see
that the D is flipped but you can see
that the rungs one binds its own Motif
S1 binds its own Motif and rung one
actually has this Linker the flips over
with the extra domain that interacts
with s and then previous Studies have
found that S1 actually inhibits itself
through Auto inhibitory domain but this
interaction with rung one relieves that
in inhibition so now S1 is more active
so this is indeed a phys physiologically
relevant um interaction that we're
picking up by the model here and of
course in the pdb you also see S1 S1
dier very similarly matching I think uh
this and then it's also relieving the
auto inhibition of
s but in our data uh in addition to
these two structures we see a lot of
different orientations and
configurations of the motives especially
between S1 and R one so for example all
of these configurations they go up in
aging they have a ranks they have an X
but have different distances and they
have different
orientations and then we're like all
most of these didn't really have like
structural data are they physiologically
relevant just out of curiosity We
compare it to Alpha fold so we use Alpha
fall 3 to predict what could be
happening so basically throwing that DNA
sequence throwing in those two TFS to
see whether Alpha fall is predicting
certain sort of U interaction and what's
kind of surprising was that Alpha fall
was actually predicting the exact same
type of uh interaction as turn here so
for example for moti 43 which is if you
can find it here you have uh rungs here
adds here and then you can see that
rungs is Alpha Four predicts that R will
bind its own
Motif and X will bind own Motif and Ron
still has this flexible Linker flipping
over to the other side of the with this
interaction domain that interacts with s
to remove his a inhibition and then this
is a totally uh different of
configuration Motif 61 which is this and
this you can see is much farther apart
but still runs with bind own Motif and
then flipping over through this Linker
interact with ads and this is all
consistent with the know data so it
seems that the Deep learning model
through learning the dep dependency
between DNA sequence and the for prints
it's capturing both known and novel TF
corporations uh but whether this plays a
role in aging we don't really know we
just see this going up does it have a
caal ro driving the Aging of the cell I
feel that's something that we still need
to validate so just want to summarize uh
with some TI messages uh so first of all
we know that uh we developed this multi
multiscale for printing method that
detects the the DN binding factors of
different V various sizes and kind of
delineates the local organization of
chatin and we trained a sequence to
footprint model uh that kind the Cod the
D in a sequence dependence of protein
binding and with this you can highlight
you know the positions that are more
likely Bound by
TFS and then combining for printing with
single cell data you can actually look
at every little corner of that state
space and track how the protein binding
Dynamics change across cell States like
differentiation and uh we can apply this
to aging or any other disease relevant
uh context comparing healthy and not
healthy to figure out what has changed
uh across
disease and eventually uh you can call
the noal motives and capture some
interesting interactions like
Partnerships between TFS uh which could
be uh useful for people studying like
how TFS work
together and I just want to mention that
uh this is very recently online uh on
nature actually just like a month ago
and our lab has prepared a uh GitHub
repository so we have all of the code
and we uh we we implemented a um python
package that's user friendly so if you
really want to use this uh you can check
out our GitHub repo and download our
package and we also prepared a lot of uh
tutorials to show you how to run this
and we have tutorials to run this on
single cell Tack and B attack so you can
I highly encourage you to check it out
uh and in the in the end I want to uh
thank everyone in the lab especially
Jason and also uh my co colleagues of
this project Max and r and Max was
supposed to give a talk today but
unfortunately um he's kind of sick today
so uh and um also want to thank Sai and
V who really played a big roles in the
early phases of the project and our
collaborators at the broad and also
collaborators in the Wagers Lab at
Harvard uh and I'll be happy to take any
questions thank
you thanks that was fantastic and I
can't believe you did it all with hours
notice and we even had someone drop in
from outside to
watch um yeah go ahead oh thank you for
the great talk um so I just have one uh
technical question so how deep do you
have to sequence to in order to generate
reliable uh data something like this
yeah so that's a really good question um
overall I think so first of all it
depends on your data quality right you
can imagine that if you have really good
quality attack data you can get away
with slightly feor reads uh and then
overall I think you would start from you
know 5 to 10 million fragments which is
a good start and then the deeper you go
the higher the quality usually when I
think when people sequence bulk attack
if it if they don't do full printing
they probably sequence like one to two
million reads something like that so
this is slightly deeper than that but uh
if you have really good TSS scores or
like really good you know distinguish
ability to distinguish
accessible and not accessible critin I
think you can get away with slightly
less but more is better yeah uh so in in
the context of the single cell taxic
data then how many reads do you need uh
per cell like fragment yeah so uh if you
do the backup level calculation uh for a
standard 10x multi uh data set I think
you can get something like 20ish K reads
per cell right so so 10 to 20 Kish well
a good data set that 10 to 20K uh reads
per per cell and then that means you
probably need a few hundred cells to
close a million close to a thousand
cells to form a PUD that's like a few
million reads right and then that would
be enough for um doing a PUD box that's
de enough for foot printing in the data
set that we generated like the the bone
marrow data set
um like this one
oops this one we sequenced we we try to
go for higher number of cells so this
one I think had lower um coverage per
cell so like a few thousands so
definitely not to 10 to 20, so we kind
of have to suitable a little more cells
to get enough coverage this one I think
we did a few thousand cells per suit B
but we have 900,000 in total so it's
like easier one more question it's it's
completely different but um So tm5 Pro
uh uh
transposes uh actually insert nine uh
base pairs when they attach the adapters
right right um so how do you deal with
this you know artificial nine based
pairs when you model or identify this
footprint okay so for those who are not
familiar with this how TMI works when it
cuts I wish there's a way for me to draw
uh draw on the
B uh actually I'll just explain it uh so
sorry so you have DNA tn5 sits on it and
will create a nine based pair of
staggered end and then we like get your
adapters you know to the end of the the
uh sticky end and then after PCR that
single end Gap will be filled in so
basically you will get like a 9bp
duplicate if you think about this on the
two ends of the re uh So eventually when
you sequence uh your your fragment and
map it back to the genome the the start
part of your read is actually the end of
that nine Bas pair which is not the
center of that you know symmetry of the
nine base pair so what we do is that we
do a shift so you get a nice base pair
if you're on this end you shift it
backwards for four base pairs if you're
on this end you shift it forward for
four based pairs so you're actually
getting the right center of tn5 and then
there's a a bunch of different versions
on the market some people do plus4 minus
5 some do plus plus4 -4 I think the
correct thing is to do plus4 - for uh we
actually looked at this pretty
extensively uh when you don't do full
printing we don't quantify a single Bas
resolution if you just calling a taxi
Peaks it doesn't really matter whether
you do this do the the the shift but
when you do foot printing is very
important when you do the shift that why
you're getting the right thing and then
in the python package we provided we
realized that different people might
have pre-processed the data differently
some people do plus4 minus four some
people plusus 5 so we have automatic we
have a module that a automatically
detects how what's the shift that you're
doing and it will automatically shift it
shift the ends to the correct single
base pair so you don't have to worry
about it when you run the package that's
great thank
you right let's thank our speaker one
more time that was great