Good morning, everyone.
And thank you, Sally, for
that nice introduction.
Thank you all for inviting
me to speak with you today.
It's a genuine honor to be here
to see some familiar faces,
but also to meet
some new people.
Today, what I'd like
to do is share with you
some early reflections on the
future of management education.
And what I'm going to do
is divide my brief remarks
into three parts.
First, what I'd like
to do is describe
how this is a pivotal moment
for the world of business,
and as a result, for
management education,
given some significant
challenges under way.
Second, as the still
relatively new Dean
of the MIT Sloan
School of Management,
I'd like to offer some thoughts
on how MIT Sloan, by becoming
even more embedded
in the MIT ecosystem,
can lead in addressing
some of these challenges
and in reinventing
management education.
And finally, I'd like to
provide an example of how
we can collectively, all of
us, do this exciting work
by discussing the challenges,
but also the opportunities posed
by generative AI,
and how bringing back
the human side of
enterprise is key to how
we manage this moment.
So let me begin with
the challenges, which
are also opportunities.
In recent years, the context
within which business
has been operating for decades
has changed in significant ways.
Now I'm going to present a
highly stylized description
of that context and
the changes underway.
The reality, of course, is
that's much, much more nuanced.
But let me just give you the
less nuanced portrait of things.
Over the last several
decades, business
has operated in a
more or less flat
world where geopolitical
and cultural differences
across countries and
regions were eroding.
A world in which innovations
and communications, logistics,
design, and the spread
of global supply chains
allowed firms to produce more or
less anything anywhere, usually
driven by low input
and labor costs,
and then sell their
products or services
across the globe in
an array of markets
with little concern for
trade restrictions, tariffs,
cultural barriers, or even
the true cost of externalities
like carbon emissions.
Again, this is a very
highly stylized description
of the context.
The world was never as flat as
Thomas Friedman once argued.
It was always much more lumpy.
But the assumption that we were
living in a globalized world
with a more or less
friction-less flow of capital,
of products, of
people, of services,
was one that was shared by many
business and political leaders.
This model of business has
been challenged in recent years
by a variety of
forces, including
the rise of geopolitical
tensions between countries.
And we can talk about
the US and China.
But of course,
it's more than just
those two countries
that have led
to the rise of trade barriers
and the reconfiguration,
or even diversification
of global supply chains.
Now that reconfiguration
of supply chains
happened before
the current moment.
It happened during the
first Trump administration.
It happened because
companies were
thinking about their
global carbon footprint.
It happened because of
the pandemic and the need
to have more resilient
supply chains.
But recent efforts have really
accelerated this process
of trying to reconfigure
and change global trade
and commerce.
The second pressure,
and this is one
that we don't talk
about as much but I
think is equally important, is
the reemergence of regulation,
not just in the EU but in
the US, in different states
and in other countries, as well.
Think about the Digital Services
Act or the Digital Markets Act
and what that has done for
especially the digital economy.
This is shaping how companies
make and sell their products
and services around the globe.
Third, there's a
growing awareness--
and I think this is a good
thing-- and concern over climate
change and its
impact on society,
and thus the need to develop
low carbon products and business
practices, business
models in the near future.
Fourth, there are these
emergences of and maturity.
Or maybe not maturity,
but evolution
of disruptive new
technologies like AI
that will impact
existing business
models, work arrangements,
and employment patterns.
And finally, there are changing
employee attitudes towards work,
towards work life
balance, and expectations
they have of their employers.
These and other
challenges threaten
to up-end existing business
models and management practices
in the US and around the world.
I believe that we are
in a pivotal moment
when individual firms and
even entire industries
need to rethink their business
models and ways of operating
in the world.
And there is no clear,
already established path
for them to follow.
In enterprises across
the world, leaders
are trying to figure
out how to operate
in a more regulated and
politicized environment.
How to reduce carbon
emissions while still making
innovative products and taking
advantage of their globally
dispersed suppliers
and customers.
How to manage a workforce
with new demands
and new expectations.
And how to integrate the promise
and potential of generative AI
into existing and future product
services and business models
in ways that will increase their
company's competitive value
and not undermine it.
And the sad truth is that
most management schools,
business schools, cannot guide
these leaders since we, too,
are stuck in the past.
To be completely frank, most
management business schools
have been teaching
the same material
in the same way for
decades, not adapting
our models, our frameworks,
and our theoretical approaches
to the dramatic changes
underway in the world.
And the students know it.
And so do their
future employers.
Now, I don't expect
this crowd to be
a regular reader of a magazine
called Poets and Quants.
This is a magazine that
talks about business schools.
But last late July, an article
came out in Poets and Quants
basically quoting all these
business school students
at Graduate School of
Business at Stanford,
where the students
were basically saying,
we're not learning anything.
We're not learning any skills.
About a month ago, a similar
article in the same magazine
came out about Wharton,
where they basically
argued the same thing.
These professors are
teaching the same things
that they've been
teaching for decades.
We're not learning
any new skills.
Now I was, as the
new Dean of Sloan,
greatly relieved that they were
writing about others and not
about us.
But the fact is, they could
have been writing about us.
This is an industry problem.
This is not a school or
particular university problem.
And this is something that
we have to take on head-on.
But I believe that these
and other broad challenges
create exciting
opportunities for MIT Sloan
to build on and expand
its unique assets,
to play a leadership role in
addressing these challenges,
and in the process, reinvigorate
management education, management
research, and practice.
Now, I know this sounds
like a sales job.
But I really, actually,
really believe it.
So why Sloan?
Why do I think this is such a
great moment for MIT and MIT
Sloan?
And I believe it's because we
possess several amazing assets.
The first is that
we have a world
class, research-oriented
faculty, many of them already
working on some of the
important issues of the day,
whether it's health or climate
or advanced manufacturing,
or the future of work or GenAI
or any of the other key issues.
We have people already
working and collaborating
across the university
on these issues.
We have amazing faculty,
incredible students,
and an incredibly dedicated
professional staff.
And our curriculum
has traditionally
blended theory and
practice, hand in mind,
which is exactly
how adults learn.
So we have these incredible
assets in our people
and in the curriculum
that we have already.
Secondly, and this is the most
important asset I think we have,
is our embeddedness in MIT
and in the MIT ecosystem.
Across this great
university, colleagues
are conducting
cutting edge research
on some of the key challenges I
described earlier, whether it's
climate change, health care,
advanced manufacturing,
generative AI, and so much more,
by becoming even more embedded
in this ecosystem.
And what does that mean?
What it means is more
collaborative research,
more collaborative teaching.
Between Sloan and the
rest of the institute,
I believe that MIT Sloan can
help translate innovations
in these and other areas
into new enterprises,
into new business models,
into new policies,
into new ways of thinking about
the world and the economy.
This is Sloan's role
in the MIT ecosystem,
is to play that translational
management role.
And let me just
elaborate on this.
As I said, MIT's Sloan
faculty already very
actively involved in many of
the presidential initiatives.
When I think about the GenAI
or climate, even MITHIC,
we have Sloan faculty who are
involved in either the steering
committees or
co-leading these things.
And this is great.
This is a way that we're
bringing people together.
But we can do so much more.
And the way that I think about
this is, how can MIT Sloan lower
the barriers so that students
from all over the institute
can take our courses,
maybe even earn a degree?
How can MIT Sloan
begin to develop
with other parts of MIT
cutting-edge certificate
programs or other
courses of study
where we're bringing together
people from engineering
and science and
humanities with Sloan
to actually address some
of these big issues?
I think there's so
much that we can do,
which is not only
good for MIT, but it's
a way of really reimagining
management education
and management research.
Now when I think
about this, I think
about increasing MIT'S Sloan's
embeddedness within MIT means
more than simply deepening the
ties between, say, the technical
and the commercial
sides of campus.
It also requires that MIT
Sloan work more closely
with colleagues in SHASS and
reinvigorate its long standing
tradition focused on the
human side of enterprise.
As many in this room
may or may not know,
MIT Sloan has a long and
distinguished history
of focusing on the human
dimensions of business.
In its early days during
the post-war boom,
the US enterprise,
as US enterprises
were growing and
trying to figure out
how best to engage and
motivate their employees,
Sloan Professor Douglas
McGregor published
an important book called The
Human Side of Enterprise.
It was published in 1959.
And in that book, McGregor
outlined Theory X and Theory Y,
opposing theories
describing why people work
and how they should be managed.
Theory X assumes that workers
are inherently unmotivated.
And this leads to a
top-down style of management
based on compliance
and a mix of carrots
and sticks to reward
or to punish employees.
Theory Y, on the
other hand, assumes
that employees are intrinsically
motivated to do their best work
and to contribute to the
organizations that employ them.
This leads to a very
different management style,
one that empowers
workers, that gives them
greater discretion
over their jobs,
and cultivates higher
levels of engagement.
McGregor was only one of a
long list of MIT Sloan faculty
who worked on this more
human-centric approach
to management.
And I think of the
work of Lotte Bailyn
or Ed Schein on organizational
culture, or of Tom Kochan,
Bob McKenzie, and Paul
Osterman on what they called
high performance work systems.
They fall clearly
in this tradition.
I see my own research on labor
standards and global supply
chains following this tradition.
And faculty and students
in what Sloan now
calls the Work in
Organizational Studies group,
continue this important
line of research,
as do our colleagues at the
MIT Leadership Center, which
is also based on Sloan.
And so for Sloan to deepen and
expand and expand this work,
we need to increase
our collaboration
with colleagues in SHASS
and across the institute.
And this is why MITHIC
is so important for MIT,
but also so important
for MIT Sloan.
I believe that tapping into all,
every part of MIT, everything
that has MIT to offer, would
help MIT Sloan chart the future
to shape how new
technologies like AI
will reconfigure
industries and careers,
how new enterprises
will be created and run,
how individuals
will work and live,
how business practices will
become more sustainable,
and how national economies
will develop and adapt.
It's an incredibly exciting
time to be at MIT--
to be back at MIT.
So let me illustrate--
And I'm almost done.
Let me illustrate how we can
together do this important work
by highlighting some important
research on GenAI that
is already taking place at
both MIT and at MIT Sloan.
Now as you all know,
Americans today
are both ambivalent
and anxious about AI
and its impact on their
jobs, on the economy,
and on society as a whole.
Many see opportunity.
62% of respondents in
a recent Gallup survey
believe that AI will
increase productivity.
53% believe that it will
lead to economic growth.
But still, 61% of respondents
in this Gallup survey
think that AI will destroy
more jobs than it will create.
And nearly half, 47%
of the respondents,
think that it will
destroy more businesses
than it will recreate.
These are real concerns
from an anxious population
voiced at a time of great
economic and political
uncertainty.
This is a critical moment,
with enormous consequences
for the workforce, for
organizations, and for humanity.
And as the latest generation
of artificial intelligence
leaves its nascent phase, we
are confronted with a choice
about which path to take.
Will we deploy AI to
eliminate millions
of jobs across the economy?
Or will we use it to
empower the workforce
and enhance our
human capabilities?
Fortunately, colleagues
at MIT and MIT Sloan
are already doing important
work to show the viability
of the second path.
For example, in their 2023
book, Power and Progress,
Daron Acemoglu and
Simon Johnson argue
for recharting the
course of this technology
so that it promotes shared
prosperity and complements
rather than substitutes
for the work of humans.
Writing later with another
MIT colleague, David Autor,
the pair argue that the
direction of AI development
is a choice, and argue
that leaders and educators
must choose a path of
machines in service of minds.
But what does this mean in the
context of today's workforce
and workplace?
How do we create
organizations and paths
that travel this human
centric, worker friendly path?
Part of the answer
lies in research
from MIT Sloan Professor
Roberto Rigobon
and postdoctoral
researcher Isabella Loaiza.
These scholars analyzed 19,000
tasks across 950 job types
and found five human
capabilities that are increasing
in value as AI advances.
These are empathy, presence,
opinion, creativity, and hope.
This Epic framework points us
on a path towards upskilling
workers, with a
focus on what they
call the fundamental
qualities of human nature.
These are simply a
few of the examples
of the exciting and important
work taking place across MIT.
There's so much more
work taking place,
but work that allows
us to see the choice
and begin to imagine how we
take that second choice that
enhances our humanity
and empowers people.
This work suggests that job
loss and de-skilling are not
inevitable outcomes
in this new era of AI.
From Theory X and
Theory Y to Rigobon
and Loaiza's important work--
I've now lost my notes--
I'll find them.
Here it is.
Insightful, epic framework to
the new educational paradigms
made possible through
initiatives like universal AI
that was recently released
by the MIT Open Learning
Initiative.
MIT and MIT Sloan have a history
of charting and paving pathways
to an exciting and
productive future of work
that not only includes
humans, but makes
the most of our humanity.
Together, we can
invent this future.
Thank you very much.
[APPLAUSE]
So imagine that
you're Dean of SHASS,
and you learn that
someone like Rick
is going to be your
fellow dean, someone
you're going to be able
to brainstorm with,
someone who is going
to share insights.
I mean, it's extraordinary.
It's extraordinary to
have you as a fellow dean.
Likewise.
So you talked a
little bit about ways
in which the world has changed,
and business schools have
been slow to adapt.
I was hoping you could speak
about that more broadly.
So, as you said, we're
at a pivotal time.
How do you think higher
education more broadly
should adapt to the time?
Big question.
I don't have all the answers--
I don't have a comprehensive
answer to that question.
But I think we have fragments
of what could maybe be
woven together into an answer.
And that's why I think this
is such an important moment
at MIT and for MIT Sloan,
because of the assets that we
already have.
A couple of things.
One is for education, I don't
think the traditional model
of education, of
just being in a room,
passively sitting while
the professor, fountain
of knowledge, is
spewing on and on works.
I don't think it's
worked for a long time,
but it certainly
doesn't work today.
Instead, I think that we
should reimagine education
using what we already
do well, which
is we have great work that's
taking place in the classroom
and the labs, et cetera.
That should continue.
We got really good
at using technology
to do virtual learning, online
learning, whether it was
synchronous or asynchronous.
And again, we have Open
Learning and other assets
at MIT that continue to do that.
And we have this
tradition of what
we call at Sloan
action learning, which
is being in the world, whether
it's the MISTI programs that
exist in SHASS, or some of
the other more clinical work
that takes place
across the university,
or what we call action
learning at Sloan,
I think that's really important
because it's actually embedding
students in real organizations
with real challenges
and applying what
they learn in the lab,
in the classroom, et cetera,
to try to solve those problems,
which allows them to
actually-- as we know,
because we're teachers, that's
when you actually figure out
what you know, is when you
have to actually teach it.
So it's going to
help them learn that.
But also, even more
importantly, it's
going to show them what they
still don't learn so that they
come back hungry to learn more.
And it's those cycles, repeated
cycles that are important.
We have this, but
they're not connected.
And I think we have
to connect the dots.
And when I think
about this, I think
that an education
at MIT Sloan, but I
would say it should
be for MIT as a whole,
should be a seamless experience.
It should be something
that takes place on campus,
off campus, in
person, virtually,
synchronously,
asynchronously, et cetera.
And if we can connect those
dots, then what we can do
is have students learning and
really, really interesting ways.
And that will, I think, allow us
to actually meet the challenges
that I talked about.
I mean, the dream that I have is
that we have a student from MIT
who is maybe--
since I was one of the founders
of the MIT Italy program,
I'm going to use
that as an example.
They're in Bologna.
They're working for, doing
an internship at Ferrari,
or something like that.
They are taking an Italian
language or literature course
at the University of
Bologna, but they're also
online taking some classes
here so they can make progress
towards their degree.
So they don't have to
have the on/off switch.
They're connected.
We can do that because
we have the assets.
And I think if we do
that, we can better
meet the needs of our
students, better meet
the needs of their
employers, future employers,
and allow us to
actually have even
greater impact in the world.
Yes, I love that vision.
And I mean, here's
one way of emphasizing
why I think you're so right,
that the model can't just
be a professor spewing
information on students.
In the age of AI, to
a first approximation,
all information is available
to everyone always.
So of course, that
can't be the model.
Now, here's a way of getting
deeper into this issue.
So, as emerged in
your presentation,
AI is changing the nature
of the labor market.
It's changing what companies
expect of employees.
And of course, that
affects higher ed
because it affects the ways
in which we can bring value
to students who are
hoping to get jobs,
and really to students
who are hoping
to find a path to financial
stability in their lives.
So could you say a little
bit more first about
how you expect the labor
market is going to change,
and what the paths to financial
stability of the future
are going to look like?
And secondly, what MIT can
do to meet that challenge?
Yeah, so the way
that I understand
what might be happening
to the labor market
is informed by our
wonderful colleagues,
whether it's David Autor
and the work that he does,
[? Daron, ?] Simon, et cetera.
And it seems like
this is a version,
maybe a more extreme version
of what we've seen before,
where certain skills will
be automated or eliminated
as a result of AI,
and others won't.
And in the past, those have
been, more task-oriented
routine jobs.
Now people are thinking
about what they may be,
whether it's a lower, more basic
analytical sort of analyst kinds
of jobs, as opposed to others.
We have to see where that goes.
But if that's true, that
some of the things that you
can do with generative AI, you
don't require the basic level
of people who are
doing just a lot
of grunt research and
easy analysis, then
what can we do for them?
And this is what
we've been doing
at MIT Sloan in the
last several months
is the genie is out of the
bottle in terms of gen AI.
You can't put it back.
It's not going to be
like, oh, you're cheating.
You can't use it.
I think that's not the
way to think about it.
I think what we have to do is,
how do we use this incredibly
powerful tool to enhance
our human capabilities,
our reasoning, our analytical
skills, our decision making?
And so what we're
doing at MIT Sloan
is we're making sure that
everyone students, but also
staff and faculty,
understand the basic-- are
literate enough about the
basic models and tools.
So we do already a boot
camp for orientation
of our master's students.
But we are now inviting
everyone in the community
to use the universal AI
that was recently released
as a way of being educated.
Then what we're doing is we're
weaving AI into all our courses.
So we already have a
whole bunch of electives
that are really, really great.
But rather than just
have those electives,
how do we weave in
the basics of AI
into finance, into marketing,
into strategy, into operations?
And so it's not instead of.
It's actually showing how you
use those tools to enhance
your human decision
making, reasoning,
analytics using this tool.
And we're going to do it this
way, because I think that way,
we lean into this technology.
We equip our people for the
future of future developments
of the labor market.
We lean into the
MIT brand, which
I think is very, very
important to distinguish
our graduates from others.
And it allows us
to actually design
curriculum that can
quickly be adapted
since AI is moving so quickly.
So if we had the
module around AI,
as opposed to the
12-week course,
it's much easier to adapt
that, layering it on top
of the finance,
strategy, ops, et cetera.
So that's how we're
thinking about it.
And I would say based
on conversations
that we've all had
as faculty, that
thinking about it
that way might be
a good way across
the disciplines,
I love it.
I mean, you would think
that if you were a company
and you're hiring, the
absolute first thing you
want is for your people you hire
to be not just literate in AI,
but they'd be the
kind of person who--
absolutely the kind of person
whose work is empowered by AI.
So I totally agree about that.
Now, what about
expected disruptions
and just what an entry-level
position might look like?
So here's an example that I find
both illuminating and scary.
So a law firm--
entry-level people in
a law firm up to now
have done tasks
that, in many cases,
can be done better and certainly
more cheaply using ChatGPT.
So that suggests
that we might move
to a system in which a law
firm is just going to hire
fewer entry-level people.
But of course, the world still
is going to need top lawyers.
So there still is a
path to getting there,
but it just becomes
much more narrow.
So how do we in higher
education prepare
for a world in which
these paths are
going to be much narrower
than they are today?
It's a great question, and
we're already seeing that.
We're already seeing it.
Not just in the
legal profession,
but even in the management area.
It used to be that some of the
top consulting or investment
banking companies would come,
and they would hire 20 or 30
of Sloan graduates at a time.
Every year, there was
these huge cohorts.
They still come, and they're
hiring a number of our students,
but in smaller numbers, because
they don't need as many of them
as they used to because
of the, more or less,
automation of some of
those tasks because of AI.
And so let me talk about how I
think we should operate at MIT,
and then whether or not
that's a model for higher
education in general.
It may or may not be.
The way that I think
about this for MIT is,
how do we really
produce students
that understand the
technology, that
have deep technical or
functional knowledge,
and know something about
how to manage people,
how to engage with people, how
to run organizations, et cetera?
And if we do that,
that will be unmatched.
And so when I think about MIT
Sloan being even more embedded
in the rest of MIT, and thinking
about innovative new courses,
or certificate programs,
maybe even degree programs.
I think about how might we
bring together, I don't know,
engineering students and
faculty working on fusion
with Sloan students who
care about climate and less
carbon-intensive energy?
And can they come
together, learn enough
about the technology,
learn enough
about how do you
manage people and run
organizations, et cetera?
And together, working
together, creating
a cohort of people who have
skills that would be unmatched.
And you could do
it around health.
You could do it around
advanced manufacturing.
You could do it on so
many different areas.
And again, and it's not just
the technical and commercial.
It's the human side that we
were talking about earlier.
I think if we do that, our
graduates will find that pathway
not as narrow as others.
I don't know if that's
possible for everyone
just because of what's
going on in the world.
But I know what's
possible for us,
and I really believe in the
power of demonstration projects.
So I think that if we can
show that it's happening--
that's why I think the New
Educational Initiative is
such a cool thing that's
going on here, as well.
If we can demonstrate its
possibility, then maybe others,
in their own ways, could
also learn and do something.
That's what I think.
No, I totally agree.
Because surely one
thing that's happening
is that narrow technical skills
are just going to-- they're
going to become
obsolete so quickly
that that's not the way
for higher education
to bring value to students.
And you mentioned
the EPIC framework,
which I like in its own.
But also I like having
MITHIC and EPIC.
I definitely think that
those are key skills.
But I think leadership--
I think leadership is
a key skill, as well.
So the way I imagine
high performing-humans
in the age of AI is, part
of what you need to do
is lead a team, which is going
to include humans, but also AI.
And because, more
broadly, AI is going
to be very good at
accomplishing tasks.
But humans are needed
to provide the judgment
to decide what tasks
are worth executing on.
And that is a human problem,
and it's a leadership problem.
So I think there's no question
that we need to collaborate
and that we need
to make it the case
that you leave MIT with
this sort of skill.
And I don't think
we need to abandon
the idea that we're the world's
top technical institution.
Because I think part
of what it means
to be a top engineer in the age
of AI is to have these skills.
I 100% agree with that.
And I think this is actually
a really, really important
message, is if MIT is
the institution that
is saying it's not
just technology,
it's also the human values,
it's the human reasoning,
it's how do we interact
with one another,
people will listen to that.
Because they-- oh,
yeah, of course.
They believe it, as opposed
to coming from elsewhere.
And I believe it's actually
an incredible opportunity
around leadership, but
also around values.
When I think of
MIT Sloan's mission
is to develop principle
innovative leaders who
are going to improve the
world, that's what we're about.
That's what we say we're about.
And so if that's what we're
about, then, of course,
we have to give a
cutting-edge education.
So people can do
well by themselves,
get good careers, et cetera.
But also go and implement
that mission, make the world
a better place.
For them to do that, they
have to be good leaders.
They have to really understand,
the complexity and the richness
of humanity, et cetera.
And they have to have not
only play a leadership, role,
but actually have an
anchor around values.
And one of the things that I
have loved about coming back--
I mean, coming back--
going away and
coming back, it's not
like you don't see the
warts of the Institute.
Of course you do.
But you appreciate what
makes this place so special.
And it's a community of smart
people doing important work,
but who are anchored
with really great values.
And I think that that's an asset
that we don't talk about enough,
but we should.
And so I think building on
the human side of enterprise,
as I broadly described it,
is key not only for Sloan,
but I think it's key for MIT.
Yes.
Now, here's something
that sometimes worries me.
So I totally agree with
everything you said.
I was once talking to someone
who thinks a lot about AI,
and the future of the labor
market, and the age of AI.
And I shared a version of
what you're talking about.
And here's what he said.
He said, yes, yes, yes.
But I'm just worried that
when there's a career fair,
and representative of Google
or some other big company
is getting to know students,
the thing they're really
going to care about is
whether they have the latest
technical skills.
And whether they seem like
just an interesting person,
a good person.
But at the end of
the day, companies
aren't going to prioritize the
things we're talking about.
And, of course, if that's
true, then students
are going to notice, and
they're not going to value them.
So do you think that what
this person said is right?
Or do you think that
companies really, truly
will value these
skills to the point
that they're going to convey
that to prospective candidates?
Yeah, so I can't speak
for all companies.
But I think that your
interlocutor is wrong.
And so some of you know this.
Prior to coming back,
I worked at Apple.
I ran their
corporate university,
which is an interesting place
because it has recruits, faculty
who are tenured faculty
at leading universities,
as well as practitioners
who come up
through the ranks of Apple,
and who are software engineers,
or hardware engineers,
or marketing people who
have a passion for education.
And what I saw
there is, of course,
the essential requirement is,
if you were going to be hired,
you knew your stuff.
Of course.
You were good at technical,
or functional, et cetera.
But what they also were
looking for is not--
they just expect that if
you're hired, you're good.
You're top of your game
at a technical level.
But they were looking
for something else.
And that something else is, can
you work well with other people,
since work is cross-functional?
You're working in teams all
the time, different teams
to get things done.
Do you know how to do that?
Do you know how to
bring people along?
Do you know when
to lead and when
to sit back and let
other people lead?
And are you guided by
a set of core values
that, at Apple, are
really, really important?
People were flushed out
not because they weren't
good technically, but because
they didn't align with what
the values were of the company.
Now, I can only speak
about that one company.
I don't know how it is exactly
in all the other companies.
But I think it's
that combination
is what people are looking for.
And that's a combination
that MIT is very well
positioned to deliver.
I love that.
I love that just as
an aspiration for MIT.
So that it could just
be taken for granted
that if you graduate
from MIT, of course,
you're going to know your stuff.
Of course, you're going to
have the top technical skills
in the world.
But you're also going to
have that extra element.
Of course, you're going
to be an excellent leader.
to have a moral compass.
Of course, you're
going to understand
the human side, the social,
ethical, political, economic
context.
I love that.
Because of the education
that we can deliver as
we're reinventing the education.
Yes.
Yes, yes, yes.
We don't exactly deliver on it
yet, but we're getting there.
But that is a vision.
And I think that MITHIC
can be part of that vision.
This is very exciting.
OK, I like where we've
gotten to so far.
Let me change tacks a
little bit and just ask you
about how you got to this point.
So, as Sally mentioned,
you actually got your PhD
in political science at MIT.
Can you tell us a
little bit about that
and how that led to the
next steps in your career?
Yeah.
So one of the things, when we're
talking about labor markets
and jobs, is I think
it's important for people
to realize that it's not linear.
It's actually really non-linear.
And that's a good thing because
you pick up different skills.
So I studied here in
MIT Political Science.
Amazing department.
I understand it's
a good department.
That's what I hear.
It's an excellent department.
Did you hear that, Mr. Provost?
It's an excellent
department, and I specialized
in political economy.
And the work that
I did was so MIT,
which I was studying initially
how are industries adapting
restructuring to
changes in technology
and into market conditions.
I did my dissertation in Italy.
Later on, I did work in
Eastern Germany, et cetera.
But as part of the work that I
did as a graduate student, which
I loved, I was involved in
some of these institute-wide
initiatives.
The one that I was involved
in as a grad student was--
later on, IT became
Made in America.
It became this.
It was called the
industrial performance,
or the commission for industrial
productivity, or something
like that, that had grad
students and faculty from all
over the Institute.
And we were trying to
understand the issue
of American competitiveness
in a changing world market.
And so there was a lot of
work being done in the US,
but a lot of work that
was done comparatively.
And I was involved in that.
And I learned so much
by speaking and meeting
colleagues in engineering,
and economics,
and the different parts of MIT.
And I think that
really imprinted itself
on me, which was the importance
of interdisciplinary work,
the importance of being out
in the world, in the field,
and not just sitting
behind a desk
and gathering and
analyzing data,
and to be focused on the
big problems of the day.
And so that really guided me.
Now, I was hired, actually, by
Sloan, not by political science.
Lester Thoreau was
the dean, and he
was hiring a bunch of people who
didn't have traditional business
backgrounds.
Because he, too, at
that time, wanted
to reimagine what
Sloan could be.
And so a whole cohort of us came
in who were non-traditional,
and that was great.
And I had the great
fortune of teaching,
both in political
science, and at Sloan,
and eventually as serving as
the head of the Department
of Political Science, which
continues to this day,
to do this amazing work,
which is integrated
with the rest of
the Institute that
has real impact in the world.
And I thought that
was super important.
So that really shaped me.
I mean, I'm excited about
the fact that you joined--
that you came back to
MIT for many reasons.
But I think one of them is
connected to that, the fact
that you just have a perspective
that is much broader than what
you would expect.
Not just because your PhD
is in political science,
but also because, as Sally
said, you served as provost.
And you served as dean
at Apple University,
which is a very different
kind of institution
than Brown or MIT.
So could you say a
little bit about how
that broad perspective has
shaped your vision of Sloan?
And also, what surprised you
now that you've been on the job
for a little bit?
What have you found
now that you're here
that you didn't expect?
Let me answer the
second question,
and then go to the first one.
What surprised me, the
pleasant surprise is
just the incredible community,
coming back and being
able to work every day
with a group of colleagues,
whether they're faculty,
or staff, or students
who are bright, doing good
work, have good values.
I mean, I come to work every
day with a bounce in my step.
I pinch myself that I get
to work here because it's
such an amazing community.
And I always knew it was great.
I forgot how wonderful it was.
And I think that's something
that we have to just remember.
Sometimes we take it for
granted in today's world.
That we have the luxury of doing
what we do here is amazing.
So that's the
wonderful surprise.
The less-than-wonderful
surprise is
our systems are still terrible.
And you can't-- like, how
many faculty do we have?
And you have three different
sources of information on it.
So I know we're working
on it, and it's just part
of the beauty of MIT, of that.
I think what I learned in
these other experiences, which
I hope will shape how I
try to do the work as dean,
at Brown, as provost, provost
is a really tough job.
And because you
really are the CEO,
and you're the front line
of so many of the challenges
that happen.
And you have to make
unpopular decisions.
You have to.
It's part of the job.
You're not going to make
friends by being a provost--
real friends.
And--
[LAUGHTER]
Yeah, there's a lot
of transactional,
like, hey, and forget
it, and stuff like that.
And what I learned there was
the importance of really going
out and listening to people in
the community, to the students,
to the faculty, to the staff
when there were tough moments,
and I was on the other side,
and they were yelling at me,
or when there were
common issues, et cetera.
And being able to tap
into the collective wisdom
of the community is
really important.
You can't do everything.
You have to prioritize.
We know a lot, but we just
don't know everything.
And so how do we
actually embrace
the richness and diversity
of our community and use
that to inform us.
That was the number one
lesson I learned at Brown.
And I think that's
something that I really
feel I need to
continue doing here now
that I'm back at MIT Sloan.
And at Apple, I learned
many, many things.
And it's an amazing company.
It reminds me a lot
of MIT, actually--
filled with engineers doing
great work, et cetera.
Many MIT people are there.
But I lived in San Francisco,
and I would take often
the Apple Bus from--
an early in the morning bus from
San Francisco down to Cupertino.
I was by far the oldest
person on the bus.
And most of them were the
age of our MBA students.
And while a couple of them
were napping, what I noticed
is that most of them
were consuming content.
They were listening
to a podcast.
They were watching a video.
They were reading
a short article.
They were doing something.
And I was sort of
watching this, and I'm
like, we need to meet our
students where they are,
not where we think [INAUDIBLE].
We have to think about, what are
the different ways, and bits,
and bytes that we can actually
get people on their commute,
in their work, whatever,
to educate them?
And so that's
something that I hope
to be able to integrate
more in Sloan.
I totally agree.
As you were talking,
you described
a recent SHASS-Sloan
collaboration which earned us
a couple of Nobel prizes.
And to me, that's a
reminder that the potential
for collaboration is not
just in terms of contributing
to the MIT of the future.
But it's also on
the research front.
I mean, we, together, have not
all, but many of the institute's
social scientists.
And I think that there is so
much that we can do together,
including understanding how
to adapt to the age of AI,
understanding what the right
vision is to help shape
the age of AI, as
you were saying,
so that it's something
that is good for society
and not something that
just costs us jobs.
So could you speak a
little bit about how
you see the potential of this
work in the social sciences?
So I think we have an
incredible opportunity based
on the strategic initiatives,
presidential initiatives
that Sally and Anantha have
seeded in the last 18 months
to two years,
which is important,
which is all about
bringing people together
around big issues.
And I love that MIT Sloan
faculty are integrated
in just about all of them.
I think that that's
really important.
So building on that,
what I would like to see
is how do we encourage our
faculty and students to get
engaged in projects, whether
it's around climate or energy,
or whether around
health, whether
around the human Insight,
collaborative, where
we're doing work together.
Because at universities,
I think you all know this.
If you really want
people to get together,
they get together
really for two reasons.
It's not like by
serving on committees
because they tolerate each
other when they're on committees
and stuff like that.
They get together when
they do work together,
when they do research together,
or when they teach and mentor
students together.
That's the opportunity.
And so now that we have this
structure that's bringing people
together, how might we deepen
it by thinking about how we
do more collaborative research?
Which is exactly what I had when
I was a graduate student here.
The experience I had as
a grad student was not
like what my other
political science grad
student colleagues at other
universities were having.
That's part of the
MIT secret sauce.
Let's do more of that.
So I would like Sloan
to-- in any way it can,
to deepen those
relationships and, again, do
more collaborative research,
and even collaborative teaching,
which I think is important.
Rick, thank you.
Thank you for your remarks.
But more importantly,
thank you for your vision,
and thank you for being back.
Thank you for being back to MIT.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
[APPLAUSE]
Great.
Thanks.
That was good.