If you take a slinky and stretch it out
like this, it represents the space
between Earth and the North Star. Quite
a ways to travel. But if we can somehow
find a way to expand the space behind us
and contract the space in front of us,
then we've made it most of the way to
the North Star without having moved
hardly at all. Now, this sounds like
science fiction, but NASA is actually
funding some really, really early
research related to the Alcubier warp
drive, which would allow us to appear to
be breaking the universe's speed limit
by bending space itself around us. The
space in this bubble hasn't been warped,
so you still experience time the same
way you normally would. That's different
from if your ship itself was traveling
close to the speed of light, where time
would pass more slowly. So all NASA's
doing now is trying to create teeny tiny
warp fields in order to see if this sort
of thing is even possible. And if it is,
we're still probably a millennium away
from actually using it. For more MIT
moments from MIT Open Learning, like,
subscribe, or follow.