let me first start with some
Administration so actually some of you
noticed that the pet problem number
2B there's a slight problem I posted a
comment about this in the website uh and
I'm going to so there's an assumption I
want you to make for problem Tob just
look at the website and the announcement
if you have any questions come to me
okay so that's one thing the other thing
is uh in uh not well next week is
Thanksgiving so Happy Thanksgiving and
uh the week after I'm actually away
giving some kinot talk but we're gonna
actually it worked out really well
because uh the topic of that lecture is
going to be about what's called bargs or
batch arguments
uh that would lead us kind of in the
final class to get kind of our snars
that we were kind of you know building
for and that lecture is covers a work by
three authors Jane jyn uh uh
um korti Jane and Jin and Jen Jung Jin
is Gonna Come here and present the
results so you'll get the author kind of
presenting the relevant work and then
the final class will'll kind of wrap
everything up and show you how to get
kind of the what we work for this entire
semester okay so just kind of what we're
going to focus on uh for today so any
questions about Administration about
questions from last class anything
before we kind of go into the
material
yeah when doing the homework I realiz
one thing I'm not sure like something
change with GK GK only has like the ad
and the M case right but there's no is
there way to get subtraction
work so let's talk come to me after
class okay okay uh okay any any other
questions I'll talk about this after
class okay so what's uh what's the the
plan for today or where we kind of left
off last class and what we're heading
for uh today so last class we defined
kind of the phir Paradigm so kind of
from the beginning what did we do we
showed kind of this kind of interactive
protocols and then we showed like uh
from example gkr which is only for bound
to depth computations then we showed you
can build from that a PCP and then use
that PCP to kind of shrink it using
cryptography and get actually for
message that was the kilan mikali
protocol for message protocol proofs or
arguments computationally sound proofs
for all of NP where it's very succinct
okay so you can kind of take any witness
for NP and instead of sending this
witness which is long I don't know ply n
Bits I'm going to shrink it to kind of
via an interactive protocols so four
messages to get it kind of the number of
bit is proportional to the security
parameter which can be much much smaller
so that's what we showed that was the
kilan mikali protocol but that was four
messages so now we're kind of towards
the home stretch we want to kind of get
around these four messages and reduce it
down to just one message so how do we do
that so last class we defined this uh uh
Paradigm called the fimir Paradigm it
was introduced exactly for this purpose
to kind of eliminate Interra inter
eliminate interaction from interactive
protocols uh so by essentially replacing
the verifier with a hash
function and now there was a question
it's a very nice very simple very
efficient kind of Paradigm very elegant
in my opinion but then there's the
question is it sound if you start with
an interactive protocol that you can
prove soundness when you apply the pH
Paradigm is the protocol or the proof
still sound that's the question and uh
what we proved for for this protocol Kil
meali protocol is it is sound if you
apply the F Paradigm but if you this
hash function is kind of what's like uh
is a random Oracle so instead of being
actually an explicit kind of circuit if
we think of it as a completely random
function that both parties have Oracle
access to then it's sound but in real
world there's there's no kind of random
Oracles in the sky that all parties have
access to we actually use specific
circuits uh to replace this hash
function
and then there was uh kind of this
question of when we actually use the F
Paradigm with with a specific circuit
with a specific uh hash that's
computable by specific kind of circuit
is it
sound okay and that was kind of open for
a long time it was a very very important
open problem because fut is viewed all
over the place in practice so kind of
understanding whether it's secure or not
is very important and we had we could
only analyze it in the random Oracle
model so now not in real world uh
settings and as I pointed out last time
there the random Oracle model actually
worked out to be a very good proxy so
none of the schemes in practice actually
that we proved Security in the random
Oracle model turned out to be broken so
turns out it's a very very good proxy
for
security but still kind of at least for
me as a theoretician I want to
understand kind of why you know when we
replace it with an actual function an
actual program why is it secure
so uh and frankly I still don't
understand why it's such a good proxy I
have to say it's still kind of it's
surprising to me that never ever we had
like it's really really kind of
approximates you know Security in to
Good Very uh very well even though as I
mentioned we do have counter examples we
do have examples contrived not real
world examples but contrived examples
where the protocol are secure in the
random morical model and not secure in
you know um when applied F and actually
interestingly Kean mik is one of them
it's actually one of the protocols where
actually it was proven that if you use a
certain hash function Collision
resistant but certain hash function then
actually you can prove security if no
matter which specific function you use
for the it will for the uh for the
function it will not be secure but this
specific hash function which is
Collision resistant is contrived so we
still don't have kind of real world
natural application of where security
was proven in the random Oracle model
but turned out to be false in the in the
real
world okay so uh so so kind of that's
where we're heading to okay trying to
prove the security of or the soundness
of the F uh Paradigm and kind of along
the way what we did is I defined a
certain protocol uh which is zero know
so we kind of took a detour talked about
zero knowledge and we looked at a spefic
specific protocol zero knowledge
protocol for graph uh for hamiltonicity
for hamilt whether a graph has a
hamiltonian cycle or not that's an NP
complete problem and so here's just a
recap because we'll look at it again
today so here's a proof and three three
message uh proof system the prover is
trying to prove to the verifier that a
graph G has a hamiltonian cycle and we
want to do it in zero knowledge so in a
proof that gives no information and the
way we did it we said okay the prover so
the prover has the hamiltonian cycle he
does not want to reveal any information
about this hamiltonian cycle to the
verifier what would the prover do he
will choose a random permutation
Pi he will commit kind of put in a safe
locked safe uh only the hamiltonian
cycle of Pi of G so if C is the kind of
the path the Honan cycle in G he will
compute Pi of the cycle okay to the
cycle inside Pi of
G and then he's going to get a random
bit and he's going to give an answer
what is the answer if the bit is zero
he's just going to open the
cycle uh he's just gonna open uh the
cycle okay so or maybe I should say like
Pi of C so he's going to open only the
places where where there's a where uh
there's a cycle and the guy's going to
check that yes it's an indeed
cycle okay but we need to make sure that
the cycle has something to do with the
graph itself so if the B is one then we
check that indeed that you you give the
permutation you do not give the permuted
cycle otherwise you'll give information
so you only give them the permutation
and you open only non edges in pi of G
so now you know everywhere in pi of G
that there's no Edge in the this
commitment there's no
edges okay so again let me just
emphasize to recap this commitment you
should it's committing to n if n is the
number of nodes in the graph it's
committing to N squared values where
there's a one if there's an edge zero if
there's not an edge okay for any i j it
says zero or one whether it's an edge or
not an edge and when we if B equals zero
we only open kind of the places where
there's a hamiltonian cycle we check
that everything there should be one and
you check that it kind of closes that it
corresponds to a cycle and if B equals 1
you give the entire permutation and you
open the non-edges
okay and now the claim was that this is
indeed zero knowledge and the intuition
was well if you open zero he doesn't
learn anything because he just gets a
random cycle has nothing to do with the
graph just any random cycle that's what
he sees okay he could have generated
there no information about the graph and
if he gets b equals 1 then what does he
see a random permutation and a bunch of
openings of zero that's no information
and as we said the soundness here is
only half that's the problem for only
half you can cheat because if you
guessed a cheating improver I can guess
B and if I guess b c if I guess B I can
at least cheat on that b so I can always
kind of even if G doesn't have a
hamiltonian cycle I can always answer
correctly on one of them but not
both so if I guess your P I can answer I
can cheat you so this gives only
soundness half okay this is just a recap
and that was kind of I motivated this
kind of show that this is not even
secure in the random oracal model so
actually to get Security even in the
random Oracle model you need to repeat
in
parallel so today we're going to cons
when I say now PV like uh this so when I
say like the protocol PV let me think of
I'm I want you to throughout this class
let think of it is parallel repetition
of this
with like secur security parameter
Lambda copies okay so now I mean sound s
is really not good for us that's not
what we want so think of it that we
repeat this in parallel security
parameter number of times okay so in
other words the prover Lambda number of
times each time chooses a fresh
permutation
Pi commits so he does this Lambda times
each time with a new permutation Pi this
is very important and people see why
it's important that the per
ation it's fresh each time if you use
the same permutation and you open b0 B1
you learn
everything so each time you give a fresh
kind of random permutation you send in
Lambda times you get a B for each one
and now you send a message for each
one okay so that was the protocol now
there's now we Pro that it's secure in
the random Orco model actually we proved
that any
cound protocol that has negligible
soundness is secure in the random
morical model we showed that last time
so it's secure in the random morical
model and now there's the question okay
is it secure in the standard model when
we use
F and what we're going to show today is
yes it is secure so that's kind of the
first thing we're going to show that
this protocol pnv and again when I say
p&v throughout today's class it's a
parall repeated version okay so we're
going to show that PV are C when you
apply F in the standard model okay for
some commitment not every commitment so
we'll open this box a little bit and
show that there exists a a very natural
commitment scheme that with that
commitment scheme we can argue that this
is secure when the hash function will
actually construct a hash function I'll
give you an exact hash function and say
if you use this hash function for the
you'll get security or
soundness okay but this hash function to
argue you'll need to assume something
about the hatch I mean you'll need to
this hatch function assumes some
cryptography and the cryptography it
assumes is the existence of a fully
homomorphic encryption I'll Define what
that is but not just a fully homomorphic
encryption we'll assume also that it's
circular secure fully homomorphic
encryption I'll Define what that is as
well I just want to say actually today
we don't need the circular secure
version we know how to get rid of it but
what I'm going to explain today does use
this version It's just simpler okay and
this can be uh this we believe this is
true there's instantiation based on
circular secure learning with air lwe
but we don't need to get into these
details okay so that's what we're going
to do in the uh first part of the class
and the second part of the class so now
you can say okay let's say we Pro F why
am I obsessed with this protocol andless
Pro f for this protocol so what like why
why is that why should you be engaged so
let me try to give you motivation for
you to stay awake and listen to me so
why is it so this protocol in particular
is so is very important why
so what I'm going to show is when you
apply F chamir to this protocol you get
what's called a noninteractive zero
knowledge proof niic for short so uh we
get once we we do that for this protocol
because it was Zero knowledge we can
argue that when you apply F you get
non-interactive zero knowledge and to
get noninteractive zero knowledge based
on lates was a open question for a very
very long time and this was resolved in
this paper that I'm going to present in
this work that I'm going to present you
by ketti Lombardi and uh Wix so kind of
the one of the motivating examples is
that we get this non-interactive zero
knowledge that's one but the other
motivating example is that actually this
technique is much more General okay the
technique of F that that I'm going to
show you is much more General than just
for this protocol actually it's a very
general technique that can be used for
many protocols and in particular we used
it later this exact technique and I'm
going to try to show you how we can how
it can be used to get uh to show that
the GK protocol that we studied in the
beginning actually is secure in the
standard model uh in uh when you apply
Fu to it you get security under learning
with air or FHA again as I mentioned the
circle of security can be prevented I'm
just showing you the result I uses it
for Simplicity okay so so it's not just
for for this protocol to get n it you
can actually use to get snars and
moreover what you'll see uh after
Thanksgiving that Jang Jong is going to
present he's going to use this exact
same tool to get uh batch Arguments for
NP so this kind of is baked into all our
our results almost okay so it's very
it's actually very general and
nice
yes like relate
to because last uh last time we like a
little bit over the result of w bar
about the fact I can't have great
question great great great question okay
let me let me review your question
because you have a great question so
last time I kind of showed you that
there's actually a tension if you have
an interactive proof that is zero
knowledge then I kind of gave you this
high level intuition that if it is
really zero knowledge you cannot apply
fimir to it it will
fail and and here I'm saying oh we're
going to apply F to it and not only that
we're going to get zero knowledge not
interative zero knowledge like wait wait
wait wait wait last time you said you
can't get zero knowledge now you say
this I'm kind of contradicting myself
here okay so again let me repeat it just
to make sure we're all on board last
time I said a protocol that is zero
knowledge cannot be F
secure now I'm saying guess what this
protocol is fair to me
secure okay so first of all
indeed I have no reason to believe that
this protocol is when you repeat it in
parallel that it's zero knowledge we
know that it's zero knowledge if and the
probability H in without parallel
paration we know that it's zero
knowledge if you repeat it sequentially
if you repeat it in parallel we don't
know that it's zero knowledge
anymore that's first second so now
you're saying next thing you can say is
oh so now we know that it's not zero
knowledge
almost almost actually the result does
show that Peril repetition does not
preserve zero knowledge but actually
it's not going to be completely because
I'm going to change the commitment in a
way that you'll see in a minute so not
quite but then you can say okay but how
do you get niic out of it how do you get
none it seems completely opposite
because I just said f is in
contradictory of of zero knowledge and
not you apply F and you get zero
knowledge
knowled okay so what we get is non
interactive zero knowledge and
non-interactive zero knowledge the
simulator I I didn't Define what it is
so it's hard I'll explain it as I go but
the simulator has more power than the
cheating prover remember if the way the
reason I said that if you have a zero
knowledge protocol why can't you apply
fat because we said look the verifier
can a cheting verifier can use the F
chir function he can behave maliciously
he's behaving with the F chir function
now you should be able to simulate The
View so if you have an efficient
simulator that simulates the view for X
in the language he can't he's an
efficient simulator he doesn't know what
which instances are in the language or
outside the language it's NP it's hard
languages so he probably will succeed in
simulating the view of instances outside
the language otherwise he's like a p you
know he's a kind of
distinguisher you can use him to show
that the language is an in not an NP so
he you know so so and that's why there
cannot be a simulator because the
simulator he can act like a cheating
prover in the non-interactive setting he
cannot because we're giving the
simulator extra power to choose the
common reference stram we'll talk about
it when we get there but it's a model
that's a little different so actually I
planned I'm going to talk about this
more in length when I get there but
since you asked I want to to give a
preview so indeed there's tension and
we'll see how to overcome it it's
actually really interesting that kind of
uh you know uh that it's a belief that
you can't get
use once zero knowledge is in kind of in
contradiction to but actually we use to
get the non-interactive version of zero
knowledge but we we'll go into detail
when we get there great question a any
any other
questions so my plan next is to prove
the secure the sound of this protocol
the Peril repeated version under F but
any question before we go
there okay so let's I I let the the
result so as I said this is a result of
a ketti lombardian weeks from
2019 it's so beautiful and simple so
this was an open question for a very
long time uh and we I I want to give it
to you as a kind of a evidence or an
example of something that we thought was
so hard so hard so hard and then comes
if you just think about it like a little
differently you twist a little bit it's
so easy
so I want I'm G to have you guys try to
come up with a proof okay of this so
let's try to do it interactively and I
want you to prove to me that this
protocol PV but think of it again par
repeated and in parallel it
sound okay so I'm going to give you a
few hints and we'll get there together
okay so one thing that's really nice
about this
protocol is uh so okay I want to argue
okay I want when we let's recall what is
the F chamir Paradigm the F chamir
Paradigm says that you know we choose
some hash function some hash key
from you know there's some f hash
function that generates a hash ke and
now we want to say Let Let Me denote for
Simplicity this kind of these messages
by alpha beta and gamma okay even for
now let's even not think of this
specific protocol okay let's think of
just a protocol the prover sends Alpha
verifier sends beta prover sends gamma
okay even don't let's not even go into
the specific details I want to prove to
come up with a hash function so I want
to come up with a hash function H which
you know generates a key for a hash and
then
evaluates that's just a hash
function such that this remains sound
okay so I have this there's some NP
language X I want to prove whether it's
in the language or not this is my proof
system and I want to find a hash
function for which is
sound so what does this at first it
seems like it should be very easy why
should it be very easy look take let's
say x not in the language we need to
focus on X not in the language X in the
language it's complete like completeness
that's easy I you cannot cheat okay so
now what do I need to say I say let I
want that for any X on the language so
fix One X on the language I want to
argue that you cannot find an
alpha and beta which is H of Alpha and
the gamma that's
accepting but now this is a proof system
so every Alpha has very few betas for
which there even exists a GMA that's
accepting right so again because it's f
X the language first thing we notice
just by definition of a proof that for
every Alpha any possible Alpha there
exists very few betas for which there
exists an accepting answer so there
exists few very few
betas such that there exists
gamma for which Alpha Beta gamma are
accepted
okay so that's the first thing we notice
because it's a proof system by the
virtue of a proof system for every Alpha
there are very very few actually not in
this protocol specifically there's one
one because
if the graph G does not have a
hamiltonian
cycle take a cheating Pro the gener
sends alpha alpha is a bunch of
commitments now let's actually each
commitment look either they're sitting
aonian cycle or
not you can't answer both questions we
know that if you can answer both
questions well it won't be sound so you
can only answer one question and each
one can only answer one so this protocol
it's even for this specific protocol
let's assume even let let me be let's
even
assume what what any proof tells you is
that for every Alpha there exist a few
but you know let's for Simplicity
because that's the protocol we're
dealing with
let's
Suppose there exists a unique this is a
symbol for Unique by the way there
exists a unique beta that can be
extended now all we need to do is not
hit that
beta so all we need I mean think about
it seems so easy all we need is Def find
a hash H like a hash key such that Ian
of hash key and in Alpha is not equal so
let me call for every Alpha there exists
a single beta let me call it beta bad
like that's a that's the beta we want to
avoid okay so for every Alpha there
exist a
single beta bad of alpha it's a function
of alpha for every Alpha for every
commandment there's a different either
you can answer zero or one so for any
Alpha there exists One Challenge beta
for which the prover can cheat now the
cheating prover wants to hit that bad
beta because that's what he can cheat
on our job of protecting this is to find
to make sure that every Alpha does not
equal to this beta
bad but how hard can it be we just want
to avoid
one you know what let me here let me
give a
suggestion IAL hash key or me here h of
alpha equals beta
bad of alpha +
1 it's not better to bad I avoid the bad
one I'm going to use this for my hash
function anybody see a problem with this
yeah well it's not really unique
because no actually I'm I'm using the
computation okay good so what will say
well actually it's not uh unique because
the commitment here has a computational
assumption but actually this commitment
will be statistically binding so it's
only the hiding is the zero knowledge is
computational but actually you can open
it suppos there's really like you're
binded okay you can really only open it
in one like you can't open two different
ways many permutations for one that's
fine that's fine but you're right
there's many permutation but suppose you
can open to both then you can give me
both this message and this message if
you give me both this and both this it
means
that you have to have this G must have a
cycle
because I know that there's a cycle and
guess what it's not in the non-edges to
the cycle has to be in the
edges so so you cannot really cannot you
can open only one okay so again all I
want it seems like so easy I have a
proof system for every Alpha the
actually the pro can only cheat on one
single beta all I want to do is avoid
that beta
okay I'll give just avoid that do beta
plus
one this is delicate anybody see why why
this doesn't
work yeah don't you have open commitment
to find out which is the bad beta
exactly the problem is Computing beta
bad is really hard how do you know what
beta B for example so Computing this is
hard actually if it were easy you
wouldn't need interaction at all it
would B and P you have a suing for p you
just give Alpha you you compute this is
the beta and the then you give gamma and
everything's information
theoretic the problem is
Computing the power of this thing is
lies in the the power of this
interaction lies on the fact that
Computing what the bad beta is is
hard here for example how do you know
which beta you can cheat on well if you
open the Commandment then you see okay
is there you
know is there a lot of ones is it only
cycle but you need to open this
commitment so Computing this beta is
hard without additional
information okay so now now what do we
do so we can't give that as a hash
function because this is a hard
computation
okay so here's the first kind
of uh so there are a few aha moments in
this paper the first one is you know
what maybe if this
commitment had some trapo maybe you know
there's some trapo information that with
the trapo it becomes
easy so let then let's do
that let's use trapo in our hash
function okay so now two things I'm
going to do next first show you how you
construct a commitment with a trapo that
will also be useful here so it's going
to kind of be a stepping stone so so
your specific commitment which is what
we use which has a trapo to make beta
easy and then we're going to deal with
uh the next issue that comes up which
kind of the next aha moment appears in
which is well you can't use this trapo
and the clear because if you just that
you can't give the cheating prover theat
you can't give the cheating people like
the trap door actually the problem will
not be the cheating prover the problem
if you give the trap door it's not zero
knowledge anymore so that this trap
don't needs to stay hidden you can't
just use it like put the the reason it's
a commitment it has a purpose it's we
don't put things in the clear for a
reason
so well first see you can make it
efficient given the trapo and then we'll
show how this nevertheless even though
we need to keep this trapo secret the
fact the mere fact that it exists can be
useful for us to to do the fure meal
okay
questions let me remind you that I
really like
questions good bad all of them they're
all fantastic yeah is like the Comm
random screen coming to the second like
step where you make the Trap like someh
vom enough not so the the common random
string will be used in many places the
first place it's going to be used is
even to make to make sure my commitment
has a trapo so and then it's going to be
used again and again it's going to vied
all over the place so we we'll see that
next so any any other questions before
we
proceed okay so step one let me just
tell you how to construct the commitment
so that it has a trapo and the way I'm
going to do it is just using encryption
scheme okay so let me Define the notion
of public key encryption and did we
Define public encryption last
time no right okay so okay so let me
Define the notion of encryption and
we'll use that as our commitment scheme
okay so what is an
encryption so a public key
encryption with uh message space there's
a message space associated with
it and these are the messages that we're
going to encrypt it consists
of three
algorithms so one is
Gen not to be it has its own key
generation not to be confused with a
hash function that generates hash key
this
generates public key and secret key so
this just
generates a pair of public key and a
secret key let me just mention three
PPT algorithms so we have probabilistic
polinomial time algorithms the first
just generates two keys a public key and
a secret
key the encryption algorithm takes as
input a public key and a message from
the message space and it
generates a cipher
text okay from a cipher text space and
the third algorithm decrypt so it takes
a secret key and a cipher text
and it generates a message in the
message space or or like bot namely I
failed I tried to the cryp but I
failed okay and the properties we want
the first is correctness or
completeness which just says if you
encrypt a message and then you decrypt
it you get your message back okay so it
just says for every M for any message if
you the probability
that you decrypt so the probability over
sample secret key and Public public key
and Secret Key from Key
genen and then use the secret key to
decrypt an encryption of
n so it says if you encrypt n you
generate a pair of keys you encrypt the
message M and then you decrypt it you
get back the message with probability
one okay that's just correctness what do
you expect if you take a message you
encrypt it and then you decrypt it you
should get the message
back the important property then is
security or what's called semantic
security
and this says that any two messages if
you encrypt one or encrypt the other can
distinguish between the two they look
the same they're computationally and
distinguishable so it just says for
every m0 and M1 in the message space so
typically we think by the way the length
of M is revealed typically we think of
the message spaces having fixed size for
us throughout
this entire lecture and often is the
case we can think of M as just
containing two messages the zero message
or the one message and if you want to
encrypt longer message you just encrypt
bit by bit by bit that's a common way to
do encryption not in practice but in
theory in practice it's often not fast
enough but in theory you can just
encrypt each bit separately but in
general for any two message in the
message space if it's just if it's just
01 then for the message zero for the
message one the claim is that if you
generate public key according to gen and
encrypt
m0 this is indistinguishable
computationally IND distinguishable from
generating a public key according to gen
and
encrypting message
one so for any messages you know the
messages I'm I'm telling you I'm
encrypting m z or
M1 you can't tell the difference I'm
giving you don't know I'm giving you one
of them you have no idea if them zero
encrypted or them one encrypted okay not
there's no Randomness over the messages
for any two mess fixed messages you
don't know if I encrypt yeah so even you
don't know if I encrypt and if I give
you two encryptions of zero I give you
encryption of 01 can't tell the
difference okay so that that's the
definition and we have these public key
encryption schemes under a whole slew of
of uh of assumptions ltis based
assumption not lce based like a discreet
log that we saw earlier in the semester
uh and so on but I don't want to talk
about instantiation because this is more
kind of class on proof systems and I
don't want to make it too hardcore uh
crypto so let me just use this nacho how
to actually construct this but we have
many instantiation constructions but
suppose we have this let me show you how
what what the commitment would be so now
what I want the commitment to be instead
of commitment make this an encryption
let me actually put
another
color so make this be an
encryption with some public key of
Pi so what I'm telling the prover now
I'm telling him look I want to be able
in the analysis at least to open up
there and see kind
of what where the ones are and where the
zero so that later I'll be able to
understand where the non-edges are and
so what's the bad
beta so now I uh I want to tell the
prover so please don't the commitment I
want you to send me is the encryption
now a Tiding it's still hiding yeah
nobody uh so nobody so the it's still
zero knowledge still satisfied kind of
it's locked it's like the verifier can't
doesn't has no idea what's in
there and supposedly it and it's so
binding because uh because you know once
you encrypt you're stuck it's like it's
it's uh uh the message you're the
message is sitting there because then
you can use a secret key to decrypt it
so it really has the hiding and binding
property great it's like a real
commandment
scheme
yeah
yeah does publishing encryption imply
that there's no possibility of a second
secret key that to something
else okay great question great question
so the the great so you're asking wait
what of the public key has many secret
Keys associated with it and one of them
decrypts to M and the other one decrypts
to M Prime let's say so no here I Say No
by my definition no because my
correctness
says that if you choose public key in
secret key pair with ability one you
will always get your message back so
there's no secret key that will give you
a different message that's my definition
so you're what you're proposing is not
for me it's not uh doesn't satisfy my my
definition so now use a public use a
public encryption that satisfies my
definition so now we kind of now you're
binded good great question the these are
really really great questions
yeah here in the expression you're
chosing publicy and secret keq all come
from the same G function yeah what if
like another like it doesn't gu anything
about like a different okay very very
good question very good question so what
what uh so the point was the
following look we have all these
guarantees the correctness and the
security assuming the public key is
generated according to
gen now my question here who generates
this public key
how do I know it's generate according to
Jen if we let the approver generates
generate the public
key he may may then maybe it's a bad
public key that is never going to appear
here and for that bad public key maybe
your concern is valid maybe you can open
it in different
ways and you're completely right that is
a problem actually even in our it's it's
not a hypothetical problems a hypoth
medal problem our scheme that we use
that we want to get we want to get this
andus assumption that specific scheme we
use has that property has that problem
that if the key is generated badly
actually there's no binding I can cheat
I can open two different ways I will
never be able to do that if I generate
according to Jen but if I generate it
maliciously I can choose a very bad
public key nobody will be able to tell
the difference it will look like a good
publicy but it's actually generated
completely
differently and it would have never
appeared in J and with that public key
there's no no uh correctness and I can
cheat and I can do whatever I
want so very good you you you found the
the problem in this
approach so what do we do how do we fix
it so this comes to your question in the
beginning well you know what let's
assume that there's a trusted party that
generates this publicy for us so let's
assume for now that there's kind of a
common reference string we all agree
there's like a public key sitting here
that's in the kind of what's called a a
common reference string or common random
string everybody knows it both the
approver and the verifier we all agree
on this public key and we assume that it
was trusted like generated according to
Jen nobody has the secret key okay
nobody has the secret key we'll never
need to open the secret key so in this
protocol what we do what do I do I'm
approver I encrypt bit by bit so how do
I encrypt I use random so I didn't say
but this encryption is a randomized
protocol so I choose Randomness I
encrypt the bid I choose Randomness I
encrypt the next bit I choose Randomness
I encrypt the next and so on so forth
and when I'm asked to open I reveal my
Randomness I so look how I encrypt it
see there's Randomness I took the
encryption with public key and my bid 01
with this Randomness and see that's
what's written here so I I can just open
by by without using secret key Nobody
Knows the secret key the secret key is
gone someone just came with the public
key and I use the I I open here not with
a secret key but I I I show you the
randomness that I Ed to encrypt and that
kind of uh you know uh is an opening for
me yeah does that mean your CRS be like
a fully like uniformly randoming because
if you were to read out the public also
like secretly so okay so the question
was great great question the the
question was does that mean that the CRS
here cannot be truly random because it's
not truly random it's a public key a
public key may not be truly
random and the answer is well first of
all some publicy have happen to be to
truly random the public key for this
schem scheme is not truly random however
it's
indistinguishable from being truly
random now so the scheme we actually use
the public has the property it's not
random it's like a lw2 for those who
know what learning with a is but it's
not it's that's not truly random however
it is indistinguishable from
random now if you have soundness with
public key that indistinguishable from
random soundness should hold even if
it's completely
random so actually you can make this
completely random and actually in the
paper they actually take advantage of
that because if the public key is
completely random then you get
statistical zero knowledge computational
sound is whereas if it's you can play
around with in this protocol especially
when you go to the N to the non-active
version there's a tension you can either
get statistical soundness and
computational zero knowledge or or
statistical zero knowledge and
computational soundness and you can play
with this public key whether to make it
kind of the true public key in which
case you get statistical soundness and
computational zero knowledge or if you
want to take like a fake public key
which is the all zero and then you get
comput ational soundness and statistical
zerom so you can kind of play um with
these uh with these
things okay so this is the the protocol
for which we'll show the fing holds okay
so again the commitment is just replaced
with a public
encryption
yeah Comm reference I mean the public by
for example change the the way of
opening for example we also uh also
require approver to provide the random
for for
J oh that's a good okay I didn't okay
good so what you're saying good good
suggestion what you're saying is you're
saying wait how about he gives us public
key it can be malicious but when he
opens we'll ask him okay so I'll tell
you the problem with that if when he
opens he gives the randomness he used so
you're sit why don't he give the
randomness he used to generate this
public key and now you know that it's a
valid public key you'll that will indeed
ensure soundness however that will break
the zero knowledge because once you give
the randomness you also give the secret
key away because this Randomness was
used to generate both of them and if the
secret key then you lost the the zero
knowledge but great suggestion okay
great you guys it's clear that you're
thinking which is fantastic great
suggestions
any any other questions before
we we move
on okay so okay so we're making progress
now what do we know so let me uh hide
this encryption for a
second let's go back here now okay now I
want you actually to for forget that
this was an encryption because we'll use
another encryption okay and I don't want
you to be confused with this encryption
the other encryption what I want you to
remember about the commitment that
there's some trap door like a secret key
I'll call it trap door on purpose
because we'll have another encryption
which will have a secret key so I want
what I want you to remember about this
commitment is that there's some trapo
information that with that trapo
information you can open and know which
B is
bad okay so a trapdoor has a a
commitment has some trapdoor information
okay which allows you kind of to open it
in that case open the encryption and
then you know where the ones are and
that will help you
decide
uh a where where the bad be
lies actually know I think I I need to
also add a commitment to pie
there because otherwise
I'm how do you know which maybe you can
tell anyone way if you add a commitment
to Pi it's easier
but if you don't add a commitment to Pi
is it clear that just by seeing ones
it's easy to
test
uh
a yeah I guess I guess if you open both
you can see both yeah I don't think you
need it okay uh but anyway so so so good
sorry uh so so now what I want to I want
to do I want to say here's my hash
function it has trapo hardwire to it
once he knows the trap door it's a trap
door depends on the public key on the
kind of the CRS it doesn't depend on the
actual once he has the trap door he'll
know what the bad thing is and
done okay it would be it's one can say
Okay use
this as the fure Mir hash
function it's efficient it's good
however as we said the problem is then
you know the trap door it's sitting
there you know you know the trap door
and once you the trap door it's not zero
knowledge so that's the
problem and then there were attempts to
try to
do okay let's obfuscate these things and
a lot of kind of hammers were thrown in
this direction and it resulted in crazy
assumptions and anyway there was a long
kind of line of work well that's what we
tried to
do okay but then then here is their idea
so now I'm can tell you the next aha
moment so again one option is to throw
kind of what's called obfuscation at
this for those who don't know
obfuscation don't worry about it
essentially garbling so that the trap
door will be really hidden there nobody
would be able to find it and even that
it was like a messy approach that we
tried and we got really really strong
assumptions which I have no idea if
they're true or not it was kind of a
messy approach that a bunch of us bunch
of papers kind of followed that approach
very complicated and you know okay then
came this paper and here is the the
here's the beautiful idea okay so the
beautiful idea was the following they
said you know what yeah you can't give
trapo that's a problem give an
encryption of trapo forget about this
encryption right that's a different
encryption so now fresh new
encryption why don't you give encryption
let me denote the encryption of trapo
here by hat that's off a common way we
use fully homomorphic encryption which
I'm going to Define next so they said
put in this in the in the function an
encryption of the trap door that helps
you open the
commitment I like so okay and then what
what do we can do with the cyppher text
we can't do anything with it cyppher
text is like junk what do we can do with
that so the idea the idea was you know
what don't just use any encryption use
what's called a fully homomorphic
encryption what is a fully homomorphic
encryption I'll explain that next but
essentially what it does it allows you
to compute unencrypted data okay so a a
fly homomorphic encryption is exactly
the
same as a uh encryption scheme so a fom
morphic it's a public key
encryption so let me write a fully
homomorphic public encryption scheme is
encryption scheme gen encrypt and
decrypt but it also allows you to do
computation and encrypted data so what
do I mean there's an eval
function it takes a bunch of Cipher
texts and it can do computation on the B
hiding underneath the cyppher
Tex so it takes a public
key a description of a circuit C think
of it with additions and multiplication
M
two and it gets a cipher text so
encryption of one of B1 bit one let me
think of it now as I said think of it as
the message space being zero and one so
it gets encryption of bits let's say
encryption or I'll just call it Cipher
text Cipher text one up to Cipher text
n each one encrypting a single bit the
circuit takes as input n Bits and
produces a
bit and it outputs some Cipher
text and this Cipher
text if here you have encryption of B1
B2 up to
BN this Cipher text should have
encryption of C of B1 up to BN
okay so what this eval does it gets
encryption of bits and it can kind of
compute an encryption of the addition of
the bits encryption of the
multiplication of the bits and so on so
forth it can do arbitrary computation it
can compute an arbitrary circuit c c
goes from 01 to the N to
01 it can be arbitary computation under
the the so let me I'll just write
maybe I'll write here the completeness
property for the eval so I wrote the
completeness property where all you do
is decrypt if you encrypt and decrypt
you get back the message the Evan also
has a completeness property which
essentially says so let me just write it
down so completeness of eval I'll write
it
here it says that for every
B1 up to
BN
and uh the
probability that when you decrypt Evan
oh sorry for every
C for every circuit C when you decrypt
so choose a public key secret key pair
when you decrypt use the secret key to
decrypt the eval function so now
evaluate with respect to the public key
and that's the circuit C evaluate on the
on the N Cipher text corresponding to B1
up to BN so
encryption public key with
B1 up to encryption of public key on bid
b
n so encrypt each of these bits you'll
get encryption of B1 up to encryption BN
then evaluate do homomorphic
computations on these encryption bits
with respect to Circuit
C now you get a cipher text you should
get a cipher text that encrypts c of B1
of to BN and indeed the probability that
when you decrypt you get C of B1 up to
BN
is one or close to
one okay so again what eval does it does
a computation on this encrypted data it
computes an arbitrary circuit
C that that when you decrypt it and did
you get C with probability very very
close to one I wrote here one minus
negligible as opposed to one is be
because our scheme have this negative
probability of err so that's why
I okay so again high level what the FHA
allows you to do fully homop encryption
allows you to do is to do this
computation and encrypted
data so now the idea is okay so okay
questions about the fully homomorphic
encryption we're good yeah
matter what C is like oh never mind mind
like I was thinking just like uh
arithmetic or good good no that's
actually a very good question uh it's a
very good question so the question was
this circuit C what is it so the circuit
C think of it as a circuit that has
addition and multiplication Gates mod
too okay so any polinomial size uh
circuit that has addition and
multiplication Gates mod to great thank
you other questions
okay so now let's go back so now we have
an encryption scheme that we can do
computation and encrypted data now let's
go back remember where are we we're
saying all we want is to avoid this bad
we want to Hash function it's only
purpose to avoid one single point how
hard can that
be the thing I'll tell the hard problem
is it needs to avoid the bad point for
each and every Alpha that's kind of the
hard part that for every Alpha avoid the
bad one if you just wanted to avoid the
bad one for one alpha choose random
probably probably you're not going to
hit the bad one but you need to
avoid the bad one for each and every
Alpha that's kind of harder okay so now
but if we have the trapo then it's easy
but we said look we can't give the trapo
that will break zero
knowledge so instead we say you know
what let's give a homomorphic encryption
of the
trapo now now this seems like not
helpful why is it not helpful okay let's
say you can encrypt on you can compute
on encrypted data so okay do the
computation of computing bad so suppose
you have so now here's my hatch function
it has trapdoor hard wire it so think of
it like h of instead of trapo they'll
have hat of trapo why
not and it will do this computation
under the hood like with eval you know
under the hood of the encryption very
nice so now on input Alpha you will get
the
bad bad Alpha uh plus one very nice but
encrypted so why is that
helpful yeah I I guess solution but you
can also encrypt the eval encryption the
protect two different meth are not equal
again what are you saying encrypt
encrypt EV H the left hand side of the
equality
you can encrypt exactly that's kind of
what
so that's kind of what I'm doing I'm
saying this is the this is okay this
okay this is a shorthand for this is
actually
eval of this is kind of the hash key the
hash key will have kind of trapdoor in
it and an input Alpha it should output
this and what we're doing we're saying
okay and crypto or you can think of it
the Hash k being trapo and encrypt the
entire
thing you can do everything under the
hood of the encryption the problem is
you'll get it you want the output to be
different than beta you don't want the
you got a cipher
text I want I I want this to be
different than beta that's what I want I
don't want like underneath the hood to
be something that's different than
beta so this seems like a bad idea like
it gets us nowhere
yes again where are we we said if we
knew
trapdoor we would be done the hash
function the EV Val the hash function
we'll take this trapo compute beta and
output not beta you know move it by one
move one of the bits by one whatever as
long as it doesn't not the
beta and now they say you know what
let's do everything under the hood what
then we'll get an encryption why would
that not be bit like it seems like
you're not getting anywhere to me it
seemed it seemed like when they first
presented this idea I'm like okay this
seems completely useless so what now
everything is under the hood and guess
what we're almost done
yeah you take the
randomness so you know what I want to
say something even before that there's
even a mismatch
uh beta let's say consists of Lambda
bits for example in our case because we
repeated it it's Lambda bits this is not
even Lambda bits it's much more than
Lambda bits because we inced by bit it's
much bigger it it doesn't
even it's like seems like completely B
this is going to be the length of beta
time security parameter so it's
not it doesn't even correspond
to like the sizes don't even match
so it seems like an encryption is not
helpful
yeah beta bad given Alpha in oh good he
the only way he can compute beta bad is
if he has the oh how can you compute giv
the trap door you're saying
okay what yeah so what he will do the
trap door in this protocol allows you to
kind of open the
commitment okay so now you see each and
each point if it has a zero one Z One Z
one so now why why do you know what's
bet bad because now you
look if it has just a hamiltonian
cycle I mean the truth is it's easier to
see it if you have the the com the pie
suppose you always also committed to Pi
why it's just easier to see it that way
suppose I tell you don't only commit to
that commit also to your Pi now you see
what's in there either if you remove Pi
you see what if you so you see if
uh so you look at all the edges of Pi of
G and you make sure that these edges are
zero everywhere there's zero if one of
them is one you know that he won't
succeed in open in then then this is not
bad then the Beals one is not bad
because uh here or he will fail the bad
is where he will succeed a bad be the be
that like a bad beta the beta that will
allow him to succeed so now if you can
open everything now you can see if
there's one Edge Of Pi of G if there's a
non Edge that has a one then you know
okay this is definitely not bad he can
and and so he won't be able to see so
this is the bit of bad on the other hand
if all the non-edges are indeed zero you
know there's he can't open hamiltonian
cycle because there is no hamiltonian
cycle so then this becomes the so then
this becomes the bad so if you know
what's in the commitment you can tell
which one is the bad so the trap door
allows you to compute the bad
efficiently that's the point yeah so
does that me the tra the random coins
used in each
C the random coins used like the
randomness that's used inside each like
is that what the trap door is
um no I I I want I'm thinking of the
trap door as being the secret key
corresponding to the public key so you
you I'll tell you the problem the
problem of using the randomness then
it's chosen by the cheating prover and I
don't know what it I don't know how he's
going to use it I don't want to the
trapo you write the the trapo okay let
me this is an important point so note I
can open this
commitment by use giving you the
randomness that I used to generate this
commitment that would be that would be a
good
trapo but when I designed the fash
function I have no idea what the cheat
what Randomness the cheating Prov is
going to use maybe it's even
deterministic I don't know what he's
doing he may just give me a a bun I
don't know so I I I don't know ahead of
time it's random coins and different
cheating Pro will have different random
coins so I want to put something in the
CRS you know the hash function the
Fatman hash function so this track door
is actually going to be the secret key
correspond to the public
key the secret key is not going to be
used in here it's never going to be used
in the protocol but it will be used in
the
analysis okay great yes
to uh interactive Pro where you com to
the witness or can to where the first
message
is again you're saying is this is only
limited to Pro System where you commit
to the weakness or can youe to Pro
somewhere you the
firstage so okay so this this technique
works okay so this technique works for
this protocol where you commit to
Something in
open and after I'll show you why I'll
show you that it's actually more General
and it applies to a large actually slew
of protocols where there's no commitment
whatsoever for example it applies to gkr
protocol where it's just Su Che it
applies to the Su Che
protocol and so it's not specific to
this and I'll show you later all you
need is kind of this trapo that tells
you where the bad kind of challeng
challenges are and once you have a trap
door that tells you where the bad
challenges are then you're you kind of
can use it but we'll we'll we'll mention
that at the end of class like towards
the end but yeah it's we'll see that
it's General so in some sense you don't
even need to look too too detail to that
protocol it's the idea here is more high
level we say look in any interactive
proof there's the beta that are bad that
like bad for security that are good for
the adversary but they're bad for
if the adversary managed to hit a bad
beta an alpha for which h of alpha gives
him a bad beta then he can cheat me I
want to avoid these bad bad betas and
now we're saying suppose there's only
one bad beta for Simplicity this one has
one bad beta so we're good if it has one
bad beta oh I want to avoid that
one now if there's some trap door that
allows me to compute that bad
beta then I can't put the Trap in the
kind of the hash function and give it to
the world there's a reason why it's a
trap door and not public uh here in this
case it's for zero knowledge but what I
can do is give an encryption of the
trapo and actually in the actual scheme
it won't be encryption of the trap door
encryption of zero nobody's G to ever
decrypt this thing but let's think of it
as an encryption of the trapo for
now now again where are we why did we
make any progress here
okay so next is the most amazing point I
think when I saw this it took me a very
long time to process because it's such
an ingenious
idea but here's the idea okay so they
say yeah you know what I'm going to take
the I'm nevertheless my hash function is
going so so they so oh Sor so then they
say okay you you're right this kind of
hash function that has the a the trap
door in it and you evaluate the trap
door that's you're right it's not good
it doesn't even type check the output is
not the me the length it's supposed to
be yeah this is nonsense let us fix this
and here's how they fix it let me put
the Val here so because it' be nice to
see so here's the their fix they said
you know what fine that may have been
the wrong function we're gonna encrypt
so our RCR hash key is going to consist
of encryption of another function
g i I'm using by the way I'm using the
hat to denote fully homomorphic
encryption as opposed to standard
encryption okay that's often we use in
the literature the hat is kind of a
shortcut to denote public key comma
encryption of of G and when you use this
hat we usually use it when we want to
talk about fully homomorphic encryption
okay okay so now they say okay this is
going to going to be my nevertheless I'm
going to encrypt a g what's the G we'll
see I'm going to encrypt a g and my so
so my uh the so here's their hash key
what the here the hash key is gonna
be I'm going to generate a public key
and encrypt a function G okay so it's
like the public key corresponding to G
and then G which is just another
shortcut to say encryption of G and when
I say I encrypted G just think about
encrypt the description of the circuit
okay so there's some way to describe the
circuit I encrypt the
description okay so I encrypt this
description of a circuit G what this
what this G is we'll see okay but that's
my hash key so this is the hash key how
do you what how do you
evaluate hash key and
Alpha they say you know what just
compute G of alpha under the hood how do
we compute G of alpha under the hood
essentially they say do the eval of the
FH there's two eval it's a bit conf
confusing because we usually don't know
the evaluation Computing the hash
function by eval but now we also have
the eval of the fol morphic encryption
scheme so take the fol morphic
encryption scheme take the cipher text G
so take the public key corresponding to
the cipher
Tex what's the function what's the
circuit C it's going to be kind of a
universal circuit sub
Alpha I'll tell you what this is in a
second and the certex is
G and this universal circuit sub Alpha
all it does the definition it takes as
input a circuit g and an out outputs G
of
alpha so essentially what we do what
this hatch function does is exactly what
it said before it takes an encryption of
G how does it relate to the trap door
the C I'll tell you a say
before we said g is just kind of the it
has the it it just has the trapo in it
and before we said g is just this G
computes bad and it has the trapo and we
encrypt G now they say okay you're right
there's a problem we'll tell you what G
is in a second but same idea same idea
we encrypt this G maybe it'll be a
little different but we encrypt G and
the hash function computes G and Alpha
under the hood
so it takes the original first message
Alpa and computes the function gandra
the
hood I'm like we just went over through
it it doesn't work what then you get the
encryption doesn't even type check
what so here's their
idea okay now this is the most beautiful
part of today's lecture okay so they
say Okay so this think of this another
let me just write it short short kind of
hand wve this is going to be G of alpha
encrypted right because this is what U
does U does it computes g of alpha so
what you get back is encryption of G of
alpha now they say okay and by the way
in their scheme let me first say in
their scheme what is g doesn't matter
because it's encrypted it's the all zero
Circuit of a certain size so in their
scheme this G is going to be the all
zero
Circuit of size like T Zer what T is
we'll see in a
second okay but that's all it is that's
the hash this is the F hash function the
question is why is it secure because it
seems like there's no way this works but
let me just say again the the F your
hash function what does it
do it generates a public key it encrypts
in the actual scheme to all zero string
to 00 Z up to T times we'll see what T
is in a second in the analysis we're
going to play with this G but this is
all this is what it is and when you give
him Alpha it
computes the circuit which is all the
all zero circuit under the hood that's
all it does and that's the that's that's
the B that's going to be the
beta you should be very confused but
I'll explain
yeah just think the zero every
everything is I don't know whatever it
doesn't matter it all pluses all plus
Gates or it actually doesn't matter
because nobody's going to ever decrypted
so it you just so I I I guess I'm saying
each circuit you can describe it with
kind of bit Z one0 one01 in some some
way you know so put all zero bits so I
don't know if it even describes a
circuit just just
yeah
origin the has some CC that gamma as a
function of beta just do that under F
and get
GMA and no I'll tell you why it doesn't
work okay good no great question so the
question was the following you're saying
you know what change the protocol Al
together you change this protocol and
ask the guy put on put like don't you
don't need to be you know blinded to
this F Paradigm change it a little bit
and CH now you put a a encryption of of
the trapdoor tell this guy so now he
computes bet under the hood tell him to
compute G also under the hood and then
we we don't have a problem the problem
is that he can cheat why because when he
answers GMA he knows the
trapo but no he but actually one second
you're right under the hood he knows the
trapo yeah so hey hold
on yeah the problem is that under the
hood he knows the trapo however um
I'm not sure actually that that's a
problem because at that
point let me think for a second
um I think it actually may work uh okay
so look it changes the protocol for
example now it's no longer publicly
verifiable because you need to now his
message is encrypted so you need to
decrypt in order to learn it so there
there are uh issues with these but also
I'll tell you more than
that if indeed you put in the F in the
actual in the actual scheme you should
think of it the people who generate feir
they actually don't know the
trapo they don't know the trapo someone
there's a scheme in it swn and there is
a trap door but nobody knows it and the
people they don't actually know the
trapo so in the actual scheme there
won't be an encryption of the trapo it's
in kind of the idea is will say well the
actual you don't use the trap door but
it's indistinguishable you don't know if
you encrypted zero encrypted the trap
door so we're going to prove soundness
assuming you encrypt the trap door but
in the scheme you won't encrypt the
trapo so then in the scheme the gun is
going to be useless kind of because it
won't
correspond yeah okay great so okay great
great great questions so where are we so
we said here's the F has function the F
hash function will take actually an
arbitrary G of a certain size it doesn't
matter because nobody's going to cryp
that surface cyppher text
anyway and all it will do is a
computation under the
hood and now it seems like I don't know
it seems like that cannot work
nevertheless I'm going to prove Security
in like two
lines it's uh okay and the proof is like
ingenious really this construction is
very it's very tempting to try it just
doesn't work that when you look at it's
like okay and then what and then
what but here's their idea their idea is
following all we need to
argue is that for every Alpha G of
alpha is not bit
bad that's all we
need so then in the
analysis I'm going to say so again this
is the actual hash function we have an
encryption here of G what G this G is I
don't care it's like the fixed circuit
whatever Circle you want to put and
nobody's going to Crypt it in the
analysis I'm going to say you know what
I'm going to replace this G with a very
special G with the G whose encryption is
not b
bad but you're
like which G hat which G hat how do we
construct a g so that we know that
encryption of G and Alpha is not
beta
Yeah question what does this notation
like is like an encryption of G like
it's the head of the whole thing yeah
this yeah sorry yeah yeah yeah yeah
sorry this this is a a
encryption of with public key of G Alpha
yes sorry thanks thank
you so any idea what uh
okay I'll tell you you won't believe me
but I'll tell you anyway it's it's MTH
of course you'll believe but you'll
you'll be mind-boggled for a while so
here's their idea the idea is they say
okay here's my G I need to ensure that
you're not beta so I'm going to make my
G B the
decryption secret key of beta
and I'm just going to add like the one
to it so I know you're not like I guess
we're I'll rightor because we're over
Zer one alexo this with one that's my G
in the analysis so in the analysis I'm
going to say suppose you succeed in
Breaking the fure mirr you're also going
to succeed with this G because it's
encrypted you don't know the difference
you don't if you have no idea what's
underneath the cipher attack underneath
the encryption so you should also
succeed in Breaking with this G now this
G looks bizarre because I'm decrypting
this is not a cyer text this is just a
bunch of strings like a z one string
it's a random string it's not a cyer Tex
what does it mean to decrypt this thing
it's like this makes no
sense
however so but okay but but if this the
length of this is the the take a cyh
protect that the length is like these
Lambda
bits so you can look this is function so
you can compute this function not on a
cipher text but compute this
function okay so I decrypt the beta
message which is not even a Cypher text
and I add one I exort with one I exort
with anything that's not zero just to
Move It from the
bad now I want to
argue now we know that encryption of
this cannot be
beta why now now I can argue this why
because
if it was equal if you decrypt
this then you'll get a decryption of
this if you have two strings and they're
equal if you decrypt one you can apply
decryption for but they'll still be
equal the decryption is just a
deterministic
function
so so I guess if I want to argue now
with if for this G I want to argue
that this which is the F function on
Alpha this is the F your function on
Alpha I want to argue this if I want to
argue if if it was beta I'm going to get
a
contradiction I want to argue it's not
beta why if it
was then I can apply decryption on both
sides then it means that decryption of
this will be equal to decryption of
this of
course okay what is decryption of this
G
Alpha so I just decrypt the encryption
of of G Alpha I get back G
Alpha but I know G Alpha is not the
decryption of bad
Alpha because G is
thetion not plus one so it can't
be so again in the analysis so let me
maybe write this a bit formally so where
let me write it up
there I'll use this part so here's the
actual proof of SEC of soundness so
suppose oh there's a sorry there's one
thing I glossed over
fast okay we'll go over it and then
analysis we'll see it so I say Suppose
there
exist poly science cheating
prover and he fixes some graph G that's
not does not have a hamiltonian cycle
and
cheats and successfully and
cheats with probability you know big
let's say greater than Epsilon Epsilon
is not negligible
then I'm going to say let me then I want
ARG then it means that P star also
succeeds with
probability you
know I said
close X may be minus negligible but
similar probability if I change the hash
key before the hash key was public key
and some encryption of some bogus
G now I say it will also succeed if I
take public key and this specific G let
me call this
G G Star okay so that's the G in the
analysis so again how does the analysis
go I say Suppose there exists a cheating
prover that takes a false statement and
succeeds in in proving nevertheless and
convincing then I want want to say that
he will also succeed If instead of
giving public the if the with will also
succeed with hash
key which is public key and
encryption of gar of this
gar Why by semantic
security okay because you don't you
can't distinguish between encryption
encryption of gar ition of
G
yeah we're using the fact that the proof
is
efficient computational soundness
computational soundness yes we're using
the fact that the CH polyes he's
efficient and therefore he cannot break
semantic security so we cannot
distinguish between g whatever the bogus
G that we put in the CRS for the all
zero circuit or whatever and this G
Star I cheated slightly here but let me
move on and we'll go to the cheat in a
second okay but let's say you believe
that even though you shouldn't but it's
very delicate so we'll go there but but
okay semantic security now I'm saying
with this G Star now information
theoretically cannot cheat he's stuck
because guess what for every you're
saying he he produces Alpha Beta gamma
accepting right that's what he means he
cheated so he got it means that
he got Alpha so that h of alpha is
bad because you can only cheat with a
bad Alpha that's the definition of bad
of a bad beta that's the definition of a
bad beta one that you can treat with so
he found an alpha said that h of alpha
is
bad but this G Star never hits bad that
that's how we made it it's so that g of
alpha is never the bad alha
yeah
Ah that's what I glossed over exactly L
good good good so that's the proof
however there is a cheat and the cheat
is look
gar to compute gar I said just describe
gar like G when I when I mean encrypt
gar I mean give the description like
encrypt the description of gar okay so
let's recall what does gar do gar
decrypts so you need to know the secret
key corresponding to public key
we said that like you can encrypt you
semantic security holds for any fixed
messages m0 and
M1 you cannot distinguish
between is it here yeah for any fixed m0
and M1 you cannot distinguish between
encryption of m0 and encryption of M1
but here I'm saying you C cannot
distinguish between encryption of the
secret key and encryption of let's say
other bits that's a different story and
indeed we assume what's called circular
secure FHA so we assume not only that
you can we assume all that you cannot
distinction encryption of the secret key
and encryption of the all zeros that's
an assumption do you have question
yeah so far it seems
likea beta so
given not
computed like how do we oh no no no no
it's computed sorry sorry sorry okay
good good good no what I meant here okay
thanks thank you very much for the
question here's what gar Alpha does gar
of alpha it has actually let me write
more more carefully it
has trapo and secret key hard wire the
first thing it does it computes bad it
computes bad Alpha using
trapo this is kind of corresponding to
our to our scheme then he takes what he
got the bad Alpha he decrypt it using
the secret key then he exor one to the
least significant bit or something like
that so yeah it does compute it yeah so
this G Star you need to encrypt trapo
and you need to encrypt secret key now
encrypting the trap door is not a
problem it's has nothing to do with the
key but the problem is you also need to
encrypt the secret key correspond to the
public
key but yeah thank you for the question
that's a great question so you know GF I
want to repeat gar Alpha what it does it
do it takes Alpha it first computes the
bad beta corresponding to the alpha
using the the trap door then he takes
this string he decrypts this weird
string using the secret key and then he
exors it with like ex the least
significant bit with one or any bit with
one just to make it not equal
police is it still the secret key it's
the secret key corresponding to this
commitment that's why I said this track
door in some is also a secret public
encryption but there's two there's two
encryptions going on one is the FHA
encryption and one is how we implement
this
commitment so you're right that we
implement this commitment also with an
encryption scheme but it's better to
kind of forget it because otherwise it's
confusing that there's two encryption
scheme so here I want to say suppose you
have a commitment and there's a trap
door that allows you to open it forget
that this trap is also a secret key
because so now I'm saying you need this
trapo to open the commitment which
you're right this trap door happens also
to beat some encrypt secret key because
that's how we implemented the
commitment and it has the secret key
corresponding to this same public key
you see so I guess what's the
problematic part is that the hatch key
consists of a public key of a fully
homomorphic encryption
scheme and to to describe gar you need
to describe you need to hard you need
the trapdoor which is not a problem you
could just encrypt this trapo under
public heat fresh public key you can
encrypt any this is kind of fixed
compared to this public key but you also
need to encrypt the secret key
corresponding to this public
key and for that we need to rely on
circular security
so let me just quickly write what I mean
by circular
security and then we'll break so I'll
write it
here it just means that public key and
encryption of the secret
key is indistinguishable
from public key and
encryption of let's say the all
zeros and let me just mention the secret
key here you can think of it as Lambda
bits let's say security per number of
bits then when you know if we think of
bitwise encryption this is encryption of
it's like encryption of secret key the
first bit of secret key encryption of
the second bit it's like Lambda
encryptions and this also I mean
encryption of zero encryption of Zer
encryption of zero we do everything bit
by bit and the assumption is that you
have an FH scheme so that you cannot
distinguish between whether the Lambda
encryptions each one bit encrypts a bit
whether these encryptions are all zero
or whether they correspond to the bits
of the secret
key so that's an
assumption uh by the
way we do we we know so the question is
well do we have FH that have that are
have circular security question mark
well we do under an assumption it's
called circular secure learning with air
so we just move this kind of circular
secure into the Assumption we believe
this assumption to be true we don't know
but actually we can remove all this we
actually don't it turns out we don't
need to put the secret key there and
there's a follow-up work that kind of
did more work a lot of lattice work so
you need to kind of really here I didn't
talk at all about l I mean as long as
you have fully morphic encryption that
Circle are secure we're all set I don't
care how what this is like but then
there's follow-up work that looks at the
specific kind of polymorphic encryption
scheme based on lates and does a bunch
of lattice tricks to remove the circular
need for circular security so this is
something we I I didn't show you but
there's a follow-up work uh that does
that okay so I want to take a break but
if before a break are there any
questions yeah the SI of the circuit has
to large enough to contain this specific
good exactly so good good good question
very good question guys you're really
having fantastic questions today thank
you so going back what is this T this T
is the number of bits needed to
represent this G Star because in the
analysis I
convert the zero to the T with G star
with the description of of G Star so
this is exactly what T is in the
analysis
any any further
questions okay so let's take like maybe
I don't know eight minute break feel was
intense takes like eight minute break or
so uh and uh when we'll go back we'll do
the niic