yeah thanks for that kind introduction
and thanks for inviting me I'm really
excited to be here because I was once a
student at litz as well like Q like over
10 years ago not I'm not going to say
exactly how long I I was advised by Yuri
pansi and Mario madart so I had a foot
at lids and a foot at Rite and when I
look back those were like some of the I
guess some of the best and most
intellectually stimulating times in my
research career so I hope you all enjoy
it and it's great to be back here to
share some of the work that we've been
doing down and now across the river at
the School of Engineering and applied
sciences at Harvard so since this is a
student conference I thought it would
take the first about 10 minutes of the
talk just to say a little bit about what
my research group does at Harvard and
particularly how we work both with
information Theory and also applications
in machine learning AI focusing on a
private responsible design of these
algorithms and one of the reasons we use
information theory is because
information is everywhere in machine
learning when you think about the
information in in a machine learning
algorithm or now I guess an AI algorithm
usually what comes to mind is the data
set the data that you use to train this
algorithm and how information from the
data is somehow mapped on to the weights
of your model in order to produce some
do some kind of classification or
prediction task but the truth is in the
pipeline of Designing these models and
there are many other information sources
for example there design choices that
are made by the people developing those
algorithms like the model class the
number of parameters your regularization
strength your train test split u the
choice of training algorithm and
optimization even the random seed that
you choose to initialize your weights
right determines which local Minima
you're eventually going to converge to
and ultimately how your model is going
to perform and what kind of predictions
it's going to make and all that
information is mapped to the model after
training um and that could lead to
unintended consequences when these
models are deployed U one such
consequence are privacy risks U models
can contain information about the
training data and just by examining
these weights or the input and the
output of the model you might be able to
reverse engineer potentially privacy
sensitive data used during training um
uh such privacy attacks have been widely
documented in the literature U models
can also include biases and have dis
performance on different population
groups specifically even though your
model might be accurate on average when
you evaluate that model on different
groups you might see a disparity of
performance and these kinds of
disparities have also been widely
documented in applications that go from
facial recognition to policing to um to
uh education and so on um generative
models right uh they can produce outputs
that also inaccurately represent uh
population statistic this is one example
that we did in our group where if you
query the uh if you input the query a
photo of a computer program for the ANC
on Google image search uh historically
uh the main programmers of the ANC were
all women but if you uh add the same
prompt to stable diffusion you get a
bunch of pictures black and white
pictures of men um and this could be a
challenge not only from a kind of U
moral sense but this is a challenge also
when you're deploying these models in
practice because when you don't account
for this uh you can get headlines
written about the models they are deplin
in your company like Gemini's AI image
results might offend your users this is
an incident that happened with Gemini's
AI image generation algorithm about a
year ago where these algorithms would in
accurately represent certain populations
and in some cases these models can have
no information at all for certain inputs
uh the model output can be um arbitrary
an artifact of the randomness used
during training this is an another
example that we did of a few years uh
back where um we trained a computional
neur network to detect different
spectrograms and detect what kind of
sound is in that spectrogram and simply
by changing the random initialization of
training you keep everything the same
the data is the same the the the model
architecture is the same and so on but
just changing the random seed that uh
you use to initialize your training
process uh you end up with models that
have different weights that on average
have approximately the same performance
but on individual samples they make
conflicting predictions um and sure in
an application like uh audio recognition
that might not seem like a big deal
that's known as the Rashon effect but
when you look at other applications of
social consequence like content
moderation and so on um decisions
supported by Machine learning models may
depend on arbitrary and unjustified
choices during their
development so what I'm going to do
today is to talk a little bit about some
of these challenges and how we um use
tools from um information Theory to uh
address challenges in privacy uh In
fairness and in arbitrariness
information theory is a tool set of
choice um because information Theory
allows us to delineate the limits of
these machine learning systems that are
independent of specific models
applications and semantics we can really
try to get at some of the heart of these
problems so and in order to understand
how we apply information theory in the
cases there are two questions that I'm
going to answer if you're already
already taken an information Theory
class here at uh MIT this is going to be
pretty obvious for you um so just sit
back back and relax if not you're going
to learn something new and we have to
answer how do we measure information and
how do we model information right so how
can we measure information how do we
quantify it so information in
information theory is measured as a
change in
uncertainty so if I tell you that the
Sun will rise tomorrow that's a
statement that's significantly less
informative than when I tell you that
the outcome of the dice row of a row of
truece the sum of the faces of chudis 12
and the reason why the first statement
is less informative than the second is
because I'm pretty sure the sun will
rise tomorrow right with probability
overwhelmingly close to one um but if
you ask me what's my prior belief of the
outcome of the sum of uh the roow of
true dice I have much more uncertainty
and once I observe that dice row that U
distribution collapses
to a single distribution here so in
general information is measured and
Quantified in terms of these difference
between beliefs as represented by
probability distributions between the
state of a system and in and one way of
quantifying this change in distributions
is using something called a Divergence
measure and there is a world of
divergences to choose from there's
integral probability metrics uh F
divergences regman divergences and so on
uh should they this talk we're going to
spend a lot of time talking about F
divergences these are divergences of the
following form where if you're give me
true distributions p and q i compute the
expected value in Q of this function of
the uh likelihood ratio between p and Q
and there are many divergences of this
type that depend on this function f um
our constraint is that this function f
is convex that at one it's evaluated to
zero and F is also finite for all T
greater than zero like some of these
diver es you've probably heard of like K
Divergence you can recover it for f
equals t loog t AMA Divergence this is
going to be a very important Divergence
for us toal variation K square and so on
and what we're going to be doing in a
few minutes is that we're going to be
analyzing challenges in privacy and
fairness in machine learning using these
divergences so we can use these
Divergence metrics between distributions
to measure information to measure these
changes and beliefs now the second
question that I ask is how do we model
information in machine learning um so in
this case what we do is that we measure
uh data sets or we represent and model
data sets as samples from a sar p ofx
and we when we think about a model or a
training algorithm we think about them
as a channel you can think about an
algorithm for example a Transformer
model as a channel where a sample comes
in or a text comes in and the output is
a probability over the next token or a
classifier as a channel as well where an
image comes in and the output has a
probability distribution over classes we
can also think about a training
algorithm as a channel randomized
training algorithm a data set comes in
and the output is a distribution over
weights and this abstraction allows us
to um do an analysis that is uh
independent of semantics and specific
applications and also find patterns and
questions of privacy and fairness that
hold across model classes and training
algorithms so these information measures
and models they're mathematical
definitions right and historically
they've been used to quantify the limits
of many engineering and Computing
systems and the use of tools from
information theory of course dates back
to Claude Shannon and what his
breakthroughs allowed among many other
things is for us to move away from ad
hoc engineering from like designing
systems that transmit and communicate
data that were tailored for different
kinds of specific applications and
really get it at the heart of the
problem and distill the problem down to
like a common little model that was
common across these different
applications in this case the question
of um data compression and data
transmission could be boiled down to
figure one in his paper where you have
an information Source a transmitter a
receiver and so on and by analyzing
these models you can find uh he found
limits of how far you can compress data
and limits on how fast you can
communicate or how many bits you can
transmit per Channel use and obviously
there is a gap between theory and
practice right you can't say that oh
here's a bunch of diagram blocks in a
PowerPoint slide and by there and just
by looking at that we can understand how
to engineer a Wi-Fi router right but I
think for me and um the power of
information Theory and this is something
I learned at at Lids is that it gives us
operational limits that engineers and
computer scientists can aim for and for
the next uh for the following decades
after Shannon introduced his paper folks
have been reaching for these limits
right developing better coding schemes
better communication protocols and so on
um these Technologies led to the
widespread deployment of meth of um of
of algorithms and devices that collect
and store data at a global scale and
since early 2000s this data has been
fueling the fast development of machine
learning which today exposes many
emerging challenges and what I do in my
research what my research group does is
that we ask can we apply information
Theory to address these
challenges and this is very much in the
spirit of the field like if you this is
a picture borrowed or adapted from
cover's book where um information Theory
historically has found connections with
many different fields that range from
probability Theory to statistics
communication theory of course physics
computer science and economics and what
my research does is that uh we' add
another petal to this flower and ask how
can we apply information Theory to
understand these emerging challenges in
machine learning related to questions of
private fairness arbitrariness and so
on so I want to mention one last
Divergence which is this Divergence
between um theory and practice like I
mentioned um I'm not going to claim that
just by looking at simple models you can
understand the complexity of like
regulating 5G networks right this is
this is a much more complicated problem
and in the same way just by looking at
these mathematical models behind privacy
and behind questions of fairness that
doesn't perfectly as far from perfectly
capturing a regulations be uh uh in
surrounding the topic or even the
personal feeling that someone has when
they're discriminated by by an
algorithm but theory is um only one
piece of this puzzle right but it's an
important piece it's an important piece
because by looking at Theory it helps us
understand the limits of these systems
optimize and critique their design and
create algorithms and cods that
massively outperform horis sixs um and
for me the most precious moments in
research is when we can make these this
Divergence between theory and practice
small so that's what we're going to talk
about next um now we're going to talk a
little bit about privacy and fairness I
won't have time to talk about our work
on predictive multiplicity and
arbitrariness I'll leave that for next
time you can look up our papers if
you're interested in that um but for the
next about 40 minutes uh maybe a little
bit less we're going to be talking about
design and limits of privacy mechanisms
and design of limits of group fairness
interventions wait are youall with me
yeah cool so let's start with a little
bit about design and limits of privacy
mechanisms so the flavor of privacy that
we're going to be looking at today is
differential privacy who here has heard
about differential privacy he quite a
few of you great so if you haven't the
core idea behind differential privacy is
the following you have a data set D and
you compute a query over this data set
set for example you ask what's the
number of chefs or the average number of
chefs in this data set and the goal of
this uh of differential privacy is to
measure how much your belief about the
data set changes or how much this output
distribution changes uh if I change only
one entry of the data set say I change
the data of the of the chef for an
engineer here so the goal is that a
quiry does not significantly depend on
any single individual's data and the way
you can Ensure privacy in practice how
differential privacy is insured in
practice is by engineering this green
box here something known as a privacy
mechanism you can think about a privacy
mechanism as a conditional distribution
or a channel where the input is say a
query or maybe a data set itself and the
output is a randomized version of that
query the simplest form of ensuring
privacy is by adding noise to your query
so I you ask me how many chefs are in
this data set then I respond a number
plus some gaussian noise that was
calibrated in order to hide the
dependence in terms of individual
samples and in general this differential
privacy can be measured abstractly in
terms of a Divergence right in in terms
of the change in your output
distribution across neighboring inputs
here so um the way this is uh
differential one of the most popular
flavors of differential privacy is known
as Epsilon Delta differential privacy or
approximate differential privacy where
we say that this green box here this
privacy mechanism is differentially
private satisfies Epsilon Delta
differential privacy for every Epsilon
greater than zero and Delta between Z
and one uh if for all neighboring data
sets the probability of any output event
doesn't change by more than an additive
factor of Delta and a multiplicative
factor of e to the Epsilon so for the
rest of the stock just to simplify a
little bit the notation we're going to
substitute the condition of neighboring
in terms of um uh neighboring data sets
inducing neighboring queries so if your
data sets are neighboring your query
doesn't change my the norm of your query
doesn't change more by a sensitivity
parameter s and in this case we can
express differential privacy in terms of
one specific uh F Divergence known as
the egma or hockey stick Divergence
where we choose our function f to be a
function that looks like a hockey
stick and in this case you can rewrite
the differential privacy in a form that
is not as common but um is entirely
equivalent where we say that a privacy
mechanism is differentially private if
the egma Divergence or this hockey stick
Divergence a kind of f Divergence
between neighboring distributions is not
greater for a parameter each of the
Epsilon is not greater than Delta and
one thing that's really important is
that any privacy mechanism is
characterized by a range of these
Epsilon Delta values in practice when
you uh read about differential privacy
disclosures usually folks uh fix Delta
to be a small value like 10 to Theus 6
or 10 to Theus 7 usually one over the
size of the data set and Report the
corresponding Epsilon but it's important
for you to understand that any privacy
mechanism any one of these channels is
characterized by a range of these
Epsilon and Delta values and ideally we
want to make these very small smaller
they are the more private your mechanism
right the closer true neighboring
distributions
are and differential privacy is widely
adopted uh I think it's not an underst
understatement to say that in many
places in applied machine learning in
Industry differential privacy has become
the standard privacy metric uh it's
adopted at Google at meta at Apple uh in
fact it was adopted also by the US
government in the 2020 desial
census so the goal and the question that
I'm going to be exploring in the rest of
this part of the talk is how can we
ensure private Acy and how can we
measure and understand the behavior of
these privacy guarantees when you access
data multiple times because when you
apply a privacy mechanism you usually
don't apply it only once right you have
your data set and you ask a query and
you feed it through your privacy
mechanism and you get a response but
then you're not done usually that that
data set is hosted somewhere or you're
using acquiring this data multiple times
to train a machine learning model and
you ask multiple queries right either by
the same or by different users and every
time time this data is accessed your
privacy curve becomes looser and looser
like your privacy guarantees they become
less and less strict so one example
where you data is accessed uh uh tens of
thousands or hundreds of thousands of
times and a privacy mechanism is applied
many times is when you're doing
differentially private training of
machine learning models like when you're
doing differentially private stochastic
gradient descent in this case each query
for the data set is a computation of a
gradient at a given parameter point and
a popular algorithm is dpsg where you
clip your gradient and you add the
gussan noise in order to ensure privacy
and you can assume that in this case
this privacy mechanism in this case
clipping the gradient and adding noise
is applied T of thousands or hundreds of
thousands or maybe millions of times
during training so the idea that we had
me and my
collaborators was well how can we
optimize privacy mechanisms for this
High composition Reg
right so if we're designing these green
boxes these privacy mechanisms that add
noise to the data how should we engineer
them so that we can have the best
privacy for the best utility possible
and in order to answer that we need to
answer two questions the first question
is well how do we measure uh privacy
loss under many compositions how does
this privacy curve behave right how do
these divergences increase and the
second question is shall how should we
design design privacy mechanisms that
operate under many compositions once we
can measure privacy when you're
accessing data multiple times how should
you optimize the noise that you add to
the data in order to achieve the best
utility so the first question that we're
going to look at is this one is how do
we measure privacy laws under many
compositions so in order to understand
this we need a slightly technical uh
Mark technical definition which is this
notion of a universal privacy curve like
at the end of the day what we want to
understand is the worst case Divergence
across these two distributions for the
worst case pair of possible queries that
someone can ask and we want you
understand how this privacy curve
behaves and how it increases as you ask
more and more and more and more car
queries and ever since you have
differential privacy there are methods
that do privacy accounting which is
essentially this process of keeping
track of your privacy
loss um the first methods were basic
composition results so basically what
they did is that instead of considering
an entirely entire privacy curve they
considered uh for each use of the
mechanism a specific pair of Epsilon and
Delta VAR values and asked well how can
we combine these Epsilon and Delta
values in order to get a new or an
overall privacy guarantee you can think
about this as well each time I use a
mechanism I report a given Epsilon Delta
and now if I query the data say a 100
times how can I combine these in Deltas
to get a guarantee on my privacy
leakage over the past uh especially over
the past 5 years for years you've seen a
flurry of work that tries to refine this
analysis by considering the uh the
entire privacy curve like uh there are
large deviations approaches CLT based
approaches numerical approaches and
specifically I'm going to focus on one
approach we presented at icml a few
years back called the sample Point
accountant and really what made these
methods work is that they focus on the
concentration of one specific random
variable known as the Privacy loss
random variable so bear with me on this
because if you understand this part
you're going to understand really what's
at the heart of differential
privacy so what is this privacy loss
random variable right so remember that
we have this green box this green box is
our channel it's our privacy mechanism
we're going to add ask a query on the
data and then we're going to randomize
that query in order to Output uh a
randomized value in order to ensure
privacy um and we measure privacy in
terms of neighboring queries right so we
can Define this random variable known as
the Privacy loss random variable which
is nothing more than the log likelihood
ratio between the output distributions
if the input were X or X Prime so it's a
log likelihood ratio that you would see
when you're testing between these two
distributions and here we're assuming
that Y is distributed ACC Accord to P of
Y given xal Little
X so the mean of this random
variable is
anyone KO Divergence great that's how
you know you're at MIT so uh the mean of
this random variable is K Divergence
right it's the K Divergence between
these two neighboring distributions so
remember this because this will be
important for us later why because
eventually we're going to be accessing
the data multiple times and the random
variable will concentrate through its
mean and we can write these this privacy
curve in terms of the Privacy loss ROM
variable it's a pretty straightforward
exercise in algebra just you rewrite
this egma Divergence that captures your
absolent Delta guarantees in terms of
this privacy loss random variable um we
still have this annoying subterm here to
get the exact Delta where you have to
look at the supremum across all
neighboring distributions you kind of
you can get over that by looking at
something known as a tight privacy loss
random variable basically you create a
pair of random variables who Z GMA
Divergence whose privacy curve dominates
those for any pair of neighboring
distributions so we can in many cases
create a tight privacy loss ROM variable
often it's just the the distribution
that you get for the Privacy loss ROM
variable for the worst case inputs and
in this case you can write your privacy
curve as a function of this Privacy Law
strend and variable
and since since this is a log likelihood
ratio uh when you're quiring the data
multiple times and you're considering
this uh worst case uh
PV um your privacy guarantee becomes a
sum of these privacy loss random
variables right so the problem of
privacy accounting boils down to
quantifying the sum of these usually IID
privacy loss random variables and over
the past few years you've seen several
papers that try to do exactly that um so
one natural approach is for you to uh
approximate this some using the central
limit theorem in this case you
approximate the sum of the Privacy loss
random variable by a gaussian um
naturally another approach is that you
look at the cumulant generating function
of this privacy loss rendom variable
this is a large deviations approach this
is what's at the heart of something
called Rene differential privacy and the
moments accountant um in this case you
apply a turnoff Bound for um for the
accumul Jing fun using the cumul Jing
function of your privacy loss random
variable which is essentially R
Divergence for for neighboring
distributions but the challenge of these
approaches is that they're nice because
they give us an analytical form of your
privacy loss and remember ultimately
where we're going with this is that we
want to optimize our noise distributions
U but they can be not very tight like
RDP can overestimate your privacy loss
and the calcium differential privacy can
underestimate your privacy loss so if
you have a bunch of distributions right
and you're adding them up and you want
to compute the density of this sum you
can involve the individual densities and
what's a fast algorithm for computing
convolution the fft yeah and this is
another set of approaches known as the
fft approaches that does exactly that
that you numerically compute um the
convolution via the fft so here you have
a set of accounting procedures one that
gives you nice analytical forms that
later we can optimize but has relatively
low precision and the other one that's
purely numerical so it's something
that's purely computational but gives
you
incredibly precise approximations of
your privacy loss fromom variable so we
proposed an alternative approach a
couple of years back
ATL called the saddleo accountant uh
which is nice because it has an
analytical form and it has high
precision and it's just one key trick
that we use and one key idea is that
instead of looking at the concentration
of the Privacy loss random variable we
look at an exponential tilting of the
Privacy loss random variable so what do
I mean by exponential tilting that we
create a new random variable L tiled
whose distribution is the Tilted
distribution of your random variable L
and here K is your cumulant generating
function so for example if you have a
continuous random variable if you have a
density for your privacy loss random
variable uh the distribution of your
tilted distribution is just your
original density times this term where
again K is your cumulant generating
function and cting distributions are
very nice this is a a common trick to
use in large deviations Theory uh
because the first property that they
satisfy is that if your underlying
distributions are independent the Tilted
distributions are also independent that
uh the tilting of the sum is the sum of
the tilts um and we can also measure the
value uh of of certain functions of this
random variable in terms of its tilted
distribution and it's particularly this
third property that we use here because
what we do is that we reexpress your
privacy curve in terms terms of the
Tilted distribution of your privacy loss
random variable and when you look at
this uh at your resulting Delta
guarantee for given Epsilon in
differential privacy for the Tilted
version you can uh your in the large
composition regime you're going to have
the sum of multiple random variables and
you can approximate it using the central
limit theorem but now applying the
central limit theorem to your tilted
distribution and that's at the heart of
the SLE Point accounting um when you
look at this formula um here you can
actually apply Paro and write it in the
Fier domain so you can write it in terms
of the uh um in terms of the moment
generating function of your tilted
distribution or the characteristic
function of your tilted distribution and
then you can write your privacy
guarantees in terms of an integral where
T here is exactly the tilting parameter
that you choose so in a sense the
tilting parameter this determines the
real intercept of this line integral
that you're solving and again K here is
the is your cumul generating function so
if you look at this exponent here uh and
you it's uh it's imaginary and it's a
complex uh exponent and if you plot it
in the complex plane uh this function
has a saddle point here um and this
saddle point is where we choose our
integration uh our integration point and
that's something that's very common in
mathematical physics it's known as
lass's integration method and we apply
it here and once you do this you get a
very precise approximation of your Delta
Epsilon curve you can derive bounds for
this as well where the point that we
choose are tilting is exactly the
solution the unique solution um of that
CLE Point um if you're familiar with
Rene differential privacy or the moments
accountant that was proposed a few years
ago um this you can think about this as
a correction of the moments accountant
where you add this additional uh
denominator here in order to um and
these additional terms when you're
Computing your your
integral and the result is that this
gives us uh approximations that are very
very accurate including in these in the
tails for uh your privacy loss so uh
what you see here are um uh the black
line or upper and lower bounds given by
the Sal Point accountant the Blue Line
Is What You Get by Computing the fft
eventually it stalls out because of
numerical precisions of precision of
course you can always improve your fft
to handle larger Precision but this is
what we use out of the box in Python and
we can see that our approximation is
very precise and more precise than the
moments accountant for
example
so because in part of your information
theorist as well a natural question to
ask is well how does privacy behave when
you're in the regime where you have an
extremely large number of compositions
right if you're accessing data hundreds
of thousands or millions of times right
this very asymptotic regime where you're
accessing data multiple times
and at and you can ask well can we
derive something that looks like a
capacity result here so if you were to
fix a given Delta at what so usually in
practice as I mentioned Delta is fixed
through a value of 10 to Theus 6 or tus
7 one over the size of your data set you
can ask well how does your Epsilon grow
with the number of composition K and can
we characterize this linear growth rate
of your Epsilon guarantee and Epsilon
Delta differential privacy um so the
goal is that for a fixed Delta can we
characterize the growth rate of this
privacy curve and specifically we want
to characterize this growth rate across
a range of possible mechanisms right so
the constraint that we ask is what is
the smallest privacy per composition uh
epon here given a distortion constraint
right so over all possible mechanisms
where the Distortion at the output is
bounded for example the msse is bounded
what is the smallest possible growth
rate that we can achieve in terms of
Epsilon per
composition so and we Define the set of
mechanisms that satisfies this
Distortion constraint by c r here this
is so this is the set of mechanisms that
satisfies our Target Distortion and we
can ask again the question that we're
asking is what is the smallest privacy
per composition given across all
mechanisms that satisfy this Distortion
constraint and we Define this quantity
as privacy capacity so this Epsilon
store uh for a given um Alpha Norm here
and for a given cost constraint C in
your Distortion our goal should
characterize the infimum across all
achievable privacy growth rates in this
problem um this is something that we
presented at isit last year and um we
say that a growth rate Epsilon is
achievable if there is we can design or
there exists a mechanism P of Y given x
uh such that this growth rate in epsilon
is smaller than Epsilon for some Delta
that doesn't decrease CH true quickly so
there's an analogy for privacy capacity
in terms of rate Distortion Theory where
here uh C plays a roow of distortion
rate Distortion Theory you can think
about K as your block length and Delta
here almost as your decoding error
probability so it turns out that privacy
capacity uh this growth rate of your
Epsilon as you query data multiple times
is related to another quantity which is
the minmax scale Divergence so you can
ask across all mechanisms in this set
that satisfy a given Distortion
constraint what is the worst case scale
Divergence across all neighboring
distributions so you can think for
example that um what across all
distributions that set by a given
constraint for example true gaussians
what is the worst case
scale um across all possible
shifts and it turns out that in this
limit of many many accesses through the
data your privacy rate um uh your
privacy capacity the linear growth rate
of Epsilon is equivalent to your minia
Max K Divergence rate so in a sense in
this case your privacy guarantee single
letter isers and the the row of like if
you would have like MRA information and
rate Distortion Theory here you have the
minmax scale Divergence across
neighboring distributions but not only
that we can show that for um if you're
uh for the cost constraint that we're
considering these Norm cost constraints
we have that um additive continuous and
spherically symmetric mechanisms can
achieve privacy capacity so what we're
what this means is that even though
we're optimizing over an abstract set of
channels it's sufficient to design an
additive noise to your query in order to
achieve this capacity that there in
other words there exist additive noise
distributions that achieve privacy
capacity this is interesting for us
because now we can try to optimize the
PDF of this noise in order to achieve
favorable performance in this large
composition regime and this is the
second question that we ask so how
should we design privacy mechanisms that
operate under many
compositions so just to recap where we
are so again the goal is should design
privacy mechanisms that minimize privacy
loss and maximize utility ideally we
would want you do this by Computing the
Privacy curve exactly but that's very
hard we can only compute it using things
like the fft um ongoing work is actually
optimizing the saddle point accountant
method it's kind of complicated because
you have to back propagate through OD so
it's not super simple to do that what
I'm going to show you today are results
that we already published where we
optimize for privacy capacity so we
optimize for this like limit of the
growth rate of Epsilon and in this case
you have this optimization problem where
you're minimizing K Divergence subject
to a cost constraint as I mentioned
before uh you can show that it's
sufficient to consider additive
mechanisms so the optimal thing to do is
to optimize the PDF or pmf in the
discrete case of the noise that you're
adding to your data and that's exactly
what we do like we quantize this uh PDF
and solve it
numerically uh so if you squint at this
problem you can probably see that it's a
convex optimization problem so we can
just kind of boot Force numerically
solve it so you can quantize this PDF
right you can just quantize it in
multiple buckets in the one dimensional
case and uh solve this very complicated
this optimization problem that is looks
pretty complicated but it's still convex
so you can solve it using standard
interior Point methods um this is the
convergence of your optimization problem
you can see that it converges to a very
kind of crazily shaped noise
distribution uh we call this the cactus
distribution because of like the the
other authors of this paper they're from
ASU so they think a lot about Cactus I
guess and it has this nice spiky
distribution you can do this for
multiple Dimensions as well uh this is
the the PDF of the radius of the noise
in 10 dimensions and the optimized noise
distributions they do not look like gin
they look like something
something different and here we're
looking at 10 Dimensions Delta equal
10us 8 and a MSC Distortion constraint
and you can see that it achieves a more
favorable privacy Decay for the same
Distortion level and as I mentioned this
is how it looks in one dimension this is
the the the the PDF of the noise in in
one dimension it looks like a
cactus you these these noises are
optimized should be better in terms of K
diver
right so you can you can compare the
maximal K Divergence across worst case
neighboring um inputs
for our optimized noise distributions
and gussan and if you look at this curve
so here on the x-axis you have the MSC
right the the the standard deviation of
the noise on the y- axis you have your
maximal K
Divergence and here we're considering a
sensitivity of one a shift of
one but what's interesting is that not
surprisingly the the optimized noise
distribution is better and it has a
lower maximal K than the gaussin
distribution but it seems that there are
certain regimes where gussan is
optimal right and so what's when we
first saw this graph it got us thinking
like what's happening here like we went
through all this trouble of like
understanding how privacy behaves in the
large composition regime we quanti we
found a setting where like additive
mechanisms are optimal we can quantize
the PDF and formulate this giant convex
optimization problem we get a noise
distribution out of it but it seems that
in certain regimes it's hard to beat
gaussin it seems like gaussin is pretty
good so what's happening and it turns
out that there's something really
interesting happening in this regime
that in the small sensitivity High noise
regime optimizing differential privacy
mechanisms is equivalent to finding igen
functions of the shinger operator so
surprise physics and um so let's go
through this
so this follows from a a property of K
Divergence so if you look at K
Divergence so if you look at the
optimization problem that we're looking
at um here TFA is the shift operator and
we're looking at the PDF that minimizes
the worst Cas scale Divergence across
all possible shifts of a distribution
with itself this is the simplest form in
one dimension subject to a cost
constraint where assuming in the simple
onedimensional case that the cost
constraint is something of this form
like you can think about Alpha equals
true and we're minimize
MSC but what happens when you make your
your sensitivity very very small when
you make the shift very very small you
can approximate a kale Divergence up the
first starter term of its Tor series
expansion on the shift in terms of fer
information so for small shift scale
Divergence behaves locally like Fisher
information where in Fisher information
is defined
here so in this case if your shift is
very very very small or equivalently the
noise that you add is very very large
you can approximate this optimization
Problem by minimizing the Fisher
information subject to a cost constraint
and you can show that this optimization
also has a unique optimizing
distribution now the thing that's
surprising here is that again in this
small sensitivity regime or cently large
noise regime that you're adding to the
data um the fure minimization problem it
boils down to uh that solving this
optimization is equivalent to finding
igen functions of the shinger operator
and what I mean by that is the falling
operator given here so if you have a
measurable function V uh the shinger
operator h of V uh over this uh the
space of squared integrable functions
with the potential function V is given
by this operator here you take a
function y and you compute it second
derivative and add it change the sign
and add it to V times Y and we say that
a function is an igen function for this
operator if there exists an e such that
when you apply the sh gr operator to the
function you get the function
back so it turns out that you can relate
the optimization problem to finding igen
functions of this shinger operator where
you adjust this potential function to be
related to your cost function here and
Theta you can think about this almost
like a lrange multiplier that def
defines what value of the cost that
you're going to achieve and the theorem
here and this is a theorem that is not
ours it has been a uh observed in other
work as well that um in this case we can
Define um a new noise mechanism that we
call the shinger mechanism where we add
noise to your query where the noise is
taken from a PDF whose distribution is
the is equivalent to the square of the
igen um of the of the igen function that
achieves the unique smallest igen value
of this shinger operator um and you can
show that in this case the square of
this sig function is exactly
the the PDF of the noise that you would
add so the takeaway that I want you to
get from here is that KO optimal privacy
mechanisms in the small sensitivity
regime are given by igen functions of
the shinger
operator so when you choose your cost
function should be quadratic
cost then um and find the corresponding
igen function the this is a known result
in mathematical physics the function is
exactly the gaussin so this explains why
gaussian is optimal right why we
observed this favorable performance of
of gaussians in this small sensitivity
or large noise regime what's interesting
is should explore other kinds of
constraints so you can ask what happens
if I add an L1 constraint here so in
this
case um one might expect that you're
going to look of get something that
looks like laast noise which is a very
popular mechanism in differential
privacy but in fact you don't the
optimal noise distribution is something
known as an Airy distribution that's in
terms of these ay functions we haven't
seen this in differential privacy and we
call this the a mechanism um compared to
true laast to the laast noise to the
standard laas mechanism um these
distributions are actually quite
different not only in terms of their
shape but also in terms of their tail so
you get so if you look at a laass taale
like it falls as e to the minus X if you
were to look at a gaus the it's each to
the minus x square and for the AA
mechanism you get something in between
so okay so these are the two questions
that we were asking and we've been
studying for a few years now so the
first one is how do we measure privacy
loss under many compositions and how
should we design privacy mechanisms that
operate under many compositions and I
think by now we have a really good
handle of how these absolon Delta
privacy guarantees behave in the limit
of large
compositions um the question of how to
design optimal mechanisms is still
ongoing work what we've been observing
in our experiments is that many many
many machine learning settings of
interest is this kind of small
sensitivity regime so um effectively
your data is very large or you have many
parameters and um and in that case
gussan is um performs really well so it
it might turn out that what people have
been doing all along of adding gin to to
data is actually optimal or really close
to Optimal but at least now we can show
that Beyond just
theistic so in the 10 minutes that I
have left I just want you switch your
gears a little bit and just give some
high Lev overview of some of the work
that we've been doing on fairness um so
particularly if anyone is interesting in
collaborating with folks down massav and
across the
river so just for the last 10 minutes
I'm just going to highlight some of our
contributions here so the challenge
we've been asking for a while is the
challenge of group fairness which is if
you give me a classifier
and a data set right I train this
classifier and I want you ensure that
this classifier is not only accurate on
average but across different population
groups there's no significant difference
in performance and by difference in
performance here I mean for example
differences in accuracy or false
positive rates or false negative rates
and what I mean by population groups I
might address this again towards the end
but um what I mean by that or groups for
example um this has been since taken
down I Believe by the by the White House
but um uh to avoid discrimination
against groups determined for example by
uh race color ethnicity sex and um so
on so um there are many methods that uh
and many metrics should measure this
disparity in performance uh in so-called
group fairness and usually they follow
the following recipe at least for binary
classification tasks where you have an
input example and you have a classifier
output and you have a binary group group
attribute and then you can if um denote
it by S for example two groups here and
if you're doing binary classification
you can build the group fairness metrix
by building this confusion Matrix
between both groups and comp and
comparing their entries so example for
example if you trained a classifier and
you want the average number of ones uh
the average number of of inputs marked
as one across both groups are trying to
ensure something known as statistical
parity you might want to equalize false
positive positive rates that's known as
equalized odds but you can already see
that there is combinator many different
ways of defining fairness metrics uh in
terms of how your Model
S um when your classifier outputs a a a
risk score or a distribution over
classes uh so for example when you think
about your classifier as a as a
conditional distribution that outputs a
distribution over a certain set of
classes um you can also extend these
privacy def these fairness definitions
that is scar equalized odds and so on in
terms of this output distribution here
so something that will be important for
us in just a few slides is that several
score based group fairness metrics can
be written as linear constraints on the
classifier so this will this is an
important Insight because it'll allow us
to formulate optimization problems where
we add these group fairness constraints
as linear constraints and try to
minimize the change in the output of the
classifier but over the past like 10
years there's been just Myriad like
fairness interventions they can be
broadly divided into pre-processing and
processing and post-processing methods
where you change the data before you
train in processing methods where you
change the classifier while training and
postprocessing methods where you correct
the outputs of a classifier and usually
these interventions are compared in
terms of these fairness utility
trade-offs so here on the uh y- AIS you
have accuracy on the x-axis you have
some kind of fairness metric
and you compare what accuracy on average
does your model preserve while closing
some kind of disparity Gap in fact there
was a study recently that showed that
this is already from last year so this
number probably increased that there
were 341 Publications with over 400
methods proposing different fairness
interventions so our goal was like well
can we design a better fairness
intervention and specifically how can we
show that maybe we're approaching some
kind of paral Frontier of the best that
you can do so our goal was to design a
fairness intervention that worked for
large data sets multiple classes and
multiple potentially intersectional
groups for ensuring U performance and
there are many fairness interventions
out there but most of them have certain
limitations they were benchmarked on
overused data sets like abon compass
that were pretty small um they only
consider either binary classification or
only consider disparities in performance
in two groups
so um in Europe a couple of years back
we proposed a new fairness intervention
called Fair projection that overcomes
these limitations we Benchmark it on a
data set with over a million samples it
can be applied training classifier
without retraining it's a
post-processing method so the complexity
is the same if you're training a a
neural network or if you're training a
logistic regression and can be used for
any finite number of classes and
protected groups and F projection is
actually based on an optimization
formulation known as information
projection that you might be familiar
from your information Theory
class um where the vanilla information
projection you have a distribution p and
you want to project onto a convex set of
distribution scal of C that are
determined by a finite set of moment
constraints so the idea is that if you
have a reference distribution P you want
to find a new distribution Q in the set
that minimize minimizes the quote
unquote distance often formulated in
terms of K diers
subject to uh being in this class and
this finds many applications in large
deviation Theory Universal are scolding
compression and Beyond you can actually
generalize this this this projection
operation in terms of a f Divergence so
you can ask what is the closest uh
distribution in terms of a given F
Divergence um and you can further
General this was done by cheer in the
70s and you can actually further
generalize this and instead of
projecting a single distribution you
project a conditional distribution a
channel right and you can ask well what
is the channel within a set of channels
that satisfies a convex set a convex set
of moment constraints that minimizes the
this conditional F
Divergence um we presented this at IIT
already now a few years back it's not a
direct extension of information
projection you have to be care take a
little bit of care to show that this the
solution to this optimization is well
defined and model projection is very
useful for ensuring fairness because in
this case as I mentioned earlier in the
talk you can think about your
conditional distribution as your model
right as your classifier so you can
think about a classifier as a channel
where a sample comes in and a
distribution over classes comes out
right um so a dist um and as I mentioned
earlier the set of group fairness uh
several group fairness constraints can
be written as linear constraints on this
classifier so you can formulate the
problem of minimizing the changes of the
output of a classifier
um or finding a new classifier that
minimizes the average change of a base
classifier but also satisfying your
fairness constraint as an F Divergence
minimization problem that looks like
model
projection and you can prove that the um
optimal output the optimal classifier
that you get is actually a tilting just
like we saw earlier but now an F
Divergence dependent tilting of your of
your original classifier where these
dual parameters these parameters of the
tilting depend on the your F Divergence
of choice and on your fairness
constraints and this is the basis of an
algorithm that we proposed that was an
oral ad neurs a couple of years ago um
called fur projection which is a model
agnostic uh post-processing approach
that can be applied to any based
classifiers so if you buy this model
projection framework this is that
post-processing is the best thing to do
and um we tested this as well uh you can
implement it this um this algorithm is
highly paralyzable you can solve it
using admm this is the the algorithm uh
for fair projection I'm not going to go
into details but the important thing is
that it you can paralyze it and run it
on a GPU using standard like uh proximal
admm like algorithms and we benchmarked
it on several data sets data sets that
are of a nation state scale with like
this is a data set from the Brazilian
University entrance exam with over a
million samples and this is restricted
to binary classif ification because most
competing Methods at the time were only
restricted to Binary classification
tasks and and you can see here the dark
red line a which is for projection is
competitive with the state-ofthe-art um
in this case our base model is a random
Force
classifier um the most competitive
method to ours was the reductions
approach but our method ran like a 100
times faster exactly because we can
paralyze it on GPU and since then we've
tded on other methods also for
correcting your networks and things like
that so the last thing I'm going to
mention is that if you look at this this
plot it seems like there's some
diminishing returns here right it seems
like oh we we're optimizing this this
fairness correction process but it seems
like we're not getting a lot out of it
so there's a question if are we close to
this best fairness accuracy Frontier
like for example is there something like
a Converse bound that we could show that
proves that maybe we're already very
close to the best that we can do and
this is something we presented at
Europe's 2023 that in fact we can for
certain semisynthetic experiments derive
this Converse bound it's based on a
result by black B comparison of
experiments and for popular data sets
you can show that we are actually very
close to
Optimal so yeah I'm going to wrap up
here so if you found this in interesting
and you're looking for folks to
collaborate around the river um we have
also other ongoing work and that range
from like pure kind of Shannon Theory
kind of things on measuring information
from moments to things that are uh more
uh coding theoretic flavored like
approximate coding Computing and private
Vector data database retrieval work on
like trying to understand the
generalization properties of of of
learning algorithms based on these
information theoretic
quantities and um to wrap up just
talking going back to the Divergence
between theory and practice
so information Theory can help us can
help guide the design of trustworthy or
more trustworthy machine learning
algorithms through for formulations that
are imperfect right specifically when
you talk about like regulation of
privacy and and of I don't know ethical
aspects of fairness but they are good
because they can be they're formal they
can be analyzed critiqued and tested um
another thing we've been doing in my
group is also trying to bring these
things in practice both with um Outreach
programs in Latin America to
collaborations with like the op DP uh
project at Harvard where uh which is a
big project for developing open
differential privacy software um we
actually wrote a policy brief that was
published at the G20 meeting in Brazil
about arbitrariness and fairness and
machine learning and so on um we have a
big research group I have a my research
group is now about 12 people uh all
thinking about things that are very uh
close to the lit student heart like
learning data optimization uh
information Theory and so on um and I
would be happy to answer any questions
thanks
[Applause]