I'd like to introduce Marvel Velasco,
co-founder of
Neta. Mar, take it away. Thank you so
much for the intro. Hi everyone. Um, a
pleasure to be here. So, we're going to
start sharing our screen and go through
the presentation open for questions
after. So, yes, my name is Marvel Lasco.
I'm the co-founder of Neta, the product
packaging intelligence platform.
Before MIT, I worked at the CFO's office
at Groupup Bimbo where multi-million
dollar packaging decisions impacted
directly the bottom line. And Grace, my
co-founder, was um was a CPG manager at
the McKenzie. Um so she worked with a
lot of these Fortune 500 companies
before she did her MBA and MPP from
Harvard.
Packaging is everywhere and it's not
only what you unwrap, but it's a very
important part of the product. In fact,
it accounts for up to 10% of its total
cost. That's why we created Neta, a
product um that's why we created Neta,
an AI powered platform that helps
companies navigate packaging regulations
and make informed decisions to purchase
the best packaging design. We'll be
talking more about the tech more in
depth later on. So, why does this even
matter? Let's take your local Chipotle
store for example, which happens to be
our third first paid pilot customer.
When you go into the store, you'll see
burrito bowls, foil wraps, drinking
cups. You'll see even more behind the
counter and before the store. One
typical Chipotle store has over 100
unique packaging items. And packaging
isn't just about the branding and the
functionality. It's about cost and
compliance. Regulations around packaging
have existed for decades covering
safety, chemicals, labeling,
environmental standards and tariffs.
These regulations are fragmented and
complex and Anna Aipo has to manage them
across hundreds of cities. This is truly
impossible for her to do by
herself. She's navigating over 400
unique regulations, mapping Chipotle's
packaging specs to legal definitions and
possible exemptions, estimating cost and
looping and sourcing or packaging
engineers to redesign
SKUs. Non-compliance can cost up to $1
million per month per state. So, that's
where we come in. Not only do we help
you navigate regulations, but once we
help you understand them, we guide you
to the latest packaging materials and
we'll help you procure them efficiently.
By making smarter decisions, companies
can cut costs up to
25%. This is huge. So, let me tell you
how this works. Our platform connects to
our client spec systems. We scan their
full SKU portfolio to analyze packaging
weights, materials, and sales data. We
leverage large language models to track
thousands of regulations across various
jurisdictions. These models process
complex regulatory text and map them to
real packaging SKUs, ensuring that
insights are precise, actionable, and
tailored to each customer's unique
packaging footprint. So, as regulations
evolve, our system will continuously
update and provide real time compliance
alerts. This helps companies make
smarter, faster decisions to stay
compliant and minimize the risks. In
parallel, we use AI to enhance cost
optimization, procurement, and packaging
efficiency. We map brands demands data
to suppliers material cataloges,
enabling us to match packaging demand
and supply a lot more effectively. This
approach will help companies build more
resilience and futurep proof supply
chains. And after the webinar, Grace and
I are happy to share a a demo video of
how this really works. So you can look
into our
platform. Now $700 billion is spent on
packaging every single year in this in
the US. Yes, $700 billion. And every
business that sells packaged products
needs better tools to make smarter
decisions. So we bring in companies
through regulations. But the real value
of what build what we're building is
what comes next which is which is
packaging procurement. When a company
needs to comply they also need to
rethink what they're going to buy. So at
Neta we turn regulatory data into action
helping teams choose smarter materials
lower fee formats and better designs.
We're becoming the platform where
packaging gets optimized and eventually
purchased. And on top of that, we're
enabling packaging manufacturers to
produce exactly what buyers like
Chipotle actually need. So that is how
we move from a $3 billion regulatory
compliance market into a $30 billion
plus packaging procurement opportunity.
And we are really happy to be here with
all of you today as we have the capacity
to work with two or and to three more
companies for our pilots. This is an
opportunity for you to be part of the
design of the product tailoring it to
your needs before we roll this out in
the standardizes platform. So if any of
anything of what we've just presented
resonates to you or you think it would
resonate to someone in your company,
please reach out to us as we are ready
to scale and support companies save
millions on packaging related costs. I'm
Marvel Velasco and this is Neta. Thank
you so much and open for Q&A.
Great Mark. Thank you so much. And also
I'm welcoming uh Grace for the Q&A, a
co-founder as well with Neta. So as
people um pose their questions to the
Q&A at the bottom of your screen um I
will get started. So considering all the
geopolitical changes that are happening
nowadays, what would you say is the main
thing that Neta can bring to the table?
Great question. Thank you so much for
that. um what we bring not only for
companies to stay on top of the
regulations what is more important is
the cost analysis to inform companies
what is the most important decisions or
the reactions to these regulations so we
help them companies with these analysis
which right now there's very little
visibility on so with better
understanding of cost and where the the
the money is going to go to this helps
company make decisions around where to
com where to procure their products
format changes as required and
visibility on what's the fees or
penalties or any additional costs that
will incur as a result of new
regulations that are coming in.
Thank you, Grace. Um, and a question
that I was actually it's it's connected
to um the next one. Do you well tell us
a little more about the business model
and also what it would it mean to work
um with you for a pilot for a corporate
but also in the US outside of the US.
Tell us about that. Yeah definitely. So
we are right now working with any
company that sells packaged products
into the US. So you can be an
international company but if you sell
your products in the US we are covering
the US regulatory landscape as of for
now as our go-to market. So definitely
we can support you. The way we're
working with our pilots is we are
designing the pilots in three months. So
we design the scope of work with the
company that we are going to on board as
a pilot and we define what regulations
and states. So geographical coverage
within the US is most important to the
company. We demonstrate how we add value
giving full visibility to the company on
what these regulations actually actually
represent for them and how much it's
costing it because procurement normally
just looks for the cheapest packaging
but doesn't aggregate all the taxes that
come on top of that. There's a lot of um
new legislations for example extended
producer responsibility EPR that is now
incentivizing companies to change to
more recyclable compostable packaging so
more sustainability. um what they're
doing is taxing a lot more higher fees
to the materials that are not as
recyclable as others could be. And so
what we will do is bring that cost
analysis to the company so they can then
look go back to the procurement and see
if there's they need to make any
changes. Um our business model is right
now we'll define um um fixed fee on what
that pilot would look like depending on
the scope of the work but then
transition into a SAS subscription
model. Great. Thank you very much to
both