The following content is provided under
a creative common license. Your support
will help MIT Open Courseware continue
to offer high-quality educational
resources for free. To make a donation
or view additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT Open
Courseware at ocw.mmit.edu.
Some content in this audio is not
covered under our creative common
license. For more information, see the
course materials on the MIT Open
Courseware website.
>> I'm finishing assignment two and we will
spend the next couple of weeks grading
him. Uh but uh you know, that was pretty
fun on Friday. So, so I think both
pretty well and um
you know we we've been talking these
past couple of uh oh actually
>> yeah we hope um we've been talking the
past couple of weeks about you know
serious games games games games games
games games games games games games
games games games games for education
game as an art form as a means of
expression and we're going to be
continuing some of those uh discussions
later on um but the whole idea is sort
of give you um to sort of prep you for
the situation where uh you're going to
make a game for a client and for this
last assignment you're actually going
going to be making a game on a based on
a problem that these guys are going to
be talking about actually.
>> Sure.
My name is Jim Cartran. I'm a clinical
psychologist. uh work at Beth was at
Beth Djan just started at Brighamin
Women's Hospital um in one of the
Harvard mafia hospitals and um my area
is using interactive media for um for uh
both uh clinical training but especially
for treatment of clinical problems. So
building computer programs to help treat
uh clinical disorders in psychology.
>> Okay, it's my understand
I'm a psychiatrist at UMass. I trained
in the same uh uh place like used to
work as uh and my focus is primarily
clinical. I'm I'm an attending
psychiatrist in a variety of setting
settings inatient outpatient and uh uh
what I brought up to Jim and then Philip
was a practical question that I'm going
to try to uh present uh which is helping
psychiatry residents deal with angry,
agitated and potentially disordered
patients as I'm going to say later. uh
this is a uh significant and largely uh
unknown issues. Certainly uh the
research is uh picking up and people try
to understand uh the extent of the
problem and uh um but I see more I'll
say it for for the presentation. So u
thank you for having me here. So um when
they contacted me um that there was the
initial interest in trying to make some
sort of digital uh uh piece of software
to to be able to help the the training
residents um in in learning how to deal
with violence or violence in in in in u
in mental in mental institutions um and
um and immediately the first thing I
thought well before we jump right into
digital let's try doing something in
analog first let's try um uh prototyping
something first but it also occurred to
that um in the real world of game
design, there's actually a lot more jobs
in game design outside of the game
industry and inside the game industry.
Uh there are a lot of companies out
there that are basically looking for
solutions, some of which may be games
and uh you might end up working uh in in
in some of those um in some of those
capacities. A lot of folks in
advertising for instance who are
involved in games. a lot of folks who
are interested in uh improving teaching
methods or improving uh simulations, you
know, working on um trying to think of
an example uh public awareness uh and uh
uh people who are also interest who who
are now working in website design and
you know v various online services who
are trying to think about how to make
their experiences a little bit more
gamelike. There are really really good
ways of doing them and there are really
really bad ways of doing them. And for
the most part, what we're hoping is that
if you end up getting one of those jobs,
you're you're going to be able to bring
some of your personal insight as having
actually done game design as opposed to
just copying what games have done and
and and just assuming well it kind of
looks like a game therefore it is game.
uh you guys that now. So, so, so this is
this is kind of get your feet wet in in
terms of designing something uh the
designing for somebody else's needs. Um
the the important things to keep in mind
is, you know, who's who's going to be
playing your game or who's who who's
this game intended for and in what
context are they going to be playing
your game and what are the particular
problems that you're trying to address?
what's what what's the part of of the
system that you're trying to to simulate
uh and what kinds of things do what what
what kinds of insights do you hope
people are going to be able to get out
of that the problem they're going to
talk about is huge is that um if you
notice I uploaded actually like four
readings to the class web only one of
them required but all of them are useful
I'm going to be uploading more these are
all reference material for your team to
use um however you you wish because the
problem is so huge and vast You don't
have to solve the whole problem. You
pick one thing that you are excited
about, that you're interested about, and
that you think that you might have a
good strategy. And then do the the usual
brainstorm. We're going to be going
through brainstorming and team selection
pretty much this this week. Um, and uh
and try to identify some small part that
might be, you know, addressable with a
card game, world game or I'll talk a
little bit about uh role playing games
uh in a couple of weeks. So um with that
being said, I'm going to hand it over to
you guys.
>> Great. So who's first?
>> Uh Caesar will take the lead on this.
>> Okay. So we'll try to take turns to uh
talk about uh about violence and
psychiatry in particular. So uh as
Philip pointed out, violence is a is a
large is a large issue. uh what I'm
going to try to focus on is uh as I
mentioned earlier uh the relevance in in
dealing with uh psychiatric patients
especially psychiatric patients on an
inatient unit uh which is what uh you
know what they actually request or the
question for me uh came from um and uh
obviously uh violence can be looked at
in in a variety of uh of ways and uh uh
I think in in one of the handouts that
uh that I sent to Philillip, violence
and mental illness. They talk about uh
the biological the psychological
theories, the the social uh uh dimension
of uh of violence and how it can be
understood. If you look at the human
development and no matter what theory
you uh you consider either trai
traditional drive-based theory like
pride or or Ericson stages uh each seems
to define a certain um developmental
goal and and often achieving or
achieving in a faulty way that goal uh
can create uh um the potential for
aggression and sometimes violent um a
little child or or an adult whose uh
dependent oral needs are frustrated may
try to take over and and get those uh u
u you know those met in a way or
another. So
what I use as if you want the metaphor
for uh for uh uh the origins of violence
is the communication uh breakdown. at
some level uh something doesn't happen
right between you know the person who
gets angry and uh those around him or
her. Uh so in a more in the most generic
way basically communication as Lasso
said is about who says what to whom and
what channel and with what effect. Uh
the breakdown can occur at many levels
and again this is the the generic
reform. I hope uh I'll I'll make it
clear what I mean and especially uh what
can be done at a practical level when
you're let's say the resident on call uh
at night and the staff calls you up says
so and so is getting out of control
she's she's raising her voice
threatening pounding walls wanting to
get out refusing medications how do you
approach such a person and again the
intervention can happen at different
levels and actually one uh one goal of
uh of the training
uh or or potentially the game uh that
you might consider is what to do. How do
you establish when to engage fully uh by
yourself with outside help when the
intervention is minimal and you just
bring uh pens with you, restrain the
patient, use pharmarmacology. So, it's a
continuum of interventions. I'm going to
just focus on what to do when you can
actually engage the patient. Um
again continuing the the metaphor uh is
what people have what Walter Fish has
described as as this type of uh uh
narrative uh rationality as opposed to
the uh um to the traditional rational
paradigm that defines people as uh as
thinking beings that have actually uh to
make make decisions and and uh um and
base their actions on evidential
reasoning for aggression people. We
analyze the situation and come up with
the best possible outcome. Walter
Fischer talks about uh uh the fact that
we are all storytellers that we try to
to interact to understand others based
on a narrative that we have about
ourselves and about others. My my
assumption and again this is just the
introductory metaphor if you want that
at some point uh violence can be caused
by by a disruption uh in in this
narrative. Things don't make sense
anymore. We feel u misunderstood. We uh
we feel the victim of an injustice. And
th those principles apply to uh to
somebody who's who's struggling with a
mental illness where things are, you
know, have a much narrower window of
opportunity than than the for people who
are able to flexibly adapt to the
demands of of reality. Um,
so
we all know who this is and uh uh the
reason I I put it up and I have to admit
I haven't looked into the copyright uh
part of this uh I know there are uh
longer and longer copyright rules for
using cartoons so you'll have to forgive
me. Uh my point is that this is an angry
person. Uh and uh as a as someone who's
communicating, I think we get uh quickly
and and and clearly the fact that his
emotional range may be intense, but it's
fairly narrow. Uh doesn't cover white
light broad spectrum and and the
communication is fairly simple. He's in
distress. He's he's imposing his point
of view. He needs space. He uh he uh
could uh become uh very aggressive and
assaulted. I think that uh the language
is very simplistic. How would we
approach the Hulk and and trying to calm
him down and change his color? Well,
again, that's the end of my health.
Um
briefly and and please feel free to
interrupt, jump in uh I can make this
presentation as long as short as as as
you want me to. There are many slides
but don't I'm not going to go through
every single line. I'm just using this
as a as if you want as a stimulus for uh
for the conversation especially from
from your perspective and from from your
needs. As I said I'm a clinical uh
provider. I'm a psychiatrist. I deal
with patients uh all the time many of
whom uh are angry or potentially angry
or potentially assaulted. And and I may
do things some you know after so many
years instinctively but sometimes I have
to think through okay this is the
situation. How do I do to to maximize uh
the benefit for for the patient I'm
treating and to keep myself safe? I've
been assaulted just once in in 15 years.
And it was like in the movies. Um a VA
patient, former Green Beret, who got
upset to the system and picked up a very
heavy armchair and you know lifted above
his head and I we we uh established eye
contact and I think he wondered what
should I do with this puny little little
doctor? Should I squash him or not? And
uh and in the end, I guess it was a
last, you know, split-second moment, he
decided to throw it, you know, to my
side. A large section of the wall came
down. So I looking I I was wondering,
you know, I could have been that wall
coming down. He ran out. It took him,
you know, a while to to be, you know, be
able to catch up with him and two
cruisers full of police officers to
subdue him. So I guess no communication
there. Uh he was just subdued. what's
the magnitude of of the problem? Uh I
think it's substantial and actually more
than 10 years ago there were some
isolated reports of of how significant
uh uh uh the problem was in terms of uh
trainees and especially psychiatry
trainees being uh uh the target of of
verbal and physical violence. Um
uh on this first page I I talk about
medical students. Uh in one study you
know numbers are relatively small uh but
again uh the study is uh uh 14 years
old. Um
a survey of psychiatry residents showed
that assault or threats of violence uh
are clearly one of the most difficult uh
events in their training. And some were
wondering retrospectively this is the uh
uh the right field for them. Actually
some students may wonder reading this
literature whether psychiatry is the
right field for for them to go into. Uh
and as you as you see uh uh the fourth
um in the fourth article almost
twothirds of psycho residents were
assaulted at least once during their uh
their training.
And obviously like with any kind of
dangerous situation, the risk of
post-traumatic symptoms can be
substantial either an acute stress uh
response or longerlasting long
longerlasting issues. The idea of uh
improving their training and their
ability uh to deal with the situation uh
has multiple benefits. Those who know
what to do are are almost never
assaulted. Not only that, if they happen
to be exposed, the likelihood of
developing post-traumatic symptoms, you
know, goes down significantly. So, uh I
don't think I need to to demonstrate uh
that point any further. Uh the assault
rate in a in a more detailed a
relatively more recent study, 10 years
old, pretty old. Uh you see, uh that
overall the number of assault rate was
30 to 40%. uh men tended to be slightly
more frequently assaulted than than
women. Uh
>> can you define what what assault means
exactly?
>> Uh what qualifies as an assault?
>> Assault um basically means kind of
laying hands on on the person and uh uh
the assault resulting in an injury uh of
of any kind. Skin, you know, being kind
of uh broken through or or some kind.
just just holding the per the the
clinician wouldn't be an assault.
>> Well, it would be an assault because uh
that such a kind of grabbing action
could actually result in a in an injury.
Um and uh um I think it would be uh
probably very limiting to talk only
about physical injuries especially since
the psychological consequences are often
uh the longerlasting and much more
significant. I think what the surveys uh
have shown also is that how unprepared
uh trainees in the mental health and
outside the mental health field are.
Actually often this is reduced to a few
lectures especially during orientation
and then they are thrown into the uh you
know lion cage and they learn on the job
u and uh many of these findings are
retrospective many trainees felt that
well I didn't say anything because I
thought I was supposed to just toughen
up and bite the bullet and move on or
this is part of the job I chose this
it's my fault or maybe I did something
wrong. Maybe I was the one who uh made
it so that the assault happened. So, a
lot of reasons that were just again not
looked into. Um fear of being
scrutinized. How come that I'm the one
who want assaulted among 10 10 trainees?
Uh how how I'm going to explain this? I
was so frightened that I cannot even
remember clearly what happened to me. So
there are a variety of reasons why
people who are in training and again I'm
focusing on and again with a ve on on a
very small segment uh specific group of
of trainees in a in medical and psychic
training but I could easily think of of
other situations of people who are kind
of exposed to the potential for violence
and and where you know such training
could be helpful
uh until now and for the most part the
data that I was able to collect that
most people you know looking at this
have been able to collect is fairly
limited Um there are certain you know
limited number of programs
methodologically the research is is
quite faulty. You can just talk uh about
you know how uh you know how limited the
generalizability of the findings are uh
and often people talk about what
happened in the past. So clearly the
recall bias is a major limiting factor
in understanding um what what happened.
Also as uh Jim asked me so how do you
define assault? One of the biggest
problems with with most research in this
field is that uh defining assault
aggression is done in very ways. Uh it's
hard to compare different uh uh
different studies. Uh so
this is a compilation of uh of what
people in you know different areas have
have thought about in terms of improving
their psychiatric training. And as you
see most often uh in the last few years,
the idea of using simulation uh to uh
expose the trainees to a uh to a
protected environment that has really
defined boundaries and consequences and
basically uh that can be repeated almost
in identical fashion in order to gain
proficiency. Uh you know is is coming up
more and more. Uh what uh many training
programs uh are doing is to use
standardized patients that are uh that
use actors um and that of course will
behave in a in a uh uh kind of
programmed fashion. They may get up to
you and make fists, but hopefully
they'll not get so much into the role
and end up punching you. So
>> I think this is the real challenge is
that there's there's different levels of
of learning. You can learn kind of a
list of facts, things to do if your
patient starts to get agitated and
threatening. And you know, you can learn
that and take a test on it and forget it
the next day, especially if it doesn't
come up for you right away. Um, and then
there's there's the question of
internalizing it so you actually have a
not just a kind of a working knowledge
of really understand what you should do
in different kinds of circumstances. And
that's where the um the idea of role
playing with live role plays for the
trainees for the residents and mental
health providers can really be helpful
so that they've had some se semblance of
this kind of um training. Um but it's
the the tricky thing with these role
plays is it's not easy to ensure that
everybody receives you know high quality
access to you know well-trained actor
you here in you know Harvard Medical
School they probably do probably but you
know there's a lot of places and if you
expand beyond psychiatry to every mental
health center in the country every case
worker who's going out to visit a
patient at their home or social worker
you know they're definitely not getting
this kind of training and so you know
the ones really I think you said before
are really well trained are the nurses
actually because they they they get a
different kind of training that's really
pretty effective it sounds like but the
mental health care providers often have
no training and then they're the ones
who are kind of in a closed room with
the person who can become really violent
especially at their home or in inatient
unit.
>> Yeah Jim was making reference to that
psychiatrist at MGH who last year was
stabbed by a patient in the outpatient
clinic in a rather
>> you don't hear about this last year.
>> Can you just describe the situation?
Well, it was late in the evening when
most things like this have this
potential of happening and this was a
new evaluation for uh this psychiatrist
in the life of the clinic at MGH and
basically he he was angry from the
beginning and was able to staff
repeatedly. Uh an offg guard, you know,
person just happened to walk by.
>> Was that police officer? Uh yeah, he was
one of the security uh uh people for
that particular clinic and he came
apparently had a gun. I don't know how
often offduty security people carry
their guns with him but he opened fire
and killed the the patient. So he was
charged I think
>> yeah eventually was cleared but for
using excessive force.
>> What happened to the psychiatrist? Well,
psychiatrist was admitted and uh to a
hospital and required, you know,
extensive surgeries and I think um she
was stabbed in the chest and in the neck
and it was a fairly gruesome. She
survived and I think she's back at work.
But this is an extreme case and uh I'm
afraid that uh many of the things that
we talk about and principles that we may
come up with may not necessarily be uh
uh so helpful other than thinking back
at a level intervention. It's quite
conceivable that for somebody who
charges at you, you won't be able to
talk him down. You won't be able to use
any of the uh nice deescalation
principles that I'm going to talk about
in a few minutes. But figuring out what
to do, I think it remains important.
>> Um so I have a question. You mentioned
that nurses have sort of like a
different training system for this and
and it seems to be effective. Like what
what what is that training? like what is
different about what nurses get taught
in the
>> Well, um there are some in most states
there are uh regulations that um try to
implement some level of training for
designed specifically for patients who
get out of control and that's not in
only psychiatry. uh emergency room uh
teams have probably the most one of the
most kind of the highest rate of of
assaulted patients across uh across
diagnostic boundaries. Often psychiatric
patients especially patients using
substance abuse will will uh will get
out of control emergency room. So if you
want to become emergency physician or
you if you work in the field an EMT or
another capacity you'll have to deal
with these situations. what what makes
the nurses uh somewhat better trained is
that uh um they often are the frontline
uh uh staff dealing with out of control
patients and I think that's probably
pretty probably sad because physicians
should be equally you know and trainees
and physicians in training should be
equally well well trained but uh but on
the nursing front uh there has been some
progress in Massachusetts the department
of mental health uh has some method of
retraining there's a lot of red tape
there. But there are a lot of um helpful
helpful aspects uh including aspects
related to self-defense
and I wish I I could have presented a
recording of of a of a training session
for staff. Uh it's when I went through
it I I thought it would be something
like a very spectacular kind of kung fu
how you do it. But in fact uh the
emphasis is how to keep yourself safe
and believe it or not how to keep the
person safe. the person that you're kind
of blocking the way punches uh the
person that might be trying to kind of
strangle you or or keep you in a
stronghold or or scratch you or you know
rip your your hair again even when you
try to intervene or you're trying you're
trying to protect yourself and keep the
other other person safe. So no punching,
kicking, no kind of spectacular
kind of stunts in that respect. But
again that also I feel could be you know
an interesting topic for for simulation.
How do you kind of interact with uh
especially since again I'm I'm a total
kind of outsider in the field but I um
having kids you know they they were
asking me the other day about
Microsoft's connects uh connect um and I
thought that was really interesting
because the level of interaction with uh
kind of computerenerated uh interfaces
is very is very interesting and
certainly would be a that to be attacked
by by somebody from the TV
person.
>> It sounds like nurses get better
training because the states require them
to have better training.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. That's correct.
>> All right.
>> That that's in part of it. And I've been
trying at at UMass to to suggest that
not only the staff physicians get
exposed to the training but even the um
psychiatry trainees and other trainees
especially in an emergency medicine.
they they should all really, you know,
know about it.
>> I suspect some of this has to do with
with the benefits of being in a union,
which the union can demand that the
nurses receive this better training
where the physicians are not in the
union.
>> Uh, and it's also about numbers. I mean,
on the on any unit, you know, the you
have uh six, seven nurses per one
physician uh and the nurses are they're
in shifts around the clock. So the lackl
of being exposed to a uh to an out of
control you know much higher usually on
on these units people intervene as a
team uh and there's a team leader that
tries to you know applies many of the
principles I I hope to talk about uh and
then if there is need for seclusionary
strength then that has to be done in an
automated fashion and and things are
clearly much much clearer as I said on
the nursing front maybe because they're
doing it all the time because there are
some ty relations maybe because they're
unionized and
you know at least half of the literature
uh really comes from from the nursing
direction. So uh so that's a that's a
tangent
just want to write on the on the connect
uh uh uh comment that you were making. I
mean we will be talking a little bit
more about live action games. So, um,
that's kind of how you prototype how you
prototype something that's going to be a
motion gesture computer game. You don't
obviously actually having to write code
to do that. That sort of body
recognition is kind of annoying uh and
and expensive, but it's but you can test
out a lot of ideas uh just by having two
people play physical game. Of course,
safety becomes the biggest concern for
players as well. It's kind of
interesting because in this particular
case, you're trying to teach someone how
to prevent damage to both parties at the
same time, which is an interesting it
actually kind of helps you with the
design of of of a live action. Now,
that's only one problem. That's not the
you go into more details about the kinds
of things that you can do to prevent it
escalating into actual combat. Combat is
one of those things that
>> and the idea is basically to do you know
your best to not end up at that
particular extreme of of a direct kind
of combat which is not uh uh you know so
ideally you don't have to go there and
as I said in 15 years I've been
assaulted once I'm sure I was lucky uh
people see think that my eyebrows are
intimidating so
don't uh you know tend to to get very
you know, friendly and and and and
again, I'm going to, you know, sell a
few, you know, tell you about a few
pearls and a few tricks that I I
personally use. It may not be, you know,
they may not be helpful for for
everybody over time. You develop your
own style. The idea is to to uh be able
to make an assessment and try to take
preventative steps. And I think that
that's the secret. And this is what I
hope, you know, better training, maybe
the use of simulation and and kind of
gaming could be could be helpful. Okay.
So, uh now I'm going to just uh you know
I'm going to jump into uh uh talking
about prevention and uh uh I not
prevention but identifying how you
assess and how you think about the
potential for violence and uh and these
are some some known uh um risk factors
for aggression. Obviously the history of
violence uh is is the top um how recent
how frequently uh you know those people
become uh assaulted what's the pattern
of escalation what are the associated
symptoms what happens when before
somebody gets uh becomes assaulted. Why
is this important? because you can you
can do and at all you should do quickly
before you know engaging with the
patient uh an assessment at that level
and it will help you uh figure out how
deep to get involved how likely you are
to gasolate the patient versus saying oh
I don't need this I need help let's go
in as a team you know so uh so that that
makes it important uh people often talk
about violent threats and fantasies
young people uh tend to be more
assaulted and there's no surprise also
older people who have uh uh dementia uh
and get uh more disinhibited and more
likely to become reactive. Uh I always
like to tell the story of a patient with
dementia. I was moonlighting and he
swung at me as I was passing and then I
went to talk to him. So what happened?
Well, I don't know. He just passed by me
and I was upset and he was the closest.
So I thought I would try to talk. Uh so
um there was no way for me to to predict
that it wasn't a serious thing. It
wasn't the predatory type of of uh of
assaultiveness where somebody plants you
know you know doesn't like you goes
after you
colleague of mine was attacked by a
patient patient watched when people were
not around
went into the doctor's room locked the
door and started contacting. So that's a
totally different animal. Uh so the
distinction between impulsive, affective
when you want or uh you know type of
aggression and the predatory you know is
essential to um
in some uh subcultures violence is is uh
is not allowed certainly much more much
more frequent. Um people uh of a lower
socioeconomic status uh may may be more
likely to become uh assaulted. Patients
of a limited cognitive ability
especially when institutionalized may be
more likely to to become assaulted and
then it's a uh many many diagnosis
uh increase the likelihood of assault.
Uh the top are psychotic disorders like
schizophrenia. Uh mood disorders like
bipolar uh I told you about what uh we
call cognitive disorders especially
dementia and confusional states. um
patients that have had traumatic brain
injuries or that have have you know have
epilepsy may be more likely a real
problem with Iraq veterans coming back
or rack or Afghanistan veterans when
they have had an IED explode under their
vehicle and they've had a brain injury
and now they have a lot of just
admission about violence and they can
just go off sometimes very unexpectedly.
The frontal lobe exerts an inhibitory uh
influence on our ability to uh to
function and that allows us to plan to
think ahead to sequence events. Often
when uh the exe this is the executive
function of of our frontal lobe when
he's impaired either you know in a
trauma or after surgery you know or uh
being in a in an accident or becoming
demented that ability to
uh to operate in that fashion maybe
violence is a is a possible uh side
effect. Substance abuse I think are are
the top of the list. Uh because of the
disinhibition both during the
intoxication phase and during the
withdrawal phase people tends to become
very agitated and assaulted. There are
certain personality disorders. Uh so uh
when uh when we think as about a
personality disorder we have this
enduring maladaptive patterns of of
relating to you know to the to you and
to others and to the world.
You know the obsessive compulsive
personality disorder likes to have
things organized, planned, nothing. Even
going on vacation is an exhausting task.
Nothing has to happen randomly.
Uh grandio personalities really need
this kind of feeding coming from from
all directions. Uh they they need to be
in the limelight. they they use people
not as good people but as people that
kind of uh provide sustenance their own
self-esteem. two uh two type of uh
personality disorders uh are
particularly likely to uh promote
violence. Uh the antisocial
uh and you may have heard the term
borderline personality disorder which is
basically uh at core has uh significant
instability in emotions in interpersonal
relationships and identity and uh
basically their lives are are a mess.
often they feel abandoned, they feel put
down, they uh they may get briefly
paranoid and often uh they make they
become assaulted. So again I'm throwing
a lot of uh a lot of terms and
definitions at you. I don't want to you
know make this u lecture about
psychiatry but these are conditions that
I think u are helpful uh to think about.
Yeah.
>> People with delusional disorders like
schizophrenia get violent. Is it usually
because they're frustrated about
something or is it because they suddenly
have some sort of delusion about their
their clinician that involves uh great
question,
>> you know, requiring them to to take some
sort of action that is violent?
>> I think both. I think even people that
have a psychotic disorder have the right
to, you know, feel the victim of an
injustice or feel frustrated or u many
of the reasons that I I I talked about
could could happen. But in particular uh
I think the other point is equally
important that they may act on a on a
delusional delusional conviction or
their psychosis may also have uh may may
have hallucinations and uh command
auditor hallucinations uh are known to
often be the forers of the violent
attack. You talk about me and say things
you know or the voice tells me I'm going
to go after you. uh you do it and the
person feels uh uh uh hopeless to uh uh
to resist that. I discharge the patient
who's doing great. Next day he comes
back, went home. The boys told him that
he needs to uh hurt his mother otherwise
he will get disembowled. So he started
punching her and then chased her with a
with a knife. She had to hide in you
know behind you know in in the
neighbor's house until the police
arrived. Uh there is an interesting
threat control override pair that that
people have looked at violence u have
described as uh being sometimes the
proximal uh cause for violence. People
feel directly threatened uh and they
also uh have this overpowering you know
urge that they need to act on that
cannot resist. It's a controversial
concept. But I'm not for sure why I
would give it give this particular
association a a higher status than than
other convictions about the neighbors,
you know, watching me and uh and or
planning to kill me or putting together
a variety of clues that my friends are
really trying to to to get rid of me and
then I need to protect myself. But but
you're absolutely right. What's
interesting, even though patients with
chronic psychotic disorders may have
their reasons to um to become assaulted
in the overall bigger scheme of things,
when you look at actual uh violent
assaults committed in in society,
they're responsible for a tiny one. So,
it's it's an interesting way of looking
at numbers. Yes, they could uh
become violent, but the reality is that
the their numbers, you know, in terms of
the actual violent acts very small. But
anyway, this may just be a kind of
statistical uh trick.
>> You're talking about the number of cases
of violent episodes where compared to
the general population.
>> Exactly. Okay. So,
>> exactly. That's that's exactly the point
I'm trying to make. And then there are
uh various acute findings when you
examine the patient on on what what we
call the mental status examination.
Obviously, hostility, suspiciousness,
agitation are all associated with uh
with violence.
In terms of uh uh one one I want just to
focus one minute on on the so-called
aggressive attributional style. Um how
do we uh uh respond to stress in when we
have the per perception of uh uh of
threat? Um
this is the uh um threat override uh
delusion that I mentioned but I think
that's that's probably relevant and
command explanations
what happens in conditions of
uncertainty and many of the patients or
people may have to think in a distorted
fashion. I was talking at the beginning
about uh um
the uh communication breakdown.
You have the layer of the mental illness
that that shrinks your options. You have
a particular situation to deal with uh
that makes you even more likely to
become uh uh uh to become assaulted. And
and this constellation of cognitive
distortions may make you more likely for
you to uh to become assaulted.
neglecting the base information which
kind of assigns a high weight to to
certain events that otherwise uh you
know are you know are low frequency uh
attending uh only to facts that would
confirm your assumptions I think. Go
ahead.
>> Oh okay. So if uh the psychiatrist's
office calls to reschedule appointment
the person assumes that this is because
the psychiatrist doesn't like him.
>> Exactly. this guy, this this person
doesn't want to treat me. They don't
like me. They don't want me to be their
patient because they rescheduled me.
>> Ignoring facts that could disisconfirm
your hypothesis. Um, I just talked to
the psychiatrist who who was nice to me,
but still the fact that that he called
and canceled is the overriding, you
know, explanation that he doesn't like
me. or focusing on on common events just
because you remember them, which is an
interesting way of explaining the fact
that you remember them kind of brings
them up in the in the rank. Uh, and
other disisconfirming evidence is
totally kind of ignored. It's like the
assumption that the train on the other
platform always always seems to arrive
first because those are the ones you
remember or kind of the garden ride with
grass is always
uh and I talked about uh about
medication and street drugs some are
more likely to be associated alcohol
just by the sheer volume and especially
because withdrawal is so violent uh you
know it's it's a significant issue the
intoxication phase your level of
coordination you know your perception of
facts. You know, it's it's just uh
they're so off that you're more likely
to to lose control. Uh anti-depressants
um have an interesting impact because in
people that have an underlying tendency
to swing in their moods may actually
augment those things. You may have heard
of of the of the news of
anti-depressants promoting violence and
suicide in adolescence. Uh and while
statistitians are still scratching their
heads to figure out the exact numbers uh
the truth is that mood is very unstable
in in adolescence uh and uh often
initial depression may turn out to be
something else. You give somebody an
interdepressant call him or her for
followup in six or eight months in
meanwhile lots of things happen. And I
think in those cases when actually uh
those young
adolescents committed suicide, it was
not so much about anti-depressant
causing it. Probably the depressants
made the symptoms worse. It was very
poor followup and and poor diagnostic.
But anyway, this is getting too too
technical. Uh I included this in the
last minute. This is an interesting
summary of of a nationwide uh study uh
focusing on violence violence risk
assessment. Um
let me um just say two minutes about
useful measures in assessing dynamic
violence. Um people have looked at
violence uh in two ways. They have put
together all those factors that I that I
presented initially and uh uh they have
looked at retrospectively that those
would become violent and they compiled
um the history clinical risk assessment
scale. The problem is that when you're
dealing with somebody those scales even
though they may give you a good image of
what happens in the long run uh they may
not help you deal with the immediate
situation. So clinical scales have have
been used in IL you know one developed
in Norway uh the other one the dynamic
appraisal developed in Australia. This
these are the items for the HCR20
uh and it's almost like a repetition of
what I said earlier in terms of risk
factors. This is the historical risk
factors and these are validated skills
that have been used for for more than 15
years. The clinical scale uh is the the
dynamic part of the HCR. Uh and then the
risk management scale is trying to
project in the future what do you have
to do in order to uh ensure safety what
could go wrong and and
>> so so the value of these scales is kind
of sizing up the likelihood of this
person becoming violent um in the
absence of other information. Now the
best predictor is probably what they're
actually doing behaviorally in front of
you. you know, they're reaching for for
something heavy, you know, that's, you
know, I take that into, you know, weigh
that heavily. But, um, but in the
absence of anything else, you know, that
the people who meet a certain, I guess
you could say, certain profile are more
likely to be violent and as a
psychiatric patient than others.
>> This is a dynamic scale that looks at
what happens in front of you. As you
pointed out, u, you're considering
confusion, irritability, how boisterous
and how verbally threatening the person
is. uh the most recent one is the
dynamic appraisal of the situational
aggression that has seven factors that
seems to be the best uh one assessment
or uh prediction of violence over the
over the next 24 hours. Uh and uh this
is an interesting psychopathy uh kind of
index. Psychopathy uh is uh has an
interesting history. I think the the the
current uh version that we will talk
about is the antisocial personality. Uh
but basically refers to people with uh
with minimal capacity for empathy uh
whose kind of moral dimension is fairly
fairly primitive who engage in stealing,
cheating, violence and don't have a lot
of kind of uh moral drawbacks to do it.
Uh it seems to be associated with
violence not surprisingly. And this is
actually a factor analysis that you know
identifies those two uh those two
dimensions. Um now just at the end I
want to talk about uh uh the
deescalation principles uh that I
actually I'm trying to incorporate in
standardized patients u because the
these should be uh fairly easy to to uh
at least present and then maybe
hopefully to to teach the residents how
to use uh in terms of dealing with
educated patients. So, and actually many
of many of them are are are used by by
staff u how to how to start the
interaction with a um with a violent
patient, how to position yourself within
kind of arms length uh uh probably at 45
degrees u for two reasons.
uh one to uh um if in case you're
attacked to offer a much smaller surface
uh of the impact and also to allow you a
way to escape if you have to. Um not
obviously to block the exit or stand
over if the person is kind of kneeling
down or or in the bed. Never turn your
back. Uh what to do with your hands?
Never make fists or kind of keep your
arms crossed or behind you or in your
pockets uh to kind of appear as uh um as
non-threatening as possible. How to
regulate the the eye contact? If it's
too intense, it can become bothersome.
If it if it lacks completely, then
people could uh conclude that you're not
really interested or involved. Um
>> the thing that that's um important to
keep in mind with a um psychiatric
patient is well, a couple things. One is
that mental health uh patients are much
more likely to be the victims of
violence than actually to commit
violence. And this is, you know, that's
really the outlier, the unusual case
where the psychiatric patient becomes
violent. But obviously, it's an
important situation. It does happen
frequently enough to be a real concern
for the the providers for their
well-being. Um but then um
the I think I've lost lost my train of
thought here and basically there's
there's different levels of what you
have to understand how to do. One, how
to protect yourself and then two, how to
protect the patient. It's almost like if
your child who's 11 years old comes at
you swinging, it's really different than
if you're getting bugged on the subway
in terms of what you're going to do.
Now, the person who's sitting in your
office might be a lot bigger than your
11-year-old, but you kind of get the
idea. You're not you're not trying to
punish them. You're not trying to uh you
know inflict any more harm on them than
is absolutely needed in order to stop
the situation and for you know you to
get out or let them out.
>> Yes. And and that's important and that's
somewhat counterintuitive because when
uh I think an interesting aspect I'm
just thinking or trying to think in
terms of potential simulation uh and and
targets for for a training uh paradigm.
I think an important aspect is to uh uh
for the person who's going through the
training to understand himself or
herself. How what's the reaction when
you're threatened and how to uh to
continue to think on your feet and and
take decisions that are not based on a
kind of flight or fight or tendon
befriend you know attitude. Uh this is
not about dealing with with a common
situation. This is uh when you have to
maintain your ability to uh to remain
therapeutic and helpful and to minimize
harm to yourself but certainly harm to
to the other person. And the truth of
the matter is that many people in this
situations react the way they have that
they have always done. I mean, I I I
gave Jim the example of a social worker
I work with who every time when she's
confronted by
a patient. She gets angry and and she
gets defensive and and tells things, you
know, to her that I find are are hurtful
and are just kind of, you know, adding
gas to the fire. I need to intervene
between the two of them. It's almost
like uh, you know, I'm there the umpire.
I say, "Okay, time out. Stop. We need to
do something else." And I I I try to
explain to her, she just doesn't uh
doesn't get it or you know can't
theoretically figure it out but uh you
know doesn't uh doesn't do a good job at
it. When we are angry or frightened our
behavior, our the way we talk, the way
we track changes and that can those
things can uh be major triggers for for
the other person. So
>> yeah, if you're if you're s stay really
calm and the other person's escalating,
that's a real dampening force on that
other person from escalating even more.
And it's really really hard to do
that. Stay professional and recognizing
that this this aggression is a really a
medical symptom just like if there were
bleeding on the floor that you know the
difference obviously is that it could
actually hurt you the provider. But you
know you need to to recognize as a
medical symptom that needs to be dealt
with as opposed to taking it really
personally or or you know getting
violent act.
>> Yes. Uh
how do you hear? How do you uh uh
obviously being calm, centered, self-
assured is always helpful. It's it's the
message that that you're you're you're
conveying. often uh if you respond you
know to anger by being fearful or anger
yourself you know obviously this will
just kind of escalate uh or if you're
fidgety and you know pacing and
gesturing yourself and and wondering so
what do I do now I think uh the other
person will clearly pick up that that
feeling uh touching
uh most often than not is not a good
idea even though I mean instinctively we
would like to kind of calm calm the
other person down or wonder what it is.
This is how we learn to show kind of
empathy and that we care, we want to
help. Well, it may not may not be a may
not be a good idea.
So, uh and then
this could be a topic in itself. Um
active listening would be uh the most uh
u if you want the buzzword in terms of
the verbal deescalation uh principle.
often when I uh when I'm called and many
of my colleagues are called to deal with
such a situation I introduce myself I uh
I'm telling the person no matter how
agitated he is why I'm here uh and I'm
trying to understand uh I may not
respond or react to you know the
person's curses or threatening behavior
of course I try to maintain a safe
distance and I continue my assessment I
can I deal with this or I need help or I
I need to stop and and and find another
way. Uh and I give that person feedback
about uh what I see, how he or she makes
me feel. I feel, you know, you're
threatening. I feel uncomfortable. I
think we need to stop. Do you want to
talk? What are the issues uh that that
you're dealing with? And um I also
explain uh and set limits on on what is
acceptable and not acceptable. often
that combination works. Um
I listed phacotherapy and seclusion is
trained because they're part of the
process and I think uh I would like u
people you know who are trained you know
uh for this to understand that those
things are available. Um,
any questions so far?
>> I I've just got a couple of comments on
the position of the table. So,
>> yeah, we can do that. And also, I wanted
to suggest see what you think about
this. If someone would like to play the
role of a patient, I can meet with you
briefly and just kind of prepare you to
do that. If anybody's interested in
taking on the role of the aggressive
you'd like to do. Okay. So, why don't
you and I step up for just a couple
minutes and then you're talking.
>> So, that's going to be a bit of a role
play demonstration.
>> No, that's okay. So, uh, so I mean
there's a couple of things that that
that that have been brought up that
already immediately seem to be possible
places where you guys can think of what
what you're going to do your project on.
Um that's that's uh that's identifying
factors of course that I mean there's a
whole bunch of different schemes that
you that that that and different u
metrics that that people have been using
uh all the way from from known
personality types to you know to social
economic factors and and personal
history. you can make some some some
kind of kernel of war game, you know, I
can imagine some some sort of like can
you figure out enough information before
it's too late, that sort of kind of
thing. Um, the dynamic assessment of
violence seems to be more of a time
pressure kind of thing because it's like
you almost have to like figure it out on
the spot, right? But the factors are
very different. But I thought it's like
identifying um activists. The the
deescalation
um the active listening thing is kind of
interesting because it almost seems like
you could make it a word game or a face
to face kind of party game kind of thing
out of that of the can you remember what
you're supposed to do with you know in
conversation with each other without
missing any of the any of the points and
and that might be something that they
could do. So that that would be like a
live action game but not necessarily a
physical game. It would be like you know
like more like a party game you can
imagine working.
>> I mean one one way I uh I this is by the
way I didn't want to go there to make
this too long but this these are some
parts of a standardized uh patient that
I'm putting together. that I'm going to
try actually to uh to talk to the
simulation department at the mass to you
know train an actor and this would be
kind of the goals for uh you know the
training modes um and I'm really
particularly interested in how people
respond when they're exposed to an angry
situation or even to an angry face. What
do you have to do in order to deescalate
the patient? And what I'm what I what I
think to you I'm going to suggest to the
actor is that uh
uh you are in the room and you're pacing
up and down and you're very angry and
you're allowed to use some generic swear
words and uh uh and to have a number of
complaints. Could be a number of them.
Nurse was too late to give the
medications. The girlfriend didn't come
in time. Uh you owe money. you you just
had a job interview today and you missed
it because you're in the hospital. Could
be a number of things. And then uh and
then the person approaches approaches
you. Uh the trainee should uh
follow some rules in terms of the verbal
and non-verbal deescalation. If that
person is able to to engage you, you can
become uh uh less angry, less agitated,
more interested, uh face, they seem less
uh uh lower your voice. If the trainee
is just uh uh doing the right wrong
things, you either stay at the same
level or get more and more angry. Of
course, it's fairly demanding for a uh
for a for a standardized for an actor
because the nonverbal elements are easy.
How you regulate the distance, you know,
how you look, how you approach, you
know, you inhibit, you know, your
natural tendency to kind of pat the
person on the shoulder, whatever. But
but the verbal aspects are more
difficult.
>> Improvising dialogue at the spot is
hard.
>> Exactly. But at the same time the goals
of the dialogue are not
>> u because you should probably find out
what's going on even though let's say
the the actor will try to tell you about
his life and how miserable things are
and you know uh I lost my job and you
know I was kicked no but you need to try
to bring the person to what really
happened. I think that's very very
helpful because you're you're pinning
down a particular conflict that
triggered it. uh uh and if you're able
to do that then you can take some steps
okay I I have a patient right now who
has difficulty expressing herself and
systematically there is one particular
shift where the staff is not patient
doesn't wait for her you just need to
give her a little bit more time and she
gets upset and and angry and starts
facing and I have to every time say
please listen to her or she comes up to
me she tells me the story and then I go
back to the staff. Okay, people just
don't don't have the patience or don't
care. Okay, so that's that's just a
simple intervention. This is why you
need to find out what's going on. Okay,
and then if you can get more information
about what brought the person to this
place. Uh,
okay. We prepared him and
>> she did a role play before
>> I showed this because this is a little
bit.
>> Yeah,
>> you want to do it? You've been trained.
>> No, no, no. You're you're the expert
actually.
>> Okay.
All right. Let's see what happens to me.
>> Hello.
>> I'm uh I'm Dr. C.
>> It's John. And I was John. I was born in
oneonone with him. Why isn't he here?
Why?
>> Who Who's this person? I don't know.
>> There's John. I only want to speak to
him.
>> Well, nurse Johnny is not not available.
>> Why is he available? Why? Only only I
can talk to.
>> I don't want to talk to you right now.
>> How can I help you?
>> Get a job.
>> Okay, I can try to see if he's around.
>> Get right now.
>> Okay, but what else can I do? Um,
the medication stop not good. Try to
poison all me dead.
>> What does medication do?
>> Desc.
So tell me what what kind of problems do
you have with medication?
>> Kind of poison you owe me dead.
>> So you don't think the medication is
helpful?
>> Of course not. You already killed me.
What else can I do to help?
>> Family. Family.
>> You want me to contact the family?
>> No. I hate them all. They're all against
me.
>> Must be very hard to not have anyone to
talk to or feel comfortable with. That's
why I want to have a chance.
>> But I'm sorry you're struggling so much.
>> And I know we haven't met before, but
I'm here and trying to to be helpful to
you.
>> You want to kill me, don't you?
>> No, I don't think I want to.
So, we have a number of options.
And I think you're you're looking angry
and you're scaring people. Why?
>> You're scaring me.
>> Of course, you're just laughing behind
me. You're not scared. Just laughing.
>> No, I think you're you're a big strong
guy and and when you get angry and
upset, you can intimidate him. Uh, and
there are other other way to push me
>> scared me.
>> Well, I'm not trying to hurt you. Uh,
but we need to come up with a solution
because you could get hurt and uh and
other people could get hurt. So, we need
to do something about that.
>> Who would be better off? Dead. Everyone
wants to be dead.
>> Well, I understand you're you're quite
destructive today
and I want to help you. I may not be
able to
right away.
I'm going to try to get the nourish that
you want.
But uh what if I cannot get what's the
next best thing?
>> I don't know.
Would he help to uh uh contact your
family?
>> Okay, I can try to reach out to her.
And uh do you think that if you change
the medications, maybe you can uh try a
combination that could be helpful?
>> So, it's not poison.
>> Okay, I hear you. You don't like the
medication. You think it's uh it's
hurting you, but it's helped in the past
and maybe a different combination could
be more uh will be better.
>> Maybe maybe
thank you. We can do all this.
[Applause]
>> Oh, we have to put the fire.
You want to hire him? Very
good.
>> Um
uh I have a question actually about the
uh the the disruption of narrative uh uh
model of why violence occurs. Is that is
that pretty much accepted as as like
this this is the way you find
>> I just made it up for this.
I was just wondering if there are
competing uh different theories might be
useful for people to understand more
than one model or is that pretty
the the narrative perspective is uh if
you want a a cry from the past I think
the last 20 years uh from science and
certainly medicine have been dominated
by by hard hard evidence
>> actually uh uh the evidence-based
medicine has been kind of taking over
the entire world as as if you want the
ultimate standard. So there are
lists of the strength of the evidence
and uh uh randomized
control designs are are the best and
clinical impression anecdotes are the
worst. So in this on this map
um the narrative or a personalized story
about the patient uh may not may not be
if you want the accepted uh model today
but I think in dealing with individual
cases I feel that makes a lot of sense
when you have to deal with somebody
who's very distraught
>> if I tell him that the best available
evidence was published two years ago and
showed that you know 20 milligrams of
Adilify would work best for psychosis.
I'm not so sure that that you would you
would feel the warm at the end of it,
you know, but the reality it could be
that that evidence is right. He's
psychotic and he tried a very various
medication. Some of them made him fat
and pushed his triglycerides up and and
raised his blood pressure. If I switch
him to ailify and you know in two months
he'll get better. But dealing with the
immediate issue
uh I think is just uh uh it's something
else and and that knowledge about
medication while while helpful in the
long run would not make it very good. So
this is why I kind came up with a if you
want uh for the purpose of this meeting
with a with a way of kind of creating a
metaphor uh that could sustain my verbal
and non-verbal if you want espiration
I'm trying to uh to create some sense
some coherence some meaning some meaning
to to that interaction and in doing that
I'm empathic and I'm trying to to
channel theuh the energies in a way that
uh that it's almost like a beginning.
He's distraught. He's ready to give up.
He's ready to to shut himself away from
the world. I'm trying to reach out to
him without becoming his friend, without
becoming his brother or father. Uh but
I'm trying to and I think in a sense I'm
restoring the meaning of his narrative.
>> Somebody cares, somebody reaches out.
So because it seems like a very
interesting system for people uh for
designers to play with like the the the
idea of trying even though there is this
distorted narrative and you may uh you
may not know enough about the narrative
to be able to act on it but you can find
out things about it by talking to the to
to the patient and what you're really
trying to do is make things fit within
that person's narrative.
you're filling the blanks that were kind
of somewhat destroyed by
>> by events and it could be variety of
events
>> and at times you have to use the
imagination in a sense it's almost like
the intuition I mean I know the
principles in every case but how I'm
going to do it it's it's not
pre-programmed
>> and it seems like that's that's that's
also something that you could play with
from a design point of view and this
this idea of it's disrupted narrative
and then how do to put it back. You
know, the spec putting the pieces back
together might be something that you can
do.
>> Um, that may be the reason, and that's
not the speculation. I'm just making
this up. Why why uh adventure games are
are so powerful
>> because in a sense, you're finding a
substitute narrative
>> uh that is much more controllable than
your own.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh and for for the time of the game,
you're you're you're there. It's almost
like kind of you're buying a few
minutes, 10 minutes, 20 minutes of of a
different story line.
>> Actually, one of our researchers, you
look specifically at adventure games and
and her point of view is that playing an
adventure game is like being a performer
who hasn't been given the script. Uh,
you know, you're you're still an actor
in the story and you have to figure out
what that story is um in order to move
along. So, so that that fits really
well.
Um there there's one other thing that I
do want to bring up. Um obviously I
don't want any of these games that you
guys are working on to be quizzes to be
like really fun quizzes even. Uh you
know it's like no that's that's not what
this class is about. I do want you guys
to be designing games uh you know not
just
pursuit psych psychiatry version you
know that that's that's kind of
pointless. We we have had um games in
the past in this class where people
basically pulled questions out of a hat
and had to answer them and there were
like various penalties that were kind of
fun but that's not what I've been
teaching you guys. So so so try to think
about systems try to think about um all
these things that that they want uh
their traineees to learn you know think
about how they can engage with the
system you know in some small way uh and
and that's and that be a project.
Great. Well, ask a question of u what
are your thoughts or what are the field
thoughts I guess on lying to people to
like mitigate a situation?
>> Well,
um I would call lying a distortion. Uh
and it's very uh in a genetical way. And
uh
when people lie, they they have to make
a decision. Uh often People lie for a
variety of reasons. What I always seem
surprised by is the reason to to make
friends, to get friendly, to resolve a
situation. Okay? And uh
I don't believe in lying as as a as a
communication tool. Uh even if it if it
may make things easier in the short run,
certainly clinically, it's not it's not
it's not helpful. Uh I was telling you
about patients with borderline pathology
that have this affective and relational
instability that is basically taking
over their life. They are some of the
most accurate lie detectors that you can
imagine. You cannot design something
more perfect than that, especially
having been in the system for a long
time. They can they can feel the light
even before it comes up and then if
you're going that path, you're dead.
>> So this role play for example, if you
told Bobby, "Well, let me go get John."
on your way here for a minute and then
you and you know that John isn't working
right now. He's nowhere in the hospital,
but you just told him that to so you can
get out and then you get security to
come back in with you and then we can
subdue him or something. That's a great
example. Uh and that happens all the
time because often when you're in this
place, many of your requests are
unreasonable.
Uh so you need to set some limits. Uh
and eventually you'll end up setting
some limits. he could have continued to
escalate until kind of attacking me,
breaking everything in the room. I
usually tell them about uh how they make
know others feel uh how unacceptable
some of the behaviors are and what are
the consequences. Okay. Uh so I'm I'm
going to probably tell you if this
continues I don't have any other choice
but to call security and you end up in
these strengths and with the chemical
medication given to you injectable you
could take it by mouth. So I'm coming up
front with the with how the next few
minutes the proximal future looks like
as opposed to trying to kind of fudge it
and kind of get on his friendly side and
oh I don't mean anything but the
security will put you in strength. You
know what I mean? So I don't want to to
buy him out by just becoming a friend if
that involves lying. That's some people
do it when you're in a corner. You're
okay. So what do I do now? A little lie
won't hurt any. Maybe it's just my my
>> Yes. And what you just mentioned too,
that sort of like good cop, bad cop.
Well, you know, I wish we could have
more conversation here, but security
needs to put you in your security is the
bad guy when you know that's exactly
where you want the patient to be anyways
because they're not
>> I'm okay, but you know Jim, you know, he
doesn't he's the director and he's going
to, you know,
>> so does that answer your question?
>> Yeah. But I mean, would you like Yeah.
Yeah. Would you
>> I guess the followup is like would you
ever seek you put medicine in someone's
food or do something just
>> it's not only uh you know a loss of
waiting to happen
of a of a major magnitude uh but I don't
think it's right
>> for me even though even though probably
reality is that family members and
sometimes even providers and nursing
homes may uh may do that but I think
it's a
>> and you may you may need to treat the
person against their will, which which
is often meaning putting them into
physical restraints, which is usually
like lover kinds of things that can, you
know, kind of a straight jacket thing or
maybe to a bed and maybe physically
inject them with something to really
sedate them. But you should always be
telling them what you're going to do,
right? And and the reason why you're
doing it even if they don't have any
choices.
>> And if you feel that the person is
unable to to comprehend, you know, the
then you may need to kind of work
towards the being a guardian will take
decisions for that person. So, and it's
not necessarily that the legal field has
pushed itself very hard in this field.
But I think it's it's fair. Okay, you
meet the person where the person is at
and try to be helpful. And I think in my
view, there's no substitute for being
upfront and think what's going to
happen. You may not he may not be my
best friend, but he knows exactly. I'm
telling the patients often ahead what's
going to happen in the sense that I'm
giving them choices. Uh so if I end up
taking them to court for a commitment,
they know that and they would be
surprised. You would be surprised how
you know how angry they are at the
beginning and how okay they are later
and how often they come up to me and
said you know thank you. I was in a very
bad place but you know and I know I
didn't want to and I fought you all the
way but I think that was the best
solution for me and I don't necessarily
do that to get that uh you know thanks.
I just do it as a principle. This often
doesn't come. So it's not like people
are grateful. Often they leave the
hospital
you let me share a little bit of this uh
um this change is just a few minutes.
This is the project I'm I've been
working on uh a lot for NASA which is
basically to develop a mental health uh
support system for the long duration
space crews. And this was kind of a
whole other topic, but just one piece of
this was teaching the astronauts how to
manage um conflict, interpersonal
conflict more effectively
for state.
Astronauts being a very different
population from who we're talking about.
We don't have any sound.
>> Oh, it's just probably turned down.
Is it turned up on your computer?
>> Um, let's just see.
>> I just checked the muse.
It's probably just turned on really.
>> Oh, I'm sorry. It just turned off. Um,
you can't go there and then I'll I'll
adjust it.
>> Okay.
>> Should we be doing something at this
point?
>> Uh, not yet.
Welcome to the virtual space station,
where you can access training and
resources to help deal with the stresses
of long duration space flights. In the
training simulator, you'll interact with
virtual crew members to learn and
practice managing some of the problems
that might come up on longduration
missions. The resources module has more
advanced training that you can do to
learn about adapting to the stresses of
living in isolation, plus interviews
with long duration flyers. It also has a
number of ebooks and audio books on
dealing with stress, plus survival
stories about polar missions and other
adventures. In the self- assessment
module, you'll find questionnaires that
can help. I'm going to
>> skip out of this. Um, this is basically
the whole the whole uh interface, but
what I'll show you here is our
simulator.
This is the training simulator. Click on
the topic you would like to learn about.
Then the coach or mentor for that topic
will take over and guide you through.
>> This is the conflict management part of
the simulator. We recommend that you do
the 10-minute briefing first. After you
complete each simulation,
>> I am greenhouse, your conflict
management coach. Here's how these
simulations work. You are flight
engineer one or F1 and your crewmate
Chuck is flight engineer 2. We'll be
giving you three choices of what to say
or do. You can roll your mouse over them
to hear how they're said, even though
some options are more likely than others
to reduce the conflict. I recommend that
you try out options you might not choose
in real life. That's because all paths
in these simulations lead to teaching
focus. You can click the backup button
anytime if you want to change your
choice and go down another pathway. You
can click on the fair fighting manual at
any time to read some tips. You'll also
find this manual in the resource modules
library. Now, as you go through the
simulation, I'll be right here coaching
you along the way. Okay, back to the
simulation.
It's 4 months into your mission with
five and a half left to go. So far, the
mission's been going pretty well. But
you're both tired having had to sleep
shift last night.
>> Hey, is your display getting squirly?
Shoot. Mine, too. Damn, I can systems
down.
That was the wrong cabling.
And when I was installing the recorder,
I disconnected the A10 cable. I mean, I
fixed it right away, but I think it
screwed up the whole system.
Hey, look. If ground calls up, don't
tell them about the cabling.
Ah, this is a tricky situation. You
believe it's important to tell the
ground what happened. At the same time,
you don't want Chuck to get in trouble.
What's your response?
>> So, here
>> they'll spend hours trying to figure
this out. We got to tell what's wrong
with telling the ground.
>> Okay, but you're putting me
>> make a choice.
>> Okay, you're putting me in a bad
position.
But thanks. You're a real friend. I read
you big time.
Yeah. Houston, this is FE2. Go ahead.
Uh, no. Negative. I have no idea.
Yeah, I know. Well, I already got the
reboot started, right?
I guess it's too early to say what the
effect is.
Roger that. I'll let you know if it
happens again. two up.
>> You're feeling very anxious having just
heard Chuck lie to the ground. You're
worried that this might backfire on you
if the ground finds out that you knew
what happened. This makes you very angry
at Chuck. How would you like to respond?
>> So, the reason I'm showing you guys this
is that this is one one approach I've
taken to to teaching how to how to
handle an interaction with somebody
through sort of a simulation. Now, this
is obviously not a game. There's no
score. There's no time limit. It's more
of an interactive movie. Um, but with
with the teaching points here, just just
like what Caesar's giving you is, you
know, we can give this to an astronaut
um and they'll read it in 5 10 minutes
and say, "Yep, got it. What's the next
thing?" That doesn't mean they actually
can use it. They remember it. They've
absorbed it. So, and that I'm not saying
that this is the way that you should do
your games, but just that this is one
approach that we've taken um
to try to get them more involved with
with the kind of material in more of a
kind of a sim simulated way. We can just
maybe do one or one or two of these.
What would you like to do here?
>> Chuck, we
>> Chuck, we need to talk about this. I'm
just to talk about it. Brown doesn't
need to know every single little detail.
All right. Plus, if we do tell them,
next thing you know, we're going to be
all over the news.
>> This was a good choice. Even though
Chuck seems exasperated, you know what's
going on in his mind. Understanding what
each other is thinking goes a long way
to solving conflict. Chuck is concerned
about the ruckus this might cause and
about negative media attention. But now
you have something to work with. What's
your next move?
>> Sure. I know you don't. You've been
doing excellent work. So far, I can see
you're really scared of them.
>> I know you don't I know you don't want
to draw a lot of attention, but what do
you think will happen if they figure it
out?
>> Yeah. Okay, you got a point. I'd be fry,
especially if it looked like I was
trying to cover it up.
You know,
this really is a team issue.
On the one hand, you seem to get chart
to come around to your perspective that
the ground really needs to know what
happened. On the other hand, he's asking
you to share the responsibility, even
though it really wasn't your fault. You
have mixed feelings. You don't want to
be blamed for a mistake you didn't make,
but you're concerned about keeping a
good relationship with Chuck. How are
you going to respond?
>> Just do one more of these and wrap up.
I'm sorry, Chuck, but this was your
mistake to take responsibility for
>> visible ground control.
That's a good idea.
>> Houston has too.
Houston, I think we found a problem. The
instructions you set up for the recorder
had some serious problems. When you
follow the recorder connect procedure,
you can end up disconnecting A10. May
need to be validated.
>> Copy that, FB2. The procedure team ran
through this in the mockup, but they can
give it another look.
In any organization,
sometimes this can help to create a bond
within the work group because everybody
has a common enemy. But even though
scapegoating the ground may keep the
crew unified for a while, this is
serious cost.
Obviously, a rift between space and
ground,
>> you kind of get the idea.
>> We we'd like to be available by email in
case you guys have any questions.
Well, I'll I'll I'll I'll send our
contact information to the fast list and
um we're probably going to spend the
rest of the week. So, uh so we're not
quite sure exactly what we're working on
yet, but you know, hopefully hopefully
article uh on web
and uh I just have a couple more admin
to deal with. Uh, I want to thank you
guys very well.
[Applause]
So, uh, let's see. On next Wednesday,
which is the Wednesday right before
Thanksgiving, um, I think a couple of
folks are probably going to be like
heading out for the
>> Okay. Yeah. So, um, there because I've
been hearing some like naffy stuff about
like what the TSA might be doing and
what people will be doing with in
response to TSA. Uh yeah,
>> getting to the air to the airport early
if you're flying out might be a good
idea. Um because if everybody decides to
refuse the uh the back scatter scans and
the body searches, then we're talking
about some of the utilities. Anyway, um
so I think what I'm going to do is
actually call up once it's passed. Um
and uh but if the people if there are
teams who are really wanting to do a
live action game and they want to sort
of get a head start on that, talk to me
directly and maybe what we can do is we
can just sort of like uh meet up with
you guys as a team and sort of come talk
uh try to get some ideas across do like
a brainstorming with with me. Um I will
still get to talking about live action
games um the following week. Uh uh I'll
schedule uh one of the classes uh for
that. So, we're not going to miss that
topic uh at all. Just going to be I just
worry that if we get to it too late and
you're making a live action game, then
you don't actually have enough material
to work with. Um let's see. So, that's
the class on Friday. And oh, and uh
finally about this assignment, if it if
if the subject matter, you know, is a
little uncomfortable for you to work
with and you know, and and and and you
can't really find something that that uh
in in this fairly large large uh top
topic that you will be comfortable
working with. You can't find a team. Uh
again, talk to me directly and you know
and and and we can work out some some
some other assignment. I can't say that
I have an assignment in my back pocket
already to uh to go and more likely than
not I'm halfassing it too.
I would much prefer uh folks to to to
work on this problem because I think
it's fascinating and it and I think it's
a pretty big problem that you can like
find some small uh small parts but if
you are I don't want to put anyone I I I
don't want to make anyone uncomfortable
do their homework basically. So just
talk to me and pick this up. Okay.
>> Thank you. Please.