[MUSIC PLAYING]
CLAUDIA URREA: Systems
thinking is a discipline
for seeing the whole,
rather than just the parts,
and for understanding how
things fit together and change
over time.
So understanding the
interconnectedness
of the work and the actions
that bring us together,
the power of collecting
efforts really
brings us hope today and brings
us together at this event.
Climate change offers
a unique opportunity
because it's the first
time in human history
that all nations face
a common problem.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- Roger main B undervolt.
- And from the crew
of Apollo 8, we
close with good night, good
luck, a Merry Christmas, and God
bless all of you, all of
you on the Good Earth.
[END PLAYBACK]
YASHASVI RAJ: This photo
is called Earth Rise
and it was taken in 1968, during
the Apollo 8 lunar mission.
And this was a really
impactful photo at the time
because it showed our
vast and powerful Earth
as actually just a small and
delicate and finite planet.
And this helped realize that
we really need to protect it.
JAYLEN BROWN: A lot of people
have a hard time seeing
that climate change is
affecting our day to day lives,
they see it as
something distant.
But the reality that climate
change is already here,
our air, our oceans, our forests
are already being compromised.
These aren't just
social media events.
We've already seen the
fires in California
to the hurricanes
in the Caribbean.
PETE BOUCHARD: And when
I think about that,
I think about climate change
and how the now is probably
the most important part
of where we are because we
can't change the past.
We're living on what
happened in the past
and in the future
it's still undecided.
We still don't know
what's going to happen.
But if we plan for the now,
if we plan for the future,
and everything that we can do
to stem the tide of emissions,
we can actually
make a difference.
But we're at the
precipice, time is short.
There's not a lot of it left.
LAELIA MAYNOR: I know
like Sophie, I've
struggled a lot with climate
anxiety and depression
and doomism.
Public officials
aren't doing anything,
the companies aren't
doing anything.
How are we ever
going to change this?
And being able to
critically reflect
on my own thought processes and
feelings have allowed me to show
up more presently in
these climate spaces,
alongside learning about
the amazing initiatives
that students and teachers and
just people across the world
have done that have deeply
changed their local ecosystems,
it's very inspiring.
[BACKGROUND CHATTER]
It gets absorbed into the
water and it stays there.
The water has a memory.
It remembers what you did.
CHRISTOPHER KNITTEL: We at
MIT have a lot of resources
available, not just to
MIT students, but to K
through 12 more generally.
And that got me really excited
about potentially developing
a high school curriculum that
was based on MIT resources
and based on MIT research.
That all came together
to what we call CATE,
so Climate Action
Through Education.
It's a interdisciplinary
high school curriculum
that's science-based,
standards-based, and modular.
And most importantly, it's free.
SOPHIE SHEN: There
are so many ways
to get involved, that could be
starting a community garden,
they can be great community
hubs, great learning spaces.
That could include advocating
to your local or your state
government.
They're super accessible
a lot of times,
and that's a really great
way to get your voice heard.
YASHASVI RAJ: And
that's where you all
come in, not just as future
scientists, but as educators
and activists,
policymakers, engineers,
and informed citizens.
Because climate action
isn't just about technology,
it's about collaboration
and community.
CLAUDIA URREA: There is an
important emotional dimension
that I want to highlight, and
it's the importance of love.
Falling in love with
knowledge, falling in love
with learning, with action, and
with the people you work with.
CHRISTOPHER KNITTEL:
So it's days
like this, a Day of
Climate that is just
a small stepping
stone in actually
solving this worldwide dilemma.
And I look at all you kids
because unfortunately,
the old guys like me are not
going to be able to do it.
But I trust that you
will be able to do it.
JAYLEN BROWN: I want
everybody to close their eyes.
Imagine that we're
all on the same team,
and the game is on the line.
We're not just
playing for ourselves,
we're playing for
the next generation.
Open your eyes.
Who is willing to do
what it takes to win?
This is the city of
champions, right?
[CHEERS, APPLAUSE]
So I think we should all
take responsibility and carry
a championship mindset
in our environment.
It starts with us, and we
can start a global movement
in the future.
Let's stand together,
united in our purpose
with unwavering commitment.
The time to act is now.
Thank you.
[CHEERS, APPLAUSE]