So now uh let's let's talk about the uh
let's talk about first the different uh
concepts uh that we have talked about in
class and then get and then in the end
I'll get to just some example of some
problems that you might face on the mid.
So the first is this that if you take a
subset
of Rn uh to say that a is bounded from
above.
This just means that there exist
m such that for all
a in a a here is less than equal to a.
This is what it means to be bounded from
about from a subset, right? And now the
there's a list of about
um this is a number uh so so m here is a
least
so m
is a least upper bound.
If
uh um if uh m is an upper bound
and any other
bound
let's call it m
uh uh is
bigger equal
to it. So this is what it means to be a
least up
and so the least up bounds. So so the
least upper bounds is this is what we
denote by super.
Okay. And similarly, similarly form
for lower bound
and uh and in
right and the real numbers have this
property that if I set this bounded from
above then it has a then there is a
least upper bound.
uh and likewise for uh assets that is
below.
Okay, so that was soup and we'll get to
this mean soup and make uh I'll just
review that a little bit later also.
Uh but that's another important thing.
Uh a sequence. So another key uh concept
in this class is sequence
and we let's begin with a sequence of
real numbers.
[Applause]
So this is a map
from the
positive integers
into
and again it denotes so the image. So if
you're looking at uh the image of some n
we typically denote this by a n or by a
n or xn or something like that
where we use the subscript
but it's just the image under this map.
So that's a sequence. So for each
positive integer you get a real number.
Then um
then for a sequence one of the first
things you are interested in is
convergence.
So if you have so if this here is a
sequence
[Applause]
that xn converts to some x here. This
here just means
for all
uh epsilon greater than zero they exist.
I I will use this symbol. I haven't used
it until now but it's so hard not to use
it. This means they exist.
It's not on
but it's a totally standard symbol. So
they exist.
uh capital n such that
if little n is bigger equal to capital n
then uh xn - x
small.
So this is what it means for a sequence
to convert
to x sequence x to convert to x and you
write like this or you can write xn and
then the limit here as n go to infinity=
both of these
are standard use.
So and then also if a seage is not
convergent
is not convergent
then
then we say
is diver.
So sequence is either convergent or it's
divergent.
Um and then you there's this
property
useful property.
[Applause]
So a lema
if x
is convergent
Then the set
this as a set this here is a bounce set.
Okay, we talk about that.
And then another thing about sequences
is that the algebraic processes
of sequences
and what are the algebraic properties
they are that if you take two sequences
a n and bn and let's say that a n
converts to a and bn convert to b then
the algebraic and c and c is just a
constant
Then you have that sort of and often
when you combine what I did there is one
and two before you combine you're
looking at a n + c * bn this here
converts to a c * b
this is the first and this when I state
it like this it actually combine two of
the one properties that we talked about
earlier
uh the second one is that a n * B n will
converge to a * b.
Third property is that if uh if a n if
these here are not equal to zero and the
limit here is not equal to zero then 1 /
a n converts to 1.
And so of course this last one
you know this one implies in particular
of course that also bn / a n converse to
b
this is just because this property here
combined with property two that will
give you this
okay so that's
the algebraic properties uh of limits
um then you have um the concept of a
subsequence.
So a subsequence.
So we are imagining that we have a
sequence and often we don't go all the
way back like this but but a sequence
again is is a map from the positive
integer into R and we know the image of
N like typically like Xn
then a subsequence of this sequence and
this is typically denoted something like
this where you have a further subscript
And this is and this is important again
that this is like equal to f of g of k
where g here and this is the really
important property that g is a map from
the positive integers into the positive
integers and the really important is
that g here is strictly increasing
And so strictly increasing guarantee you
that these numbers here is taken in the
same order as in the original sequence
but you may skip a bunch right I mean
you know you take one and then you may
skip a bunch and then you take another
one and then you may skip more but it's
in the same order and that's what
increasing this guinea
[Applause]
and and then you have
then you have this property.
So you have this theorem
that a sequence xn is converged
if and only if
or all subsequences
And one of these two was one of the two
directions for this was trivial because
if you have a um
because because if you take a sequence
then it is if you're thinking about this
map here G as being the identity
that's so that will give you a
subsequence but that really is the
original sequence, right? So the
original sequence is a subsequence of
itself. So if all subsequences are
convergent, well then in particular the
sequence itself is convergent. So one of
those two directions was trivial.
Okay. Now then we had these two theorems
and they were right by then. So you know
the like the sing the sort of the
singing mathematics is a sinks built on
each other right and hopefully like each
step is fairly trivial but you build
step by step and then you end up with
something highly non-trivial right? So
this here was was pretty trivial but
then we used it later on to prove
something
non-trivial. So this was this model from
convergence theorem
and it has two there was two versions of
this. you had a sequence xm
and and xm was increasing.
So that means that the next element is
bigger equal to the previous element. If
this here was the case, then XN is
convergent
if and only if
uh XM is is bound.
If the sequence is bound
and uh the soup
of the exam
this here is is is
the
here is the
second pro the second verse. of this is
if you have a monot. So instead of being
increasing it's now decreasing. So the
next element is smaller equal to the
previous element.
And then similarly uh the sequence uh xn
is convergent
if and only if
X is found from below
below and in this case and if it is part
from below then the limit here
is of XN.
Okay. So that was the monitor
convergence there and it has these two
versions the increasing version and the
decreasing version.
Then
another important concept
was that of the precence
and the use the the the
reason why sequence is useful even for
the real numbers right I mean you know
later on we generalize these concepts
there was obvious generalization of of
the concept of convergence but also of
that of being a cruise sequence to
metric spaces
But even for the real numbers C
sequence,
you know, you might be interested in
whether a sequence is convergent. But
sometimes it's much easier to prove that
it's a C sequence than to prove that it
actually is convergent. And so if you
don't really care about what the limit
is, then it's often uh easier to prove
that it's a co
So cushy sequence.
So you have a sequence again. We're
still in in the real numbers.
And this is a cushy sequence. It just
means that for all and now I will use
also this here. This symbol just means
for all and that's also a standard
symbol. It's a inverted a
for all epsilon greater than zero there
exist again this here the inver you know
inverted e there exist
delta there sorry there exist capital n
um such that
if little n and little m are bigger than
capital n Then those two elements are
bunched
epsilon close together.
This is what it means
for a sequence to be precise sequence
that the tail of the sequence lies very
very close together.
Then um
let me skip uh in my notes I have
something about contracting that but
actually there won't be anything about
contracting that so I'll skip that
uh
let me uh let me look at let me now next
talk about the
convergence
and Put some wires right there.
So you see
also let me just remind you that again
on the midterm so there are these five
main problems then there's a six bonus
problems but make sure that you uh if
you know it doesn't matter which one you
do so you might as well uh start like
with the ones that seems easiest
to
uh and you can see anyway say exactly
how many points each of them give. So
you can uh if you don't have you know
enough time to finish all of this you
can make sure to try to optimize.
Okay. So what is the cushy convergence
theorem? So again we are in R sorry uh
and uh and we have and so the CI
convergence is the
let's say that if XM is a C sequence
then
uh XM is converted
That's a pushy convers
and and and this trans we talk about
that. So like the concepts if you when
we in a minute review metric spaces then
convergence sequence that makes sense in
a metric space could see sequence makes
sense in a metric space
um but it's not and the statement of
this theorem makes sense in a metric
space but it's not always that it holds
it holds in on but it doesn't hold in a
general metric space. The possum
statement of that
also makes sense in a general metric
space but it doesn't hold in a general
metric space. So these are again these
are things about the real numbers.
I mean they they extend to more than the
real number but you have to for other
spaces you have to kind of prove it
individually right.
So banana bias theorem say that if xn is
a bounded sequence
then
uh xn has
a convergent subsequence.
Okay. So that's simp.
Um the next thing is the next thing I
want to review is what it means for a
function to be continuous. So continuity
is another important property. It's
closely tied together with this sequence
and we'll get to that in just a minute.
So if you take a
if you take and you have
so so
if you have a function let's say on R
but it could be defined on a subset of
R. So if you have a function like this
then we say that f here
is continuous
at x0
if for all
uh it's continuous at x0
if for all u epsilon greater zero there
exist
delta greater than zero such that
if uh x - x0
is smaller than delta then the images
smaller than epsilon
um so that what it means for a function
to be continuous and there was this
this theorem or lema
that was that tied things together. So
lema
if
uh f is continuous
at x0
and xn
converge to x0
then
then then
the images
of this sequence. So that's another
sequence convert.
So we prove this even in a metric space
but we're still not.
Okay. And so
uh right and then we had the algebraic
properties of functions and they were
very similar to this. So let me just
review them. So algebraic properties of
continuous functions.
So imagine that you have f and g
are continuous functions.
Everything is defined on r.
C here is a constant.
Well then property one that correspond
to that property one here is that this
function plus C * this function here
this here is also continuous
and then two is that if this function
here
is never equal to zero
then one over this function again is is
also continuous
and then sorry that was not that should
sorry I should not make that the second
I should make that the third property
sorry that f *
is also continuous and then the third
property would be that f is not equal to
z correspond to it then this function
here is also contin
and Again I divided it up when I did it
I divided up into four steps because I
separated this out as two steps.
Okay. And so from this one we got that
right just because then we proved that
the constant function was continuous and
the linear function the function f ofx=
to x is continuous. Once we have that
then we then we just use one and two.
>> Yeah.
>> To prove that all all uh polomials is
continuous. And then if we bring in
three then we have this with all
rational functions are continuous except
of course where the denominator vanishes
by.
Okay. So, so that was how you sort of
built uh continuous functions from non
continuous functions.
Um then we proved the extreme value and
the intermediate values theorem. We had
these two zero and they were proved. So
one way to prove it that we did last
time was to use this lemon that tie
together
um that tie together continuity and
sequences.
And so we had the extreme values there
and this just say that if you have a
function but now it's crucial
that this here is a bounded interval and
the end points are included in this. So
if you have a function like this and
this function is continuous
then the soup and the in over the set
here is achieved. So max or if you go
the max of f and min of
of f are achieved.
in particular the function is bounded.
So I just state it like this little
brief like that. So that was the extreme
value theorem. The intermediate value
theorem
it say that if you have a function
imagine that starting off here and it
ending there. So this is like the
function the intermediate value shall
say that everything in between these two
is also the image of something right. So
if let's say that f of a smaller than f
of b
then n y here is between f of a and f of
b
then there exist
x between a and b
so that f of x
is equal to one. Again the functions
we're talking about are continuous right
and they're defined on this inter
this inter
okay so that was those two themselium
right and then they used uh And then he
used how sequences and continuous
functions was tied together. The Banana
bias theorem is using something about
the real numbers are ordered and like
this will soup and if uh uh you know you
have the least upper bound property and
the greatest lower bound property,
right? So
okay now another thing. So there was so
we tal about so like some of the
highlights is like the in terms of
concepts are sequences and continuity of
functions
and then various properties that follow
from this. Then another thing is
sequence series.
So that's another key property
key concept.
So series.
So series is where you started with a
sequence.
So
serious.
So you started with so this here is a
sequence
and now you form another
sequence sn but here you sum it and it
could start wherever you want to start
it let's say start from zero you're
summing the first in this case it would
be because you're starting at zero
you're summing the first n + one
so ai this is A z +
a n is like n + one in this case, but
you don't have to start at zero. You
start at one, it would be the first n
numbers.
So you're looking at so a series is
really kind of the same thing, but you
think about it a little bit different,
but really the same thing as a sequence
where you starting with a sequence and
then you form a new sequence.
And then the the key question here is so
key question
is the serious conversion
conversion,
right? And um so that's a key question
and if it is convergent and you often
the series is often written like this
and so this is so this here will
symbolize the series and if the series
is convergent it will also symbolize the
limit. So it has two meanings. Okay.
Um but you can but even if it's not
convergent then it well but if it's not
convergent you would just write down and
you think about this as as as a series.
Now there are some series that are
particular
you know important
and and they can then be used to
determine whether or not other series.
So let me just review them. And the most
important of all is the geometric
series.
And the geometric series is the series
um
C to the N=
to Z to infinity.
This is C is just some fixed number,
real number. And you're looking at this
and this is called this is the geometric
series
and this is is convergent.
uh if
the absolute value of C is less than one
and divergent otherwise
and if it is convergent when
when C here in absolute value is less
than one then this here
is = 1us
but remember two things one is that when
you actually want to evaluate the sum
it's crucial where you starting if I
started at one then it's not anymore
equal to this but you have to subtract
the first element right that was missing
so it's really for convergence it
doesn't matter where you start but for
the limits it's it's it's
That's one thing and the other thing is
uh is like when you again we talk about
this that when you're given a series
even before there's any question the
first thing when you have a series the
first thing you look at is does this a
end convert to zero or not right if a
end does not go to zero well the series
is not going to converge there's no need
to apply any fancy test right and and
for a series it's it's always the
question is always whether it's
convergent or not.
Okay. So that's so that's a geometric
series
and then there are two other series that
we talked about and let me just you know
that not only talked about but we also
determined whether or not they were
converging and they were used then we
used them to determine whether other
series were convergent.
But but the again the most important of
all of them is the geometric series.
That's the one that we use to determine
whether power series in general was
converging or not. But there are two
other that are worth mentioning. One is
the harmonic series.
The harmonic series is the series
1 / n.
So this here is diverg.
So let's call this second
and then there is like a
closely related. Let's call it two and a
half.
That's called the alternating.
So the alternating was that the it was
like the harmonic series but the sign of
it was alternating
and this here is actually converging
and then so there's one two two and a
half and then there's three
uh three and that's uh that's the series
this series. Here we this year and this
year was converging.
The only one where we determine what the
sum was was actually the geometric
series.
Okay. So that's like some key series.
Um
then
then there are
then there's when you have a series
there was one concept that proved to be
quite useful and that's was the concept
of absolute
convergence.
of a series
and so you're looking at a series
and absolute convergence was
that this sum here
was was converging. So this here is
absolute
convergent.
If this series where you just the a
replaced by the absolute value is
convergent. Okay. So of course a non-
negative for non for a series of non-
negative numbers it's automatically if
it's convergence it's automatically
absolute convergent.
And like we talked about it a little bit
that that one of the things about an
absolute convergent is that you could
kind of reorder the value of summing
things and it wouldn't matter for the
limit.
But if it's not absolute convergent that
really matters we thought about it. We
didn't really prove anything there but I
think it was kind of clear you can do
this.
One thing where we used it was that when
we look at product of series
then the product of series was
convergent if each of them was absolute
convergence and there you saw that we
estimated some remainder term and there
was really kind of key that that we had
absolute convergence. Okay.
So anyway, so absolute convergence is an
important uh you know it's it's it's for
a series it's a it's a stronger property
than convergence. So absolute
convergence implies convergence. Maybe I
should write this as a theorem. So we
had that theorem. So absolute conversion
but it's not it's it's stronger.
general.
Okay. And now then we had some tests.
Then we had some tests and so we had uh
we talked in particular about
there was a few other tests that we
talked about but but I didn't
um I mean they're not actually going to
be on the victim uh and and some of them
we get back to this one here won't be on
the victim alternating but we talked
about how to prove the convergence right
and the important and and when we talk
about
that we discovered that this thing here
that there was a stronger statement that
if you have alternating and the a were
all non negative and these guys was
decreasing goes decreasing down to zero
then actually any alternating sequence
like that would be would be converging
anyway but but but the test we really
talked about was three test. One of them
had two parts
and then then in a minute we'll talk
about how we apply them to power series
which one. So we had some tests
to determine
whether or not the series
or not as serious
uh
is convergence.
Okay. So what are the tests? So there
are the comparison test.
Let me just first write down the test.
So the comparison test and there was two
versions. Version A and version B.
Then there was the ratio test.
And then there was the root test.
the ratio test and the root test they
are both offsprings of the geometric
series right in both of these you got
let's just talk about these first uh the
ratio test was looking at this
ratio of a n a divided by a n a n + 1 /
a n so you are implicitly assuming
that the a does not vanish not zero.
Right? So you can form this ratio and
then if this limit here as n goes to
infinity if this limit here is less than
one
then then uh the ratio test say that uh
the series was convergent.
If the ratio was bigger than one then
this ordinary element a n would not even
go to zero. Right? So this here is so
that in this case here maybe maybe I'll
write it over here.
So for the ratio test,
for the ratio test, you assume that a
none of the a
and you're looking at a n + one / n.
And if this limit here,
let's call this limit, let's assume that
the limit exists. Of course, it may not
exist, right? But if the limit existed.
So if if C here is less than one, right?
It's always not negative. These are non
negative numbers. See is is less than
one, then the series is converted.
If this C here is strictly bigger than
one, this implies that the series
is diverted.
And if the C was equal to one then it's
unclear
and so unclear which means that further
test are needed.
And so now
um
so that's the ratio test and the root
test was similar.
the root test where so you're looking at
the AM you take the so this is the root
test and again this is tested by
comparing it to the geometric series so
the root test
so you take the am
take the nth root of this
and you're looking at the limit here and
we actually looked at the name soup.
I write in the new soup. Reason why I
want the new soup is
that I want to make sure it's later on I
want to apply more generally. Okay. So I
have uh so if the loom soup here was um
was less than one is called soup. It's
called C. If if C here is less than one
then uh series is convergence.
True. If the C is bigger than one series
is divergent. This fails the most basic
test divergence.
And again uh three if C is equal to one
then it's unclear for test or leave it.
That was the that was those two tests.
The comparison tests, let's get back to
that. The comparison test had two parts
that you had suppose you had a n and bn.
The first part is this statement that if
you have two series, one based on the a
series based on the bn. If you have this
if BN
so this if if this
is converted
then it fires like this it's converted
right and this is sometimes used both
exactly like this and it's also
sometimes used where you know that this
one here is divergent and so you
conclude that this
The other part of the comparison test
was if you had the limit here if this
limit here exist and it was some L
then actually it it say that let's say L
here is not equal to Z
then then uh then um then um If
if one of them is converging the other
one is also converging. So
a
b
is converted
that a
and vice versa is actually equivalent.
So those were the three tests that we
really went through. There was a few
other tests like again this alternating
series test that sort of proved but it's
not being unmet and you will be trapped
to this later.
>> Yeah.
>> Um are there like patterns of like when
we should apply which tests?
>> Yeah. No. And I want to get to this
um I want to get to this in just a
second.
Uh
let me let me just say a couple of words
first and then let let me jump to some
of the examples of problems and then
I'll come back and I'll review a little
more. So uh but let's just talk about
power shares.
Um maybe maybe a little
whether uh just now when you were asking
the question
uh no this this just review the power
series.
So a power series was a series but it
was something that also defined a
function right and so you take so you
have a you have a u
you have
see power series
so you have a sequence a
and then you think for each x but x but
x is being fixed you form a series
and this is the series that you form
and so for each x you can ask is this
series convergent or not right this here
is called a power series
and uh and the the key point for a power
series is uh again of course whether or
not this is convergence
and this give rise to the radius of
convergence.
And so the radius of convergence was
that we defined we looked at at le
of the nth root
of a n like that.
Right? And we looked at when this thing
here
uh if this thing here is uh right so we
define this thing here
and so we get this thing here and then
we define the radius of convergence. So
the radius of conver
of convergence
this is r and the r is 1 /
This should
but there was an understanding in this.
The understanding is that if this number
here this number here you this one of
potential could be infinite. Right?
If it was infinite it meant that this
thing here was zero.
Right? If this one here is is infinity,
if this here is zero, then this here
would be infinity.
Okay, so that's so that's like a
convention in this particular case,
right? I mean, usually we don't want to
divide by zero that kind of stuff, but
this is convention in this particular
case.
And so using this radius of convergence,
we saw that if you take a power series,
if you have any power shares like this,
there have any power shares like this,
it's going to be if this here is R and
again R could be zero or it could be
infinity, right? But if this is R. So I
should write this minus
then the for x in between for x not
including the end point but in between
the series is converging right the power
series is converging and outside here
it's it's diverging
outside it's diverging here it's
converting
and and at those two points here
further test are needed right so this is
always this picture so this come back to
your question about you know which test
I mean of course you can use any test
you want but when I you know like if
you're looking at a series you can use
whatever test you want but if it was a
power series you already know that
there's some integral around here where
it's convergent and then there's a
question about the end points, right?
And so um okay, so now let's look at
let's look at some examples of this
and suppose you look at
and so
it's usually not too hard to use either
either the roof
to to use either um
the this here was based on the root test
to either use the root test or the ratio
test for power but but you can take
advantage of it sometimes slightly
easier. So let's look at two examples
here. So suppose that
that you ask to find the the radius of
convergence
for the power sh
and then let's say that this is n to the
fifth power x.
So suppose that you are this is a power
series you're given
and you want to find the radius of
convergence right you can either just
form you know do
plug it into this test right or you can
just say okay we just apply we know that
it's some interval and I just want to
see for which x does this here converge
so if I looked in this case you might
find it slightly easier to do the the
root test. So if you're looking at the n
+ one elements in this series the n
elements sorry the n elements would be
this to the fifth power think about x as
being fixed right and you're asking for
which and then you want to for given x
you want to determine whether the series
this series here is convergent right
so if you using the root test you would
look at this one here and you might find
in this case slightly easier to use the
root test.
So if you're looking at this, this thing
here is now n + 1
to the 5th power * x to the n + 1
/ n 5th power * x to the n. Right?
That's a ratio.
And so of course you can write this in
here. This is like x n + 1 * by itself
five times
divided by n * by itself five times and
then this thing here you can write as x
to the n * x
uh over x to the n.
So you see this thing here you can then
think about as n + 1 / n
to the fifth power
um and and time sorry time x right
and I can write this in here in the
usual way if you want you can write it
as 1 + 1 / n I'm dividing by n in both
denominator and denominator so you can
write it like this to the fifth power *
x.
And so now
the root test it's asking
it's asking whether this the absolute
value of this root test would be then
asking if the limit here of x n + one
sorry n + 1
if this here has a limit
and then it's asking you if that limit
is less than one if it has a limit and
the limit is less than one when the
series is converting and it's diverse
one. But in this case, this thing here
this ratio here
is 1 + 1
to the 5th power * x
that this is all non negative. So the
absolute value just go over here.
The algebraic property of the limit say
that this this one here goes to zero and
so raised to the fifth power still go to
zero right it's multiply bunch of
sequences five times together that go to
zero to one so so this here this goes to
one and so even raised to fifth power
still go to one so this here goes to to
the norm of x right and so the ratio
test would be that if x so ratio test
gives you
is that if this norm here is less than
one then this series is convergent.
If the norm here is bigger than one the
ratio is divergent
and it's unclear if the norm is equal to
one. So in other words you see that the
ratio test here gives you directly that
the radius of convergence is one. Right?
So and and of course you could apply the
root test, right?
The root test is great on this here.
It's ah it's a little bit more know I
mean you have to do a little bit more
argument. It's not very hard but it
actually in this case the root ratio
test would be easier to it would be less
to argue than in the root test.
Let's do one more example of this.
So maybe I'll just switch a little bit
to and then I'll come back and review
some more stuff. I will um I'll just
talk about a few of the problems that I
added to the end of my review notes
again. I post this with these problems.
Um and and obviously they are I mean
it's not exactly problems on the met but
Okay. Also another thing I want to say
is that uh that the the homework uh is
graded up to an including four. So I
wasn't actually aware of over the
weekend. It was supposed to be handed
back within latest a week of when you
handed it in and I just discovered it
over the weekend that it was uh some of
them were late. So, but I it's fixed uh
you know I'm I'm not the grader. There's
two ways that are grading and a greater
um but it's all fixed now. So the first
four are are you know you can review
those also for the lecture.
Okay. So the other the other series or
power series I want to look at is that
so again what is the radius
the thing about power series the nice
thing about power series is that you
know power series also test about series
right so it's like you know
So what is the radius of convergence?
And now the series it's a slightly
different series. It's this series here.
So this series.
Okay. And so now let me again I mean you
could apply the root test. The root test
is the one that sort of just give you a
answer. It always give you an answer,
but you know it you may have to work
harder to find the nth root. So, and
sometimes it's just easier to use the
ratio test. So, let's use the ratio test
again. So, a n here is n to the 5th
power x^ n / n factorial.
So if you're looking at a n + 1 / a n,
maybe I should maybe let me write over
here.
So if I'm looking at at a n + one a n
so then I have uh n + 1
to the 3 power
uh * x to the power n + 1
um
over n + 1
that is a n + one and then I have to
divide by this. But when I divide by a
fraction, it's like multiplying by
the inverse of this. So like this in
here
n
power
x to the n power like that.
And so again I can what I again I can uh
I can write this in here as um so if I
just do like I did before I would have n
+ one over n to the fifth power that's
when I take this one here and that one
together
then I have when I take those two
together I can get rid of the n here and
I just get x
and then when I look at the ratio of
these two this one here n + one
factorial you can think about that as n
+ one and then times n factorial.
So this n factorial cancel out with that
and you're left with n + one. So this is
what you get
and this one here just writing it as we
did before dividing this fraction by 1 /
n in both uh denominator and denominator
and getting this ring here
5 * x n
and now you see that if and this here I
guess it should have been absolute value
of So it's absolute value on this
like that.
This one here converts to one.
This one is just x and this converts to
x. And then this here goes to infinity.
So the ratio here goes to zero. Right?
I'm using the algebraic property of
limits. So this is converted to zero.
And so you see that it does have a
limit. So the ratio test apply because
that limit is zero for all x. It's going
to be converged for all x. So the radius
of convergence in this case
and of course on the midterm don't just
say that the radius of convergence is
infinite explain this thing here and the
more detailed the better right because
even if there's some typos you would
definitely get you should definitely get
I mean I'm not great in mid either But
you you definitely should get positive,
right? Yeah.
>> So to get R, is it always like you
divide by the limb soup? Cuz like is the
thing on the bottom board the limb soup
or just the
>> Yeah. So
So
when you take just a complete general sh
then
then um you then the radius of
convergence is by definition this this
is related to you. You asked this
question a couple of times ago that
because we started with the RA ratio
test. We did that before we did the root
test and you were noting that the in the
ratio test you always comparing an
element to the previous one, right? And
so but in and in general, right, the
series can be convergent even though the
next element is slightly larger than the
previous. If that keep happening, it's
not convergent. But it could happen a
few times and then it go really down,
right? And that's fine, right? And so
that's why like the the the the
root test, right, gives you this general
result about that is always right. It
always work. It doesn't assume that a
end not zero etc. right in any part for
any particular and and it really should
be in suk right and then it's like
defined it's also you know it's a number
that's always defined
um and it it's and again you know the
way it's stated here the way the proof
goes is it's not comparing two uh
consecutive a
um in any particular example the root
test may not be the easiest way to
argue. Often if you can for a power
sense
almost always I would say if if it
almost in a power sense it's almost
always easier to use the ratio test but
it require that power shares has some
nice property for this to apply.
>> Yeah. So the reason you know that r is
infinity for that example because you
know for all x
>> so in this example here
yeah this guy is infinity which means
that this thing here would be zero yeah
>> but you like you know it's very
>> but I didn't actually calculate you see
I didn't calculate the end booth in this
example but if I had calculated I would
actually it's not very hard to calculate
but it needs some small tricks and So
and we have yeah which we haven't talked
about
but so that's why like
let me talk about a few other things and
then I mean so again I mean you you know
I I didn't necess I don't think I can
probably review all what I what I hadn't
my review notes but let me just talk
about a few of the problems that I had
but again
so the things I Let me just quickly
mention the things I I I may or may not
get to that I have in my review notes.
So I had also
poverty you know what is le what is le
and so definitely review that also talk
about the radius convergence
um and maybe this is all and then talk a
little bit about the power series for
the exponential functions but again all
the stuff we did on the power series for
the exponential functions
And you know at this point we have
established it. This is like um it's
more like uh I mean there won't be
anything particular about I mean the
exponential function itself could be on
the uh midterm but it's not like you
would have to prove the properties of
the exponential function. This property
that it has property that the
exponential function of x + y is like
the product of that kind of stuff. It's
not on the midterm. Okay. So, I didn't
so it's not part of this review.
The other thing that I probably won't
get to because I in a minute I'll just
turn to these other problems is that
metric spaces definitely review metric
spaces. Uh it was in the last lecture.
So, you know there's a bunch of you know
like there's three properties for metric
space. The distance should be non-
negative. It should be symmetric and the
distance between two points should be
zero if and only if those point are the
same. And then the crucial the crucial
property in the metric space and that's
like the powerful property is the
triangle.
Okay. And so there was a few examples
and review those examples. I I there in
my review notes like the most important
example I would say this the French
world metric is kind of uh you know
crazy uh metric that's not one of the
important ones so I just in just the
most important ones and then there's
this with what does it mean to be
convergent in a metric space and what
does it mean to be a C sequence
and so now let's get to a couple of the
other uh problems that I suggested that
you look at
u and so
so here are two other problems
u and again you know I won't get to
there's also problems about message
bases and you should definitely look at
it but I I don't have the time
even though it's relevant for the mum uh
I just have to pick some
all of all of the problems that I I I
have four problems here. All of these
are
okay. So now uh suppose you take suppose
you take a sequence. So I have a
sequence here xn and so often a sequence
is defined recursively.
So recursive
so recursively defined
sequences.
So what does it mean? It means that
typically you have the first one is
defined to be whatever and then the next
one is defined from the previous one.
And so the one I was suggesting
looking at here is that you said this
here the first one.
Um
right and then actually let me let me
and then the next one let me just do
this one here. It's actually simpler
than what I have in my notes, but maybe
that one. But but I just want to So the
next one is defined to be xn.
Okay.
And so then uh right. So now uh the
question will be uh for what
for what
a does this
have a limit the sequence
have a limit
and so you see that in this case we only
have four minutes left so I only say few
but this is also it just you do I just
wanted you to review what it means like
for a sequence to be defined recursively
okay and so you see that in this is
right. You have you have that this thing
here. It is going down. It's actually
going down. It it even could go down by
a fraction. But now it's like if you're
looking at this thing here, if you're
looking at XN, this here is definitely
going to converge. Whatever you start
with.
So I claim that you will always get
that you will always get that xn here
converted to zero
and it's just you see that if you when
you have something recursively
it's often can pay to just write out the
few first few terms. So you have x and a
x2 is equal to uh a over uh y a is also
a right because it's the previous one. H
x2
is now uh a / 2 x4
is then uh a / 2 / 3. So this is a / 6,
right? and so on, right? And so if you
continue like this, you will see that
they get that it's like a divided by
some larger and larger number, right?
And but you have to of course write it
nicely out as a proof, right? But this
is so this is proving that. But again,
you know, this here, if you just did
what I did, that would not be enough to
get full credit, right? So definitely
write out the other thing in the last
minute here. The other thing uh
uh the other
thing here for my example here we look
suppose you take a series like this and
suppose that a yeah here was less than 1
/ n
and then the question could be is this
series
is the series because you knew this but
that's all you know is the is
convergent or divergent
or divergent,
right? And and and and then I say in the
notes here, I mean in the in the review
here, right? that if either you should
prove that for all such series it's
convergent or if that's not the case you
should give an example of a series with
this property that is divergent because
obviously if all the a was zero it would
be convergence right but it still could
be another series with a end that
property that was divergent right but in
this case it is going to be convergence.
And why is it convergent? Because that
this series here is convergence, right?
But we've already seen. So this here
would be like the simple comparison test
like the first comparison test.
Okay. So
um right. So these are just like
examples of things you should be
reviewing. Right? They are this like
these sinks here, the two sinks to the
end that like this one here like this is
super fast. So don't expect it to be
quite as fast on the m but it just give
you it just give you an idea of what you
should be doing. Okay.