Hello everyone, my name is Somaya and
welcome to a case study of using the
genomics to proteins portal, a resource
and discovery platform for investigating
genetic screening outputs to protein
sequence and structure.
Before starting the case study, a few
info that might be helpful. If the
portal is useful for your research,
please site our publication.
We have a series of tutorials that are
posted in the G2P portal's YouTube
channel. If you don't want to miss a new
case study, then please go ahead and
subscribe.
Finally, do you have feedback for us?
Want to partner with us for a specific
analysis or collaboration? Then reach
out to us via the feedback form on the
homepage of the portal. So with that
let's start today's case study which
will focus on analyzing the protein or
molecular level effect of a clinically
identified variant in KIF2A
with significance level listed as
uncertain significance in cleanvar
database which means that with the
current set of evidence the variant
cannot be classified as benign or
pathogenic
but what's the effect of this mutation
on protein. That's what we will try to
answer in this use case. A little
spoiler, we will also see that this
particular variant is annotated on a
non-anonical transcript and we will see
how you can use the genomics to proteins
portal to analyze the protein effect of
a non-anonical transcript variant by
mapping it onto the canonical protein.
All right. So let's go to the portal and
we will use resource module for this
case study.
And now we will type the gene name to
load the gene page. And here the first
tab that is open is the protein sequence
annotation with the protein feature
viewer where you have a suite of protein
sequence structural and interaction and
also functional features that you can
display at the amino acid level
and then we will go to variant to
protein sequence tab to find the target
variant of interest for this particular
tutorial.
So after you load this tab you will see
that by default we have a protein
isoform selected which is a
non-cononical protein isoform. So we
will first select the canonical protein
isoform uniro database which is marked
with this asteric here
and then we will scroll down to identify
cleanvar variant. However, the portal
will display now that all clean bar
variant for this particular gene
are annotated on a different transcript
which is not the transcript that is
associated with the canonical protein
isoform. So we will use this particular
feature offered by the portal and we
will align variant from another
transcript. So we'll click here and we
will identify this particular transcript
that ends with 18 which is this one.
This is the canonical transcript but not
matched with the canonical protein
isopform.
So we'll select this one. And now you
will see that clean var variants are
mapped onto the protein sequence. But by
default we show only the pathogenic
variants. But remember this particular
target variant of interest is um a
variant of uncertain significance. So we
will click here to bring in all the voss
and map them onto the protein. So our um
variant
was this particular uh glycine to um
arginine mutation that is located on to
uh the 478
position of the protein sequence. So we
will zoom in
And we will identify that position which
is this one. And now on the platform you
can click on this orange sphere to open
the details of this variant and also the
protein feature of the reference amino
acid
as the card information. So um in this
variant information card you can
identify this particular uh mutation
that we are currently analyzing listed
as a VUS uh along with the phenotype
information. And now let's look at the
protein feature card to understand the
protein level effect of this particular
mutation glycine to arginine. Uh so at
the amino acid level the uh impact is
substantial because the glycine and
arginine are two very different amino
acids and also uh uh according to the
structural feature um uh according to
multiple structural features um this
particular mutation is located on a
helical structure uh pretty much in the
core uh of the protein and also has a
very high confidence level per alpha
fold which demonstrate that this
particular mutation will have an effect
on structural features of the protein.
Um and additionally this mutation seems
to a mutation seems to impact the
protein protein interaction as well
according to this experimentally solved
structure 6BN. So it breaks a hydrogen
bond
um and also um this particular mutation
is located on the protein domain as
well. So because we uh understood now
the protein structure uh that uh have an
effect uh by this mutation on the
interaction site. Let's try to
investigate this protein structure and
find out where exactly this mutation uh
is on the structure. So for that we will
go to the next tab variant to protein
structure and we will click on this uh
uh experimental structure 6BN.
So after uh the page loads we will do
the similar exercise to map the
non-cononical variant uh to canonical
protein isoform first. So we'll use the
align uh variant feature and we will
bring in this particular transcript and
we will select all the vss to bring our
target variant um onto the protein uh
sequence.
So I believe this is the particular um
variant at the position 478. And now
let's look at the structure. So this
color
structure is the structure of the
protein encoded by this gene. Now to see
the mutation on this structure, what we
will do is we will uh click on this row
header on the sequence viewer and that
will map all the mutation as orange
spheres on the structure.
So now when you hover over the mutation
position on the sequence, it will
actually show that where this mutation
is on the structure. Now it highlights
it and it will also display the disease
annotations and protein consequences
from the clean bar. So now with that we
now know that this is the position of
the mutation
this particular sphere. Um now let's
also map a protein feature onto the
structure. So for that we will hit this
domain um and that will highlight the
part of the protein that is that
particular domain. But our target um
variant of interest is this particular
position. Um and by mapping it on the
structure now we can clearly see that
this particular variant is at the
protein protein interface interacting
with this particular protein and it is
on a helical structure um um and it is
very likely that it will have an impact
on uh protein structure and function. So
I hope this uh tutorial has been useful.
Um come back again for a new tutorial.
Uh thank you.