okay good
afternoon here we
are March 19 lecture
we are still in the process of studying
mixtures the one wonderful word of
mixtures and so let me just uh
briefly see where we
are you remember that we discussed
um the properties of isobaric mixing
which
are uh measurable properties that allow
us to
infer uh the chemical potentials
thanks to this uh expression
here we
[Music]
discussed the intermolecular forces
between
molecules and for example the fact that
in the gas or ideal gas
regime
molecules spend most most of their time
far away from each other in spite of
having an enormous amount of collisions
per
second during which they do get
close but the time they spend close is
small with respect
[Music]
to uh the average and
so since the properties are determined
uh by the
average the effect of when of the
intermolecular reaction
interactions uh is
relatively
negligible and that's the ideal gas for
regime we will see more about
that uh
today uh from another point of view
which which uh we will see in a
moment we introduced a first ideal
Behavior Uh model based on this idea of
uh particles not
interacting which is the ideal Gibs
Dalton mixture
model in which as you remember the idea
is that that we uh represent the the
properties of the
mixture as
equivalent to the properties of a
composite system in
which the various components are
separate they occupy the same volum they
are the same temperature and they are at
the partial
pressure according to this uh model if
we
if each of the substances
behaves as an ideal gas so obeys the
ideal gas PV equals RT
um equation of
State we found that the partial
properties add up to the pressure of the
mixture that's D dton law this
here and the partial pressures are given
by the pressure of the mixture times the
mole
fraction plus the chemical potential of
the components in the mixture of each
component is equal
to this important expression that gives
the that is the sum of the chemical
potential of the pure component at the
same temperature and pressure of the
mixture plus RT the log of a mole
fraction
we
then um proved also the amagat low
additive
volumes uh whereby an ideal gas mixture
is such that uh you can also view
it as a composite of separate uh pure
gases
each all at the same temperature
pressure but each occupying the
the uh so-called proper
volume which is given but the volume
that the they would occupy at the uh
when pure in the same amount uh at the
same temperature and
pressure then we discussed mixing
spontaneous
mixing what happens when we have
separate
gases kept separate by partitions that
are movable so they are all at the same
temperature and
pressure and without any external effect
you see the weight is at the same level
you just let them mix if you take the
partitions away and let them
mix we found that the mixing under these
conditions
yields the final temperature and the
final pressure equal to the initial
ones and the
entropy increases by the so-called uh
entropy of mixing which is given by this
term
minus the number of particles total
number of particles the gas constant and
the sum
of Y log y
so the mole fractions time the logarithm
of the mole
fractions we also noticed
that we could have done that mixing in a
better way better from the thermodynamic
point of view in other words
reversibly in a weight process and we
computed how much work we could uh oh so
that for how much weight lifting we
could get if we did that uh uh indeed
reversibly and here's the
formula and the last thing we discussed
was a
pictorial idea
of how
that extraction of thetic availability
could uh could be done if we
have uh semi- perable
membranes so here we picture first of
all the idea is that when we have a a
gas um confined in a volume by a
partition and on the other side of the
partition there is volume I mean there
is
vacuum um the pressure of
the molecules here on the Piston will
tend to push it
uh uh so as to increase uh the
volume and that will lift the weight if
properly
connected similarly the black
particles now the idea here is that in
ideal G Gibs Dalton mixture Behavior the
particles essentially even in the
mixture ignore each other they don't
they live in the entire volume even as
if the others weren't
there so for the gray particles to
expand to to here whether there is a the
black particles or not isn't really
difference
so that is the idea that we can
achieve with these semi-permeable
membranes this one
allows the black particles to go through
but not the gray so the gray will push
it to the right and pull up this weight
this other membrane is
permeable to the gray particles but not
the black so the black will push it
leftward and pull up this other
way
okay you asked uh do we have membranes
in
reality uh and yes we
do we have uh we can manufacture them we
make we make we engineer uh
materials these are some YouTube videos
that you may want to to go and watch I'm
not doing it
here and uh so you you can essentially
have a wall of uh
materials with holes and if the holes
are the proper size they can allow the
passage of some particles and prevent
the particles the the other particles to
to pass so that is the way we achieve a
semi perable uh
membrane in nature also in
biology this is very important on the uh
on the surface of
cells where you may have uh not you you
may have active and passive
transport active transport is a
different story because it requires some
energy uh for the um particles to
move but also there is uh passive
transport and the fact that membranes
can be changed
uh by the the cell uh depending on its
need so for example if the cell needs to
eat so to speak it could open little
holes so that the say oxygen comes
in uh if the cell needs to uh discharge
maybe CO2 then it needs to open a little
bigger holes so that the molecules these
molecules can go out
uh I'll have another reference about U
biological structures uh but I don't
want to talk about them because I'm not
at
all expert on
this but so the world is is full of
membranes and we will see more in in a
few
moments now there is one uh historical
topic that is maybe interesting just fun
to uh
discuss it's called the Gibs
Paradox and we have the tools to Now
understand what it means and essentially
to resolve
it the idea is this we just
uh mentioned what happens when we have
uh particles that mix so here suppose we
are just a binary mixture only two types
of particles the gray and the black and
the spontaneous
mixing occurs this
way and if you compute the entropy of
mixing this summation when you have only
two uh types of particles becomes a some
of just two terms and of course the mole
fractions when you have two particles
are not independent because one because
they might they must add up to one so
the mole fraction of the second type
must be equal to one minus the mole
fraction of the first type of
particles in the particular case in
which you have 50% of one and 50% of the
other so the more fractions are 50% or 1
half this entropy of
mixing
becomes
uh n R log of
two now if we consider for example a
case in which I
have one
particle okay if we express one particle
in terms of
moles uh that's one
over the avado Ross
number
mole because in one mole you have these
many particles
6022 * 10
23rd
okay so
NR in that case is equal to R
over the avocados number
and this is called the boltzman
constant which is one of the physical
constants so if we uh suppose
here uh we have
uh
just one particle on one side and one
particle on the other
side so the total n is
two it's it's actually two divided by
av's
number
so that entropy of mixing is uh
twice BS one constant log of
two okay
so what is the the Gibs
Paradox the Gibs Paradox runs as follows
uh
um there is a saying uh that
uh I know it in
uh in Latin NATA
non
fit
salum it means nature doesn't make
jumps and this is a I think it goes back
to Aristotle or maybe Li NS I mean
everybody every every
philosopher uh has uh touched on these
idea so what what Gibbs I think the Gibs
they call it I really don't know maybe
when we should look it up about the
history of these things is is
interesting is a chapter in itself so
I'm not an expert in that in that either
but suppose that it was Gibbs who
realized that all right suppose
I I have um I'm coloring these
particles with a d and so
suppose the amount of
uh
distance in color is measured by this
parameter Lambda so I say zero means the
particles are the same color Lambda
greater than zero it means that the
particles are different
color all right so regardless of the
color here we see that the result this
result the entropy of mixing is the same
regardless of how different the
particles
are there is no detail about what the
particles or the mass is it's just how
many they
are so the entropy of mixing is always
given by this amount and are uh log of
two
say
except and so you would you say right as
Lambda goes to zero I would
expect that to also go
uh continuously instead as you go to
zero that jumps to
zero
because
we if we think in terms of the simple
system model you remember
that uh when we have a a pure substance
putting a partition or removing it
doesn't change the properties so that's
one quick way since we have seen
uh a lot before to show that if the
particles are
identical there will be removing the
partition will not change any of the
properties including
entropy so there is no entropy of mixing
in this case if you
mix the same substance there is no
entropy of mixing as soon as they become
different there is entropy of mixing and
it is
discontinuous so that's why the
philosophers didn't like this
idea but in
fact it all has to do with the fact that
we are doing modeling of
reality
so
nature is the way we model
it so if we have a possibility to
distinguish the particles and
therefore they are different for us
then there is
mixing and if there is entropy of mixing
there is also the possibility to do
work as we've seen we can we can do this
work this U mixing uh properly and
extract some work
but if we don't have uh the possibility
to recognize to identify to distinguish
the
particles that work is impossible for us
so it has to do with the the way we
model it or if you really want to go
nature if the particles are truly
indistinguishable
in the sense quantum mechanics
distinguishable
indistinguishable fermion bosons and
that kind of
discussion
then there is no way you can distinguish
there is no way you can uh extract any
work uh if the particles are
distinguishable then it all depends
on your model namely on your kind of
tool that you are considering in your
model so so that's essentially the
resolution of the Paradox there's no
Paradox it's it's it's through like this
and the this continuity going from here
to there
is essentially embedded in uh in the our
modeling or from the Practical point of
view our ability to control the
differences in
particles because if the particles are
different but we have no ways to uh
control their differences and
therefore uh
build semi-permeable membranes
that can
select then obtaining that
work is out of our
reach
okay so that's the Gibs
Paradox and since we are at it I want to
take a little DET tour today
uh uh also on some other topics that
are important in statistics in
information Theory and also in Quantum
uh
Theory so again look at this um box with
particles different
particles and suppose you make an
experiment by having a little um
window someplace like a control volume
somewhere in that in that U uh
container where you can look if there is
a particle in there there can be only
one at a time it's a small control
volume
you you write it down in your
experimental uh uh
notebook I say oh yeah I saw a molecule
of nitrogen or I saw a molecule of
oxygen or I saw a molecule of
argon or I saw a molecule of
CO2 if that's
air this
is uh the
idea and if you are in a stable in a
stable equilibrium
State um and
therefore the probabilities
that you find that you observe one of
these molecules is
proportional to the fraction of
particles overall so it's the mole
fraction so the mole fraction which by
the way is a number like probability now
it's a number between zero and one and
it adds up to
one so the mo fraction is the
probability to get the particle of that
type
okay so there is
a a measure if so if
you if you are facing this situation
with
probabilities you are in an
uncertainty
situation you are uncertain uncertain
about
what will be the outcome of the next
observation you cannot
predict the next time that's what I will
get but you can predict because you know
the mo fractions with what frequency you
will get these results upon repeated
measurement but when you are facing uh
the next observation and uh you a big
question mark in your in your mind and
asking all right what will be the next
outcome you are in a state of
uncertainty and the the
uncertainty can be
measured by this measure of
information is called the Shannon
information entropy Shannon
1948 uh said well if I uh look at the
situation described by probabilities
like these events and I want to find uh
the most uh uh logical
uh mathematical expression or or
function of these probabilities that
expresses my state of
uncertainty he set up some postulates
some desiderata about this measurement
uh um
function of
probabilities and uh the only function
that satisfies those criteria is this
one for
example see if you are that is equal to
zero if you have certainty so if if the
probabilities are all zeros except one
event that is equal to
one so you have certainty so particles
of only one Type M fraction is
one okay uh well log of
one is
zero and X log X for those that are zero
is again zero because you remember that
this functions uh P log
P look this way between zero and one
this is the
function uh X log
X
okay so in that case of complete
certainty the information entropy is
zero or on the opposite side if all
particles have equal
probability so all the uh Mo fractions
are
equal and in that case uh the
entropy is equal to
uh
log of n of uh the number of of log of R
in this case it's it's the number of
different
particles you can work it out you
substitute each probability is one
over
R and that this summation gives a um log
of
R that's the maximum the most uncertain
situation when they're all
alike if you have instead a situation
like uh for the molecules of
air it's not
even and therefore some are more uh
frequent than others so you could get
you could guess some uh um some better
than if everything was just
50% you can also
view this is interesting also for us for
the next step in the next definition
of ideal
solution you can also view this as a
weighted
sum weight on the mole
fractions see I can view this as the
summation the mole
fraction times
minus log of
Y now this term in parenthesis we
could call it the
surprise the
surprise the surprise is a measure
uh it's high for the least probable
ones so if I get H I could say that if I
get a if I see a molecule of CO2
there and I know that there are only 500
ppms part per million so there is very
low probability so if I see that one I'm
kind of more surprised than if I see
nitrogen or an
oxygen argon also is a bit of a surprise
because argon is less than
1% so I need
to uh do 100 trials to have on average
one
argon and uh here I need the uh
2,000 trials to get one
CO2 okay so that's the
surprise now in information Theory there
is also this problem that is also
relevant for uh
measurements for example suppose that
you uh your device that finds the
particle uh and characterizes the
particle by uh the
mass so when the when the particle is in
your
window your
device uh maybe a spectrometer or
whatever it tells you okay it was a mass
a particle with this
Mass so in the end when you do a
measurement like a repeated uh
measurement procedure in the end you
will
find uh the average or the
mean
mass that shows
up and suppose that that's all that you
can measure of your
substance so all you can measure is the
average value of the
mass if that's the only information I
have about my system could I make an
educated guess of what the probability
uh distribution so therefore what the
mole fractions
are and here
comes U information Theory and again
based on Shannon information
entropy you say all
right in order to make the educated
guess I should uh
avoid any bias that is not contained in
the information I have about the system
so I should
use the information I have the measured
values but not extra
stuff so I want to make the least biased
guess and the least guy bias guess is is
obtained by saying all right what is the
probability
distribution that maximizes the shown
information
in other words it leaves me with the
highest possible uncertainty compatible
with that mean value that I I have
observed in this way if uh I have not
built in uh the probability distribution
any extra
information
uh and so mathematically this means you
have to
maximize the on
entropy subject to the constraint that
your mean value be the non or measured
value of course you also have to put the
uh auxiliary constraint that
probabilities must add up to
one and if you solve
this uh problem with the method of
lrange
multipliers I'm don't want to just go
over that today but maybe later on on WE
since we uh we we will uh will we'll
review it uh uh in any case I presume
that you have seen it somewhere else uh
so the method simply says all right if
you have a constraint maximization you
must assign to each of the constraints a
lrange multip a multiplier and under
term in the
multiplier uh then
do an unconstrained maximization of the
optimizing
function uh minus the constraints
multiplied by these
multipliers and then once you obtain the
solution of the unconstrained maximum in
terms of these multipliers you will
substitute back into the constraints and
uh get the values for the multipliers
all right that's
a quick so I don't expect you to have
learned it from from these words but in
any case if you do the job here's the
probability distribution that you
get and
uh if you
substitute this probability back into
the
constraint this one that gives you the
average
M it uh gives you a
relation between the Lambda M which is
the lrange multiplier and the mean value
so you get that the lrange multiplier
depends on that mean value of the
mass so this is the
best or at least the least biased
assignment of M fractions that you can
do upon a measurement of only the
mass we will see in a while that uh this
probability
distribution is very similar to what you
obtain uh what you have for the
description of stable equilibrium States
within statistical mechanics and quantum
theory it's called the canonical
distribution If instead of mass you put
energy and that allows or
allowed uh
researchers like uh
James it's a big
name who made uh
these very neat connections between
information Theory and statistical
mechanics or also uh if
you if you if you still go to the
library here at MIT there is a wonderful
um set of video
lectures by Professor myON
tribus back in I think the 60s or the
70s uh where he does uh the information
Theory point of view of thermodynamics
so he develops the entire thermodynamics
just by building up on uh information
Theory
concept and indeed
there is uh a ground for doing it
because the molecular view that we are
discussing here and the tools developed
by Shannon do pro do provide that
possibility so I said that I wanted to
make a little uh degression today
so here is a degression in the
degression
and
uh it has to
do with the
treatment of a
particle in a
box okay so we take a
box of uh sides L1 L2 and L3 in the
three
directions and we consider only one
particle inside this
box that's the
idea of uh of this little uh survey of
uh with some equations that are borrowed
from quantum
mechanics
uh which you may be familiar or not but
uh uh even if you are not it's okay this
is a just a quick
view that tells you how all these things
are related so it might might be
interesting um I will not ask for this
in in
the oral exam of course and actually one
day I will let you know
which are of the many things that we
cover the uh slides that uh are to be um
I me are going to be part of the exam so
that you can focus and because otherwise
it's too much I I perfectly realize all
right so uh the idea in quantum
mechanics is that um in order to uh
describe uh
molecule like that or even
simpler if you have a molecule on a
one-dimensional box that we already
mentioned
uh so suppose we have just
onedimensional
box in classical mechanics the particle
is here and it goes uh back and forth
It's Perfectly uh uh situated somewhere
at every instant of time in uh quantum
mechanics the story is different
particle cannot be is not I mean the the
idea of viewing the particle as
localized is wrong it gives you some
results that that are
wrong so the idea of quantum mechanics
is that you start from you have
to uh
find a
probability
distribution which uh can be obtained by
a function let's say
Fe
okay and this
function uh is the uh
solution of U an igen value problem
and uh for
example first of all this function can
be also written as uh the
factors so it's a product of a function
of X and the function of uh
time and the function of time uh
remember uh it's
minus uh H bar times the
energy times time
over
something it will it will come up uh
somewhere uh over M
probably not sure okay so the idea is
that this function here the one that
depends on
X is the solution of an igen value uh
problem uh
and these
functions are you can plot them as
follows as we as we know uh um actually
I think we have we have the expression
it's something like square root of
uh
um 2 over
L where L is the side so this is from
zero to
L
times s of uh some
J some maybe X
and there are some other constants here
that I now slips uh my uh
memory and it's maybe
uh maybe uh H over 2 m or something like
that or maybe also an
L uh there is also an L here
okay so the idea is that this
J is the integer
numbers so there are many possible uh
contributions each one of these for each
J corresponds to a
solution uh and to that solution
corresponds
also a uh an energy level so for example
the the low lowest energy level
corresponding to J is equal to
1 is a function like
this then you may have the second energy
level uh in
which the
function is something like
this and then J equal to uh
3 right and so
on corresponding to each of these
JS there are
energies or actually on the slide I'm
calling them uh Epsilon J
okay and these energies are
H squar over 2
m multiplied by J 2 over L
2 maybe there's a pi
here because it needs to go to to to
zero at zero and at L
so okay so that means
that if this Epsilon one is the lowest
energy
level Epsilon
2 is equal
to uh it corresponds to J equals 2 so
it's equals to j s is four times Epsilon
1 and Epsilon 3
is 3 to the 2 so it's 9 * Epsilon
1 and so on
okay so already this gives you the
energy
levels now in an in an experiment that
you do for example with uh
spectroscopy on the
particle uh you can measure the energy
of the
particle and it and you're facing a
situation like the one that we just done
with the uh the mass of the particles
that you don't know which one uh okay
here it's a similar situation you do a
measurement of energy and you don't know
which
one of the energies possible energies
you get because the particle is not the
definitely on this not always I mean
most of the times it's in a
superposition of energy levels so each
one of them has a
probability and the energy of uh of the
particle is the weighted sum of these
probabilities with with these
probabilities of these energy
levels so the state
of the particle is represented by a
probability distribution which
uh at least in the stable equilibrium
States can be viewed as the uh
probability of finding the energy levels
among these
possibilities that is for the particle
in one uh dimensional box if you have a
three dimensional box each Direction has
a it
own contribution and actually this
functions
Factor so the
three uh orthogonal translational
degrees of freedom of the
particle super superposed to in each
other so it's like uh uh having three
kind of uh of of of sub particles like
in a perfect gas that uh sort of don't
that ignore each other each each degree
of Freedom lives by itself occupies uh
its uh directional modes by itself
without interacting with the other
modes that's why this is such a simple
uh uh extension of that just multiply so
to speak or the the various uh
functions not only but
from this one from these results you can
also obtain the
probability of finding um the prob
probability
density of
finding this uh uh particle if you make
a position measurement finding it
between X X and X Plus
DX that's the PDF the probability
density function it's given by the is
s the modulus of this one or also that
one
and I think there is an I here that I am
missing because this is supposed to be
uh I is the square root of minus one
okay so that means that when I do uh the
complex conjugate of this one that be
that I becomes minus I
and so the modulus uh of V is equal to
this one cancels and you're left
with uh
this which is the modulus of uh s
squared and that is the probability
density function so if you want to know
how much is the probability in that
interval you multiply by DX
and if you want to know um the
probability to go from to be from uh say
from here to there you just do the
integral from uh whatever X say X1 to X2
to get to get the overall
distribution so these
functions are these ones that I
plotted I wish I had more space okay
let's do this
way so the
probabilities are the
square of these functions see this the
way functions can go negative but the
probability is essentially the
square so take the square of this sign
and become something like
this the square of this other uh sign
with it becomes something like
this and so
on and so on
okay when the particle is in a given
State uh it is not typically in just one
of these energy
levels it is in a probability
distribution so each one of
these um distributions in space is is
weighted by a probability distribution
so there will be a P1 it will be a P2 a
P3 and so on so you have
a weighted
sum of these probabilities with which
you can compute for
example uh the
um probability that your particles is
between X and X Plus
DX it's this area times
P1 plus this area time
P2 plus that area time P3 up to to
Infinity because you have to go up this
J goes up to
infinity and that's how you
compute the actual stable equilibrium
State probability
distribution this is already we already
mentioned the fact that when you do this
job and you can compute therefore
the uh the probability density
for every for every X you will find that
it will always go to zero uh at the
edges because at the edges no matter how
you weight it it's always zero so the
sum of zero is
zero whereas in the
center uh it you'll have some
Wiggles
especially if the
low energy levels are important as you
go upwards this becomes so uh you may
have if the quantum number goes um as it
goes higher these Wiggles become more uh
intense and then they add up and so the
one cancels the others and so the zero
you'll get only zero at the walls but
not in the middle not in the bulk
okay so these are the energy
levels here is the name for the
probabilities that we simplified
here in three dimensions you have three
labels because you have one quantum
number per
Direction and the typical
problem that you face if you do energy
measure measurements
is well how do I what's my best guess
for this probability
distribution that's the information
Theory point of
view uh the thermodynamics point of view
is all right probabilities if we accept
that probabilities represent the state
and if we accept that
entropy uh is measured by a function
like
this then we can use the maximum entropy
principle which
says for a given
energy my
system uh has
um see of have an energy and an entropy
an entropy
diagram and for a given
energy I may have many different
states but if I'm looking for the stable
equilibrium State I know that it has to
have the maximum entropy for that given
energy so that's precisely the same
problem that we've seen before maximize
entropy and provided you accept that for
fora for the entropy of the Quantum of
the quantum
particle then the mathematics of uh
maximization is the same use lrange
multipliers now see since we know
already the
answer instead of call calling the
lrange multiplier Lambda e
which
um uh
since later on WE recognize that that
Lambda is the inverse of the temperature
divided by the boltman constant we we
already call it 1 /
KT and so you find this
distribution so the
probabilities are given by e to the
minus the
energy is energy
values divided by or multiplied by the
lrange multi
mullier divided by this Q you can view
it as a normalization factor it's
essentially the summation of all these
things at the
numerator this
q a also see that since the energies the
energy I values add
up uh the exponential of sum is equal to
the product of the exponentials so these
probability distributions
factor
into separate probability distributions
for each of the directions of the
box so so you can view the problem also
just as you can solve it in One
Direction per time and then simply
multiply the results
these denominators or denominator for
the overall is called the partition
function and uh it is yes it plays the
role
of the normalization factor so that
uh uh when you sum the probabilities
they add up to
one but it also plays an interesting
interesting role because uh uh uh
essentially all you you you can extract
everything if you know this partition
function if you know this
summation by playing with it in terms of
taking some
derivatives you can get uh everything of
the distribution including the the
probabilities
themselves so if you take the the
partial derivative of the logarithm of
the partition function as written here
and take the derivative with respect to
the energy
level you get the probability and
multiply by KT and minus you get the
probability of that energy of observing
that energy
level
or you take this other derivative you
take the derivative of Q respect to
temperature because yes in a moment will
recognize that
U this
T is also this lrange
multiplier satisfies our definition of
temperature is the partial of s e with
respect to
S and so you identify it with the
temperature uh so you take the log the
partial of log Q respect respect to
t uh you get the
energy the mean energy the mean energy
is the average value of the energy it's
so it's the weighted sum of these energy
levels weighted on the probability that
represents that
state and also uh the
entropy also the entropy because the
probabilties
Factor the entropies add because the
logarithm you remember the logarithm of
the product is equal to the sum of the
logarithms so you can write the overall
entropy and split it in the entropies of
the three directions of the
box and each one of them can be obtained
as a proper derivative of
Q or if you already taken the derivative
that give the energy you can write S as
e/ t
plus bman constant time times the
logarithm of the partition
function this is somehow uh close to
the as close as you can get to the oiler
free free energy or the free energy
because in fact some people call it call
I mean you could also rewrite that as
EI minus t SI I is equal to uh KB t log
of
Q probabbly with the minus sign
yeah okay
okay
so now going
back to these
probabilities this probability
distribution is the one that
characterizes the stable equilibrium
state it characterizes this
state how about these other ones
okay
so this canonical distribution the one
maximum entropy one looks like
this here for
Simplicity I have drawn a system which
doesn't have a
uh this I value structure but it has
energy levels that are equally spaced
and there is only seven of them the
lowest one one two 3 four five six seven
okay equally
spaced we have
already uh mentioned that they that for
a system with an upper bound to the uh
energy Spectrum this is an R
here that would be
Spectrum the the ersus diagram doesn't
go up indefinitely but it bends and
returns so that's that's the
case so we have only seven energy levels
and we can uh picture these
probabilities by an instogram
histogram so this is the max maximum
entropy the canonical
distribution for example this is a zero
entropy a zero entropy state in what is
one in which you are
certain remember the the the entropy in
in terms of probabilities represents
your state of uncertainty well if I know
that every time I measure I always find
the particle in that energy level uh I
have no uncertainty the entropy is zero
and that is when uh I have zeros for
all um Poss probabilities except one
which is equal to
one a point like
here is one that has an intermediate
probability between zero and the
maximum you can
concoct uh an infinite number of
possibilities
of different probabilities probability
distributions that have the same entropy
and of course the same
energy here are the
ones
okay uh why is that
important okay when
we when we are interested in describing
non-equilibrium
States what is important is
to uh be able to understand or
model how these states or these
probability
distributions evolve towards equilibrium
because
nature F salum
but uh nature usually likes to go
towards equilibrium
and so there is a spontaneous uh
tendency so there is a natural law that
pushes a Pro system to uh even out or
redistribute the energy load you can
interpret these u in
histograms as uh the probabilities you
see is written here measure the degree
of involvement
of level of level EJ in sharing the mean
energy
load you give some energy to the
particle and the
particle has to decide where to put it
it can put it um in in translational
mode but as we've seen here if the
particle is confined the translational
modes have this kind of energy levels so
how much energy do I put in this mode
and how much in that and how much in
that if the particle also has a internal
structure uh so for example it could uh
vibrate or if it if it has a structure
so that it can
rotate can put also you get additional
modes uh rotational
modes uh and then you have electron iic
modes all right so the particle uh has
to
decide how to distribute and uh uh
distribute
evenly so if it is
unconstrained the the most even
distribution is the maximum
entropy the equilibrium one at
equilibrium it will have distributed
things so as to Max maximize the entropy
so entropy also measures the uh degree
of
sharing the highest degree of sharing is
achieved here and the natural phenomena
are in common have in common the idea
that there is a spontaneous tendency to
uh uh share uh the energy as evenly
possible as possible
uh among the uh available energy
levels
so the question about Dynamics is how do
this thing evolve in time and here I
have a slide with a
some uh animation hopefully it should
work let's
see yeah okay so for example I started
from very close to uh zero entropy and
this is a smooth transition in which uh
the particle while keeping the energy
constant redistributes the probabilities
until it eventually achieves the stable
equilibrium canonical
distribution
okay and also this one is another
example
started from an intermediate state with
two
initially uh full um energy levels and
the the other ones get
filled until in the end you get to the
same
state I rescued
these view graphs from U
work that I had
done for my PhD thesis
here
1981 to devise a an equation of motion
that would take any probability
distribution of this sort and
evolves uh it smoothly towards a stable
equilibrium
and that's developed in the subject that
um u i Now call it steepest entropy
asent but also has to do with what I
like to call the forlow of
thermodynamics because essentially this
kind of uh dynamical description of
non-e equilibrium
States is uh is is common of a large
number of theories of on
equilibrium there are some
features
uh and
uh and there are some aspects some
general aspects of this modeling
uh
ideas uh that are so uh common in spite
of the different fields in which you
find
them uh uh that you can say that perhaps
they
represent uh another law
of shouldn't say of nature but in our
law another law of uh modeling nature
correctly like the second law we have uh
described as something that uh your
model should not violate otherwise it is
a bad model okay also the forth flow
will be something that is similarly to
be uh satisfied if your model has to
provide a
compatible description of how States
evolve towards equilibrium uh in
compatible with all we know
about evidence of of physical
reality well little more because we
haven't done we haven't finished the yet
with the particle in the
Box
um let me uh take it um start again from
the partition function
Q of the onedimensional
case which is therefore this summation
of e to the uh the energy levels over KT
and here are the energy levels uh
substituted directly so you see now in
this expression what are the fixed the
parameters I mean some are physical
constants plank constant H uh bman
constant KB m is the mass of your
particle J is just the dummy variable in
this summation there are only two
parameters in this formula T which is
the temperature and L which which is the
side the size of of the box or the side
of the
box so Q is a function of two variables
that means that as we like to do when we
have functions we take the
differentials so if I take the
differential of the logarithm of this
summation logar of
q and u it takes a little while but uh
you can do it that's just uh you can
check
um it can be written this
way so of course it has a DT and a DL
because the two variables are T and
L uh so once you have done it you may
say um that the coefficient that
multiplies DT is equal to the derivative
of what you of of of the log of
Q with respect to T and so you obtain
this
relation and this other one is equal to
the derivative of uh uh log of Q with
respect to
L actually notice that if since it's DL
over L this is also you the derivative
of the log of
L so we can so we obtain that the
derivative of log of Q over uh log of L
is equal to e subi over
KT now
isab
um I don't find it in this slide but it
is is a
by if you go a couple of slides earlier
you find it and you should correct me if
I'm writing it
wrong isi should be the weighted sum on
the
probabilities of the energy
levels of the single uh
um uh
Direction so essentially
it's the uh it's the partial energy see
the the the overall
energy is equal to the sum of the
energies that the particle has in the
three
directions it's like
additive they are independent
modes independent lives that the
particle has in the three Direction okay
so here we're watching it just Just One
Direction
okay then another formula that we
had couple of slides ago is this
one the one that I also wrote uh here
for the free
energy so if I take the differential of
this
one here is what I
get again it takes a little bit of doing
because I have to substit I have to take
the differential of log of q but the
differential of log of Q we just take
it we just took it and so here it is we
substitute it there this one cancels
with one of of the minus one / t^ s that
comes from the derivative of this and so
here is what I'm left with Ds 1 / TDE
plus something
DL this is an ropy form of the
fundamental relation for the stable
equilibrium
state so this is the Gibbs relation you
like to put it in energy form you just
solve for de and here is it it's de is
minus
TDS minus something
DL now if
you if you remember
when we have a a sing a substance in the
simple system model
limit uh the Gibbs relation is that de
is TDS minus
pdv
pdv okay volume is the parameter and
pressure is the coefficient in the
differential that measures uh the the
partial of the energy with respect to
volume at constant s all right so that
prompts Us by just looking at this here
we don't have volume because the volume
there's no volume for this particle it
is only the length of the Box the size
of the box is the equivalent of the
volume so we can
Define the equivalent of a
pressure I will call it don't know what
name to to give but I will call it
directional
pressure it has dimensions of
pressure and I
say and I Define it uh as the partial
the negative of the partial of the
energy with respect to
volume but
done while changing
only the One
Direction so you see see since I have a
box now this size this
shape there are three different ways in
which I can change the
volume one is to uh keep L2 and L3 fixed
and make L1
longer and then there are the other
two okay so I'm changing the volume just
by changing
L1 that's the
pressure assigned to Direction one
how much how much the energy changes in
the stable equilibrium at fixed s fixed
L2 and L3 when I change
L1 okay so you can also rewrite it this
way and if you rewrite it this way
because the volume I mean yeah I'll let
you think about this this very
simple um all right so the partial of e
with respect to the the the logarithm of
L1 is obtained
here because from this
differential this
coefficient minus 2
e is exactly the partial of e with
respect to the logarithm d l over L is
the logarithm of
L okay so here what we find is that uh
that pressure is two e over
V that is the closest we can get for the
moment without additional assumption so
we found that
P or
Pi say
one times the
volume is that the
volume yeah is equal to 2 e
i Pi
I in a
moment if you add the information that
uh eventually we will have that e subi
is equal to
one2 of
KT and you substitute up
there you find
that Pi V equals the two cancels equals
KT K remember is the gas constant n r so
you found that Pi V equals
nrt that's the ideal gas equation of
state it requires though this step which
we didn't we don't get yet and it's not
always but but at this stage without
assumptions about uh uh how large the
temperature
is which is something that we we require
to discuss to get to this result we have
obtained essentially the equivalent the
the equation of state and of course you
have one such uh equation of State for
each
Direction you have you may have energy
in uh in the X Y and Z Direction and so
you have these directional pressures so
you have three such relations
here you also find that the since the
energy sums I mean is additive
the energy of the three directions adds
up to the overall energy of your
particle this relation between energy
and pressures so you can also be written
as the sum of these three uh
pressures times V
/2
and from the fact that the energy sums I
can
also uh take the if I take the
differential of
these so de is equal to the sum of the
DI de I but the expressions for the de I
is is here so the Gibs uh relations for
the various directions are here I can
sum them up to get the overall Gibs
relation for my particle in the Box and
so I have the equal
TDS and instead of
pdv we have three contributions one for
each
Direction so this is in general the
gives a relation for the particle in the
box and it has it requires three
pressures
now we can uh uh make an observation
that
uh the partition
function that we now recognized the the
role
uh is a
summation okay so is a
summation of various terms you can
uh think think
of a
summation
as the various terms consider them as a
the terms in a histogram and then the
summation is the is the area so this is
like the first term like from 0er to one
and from from here to two and three and
so
on and so the summation
gives you is essentially the area uh and
this is the value of the element in the
sum
okay the idea here is that you sometimes
can approximate this
summation as the integral of a
curve and that approximation is
good when the error that you make these
differences here become small
so this is the
idea it
requires that U this these things be
small uh somehow and that condition is
written here it means that this um
combination of terms must be smaller
than one this is an
dimensionless uh number which contains
temperature and the square of the side
and it has to be small if this is
small you can approximate the summation
with an integral and then this is a kind
of integral that can be done because
it's an integral from 0 to
infinity and here is the
result and this is the partition
function for One Direction if you
multiply the partition functions for the
various
directions uh so you must multiply the
three you get the partition function for
the overall particle in the
box and
uh you see here I have L uh
I it's
squared uh but actually
it's to the 1/2 so you can take it
outside
also and when you multiply the three of
them it becomes L1 * L2 * L3 which is
the
volume of the
box and so the partition function also
here is a q to the
2/3 but it's to the three halfes so you
can take the V outside so essentially
this says that the overall partition
function depends on the volume
only essentially in this limit you are
uh losing the um
effect of the details of the shape of
the Box what
counts is just the product of the three
which is the
volume uh in
fact in that limit
uh if you if you take the formulas we
have up up here for say for the energy e
subi you have to take uh the log the
partial of the logarithm with respect to
T well here is Q take the
logarithm with respect to
T it's just 12 time
KT that's the
result and
therefore and is equal in all directions
this is so-called equip
partition theorem uh
the
uh the particle has decided in this
limit to
distribute equally the energy in the
three translational
modes and each one gets a half of KT
meaning that since the energy of the
particle is the sum of the energies of
the three
directions e is equal to three halves of
KT this a structureless
particle and the so the specific heat
which is the partial of e with respect
to T is
three2 K of the bement constant
also these pressures become all uh equal
to one
another so if I take the Gibs relation
and these pies are equal to one
another uh I can write it this
way and uh so I get uh uh so these three
terms becomes
KT which is here times the sum of the L
over L this is the sum of the log of the
of the logarithms so the it's the
derivative of uh the volume over the
volume it's D of log of
v and so we have the GI
relation but now if if we take the G
relation and uh remember that what
multiplies DV is what we call
pressure here we find that therefore the
pressure of the particle in the box is
KT over V so we get PV is equal
KT which is theal gas
law we also get of course the expression
for the entropy
which is a function of temperature which
can be written as a function of
temperature and volume
only so we lost uh the information about
the need to uh know the details of the
box so that means that in that limit and
this limit uh this condition that this
is small can also be uh written this
way that the temperature if you fix the
volume it means that the temperature
must be
big enough so
that these constants divided by the
volume to the
2/3 uh so that the temperature is much
greater than this
number or you could also put it
differently if you fix the temperature
you need the volume to be big
enough the system must be diluted enough
so in these
limits
um we find the ideal gas law and we find
uh that
the box of the same
volume uh it could be very many
different shapes have uh can have the
same volume they all have the same
properties that's why
uh in most practical situations this uh
uh since this is
satisfied except when you go to very low
temperatures that's why we typically use
just the volume as
parameter because otherwise you would
say all right you said the beginning you
need to put the parameters in the
fundamental relation but then you end up
always putting only volume why well
here's the reason because for most
practical situation but not for small
systems
uh volume is all that
counts
okay so
uh just a couple of
minutes uh we are left uh I want to
introduce this idea which is going to be
our next step
remember that we talked
about the gas uh
State uh as one in which the particles
spend most of their times distant from
one another in spite of their colliding
okay
uh so in
the ideal
gas Gibbs Dalton
mixture of Ideal
gases we found that essentially the
particles live in the space without
seeing each other except when they
Collide and
uh and that results to the
fact that the entropy of mixing
is the only
effect uh that results upon mixing you
mix
gases at given uh the spontaneous
process the temperature doesn't change
the pressure doesn't
change and the only thing that changes
is the entropy is the mixing uh
now we need
to Define also an ideal behavior for
liquid phase now in liquid phase the
particles do see each other actually
they live most of the times close to one
another so close
to uh where this um um
intermolecular potential has a min
so for them that is
important
however we're going to Define an ideal
solution Behavior one in
which uh the
curves for the interaction
between uh equal
particles or different particles are all
very
similar so if they are all very
similar the particle doesn't care what
the neighbor
is okay in this
limit again when you mix
stuff the only effect you don't get any
energy of mixing or enthalpy of mixing
you don't get any change of volume of
mixing because the particle doesn't want
to change their preferred distances
which would
imply enthalpy of mixing or uh volume of
mixing which would imply uh stay
changing the
distance because essentially they
uh they like each other in the same
way uh the
only effect upon mixing is the
randomness so the entropy
mixing
okay and therefore in this model that we
Define uh we will assume that the
entropy of mixing of the single particle
is related to the
surprise uh and that is the only effect
of this ideal situation that we're going
to
Define
okay so with that we set the ground for
the next uh lecture