The following content is provided under
a Creative Common License. Your support
will help MIT Open Courseware continue
to offer high-quality educational
resources for free. To make a donation
or view additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT Open
Courseware at ocw.mmit.edu.
Um, so some of my my perspective on what
kinds of things you can do with bio
action game mechanics and kind of like
see through that.
Yeah. But it's not it's not the be all
and end all. Uh, I'm basically sharing
you my my my perspectives, but it's not
the only perspective on that. In
particular, I have very little that I I
I feel qualified to say about things
like sports. uh things where you're
talking about athletic competitions, uh
you know, faster, higher, uh stronger,
that that that sort of thing. Um but I
I'm a little bit more engaged in games
where there's role playing where you're
taking on a a persona or at least some
sort of behavior that you aren't just
normally doing in real life. Um, it's
not just about how fast you can run or
how skilled you are at hitting ball that
that that sort of thing. Um,
let's see. And and also not every single
liveaction game needs to necessarily fit
within role playing or sports. You know,
you've got things like party games. This
a this afternoon uh we'll have uh uh the
lead designer for Dance Central coming
in to to uh do a little Q&A about D uh
about Dance Central around 4:00 4:30 in
the TV lounge. You guys all welcome to
do that. And that's arguably a live
action game. It sure you got a computer.
You got a one. How How much is the is
the connect?
>> $150 something like that.
>> Something like $150
piece of equipment connected to a $250
Xbox
to a screen that's probably even more
than that.
>> You know, oh, you got all this
technology, but in the end, what's that
game about? You know, what's Rock Band
about?
>> It's about the people who are in the
living room. you know what and and and
and what that's one of the arguments
that Jesper Rio um in a different
chapter in um in casual re revolution he
argues that uh one of the big things
that's happened with gaming is this
reintroduction of the space in front of
the screen the the the uh the the living
room space has has come back into play
um you you you you haven't lost that
with board games or card games but you
know for electronic games really. It
used to be something that existed with
arcade games. You know, you got these
giant um motorcycles or uh steering
wheels and stuff like that. Um and you
still kind of had it with some really
expensive computer games like Flight
Simulators with people buying like
joysticks. And I'm I'm a big train fan.
So, I've got uh I've got a PlayStation
one train controller. It's a speed and
it's throttle and brakes. That's all it
is. That's a steering when it comes to
trains.
It's a lot of fun. Um
uh but you know, so with with arcade
games and of course you have things like
DDR, there's this whole idea that you're
going to be engaging your entire body.
Um
and and you could argue that those are
live action games. And you take the
technology out and you and what and what
you've got this whole idea of this
here's this human body and you're
playing with it and all its constraints.
It's beholdened to gravity. Uh it's uh
it can't move faster than a certain than
a certain speed. It's kind of ungamely
and it's got roughly a certain size. Um
gives you constraints that you can work
with in terms of game mechanics. One of
the things that we did last year was uh
we had a live we actually had a live
action game assignment in this class and
the constraint was you had to be able to
play the game in this room. Um and I I
was newspaper a constraint uh
>> no
>> no that was one team's decision to use
uh to use the newspaper as a constraint.
Um, but they did things like blindfold
people, you know, they like they were
playing around with the senses of the
body so that you could hear where one
where one person had unlimited
ammunition in terms of like little balls
of newspaper um and and and a bucket um
but uh but couldn't see where everybody
else was. And everybody else could move
around the room
uh on on sheets of newspaper. They had
to step on sheets of newspaper. So you
could always hear where they were
stepping and you know the the the the
person with the bucket was trying to
help the people who were starting
around. If you got hit, you had to like
go out of the out of the the magic
circle and then you know start coming
in. The whole idea is to be able to tag
the person who's actually throwing all
of these newspaper balls. They had a
little newspaper hat that you could like
grab. It was pretty awesome because you
know what do you need to play that game?
You need one set of rules, a chair, a
clean recycle bin, specifically that was
that big and a newspaper, you know. Uh
but but there were all these things in
flight about what you can do. It's like,
well, okay, your target is going to be
roughly the size of a human body and
roughly the weight of a human body. It's
going to be able to move at roughly the
same speed of human body and cannot be
you cannot have multiple targets in the
same place at once. In fact, it's
hilarious when they try because you know
you get these collisions and um uh and
because they're playing with the human
with all five of human senses usually
just sight hearing. I don't know
anyone's made a smell game but um the
you you will have uh you will have a
situation where some where the people
who were standing on the newspapers will
try to make noise near their near the
other people who are playing the game so
that uh so they will draw attention away
from themselves. Uh, sometimes it works,
sometimes it doesn't. Sometimes it leads
to hilarious uh collisions. A good time
to set up. Um, and those kinds of party
games, you know, King of the Hill, uh,
you know, uh,
um, any other Can anyone think of any
like playground type games that that are
personal favorites?
>> Lava. What's a what's you have like
playground like you know swings and all
all the things you can climb on and like
you you're playing generally on like a
rock like the little pedal like rocky
stuff and like you step on the pedal
stuff that's like the lava and you get
burnt. Um and so like you have to stay
hanging on like all the metal parts and
then usually there's someone who's like
immune to the lava trying to tag you so
that like they can walk all over the
lava but they can't go on the structure.
>> So lava monster
ever stopped just out of curiosity.
Well, someone comes the next lava
monster.
>> Yeah. Once you take then you switch
roles, keep going.
>> But the thing is like I never played
that in like playground. I always played
in like my living room. They're like
couch cushions and stuff. All I ever
did.
>> Cool.
>> That sounds really dangerous.
>> I used
wheelie chairs and push off thing. Yeah.
>> I used to have the bunk bed. So So there
was like some verticality that I could
have in my in my bedroom bedroom and
with my uh with my two brothers and but
they were both bigger than me. So I was
lost.
about that would be awesome.
>> I mean you can sort of think of you know
that on one hand these are athletic
games because they they do test your
ability to move and the control that you
have in your body which is why it's so
popular among kids who are sort of
trying to master what their bodies are
capable of. Um, but on the other hand,
um, they're also sort of games of
mimicry, going back to Kalawa, uh,
definition, because they're sort of
pretending that there's lava and they're
sort of pretending that you're a person
who cares that there's lava. Uh, you
know, or a monster that's immune to it.
Um, and
these games don't necessarily, and there
may be some rules about, okay, you've
been tagged, now we swap. Um, I've seen
games where sure I've technically been
tagged out of this game, but since this
game really has no end state, that just
means that, oh, I lost now. I'm back in
the game again. Um, it's like it's like
playing a Doom Death match, you know,
and you die and you just you're just
right back in the game again, right? Um,
>> let's see. and want to play those um I
think it's like I can't remember what's
the name of the football variant where
you just have like a scarf attached to
your
>> Oh flag football flag football yeah and
um for those people who everyone knows
what it is yeah anyone doesn't
>> I mean like
you just have a flag and instead of
>> being
instead of tackling you just grab the
flag and that's that's an abstraction
All right. And that's an abstraction of
something that you well could physically
do. You could grab this person and pull
him to the ground.
>> This touch football.
>> That's another
smaller level of abstraction because you
can really hit someone pretty damn hard
with touch with touch football. Um, but
it's an abstraction of here's this thing
that I personally physically could do,
but I'm going to introduce a level of
abstraction for I don't know safety. Uh,
that's usually the reason. Um, and so
you've got the human body and you've got
all of its all of its values and virtues
and all of its curses. You know, you've
got issues of safety. You've got uh uh
you know, you you don't want people to
hurt each other and you can and but yet
human beings and their bodies are
extremely capable of hurting each other
with no added implements at all. Even
worse when it gets to a game and there
and someone's trying to win something,
you know, and and you know, if you don't
have an explicit rule that says you
can't punch this person, but you have a
game that that's very athletic,
someone's going to try. Um, that's why
you get these sort of abstractions or uh
and you can't to pretend in that
military form like all right, I grabbed
this thing off you now, you have just
been attacked uh and now I've
effectively tackled you. You can't move
anymore. Um,
so what I'm trying to draw attention to
with these examples is that um, with
live action games, the thing that you
have to keep in mind all the time is at
what point is the person who's playing
actually the character who's playing?
It's really, really hard to tell when it
comes to live action games. If you're
playing in um in sports, it's the same
it's it's the same thing, you know. Um
name any given athlete, you know, and
and and their performance in the sport
is who they are. It's the same person.
If I'm role playing, then the person
that I'm playing is not supposed to be
the same. But there need to be a whole
bunch of rules that basically specify
that the character that I'm playing is
not actually the charact the person that
you're seeing in front of you. Um, you
know, Philip Than the player is not the
count of Monte Crystal or something like
that. One interesting exception to that
is like uh like wrestling like like like
the not like wrestling like actual like
high school wrestling but like wrestling
that's on TV like I don't remember what
it's called.
>> Oh yeah
>> cuz everybody puts on a persona like
they're never the same person that they
are. I just thought it was interesting
when you said that any sports person but
like that's one exception
>> that's true and well it's and and that
leads a lot that creates a lot of
discussion about whether is wrestling is
a spot a sport. It's athletic. Everyone
agrees that it's athletic basis artists
are athletic but you wouldn't call
consider that sport right. So um in fact
if I understand correctly wrestlers are
insured as circus performers uh because
they have the same risks and they're
sort of playing the same role as a
performance. Um but you're right that
that's that's that's one of those things
where it's a persona. Um
the really really good wrestling
networks play around with what's real
and what's not, you know. Yeah, sure.
This these two people are putting on
these ridiculous uh personalities,
you know, threatening to kill each other
over the most trivial and made up of of
circumstances um and uh and crazy
accents and costumes and everything. But
when they're bleeding, they're actually
bleeding.
that there's no denying on that and no
doubt occasionally they actually get
angry at each other and you know people
actually get get hurt and playing around
with that line is actually some of the
appeal that you get in in things like
professional professional wrestling I
guess that's what's the term the
terminology
um that we use very different from
something like mixed martial arts right
you know there's no
>> it's I don't watch mixed martial arts
>> I don't think so I'm pretty sure it's
just
But they are very associated with the
person.
>> Yeah.
>> So they are the person stage
personalities but they do have strong
personalities.
>> That's definitely a sport. I mean
they're actually fighting.
>> Yeah. I mean I mean that's I mean if you
take if you look at Muhammad Ali for
instance you know half you're extremely
athletic person but the personality had
a lot to do with it with how successful
that he was. you know, the way that he
taunt people uh you know, on TV and on
cameras before the game so that people
would get all worked up for the game
made him a star. Sure, he was athletic,
but you know, that's most part of it. Um
so where that line is and as designers,
you get to you get some control over
that through the rules that you that
that you're writing. Um, and there are a
couple of tactics that that that uh that
you can focus on, but um I want to segue
into that. That's attention. That is one
thing that's pulling your design in one
direction, which is how am I going to
figure out what the difference between
the person who's playing this game and
the character that they're playing or
the role that they're playing is going
to be. um you know in your games for
this next assignment. You know you if
you got people playing mental patience
then you've got to figure out how you're
going to draw that line. You don't you
don't you want to be kind of clear
whether it's the player who's actually
upset at you or the characters who's
actually upset at you. Um, but if you
draw that line too broadly, then you got
this situation where I'm supposed to be
angry at you, but I'm laughing all the
time because this is a ridiculous
situation and emotional pretending to be
really emotional can possibly can
usually
make a lot of people react by laughing
just to release the tension in space.
Um, in fact, that happened when uh Dion
was were playing with Cesar, right? I
mean, sure, they they were laughing.
They were trying their level best to
take it as seriously as possible. And
everybody else in the room was trying to
um to relieve that tension and sometimes
that's okay for your game. In fact,
sometimes that's great for your game and
sometimes that's detrimental. Depends on
what you're going for. Um but you have
to understand that that that is
something that's pulling all your
design, why your rule exists, why your
game mechanic exists, and why your game
mechanic is written in a certain way.
That's one of the tensions that's
pulling it in the in a certain
direction.
In reality, that's actually two
different tensions because on one sense,
you're trying to make an experience as
as immersive, as you know, feeling like
you're actually doing it as possible.
And on the other hand, you don't want to
make it so associated with who you are
and what you're actually doing that
people start to think, "Oh, wow. This
person, this this player is actually mad
at me, you know, or this player could
actually hit me at this point." Uh, you
know, whereas they say, "No, the
character could hit me, but the player
is not going to hit me, you know." Um,
so I call that um uh very simplitude. Uh
these are just words that I that I
picked up from dictionary to to describe
these things. This will be during my
master's thesis. Um,
jurisditude is basically the um when
you're trying to it's it's it's a
tension when you're designing a game
mechanic. And that tension is telling
you I want to make this experience as
immersive and as true to life as
possible. Um, and the opposite of that
is uh what I call dissociation. Um,
which is really hard to pronounce. So
sometimes I just call it separation. Um,
but how do you draw that line between
who I am and who my character is? Uh,
and I I'll give you a couple of
examples. Uh, just just just to get
these ideas down. Um,
in in a live action role playing game,
uh, actually, who doesn't know what a
live action role playing game is or
doesn't have a good a clear idea
>> how they work?
>> Okay. Um, okay. Okay. So, so some so
some so maybe a little bit of background
on how on ju just so that I I can use
the examples. Um do you know do do you
know do you folks know how a tabletop
role playing game generally works? You
know like a D and D game.
>> Not really. No.
>> Okay. All right. So start from scratch.
Imagine improv theater. Imagine you have
a environment where you have a bunch of
people who want to enact some sort of
scene together. This scene in on
theater, the scene is usually something
like five minutes, maybe half an hour.
Uh in a live action role playing game,
that's more likely an hour to 10 days to
30 days long. Uh a much longer uh period
of of time, but the but the motivation
is the same. We're in this space to
enact some sort of shared reality,
shared created reality to together. Now,
in a role playing game, that's done by,
you know, the usual additional rules,
uh, uh, and usually some sort of world
setting and some sort of character
description. And how these things are
told to you could be as simple as the
game master walks up to each person and
explains what's going on. You know, you
are all cats in an alleyway, you know,
and that and some of you are, you know,
are hungry and looking for food. you're
on top of the packing order and you kind
of make sure that you get all the food.
Here's how here's how you eat food.
Here's how you move food around. Go, you
know, that sort of thing. A GM, a game
master could could just do it at that
level. And you've got a live action role
playing game. There's usually some sort
of win condition or at least some sort
of time limit to tell you when the
game's over.
Um, when you get a little bit more
detail and when you start mixing and
matching it with thing with the
conventions of other kinds of role
playing games, computer and tabletop
role playing games, you have things like
character sheets where you're given your
information on a piece of paper or you
create your information in a piece of
paper. Um, and that information's
information is only available to you and
the game master. Um, the secret
information for intents and purposes.
Um,
and uh, and you will use different means
to convey chunks of the information to
the rest of the world. Like um, I'm
actually not female, but I'm playing a
female character, so maybe I'll wear a
badge or something that has my gender on
it, and that tells the rest of the
world, treat me like a female. Uh,
that's that's that's one example. Um, I
may actually be psychic, but the rest of
the world can't necessarily see that
except for maybe other psychic people.
So, maybe I'll have a little Greek
symbol or something. Um, not not sigh.
That would be too obvious.
Omega
um or or you know or maybe my badge is
just a different color or something. And
people who are not psychic have no idea
what it means. And people who are
playing other psychic characters now
say, "Oh, that person has a red badge.
you know, I am sensing psychic ways.
Um, and maybe then now there are game
mechanics that I can do with that
person. It's like actually all the
psychic people know each other's cell
phone numbers or something. We can talk
to each other. Uh, that's that's an
example. Um,
>> that's awesome.
>> That would be an easy way to to manage
it. Um
uh then um so so the connection with
improv theater is actually
stronger than a lot of people may
generally assume because a lot of people
think of it think of live action role
playing games and they focus on the
games part of it you know and they and
they think of it as an RPG uh in the
computer sense so you ro your character
um in the sense of I have my character
stats my character's abilities
A lot of these stats and abilities don't
necessarily need to be stuff that's
written down because again you're
dealing with a human body. So um how
strong is your character? I don't know
how strong are you? You know um how long
you know how long a sword do I have?
Well how long is that piece of foam over
there? Like that's your sword now.
>> You got to when I left the assassin
skill I played a character that's
supposed to be very very strong. I'm not
very very strong, but I had like as you
describe a little badge, the way that it
manifested itself in gameplay was that
at some point I challenged someone to an
arm wrestling duel
>> and they made sure to like looked at my
stat and saw, oh, I know what this
means. And so even though they were
about twice my size, they pretended to
lose.
>> Yeah, it was it was very entertaining.
So, so that that's the spectrum of, you
know, on one hand there are these games
where uh well the the kinds of games
that Jeremy
describes allows you to play things that
are physically very different from you
and then there are games there are some
live action role playing games
>> it's just how strong you are.
>> Yeah, it's just how strong you are. Um a
lot of those are like buffer LARs. Um
people uh will dress up in actual armor
that they've decided to make out of
leather or duct tape. Uh and you know
they will swing around swords that are
foam padded. They'll go out to a forest
somewhere in typically New England and
you know spend two two days three days
in the middle of forest you know
sleeping in in a cabin somewhere and
pretending to do fantasy adventuring.
And every once in a while there will be
GM control volunteers who will be
wearing like monster masks and people
you know that's that's that's one for
that that's that's that's on the other
spectrum but it's all this it's a
spectrum you know it's not like you know
there's there's these life um there are
bottle arps where you run around with
sticks and there are
um assassin guild type arps where your
and where most of your abilities are
governed by numbers and stats. Yeah,
kind of this spectrum. You can think of
the assassin guilt type things as being
very much inspired by what you could do
on a computer, what you could do on
tabletop LAR because on tabletop LAR,
how strong the character is has nothing
to do with how strong the player is,
right? It's what's that you
just recently found out that in New
England there are basically lots which
get done with air rifles.
>> Mhm. So
>> military
paintball people,
>> but they're not they're not paintball.
So institute people with plastic
pellets.
>> And yeah, airsoft is what they're
called. And then and so like one team
will dress up as US soldiers and the
other one's like Middle East insurgents
or something in town. Yeah. Yeah. It's
it's elaborate but it's slightly
distasteful.
>> And you can go and look at their
website. I think it's the New England
Airsoft Association or something like
that and they have like little excerpts
that have been video cam of these
>> but but the people who are
>> when there's like negotiation between
between the two sides and what have you.
They actually could tend to take on the
roles of the insurgents or the people
sometimes. So yeah, sometimes they're
just shooting each other. Other times
they're like trying to find out who in
the town is the person who's the bad
guy.
Sometimes it gets more elaborate and
it's like, you know, we're all going to
some of us are actually going to be
civilians and some of us are actually
going to be combatants and the other to
figure out who's who.
>> Um,
that one will be really really
interesting to have rules for IEDs. Uh,
because I think that will that will
that's something that I that I that that
annoys me about games that involve
Middle Eastern combatants
>> is that they don't have rules for IEDs.
And it's like that's the primary form of
combat in that space. Anyway,
um but yeah, but but actually that
that's a good point. Military military
exercises are actually a lot of them are
basically live action role playing
games. They all the way from I'm
actually running around with a gun full
of blanks or shooting pellets or
shooting a laser beam that is going to
register on some other soldiers gear uh
as as being hit.
>> We call them war games.
>> Yeah. And
Yes, that that's really um um but you
also have the other end of military
simulations where it's just a bunch of
people in a room on looking at a screen
uh or you not not even a screen a
whiteboard uh with a world map on it and
they're moving forces around you know
like a tabletop LA but those are still
considered sort of live action things
because every person in the room is
representing someone in the chain of
command that would normally be in a war
room at a like um you know I'm the
commander,
you're the lieutenant or something like
that and I'm going to say give me the
status of you know Washington DC has it
been used yet that sort of thing and you
know lieutenant says you know we have
three three three missiles coming in or
something based on some lookup um the
term for that is typically called creek
spiel especially when it's um when it's
real people playing against real people
uh like this is two or more player uh
game uh where not everyone's on the same
side. If it's on if it's just on one
side, then just the war game terminology
tends to be more a catchall. Um but when
you have two players on each side and
they're playing through these things,
how results get resolved uh uh also uh
can vary. There are obviously digital
and mathematical ways to compute. Okay,
I fired I have given an order to fire a
missile at
Singapore and and
you know and it's going to take you know
two hours for it to land and there's a
percentage that it might land and things
like that. you you you could do it you
could do it that way but traditionally
what's actually been done is that you
say this is what I'm going to do and
someone far more experienced than you
usually your instructor or one of
several instructors takes that
information and goes into another room
and talks to the people who are actually
doing the same thing with your opposing
team and they're just saying okay in
this in this event what's going to
happen and then they go back to each
team and they report, you know, your
missile missed or, you know, your troops
engag you found your opponent's troops
in this location and you lost 50% of
your troops. This sort of thing. And
that's kind of the traditional pre-
creature game. The nice thing about that
that takes advantage of the fact that
not just the players, but everybody is
live action human being because you have
flexibility. You know, you can do
ridiculous things like, you know, uh
that that programmers or game designers
may not necessarily have assumed were
possible, but happen to make sense in
the heat in the heat of that particular
game. Uh and you have real people
deciding this is what's going to happen.
So, we'll we'll make up a logical uh uh
solution. In military, that's why you
want people who are really really
experienced. um in a non-military live
action role playing game by the kind
that has played around in MIT. People
will still still do that, you know. I So
I'm in a game where
I know it's a steampunk setting and I
don't have all the equipment I need to
build this machine of death that I'm
trying that I'm supposed to be
completing, but I could take apart some
of the other machines that are in the
world. And then the game master says,
"Wait a minute. If you're going to put
rules about that or we never thought
about anyone taking a part of the abuse
quick, but it makes perfect sense in
this world. So, okay, it's going to take
you two hours and you have to be in this
room, but after that, you all the parts
you need, you know, and and that's one
of the the other side of live action
role playing is that often the people
who are controlling the game are also
live action. They're also there uh and
and and they can they can improvise
along with the players.
Um, so you have that bit of flexibility.
You're limited by how experienced those
people are. Um, people who don't tend to
be terribly experienced tend to make
rash decisions
uh that end up hurting the playability
of game. Sometimes they get lucky,
sometimes they don't. Uh uh let me see
one example
in early on when I was making live
action role playing games was I had a
game mechanic where if anybody um if if
one of the police officers you know in
in this sort of detective scenario
wanted to do a background check um they
could they could ask the game master and
some amount of time actually you'll
spend instant because a fairly modern
kind of uh system and the assumption was
that they find a computer and they will
look it up and I will give them
information
and that led to two problems was that
first of all what happens if I'm not
have physically in the same location as
a person who has the information and
it's just weird to think of a computer
with legs walking around all stuff it's
not a science fiction game um and on the
other hand it means that I needed to
have all the information about everybody
at my fingertips at all times
uh which often was not true. So someone
will come here, I need the information
about this character, you know, I'm
performing a lookup and it's like I'll
get back to you in two hours because I
do not have that information with me.
I'm going to look it up and I'll give it
to you later. Now I don't make that
mistake anymore but that was the kind of
mistake that I used to make when I was a
when I was a VGM because I hadn't really
thought about about what that will
require from me as investor. Now that's
a different tension. Um I am actually
going to take a chunk of this to sort of
figure out the tensions while I'm
discussing them. I talked about very
simplitude.
I talked about dissociation
or separation
and and what I'm talking about with that
mistake that I made is just plain old
feasibility. um some something that you
probably have already run into with the
games that you've designed,
>> but
you know, in many of the games that you
designed, feasibility could be thought
of as just playing on scope. You know,
it's like how big is this game? Uh how
long is it going to take us to put all
these bits together?
I'm looking at you.
um you know can we order these bits in
time and are they going to be delivered
in time for the class? I know multiple
teams had this problem. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Uh
one thing that the uh Okay, so here's
let me see whether I can combine some of
these ideas together. Um, one thing that
the uh that the assassin guild likes to
have are people who kind of have locked
memories. You know, they know something,
but they don't know that they know it.
>> Memory packets.
>> Yes. Little memory packets. Little
pieces of paper that they print it out
and fold it up and staple. You know,
takes you about 20 seconds to make one
of those. Um, now imagine a game that
has maybe 60 people and about and each
person maybe has five locked memories
because the GMs really love this idea.
And how long is that? 5* 60 300
>> that's only about an hour.
>> Huh?
>> Only about an hour.
>> It's only about an hour. Does it ever
actually only take an hour to actually
produce that? You You get like staple
codes and paper
towels. It's like 2 hours. Oh yeah.
>> Okay. It's it's a little less than 2
hours actually.
>> Yeah. But
>> by the end of it
>> 20 seconds
>> 20 times.
>> And then and then what happens is that
oh wow we have 300 pieces of paper all
of which are now folded and almost
indistinguishable from each other. And
we've got to figure out who gets which.
>> And this and these are the the the
concerns. You know it's like when when
you know that that's a feasibility
issue. It's like um doing something for
doing something like that for one or two
players is extremely feasible. Takes
almost no time from the game master's
point of view. Um doing like that for
your entire player base if you have a 60
person game and on a large scale you
know becomes the majority of your of
your prep time. You know s c suddenly
you're setting aside a whole day just to
deal with that and your game's only like
three days long or or something like
that. You know exactly that that level
of effort. um things to preserve the
game master's sanity, you know. Um
the MIT uh janitorial staff, the
facility staff are pretty ruthless when
it comes to picking up stuff that has
fallen on the floor. So, say that's a
really important piece of paper that
you've taped up on the wall somewhere
here in MIT. Uh and uh you know, this
information and this is the place that
your players are looking for. They've
combed all of campus and they need to
find this location. And that tape that
you used just wasn't that strong. It
fell on the piece of giant stuff just
vacuums it up, throws it away. Now, what
happens to your game? You know, can your
game even end? You know, um are you
going to just have a whole bunch of
really tired pissed players on your uh
you know, chasing you down as a game
master? Um so that the way how you
resolve this can be built into your game
mechanics. You can build things like
multiple redundancy. You know it's like
in addition to a sign that will usually
be this other thing in that same area.
If you find one and don't find the
other, it means something has dropped
off. You know, inform the game master
and the game master will go and fix it
at some point in time in the future. Um,
you could give people, if you have a
game that has no secret locations and
you're making it, I don't know, campus
wide, you could just give people a map
of all the information. Sure, you still
want stuff on the wall because, you
know, it's kind of neat to be able to
walk into a classroom like this and say,
"Oh, mortuary, that's where I am." And
then you're suddenly reminded, okay,
maybe I should be role playing for the
fact that I'm more, you know, that sort
of thing. Um but uh you know instead of
like walking through a space and you had
a map that told you that you were in
mortuary but you weren't looking in your
map so you just walked through the space
and you entreated it like classroom like
yes I am going to do my tooling in this
room. It's a bor what you doing.
Um, so it's really neat to be able to
have those things to give players
information about what's going on in the
space and to help them make believe,
help them imagine what they could
possibly do in the space, maybe even
give them clues about what they need to
be doing in order to advance their
goals. But, uh, but then you also want
to be able to have backup plans for when
those things fail. Uh, that's that's
part of feasibility. you know, you don't
want your game to break halfway just
because janitorial stack came to or the
glue, you know, the wind blew or
something and now you your your your
um
so that's that's another information
and that's not entirely unlike the
information that we've discussed in this
class uh back earlier this semester. Um
but uh with live action games,
especially live action games that don't
have any kind of turnbased thing,
they're happening in real time. You're
you're moving in real time. Um
information overload on the player
becomes something that you have to be
very careful when you're designing a
game mechanic. How much is someone is
someone expected to know at any given
time? Um, this is going to be very
applicable for any of the games that you
design for the third assignment bin. Um,
if you decide to do a live action game,
you think about here's somebody who's
moving around in a space. Maybe it's a
hospital or maybe it's a doctor's
office. Um,
and this person is trying to remember
ex uh some number of stat of statistics,
you know, about their character, how
agitated I am, how um what's what's my
current uh the the a number that
determines how many drugs I've got in me
right now, you know, that that sort of
thing. um that you've got these stats
and once you get too high then what
happens is that you've got a character
standing there trying to do all the math
in their head and not role playing. If
they're role playing anything they're
roleplaying like a mathematician or or a
deer in their legs. They you know you're
losing their immersion. You're losing
the diverse meat of the I'm supposed to
be an angry person but I'm instead I'm
standing here trying to do math about
how angry I am. um and you've got the
attention of information and person.
Um there are times where you actually
kind of want that though. Uh this there
are ways to take that to uh turn that
into to your advantage. Um
uh this the in particular when the thing
that you want people to be doing the
kind of activity you want them to be to
engage to engage in are the things that
players will generally be uncomfortable
doing with each other. Physical violence
would be a good example of that. You
know, I want to be able to hurt this
other character, but I don't want to
hurt this other player. So, what are the
things that I can do to to bridge that
gap?
>> Insult is another
>> verbally. Sure. there there are ways to
to do that but you might need rules or
at least some guidance from the GM to
say take that seriously you know because
that can very easily drift into the
realm of yeah that's just a joke you
know um
>> rockiss rock paper scissors you know
it's like that that could mechanic that
that could be a mechanic for a fist
fight for instance you know or or just a
fist do you succeed in avoiding that
>> nerf guns
>> Nerf guns things games of
>> shoot pieces of plastic dice.
>> Odds or something.
>> Odds and evens. Yeah. Okay.
>> Health tokens like football.
>> Say what?
>> Health tokens like in fact football.
>> Give me some more detail.
>> Tokens football.
>> I mean like in if someone has like a
certain number of like flags and so you
hurt them by taking one.
>> Oh, I see. So like you might have like
multiple flags for instance. Okay. Yeah,
that's an idea. Yeah, it's like a health
bar almost. Okay.
Uh
>> uh so CR ratings, dice rolling and or
sorry ratings, dice rolling and puffers.
>> Yeah. So so dice dice rolling in sort of
the general term of like things
randomizing uh numbers. In fact, rock
paper is kind of randomizing thing
almost. Um and then you have like toy
weapons, right? you know um probably not
so relevant for the V uh for the Yin
virus but you could imagine
a setting up a room full of foam things
and which you will be quite happy to
throw at each other. You know that this
cylinder of foam of pipe insulating
material is not going to hurt anyone
when you throw that. Um which makes it
more likely that I'm going to pick it up
and throw it at someone. you know, it's
like clearly it's something that was
designed for me to throw that the GMs
put there. Um, and if you want your
players to be engaging in that kind of
activity, that is technically you could
have put a real bottle there. You could
have put a real bug or or a computer or
something like that. Um, there's no
reason why you as a GM couldn't, but
they are deliberately deciding to put
something fake there to clue the player
into maybe there is something I can do
with that that I wouldn't necessarily
want to do if it was a real thing. I
wouldn't want to throw a real bottle at
somebody, but I could easily throw a
full model at somebody. Um, same thing
for uh for Nerf I mean for Nerf guns,
dart guns, this guns, you know, it's
like you put this something with a
trigger and somebody's hands going to
launch a little cheap piece of of
plastic at someone that they're itching
for a chance to use it. Uh really
um um let's see
what else. Dice are difficult. Uh the
problem with dice is you kind of need a
flat surface to roll it on and you may
not you might not have that and
>> much more frequently people do card
drawing. So you have to get
>> card of currency.
>> Still a little bit risky. It could end
up going all over the floor.
>> Another thing that I've seen people do
is um some kind of resource management
style thing where essentially you have
like set of like might cards or
something you might have three of them.
You can win a challenge by just by
giving one to the other player that
you're you're fighting with.
>> Mhm.
>> And then kind of when you run out of
them, you can't like overpower people
anymore. So
>> So it's like the amount of energy I've
got.
>> Yeah. It's like the amount of energy
you've got.
>> Yep.
>> And also if you discard them or give
them to another player, then it's kind
of the difference between
these things are just gone and the they
kind of circle circulate around.
>> There's a limited amount of resource.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So if there's the
circulation thing then you can get
whooped a few times but after being
whooped then suddenly you get a chance
to whoop back
>> then it becomes
>> well that that one's interesting um this
is the this is the biggest point that I
want to talk about which is just
competition
you know a term that you guys are
already very familiar with but you know
at what point do your game mechanics
are you designing your game mechanics
not necessarily to enhance the reality
ism or to encourage certain behaviors or
to give the player enough information
about what they're allowed to do or what
they should be doing and you're just
going into the realm of how do I make
this competitively interesting. Um, real
fights if you've taken a bunch of blows,
you do not get stronger. But from a game
point of view, well, well, if a Bruce
Banner maybe I
but you know, but from a from a
competitive point of view or at least
from a game play traditional gameplay
point of view, that sounds like a great
idea. You know, it gets you back into
the game. Uh whereas um you know,
whereas any very realistic fight
mechanic is really probably going to be
a positive feedback mechanic. you win,
you you keep winning. Um
so so you can think of these five
different things as you know
not not it's not like game balance but
these are decisions that you have to
make either as an individual designer or
as a team about what any given mechanic
in your game is trying to accomplish.
It's you is rarely mutually exclusive.
It's usually trying to hit multiple one
of these things. You don't want to fall
down on any of these things, especially
not feasibility. You know, it's like,
yes, this is the perfect game mechanic
if we had two years to be able to put
together this uh all all the things that
that we had. Um, and there are games
that have failed to run because of that
idea. Um, especially uh live action
games that have a hidden computer
component uh very rap especially if
they're designed by MIT students,
rapidly designed into a software
engineering project that never finishes.
um and the the game kind of disappears
and it's all about this damn website. Um
that won't have solved everything else.
You know, it's completely realistic
because it's a hacking mechanic. It
actually happens on a computer and the
skills scale to your ability as a
character which the computer already
knows and you don't have to remember
because so you can feel really neat and
it's competitive because it's like you
know you know what your opponents are
doing but not everything that you're
doing and it's going to take us five
years to write this code. Never game's
never going to happen. So,
so let's see. Let me think of other
examples just to sort of uh put some
ideas in your head. Um,
back to the idea of things that you
might be that players might be
uncomfortable doing with each other. Uh,
seduction is one of those things that's
if you don't have a game mechanic for
it, it never happens in the way that you
want it to. uh and that that that helps
the game. You know, if it happens, it's
happening between the players and that
causes all kinds of problems to the
game. Um so you so you come up with a
rule, come up with a game mechanic that
feels nothing like real life seduction.
We're going to play a game of blackjack
now. If we win, you're now in love with
me, you know? It's like that's not how
seduction actually works. But it
actually makes it easier for players to
say I can I can do that. I can play a
game of blackjack. There's no social
awkwardness in playing a game.
>> I mean, you can associate that with
like, hm, I I win this game, so I
slipped I slipped inside your glass a
love potion, so now you're in love with
me.
>> Yeah.
>> Something like that.
>> Yeah. I mean that that's but you see in
that particular case you're describing
uh
you're describing an action that people
might be more actually willing to do uh
through some sort of simple mechanic
like okay instead of love potion we're
going to mechanic that with maple syrup
or something you know we're going to
actually give you a vial and if and if
you drink something in the game that
tastes like maple syrup talk to a GM
because you probably just to drank some
some magical potion. Um, but if you're
going to if if if the goal is all right,
you're playing in a film no more game
and you're supposed to ex you're
supposed to be engaging in constant
witty banter lead anyway.
A lot of people have a lot of difficulty
with with with with that. Sometimes they
sometimes it works. I I I've made it
work in some games. uh but uh it makes
it a lot easier if the success or
failure in that is not going to be
bottlenecked by whether the players feel
comfortable doing it, you know. So
creating a game mechanic that actually
feels a little bit less than what what
activity you're trying to to to
represent uh may make it easier for
people to engage in in the activity. The
same thing goes in combat. Playing rock
paper scissors feels nothing like an
actual fight. But people will be much
more willing to play rock paper scissors
with each other than to punch each
other. So, you know, come up with that
rule. You know, give them a little
plastic gun, give them something to make
it easier, and they'll be willing to
engage in that activity more often.
Uh, violence will probably be the thing
that comes up a lot in the next segment.
Um,
so
let me see what else we can get into.
Um, how many of folks here have played
some variant of Mafia or Werewolf or
Okay.
Um, who's who's played Mafia in
particular? Okay. Who's played Werewolf?
Okay.
Um, so, um, those are live action games,
too. And those are live action games
that specifically don't try to draw too
sharp a division between who you are and
who your player is.
>> You're you're given a role that's, you
know, that that that's a card that
basically says whether you're mafia or
whether you're you're you're a villager.
I think those are
>> civilian,
>> right? And the whole idea is that
everybody who's that that's a character
sheet that tells you that gives you
private secret information about the
role that you're supposed to play. But
that's in my opinion those these
particular games and we're going to play
uh some variants of them. Um they are
there what what you are told by the
cards is only what you're allowed to do.
What actually gives you the role is what
you decide to do. It's what it's like
I'm playing mafia and I'm going to say
Patrick gets you know you know and other
people in in in a room agree with me and
you know Patrick's character gets taken
out of the game. That decision is the
decision that actually made me and
that's and that decision is the decision
that other people are trying to catch
cuz that's because that's why you know
that the the they're trying to find a
person who's actually responsible for
various acts when everybody's eyes are
closed. Um the general model for these
games is you know there are cycles there
for werewolf is a day and night cycle
and for mafia it's also day and night
but the idea is that um during the night
everybody who's not mafia gets to have
their eyes open uh everybody who is
mafia sorry everybody who's not m mafia
keeps their eyes closed everybody who is
mafia keeps their eyes open and the
people who are mafia can communicate
through some GN mediator some game
master mediated way to specify a player
to be taken out of the game. It's point.
It's usually a point. Yeah.
>> Uh I I I I've seen things with links
with with because as the GM moves around
sometimes that gives you clues because
you can hear even with your eyes closed
you can hear where the GM is. Um but uh
the and and then and then you then
that's like the night cycle and then
during the day cycle everyone opens
their eyes and then the whoever's been
taken out of the game you know is is is
informs you and everyone knows and then
everyone starts discussing and accusing
each other of being responsible for it.
And the whole point of the game is uh
for the villagers to identify who all
the mafia is before everyone in the
village does. Um
so um
you know that's a it's a live action
game that doesn't have a lot of action I
would say. You know this is one action
which is closing well there closing your
eyes opening your eyes and it's pointing
um uh there are variants where uh
sometimes there is a this godfather
there's a I've seen websites with whole
list of different roles that are just
ridiculous like this gravekeeper
necromancer or something like
>> yeah it's like there's like people can
bring characters back back from the dead
there people who can basically do a
background check you know I think that
angels I've heard of angels in cops
um who have, you know, and then you you
go from two cycles to three cycles per
round, you know, four cycles per round
where different people have eyes open
and you get different bits of
information about what what's in the
what what the world stated is like, you
know, the fact that killing somebody is
pointing at them, you know, that's
that's a dissociation mechanic, right?
It's not that you're actually being
asked to engage in physical combat with
with with them even though the fiction
of the game is that you're assassinating
this person in a build tonight. Um
but uh the very similitude I would
imagine and and compet and competition
largely comes down in the discussion
phase. You know, they're trying to
put players in an environment where you
got a paranoid group of villagers, a
paranoid town, and they're all mutually
exclusing uh uh uh mutually ex accusing
each other. And um both the the act of
trying to not be accused and trying to
deduce who is the right person to accuse
um is a compelling competitive
experience. That that's what all these
games are really about. Um so all the
emphasis is all all the time of the game
frankly is devoted to that phase of when
everyone sits down and discusses with
each other who could be the mafia in
this in this environment. You want to um
walk us through one of the the the
variants maybe?
>> Yeah. Do you want to like actually play
it or just describe it?
>> Uh if it we have one, two, three, four,
five, six, seven, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13,
14.
>> We could have two groups or one big
group. One big group will rest. Yeah,
take a while. Yeah,
>> let's let's do two two groups, but how
many different rule variants do we
>> Well, I I only found one I thought was
really interesting. Although we can
certainly like even the Wikipedia page
has a million variants. We
>> could the one I normally would play
would be the one where there's there's
mafia and there's cops. Maybe there
might be a medic, but
>> inspector angel and prostitute. Oh, I
was
>> Where's the pro?
>> If you sleep with the mafia, they don't
tell anybody. If you sleep with
inspector, they get incorrect
information. If you sleep with the
nurse, they don't heal.
That's just the most interesting
prostitute rules that I've heard so far.
This this is why it's very important to
make sure that you know what rules that
you're playing with before the game
starts.
>> Um so so walk us through the rules and
then what we'll do is we'll break this
into two groups. Uh and we'll have two
groups play separately and uh
uh that's probably the end of the class
activity.
>> Yeah. Well, so I had I had found a
variant today called thing, which is
based on the John Carpenter movie, which
it seems interesting because it takes
out one of the roles. The idea is um one
person is the shape-shifting thing and
at night they infect someone else and
that person becomes a thing as well. So
they're not knocked outright.
And then during the day, the group votes
and decides on one person to test. And
if they test a thing, that person is
killed and they get to test another one.
>> And the idea is the things are trying to
outnumber the people,
>> which to me sounds interesting because
it takes away that kind of inspector
role.
>> Do you do you know who gets thing in the
middle of the night or like just
>> So I was I was thinking about this. What
you would need is like for the person
who's the thing to kind of indicate to
the moderator and then maybe the
moderator could tap them or something
and just
>> Okay. So, if you're a thing, you know,
you're a thing.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. The things are spreading as
opposed to just
>> then if there's two things, do they both
agree on another
>> presumably the only So, this is really
interesting because apparently it's
played at like um this conference for
science fiction writers.
>> So, there's little snippets of it on the
web about
um the rules from like different blogs
and stuff and it sounds interesting but
of course the problem is how do you
Google for mafia thing
>> but it sound interesting to me and then
it seems like there's
>> probably the thing mafia
>> to try and like trust me I spent a while
>> so it might be fun actually to have two
groups figure out how to play that game
just from the description that you just
given I mean I think if we split this
path to two there's going to be enough
people who traditional mafia to know how
that works and uh and then we'll just
reconvene at the end of it to see
whether what each version people came up
with uh what what were the similarities
and what were the differences. Um again
that's the flexibility of doing a live
action game where the people who
actually coming up with the rules are
actually in the rule the same rule as
the players or or the players
themselves. You get to make stuff up on
on the fly as long as everyone agrees.
Um
so let's give that a shot. Um while
while uh uh Jason is sorting out the
cards, any questions about the stuff
that we Yeah.
So
the two biggest challenges that I come
across in coming up with like good
mechanics
have to do with
social challenges and and like
intellectual skill.
>> So um let's go with intellectual. So,
it's easy to play a character that's
stupid than you. It's really hard to
play a character that's smarter than
you.
>> And it's and in particular, it's really
hard to play a character that's smarter
than you if you don't have a GM around
all the time to tell you
>> stuff. Yeah.
>> So, I don't know if you have any ideas
about how to deal with that. No, the
other one is um arbitrating social
social conflicts. Like this is this is
hard in any role playing game. Mhm.
>> Um because it feels like if you want to
be able to persuade a character of
something, you just want to persuade
them because you're role playing, right?
>> But you're supposed to be playing a
character who is more persuasive than
you.
>> Um but it feels really cheap.
>> Mhm.
>> Um if you can just sort of
>> you believe me,
>> you believe.
>> This also ties in with a with another
issue which frequently pops up in in LS
and role playing games in general, which
is like use of metagate knowledge. Mhm.
>> So frequently if you've been persuaded
to do something, then you come across
players who know using their metag game
knowledge that they don't want to do the
thing that they've been mechanically
forced to do.
>> So they try and find loopholes
constantly.
>> Um I don't know if you can really force
people to abandon their navigating
knowledge mechanically,
>> but uh I don't know.
if you have any behavioral
>> I I I I have some examples on how the
Assassin's Guild in particular has dealt
with that. Um and um and in some ways
it's cheating because they they decide
in some in some we're not going to try
to do some of those things. Um in
particular, let's take persuasion for
one of those things. Um the I the
problem with persuasion is that whatever
mechanic you come to use other than what
you see is what you get. you know, it's
like, well, if you manage to persuade
someone to do it, then I'll get
persuaded. Um, any other mechanic that
you come up with has runs that risk of
the wait a minute, this is not what I
really really want want to do. So, um,
the assassin skill has replaced that
with brainwashing, which is the whole
idea of you are not being persuaded, you
are being forcibly your goals are being
forcibly changed, but now you have other
goals and that's the big difference. um
uh you now have your old goals are no
longer your win conditions. Your new
goals are now your win conditions and
you can still win the game by obeying
your new goals. So, um
>> that's cool.
>> Yeah, that's that's the brainwashing
mechanics,
>> right? It kind of aligns the interests
of the player with the interests of the
character. Yeah, it's like you want to
you you you want to go with your new
goals now because uh and then um how
this came up typically uh in the
Assassin's Guild, the Assassin's Guild
actually grew out from Circle of Death
games, which is kind of like getting to
know you. I've got a name of somebody
and I need to shoot them with this water
gun. Uh who's this person again? I don't
know. I'm a freshman. I haven't met
everybody on campus. I'm going to figure
out who this person is. That's where
those games came uh uh came from. The
assassin skill kind of grew out from
that. Then they became teams. Um, and
brainwashing was basically the game the
set of game mechanics that were used for
recruiting people into your team. You
know, it's like, all right, everyone's
got one target, but there are a few
people out there whose job is destroy
everybody on this opposing faction, but
there's only one person in that opposing
faction right now. There's only one of
me, but I have this brainwashing
mechanic that recruits more and more
people. So what you thought was one uh
I'm just against another individual
becomes a my group is against that
group. Um and it comes it feels pretty
awesome actually because what it
actually feels it's it's a weird game
mechanic way of making your character
have some sort of development in the
game because if you think about a role
playing game character development means
your goals now change somehow. But it's
really really difficult for players to
give players a a means of doing that
themselves. Brainwashing was one of the
few ways that seems to actually have
worked as I'm actively going to knock
out this character, put this blicky
helmet on them for 5 seconds, and if
nobody catches me in this process, I
give them new goals and the person who's
reading it, dude, this is way more
exciting than anything I was doing
earlier. You know, um and um you also
avoid the metag game problem of loyalty,
right? It's like, "Yeah, I've got this
information from this other group, but
I've been brainwashed. I don't want to
tell you." It's like, "No, if you want
to tell me now, because it's actually
going to help you win." Um, but
metagaming um in the in live action role
playing games, all kinds of live action
games is a big thing is that you know
things about the player that or you know
things about the games that they not
really supposed to know. You know, if a
person is supposed to be able to
teleport from one end of campus to the
other end of campus, unfort the
character may be able to do that, the
damn player is going to walk all the way
in between. Uh, and you happen to run a
player halfway. I now know that that
player is probably on this side of
campus. Uh, even though they your
character really had no idea on how to
deal with that. That's just one of those
like um there are game mechanic designed
there are ways to design game mechanics
to sort of avoid those situations but in
many many live action role playing there
is a there is a honor system that really
has to kick in. The nice thing about it
is that if everyone decides to go by the
honor system and agrees that that this
honor system is necessary for the world
to be reinforced um it actually helps
reinforce that mutual
illusion that this world is real. you
know by by by by saying I know that I'm
not supposed to know this thing but I am
going to play this game as hard as I can
in uh in a way that does not take
advantage of that information actually
reinforces the world for everybody else
it's the same thing for improv theater
you know it's like um anyone here
involved in improv improv comedy ro yeah
so you know yes and sure so you know
what what's what's what's the basic
concept behind that Um, yes. And is an
idea where if you give someone an offer,
they'll take your offer. Uh, so if I
say, "Man, we're all out of tomatoes."
Someone will say, "Yes, and the big
tomato cookoff is tomorrow," or
something like this. You cannot
contradict what was said.
>> Yeah. Not only do you not contradict,
you all you always add information.
Every line, at least in the beginning of
the scene, you should be adding
information to the scene. And then after
a few lines, you have very very
elaborate setup that's kind of
ridiculous.
>> Yeah.
>> But mutually shared.
>> Exactly.
>> So, so in that same that same situation
of like metagaming is one of those
things that's actively working to
destroy the reality of your world and as
all of your if all your players agree to
try the damn hardest to not let it
interfere with the world. that actually
strengthens uh the illusion um in a way
that it strengthens the scene for for
improv theater.
Um hold on just just one second. There
was the other concern that you had
before the persuasion issue which was
characters who
in particular this comes up a lot in
superhero type situations what have you
where you have somebody who's either a
super genius or
>> so abilities that are just much better
than you
>> and like how to do mechanic that
[Music]
>> the best way that you can do that is to
the right person. But uh what I've
generally found is is that old role
playing game chestnut of separating
intelligence from wisdom makes it a
little bit easier. You know, there's
intelligence which is your ability to
think on the feet. It is wisdom which is
how much you know about the world. Um
and if you are as if you in as a game
master designing a game can figure out
when I say someone's really smart, what
do I mean? Intelligence or wisdom? It
helps you a little bit on thinking what
how I can use game mechanics or gamew
writing to uh to fix that problem. So if
it's intelligence, it's just like um I
have the ability to do stuff that other
people can't do because I am so smart
and you can literally just give them
abilities to act on things that other
people do not have that people just
don't have. I am able to build a
telephone out of this co because I'm the
freaking professor of pilot, you know.
uh quite smart, you know, it's like
doesn't mean that I act have to act
terribly smart if I'm capable of doing
things that other people can't because I
have I've been told specifically I have
these abilities. But that's like the
intelligence side of things. The wisdom
side of things is a little bit harder
which is basically you dump you dump a
whole bunch of information on somebody
and you hope that they are capable of
making the associations between what's
happening in game and what they read in.
That's a lot harder. Um it's it is a
problem but uh but I find that by
separating those two it makes it makes
it a slightly easier problem.
>> Uh Patrick um
>> yeah this is a bit of a notice question.
Uh are LARs usually played in real time?
>> Typically um they have rules about when
to hit the pause button. Basically uh in
MIT those are usually enacted when
safety becomes an issue. um people are
running too fast. Uh somebody just fell
down and you want to be able to stop
everyone from running, you know, and so
they so they shout halt. Um but
typically they have they're happening in
real time because it's really hard to do
turnbased stuff that doesn't quickly
feel like a board game.
>> I mean like when you uh when you say
someone would want to do like a
background check and you say I don't
know come back in two hours, but you
literally was like two hours. So yeah,
it's it's it's like often that that
literally means just two hours. And and
and that's an interesting thing of the
it's real time, but it's kind of a time
delay at the same time. And so so you as
a as a game master, you can build in
game mechanics that take advantage of
real-time delays to be able to give you
give you as a game master some time to
breathe. Uh typically they're happening
in real time. Uh, I wrote a game where
no where the clock stopped somewhere
between midnight and 8:00 a.m. like like
the like the game world literally froze.
Well, not literally figuratively froze
at 12
and um and and 1 minute after 8, the
clock will practically uh in game terms
have moved one one one minute even
though there were eight in the meeting
hours in three so that people could go
and take a break. Um,
so which will be great for like an army
of darkness type type of scenario,
right? Because those three people I
don't know how familiar people are with
the dark time, but those three films are
supposed to all happen like within 48
hours.
>> Um, so Andrew and I just are moving
across.
>> So I guess two good things. One is in
terms of wisdom, could you possibly have
little note cards start flipped over
everywhere and then the wisdom person or
person with high wisdom could read about
like information in there?
>> You could you you you could certainly
have you know take advantage of oh you
know if you have piece of paper tape on
the wall just put them on the back right
you know it's like some people can are
given the ability to read the back of
the paper some people aren't uh which
will be a little bit easier than trying
to keep it all in your head at once. Um,
you can also give very limited wisdom
like the whole like the psychic example,
right? You know, I I am sensitive in
some way. I can tell when certain things
are cursed uh by giving them clues on
printed pieces of paper that nobody else
knows how to interpret. You know, like I
see this there is a there is a number
associated with each one of these rooms.
If that number happens to be even, this
is not a place that that any sane person
will want to be, you know, and there are
people who have the wisdom to tell that
and there are some people who don't. Um,
so that that's another way that you can
put little environmental clues. uh
the there are in particularly um in MIT
the sort of like hiding clues in plain
sight uh and every single way that you
can possibly do that uh is uh is really
exploited. So the numbers for instance I
I've seen games where where everyone has
like five digits on their badge and
every single one of those digits means
something if you happen to be the you
happen to have the ability to interpret
that but each one of those digits means
something different. Um, so that's an
example.
>> And just really quickly, in terms of
space, how much space do like Assassin's
Gild?
>> Assassin Guilds. MIT Assassin's Guild
has the advantage of the MIT campus. So
it it can go anywhere from uh main
campus uh you know by Mass F and A
Street to all of freaking campus. Uh but
players hear that. Players walking all
the way across campus. it kills their
feet. Uh so um often it just turns out
to be the few rooms that they could res
could get room reservations for MIT
campus activities complex and the sort
of general vicinity around there. Um
outdoors is really not used much because
MIT Assassin's C loves shooting little
plastic things at each other and with
the wind blows that just sucks.
Can you tell us a story or anecdotes of
games that have like gone really
horribly slash fallen apart
>> and just how much time have we got and
then just more specifically highlight
like what are the like mistakes that
made everyone who's doing these
especially MIT they're all smart people
and they're written by smart people so
what kinds of mistakes do smart people
still make that result in these games
like falling apart
>> well or or or bad things
>> the most common thing that happens is
not even an issue of how smart the game
writers were, but how much experience
they've had in seeing things go horribly
wrong. Um,
>> and I'm asking
>> just as this class, you know, has given
you experience making games, you've seen
how some projects can go wrong, a lot of
it is just system dynamics, right? You
know, it's like I put together a bunch
of rules and I did not expect those
rules to interact in that way. But
because a live action game is difficult
to run multiple times, uh
>> the first time you see it,
>> you play test a live action game that
lasts two a month.
>> Uh that actually came up in the forums.
I believe somebody was asking about
this. Um you can at best play test given
mechanics. Uh you can you can play test
certain game mechanics and write down a
stripped down version which takes out
all of the plot motivations and just
test say combat. This is our combat play
uh play test. I did that for a matrix
game once. You know it's like I'm
writing a game about a matrix. Combat is
really freaking important. Uh so I just
made an entire game where all it was was
you want you want to go in and get this
thing and then get out. That's the whole
rule. And here's your three pages of
combat. And people like holy this
is a lot of memory. Um but uh and that
showed me the problems uh that I had.
Unfortunately, it's not one of those. It
didn't it wasn't so catastrophic that I
would use it as a catastrophic game
example. So
>> tell us about catastrophic examples.
>> Catastrophic game examples. Uh okay. I
think
>> someone tripped and hurt himself. That's
what I'm not.
>> No, no, no, no, no, no. That's that's
that's uh that's that's that's not what
you're looking for. I understand. It was
a game where
everyone was uh
was was playing undead. I can't remember
if they were vampire. I think they were
vampires. So, they could get knocked
down if they got shot uh and they will
get up again in five minutes because
they were immortal. Unless they got
staked or something, they would get up
again. Unfortunately, there were a lot
of vampires in game. Often of them, many
of them were on different factions. So,
they were going after each other with
guns. So when two people who were
obviously against each other shot each
other, fell over, they would get up in
five minutes and shoot each other again
repeatedly begging for someone to show
up for a certain to come and do
something to break this deadlock cuz and
that's one of those things where it's
like game mechanically you know what's
supposed to happen but it sucks, you
know, and
and then was it really Right. So that's
that's funny.
>> We have to wait five minutes. Can we
just do can we just continue like shoot?
>> Well, but but that's the but the issue
is again these games are happening in
real time. So the five minute rule is
there possibly for a reason you know uh
uh while you are down for five minutes
those five minutes may become very
valuable for someone who wants you down
for for those five minutes. So you know
I you can't kill me I can't kill you but
both of us can knock each other down for
five minutes. That's a great delaying
tactic. If I can send one of my friends
and do something that I don't want you
interfering with. Um, and if that's the
case, then that's great. But often it
was just that, oh crap, there's just no
way to break the deadlock.
>> You'd fear the the limiting factor of
the ammunition, though.
>> I think that game actually let you pick
up your ammunition while you were
>> because because it can be a really
annoying limit limitation to run off to
run off ammunition, especially if you're
playing with the little rubber dart
guns. uh cuz carrying a whole pile of
them is really annoying. So if the if
the rule is I can I get to pick them up
then you you have the illusion of having
a lot of ammunition without having to
carry a lot of ammunition.
Uh so that's one example of a
catastrophic failure that there's a
really funny quote regarding u
brainwashing actually which is you know
um
who were know what where were you I was
not being brainwashed. Who are you with?
Not with the people who are
brainwashing.
This is exactly the problem with the
persuasion thing, right? You know, it's
like, you know, I I I want to tell you
something because my goals haven't
changed far uh far enough to want to
align me to my new goals. So, I'm going
to do everything that I can without
breaking the rules. I'm not allowed to
tell you that I was being brainwashed,
right? So, I can say that I wasn't being
brainwashed.
Other catastrophic
How long does the thing take? Probably
>> I don't know.
>> Probably about as long as
half an hour.
>> Yeah.
>> Depends on the people.
>> Well, if you put a time limit on like
discussions then
>> cuz I plan on a password where it's less
hours just because there was no cap and
people just went to these long
discussions in between rounds.
>> So if you put a cap like okay we're
going to it's going to be this long
discussion and then we're going to kill
someone off. So something
Let's see. I have one. Anybody here
played online mafia? So totally
different experience.
>> Yeah, for sure.
>> Pinball or something
>> on forums usually.
>> Oh,
>> yeah. So anybody?
>> Yeah.
>> So basically when you can look at the
history of what people have said and who
they've accused and what order they did
it in changes how mafia pans out, right?
Mhm.
>> Because all of a sudden people start
going back and look at the history of
compiling statistics of who says who and
who said what and then who must be on
their side if that's the case. But then
there's this kind of meta knowledge that
you can use of this if you're a mafia
>> because you can kind of tell your m so
in in our particular case with forums we
were able to kind of communicate at the
mafia privately. Mhm.
>> Um, and that meant we could, for
instance, do things like making sure
that we were never the first people to
accuse anyone.
>> So, as a mafia, you should never do that
because it immediately makes you look
suspicious later on if somebody turns
out to be or not be in the mafia.
>> Like, there's no way that you can admit
if you're the first person who accuses,
but bandwagoning somebody who's not in
the mafia is always great. So, so you
can kind of coordinate to do this sort
of thing and then like try and defeat
the statistical analysis that somebody
else is doing.
>> You've got you've got this whole shadow
governing feeling.
>> Also, a great like tactic to get to draw
get you away from being on team someone
else is to execute someone on your team
and hope that if they they don't
actually like vote.
that. Yeah. I mean, I've definitely been
in a game where we purposely killed off
one of the people on our team just so
that we wouldn't be accused. I like,
"Oh, you he cannot be on mafia because
he killed off a mafia."
>> Okay. He's And then we end up winning
because no one no one figured that out.
I I mean that's one of the best things
about all kinds of live action games is
that it almost encourages people to look
for these kind of slightly out of the
box illusions. These sort of emergent
I'm not really going to expect that but
still fits within the rules because
you're dealing with real people for the
most part. You're not you're not limited
to the cards that you're allowed to play
or the turns that that you're allowed to
take. Uh so taking advantage of that. Um
I I have one more disaster story. Uh
>> I want to hear
>> there is I I'll I'll limit it to just
one for the people who don't. Um the the
this is a game where there is a virus
that was spreading.
People who are in the assassin skill
might have really heard of this one but
um the whole basic idea is that there
was a explosive nano virus. um people
who got infected after a certain amount
of time will explode and anybody in the
room with them will now be infected. Um
of course this was a game, you know,
this is kind of a game in set in science
fiction kind of thing and they've got
doctors who are capable who have
mechanics to be able to research cures.
Um however when the doctor happens to be
one of the first people to die
game um what rapidly happens is that
what should have been a one night game
turned out to be a one-hour game when
everybody exploded.
So you know um I guess that might come
down to feasibility but that that I mean
you can think about it as as a you need
a certain amount of redundancy when
you're coming when you're designing any
game but particularly live action games
because happens. Um and you've got
to expect that to happen. You there's
always this fear about oh I put in too
many resources into this game then the
players are going to find it too easy.
And it's most more often than not, yeah,
there are some players that are going to
say, "We breeze through that." But
rarely do people get terribly upset in a
live action game when something is
slightly too easy. Um, they get really
upset when it becomes when it's even
near possible. you know, it's like, oh,
so the GMs only made it possible for
only made one made it possible for one
person to fix this problem and that
person and they didn't think about that
person just dying in the beginning of
So yeah, that was that was another
example. None of which were my my games.
I'm sorry. I feel really bad about bring
not bringing examples for my games, but
I don't know which ones were the ones
that I generally Oh, I do have one more.
So, this was after The Sims came out and
and people should already be worried
about that. Um, I I I thought having a
blatant stat would be a really good idea
for a game. This was a game that was set
on a train.
>> Oh,
>> this was this was a game that was set in
a train. It was steampunk. So, tea was a
game. I think tea was in fact a combat
drug. Um, if you drank tea, your combat
stats will increase, but so would your
bladder stat. every once your bladder
stat was past a certain point uh all the
combat stats went down and you really
had to get to the restroom. Um which was
really interesting.
Most people just reviled that that game
back me back me back me back me back me
back because it was one more number they
had to hit cold in their head that was
stupid annoying and really didn't do
terribly much for the immersion of the
game. You know, I I was thinking, oh,
it's a game about traveling on a train.
So, you use the restroom all the time.
That's the only thing I do when I'm
traveling. I use the restroom. It's the
most momentous event. Um, but um but
then that even that led to some
interesting emergent situations because
when this train gets attacked and
everybody needs to find a safe place to
hide, what they all do is they get into
the washroom,
barricade it, and drink tea until all
the combat stats go up the roof and then
win the fight. Um because we were right
there in the restroom, we could afford
to do that.
>> It was hilarious.
>> These people come up with exploits and
>> that's fun.
>> They may hate the rules, but once they
understand how the systems work, they're
going to come up with ways to to to use
it to their advantage. And that can be
some of the most enjoyable.
>> I saw a squirrel this past weekend and
figured out it stood under a bird feed.
um
>> ah
>> thing that was spending the tree
>> it could just get pre-cluded because
when the birds ate it once every two
three minutes they would drop a grain
accidentally
>> and and there was this really fat
squirrel in it just sitting there and
spent the entire day just sitting under
you know
>> so I mean like it's so natural to just
try to find exploits everything and
>> there is there is a moral
>> like it doesn't work for immersion but
you still do it anyway
>> there is a moral to that though is that
for live action games especially if
you're playing a live action game
community. Uh there is whatever you
write down as a rule, you may put it up
on the wall, you may put it in a piece
of paper, someone's going to try to do
it. And uh and you you have to think of
I'm going to put in a rule that's so
ridiculous that that people are not
going to want to try to do it uh because
it's going to hurt them. Something like
jump on this jump jump on the spot 100
times and you unlock this door. Or you
could find someone with lock with
lockpicking, you know, and you would
just assume that person's going to find
someone with lockpicking. No, someone's
going to jump on the spot 100 times and
they're gonna hate you for it because
you put a rule in there for it. So, um,
you know, try not to hurt your players.
It'll be tomorrow, you know, because
they will do what you tell them to do.
>> Disclosure form.
>> All right, that's uh cards. Um so um
before we go I want to like clarify the
in this version the um investigation
mechanic. So the group gets to the group
of scientists gets to test two people.
Um if you catch the thing then they're
dead and out. If you if you catch them
on the second time, this is what I've
read. If you catch them on the second
guess, you get another guess. Um I'm not
sure if that means you can have infinite
guesses or not. So that's something to
play around. If you test your wrong
person is not a thing, they don't die.
>> No. Okay.
>> So, I test someone the first time
they're a thing, then they're out. But I
have someone a second time.
>> Yeah.
>> Regardless of whether or not I've tested
a thing the first time.
>> Yes.
>> At least two guesses.
>> But if you test someone on the second
one, they don't die.
>> If they're the thing, they're dead.
>> Thing dies. But if you test someone on
the first time and they're the thing,
you don't get an extra guess.
>> Well, not necessarily.
>> No, you get you get two.
>> You always get two of these two. So you
have if you guess anytime I'm saying if
you get a thing only one person a knife.
>> Yeah.
>> But if you guess a thing and then not a
thing and you get a thing.
>> Yeah. Like you can catch the thing.
>> Yeah. I think you can catch the thing
without actually doing anything other
than like making a system where you
automatically catch the thing
>> and you're getting two guesses. So the
ratio of like by randomly guessing
you'll certainly change it, right? I
mean this is just what I found and it
seemed like an interesting way. part of
the point, right?
>> Which which which means do you start
with?
>> No, you're not perfectly because you
could then
>> as I recogn
like
bias towards the nonffected
Appreciate something.