the MIT energy initiative presents
decarbonization amid Global crisis at
the MIT energy initiative fall
colloquium Philip R sharp highlighted
dramatic steps the US government has
recently taken to combat climate change
written by Calvin
HCK a global pandemic Russia's invasion
of Ukraine inflation the first ever
serious challenge to the peaceful
transfer of power in the United States
forced to face a seemingly unending
series of Once inag generation crises
how can the world continue to focus
attention on goals around carbon
emissions and climate change that was
the question posed by Philip R sharp the
former president of resources for the
future and a former 10-term member of
the US House of Representatives from
Indiana during his MIT energy initiative
fall colloquium address titled the
prospects for decarbonization in America
will global and domestic crises disrupt
our plans perhaps surprisingly sharp
sounded an optimistic note in his answer
despite deep political divisions in the
United States he noted Congress has
passed five major pieces of legislation
under both president Donald Trump and
President Joseph Biden aimed at
accelerating decarbonization efforts
rather than hampering movement to combat
climate change sharp said domestic and
Global crises have seemed to Galvanize
support create new incentives for action
and even unify political Rivals around
the cause almost everybody is dealing
with to some degree the absolutely
profound churning events that we are in
midst now most of them are unexpected
and therefore we're not prepared for
them and they have had a profound
shaking of our thinking sharp said the
conventional wisdom has not held up in
almost all of these areas and therefore
it makes it much more difficult for us
to think we know how to predict an
uncertain future and it causes us to
question our own abilties a nation or
anywhere to actually take on these
challenges and obviously climate change
is one of the most important however
sharp continued these challenges have in
some instances spurred action the war in
Ukraine he noted has upset European
energy markets but has also highlighted
the importance of countries achieving a
more energy independent posture through
Renewables in America he added we've
actually seen absolutely stunning
Behavior by the United States Congress
of all places what we've witnessed is
Congress put out incredible sums of
money under the previous administration
and then under this Administration to
deal with the co crisis sharp added
later in his talk and then the United
States government came together red and
blue to support the ukrainians against
Russia it saddens me to say it seems to
take a Russian invasion or the Chinese
probing us economically to get us moving
but we are moving and these things are
happening Congressional
action sharp cautioned against getting
caught up in the familiar Viewpoint that
Congress in its current Incarnation is
fundamentally incapable of passing
meaningful legislation he pointed in
particular to the passage of five laws
over the previous 2 years the 2020
energy act which has been characterized
as a down payment on fighting climate
change the infrastructure investment and
jobs act sometimes called the bipartisan
infrastructure bill which calls for
investments in passenger rail electric
vehicle infrastructure electric school
buses and other clean energy measures
the chips and science act a $280 billion
effort to revitalize the American
Semiconductor industry which some
analysts say could direct roughly one
quarter of its funding toward
accelerating zero carbon Industries and
conducting climate research the
inflation reduction act called by some
the largest climate legislation in US
history which includes tax credits
incentives and other Provisions to help
private companies tackle climate change
increase investments in renewable energy
and enhance Energy Efficiency the kagali
amendment to the Montreal protocol
ratified by the Senate to little Fanfare
in September under which the United
States agree to reduce the consumption
and production of hydrocarbons
hfc's it is a big deal sharp said of the
dramatic increase in federal climate
action it is very significant actions
that are being taken more than what we
would expect or I would expect out of
the Congress at any one time along with
the many billions of dollars of climate
related Investments included in the
legislation sharp said these new laws
will have a number of positive spillover
effects this enables state governments
in their policies to be more aggressive
sharp said why because it makes it
cheaper for some of the Investments that
they will try to force within their
state another pretty obvious spillover
effect sharp said is that the new laws
will enhance us credibility in
international
negotiations finally he said these
public investments will make the US
economy more competitive in
international markets for clean energy
technology particularly as the United
States seeks to compete against China in
the space competition with China has
become a motivator in American politics
like it or not sharp said there is no
question that it is causing and bringing
together politicians across blue States
and red
States holding on to
progress even in an uncertain political
climate in which Democrats and
Republicans seem unable to agree on
basic facts recent funding commitments
are likely to survive no matter which
party controls Congress and the
presidency sharp said that's because
most of the legislation relies on
broadly popular carrots that reward
investments in
decarbonization rather than less popular
sticks that create new restrictions or
punishments for companies to fail to
decarbonize politically the impact of
the this is very significant sharp said
it is so much easier in politics to give
away tax credits than it is to penalize
or put requirements on people the fact
is that these tax credits are more
likely to be politically sustained than
other forms of government intervention
that at least has been the history sharp
stressed the importance of what he
called Civil Society institutions such
as universities nonprofits churches and
other organizations that are apart from
government and business in promoting
decarbonization efforts those groups can
act highly independently and therefore
they can drive for things that others
are not willing to do now this does not
always work to good purposes partly this
diversity in this decentralization in
Civil Society led to deniers and others
being able to stop some climate action
but now my view is this is starting to
all move in the right direction in a
very Dynamic and a very important way
what we have seen over the last few
years is a big uptick in philanthropy
related to
climate looking
ahead Sharp's optimism even extended to
the role of social media he suggested
that the wild west era of social
platforms may be ending pointing to the
celebrities who have recently lost
valuable business Partnerships for
spreading hate speech and
disinformation we're now a lot more
alert to the dangers he said some in the
audience questioned sharp about specific
paths toward
decarbonization but sharp said that
progress will require a number of
desperate approaches some of which will
inevitably have a greater impact than
others the current policy and the policy
embedded in this new legislation is all
about doing both he said it's all about
advancing current Technologies into the
marketplace and at the same time driving
for breakthroughs above all sharp
stressed the need for continued
Collective action around climate change
the fact is we're all contributors to
some degree he said but we also all can
do something in my view this is clearly
not a time for hand ringing this is a
Time for Action people have to roll up
their sleeves and go to work and not
roll them down any time soon