The following content is provided under
a creative common license. Your support
will help MIT Open Courseware continue
to offer high-quality educational
resources for free. To make a donation
or view additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT Open
Courseware at ocw.mmit.edu.
Some content in this audio is not
covered under our creative common
license. For more information, see the
course materials on the MIT Open
Courseware website.
>> All right. So, so uh this of course does
not actually mean that you have more
time for assignment three. In fact, it
needs a little bit more time than for
assignment three. Sorry about that. But
I think this is a net game for everyone.
Um all right, that with that out of the
way. Um Konamo actually a lot of you
probably are already familiar. You might
have taken any of her classes. She's uh
uh she's a visiting uh lecturer,
visiting professor. Visiting professor.
>> Um uh here at Gambit uh and um
>> are you doing something?
>> Yes. Cheating and ethics and games.
>> So this
>> Brian can tell you all about it.
>> You can take this as a the sneak
preview.
>> Yes. This is the taster of it.
>> Thanks.
Okay. Um, so it sounds like you all have
lots of opinions,
which will be good. So to get started,
and actually I don't like the term
lecture because I don't actually lecture
very much. Um, I'm going to start by
handing around some online index cards,
and I want you to take a few minutes and
generate some examples of uh ethical
elements, procedures, episodes, games.
The more specific you can be, the
better. And I'm actually going to
collect these at the end um because as
Philip mentioned, I'm teaching this
ethics and games class and I want to
bring in more examples and stuff. So
this will actually be useful for me. So
>> talking about in games.
>> Yeah. So you like we were just talking
about Fable. Um, but like if you can
think of a more specific example from
it, a level, um, different choices that
you get with characters in certain
games,
whatever you can come up with in terms
of like are there interesting ethical
dilemmas,
situations?
>> Wait, is this within the context of the
game or are we talking about like in a
multiplayer game, your conduct towards
other players and this kind of thing?
>> Or when I was in Owen's office, whether
or not they steal the swag. um within
you can do within MMOs as well or you
know multiplayer game
>> you can continue to write examples for
hand uh if you can think of them but
just to get started um
you're going to stand behind me
>> well then you can start by giving me an
example
>> sure um okay so I have a couple um names
obviously um there's there's always kind
of questions and debate about whether
something it's cheap or viable or should
you be allowed to do it?
>> Oh
>> yeah. So like if maybe um
I'm trying to think how to describe it.
So people who play casually will tend to
say um oh if you do this with this
character that's cheap and you shouldn't
do that. Whereas the you know the
community at large and people who play
seriously tend to say well if you can do
something you can't do something you
should be allowed to do it and if you
can't overcome it that's your own fault.
>> Okay. is like violating a community
norm.
>> Yeah, kind
>> like it's allowed in the rules,
>> but it's like against like the community
norm
that
Evan Owen
>> Owen sorry
>> so I have a bunch of stuff which is
related to griefing just generally um so
let's just go for the one which is one
of my favorites
um so this is griefing for comic effects
or role playing griefing but doing it in
a way which you are then going to write
a blog about and from your character's
perspective. Um the griefing makes
sense. Uh so there is a there is a
particular player that played EverQuest.
His name is Fancy the Famous Bard. Um he
was on the good team side
and um he he griefed evil because evil
is bad.
So people who would play evil
characters, he would run around and
annoy in a really frustrating way, which
eventually caused the makers of
EverQuest to change the rules of the
server so that bad people could kill
him, whereas previously they weren't
allowed. They weren't able to.
>> What did he do?
>> Um, so there was this thing there was
this mechanic in EverQuest where if you
were close to a monster, it became
aggressive and attacked you.
>> Yeah. Um, so he had a lowle character
that was able to run really fast and
>> I've heard of him
>> would run around and then run over the
top of evil people and then the the
monsters would detach from him and then
kill them.
>> Yeah.
>> But Oh, yeah. And the the catch was that
um the the server was a no rules server.
Aside from that is like so you can't
complain to GMs about player
misbehavior.
Aside from there was a built-in
protection for players so that if
they're like level four or below, so
very low level, they can't be killed by
higher level players. Um, and so he just
sat on the cusp of that yet was still
able to use his ability to go around and
people who are much higher level. And it
was it was pretty great. And he did it
all totally in character as well, which
is what makes it super good.
Is that me? Okay. Uh I thought of I
think of portal when they ask you to use
them as your portal.
>> You have to burn up the cube.
>> Yeah. You don't want to and they make
you and you try to like leave without it
for a few times and you try to break. It
doesn't work.
>> It's very sad.
>> I didn't want to do it.
I thought of uh Jason Roer's Sleep is
Dead.
>> Um
what was that one?
>> It's more of like a storytelling tool
where you have one player can control
like the the 2D world and then you have
one player who is the player and they
can interact with it.
>> Oh.
>> And each player has like 30 seconds to
make some kind of action and then you
make a story going back and forth. And
um what happens is you can play online
with people and uh like the controller
character will or player will have some
kind of story that they want to tell and
so it's up to the player whether or not
they want to go along with the story and
act like a character in their world or
like try and break the story.
>> Okay. What's the name of it again?
>> Sleep is dead.
>> So actually or brief you say
>> kind of.
>> Is that the same person as passing?
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
>> Um, in Ocarina of Time, there's the
treasure box gambling game. You can
actually cheat if you use the lens of
truth through boxes. So, it's a built-in
mechanic, but that sort of allows you to
cheat.
>> You just got to do that legit.
>> Yeah.
You can get money easily anyway. It's
not really good.
>> I do that.
>> I do that completely chip.
>> Lucky man.
>> So in the sip hord there's a
pretty much every sip there's some sort
of slavery mechanic. But I guess in S
force example I know uh many players
don't seem to mind the fact that we
would all consider that slavery is
ethically wrong. But in in game it's
actually affectionately called whipping
and is considered a very efficient way
of converting food into
>> whipping whipping
unit.
>> Okay. So it's efficient but it's
slavery. But you combine it, you use
granaries to offset the population loss.
And if you spam farms, it becomes a very
effective way to uh produce, especially
in hell for your
>> usually used to exploit a lot of people
that way.
>> Anyh who,
>> um so in Sims, my friend used to do this
all the time. You just like off your
characters by putting them in a lot of
like the pool and then
>> but you have to watch them flail around
and die
>> and get tired and
>> um I have a few I guess a more obscure
example that kind of goes along the
lines of briefing is uh discussions over
the point of the game in communities in
MMOs. Uh specifically, there was
apparently a
huge problem in an obscure mode called
Skys where a large community of the
players was there to basically
anthropomorphic RP and a large community
of the players there was there to play
to win because it had a large combat
economy system. Um, and this effectively
almost tore the game apart because it
was such a small number of people um
over what should be the point of this
game when mechanically so many things
are bad.
>> Uh, also in Cal Hard you can roll up
people
and then a star. It was traumatizing.
>> Yeah, but they're in a giant ball of
awesome. That's true.
It's not really murder.
[Music]
>> They don't suffocate on the inside of
the cavary first.
>> It's like a gour. Once you're in there,
you know, it's a better way.
>> You're grateful.
Um, so in fear there's um there's a nail
gun
and when
>> can't end well
>> and when you kill people with it, uh,
the game does a really good job of
spectacularly nailing them to surfaces
in the environment. So if you if like
someone jumps and then you shoot them in
the shoulder, you'll like you can like
nail them up to the ceiling. And if you
nail them multiple times, you can have
them like hanging by hand and by their
head and by a foot from the ceiling or
something or from the wall. Anyway,
>> on awesome. Yeah, on forums there were
entire threads devoted devoted to
sharing
screenshots of your most spectacular
nails like like you know just like the
absolutely most gruesome like you know
five nails to the eye suspending a guy
from a pole kind of thing. And
um anyway, and there was just a lot of
debate on these threads cuz most people
be like, "Yeah, look at this picture.
This one's awesome." And thinking, you
know, has blood splatters everywhere and
all that, but every like third or fourth
post it be like, "You guys are so messed
up." You know, this is like this is
wrong. And it was and it was it's not
real, you idiot. You know, like but it
but but the fact that you like it is
still real. Well, then people would
argue at, you know, at great lengths
over this. I just remember chanting upon
these forms and being like, "Is this
messed up?" I'm not sure.
>> So, is it more
efficient in the game to use the nail
gun to kill people than other
>> It's a hell of a lot more fun.
>> Okay.
>> Um,
>> but it's not like the game forces you to
do it if you would not want to.
>> No, it doesn't. You could use other
guns, but at some point, you know, if
you don't have enough ammo for other
guns, you do you would switch to nail
gun, I guess. It's a good gun. Shotgun's
kind of fun, too. It disintegrates
people at short range.
>> Okay.
>> A gun that turns people into skeletons.
>> Yes, that one was in the expansion.
>> Yes. No, it wasn't the original. The
sniper rifle was a rail gun that shoots
a beam of electricity and turns people
vaporizes the flesh off other opponents.
What?
>> Um, Grand Theft Auto, you can get a
prostitute for money, get health, and
then potentially kill the prostitute and
get your money back.
>> The hook or cheat.
>> Yeah. Um, and then like some of the ones
related to that is like Bioshock where
like you can either kill the little
sisters or and harvest them for like
lots of good or like lots of points
rather or like save them and get a
smaller amount of points but like you
feel better about yourself which
actually in the end ends up being the
better way to go. But
>> yeah, you get more. It's like you get
more to save.
>> Yeah, cuz well cuz like at like you get
small like if you kill them and harvest
them you get like 10 points let's say.
If you save them, you get like five
points, but then after like 10 saves,
you get like a bonus of like 100 points.
So, it ends up being like more efficient
or not like more efficient in the long
run to save them. More efficient in the
short run to kill them.
>> And also, if you're going to kill them,
you should kill them all,
>> right?
>> Don't just knock off one.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Okay. Uh in Age of Empires 3,
there's uh when you're colonizing your
colony, you have the option of
expediting the native people. So like to
help you uh fight like basically to help
you fight.
>> How do you how is this presented to like
explain?
>> No, I mean you like present them. You
establish an outpost inside of their um
residence area and you supposedly trade
with them, but I mean there's nothing
really there in the game. You just
literally just put a house of yours
inside of their colony.
>> Nice.
>> Also, Microsoft's selling that for 10
cents.
>> Yeah. inverse.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> I think it was just yesterday.
>> Yeah.
>> I'm not sure.
>> Um I guess infamous you can choose
whether to be bad or good like go around
killing people or to help them survive
postapocalyptic world.
>> And I guess you can kind of do the same
thing in Fallout.
Well, also, um, Infamous forces you more
to choose. Remember Ash was playing that
in our class and she said like you
really had to go one way or the other to
get, you know, it's like on either end
of the spectrum there were special
abilities. If you stay in the middle,
you got nothing.
>> Yeah.
>> Really note
>> follow. I just follow I mean there are
certain things you can build off. So
there's also like in Fallout you can
gain like people that travel with you
like based off neutral
>> oh sorry um I was going to say in
Fallout as well like in in Fallout 3
there's one particular really good
example um where you get trapped in like
this dream world that this guy is
creating for you and a bunch of other
people um which you don't know that it's
a dream world at first like you know
it's a dream or something but you don't
know that these are real people in the
dream with you and he tells you to kill
the other people in the dream in order
to like let you get out cuz he's in
complete control of it. Um, and you can
kill them and you'll get out fine. All
the people will be dead. Um, or there's
ways that aren't like you're not told,
but there's there are ways to like just
go around all of it and just get out
without killing anyone.
>> They stole that from I guess in Balders
2. There's the similar thing. was
actually going to talk.
>> Y
>> So I guess the first thing I'll mention
is uh items but
>> just watching.
>> Yeah, just uh go out of all of them. how
so many times you'll be fighting
monsters and all of a sudden a bunch of
civilians come by and you can just let
them go, but there's no fun that if you
kill them, you get life and experience.
So, it's better to reward you for
killing them.
>> Yeah,
>> you get you get some life back. Maybe
some usually do that in the story,
>> huh?
>> You're Kratos.
>> Kratos.
>> You are the god of war. Well, you become
the god, but pretty much you just go
around kill hackers and slashing
everything up.
>> Okay. So, you get these are just in
civilians who are doing nothing.
>> Yeah. Who do they're just running
running for their lives from scary
monsters and then you come and just like
hack them all into pieces.
>> Well, also there's in the in the game
you could there's like the second one in
order to pass on you have to translate
something and then translate it you get
a priest. You smash your head to it and
then they say they have to sacrifice in
blood. So you just smash them into
pieces until the the blood sacrifice.
>> Yeah.
>> This feels so good.
>> Do you happen to do that?
>> Yeah. Oh, okay.
In Indigo Prophecy, uh you switch
between different sets of characters.
One of them is a guy who committed a
murder and then you switch to the cops
who are trying to catch him. And so in
one of the earlier scenes you play as
the cops, you bring in a witness and you
um you're trying to make up the artist
rendering of what the murderer looks
like. And so you can choose whether or
not to make a faithful rendering and
bring the cops closer to catching him or
to make one that looks not nothing like
him so you can like evade them when you
play as the other guy.
>> Interesting.
>> If you uh make it not look like you as
killer
I think he just there are other clues he
has to find in order to finally track
him down.
>> Can you
win this game?
>> Yeah.
>> I mean, is the goal to catch the killer
for the killer to get away or is
>> it's actually an adventure game. So, the
goal is to get the story.
Hello.
>> Um, so in the LAR that I played a long
time ago, I was allowed to draw one item
from a location every hour. The game ran
from noon to midnight on three different
days. Um, but I couldn't play before 2
p.m. So, I come in at 2 p.m. How many
items am I was I allowed to draw at the
be when I came in the game? Um, given
that I only missed two hours of game.
And what happens? And if the answer is,
well, I can make that up. And what
happens if I miss an hour halfway
through and if I forget? Um, so yeah, no
one's looking.
>> Oh, what did you do?
>> What did I do?
>> Yes.
>> What did I do? I think I threw more than
one item at the beginning. Okay.
>> And I made sure I never forgot.
>> So, honor system. A lot of are based on
honor system.
So, in uh Final Fantasy 7, uh like a lot
of Japanese RPGs, you get used to the
idea of walking into people's houses and
just leaving any items you find.
>> Except in FF7, they actually mix it up a
couple times. There are a couple
instances where you go in there and do
that and the item is fairly
insignificant. Like, you could buy it
easily, like a couple pieces of gold or
gill or whatever it is, and then the
person walks out of their kitchen or
something. It's like, did did you just
take my item? And you have the option of
saying yes or no. And if you say no,
then you get to keep it. But if you say
yes, they're like, "What the hell? Give
it back."
>> That was interesting.
>> Yeah.
>> I had something that hasn't really been
touched on.
>> Okay.
>> So, when you're running a very large
scale guild in an MMO, you reach a point
where you need to distribute loot from
these high-end rating things. Like the
kind of community optimal thing to do is
for the people who are in charge of the
guild to allocate who gets what so that
you can for instance like kit out the
characters that it's most important for
the guild to have for gear to progress.
But for the most part actual members of
the guild don't really like that because
you kind of wouldn't like to receive
some kind of reward for having put in
time for the guild and going a long time
without ever having gotten anything is
really frustrating. So people come up
with these intricate systems
>> DK
>> for DKP.
>> Yeah. For distributing your um resources
essentially to try to balance the
interests of the individual and the
interests of the community.
>> How many of you are unsure what DKP is
driving kill points?
There are these sometimes elaborate
schemes for if you participate in these
raids, you get so many points. Um, and
the idea is like the guild claims
everything that drops supposedly and uh
you build up points and at some point
you have enough to buy, you know, a
certain item. So, like let's say you're
on a raid and you just got something
really cool last time and something
drops this time that you could really
use even though you're there, you don't
necessarily get it because you just
spent all your decrim
primary source of your problem.
>> People play.
>> You learn that by going on raids and
then catch them in practice.
>> And they're a blockout day, too.
>> So, running one of these things is
actually surprisingly complicated and
hard. Um, particularly, so my little
experience, I ran a guild which which
incorporated this. Um, one problem that
happens is that if you have fixed prices
for things, then you kind of get DKP
inflation as prices change and what
happens at whatever you and it's
incredibly complicated to work out and
you got to repric everything constantly.
So instead, we went for a auction based
system where people kind of bid on
things and then prices correct
themselves. However, people can collude
in auctions in auctions which then
causes a resentment in people who aren't
in on the collusion and the whole thing
is just a nightmare.
And no, I don't run a guild anymore. I'm
really happy.
>> Okay.
>> Um, in games like Pokemon or Animal
Crossing, uh, you can decide whether or
not to change the time on your DS or
GameCube.
Like when Pokemon Gold and Silver came
out, I was like 10. I had a bedtime. I
didn't have a lot of time to catch all
the nighttime Pokemon.
>> You can do that to manipulate the RNG
and uh, get the stats you want. Perfect.
>> There's also uh times whenever you do
the um random number generator hacks in
games in order to get in order to get a
certain drop that's normally like 1% but
you can increase it up to like almost
100.
But what I was going to say was that
Fallout 3 u so in Fallout 3 you can
pickpocket people and something you do
when you pickpocket as long as you don't
get caught. You can take a grenade from
your inventory and place it in their
pocket and all of a sudden they be like,
"Oh my god, there's a grenade. Run
away." And it will blow up inside their
pocket and they will blow.
>> What game?
>> Fall.
>> Fall asleep. It's also And the funny
thing is that's that's actually an
achievement to blow someone up.
So you get other than the joy and
giggles and
>> well you can also you get you you they
start from the joy and giggles
>> you get that you can well yeah you can
pick their pocket so you can whatever
they have in their pocket you can get
>> that is still left.
>> Yeah. Well no I mean you take it out you
take it out as you're putting the
grenade in.
>> Uh
>> you wouldn't want that boot to be
damaged by the grenade.
>> Put the grenade after
>> you're just hiding the evidence.
>> Yeah. You're just putting them in at the
same time simultaneously.
And it can be traded
examples we haven't touched on.
>> So I used to play a lot of Ultima online
and they had a bunch of really
sophisticated rules that applied in
certain situations and didn't apply in
situations. So uh there were a lot of
times in the game you just flat out lie
to people and have them go into
situations that were unsafe for them.
For example, if people were in your
house uh In an early version of the
game, if people are inside of your
house, they're automatically flagged as
like attackable by you because they're
because they're in your house and you
might not have let them in. And they can
like run outside their house and they'll
be unattackable by you. But you can also
like put a trash barrel in front of your
door, which only you can destroy and
nobody else can destroy and they can't
run through that. So you like invite
them in to like trade them something or
join your guild and they're in your
house and then you put a trash barrel
there so they can never leave and you
just kill them
>> or like
>> or just leave them there, right? or just
leave it. There were there were tons and
tons of ways.
>> Was so cool with this stuff. It's
>> Oh, it's really bad. It's really bad. I
was part of a guild that that did this
to me and then like I told them that I
had a couple other things. I was like
10. It's pretty sick. A bunch of ways to
like steal tons and tons of money from
people and they didn't realize they
could do it.
>> Yeah.
>> But I feel like just blatantly lying to
people as a as a tactic instead of just
being mean to them. Okay.
Yeah.
>> Uh the question of uh real world play
for in game items especially in
competitive games
>> um whether or not it's allowed by the
GMs.
>> Well,
>> I mean those are two different
questions. One is ethical question from
a player standpoint and the other is
what does it mean in terms of
>> the player character relation
>> in the game.
>> Okay.
>> Oh yeah. I was going to say one thing
that comes up in um especially in board
games they have um a lot of positive
feedbacks called kingmaking and um good
examples are like in Monopoly or
Settlers or Munchkin and how it works is
like let's say you know you and Owen and
I are playing Settlers and uh typically
what'll happen is say Owen is winning
but I'm typically really far behind or
someone is going to be in a position
where they have no chance of winning. So
hypothetically like he's winning you're
close second and I'm distant third. What
people do is say, "Hey, Mia, I will give
you everything for your one level card
and then you can win because I'm mad at
all." Right. And that comes up, like you
said, in Monopoly and there's this
question of like, is that a really jerky
thing to do? You know, the rules don't
disallow it.
>> That's kind of an ongoing debate.
>> Yes, it is a jerk.
>> Similarly, Monopoly rules don't
specifically allow like if I have two
orange, we'll like exchange them and
promise each other immunity. properties
or like something that you're not
allowed to actually promise each other
or if you have two reds. I have a red
I'll give it to you and you promise me
half the profits or something like that
where clearly the third person is now
shut out of the game and can't win
because we have an early advantage even
though we're like agreeing to things
that aren't explicitly allowed.
>> Maybe you play Dragon Age.
>> You see
>> I've seen a play.
>> Okay. I've just I'm playing for it right
now. I've been thinking about these
issues a lot. Actually, on my first
playthrough, there's like scene where
there's a kid possessed by a demon. You
have the choice whether to kill him or
not. First time I killed him,
>> I thought everybody did.
>> I had no compulsion about it. Like,
yeah, he's demon.
Turns out everybody really hated that,
you know, all the other characters, my
companions. And this this play time
through, I was like, ah, try it. It's
like all this extra work involved. And
um but it seems like in the game um
whether you want to do the good thing or
not, it generally works to your
advantage to do the good thing because
you get like more stuff either better
approval ratings from your companions
who then like unlock bonuses or um you
get stuff. Whereas, you know, being the
jerk
>> kind of depends on who your companions
are.
>> Yeah.
>> Does it approves? Um, people like the
the like elven assassin. I can't
remember what his name is.
>> Oh, I'm pretty sure approves as well. He
likes all the jerky things.
>> I didn't have the first play through.
>> Also, um, that one guy, the berserker
guy, um, that you can spot. No, no,
another guy. Um, I think you can get him
on your team at least. He's in the
temple where there's that big dragon and
where you're like doing some ash quest
or something. Um, and like he wants you
to pour dragon blood on the ashes or
something. I'm pretty sure you can get
them on your team. Am I right or am I
wrong?
>> But I know you can get them as part of
your final army and they're pretty good
>> and they're bad.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah,
>> I just chose poorly my companions like
moralistic ones. I kill a kid.
>> Yeah. Okay.
In the reading that you did, um, Seart
talks about, you know, different
choices, um, and and the way that game
designers are are putting these
together. And he talks about two
different categories, the open and the
closed ethical systems.
And, um, the open was, you know, more
letting players kind of determine for
themselves the stance that they want to
take and kind of seeing how that goes
through. whereas the closed is the
system kind of you know forces a
particular way of playing upon you. And
so just kind of going through these
here, where do you see them falling in
terms of closed and open?
>> Um I'm confused what closed means. So
you said open means that you have the
decision like on how to value your
actions and what or what to do. Um both
well like he says for example, you know,
in the Sims with drowning, um he
mentions The Sims as an open game
>> where you can do what you want and uh
kind of think about what happens.
>> I have a definite closed example. It's
not up there. There might be a closed
example up there. I'm just missing. But
um in the first Modern Warfare game,
they have a flashback uh sequence where
you have to snipe
>> the future bad guy Zakayv. And even
though in the game story he survives
your attempt to kill him, if you don't
actually hit him with the bullet, the
game won't let you progress.
>> So you have to go and basically snipe
this dude no matter what. The game won't
won't let you do it. And that's just
part of the story. That's how it works.
And it's dubiously moral that you should
be meddling in such affairs. But you
know,
>> and it actually comes back to bite you
later in the game because well, you're
at this you're at the place where it's
causing problems for you. The fact that
you tried to save this guy and then they
play the flashback in which you have to
do it. Um and it's all directed, you
know, you didn't close this.
>> Yeah.
>> Isn't like the Q murder close as well?
Cuz like you don't have a choice like
that you have to kill them to move on.
The what?
>> The cube murder like in uh
>> Oh, the
>> Oh, the cube.
>> Yeah,
>> I'm thinking cube.
>> Yeah. Yeah, that would be close because
you you simply can't move on. You just
have to deal with your
>> joke. Yeah. Yeah. No, exactly.
>> Start vacation is currently closed.
>> Yeah.
>> You feel bad about those people. You
just can't play Tamari. I'm sorry. Uh
I have a question actually about um
probably when we asked like the steepest
death briefing. It seems to me that was
intended by design
briefing briefing directly in the cube.
Like the idea that I'm a GM, you're a
player and part of the challenge of the
GM is not knowing whether your player is
going to play along with you, but that's
part of the game. So I don't know if
that's something
That tension is intended.
>> I don't know.
>> Well, I mean,
>> it's still open, right?
>> I would say this one is open, I guess,
>> because you are allowed to do what you
want.
>> I mean, the example he gives for
closedended is one of them is manhunt,
>> where you have to kill people and you
know, the more grizzly you kill them,
the better. And so like if you don't
like it, you know, there's just no way
to get through the game. And the other
example he also gives is um Shadow of
the Colossus.
>> And that one especially where it's sort
of not really it's ambiguous in terms of
like, okay, I have to kill these things.
And you know, if you play through you
realize like, well, wait a minute,
they're just sort of hanging out.
They're not really doing anything
necessarily bad, but I have to keep
killing them anyhow. Then you can start
to feel sort of guilty, but it's what
you have to do to play the game. So you
would say that's that's a closed system.
So uh let's see I would almost say
Indigo Prophecy might be closed because
you have to go on with the story which
in order you have to make decisions and
such in order to go progress on I feel
like isn't is that right?
>> I think the idea is that close would be
you don't have to make decisions like
close is like if you want to play the
game you have to make this moral
decision. You don't have a choice in the
moral decision. You have to be evil or
like and that that's that's one thing.
And another game could be you have to be
good. But if you have the decision
between both paths and that's open, I
believe. Right.
>> The premise behind Indigo Prophecy was
that like you could choose to do any
action and the game would just have a
different ending as a result. Though I
think in practice it only had a few
endings, but the premise was sort of
that it would have like countless
endings depending on your actions.
pretty sure that Age of Empires 3 is
going to have some closed
>> um
>> native exploitation because for the
campaigns at least I'm pretty sure there
are like
>> conditions for completing a scenario
which
is pretty
>> the hooker sheet is open
>> most of the mess are open
>> yeah follow through is definitely
>> the western style one.
>> The fear nail gun is is actually
>> the nail gun is what?
>> I don't know anyone who's gotten through
fear without killing someone with a nail
gun at some point.
>> I mean,
>> I'm wondering actually like you can run
out of ammo and everything else.
>> Yeah. Can you punch things?
>> Yeah, you can. Yeah,
>> you can't run out of ammo. You can
actually kung fu kick things which is
pretty cool.
>> Nice
>> in slow.
>> In fact, I would almost say all the rest
of them seem open.
>> Pretty open.
>> One of my favorite things.
>> You don't have to do this at any point,
do you?
>> Okay. So, most of these What did we say
about?
>> Oh,
>> okay.
So,
>> regarding Bioshock,
>> would that be open or closed?
>> I mean, there's you have a choice, but
it's in your best interest to do one or
the other.
>> Mhm.
>> Well, is it really?
>> So, if you have one only one thing you
can do, it's clearly closed. If you have
only two things you can do that are very
clearly defined, is it really an open
system or is it just a closed system
with two paths?
impressionist arguing was closed.
>> Yeah,
>> because you weren't self-evaluating the
system was determining whether what you
were doing was good or bad.
>> I was thinking so like I thought
infamous like the goods would also be
closed.
>> Some of them I think there's a
difference between only having one
option the system telling you which
option is the right option.
So in that case, some of these turned
from open to
>> Bioshock,
>> like Bioshock would then be closed. Like
Fallout 3, the Dreamland would then be
closed.
>> Like telling you what was the right
optionally
acceptable option.
>> Yeah.
>> What do you think? Do you think um he's
saying I know what you're saying because
he also mentioned the Old Republic as a
closed option.
>> Um
Is it that there are two discreet like
like good or evil you know the lights
the Jedi or the nar path? Um is Fallout
that concrete follow three? I mean like
I know uh so
>> Infamous is you know you're either going
one way or the other. Um but I'm not as
sure and I'm just asking people who
played it. Is Fallout 3 that particular
in how it's kind of is it setting up a
dichotomy of like the good character
versus evil or is it much
>> it's much more of a gradient
>> yeah
more emphasis
>> in Boulders Gate it's weird because
there's two things there's your
alignment which you pick at the
beginning of the game
>> uh D&D style that is just fixed but then
there's this thing that's your
reputation which can be decreased if you
do certain things from the game's point
of view in view of others. So, you can
get away with doing bad stuff sometimes
without actually decreasing your
reputation. You can also just pick a
like chaotic evil alignment and then do
only good things and then it's just very
weird. Um, so I don't exactly remember
it how the alignment really factors in
the game play. But there's a moment, for
example, in the game there's a big story
for sort of rejoins that afterwards, but
you have to, you know, ally yourself
with either the thieves guild or the
vampires in a in a town who are sort of
competing factions. Sort of weird, the
thieves against the vampire because the
thieves against the vampires, you got to
pick one uh to help you raid a certain
area. Um, and you don't really have
other choices and there's no there's not
one is not
>> does it make you gooder or evil? They're
both kind of bad, but you have to do it
to kind of find the person that you're
trying to get.
>> That's kind of closed.
>> Yeah.
>> So, in terms of Boulders Gate 2, I would
say one there's like the reputation
stat, which I found never really into,
which is some type of metric for your
That's not true. If you kill everyone,
then you have to go and start attacking
them. Do that.
>> People in your party can duel you for
your honor if they get upset at you.
Kellorn duled me, left my party, and
then tried to attack because I was too
evil.
>> Anyway, so that's uh like very very
specific actions that will affect your
alignment. And there aren't very many of
those. In addition, you have kind of
like these scene type decisions which
are also very black or white, good or
equal. I would say there's a lot of
decisions in the game that don't impact
both of those to have both an ethical
choice but not nearly as much of a
mechanical
impact.
>> One of the things he also mentions in
relation to the open system like going
back to the Sims is that um
you can do what you want and the game
doesn't necessarily punish you. you
know, like you can murder, you know, you
you can drown your Sims and the rest of
the Sims in the house like joy in fear
or, you know, like disapprove of their
action.
>> Um, it's just sort of up to you like
whether you want to feel bad about it or
not or or you know, the game has no
larger response other than uh light the
Sim die once because I let him set the
stone on fire and I foolishly mold for
his life and got his zombie back. Turns
out the only way zombie is happy in the
game is if he makes everybody else
unhappy. So then I had to kill zombie.
But
so that was another kind of element to
it. One of the things that he talks
about in general in relation to all of
this and a lot of these kind of fit is
like ethics through statistics. You like
that somehow ethical systems are on this
point or sliding scale and that you know
you're heading towards good or you're
heading towards evil. We were even
mentioning this before class started
that, you know, you can blow up an
entire town, but then if you know, like
you give like three beggars 50 cents
each, suddenly, you know, you're back at
neutral because of the way that these
lighting systems work, you know, in
bizarrely mechanical.
>> Yeah, you you can buy reputation back by
donating to temples.
>> It's like indulgences.
>> Yeah, it is exactly like
>> I want that not going to happen.
I have to close this now because I'm
getting high off of the microphones. I
wanted to show you an example um of one
that we haven't talked about yet.
Somebody mentioned Call of Duty. This is
actually from last year. It's not
Castro, which is the new one. Um but
>> is it the Russian hostage thing?
>> Yeah, it's the no Russian level
>> from Modern Warfare 2.
>> It's like a competition.
This is um so this was last year's
modern uh Call of Duty and this was the
optional level. You did not have to play
it and of course it caused a big storm
when it was released. Um I'm just going
to play it and then we can talk about it
after.
>> So what's has anyone played this?
>> Yeah.
>> Want to um provide a little context or
explain the a little bit more?
So the convoluted plot is that this is a
false flag attack which is staged by a
terrorist organization which is meant to
frame the CIA to start a war between
Russia and the US. And so the idea here
is that you are playing a character who
is undercover as part of the CIA who was
part of this terrorist organization.
And then you end up being double crossed
because they as it was just revealed at
the end they knew that you were a CIA
agent and they're trying to pin the
attack on America.
>> So that's that's you have the option
>> story context. the option of shooting
Makarov in the back or
>> if you try and shoot Makarov then the
game then the level ends with a fail
>> um and can't progress in the game. If
you try and get through the level
without shooting any civilians the level
also ends off discover decides that
you're a traitor and shoots you
before doing anything else
>> before he's supposed to shoot you
>> before he's supposed to shoot you. I
seem to remember.
>> I I think you can get through the
mission by not shooting any civilians,
but you can't get through without
shooting any of the cops.
>> Yeah. Like something
>> if you don't shoot the cops, I think you
can.
>> Yeah. You still have to shoot civilians.
>> Yeah.
>> Maybe different difficulty settings as
well.
>> Yeah. I don't know. Also, that guy was
incredibly diligent about killing
civilians.
>> I mean, I I was I was impressed. I did
not play that level that way. Oh, I
think
that's
>> Yeah, that was uh that guy took his work
to heart. Like
>> I don't think that I would have like
like Owen says if I was I haven't played
Modern Warfare 2 yet, but or Black Ops
for that matter, but don't feel like it
would it would come to me that it was
really necessary to just hunt down every
last
>> thorough. It was very thorough.
>> Yeah, blend in. And but you know it's
also interesting that you're the dupe in
this, right? You think, well, I'm
killing all of these people
>> so that I can then kill him probably or
something,
>> right? Or it's for a greater good,
right? That you know, I'm going to get
in with this group and and help bring
down this terrorist cell or haha, you
know, not so much.
>> And I mean, Call of Duty like has anyone
played Black Ops?
There's the scene in it, another uh
level where you can assassinate Castro
>> and um I was just watching it off Castro
>> this morning and uh
>> is it they they
Russian uh Cuba objected
>> um to to the video game.
But um I watched that level. It's not
nearly as exciting as this one. Um
although it's interesting in that you uh
he's you infiltrate his compound, you
know, you get up to he's like in his
bedroom with his or whatever she is and
um you shoot him and in this uh clip the
guy shot him in the head and it's it
slows down to bullet time actually and
you see it enter his forehead and he
falls over and and then the enraged
lover grabs the machine gun and starts
firing at you in her negligence so you
have to kill her too. And yeah, Cuba is
outraged,
but I I don't think it takes a lot to
get Cuba mad anyway.
>> Can you score statistics?
>> Don't like statistics.
>> 495 likes, 85 dislikes.
>> It's pretty high for dislikes.
>> For something that's not like video,
>> um
I I No. Yes. I I in the previous Modern
Warfare game, there's actually It
it it I haven't seen anyone draw this
parallel, but there is a level where you
are in the middle of a firefight, a US
marine in some Middle Eastern wars,
and you're told to shoot at enemies who
are coming on the on your center, but
they're at such a range that you cannot
tell friend. there's you're absolutely
certain that whatever you're shooting
at, there's a 50% chance that there's
actually some one one of the allies.
>> There there's also the really creepy um
>> that's the gunship sequence. the gunship
>> which is which is which is uh which gets
most of the attention but I I I but but
the I was surprised by the subtlety of
the the the sequence where you are just
in the middle of a firefight in in
Modern Warfare one because it has that
situation of the you are being told to
kill but you
may not even though everyone on on um
that you might be shooting at is a
combatant you may not want to shoot
everyone. in this space, you know, maybe
I felt that actually made a more
interesting subtle point of well,
actually that's kind of what the
situation of being in the Middle East
right now is like it's hard to tell
where
>> Yeah.
Um, I was thinking about this because I
actually um I did an interview last week
or two weeks ago with some radio people
and it was about Black Ops being
released because it's like the best
selling entertainment video ever and uh
they introduced it of course on the
segment as the ultraviolent video game
>> Call of Duty.
>> H
>> that's pretty accurate. It is, but it's
and one of the thing, one of the
questions that they asked that each
affiliate asked over and over is, you
know, they mentioned the caster level.
They said the video games gone too far.
You know, is there is there a line that
that shouldn't be crossed? And I'm sure
if they had I mean, none of these people
actually played video games, so you
know, they had they were just reading
their script.
This might have even fit even better,
you know, in terms of how
>> this is pretty I'm surprised this got
through.
>> Well, it's an optional level,
>> right?
>> You know, you don't have to do it.
Interesting comment right there. You
know, JFK airport US citizens.
>> But, you know, leaving aside the just
like the the knee-jerk kind of gamer
defense, well, it's just for fun or it's
just a video game. I mean, how do you
answer that question? I mean, I know
what I spew to them, but I'm just
curious in terms of like what is what
does it mean and beyond just like games
as like statistics for like the good or
the dark side? Um, you know, is there a
point you think where it can go too far
with the game? What um what's the
assumption behind that question?
this really
disturbing news report I was reading
about this Japanese game called Wave
Play.
>> Oh yeah.
>> And the disturbing for me it was clear
like this is totally messed up. Can't
believe that this is like this exists.
But the part that was disturbing was the
the defense put forth by the developers
and they were say who are you guys to be
telling us this is messed up. You
Americans, you make games all the time
where you have to kill people. Murder is
a much worse crime than rape. Our game
is not nearly as bad as for say this.
And I was just like, wait, no, but but
that's more messed up. But but what and
and I don't know what what to think of
it. Um South Park.
>> What?
>> South Park episode that addresses South
Park.
>> Not seen that South Park
actually. Um just on that on that game
in particular, there was a lot of
backlash I heard in Japan about um
Replay. Mainly because the game had been
out for maybe 2 years and gone
completely unnoticed until basically the
West heard about it, America and Europe,
because I think it showed up on like
Amazon.com or something at some point.
And of course there was a gigantic
controversy and the media blew it up
completely. And so then in Japan I think
I think it was it banned in Japan I
think.
>> No.
>> So something like Japanese politicians
out for a while like negative attention
all the time.
>> Apparently like Japanese politicians
started cracking down on these types of
games and a lot of fans got like really
angry and they said well this is just
like your western eur eurosentric view.
It's like and why is this backlashing
onto us kind of thing. The only reason
why there was a backlash was because of
political attention, not necessarily
because of moral.
>> Well, I mean, a lot of our moral
framework is sort of Judeo-Christian in
nature.
And I was I read an entire entire
Wikipedia article on such things
afterwards. Uh, child pornography
as as long as it doesn't actually use
child actors. So like representations,
animated, 3D, whatever, is not illegal
in Japan. U and and there's no real
political pressure either to make it
illegal. It's just not part of the
public consciousness that's something
that needs to be made illegal. Um
and and the point is not a a weird point
like completely crazy that that you know
killing people is probably the worst
crime and and you know and the West
makes games advocate that all the time.
>> So the question
Well, in the radio interview with that
answer
question in terms of like the question
of uh whether or not a game crosses a
line first assumes that there is a line
to be crossed and
>> I guess second I guess my answer would
be yes there is a line but that line is
basically whether or not people buy the
game. If people buy the game, the game
hasn't really crossed the line.
>> So, see this image reminds me of like
the video reminds me of remember the
game of 9/11 where you are a person on
one of the top floors.
>> Oh, you can jump.
>> Yeah. Well, that's the only way to end
the game. You can go anywhere you want,
but there's no escape. And so, the only
way to end the game is to jump out of
window.
>> And that that had the same response. I
think
>> I was just going to say back on the
point of like is there a line or not? I
think the line is not a line on whether
like it becomes okay or not. It's a line
between I know we've mentioned this
before, but like between like
pornography and art. Like like there's a
line like if you're you know there's
there's ways to like take pictures of
like naked human bodies and like it's
artful like people respect it and all
that. And like there's there's ways in
games to represent killing and rape and
all that kind of stuff in a way that
provides a message within this framework
that makes it okay. And there were
there's like there's games where like
you know I think Manhunt was one of
these where it's like there's no real
like point other than just like
displaying just terrible terrible images
for the sake of displaying them. And
like in my mind it's very very similar
to like the discussion of like is that
image like pornography art and so I
think that's that's the right way to go
with this kind of thing in particular.
Like I feel that there's this question
of like is it doing anything meaningful
in the game other than just being
virtuous and in this case it's
definitely yes like it progresses the
plot um kind of
makes you think I guess a bit about the
characters that are involved like
there's there's actual there's character
development of Marov of Marov here. Um
it's showing the shady dealings of the
CIA and all this kind of business. So
like it's also making a political
statement at the same time. Um so yeah,
I mean it's it's not just nailing
people's eyes to the ceiling or what
have you.
>> I definitely feel like there I I was
thinking like are there any games that
are over the line? I definitely imagine
a game would be over the line. Like you
could imagine if like in Rafe or
whatever it's called there were like a
customizable character thing advertised
like rape your neighbors or something
like that. I would be uncomfortable with
something like that.
So I feel like I I almost wanted to say
that there is no line to make people buy
it, but I feel like there are some
things where like they would be over the
line regardless of whether people buy
them.
>> People might even buy them because they
are over this line.
>> Oh yeah, of course. That's why you would
buy that.
>> What about how many of you have uh
played or seen Super Combine Master RPG?
How many of you have heard of it?
>> Okay. I mean, does that game cross a
line?
Can somebody describe this?
>> I mean, I get an idea from the title.
>> Attent it's it's kind of a Super
Nintendo era styled RPG. It's it it has
you walking around in a sort of Final
Fantasy Nintendo
era kind of graphics with quotes and
dialogue that have been
um that have been collected from the
actual news reports uh or and you know
the the deliverables um uh diaries and
stuff like that
and uh and yeah it it it it is largely
about the events leading up to and the
massacre itself and yes you do go around
and I I can't remember whether you
actually
>> you do everything
>> yeah you you shoot
You have to plant you you have to sneak
into the school. I forget which one you
start off as either, you know, gold or
Harris, but you you pick up your friend.
It's very RPG-ish in the beginning where
you're in your room because you touch
objects and it gives flashbacks to like
your friendship with this guy like
learning how to make pipe bombs behind
the convenience store and you pick them
up, you go to the school, you have to
sneak in and plant some bombs and after
those go off and you move through the
school and you're shooting and um it's
interesting. Brian fire this five times
now, but I showed it to a class once uh
in Ohio, my old school, and
we're I'm like sneaking into the school,
right? And there are security cameras
you have to avoid and uh students who
can't be seen by them either. And
there's a point where, you know, I'm
trying to manipulate the character and
and everyone class like, "Oh, that way,
that way, that way. Oh, oh, you know,
you blew it. You got seen. You got
kicked out. You get it." And it was like
this moment of like typical gaming. Ah,
I did it. And then you realize like I
got kicked out of the school because I
was trying to plant a bomb. This was
based on something that really happened.
And it was that moment of like you were
saying with the friendly fire and not,
you know, not sure who you're shooting.
And it was like, wow.
>> You know, this is something that made me
think about what about all those other
games where I'm happy to kill people and
I don't really think about the
consequences. And this is a game where
you were forced to. say I think there's
a really interesting parallel in a film
um that I can think of with the battle
of Alers. I don't know if you've seen
this, but so there's this scene where
you're following um the insurgents who
are these two women who've managed to
smuggle bombs into a cafe which is
basically just a a civilian hangout
which is largely um frequented by the
the ruling French um section of society
there. And there's this incredibly tense
scene where they're trying to like leave
their bombs
in the cafe without being detected and
get out of there. And you're like, "Oh
my god,
are they going to be able to make it? I
hope that they can bomb this cafe." And
you're like,
>> "What are they thinking? This is
terrible."
And it definitely you definitely have
that same kind of tension though. Yeah.
I feel like people spend devote too much
emotional energy into getting offended.
Um people really pour their heart and
souls into getting offended by things.
Um and the the line for me is is it does
it advocate and is it instructional?
If it's not either of those two things,
it doesn't affect me really. And if you
really want to go out and play some
messed up it's not my none of my
business.
and my line is not going to be the same
as your line. It's not going to be the
same as someone else's line. And because
there is no easily definable line, it
really scares me that someone could
define a line. And since since I don't
like that idea, I'd rather say that as
long as it's not advoc,
you know, my attitudes are so liberal
and someone else's attitudes might be so
conservative and oh god, someone else's
attitudes might be even more liberal
than mine. and be okay with things that
I wouldn't feel comfortable with. If I
was allowed to draw a line, someone else
could draw it somewhere, you know,
either before or after, and that would
just mess everything up. And and so, you
know, that that that's how I kind of
feel about it. And I think that the
environment right now kind of is tends
towards that. Um, in that
>> what
>> the the line drawing the
>> tends towards line drawing.
>> Yeah. People in general are not people
who make games are not intrinsically on
average really messed up and so tend to
make stuff that they feel generally
comfortable with. Uh and those who are
messed up, you know, I mean you just
draw attention to them really by giving
them publicity anyway. But but uh for
every person who says that that you know
what what game like Diablo II got an M
rating because of violence. Now if you
look at it today, it's like little
sprites whacking at each other, you
know, but that was the line back then.
and and if that's the line today then
that this stuff is is just absolutely
horrendous and should not be
disseminated. I think it should be and
someone else might think that what I
think is okay is not okay and it's just
going to be what I think is not okay is
okay and
it's very complicated.
>> Just got to get death threats.
>> Yeah.
>> For releasing this game. I I strongly
like to
uh to to agree with the a lot of effort
being put into the line drawing u and
especially public discussion
uh the the the public display of hand
drawing the line here mostly by
politicians but people with with some
sort of u
>> possibly self often self-interested
agenda you know it's like for um both
and both by the game industry and
It seems it seems like there's more
effort
either being used to figure out what is
offensive and what is not offensive than
to possibly
uh to discuss the the the need that some
things can should be able to offend.
Then we should have stuff that allow
that that that needs to exist. Well,
then because it's so hard to actually
figure out where the line is. It's like
then then there needs to be some stuff
that crosses because maybe the line you
can't draw.
>> Yeah. And it's a method to desensitize
adults to violence. There's so much
violence these days. Be better if you
didn't freak out at every level.
>> I think it's totally okay to be freaked
out at things. I think that you should
definitely say when you're offended by
something and I think that should be
open to debate like whether something is
like a decent artistic expression or
>> but I mean
>> I mean like so there's there's a
difference between
stating that you find something
offensive and attempting to have these
things banned or right so
>> I agree and I'm totally fine with people
wasting words on on saying whether it's
like
>> no clearly But as long as because you
are offended, you think I shouldn't be
able to look at it. That's that's the
problem.
>> Okay.
>> Or even or even better, if by by being
offended, you get to now make your
point. You know, it's like, you know,
this is this is why this offends me and
this is these are my reasons for it
might be more informative and actually
better for society to get that those
ideas in the open.
>> People also get offended by proxy. This
doesn't offend me, but I can see how it
would affect other
>> well and people are I think there's also
a conflation of of taking offense and
discomfort. Um because you know playing
these games might be uncomfortable. Um
and I don't think that's necessarily a
bad thing, you know, if makes you think
about like what Ellen is saying or like
this game combat massacre if it makes
you think about things in a different
way or like that film. I mean, and
especially games have the ability to
kind of provoke that in you to make you
think because you're the one, especially
these games that force you to do certain
things. It's like, well, and I mean,
think about is there a game that you
absolutely refuse to play because, you
know, there was something in it that you
just really did not want to do.
>> So, that's fine. Yeah, I think we'll end
there.