Hey everyone.
Um, today and this week we are going to
talk about the a connection between
homogeneous dynamics and projection
theory. Um today is by the way the first
day of the Simon's lectures. Marina
Vioska is giving them this year and
she's going to be talking about sphere
packing and um I got interested in this
two years ago when Alon Lynen Strauss
came to give the Simon's lectures and he
was talking about homogeneous dynamics
and he explained a little bit this
connection with projection theory and I
have been trying to understand it since
then. um and uh it's uh it's a pretty
geometric visual thing. So I brought
some tools with me and the goal of the
class is to try to understand visually
geometrically uh how homogeneous
dynamics is related to projection
theory. Um
okay so let's let's first say uh a
little bit what what is homogeneous
dynamics.
Okay. So we're going to uh be working
with spaces that have a lot of
symmetries. And so the spaces will come
from a league group. So G will be a
league group. Um for example, SLNR
and inside of G there'll be a discrete
subgroup.
So EG,
SLN Z.
And then we're going to be studying the
quotient space G mod gamma.
So this is called a homogeneous space.
So we'll see it has a lot of symmetries.
Um and so the homogeneous and
homogeneous dynamics is we're acting on
this homogeneous space.
Okay. Now what does dynamics mean? Um
suppose that H is a subgroup of G
and then if X is a point in G mod gamma
then we can look at H dox. So H acts on
G mod gamma. So you can talk about H dox
that's called an orbit. And the question
is to describe the orbits.
Okay. So let's make a picture. Um so in
actual group GR
G this um there might be some group
element and then um you could take a
co-et
h.g and that h might be non-compact so
that might go on forever but somehow
it's not that complicated. Yeah. for
taking the quotient gamma
is what are the conditions for gamma to
be a normal subgroup fill out this
question. So this so this object is not
a group
>> it's just a space
>> right so gamma is a so so the question
was about whether whether gamma is
normal um and the answer is gamma
doesn't have to be normal so this this
is not a normal subgroup of this that
means that this is not a group but it's
still a space
okay um so gm mod gamma oh and I I I'll
put something else so gmod gamma uh
where we'll assume that the volume of or
we'll be interested in cases where the
volume of G mod gamma is finite. So the
volume of G is infinite but the volume
of G mod gamma is finite. So G mod gamma
looks sort of like this.
Um, and so then there's a point X in
there and the orbit goes through X, but
then it wraps around
and the picture looks a lot more
complicated already. And we want to
understand what what does this do? Is it
um is it going to wrap back on itself
and just just go around over and over
again the same thing? Or is it going to
evenly distribute all over G mod gamma
or or something else?
Okay.
So to make it concrete, I'd like to
begin with a with a very simple warm-up
um which is with a commutative group. So
it's it's simpler than that.
Okay. So uh so I think the simplest
example of this is that G could be R2
and then gamma could be Z2. So G mod
gamma is uh R2 mod Z2. It's a Tors.
All right. And H is going to be a
subgroup of G. And let's say it's like a
one parameter subgroup.
I'll do a couple of examples. H could be
the subgroup T2 T
and R there's a subgroup of R2 and if we
do this what happens um so I'll
visualize G mod gamma as a square with
sides identified
um and if I were to take so let's say X
knot is like is just gamma which is an
element of G by gamma it's like you you
take the identity in G and push down.
Um, okay. So, what does the orbit
through x knot look like? Well, it's
this line of slope 2 looks like that
and then it comes back where it started
and it just keeps going like that. Okay.
And actually, it wouldn't be it's a
little harder to draw accurately, but it
wouldn't be different if you started at
any other point. So x if you start at
any point x then if I were to add 1
comma 2 that would be equal to x in r2
z2
and so actually every orbit is periodic.
So the conclusion in example one is that
h dox is periodic
for every x.
Okay. Example two, I'll take a different
one parameter subgroup t comma
square of 2t
t.
Okay. So now what happens?
Well, if I if I again start at x knot is
the identity. Um now I'm going up at
slope square of two
the top and keep going at slope square
root of two. And this time this will
this will never close up because uh the
slope is irrational. Um and in fact this
this orbit will be dense and even evenly
distributed.
So now what happens is that h dox
is dense
for every x.
Okay. I won't do a proof right now. Um
but um I'll make a remark there. So
there are several proofs but there's
there's a nice proof using for analysis
that we might talk about later if we if
we feel like it.
Okay. Questions or comments so far?
Okay. So we've seen two things that
could happen. The orbit could be
periodic and the orbit could be dense.
uh and we haven't yet seen other things
but we might wonder about whether other
things could happen and now we can shift
to a more complicated non-communive
group like SL2R
okay
um
so Now let's say G is SL2R
and gamma is SL2Z.
Okay. And um there's there are multiple
reasons for looking at these quotients G
mod gamma but one of them that comes up
for this particular example is that
these parameterize lises.
So gamma is this space of latises
in R2
with the property latticees lambda in R2
with the property that the area of R2
mod lambda is one.
Um so let's do a proof sketch.
So um any such lattice we can write as G
times the lattice Z ^2 where G is an
SL2R.
So you can make any lattice by starting
with with Z ^ squ and applying a a
linear transformation. Okay. However
there's more than one G that gives you
the same lambda. So um if H is in SL2Z
then HZ2 is Z2 and therefore G * HZ2 is
G * Z2 and these guys give you the same
lice. So the space of lises is G modulo
SL2Z.
Okay.
All right. Now, this uh space of lises G
mod gamma is not compact. Um and I will
give you an example of a sequence of
lises that don't converge to anything.
Don't have a subsequence that converge
to anything. So example we could take
lambdaepsilon
to be epsilon z direct sum epsilon
inverse z.
So this is a lattice which is very
skinny in one direction and very tall in
the other direction and has co- volume
one and as epsilon goes to zero this is
not going to converge to anything. So
the space of lises is not compact
and this is the only reason that the
space of lises is not compact. So a
definition k epsilon is a subset of g
mod gamma.
Kepsilon is defined to be the set of
lises. So that the minimum over nonzero
v in our lattice of the size v is at
least epsilon is greater than or equal
to let's say epsilon.
Okay. And there's a a proposition which
is called the moler criterion.
that says for every epsilon bigger than
zero kepsilon is compact.
Um so um so a picture of of G mod gamma
it's something like this. G mod gamma is
threedimensional so it's um not super
easy to draw. Um but over here so this
would be G mod gamma. There's this
non-compact part
and you make a cut off maybe here and
this stuff is K epsilon.
Okay. Um so I won't prove this in
detail. This is not super difficult. If
you think about uh two vectors that
generate lambda, um if there if we're in
k epsilon, the vectors definitely cannot
be too close to zero. And you can also
always find two vectors that are not too
giant because the area of the thing is
one. This gives you sort of a compact
set of choices of these two vectors.
Okay, so it gives a little bit of
intuition about what the space gamma
looks like.
Okay. Now, inside of there, we have some
interesting one parameter subgroups
of of of G of SL2R.
So, one of them is the unipotent
subgroup. So, that's the set of 1 T 01
T and R. And the other one is the
diagonal subgroup. So this is I'll call
this so it's the set of u t. So this
matrix is u subt and there's the
diagonal subgroup e to the r e to the
minus r 0
little r the reals and this I'll call
the set of a sub r. So this matrix here
is called a sub r. Okay. So those are
one parameter subgroups. And now we can
ask our question about what the orbits
look like.
Okay. Um,
cool. So, um, so there's a theorem that
goes back to the 1930s. Headed in the
1930s,
he said that a U orbit
is either
periodic
or dense.
Okay. And but in contrast there's a
guess I'll also call it a theorem. I
don't know who proved this when um that
uh d orbit does not have to be
maybe neither
periodic
nor dense.
Okay, let me say something more than
that about how these d orbits can be
really quite complicated. So here's G
mod gamma and inside of G mod gamma pick
out three small balls that are not too
close together. So B1, B2, B3 are small
balls.
Okay. Then for any sequence of ones and
twos.
So for example the sequence 1 one two
one two one two two two one any sequence
um there exists an x in gamma
so that
the d- orbit of x
never hits b3
and the d- orbit of x hits b1 and b2
many times.
in this sequence.
So, what must this orbit look like?
Um, let's see. So, first it hits B1 and
it goes through there. Then it goes
around and it the next thing it hits is
also B1.
And it goes around and the next thing it
hits is B2. and it keeps going and the
next thing it hits is B1 and so on
and it never touches B3.
Okay, so this orbit apparently is not
dense because it never intersects B3 and
it is not periodic if this sequence is
not periodic. So it's something else.
Okay. So, so d orbits can do this
somewhat crazy thing, somewhat chaotic
thing that we're anyway. Um, but U
orbits can't. U orbits can be periodic.
Um so if you were to take
u of x knot um
uh this is periodic
and the reason is um so if you take so x
so x knot corresponds to the matrix 1
one
uh times time s 2z
so now if I were to take one one tx knot
that's equal to x knot in gy gamma.
Uh if t is an integer.
So that's a periodic orbit. It makes a
closed circle in in gm mod gamma.
Um okay. Uh but if you were to start
with a kind of weird looking choice of x
knot um and you were to do this then it
won't there won't be any obvious
periodicity.
Um so for most
for most x so that's that's let's that's
let's let's suppose now x is uh 2
01 over 2
okay so now what happens when we and
then times sl2z
so now what is
ut of x that's one t 20 one over
Um,
okay. So, that'll be 2,
that'll be
2, that'll be t over 2.
Um, this will be zero.
This will be 1 over 2.
And
oh, that one might be periodic. I think
I picked the wrong example.
Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Sorry. Um that was
unhelpful.
Okay. So, so to see why they're not all
periodic, let's let's instead try to
visualize what is happening to the
lattice.
So a point uh a point x corresponds to a
lice
uh lambda x.
And if you think about what what is
happening if you take gx
that corresponds to the lice
g of lambda of x. So g is in sl2r. It
acts on r2. It moves a lattice to
another lattice and that's what the
action is.
Okay. And so now G is going to be UT.
And the way UT acts on R2 is by
shearing.
So UT acts on R2
um by shearing. So I'll I'll do it this
way.
So I'll draw some points in R2. And
perhaps coincidentally, these points
come from a lattice. Um, and then I'll
illustrate what UT does. Um, so if this
is the point P, then this over here is
UT of P.
It's a shearing motion. And so the
shearing motion moves everybody
horizontally. And it moves you
horizontally, but at an amount
proportional to your height. So this one
moves horizontally, but a bit less. And
this one moves horizontally and a bit
more.
Okay. Now what would it mean? So this so
so you start with a lattice and when we
apply this uniport orbit to the lattice
every point in the lattice is shearing.
What would it mean if the orbit was
periodic? Well, it would mean that this
point this lattice point is shearing
along and eventually it reaches another
lattice point.
So
if ux is periodic,
um that implies that each
lattice point
is at the same height
as another
lattice point,
right? So there must be another lattice
point somewhere over here.
Okay, but now think about this. This
difference is also in our lattice
because a lattice is a subgroup
and this distance is is horizontal. So
this is
um if and only if um there exists if and
only if lambda of x contains a vector of
the form x1 comma 0.
So most lises don't contain a vector on
the x-axis. So u * x is usually not
periodic.
And then um the difficult theorem is
that in that situation u * x is dense.
Okay,
cool. So this is the situation in SL2
and the situation in other league groups
say SLNR for larger N is more difficult
and more recent but there are similar
theorems. Um so for SL3R
uh for SL3R Margulus and Donnie in the
1980s proved an analog of this theorem
and then for all the SLNR and and all
the groups Ratner around 1990 proved an
analog of this theorem.
Um cool.
Okay.
Um
so that's a little summary of some kinds
of theorems.
There's some motivations for this.
There's some motivation from Yeah.
>> Just a kind of a question about the link
between the lises and the elements of
the uh quotient group. Um so up up there
in the definition of kp epsilon there's
kind of what looks like some sort of
norm the minimum size of v or the
non-zero vector v in the does that
generate the same topology as the the
quotient topology from so
um
so the question is about the topology of
gmod gamma and how the topology of gmod
gamma plays with this definition of
Kepsilon.
Yeah. Um in a moment we'll put a metric
on G mod gamma and that's what its
topology is. It's a manifold. It has um
topology manifold. Um and um this thing
here is a continuous function on on our
um on our uh space of lises.
Another way to say what the topology is
is you know if you describe a lattice as
the span of two particular vectors if
you slightly perturb those particular
vectors that will be a slight change in
the in the space of latises
>> is is that definition similar anyway to
have a minimum I guess you're right not
quite thanks
Okay. So when I introduced homogeneous
dynamics, I mentioned some application
in number theory. The uh uh connection
to the Oenheim Davenport conjecture
which is about the values of quadratic
forms. Um and it's a nice that that's a
nice connection. I feel like we already
talked about a little bit and if you
wanted to read about it, it's also easy
to read about it. Um, so I wanted to
spend the class time on um, uh, yeah.
Okay. So I wanted So okay, so I wanted
to spend the class time on trying to get
intuition for why something like this
would be true and also maybe why
something like this would be false. And
um, there are many different ways of
thinking about homogeneous dynamics.
There's a big literature, but I want to
highlight the way of of connecting it to
projection theory. Um, and that's not
one of the classical ways. It's actually
not super easy to find in the
literature. Um the the
um
um so it appears in these recent works
of Lynden Strauss and Mohammadi and
their collaborators and they're trying
they're doing you know the cutting edge
of homogeneous dynamics and the
particular problem they're trying to
solve is to do first of all these
higherdimensional things that Margulus
and Ratner and Donnie were doing and
second of all instead of having a
qualitative theorem like this to have a
quantitative theorem that says If you're
not approximately periodic for some
length, then you're, you know,
quantitatively
uh dense.
Um, okay. And at that point, the they
had they ran into some things that the
many interesting classical techniques
did could not do or could not obviously
do and they invented this new technique,
this connection to projection theory.
But in hindsight, you could also look
back at the oldest theorems, the oldest
theorems like this one, and you could
approach it using projection theory. And
it may not be the best approach to this
theorem. It's certainly not the only
approach to this theorem, but but uh but
it's a it's a way of looking at it and
and quite a visual way of looking at at
what's going on. So the goal of the
class is to try to explain um uh
uh the how projection theory could help
to understand something like this.
Okay.
Okay. Um great. So we're going to do
some geometry. So next we we need to
think about the geometry on the space G
mod gamma. Um and um
uh and how that geometry interacts with
the action.
Oops.
[Applause]
Okay. So geometry of gamma.
Okay. So
first we'll talk about the right action
of G on itself.
Right? So if G is in G, there's a right
action which is a map from G to itself.
And the right action G of H is H. and
you multiply by G on the right side. So
these groups don't commute. So it's, you
know, it matters which side you put it
on. And actually you have to be quite
quite careful in this story.
Okay. So that's a map from from G to
itself.
Um,
now we're going to use that to start to
put a geometry on G. Going to have a
right invariant
metric
M.
Okay.
So, how does this work? Um, so, so what
does that mean? So, M is going to be a
Romanian metric
on G and for every G and G, we have this
right action G. So, that's a map from
our group with its metric to itself. And
this is for every G and G, this is an
isometry.
That's what it that's what it means to
have a right invariant metric. Where do
they come from? Um the idea is that
we'll put a metric at the origin and
then we'll use R subg to help define the
metric at every other place.
Um
okay.
Okay. So um a lot of what we'll say here
works for any group but to be concrete
I'm going to stick to the group SL2R
the tangent space at the origin. So E E
is or the the identity I was using the
word origin I should say identity T is E
is the identity in the group. The
tangent space in the identity of this
group is the space of matrices A B C D
with A + D equal to Z.
Um so this is not a deep factor. This is
so SL2R is matrices A B C D where A D
minus BC equals 1 and the identity is a
is a matrix that's sitting in there in
R4. So it's the the group is a
threedimensional manifold in R4 and this
is just its tangent space in the usual
sense.
Okay. So that's it tangent space. So now
m is going to be a metric
on t and I can specify it by by
specifying who an orthonormal basis and
this choice doesn't matter super a lot
but um but there's a convenient choice.
So my orthonormal basis
of Mn is going to be 0 1 0 0. So which
I'll call u 0 0 1 0 which I'll call u
tilda and then uh 1 / 2 0 - 1 /2
which I'll call D.
um these root twos are not actually
important but this this orthonormal
basis happens to be the orthoral basis
that corresponds to the metric where you
just take the metric on R4 and restrict
it to to uh this subspace.
Okay.
So now how will we define the metric
elsewhere?
So now suppose G is in our group. Um
R subg
of the identity is G. It's easy to check
from the definition of R subg.
And therefore R subg defines a map from
T tangent space E of G to the tangent
space G of G. And this map is an
isomeorphism.
We have a metric over here. We use this
map to define a metric over there.
So now we define
mg which is a a metric or inner product
MG on TG.
So that
RG goes from T E G comma M KN to T G
comma MG. So that that's an isometry.
Okay. And then it's an exercise to check
that this thing we just defined is right
invariant. So So
[Applause]
that all of these maps are isometries
everywhere.
[Applause]
Okay.
All
right. So now because m is right
invariant
um
uh
we we get a metric it it sends to a
metric m on g mod g.
So how does that work? Um so we have
like all of G have a projection map pi
to G mod gamma. We have a point X and G
mod gamma. And X has many pre-im images.
Um so X is equal to say little G *
little G little little H* gamma.
So
okay
so the pre-image of X is these many
different points. Okay. Now I have a
metric upstairs and I'd like to try to
define a metric downstairs in a natural
way. So I'd like to define a metric
here. So for each of these lifts
upstairs, I can take the metric there
and I can use the map pi and I can
produce a metric over here.
There's no canonical choice of which of
these purple points in the pre-image I
should use. But because our metric
upstairs is right invariant, they all
give the same answer. And so there's a
coherent choice.
Okay.
So that gives us a metric on GMO gap.
All right.
So now have also a left action
of G on G.
Okay. So if G is in G, the left action
of G is also a map from G to itself.
Left action G of H is G inverse on the
left H. So the word left and left action
is because the the thing that comes from
G is over here. Um the inverse is not
super important in our discussion today,
but it causes this to behave correctly
when you compose elements in the group.
And so it's traditional to do this.
Okay.
Right.
So um
SLG
is not
an isometry
of our group with our right invariant
metric
and that's very important. It's very
important to our whole discussion to
understand um geometrically how this
operation uh affects this space. Right.
Okay. So, let's see what happens. Um,
right. So, it's easiest to see what
happens around the identity and you can
do it starting at other points too.
So here's the identity and here's some G
and I have a map the left action by G
inverse that takes the identity over
here.
And now this action it's not clear from
what we've said whether it preserves the
metric. In fact it distorts the metric.
Um but how can we figure out what what
this mapping is doing to the metric?
Well, our metric was defined to be right
invariant. So there's a map going the
other direction. The right uh action by
G inverse that takes G back to the
identity. And this one we do understand
what it does to the metric. It's an
isometry.
So if I want to understand what this map
did to the metric, it's a reasonable
idea to look at this and then this.
That part is an isometry. So all of the
distortion of the metric came from this
part.
Um and this composition is going to be a
little easier to understand.
Okay. So what happens if I if I do this?
If I take a left action by G inverse and
a right action by G inverse and I apply
it to H.
These these guys uh commute with each
other. We'll see when we write it out.
So, um, I don't have to be super careful
what order to write them in. Yeah.
>> What's that?
>> Yeah, I guess I should really write it
in the other order, although it doesn't
matter.
So, I want you to imagine I started with
E or maybe somebody else near E. I
applied left G inverse and then I
applied right G inverse and we're gonna
see what happens.
Okay. So just from the formulas this is
right action of G inverse of GH
and that's GHG inverse. So actually it's
something natural and important. It's
conjugating.
So I'll call this uh C subg of H
conjugating by G of H.
Okay, cool. So conjugating by H then
induces a map from the tangent space of
E to itself.
Right? So so conjugating by G is a map
from the group to itself and it sends
the identity to the identity and
therefore it sends the tangent space to
the tangent space. All right. And uh we
can see what we we can write we can
write this down and we can see what it
does. Um and
um if if this thing is distorting the
geometry it means that this thing was
distorting the geometry and in exactly
the same way.
So we could say it's you could say more
than this but the singular values
of LG inverse are equal to the singular
values
of um CG.
All right. So what you know what they
are depends on G. So I'm going to pick a
nice G and we're actually going to
compute them to see how the geometry is
being distorted. All
[Applause]
right. So the interesting uh G's are
going to be from those one parameter
subgroups up there. And the one that
looks up looks the nicest and where this
is calculation is the most important is
for that diagonal matrix A R. So we're
going to compute what that does.
Okay. So I'm going to look at C A R
that goes from the tangent space to
itself.
Um so the tangent space is the set of
matrices a b c d with a + d equals zero.
Let's call this matrix m
and we're
so c a r of m is a r m a r inverse.
So that's e to the r e to the minus r a
b c d e to the minus r e to the r.
Right? So this is a sub r. That's just
the definition. This is a sub r inverse.
So I switched the minus signs.
Okay? So
I did this very carefully. Uh it's not
super instructive to watch me do it very
carefully. So I'm just going to write
down the answer.
It's a d e 2 r b eus 2 r c.
So this conjugation what it does is it
doesn't change the diagonal. It
magnifies
this component and it uh demagnifies
that component. So that happens to be
something we can describe really nicely
in the orthonormal basis that I picked.
All right. So,
C A R of U.
So,
is E 2R U.
C A R of utilda is E to the minus 2 R U
tilda and C A R D is D.
This conjugation behaves really nicely
in this basis. But you can see that it
does not preserve the metric. It
stretches that one. it compresses that
one and it preserves that one.
Okay. So the conclusion from this is
that l a r inverse
uh
of u
the length of that is e 2r
l a r inverse of u tilda has length e to
the minus 2r
l a r inverse of d has length one and uh
it also preserved angles right so We
just stretched things but we didn't tilt
anything. So
l a r inverse of u of ut tilda and of d
are orthogonal.
So this describes how the left action by
this matrix is distorting the geometry
of the space.
Okay. And we also can make some kind of
picture. Um
so suppose this is a quote unquote cube
in G. Um where this is the
U direction this is the utilda direction
and the direction into the board is the
D direction. So what will happen to it
when we do this? Um the U direction gets
really long the utild direction gets
really short other direction is
preserved. So it looks kind of like
that.
Okay.
Um, one thing that you can notice from
the picture and from the calculation is
that um, while L inverse distorts
lengths, distorts the metric,
it nevertheless preserves the volume.
Okay. So that's how the left action uh
distorts the geometry.
Okay.
And we also have a left action.
of G on G mod gamma,
right? And so how does that work? Um
well, LG of H gamma is just G inverse H
gamma
because the gamma is on the right and
this guy is on the left. They sort of
don't interfere with each other. And so
this is an actual group action.
Um so LG maps
G mod gamma to itself
and it is a bjection.
It distorts the metric
but it preserves
the ball.
Okay. And maybe I should say we just
computed this carefully for a particular
element G which is these diagonal
elements. You could take any G there
don't doesn't have to be diagonal. It
will distort the metric in some
different way. Every G is different but
they all preserve the volume. We didn't
really prove that because I just did one
example but it's true.
>> Yeah.
>> Are you able to show that by showing
like that in a second? uh the u u of t
one parameter subgroup um does it change
the volume and like do those two two one
prime subgroups generate a g of pump
>> yeah so the question was if we wanted to
to check that it preserve that that
every G preserves the volume it would be
enough to check a few G's that generate
it um and um yeah so so we could if we
did the computation with the potent one
that would basically finish the job okay
so it's not that difficult um we also
could just describe the G as you know
ABC D
um and and then the computation a little
messy but could just check once and for
all. There's probably a better way of
doing it but it's not my part of that.
Okay, cool.
Okay. So now we can say um
all right.
So now important and interesting part of
this story is um
um
what is the difference between the
unitary ones and the diagonal ones?
And there are many different answers to
this. Um, we could come back to it
multiple times,
but I'm gonna mention one way of looking
at it which will start to get us to the
projection theory.
Um, so there's a special feature of
unitary matrices that we saw also maybe
by coincidence, but it also came up when
we were talking about SL2 of FP, which
what we saw there basically is that
something cool happens when you
conjugate a unitary matrix by a diagonal
matrix. And that that is a special
feature of unitary matrices and it
really helps to understand.
Okay.
So what is special
about
unitary
matrices?
Okay. So there's a computation that if I
take a unitary matrix and I conjugate it
by a diagonal matrix. So I have e to the
r e to the minus r
potent.
>> Uni potent. Yeah, thanks.
>> Yes, thank you. Uni potent.
Okay,
so if you multiply this out, you get
this.
So if you're interested in a uni potent
matrix UT where this T is really large,
you can get at it by starting with U1
and conjugating it by one of these
diagonal matrices.
Um so let's let's say U0 T. This is a
set of unitary matrices. This is UT
t goes from zero to t. And so to
understand an orbit we you know our goal
is to understand
um
u 0t of x where t is large
and because of this slick little formula
we can write u0 t x.
So let's let's say
um we can write it as
a r
u01
a - r of x
where e 2r t.
Why is this helpful? So this here is
just some point in uh in G mod gamma.
It's not the point we started with. It's
some other point but it's just a point.
This here is a short unitary orbit.
Um short unitary orbit isn't so
intimidating to to draw. And then all
the action is here. And the question is
what does this uh map do to a short
unitary orbit?
Okay, so if we make a picture,
here's our G mod gamma. Here's our new
starting point a minus rx.
Here's our orbit. It's not very long. It
doesn't wrap around yet, so it's not
that intimidating. That's um this guy
short unitary orbit. Okay. And now we're
going to take this map of Gamma to
itself and we're going to apply it and
we want to see what happens to this blue
thing.
>> Again, uni potent. Thanks short.
Thanks.
Okay. And we can also make a remark a r
is a subgroup. So a r is like a1 to the
r or a little r to the big r over little
r
big r little over r is a natural number.
So we don't have to do this all at once.
We could take a less dramatic map of gi
gamma to itself and we repeat that over
and over again. We want to see what
happens to this thing. Right?
Okay.
Okay. So we are led to try so we led to
a goal which is to try to understand
and visualize
the action of a little r and ga
and if we understand that really well we
should be able to understand this orbit.
Okay.
[Applause]
All right. So, how might we try to get a
handle on this? Let's look at a
fundamental domain. So, f is a
fundamental domain of gamma.
So, f is a subset just of g. And I'll
draw it as a cube. It's not literally a
cube.
um uh god gamma is not compact. So f
cannot be compact. So it should have
like a little tail that's going off to
infinity. Um but for what I'm about to
say that's not super important.
And actually by the way the whole story
also makes sense for gamas that are
co-compact and then you would this
picture would be better. Okay. So now uh
we'd like to understand what a does. So
the first step is I'm going to apply AR.
And we just thought about what AR does
geometrically, how it distorts the
geometry. Um we were looking at what it
does to the metric, but it's very
similar to what it does to like a unit
cube. Um so this thing um is going to be
so this is a r of of um of f which is
still sitting in the group g. It got
longer in one way shorter in another
way. The real thing would have more
dimensions than this but just to give
the idea.
Okay. Now the next thing that happens is
we have to apply the quotient map. So pi
is the map from G to G mod gamma.
Um and when we do that I'll visualize G
mod gamma again as this fundamental
domain. And what happens is that this
thing is going to kind of wrap around
the fundamental domain.
Okay. So it will look something like
this.
There it'll go in there. Um
okay it's very difficult to draw this
well um this map from the fundamental
domain to itself is going to be of
ejection right so somehow this is going
to wrap around it's going to cover every
point exactly once uh it's like a some
sort of beautiful jigsaw puzzle I don't
know how to draw that so I'll just do
I'll just have this come out here and
I'll do sort of a dot dot dot
okay and then I don't know if We were
visualizing if we had something of
interest eventually it would be some
unipotent orbits but maybe initially
we're interested in what happens to
that. So in the first step
it did this
and then in the next step we see this
and this
somewhere over here we see this. Okay.
All right.
Cool. Um all right. So
>> yeah,
>> why does the map have to be a bjection?
Like why can't the projection map sort
of not be injective?
>> Yeah. So the question is um why is this
map a bjection?
Um so we were saying so this this uh I
guess is actually there um
um right? So we said earlier that the
left action of G god gamma goes to
itself as a bjection
and if we believe that then if we start
with the fundamental domain we have one
representative of each point in G mod
gamma and then we end up in back in G
mod gamma we should cover everything
exactly once if this is a bjection.
Okay. Now why was this a bjection? So
what is this map? It's the map H gamma
goes to G inverse H gamma.
So why is this a bjection? Um
um
right. So uh it's injective that means
that if H1
G inverse H1 gamma is equal to G inverse
H2 gamma then um H1 gamma equals H2
gamma. That's what it means for it to be
injective.
So is this clear?
Yeah. You multiply on both sides by G.
Okay. Serjective.
That means that um
for every
uh
every H2
in
in in G there exists H1 in G. So that G
inverse H1 gamma is H2 gamma.
So yeah, we set these equal and solve
for G.
>> I guess that convertibility.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Um,
right.
I have to say I went through this too
when I when I drew these pictures. I
asked myself like, is this actually
going to like fold up and cover
everything exactly once? And then I was
like, is it really vigive?
Yeah, it should happen.
Yeah.
Okay.
I guess you can make easier fun examples
where that are more linear. So you just
have like a matrix acting on R2 mod Z2
or something like that. Um and then the
fundamental domain is a square and you
can draw what happens to it and you can
look up. So this was inspired by the by
that example. They called that the cat
map, a particular map. And instead of a
smiley face, they draw a cat. They've
better artistic skills than me. You can
Google that and see some nice pictures
like this.
Okay, cool. Okay. So here, so so this um
this thing LG LL with with this diagonal
action, they've broken it into two
steps. And out of these two steps, I
find this one quite confusing.
uh it's difficult to write this down
sufficiently accurately and then to say
what happened here and and you know did
this come back over here over there when
it wrapped you know where did it wrap
and that all of that seems very
intimidating to me so very difficult to
write down in a clean way but this first
step is not so bad right
um and so we're going to try to
understand the first step very well and
use that to see how much we can figure
out about the about this map um LG
acting on our homogeneous space.
Okay. Now the object that we want to
follow is not a smiley face but a
unipotent orbit.
Okay.
So
let's see here.
Okay. This we can erase all of it.
Okay. So I erased something that is
useful for us. So recall we worked out
um that the left map by a r inverse we
found its singular values and singular
vectors. So in the u direction um the
length of this is e to the 2r
and in the utilda direction the length
is eus 2 r
and in the diagonal direction the length
is one.
Um
so this is this is if we're thinking of
l a r inverse from t e g to t a
right and this little u
this is also the tangent direction
of our group u.
So that group is going to get stretched
which is the same thing we saw in the
computation over there.
So um
step one so if we start with a single
unipotent orbit starts at some point we
have like this.
So that's u01 of some point x. What
happens when we apply L?
Okay. Well, this thing is going to get
tall and skinny
and the direction that got stretched is
the direction of this orbit. So now
we're going to have a long orbit
and the height of this thing is e to the
2R. Then we're going to quotient.
Um, so when we quotient, I don't know
exactly where it's going to go,
but it will go along. It'll go out the
top and come in the bottom somewhere.
And then we'll have a bunch of these. So
we'll have like
e to the 2 r
u orbits of length one.
and I have no idea where they are. So,
we haven't made any progress yet on our
main question, which is to see if these
are distributing kind of evenly.
Um, but now we can start again.
Move this over here.
So, now we have a bunch of unipotent
orbits
and we're going to stretch them out.
Now, what happens when we stretch them
out this time?
Well,
okay. So, each one of them got longer.
It's going to go from the bottom to the
top.
But also, um,
there's also some compression which is
kind of in this direction. And that
could potentially cause some orbits to
get closer together or not. And this is
the part that we have to understand
really carefully.
[Applause]
>> All right.
>> So this box is some small box.
>> Yeah. So this Yeah.
>> Yeah. That's right. That's right. So
this this box here is a fundamental
domain.
So it's scale one
and sure it could be around the
identity. Thing I most want to convey in
this class is a feeling for how this map
is like twisting and distorting these
curves. All right. And so I'm going to
try to make a really big picture of it
there. I also brought with me some um
props.
[Applause]
All right.
So, I'm going to sort of visualize our
fundamental domain or maybe a piece of
it as a cylinder. And now I'm going to
draw some unipotent orbits in different
colors. And they all go from the bottom
to the top.
Um
maybe I'll draw three of them.
Okay. Now what happens to this picture?
So, first of all, it's going to stretch
that way. That part's not that hard to
imagine. It would go off the board, so
I'm not going to emphasize that. Then
each one of these uh slices, so we have
some sort of slices. Let's say this is
tals 0 up to tals 1. Other t's in the
middle. Each one of these slices, one
direction is going to be squished and
the other direction is going to stay the
same.
So let's say that at t = 1 cross-section
of this picture, I see a triangle
that looks like this.
And there's going to be some direction
that gets compressed.
When I apply l inverse, if that
direction gets compressed, the output is
going to look like so.
And that has been actually worked out so
that this blue and yellow get kind of
squished together.
And the orange is still there.
And at t equals 0,
if I look at the bottom disc, I have the
same picture.
And there's some direction that's going
to be compressed.
And it's not the same direction. I'll do
somewhat arbitrarily that one.
That one. Okay. So,
compress that way. That will look sort
of like so. And the blue point will be
over here. And the yellow and orange
point will be somewhat close together.
Okay. And as you look at all the
intermediate heights, you'll have a
similar picture. But this compression
direction is going to be changing
continuously as you go up.
Okay. All right. So I'm not sure if this
will be helpful, but I brought several
props to try to illustrate this
important process. So if you imagine
that you have a bunch of unipotent
orbits in your homogeneous space like so
and we apply a okay first of all they
will stretch this way and second of all
there will be some compression. So maybe
at the top they might get smooshed
together this way and at the bottom they
might get smooshed together sort of a
different way sort of like this
or
um if this piece of Play-Doh is this
cylinder here what's going to happen to
it when we apply the map? Well, it's
going to get taller
and it's going to get squished and maybe
the top will get squished sort of that
way, but the bottom will get squished
sort of that way and in the middle it'll
get squished some direction sort of in
the middle and that will if I had done
it carefully practiced it at home it
produces something that's sort of like a
helix.
Okay,
cool.
Okay, so let me say briefly why this is
relevant. Um,
and then if we have time, if we feel
like it, we could try to do some
computations with matrices to check it.
Okay. So, why is this relevant? Well, if
you had a, you know, a situation like
this,
then
um
yeah. Okay, let's go back up here.
So, this guy is really tall. We're going
to cut it into a sequence of pieces that
each have height one. And then each one
of these pieces is going to fold back
in.
Right.
So over here there is a an unused color.
There's a purple piece over here.
Okay. That purple piece is going to fold
back in over here.
Can you see that?
All right. And then there are a bunch of
other pieces in different colors. Those
other pieces will somehow get slotted in
in an order that I don't understand at
all, but they'll all go somewhere.
All right. Now, inside of this purple
piece, so over here we have uh a yellow
orbit, a blue orbit, and an orange
orbit. Let's just focus on those three.
They aren't all are going to pass
through here. And we could have
um the blue orbit and the orange orbit
and the yellow orbit all kind of spread
out from each other. Or we could be that
they are smooshed together close to each
other.
Anyway, whatever happens here, this is
just slotted in over here. So that will
tell us how they're spaced over here.
Okay. So um
uh
when we have something like this that
will produce two unit length unipotent
orbits over here in this purple thing
that are really close to each other and
that that phenomenon is the enemy of the
unipotent orbit spreading out. Unipot
orbit is definitely going to be really
long but it may not spread out because
it may have many segments that are
really close to each other.
Okay. Um
so let me scribe.
So to prove
that u 0t of x spreads out
we want to prove
that coincidences
of this type are rare.
Okay. And why are they rare? Well,
they're rare because this compression
angle is rotating smoothly as we vary t.
And so even though there may be one
projection that smooshes a lot of things
together,
we have learned in this course that if
you look at the projection in all
different directions, most of them do
not smoosh things together very much.
And that forces this unipotent orbit to
spread out.
Sorry for so confused. Why does like the
direction get like compressed change
like from that picture after you apply L
A R inverse it's always
get long and
and get
another direction gets
>> Yeah. Yeah. Okay. All right. So the
question is why does this happen? And in
fact there was a point that the picture
that I drew up there sort of makes it
look like it doesn't happen.
Right.
[Applause]
All right.
So in my picture I this is not exactly
accurate but but I I drew it as though
this map was just a linear map that
takes a cube to a rectangular solid. and
I drew it as though well I tried to show
that this would okay so these unipotent
orbits are more or less vertical.
All right so here's what so here's what
wouldn't work. So if the unipotent
orbits were literally vertical and if
this map was literally a linear map then
this would not happen the compression
direction would be the same at every
height.
All right. So, um I think you have to
kind of
pick
um this this this Lee group is like, you
know, it's a sub manifold of R4, but if
you want to represent it in coordinates
in three dimensions, you have to make a
choice. There's not a completely
canonical choice.
So, um, we could make the choice that,
um, the unipotent orbits were literally
vertical.
And if we did that, this picture would
not be right anymore. Um, if if we did
that, then this would have a bit of a
twist. This would be more this would be
like a helixy thing.
Or another way of looking at it is I
think we could choose coordinates in
such a way that um this map was pretty
close to a linear map but then these
unipotent orbits would not be vertical
and instead they would kind of spiral a
little bit as you went up
and so the angle between two unipotent
guys would be changing.
Okay. Now at some point
you know why do you believe that?
So at some point we should do a
computation right. Um I don't think I'll
do it in the last two minutes but I'll
just say what you should do.
Um
okay so
we figured out which direction is
compressing. Um we could have written it
down a little bit more clearly but if if
you trace through our thoughts today at
any point in the homogeneous space if
you ask which is the tangent direction
that's going to get compressed when you
apply L we have a formula for it.
Okay. And then we can also say if you
have two nearby unipotent orbits and
down here at the bottom there's like a a
little vector between them as you go up
the orbit what what happens to that
vector. There's a formula for that too.
If you compare these two formulas you
will see that they don't match. So that
the the if if this direction initially
was the compression direction
compression direction if you follow it
up you don't get the compression
direction up here and you you can
compute it all with matrices.
>> Yeah
>> this just kind of saying is a curvature
tensor that's not zero any from the
guess one of the two one parameter
groups.
Yeah, the question is is is this saying
that this there's some kind of curvature
tensor that doesn't vanish? Maybe it's
it's not the remon curvature tensor, but
uh it might be something in that spirit.
Yeah.
>> The picture kind of makes it seem like
it stretches.
It's not periodic. Is there something
I'm missing?
Yeah, great question. Okay, the question
was this appears to be a proof sketch
that every orbit of the uniport group is
uh evenly distributed and we saw at the
beginning that that is not true. So what
did we what did we do wrong?
Okay. Um
all right. So this orbit we can write
this way.
All right. Actually, so let me say that
the the shortest answer to your
question, the key thing is that the cusp
of the homogeneous space is really
important here. And we were neglecting
the cusp. Um so you know the the cusp
produces a piece of the fundamental
domain that's really skinny and it
doesn't look like the rest of it. And
when something's in the cusp, it doesn't
apply.
Um and so actually Hedland proved
another theorem which is that if you
take a a co-compact subgroup gamma then
in Gmod gamma every unipotent orbit uh
is is dense and this is a sketch of the
proof of that theorem.
Okay. But now what goes wrong um is that
this a minus rx
could be very far in the cusp and then
our whole analysis is wrong. So what
what we've roughly shown is that either
our orbit is very well distributed or a
minus rx is deep in the cusp.
And if you unwind what that means about
x, it means that it's very close to
being a periodic or
cool. Okay. So, we'll talk a little more
about homogeneous dynamics on Thursday.
I'm not sure exactly what we'll say.
Maybe we'll fill in some things.