thank you uh my name is JJ I'm the uh
Chief scientist and co-founder of tupai
uh which is a startup SP of my lab MIT
uh focusing on Innovative optic
Solutions so today we all live in a
information era and nowadays more and
more information are now being delivered
and processed in the form of light as a
result the optical systems are also
getting larger in size and more complex
this has become a showstopper for many
applications so now if you look closely
into Optical system you found that they
really have not changed that much over
the past few decades on one hand you
have glass lenses that deliver high
performance but they have to be
fabricated using grinding and polishing
that is costly and not scalable on the
other hand you have polymer lenses or
plastic lenses that can be manufactured
at extremely low cost using moding but
they suffer from concerns in terms of
performance and
reliability when it comes to packaging
assembly you also have to put together
one of these lenses are one by one piece
by piece with a careful alignment
between them and as a result this Le to
traditional Optical modules that are
complex larg in size and also
costly so we at two Pi Optics have
developed this matter plus Optics
technology to address this challenge so
the main idea here is that we want to
leverage mature semiconductor technology
that's been developed in the IC industry
to transform Optics more specifically
unlike traditional Optics where we using
Cur curved surfaces to B propagation of
light we actually fabricate these tiny
little structures Optical antennas on a
wafer and they are designed so that they
can precisely control light proping
direction to impart different Optical
functions when it comes to packaging
assembly we can then actually stack and
bond multiple of these wers together
each of them containing array of this
flat Optics components with lithographic
Precision in the end we then dice them
each wafer into hundreds or thousands of
packaged miniaturized Optical modules so
the end product are this Optical modules
that has a fo factor of a small chip
that deliver high performance Superior
compared to glass lenses and also low
cost and scalable manufacturing similar
to that of plastic
Optics so now just show you a couple of
examples where our technology has
already been applied uh one example here
is a driver monitoring systems of DMS so
DMS are basically small cameras on
passenger vehicles uh they essentially L
drivers when they getting distracted in
driving so traditional DMS requires a
stack of glass and polymer lenses
they're complicated to assemble uh in
our case we can replace all of them with
one single piece of our met plus Optics
and this give rise to Superior thermal
and mechanical uh robustness which is
critical to meet the stringent demands
of Automotive
regulations at the same time we can also
provide higher resolution which is
important to improve the detection
accuracy and lower the force alarm rate
so through a collaboration with our
Foundry partner we have already realized
mass production of this type of Optics
and they have been delivered to Leading
Tier 1 and tier 2 suppliers in the
automotive industry and we have received
excellent feedback from our
customers the second example where our
technology has made an impact is in
augmented reality and virtual reality
systems in state of the arvr modules uh
you typically has anywhere from 15 to 20
individual Optical sensors to perform
functions such as hand uh uh gestural
recognition eye tracking hand tracking
and so on and as a result the size and
weight of the sensors adds up quickly in
our case we can deliver sensors they are
far more compact lightweight and that
can also be similarly integrated with
arvr modules uh we can offer higher
resolution and also a large Field view
comparable to that of human peripheral
vision and this is crucial in delivering
an immersive user experience so this
performances has already been tested and
validated by key OEM vendors across the
world and we are now transitioning into
mass production of this
product so in summary we believe that we
have developed this kind of platform
technology that can Empower many
applications across different sectors
from consumer electronics to automotive
and robotic sensing uh to Medical
Imaging and Beyond so we definitely
welcome uh collaboration opportunities
and partnership with you so if you're
interested please do stop by our booth
and I would love to chat thank
you thank you so much JJ