before we go to the test I just want to
point out this PCP is nonadaptive okay
the what are the queries of the verifier
he behaves like
a a verifier of of the gkr or in other
words verifier for Su check and and some
check is a public coin protocol so the
messages don't depend on anything you
just choose some Randomness and that
defines the queries so uh so it is a
non-adaptive the the questions you ask
don't depend on the answers you get this
is because the Su check is public coin
okay so that we do get nonadaptive and
as we said though we do need to check
that the witness sitting in the PCP is
of low degree so let me just do that
quickly
so a what how do we check it so the
prover what he does he you know there's
the H to The
N he should put a some witness here 01
02 0 w0 W1 W2 and so on uh so all the up
to
WM okay m is over uh up up to let's say
let me call the number of bits in the
witness s we'll just have a lot of of
zeros a a appended just so because m is
taken to be log s so not to confuse and
now he's giving kind of he takes the
extension right so this is f to the
m and this should be this is just what
it should be this is what the honest
mover does this is the low degree
extension uh of H ofm which should be of
degree hus one in each coordinate
and I want to check that now okay here's
the sad truth I can't actually check
this this thing is low degree with uh
degree H minus one in each coordinate I
can't check it because maybe maybe it is
but here he put something
bad I can't check it I mean I'm not how
how can the the verifier has small
queries so he can't actually check that
this is low degree that's
impossible okay so what does he what
does he do instead he's going to check
that it's close to low degree okay so
here's the guarantee the guarantee we
want is to say that this I'm going to
check I'm going to do a test and if the
test passes the guarantee I want not
that this is low degree but it's close
there's another polinomial of low degree
that agrees with this at most
points okay so we have we have a low
degree
test is a check at the end of the check
what the verifier the guarantee the
verifier has is the guarantee we want is
that with high
probability there
exists a low degree
polinomial W till
such
that dou
Tilda such that for most
Z or the probability over a random
Z the w z
equals is
uh greater than one minus Epsilon for
some Epsilon okay that's what we want to
check for Mo Z now if if we got this
check if we succeeded in this if we
succeeded in this check then now what we
know is that okay let's think in our
head that this is he put this up there
yeah he put He put this but they're so
close let's put this up there anyway the
probability that we'll ask on a z for
which they're different is only exson
mostly they agree on so all we need is
to to verify
that you know there's the be because we
check V Zer on a random Z at the
end most likely it's disase for which
they agree so all we need to check is
that they agree almost everywhere the
fact that there's few location that they
don't agree a there's nothing I can do
about it because if I don't query them I
don't know if they ex I don't know you
know what they what's sitting there but
actually I don't care that much cuz
they're not going to I'm not going to
query them anyway with high
probability so really all to say is that
there exists a w Tilda that is low
degree and agrees with that with high
probability how do I do that how do I
check that this W that this
V completely malicious vzero
Tilda behaves close at least as I said
we can't assume it's low degree but
close to low degree agrees with the low
degree polinomial in many
places yeah
exactly exactly let's check on some
random let's do a random sample the way
it's done the way it's done so there are
many low degree tests out there by the
way uh but one kind of common one is the
following I'm going to take a random
line in F to the
m and I'm going to check like I'm going
to ask open this random
line now this random line should be of
degree
M times H minus one that's what it
should
be I'm G to check that that's the degree
if it's not the degree I reject then
you're immediately
rejected okay so now what I know is that
in a random
line you agree with the low degree
polinomial okay because otherwise you're
rejected now one needs to argue that
because you agree on a random line with
a low degree polinomial why does that
mean that you're actually close to a low
degree polinomial all all
around okay but this is the test this is
really one of the low degree tests
that's out there you the verifier choose
so this is sitting in the PCP the
verifier will choose a random line and
he will test uh he can even test like M
* H random point on this line uh you
know he'll take M times or you can test
this plus one it doesn't really matter
uh depending on how you know soundness
you want but you can even take this plus
one this defines a you know this defines
uh polinomial of low degree of of this
of this degree and now you check that
the additional Point agrees with
it or if you want you can ask the entire
f f is only anyway only poly log s bit
so you can just read the entire thing
and see that it you by interpolation
that it's a low degree polinomial and if
it's not you reject
okay and then one needs to check though
okay so a random line agrees with a low
degree polinomial why does it imply that
everything agrees with the lowre
polinomial that's uh leap or with high
probability okay so we're g to I have a
good homework problem around that so
let's uh let's leave that alone a I have
a lot of this this a I have a lot of
good homework problems today a which is
nice because it summarizes the all the
information theory part of of the class
um okay any any questions before before
we
proceed yeah so is there some argument
here that if the Pol is low degree that
corresponds some witness in in this like
PCP um yeah so okay so if the argument
if you can argue that this this is close
to to low degree then take the actual
low degree that it's close to okay now
this defines a witness Oh by
by and and yeah now yeah now this is
going to be the witness that you
violated on exactly
exactly great so a okay so yeah oh I
feel like we don't really need to like
do a l layer circuit because if three
side it's like an gigantic end of
several like three
uhhuh bra sing and you can just do a
single to do this to to to to do the and
you're sing yes some kind of because we
don't need to like
okay yeah yeah yeah so what you're
saying is what you're saying look there
may be ways to do optimizations here
what I the way I showed you is very kind
of generic it said well you
know this is low depths H you no saying
wait it's not just low depth look it's a
very specific circuit it's one big end
with three ores and you know maybe you
can do it much better so let me say
you're 100% correct there's a lot of
optimizations on gkr I kind of showed
you the just kind of a feasibility
result but as I said these things are
used and they're not used as I as I
showed it uh because they optimized so
there's a lot of optimizations that they
do in a lot on the circuit level as as
you say like what's the best way to
arithmetization
we don't want to just maybe open it to
just random like degree 2 degree two
degree two maybe we don't want to do
exactly the gold maybe we want to do
something else that how to generate the
circuit to make it the most efficient
possible there's a lot of optimization
and on that part um so yeah I I showed
you and as I said today you can use
actually GK to be like the GK protocol
can be linear time prover they managed
to get to actually I don't actually I
know how they got to poly to quasi
linear the linear is actually new work
that I didn't yet have time to dive into
but apparently they have really nice uh
optimization that they use and most of
them I think is exactly on the circuit
level around ideas that you
mention a great so uh any any other
questions you have you guys have great
great questions so this
fantastic okay so I want to say a few
things that I didn't talk about maybe
they'll show up in the in in the
homework maybe not but I and it's
related to to questions that people
asked that Leo asked and others so first
of
all you know I said I I showed poly
login I said we can go all the way down
to three okay let me just mention three
is the best we can do we can we cannot
go below three okay uh from poly login
you can do kind of log Logan using
recursion you can do kind of PCP on the
poly login queries you can kind of Rec
first and then from a log log n to three
you can do kind of there these
exponential size proofs but to take a
log log n and make it exponent there's
like exponential size PCP with only
three queries so you apply kind of an
exponential size PCP to this log log n
size PCP they have all these cool
tricks uh and they manage to get to
three three bits okay three bits can you
go to two bits no yeah is that only for
sound as half like if if no any constant
soundness no what about for like
negligible sound
ah yeah no I constant soundness okay
constant soundness yeah for constant
soundness you can't we can get three the
con actually I think is better than half
but whatever uh but uh you can get three
and can you get constant sounds for two
no and no I think you just can't the
point so I don't want to get I I I yeah
I don't want to get and can you get one
definitely not how so can you get two no
however you can get two if you make each
the answer to each query like a block so
if you want two queries where each query
gives you an answer a bit you cannot
have PCP and the reason actually you
could intuitively the reason you cannot
have a PCP is because like because two s
is easy if you have only two query two
kind of queries intuitively the reason
why it's because too sad it's easy I
don't want to go into it maybe it's
going be homework so let's leave that
but you can have what you can have and
we do have it's not just theoretic like
we do have pcps that have only two
queries but the answers are large not
not I mean okay you can have one query
if the answer is aside the witness okay
that's easy but we can have two queries
where the size of each answer is polylog
okay but not one or constant for all I
know so maybe we'll do some homework
kind of to get you know intuitions
around these things yeah actually I
think do have like two B if we like
allow to have like imperfect
completeness you have oh if you allow to
have imperfect
completeness then a you're right the
situ sorry everything I'm saying is for
perfect completeness once you allowed to
reduce completeness to 1 minus
Epsilon things change so what do we know
um
with yeah with two if you have yeah I'm
not I don't remember off from top of my
head what two but what's the soundness
two queries constant soundness two bit
two 1/3 two3 okay okay con yeah yeah
yeah yeah okay yeah you're right so here
I'm assuming yeah you're right yeah good
point thank you yeah so if if you're
willing to relax completeness we can get
to but perfect completeness you can't
yeah thank like and you like two blocks
it's possible are you talking about
contigous bits blocks yeah so yeah think
think about it each query you read so
the PCP consists of like instead of bit
bit bit think about it like a word a
word a word a word and each word is like
polog and bits for example and now you
can read only two words so because I
want to word read Word I am more
J yeah
yes okay good no so good good good
question so the question is now do we
have perfect completeness and the answer
is yes because if you're honest if
perfect competance means if you're
honest you'll be accepted with
probability one so if you're honest you
are going to give W Tilda which is the
the low degree extension of your witness
and when I take a random line it's going
to be of low degree for sure everything
is low degree if you're if you're
malicious then so
sound the soundness exactly that you
lose you're right good point what what
you mentioned is you say because we do
the L degree we lose a little bit in the
soundness because you know maybe you're
a little malicious and we don't catch
you or you know and that goes yeah so
you'll need to make you'll need to make
the sound a little bigger so that you
can eat up what you lose a little bit in
the low degree yeah yeah great question
yeah when you repeat the prot
bring the same Che yeah yeah yeah good
so the question is when you repeat so
let's say you're not happy I you know we
have soundless half we're not happy what
do you do you need to actually repeat
the entire PCP or no you don't because
uh like why the the Prov will just give
you the same PCP over and over so no you
keep the same PCP all you do is you run
the r the verifier the PCP verifier
fresh with fresh Randomness more times
so if you have soundness half and you
want to have soundless 1 over two to the
K what you do is you run the PCP
verifier K times so he generates one set
of queries you run him fresh again
another set of queries fresh again each
time he's going to be rejecting
probability half independently of the
other time so you'll just get like uh
you know that is rejected he's accepted
probability one over uh 2 to the K yeah
so just the verifiers it needs to repeat
the prover is not involved in this great
great question guys any any other
questions what's the reference with this
thing I can put it I can put it in the
in yeah and I can put it in the in
canvas in the website a okay if I don't
remember remind me okay so um before we
move to crypto I just want to wrap up
kind of the information theory part and
say that in some sense I taught you
almost like okay so what what's missing
what did I what did you not get a chance
to see you didn't get a chance to see
the three query okay so you didn't get a
chance to see the recursion and the
Hadar and this nice way to get to
getting three pcps um there's another
beautiful beautiful result uh by uh Ryan
gold and Roth Bloom and Roth Bloom from
20 18 18 16
yeah yeah okay well started in 16 uh and
since then there's work uh but
essentially here's the question this is
kind of a question that's still missing
um and here here's the question the
question is um you know we have
efficient doubly efficient protocol for
bounded
depth do can we construct doubly
efficient protocol for bounded space now
look we know that we cannot hope to have
doubly efficient or not dou efficient
for that matter for more than P space
like we know that IP equals P space so
you know that's you can't have
interactive proof of be the pro
efficient or not efficient for more than
P space okay so we're stuck with P space
now you can exchange you can go from
depth to space actually there's a way to
convert depth to space and vice versa
but it doesn't preserve efficiency so
you can go from bounded depth to bounded
space now you must go because I showed
you a double bounded space if it
required more than poly space some
something in the world would go wrong
because we know IP equals P
space so the point is we do know we can
we can convert a bounded depth
computation to bounded space
computation but these this conversion
doesn't respect the efficiency of the
circuit so if you take a double A
bounded depth circuit and convert it to
a d to a bounded space circuit the
bounded space circuit or bounded space
computation I should say the bounded
space computation now will just be very
very long even if the bounded space the
bounded depth circuit let's say was only
size s
polinomial the bounded space computation
can be
exponential okay so it doesn't it
doesn't respect kind of the efficiency
of the computation when you do the
transition from bounded depth to bounded
space or vice versa so now there's a
question can you do let's say you have a
bounded space computation not a bounded
depth yeah you can convert a bounded
depth and pay a price but you don't want
to can you do a doubly eff can you do an
abounded space computation make it
doubly
efficient okay so here is kind of a
goal and those who who've been working
with me for a while may be traumatized
by this goal because I tormented
them I think this is one of the most
interesting problems out there it's
really frustrating to me that there's no
solution I'll give you an incentive in a
second but here's
the okay so here's my question if you
have
any time t
space
s
computation uh T of n s of
n here's the goal
goal we want an interactive
proof such
that prover
runtime is efficient poly t
we want verifier run time or let's start
okay verify run
time well the poor guy has to read the
input length so you know
X Plus times you know I'll be I'll be
nice with you times whatever it can be
even poly um I'm happy even with ply if
you want to put ply here I'll be
generous times ply and the
space not depending on T so he should
run it he can read the input and run
time the space
and usually we want the complex the
communication complexity to grow only
like poly space but if you want to put X
in there fine be my
guest this is what we want this is open
so we want a douly efficient interactive
proof for p space let me tell you what
Ryan golden the r Blom brothers did they
almost did this but here's this annoying
part the verifier run time
and the communication complexity is s
great but times t to the
Epsilon and this Epsilon has to be a
constant because the communication
complexity grows with like two to the
something oh till I think one over
Epsilon or something like that so
there's exponential growth in in in
epsilon so you can take you can maybe
take Epson like H one over log log or
log log log like log log log n over log
one over log log n think of it as
constant you don't really gain by trying
subc constant it's not giving you much
so they present their result as EPS
being a constant so this is really
annoying because now the verifier if T
is polinomial is super polinomial the
verify is not even efficient so this is
really for p
actually I want to get rid of this and
do for a big
T okay this is still an open question
okay now I need now okay I'm begging you
guys a plea for the smart all you smart
MIT students or Harvard or at bu nor
Eastern whoever you are this is a
personal favor can someone please solve
this and I know I need to give you guys
incentive so beyond probably you know a
a I don't know like a ACM PhD award or
whatever that's nothing but I'm willing
to give you a $500
prize okay so you're you're out biding
the
not we know didn't give a prize on this
right he gave like an FH Prize or
something but it was like
$15
okay okay so this you get rid of the tea
do this you can take pictures so you can
actually work on this please
okay let's uh um move on okay so this
essentially concludes the unit on
information Theory okay there's another
proof system that I didn't talk about
which is a multi- prooof interractive
proofs uh the reason I didn't talk about
them is because they're really
equivalent the probabilistically
checkable proofs they're not much
different maybe I'll put something along
these lines in the homework I don't know
I need to think about it but uh that's
another thing we did not cover but
they're really an equivalent thing to to
PCP so
but it's another proof model that was
considered in the
literature okay so that concludes a
information Theory so that's all we know
we're stuck with P space uh actually we
don't even and okay and uh and we can
get like a very efficient verification
but then we have a very long proof like
the PCP you can verify things super
efficiently like uh fantastic but you
need to write somewhere this
gigantic uh PCP proof okay that the PCP
and note it's very important it's very
important that the
verifier like has that that this PCP is
written if the PCP is not written
somewhere and he's talking with theover
and tell him look you know I know you
have a PCP written there somewhere can
you give me locations IJ and K a
cheating po will choose the locations
based on I and K and then for you know
JK he'll put in location I zero and
maybe for I and J Prime K Prime he'll
then put location i1 and cheat so it's
very important that the PCP is written
and now when you ask query I it's what's
written there it can't depend answer
cannot depend on query J or query K so
it's so it seems like it's very nice
model it's fantastic but where's this
huge thing going to be
written okay so uh like if we want at
the end of the day what here's our goal
really what what we're after really is
to take an actual proof like a witness
and drink it okay it's big I don't like
big shink make it small here now it's
smaller now of course we can't do it
right so like can't do it so now we
start changing them out say okay you
know what let's try interactive you know
what let's try PCP you know all these
are very nice but they all have really
strong problems okay like the
interactive proof one it's very very
specific it's an interactive proof I you
know I can talk to Tina I can talk to Su
I can talk to but it's it's um it's per
person what if I want to give a proof to
the
world how I can do an interactive proof
I want to post some on my
proof okay now I can do PCP I can post
that but it's really big so if I want to
make it sucin I
can't so I want to be able again my goal
to take a proof and just drink it and
put it
somewhere now of course you're like okay
it's nice you know
it's good that you have desires well you
know it's good that you want but
actually what's really interesting is
that using the magic of cryptography we
can get these things so now what I'm
going to do next is we're going to dive
into the world of cryptography and see
how we can use cryptography to get like
uh towards kind of these suin
noninteractive proofs
Okay so
okay so let's start so the first way
we're going to change the proof model is
to say to consider what we call
computationally sound proofs also known
in the literature as arguments so let me
explain so instead of talking about
statistical proofs which is what we
talked about so far we're going to think
about
computationally
sound
proofs okay so what is a computationally
sound proof it's a proof that has much
weaker guarantee soundness guarantees
than the standard one so it's it's the
completeness is the same it's a pro you
want to prove if you have if something
is true you succeed but that soundness
proof so this is also called an argument
so the
difference between a actual proof and an
argument is in soundness that's the only
different it's the soundness condition
so let me just tell you what the
soundness condition is here so the comp
it's a computational soundness
condition and what it says
is that so let's say for let's let's say
for some linguage
Al what it says is that for
any computationally
bounded only if the approver is
bounded okay if you know that the
approver is bound resources are bounded
it's run it's runtime comput it's it's
computationally bounded runtime so only
for a prover that's runtime is
bounded and for every X not in the
language the
probability that P star and V and X that
the verifier
accepts is small okay let's say negl
Okay smaller than half
whatever usually usually in this in the
language of arguments we convert we
convert this constant to negligible and
non- negligible we'll talk about that in
a minute but we now we say you know what
how do we get around all these negative
results so the idea we say you know what
actually why do we care that there
exists a time two to the Thousand Prov
that can cheat nobody can run in that
time okay there's not enough molecules
in the universe like there's no so so
these things are they don't exist so why
do we care let's only consider provs
that run in Bound in time now you say
what is bounded we'll talk about that is
bounded what there's an input length n
is n and and Cubed two n well it's the
bound so yeah we each we'll talk how we
bound it but the first idea let's bound
his runtime let's consider aover that is
runtime we know is bounded now let's try
to to argue s this only against such
provs
okay so you take the bound to be
something that you believe is realistic
you know yes do we have distribution
over X or no for any ex so yeah so the
question is this distribu no I want I
still want to say look I don't even want
to I don't want to say that you can
cheat on any ex so I still want look I
want I want the same guarantee I want to
have the same sound guarantee say look
nobody can convince you of any false
statement but couldn't your just like
memorize the proof of like some easy
okay okay think okay good good good I
right so you're saying wait where what
do you mean if if you have an act you
take a proof and you put it there let's
I'm defining here com yeah so okay so
you can't have the what you're saying is
you can't have this non-interactive
you're saying if you want a
non-interactive proof this is impossible
even computationally why I'm a cheating
prover I'm going to have one bad x x not
the language I'm going to hardwire one
bad proof because we assume it exists it
just hard to fine fine it's one so I can
kind of think of a non-uniform model
it's I'm going to hardwired it hardwire
it and now I'm going to give it you're
right we do not have
non-interactive proofs uh
computationally sound proofs but we
almost do almost so we'll talk about
what I mean by almost yes that one
V yeah exactly we okay so I I'll jump
I'll jump ahead and say the way we have
it is we assume some common random
string some common reference let's say
we all agree like there's some hash
function and we're going to use this
hash function when we can talk the
proofs and now we're going to argue the
only way you can cheat is by breaking
this function so there we are going to
at the end get the exactly what we want
so this is kind of jumping ahead we will
actually be able to construct these
succinct proofs okay and
non-interactive however we assume that
both the verifier and the pro kind of
agree on some common reference string
that both agree it's it's Universal
doesn't depend on X like it's a has
function and we all agree it's ch to 56
whatever any any kind of for those who
do cryptography and are familiar with
these kind of off the-shelf hash
functions for those who don't don't
worry whatever we agree on some
reference string and now we're going to
argue that if a cheating prover can come
up with X not in the language and a
false proof it means he broke something
about about the common reference string
so this kind of the idea is why so I I
already said it actually but when you
first think about it you want to say
look I want to get
around these imp like the fact that IP
is only P space all these kind of
barriers I want to be able to consu the
suing proofs now we know we can't so we
need to change the model and one way we
say you know let's let's consider
bounded provs why not let's assume I
approver runs in time less than two to
the 500 what anybody object is there any
pro the r time more than 2 to 500 no so
fine what we didn't lose anything the
question is what did we gain is it
easier okay we we said the pooper has to
run time most two to the 500 so what
like how do we use that and the reason
we use that the way we use that is using
cryptography now we can say our approver
cannot break a cryptographic assumption
so we add the cryptographic Assumption
to our proofs and we can assume that the
pro can break it now who Like A Whole
New World opened up to us and which we
can
use okay so what I'm going to show you
next it's actually how a to use so
here's a
theorem I'm first going to show an
interactive protocol okay still
interactive but very strong so here's
what I'm going to show you this is a a a
a theorem due to a a Kilian and mikali
92 and
[Music]
'94 which were really the kind of
results that kind of laid the foundation
for this field a and what they showed is
the following they showed how to take
any
PCP and some little cryptographic tool
called the collagen resistant hash
function I'll Define what that is and
take these two and construct a succinct
form message so not unattractive for
message argument so computationally
soundproof so essentially what they show
is give me this long PCP that can be
efficiently efficiently a checked I'm
going to use cryptography to kind of
shrink this PTP put it in a little
box send it to the
verifier and then convince the verifier
that what in this box is an accepting
proof so the use
cryptography together with PCP to
construct with the
following
assuming Collision resistant hash
function I'll Define in a minute A
cryptographic
Primitive for any language in NP
there
exists a for
message argument
system okay now let me
Define the argument system more formally
because here was just kind of a bit and
now
I'm okay so
when we talk about once we use
cryptography when cryptography comes
along then we use some cryptographic
Primitives and these cryptographic
Primitives have some security parameter
associate with them the security
parameter intuitively tells
you how much so when when I say like I
want let's say a 100 bits
of security we usually in cryptography
essentially what we mean as aover that
runs in time two to the 100 cannot break
the scheme or in time depends on the
security cannot break the scheme so
whereas statistically we say when we say
you know we want a I don't know security
Epsilon we say probability of breaking
any you can have whatever power you want
but the probabilties
Epsilon once we're in crypto land
usually the security talks about the
runtime like what is
the bound you you place on the approvers
runtime and usually we think of the
soundness is like negligible okay so
negligible meaning smaller than any
polinomial I I'll I'll explain in more
in more detail but so when we talk about
A cryptographic Primitive It's
associated with the security parameter
and we don't like uh in practice when
they write things they write usually
they just set security parameter to be
128 bits 256 bits they said they set
number but here we're in complexity land
so where we have a parameter Lambda
that's the security parameter and we
keep it as a parameter in real world you
said you know the people said it to
their heart's desire uh but we're going
to think of it as a parameter here okay
so um okay so here's the guarantee uh
the so uh so
the okay so this four message argument
system let me start with a complexity
actually
the Prov run
time will be poly n the instance length
and Lambda security
parameter and V
runtime is going to be only poing
security
parameter and also in our case also in
uh the plus v PCP
runtime so of course he needs to read
the input and he needs to behave like a
PCP verifier but the PCP verifier is
very efficient the problem is the Oracle
so now there's no Oracle but his runtime
is like the runtime of the PCP
verifier okay so uh
which
uses some
PCP okay you can think of the PCP the
PCP I just showed you poly Logan poly
Logan okay so we use some PCP so that's
the complexity okay it's four messages
the Pro run time is efficient and like
prob of course and and the verifier is
very
efficient well he generates oh oh oh
sorry p uh yeah okay sorry uh P given X
and W and the witness yeah thank you the
prover is giving X and the witness in
the
language and he's going to be efficient
he's going to run in time and and
Lambda let me just mention okay I'll
mention that in a second actually okay
so the completeness is
one just says that uh for every X and D
X and L and Witness
W the
probability that P with witness W and V
both of them have X and security
parameter there's some security
parameter
involved the probability that verifier
outputs one is one so the verifier
always always accepts if you're honest
if the prover is honest he has a witness
corresponding to x with any security
parameter he
accepts okay actually a
almost it's
assuming no it accepts no no no ifs in
buts okay what about the
Sis Sis
says that for
any P star of size
okay now you can say for instance if SI
poly Lambda poly in the security
parameter then you can say let's say
that for every X not in the
language the
probability that P star now he doesn't
have a witness because it's not in the
language this is a cheater I want to say
for any P star that tries to cheat but
he's bounded he's poly Lambda and for
every X not the
language the
probability on X in Lambda that the
verifier outputs one is very small it's
negligible in Lambda and negligible in
Lambda is just a way to say it vanishes
faster than one over poly for any poly
okay this just
means that for any poly
P there exists some Lambda star such
that for any Lambda bigger than Lambda
star P
Lambda a the
negligible is smaller than 1 over P
Lambda so it vanishes faster than any
poly if you go above some constant
okay so the negligible Advantage is
quicker than one over poly for any poly
okay that's the definition of negligible
yeah just what size means so we're
assuming all these things are
circuits oh okay yeah yeah yeah okay
good good good good yeah we're thinking
of usually in cryptography we always
allow the adversary our adversaries to
be non-uniform because they may get
advice so usually we model them as
polinomial size circuits this is opposed
to saying P star that runs in time
poly Lambda So when you say he has signs
poly Lambda it's just to say he has it's
another words say you know he can he
runs in time po Lambda but he may have
like advice okay we allow him to have
some kind of fixed advice that's why we
say size yeah great great question yes
but if Lambda is like less than the size
of X how do you even fit in the X
bit good okay so okay the problem is
actually yeah the problem is we don't
okay what you're saying is look uh so
that's why I have my red pen coming up
my red chalk you're saying if x is
smaller than let's say Lambda to the
Epsilon if x is of size even we allow P
to be size poly so what you're saying
the function wow wait that's weird
you're not even allowing the if L is
smaller than x p star can't even read
X he can't even read it like it's run
time is less than
x true if X is bigger than po Lambda any
po Lambda that's first right because he
can run in any time we allow P star to
run in time any po
Lambda so X can be size any kind of if
you take a sequence of x's that are each
of sides kind of for any Lambda if you
have X BL so I'm a cheating improver and
for any Lambda I have like x sub Lambda
that I'm going to cheat on and as long
as these x sub Lambda are at most Lambda
to the 100 I can I can run time lamb to
the 100 here this is Theory land so I
can do that but sometimes we want to
actually have communication complexity
which is like poly
login so now the security property need
to be poly Logan and now you can't even
read
so SEC science the reason we WR I wrote
sience po Lambda is because this will
allow us
to have so the communication grows polom
with Lambda if I allow the the approver
to run at most poly Lambda it will allow
me to rely the the I I can assume that
my cryptograph my cryptography whatever
I use here Collision hash function or
oneway function whatever whatever
cryptographic assumption I use the
assumption is a
polinomial time a pomal size cheater
cannot break it but I can you know let
me strengthen the Assumption I'm going
to say that
it so I'm goingon to say for every piece
tar of size you know 2 to the Lambda to
the O of one you know as long as you're
inun time at most two to the Lambda to
epon to plus some
Epsilon you
can't you can't break now you know it's
you X can be like a poly l in
Lambda the thing is now I'm assuming
that a p St that runs in time this
cannot break my cryptography with
security parameter Lambda it's a
stronger
assumption so there's a delicate issue
here with soundness which I glossed over
in the definition above where I said
computationally
bounded what's the bound so again the
reason these computationally sound
proofs are useful is because then we can
use cryptography so now we say let's use
cryptography in our proof system when we
use cryptography there's a security
parameter Lambda now typically we we
assume that so now what do we we want to
say our cryptography cannot be broken
and therefore our scheme is secure okay
cannot be broken in what time so
typically we would like to say oh in
time poly Lambda cannot be broken that's
kind of our polinomial assumption that's
kind of what we think of standard
assumptions in cryptography that uh some
assumption with security parameter
Lambda cannot be broken time po Lambda
we call that a
polinomial uh
assumption this is what we want but then
you're right to say well it's weird
because then if you want to think of
Lambda as being like Po log n you know
if you want at the end of the day we
want suing proofs so we let's say we
have X of size n and suppose we want the
suing to be like polog in like in
gkr so now Lambda needs to be a size
poog in in a sense so it's like wait the
cheating po can't even read x what a
weird kind of uh so I'm I'm the honest
prover runs in time more than the
cheating prover that's
bizarre so the the answer is okay so so
the answer is look it
depends how
um it depends on how how much risk
you're willing to take okay what do I
mean how much risk
if you want to say look I'm very very
conservative I'm not willing to assume I
I don't my trust in cryptography is very
limited and I'm only willing to assume
if I use a Lambda bit of security I want
to my assumption is that a PO Lambda
cannot break it I don't want to assume
that a two to the Lambda person cannot
break it two to to no that maybe he can
I don't trust that
assumption that's all I'm willing to
assume now but here's the thing that
once you once you bounce the cheating
Pro to be poly Lambda essentially what
we're saying is that in the world
there's no way you can run time more
than poly Lambda if you can then this
has no meaning in a sense you know so
now we're saying look in this world you
can't run more than this time whatever
it is this this otherwise this this
computationally bounded is like a bit
meaningless so if that all the time you
can run in the xsr can't be bigger than
that in a sense because nobody can run
in that time nobody can read that X so
essentially what you're saying is you're
saying look I'm telling you I want a
cheating Pro that runs in time more at
most to the 500 you're saying well what
if there's an input of links two to the
Thousand okay look whatever he still can
run time when most two to the 500 the
fact I'm not going to give him more
runtime it's ridiculous you know I still
want to say for every ex but I don't
want to give now the PO more runtime no
in this world provs run in time at most
on security this is this is about the
world about the SEC security of the
world like I give a bound on what I
think is a reasonable runtime of like
real world
adversaries nobody can run in more time
okay now you're saying well uh you know
it's weird you're giving him less time
than what if you know for an X that that
is size two to the Thousand that honest
Prov well there is no honest Prov that
will prove something of about X of size
two to the Thousand like so it's so we
anyway we bound and even if they're like
xes that are bigger than this yeah our
poor can't run in time bigger than this
still our poor guy needs to prove
something about act that he cannot even
read fine the point is in our world
these are our adversaries that's how we
should think of
it
okay yeah so the reason we're giving the
honest like this extra po event is that
we're assuming that they have to do
something with the witness exactly so
the the prover the honest prover of
course he needs to read the witness
essentially you know he needs to look at
the input he needs to read the witness
he'll need to generate a PCP or whatever
he needs to do something so the honest
Prov of course he needs to run in time
that depends on X but the point is you
should think okay what if honest pober
works with X and that is a size two to
the Thousand yeah but it doesn't exist
it's a theory it's um mental experiment
you know we don't have these things but
yeah he would run and now he saying our
adversary no he can't run because our
adversary don't have that power nor do
our Hest Pro they don't exist for that
sizes
yeah so like before when we were talking
about the information thetic uh IPS and
the sound is I mentioned that as long as
the sound is less than like a half or
something you can just repeat it over
over you get better better yeah same app
here good yes so um yes the same applies
here so you can ask in a sense why are
we uh like why why is here so
okay let me it's yes but uh we need to
be careful
uh in in a inactive argument you can if
the sound is here is only half you can
reduce soundness by repetition
exponentially however you will need to
do it
sequentially okay so you'll need to do
one interactive protocol after the other
after the other after the other actually
it was uh a open question for a while
was if you have an interactive argument
and you just because people don't like
people care about round complexity they
don't like protocols that take gazillion
rounds so they say well why don't you
repeat interactive if you take an
interactive proof and you repeat it in
parallel many times with fresh
Randomness everything fresh you know
just independently but repeat in
parallel The Sounds go down
exponentially like you want now you can
say does the same thing hold for
argument so this was actually an open
problem for a while and then at some
point it was a long time ago was was a
post uh probably 16 15 years ago uh he
actually gave an
example of oh sorry no no no there was
sorry so there was an example I'm
messing up the the uh by mon Na and two
other people I don't remember now they
showed actually no there is an example
of an interactive argument that if you
repeat it in parallel soundness doesn't
go down at all so you have to repeat it
sequentially okay so when you repeat
interactive arguments in parallel the
crypto doesn't work in parallel as like
a a it's not really true it's like there
are contrived examples where you can
show that the crypto soundness doesn't
reduce like you would hope and therefore
the sounds doesn't go down now the
examples that we have are pretty
contrived okay okay it's not like but
there's no definitely it's not true in
general it's not true in general that if
you take an interactive argument and you
repeat it in parallel with fresh
Randomness many times sound does not go
down even though if show that there's a
way to repeat it in parallel but you
need to be a little clever don't just
repeat he like a very weird trick he had
of like with someity you abort the ver
said you know what I don't want to
continue in this let's just like just a
weird abort he added a weird abort
condition and then all of a sudden
things
kind of the sound is vanished
so okay so I guess my answer to your
question if you repeat it in
sequentially yes air goes down
exponentially exactly like we would hope
it goes from like s to s to the K if you
repeat it K times if you repeat it in
parallel naively no and there counter
examples yet there are ways to repeat in
parallel a little less naively with some
abort kind of thing uh that then it does
go down so I guess the short answer it's
complicated okay but okay great but
typically we just write uh negligible
because of this issue it's like we like
to just we you know um we like to write
when we talk in cryptography usually
write like one minus negligible or one
for completeness and then negligible for
soundness okay so this is uh this is uh
the the theorem any questions about I I
need to define the the a what the
Collision resistant hash function is but
um any questions before I
Define okay so by the way just from just
so I know who I'm talking to how many
people know what a collision and hash
function
is okay a lot okay uh but it's not uh
it's actually not important uh and I'll
I'll Define it in a minute uh
okay so uh let me just
Define so a collision
resistant hash
family it's actually a family it's not a
function
H consists of two algorithms
okay first is Gen gen is an algorithm
that generates a key to the hasch
function so gen takes his input so gen
is a PPT propos polinomial time
algorithm it takes as
input one to the security parameter so
in crypto we have this Hack That we
assume our algorithms take as input one
to the security parameter instead of
security parameter which is you know
it's a bit like I feel like a moreon
sync one to the security parameter the
only reason we write it this way is
because we want to think of our
algorithms efficient poly time and poly
is in the input and all our algorithm
run in time poing the security parameter
so to say that our algorithm are
efficient our poly time we always write
the security parameter in unary okay
because that's the input so it's just
kind of a hack to to make the theory
kind
of nice okay and it
outputs a hash
key so this hash is a size poly Lambda
yeah because this algorithm is
polinomial takes input Lambda and unary
lamb so it can outp put something
only uh F size poly Lambda and then
there's the eval
algorithm and the eval algorithm takes
as input it's a polytime algorithm
that takes his
input hash
key and X any X in Zer one
star and it outputs you can also
restrict you can restrict the X to be
let's say you can restrict it but let's
think of any input and
outputs a value V in 01 to the
Lambda okay what's important the way has
use what's important about hash
functions is that they're shrinking so
you can think if it takes an an input
any X you can think that it takes as
input like something of size two Lambda
like Tak two Lambda to Lambda you can
even think Lambda plus one to Lambda if
you want but let's think of so there's
many ways people Define it let's let me
go with star like any input okay and now
the the security says that a polinomial
time or a poly size algorithm that is
given a hash key should not be able to
find two different X's that hash to the
same value that's the Assumption yeah
caned
whated okay it can be the the empty
string but then there's no it won't be
secure and I'll explain why so uh uh
it's a good question it's a good
question the question do we really need
the hash key or can we just make that
empty I'll uh
so it's a the answer is a bit it's again
it's a modeling answer but I'll get to
it I'll I'll answer your question in a
second let me just write the the
security and then we'll talk about it
because it is a great question um okay
the
security the Collision resistance
requirement says that for any any poly
poly Lambda
size adversary a the
probability that a given hash key where
hash key is
chosen by
gen the probability that it outputs x
and x
Prime that such
that X is different not the same and
and
eval of hash key and X is equal to eval
of hash key and X
Prime is negligible so so for every poly
size a there exists a negligible
function mu such that for every Lambda
the security
parameter so maybe I'll write it
better for any poly
size for any poly size a there exists
some negative function so a function
that vanishes faster than any polinomial
such that for any security parameter
if you generate a hash key using the
security parameter you give the
adversity the hash key his goal is to
Output two different inputs that hash to
the same value the probability that he
does this is at most negligible in
Lambda so as Lambda grows big this
becomes
tiny yeah is a size
po good yes exactly when I say poly size
I mean poly input so poly Lambda
okay that's the
definition now I want to first answer
your question which is do we really need
a hash key can we just tell him this is
the security parameter like why do we
need a hash key and the answer is
actually we don't it's interesting we
don't quite need a hash key and actually
the hash functions we use in practice
don't have a hash key in a sense well
they're fixed I okay is a different
story but the reason the reason why we
have a hash key is we allow it's a a
question of modeling who's our adversary
what kind of adversaries are we thinking
about if we think about adversaries that
are poly size that are circuits or or
chewing machines that have some
non-uniform
advice then you know what if the
adversary just has in his belly somehow
someone gave him advice x and x Prime
that are different and hash to the same
value
like someone gave him two xes that has
to the same value then he'll just spit
it of course he has collisions yeah I
mean collisions Exist by pigal principle
I mean it's huge it goes to a small
these exist we want to say they're hard
to find but if we think of a nonuniform
adversity that has advice he may have
this as advice and then he'll output it
so if we think of a non-uniform model
then we have to have a hash key another
option to think of a uniform model let's
think of a not as poly poly time he's
uniform then we don't need to have a
hash key we just because we can assume
that small axes don't Collide because
you know uh we'll just make the hash
function so they won't Collide and then
big ones you can't you can't hold in
your belly because you're bounded you're
your your uniform you have only constant
size kind of your constant Siz
description so so actually there have
been works in the literature uh in
the theoretical cryptography literature
they talk about hash functions with no
keys but then they need to talk about
uniform
adversaries and that's this is something
that that is considered and talked about
but the most standard is to talk about
non-uniform adversaries and then we need
to have keys
yeah okay any any
questions Okay so oh time's up in five
minutes okay so um good so now what I
want to do is I want to give you uh I I
want to prove this theorem and I want to
give you a construction of a hash
function that we use now let me tell you
we actually we use a hash function with
an additional property for this theorem
we use a hash function with additional
property we don't need to assume it
because we can construct it from a hash
function so that's why I didn't I didn't
write it as an assumption because I can
construct it but really the Primitive we
need for the
theorem is we want an
additional uh we want a hash function
with what we call local opening what do
we mean by local opening here a hash
function we say look there's an eval
that takes a hash key X output a value
now if you want to check you I'll give
you let's say I hashed a value I told
you here's V now you're saying okay I
want to know what you committed to fine
I can give you my X and you can what you
hashed sorry uh what you which value you
hashed I'm like no problem here's my a
and you can
check but what I really want for this
theorem and it's something I want from
this is a common uh primitive that we
need in many applications is I want to
say Okay I hashed I took a hash function
I hashed a value I don't know I I want
to argue look I has the value I don't
want to give you my entire value it's
too big you guys are my the verifiers
you can't even read everything I wrote
in my I can't give you my what I hashed
it's too big I want to open one bit I'm
going to tell tell you look I hashed a
value but the I bit of the value I
hashed is
zero how do I know how do you know that
it's zero oh I'm going to convince you I
can kind of give kind of a local opening
to this
x this is what I want okay so what I
defined here is just a hash function but
then I can Define another primitive
which is a hash function with local
opening and that's what we actually need
for the
theorem so a hash function with local
opening has two additional algorithms
corresponding to it there's an open
algorithm which allows you kind of to
open to show kind of a I think to give
you a little proof that the I bit of
what i hashed is a certain value and
then there's a verify algorithm that
verifies
it okay since we have only two minutes I
think I'll I'll skip I'll next time I'll
show you the the local opening but maybe
I'll just say tell you one minute of
like the idea uh behind
is my theorem hiding somewhere maybe
here oh yeah sorry it's the opposite
okay behind this theorem so the the idea
is what what I want to do is the their
idea the high level what they do they
take the prover will take this ginormous
PCP he wants to give it to the verifier
but the verifier can't hold it so what
he's going to do he's G going to give
him a hash of this PCP hey this PCP and
just give him the hash value just slam
the bits now the verer has this hash
value now now in some sense now theover
is now the pro now the hash Val now the
verifier is going to tell him okay thank
you very much I'm going to behave as a
as a PCP verifier so I'm going to
generate Randomness ask to look at
locations I want I to up the i in your
PCP give me opening show me show open
don't give me the entire PCP I can't I
hold it give me only location i1 I2 of
to
I now the prover wants to give here no
problem it's B1 B2 of to BL but the
verifier needs to be how does he know
that it it's indeed the opening of of
the hash so we're going to use a hash
function that you can open so he's going
to give him the bits with opening that
see here's a opening or a little proof
that in location i1 is sitting B1
location I2 I have B2 B2 and so on so
forth and then the verifier is just
going to check the opening that they're
good and accept if the PCP verifier
accepts so essentially all the idea you
combine this PCP with kind of this
cryptography a technology that kind of
smushes this PCP into a small thing and
allows you to kind of look kind of only
at spe allows the Prov in a sense to
look only at specific locations
computationally like you can give him
little proofs that open in specific
locations and then and and that's it
that's what you get so next time we're
going to Define uh the local opening
we're going to see the the
interactive argument in detail and prove
uh that it satisfies the guarantees
written here okay so we'll see you next
Friday thanks