Hello again. I'm Vicki. I'm a first year
posttock at the Schmidt Center. And
today I have the pleasure of introducing
our next speaker, Maria Barbettich.
Maria is an assistant professor in
computer science and life science at the
Swiss Federal Institute of Technology,
EPFL, and the head of the machine
learning for biio medicine lab. Before
taking on these impressive roles, she
did her postto in Stanford and received
her PhD from the University of Zagreb in
Croatia. She has received numerous
scholarships and awards already and most
recently the prestigious SNSF starting
grant. Maria's research is a wonderful
example um of uh the what we do here at
the symposium. Um her lab works on
cutting edge machine learning methods
informed by biological problems and is
contributing impressive advancements in
multimodal generative modeling for
cellular bi biology. I'm very excited,
Maria, to hear your talk and the floor
is all
yours. Okay. Thank you so much Victoria
for a nice introduction. Thank you also
Caroline for inviting me. and uh super
excited to be here and be part of these
exciting two days and this
workshop. Um so today I'll tell you
about how can generative AI help us to
unlock the complexity of cells. So we
are in the midst of genomics revolution
that is transforming uh our
understanding of biology at a cellular
level with the advances of single cell
RNA sequencing technologies. We can now
imagine expressions in hundreds uh or
even millions of cells in a single
experiment leading to the creation of
these large scale salatless data sets
that offer the opportunity to
characterize ourselves at unprecedented
resolution. And not only that we can
measure cell transcriptto we can also
measure proteins epiggenome pro phenome
and with multiomics technologies we can
even do multiple measurements in the
same time at the same cells and very
latest spatial technologies enable us to
study cells in their native tissue
context while at the same time capturing
the gene expressions of the
cells. At the same time we are also in
the midst of AI revolution. So with the
rise of generative AI paradigm, we've
seen completely new capabilities of AI
system um that um that um kind of offer
completely new capabilities that were
not possible before. Uh and this brings
us all to the era of foundation models
where kind of most famous example would
be large language models such as CH GPT
that are pre-trained on internet scale
data to predict next token in a sentence
and then can be applied to a variety of
downstream tasks.
But the question is how can AI help us
to advance our understanding of biology?
How can really it brings us closer to
understanding ourselves, how their
function and what goes wrong on a
cellular level in disease state. And our
goal is ideally is not just to make
predictions but really to use AI to help
us to discover new biological
mechanisms.
And one of the kind of big challenges
when you think about biological data
compared to for example computer vision
or natural language processing is that
biological data is inherently
heterogeneous. So we collect these data
sets from different tissues, different
donors, different time points, different
species and also we measure different
modalities. And the ultimate goal is
really to develop an integr integrative
holistic understanding of biology that
captures the complexity of life across
different scales. and artificial
intelligent technologies really kind of
hold this promise to help us to unify
these kind of fragmented views and to
discover generalizable patterns across
these different biological
contexts. And in our prior work, we
tackled individually some of these kind
of challenges. For example, how can we
transfer learn across different tissues,
different donors? How can we integrate
data sets across different species? How
can we analyze data sets across
different time points to kind of mention
few
examples but in this talk what I want to
focus on is more kind of this aspect of
different modalities in particular uh
combining kind of information from the
transcript of the cells and their
spatial organization. So how can AI help
us to learn the relationship between the
spatial organization of the cells and
their gene expressions.
And in the second part of the talk, I
want to kind of briefly uh touch upon
how can we leverage kind of these big
foundation models that we have nowadays
to help for unsupervised inference and
kind of to help us to discover what
classes automatically exist in the data.
For example, what kind of cell types we
have um in in our data set.
So while single cell RNA sequencing
allows us to kind of study our cells at
unprecedented resolution, the
fundamental problem and challenge is
that cells are dissociated from tissue
and we lose the spatial context of the
cells. On the other hand, we have
spatial transcries that kind of capture
this native native organ that capture
organization of the cells in their
native tissue context. But the number of
genes that we can capture is limited.
But can we overcome the limitations of
these uh technologies with computational
approaches and kind of can we get the
best of both worlds to really obtain a
more complete pictures of how tissue
function and understand cell
interactions. So ideally we would like
to have kind of spatial context of the
cells captured as well as like a full
transatomic information.
So we started this project with a
question and idea how well or can we
reconstruct complex tissue structures
denovo. So if someone gives me
dissociated single cells can I be able
to predict the kind of complex tissue
organization? Can I predict how cells
get organized in the
space? And we call this process of going
from dissociated single cells to kind of
these tissue structures uh the tissue
reassembly because kind of we want to
reassemble tissues from these kind of
dissociated cells and predict how they
get how uh cells get spatially
organized and conceptually you can
imagine this as kind of alpha fold for
cells where in alpha fold we go from the
protein sequence to the protein
structure. So here what we want to do is
we want to go from the expressions of
dissociated single cells to these kind
of uh tissue
structures. But the question is of
course to what extent and uh is this uh
tissue reassembly possible and of course
the answer will probably defend will
also depend on different biological
systems. But given kind of that if you
think about you know vast cellular
heterogeneity, complexity of tissue
structures, intricate cell cell
interactions and also elusive biological
mechanisms that underly tissue formation
and if it is indeed possible, how can we
learn it? How can we learn these
underlying rules of complex spatial
organization? So the good news is that
uh we have like bunch of existing
spatial transatomics data sets. uh so we
could leverage these existing spatial
transcri proper spatial priors of uh
tissue
organization. So in order to do so what
we need to do is we need to capture the
cellular interactions locally as well as
globally across the entire slice.
So in particular what we need to learn
in or order to capture these um cell
cell interactions is how each cell
should kind of attend to other cells
based on its own location and the gene
expression. Uh and we can kind of in
machine learning language the way we
could kind of capture this is using kind
of well-known principle which is a self
attention mechanism. So basically what
we can do is we can learn how each cell
should attend to other cell based on the
relevance of other cells to a cell's own
location and its own gene expressions.
So in this way kind of we can enable
each cell to learn how to communicate to
other cells guided by the attention
weights or attention
scores. And the secondly we one we model
this kind of tissue reassembly process
as a generative process. So in
particular we model it as a conditional
point cloud generation where the
conditioning is applied uh on each
individual point using the gene
expressions of the
cells. So during inference ideally and
Joey kind of gave a really nice
introduction to the diffusion model. So
it was really um a good introduction
before this talk. uh but ideally then
you know during the inference what we
want to do is we want to sample noise uh
and then these noisy cell coordinates
and I want want to condition these noisy
cell coordinates on the gene expressions
of the cells and then with a number of
steps I want to be able to kind of go to
reconstruct these um tissue
structures and these two ideas to kind
of first model cell interactions via
attention mechanism and secondly the
model tissue reassembly process as
generative process uh bring us to the
framework that we call Luna and this was
work done by my amazing PhD student
yeast and master student Shanaka uh who
is now PhD student actually here at
MIT. Uh so what Luna does is uh like
Luna leverages this existing spatial
transatomics data sets with ground truth
cell locations uh and as a diffusion
model it consists of two main steps. So
first step is corruption step. We are
going to add noise to the ground true
cell location. We are going to sample
diffusion time and then we are going
going from this ground truth cell
locations to this kind of noise cell
coordinates and then during the
denoising process the model will learn
to recover the original cell coordinates
through the denoising process. So
basically we are going to learn these uh
cell embeddings using the tension
mechanism and then from these output
cell embeddings we just add in one fully
connected neural network layer to go to
these uh predicted physical locations
predicted cell coordinates and then
during a training the model needs to
learn to den noiseise um the uh cell
coordinates. Another challenge is
basically that uh when you think about
this data set that the spatial
arrangements of the cells in a tissue
actually it may undergo transformations
due to an experimental artifacts while
for example tissue slices can be
arbitrarily rotated and reflected while
gene expressions actually remain
unchange. So so this means that we want
to basically design the objective
function that is invariant to these
rotations and reflection. So this means
that we want to basically be able we are
not care really about the absolute
positions of the cells but what we care
about is about the relative spatial rel
relationships of the cells. So we design
an objective function that kind of is uh
is based on this pair wise distances of
the cells rather on their absolute
positions and then during the inference
stage we sample from the standard normal
distribution and then with a number of
diffusion steps eventually ideally
converge to the ground truth uh cell
locations. Uh Luna has also linear time
and uh memory complexity during the
inference uh because we use attention
with the linear complexity. Uh so this
means is like a highly scalable. It can
um it can infer locations of tens of
thousands of cells in just a few minutes
um on a single
GPU. And next I'll show some of uh some
results um of uh applying Luna. So first
we applied it on the Murfish mouse brain
atlas where actually we have the ground
truth cell location. So we trained the
Luna on the 2.8 million cells from one
mouse and then we were interested
whether we can kind of reassemble the
brain of another um mouse. So we applied
it to 1.2 million cells from another
mouse and here results of uh on the left
I show the ground truth locations on the
right are Luna on the right are ground
locations on the left are Luna's
predictions and this is how for one
slice of isocortex region and here is
how the diffusion process happens. So
with the number of diffusion step model
eventually converges um to the locations
that really highly resemble the ground
truth locations. And here uh cells are
colored based on about
338 different uh uh subtypes that are
annotated in the data set. But we also
see high accuracy if you look at the
more finer grain annotations over a
thousand types and also cell cluster
level which has over 5,000
types. And overall overall Luna's
predictions agree well across 11 major
regions that identified in the ABC atlas
despite their um distinct structural
characteristics. If you look within a
particular um cell subtype so for
example if you look at this is just an
example of glutathic neurons. We further
look whether basically Luna is able to
infer this kind of spatial distribution
of gene expressions correctly. So these
are example of two spatially variable
genes RX FP FP1 and RB1 gene RB gene uh
where here uh on the top are ground
truth locations on the bottom Luna's
predictions uh and this RXF FP1 gene is
actually uh highly expressed in this uh
lower part of the region and here uh a
bit um mildly expressed uh here and this
is actually correctly captured by the
model as well as also spatial
distribution of the RRB B gene.
This is also case for some of the
non-neuronal types. So this is an
example of appendimal asteroite
appendimal cells where there's a small
group of cells expressing the CF AP 206
gene which is actually also correctly
captured by the
model. And given the kind of high
similarity of the two brains, we were
also next interested to see whether
model could generalize if we for example
exclude certain major cell class during
training. So we excluded um one uh there
we uh went to make the ch task most
challenging we actually excluded uh we
went to the most coarse grained
annotation. So on 30 uh there are 34
different major classes defined in ABC
atlas. Um and here basically we during
the training we train on all cells from
animal one but we completely exclude. So
here is just an example of glutamatergic
neuron cells in layer 6b. uh and then we
were interested to see whether model can
still be able to correctly predict where
to locate these cells in another animal
even though this cell class has not been
seen during training.
Um indeed we found that the model
correctly presositioned this unseen uh
cell class in the spatial architecture
of the tissue. And again if you look at
the specially variable genes for example
TS HZ2 gene and SYT6 gene um it was able
to correctly capture the spatial
distribution of this gene within a
certain within this cell
class. Uh this is also the case for
other cell classes. So this is just an
example of another cell class which was
the excluded vascular class. uh which
has also very different distribution
across different slices and was actually
correctly captured by the model as well
as uh the expression of the GFAP uh gene
which is specially variable gene for the
vascular
class. So Luna is uh unique in terms of
kind of learning these spatial priors
across multiple slices. Uh but one could
potentially apply some of the existing
methods to this task. Uh for example,
the most closest methods would be
methods such as tanggram. Uh so these
are methods that are uh that uh map
dissociated cells to a reference data
set but the limitation of these methods
is that you have to have exact spatial
reference to map your dissociated single
cells uh to um to uh your data set.
Another class of methods are methods
such as nova spark where do kind of also
this kind of denovo reconstruction but
they are based on the assumption that if
two cells have similar gene expressions
they should also be specially close
together close to each other which is
not satisfied in complex tissues and
actually the core idea in Luna is that
we try to learn these spatial priors
using AI
methods. So we compared Luna on this
kind of smaller mouse cortex data set
because some of these methods are also
not very scalable. Um and uh if you
don't have any prior information put
into these models, Aluna is actually the
only method that is able to correctly
infer the spatial priors of the tissue.
Here the performance is measured as
spermman's rank correlation where we uh
order cells based on their similarity
and compare uh closeness and then
compare to the ground truth um
ordering. If we put some prior
information about the reference lies for
these baseline methods uh which Luna
does not use uh we still see um large
improvement over existing
methods. So and uh next we were actually
um wanted to really apply Luna to infer
the locations of the single cell RNA
sequencing atlas. So in particular we
take the single cell central nervous
system single cell RNA sequencing atlas.
Um and of course for this we don't have
ground truth cell locations. Uh so in
particular the good thing about this
particular atlas is that we could
estimate the ground truth. Uh because u
there is um star map atlas which one can
integrate with a single cell sequencing
atlas. We don't use it to train Luna or
anything. We just use it to validate uh
whether these predictions would be
correct.
So this is the estimated ground truth
that we observe that we obtained by
integrating uh this uh single cell RNA
sequencing atlas with the star map
atlas. So these are estimated locations
of this single cell RNA sequencing data
and these are predictions that we obtain
by um training Luna on this smurfish
mouse brain atlas and then applying it
to single cell RNA sequencing
data. Um again we see a good resembles
between the estimated ground truth and
Luna's predictions uh also on the
broader classes. And here again I
visualize how the process happens in
Luna. If you look again on the gene
expressions for example the model is
able to correctly capture the
expressions of some of the spatially
variable genes. For example IQ Gap2 gene
which shows down regulation across the
ammon region. It's kind of this um down
reggulation is correctly captured by the
model uh is uh as well as um for example
MFTt gene uh tc gene whose expression is
minimal in the c2 region but then it's
subst substantially upregulated in
risoortex and all all factory areas. So
we can now also use Luna for example to
infer uh the expressions of genes that
have not been seen during model training
because now we can infer this for the
single cell RNA sequencing atlas uh and
look at the spatial distribution of
these unseen genes across different
regions. Um next we were also
interesting whether Luna can overcome
have to overcome limitations on some of
other existing methods. For example,
yesterday we heard about Slitex from F
Chan's lab uh and Evan Makosko's lab. Uh
and Slitex enables this profiling of
single sentence spially resolved uh
transcryto. But the limitation of this
technology is that many nuclei lose
spatial information during the barcoding
process. So we asked the question can we
now use Luna to actually predict the
tissue locations of the nuclei that have
been lost during a cell profiling with
slideex. So here uh we applied it for
the human melanoma data set. So these
are spatially mapped nuclei with slide
tags and then we enriched this data set
uh using Luna by predicting the
locations of these specially um map
nuclei. So Luna successfully enriched
this data set from 4,800 to 6,00 500
cells. If we look at in particular like
two tumor cells that are placed into two
tumor subopuls that are placed into
spatially distant compartments. Uh so
these are uh spatially mapped nuclei
with slide text here are nuclei mapped
by Luna and uh this one group of tumor
cells is expressed in the clue gene
other is expressing the disk 2FP one
gene and this is actually also correctly
captured by the
model. We next investigated whether this
Luna enriched Slitex data set can help
us to increase the power to detect
spatially variable genes um in the human
metastatic melanoma tissue. So we detect
detected specially variable genes using
only on original sample where we were we
were able to find about 400 genes that
are detectable both uh in the original
data set just using original data set
and also Luna enriched data set but
using Luna enriched data set we were
also able to detect additionally uh
about 400 additional spatial variable
genes. If you look at the gene pathways
that are enriched in this um this set of
genes, these are indeed for example the
most significant pathway uh is um the
pathway uh regulated by the uh NYC
gene. We also applied it to other slight
data. So this is for example for the
mouse embriionic data set where it help
to enrich the data set by uh
twice and
uh and so actually Luna could also be
used potentially you know to um to think
about kind of knocking out the effect of
knocking out certain gene and kind of
going potentially towards this kind of
virtual tissue models when we can kind
of knock out certain gene and then ask
what happens to the spatial architecture
of the tissue.
Uh so what we did is we um just trained
the Luna on the one on the all data set
of on the Murphish mouse bin atlas from
an animal one and then during the
inference stage we were interesting to
see what happens if with the predictions
of the Luna if I knock out one gene uh
for per study and then measure the
effect basically of knocking out this
gene on the prediction and the spatial
architecture of the tissue. So in
particular what we can do is we can uh
for every study if I knock out certain
gene I can then measure the effect
knocking out this gene has on the
spatial arc structure. So basically I
get the maximum performance if I include
all genes and then I measure how much
excluding this gene is affecting my
performance and then I can have then I
can identify these genes that can kind
of that have the highest effect on the
spatial on affect on perturbing actually
uh the spatial um uh the spatial
structure of a tissue
um and we can do this for example for
different also cell subclasses. So here
I show example for five different
subclasses and here are genes that have
highest effect on this uh on the spatial
architecture. So for example these are
indeed genes that are very important uh
the crucial genes for the cell identity
and function of these cell classes. For
example, cludin 11 gene um is
oligodendrite specific protein and
previous work has shown that mutant
mouse that lack this protein um exhibit
central auditory deficits uh and the
neurotransmitter imbalances. We can also
do this for pairs like basically seeing
what happens if we exclude pairs of
genes. But of course the number of
combinations in that case is very large.
But what we do is we use existing
receptor lyan databases and only focused
um on certain sub a certain sub only
subset of possible pairs.
And in the last uh part of the my talk,
I want to also quickly talk about how
can we you know now in this kind of era
of big foundation models how can we
actually do something like unsupervised
transfer. How can we use this big
foundation models that people have been
developing to actually tell us you know
what kind of categories exist in the
data in a fully unsupervised fashion.
Um so if you think about you know
current paradigms in which we use these
existing foundation models they still
majorly require supervision. So the
standard way you know if someone gives
you this foundation model we kind of
fine-tune it on the task of interest
using label data. So this is just a toy
example where you know someone gives me
large pre-train foundation model and
then I have my labels and I want to
solve a new task. I would kind of add a
linear classifier uh to distinguish
between different um cell classes.
uh but as we've seen yesterday in
Jennifer's talk as well is basically
that in many cases in in biology we
actually don't have these labeled
examples. So we cannot kind of just add
a linear classifier to solve our task of
interest because we lack the labeled
examples. We cannot have ab abundantly
labeled examples for every possible
class. Ideally we want to use these kind
of big models to tell us what exist in
the data in a fully unsupervised manner.
So alternatively in machine learning
community people do like a zeros
transfer on the task of interest using
instruction set where you basically the
mostam famous example is open eyes clip
model where you have this image encoder
you have the text encoder that encodes
this kind of class descriptions that you
expect to see in the data then you match
them but in this case you still kind of
require to know which kind of classes
you expect to see in your data and this
is still not kind of suitable often for
biology and for biomedical applications.
So the question we ask is how can we
infer this underlying classes without
any supervision. So if one gives me you
know large pre-chain foundation model
and this is like we think about this
very generally. It could be kind of
computer vision foundation model trained
on real world images. It can be single
cell foundation model trained on single
cell data. Uh it could be you know
hisystopathology foundation model
trained on histopathology images. How
can I in an unsupervised way say you
know what classes exist in this data
set? Of course the trivial solution
would be I just run the clustering uh uh
to discover these uh set of classes. But
the question is can we do better than
that um and we call this um unsupervised
transfer because we want to leverage
these foundation models to in an
unsupervised ways transfer knowledge to
a new task that I'm interested to
solve. And the key insight to solve this
problem uh for us was that if you think
about you know how we currently use
these models we use this uh models uh
the key insight is basically that linear
models in representation space
generalize well. So that's why we can
just add a linear classifier on top of
this preient representation and
typically we get very high performance
if we have the
labels. Um and what we observe indeed
that if you look kind of at the
agreement of uh with the ground truth
human labeling of the possible labeling.
If you imagine kind of I give you
labeling you can generate many possible
labelings of these data sets. But if I
measure the agreement with the ground
truth human labeling the generalization
of error of the linear classifier will
be lower. If this is this uh uh is kind
of agrees labeling agrees better with
the ground truth human
labeling. And this um kind of idea
motivates us to develop a framework that
we call turtle. And this is work done by
uh my PhD student and Yulun. Um and the
key idea is that basically we want to
rephrase this unsupervised learning
problem from the representations of
foundation models as a problem of
searching for such labeling so that
linear classifiers will generalize well
in this representation space. So I can
take my data set of interest again it
can be you know whatever foundation
model or whatever data set it is. So
this is just for example this kind of
real world images I can embed it to one
or multiple foundation models. If I have
multiple representations I can leverage
multiple foundation models and now I can
basically solve this problem by finding
such labeling that will give me um low
generalization error of a linear
classifier. So we formulate ble
optimization procedure when in upper uh
in uh in the upper loop we basically
search we generate the possible
labelings and then in the inner part of
the optimization we evaluate how well
does that labeling uh gen how well can
linear classifier generalize on that
labeling and then we optimize over
possible labelings of a given data set.
So I won't go into many details. I'm
happy to chat later. But um basically
searching for these labelings requires
solving discrete optimization problem
over all possible labelings. So instead
we resort to continuous optimization via
relaxation. Uh instead of doing discrete
search over labelings, we do continuous
search over parameters of the task
encoder. uh and we can also show
theoretically that the labelings that
will be uh found by this optimization
procedure under some assumptions are the
labelings that maximize margin of a
linear model in the corresponding uh
representation
space. So
um interestingly this kind of idea
although very simple it actually allows
us to leverage now any foundation models
train linear classifiers on top and
search for the possible labelings. We
show that it achieves state-of-the-art
unsupervised performance across various
benchmarks. So it's available on the
papers with code. You can use it with
any you know your favorite foundation
models. Um uh so this is an example of
the imageet data set where actually the
state-of-the-art method as well as also
many other data sets including for
example
pathological data set of histopathology
images like patch
chameleon. Uh we went also a step
further to compare it to the zeroot
transfer uh like for example to the clip
model that actually uses information
about the classes while turtle is fully
unsupervised and we show if we run the
turtle in the same embedding space as a
clip we have the same performance. Uh
but if you just add another foundation
model which is much cheaper than getting
the labelings for example for from the
clip model uh you just add another
representation space for example here we
just add a dino model um then uh model
significantly outperforms um clip model
across this 26 benchmark data set
achieves a large margin uh a large uh
improvements. We can also apply it to
single cell data. So this is an example
of you know using existing foundation
models for a single cell where you can
do this unsurprised transfer to discover
for example different cell classes that
ex exist in the data. But I would say
disclaimer here is that the core idea of
the method uh is that you know you
assume that the representation space of
foundation model is strong enough which
is sometimes case for this foundation
models by uh that we have for single
cell but sometimes still I think we have
a large space uh to improve uh these
models
um and uh so this is just one slide so
very latest uh in the very latest work
we um also show that we can do
unsupervised adaptation of uh these big
foundation model. So we can even
fine-tune them in an unsupervised way.
So instead of doing this kind of linear
classifier in the inner loop, we kind of
perform in context learning in the inner
loop. Uh and now we show that uh
basically this kind of framework that we
call joint inference that was just
presented as I clear. It can make
predictions simultaneously for all
inputs in a given task. And we show that
this is applicable to for example large
language models, vision language models
and achieves state-of-the-art
performance on the difficult math
reasoning benchmark compared to even uh
this unsupervised ICL can even
outperform supervised ICL on these math
reasoning
benchmarks. Um and finally I would like
to thank my uh amazing PhD students
whose work I presented here. So in
particular yeast who worked on Luna uh
Yulun and Artium uh who worked on turtle
and this also unsupervised inference
framework and uh happy uh to take
questions.
[Applause]
Thank you so much for an amazing talk
Maria. Um
questions thank you fantastic work. Um
just a question about Luna. If I
understand well it's a generative
process that is stochastic. So if you
run it 10 times, you get 10 different
images. Could you comment on the
diversity that you get or is it always
consistent? No, it's not always
consistent because it's a generative
model, right? So of course if you run it
different with different uh you run it
different times, you will see some
variation. Cells would not be exactly
positioned at exactly same locations,
but still this kind of spatial
distribution that I was showing would be
preserved. So in terms of maybe you know
two cells will be kind of switched
locations because but these kind of
results that I was showing they are kind
of consistent across different fronts.
Okay. Thank you. Hi.
Hi there. Uh thanks a lot for a great
talk. Uh I have a question on Luna. So
what are the limitations of L Luna and
what are some of the future directions
that you see? Yeah. So uh yeah uh so
first the major limitation is actually
that tissues are not 2D right uh so for
single cell RNA like ideally one would
actually be able to embed any single
cell sequencing data set in the 3D space
right uh so here for example for single
cell RNA sequencing data we do this kind
of integration you know with the star
map atlas we have this uh you know uh we
know from this which 2D slice the single
cell RNA sequencing data comes but
ideally one would apply this to 3D data.
Uh but I would say this is not really
limitation of Luna because the idea the
core idea would be applicable to the 3D
case but we just don't have the good
data to train this model on the 3D on
the 3D data. So the objective function
and everything we can immediately apply
it for 3D case as well. But uh another
limitation um is that um and what we're
looking now further is basically that uh
currently so when we train the model we
um you assume that you measure for
example existing special transatomics
data sets that you capture this uh the
the basically for example for the
merfish it's okay because we have the
same gene panels but ideally you would
kind of be able to train it across like
different spatial technologies uh then
we would need to kind of be able to
capture also like different gene panels
that can be measured across different uh
data sets. So this is another uh
limitation of the method.
So much uh we sadly have to stop at the
two questions. Thanks again. Uh please
applaud Maria again.