okay well thanks for the intro and
thanks for inviting me it's fun uh I'm
Zach please um I hate talking at people
so please you know like speak up and
harass me uh and I guess I I decided to
open this with like you know the most
videos possible on a single slide I
don't know if that was a good or bad
idea it's like a shock and awe or
something um but yeah hopefully I'll get
to talk about most of these things um
and I I think hopefully from this you
can also glean that I'm like kind of uh
my my two loves are like weird space
things and uh and robots so that's what
we're going to talk about um so first to
open up uh and kind of set the stage a
little bit uh hopefully everyone knows
what this thing
is H definitely not no we have some SP
people in the room right so this is
curiosity right and this thing has been
on Mars for 12 years which is incredible
if you think about it as like a feet of
engineering right this thing's been in
like one of the harshest environments
imaginable uh you know storms crazy
temperatures
dust everywhere all that kind of stuff
uh and in that time it's managed to
travel 32 kilometers sounds pretty good
until you divide those two numbers uh so
like 7.2 meters per day roughly like you
know here to the other side of the room
over there this is not impressive and uh
you know it's sort of a bummer and
unfortunately it limits a lot of the
science we can do on these things and
there's a whole bunch of anecdotes about
this um that I could share but um I
think this kind of sums it up nicely
does anyone know what this is
who's been
here maybe no okay so really letting me
down on the on the space nerd uh you
know stuff here so this is the Mars yard
at JPL uh maybe a couple of You' have
heard of this so basically what this is
a giant sandbox out back at JPL where
they have a bunch of rocks and a
bulldozer and some shovels and they
drive the Rover around so the Rover can
drive autonomously it's pretty cool but
um they're super conservative with it
for obvious reasons right you can't fix
stuff you can't go get it out of the
ditch Etc and it's very expensive so um
anytime it runs into anything scary
looking like a slope more than a few
degrees or a big rock it's uh set up to
just stop and then like look around and
send all the imagery back to Earth and
all the JPL Engineers go out in this
sandbox out back and try to recreate the
environment around the Rover on Earth
with a back hoe and a bunch of shovels
and they kind of put the rocks in all
the same places and then they
painstakingly
handd design a trajectory for the Rover
to go around all the obstacles and test
it a whole bunch and drive it with the
real Rover and then when they're
satisfied that that's going to work they
Uplink it to the Rover and it and it
executes it and then it goes on its way
um this is as you know somewhat
obviously super painstaking lots of
human in the loop kind of stuff and
ultimately limits what they can do with
the Rover anecdotally if you talk to the
the Rover drivers and stuff um if the
Rover stops moving on a Saturday morning
it'll be be stuck until Monday morning
when everyone gets back in from the
weekend if it happens over a holiday it
just won't operate so you'll end up
losing days of op operational time on
this thing because of this kind of thing
and it's sort of constrained by humans
and you know we have to sleep and stuff
eat occasionally so uh it it's actually
a major major thing right okay and so
where we like part one everything is
optimization hopefully some of you agree
with that statement we'll see um but I'm
going to now kind of walk through a
whole bunch of you know of the problems
that we encounter in these sort of
domains that hopefully all you guys have
seen before and how each one of them at
least can be posed as an optimization
problem and in there I'm going to mix it
up a little bit and show you some of the
stuff that that we've done in each of
these specific areas then we're going to
try to bring it all together the first
one you know obviously control is
optimization I don't think I have to
tell you guys in this audience this
right and usually we kind of set things
up like this and we have a model of our
robot maybe or if you're an RL person
maybe you have a blackbox simulator same
thing whatever uh and then you have some
kind of cost function thing that encodes
what you want the system to do right and
maybe some constraints that say you know
your actuator limits and and don't hit
stuff and whatever uh and this is very
powerful and very general right and I I
kind of in this I would I would sort of
subsume all of you know kind of
trajectory optimization and RL and all
of these under this kind of framework
right and just to tease a few of the
things we've been doing in this area uh
we worked a lot on numerical solvers and
in the last year we've had kind of fun
papers on getting these things to be
really computationally efficient so they
can fit on Tiny microcontrollers on
stuff like this crazy fly um and do all
kinds of fun obstacle avoidance and
stuff uh all on board we've also kind of
tried to scale these the other direction
and build new solvers that can run on
Modern compute Hardware like gpus right
and actually take advantage of thousands
of cores this is an example of of a full
body model of the atlas humanoid running
at 2 kerz kind of pretty good if you if
you know how this stuff goes typically
okay so that's you know control um also
people in here I'm sure you know lots of
people do state estimation this is
almost the same problem it turns out um
got your model maybe got some noise in
there and then you've got some kind of
lease squares loss or something that you
minimize to figure out where you are
we've also done some work in this area
specifically um on the space side we've
done a bunch of work on sort of
satellite swarms and um doing kind of
distributed estimation there's actually
a mission we flew this year where we um
did range only relative navigation uh
between satellites and space and
actually got down to 70 CM kind of 3D
position are on this whole thing which
was pretty awesome to actually do it
finally in space um okay and then kind
of moving away from from maybe some of
the stuff that you've seen a lot of to
maybe some stuff that's a little less
familiar is um you can also pose physics
as optimization anyone know what this
thing is yeah so this is you know
Hamilton's principle principle of least
action sometimes people get really
pedantic and tell me it's not least it's
stationary action and I'll fight you on
that if you want to if you want to take
me up on that after this uh so so you
can POS physics as and this is kind of
the the for those who haven't seen this
before that Q of in there is the the
pose of your system configuration of
your system right um and Q dots
obviously the velocity and then this is
the lran right so kinetic minus
potential energy and this is classical
stuff you probably saw in some kind of
you know intro grad level mechanics
course and then you probably did some
weird calculus of variations e thing one
time that you forgot how to do and you
got the oiler lrange equations and if
you're a roboticist you maybe called
that a manipulator equation and then you
know kind of dealt with that from then
on and never really went back to this
optimization formulation so I'm here to
tell you that maybe maybe you should
think about this a little bit more and
there's maybe more to this so um in
particular if we kind of like squint at
this for a second this looks just like a
trajectory optimization problem where
the kind of the pose or configuration
trajectory of the system is kind of
doing State like things um if you and
this is like your your cost function
right integrated along the trajectory
and we can go ahead and discretize this
thing in time just like we would do with
a trajectory optimization problem a
motion planning problem and we can
directly minimize this numerically and
get out physics kind of cool why would
you and by the way this is not a new
idea this is uh from about 20 years ago
from Jerry Marsden at calch and a bunch
of his students pioneered this kind of
thing it's called discrete mechanics um
and there's a whole like kind of
literature on this stuff and the the
main takeaway is you get really cool uh
conservation properties out of this it
conserves energy and momentum and all
kinds of stuff automatically and you
don't have to uh it does very nice
things for the for you we don't really
care about that to be honest um runga
cut is fine for us but there's there's
some other kind of cool things if I can
get it to this state um and it looks
like a trajectory optimization problem I
can apply all the tools I know how to
use from numerical optimization to this
and in particular um if I care about
impacts and and that kind of stuff which
show up all the time in robotics right
if I'm walking or grabbing onto
something that's classically really hard
to deal with because it's nons smooth
and technically you can't even really
write that as an OD uh there's
discontinuities and all kinds of Badness
right well we take this Viewpoint we can
actually um just deal with those as
inequality constraints so if you imagine
like a falling brick and you want to hit
the ground you can just say uh you know
Brick's not allowed to go through the
floor and that's that inequality up
there and then I just kind of turn the
crank on this and solve it as a
constrainted optimization problem and
all the things you expect happen so um
you know the kind of Jacobian of that
constraint becomes the normal Vector the
lrange multiplier becomes the normal
force the kkt conditions end up kind of
telling you all the things you expect
about physics and it's it's really
natural and really cool um and this kind
of you know and it's all all the
numerics are nice and there's no weird
you know super stiff Odes it's kind of
cool um similarly uh friction which is
also annoying and nons smooth can be
posed as an optimization problem anyone
seen this before this is uh called the
um uh maximum dissipation principle so
it turns out if you minimize kinetic
energy uh turns out the force due to
kolum friction is the one that
instantaneously sucks out the most
kinetic energy from the system
subject to this cone constraint called
the friction cone which is really just a
generalization of that whole like New
Times normal force thing you saw in high
school or whatever that's kind of cool
too U okay all this physics stuff uh and
then another one that we see all the
time in these kind of Robotics
applications is Collision detection so
this is you know if I'm like the falling
brick example well if I have slightly
more complicated geometry just saying if
you're touching or not becomes kind of a
non-trivial problem right if I have some
complicated robot with fingers and I
want to go grasp over here I have to
figure out what the closest points
between all my fingers are and this you
know non-convex object and that's kind
of tricky it turns out and computer
graphics people and video game people
have spent decades trying to trying to
make this work reliably and be fast and
that's all great um and it turns out um
we we've also kind of looked into this
recently from the perspective of
differentiability and as you can kind of
imagine if I take two convex objects you
know and I ask for the closest point
between those you know distance two Norm
a convex thing and if the shapes are
convex you can kind of like convince
yourself pretty easily that's a convex
optimization problem um unfortunately
though that has some problems in
particular if the two objects penetrate
each other and they kind of overlap that
problem becomes ill posed and sort of
breaks and that happens actually
somewhat regularly in in real data uh
with noise and in other kind of context
so one of my PhD students recently came
up with this thing which is really slick
so it it reformulates the problem so
rather than asking for the closest point
it asks for the minimum sort of scaling
uniform scaling of these two objects
such that they just touch and that's
kind of slick it turns out this is
always well posed and always has a
solution and it's also differentiable so
you can get like nice gradients out of
this for other Downstream you know
applications super cool uh we call that
deall um okay so Collision detection so
now hopefully I've shown you like most
of the problems I care about as a you
know kind of motion plan and control
robotics person uh at least can be posed
maybe not don't have to be but can be
posed as optimization problems so next
part two how do we put all these things
together right so I showed you all of
these pieces are nice clean little
self-contained optimization Problems But
ultimately I need to wire it all
together right I need the Collision
detection thing to inform the friction
and contact physics stuff which needs to
talk to the control algorithm right so
it all has to work together and that
turns out to be kind of tricky um so as
a brief interlude into into part two I
want to talk a little bit about this
kind of contact stuff which has Obsessed
me for um the better part of a decade
now so this all seems fine right this is
our optimal control problem we solv
before but if I'm doing something like
this little quadraped robot over here
where I'm making a breaking contact with
the environment whole bunch the kind of
alluded to before um that's nons smooth
right so if you write down kind of
normal f equals ma stuff for that you
end up with either really really stiff
Odes that are a huge pain to deal with
or you end up with sort of switching
constraints that are uh sort of integer
flavored which is also bad um so you
kind of have this smoothness issue
floating around and it turns out
standard numerical techniques for
solving these problems kind of don't
apply here and you need to do something
else there's there's kind of a couple
ways people have typically dealt with it
one which is I would say kind of the
industry standard approach is this
so-called hybrid approach and that is
kind of doing that integer flavored
thing where you enumerate all the times
and locations where contact switches
happen and you have to do this with some
kind of heuristic or some Oracle or
whatever so if you know those times then
you can bake them into the problem
formulation as given and basically get
them out of the optimization problem and
then you're just optimizing over the
smooth arcs between those context
switching events and that's back to a
problem we know how to solve well so
that's one approach the downside is now
you need some way to pre-specify those
what are called mode switches um so you
you know in leged robotics maybe this
isn't too hard if your you know Left
Foot Right Foot but it it quickly breaks
down and becomes intractable if you're
doing like really complicated inhand
manipulation stuff where the contacts
can be really rich that can be super
hard right okay so I have to say though
this this is kind of I I alluded to this
is kind of the standard thing to do and
it's been really really successful so
you know we've all seen these videos um
this is kind of what these guys are
doing and and every other you know
really cool looking legged robot video
for that matter but these guys have
taken us obviously really really far um
okay so the other thing I love about
these guys though is they actually
published the blooper video videos we're
going to look at one of these blooper
videos real quick and I want to actually
ask you to look really carefully uh at
when these um these kind of you know
bloopers happen so this is a really good
one that I slowed down so what happened
there why did it face
plant putot touch the beam right so in
in the lingo that we were just kind of
like you know kind of going for here um
with you know modes and all this kind of
stuff what happened there was an
unplanned contact switch
so another way of saying this right if
I'm doing this pre-specification of flit
steps and all this the controller is uh
really open loop on the contact modes I
have to pre-specify when those things
are happening I might have some outer
loop heuristics that are trying to
update those things online but the the
actual control uh opal control solver
that's doing this at you know a couple
hundred Herz or whatever it can't reason
about uh anything like that so when the
foot touches the you know the ground uh
or the the beam there the controller
doesn't know about that it doesn't know
that the environment can exert forces at
that location on the body it has just no
knowledge of whatsoever and it
completely fails so this is kind of I I
would argue a really deep issue that we
don't currently have control methods
that can reason about uh this kind of
physics in a in a rigorous way okay so
there is another way uh this is called
Contact implicit and people have been
working on this for you know decade plus
um including you know people here uh and
historically the is is with this here
you're trying to solve for the the whole
thing right the the modes the contact
forces and the problem with that right
is all this non- smoother integer
flavored Badness so typically these have
like really serious numerical problems
they either take way too long to solve
or you end up with ill conditioning
because of stiff you know Odes and it
just kind of hasn't really worked out
that great historically okay so now
we're going to try to like fix those
problems and I'm going to kind of walk
you through the way that uh sort of like
we've come up with thinking about this
in my lab I call this composable optim
so the gist is all these little blocks I
just walked you through we've developed
techniques for solving those well and
ultimately we need to hook them together
and so now I'm going to talk through
like how we approach that hooking
together and essentially like jointly
solving this entire coupled mess of
optimization problems jointly right okay
so the the first key idea here is what
we call a differentiable interior Point
method we've seen interior Point methods
before like pretty standard way to solve
constrainted optimization problems right
okay so we're going to like go with this
sort of very simple prototypical problem
where you've got cost function and a
single like inequality constraint just
to kind of illustrate the idea and the
thing that's key here is that we're
minimizing over X so X is what we call
the decision variable and then there's
this other variable floating around Y
which we're not optimizing over and
we'll call that the problem data or
problem parameter or something like this
so the idea is that the solution to this
thing depends on why but we're not
optimizing over why it's like this sort
of input to the problem cool
okay so I said that out loud okay so
what we're going to do now is imagine
that this block here is the K friction
box just for illustrative purposes right
so that's this block we're going to zoom
in a little bit so for for illustrative
purposes right this inequality is going
to be that friction cone thing that we
talked
about and this x is going to be the
friction Force so we're trying to solve
for the friction Force but remember that
thing also depends on the normal force
right so I'm not optimizing over the
normal force but the friction answer
depends on the magnitude of the normal
force so that normal force is going to
be our our problem parameter right that
this thing depends on okay so and you
could flip this around right if this
were the uh the normal force coming from
the the contact the impact mechanics box
right and if you flip this around that
impact mechanics thing depends on the
coolum friction and it's solving for the
normal force right so there's kind of
symmetry there you can hook these all
together but they all depend on each
other right okay so uh first trick is we
take this thing and this is just
interior Point methods 101 we're going
to take that inequality constraint and
and varried inside this thing called a
log barrier it's just a log which blows
up as the C of X as that constraint
approaches zero right and we stick it in
the objective function so how we
basically remove the constraint and put
it inside the cost and just to kind of
give you an idea of what this looks like
right we have this little tuning
parameter row out front which we call
the barrier parameter the idea is as you
crank that this log which is nice and
smooth kind of gradually approaches a
brick wall which is non- differentiable
right so in the limit becomes
non-differentiable but for any finite
row it's differentiable and nice and
right we've been doing this for decades
now and it's super Works super well and
that sort of smoothing effect is what
lets you actually get gradients out and
solve this thing efficiently with with
Newton's method or whatever you like
Okay cool so this thing we take this and
then we're going to write down the
optimality conditions for this guy which
are kkt conditions if you if you know
what that is but I'll really just like
basically setting the gradient equal to
zero right like freshman calculus kind
of stuff and set the gradient equal to
zero and solve that root finding problem
for zero right there so that's what
we're going to call R okay so that's you
know I take the gradient of this thing
with respect to X set it equal to zero
still depends on y though right okay so
the key next move is if I've got that I
can use this trick called the implicit
function theorem we've seen this before
couple people so the idea here is if I
got that R of X and Y I tailor expand it
in both X and Y and I just kind of move
move stuff over to one side and I can
solve for
dxdy okay so now what this did for me is
all together now this block I can treat
it as a normal function X of Y and I
have its derivative DX Dy internally
it's doing some crazy stuff with you
know a numerical solver but outside the
box it just looks like a normal function
that I can query and I can also query it
for its derivativ so now in principle I
can take this entire optimization solver
and treat it as just any other
differentiable function can do whatever
I want with it I can optimize with it I
can bury it inside a constraint function
and another optimization problem I can
put in an objective function whatever I
want and this is kind of the the magic
trick that lets you do this wiring Okay
cool so far feel free to bug me and
interrupt if you you know have thoughts
yeah turns out log the log barrier is
somewhat magical there's a whole like
really highly developed theory for these
interior Point methods you can use other
barrier functions the main property you
need to have is that they blow up to
Infinity at the constraint boundary
that's why they're called interior they
keep you inside the feasible region
uh you can use some other functions
these things um there's this magic this
is not going to make any sense you can
look this up if you want it's called a
self-concordant function and that's what
you really want for a barrier to be nice
it basically means its higher order
terms and its tailor series are bounded
in a nice way such that Newton's method
or gradient-based optimization methods
that rely on tailor expansions work well
on it so that's kind of why log is nice
there are other examples of barriers
that have that property that you can
make up or find But like everyone uses
log and it works super well
yeah you want to you absolutely do yeah
yeah so this is a thing there's been a
bunch of work on this convex layers from
ziko couter and and others um basically
the other option here is to if you did
autod diffing for example on this
algorithm it's going to unroll the
solver Loop and you're so this thing
might take you know a dozen iterations
to con converge if you unroll that with
an autod diffing toolbox it's it's going
to take a ton of memory and basically
just not work so what this lets you do
is you can hand code uh this this you
know uh the other thing to mention is
that that Jacobian you if you solve this
with Newton's method for instance where
you're you're already evaluating those
derivatives so this is free so at
convergence the algorithm I can give you
that Jacobian for free almost cool
anybody else all right moving on okay so
what do we do with this so the first
thing we did with this is we kind of
wired these blocks together like the
impact Dynamic stuff coolum friction and
collision detection stuff made a
simulator we call this thing Dojo U it's
kind of cool in that it has these these
kind of nice properties that I would
argue no other simulator really has um
in spite of lots of investment by lots
of big tech companies so first of all it
it does real hard contact as in you know
I don't get forces off the ground in the
air and I don't penetrate through the
ground both of these are very common in
current robotic simulators for various
reasons um you also don't get yes you
don't get any inter penetration where
you sink into the floor which you know
things like Moko do that a lot um you
also don't get creep so it turns out a
bunch of these other simulators they do
very smoothing tricks and they can't
actually do kolum friction which is
fundamentally non-s smooth so they can't
do stick slip so if you put something on
an inclin plane it's always going to
creep a little bit it never actually
gets sticking friction which is annoying
and then I kind of alluded to before
that we get really nice energy and
momentum conservation properties because
of that magical uh discret mechanic
stuff which we don't NE care too much
about but it is nice it means you're
stable and you can take big time steps
and that kind of stuff simulate really
quickly and the last one right as we we
already know we can we can actually give
you the gradients of all this stuff that
lets us do optimization in kind of
outside of this in an outer loop and a
couple examples that right so this is
just showing you this is like showing
you the derivatives of an impact or a
stick slip trans transition as a
function of that row barrier parameter
so I can give you any smooth version of
this you want and kind of one of the
interesting things here is that I can
simulate the hard impact which is the
black line but then if you want to do
optimization that's terrible so the idea
is I give you the answer with the hard
impact but then if you ask me for the
gradient I give you one of those pink
curves and I cach them as I converge and
I can give you any one of those you want
so you kind of give me this kind of
relaxation that you're willing to
tolerate on the derivatives um but you
can still get the real physics answer
which is kind of an interesting thing um
okay so I get gradients now I'm going to
tell you I lied to you a little bit uh
about something subtle and I just want
to point this out because it's very
subtle um and I I stole this language
from the like FEA cfd people which we'
we started talking about for some other
stuff um so they have this notion of
strong versus weak coupling and this is
like a good illustration of it so the
thing on the left is what I would call
weekly coupled what's going on here if I
have this Collision detection box and
this impact mechanics box right if I
just treat these like functions and
query them which is what most simulators
right now do about by the way so if I
have these boxes and they're about to
collide and I ask you for the closest
point between the two boxes if I have
these two boxes and let's say
everything's perfect right and I it's in
my simulator if I put them like this
right on top of each other what's the
closest point between those two
boxes it's it's ill posed right it can
be anything on that surface um so how do
I pick one if I use a collision Library
which is standard right there's fcl
there's things like this out there and
give it that problem it has to return an
answer to me so what's it going to do
well in general it's going to regularize
somehow and it's probably going to give
me something like the geometric Center
at the centroid of that face perfectly
reasonable in the absence of any other
you know choice right so if I just run
my simulator where I query that
Collision detection thing get the point
and then plug it into my simulator with
some force model and simulate a step you
get the thing on the left so basically
what's happening there is it's it's
giving me the centroid um but it doesn't
know anything about the mass
distribution of the boxes or anything
else and so it turns out if you line
these up off center even a little bit
they can't balance on top of each other
you get this weird unphysical artifact
of them bouncing in practice all these
simulators Implement a bunch of hacks to
try to avoid this but it's it's there
from the the fundamentals of the
formulation what you want to do instead
is this thing on the right which we call
strongly coupled so what that is really
doing is embracing this idea that these
um these things depend on each other and
you have to solve them jointly and
something really cool actually happens
here so this Collision thing where I I
have the face on face box thing that's
ill posed it turns out if I take that
problem and solve it jointly with the
physics problem the physics problem is
using that least action thing you can
kind of think of that as like an energy
minimization kind of metric right turns
out that energy minimization thing from
the impact Dynamics regularizes the
Collision detection problem if you solve
them jointly and the answer you get out
for the closest point is the one that
minimizes the action like basically
minimizes the energy and then you get
then it gives you the correct balance
point and it all works out and you get
like sort of physically the right kind
of simulation so um to explain in a
little more detail like what this
actually looks like under the hood we
have these two boxes and we talked about
writing down their first order necessary
conditions their their gradients the
first one I'm solving with respect to X
so that might be you know the Collision
uh detection stuff and X is the closest
point and then Y is like the pose right
and then the second one might be our
impact Dynamics where Y is you know the
pose and X is the closest point right so
vice versa and I write down the first
order necessary conditions for both of
them so great and equal zero stuff I
stack them together like this so they're
coupled right those those kkt conditions
those first order conditions they depend
on each other and if I stack them like
this and solve that problem jointly uh
with say Newton's method then I get the
right answer basically so they're able
to inform each other as you iterate
inside the solver and give you the right
answer okay so far so good they have
anything bug me with all right
okay so we can do lots of cool things
with this I mentioned you know we get
the smooth gradients and all the all
that stuff so you can do kind of uh kind
of vanilla trajectory optimization stuff
you can do RL that's the middle one
where you actually use the gradients and
just do actual gradient descent instead
of like SGD kind of stuff and that has
obvious benefits you can also do system
ID so we diff through this kind of
collision stuff and solve for the Box
geometry um and you can do kind of other
fun motion planning things that thing on
the bottom um is using gradients to
solve this like kind of simple motion
planning problem an arm okay cool we
have
gradients um so we care about doing
control we spend a lot of time thinking
about trajectory optimization and model
predictive control in my group and so
now we've got all these pieces right and
we could go solve this trajectory
optimization problem so we did that here
are some examples um punchline though
these took like 10 or 20 minutes to
solve offline which is obviously
terrible and not going to be real time
so then you start asking the question
okay I want to do this online I want to
do it in real time what can we
approximate from this thing try to speed
it up
without losing the core kind of flavor
right so we start approximating things
the the key Insight here is we want to
keep this block structure and keep this
overall sort of solver method where
we're jointly solving all these
optimization problems we're going to
zoom inside each box and start
approximating things inside the box so
specifically in that optimal control
problem instead of trying to solve it
from scratch we're going to solve a
tracking problem so that lets us locally
approximate the Dynamics and everything
around some reference that makes that
easier
um inside the Dynamics there we can loc
it turns out we can locally linearize a
bunch of stuff we're not linearizing
anything about the contact Dynamics but
like the sort of um manipulator dynamics
of the robot right we can we can
linearize a bunch of those about a
reference do reference tracking uh we
can also linearize the sign distance
functions in this guy so we can
approximate those in a way that's that's
fast and
cheap um and we can also approximate the
friction cone and uh uh a way that's
standard in robotics what sounds weird
maybe at first so this is a it's a round
cone right like an ice cream cone uh you
can linearize this uh by approximated as
a pyramid with flat faces that's another
standard approximation uh you take an
inner approximation Okay cool so we do
all that stuff and then it turns out we
can do this really fast so there's a
couple examples so this is one we call
the punch bot it's an inverted pendulum
with a little arm and it can push
against these
walls and we've initialized this about
that kind of balancing point with no
other information so it I mean it
obviously knows you know in there the GE
omes in there so it kind of knows it can
reach out and touch the walls but
there's no information about you know
contact modes or any of that in the
problem uh it's linearized inverted
pendulum Dynamics blah blah blah we hit
this thing and it can kind of reach out
and figure out how to balance this runs
at a couple hundred Hertz um it's pretty
good this one is one of my favorite and
this is one like I actually saw this and
was like okay this is actually going to
work now so this is a quadruped model a
dumb quadruped model we call the point
foot model so it's a single rigid body
with Point Mass feet and the reference
in here that we gave this is trotting at
the origin trotting in place at the
origin so that's all it has it has this
nice periodic linearization about the
origin just doing that chop thing and
then we just kick the crap out of it it
flies through the air flails around
lands on its feet figures out you know
how to catch itself it reaches out a
little bit and then it trots back to the
origin all of this is coming out of a
single linearization when I saw this you
know I was I was like super because
normally to get this kind of behavior
out of standard methods there's a bunch
of push recovery her istics right
thinking about where to put your foot so
that it sort of can arrest your fall and
and cancel out your momentum all this
kind of stuff this just comes right out
of this so I don't know I thought this
was really impressive and cool maybe
it's not that impressive in light of you
know things you've probably already seen
right um okay so we we've done this on
Hardware these are not you know amazing
either but still kind of cool that this
actually runs at real-time rates and
it's totally you know there's no contact
information pre-planned in here um and
we started like messing around with you
know if you can do this and you can
reason about contacts all over the body
most of the methods out there right now
assume point contacts with the feet here
we've got all the body geometry though
so you can like do weird things with the
rest of the body which is kind of
interesting this is early stuff we've
got better stuff now that um is not
quite out yet so stay tuned doing some
fun things with this um okay so that's
kind of how we did this now I want to
kind of like close up a little bit with
part three what else can we do with all
this stuff so there's actually there's a
very rich set of connections between the
stuff I just showed you and a whole
bunch of other areas of optimization and
whatever um so in
particular uh this kind of problem
formulation where we have all these
coupled optimization problems that we
solve jointly um does that look familiar
to
anybody so so this is exactly it turns
out a nash game a Nash equilibrium from
Game Theory which is a very very rich
problem domain that we've dabbled in a
bit to um it turns out I was doing this
stuff for contact mechanics and I talked
to someone who's a game theory person
and then I realized oh wait all the
solver tools we're building like
actually solving Nash equilibrium
problems actually so what we solve here
is is what's called a uh generalized
Nash equilibrium problem it's when you
have a bunch of players and they all
have constraints and they're trying to
you know sort of do the best they can so
that kind of weird stacked set of kkt
conditions we write down is actually the
conditions for a generalized Nash
equilibrium so you do other cool things
with that um we've played around with
autonomous driving for this which is um
you have a bunch of you know drivers and
they're trying to negotiate you know
merging on the highway for example has
anyone heard of the Frozen robot problem
it's a classic where if you have cars if
you have an autonomous car with
collision avoidance constraints in its
sort of setup where it's not allowed to
hit anybody if it's trying to merge into
dense traffic bumper to- bumper traffic
on the highway it'll just sit at the
bottom of the off on ramp and just
freeze and not go anywhere the reason
this happens is it looks you know over
there and it says there's not a space in
between the cars big enough for me to
fit through what do we do in that case
we're like oh well if I just kind of
nudge my way in there I'm going to force
the other drivers to make space for me
right but if you just have collision
avoidance constraints you can't reason
about that that's fundamentally sort of
a multi-agent game theoretic concept
right what you're doing there is
thinking about the other agents behavior
and kind of what they're going to do in
response to you right and that actually
is very naturally modeled by this uh
Nash equilibrium thing so we've done
that kind of stuff turns out also uh
under the framework we've kind of set up
here uh Falls a lot of classic robust
control stuff so Minx games stackle BG
equilibria all that kind of stuff also
falls into here and and we've done like
toy examples of that stuff where you're
sort of games against nature where you
have a disturbance input and you're
trying to make that's trying to make
your life bad and worse uh and then
you're trying to do the best you can in
spite of this worst case disturbance
stuff so these are like toy examples of
a rocket Landing with fluid slos model
that way they're kind of fun so lots of
interesting stuff there with like Game
Theory kind of stuff with this these
ideas um we've also dabbled a little bit
in manipulation stuff um and we're still
working on that this is kind of a fun
example where we um we took Collision
checking method that we have decall and
it turns out um if you do something like
this so I've always thought you know a
lot of the work in robotics decomposes
objects into meshes or uh a bunch of
like convex
um um sort of it does like a convex
decomposition where it breaks it into a
bunch of convex bodies or whatever and
to me this is always a little bit weird
in that you know the environment if I'm
going into a new space I don't know what
that stuff looks like a priority but the
robot I know what the robot looks like a
priority so we've done here is done this
convex decomposition thing offline for
the robot but then the new object in the
environment we're modeling with a point
Cloud which is kind of what you get
already out of your perception system
right so the idea here is this G call
thing parallelizes across all those
points super trivially we implemented it
on a on a GPU with Jacks and it turns
out we can do like 5,000 points in the
same amount of time as one by putting it
on a GPU so now we can have like 5,000
points on this bunny which has got a
really weird crazy non-convex geometry
and we can do it in real time because we
can solve for all the points in parallel
which is kind of cool and kind of I
think the idea here is to to try to get
ourselves closer to using the sensory
data that we are getting on these things
online in our simulations right so be
able to pull this kind of really complex
geometry natively just take that point
cloud with minimum minimal processing
and pull it right into your simulator um
and then kind of along these lines right
one of the things that i' I've kind of I
started started hearing people talk
about a bit more um we hear all this
kind of stff about the Sim toore Gap in
in robotics especially you know RL kind
of stuff um Sim to real transfer and how
you know errors in the simulator make
this harder um and it's always bothered
me we haven't seen so much real to sim
what classically we would have called
system ID in robotics with these
simulators where we kind of go do this
stuff on Hardware then rather doing than
doing like transfer learning where
you're trying to take your offline learn
policy and tweak it a little bit why
don't we take that same data and pump it
back into the simulator and try to
improve our models in the simulator so
we don't have to do that again next time
right so you can imagine all kinds of
stuff like actuator models compliance in
the robot weird friction effects um
maybe better geometry right all this
stuff we could be taking this Rich data
and pulling it back in and making our
our simulator making our models better
uh and particularly the
differentiability of this whole pipeline
enables this right I can just do normal
lease squares kind of stuff on the data
because I can diff through the whole
simulator
pipeline okay and then uh last thing to
briefly is this kind of idea this like
data driven kind of Sid control stuff we
we've actually started doing this
recently with um a few collaborators in
Quantum Computing it turns out the
making cubits work it turns out is hard
and the models are bad right and there's
lots of noise so we started doing this
sort of thing on these Cubit systems
with some cabers um a quantum computer
that one of our collaborators Dave
Schuster who's at Stanford now has that
we've actually run these kind of
algorithms on and sort of improved the
gate fidelities on these systems
um by quite a lot and I think we're
we're hitting kind of state-of-the-art
fidelities now in this Quantum Gates
kind of cool um okay with that um I have
been extremely lucky to have all these
really awesome students uh work with me
over the last five years or so who
really done all the stuff I just showed
you um and uh that's that's who makes
all the magic happen so thanks to all
these guys and um yeah this is how you
can find me if you want to harass me
some more and uh I'm happy happy to chat
more whatever you guys want to do right
now
[Applause]