I have literally, a very good memories from
my childhood a lot of books because this
was the main entertainment.
It sounded like life in a totally totally
different world because the life was very
much limited to what you know.
There was no internet. The TV or radio
were very very filtered.
So the books were really the only way of
escape and seeing that there is much
bigger world out there.
I haven't been in Moldova since we left
and I was 20 when we left.
Surprisingly, despite the fact that it
was part of Soviet Union and it was
communist country, it was very peaceful.
A lot of light, sun, beautiful buildings,
a lot of flowers and plants.
I was always an excellent student. I was
always competing to be
number one in my class.
In my last year of high school when the
perestroika started and all of a sudden
from this very peaceful, maybe
artificially peaceful environment,
everything really falls
apart in a very short time.
There were demonstrations, there were a
lot of people who were misplaced and then
my family left to Israel.
I always thought that I wanted to be a
maths teacher. It was clear to me that
that's kind of what I'm interested in.
And at the time I realized that maybe I
don't want just to do teaching because
you're always teaching
with the same textbook.
So I couldn't imagine myself, you know,
for the next 30 years coming
and teaching the same material.
That's how I ended up going and doing my
masters in computer science.
The internet was only in the very early
stages, but it was clear from the
beginning that there
are so many possibilities.
I selected somebody who I liked as a
professor and he told me that he's doing
natural language processing.
What was interesting, that the field was
so early on, just jump in, claim some
territory, it's not building up.
And I really like this freedom of
uncovering new things and being able to
go in new direction and see how it works.
In 2014 I got breast cancer.
Information technology really didn't play a
significant part in what was going on in
patient diagnostics and treatment.
So when I came back to MIT, there are two
things that happened.
One, I really wanted to
do something to change it.
And second, I started thinking in my
life, and at the time I was interested in
deciphering ancient languages, is it the
best way to contribute to humanity?
So I was in this big dilemma with myself,
you know, what is
meaningful? Like, what is my role?
I decided to work on machine learning for
small molecules. It
was really a new area.
Today, machine learning plays an
important role in drug discovery already,
but it's still not a dominant technology.
It's still not the case that for many
diseases for which we don't have the good
treatments like neurodegenerative
diseases or advanced cancer,
this machine learning really helped us to
change it. So I think it's something that
will come in the next few years, but we
really have to push it to
make this dream a reality.
MIT is a very special place, and the more
time is spent here, the more you see it,
because there are so many
brilliant people around you.
A lively place where a lot of
intellectual things happen. It actually
goes across different ages.
You see these students who really come
here, and they're ready to change the
world, and they would spend day and night
trying to think about ideas that other
perceive as crazy, and
they're excited about it.
It's really an exciting place to be.