okay so here we
are
uh
hi we're just starting yeah we are a bit
late
okay so
so today we um talk about liquid Vapor
uh equilibrium in
mixtures you we have seen something
already when we did the the Gibbs phase
Rule and
uh
you remember that um if we have U
if we consider the list
of properties of these properties like
temperature
pressure uh the
compositions of say two phases for
example a
liquid and a
gas
phase um depending on how many
components you
have uh R is the number of
components
plus
two uh minus the number of
phases this was called the variance
namely the number of these variables
that are uh independently
changeable uh so that you remain in the
same kind of uh
equilibrium like in this case we talking
about liquid Vapor but you could also we
also talk a little bit about solid
liquid and and you could also do it for
solid vapor and so
on um
okay of
course the chemical
potentials as usual will play major
role as they did in order to derive the
Gib space rule
so the first uh
uh result that we want to derive is the
R's
law R's law has to do with uh and we'll
do it for the simplest situation so the
simplest situation will be one uh
like one of these two
cases uh this one is a liquid a liquid
solution with compon components one and
two for example you can think of water
as being component one and two could be
salt so this is salt
water and it is in mutual
equilibrium with a a gaseous
phase in which there is also water so
one and there is another component three
for example it could be
air because humid air air has some
humidity and humidity is water
vapor so this is for example salt
water uh and humidair moist air in uh
Mutual
equilibrium we are considering the case
that um we will do this as a major
example in which
the uh other
component in this case air so the
molecules of oxygen and nitrogen in air
are
noncondensible so you do not find them
in the liquid
phase and
conversely the other component in the
liquid phase salt is nonvolatile so you
don't find it in the vapor f
that means that for Mutual
equilibrium it is required only that the
chemical potential of the component that
can be exchanged between the two phases
be equal so it means that the chemical
potential of water in the liquid must be
equal to the chemical potential of water
vapor in uh the gases
phas and this is one
example the
other is
uh liquid over a solid so again think of
water and
salt and this is
ice okay so again salt uh we assume is
not um
freezing so it's it's a solute of the
liquid solution but it doesn't
freeze and
uh and therefore we need only equality
of chemical potential of component one
between this and this and this actually
is not a mixture it's just a pure
component I mean this is just pure
eyes and of course the example
this example is
the is very practical for example when
you put salt in on
the uh side
walks um for avoiding freezing uh for
for changing the temperature at which
freezing
occurs and this is also uh you put salt
in water and that will change the
boiling pond point of this of the
solution so when you
make
pasta uh you and you have salted your
water the boiling point is not 100
degrees celus is just a little bit more
depending on how much salt you
put okay
so so how do we derive R's law
as usual we only need to apply the
equality of chemical potentials and then
uh manipulate the equations
somehow so uh let's say that we have two
phases that for the moment we call A and
B just generic fa two
phases so the chemical potential of
component one in Phase
a we going to uh
assume uh to derive R's slw ideal
mixture or solution behavior for all
components
uh or actually for this component not
for all components for this component
and
um so this is the
pure uh phase a pure component one plus
the RT the log of the mole fraction of
component one in in in the phase and
then we rewrite the chemical potential
at pressure
p we rewrite it by integrating the
derivative of the chemical potential
with respect to P from P to P
sat Pat being the saturation temperature
at which the pure substance at that
temperature changes or boils or
freezes okay so this uh we
so we rewrite this
as chemical potential at another
pressure and we pick the saturation
pressure and then we integrate the
derivative and remember that the
derivative is just a specific
volume and then we do exactly the same
also for the other uh phase
B just change the A's in
B's then we recall that when we have a
pure substance this is the reason why we
decided to use the the saturated
saturation pressures when we have a pure
substance the saturation pressure is
defined precisely by that pressure at
which at the given temperature the two
chemical potentials of the two phases
are equal so they are in mutual
equilibrium so liquid and Vapor for
example uh at the boiling point uh have
uh equal temperature equal pressure and
equal chemical potential but the three
are not independent and uh the equality
of chemical potential defines the
saturation uh pressure at that
temperature so that means that this and
that cancel because they are equal the
moment we equate the two chemical
potentials these two will cancel and we
are left with just the remaining terms
and so these remaining terms apart with
the logarithms that be put together the
logarithm of becomes the logarith of the
ratio of the mo
fractions and the integral you can put
it in this form is the integral of the
difference between the
specific volumes of the pure phases pure
substance in in the two different
phases so this is uh what you would call
vfg for example or
vjf it's the
volume of vaporization or freezing and
so on of the pure
substance so this
connects the
compositions of these
mixtures to
properties of pure
substance for example if we take uh uh
this case
where we have a air
on moist air on on on salted water then
for air we can assume the uh for the
specific volume we can assume the ideal
gas
law for the liquid we can assume liquid
water assume Inc compressible fluid
model so that the volume is constant
specific volume is constant
remember these are molar specific
volumes and then you do the integral
here so do the integral for for
the this is the part that contributed by
the fact that the volume is constant so
it's just a difference in the limits of
integration and the other is you
integrate DP over P so you get the
logarithm of
P so
this is the
result now it turns
out
that this term
here is much smaller than uh than one
and therefore much smaller than this
other
uh value which is the logarithm of RT *
the logarithm so
U if you neglect
that and you can compute it and and find
that for example even for very high
pressures and uh uh normal temperatures
uh for liquid water and typical
temperatures you this is of the order of
less than one
100 which is definitely enough lower
than one to be neglect
negligible and and so you neglect that
if you consider it it would be called
what is called the
pointing pointing effect the pointing
contribution so what we are doing is
currently is um um normally described as
neglecting the pointing
correction and pointing is a is the name
of a person
so the the end result yeah this is a
square bracket to
many uh we find that log and log can go
away and you get the ratio of the mole
fraction of water uh in the air so
that's the moist
content over the the more
fraction of water in the
solution and here it is a solvent so
it's the predominant uh
uh you you could also apply it for for
pure water in this case y1f is equal to
one then that is equal and this is R's
law to the ratio of the pressure over
the saturation pressure of pure
water this is the formula you can also
remember then that the since the for an
ideal
gas uh mixture um ideal Gibs Delton
mixture of ideal gas is the partial
pressure uh of the component is equal to
the mole fraction times the pressure of
the mixture this can also be written as
the partial
pressure and so the partial pressure of
the uh component one in the mixture is
equal to the mole fraction in the liquid
times the saturation pressure
of component
one if you apply the same formula here
equation one for the case of liquid and
solid F and J for
solid so that means
eyes both the volumes can be considered
constant so they get out of the
integral and so you have the difference
so the volume of freezing the change
that little change in uh density between
pure water and the ice that make so that
the ice floats on water that's the uh
volume of
freezing and
um and so R slw become takes this other
form so it gives
you um the mole
fraction of water in the
solution in terms of the difference in
pressure saturation pressure this time
this is the saturation pressure of
course of the liquid ice
transition times that volume of freezing
ided by
RT so with this you can
compute uh
these relations and these have to
do with the phase
rule so for example in this
case we have
U since it is a binary
mixture it has uh just two
components okay
but of
course of course uh
the second Mo fraction is is one minus
the the the first and so you have one
relation between these two and the same
another relation between these and then
we
have the relations between the chemical
uh
potentials that uh remove two other
relations and so you are left with the
fact that the moment you fix uh
temperature and the
pressure uh everything is
set so the mole
fractions are fixed like here you cannot
change
arbitrarily the mole fraction and still
uh stay in mutual
equili and here also you
cannot the ratio of the mole fraction of
the the of the liquid and the vapor is
is fixed by the given temperature and
pressure um you can
U interpret
u in a molecular
way uh the r law
see R's law says uh for
example here we are considering a a
different situation than the one before
in which um not
only component one but also component
two can go um um Can can cross
phase so it it can be for example the FG
case it can be both volatile and
condensable as this would be for
example wine wine is a solution of uh of
alcohol and and um and water and when
you boil that you'll get a vapor in
which you have both alcohol and water
but they are in different
uh compositions so the mo when the are
in mutual equilibrium the mole fraction
uh of alcohol in in the liquid phase is
different from the mole fraction of
alcohol in the vapor
phase so R's law gives you which is
written here
again partial
pressure of say water is equal to the
mole fraction times the saturation
pressure and if you have two components
you have two RS slw one also for the
second component because now that also
component two can be exchanged you
should write also the CH equality of
chemical potential for that
component so you get a second
equation
and you see uh here
the the the the idea
the molecular interpretation is this if
you have a pure
substance at
equilibrium um there is somehow
uh an
exchange
um an equilibrated balanced exchange of
molecules that are in the vapor phas
that go down in the liquid and some and
an equal amount of molecules that from
the surface surf of the liquid go up in
the vapor phase and this is for
component one and this is for component
two now when you have a
mixture uh you see that on the surface
you have some dark and some gray uh
particles so the this Dynamic exchange
that occurs between the the liquid and
occurs
only proportional to the amount of of of
dark particles for the dark ones that
are on on the
surface so if you assume that the
fraction of particles that are on the
surface is equal to the mole fraction in
the liquid
phase then you see that the the partial
uh pressure which is driving which is
sort of driving this exchange with the
black
particles
uh is only limited by the by a fraction
which is the mole fraction by the
fraction with which they occupy the
surface and equally the other ones and
therefore uh since the pressures add up
um that's the uh that's the relation
that is one way of interpreting
this in any case when we have the two RS
equations we can usefully combine
them by using the obvious fact that the
mo fractions add up to
one so for example I could add this and
that if I add these two you see y1g +
y2g is one so I remaining I'm remaining
with P so so I obtain this pressure this
expression that the pressure is equal to
this plus that and of course instead of
Y2 I write 1 minus YF this is called the
bubble
line it expresses for a given uh
pressure and temperature the composition
of the liquid
phase so if I give you the temperature
and the pressure you can compute the
mole fraction
y1f uh because you can go on the tables
of the pure substances for the
pat of the two substances and then with
this equation you you solve for YF
y1f
or if you would
um you if you
sum if you solve this equation for y1f
and y2f and then sum up so that it's
equal to one this is the other
expression that you
obtain this is a du line it contains uh
the relation that gives you uh that
allows you to solve for the uh mole
fraction of component one in so the
composition of the
vapor at
uh in the two-phase stage
okay and of course once you have the the
B the bubble Line This is really an
equation of a line so you see that if
you plot pressure versus mole
fraction and in this case we're talking
about if you're doing this equation here
it's the mole fraction of the
liquid uh you get you get a straight
line that we call the bubble line and so
for a given temperature and a given
pressure you go here and read the mole
fraction of the
liquid the DU
line is not a straight line because it's
one / P that is linear in
y so it has this shape and so for a
given uh for that temperature and the
given pressure you go down here and read
the mole fraction of the vapor of course
you you can eliminate pressure from the
system of these two equations and then
you get a direct relation between the
composition of the vapor phase and the
composition of the uh liquid
phase where
the where what counts is the ratio
between the saturation pressures of the
two substances which is called the
relative
volatility and here is a plot so this is
y f y1f this is y1
G and this is how that equation
looks of course remember that here if
you have if we have written
this for both substance one and
substance
two uh it it means that we have assumed
that at all
compositions the liquid behaves as an
ideal uh solution
is
ideal solution yes and
so this is a very strong assumption
because most uh liquids do not uh behave
like
that but still this is a sort the
starting point so that's how the bubble
line and the D line uh look for uh an
ideal model completely ideal model
and that is enough to give an idea
what what is done when we when we do
distillation um you see this plot is
done at constant
temperature because it's easy because
you fix the temperature you go and read
the saturation pressures from these
lines of course I can do also
uh
numerically a plot in which I fix the
pressure and then for each temperature
so if I fix the
pressure for each temperature there uh I
have to go and read the values that will
give me the mole fractions and I do a
plot and a plot will generally not
produce uh straight lines any any longer
if it is a plot at fixed
pressure this is more useful because um
mostly uh you you boil things at at a
fixed
pressure so here's the uh
idea so we got the the bubble
line um in the D the D line sorry um
the D line here and the bubble line here
so uh
we suppose you start with a mixture in a
liquid phase at this composition say
50/50 and uh I hit it up at certain
point I reach the bubble line and uh the
first bubble gets
uh boiled
off that bubble is in equilibrium with
my saturated liquid and has a
composition which is
here it has a different composition and
we computed by that formula that we have
uh derived based on the
relative
volatility of course you can express the
relative volatility as ratio of
pressures but it's it's also related to
the ratio of the saturation temperatures
because this T sat of p is the inverse
function of P sat of
T okay if I keep U uh heating
up for example I have an equilibrium at
this
temperature and for an equilibrium at
temperature the the bubble line gives me
the mole fraction of the liquid and the
the due line gives me the mole fraction
of the vapor again for following this
this
expression if the temperature goes
up up to here I have saturated
Vapor which is in equilibrium with the
first or say last drop of uh liquid so
this saturated Vapor then if I still hit
it up it will go up
okay so the idea is this if
I if I start with a composition like
50/50 and I want to
separate what I could do is to go up to
this temperature here like an
intermediate temperature between the
temperature the saturation uh liquid
temperature and the uh saturation Vapor
temperature and notice
that where as for a pure
substance
the
the the DU line and the bubble line
coincide and there is only one
temperature at which uh the pure
substance becomes liquid and is also uh
saturated so if you so this uh lens
shaped thing will reduce to
just a line
but
here uh the boiling occurs over a range
of temperatures between this and
that this is not only for liquid and
solid for example in also uh Metals if
you go
metalurgy this would be solid this would
be liquid and this would be the
solidus uh temperature and that's the
liquidous temperature and this Gap uh
is is like
here okay so let's say we we we we put
the
temperature we are at the temperature
intermediate between the liquidus and
the vaporous so to speak temperature
then you see that the two phases are
one uh enriched in component two and the
other en reached in component one
so this is what happens in one stage of
a distillation
column then what you do is you take the
liquid and you set it you send it down
to another
stage which works at a different
temperature and then you you take uh the
the vapor and you send it up to uh
condense into the
uh uh upper
stage and so on so that uh
eventually you can
um you see since you in the upper level
you
collected a mixture which is more rich
in in
in in um in
alcohol then
you could uh play the same game go to an
intermediate temperature like this one
and then you generate an even more
enriched um vapor and so on you can
continue as much as you need in order to
obtain um up to
99% uh for example this is how they get
96 uh
volume percent alcohol that is used to
make
liquers
okay all right so this is for
distillation
principle now
another thing that can be explained by
ral's
law is as I mentioned this idea that uh
this fact
that when you add salt on water that
water will freeze at a lower temperature
than zero
Celsius or when you add salt in water
that water will boil at a higher
temperature than 100 degrees
celsus how do we derive that okay okay
we start from the routs law for the
specific case so this is the the routs
law for the uh liquid eyes case that we
have seen couple of slides
ago and we
take the differential of
this and
then realize that uh when we take uh the
different itial of
Pat we
actually this is a pat of the pure
substance so for the pure substance we
can remember the Claus claperon relation
that gives you the slope of this curve
on the PT diagram this this is the the
saturation pressure curve and the slope
of that curve is the is given by the
closes claperon relation and it is
related to the enthalpy of a change of
phase divided by the volume of the
change of phase it's it's actually it
should be the entropy of the changes of
phase divided by the volume but the
entropy of the change of phase is equal
to the enthalpy over the temperature of
the change of
phase so you use this in this
relation
neglect
um this term
here if which is good if if you have a
dilute solution therefore the mole
fraction is close to one and therefore
the logarith is close to
zero and you're left with these three
terms then if you consider that you're
not changing the
pressure so if you remain at constant
pressure and change the
composition of uh of the
solution this relates this tells you how
the temperature will change so
essentially from this equation DP you
can compute the derivative of t with
respect to a change of mole fraction of
constituent one but the change of mole
fraction of constituent one is also
equal to the negative of the change of
the constituent two this case the
salt and uh and and then you have a
H and
RT so in the end you
find that
the if you add a little bit of salt to
the liquid
solution the temperature at which you
have equilibrium therefore the freezing
uh
temperature is
changes from before by an amount that is
related by these things RT squ the
enthalpy so all properties that you can
look up for the pure substance with a
minus sign so this is the uh freezing
point
depression uh
case and you can you can also plot it on
this diagram so if you have a
solution
U here I enlarge this area so the black
curves are the pure substance if you add
a little bit of salt in the solution
then this black curve shifts to the blue
curve at lower
temperature and then also the same for
the other side for the
uh for the other case liquid over Vapor
so
boiling of a uh salted
solution here we have to start from the
rout law written for these two phases f
and
g which is this one again we do the
differential again we use the clus clap
relation and again we obtain uh a
partial derivative of T at constant
pressure
uh how that boiling temperature changes
when you add a little amount
of component two which is the salt this
time you have a plus sign the
ingredients on the left hand side that
look similar except that of course you
have to put
here the enthalpy of vaporization
whereas here you have the enthalpy
of
melting and the plus sign so the curve
the shift is on the right so the boiling
temperature is
higher
actually
um
these
boiling and freezing
effects can also be
used as means to measure and are
actually used as means to measure the
Sal content for example you take sea
water and if you want to measure the
salt content you run the experiment of
freezing it and boiling it and then uh
with that you can compute uh you see
here by measuring the delta T and
uh that is related to the amount of uh
of um of salt that is salt content and
therefore you you infer from that
measurements those measurements
these composition and salt
content
okay okay the problem is that of
course ideal
mixtures are good
models for the gasos
phases not so good for the liquid
phases and therefore not so good for the
liquid equilibrium cases we are
interested in because uh the reality is
more complex than the ideal
models so we remind ourselves of some
results that are useful uh any in any
problem with mixtures it's going to be
useful here
and they are going to be useful also
from I think the next time we will start
the systems with chemical
reactions and these and these
expressions are uh important namely that
the the properties are given by the
weighted sum weighted on the amounts of
the partial
properties the lower case with this with
with a single subscript
and then these partial properties can be
related to
the specific properties of pure
substances if you add what we called the
um the mixing
property but uh now what I want
to uh go back to is this result that we
haven't uh um used yet it's the D
margules
relation that we obtained when we did
this for the simple for the simple
system it was one of the
various say byproduct of this
derivation so the do margus
relation can is is this one
and is important when you try to uh
develop uh models for non ideal behavior
of the stable equilibrium State
properties of
mixes why is it important because it
imposes
um uh in rules about the interrelations
that must
exist you see this is a system of
equations it's not just one
there is one for every
component and so it's not that
you you see when you want to uh model
properties of substances you have to uh
come up with
correlations for these functions
and you might be tempted to use any sort
of
analytical uh form of these inter
relations but do margules says no or at
least you you may try but you should
check the consistency with this relation
because not all relations are good for
that purpose because some
violate this
condition actually this condition
remember that mu I comma J is the
derivative of the chemical potential of
component I with respect to the amount
of component
J and so it is a second derivative of
the Gibs free energy with respect to two
different uh um
components or also equal
components now you can view this uh
system of this system of equations as a
homogeneous uh system of linear
equations in the unknowns
n where uh mu i j is the Matrix of uh
the linear
coefficients and if you if you go back
into your math courses you will find
that the system of homogeneous equations
has a solution only if the
determinant of the Matrix of the
coefficients is equal to
zero so but this
determinant in this Matrix is the Matrix
that is that we called the uh H because
you see it's the Matrix of the second
derivatives and its
determinant is also something that we
have encountered it's the
Jacobian of the chemical
potentials with respect to the
compositions of course done at constant
T and
P so you need that Jacobian to be equal
to zero so that is the condition so you
cannot arbitrarily select these
functions you have to check that that
Jacobian be equal to
zero for example
as you
know we have
decided to call this functional
relation uh the
ideal so and in fact we're going to call
this
uh new I
idea of t p and Y this is a particular
functional
relation so we have to
check that um it
satisfies the do
marulas theor or
relation so here is the ideal
mixture
assumption uh so in order to do this uh
this derivative Computing this
derivative you have to
be a bit careful in do in doing those
derivatives
uh I think I forget now if we have done
this already but uh um the the key Point
here is that you have to take the
derivative of mu with respect at fixed
temperature and pressure so this doesn't
contribute it's only the logarithm of
the mole
fraction so the logarithm of the mole
fraction you have to take its
derivative with respect to the uh
njs okay so NJ now NJ
it's easier to write it this way so I'm
taking the derivative with respect to
NJ of the logarithm of the mole fraction
the mole fraction of component I is n
i divided by the
sum of all the NS
let's use another subscript
K all right so that
means that sometimes you find uh you
have a contribution
ution of the numerator When J is equal
to
I and that's why I use the chroner Delta
and then uh that contribution is simply
uh what one over the mole
fraction okay something like that
and sorry not uh correct it's and
subai because it's the
logarithm the derivative of the
logarithm is one
over the the
argument and then
uh sometimes
the derivative picks up something from
the denominator the denominator this
could be viewed as that is a constant so
that is a log minus log of the of of
this so it would be minus
one over
n yeah so that's written here now that
you've taken this this
derivative you can substitute itute into
here so you sum over
n and verify that indeed that is equal
to zero
identically so
obviously people have been careful in uh
uh D people and also ourselves when we
derive this we did it using the rules of
the game and therefore it does uh obey
the uh the marulas D marulas relation
but when you when you start uh uh
correlating experimental data for non-
ideal
Behavior you have to be uh careful in U
cooking up uh functional relations that
are U
compatible and this uh if you remember
now that so
um here it is so if we write we're going
to decide to write uh the
actual chemical potential as a sum of
the ideal
plus excess so in other words we we are
going to call excess chemical potential
the difference between the actual
chemical potential and what uh uh and
this ideal
one so essentially we're going to
say for the real
uh substance for for the real
mixture we
need to Define how the behavior departs
from
ideal and this is called excess chemical
potential or remember also
this more
the uh
chemical potentials of the pure
substance are
equal to the Gibs free
energy so the to the specific GS free
energy this will come
up
also uh
since we have defined uh these
properties of uh of
mixing by the way we Define them it
turns out that what we decided to call
the excess chemical potential is equal
to the difference between the enthalpy
of
mixing and the entropy of mixing
multiplied by the
temperature not quite
only that part of the entropy of mixing
that is not already included in the RT
log of
Y so you see here we call that the Delta
s x so it it is an
excess entropy of mixing because in the
ideal solution there is a mixing effect
that counts for that remember the
surprise discussion uh counts with that
R log of of Y this is the surprise and
this is an
entropy a part of the
entropy of of the mixing entropy it's
the only mixing entropy that we
have uh under ideal behavior and you may
have some extra some excess one
so that's why we call we say here
chemical potential
excess is equal to the entire enthalpy
of mixing because for the ideal mixture
there is no enthalpy of
mixing and only this uh excess part of
the entropy of
mixing
Okay so with that in
mind of course the another thing that we
should remember is that the Gibs free
energy if we are interested in the Gibs
free energy of our entire mixture that
is equal to
um to
this and so if you want you can also
Define parallel with the fact that we
decided to write the chemical potential
as
mui ideal plus mui excess you can also
plug that into here and obtain
a overall mixture uh gives free energy
as a sum of an ideal part and an excess
part with that in
mind here is for example for a binary
mixture let's
fix this limit for
ourselves binary
mixture uh here is the expression for
the um
specific gives free energy so now if I
take this
G and divide by
n that gives me G Over N
okay of course that summation becomes
the mole fractions weighted chemical
potentials and this becomes
G Plus g x
now
G is therefore the weighted sum of the
ideal chemical potentials weighted on
the mole fractions and the ideal
chemical potentials are these
ones so if I take that let's see if I
can do this game like this take the
weighted sum of these
ones that gives me
G small
ID okay so you see that in
this
summation I have two contributions one
is the weighted sum on the mo fractions
of the pure component chemical
potentials which are equal to the pure
component gives three energies and that
is this plus
this because in this case binary mixture
the sum is just limited to two
components okay and then I have this
this other summation that is here it's
RT times the sum of Y log y That's the
entropy of
mixing isobaric
mixing okay so that's the G
and these are the ideal chemical
potentials and then we recall
that now below here I have listed some
of the
historical
um guesses or sort of um
semiempirical uh theories that have been
developed
in order to come
up uh with ways of representing the
excess part so the the non ideal part of
the behavior of
mixtures the simplest
one by
margules see this is 19 18
yeah my grand father was 1889
so he was six years
old uh
okay so
GX
uh is so it's so it's assumed to be like
like symmetric a single parameter which
may depend on temperature and
pressure but the dependence composition
is just the product of the two more
fractions and if you do
the uh the proper derivatives in order
to to obtain the the the excess chemical
potential that derives from
that you find that the chemical potent
the excess chemical potential of
component one is equal to that function
to that let's call it Con Conant
a constant in terms that it doesn't
depend on composition times the square
of the mole fraction of the other
component and the same
here if you go down below here uh I have
written an expression that um we
have derived y
ago that
relates
the uh enthalpy of mixing to the
chemical
potential now
actually since for the ideal uh chemical
potential there is no enthalpy of
mixing and
okay if I if I take this expression here
and uh uh do this
derivative I obtain let's
see uh so that's
a
[Music]
Y2 over
t with
respect to one over
T so
it's so it's a so it's it's equal to the
chemical potential itself yeah there it
is because you divide by T div and take
the derivative with respect to one / T
that's just the one / T So derivative
some simply
one okay so
it means that this so the the chemical
the enthalpy of mixing is a Y2 so in the
limit when Y2 is equal to
1 it means that the constant a
represents the the enthalpy of
mixing and remember the
enthalpy the mixing yeah the enthalpy of
mixing is u
um is the change in in enthalpy when you
add a little bit of of that of substance
one
into
a a a mixture when in which uh the
predominant component is
two that's why we
evaluate we evaluate it at uh
um at Y2 Y2 equal
1 but you can also find the same for the
component one so it turns out that
constant a is also equal to the to the
mixing enthalpy of component two in in
pure so essentially this says that the
marulas one parameter model is able to
modeling only liquid mixtures in which
the effect of adding component one to
Pure two is equal to the effect of
adding component two to Pure one so in
other words this
mixture uh is very symmetric molecules
are very uh similar to one
another so he developed a two parameter
model is slightly more complicated but
at least I have two parameters and these
two parameters turn out to
be related to The Mixing enthalpies of
the two
components which makes more sense
because uh if I have a bunch of water
and put some alcohol in it I obtain a
different effect than if I had a bunch
of alcohol and I put some water in it
and so this is margul two parameters van
lar also is a two parameter some sort of
an inverse of marus 2
parameter it
also of course
satisfies the do and
margus
condition and again these A and B are
related to the delta when you write it
this way are related to The Mixing
enthalpies but two
parameters for many many mixtures are
not enough
because molecules may be very different
you may have long molecules small
molecules you have to account for the
fact that maybe a long molec is
surrounded by many small molecules and
so you need more parameters for
reality and people over and over have
developed models with more parameters
they all satisfy the D margus relation
for example this
one was considered by gugenheim and then
became famous under the name of redlick
ker uh this other
one was developed by Wilson it's not the
same Wilson as the uh Cloud
chamber and based on this
model uh developments and improvements
of the Wilson model by prits and
co-workers you have uh the models that
you found you find now in your softwares
that do
modeling which have which have several
uh par parameters which are
related these epsilons are related to
the Leonard
jnes potential so to to the strength
with which molecule one is attracted Ed
by molecule
one and this is molecule one attracted
by molecules
two and two by
two and so you see there is some uh the
physics the the physics behind this
model uh is
still related to the fact that we're
trying to describe intermolecular forces
and their
effects and these are the specific
volume over the pure uh
components
so in practice you
describe chemical potentials and
therefore it GS free energy uh of a
mixture in this uh Way by adding up
contributions so here are some examples
I mean examples of uh how these
contributions look as function for a
binary mixture as function of U uh the
mole fraction or of component
one for
example
um just the term y log y
is this pinkish curve
here if you
add also this other
term and of course it depends on on what
assumptions you take for
the for the GI free energies of the pure
component here I assumed zero for
component two and
uh is this number here maybe 0
point five or or or
six for component one just to make this
so
this this is the linear part the first
two terms are linear in in the mole
fraction and that's the blue
curve so you add up the blue curve and
the pinkish one and you get the red
curve that is g
ideal just like
that and then here I
plotted the marulas one parameter that's
the
green margul has two parameters the
black and Van the orange
now when you add
up the ideal and the excess gives three
energy see this is negative this is
positive they add up and here is what
you take you you
obtain these are for the three cases
marulas one parameter two parameters one
lar you obtain shapes that are
non-trivial
and
actually in some cases that also they're
also no good in the sense that they
violate the stability
conditions
because the second derivative of uh
G must always be
positive we we'll come back to this
uh in in a short
while um so here we will find that there
is where where the the convexity is uh
second derivative is negative this will
have unstable
States and uh this will drive us to
exactly the same uh ideas that we have
seen for the Vander valal case for the
pure substance un unstable States and
also stable states are
possible but we postpone that for for a
while when we are in the business of um
mixtures there are other terms that I
only want to mention because they are
used in the by the practitioners
and that might be confusing so I want to
link to what uh we're
[Music]
doing these are called for the
condensed
phases we use activities and activity
coefficients it's just another way of
writing of of of of of writing the
chemical potential so to
speak you could Define the activity this
way so you take uh the chemical
potential this
one you
subtract the same at some reference
conditions of pressure and
composition so not necessarily the pure
uh the pure
substance divided by
13 that
means that essentially you rewriting
your chemical potential as a term
evaluated at those reference
conditions plus RT log of the activity
so that you have an an equation that
resembles this
one except that here you have the
activity and here you have taken uh a
reference
chemical potential not for the pure
substance but for the mixture at
some uh uh conditions that you decide to
be reference useful as a
reference and you can also Define the
activity coefficient which is the ratio
of the activity to the mole
fraction so that here you
have uh the logarithm of Y
which represents the ideal
part of the contribution and the non-
ideal or the
excess is sort of all contained in this
activity
coefficient so that's just changing
names defining variables but the
substance of the matter is what we've
done
uh in in the
same way people have uh sometimes used
fasi this is used for for uh the gaseous
phases so Fugi
is um play the
role
uh of sort of a general
the partial pressures
but the idea is that
here you
you so you
define you see this relations let start
from this relation here uh the chemical
potential you write it again as usual
like we did we do we
did uh
as we take as reference the pure
substance then you you have rt log of
Y okay and then you have plus RT log of
p over p 0 plus RT log of so essentially
you you you rename uh the
excess chemical potential in terms of
this uh fugacity uh coefficient
or if you uh want to start from the
chemical potential you define the
fugacity by selecting again a reference
uh uh condition for your mixture not
necessarily like we do here the pure
substance by
selecting uh you select this coefficient
this
this this this this prefactor here has
a something that in the limit of ideal
gas behavior reduces to the partial
pressure so the
fugacity in those limit is the partial
pressure times the exponent of
this okay so again just this is just
because I wanted to mention it
for example if you compute the
activities for the marulas van and
marulas 2 parameters here are the
expressions and here are
their for the van L this is I think this
is for the one L
um how the activity depends on mole
fraction and on that parameter that
characterizes the model or the
parameters A and B that
characterize the
model and that
means that when we talk about liquid
Vapor
equilibrium for example let's suppose we
use the vanar
model and you remember that we have to
[Music]
apply uh if we have two substances that
are both volatile and uh
condensable we have to apply twice the
routes law now routs law rites for for a
for
a an non ideal
mixture where you substitute the mole
fraction with the activity the mole
fraction of the for for the components
in the liquid with their activities and
we've given the expressions for the
activities in the previous slide also
for the vanar so if
you if you do that
substitution here is what uh the
equations of the
um Bubble line is and this is for the DU
line
they used to be uh one of them used to
be a straight
line but with this uh non ideal
model uh it
becomes very
different and the DU line also becomes
sort of
interesting so just two parameters
introdu use a lot of structure and the
behavior of your
mixture including the possibility of
this which is um called the
aotop the aotop is a a condition in
which you go from
liquid to uh vapor
uh and that change is not across a
finite temperature
difference but at a single temperature
so it behaves as if it were a pure
substance like few substance boils and
condenses at the same unique
temperature but this occurs only at that
particular composition at other
compositions instead you have a range of
temperatures so the temperatures the
temperature of the
U liquidus is is
is is different than than of the uh of
the
vaporus
okay uh this is
done by combining these two you can
construct a plot at a constant temp
temperature but you can also the same
equations construct the plot at constant
pressure
okay and of course you can eliminate the
pressure between the two and
construct for a given temperature or for
a given pressure the relation that you
have between the composition of the
vapor phase and the composition of the
liquid phase
so these are all things that you can
Implement in an Excel file and so on and
very easy if you have few
parameters uh there is
also a Lenard John model
of the mixture of the binary
mixture so
here this model is
taken again this article on Wikipedia
from which I take these plots very
nicely uh
done it explains that you can
assume for the sigma you remember that
the model of in the Leonard mod model
lard Jones model Sigma is a
representation of the
the the diameter essentially of the two
of the
particle so when they Collide the two
centers of the two spheres are at a
distance which is equal to the their
diameter if you have uh spheres of
different
sizes the
diameter at which they Collide is sort
of the the sum of the
radi so the radi is a half of the
diameter so the sum of the halfs is just
the
average diameter of the of the two
proper
diameters so you assume
a ler John's
curve uh or
potential characterized by a sigma one2
for the for the uh interaction between
two unlike
particles that is equal to this
mean
value and then for the depth of the
Leonard John's
valy you use um
the geometric
mean of the S of the pure component
ones but then you also use an adjustable
parameter
C now the
geometric if assume if if C is equal to
one this geometric uh uh
mean uh gives you the equivalent of the
ideal uh solution
model and in fact you
get that the bubble line is straight is
a straight
line and this is with C is equal to
one uh if you change instead
C to like greater than
one you
get real a non ideal mixture Behavior
with an aotop at this
composition if you change C from 1.2
to 85 it goes on the other side so it's
an isotrope uh upper isotrope lower
isotrope
and
also if
you play with the ratio this is wrong
this should be a Epsilon 2 over Epsilon
one of course I need to correct that so
if you change that from this one to very
different you may find a
critical region in other words that you
could allow you to go from
liquid to Vapor without a phase change
similarly to what happens in a pure
substance or if you have if you go above
the
critical uh point you can you can take a
liquid to very and vice
versa
so this case is
one see for example
here
um in which you have a
um well if you were in liquid liquid
this would give you partial visibility
but we'll do that in another in
another
occasion
okay so now let's talk about a bit of
the uh stability
conditions so I as you uh as we have
seen we can go see the business here is
to go from the properties of a pure
substance to the properties of the other
substance and all the way to all the
compositions in
between and when we uh when we do these
uh diagrams
here everything is
fixed by the condition this is a binary
composition so is fixed by the fact
that
mu1
F uh must be at
TP y let's say one
YF so for component one in the phase
F I have to have the same chemical
potential of the of that component in
the phase
G
okay and that's one condition of of
chemical of um Mutual stable equilibrium
the
other uh
m2f um
yeah well let's let's call it again one
one F in the let's choose the for
variables the mole fraction of one of
them
otherwise but I need to impose the
condition for uh equality of the
chemical potential also of the other
component so mu2 must be equal to
mu2 okay so I have a system of two
equations
here and that system of two
equations can be
solved in
general to give
me
this to give me the comp for a given
temperature and pressure I can solve
this system for the unknowns that are
the mole
fractions of component one in the gasius
and in the vapor
phase so here I have pressure and
temperature I fixed the pressure and the
temperature and then that system of
equation
gives me the mole fraction of the liquid
and the mole fraction of the vapor so I
have this surface so that equation here
gives me is an equation
of of this surface here actually this is
on the liquid and on the vapor so it's
on the other side but you can do it for
all the
phases and you have these gaps here
these empty spaces between these
surfaces which doesn't represent any uh
um State because any stable State
because if you are there this system
likes to find stable equilibrium by
separating and generating the two uh
phases so that's uh the
idea and uh yeah I think we we stop here
because there's not enough time to do
hry law uh but we can um yeah we so next
time we will finish up this part and we
start the systems with chemical
reactions