Welcome, everyone.
Thank you for joining
us today from all
around the world for what will
be a terrific conversation
with our special
guest, June Odongo,
on how opening up learning
can close knowledge gaps.
My name is Chris Capozzola.
And here at MIT, I'm our Senior
Associate Dean at Open Learning.
And this is the first in
a new open conversation
series that focuses on the
experiences and impact of Open
Learning for empowering
people to improve
their lives, communities,
and the world.
And as we set out to craft this
new open conversation series,
one person we really wanted
to talk to is June Odongo.
June is an innovative
entrepreneur, a founder, and now
the CEO of Senga Technologies, a
logistics software and services
company in Kenya, catering to
businesses that ship in Africa.
Today, she'll share her insights
on learning, entrepreneurship,
and the role of open education
in upskilling and changing
our world.
So, June, thank you
so much for speaking
with me and our audience today.
Your experience is
truly inspiring.
Thank you so much.
I didn't know I was your first.
Thank you.
It's an honor.
Yeah.
No, it's been great to hear
and learn about the work
that you've been doing
over the last few years.
And I wanted to just
kick it off by asking
you to tell us about your
personal learning journey.
Mm-hmm.
Well, let me tell a little
bit about my background, which
actually connects somehow with
OCW So in terms of my education,
I have a computer science
degree from UMass Lowell, which
is about 40 minutes
or so from MIT.
Many of my university
professors were actually
MIT Computer Science graduates.
And I also have an MBA from
the Harvard Business School.
In terms of how I'd summarize
my learning journey,
I mean, a combination of
formal education, as I've just
described, and then just
complementing my education
here and there.
I think because of
these lecturers that I
who had been at MIT and--
a lot of our coursework was
actually mimicking MIT classes.
So when it came to studying--
And, by the way, I went
to-- if I can date myself,
I was in undergrad--
I graduated in 2005, so a long
time-- quite a long time ago.
And that's actually how I came
upon Open Learning, effectively
to complement what I knew the
MIT students were studying
to help me perform better.
You started by taking some
courses on MIT OpenCourseWare,
but you certainly
didn't stop, right?
And so you've
definitely been engaged
in online learning,
continuous learning,
upskilling throughout
your career,
even after sort of two
really significant degrees.
So what motivates
you to keep learning?
You're a busy professional.
How do you make the time?
Why is it important to you?
I almost feel like
there's no choice.
I mean, like in our
company, for example,
I mean, we're trying
to apply technology
to some very complex computing
problems, I would say,
or mathematics
problems in logistics.
Also, by the way,
I should say this,
I happen to be one
of those people who
I apply so much
of what I learned
in uni, both in undergrad
and graduate school.
Oftentimes, people
say, oh, whatever
I learned I'm not using.
I am the exact opposite of that.
So building on that is context.
The way we think about--
I think the way I mentally
think about problem-solving is
the same, but the context
is constantly changing.
There's new ways of solving
some of the same problems.
Or if you're getting
to-- if you're
encountering a new
problem, you need a new way
to think about it.
And the solution can
either come from you,
or you can borrow
from other people.
And if you're borrowing
from other people,
it could be traditional.
It could be new.
And the way to get
that information
is to insert yourself into
materials, talking about how
other people are thinking
about these things,
or even enhancing
your own knowledge
if you're trying to come
up with your own solution.
So for me, I just think I
have absolutely no choice
but to continue learning.
And in our company, we have--
our team members
are quite young.
Oftentimes, they're recent
university graduates.
I do not write software anymore.
I used to.
[LAUGHS] I just don't.
It was one of the
things, for example,
I'm trying to do is we're
using languages that I didn't
use when I was a student.
I think we used C or
something in computer science.
They're using Ruby.
I need to learn how
to use Ruby on Rails.
But more importantly,
we're also trying
to apply technologies that
have advanced significantly
in the two decades since
I've been outside of school,
whether it's things
around machine learning,
artificial
intelligence, and so on.
So some of the work I have
to do in terms of learning
is relearning what
I learned in school.
So I actually go through
some of my old curricula,
and then introducing new
concepts on top of that.
So it's just embedded in--
I think learning
has to be embedded
in what we're trying to do and
what I'm trying to accomplish.
Yeah, that's a fantastic story.
I think it reminds us
that the education that we
get with our degrees,
for those of us who
have had the
opportunity to study,
is sometimes a set
of concrete skills,
but it's really just an
investment in our future.
If you don't keep
investing, right,
if you don't keep
watering the plant,
it won't continue to grow.
That's really neat.
So you've talked a
little bit about some
of the work that
your company does,
Senga Technologies, and the ways
that technology and software
and software solutions
to logistics problems
are part of the work that
everyone in your company does.
But you've also, in other
discussions that we've had,
sort of reflected that
it's been difficult to come
by software developers--
to hire, recruit,
train, retain them.
And so tell us a little
bit more about how
you've managed not only to
continue your own education,
but to build this up
for all the people
who are part of your team.
So it's less an issue of
finding software developers
because there are actually
plenty of them here, but more
about finding software
developers we can afford
in an era where
software engineers are
such a hot commodity.
And you bring them up, and
Google or Microsoft or whatever
comes and snaps them.
So for us, it was
actually more--
the issue was more a
resource constraint.
When I started this
company initially,
I was bootstrapping
it using my savings.
And then when we
got initial funding,
it wasn't a super
substantial amount.
So we've had to run a
really, really lean company.
And that meant we couldn't
afford senior developers and so
on.
And then even if we
could, there's a--
because of how hot the
market was for engineers,
they likely wouldn't have
lasted because there's always
somebody who can pay them more.
So the approach I took was to
hire very high-potential younger
people--
so fresh computer
science graduates,
folks who've been-- who
are just graduating or have
been out of school for
no more than three years.
Yeah.
So that was the
fundamental problem.
And then the way OCW actually
came into the Senga story--
it was not intentional at all.
So what happened was
there was a candidate
who had been recommended
by one of our engineers.
She was an electrical engineer,
and she was very, very green.
And we initially
rejected her application.
So her name is Cynthia.
And the person who had
recommended Cynthia
is called Warren.
So I go back to--
so I reject her, and she
doesn't say anything,
much like how I used to
be when I was a candidate.
I don't take
rejection very well.
[LAUGHS] Maybe--
I don't-- maybe
she was nonchalant.
Who knows?
But, in any case, I
get back to Warren,
and I'm like, hey, so this is
the feedback on your friend.
She's just too green.
And he says, she's
really high potential.
You need to just think
about that again.
So we go back, and
I talk to Cynthia.
And she was working--
she was designing some kind
of hardware board somewhere.
And I was like, OK, that's
pretty cool for someone
who's barely out of school.
And I just-- and I thought,
OK, she was very, very bright.
What she didn't have was
a computer science degree,
which for us is very, very
critical in our company
because we are
applying algorithms--
complicated algorithms
and complicated math.
And I just thought, well,
when I was a student,
there was this
resource called OCW
that I used where
you could learn
some of these things
that were complementary
to these textbooks.
So I just suggested
to her, hey, you
could join Senga if you're
willing to quit your job
and do this for six months.
And I created a
curriculum for her
which actually mimicked the
last two years of the computer
science program.
And she said, yes.
And then we ended
up finding this path
of bringing on board otherwise
talented individuals who,
for one reason or another, do
not have the education we need.
So as of today, we've
got-- so Cynthia,
she did that program in 2020--
was it last year?
Maybe a little bit--
I think she started end of 2022.
No, no- end of 2023 because
this is her first full year,
actually, as an
engineer at Senga.
And then we've since put
two other individuals
through that program.
The second person we
put through is actually
not a full university graduate.
He's someone who comes from
an under-resourced background
but had the desire
to be an engineer,
had gone to a coding boot camp.
Coding bootcamps, for
us, do not give our folks
what they need, at least for
what works in our company.
We put him through that.
And then we've
since put in someone
else who has sort of
like a similar skill set.
So we've been able to
complement our team.
So half our team is
from this program.
Wow.
Yeah.
So that's really interesting.
And that's exactly
the kind of story
that makes us excited
at Open Learning.
It's the kind of thing that
motivates the staff who
work here, and certainly,
the faculty at MIT who
share these materials.
They don't have to do that.
They don't get paid to do that.
They sort of sharing
these materials in order
for other people to use them.
Now, it sounds like
the special sauce
that comes from Senga
Technologies from June Odongo,
is that--
is your work in identifying from
this big curriculum of materials
exactly what's valuable for you
and your firm and your team.
So that's some
really amazing work.
It does raise for
me another question.
I've taken courses,
watched videos
and lectures from
OpenCourseWare, and some of them
are really hard.
And some of those
problem sets that we
share with the world
are really difficult.
So I'm curious, the
staff who you've
kind of shared this
curriculum with,
do they think it's too hard?
Do they think it's hard and fun?
What's been their reaction.
It's hard.
[LAUGHS] I mean, they're
very complex courses.
I mean, you know, networking
theory, algorithms.
I don't know if they
consider it fun.
No one's told me
they find it fun.
But one thing that's
universal amongst
them is that the amount
of learning they get
is so, so, so significant
just in a span of six months.
So I think they feel
better about themselves,
in terms of what they're
capable, even from a learning
perspective, [INAUDIBLE].
There must be a moment in their
work, or even in your own,
where that light
bulb goes off, where
you're just dealing with some
really tricky work problem.
And then suddenly, you realize
that you have the tools because
of a course that you took
through OpenCourseWare
or something else, right?
Mm-hmm.
You've reminded me of something.
So the team member who
recommended Cynthia
was also mentoring her
during that process.
And one of the courses is
something called automata--
I forgot the full
name of the course.
And whatever problem he
was working on at the time,
he was like, oh, goodness.
There something in
the automata class
that he was helping Cynthia
with that he recognized
could help him solve a problem
that he was working on.
Yeah.
So it's almost like--
yeah, it's almost like this
extended hook in the learning.
It's not just for the person
who's going through it.
Because what we
also do is we want
them to present to us something
at the end of the coursework
on some topic.
So in Cynthia's case, for
example, it was graph theory.
Could you tell us what you
learned in graph theory?
So what happens is there's a
re-learning also for someone
like me.
And then I remember
there's some algorithm--
I forget which
algorithm she presented.
And I was like, oh, my God.
This is an insight I had in
terms of these kinds of nodes
I was thinking
about in the network
design for the logistics.
And I couldn't remember
that I had been taught this.
I don't even know
if I was taught it.
But I was like--
it was very validating for
me because I'm like, oh, wow.
I recognize something by
myself that isn't a textbook.
[LAUGHS]
Yeah.
No.
It feels pretty great.
[LAUGHS]
I love it.
Ans that's a part of the joy
of teaching and learning.
And some of that happens
in the classroom,
but it happens our whole lives.
So let me turn now and ask
sort of a bigger question.
I've shared a
little bit about why
MIT does this-- the
big so-what question.
And I want to hear
from you a little bit
about the kind of impact
that you try to have.
I mean, you have not
just developed a company.
You've also-- you've been
involved in and starting
nonprofits.
You've been trying to make
an impact in the world.
And I wonder what advice you
would give to other people,
to the younger
version of yourself,
or someone who's out there
today, for how they could--
how they can make a difference.
Hmm.
I think the impact
question is big.
I don't know what I would
tell my younger self.
But I think I can
think of what to tell
other folks, which is for me,
there are certain kinds of--
the ideas or problems that
latch on to me so viscerally,
that I feel I have
no choice but to get
involved in solving the problem
or addressing the problem.
And when I have that emotion,
I just pursue the emotion.
I think that's
behind the nonprofit.
So the nonprofit we have is
called ZOO Memorial Foundation.
And what we do is we equip
community centers and schools
in very rural underserved places
with computers and computing
education.
And that is linked to my dad.
So my dad was an
electrical engineer.
Unfortunately, he died
when I was quite young,
more than 20 years ago.
But I would hear
stories of folks saying,
oh, he showed me
my first computer.
Or the first time I touched
a computer was with your dad.
Or he taught me
this or whatever.
And I wanted to do something
to continue, let's call it,
his work.
And that's how--
And a little tiny story.
I worked for this
company called EMC
in Hopkinton, a data
storage company that's
now acquired by Dell.
And it was Earth Day, and
they were recycling computers.
Like, there was some email where
computers were being recycled.
And can I just say, I
was crying at my desk.
I'd broken up with some person.
And I see this email.
I'm like, wait.
I stopped crying.
And I'm like, I know what we
could do with those computers.
And those computers end up--
long story short, we
end up kicking off
the nonprofit that way by
refurbishing these things.
With the company,
in terms of how
I got interested in logistics,
I just was so frustrated.
I was moving quite a
bit in a short period,
and just moving was so
awful And I was like,
people have been moving
since time immemorial.
Why does moving suck so much?
And I just got sucked
into logistics.
Not that I had necessarily
a passion for logistics,
but it was a nagging problem.
And then I'm also very big
on not regretting things.
I'm very big on the
regret minimization thing.
So I tend to just ask
myself at any given point,
if life ended
today, would this--
would I feel OK about
where my life has reached?
And sometimes the answer is yes,
and sometimes the answer is no.
And I find it's yes
when I feel I've
done something that
was meaningful to me
and seen it through completion
or a good outcome or something
that could continue.
And I find that it's no when
I'm in the middle of something.
I'm like, oh, wait.
I have this thing to do.
Yeah.
So for me, I just move with what
grips me, I think, I would say.
Yeah.
No, that's a fantastic story.
I appreciate that-- those
kind of personal connections
that whether it's with a
family, with just a moment that
hits you, that we
feel things, and then
we reach out and act on them
and build either as individuals
or with others.
Is there a role
for open education
in moving from that visceral
feeling to the doing?
I mean, for sure.
But I would just
add just one point
to my earlier one is to
also just go for it, even
if you don't know how
it's going to end up.
So in the story of the
nonprofit, what I did was I
just wrote the company
back and I said,
could you give me
those computers?
And then before I knew it, they
were interested in the idea.
Then me and my colleagues were
refurbishing the computers,
and then they were
donating money.
I just never foresaw that.
I was like, give
me the computer.
So folks should just start.
And then in terms of
with Open Learning.
So after I-- at some point,
I think earlier in the year,
late last year, maybe
a year ago, I posted--
I did a LinkedIn post
about the coursework.
And the response was pretty
good in that folks said,
we didn't know we
could learn this way.
Or can you show me where
I could complement this--
where I could mine
courses for my company?
So a friend of
mine, for example,
runs a rose farm in Kenya.
And she's in agriculture, so
her problems are different.
And she asked if I could help
figure out how they could also
use Open Learning.
And in her case, it's a company
of 800 people, many of them
are farm workers.
So how one would think about
what kinds of lessons one
could glean from something
such as Open Learning
is very different.
It's a very, very wide scope.
So for me, I think it's pretty
applicable in just about every
scenario-- the classes
on how to think--
making decisions, for example.
For me, I have
this deep interest
in behavioral economics, just
how one thinks about when you're
building technology,
but the behavior
of folks, which is
always not how we
think about things rationally.
Like, how do you
think about this?
So for me, in almost
every setting,
I think somebody
can find something
in Open Learning that's going
to complement that thinking,
whether it's
something pretty basic
or something pretty advanced.
All right.
OK.
No, that's inspiring, and I'll
borrow that line-- just start.
We'll sort of-- I
think a lot of people
will take that away
from our conversation.
And speaking of all those other
people, it's time now, I think,
to pivot.
And now I think it would
be a great chance for us
to take some questions
from the audience.
All right.
So, June, I wanted to just start
with one question that came in
from the audience from
one of our-- online
from Mary, who was
listening in and hearing
about the ways in which
you've talked about how you've
upskilled your workers and
yourself on the technical front.
But one thing that
Mary is asking
is how or what
recommendations you
would have for
helping people develop
their social skills
in communication,
in leadership, in networking?
Have you found
resources to do that?
And have you done
that in your own work?
And how have you helped
people in Senga Technologies
do that as well?
Hmm.
OK.
So I think-- hi, Mary.
First, thank you
for your question.
So for communication I think--
many of my colleagues
used to do Toastmasters,
and that worked for them.
So if Toastmasters is
around you somewhere,
I would recommend
that because I think
many people can write well or
communicate through writing.
And it sort of--
communicating verbally or in
public spaces or in meetings,
that tends to be difficult,
maybe because of confidence
or that kind of a thing.
So I would recommend something
as simple as Toastmasters.
Something that was useful
to me was learning tips
on something called
executive presence.
I remember looking at
executive presence tips
very early in my career, things
like sit up when you're talking,
how you should stand
and things like that.
For me, I found those to be
super, super, super valuable,
especially in the
early days when
trying to establish my career.
For my team, I think the current
generation is facing, I think,
a different set of
communication problems, I think,
than that we used to face.
For us, it used to be a
lot about public speaking.
But I think because of
a lot of social media
and so on, what I see commonly
is writing challenges, or being
very curt in writing--
very, very brief.
So for our team, the thing
that I'm usually pushing on
is just written communication.
I don't like to see slides
or that sort of a thing.
I want someone to
express their idea
in writing and with the correct
spelling and things like that.
And I will send it
back if it is not--
if it doesn't meet
that standard.
Yeah.
So I think it just
depends on where
someone is in their career, what
their background is and so on.
And just also observing.
If there's someone who one
admires, who speaks well,
I think there's nothing
wrong in emulating that.
Yeah.
No, I think that,
among other things,
one of our most popular videos
on MIT OpenCourseWare is from
the late Professor Patrick
Winston entitled "How to Speak."
And it's been picked up millions
of times, millions of views.
And I think it's just an
indication of the importance not
only of mastering technical
content or business
content or other
things, but actually
being able to express
it and to share it.
I'll look for it now.
[LAUGHS]
You had mentioned,
actually, the importance
of emulating a
public speaker as one
path toward developing someone's
personal public speaking skills.
And that brings me
to another question.
This came in from Rodrigo, who
has also a joined us an online
and sent this via
email, who asks,
who was your most
influential professor?
So who most influenced
you as you were learning
and whether that was in
the classroom or outside?
Hi, Rodrigo.
Oh, that is a
difficult question.
I got along so well
with my professors.
[LAUGHS] And even
professors in my school
who were not
teaching me directly.
One of the people I think
who was most impactful to me
was this guy called
Professor Moloney
who worked at EMC, which
I ended up joining.
He was not my professor,
but we got along.
And then, I got an internship at
EMC that I ended up not taking.
And then I got a
full-time position.
And I don't think I would
have gotten that without him
because I had not imagined
working for a company like that
or an industry like that.
Yeah.
I think Fred Martin is
someone who stands out to me.
Oh, my goodness.
He was an MIT Grad, actually.
I think now he is--
he might be dean of the CS
Department of University
of Texas at Austin.
Yeah.
So I didn't really enjoy very
much my hardware courses.
[LAUGHS] But he was my
professor, and he made
it fun, and I did well.
And I think I purely did
well because he was great.
Yeah.
So yeah.
I don't know.
I love academia.
I love many people.
So I really cannot
pick just one person.
I cannot.
No, that's a great point.
In many ways, part of
the joy of learning
is learning from different
people in different ways.
And so sometimes there is one
individual teacher or professor
who makes that huge
difference, but sometimes it's
the range of them that makes
all the difference in the world
and why we need to keep learning
and keep finding new voices,
new mentors as we move in
different parts in our lives.
Nice.
And so one thing--
another question
that has come in,
and I think this is really
important for a valuable-- sort
of insight that might be
valuable to other people who
are looking to use MIT'S open
resources in training employees
in their organization, which
is the question of assessing
the impact and the learning.
So a lot of our
course offerings,
particularly on MIT
OpenCourseWare, they're open.
They're self-paced.
There's no sort of necessarily
metrics of whether you've
passed or failed.
Our MITx courses do
have assessments.
They do have certificates
for people who complete them.
But for you, as a manager and
as the CEO, how did you know?
How did you measure, or did you,
your employees when they were
using MIT's open resources,
were mastering the material,
that they were
learning to apply it,
and they actually
really were making
a difference in their work.
Mm-hmm.
Well, in our case, I
would say the measure--
there were three kinds of
measures, though I think one--
well, one is not--
[LAUGHS] I don't know
how useful it was,
which was do the
exercises in the course.
Don't just listen
to the classes.
Do the exercises,
and then report.
It was self-reporting, which
is why I don't know how--
I don't know what we
can say about that.
But self-report on
how you performed.
Because at some point,
answers are given,
and you can see whether
you got something correct.
So that was one.
And then the second measure was
actually the pace of learning.
One can tell how one is doing
based on whether somebody
is taking too long or
something like that,
just like what's going on.
And then also asking
questions because we're
familiar with the material
because we are technologists.
And then also, asking
the team member
who's going through it
to present on a key topic
at the end of it.
So to present well, you
need to at least master
at a theoretical level what
it is you're going to present.
Because we-- all of
us gather together,
and you need to make a case.
And we're learning and
answering-- asking questions
that we want answers from.
So those were some of
the ways to measure.
And then the last one, I would
say, is just application.
Because our ultimate intention
is that the way of thinking
about a problem is reshaped.
So then the proof
of the learning
is in the pudding, which
is your actual output
once you start solving
problems within the team.
Yeah.
No, I think--
And I just want to
add something on this.
So one of my very
close friends is a--
I was about to say
he's a CTO, but he's
now a CEO at this
financial technology firm
here that's doing really well.
And he has helped recruit
just about every engineer
in our company.
And we've been talking
about recruitment
a lot because of these GPTs that
help people answer questions.
Once upon a time, you
could give a coding exam
and you watch somebody do it And
now, somebody can do it online.
And then credentials,
like I've mentioned
before, I think even
earlier in this chat,
that having a computer science
degree is very important to us.
He challenged me on that,
actually, quite a bit.
And he is someone who also
holds like a master's and--
a bachelor's and master's
in computer science.
We're changing the way we
hire to test problem-solving.
And yeah.
So it's actually no
longer about credentials
because we have had experience,
and I think many employers have
had this, where folks can have
the most amazing credentials,
and they still
can't do the work.
And what I'm finding
also is folks
who are self-directed and
have a lot of deep interest--
and I this was true, too,
when I was an engineer myself.
The best engineers
ended up being
folks who just, for whatever
reason, they chose that career,
and they didn't
actually necessarily go
through a machine
like me for learning.
For whatever reason, they
just had this deep passion,
and they opted in.
And I think that's where some
things, such as Open Learning,
becomes very powerful.
And actually, someone
added me on LinkedIn.
And when I looked
at his profile,
he had switched his career
to finance or something
just from Open Learning.
I literally just looked
at his profile yesterday--
complete switch of a career.
People see good work.
The world is changing.
It's hard to argue with
folks who work hard.
Yeah.
No, I think those
are great points.
And I think the proof is
in the pudding, as you say.
And I would also pull
out the importance
of knowing that
someone has learned it
by having them present on it.
They always say the best way to
learn something is to teach it
and to be able to
teach it to others.
And also, that sort of
self-pacing, self-ownership.
So, in some ways you're
opening learning opportunities
to people in your firm,
but it's really up to them
to track their
progress, to apply it.
And that that's the best
way for them to learn it.
But I think the number one thing
I'll take from what you just
said is that phrase "opt in,"
of just opting in to learning,
to curiosity is really key to
what it means to be an agile
worker in the 21st century.
These technologies are
changing so rapidly.
And that even the best degrees
won't last anyone for a lifetime
anymore, if they ever did.
So let's-- I want to switch
now to a little bit--
some of the questions
that have been coming in
are really about and your
work and your journey.
So I'm going to turn some
of those to you right now.
And so one of the things that
comes from Mark along the way,
is a question about what's the
most valuable lesson that you've
learned as an entrepreneur?
You've reflected a little
bit in our conversation
about being an entrepreneur.
What's one that you
would share with Mark?
Oh, Mark.
Hi.
That is a tough,
tough, tough question.
Most valuable-- so first, I
think entrepreneurship is more--
for me, it's a
career of the heart.
[LAUGHS] Because it's just so
difficult to be an entrepreneur.
Everyone's read about
the roller coaster
emotions and the
difficulty and maybe
getting financing and
product-market fit
and all these things.
I mean, the reality is
much, much, much tougher
than one will ever
read anywhere.
Or even if you have friends
who are entrepreneurs,
and you are observing them--
it's just one of those things
where you can't actually
explain what it's like
to be an entrepreneur.
You just have to experience it.
And that's why I think-- like,
my mom is a businesswoman.
And the times she
told me the way--
the things she's
pursued, it's when
she can't sleep over something.
And it's persistent, and she
just cannot run away from
an idea.
And I think entrepreneurship
is, or should
be-- should be driven
by that kind of thing,
a kind of obsession
because there's
so many things that are
happening to make you
want to quit.
And just to give you an idea.
I know very many entrepreneurs.
I know entrepreneurs who
do not have resources,
who have a lot of resources.
But all of them sort
of suffer the same--
the kinds of emotions
they suffer are universal.
So I think if it's not
driven by something internal,
it can be very challenging.
I mean, of course,
there are people
who are just super
rational about it,
and they have a time plan.
And in three years, they're out.
And they've sold their
company and whatever.
They know how to do it
like an assembly line.
But yeah, I would say- yeah.
I think the heart piece
is probably-- for me,
it's the thing
that's kept me going.
And therefore, I would
say that's the lesson.
No, that's fantastic.
That sticking to it
is really important.
And that's-- so that's also
a question that comes in from
YouTube from
Christopher who asks,
how do you stick to
your learning goals?
So in some ways, it's
that related question.
Is the answer there the same?
Hi, Chris.
I think let me talk a little
bit about my primary learning
right now, which is reading a
lot of biographies from founders
and founder podcast.
I love, love, love this podcast
called Founders, which is--
and in the definition,
founder is not
just someone who
started an enterprise,
but historical people who've
just done enormous things.
So it's anyone from a
Rockefeller to Oprah--
just standouts.
And so I'm a bit
obsessed with that.
And so basically this guy
called David Senra just
summarizes these books.
So I end up buying
some of those books.
And then subscribing
to something
called Founders Notes, which
is a summary of the books.
And I literally have five
of those up on my screen
all the time just to refer to.
I'm not measuring my
learning right now
as something around breath.
So it's not-- I don't
need to have a wide scope.
For me, it's like the
depth of something.
And sometimes it's
just a singular concept
that I'm sticking on.
And then that concept is
changing because sometimes it's
something about what
makes a great team.
But sometimes it's how do
you apply technology, like
in our case, even
internally, not just
externally for our customers.
And then I'd
mentioned-- for example,
I like something like
behavioral economics.
So I have Richard Taylor's book.
And then-- there's
just a set of books
that I just keep in front of
me, even if I haven't read them.
Sometimes I'll just pick
and try to go and see
if it's referring to something.
So I don't have a specific goal.
I would say for me,
it's a moving target.
And then I just find
that at any time
when I'm struggling with
a particular concept,
for whatever reason, if
something pulls me to it.
We're building some kind
of a document reader using
something called Clover.AI.
I think I saw someone
post on LinkedIn
this paper by these students.
And I was like, oh,
let me just read this.
And then it ends up
being this thing that's
now a very, very
key part of what
we're offering as a company.
So yeah.
So sometimes-- it's
just clicking now.
I don't have a calendar.
I don't have a list of
things I have to learn.
Yeah.
That's good to know.
Because I think for someone
who's hearing your story
imagines that it's all
very disciplined, all very
by the book.
So it's very heartening
to know that sometimes you
just fall down a rabbit
hole and just discover.
And that's good
because that's actually
one of the questions that
came in on YouTube from Agay
was asking about whether it's
better to be more systematic
or to go down these
numerous rabbit holes?
And I think I'll take a stab
at answering that question,
that I think it's important
to do a little bit of both,
that sometimes there is a
need-- if you know that there's
a particular skill that
you need to master to try
to find a path to doing that.
And here are on Open
Learning, we're developing
and we'll be rolling
out new tools
for people who come to our
website to actually find
guided pathways
through our learning--
through their own
learning journeys.
So if they say, I want to
understand this corner of data
science, or I really
need for my work
to be able to understand
how vaccines work.
And that'll be coming over
the course of the next year.
So I encourage people to
come back early and often
over the next few months as
we roll those things out.
But there's also--
I think what our YouTube viewer
described as a rabbit hole,
another term for
that is serendipity,
which is never quite know.
And you gave an example of that.
You stumbled across
a post on LinkedIn.
You followed the links, and
it led you in a new direction.
And so I wish--
for my answer to that question
to our friend on YouTube,
is I wish I knew which
things were serendipitous,
door-opening, transformative
experiences, which are just
rabbit holes.
And I'm not sure you
know it until you see it.
Is that your experience?
Serendipity is my favorite word.
Oh, great.
Yeah.
It's my-- I feel that that's
what guides me personally.
And so when do you turn from
serendipity to structure?
That's probably what
people who are--
the difference between
a creative person
with entrepreneurial
ambitions and an entrepreneur
like yourself.
So how do you turn from
serendipity to structure?
I don't even know how to answer
that question because I feel
these things go hand in hand.
You've heard those
sayings around--
like, opportunity
comes when you're ready
and things like that.
So I see it very much like that.
I mean, day-to-day as
a company, for example,
we have a plan that
needs to be structured.
But I also typically say that we
have an emergent strategy, which
is, yes, we have this plan,
and we're supposed to--
what we think we should
do is go down this path.
But at the same time,
we're taking in information
to see if there's new data
that says maybe there's
something we can change.
Sometimes the thing that
makes you change that strategy
is what we can call serendipity
because you something
catches you.
And then it brings
together this other thing
that you had learned,
but it allows
you to see it in a new way.
Or it opens up a path for you
to go further that you wouldn't
even have foreseen yourself.
So I don't think
it's about turning
from structure to serendipity.
I mean, I think
these things coexist.
Right.
Oh, fantastic.
That's great advice.
So another-- this is
related, in some ways,
to a question that
came in from Nima.
And so Nima is asking,
in today's world,
sort of fast-moving, high-tech
world, how can someone best
learn quickly?
And then maybe I'd
also ask you to reflect
on what are the things
that you think people
need to be learning right now?
That's a good question.
Hi, Nima.
Yeah, and I think
that kind of related.
So how do you learn quickly?
I think you learn quickly
by training yourself
to learn in the first place.
Yeah.
Like, I just noticed
something this week.
I was in a.
board meeting, and I hadn't
read the board pack on time.
And I felt very, very guilty
because that's a very bad thing.
And I open up-- it
was like 46 pages.
And I was able to go through
all the pages in a relatively
short time, and I ended up
asking the most questions
in that particular meeting.
And I was actually
surprised by myself.
And I realized, oh, once upon a
time when I was in grad school,
I was reading 100 pages a night.
And because I used to
read 100 pages a night,
now I can go through half of
that in a very quick period.
So I think learning fast is--
just training yourself to learn
and creating maybe environments
of focus while you're learning,
so that you can absorb
what you're learning.
Because then you're
going to feel better,
and you're going to notice
that you're learning.
And then it's just going
to get easier and easier.
I think it's-- learning is just
a muscle like anything else.
That's what I would say.
Absolutely.
Yeah.
And you also need, of course,
things like a clear mind
and that sort of thing.
So understanding the
kinds of environments
that allow you to learn better.
Because, for example,
if you've slept well,
you're going to learn
quicker, things like that.
Or maybe if you've had coffee.
I don't know.
And then-- [LAUGHS] I
drink a lot of coffee.
And then so the
other question was,
what should people learn now?
I have two reactions to that,
and I think even something
on the previous question.
So I'm not one of these people
who is a fan of learning fads.
I am anti them.
Like in this last decade
when folks are just like,
everyone should
learn how to code--
the last 10 to 15 years.
I'm like, come on.
We need people who are creative.
We need people who can market.
We need people who understand
philosophy and psychology and so
on.
They're very, very
important, even
in very, very technical areas.
So when I say that, I
think it's difficult for me
to pick what
someone should learn
because I think people
should learn the things
that they enjoy.
Otherwise, it's not--
I mean, you can know a lot
and do nothing with it.
But then if I had to pick
something to learn right now,
I really, really
dislike this buzz of AI,
especially as a CS person.
The term is misused and
that sort of a thing.
But we cannot deny the
super fast pace of things.
We just cannot deny it.
So if there's anything I would
say somebody needs to learn now
is about the technologies
that are completely
reshaping our landscape
because they're affecting us
and will affect us,
whether we like it or not.
And we just have to
get on board with them,
and it's as simple as that.
Yeah.
No, I think you're right.
And I think those are going
to transform every workplace.
At the same time,
I couldn't agree
more, the importance
that you've identified
of people learning in
all different directions
and following their passions,
whether they're in psychology
and economics and marketing--
all those fields that you
mentioned.
So this brings us, I think,
to the final question,
which is directed at you.
What will you be looking
to learn the next time you
visit MIT OpenCourseWare?
Well, outside of how to speak?
[LAUGHS] That's the immediate
thing I'm going to look for.
Great.
That's fantastic.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So that's a major thing
I'm going to look for.
But outside of that,
still very interested
in the sort of
behavior of things.
And then I need
to use statistics.
And I did not like
statistics once upon a time.
I need to brush up.
So just brushing up
on previous knowledge
still, just because
of my day-to-day work.
Right.
OK.
Well, that's fantastic.
And I hope you have some good
experiences the next time
you visit MIT OpenCourseWare.
Always.
[LAUGHS] Always.
So this was a wonderful
conversation with you, June.
And I just want to
thank all of you who've
joined online or elsewhere
for joining this conversation,
sharing your experiences
either now or in other formats.
And I think we all
share the enthusiasm
that June brings to
learning, her creativity
that she brings to her work.
And I'm really glad
that we've been
able to share this
with the world.
And I welcome you, on behalf
of all of Open Learning,
to stay in touch
and to keep learning
with MIT OpenCourseWare and all
of our Open Learning offerings,
and encourage you to consider
supporting our work by sharing
the resources that you encounter
with your friends and family
and colleagues by sharing
your own experiences
and your story directly
with us and the ways
that MIT's Open Learning
resources have transformed
your personal journey to
learning and to career
transformation.
And finally, for those of you
who are in a position to do so,
we encourage and
invite you to consider
making a donation that
would support our efforts
and help us bring these
to the rest of the world
as effectively as
we possibly can.
So, for now, I'm
going to just say
a final thank you to June
Odongo and to everyone
who joined us online.
Until our next
conversation, keep learning.
Thanks very much.