So I'm Hammed Nori. I'm co-founder and
CTO of Before Health Intelligence. And
I'm going to introduce to you today um
Antrike. Antshrike is an embedded AI uh
platform for preventive just in time
warnings for heart attack and stroke as
well as also diseases beyond that.
Essentially an strike is a realtime risk
calculation algorithm that provides also
head health advices ahead of time. It is
comprised of two AI elements, two AI
layers, a static AI core that has been
trained on data from approximately
125,000 individuals and a dynamic AI
core that uses realtime sensor
measurements from commercially available
smart watches. Um, the dynamic AI
element has been trained on over 130
billion preclinical data points and thus
far on over 1.5 billion clinical data
points.
Um, and we are expanding that to 77
billion in interaction with Stanford
Medical School uh to prepare for also
FDA approvals for for these settings. So
essentially what it does and what it
provides in contrast to the existing
technologies is that it predicts
catastrophic and non-c catastrophic
conditions and health events with a high
temporal accuracy. So for for the vast
majority of diseases that we looked at
above 85%
depending on the disease that we are
looking at. This translates to being
able to predict the onset of a condition
a couple of hours to up to 5 days ahead
of time that would apply for a heart
attack. A main advantage is that in
contrast to the current
state-of-the-art,
we do not rely for the data extraction
on expensive and calibrated heavily
calibrated clinical equipment but rather
can work with commonly used smartwatch
data.
And another element is that it actually
monitors
and processes data passively and so it
does not interrupt the daily life, daily
routines and habits of the individuals
using this technology. Our business
model is entirely B2B. We provide this
uh algorithm as an integrated
algorithmic solutions
uh so far primarily for tech companies.
We have major traction from I would say
the top 10 uh tech companies in the
world. Numerous contracts signed.
Unfortunately, I cannot name a single
one of them. Um but what we provide is
the the algorithm integrated into their
existing platforms uh for them to
provide it for their customers. The
range of companies and I apologize for
the PDF just jumping. The range of
companies that typically fall within the
customer uh base of our company are
sensor manufacturers, smartphone and
variable manufacturers/ software
companies but also insurance companies
and healthcare providers. And a key
factor here is that the use cases of our
algorithm go far beyond the
cardiovascular diseases for which the
algorithms were originally developed.
But nowadays you can also work with
known uh work on known uh critical
conditions that can actually have uh
fundamentally different use cases. We
see a use in employee management
particularly when the algorithms are
trained for non-catastrophic scenarios
for in such as common cold or more
seasonal diseases. It can support work
uh force uh management and worktime
disruption predictions.
But we see also applications in the
domain of safety in transportation
industry as well as also supporting the
aging population.
And what we are currently looking for is
essentially
expanding the range of applications that
we have and co-development with uh
primarily pharmaceutical and personal
care companies because we see a high
chance to use this technology also for
identifying the optimal instances for
drug administrations
as well as also predicting more in a
personalized manner the effects and side
effects of particular drugs and also the
right moment for application of certain
personal care topics. I will look
forward to any questions as well as also
collaborations that may arise from this.
Thank you.