Okay, good morning everyone. Um, welcome
to our um, second annual uh, ladders to
cures accelerator symposium. Uh, my name
is Anna Gre. I'm a uh, core faculty here
at the broad and um, physician scientist
uh, at MGB. Um and uh I it is my great
pleasure to um open the symposium um
today. Um we have a great uh program
lined up uh and I'm very excited uh for
the whole u day. Um I hope that you can
all whether you're online or with us in
person uh you can um stay um and stay
engaged. Um I just wanted to make some
introductory comments about what the
ladder secures accelerator is and where
we stand now. Um this whole activity uh
was launched um more than two years ago
now. Uh our our official inaugural
symposium was uh exactly two years ago.
Um but the process actually the
brainstorming process uh started
uh maybe three years ago when we
gathered many of you here in this
community to think about um how can we
take um all of our genetic and genomic
discoveries uh that the broad has been
at the center of for so many years and
try to harness them for the benefit of
patients. And of course uh rare genetic
diseases are an area that is ripe for um
you know translation into therapies. And
this was uh something that we really
wanted to see how we can accelerate
further. And through basically
brainstorming with the entire community,
we came up with this idea of launching
uh the latter secures accelerator which
is really a scientific accelerator
aiming at bridging you know genetic
discoveries and work in rare diseases
hopefully um all the way to therapeutic
hypotheses and therapies uh for the
benefit of patients. And so um this is
really how this uh idea was born. Uh and
it's really been a tremendous uh couple
of years, you know, building this
community. Uh this is officially our
mission. Um which was actually uh very
well articulated by our very own
director Todd Gallib. He had a lot to do
with articulating this uh mission
statement very clearly. Catalyze
progress across the research ecosystem
and accelerate advances leading to
treatments and cures for patients with
rare genetic diseases. So this is what
we aim to do. It's a big ambitious goal,
but I think the time is right uh for us
to make progress in this space. And so
to really try to articulate a little bit
further what it is that we're actually
hoping to do, you know, the idea is to
actually build a platform uh that can
uncover nodal mechanisms across uh many
rare genetic diseases. Um so I just want
to uh point out that uh nodes doesn't
necessarily only mean biological nodes
although of course that's a lot of what
we do and we will be hearing about today
but it can also mean technological
nodes. So ways in which we can bring
technologies that can be applied across
many different diseases and find ways to
accelerate uh getting these technologies
to patients. And so, uh, for example,
you know, our our, um, symposium is
timed perfectly with this, you know,
incredible story that, uh, was in the
news yesterday, uh, about little, uh,
baby KJ who, you know, received, um, a
base editor to treat his disease, uh, at
just a few months of age and he's doing
very well and it's just such a miracle.
uh and I want to celebrate that and you
know of course the entire rare disease
community has been celebrating this news
since yesterday but to also say that
that's a technological node you know
being able to figure out ways in which
we can make KJ not the exception that we
celebrate but the beginning of a
revolution of many many other babies or
people like KJ who receive these
therapies. So harnessing these
technologies and finding ways to deploy
them for patients in uh in a way that is
um actually applied you know to dozens
and then hundreds and maybe thousands of
patients, millions of patients
ultimately across the planet so that
everyone can benefit. Um I think we will
uh be hearing from Jimmy later today
about some of those ideas. But that's to
me that's a technological node and a
biological node would be you know you
find a target like some of the work that
you know our lab has been working on and
you develop treatments and then you know
targeting that particular node actually
can deorphan multiple upstream diseases
that's another way to harness the
opportunity to help more patients um but
you know in both cases I think the idea
of finding these nodes searching for
nodes and finding them and then
deploying them for therapeutic benefit
is really what we're um hoping uh to
accomplish and so you know rare rare
diseases are collectively common and we
should find these nodes so we can find
therapies that can ultimately help more
and more patients. It shouldn't be the
exception. It should be something that
we do in a highly repeatable uh fashion
as as we move forward. That's how I
would um define success. So as we make
small steps in that direction beyond
building a platform that can harness
nodes or multiple platforms really for
uh harnessing these nodes, we also uh
are hoping to have some proof of concept
therapeutic projects. And so you this is
what we call our leading edge projects.
Um we have started by seeding 10 of
them. You will hear about all of them
today. This is part of this symposium
hearing about our leading edge projects
and the progress that they have made. It
is clearly work in progress because
we're only about six months into uh
beginning this process of having seated
these projects. So all of the uh
presenters know that this is work in
progress that they're showing us and
we're really just all working together
as a community to uh come to uh uh come
to uh u progress in that space. Of
course, nothing in rare diseases happens
with without patients. So this is very
much um uh a space and a an initiative
that is uh led by patients and patient
advocacy groups. And many of you will
know that in our open call for leading
edge projects, leading edge ideas, we
actually had a requirement that all of
the uh scientists uh you know leading
the ideas will actually have a patient
advocacy group with them and we did
indeed have that. That was a requirement
for the process and that was really to
galvanize this idea that you know
patients are our partners on this
journey to therapies and they're you
know the most important stakeholder for
everything that we do and of course it
goes without saying that all of this
requires collaboration. So of course you
know a big goal of our ladder secures
mission is to uh have a collaborative
effort. So just some numbers uh so far
we count 12129 scientists who are
working collaboratively um as part of
this accelerator. We have 10 uh cohort
projects uh in our first cohort that you
will hear about. We have so far
organized um six symposium and community
events. These are our rare disease day
events which uh we celebrated a decade
of those this past um February. And
we've had, you know, our inaugural
symposium and a couple of additional
symposia on AAVs, on using AI for the
benefit of uh genetic diseases and
making progress and uh many other ideas
that are part of this important
ecosystem uh so that we can all make
progress uh toward our mission. Uh and
finally, none of this would actually be
possible without uh philanthropic
support. So, I'm incredibly grateful um
to uh two anonymous uh philanthropic
organizations who support our work as
well as the Chan Zuckerberg Initiative
and so we're just really um delighted to
have their support and uh hope of course
to uh continue to make progress uh in
that space as well. Okay, I will not
read the names of the projects but I
just wanted to show you the breadth and
depth of the different projects that
we're um uh discussing today. Some of
them are leading edge projects that are
focused more on nodal biology and some
of them are leading edge projects that
are focused more on nodal technologies.
But in both uh directions, I think we're
making some good progress in many
different um diverse areas and uh you
will see a lot of uh tremendous uh ideas
uh being shared by um our colleagues
later today. This is just to uh show you
the symposia and events that we have
organized over the last couple of years.
Um there's been a lot of activity and of
course we hope to continue to bring the
community together uh across many
different um ideas and while this was
not um a priority we are finally we've
finally um secured some funding to to
launch a nice website. So we wanted to
get into the substance of the science
but now we're also getting a website
together so that we have you know a sort
of a a place um a launching pad if you
will for for the uh accelerator. And so
this is uh coming in the next uh couple
of weeks and I just wanted to give you a
preview that uh we have uh um our
website um coming up. And so I just
wanted to end my uh remarks by uh
speaking of the people who are most
important for bringing us together
today. The first person I want to
acknowledge is Dr. Jillian Shaw. Uh no
one is luckier than me for having the
opportunity to work with uh someone like
Jillian who really all of you know I'm
sure because she brings our community
together and she's really the glue that
makes all of it happen. this uh
beautiful website and all the logistics
uh for today would not be possible
without Katie Legui. So I'm also
incredibly lucky to um have Katie in the
office and she really makes everything
tick really including including me. So
I'm really really uh grateful for
everything that they do. But something
that you may not know is that Katie
actually also has a design degree. So a
lot of the designs for what you see, the
logos, the website, I'm just so lucky
that she actually also puts her, you
know, design genius uh to work. And so
uh we we all get to benefit from that
beautiful work as well. So uh very lucky
for that. Uh and then just some final
logistics for today. Um we uh have
incredible keynote speakers. I'm about
to introduce the first one. Uh but I
just wanted to say we'll have uh Q&A
after each of the keynotes. Uh but then
when we get into the sessions and also
in the interest of time we will ask our
speakers um to uh uh sit back down after
they've spoken and then at the end
everybody if you wouldn't mind coming
back up here and uh we won't have chairs
we'll just uh have the speakers um stand
with mics and we can do a Q&A like in a
kind of friendly informal way. We're all
colleagues here and you know um and um
uh we can have uh Q&A for at the end of
each of the sessions. So save your
questions for that. Um and I think
that's it. We have an exciting day
ahead. Uh we will end with a very
interesting uh panel discussion which uh
David Mer will be leading. Thank you.
And so hopefully this will actually
allow us to have a lot of interesting
conversations during during the
symposium during the breaks bring the
community together and uh hopefully make
progress uh as much progress as possible
um all together. So uh it's my honor to
open the day today. Thank you all for
coming. Um, and let me now just uh skip
to uh introducing our uh first uh
keynote speaker to really open the day
with some inspiring science and a really
truly inspiring uh story I will say
behind the science which is really
remarkable. So our first keynote speaker
is um is uh professor Jonathan Weissman.
Uh Jonathan is an investigator of the
Howard Hughes Medical Institute. He's a
member of the Whitehead Institute right
next door and he's a professor of
biology at MIT. Um his lab is really
known for uh incredible breadth and
depth of uh work uh both in the way
proteins fold and how things go
orienting disease which is an area that
uh we share in terms of scientific
interest but also further his lab really
has done incredible innovative work in
areas like uh ribosome profiling um uh
crisper IA screening in very innovative
ways uh including uh ways in which uh
one um edits u um come comes up with
epigenetic editors and how those may be
now deployed uh in uh different areas uh
for therapeutics. And so I think we're u
here to uh uh hear an incredible story
about that. And so without further ado,
please uh welcome Jonathan Weissman.
Thank you so
much. I have a feeling you can't Oh, you
can hear me. Thank you so much for the
uh kind introduction and for of course
for the invitation to speak today about
our work on silencing uh pron disease uh
causing protein. So back
in sort of year zero of crisper to the
summer of 2012, uh right after um
Jennifer Nwell had published their
description of a single um protein and
guide RNA that could be a programmable
nucleus. A few of us, Jennifer included,
thought that we should take this
beautiful nucleus uh and break its
scissors so that it couldn't cut
anything. And you might think why would
you want to do that? Uh and the reason
is now you had a programmable DNA
binding protein. And if you then
fusedector domains so for example in the
very early work we've used
transcriptional inhibitors or
transcriptional activators you could now
in a programmable way uh bring in
epigenetic marks. In essence we got a
volume switch that allowed us to control
the expression of any gene or any
combination of genes. And if you are
interested as my lab had been for some
time in the function of uh of different
genes and in trying to understand what
is information encoded in our genomes
and what are modifiers of disease states
uh this these turned out to be extremely
powerful tools. Uh but from a
therapeutic point of view uh they
weren't particularly useful because they
were
intrinsically unstable. As soon as you
stopped expressing the cast 9, the
epigenetic marks would uh dissipate with
often within a few days and gene
expression would go back to its normal
level. So this motivated us uh to uh
instead of doing epig marks on histones
for example to bring in uh DNA methyl
transferases uh that would again in a
programmable way be able to methylate
the DNA. And the reason why uh this was
uh transformative or potentially
transformative is uh there are systems
in your cells that once the DNA uh is
methylated that both ensure that that uh
represses transcription but critically
for propagating this. So now you could
in a hit and run way bring in your
epigenetic editor your DNA methyl
transferase and permanently silence a
gene. And the reason why uh one of the
reasons why these are so stable is that
uh these are systems that are used by
the cell uh to uh silence elements like
in parasitic elements like indogenous
retroviruses. So that you're
piggybacking on the cell system for once
you put these methyl methylation marks
in uh CPGs uh for propagating them. So
for example uh when uh DNA replicates of
course only one of the two strands uh
will uh inherit the methylation on the C
and of course C CPG is a palendrome so
if you have it on one strand you have it
on the other so you then end up with uh
two hemthylated
uh uh double helix helixes and uh
there's then a um a so-called
maintenance methyl transferase DNMT1
that recognizes these hem methylated
states and then restores the methylation
mark to the
second to the second strand. So sort of
to cut to uh make a long story short,
working off of a beautiful work from uh
Angela Lombardo and Luigi Naldini, uh we
brought together uh in a single uh
aector protein uh that contain crab
domain, a 3L which is a helper protein
and 3A which is actual methyl
transferase um a crisper off machinery
and we here is a example of this where
you see there's transient expression
over over the course of a week or so. Uh
but the methylation and the silencing of
the gene that's been targeted uh after
uh a few iterations we're able to get it
extremely stable. So here's an example
where uh James Nunees who was a posttock
who led this work and is now system
professor at Berkeley uh silenced a gene
through this transient expression of
Chris off uh and then propagated the
cells in this case uh for 15 months and
the vast majority and made individual
clones and the vast majority of these
clones uh remained completely silenced.
And unlike the volume switch where you
could tune down and up, the epigenetic
silencing was really an off switch like
a a a sort of a digital was it on or was
it off? And the off was as far as we can
tell completely
unexpressed and uh and work that we uh
was not ours at all. We we uh work from
Chroma Medicine which uh in full
disclosure uh I was a founder of has
used this in LMP delivery uh to the
liver and shown that you can with a
single dose and actually very low dose
um get uh permanent silencing and this
is in NHP data uh permanent silencing of
the PCSK9 gene and this causes a
dramatic decrease in uh serum uh
cholesterol LDL uh levels. So uh this
sort of a proof of principle that uh in
at least in non-human primate that these
uh could be a therapeutic and we thought
uh there would be sort of this
separation of church and state. We would
use the epigenetic editors. We were
scientists and about discovery. We would
use epigenetic editors to understand how
these marks are initiated and propagated
and the basic biology of epigenetics and
chromas or the chromas of the world
would use these for therapeutics. And
that equation changed when um one day uh
this couple Sonia Valib and Eric Mikol
came into my office and said uh we're
writing a grant uh that the goal is to
fund up into an IND enabling study uh
for PON disease. Um and I I knew Sonia
and Eric. interviewed them a decade
earlier when they were going to graduate
school before they had graduated and now
were running a lab at the Broad uh to
treat and understand PON dise and
prevent pron diseases uh and I also of
course knew Sonia's story which is uh
she was a Harvard trained lawyer uh her
Eric was a a city planner uh and um at
some point early in their career uh
Sonia's mother died of fatal familial
insomnia which is one of these inherited
pron diseases and that she herself had
inherited uh uh uh this alil and it was
an alil that had very high penetrance.
Uh so she was uh at some point almost
certainly uh in her typically around 50s
or 60s was going to um have the same
fate as her mother unless of course they
could do something about it. So they
just being Sonia and Eric that they
really they were full in they they quit
their day jobs went to graduate school
learned science and now we're running a
lab. So with that as you know when it's
not often you have you have the
privilege of of being asked to
participate in in something like this.
So of course uh we were we were all in
on this and so I should just say uh the
pion disease is one of the uh more broad
I think motivations for uh using this as
sort of a a first uh proof of principle
uh for treating neurodeenerative
diseases is that biology was so clear
and so remind I'll remind you uh prons
are infectious proteins where an
endogenous protein the pron protein has
misfolded into self-propagating
confirmation. Essentially that acts as a
seed and when either through because of
a mutation or spontaneously or through
uh through
infection you have uh these seeds they
then co-opt the normal protein and
propagate and grow
exponentially. And the other key piece
is that uh we seem to be able to live
mammals well without this pon protein.
So you could knock out the pon protein
and if you didn't have you weren't
expressing the endogenous protein you
would have no substrate for this seed to
act on. And we knew this from a
beautiful work 20 years earlier from
Giovani Giovani Maluchcci who made a
genetically engineered mouse with a
crelock system where they uh could at at
in a defined time uh knock out the pron
protein across the central nervous
system. What Jiovanna showed was that
even after infection if you uh prevented
expression of new PON protein you could
block the PON disease. Um so silencing
we had a very clear biological
hypothesis. Silencing PON protein will
have a therapeutic benefit. Uh the
second and I say this is work led by uh
Edwin Newman a graduate student in lab
and Tessa Bertosi a posttock in the lab.
um uh they quickly showed that uh the
pron the human pron and mouse pron
protein had a promoter that could be
readily methylated. So you transiently
express the crisper off and it caused
permanent silencing of the pron gene and
that silencing was uh uh caused by
methylation of the so-called CPG island
upstream of the pron uh promoter.
So now it was essentially a delivery
problem. We knew that silencing of the
pram protein from the from the
engineered mice that it within the
central nervous system would be
sufficient to block the disease even in
an actively uh infected uh individual
and but we also knew that it could
affect most of the CNS. So you really
had to have a way of delivering across
the CNS and really the only approach at
the moment to to do that in an adult uh
was through AEV and uh fortunately we
had a wonder we have a wonderful
collaborator Ben Deman who is the world
experts on AEV delivery uh to the
CNS. The problem is that uh crisper cast
9ines are big proteins and AES have
small payloads. So just to give you an
idea of the scale uh the cast 9 alone
was pretty much too big to to fit in the
AEV let alone all the other bells and
whistles. So this motivated us uh to
then go back to an earlier technology
zinc finger proteins uh which are um
programmable DNA binding proteins. they
don't have the beauty of having the
simple rules of a guide RNA but uh
through a lot of work and work that was
uh found the foundation work for this
work was done across the street in Carl
Pabbo's lab uh we had rules that through
a lot of engineering uh you could for a
given site uh design a zinc finger and
there's a couple of uh critical
advantages of zinc fingers uh one is
that they're they're very small so it's
Even a six-finger zinc finger is only
about 540 nucleotides. So they could
readily fit in. In fact, we can put in
three different uh zincfinger silencers
in in an AV. Um the other is that there
were human in origin. And the third is
that um these crab domains, one of the
key components in the endogenous system
for silencing these indogenous
retroviruses are almost always fused to
zinc fingers. So it it was really the
natural way of delivering onto DNA the
epigenetic silencers and unlike uh the
like the beautiful editors from from
David Louu like base editor or prime
editor which really rely on
idiosyncrasies of cast 9 the ability to
do nick one strand and not the other the
ability to create a bubble
thrinase we didn't need to do any of
this in fact having a small DNA binding
protein that would that would be right
at on the DNA and bringing that the DNA
methyl transferes was um was a um both
more effective and and more uh an
elegant way of delivering their
silencers. The problem we had so this
all seemed very simple problem is we
made our zinc finger off the equivalent
of the crisper off and uh even in vitro
in cells these were these were toxic. So
why why and we showed it was the DNMT3A
the methyl transfer race that was
causing the toxicity. So, why are these
why were these
toxic? And bear with me. I'm going to
have to tell you go into a little bit of
the nuts and bolts about DNMT3A to show
how we solve the problem. So, DNMT3A is
actually a more complicated
multi-dommain protein and it exists in
an autoinhibited
form. What we and others have done is
take only the methyl transferase. So, it
removing this inhibition um so that we
circumvent this. The problem is you now
essentially have a mutagen. You were
overexpressing this uncontrolled methyl
transferase that whenever it landed or
wherever it was uh uh brought to
inadvertently on DNA would cause these
marks on the DNA and because you had the
DNMT1 the maintenance methyl transferase
once you put the marks they could
propagate
indefinitely. And we also knew from uh
the beautiful work in um that uh the way
uh this uh methyl this in auto
inhibition is released or one way is
through uh the histone tail. So
basically methyl transfer race is
sniffing around and if it's a a K4
methylation that is an indication of
active transcription the methyl transfer
race can't be activated but if you have
the K4 unmodified it binds to this ADD
domain releasing the inhibition and
allowing activation methyl transferase.
So Edwin had this idea that we could
take the 3L and not express any methyl
transface or any enzyme at all in the
cell and just recruit the endogenous
methyl transferase. It wouldn't be in an
active form uh but it could recruit it
through the 3L. But then he thought what
if we put on this histone tail in a way
and played with the linkers in a way
that it could bind to the ADD domain.
This should in principle allow you to
recruit and activate the nauseous methyl
transferase. To make a long story short,
this worked uh like a charm. Thus our
name coupled his own tail for auto
inhibition release of methyl transferase
or or charm. Um and through a lot of
optimization he was able to get this
crisper charm to work uh in general
actually better than the original
crisper off. So now uh and he also
showed that this eliminated or largely
eliminated any of the toxicity they saw.
So now we're able we had a non-toxic
zinc finger uh charm that could readily
fit into nav and we were now able to do
the experiment with uh Ben's AVs that
could go uh reach across the central
nervous system in a mouse and really
beautifully almost in this first
experiment we got dramatic and brainwide
and we showed it was actually in the
neurons themselves uh silencing of the
pram protein uh to uh in this case uh
more than 80% silencing almost to the
limit of detection and this silencing
was being mediated uh by methylation. So
we had a reason to believe that it would
be uh not uh not transient but permanent
in nature because it was permanent once
you methylated the the pronot which we
knew happened relatively quickly. Uh
continually expressing the charm could
only cause offtarget effects because
you've you've done the ontarget. So uh
what uh we did in the work that was led
by Tessa Bertosi is she developed a
self- silencing charm. So by tuning she
put in a binding site for the ZFP charm
uh in the promoter that was expressing
the charm itself and then tuned this
promoter such this binding site such
that the ZFP charm first silenced the
endogenous gene and then more slowly
silenced itself. So now you sort of have
the perfect hit and run. it came in,
silenced the the pron protein, silenced
itself, and you were left in the neuron
with a silenced pron uh gene and a
neutral piece of DNA that can't be
expressed. Uh, and this worked a lot of
tinkering. Um, we now have data actually
up to 12 months. I'll show you here six
months data showing that the charm or
the self silencing charm has very uh
robust stability. uh but then we could
look at what were the offtarget effects
and what we saw was if we had continue
expression of charm pon protein was by
far the biggest gene most gene that was
most affected but there were clearly the
uh offtarget effects on this whereas uh
the the self silencing charm was really
squeaky clean. So this one gene here was
keratin which means someone managed to
probably contaminate it with their uh
with uh with RNA from their fingers or
from the sample but other than that
there was nothing above the detection
limit and the pron the knockdown of pron
was actually if anything uh more
effective. So now we were able to do the
the actually validation experiment uh
and and I should say all of this stuff
was we were able to move so quickly
because a beautiful system Sonia and
Eric had set up that allowed us to
quickly go into mice and test go from
cells to mice uh in a matter of weeks.
So here you infect you inoculate a mouse
with the pron um wait till 120 days or
so when the animal is actually now
visibly sick and would die within within
tens of days uh um after if you didn't
intervene come in with an AEV and you
can see uh from these both the the self-
silencing or the non-self silencing form
are really able to dramatically increase
the life of the animal and I say this is
you know it's not a perfect cure in this
but it's also a very uh very challenging
problem. You're talking about an already
sick animal who who's got a very that
has a very high burden of the pron
disease pron uh infectious
pron. Uh so next step was that was all
mouse. So we uh uh then went to making
uh zinc fingers against a human uh pron
using a humani and then using a
humanized mouse model. Uh there were
some zinc fingers against the pron
promoter and literature. They were quite
effective when we made the zip charm at
silencing, but they're really quite
dirty. So through a lot of optimization,
uh Edwin was able to uh turn this into
this. And not only was he able to get
rid of essentially virtually all of the
off target visible offtargets and this
is with continuous expression not not
long after uh with self silencing. So we
think it'll be even cleaner but not only
get rid of off targets but actually have
better efficacy about against the
pron was still a a great silencer and
when we went into humanized mouse we
were can get very robust brainwide
silencing uh almost to the limit of
detection. Um so uh what's the next
step? Uh we and again we is really uh
really led by Sonia and Eric have had
had an FDA interact in February. Uh they
were uh very enthusiastic and about the
approach and uh really uh gave a a lot
of um uh support for the strategy of
going using the mouse data and then
going into human. So we're doing uh lead
optimization finalizing promoters the
UTR uh doing self silencing and
humanization. Uh they have a a contract
CRO Verilogen that's going to produce uh
enough AAV for about 10 doses uh over
the next year or so. Uh GLP talk studies
uh next year and aiming either in second
half of 2026 or early in 2027 uh for uh
the IND uh study in symptomatic
patients.
So finally where is it going to go from
here? Um as I said you know we're focus
of course was on the pronun disease that
is that is our central goal but um we
also think that both by the ae and
de-risking all this and as a proof of
principle uh this could be have much
broader applications because uh this
theme of protein aggregation and neuro
degeneration is common throughout m many
inherited or uh spontaneous
neurodeenerative diseases including the
triplet repeat diseases like
Huntington's and more common even much
more common ones like Alzheimer's
disease. Uh and so uh we hope that the
ability to shut off specific genes in
the brain uh will could prevent these
aggregates and uh potentially impact uh
diseases that affect millions uh uh of
people uh where there currently are
minimal effective treatments. So with
that, I'll end and uh thank everyone
again. I I mentioned most of the people
along the way, but I think it's worth a
shout out again for Edwin and Tessa um
and our wonderful collaborators Ben
Deman, Sonia Valib, Eric Menol, and also
uh Fiona and Alisa who just did a huge
amount of work uh behind the scenes to
make all this possible. Uh with that,
I'll end. Uh thank you.
questions.
Yes, we have a mic. Oh, sorry.
Thank you. Um, I'm sure you get this
question a lot, Jonathan. First, this is
it's just incredible work and I love
seeing every time you present it, it
it's just so exciting. Um, how do you
think about from the mouse experiments
the effects of dosing prey symptoms
versus post symptoms? Um and then how do
you think about that in the context of
clinical trials where you already have
quite a small patient population and you
may want to dose them like pre pre when
they're presymptomatic. Yeah. I mean so
this is a so the FDA was okay with the
strategy both for symptomatic and and
preymptomatic and it's a very different
situation. So for for uh people who are
symptomatic it's about 600 people in the
US are diagnosed with this a year. So
two a day. So not a challenge to get
patients at least at this scale um
because they're highly motivated. Um but
it's five months. So we only had two
months with the mouse. We have five
months from onset of symptoms uh to uh a
typical to typical time to death. Um so
and and there's nothing you can do to
intervene. So there there's a very
compelling case for doing uh for going
in for people are symptomatic. I think
that will be the first but the hope is
we're building in self silencing from
the very beginning. Uh the hope is that
that will um also that that same vector
could be uh also could be used for
preymptomatic. Uh that said, we're we're
like, you know, the one thing from my
voyeristic views of of pharma understand
is you always have a backup and we're
building in a V2 version that has some
extra bells and whistles that will we so
we're completely uh uh deimmunizing. So
any peptides that could be presented by
the MHC, we're putting in mutations. uh
we're we're doing things that will make
it even ultra better zinc fingers ultra
uh specific and better tuning of the
cell silencing. So I think it's going to
be you know it's going to see what
happens when we get into the clinic.
will be able to you can see PON levels
from the CSF so you can you can measure
um some have some measure of efficacy
and of course you'll have also a view of
any toxicity caused by the AAVs and at
that point it's going to be uh you know
a as they say a radio call about whether
you go presymptomatic or you wait for a
V2.
Thank you John.
[Applause]