All right, good morning everyone.
Welcome to today's um MPT primer. Uh so
Manda Arbab is the ladish family
assistant professor of neurology at the
Rosman Stone Xander translational
neuroscience center at Boston Children's
Hospital. During her PhD at the Hubert
Institute in the Netherlands, she worked
on IPSC modeling of neurological
diseases and crisper technologies. She
completed her post-doal training with
David Louu at the broad institute where
she published papers on high throughput
characterization of crisper tools and
developed an invivo genome editing
therapeutics uh for neurological
diseases. Her lab which she started in
2023 continues to pursue the development
of genome editing therapeutics for
various genetic conditions and works to
translate these drugs from bench bench
to bedside. and today she's going to be
talking about a recent paper um called
base editing triplet repeats of
Huntington's disease and Frederick's
dictaxia. Thank
you very much um for that introduction.
Um okay. Um yes, that's exactly what I'm
here to speak about today. So I'm going
to jump right in. Um our uh lab focuses
on the development uh of genome editing
therapeutics for various different
neurological diseases. um starting from
identification of uh good targets uh and
strategies there for um and then first
validating these in vitro and then
ultimately um taking them into animal
models with the end goal of uh taking
them into clinic and so also doing the
um IND enabling studies uh for that and
we're mo mostly been focused on um
neurological disorders that affect
movement uh including motor neuron
diseases um as well as repeat expansion
disorders which are mainly going to be
focusing on today. Um, so I'm confident
that you are all well aware of uh
crisperbased editing. So obviously
doesn't need much introduction, but I
just briefly want to highlight a few
aspects of these tools that are going to
be um relevant that you maybe don't
think about as much. So uh base editing
is a technology that utilizes um the
sort of search and find function of cast
9 but couples the cast 9 protein to a
daminase enzyme. And what this allows is
that when cast 9 binds and the guide RNA
hybridizes with one of the strands of
the DNA, the other singlestranded um
portion of DNA becomes available uh for
this chemistry by the damnase enzyme to
be able to happen. And uh in the case of
for example an adinine base editor, it
can turn this uh adenosine into an
innocine that is recognized as a G. And
then through uh DNA repair, this
mismatched position here is resolved
into um a stable uh base ultimately
turning an AT pair into a GC pair. Um so
in principle I guess the two things I
want to highlight any singlestranded DNA
is made available to the diaminise.
Obviously this is uh localized by the
cast 9 but this is also what stops the
diaminase from in general just
daminating all of the genome. Um and
also uh base editors typically will use
uh not a dead cast 9 that only searches
and finds but in fact a nickase. And the
role of the nickase is to nick the
strand that opposes the one where the
damination event occurs. And the reason
for this is that nicks are more rapidly
identified by DNA repair as being
problematic. And so you will um
typically then end up having the strand
that had the original uh nucleotide of
the pair on it being rected and
templated off of the strand that has the
daminated um position. And so you are in
fact biasing then your outcomes to uh
resolving in favor of the change that
you have made rather than reverting
50/50 or less than that um to the uh
original base card that was there. So
initially um a couple years ago we
demonstrated uh the use of this admin
based editing technology to treat uh a
different disorder. This is a motor
neuron disease called spinal muscular
atrophy or SMA. Um in this uh disorder
uh most often um infants pretty much as
soon as they are born begin to present
with symptoms ultimately leading to uh
paralysis and if untreated these
patients will not survive past about 18
months. And SMA is in fact the leading
genetic cause of infant death globally.
And even though uh to this day we still
don't actually understand the mechanism
of pathology that leads to the loss of
motor neurons, we've known for about
three decades that uh this disease is
caused by the loss of this uh essential
SMN1 gene with retention always of this
SM2 gene which is almost identical to
SM1 except for one CDT transition that
causes a splice variant. um and as a
result SM2 genes produce only about 10%
of the functional protein and SMN1 would
and the different um subclasses uh shown
here of severity actually relate to the
copy number of SM2 that patients have.
So it was known that it's a dose
responsive gene if you up the amount of
SMN uh you can also restore this
disorder. So uh we developed a base
editing strategy um to treat this uh
shown here. So we turn this AT pair into
the C GC pair that um is the one that is
found typically in SMN1 genes. Um and
after validating this in vitro, we
delivered this into animals using AV9.
AV9 importantly is a vector that is used
uh to deliver SM gene therapy to
estimate patients very successfully in
the clinic. So we have prior knowledge
not only in animal models but in
patients that this actually does deliver
cargo efficaciously to the target tissue
of interest. Um and what we were happy
to find is that in uh neurons that get
transduced in vivo about 90% of them
have this conversion of the insufficient
SMN2 gene to the SMN1
gene. Um and through some uh additional
optimization. So the uh mouse model that
we were working with for SMA is one that
um has a very rapid decline. uh so do
the human patients but in animals what
this means is that uh if you don't
rescue uh the SMN levels by about five
days after birth you really aren't
rescuing their survival at all their
median survival is about 17 days without
any treatment um what we did is we uh
used a bridging drug essentially one of
the transient therapeutics that's on the
market for SMA that can very um briefly
uh by rescuing splicing um ameliorate
disease so we gave a very small dose
only a single time uh at time point zero
and that alone alone um is able to uh
that the ASO that we use alone is able
to increase the median life expectancy
from 17 days to 29 days. But when we
then couple that together with our um
base editing drug, we can now see the
median survival increase pretty
dramatically to 77 days. Um and actually
to be fair, the animals that die after
this um time point actually aren't dying
of motor neuron disease. They don't sort
of like slowly paralyze and and and
decline in that way. They typically are
just running around and then drop dead.
Um, and that's because this animal
model, and this is specific to the
animal, not human patients, um, has a
cardiac phenotype that's associated with
the disease as well. Um, and as you can
see here, this is an example of, um,
what these animals actually look like.
So, I think a video is probably more
telling than a graph. Um, this is at 200
days old. We have an animal that's
treated with ASO uh, and the base editor
compared to one of its wild type litter
mates. And as you can see, it's mobile
and happily moving around. Um, it's not
entirely normal looking. Uh, you'll
notice among other things, it's missing
a tail. But this also is something that
we know um we're not really worried
about in case of human patients because
humans don't have tail. Um but also
because the peripheral phenotypes again
are ones that are related to the animal
model and not um to the human condition.
Um so now that we had uh demonstrated
this um in this paradigm and we're as I
mentioned continuing to uh do the
pre-clinical development of this drug we
wanted to go ahead and um start uh
working on an entirely different uh also
uh deterministic genetic disease which
is um the first disease actually that
was known to be associated with the gene
uh was discovered back in the 80s which
is the Huntington gene.
So uh the mutation in the Huntington
gene is pretty much a a very different
form. Um it's part of a class of what
are known as tandem repeat disorders
specifically trucleide repeat disorders.
Uh and these are caused by expansion of
a repeated triplet of nucleotides. And
so TNRS as a class uh include around 40
different disorders that are caused by
sematic expansion of the repeat
sequence. Um these include sequences
like CAG, CA, G, uh CTG, GAA, and
CGD. Um and they frequently cause loss
of motor coordination, and they're also
very often fatal. Uh there are many
features that distinguish these
different um diseases uh including the
genes that they're located in, the
location within the genes um that
they're located in as well. Uh and the
sequence itself um and the sequence
itself is responsible for secondary
structure that these uh the DNA can
form. um and all complications that
arise from that. Uh and Huntington's
disease specifically falls into a
subcategory that we call polyglutamine
or polyQ disorders because CAG um when
found in an exxon um encodes for
glutamine. Uh however um both KAGs and
CTG which is its reverse complement are
found both in coding and non-coding uh
region of the genome. Um and they do
similarly uh undergo these expansions
that are associated with some form of
disease. Um and then there's also uh
Friedri's taxia which is a disease um
that's caused by the expansion of these
GAA um nucleotides that are located uh
in the first intron of the freaxin gene.
So how do um repeats end up causing
these? Well, a common feature um of all
of these that I've described even though
they can differ quite drastically with
their location is that they are in fact
all um transcribed. And what happens
during transcription is that uh an R
loop can form where the newly
synthesized RNA can hybridize um with
the template strand leaving the
non-template strand exposed. And because
that sequence is highly repetitive and
in most cases as you see also very
GC-rich this forms secondary structures
that when the DNA is trying to hybridize
together once again uh can slip out and
these slip out structures then cause
also slipping out on the opposing strand
where you have these loops um that come
out uh and these become um a problem
that DNA needs to deal with and they
also become more vulnerable to uh for
example oxidative stress stress or um
cytosine damination that also native
atively happens in the cell all the
time. Uh as a result of this you get
nicks and these nicks that need to be
resolved and because the sequence is so
repetitive it becomes very difficult for
DNA repair to know exactly where that
repeat that it's trying to resolve was
supposed to match. And so what happens a
lot of the time is that it matches in an
incorrect place which then uh results in
a change in length of the repeat. So it
can either shorten, contract or uh it
can expand and this is what we refer to
as instability of the locus. Um and what
we know is that the instability of these
lowi increases as the length of the
repeat itself increases most likely
because you know the longer it is the
more far away it is from the anchoring
um points of the side that aren't
repetitive. Um but uh the
um so and sorry and while it uh can both
contract and and expand um when repeats
are on the shorter side they tend to
favor contraction more whereas as they
lengthen um they tend to favor
expansion. And so you get this feedback
loop where a long repeat then when it's
unstable favors adding more repeats on.
And so then it becomes again more
unstable and is more likely to again
acquire more and so on and so on. And so
that's how it um has this uh essentially
um ends up being an outofcontrol um
expansion of these repeat lossi. Um and
so what does it look like? It looks
something uh like this. So here we can
for example see
a set of alals.
Okay.
Oh, appointment toward my
computer. No, I think this works. Does
this
work? No. Well, anyway, you can see it
over here. um you can see a a set of
alals basically um that you can start
with. So in this case uh the um median
al size is around um 80 repeats long. Uh
and over time if you look six months
later you can see that um this peak has
diverged and the majority of alals now
have lengthened uh to get over 100
repeats. And there's also a subfraction
that has become smaller um at 76
repeats. And this is uh this um
instability phenomenon um and this
happens uh in sematic cells. So patients
in the germ line they are born with a
certain length and there are some
sematic cells uh where this expansion
can happen. Um one of the sematic cells
in which this happens as well um if you
can call it that is is germline cells.
And so uh for a lot of these disorders
during spermatogenesis there actually
also is an addition sometimes of one uh
or more um of these repeats uh and what
that can result in is that uh there
might not have been a family history of
for example Huntington's disease but
then suddenly denovo in a new generation
you can have um now uh what will be
hereditary um Huntington's disease in
that population and this is a process
that's called
anticipation. Um so the as mentioned
once they're if they are of a certain
length they will be stable. Um and so it
should be noted that in all of these
genes the repeat sequences that I've
showed you um are present in the general
population. We all have these repeats
but we have them up until a certain
length that is considered stable. So in
the case of Huntington's having about um
10 to 26 of these repeats is pretty
normal and that's most likely what most
of us have. If you have about 27 to 35
of them then you might be at increased
risk of anticipation where subsequent
generations could uh gain um the the uh
pathology. Um and then after that if you
are um 36 uh to about 39 repeats there
is uh low risk there's lower penetrance
um of uh the disease and that probably
relates to other apologenic um risk
factors uh that some of which have begun
to become elucidated but 40 with
Huntington's disease is a threshold. If
you have 40 repeats or more, it is
deterministic that you will get
Huntington's disease. Um, and the timing
when you will get is dependent um on
that length as well. So, as you can see
um if you are have a germline length, so
born of about 40 repeats, you're likely
to get honey in about your 50s, but if
you have 60 repeats now, you're more
likely to get it in about your 20s. Um
and in particular in sort of that 40 to
45 range, every additional CAG that you
have at germ lang length uh will
increase um sorry will um bring the age
of onset forward by over a year. Um so
it's a pretty um
uh sensitive uh portion of this and
that's probably because of this um fact
uh Leo was explaining where more repeats
beget more repeats and so you are
getting closer to that tipping point of
where you sort of end up um going more
rapidly out of control.
Uh so um one of the many curious aspects
of this disease is the latency until the
age of onset because once the disease
does manifest um the symptoms also tend
to manifest more quickly. But it does
seem to be true uh based on a battery of
um motor and cognitive tests um that up
until the point that patients get
Huntington's disease they are not
subclinical. They do not have um what
seems to be some small degree of
pathology that goes unnoticed that
slowly linearly builds up and then they
have disease. They don't have it and
then it suddenly happens. Um so how is
this possible? Uh and
why? Um and
uh to answer that earlier this year
there was a really beautiful paper that
came out from the Carol lab um where
they were able to look at uh the um
stryatum uh some cells from the stratum
neurons of uh deceased Huntington's
patients which is really of course as
you can imagine a pretty unique thing
where they performed single cell um on
these brains uh and they um carefully
studied uh the relationship between the
transcriptto and the repeat length um to
try to see you know how is it that
Huntington is actually progressing and
they were able to then um subdivide uh
the disease progression into different
phases A through D A through E and phase
A um it's the slow expansion phase and
this phase lasts several decades this is
where patients do not at all um have any
symptoms and apparently this is up to
about 80 repeats long then phase B after
this tipping point of 80 repeats has
been reached in some sematic cells. This
uh
expansion rapidly accelerates and then
once you hit 150 repeats now these cells
suddenly um begin to have over 500 or or
more genes uh that become disregulated.
At this point the cell is losing its
cell identity. Um and ultimately uh as
this um exacerbates uh they get uh
derpression of um certain key
developmental and scinessence and
eptosis markers. Uh and then after that
very quickly um the neuron dies.
Um what is uh also really important to
note here however is that it seems to be
that there uh may well be a reasonable
therapeutic window for treatment of
patients um based on their analysis not
only if you can catch uh neurons before
they hit this 150 mark and so before um
patients begin to uh have any symptoms
of Huntington's disease where many
neurons can be lost but even when
neurons are beginning to be lost and
patients are starting to suffer from
Huntington's disease, the majority of
the neurons um in their brain actually
have not yet met this point. So even at
the point that about 25% of uh these
neurons are lost um 90% of the neurons
have still not actually hit this 150
point which means that if you can find a
way to intervene in this process of this
expansion that ultimately leads to
disease you would have an opportunity to
rescue um the bulk of neurons um and
treat patients. And if you wanted to um
resolve it al together uh based on sort
of their their modeling if you had
someone born with about 40 repeats which
is most people um then if you would be
able to treat them before they're pretty
much in their 40s you might be able to
hold off Huntington's disease at all. So
what would be a way of being able to
intervene in this expansion process? Um
there was a G-W was study that came out
in 2019 that looked at genetic
associations with Huntington's disease
and the major finding from that is
actually that the sequence itself um is
extremely important uh in this expansion
process. Uh so in most people um I
believe also including most hundreds
patients uh the kagg repeat the polyq
region is not just kags uh there is a
penultimate caa that happens which also
includes q. So the polyq length is
actually two nucle two codons longer um
than the uh than the kag repeat stretch
is. um and that is considered sort of
this gray uh normal line that you can
see here um in the middle that predicts
your age of onset based on length. Um
however uh very often and more so uh in
Huntington's population than in the
general population that uh penultimate
CAA is lost and when it is lost which is
the red line you can see that the age of
onset um is much uh approaches much more
quickly at the same polyQ length than it
does if you did have that one CAA
interruption. And then in some um cases
that CAA CAG is actually duplicated and
there the age of onset is much further.
Uh so having just um a single or
multiple of these CAA silent uh codon
changes is able to have a pretty
profound impact in the age of onset of
this disease. Um and if you look overall
across the population, patients that
have pure CAD repeats versus uh polyQues
of a similar length but with a single CA
interruption um that delays the onset of
Huntington's disease by 25 years. Uh
which is obviously um quite a profound
difference. Um and from what we uh know
this isn't unique to Huntington's
disease. So Friedrix taxia as I
mentioned is another disorder that is
caused by GA expansion. So a different
sequence altogether. um there isn't as
large scale of study um as was done for
uh Huntington's disease, but here it is
also apparent that having interruptions
in the GA repeat track that's found in
the intron of GGA, Gag GggG um is able
to also very significantly by several
decades in some cases uh stave off this
um this uh onset of the disease uh most
likely again due to the repeat expansion
and this to a certain degree had been
known from um prior work on uh bacterial
cells, yeast, you know, where people had
inserted these sorts of sequences to
study the process of repeat expansion
that these interruptions really are very
important um in determining the um
frequency of uh repeat expansions um and
the rate of it.
So why is this important? We have a
technology that allows us to make single
nucleide changes in the genome. And so
we um set out to develop uh two
different strategies. one targeting um
on the opposing strand of CAG so CT ctg
CTG um a genome editing strategy that's
able to convert um CAGs into the
synonymous CADons
uh and then on the um GAA side one
that's also able to insert um A to G
changes in the GAA repeats in the intron
um to hopefully have a stabilizing
effect on these
repeats. So it is a bit of an unusual
strategy for genome editing which is uh
typically the the goal is to be as
precise as possible and target only one
genomic location. Here we had a
different goal. Um and here we designed
our guide RNA in a way to essentially be
somewhat non-specific to the entire
repeat region. Um our thinking was that
it would allow it to somewhat um
sporadically um intersperse um
interruptions across the length of the
repeat tract. uh and with longer AP
tracks it would allow you to insert more
of these stabilizing um mutations. Uh so
we developed a strategy that would then
as mentioned uh use cytosine damination
to convert um CAGs into CAS. Uh and we
looked at uh a bunch of different
strategies to do so with um the
available daminas at the time and we
were really happy to find that uh a
great number of them were able to edit
this locus with high efficiency. So this
is in a screen in HET 93T cells um that
have only 17 CAGS so relatively short as
it's a normal number um and I want to
draw your focus initially to the ones
that are on this side of the graph um
and you can see that uh the editing
itself is quite high but we also have um
these other byproducts that are uh not
as desirable um that you can see in
particular these stop codons. So where
are these stop codons coming from? Um as
mentioned before uh the reason that
cytosine damination um happens uh in the
portion that you're targeting your your
guide to is because the guide RNA binds
the other strand and it makes available
the single stranded DNA on the opposing
strand. Um however we have seen in the
past from hyper characterizations of
these tools that you can sometimes see
editing happening outside uh on the pam
distal end um of the guide RNA sequence
that you're targeting. Um and in
particular this is also noticeable on
the opposing strand um that you're
getting uh some of these damination
events. And this is likely due to
breathing um of the DNA as you're having
this binding event here. And this is
typically a very rare thing that happens
only with um some cytosine base editors
but most likely because we're having so
many con you know uh consecutive binding
events happening. You might have more of
that. And so we actually see some
editing of the opposing strand here. And
that in this case would result in TAA or
TAG uh stop code on confirmation. Now,
this is not something that we want uh we
think at least we probably don't want to
knock out the Huntington gene. So, we
made a bunch of architectural changes to
um alter the uh the frequency um of
these uh still relatively rare uh
outcomes and also somewhat um increase
efficiency. Um and ultimately we picked
a strategy which is this 32NLS strategy
to move forward with. And then uh we
took this strategy and we wanted to
apply it in the context of longer
repeats because we don't know how it
will behave um just because it does
certain thing at 17 repeats we don't
know what it will do at longer repeats
and so we looked at um patient
fibroblasts uh that have uh different
alle lengths which can be seen here um
shown at the bottom. So there's
typically a normal alil in Huntington's
patients and a longer alil as can be
seen here. So for example this patient
has one al with 17
Um but we can see across the board that
we actually um get um high editing um at
both alals uh both the long and the
short one um in each of these cell
lines. And there always seems to be in
fact a little bit of higher editing uh
from what we've seen in the longer al
and shorter one which could make sense
in the sense that you know it's more of
a magnet essentially for multiple
binding events as it is longer. Um, one
slight caveat to um, in particular this
last one here that has a very long
repeat of 180. Um, we do this analysis
by short read aluminina sequencing and
we're actually only able to cover um,
about half of the repeat tract for that
180 al. So we can cover the other alals
because they're within what we can um,
sequence which is about 90 of them but
we can't fully cover the 180. So the
actual editing at that al might in fact
be higher than what is shown here.
Um oh another thing that we were quite
happy to find is that the incidence of
stop codons um was we actually didn't
really see them uh here there was some
minor fraction of um uh ins I believe
but we don't nothing was over sort of
the untreated condition because these
low side are difficult to sequence so it
probably wasn't even a real finding to
begin with um so that wasn't a concern
anymore um then uh the I think more um
interesting finding is what does this do
to the repeat tract Um so here we can
see um essentially at baseline um the
two alals. So we have the alil uh
histogram for the short al over here and
for the longer alil over here for this
18180 cell line. Um this was the only
cell line with the longest repeats that
uh we could even see expansion happening
in culture. Um which you know kind of
makes sense because we can't culture
these primary cells for so long to see
this process happening. Um but uh so we
monitored these cells um either
untreated uh in blue which is I don't
know if you can see very clearly but
it's hiding behind this purple um or
with the sitine base editor treated
samples and then we culture this um over
five passages for about 30 days and what
you can see here is that um the
untreated uh expands and gets larger
uh in almost all of the um the the
baseline longer alals uh and our CDE
treated stays um pretty stagnant and in
fact drops in size a little bit. So this
one uh has increased by I think about
five or six repeats and this one's
actually dropped by about five or six
repeats from our starting point. Um so
we've in fact uh demonstrated now that
experimentally if you go in to long
repeats and you make these edits you do
in fact confer the stability um that has
been found previously by association
population.
So then uh as mentioned the um guide RNA
that we're using is not specific. It
targets the repeats. There are more of
these repeats in the genome that don't
just belong to Huntington gene. Um
importantly there are actually about a
dozen or so um different uh trucide
repeat disorders that are caused by CAG
CTG expansion. Um and of course our
genome editing strategy targets each of
these um essentially indiscriminately.
Uh what's really interesting about this
is that you know if you could then in
the future you would have such an
approach that you may uh use in the
clinic um if you validate a drug uh for
any one of these targets that means that
that drug would also then work for any
of these other um dryucleide repeat
expansion disorders. Um however aside
from ones that are associated with
disease uh and of course in any one
patient only one of them will be
associated with disease the other ones
are still there. um there are very very
many other loi throughout the genome
that also have uh around eight or so
seven or eight of these repeats that
will also be targeted by the strategy.
So uh to sort of get at how many these
are where are they what are they um we
perform circle seek initially. So circle
seek uh is a biochemical assay where you
use a nucleus form of the cast protein
with the guide RNA to nominate li where
the base editor might land um in a cell
condition to uh induce base editing. Um
and we found uh well over 5,000 of these
lossi throughout the genome um of which
about 10% were a perfect match. So they
also just had pure of the kag repeat. So
they're just they're not even off
targets they're alternative targets um
of our guide. uh and then um subasses
that had increasing number of mismatches
which we know are likely in the base
editing context and cells to actually
reduce uh the potential for um editing
events there. Um
and then we wanted to um look further
into uh what these were. And so uh we
were able to subdivide that out of these
uh 5700 um low side that are potential
targets uh about 17% of them code for
proteins. Um and there are uh of the
protein coding offtargets about 15% of
them that are a perfect match um for our
CTG. The CTG um or CAGS uh very often
encodes for glutamine but sometimes it's
in its slightly different flame frame
where it can also encode for other amino
acids. Um of the four different um amino
acids that we found that encoded uh
three of them are synonymous changes
glutamine, lucine cysteine um but
serrines will be converted into
asparagene. So that would be a miss
mutation. Uh so we were interested to
find um of the uh roughly 1,00 in
particular the 10,00 perfect match
protein coding loi what those are um but
also of the other offtargets
um how frequently they're actually
occurring and what they're doing. Now
usually when you do circle seek and for
this sort of validation you pick the top
or maybe the entire list of offt targets
to look at in the genome to see whether
or not there's editing but there's
thousands of loi here and so that's not
really something we can do in an arrayed
you know single locus amplification
fashion which is what we typically do.
So we sought and said to do whole genome
sequencing in this case um at very high
coverage 160x uh to be able to see um
after we treat cells with our genome
editing tool what is our likelihood of
actually getting an editing event there.
um even at 160x it is pretty difficult
to get good quality um calling of a
single nucleotide change that happens in
particular in repeat regions that are
very difficult to get through and are
more likely to uh induce errors. Um but
uh if we um we did this nevertheless and
if we look at any lossi that have uh
over.5% over background um of a single
nucleide change uh there is about 48% of
circle seek nominated lowi that um we
would call as an edit which is um about
2743 lowi. Um we did find uh as
anticipated that uh the frequency of
edits decreased steadily with the number
of mismatches. As soon as you have you
know essentially over two mismatches you
don't really get editing at these lowi
um which is uh pretty much expected. Um
we demonstrate this here in a table
where we uh basically subdivide where
the mismatches fall. So it had been
known um from prior work and and was
reproduced here that uh mismatches in
the guide RNA that are more proximal to
the PAM particular in the seed region
that are shown here in A and B but the
closer uh the worse it is um that those
have a greater impact on uh the um
binding ability um of cast 9. So if you
have mutations here that's worse than if
you have mutations uh in the tail end.
Um and that's what we can see here.
These are uh ones that have no mutations
at all in the entirety of the guide RNA.
you have ones where you have um no
mutations in A but you have uh only
mutation in the C region etc. Um then uh
we wanted to um to some degree validate
uh these um uh editing events uh by
doing single locus amplification. And we
find that for the most part our whole
genome sequencing analysis is pretty
accurate at calling it if o
overestimating to a certain degree um
due to our sort of liberal calling u
methods um what the editing frequency
there is.
Um but so ultimately uh we were most
interested in what we thought might be u
mutations of clinical significance. So
we found that indeed the overwhelming
majority of edits um were non-coding
interrogenic or in other regulatory
regions um or inducing silent mutations
and there were a very small subset uh
where there were relatively compared to
what we started with where there were um
potential changes. Um so if we looked at
whole genome sequencing lowside that had
over 5% editing to call it somewhat more
accurately we find that uh over 1200
sites um show editing including 243
genes. Uh and of those 91 genes in total
have um mismatch mutations. Uh so then
we wanted to um ask what are these genes
and how important are they? Uh so we
compared them with the um cancer depth
map to see um if any of these genes are
cell essential and we also looked uh
whether or not these um genes are
expressed in neurons uh because those
are the ones that we're delivering the
editing to. Um and then we also looked
at alpha missense to see if we're making
these non- synonymous changes uh what is
the likelihood that that will have an
effect on protein building or protein
function. Um and ultimately we found
that there were four uh genes that were
essential that were targeted. Um one of
which has a mutation that is predicted
to result in a change in protein folding
or function. Uh and we only actually
throughout the entire genome found with
our strategy um that we'd optimized uh
to uh induce a stop codon which is also
really nice. Um but that stopcodon was
uh in a gene that is neither essential
nor expressed in neurons. So it's you
know probably not um relevant as not
transcribed in the cells we're
targeting. So in some the basing
approach has quite a lot of offt targets
um that do happen uh some of which may
be a clinical significance. So if this
is something that uh we would ultimately
want to pursue um more for a therapeutic
angle we would need special attention um
on those uh sites in the future. So
ultimately we then wanted to um take
this uh same strategy and see what
happens when we put this into um a uh an
animal system. Um so not just cells in
culture but in an actual organism. And
so we did the same form of delivery uh
where we used AV9 um to inject this uh
basing strategy. Uh we do this alongside
um a small dose a tenth of a dose of GFP
which is basically just a a trace
control for um transduction efficiency.
Uh and we can see that when we
um sort out these uh nuclei uh and
editing pieces over weeks but at 24
weeks we have um around uh 80% editing
of uh targeted nuclei and what does this
do to the repeat alals? So we monitored
uh various cell types over um the time
course so 12 weeks 24 weeks and we
looked at cells both that expand and
don't expand. Um we were really excited
to find that similar to what we found uh
in our cell culture conditions when we
look at the stratum which is the disease
tissue and that also has the most severe
um expansion phenotype in the brain uh
we can see in pink relative to gray um a
reduction in these uh the longer hump uh
of expanded alals um and in fact we're
also gaining these contractions here
shown here in pink um that you don't
have in the control condition. So, uh
it's probably easier to see than in that
histogram um in a plot like this. Um
this is an analysis called the
instability index that as the name would
suggest um measures the instability of
alals. Um and as you can see here at
both uh 12 weeks and then more
pronounced at 24 weeks uh in cells that
have uh in animals that have received
the base editor we can see a significant
um drop in the instability index
compared to untreated animals. Um so
this is very exciting. When we were
working on this paper, um another study
came out where they actually generated
animal models that had uh either just
the the CAG repeat as is the classical
version to have in that in that mouse.
Um but they also made versions of that
same alil that had CAGS interspersed. I
think it was every third or so. Um CAG
was a CAA. Um and they demonstrated
there also that that freezes completely
the expansion of repeats. And here we
were able to show for the first time
that inducing these into what are
already long alals in an animal system
where these alals expand, you are
actually also able to do that same thing
where you um you freeze these. Um I will
also note that uh these data also have
to be qualified by the fact that we
didn't have a way of um sorting out only
those cells that had been edited. So
this is actually looking at all cells we
were able to isolate. Um and uh as we
know there's only a subfraction of cells
if you look at the um the bulk basically
uh that's here about you know there's
only maybe about 35% of neurons that
even have the opportunity to be edited
in the first place. Um and so uh this is
again most likely an underrepresentation
of the actual um rescue that
the approach of inducing edits um
actually has on alals. um and it's more
likely that the alals that have edits
are are are likely um to be frozen.
So then we uh want to do the same
strategy for Fredicaxia. So um I think
you all get the the idea here. Um so we
have a guide RNA that targets the GAA
repeats and we want to turn um the some
of those GAAS into having some uh A to G
interruptions. Um and uh
we tried to um several uh different um
cast proteins to target uh in different
frames to induce these sorts of edits.
Um and we were able to do so with um
pretty high efficiency that we were
quite happy with. Um one thing I'll
point out here is that we have the
purple bars which are um oh sorry
actually I think I put the the wrong
graph up here. I wanted to show the the
difference between um nicase mediated
editing which is the classical base
editor and this deadcast 9 but this
still suffices. Uh ultimately we went
for the um abe uh damnase. Um but what
we did is we actually paired this with a
deadcast 9. Uh so as mentioned typically
you have a nicase that makes the
opposing strand to bias um editing
toward incorporating uh the edit that
you want. Um but uh we decided in this
case because the editor was in fact so
efficient that we might not need this uh
and we made it into a dead um cast 9 uh
meaning that there was no nicase
activity and there's only the
damination. So you're going to have
fewer these conversions um but uh the
editing is enough that we thought that
that was fine. Why did we decide to do
to take this approach? um similar to uh
CAG CTGs that there are many of in the
genome um there are orders of magnitude
more um GAAS the GAA repeat uh in this
location as well as across the genome
are in alo elements for the most part
and these are um dormant uh retro
transpo transcodons that um we have uh
interpersed all throughout our genome in
many many different locations and for
the most part they form uh they perform
regulatory functions and introns and
ITRs um but just due to the sheer number
of them, we felt like maybe having nicks
all over the genome in so many locations
might not be as favorable. And since it
wasn't really strictly necessary, we
decided to um omit that um linking
feature. Uh then we took our best
strategy um and this uh was done in hect
cells that only have nine gas at this
low locus, which is not um a lot. So we
wanted to have uh transgenic cell lines
where we had more of these repeats. So
we derived um nyriionic stem cell lines
that had uh either 30 or um 60 ga
repeats which is over the pathogenic
threshold. Um and we ultimately chose
our uh top favorite strategy which is an
NRCH um AB8E editor uh that is able to
um still induce uh edits at a relatively
high
frequency. Um and then uh we also did
the same thing where we um targeted uh
patient cells. um patients with
freedaxia have a much greater number um
of uh repeat expansions. The expansion
process goes uh into the thousands um
for patients that have that. Um so it's
a slightly different problem than you
have with CAD repeats where you know
you're already very much pathogenic if
you're you know at the 80 range. Um so
these patients cells um had short alil
300 uh 330 sorry and 380 or um 541 and
and 420 alals. Uh and also actually an
important thing to note is that while um
Huntington's disease is a dominant uh
disease where one al is pathogenic in
the case of Fredricaxia it's actually
recessive and so patients will have two
alals um that are um that are uh
affected. Uh so here we um performed
editing again uh and measured the
editing that we got at these repeat
lossi. Um again here we're stuck with
this limitation of aluminina sequencing
where we can only edit uh sequence about
300 base pairs which covers for us about
380 of these GAAS. Um and as you can
imagine even in our uh shortest of these
alals that's 330 repeats long that's a
very small portion of it. Um now we
sequenced both from one end and the
other end uh and we have essentially the
same data suggesting that uh the editing
as expected is happening uniformly
across the repeat which is also what we
see in any of the shorter long repeat
alals. Um but uh because this is such an
underestimation, we developed this
extrapolation model um to say, okay, if
this is the amount of um editing that we
have here, what does that mean? Uh can
we estimate how much editing we'd have
across the rest of the le um and uh
determine what the editing probably
actually is at these lowi? Um and so we
estimate that our editing um at these
alals is actually around about
80%.
Yes. Oh, okay. Yeah, I'm almost done.
Actually, I think I Yeah. Um, so then uh
one other um valuable thing about
Friedri's taxia um is that uh we
actually know the cause of the disease
is that when these repeats get so long,
they silence the genomic locus and there
is reduced expression of the FXM gene.
So we wanted to see does our editing
actually affect this um loss in
expression. Um and we were not
necessarily expecting that it it would
per se um but it did which was uh quite
a good finding. Um so in untreated um
short normal uh fibroblasts the level of
expression we basically uh normalize um
to one and then uh if we compare um
patient fibroblasts with uh the long
repeats either untreated or treated with
an unrelated guide RNA um you have only
about half of the expression and you
rescue about half of that loss um by
doing this uh base editing interruption.
Um I guess I'll breeze past the fact
that we also did uh whole genome
sequencing and circle seek here as
mentioned an order of magnitude more
hits but actually a way smaller
subfraction that are um coding because
again these repeats mainly arise from
these aloe elements that are uh
regulatory sequences. um and we did not
find any stop codeons and for the most
part our basitting strategy just mimics
the natural variation of inducing these
um ag changes in repeat tracts. Uh there
are uh a very small number that um do uh
warrant further study um because they
are uh potentially in in regions that
might have um a negative effect. Um and
then we did this in animal models. So
just to take you through that quickly as
well um both in animals with 300 repeats
or 800 repeats uh our estimated editing
um is around 60% of alals um and this
has a profound impact um on the
instability index as well. If we look
here at the cortex where we can have
significant expansion, um our edited uh
cells have um much more stable um alals.
Uh and this is even more striking uh
when you compare uh the longer uh 800
mouse uh relative to the 300 mouse. Um
so I will leave it at that. Thank you
very much uh for listening. I want to
give a huge massive shout out to uh
co-lead author on the paper. um who's a
brilliant uh now posttock in Palar
Lada's lab. She um was a graduate
student in David's lab uh where I was
doing my posttock and that's where all
of this work was done. So also major
shout out of course to David who um you
know allowed us uh to do all this
incredible work and this was also done
in collaboration with Lucardo Muropa's
lab. Uh he runs a lab over at MGH um and
is an expert in uh both of these and and
other repeat extension disorders. uh
Guang Panga's group um who was able to
help us with um virus um Arthur Burgess
who also collaborated on the um SMA
project and Cat Lutz over at Jax um
everyone from my lab um some of whom are
shown here uh who have also helped uh
some of who helped take this paper over
the finish line um and of course our um
funding sources that uh NIH so who's
able to help support um you know all
this really important work so thank you
very