Before my first launch, I I asked many
of the astronauts who had already flown,
you know, what's it going to be like? I
mean, every rocket has its own
characteristics. With with the shuttle,
it was those two big solid rocket
boosters that cause all of the
vibration. And they they burn for the
first 2 minutes. I remember thinking to
myself, "No, this can't be normal.
Something's wrong." But, I mean, the
structural engineers knew what they were
doing. ever since I was 6 years old and
I saw Flash Gordon take off in his
rocket ship in in science fiction and I
always dreamed of doing it and and I'm
about to uh you know leave the planet.
It was it was exciting you know sit back
and enjoy the ride. I I'm not a pilot so
I didn't have to even worry about flying
the shuttle. I could just look out the
window and enjoy this incredible
experience which it certainly was.
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learnmit.edu.
[Music]