thank you um so my name is JJ and I'm
the co-founder and chief scientist of
tupi a startup company span out from my
group at MIT focusing on Innovative
optic
Solutions so we all live in an
information era today and we are
receiving ever increasing amount of
information they actually being captured
in processed using light with the
exponential growth of optical
information existing optic systems are
getting increasingly large in size and
more complex this has become a
showstopper for many
applications if you look at Optical
system it really hadn't changed that
much over the past few decades on one
hand you have glass lenses that offer
high performance but require grinding
and polishing fabrication they are
costly and not scalable on the other
hand you also have plastic lenses which
can be fabricated by Ming at very low
cost but suffer from performance and
reliability concerns on top of that an
optical system typically requires
stacking several of these lenses
together piece by piece with careful
alignment resulting in systems with
increased size cost and
complexity T Pi has developed metal plus
Optics to solve this challenge our
approach uses semiconductor fabrication
and packaging technologies that have
been matured in the IC industry to
transform Optics unlike traditional
lenses that rely on curved surfaces to
bend light uh we fabricate tiny little
structures or Optical inners on a flat
wafer and then use them to control light
propagation Direction precisely as a
result they can be produced at high
volume with low cost leveraging standard
semiconductor waer fabrication
Technologies moreover when it comes to
assembly we can stack and B multiple
Wafers each of them containing array of
this flat lenses and precisely align
them with lithographic accuracy in the
end the wafer stack is then singulated
into thousands of individual packaged
lens modules each with the form Vector
of a small chip in this way we can
leverage Industries than their
semiconductor packaging technology to
realize large scale parallel integration
of Optics will significantly enhance
throughput and
performance so here is an use case of
our technology so driver monitoring
systems or DMS are basically small
cameras install vehicles to ensure that
drivers are not getting distracted while
driving and our technology enables using
a single component flare Optics to
replace traditional stacked glass and
polymer lenses this significantly
improves the thermal and mechanical rugg
which is critical to compliance with
Automotive regulations
in addition our Optics also offers enhan
Optical resolution that improves
detection accuracy and reduces Force
alarms we have already delivered mass
produced Optics to Leading tier one and
tier 2 suppliers in the automotive
industry and receive excellent feedback
from our
customers a second use case example of
our Optics is in Optical sensors for
augmented reality and virtual reality
systems uh state of the rvr modules
contain anywhere from 15 to 20 Optical
sensors to perform functions such as
facial recognition eye tracking hand
tracking 3D sing and so on when using
traditional Optics the size and way
quickly add up using our technology we
offer sensor modules that are far more
compact lightweight and can be
seamlessly integrated with arvr headsets
at the same time our Optics also offers
high resolution and a large field to
view measuring that of human preferral
Vision which helps to render immersive
user experience that other Technologies
can hardly match the performance of our
sensor modules has already been tested
and validated by Leading OEM vendors and
we are now working towards mass
production of this
product so in summary what we are
offering here is a platform technology
that can Empower applications where high
performance Compact and lightway Optical
systems are needed we are therefore
eagerly looking for partners in consumer
electronics Automotive robotics Medical
Imaging and Beyond to explore this
exciting technology thank you for your
attention thank you very much um can you
tell us a little more about how the
Optics are mass produced since you
touched on that and at what
scale uh sure so we uh we actually have
a f partners that can allow us to
actually produce this Optics all 300 mm
stand the W for technology um so uh this
is really compatible with
state-of-the-art semiconductor mass
production okay and um tell us a little
more about uavs is there an
application oh oh yeah that's a great
question so I think that's a UAV and
Robotics are generally sectors we really
sort of want to look into we got quite a
bit of tractions in those uh areas uh
essentially what we're offering here is
sort of a Machine Vision platform
Hardware platform uh that's miniaturized
lightweight and also high performance uh
so we foresee there that potentially
many application in this areas here for
example for UAV specifically like
lightweight cameras for surveying the
surrounding environment for collision
avoidance um and uh just for all of
other kind of essentially sing
application like depth detection as well
so uh yeah if there are any interest
from the audience in this areas I will
of course be more than happy to discuss
in more detail thank you Professor
thanks