We're going to move to our first
speaker. Um, so Dan, if you want to join
us. So I'm a somewhat lapsed computer
scientist. Uh, so it's with absolute
pleasure that I'd like to introduce uh
Dan Hulocker who's the um inaugural dean
of the sportsman's MIT sportsman college
of computing. um also found helpful and
found Cornelltech uh former C fintech
CTR I believe fellow of the ACM uh
distinguished publishing career produced
a book with Eric Schmidt and uh the late
Henry K. Late Henry Kissinger. Yeah. Um
and I'll pass over to D. Thanks so much.
Delightful to be here.
[Applause]
Terrific to have the opportunity to be
with you all this morning. And actually
one of the things I was noting uh as I
was listening to the introduction there
is uh how much the Schwarzman College of
Computing is changing MIT. Uh many of
the actually the vast majority of the
people you'll hear from today uh are
part of the college and affiliated with
the college. So um so I always start
with this slide because I think uh it
just
um we are constantly confused about what
artificial intelligence actually is.
It's a technology fundamentally it's a
technology and it does things that
technologies have done for a while plus
things that technologies have only
recently started to do with the advent
of AI. But what's different about modern
AI is that rather than being, you know,
carefully handcoded by uh humans, it's
trained to perform a task. Now, the way
it's trained is very carefully
handdeveloped by humans, but the the AI
itself is not. And this yields results
that are very humanlike. They are
results that are imprecise, that are
adaptive, that can have emergent
behaviors. And if you think of
conventional software, it's almost the
opposite of that, right? it's sort of
rigid and and and
inflexible. And machine learning is the
way that we train uh uh
AI. And almost every model that we have
today is some form of a deep neural
network generally with billions of
parameters. Um I think until recently we
were in kind of a world where more
parameters was better. Uh I'm not sure
we're completely in net world anymore.
We're getting smaller parameter models
often distilled from ones that had many
many more parameters uh that are very
very powerful in many settings and these
are learned just by adjusting a bunch of
weights to improve some measure of
performance. So at a high level there's
not much magic to that but there's a lot
of magic in how that's actually
done.
Um though there are three types of uh
machine learning that are just worth
kind of having in mind. So one is
supervised learning and that's where
some human generally somebody went
through and labeled a bunch of the data
like this is a picture of a car, this is
a picture of a dog, this is a picture of
a cat. I'll often make computer vision
type references because that's the area
in which I've worked the most as a as a
scholar. And supervised learning has
been around since the very beginning of
of of uh of AI techniques. And then
unsupervised learning you can think of
as sort of clustering. you've got a
bunch of data and you try to look at
sort of inherent properties of that data
to group things
together. What's much more recent is
self-supervised learning and this is
what's been driving most of the
advances. Uh so things like masked
autoenccoders
uh um uh of various forms uh
transformers are a type of masked
autoenccoder uh are self-supervised and
the idea of self-supervised learning is
that if you the data has any structure
to it which most data does you can
actually use properties of the data to
perform the supervision. So the simple
example that probably most of you have
seen is with transformers. If you're
trying to do something like predict the
next word, you can use the words
beforehand as the training for that next
word that's unknown. Uh and this is
really what's driven uh because it
allows you to train at a huge scale
compared to any other form of
supervision. And then once you have
these models, conventionally they were
used for some sort of classification
prediction type of task. So, you know,
you could look at an image like this,
run it through one of these networks
after it been trained and, you know, out
pops car. Uh, and the sort of magic of
the last, say, seven, eight years has
been you can just sort of essentially
turn this process around and you can
start with the label and this train
network and generate an output and then
the pace at which that has been
advancing over the last five years uh is
really uh nothing short of completely
stunning. Uh, and you know, there's
weird artifacts in these images, uh,
but, uh, but they're they're quite
interesting. I also wanted to touch on
AI agents here for a minute. Um, because
there's a lot of hype out there right
now about AI and, uh, you know, I think
maybe I'll comment on the hype cycle
more generally in a moment. Uh, but you
know, today's generative AI models at
least are not so great at being agents.
They're trained on lots of text and
images which makes them good at
producing surprise text and
images and producing is very producing
sort of output is very different from
doing things. So in fact I asked uh a
generative AI to just give me a
cartoon-like image of someone who can
talk big but can't get anything done.
And among human beings we're very aware
of those kinds of people. uh and that's
sort of what these current generative
eyes have been trained to do. They're
trained to talk big uh with text and
with images to produce those kinds of
outputs, but it's much harder to get
them to get things done. So when you
think about AI agents, it's actually
relatively challenging with today's
training techniques to get them to work
very reliably. Now, of course, this is a
place where there's a lot of research
and a lot of uh engineering innovation
going on. uh so that state of the world
may change quite a bit uh in the next
couple of years and one area that I'm
fairly familiar with is robotics uh
where there are a lot of really
interesting advances going on where
these systems are being trained with
actions not just observations right if
you look at texts that humans have
produced if you look at images that
people have taken uh that's just
observing things and actions uh would
look at causes and effects and looking
at the whole chain of action uh and in
robotics that kind of training is now
started to produce very very interesting
kinds of results. Um but it it's at
least currently can often be relatively
heavily supervised. So it's not scaling
at the same in the same way as uh as
these self-supervised techniques. Um,
but I I think that will also probably uh
not become a bottleneck soon because
simulated uh actions in robotics are
proving to actually be quite useful in
training and you can scale simulations a
lot more easily than you can scale
humans training
something.
So again, this is something I like to
make sure to always say when I'm talking
about AI. It's a distorted view of the
world. It's not inherently good or bad.
People like to put lots of value
judgments on AI's destroying the world,
AI saving the world. Uh we should be
really timid about using it. We should
be incredibly audacious about using it.
I think what we have to be is attentive
about using it because it is a different
view. And it's one that sometimes we can
confuse ourselves into thinking looks
like our view. And I'll sort of say a
few more things about that. So depending
how it's trained, it can reinforce
errors, it can reinforce human biases,
or it can make decisions better or
fairer. And you know, I think much of
what you see out there just takes one of
those two positions as if it's gospel
and doesn't even recognize the other.
And I pretty much dismiss anything that
just talks about how unfair AI is or how
much it just makes decisions better
because it's the balance between those
that's
important. It also depends on how it's
used. So there have been some very
interesting studies in the last few
years looking at using uh automatic
decision-making techniques in the
judicial system and in the health care
system and depending on how you use
those if the AI presents itself as an
expert it can actually make decisions
worse. If it presents itself as you know
sort of like you know in the medical
case sort of a consult then so it's
supposed to be thinking together with
the doctor it can actually make better
outcomes. So the usage is really
important.
Um so for many centuries now we've
understood the world in two ways and
that is changing. So we've we've had
reason which has been human and we've
had faith in the divine. And what's
happening with AI is it's starting to
exhibit some form of reason. Um and it's
really critical that we always remember
this is not human reason underscored
stop think because it's very easy we're
only you know we have you know millennia
of only interacting with human reason uh
and this is a different form of reason
and really it's adding a new way to
understanding the world and this raises
very interesting philosophical kinds of
questions and in fact um one of the
things that we've been doing in the
Schwarzman College of Computing and I'll
come to that uh in a couple of minutes
is really trying to bring together uh
you know philosophers and other
humanists and social scientists who are
interested in these sorts of questions
with computer scientists uh and and AI
researchers AI also one of the things
where you know it can go either way
is the degree of agency that we have as
humans. So um this is not unique to AI.
If you think about automation and
mechanization going on for a century and
a half at least same kind of thing if
you work on an assembly line there's not
a whole lot of autonomy there. You are
literally a cog in the system but you
know power tools give people incredible
amount of ability to do things compared
to having to do things by hand. This may
be more fundamental for AI uh than it is
for uh other um uh other kinds of of of
technologies because it's sort of about
how we think. So an example to make this
very clear is a driver of navigation
systems which all have some kind of
machine learning and prediction in them.
That's how they're telling you where to
go. They can be very empowering or
disempowering. So as an
individual, you're still making the
decisions. as a ride share driver all
this is starting to change now it's
really interesting but you know at the
beginning the ride share drivers had
freedom to go anywhere and that didn't
work very well um so then the ride
sharing software they had to follow the
route prescribed by the AI now they have
a little bit of flexibility um and but
they have to sort of supposedly get the
consent of the rider and sort of inform
the system that they're doing that and
this is this tradeoff between human a
you know presence and lack of human
agency when we're working with AI
systems. So I think that a really
important thing and this dates back to
this early history of of of of AI at MIT
and elsewhere. uh if you date if you
look at work by JCR Lick Lighter and
Lick was a faculty member at MIT when I
was a graduate student uh in the 1980s
uh still um but he had a a paper in 1960
called man computer symbiosis and in
that what the framing he had is what
we're really looking for is how can
machines and humans together produce
results that are better than either
machines alone or humans alone and that
is very different than the sort of
received view about AI and automation
today, which is more rooted in Turing's
view of the world, which is AI
replicating human behavior, his sort of
imitation game or what's sometimes known
as the Turing test. And now that we have
AI that does replicate human behavior
relatively well, it's kind of, you know,
the the proof point is really going to
be the next level of these things, which
is uh which is how machines and humans
together are better than either alone.
This is particularly important for a lot
of the reasons I mentioned before in
areas like healthcare, law, banking,
education, employment, uh, and so forth,
uh, where human judgment remains really
important. So, collaborative AI is a big
focus of things that, um, we're thinking
about at MIT.
So AI in society when you think about it
it's very hard to get away from sort of
science fiction you know things that are
trying to look out many many decades
ahead and in those the utopian or the
dystopian narrative are basically the
most interesting. They make the best
stories. It doesn't necessarily mean
that they're going to be the reality of
the future. And in fact, you know, two
things that I think are really important
to remember on this is first of all, new
technologies just seem like magic
initially that just like very hard to
really understand what they're doing in
any way. Whereas technologies that we
have experience with, everybody
understands them in some sense, right?
Like you know not to shove a fork in a
toaster. Um that you know if you do
you're probably going to have a problem
at least if it's plugged in and turned
on. uh and so it's not that they have to
understand you know deeply the you know
electricity and you know how it's
converted into heat in the toaster and
everything else but you have a broad
understanding of these technologies we
don't have that at all with
AI and you know the outcomes result from
really complicated sets of societal
decisions for which we do have to
develop these kinds of shared norms and
understandings. So this is something
that it's important for all of us to be
as educated about as we can. So now I
want to just for the last few minutes
here switch to at MIT and then uh get to
some questions. So the Schwarzman
College of Computing is focused not just
on AI but on computing more broadly. Uh
but AI is a big piece of it because uh
and and and actually really you know MIT
uh and uh Steve Schwarzman uh in in
making this gift to MIT really um
there's a lot of foresight of what we've
seen uh you know the gift was announced
in 2018. So the last seven years there's
been a huge advance in AI and it
positioned us very well for that era.
But the college is about the fact that
computing now plays a not only more
important but a different kind of role
than it used to. Computing used to be a
tool that could be broadly used but more
and more now it's how progress is
envisioned and realized. It's changing
how things are conceptualized in almost
every sector and almost every academic
discipline. So there's huge student and
employer demand for people trained in
computing, but it's not so much comput.
It's not so much programming and
software engineering and system
building. It's more and more formulating
and solving problems. It's this fact
that computing can really change
knowledge of the forefront of computing
can really change uh how you look at
problems. There are the critical broader
and and and and ethical and social
aspects which if you didn't believe it
was important before this AI explosion
clearly is research being transformed
and rapid changes in the core fields. So
the college has enabled MIT to expand
its faculty by about by by about 5% 50
new faculty positions. Half of those are
in electrical engineering and computer
science in sort of core CS and AI and
and part of EE uh and half are in
departments across MIT to do what we
call infusing computing with other
disciplines. This is the fact that we're
not just going to drive things outwards
from the core advances in computing but
in a in a bilingual birectional kind of
way. We've actually hired about 50
faculty since the college started in the
last five years. twothirds of those are
using those new faculty positions. The
other iss hiring who you would have done
anyway in that kind of time period. Uh
but it's not just these new kinds of
positions that are shared with
departments across MIT that are infusing
computing in other disciplines. So if
you look at these areas like algorithms
and society, computing and human
experience, AI and scientific discovery
etc.
about um half of the faculty that we've
hired both in these core positions in
EECS and in these shared positions in
departments across MIT uh are working in
ways that infuse computing in other
disciplines and these are sort of the
key focal areas where that's happening
and about twothirds of those are doing
AI. So you know the AI revolution is
definitely uh disproportionately
represented here. The college has a
broad educational program called the
common ground. The idea is to bring the
forefront of computing uh to students at
uh at all levels in ways that involve
multiple departments in the development
and offering of those classes. So it's
complimentary to core CS and AI that
might be offered in the ECS. It's an
enabler for new degrees and about a
thousand students a year are now
enrolling in these common ground
subjects. uh and there about two dozen
uh departments involved in teaching
them. This is an eye chart. I'm not
going to do much other than you know
it's here for the historical record. Uh
but these are some of the larger classes
uh in the common ground now. And for
those of you who you know know all the
MIT numbering schemes, you can see which
courses are involved in each of
these.
Um the college also has a very important
focus on social and ethical
responsibilities of computing through
something we call CIRC. uh that looks at
education, research, and engagement.
There's a student prize called the
envisioning the future of computing
prize. I encourage you to use your
favorite search engine uh you know to
find this that the student essays from
the last two years are nothing short of
breathtaking that won these prizes in
the last two years and we're right in
the middle of the current competition
that'll be announced next month. Um,
CIRC scholars are students from across
MIT uh, who work collaboratively on on
on projects. There's about 75 of them
per year in groups of sort of three to
six working on projects that look at
both the social and ethical issues and
the technological ones. Um we've been
producing a set of briefs around policy
issues uh on AI and uh the social and
ethical issues in computing are now also
an important part of what's going on in
the classroom. Uh there's a new common
ground subject that just got taught this
year. Uh um uh jointly between
philosophy uh and computer science. So I
want to just close with uh AI for
scientific discovery is a really
important focal area in what we're doing
in the college and at MIT. It's a huge
opportunity for transforming science. So
at MIT now in material science and
chemistry and chemical engineering and
climate and the environment there are uh
people doing work that's at the
forefront of AI. It's often published in
machine learning types of conferences
and venues but it's also published in
the discipline. So it has depth in both
arenas and that's very important for
driving things forward at the forefront
but it's also having another kind of
effect of bringing different areas of
science closer together as they start to
really think about developing these
common machine learning
tools. So biology is just an area I
wanted to highlight quickly. Uh you know
machine learning has transformed the
understanding of protein structure. It
was a Nobel Prize last year uh for uh
some of these um protein structure
algorithms uh um alpha fold um and and
Rosetta. But generative AI is already
starting to really revolutionize
understanding of proteins in a in a more
fundamental way with the development of
genomic language models. sort of the
language of the genome and uh this is
not just structure it's starting to
reveal things about functional and
regulatory kinds of issues um uh and
there's actually Alex Reeves who we just
hired uh at MIT between the Broad
Institute uh and EECS uh has a startup
that's that's uh developing uh these
kinds of models uh and they're really uh
extremely interesting at uncovering
things that we really haven't seen
before in ways that just structure of
things like Alphafold doesn't. So just
to finish I think you know building a
better AI world I'm neither the utopian
nor the dystopian I'm going to put the
responsibility on everyone in this room
and on society more broadly. I think
focusing on collaboration and
partnership is extremely important on AI
augmentation. Uh and I think we will
have new insights and discoveries uh
that um that will really advance
humankind. So, with that,
um, happy to go to questions. So, is
someone gonna ask the questions or
should try to read things off the
prompter? I should just read. Okay. So,
um, uh, if I was on the board of one of
the companies here, what would be my big
takeaway and advice for industry?
So my big takeaway and advice for
industry is
um you have to be doing
uh
experiments using AI to really
reinvision your
business. And I say experiments because
it's going to be very different
depending on the company, but I'm going
to assume for a moment it's a company
that doesn't, you know, is not sort of
at the forefront of a AI and and machine
learning. uh
and you know they basically need to be
skunk works kinds of activities. You
need a few technical people who know how
technology is used successfully in your
businesses today and you need a few
machine learning people who are really
sort of at the forefront of machine
learning and they're hard to find and
hire and you need to run some
experiments. You can also of course be
just sort of you know using today's AI
tools to improve your business the way
you would use any new technology to
improve your business. But the real
issue is machine learning is going to
reinvent many many areas of work and
you'll see that I think through many of
the talks and presentations today and if
you don't have some skunk works projects
doing that you're going to be left
behind. It'll be too late. the learning
out of those things will be very
important. Um and you know sometimes
when I say that people say oh well you
know it's expensive it's so then I'll
just I'll just use something that I find
one of the most useful things uh out
there um which is uh uh you know
something that I've learned through uh
engagement uh with Amazon where I'm on
the board. One of their sort of mantras
is double down on positive
surprise. Extremely useful. You can
start something very small. Doesn't have
to be expensive. But if you get a
positive surprise, double down. And the
thing about doubling down repeatedly is
then you end up with something big. But
at the beginning, it's small. And it's
also important to remember that at the
beginning, exponentials grow very
slowly. So it doesn't get big until
you've really had a bunch of positive
surprises. So you can start things
small. You need you need sort of, you
know, good KPIs for that to understand
what positive surprise would be.
All right, the next question is, what do
you think is the timing for AI to be
able to demonstrate quality levels of
reasoning?
Um, I think AI is already delivering
quality levels of reasoning, but it's
not delivering human reasoning, and I
don't think it ever will deliver human
reasoning. So one of the things that we
need to be prepared for at all levels of
expertise about AI is that these may do
very high quality
things that don't align with the way
humans would reason about something and
how are we going to use them? This is
why I'm very skeptical of uh AI uh sort
of standalone AI systems rather than
collaborative AI systems in any sort of
uh you know high impact domain like you
could pick health care as a as a classic
example but I'm a huge believer in those
systems in a way that they're
collaborative with doctors already
today. Um and I think in science which
of course is what I understand the best
uh the opportunity is unbelievable uh
because we've gotten to a stage now
where many scientific problems the
complexity of them and the you know at
the forefront of science the complexity
of them and the degree to which you need
to know things from different scientific
disciplines is really you know beyond or
stretching the ability of humans.
to conceptualize what's going on. And so
machine learning can gather that kind of
broader information and in collaboration
can do things that are uh really really
powerful. Um all right, I think I
probably have time for one more. Um if
you look at how AI is quickly advancing,
how do you see the way students learn
changing particularly at places like
MIT?
So I'm a I'm a firm believer that like
students should be using all of these
tools right now. And I think in MIT, you
know, that's the approach that most
faculty are taking. Uh universities are
collectives when it comes to academic
programs. There's no sort of top- down
dictation. Uh but I think most MIT
faculty are not doing what happened say
you know like I'm old so I remember when
programmable calculators first came out
and a bunch of faculty banned them
because they were cheating you should
use your slide rule. Um so uh I think
that's not the approach that's being
taken. But the big opportunity is again
uh not yet realized which
is how do we start to change the ways
that students think and solve problems
by collaborating with these tools? How
do we make sure that we test student
learning? How do we reframe our learning
outcomes given that tools like this, you
know, if you're just going to assign an
essay, you have no idea who really wrote
the essay. Although I can tell you the
AIS essay is still not so great. Uh but
but you don't really know but you never
knew, right? Students could have been
hiring somebody to write their papers
for them. So it's not really that
different. But this is going to amplify
this issue of how are we framing learn
learning outcomes? How are we framing
learning outcomes for a world where
students need to collaborate effectively
with AI? And then how are we judging
those learning outcomes. So thank you
all for the opportunity to speak with
you this morning. I'm going to do my
best to stay on schedule here. uh and
hand things over. So, thank you
[Applause]