so go ahead and open up Jupiter notebook
and we'll get started working with
streams what's very different from this
topic and many other topics we'll have
is that the introduction to the topic
will also be the unlocking video for the
topic you've certainly done enough with
representation in topic 2 representation
that you deserve to have some way of
representing music to start so we can go
ahead and from music 21 import stream
the stream
module you're also going to get a second
unlock now and that is from music 21
import Corpus and Corpus is a collection
of pieces that you've either created
yourself or we'll be using a collection
of pieces that come with music 21 so the
Corpus uh the Corpus module has one
method that we'll use a lot and that's
parse and so you load something from the
dis you uh can look online in the music
21 users guide to see the list of pieces
that come together come with the music
21 Corpus but uh we happen to know one
pretty well from our last look and
that's Bach bwv 66 6.6 and we'll call
that Bach
score second n we'll just call it bach
bach equals BW
66.6 and we see what Bach is we see hey
it's a type of stream called a score uh
what we'll find out is that the music 21
basic uh way of representing music
starts usually with a score there are
some things bigger than score called
Opus and stuff like that but usually
you're going to start with score
and like any music 21 object you can
show
it so we can show the entire score it
usually takes a little bit longer the
first time but then it comes up and we
can see it has four parts soprano Alto
tenor base it's in 44 abbreviated as
common time it begins with a pickup
that's always going to be hard and uh
one of the things we'll see is that
though music 21 will call this measure 0
1 2 and so on uh your notation software
such as Muse mcore which is what I'm
using to automatically generate this
might not know how to work with um
pickup measures as generated from music
21 we're generating automatically to
music XML and then loading that into uh
Muse score and then generating a a PNG
file and putting it back into jupyter
notebook lots happening on the the fly
when we say bo. show in any case for
some reason the measure numbers don't
translate so watch out for this music 21
thinks of this as measure three and me
score thinks so is measure four so
anyhow we have four parts pretty short
score all fits over here and I've
already asked you to think about what
the key is What are some interesting
weird moments in various parts and so on
um we can also show this as a m
file though the sound's not nearly as
good as the recording we listen
to so that's kind of useful if I made my
screen bigger than uh then the thing
looks pretty right
but so we have a score and a a score is
a type of stream and a stream is a type
of container and so it works kind of
like a list you can see exactly what is
in the score and we can see that there's
a metadata object and then four part
objects and something called the staff
group and that kind of makes it so that
uh all the parts look right together so
within this we can get the soprano part
by getting the second element from it
which we can call that P0 for the first
first part
because we can get that as the first
thing and we can see that P0 is another
type of stream called a part so parts
are contained within scores think about
whether this is time wise or
partwise well it has part so it's
partwise so we can also take this and
show this particular
part and I reset for a second so it
takes a little bit longer there we go
just one part going there and we can see
everything that is in part zero since
I've said that this is a part-wise
format think about what you would expect
to see
next okay have you thought about
it that's right it's mostly a bunch of
measures there's an instrument object
that says it's a soprano instrument but
then there's uh just 10 measures measure
zero is numbered that way because it's a
pickup measure and so on so we can get
the pickup measure we'll call it
pickup and what do we want to do it's
the second element in there so we get
one right and we can just show the
pickup that's not too exciting let's get
the first real
measure yep great right and we can see
that
M1 is also a stream it's a measure
object and it reports that its number is
one yep and we can see and has something
called an
offset and as we said in music 21 we
measure things in quarter lengths for
the most part and so measure one begins
one quarter note from the beginning of
the piece itself and we we look again at
this part yeah you can see there's
coordin note 0 coordin note 0.5 cordin
note one so measure two begins
where right at offset five and then 9 13
in this particular score they're all off
by four great so let's see what's inside
measure
one and here we have the notes finally
there could be if there were multiple
voices in the Stream there could be
voices at this point but there aren't
this is just a single
part so now that you can see these
elements of a stream let me show one
other important thing that you can do
you've done this show uh which by
default puts it out as music XML when
you're putting it in a script or in the
jupit notebook it puts it out as music
XML um opens up Muse score if you have
it turns it into a PNG and puts it right
back but there's another thing you can
do you can show it as a text file and
that shows you not only what elements
are inside the measure but also what
their offsets are so every element every
music 21 object every note every clef
has a an
offset within its current stream within
its current container and it also has a
duration and in this case each of them
is quarter notes their durations are
1.0 I forgot when I was making this
video first there's something really
important here notice that this first
note has an offset of zero but it's not
the first note in the piece it's the
second or third note in the piece but at
the second quarter note so why is it
offset not one well it turns out all of
the offsets are measured from the start
of the container so this is a measure
that begins at offset one one and
therefore its first note is at offset
zero within the container so if you're
going to figure out what the offset of a
particular element is within the piece
as a whole you're going to need to add
up all of the offsets of previous
containers back to previous
point so this is how you can load up a
score that already exists and get to
particular notes so in fact let's get
that a say zero and we can see that a is
a note and we can get its full name and
all the other things that we worked with
before
pitch
duration duration.
type and so on so this is how you can
load a pre-existing stream from a music
XML file like bwv 66.6 or from a midi
file or from an ABC file or any of a
number of music representation formats
that music 21 supports but now let's go
the opposite way let's create and build
up our own stream so we'll Build It Up
from
scratch let's import notes which have
already been
unlocked and let's create a note
when we show this note music 21's
actually doing something for us it's
creating a whole set of streams around
it for us but we can do it our own way
so let's create a voice which is a type
of
stream and we
will insert that note at position zero
oops we will insert that note at
position Z into the stream You' only
think that working with music 21 for 15
years and having created it I'd remember
what goes first the offset or the
element but I size forget great um we'll
unlock
another module for you right
now unlock the meter module yay
unlocking and we'll create a meter and a
time signature of
14 we kind of see that T like this as
things like that now let's create a
measure for
it and we will insert at the beginning
of the measure the time signature and
also insert at the beginning of the
measure the voice that contains the
note we can put more than one thing at
the beginning because time signatures
don't have any
duration now we can create a part
and we can insert the part at the
beginning the measure at the beginning
of the part or we can put the measure at
the end of the part and since there's
nothing in the part right now A pend is
will be the same as inserting a zero but
you don't have to remember how many
things are in there yet now we'll create
a
score and we'll put the part at the
beginning of the score one of the
mistakes that people make with music 21
quite often is that they get so used to
appending things that they'll append the
part to the score which the first part
that's fine but then they'll append the
second part to the score and if you
think about it Parts don't follow each
other they're all at position zero so
you want to make sure to always insert
Parts at position zero now we have a
score that looks basically the same as
when we created the n
note if we modify some parts of the um
of the original note objects something
we can see that the score will be
updated as we
do
now that doesn't match the time
signature because we explicitly put a
time signature in there so it doesn't
create one for us so let's
create a rest
and then in that voice let's insert at
0.5 now let's let's make it easier
append the rest to there and
now show all
this if we do a show of text on the
score we can see that it includes the
part the measure the time signature the
voice and then the note and the rest
well that's enough for streams for today
thanks for paying attention