the MIT energy initiative presents three
questions how are cities managing
record- setting temperatures professor
of urban and environmental planning
David Sue explains what Municipal
governments are doing as climate change
accelerates written by Peter desus for
MIT
news July 2023 was the hottest month
globally since humans began keeping
records people all over the US
experienced punishingly high
temperatures this summer in Phoenix
there were a record setting 31
consecutive days with a high temperature
of 110° f or more July was the hottest
month on record in Miami a scan of high
temperatures around the country often
yielded some startlingly high numbers
Dallas 110° F Reno 108° F Salt Lake City
106° F Portland 105° F climate change is
a global and National crisis that cannot
be solved by City governments alone but
cities suffering from it can try to
enact new policies reducing emissions
and adapting its effects mit's David Sue
an associate professor of urban
environmental planning is an expert on
Metropolitan and Regional climate policy
in one 2017 paper Sue and some
colleagues estimated how 11 major US
cities could best reduce their carbon
dioxide emissions their energy efficient
home construction and retrofitting
improvements in vehicle gas mileage more
housing density robust transit systems
and more as we near the end of this
historically hot summer MIT news talked
to Sue about what cities are now doing
in response to record Heat and the
possibilities for new policy measures
question we've had record setting
temperatures in many cities across the
US this summer dealing with climate
change certainly isn't just the
responsibility of those cities but what
have they been doing to make a
difference to the extent they can answer
I think this is a very top of- mind
question because even 10 or 15 years ago
we talked about adapting to a changed
climate future which seemed further off
but literally every week this summer we
can refer to dramatic things that are
already happening clearly linked to
climate change and are going to get
worse we had Wildfire smoke in the
Northeast and throughout the Eastern
Seaboard in June this tragic wildfire in
Hawaii that led to more deaths than any
other wild in the US plus record high
temperatures a lot of city leaders face
climate challenges they thought were
maybe 20 or 30 years in the future and
didn't expect to see happen with this
severity and intensity one thing you're
seeing is changes in governance a lot of
cities have recently appointed a chief
heat officer Miami and Phoenix have them
now and this is someone responsible for
coordinating response to heat waves
which turn out to be one of the biggest
Killers among climatological effects
there is an increasing real ization not
only among local governments but
insurance companies and the building
industry that flooding is going to
affect many places we have already seen
flooding in the Seaport area in Boston
the most recently built part of our city
in some sense just the realization among
local governments insurers building
owners and residents that some risks are
here and now already is changing how
people think about those risks question
to what extent does a city being active
about climate change at least signal to
everyone at the state or national level
that we have to do more at the same time
some states are reacting against cities
that are trying to Institute climate
initiatives and trying to prevent clean
energy advances what is possible at this
point answer we have this very large
heterogeneous and polarized country and
we have differences between States and
within States in how they're approaching
climate change you've got some cities
trying to enact things like natural gas
banss or trying to limit greenhouse gas
emissions
with some state governments trying to
preempt them entirely I think cities
have a role in showing leadership but
one thing I harp on having worked in
city government myself is that sometimes
in cities we can be complacent while we
pride ourselves on being centers of
innovation and less per capita emissions
we're using less than rural areas and
you'll see people celebrating New York
City as the greenest in the world cities
are responsible for consumption that
produces a majority of emissions in most
countries if we're going to decarbonize
society we have to get to zero
altogether and that requires cities to
act much more aggressively there's not
only a pessimistic narrative with the
inflation reduction act which is rapidly
accelerating the production of renewable
energy you see many of those subsidies
going to build new Manufacturing in red
States there's a possibility people will
see there are plenty of better paying
less dangerous jobs in clean energy
people don't like monopolies wherever
they live so even places people consider
fairly conservative would like local
control of energy and that might mean
Greener jobs and lower prices yes there
is a doom scrolling Loop of thinking
polarization is insurmountable but I
feel surprisingly optimistic sometimes
large parts of the Midwest even in
places people think of as being more
conservative have chosen to build a lot
of wind energy partly because it's
profitable historically some farmers
were self-reliant and had wind power
before the electrical grid came even now
in some places where people don't want
to address climate change they're more
than happy to have wind power
question you've published work on which
cities can pursue which policies to
reduce emissions the most better housing
construction more Transit more fuel
efficient vehicles possibly higher
housing density and more the exact
recipe varies from place to place but
what are the common threads people can
think about answer it's important to
think about what the status quo is and
what we should be preparing for the
status quo simply doesn't serve large
parts of the population right now heat
risk flood flooding and wildfires all
disproportionately affect populations
that are already vulnerable if you're
elderly or lack access to Mobility
information or Warnings you probably
have a lower risk of surviving a
wildfire many people do not have
highquality housing and may be more
exposed to heat or smoke we know the
climate has already changed and is going
to change more but we have failed to
prepare for foreseeable changes that are
already here lots of things that are
climate related but not only about
climate change like affordable housing
Transportation energy access for
everyone so they can have services like
cooking and the internet those are
things that we can change going forward
the hopeful message is cities are always
changing and being built so we should
make them better the Urgent messages we
shouldn't accept the status quo