Um, my name is Dr. Phil Button. Um, I'm
going to introduce the panel here.
Before I do so, uh, while the chairs are
being set up, I'm just going to give you
some basic slides. Um, the way they
describe the MIT education is drinking
from the fire hose, which means lots of
stuff coming at you. So, I'm going to
try to replicate that by cramming
several pieces into the next five
minutes that'll give you some sort of
background to help you with the um
understand the panelists that we have
assembled. And it really is an amazing
panel. So, I'm a former government
diplomat. I'm now a senior lecturer at
MIT, which is MIT code for not a
professor, but I work with a professor,
Dame Fiona Murray, who will be beaming
in later. Uh we we hope. But my job this
morning is to say something very quickly
on innovation and ecosystems. I'm at the
Sloan School of Management, which is
MIT's School of Management. And to the
extent that we have impact in the world,
it's because we are strapped to that
rocket ship that is the engineering and
science schools. And we're delighted to
be there with our with our friends. So,
uh this is me. I realize this is a
picture from before the pandemic, before
my hair went gray and the eyesight uh
faded. So sorry if anybody doesn't
recognize me. I keep that up there for
for vanity. Uh having been a diplomat, I
remain a diplomatic adviser. But as you
can tell from my accent, I am delighted
to be back here in Britain and so
pleased to have such senior MIT
leadership uh with us here. We actually
are having an alumni event of MIT
alumni. So these amazing students that
you were hearing about from Chancellor
Nobles, uh they go on and do amazing
things in the world. It's amazing how
many banks they seem to run here in the
city of London. uh they're able to turn
their engineering mathematics skills to
optimizing all kinds of portfolios. So
it's wonderful that Chancellor Nobles
will be here. U it's the 75th
anniversary of the AMIT alumni club and
it is we believe the largest alumni club
outside of the United States. Um some of
them are Brits but many of them from
other parts of the world. They just call
London this global gateway their home.
So I'm going to do two quick things.
Innovation then ecosystems. Prepare to
drink from the fire hose. Um the
previous MIT president launched
something called the MIT innovation
initiative. As good academics the first
thing they had to do was define their
terms. What do we mean by innovation?
And as chancellor Nobles and Gayatri
have said uh the MIT innovation
initiative signed off on the definition
of take the process of taking ideas from
inception to impact. It's a broad
definition of innovation. We at MIT
particularly like to take the technology
aspects of it, but we don't forget the
human side of it. Leading an
organization, changing the culture. Um
there's a whole series of ways to
innovate. It's not only for-profit
organizations, it's also for not
for-profit purposes. And it's amazing as
the chancellor was saying how motivated
our young students are about some of the
bigger issues in the world. We like to
think about innovation in a variety of
ways on a problem solution matrix. Uh a
lot of people think innovation is just
out at the far horizon and something
really really distant and far away from
their business as usual BAU in the
bottom left. Yes. And MIT is one of
those places on the planet that is doing
amazing things out at the far frontier.
One of my favorite cyberpunk quotes from
William Gibson is that the future is
already here. It's not evenly
distributed. MIT is one of those places
on the planet and London has some as
well where that far future is being
created. So that's what we like to call
big eye innovation. Quantum decryption,
encryption, sensing, fusion. People used
to put AI out there until it snuck up on
us and came over the the close horizon.
But there's another form of innovation
which is little eye innovation. You may
not be working on quantum computers
yourself, but there's still a need to
innovate even if it feels like more
modest 10% little eye innovation.
The interesting thing about little eye
innovation is that is more easily done
by large organizations like governments
and corporates. I'm not sure if you can
see the slides behind the chairs. Um but
there is a little government and a
little corporate down there. And I work
a lot with the public sector, we heard
from Ed, but also large organizations.
Uh they are different in some ways, but
they're also large organizations with
bureaucracy, with culture, with politics
that are really slow to adopt things. So
it turns out large organizations by
their nature are much better at little
eye innovation
which is why we turn to ecosystems.
We research this around the world
particularly through a reap program.
Every one of these pins is a team uh
with which we have worked around the
world. The eagle-eyed will have spotted
that yes we did back in the day work
with communist China and Putin's Russia
but closer to home we've also worked
with a wonderful team Wales. It's
wonderful to have Matt here from the
Welsh government. um we have worked with
this around the world and so what I'm
sharing with you is not only MIT
research but also stuff that we have
tried in the real world and it turns out
that it's quite a secular phenomenon
which is fancy professor speak that the
same process of technology innovation
applies whether you're in communist
China or disorganized Latin America
whether you're in Western Europe or
Southeast Asia because it's humans
adopting to tech adapting to technology
ology.
20 years ago, this American journalist
told us the world is flat, which came
shortly after the end of history, the
death of distance, peace in the Middle
East, and Russia as a democratic nation.
Um, one needs to be a little bit careful
of these books. This one is the most
upsetting uh because it promised that
innovation could happen anywhere. The
world is flat and yet we know from our
reap program that it doesn't happen
evenly across the planet.
Entrepreneurship may be evenly
distributed. uh we had an amazing team
from Lebanon hugely entrepreneurial but
for some reason they weren't getting the
same uh outcomes as say Silicon Valley
and this is where the ecosystem becomes
important now while Freriedman was
saying this in 2005 others like Richard
Florida looked saw through this and said
the world of innovation is not flat here
they're using patents as a proxy from 20
years ago um you know there's various
proxies for innovation but it's clear
the world is not flat and so this
inspires us to understand where are the
places on the planet that are good that
are spiky London Boston Silicon Valley
but also we work with lots of re lots of
regions around the world who are trying
to catch up with that who are trying to
understand how can we be included uh
we've had some amazing teams in reap
from West Africa they are no less
entrepreneurial um they are as out there
as they need to be as entrepreneurs but
they are failed by the ecosystem around
them and so understanding what they can
ask from the other stakeholders is
really matter really matters
So the MIT professors have come up with
a five model stakeholder approach and
apologies for anybody who's been through
the reap program who may be getting uh
flashbacks to this. Um the thing about
this MIT model is it goes beyond the
traditional triple helix. They used to
say that all you needed was big
university, big government, big
corporate and you would get innovation.
Now our friends from team Belgium in
reap have tested this to destruction. If
you could be the world's most innovative
place on the planet by having committee
meetings of big university, big
government, big corporate, Wonia would
be the most uh powerfully intellectually
place in the world. Uh it's not. And
this is why I love the MIT professors.
They've brought two other people to the
table whose voices need to be heard. The
entrepreneur put them at the top of the
table. It's hard to have an
entrepreneurial ecosystem without
entrepreneurs.
Um Fiona Murray designed this. So she
makes two points. One, it's a team. It's
very rarely a lone individual. You know,
the Zuckerberg in his hoodie is the
exception. Don't be distracted by the
American myths. It takes a team and this
one happens to be femaleled, but we do
know from research that boys can be
entrepreneurs, too. So, you are
included. The important thing is it is a
team. And we see the most most
impressive startups coming out of MIT
are the ones with teams. The other new
category here is risk capital and this
is important because we have a risk
capital provider uh on our panel. So the
MIT uh modern venture capital was
invented in uh 1946 in Boston uh a
variant when then went to Silicon
Valley. One of the reasons the MIT
professors don't use the term venture
capital uh they go back to the original
risk capital term was venture capital is
now so associated with Silicon Valley
that a lot of people think that it's the
10 years closed fund but actually for
the VCs to maintain their expensive
lifestyle they really need to get in and
out in three years uh they've got a lot
of gilelets to buy they've got Nappa
wine you know bless them um they've
ended up optimizing on digital asset
light, employee light, quick in and out,
blitz scale, hypers scale, lots of
American terms. Um, the MIT professors
prefer risk capital because it's
definitely putting money at risk like
venture capital in contrast to
traditional corporate banking or private
equity with its debt laden approach. Um,
but it could be more patient than
Silicon Valley venture capital. It turns
out you need people who are going to
invest in biotech which could take 10
years to produce something. Uh a lot of
the remediation for the climate crisis
is going to come not from a digital app.
It's actually going to come from doing
hard things, tough tech, hard tech, deep
tech. Uh great example is the pandemic.
Silicon Valley optimized for digital
gave us some fascinating digital dance
apps and it certainly keep us occupied.
It was the Boston area that actually
gave us a COVID vaccine. Turns out the
vaccines are quite useful in a pandemic.
Um, but somebody had to invest in that
and it looked like an overnight success
to those who weren't paying attention.
But Madena was actually 10 years of
working on voodoo science to get it
through to a vaccine technology. So
different ecosystems are going to be
good at different things. And the
world's best ecosystems are where the
top three, the apex three are involved
because they're much better at
transformative big eye innovation.
So bringing the two together as we work
with ecosystems around the world, we've
worked with London, uh, Northern
Ireland, Scotland, Wales, Leeds. Um, it
turns out that the best innovation
ecosystems are the ones where you have
all five stakeholders involved because
while the large organizations of
government and corporate are better at
the modest little eye innovation, you
need people who are going to be out
there thinking the big thoughts of the
big eye. And from Chancellor Nobles,
you'll have got a sense of our students
who just don't seem to sleep. They seem
to operate on ramen and and Red Bull.
They are constantly working on things.
They finish their amazing homework and
then they start up a company. I just
feel so inadequate. My student
experience about 100 years ago was not
spent starting up companies and working
on technologies unlike these kids. you
really do want to see if you can land an
MIT student because they are special and
they are part of what creates these
groundbreaking entrepreneurs.
So, we've written some of this up. My
boss Fiona Mario and I will be on later.
Uh so, if after going through this
rattling through here, you have any
further interest, please do read about
this because there's a role for people
in large corporations and the public
sector to tap into this innovation that
is out there in the ecosystem. It's a
source of competitive advantage. If you
don't do it, other companies will and
innovation really will decide winners
and losers. So, we encourage you to
engage those. But with that, I'd now
like to introduce our panel and I am
delighted that we have a representative
of Risk Capital, a representative from
the corporate sector and an
entrepreneur. So, with a round of
applause, please welcome Wed Alan and
Pderi to the stage.
Excellent. And if you could make my life
simple by Predereari, you come sit by
me. Alan, you're in the middle. Wid,
you're at the far end. I know I'm
supposed to sit down, but I'm highly
caffeinated and jet-lagged. So, I'm just
going to stand up here for a moment. Um,
what I'm going to do is first a
lightning round where you get to
introduce yourselves. Wid I will start
with you. One of the reasons I set out
the MIT approach is to understand that
we have put together a multistakeholder
panel here to get a sense of the
different people. But Wed, one of our
star MIT students, alums, a leader here
in the London area. Can you give us a
minute on yourself and Soho Capital?
>> So, uh, I'm one of the nerds that you've
mentioned before. Uh,
>> and life wasn't that exciting. I'll tell
you that much at MIT was a lot worse
than it sounds. Uh
but coming back to it so since my days
of MIT uh we've been through the
entrepreneurial journey uh worked in
banking consulting and over the last 15
20 years we've built up a business in
the UK market that started in the equity
world really risk capital and then
transitioned into sort of a structured
capital model that tries to sort of
balance the risk and rewards that are in
the market and also take advantage of
the inefficiencies that we see in this
market. Uh, a lot of what we do,
interestingly enough, we are focused on
downside protection on credit, but the
key thing that keeps all of our
companies alive is growth. And our focus
is on understanding what drives these
entrepreneurs, how do you get innovation
into them? Because eventually what we
see is the most entrepreneurial
companies really are able to create
breakout scenarios that we don't expect
and that's what's over is looking for.
>> Excellent. And before I turn to Alan, we
are going to come back to you when we
get into the uh substantive part. I'm
going to ask you about growth,
particularly here as we're at ILOP's
London Symposium. Given your
international experience, how is London
and and Britain doing? And and don't
hold back.
>> Alan, you're here representing the
corporate sector, the the acceptable
face of industry. Tell us about where.
>> It would appear so. Um yeah, Alan
Stewart. I'm the group head of
innovation at research at the Weir group
where I have now been for 21 years. We
are is an organization of 152 years uh
of age where we have innovated for all
of those years and to remain relevant to
the industries that we're in. In my 21
years we've been in power, we've been in
oil and gas and more recently we are
positioning ourselves as a mining
technology company. We really want to
play our part in making mining more
sustainable. What weird does from a a
product perspective is we are involved
in extraction and benification and
tailings management. So we make hard
capital equipment that consumes huge
amounts of energy and huge amounts of of
uh water in order to give us the the
commodities that we want for to drive
technology. I guess copper um rare earth
elements, iron ore, gold to to name but
a few.
>> Excellent. Well, thank you for that. I'm
so pleased that we have a corporate from
the hard sectors like mining. We at MIT
really do like our our deep tech and the
things that are going to matter in in
the future. With that, Praderi,
wonderful to have you here. you
represent all of entrepreneurs in the
world. Um tell us tell us about which
part of the world you're from and
MSpark.
>> Yeah. So um hi everyone. I'm the
managing director over at MSpark. So,
Menai Science Park um upon Anduly in
North Wales and uh I guess we're focused
on the complete reap model and bringing
all those actors together and enjoying
life uh I guess in what we call the
messy middle of all that where all that
interaction is and uh if we can get that
interaction going,
>> we can see some amazing things
happening. So, that's that's where we
enjoy ourselves really.
>> Excellent. Well, thank you for coming
and bringing a a contingent from North
Wales and the Welsh government just to
make sure there's no trouble here in
London. Uh, we appreciate the travel.
Um, so as promised, well, back to you.
We're here. Um, you take a hard-headed
perspective of the world. How is the
United Kingdom? How is London doing in
terms of its productivity and the way it
creates those growth companies out of
innovation ecosystems? I if you think
about
how this is break how it breaks down you
have the Gaussian curve in the middle
you have a distribution productive
company and that's always been a
question we've been trying to understand
is EK more productive less productive
and you know as somebody said you know
to every complex answer there's simple
clear solution that's always wrong uh
the answer here
is if you think about it what we have
when we hire somebody to do a study for
us and we end up having this calcium
curve in the middle Okay, we're less
productive than France because we employ
more people per unit of
>> you know that's bad news in this crowd
that we're worse than France.
>> But they have they made the trade-off of
capital versus people. So they have 7%
unemployment. We have 4%. That's the
difference really in that productivity.
But then something interesting happens
at the tail end of the curve. You get
super highly productive companies that
are there. I mean if you go back to
Haldane's 2011 paper, that is basically
what he identifies as super breakout
players. And that's really tells you
that actually is that the same
everywhere else? Is it just that we're
not seeing enough of those companies or
do they end up growing at a certain
stage and then navigating to the US and
basically continuing their growth there?
I don't haven't seen a lot of that
research there. Uh in our part which is
call it middle market less late stage
tech businesses uh you do see some
really interesting companies.
I I was at a business awards uh uh event
judging uh companies about two weeks
ago. Every one of those companies was
really really interesting.
>> I mean you found a gardening business
that's now making a 100 million of I
mean who would have thought right and
they're driving through innovation in
terms of hiring the people. So there is
innovation in this market but as a whole
nation the question is you're capped by
your GDP growth and the GDP in the UK is
not sexy right we're growing at a low
rate you're trying to extract value out
of what you have and what you find is
that the most innovative companies are
not necessarily creating new markets or
taking markets away from other things
you know from other players and that
becomes a more difficult thing to mash
uh when we're looking at the companies
And growth is an important part of it
because the way we say to our investors
is you know growth is the pulse of a
business. A business with no organic
growth doesn't have a pulse and that to
us is not an investable proposition.
>> But when we look at them we also look at
the measures and what we see is sort of
a bit of
tepidness in terms of willingness to
take risk. And I'm not sure if it's a
function of a risk capital market that
has basically said we're not going to
reward you for that much growth because
we don't believe that if you take that
risk you will get rewarded. Uh there's
another issue that we see that we have
companies in the UK and we have similar
companies in US servicing the same
clients but the US clients are willing
to pay five six percentage points of
margin more than the UK. So even if you
are innovating, can your clients in the
UK afford it? I mean the perception that
the US is a very competitive market. I
think it's got nothing on the UK. The UK
market because it's smaller. You have
very good companies. It's hyper
competitive. If you've ever dealt with
the procurement uh side of some of the
larger corporates, it's brutal. There's
little margin that they will let you
have to grow. And even if you provide
them with a value add service that may
win you the contract, but they're not
going to necessarily reward you with a
higher margin to go and innovate again
and add to it. So you have to take more
and more of that risk.
There's also the last element, right?
What we see is possibly this is due to
people like me who are buying these
companies out too early of a stage to
let them create enough wealth and value.
So we say sometimes glibly to our uh
CEOs like you know in in the UK a
manager will grow a business or an owner
will grow a business and sell it and buy
a house in the country in the US an
owner will grow his business and then go
and buy a country that's the difference
of ambition
excellent thank you for that uh yes so I
can tell an MIT speaker where you start
off with you know Gaussian graphs and
how dane's 2011 report and then by by
the end you're giving us this, you know,
UK GDP is not sexy and and the contrast
between the UK and and US. So, thank you
for getting us started. Turning now to
the large companies, how does it feel to
be in this hyper competitive market and
you're the head of innov group head of
innovation? So, how do you find working
with these companies and and keeping
their margins tight? I think the first
thing we recognized as a corporate was
we there's an ecosystem out there and
there's a startup economy out there that
will get us to the margins and the
growth that we want quicker. It probably
took us of those 152 years about 150 of
those years to realize that. Uh I think
we suffered very much from the and I
don't know if it's a British thing a
Scottish thing if it's not built here we
don't believe it's real. So there was a
real internal um governance that just of
of almost distrust. Um in the last two
years that's changed quite dramatically.
You know mining is an industry that's
going to be under great strain from a a
productivity perspective. The demand for
copper over the next 30 years is going
to be greater than it's been over the
last 3,000 years. So we're going to have
to mine more copper. And I think that
was the kind of penny drop moment for
sort of big corporates within my sector
was they they don't have the capital.
they don't have the risk appetite. They
don't um have the the the patience
perhaps to to do it themselves. And I
think that's where it actually creates
more opportunity. I think that there's
never been a lack of ingenuity,
entrepreneurship in the UK or or further
a field. It's been the pathway to impact
being critical for me and that's the
part that corporates have had to change
how we play instead of pushing the
supply chain to ek out that last 2% of
of margin. And you know, you you don't
sort of cut yourself to greatness on
that death spiral. You've got to have
the confidence to to invest. You can
derisk that investment through through
startups. You can
>> um afford to fail. It's we can afford to
fail through startups. Maybe sounds a
little bit harsh, but but the impact of
that failure and the culture of that
failure bring startups big back stronger
with um with better kind of confidence
and the lessons learned to to pick
themselves up and go again. So, so I'm
always been more of a glass half full
kind of guy, but I think corporates have
to forget the last sort of 150 years of
we are evolution and look at the pathway
that we believe we're on and also
recognize the value that you bring to
startups as well within that that
ecosystem where um it's difficult being
a startup. We've spoken to loads over
the the last two three years and I think
it's it's incumbent on us to create that
pathway to impact and really crude
language. you know, bolt their equipment
onto our equipment to make it better is
the low-risk pathway which is in a very
conservative industry which mining and
other large capital equipment industries
are.
>> Well, that that's wonderful and I look
forward when we come back to hearing
more about how you change that that
culture inside the corporation to mean
that you could get innovation from from
outside and one of the things I love
about the fact that you're in now in in
mining. This is not just about you know
and British Telecoms is known as being a
leader for leading leaning into
technology and working with startups but
it's also possible in really hard
sectors like like mining as well. It's
important. So we have with us a live
entrepreneur from the startup community.
Uh thank you for joining us. You never
know with the entrepreneur whether
they're going to make it to the panel.
Um Praderi clearly we are strong at
innovation and entrepreneurship.
Corporates are understanding the benefit
of tapping into your startups. How do
things work? uh look from your
perspective in in mspark the
entrepreneurial community and how is it
to easy to work with these types of
people? I guess just listening to the
panelists just now it's refreshing to
hear that because from our perspective
um there's a few gateways there Phil if
I'm totally honest with you it's
>> Alan it's refreshing to hear that you
you are looking for startups you are
engaging because I guess our story is
slightly different we're trying to open
those doors we're knocking doors we're
having those conversations
>> but we're seeing that lack of appetite
for risk we're seeing the cultural
barriers perhaps um although when you do
see the corporates, they really really
want to engage. Um maybe they just don't
know how.
>> What is it? They don't know how or maybe
they don't want to. I'm not quite sure
uh where it is. They definitely want to
innovate, but uh as you said at the
beginning, maybe Phil, there's a there's
a balance there that as they grow, they
get caught up in this business as usual.
>> It's incremental innovation. And if they
were to engage, I guess that's my call
uh this morning really uh for for the
corporates for the risk capital do
engage and even outside of London
there's interesting things that's
happening.
>> What believe it or not there's amazing
companies uh out there. So engage and um
I'm sure you'll be surprised but there
is a cultural barrier that we've seen
and that's that's our experience
unfortunately.
>> Sure. and a cultural baren. The fact
that you've come here from North Wales,
one of the things we discovered from
from Reap Team Wales and Reap Team
Scotland is there are entrepreneurial
people across this amazing United
Kingdom. And so it's not just in London
or the Golden Triangle. Sometimes the
startup with the technology you need
could be could be somewhere else. So
thank you for coming in. Um I wanted to
go back to Alan. It it sounds like the
corporate startup relationship is not
the easiest one. uh the MIT professors
designed the the pentacle with the
corporate and the startup sort of
opposed to each other because it's a
tricky relationship. How did this
ancient uh company of yours we're not
you you're not ancient we are. How did
your ancient company however compared to
the age of predi startup enterprises how
did it change its organization to be
able to work with startups? So first of
all I think the pentacle I wish I'd seen
that a few years ago I think we would
have been further onto our journey
because um we very much being engineers
being an engineering le organization we
learn through doing and we learn through
getting things wrong I think what
changed our mind was a couple of things
just recognizing the challenges that
we're going to face our industry
recognizing there's amalgam of of
technologies beyond just making product
bigger and making product smarter which
was again a zeitgeist of the time um and
And we we always knew that our culture
wasn't the most nimble or most agile,
but I think a lot of it came through
learning. I used to joke that by the
time we had raised an NDA to work with a
startup, they'd IPOed. You know, they
live through their life cycle. Um and
and we recognized through failure that
we had to address that. Um so 2020 2013
we set up the advanced research center
which was while it's part of the
corporate function it has its own
ecosystem it own culture its own
environment we purposefully are based at
a university site so we are we have
those horrible expression knowledge
accidents we're walking through the
technology innovation center and there's
a quantum uh there's a quantum
conference going on or there there's
just something that sparks that
enthusiasm also through recruitment we
we didn't have 21 years and kind of
institutionalized. We recognized we
needed a mix of both. We needed people
that understood our industry. They
understood our products, but you also
had to merge that with outside in views.
Um, but it was that kind of people and
culture piece were critical. And also
think senior leadership. You know, we've
got very uh stable executive who I
report into our chief strategy and
sustainability officer. Um, we
understood the importance of technology
to our strategy, but we also understood
how much energy, water, etc. was going
to be consumed by mining over the the
coming years and and kind of holding the
mirror up and being quite honest that
you don't have that capability yourself.
Yes, we employed some consultants. Yes,
we took views from from other
industries. But part of it was was
failing, realizing you need to change
and get in the right people in the right
place and empowering them, letting us
feel not that we're going to fail, but
we can get things wrong. We'll allow our
startups to fail. But be quite
reflective.
>> Yeah.
>> But it's I stress we're we're two years
into that journey. We're
>> we've got a few battle scars for the 150
before.
>> Well, first of all, and before I turn
back to Perry, first of all,
congratulations on making that change
from our work with large organizations,
which is the focus of our book. It's
really hard to show that leadership that
you need to work with ideas that are not
just invented inside your own
organization. And that's true for uh
for-profit organizations. It's true for
government organizations. But the fact
you're willing to work with startups
predi from your experience in the
startup community I've not heard many
corporates willing to talk this way how
would you encourage corporates to engage
with the great entrepreneurs you have
>> well engage with the ecosystem isn't it
and I'd like to think if you're engaging
with an ecosystem you you'll get to know
the startups um you'll get to know
government you'll get to know
universities and it sounds like you've
got that within a room or within a
building. though that's a that's an
amazing thing to hear and maybe the
other the message I'm I'm hearing from
uh Alan over here is that um that risk
appetite
>> failure is expected was on your slide
earlier on and um there's absolutely
nothing wrong with that is there but
>> yeah some sometimes that risk appetite
isn't there that expectation or failure
isn't there so
>> there's a cultural shift that we need to
to see uh I guess towards that sort of
risk appetite but um engaging is crucial
and uh the reap model gives you all the
ingredients that you need and as science
parks innovation ecosystems you can
easily access that it's all there for
you and that's our job really in making
that as accessible as possible
>> so if we're not doing that we're not
doing it correctly
>> well brilliant thank you for that and
I'm going to turn to wedd as we're
talking about risk and he's Mr. risk
capital can ask him about funding these
sorts of uh engagements. But just to
pick up on what the corporate and the
entrepreneur were saying here, when we
look at the places around the planet
that have strong innovation ecosystems
and good innovation leads to strong
economies which leads to good social and
health and environmental outcomes, it's
often when these different stakeholders
find a way to talk to each other despite
the different timelines. I love the
example of the corporate NDA and the
startup has already IPOed you know just
on completely different clock speeds. Uh
talking of which there is the pigeon is
it pigeon app in which you can put
question and so this is going to be
cropping up so please put in your
questions and then you get to upvote
them and apparently the people in the
booth will give us those questions so we
can see what's out there but will lead
turning to you now on the risk side
you're obviously you like to invest in
risk where there's going to be reward um
do you see many examples of companies
that are coming through that have found
a way to fund themselves through
corporate engagements is that ever of
interest to you on the risk capital
providing side
>> actually we did uh one of our best
investment came out of Sainsbury I mean
you see some of the stuff happening
where Sainsbury try to make an
investment to solve an internal problem
I mean if you as I'm listening to the
panel it raises the interesting question
about what's driving that behavior why
do we see a lack of risk appetite what
is the and you've got to go back to as
we were talking about it with Michael
earlier on it's human behavior right and
I would say you know it's either greed
or fear In the case of wear, I would
argue that they got to a point that fear
overcame and if they weren't going to do
something, they could see the downward
trend and therefore they were forced
into doing something. Engaging with a
startup is going to come within that
dynamic. Are we doing it because we h
are missing a big hole and we need to
basically plug it or it's great it's
going to help us grow. The problem the
UK is a bit you know like academia at
this stage you know lots of politics
because there's so little to fight for.
you know, it's the growth isn't there.
So, basically, people are just eating
off of each other. Uh, if you're doing
that and you're in a corporate and
you're saying, I'm going to make an
investment into a startup, partner with
an investment startup, what is my net
gain? If the growth isn't there, then to
be honest, the cost and the riskreward
doesn't really stack up, which is why a
lot of the problem. However, if I could
see that partnering with a startup is
going to give me significant advantage
over someone else and I can take market
share that becomes the greed you want to
play with. I don't see a lot of fear in
a lot of the corporates in terms of not
doing anything yet. I think that is
beginning to change with AI. They are
going to have to do certain things
>> uh as we pass through the hype cycle and
it becomes real. There's going to be new
adoption. The question is whether the
returns on that investments are going to
be high or it's just going to be
replacement of existing capex. On the
upside, as long as you don't have excess
economic growth, it's very hard to
justify a lot of that piling into
innovation because if you do,
so what versus you just generate cash.
So for us when we look at our companies
and we engage with them and we went
through a session a couple of days ago
where even if you drive the innovation
the answer from the companies to us
great we have a lot of innovation we can
think about our consu our customers will
just not pay us more they'll give us a
contract but they will not pay us more
for the value ad that I think is a major
issue in terms of the incentives of
people to make the choices to make that
choice to innovate to partner with
startups because it's got to be worth it
Mhm.
>> If there's not enough there to be taken,
why would it be worth it? And this is
something we struggled with all day.
>> Excellent. Thank you for that. And uh
you've pivot us pivoted us nicely to AI,
which I'm going to come through the
panel asking how AI is affecting your
world. But it just strikes me that as an
important message there both for the
corporates and the startups to have that
risk mentality of a risk capital um
provider thinking about, you know, what
risks can you take? But maybe I could
just ask you one meta question about the
UK. Wid, what do you think is holding us
back from achieving some of that growth
and productivity that we could um if if
we had any policy people here just a
quick remark about the thing they should
do and then we'll come through all three
of you.
>> AI 39% of the GDP goes to tax
>> compared 39% okay
>> compared to the US which is I think at
federal levels 25 with another maybe 4%
at states. So the differential just to
give you a number if you look at that
10% differential in taxation and map it
out to the US that's an extra $2.6
trillion that of free spend that the US
has to spend. Okay,
>> that's the whole size of the UK economy
just on the tax differential. Uh there's
a lot of it when you squeeze that much
of the companies like national
insurance. So I'm not basically ranting
about taxation but the national debt
level is so high right now everybody's
concerned. constraints on it. So these
are I think the macro factors here are
really impacting the mindset and the
innovation. The taxation levels are not
leaving enough disposable income in
people's hands to basically drive that
consumer economy that you need. At the
company level, you know, you're finally
driving that human capital versus
physical capital replacement because now
it's too expensive to h to have people.
So you have this low fire, low higher
economy and people are going to have to
start shifting to it. So I do think this
the the financial situation of the UK
economy is now becoming a real real
stumbling block for actually growth.
>> Okay. Well, thank you for that. And the
reason I've come over here is not to be
weird, but I just realized but they put
the questions on either side and I can't
see them standing at the front. Um so
from your lips to any ears in number 11
Downing Street. Um but now AI will you
like to say something on AI or should we
have one of the other two how is AI
changing your world?
um early days, isn't it? I think yeah
and we've got to be really careful
around this. So there's a
>> we've had number of startups come
through looking at AI um and the sectors
perhaps that they've been looking at um
back to risk again maybe looking at our
government organizations in terms of
adoption.
uh maybe maybe there's concern there
obviously there's there's data there's u
ethics issues to tackle as well and
maybe what we have is uh from an
entrepreneurial perspective um companies
wanting to push companies wanted to to
get ahead but maybe there's from a
corporate government perspective it's
more of a cautious approach and rightly
so so there's there's a need I guess
that we see in MSPAC if you look at
those state stakeholders we need to get
the skills right we need to think about
the ethical issues the data issues
But we've also got this massive push
from the startups who really want to get
ahead and push their
balance there somewhere.
>> Yeah. Well, thank goodness for those
startups being at the cutting edge
trying these tools out in the world of
corporate and then I'll probably go to
the top question as it's got seven
votes. Uh Alan, so in the world of the
corporates, AI mining, how's it looking
to you? Yeah, I think AI right now is
it's a little bit of it's everywhere as
and it's talked about everywhere and I
think the hype cycle is a good way to
good place for it right now. If I look
at it in our application of AI without
looking at I'll name a couple of
specifics I'm personally excited about
is it's an efficiency tool. It's people
coming back from holiday and running
co-pilot over their inbox to work out
what emails they need to get. It's my
daughter putting filters on photographs
of herself and consuming gigawatts of
energy to do so through data centers.
So, so I think
>> must be a proud father.
>> So, I didn't say she was 21, did I? No,
she's not. She's 14. Um, but I think
it's got to find the application. It's
for us in engineering and corporate,
it's going to be a tool. Where I'm more
excited about it is things the work we
are doing around our generative AI. It's
we're looking at how do we design
products using generative AI. How do we
stop designing straight lines, curves,
and holes and start looking at how
products can meet fit, form, and
function if the human brain isn't
constraining it? So I think that's quite
exciting from an engineering perspective
but we've got a long way to go said
about you know where does it sit
ethically morally um it opens up more
questions than answers right now but
it's not going to go away so it's we
have to look at how we're going to apply
it how we're going to govern it and how
we drive value and I don't mean value
specifically from an ROI it can't the
end state can't be humans need not apply
it's got to be a tool that helps the the
the the advancement of from a we
perspective our products our value
offering to customer. It's got to make
the way we meet the requirements uh of
our customers and the resource
requirements of the world to decarbonize
have got to be accelerated and aided by
but it's got to be done. Um it's got to
be a partnership for me, but I'm I'm not
quite sure how we get there yet.
>> Okay, excellent. I'm going to take the
top question and I'll see which one of
you would like to reply. Um I'm here on
standing in for Fiona Murray who's going
to join us by video later today. And one
of the things that she has done as a
professor of entrepreneurship is study
the inequities that seem to have come
about within the world um and
particularly a lot of the entrepreneurs
as we see at MIT the 50% of the
undergraduate student body is that is
female is no less entrepreneurial and
yet there's something about the pipeline
not so many of them go on to PhDs not so
many of them get onto patents Fiona
studied venture capitalists one of the
reasons we don't encourage you to be
Silicon Valley venture capitalist
boys because they are pretty much all
boys is with a great uncertainty they
tend to fund other boys and so thinking
through how do we uh tackle this
pipeline issues and deal with the the
entre uh the entrepreneurs who are
female. Oh look they put it up as a big
question so this we'll no doubt be
coming back to this several times uh
during the day but who would like to
talk about female entrepreneurs and what
we can do to increase the diversity
within the sector. I'll pick for I'll be
trouble if I don't because I've with
three uh fellow colleagues and I'm aware
of the diversity on the panel as well
today. Um so I was pleased to see the
previous panel as well but yeah we got
>> three white men on the stage. Uh so it's
it's not great on the panel but uh
>> we've tried to balance it over the
course of the day. So I imagine I'm
Fiona.
>> No absolutely
>> but what can we do about it and and what
does it look like at Mana Science Park I
guess is the question. U we've been
looking at this quite hard over the the
recent years. we've been open. We've had
a gender pay gap of around 16% on on the
site and I'm pleased to report that
we've closed it. It's down to 43 pounds.
Uh so we are uh we are uh the pay gap
has reduced. Um it's it's taken time and
what we've seen as a trend over the
years. It has closed and it's it's got
to the right place now. But what can we
do proactively? I guess uh some of the
things we do is in outreach work. We do
go into uh schools. We deliver STEM
training and so forth and we take role
models with us into those sessions and
role models have been has been proven to
be one of the most effective ways of
inspiring next.
>> So um and those role models by the way
are not just STEM engineers um but
business people entrepreneurs as well.
So we need to plant those
entrepreneurial seeds not just for the
boys but for the girls as well and I
think role models are crucial for that.
>> Great very well put. Did somebody else
want to come in on that one? I mean I
think on our side again our organization
doesn't have a huge amount of diversity.
Uh it's something we're working on and
we see it I mean we do back female
entrepreneurs. We don't see enough of
them at our stage. These are well
established businesses. So they've been
around for 10 years. They're grown etc.
Uh but we don't see enough of them
coming our way. What we see is again
typically male-dominated companies
coming through typically same color and
typically very much like what you see in
typical UK corporates. So that's the
environment we operate into. Do we think
we're missing something? 100%. Uh it
it's you do get into the group think
single model uh approach to things and
that's not a healthy place to be. It was
like also said you put a bunch of white
guys in a room nothing good comes out of
it.
words to live by.
>> Alan, did you want to weigh in on this
one or the next one?
>> I think only one thing to add and if I
take STEM and engineering as a proxy for
entrepreneurship, it actually from my
opinion, it starts at school. I think it
goes right back to to primary school.
Um, you know, primary engineering is a
great uh a great institution to just
encourage that inclusion and diversity.
Unfortunately, I think if we look at the
makeup of the panel, some some of it's
just got to it's got to be grandfathered
out. You know, the changes have to start
at at ground level. We've all got a part
to play, but I think it'll only ever be
truly achieved when it's my daughter's
generation and the generation come
through who have have never had the same
constraints and never had the sort of
same um sort of bifurcation triation.
Oh, you're a boy, you that this is a
better career for you, that you're a
girl is a better career for you. We just
need to eradicate all of that and and
for me it starts primary school,
secondary school, secondary education.
>> Thank you for saying that. We're going
to turn to the next question which has
has nine votes. But just one point if
Fiona were here uh I I think she would
say there's definitely sort of the
long-term change that needs to come
through through the pipeline and we have
responsibilities as leaders through that
pipeline but there are also things that
you can choose to do after today as
Praderi was saying the role models
really matter matter. Fiona's got some
great social science. When you send out
to the MIT boys, you know, come be an
entrepreneur, they don't care whether
it's male or female. If you send out the
female CEO of some amazing MIT startups,
it sends the message. So, there are
little things you can go to do. And I
think it's not only the right thing to
do, but to the extent that we've got a
competitiveness uh productivity problem
to be holding back the talented half of
our society that is female is not good
for our competitive advantage either as
a nation uh or as individual for-p
profofit companies. Turning to those
government funding and the life cycle of
existence, um what do you think's wrong
about the escape velocity? I know
there's lots of government money
provided in the UK, UK research,
innovation, innovate UK. Maybe that's
where the taxes are going. I don't know.
Um, who would like to speak to that
question? Perhaps Predi.
>> Go on, why not? Um, there's a place for
it, isn't there? Um, especially maybe
seeding some of the early high-risk um
projects or or startups or ideas. And
maybe there's an opportunity as well
thinking about the corporates risk
appetite. Maybe there's there's
partnerships that we're not getting
right in into these sort of funding
streets and you think about government
corporate partnerships. They're few and
far between uh in this space. So maybe
there's a real opportunity there. But I
think there is role for government
funding uh in in terms of this um life
cycle. But we do need to move away from
that grand culture and we do need to
move towards uh well markets problems
solutions that and if there's a market
for it should turn to to kind of risk
capital then um so um seeding the ideas
there's something else as well from a
Welsh perspective that we need to see
more of this innovation funding um
coming into Wales. So that's one of our
objectives. So it does tend to get get
spent in the golden triangle. So, are
big advocates of of seeing uh all that
money or part of that money being spent
in in Wales and it's really frustrating
for our startup community by the way to
go through the hoops to apply for these
funding that you're in highly
competitive rounds to get a knock back
and you get another knock back. Yeah.
>> And by the third one, do you know what?
I'm just going to carry on with my thing
over here. So, um there's resilience
there for them as well and it gets
difficult. So I think the funders need
to be mindful of that and uh look to to
level up perhaps sure
>> on the R&D funding.
>> Can on that point
>> you want to come in on that? Yeah, that
one that one bothers me because
effectively if you look at the US
economy, if it wasn't for NIH money at
what 25 billion a year, 30 billion a
year, DARPA,
AE, whatever version of it, you want to
get the various SBIC funds that are
there. I would argue that you're seeing
plus the subsidies that go to tech
company. I would say that you're seeing
in the US probably and you guys have
better estimates Phil of 100 billion to
150 billion of actually ignore the
universities MIT guess what two billion
a year from the government for uh
research the amount
>> chancellor's nodding to the numbers that
sounds good
>> so you have the amount of money that is
put into very basic research into the US
by the government is very high argument
in the UK is not that we shouldn't be
doing government funding that we're not
thinking big enough about government
funding into early stage deep science
that is speculative i.e. ARPA DARPA this
is really what's going to create an
ecosystem that's going to fund
universities national labs for example
we have a few on the science side the
nuclear we need more because you're
never going to develop the nuclear
ecosystem here without it that
collaboration as you said between
government corporates and with risk
capital it's got unfortunately it's got
to start with very directed funding by
the government to take those risks that
are going to create the things like the
Francis Kirk institute like the
innovations you found in Oxford. I just
think the UK is big thinking big enough
about this thing and we don't have the
willingness to actually see a failure of
a setup. You want to see 50% failure.
You want to see 75% failure because the
25% that remain will be amazing but we
just can't see that appetite here.
>> That's really interesting. Did you want
to come in on that Andrew?
>> I just going to add one thing. So, so we
work with on lower TRL research through
government funded projects and and well
it's a bit awkward and slow at the front
end. We get there in the end. I think
the consortia works well. I think where
I struggle a little bit is with some of
the catapult centers in the UK where
they almost seem to be competing against
each other. So I think we're probably
being inefficient with the capital that
the government put in because they're
almost run like standard standalone
business units. So if we talk to AMRL
and we talk to the National Composite
Center, both will claim to have
expertise in XYZ and you think, "No, no,
I want to work for the best of our
company and the best of industry with
with the best that's out there. So take
that out there, put it there and make
that center of excellence." And I don't
know if that's the way they're they're
managed internally, how their local KPIs
run, etc., and how people are rewarded,
but but it seems a little bit
counterintuitive and it we're actually
planning in inefficiencies for us as the
um as the consumer.
>> No, that's a really good point and I'm
glad to hear that there is a role for
government but one of the things we've
seen over the years with the US it's
sort of adjusted the ways that it makes
the money available and I'm at an event
tonight with Britain's ARPA which is
called ARA. So there's definitely trying
to learn how do we do that public money.
I was going to turn to the theme
question and then as given we've got
about five minutes left do that question
and then after that come through with
closing remarks calls to action. Um but
it says here around 99% of UK businesses
are small and medium-siz enterprises
they are different from some of the
entrepreneurial startups that Praderei
has. Um, and do we see a role for for
them between the startups of Predereari
and the large corporates of of Andrews
we're we're world um is there a role for
formemes who would like to speak onto
that 99% of the economy?
>> I think there's definitely a role
formemes. Uh there's there's innovation
there that can tackle real problems. Um
how do we overcome that? I think when it
comes to uh innovation funding needs to
reflect that, doesn't it? And and I
don't I can't see that at the moment.
the the innovation calls coming out. You
don't get an extra 10 m points for being
a microme applying in partnership with a
with a corporate but it would be quite a
refreshing approach to see to see uh in
innovation for me like to see that.
>> I would say there's lots of very a large
number of very averagememes out there.
>> Do they deserve additional funding? I
would say arguably not because many of
them when we see them coming through
they're interesting but are they
fundamentally showing you know thought
processes about gaining market share
innovation I don't care for innovation
for the sake of it it's got to be is it
improving your revenue line is it
improving your gross margin or is it
improving your operating margin
>> it's got to do one of the three if you
can't put a story that says this is what
we're doing giving me the framework of
why you're going to win
>> why would I give you capital and that
what that is what's missing part of the
innovation is there's a missing skill
set in the ability to do that in the UK
middle market because naturally these
companies are smaller than what you'd
find. I mean keep in mind UK middle
market is sort of 5 million to maybe 15
million in the US that's lower middle
market. It doesn't qualify for them 25
to 50 million is sort of where middle
market starts. So the skill sets
available are higher and it also shows
in the way they're able to raise
capital. I think that's in large part
what these companies are missing is that
skill set to help them propel to the
next level. But then again, in an
economy that's fairly well constrained,
you're going to have to be taking it
from somebody else.
>> So the question is who's winning, who's
losing?
>> All I would add is exactly that. Yeah.
Yes, there is. But what problem are you
trying to solve?
>> That's true. Yeah. Given that resources
are constrained. Thank you. So, as we're
heading into the last few minutes, um
I'll make a few remarks and then I'll
turn to Praderi first for his call to
action and what you think needs to be
approved and then we'll go through and
then no doubt some refreshing bracing
advice from W on what we need to do. Um,
one thing we would say onmemes when we
do our reap program around the world, we
are as MIT especially interested in the
high-end tech entrepreneurs of of Pred's
world that get the kind of fancy risk
capital funding that really can be
rocket fuel, the kind that Wed is
talking about that can do the kinds of
risks that aren't always easy for a
large corporate like we and so we're
pleased to hear that they're engaging.
But we do also say it's really important
that themes find a way to innovate. They
may not be the big eye innovation 10x
transformational disruptive but given
that they are in most countries 80 to
95% of the economy we wantmemes to be a
little bit more innovative even if it's
little I you know without government
funding and and risk capital but just
leaders ofmemes be a bit more innovative
because they do employ so many people uh
on mass you know if we could get them to
adopt in some of their cases e-commerce
let alone generative AI you know if they
could just become a little bit more
digitally savvy. It's not glamorous.
It's the hards yards of economic
productivity, but we think there's a
role for them and I know BT does a lot
to help small businesses. So, as we
prepare to wrap up, Praderi, final
thoughts, call for action, the voice of
the entrepreneur.
>> I guess the final thoughts is and call
to action is engage with your innovation
ecosystems. Uh they do exist all over
the UK, all over the world. Um they're
there easily accessible. Um so
develop a relationship with them and
develop that culture of can do
partnerships and across the model as
well. So from government to risk
capital, corporate, startups all working
together. So yeah engage. Good. I just
like to underpin that we are the London
Symposium but we know from our work in
the UK there are innovation ecosystems.
There are pockets of great startups all
of them there. Not all is as as
well-dressed as Praderei here, but
please do come and chat with him about
ways if you're a corporate that you
could find ways uh to work with his
amazing uh entrepreneurs.
>> Where Yeah, I think it's similar. It's
but with a but it's engage but
understand what your limitations are in
the way you engage and be prepared to
change. I think that's what we are
trying to do is make sure that we have
the ability to engage and not frustrate
the entrepreneur.
a ecosystem
um and and it's not all about the hard
ROI. We're doing it to advance and
accelerate technology into our existing
product to address um challenges that
the industry is facing. I think if we
took a hard ROI, we would possibly
invest in the same number of startups,
but we would have a different outcome.
It would be cash and not and not
product, which right now isn't right for
us. So engage, but understand why you're
engaging.
>> No, thank you, Alan. wid
>> I think for us it's much more about
getting our working with our CEOs to
help them actually be willing to take
those risks help them think through
provide that thought leadership about
how do you basic how do you actually
look at the future in the different way
what can you adapt I mean we're partners
with the MIT ILP so I think we're one of
the few financial if not the only
financial partner they have with the
idea done so we haven't really done it
very well to be very honest about it it
hasn't worked very well trying to get
our portfolios to engage with the ILP
and that to us is the biggest next thing
try to get our companies to see that
there's much more out there that they
don't have to fundamentally break
everything in the company to rebuild it
but those marginal improvements in terms
of workflows and just giving them
conceptually new ways to think about the
issues they're dealing with I think
that'll have a major impact and that I
think is a lot what's missing the theme
they don't have a conceptual framework
to say how do I go forward what's
possible out there if I mix these things
together, how do what's the better
outcome that I can generate? And that to
us is probably the biggest focus for the
next couple years.
>> Excellent. Well, thank you for that.
With that, I'm going to start to pull
the panel together and close. You now
have earned yourself a coffee break uh
until quarter past. So, I encourage you
to heed their calls to action. Maybe
there's one of these three that you want
to come up and chat with. If you've not
met a real life entrepreneur, do come up
and chat with Praderei. If you are in a
large company that wonders how on earth
Allan and where did that cultural change
uh or if you're interested in hearing
more about the hard-headed approach of
these high-risisk highreward uh
hopefully W also stick around for a
while. So, uh the break is now until
quarter past, but please join me in a
round of applause for our amazing
panelists.