All right, we'll get started. Um, what I
wanted to do today was to make sure we
thoroughly cover the theory and
application of regression modeling. And
so um to begin there's a recap which is
the theory for if we have linear
regression
and we have in particular
a normal
linear regression model. Then uh we have
these properties of uh beta hat being
distributed as a multi-normal
random
uh variable with mean the true
regression parameter and coariance
matrix given by the xrpose x inverse
multiplied by sigma squared.
And we also have that epsilon hat is a
multinnormal distribution.
It's actually not a full rank but it's
in n dimensions with mean zero a zero
vector. And the covariance matrix is
sigma squar times the identity minus the
hat matrix. And with these properties
um we can show that they are independent
random variables if we have the normal
model assumption. So these are
independent
if the error vector is multinnormal.
And
with that um we're able to get an
estimate of the error variance very
easily from the residual vector. uh the
sum of squares of the residual vector
can be solved for having expectation
equal to n minus p sigma^ 2 and that
leads to dividing the sum of squared
residuals by n minus p to get an
unbiased estimate. Now what's
interesting
uh mathematically is that um because
this estimate of the error variance
depends on the residuals which are
independent of beta hat. We can then use
this information to construct tstistics
for the le squares estimates. So we have
uh t statistics
for
the j component
of the le squares estimate. So beta hat
subj minus beta j
divided by
sigma hat
cj
where cj is the uh jth diagonal entry of
the variance inverse variance and
actually this cj
should be equal to the square root
of xrpose x inverse subj.
So there's a square root missing there.
Um and
this distribution
under the normal linear model has or
this test this formula has a t
distribution.
So this is distributed
as a t distribution with n minus p
degrees of freedom.
Degrees of freedom equal to n minus p.
And this is true
if we plug in the true
beta j.
So normal or or centering our le squares
estimate at beta j allows us to write
that out. So if we look at our beta hat
value
and consider it
around the true beta j, we basically
have a t distribution for the outcome.
And why this becomes very useful is that
if we want to test the hypothesis that
beta j is equal to zero
then if this is
zero
um we can basically define
a an interval
around zero
and consider rejecting
the null hypothesis if our t hat with
beta j equaling zero in magnitude is
greater than some critical value say
some constant c
and um so so this t statistic is
commonly applied uh in judging different
regression models
of particular interest is whether
factors can be excluded from the
regression.
So if a beta j component is equal to
zero that means we can just exclude the
variable.
Now interestingly if we want to test
whether
multiple beta js are equal to zero. A
special case of that is just to say
let's assume that the first k beta j's
are non zero.
We'll just assume that that's true. But
let's test whether the beta js for j
above k are equal to zero. And what we
can do is calculate
residuals under
the two hypotheses.
First assuming that they're all nonzero,
we get an RSS1.
But if we assume the submodel is true,
we can get a second set of residuals.
And
because the full model is more um sort
of it minimizes the sum of squares
further, we can look at the difference
in residual sum of squares.
Normalize that by p minus k and compare
that with the residual sum of squares
under the full model divided by n minus
p. So this is an estimate of sigma
squared using the full model. This
numerator is also an estimate of sigma
squared based on the uh null hypothesis
being true.
Now um what's interesting to highlight
is that the F test
when K the number of non zero
coefficients is P minus one then this F
test corresponds to testing whether the
P beta J is equal to zero. And so it
turns out that
um if we have t
sorry t hat yeah p of beta
uh of the true beta
the beta with beta p equal to zero.
um this
squared is actually equal to this F
statistic.
Um I'm just going to
there's a huge rumbling in the room
right now and uh if anyone finds out
that it's something serious we should be
thinking about please let me know or let
the whole class know.
It sort of sounds like an earthquake. uh
which which I experienced when I was at
UC Berkeley. Um
anyway, all right. Well, we'll I'll
continue unless I get warnings from you
all. Anyway, it turns out that this T
squared statistic is actually equal to
the F test formalized here. So, F tests
um are very useful in special cases.
They're equivalent to uh the square of a
t
a t test statistic. Now let's see
with um the notes from last time we went
through these um we uh highlighted
how um with generalized le squares
this is another key takeaway in
regression modeling.
So,
so generalized
le squares
with generalized le squares we have an
error vector which is not
uh a a diagonal identity
time sigma squared but
it's
some base matrix sigma times little
sigma squared
And with this setup, we can actually
transform this regression model into one
which satisfies our Gaus Marov
assumptions.
And then so with xstar and yar being the
model equation multiplied by the inverse
square root of sigma then
this model satisfies the gaus markov
assumptions zero mean constant variance
and so this estimator
uh with the x stars and y stars but the
same beta gives us our best estimate of
the beta a hat best in terms of minimum
being unbiased and having smallest
variance.
Okay. Well, uh, a next
important
aspect of regression model modeling is
looking at maximum likelihood
estimation,
MLE.
And for maximum likelihood estimation we
use the probability model
of the regression which in this case is
normal linear regression models. So if
we have normal
normal epsilon vector um then we compute
the density of our data y given the
explanatory variables in x and the beta
uh
regression parameter uh beta that should
be a beta there and uh we simply
identify by those parameter values that
maximize this probability. So we're
looking at the parameter values that
make the data we observed the most
likely
and intuitively that's may be a
reasonable thing. If you take
mathematical statistics
next term, you'll learn that that in
fact is an optimal estimator in terms of
having smallest variance
in large samples as large as the sample
size the number of cases n increases uh
this will lead to the best estimator and
this MLE
for the best or the the best estimator
being the MLE will be true for different
distributions as well. We're going to
show what it is for the Gaussian
distribution.
And what we can see on this slide is
that the log of the likelihood
is the log of this density on the top
line.
It can be equal to minus n /2 log sigma^
2 minus a half sigma^ 2 q of beta where
q of beta is our le squares criterion.
So maximum likelihood estimation for
normal linear regression models can
proceed in two steps.
First we can see that the beta
regression coefficient enters in only
through a factor of Q of beta. So
minimizing Q of beta gives us the MLE
for beta.
And then once we have the MLE for beta,
we can plug that into the likelihood,
the log likelihood
or the likelihood um for varying sigma
squared. And when we do this, we
actually can just maximize this uh sort
of partial likelihood with beta fixed at
beta hat. maximize that over sigma
squared. And that turns out to be a very
easy computation calculating the first
order equation for the uh log likelihood
and we get the maximum likelihood
estimate is simply the sum of squared
residuals divided by n. Now with maximum
likelihood
in this case we have actually a biased
estimate of this error variance and um
it's important just to to note that
that's the case.
All right. Um well what's interesting
to generalize is to find estimators
which minimize
a Q function which may be different from
least squares or sum of squares. And so
we can consider a Q function which
minimizes the sum of a function H
evaluated at case I. So let's see here
this down.
So so
with
with generalized
With generalized
M estimators,
we think of Q of beta being the sum one
to N of H of Yi
the Xi
beta
and sigma squared I guess. Um and the
choice of H. Well, if we choose h to
just be the square of the linear
estimate of y given x i that's le
squares. There's no reason in principle
why we should use squares. We could use
absolute deviations and sum those.
And if we wanted maximum likelihood
estimates,
we could choose H to be minus the log of
the density.
And
there are robust estimators in
statistics. And these uh robust
estimators uh con consider variations
basically of lease squares and
mean absolute deviations
um as special cases that yield
estimators that are robust. Now what's
to me very interesting is that if we
were to know what the density is of the
errors then maximum likelihood
estimation would say use that.
When we don't know the distribution
then these others may be
very useful as alternatives and
robust estimators um were originally
proposed for models where we may have a
normal distribution most of the time but
some contamination distribution with
large errors uh a small percentage of
the time.
Now um and another interesting example
of this generalized M estimator is the
quantile
estimator
where we consider sort of mean absolute
deviation
but we scale that for positive residuals
by a factor tow
and for negative values of the residual
ual we scale the absolute deviation by 1
minus toao.
This uh h function
uh basically is equivalent to
the uh mean absolute deviation when tao
is equal to 0.5.
But when tow um
is uh if we have h
let's see
so h of yx
when this is equal to um to yi minus x i
beta
um when this is
positive
and it's equal to 1 minus toao when this
is
actually it's equal to uh minus this
when this is less than zero.
Then
for example when TOAO is equal to 0.9
this turns out to be um a a quantile
estimate that is try working to estimate
the 90th sort of percentile
of outcomes. So when we have a
regression model
and we are sort of um it just if we have
a bunch of points
and we consider a linear regression
model this would be you know y uh equal
to
or y hat equal to sort of the mean
absolute deviation estimate.
um we actually
can get estimates of the 90th percentile
of outcomes of the uh regression model.
Now um
what's
interesting
mathematically is um how how would one
calculate sort of the mean absolute
deviation estimate or this quantile
estimator?
Well, we would want to minimize
the sum of these h functions.
And these h functions actually are
convex.
So, um, as James Shepard said, you know,
this is like a bowl-shaped problem, but
it's a bowl with sort of square or with
with straight edges around around it.
And so if we take this Q function with
this H um we can't minimize it by
solving the first order equations.
So um if we have q equal to the sum 1 to
n of h of the arguments we can't solve
this
uh we can't solve for this equaling zero
but we can solve for what the derivative
is at any guesses
and we can move our guess to a lower
value of the q function.
uh with that and that's in fact how we
learn that the median of a sample
is the
best estimate of the center of the data
if we consider mean absolute deviations.
Okay.
Well, let's um consider another
extension of uh regression. uh it's
famous enough to have its own name ridge
regression. And so with ridge regression
we are estimating
the regression parameters
where we have um
basically it's sort of le squares plus a
penalty
for our criterion.
So
the left argument
of this uh
expression is simply the sum of squared
residuals. But then we're adding to that
a penalty
depending upon the squared length of the
beta vector. And so
in order for this to be
a reasonable
thing to do um we actually need to or
it's we don't need to but it's useful to
consider standardizing
our independent variables X making them
have mean zero
and also centering y.
Um, and then consider the regression
where we rescale the
columns of the predictor matrix
as centered with the inverse of the
coariance matrix between those.
So in this formulation this is the uh uh
the statement of uh how the ridge
regression parameter estimate is
specified. Now the centering of the
independent variables and scaling them
to have unit variance
is important because it places all of
the variables all of the predictor
variables on an equal footing.
If we are looking at the sum of squared
beta js
then if we just use different units we
could make any j beta beta j as large as
we want. Um but with this uh
standardization
uh we basically eliminate uh that
aspect. So there's no dependence on the
original units of X.
And
let's see with this ridge regression.
The notes go through how we compute
these. Um I want to uh
highlight though how this ridge
regression is actually related to basian
models where we would assume a prior
distribution
on our regression parameters.
And so the uh
the if we consider a B
prior
on beta
and that
B prior is uh basically multi-normal
in P dimensions
with
a mean vector of zero.
and a covariance matrix
that
is
um let's see I'll call it omega and
omega is proportional to the identity
matrix
with in p dimensions
then what we've done is
we have a criterion that corresponds to
the exponential part of the log
likelihood for
plus the log likelihood of the prior
density. So, so this ridge regression
is is interpretable as putting a ba a
prior distribution on the betas that
have this form mean zero and co-variance
proportional to the identity matrix and
what that suggests op priori is that
sort of any direction in that pd-
dimensional space is equally likely as
any other for characterizing the
regression parameters
and this beta hat which minimizes this
argument ends up being the mode of the
posterior distribution.
So that's a neat connection uh to be
aware of.
Um the notes here go through with ridge
regression how we compute them. Um the
minimization
basically leads to formulas for the
ridge regression estimate that look
almost like le squares except we have
this additional factor lambda times the
identity inside that braces before we
take the inverse.
And with ridge regression, we can look
at the singular value decomposition
of our independent variables that have
been centered and standardized.
And when we do that um we basically have
these this final formula for the
ridge regression. Um and uh we end up
basically having
the fitted values y hat
just being equal to
a sum of factors times cj uj where these
factors
are one when lambda is zero. So when
lambda is zero least ridge is equal to
le squares and so the least squares
fitted values are given here but with
ridge regression
we have shrinkage
and what's curious is that there's less
shrinkage
for the larger squared singular values
and there's more shrinkage for the
smaller ones.
So if we think of the independent
variables or predictor variables being
in pd- dimensional space
then
ridge regression will
not shrink much those regression
coefficients
that are correspond to
regressor variables that are along sort
of the first principal component axis.
is and there's much more shrinkage in
those dimensions where there is very
little variation. So, so these are
actually connected to principal
components
variables which is actually covered sort
of in the next uh section. Um so you
know it was we introduced ridge
regression using the singular value
decomposition of x but um we can
motivate principal components regression
using the same singular value
decomposition.
So with our data
predictor matrix X um we consider the
sample covariance matrix of those row
vectors
um and
we can compute the igen value IGEN
vector decomposition of that
and with these IGEN vectors which are
normalized to have length one. We simply
multiply our matrix X by the J igen
vector and we get our J principal
component variable.
So this is familiar to us in terms of
how principal components sort of manipul
uh computations work.
And
with principal components regression,
one has
principal component variables which are
orthogonal to each other.
And so the computation
of their coefficients is very simple.
We can calculate them separately
and we can consider using maybe just the
first m principal component variables in
our regression.
And so if we do this
um we
can see some easy formulas for the
estimates.
Um
ultimately uh we get fitted values
of y from principal components
regression which are a projection of the
y vector
onto the space spanned by the first
in this case the first uh m uh principal
component directions.
And
what's curious is just how these three
methods le squares ridge and principal
components regression are estimating
the uh response variable or dependent
variable using essentially the same
fundamental pieces the CJ and U.js J's
but are um either sort of skipping the
last P minus M for principal components
shrinking those based on the size of the
igen values for ridge or using all of
them.
Now uh as you might expect um
researchers have extended
u estimation methods uh beyond these. Uh
the lasso regression
model uh or regression estimate is one
where instead of having the uh penalty
be the sum of squared
beta js or the length of the beta j.
It's the sum of the absolute values.
Um and this penalty is a really
interesting one. Um, and some of let's
say I'm sure some people here have
perhaps used lasso regression. Has
anyone here used lasso regression?
Nobody. That's fine. That means this
isn't a sort of repeat information. But
um it turns out that
um
well let me just draw this uh suppose we
have beta 1 versus beta 2
and we're considering
penalties.
Um so the sum of the beta j squares
equal to a constant. This is the sort of
ridge penalty.
So um
and so if uh if we have a beta hat
say a beta hat here
point that we observe um it basically is
sort of shrunk towards zero
or we have beta hat
and the beta hat ridge
will
be shrunk towards this sort of prior
mean
some amount. With the uh lasso penalty,
we have the sum of the magnitudes of the
beta js is equal to a constant.
Then
we basically have
sort of diamonds
where along each of these diamond edges
the penalty is the same magnitude.
And so with lasso regression, we
basically consider
finding
an estimate that is minimizes the least
squares but also is constrained
uh to have sort of sum of absolute
magnitudes that's smaller. And so this
kind of uh penalty ends up
actually leading to
uh
sort of shrinkage which tends to
concentrate at the vertices of this
uh penalty function. So um so what we
end up getting often is
a lasso estimate that has some null
parameters zero valued parameters. So,
it's a way of excluding variables from
the regression depending on what lambda
is.
All right. Um,
well, let's see. There's this uh ETF
case study that I posted
um which
it's sort of a long document to sift
through but I guess what's important
is just to look at the table of contents
to see what's of interest to check out
in this. And um what I set up as a
problem was to consider collecting
uh prices on exchange traded funds that
correspond to different sectors in the
US market.
And so in the US market there are about
10 sectors
consumer staples, energy, financials,
health and so forth. And then um there
are also um exchangeraded funds that
correspond to market indexes like the
S&P 500 or the Dow Jones Industrial or
the NASDAQ market. And uh
I consider
regressing a sector ETF on the index
ETFs. Now,
why would we be interested in regressing
a sector index on these
um market index ETFs?
Well, let me just uh
go through here, okay? or this this
document goes through listing the
symbols for all of these different ETFs,
plotting them
and actually then converting
the prices to weekly returns
and then looking at how they're
correlated with each other. So in this
example,
I believe it was the uh consumer staples
sector fund that
I'm thinking of regressing on the SPY
which corresponds to the S&P 500, MDY,
which is a midcap U index, QQQ and the
diamonds.
And if we look at these sort of
cumulative returns of these different
ETFs, you know, here's the cumulative
return over a I don't know 14-year
period or something. Um, well, any other
any any any more thoughts on why we
might want to regress this on these
indexes? AJ
>> the index return should be the entire
variant should be explained by their
sectors like assuming not everything you
generates is contained within
market index they should explain
perfectly
>> right okay so that's looking at almost
the other way around if we were looking
at the ex index ETF as a function of the
sectors we should have almost a perfect
explanation of that in a regression
model. What can be useful with this
regression is if we wanted to invest in
consumer staples but we wanted to have
our investment be hedged against the
sort of market risk
that is um large. And uh and so if if we
could eliminate the dependence on the
S&P 500, eliminate the dependence on the
midcap and the QQQs,
then
our sort of hedged investment, we'd be
less concerned about major drops in the
market. So we'd be reducing the market
risk. So this is where it can it can be
very useful. Now
this kind of approach
has also been used to try and mimic uh
hedge fund strategies.
And so there's uh some papers out there
on hedge fund replication where hedge
funds basically may be have most of
their returns attributable to
um liquid market instruments that one
can trade
um in a portfolio. And so uh hedge fund
replication
methods have actually done that kind of
regression as well.
Anyway, with this um with this uh setup,
we can just regress this XLP on the
index ETFs and we get this regression
coefficient table here. Um what's
important to see is
whether
the regression coefficients are
significantly different from zero or
not.
And
the t value and p value columns
basically tell us that that all of these
uh explanatory factors are are useful
here.
And let's see when we um when we study
uh
the uh
let's see when we study uh the
regression model okay we have the R
squared of this multiple regression
the correlation of the fitted and actual
values is given by uh or the square of
that is given by the R squared
And we can do various regression
diagnostics which are used here. What
I'll let you go through these details.
Uh this a bit repetitive from what we
talked about in the last lecture. But um
let's see we can also
model
the uh independent variables
um or do a principal components analysis
of those.
And if we compute a principal component
analysis of our independent variables in
this case the index sector uh exchange
traded funds. We then have
a
sort of decomposition of variability
um which indicates that the first
principal component variable explains
90% of the variability in these data.
the first two 97%.
So we're actually explaining a lot of
variability with just the first two. Now
um in looking at
the regression on the PC variables
um
let's see
we can
consider well each of these PC variables
principal component variables are
orthogonal to each other. So in
estimating the regression coefficients,
we can do so with simple linear
regressions
of
the ETF uh fund um
y on that on each variable. And so the
first principal component variable has
an R squar of 0.545.
Um
and the second principal component
variable
has almost no correlation.
And so it's um while it's almost none,
its p value is still 0.0518,
which is almost statistically
significant. With very large samples,
we're able to judge small correlations
as being statistically significant, but
maybe it's not practically significant.
And then the third
has um a small R squar as well. And the
fourth again rather small but what's um
what's of interest um is
whether the uh or basically just how
statistically significant are the
principal component variables. And in
this sort of updated example,
um
the uh
let's see here.
Well, if we consider the regression
parameter based on only the first three
variables,
um we basically get these results. Now,
when I did this um a few years ago, it
ended up being the case that the
uh p values for I think it was the
second principal component variable was
not significant at all. And so in
choosing to
um in in choosing what factors to
include in the model, the principal
components regression approach of
basically including successive
high uh en value principal component
variables in uh successively so long as
they're significant. um that actually uh
sort of
doesn't doesn't include really
necessarily the important regressors in
in the model. So we can have
statistically significant high order
principal component variables that don't
have much variability in them but they
actually are explaining uh significant
uh factors affecting the response
variable.
So anyway, this uh this note goes
through and uh
in additionally uh considers ridge
regression and less so regression. And
so with the ridge regression
uh results,
the display of regression parameters
um is traced out as we consider
different constraints on the uh
L1 or on the well on the L2 norm. Um and
uh if we look at the L1 norm of these
estimates, one can see basically how as
one sort of decreases the penalty for
the complexity of the regression
parameters, we get final estimates given
by these
ending values. But if we increase the
penalty on those then they basically are
shrinking towards zero uh although the
shrinkage isn't necessarily in a
monotone manner.
And then if we look at the lasso
regression
with a same L1 norm sort of scaling, one
can see how as that lambda parameter
associated with the penalty is increased
um we basically have
the L1 norm getting smaller
of the resulting estimates. And this
shows you how
I guess the third variable is the first
to be excluded. Uh then the second and
then uh finally uh the fourth.
So um
all right. So, so anyway, so this note
goes through an illustration of lesso
and principal components regression
and it also provided a comparison of
different coefficients by method.
And what this uh final sort of chart
shows is the comparison of
beta estimates by method. And one can
see that most of the methods give
similar results but using just the first
three principal component variables
gives us a very different estimates of
regression parameters. So um the uh so
there's sensitivity of
the estimators um to the data and
it's perhaps
useful to um
let's see well it's useful to consider
these alternatives with very large
sample sizes you generally don't get
much difference in the ridge or the less
cell results.
It's usually in smaller sample sizes
that that you get differences. Um with
the principal components regression, um
in this example, the first three
principal component variables
um end up giving estimates that are in
the yellow.
But if we chose which principal
component variables to include based on
their statistical significance,
then the uh the more significant uh
principal component variables ended up u
leading to this green values which are
comparable to the others. So, so this
suggests that um
well actually in this case the the green
values
are equal to le squares um just because
all the principal component variables
were statistically significant.
All right. Um
well the next uh thing I wanted to
go through
um is
this linear regression modeling for the
capital asset pricing model.
And in this note,
um, we first review what the capital
asset pricing model is, how it relates
to, uh, returns on stocks and returns on
a market index.
And what we're going to do is go through
the computation
computations involved with an empirical
analysis of this capital asset pricing
model.
and then consider testing hypotheses
about individual uh coefficients
and then conclude with actually fitting
this capital asset pricing model to
all stocks in the S&P 500 index and
comparing the results of the capital
asset pricing model parameters for that.
So with this
we begin with basically a description of
what the capital asset pricing model is.
We went through this I think in our
third lecture which says that in an
efficient market the expected return of
a stock asset J should equal the
risk-free return plus a beta factor
times the excess return of the market.
And so beta j is the uh sort of the the
market risk factor. Um and the excess
return of the market portfolio is simply
how much bigger that market return is
compared with the risk-free rate. Now
with this with these parameters,
if we have
data consisting of empirical returns R
for stocks J at different times T,
different values over T of the risk-free
rate, and we consider the excess return
of each asset and the excess return of
the market.
Then this
data can be used to specify
a linear regression model
where we have an intercept
alpha j and a slope beta j
for the regression. So,
so we're looking here at
RAR market
and this is R*
J.
And we'll plot
values
over time T of
these excess returns.
And we can basically fit a regression
model
where we have y hat or rstar
jt is equal to alpha j + beta j r star
mt.
And
if the capital asset pricing model holds
then the alpha js
should be zero
because the alpha js if we take the
expectation in this equation with
residuals that are mean zero constant
variance then um we get the capital
asset pricing model equation. when the
alpha j is equal to zero. Um so what we
can do with real data is fit this model
and then test whether alpha j is zero or
not.
And
if if it is consistent with a zero value
then the pricing of the asset can be
judged to be sort of in an equilibrium
um described by the capital asset
pricing model. Um, and so let's take a
look. I think what's perhaps useful is
just to see the code for
doing these computations that's included
uh in the note here.
But if we pick a particular stock
GE stock
and fit the regression model,
um we basically in this code the only
thing we need to do is specify the
symbol for the stock
and then extract from our data
object the uh excess
uh market return and the excess asset
return
and then fit that regression and we get
this coefficients table here. Now in
this example,
the intercept
coefficient is the estimate of alpha.
And if GE is being priced consistent
with the capital asset pricing model,
then that estimate should be consistent
with the null value. And the p value for
testing whether that intercept is zero
or not gives us evidence supporting the
capital asset pricing model.
Now the market
the excess return of the market has an
estimate that's about one with some
standard error. It has a huge t value
and a huge p value. Those
values being large or a huge t value and
very small p value are not surprising at
all just because they're correlated and
a zero value for the slope is sort of
meaningless here. What could be useful
is testing whether our beta coefficient
is consistent with sort of the average
market risk of beta equal to one or not.
Um but here's uh basically a plot of the
linear regression model for GE
and a discussion just of getting
comfortable with R squared values and
calibrating our views of scatter plots
to those values.
Um
and then there's residuals analysis that
is very important as I introduced
at the beginning of our regression
study. Um we make assumptions about our
model and we then once we fit the model
we check our assumptions to see whether
those are satisfied or not. And in this
case, um, we might assume that the
residuals are normally distributed.
And here's
a histogram of the residuals from this
GE uh, regression. And there actually
are two bell-shaped curves here. There's
one that's in green that corresponds to
the maximum likelihood estimate of the
mean and variance of that normal.
Um, but there's also a blue curve which
corresponds to a robust estimator of the
normal distribution parameters. So, and
we just talked a bit about normal linear
regressions and there being optimal.
Well, they're optimal so long as the
normal distribution is applied
and one can calculate what's called a QQ
plot of the residuals
where the theoretical distribution is
normal. We can think of ordered samples
of normals
from smallest to largest and pair those
with our ordered residuals from smallest
to largest. And this plot will look like
a straight line if the residuals are
Gaussian.
And
the green line corresponds to the MLE
fit of the Gaussian basically.
the slope will equal the standard
deviation of the distribution and the
median roughly will correspond to the
mean value. Um but what we have is uh a
robust estimate of the standard
deviation of the residuals
um gives us this blue line and the
robust estimate of the residual variance
is based on the interquartile range of
the residuals. So the middle 50% you
know what kind of standard deviation
would match the middle 50% range of the
residuals.
And uh there's an argument that um this
robust estimate might in fact be better.
And another way of evaluating the
residuals is to compute
fitted percentiles under the residual
model. So if we observe an epsilon hat
with mean mu hat and standard deviation
sigma hat,
we can do the probab the inverse of the
probability integral transform
and get the
percentile of that outcome.
And so uh it turns out that these
percentiles
should be uniformly distributed from
like 1 to 99.
um if the if this normal model is
correct and so we can actually consider
different estimates of sigma hat from
robust to
uh MLE and with the MLE here's the
histogram of the
uh fitted percentiles
it's basically underestimating
percentiles
that are close to the mean or the
median.
And um and so it really isn't fitting
the residuals very well across the whole
range. And if instead we consider fitted
percentiles from the robust
estimate of the variance, then the
residuals
fitted the fitted percentiles of the
residuals is consistent with uniform
in the middle of the data except in the
top 1% and the bottom 1%. So it's very
possible that our data has a non-normal
uh residual distribution or error
distribution. Um and perhaps that
non-normal distribution could be well
modeled with uh a mixture model.
Now um okay, there's regression
diagnostics which I'll let you read
through. Um,
and then there's this section on testing
hypotheses about individual model
coefficients.
Let's see. If you have this on your
computer, you can probably see it a
little better than seeing this this
screen here. But with the normal or with
our uh testing of individual
coefficients
um we basically use the fact that our le
squares estimator
is multivariant normal with mean equal
to the true beta vector and covariance
matrix given here.
So, so we can make various tests
uh of different regression parameters.
So, we have the t statistics for testing
whether a parameter value is zero or not
and use the t distribution to judge how
statistically significant that is. In
our capital asset pricing model case, we
actually are interested in testing
whether the alphas are zero or not.
And um one could also consider testing
for whether the beta factor is equal to
one or not. One for the beta is actually
what the average beta is across all
stocks in the market. And so one can
consider judging whether var whether
assets sort of have significantly high
risk high betas or low betas.
uh using a test of whether the uh
estimated regression coefficient is
significantly different from one or not.
And so um with this I've basically uh
computed this for GE
and it turns out that
um I guess the
t stat for uh
GE which corresponds to a beta of 1.083.
That's fairly close to one in terms of
absolute magnitude but it's actually a
bit it's statistically significant
according to the arguments given here.
Now um there are uh many packages in R
but one of them is the car package which
allows one to conduct tests of linear
hypotheses like these. And so it goes
through
and performs the same kinds of tests for
whether the intercept is zero or not.
And in implementing these hypothesis
tests, this car package uses the sort of
F test
approach. So one has results that give
us different residual sum of squares and
F statistics
um and P values for the F statistics
corresponding to these.
Now um let's see with
let's see before showing the results for
all the stocks in the S&P 500 there's
another note
um on regression
analysis hypothesis testing
and
what's
interesting to think about is
we can consider testing
whether a submodel, a model with out as
many factors in it is suitable.
But one can also test for whether
there's a change in model parameters
with a regime. So that maybe there's an
initial period with a given set of model
parameters and then a regime shift
following that where the parameter
values have changed. And so
the mathematical theory for this is
covered in section three and one can
consider testing with the capital asset
pricing model maybe whether there's a
change in regression parameters over
over our entire period. And so what I
want to
just uh go to is the results. Actually
the linear algebra for these uh
hypothesis testing methods um is very
straightforward
and I encourage you to read through
these just to see how they play out. Um
but um
let's see what's interesting I guess is
with this change between two periods if
we consider sort of an original
regression model y = x beta plus epsilon
for a very long period.
um we might consider splitting it up
into the first part period A and the
second part period B and have two
equations for the respective sets of
data.
And in thinking about
the two periods,
um, we basically can test whether the
regression parameters for the second
period are the same as the regression
parameters for the first period.
And we can write out the model equations
uh with appropriate matrices.
And then uh we basically have an F test
statistic for seeing whether these
regression parameters um are different
or not.
And
one can also instead of considering
separate parameters
for each period, one can consider
a beta value here for
the entire period.
and then
use that beta value together with the
change in parameter values
in period B from period A. And so one
can set up the regression model where
one is interested in whether this change
parameter delta is equal to zero or not.
And so mathematically we get f test from
that. Now with the um GE stock
I subjectively chose this period
split for A from B. If we look at the
cumulative sum of uh standardized
residuals from the regression model,
then we basically have residuals that
are consistently negative
accumulating
to a lower value around 2019 and then
later expanding beyond that. So this
sort of time series of
cumulated residuals sort of highlights
that there's strong time dependence in
the residuals. Um but if we fit the
regression models to these uh separate
regression models to these two periods,
we end up getting
highly significant results for
the change in the two periods. There's
basically an intercept which is the
alpha which changes from negative to
positive and the market risk uh
basically changes
um from 77
3 beta uh in the uh first period to 773
plus 3537
in the second period. So
these capital asset pricing models are
not expected perhaps to hold over really
really long periods of time and if we
wanted to uh apply them we'd likely sort
of choose a rolling window approach
perhaps which then leads to questions of
how do we decide on what rolling window
is appropriate opens up other issues to
study. So um
anyway, so with with that background for
hypothesis testing, let's go back to
the uh fitting the capital asset pricing
model to all stocks in the S&P 500.
Um
let's see the code here basically fits
this capital asset pricing model
regression
for um all the stocks
that have data going back several years.
So there were I think around 380 or 400
stocks
and they're grouped by sector and we can
see how the R squares of the regressions
vary from 0 to one. Um they typically
are above 02. So there's some reasonable
uh R squar relationships that are being
explained.
Um and if we look at the alphas
by sector,
um here's sort of parallel box plots of
the alphas, the alpha estimates within
each of the sectors. And so this
highlights how uh some
let's see some sectors like uh I guess
construction sort of had positive alphas
as did computer technology.
Um
let's see the conglomerates uh tended to
have negative alphas there.
And we can calculate uh the p values for
testing whether the alphas are
consistent with zero or not. And this
graph here shows
how the p values
for almost all the stocks
exceed
the p value threshold of 0.05.
So if we
can't reject
the null hypothesis of alpha
equaling zero, the p value is above
0.05.
And one can see that there's basically
sort of a handful or a couple of handful
of stocks that have a significant alpha.
And if we use a 5% threshold, well, we'd
expect 5% of the results to be
statistically significant when there's
no statistical significance. And so
maybe these in fact are consistent with
um the capital asset pricing model
pretty well.
Now um
let's see one can plot um the alpha
versus the beta across all the stocks
and get this result um which suggests
that when you have higher beta you may
get higher alpha as well. Um and when
you have very low beta, maybe the low
beta is partly due to a lower alpha
potential.
Um but this chart doesn't show how alpha
varies by sector.
And so if we
try to look at alpha by sector, we get
sort of different fits for different
sectors, which is too complex really to
interpret as graphed here. But um it
sort of as a first step at trying to
understand how alphas might vary within
different sectors. Um
perhaps interestingly, here's the beta
coefficient.
by sector.
And here one can see that certain
sectors like consumer staples
have much lower beta
values and other sectors like computer
and technology have very high betas. So
in terms of identifying those sectors
that will have low market risk or high
market risk, these these uh properties,
you know, play out quite well.
And
let's see in terms of looking at the top
and bottom stocks by beta. Um
well we have consumer discretionary
computer technology sector stocks are
the have are the sectors where the top
10 betas are. And if we look at the
lowest betas
ranging from 37 down to 0.18, most of
these are in consumer staples.
Finally, if we look at the top 10 stocks
with significant alphas, okay, here is
the table of alpha values that were
highest and one was in oils and energy
sector ENPH
U with the alpha value of 0.003.
Let's see here's
so if we have an alpha value
of 0.003 03
it's actually
that's it to three whatever
I won't have the extra but but this is a
daily alpha
um if we wanted to annualize this daily
alpha
what would that annual how would we
compute that annualized alpha
If you're earning this alpha every day,
it sort of is an increment of return
that you're expecting to get every day.
And so if we have 1 + alpha hat to the
number of days
there's roughly 252 days per year
um and then subtract one
then we end up getting
let's see
I computed this
it's it's uh 2.12 two minus one
basically. So this is like a 100%. So
this stock happened to just deliver huge
amount of returns. Um but um what's
interesting to see though is that this
relatively simple model the capital
asset pricing model appears to be
consistent with the stocks over a long
period of time. That being said, um you
know the uh more complex models are um
warranted and um the data
collection phase of this our project um
included importing FMA French factors
that are extensions of sort of the
market risk that can be used in these
models. So,