My name is Nicholas Tomcho. I'm
professor of architecture. Um, currently
head of the architecture department. I'm
also professor of urban studies and
planning and affiliated faculty with the
program in science, technology, and
society. I grew up in Sydney, Australia
and moved here to Boston when I was in
middle school for my dad to work at MIT,
which is why I never thought I would
come to MIT. Um but I ended up being
interested in um architecture and cities
and uh also technology which I was
exposed to certainly here at MIT growing
up. And then I uh worked trained as an
architect, worked as an architect in
London and New York. Uh started teaching
um in a program first in a program in
architecture and landscape architecture
at the University of Virginia and then
at UC Berkeley for 15 years. and then
somehow they convinced me to come back
here to MIT in 2020. Here my um head of
a department of architecture. Uh I think
uh a lot of what we do today is about
really challenging what that word means
in the in the current context. We uh
when we ask students to think about what
a building is today, uh we don't ask
them to think about it as a singular
object. We ask them to think about it as
an intervention in an urban system, as
an intervention in an ecological system.
and um uh I think with a with a kind of
deep ethical obligation to be um a
driver of positive change in all the
systems that it's connected to. And so
if you think about a building as a
catalyst and not an object, you get to a
very different idea of what architecture
is in the world today. Architecture is a
very important agent of change in the
world. And I think also the practice of
architecture has to change. And so for
me, my work as the head of the
architecture department here at MIT is
incredibly important because it brings
together this uh enormous history of
architectural practice um in North
America that MIT is a catalyst of and it
also um brings together um uh that
tradition with the research context of
MIT which is such a huge driver of
change and transformation in the
profession. Historically, it's been that
way. MIT invented the first CAD system,
the first CNC system, the first plastic
house, you know, all these things came
from MIT. And so, you know, my hope is
that this department can in the best way
possible and as much as it can be um a
real agent of change in the practice of
architecture today. I talk about how
when I was being trained as an
architect, I I one of the reasons I
studied architecture is because I love
to draw. Um, and the the definition of
design that I was introduced to was
design is drawing. You you you draw
something and then it's built. But that
definition of design only really dates
from the 13th or 14th century when
architects started to be too busy with
multiple buildings to be on site all the
time. But it's really taken over um uh
in our conception of what design is. we
uh have a kind of genius you know
whether it's Michelangelo or Johnny IV
like outlining something delineating it
maybe working with prototypes but then
raw materials are extracted from the
earth and a whole bunch of it is built
whether it's buildings or consumer
objects or uh you name it whereas the
original meaning meaning of design that
um uh that the original uh Latin root of
the word has is talks much more about
what I think design needs to be today
which is a kind of strategic thinking
about the world, thinking about
resources, thinking about how we name
things, how we designate things, and
where we are now in history,
particularly in the context of the
climate crisis. I think this idea of
shaping something that's then built and
thrown away is is um uh no longer useful
and we really need to um both move
forward and also maybe also move back to
that uh historic meaning of the word
design. pre-industrial in some senses.
Um I think um you know a pre-industrial
economy was a more circular economy and
that's what we need to move back to.
Although there's huge parts of what
we've you know built in the world in the
last 100 years that I'm very fond of and
wouldn't wouldn't wouldn't want to lose
either.