the future of work. That is the topic
for the second part of this seminar.
Before introducing you to our next
speaker that comes from MIT, let me tell
you that his research is focused on how
workers, companies, and regions are
adapting to technological change.
what happens with change or with the
capacity to adapt to it to changes. He's
currently leading a work group on
generative AI. He's also authoring a
work on competitiveness of US
manufacturing. Part of his work has been
developed in Google INC and today he
co-directs the initiative work of the
future in the industrial performance
center of MIT.
Ben Armstrong, executive director of MIT
industrial performance center.
scholars of England and they became very
interested in
artificial intelligence and robots on
the future of the workforce. So what
they did was they went to some of the
leading experts in machine learning and
artificial intelligence and they
presented them with a long list and this
was a list of jobs. Jobs like home
healthc care aid or doctor and lawyer
and then they had a list of skills and
tasks associated with each job. And what
these two scholars from Oxford asked was
for could these machine learning experts
predict which jobs would be automated by
2030? which jobs would still be here in
just a few decades and which would not.
And after collecting all this data and
listening to the survey, what they found
was these machine learning experts
thought that about half of all jobs
would be automated by 2030. So they
wrote this up in a paper. The paper
estimated with these you know
complicated methodologies about 47% of
the labor force in North America and
Europe would be vulnerable to automation
in the next two decades. And as you can
imagine, this study released a wave of
anxiety among people. Newspapers,
magazines picked it up and talked about
a robot apocalypse where all these jobs
would be destroyed. And of course, in in
retrospect, you know, we're pretty close
to 2030 by now. And a few months ago,
there was a paper that looked back at
this study and evaluated all the jobs
that this uh these researchers said
would be automated. And what they found
was rather than being destroyed, many of
these jobs that machine learning experts
thought were would be fully automated
had actually grown in number since this
study was released. So I think one of
the big lessons of this study, but also
predictions of the future and the impact
of technologies like AI more broadly is
don't listen to researchers when they
try to predict the future. Don't listen
to people like me. So what I'm going to
do today isn't to try to predict the
future of work uh in any way, but
instead try to draw on lessons from the
present data that we have today and also
lessons of the past to try to understand
how we can prepare for an uncertain
future, one that we really can't
predict. And I want to start with an
image really from the present and an
image that many of you are probably
familiar with. This is a a control room,
a supervisory control environment, a
really an automated environment where a
human worker is operating uh and
overseeing a mine in a very different
way than they might have a generation
ago. And one of the big questions I
think for for the mining industry is
whether the work in 20 years looks a lot
more like this or if it looks something
like this and how what's going to be the
balance between these different types of
jobs. And I think there's maybe an
assumption that almost all operator jobs
in the future might look like this. That
there's this unstoppable path toward
automation and a more control room type
environment. And what I'm here to argue
today is that the evidence does not
favor this scenario over the long term.
It doesn't favor a completely automated
environment in mining or in other
industries like manufacturing. Instead,
what the future, you know, could be, and
I think what it's likely to be based on
past evidence is a combination. It's
going to be part supervisory control. I
think there will be a lot more control
room jobs. It'll be part manual jobs,
jobs that are require someone close to a
process, and then some jobs that are a
hybrid of the two that require a really
close connection between humans and
machines, between oversight and in the
field experience. And I think the
challenge then for for the companies
here today isn't necessarily to drive as
fast as possible toward automation
toward making that control room type
environment more and more present. The
challenge instead is to understand in
what context automation really makes
sense and can be very valuable and in
what context you need someone really
close to the field and that knowledge is
essential. So I'm going to try to talk
you through some examples, many of which
are from other industries, of how you
can make that judgment call of when
technology really has value and when it
doesn't. Okay. So I want to get started
with three real puzzles. And I call them
puzzles because for a long time the
assumption was in research that more
technology is better. That the more
technology you give to workers, the more
productive they'll be. and technology
adoption was going to be really a
frictionless path toward higher
performance. And what we've learned
really over the last 40 years is that
this isn't the case. It's the case in
some scenarios but not in others. And I
want to share with you a little bit
about why that is. And and the first is
really that what we found despite the
anxiety and and concern about automation
destroying jobs is that in many cases
when firms integrate automation
successfully, they do become more
productive and they become more
profitable at the firm level. So in
doing that, they end up growing and they
hire more people, not fewer. And that's
what some of the revisions and and
reactions to this 2017 paper show. But
given this evidence, you would expect
because the adoption of robots and
technologies like AI and being
profitable, you'd expect that every
company would be adopting these
technologies in all sorts of ways. But
that's not the case. Actually,
automation adoption has been quite
stagnant um over the last 10 years
across a variety of environments. So
here is just a plot. This is of
industrial robots. I'll show that this
isn't just the case for robots, it's for
other technologies as well. that in a
number of advanced industrial c
countries since 2015
the adoption of these technologies has
been flat or declining. The one
exceptional case is China and that's
aided u mostly by government heavy
government subsidies and I'm going to
share with you in a bit that these
government subsidies don't necessarily
translate into productive use of of
robots even in in the Chinese market.
Second, it's not just robots. This is
data from the US. And in the US context,
if you break down any of these advanced
technologies, we have robots down here,
which it's about 8 to 12% of all US
manufacturing firms have any robots at
all. But even advanced computing
technologies and specialized software, a
minority of companies has actually
invested in these technologies. So
there's this real there's this real uh
bizarre puzzle that these technologies
seem to have benefits for the firms that
adopt them, but not all firms are doing
so. And we need to really understand
why. Okay. Second,
when we have this conversation about AI
that I'm sure many of you have have
heard, there are predictions that these
new technologies are going to transform
the productivity of the economy and lead
us to a whole new era of prosperity. One
where work might not even be required.
These are the the technological
optimists make this case. And this there
was a similar case for this during the
early era of computers and the internet.
And what the the proponents of these
technologies said then was look at how
much faster a computer can do a task
than a fax machine or someone doing it
by hand. They predicted huge leaps
forward in productivity. And over time
what they found was that in the 90s and
2000s when the computers really became
saturated in the business market that
those productivity gains never really
showed up. They didn't come. And what
economists ended up calling this was the
productivity paradox. They said that
they saw computers everywhere except in
the productivity numbers. And I think
this dilemma is is captured nicely by
this cartoon where it says economists
are wondering where the you know where
the productivity gains are from
computers. And then it shows of course a
bunch of workers slacking off on their
computers. The implication being that
sure computers allow you to do some
things faster but they also lead you to
do all sorts of other tasks that might
not be adding value in your job. So just
to give you a sense of the the numbers
here. So here's just productivity growth
numbers 1970 to204 in the kind of the
computer era lower than the precomputer
era and kind of back in this early uh
second industrial revolution era. So we
didn't see the big boost in
productivity. Of course there are a lot
of factors that affect these numbers but
if we would have seen this real phase
shift in technology we would expect
productivity growth to go up big time
and we didn't. So this is a question to
keep raising about generative AI and the
new technologies like is this time
really different or are we going to be
stuck in a similar productivity paradox.
The third puzzle and the one that I find
most interesting and is most relevant to
my work is that sometimes humans are
actually better than machines at doing a
task. Sometimes a machine is better than
humans and then sometimes the human and
the machine together are the best at
doing the task. But the challenge is we
don't know to predict when each case
will be true. So let me give you two
examples. There's been a series of
studies uh of radiologists. So um
doctors whose job it is to study scans
and try to detect anomalies. And of
course this is also a great task for
machine learning algorithms. So the
studies have compared doctor's
performance in identifying uh cancer in
radiology scans to AI performance in
detecting cancer in radiology scans. And
what they found is that when you just
have the doctor or just have the um radi
you just have the doctor or you just
have the AI, they both do pretty well
and they actually have a pretty low rate
of finding false positives essentially
identifying cancer where it's not there.
And that's false positives are a problem
because they can really lead to high
costs in the system of of further
procedures. But when you have the AI and
the doctor together, the assumption
would be that more expertise is better,
right? Not really. You see that the the
rate of false positives actually goes up
quite a lot with the doctor and the AI
together, even though the doctor and the
AI together can find the cancer when
it's there and has a lower risk of
negatives. So, there's this really
interesting dilemma of the AI and the
human are better at some things and not
at others. And we don't really know the
conditions under which that's true. Um
the second thing we there was a recent
study from a colleague of of ours at MIT
um as well as others on uh consultants
and they gave consultants two tasks. One
was to develop a marketing campaign for
a shoe and the other was to analyze
market data and advise a company which
new industry to enter into. And they
thought that if you give these
consultants AI tools, they'd be better
at these tasks. They both provide the
right answer more of the time and they'd
also do the task more quickly than they
could have done it on their own. So they
tested this and what they found to their
surprise was that in creating the
marketing campaign for the shoe, the
consultants with AI were far better,
faster, and their marketing plans were
considered higher quality by experts.
But when you asked them to do the market
analysis, those with AI actually came up
with the wrong answer more frequently.
and and they wondered why could they
have gotten this wrong. So they went
back and they looked at how the
consultants were using the AI and it
turned out the consultants were asking a
lot of the right questions but the AI
was giving them misleading answers and
it was doing it so persuasively that
even these highly educated consultants
bought in and and ended up following the
AI into the wrong answer. So again the
question here is how do you exercise
discretion? How do you find out which
are the tasks where the the experts the
human experts can benefit from new
technology and which are the tasks where
the these scholars call it outside the
frontier where the technology isn't a
benefit and might actually lead you
astray. So this leads me to a few cases
that I think can be instructive for this
audience of of failures and automation.
And I think failures and automation are
are important because they can help us
identify, you know, what went wrong and
to try to kind of we can avoid stepping
in those those holes in in the future.
So one of the reasons why automation
fails is that people have a tough time
calibrating risk. And you can imagine
some failures of automation aren't
really a problem of the technology.
They're a problem of an organization
unwilling to take the risk to use the
technology. And here are two scholars
who became famous in the 1970s, Danny
Conan and Amos Tverki. Um they were at
the University of California, Berkeley.
They were psychologists who recognized
that humans pretty consistently make
what economists would think of as
irrational decisions. That even if they
could gain a certain amount of money,
they would choose not to gain that money
uh in favor of some alternative. And
they realized that the consistency of
the behavior was something they called
loss aversion. that humans would rather
avoid losing money versus taking the
chance to gain money. So you could see
here is that even with a small loss,
humans see this as a big negative,
whereas it would take a much bigger gain
to get to the same positive. So this is
kind of abstract. Let's put it in in
more concrete terms. So, when you were a
if you were asked if you had an 80%
chance of winning $4,000, let's call it
US dollars versus a 100% guaranteed
chance of $3,000, how many would choose
the 80% chance of $4,000?
Barely anyone, right? How about the 100%
guarantee of 3,000?
Okay, many just wouldn't take the money
at all, but okay. So the the the
guarantee of 3,000 wins out and that's
the case in the study that that Terski
and Conoran did too. So it was only
about 10 to 20% of all people took the
80% chance. But economists and our best
economic models would predict that a
100% of people would take that chance
because in a repeated game over time
you're going to win more than the you're
going to make more than the 3,000.
Right? So this is showing a flaw in how
we evaluated risk as individuals. And
this actually translates into into
organizations as well that many
organizations particularly ones that are
dominant in industry end up being
riskaverse preserving what they have
versus trying for more. And you might
think okay 1970s maybe this has changed
over time. In 2020 there were scholars
um that that tried to replicate this
study around the world to see if there
were patterns um they could find. And
what they found was really a lot of
consistent findings. But what I wanted
to share with, you know, this audience
in particular, Chile was kind of an
outlier down here. So what I would
expect from this audience was more
people willing to take the risk actually
because Chileans it seems are more
riskaverse than people in other places,
but we can set that aside maybe for for
Q&A. Um, okay. So so one of the
challenges with automation is that
people might not take the risk.
Organizations might not take the risk to
invest in new technologies. A second
challenge is that even among the
risk-taking organizations, the ones that
try to automate many of their activities
that that that automation might
backfire. So one of the reasons why I I
am anticipating that moving entirely in
a supervisory control direction,
essentially all operators in control
rooms is that this aversion of this has
been tried over and over again in
industrial environments in
manufacturing. Um the the term of art is
lights out automation. This was coined
in the early 1980s by General Motors and
the General Motors CEO at the time said
that he wanted the factory to be so
automated to have so many robots that
you wouldn't even need to turn on the
lights. That would be a waste of money.
And he tried to do this in 1982. He
called it the factory of the future. And
the factory did terribly. The robots
couldn't actually figure out which car
was which, which bumper would go with
which body. they would be painting each
other instead of painting the cars. It
was a total disaster. So the factory of
the future essentially became a
laughingstock until Elon Musk comes
around in 2019 2020. He says this lights
out automation idea. It's really
terrific. And he tries the same idea
really with the Model 3 for Tesla
backfires again. Even though there have
been great advances in robotics
technology, the implementation of that
technology was really flawed and and uh
Tesla ends up assembling Model 3s in a
tent outside the factory about as manual
as can be. Okay, this plays out over and
over again in different industries. And
what I think is important is that the
the lesson from each of these firms
wasn't that the technology was incapable
of automation. In many cases, the
technology was available. it was that
they hadn't really aligned the human
skills and they hadn't designed jobs to
manage automated systems. So you could
see the post-mortem from uh Mr. Musk up
top that humans are are underrated. uh
various Chinese companies that have
tried to use automation uh and a lot of
those robots that you saw in the red
line for assembling electronic devices.
They've had, you know, when scholars go
there to study how they've done it, they
see robots kind of hiding in corners
that have been they've been unable to
use and and they say, you know, the
human body is is magic. And then
finally, what they realize is that in
many cases, if you develop an automated
system, it's inflexible. Much of the
technology needs to be fixed. And what
you need in order to innovate and
continue to identify improvements is you
need human intervention and you need
flexibility. So this idea of lights out,
one of the uh German manufacturing
executives that we interviewed said um
that he he wasn't even the goal
shouldn't be a lights out factory
because that was antithetical to
innovation. So what I think it's really
important to understand, you know, one
reason why automation fails isn't
because the technolog is incapable of
performing a task. In this case, this
was a a tool company that wanted to make
wrenches in an automated way in the
United States. And what they evaluated
was that they had done the math right.
They had tried to they knew that they
could actually produce the technology
was capable of producing wrenches at a
cost-effective way in the United States
with high wage labor. But they hadn't
really invested in the training and they
hadn't invested in redesigning the jobs
to to suit an automated factory.
Instead, what they were doing was the
equivalent of asking someone who had
spent their career driving, you know,
being a manual operator in a mine and
then asking them to go operate in a
control room. And that really didn't
work in their situation. They needed to
rethink the skills that were required to
really make an automated system function
and to scale it up. All right. And this
is yeah, I'm I'm going to skip this and
we go back to it, but that was really
just a plot of of, you know, how the
jobs are mismatched between automated
systems and more manual systems. So now
I imagine what you're wondering is if if
we hear about the stories of failure,
what differentiates those stories of
failure from the stories of success. And
first it comes down to people that
somehow there are certain people,
certain workers that seem more open and
willing to champion new technologies
than others. And a group of us at MIT,
my colleagues and I did a study. We
wanted to understand what are the
characteristics of these workers who are
champions of automation who are willing
to go work in that control room
environment and fill it figure it out.
So we surveyed about 9,000 workers in
nine different countries and asked them
questions about their jobs, questions
about their perceptions of new
technology, how they thought automation
might affect their work. And what we
found which was really surprising to us
in the first instance was that many of
these workers more workers were actually
positive optimistic about the impact of
automation on their jobs than were
pessimistic. Particularly we asked
workers about the impact of automation
on their safety and comfort at work on
their upward mobility. And it was it was
there's a big gap actually much more
workers who were optimistic than
pessimistic. When it came to job
security, workers were were still a
little more wary, but there were more
workers optimistic about their job
security than pessimistic. And this
frankly is because a lot of the workers
we surveyed were generally happy at
work. We had pretty high job
satisfaction across these countries. And
I think it's easy to forget that that's
true in in most environments that job
satisfaction is pretty high. In the
United States, it's over 60%.
So what did we learn? What's the
difference between the group that was
optimistic about automation, willing to
champion it versus the group that was
pessimistic. The first thing we wanted
to know was does this vary across place.
And what we found was yes, it does. And
in in European environments, um there
was actually much more optimism about
the role of technology in shaping their
work than in the United States for
example where we were the most
pessimistic about the adoption of new
technologies and its impact on work. I
would imagine it's based on some other
some other data that if we surveyed
Chileans, they would be much look much
more like the Europeans than like the
Americans in this in this survey. But
beyond just the the geography, we asked
workers based on their tasks how they
thought about automation. And our
expectation was that workers who do a
lot of routine tasks, things over and
over again, would feel vulnerable to
automation and would resist it. Whereas
workers who did a lot of different
things during the day, they wouldn't
feel vulnerable to automation. they
might be more interested in new
technologies. But what we found was
actually something a little bit
different. We found that and I'm going
to focus for this audience on the
physical industries. So think think
mining, think um agriculture,
manufacturing, logistics,
that we when we looked at workers with
high level of routine tasks and low
problem solving, so workers really wrote
jobs, they were indeed very pessimistic
about automation and its impact on their
work. But if we looked at workers with
the same level of routine tasks, so
people who were doing a lot of the same
thing over and over again, but still had
to do some problem solving, when the
workers had to do problem solving, their
perceptions totally flipped. They were
the most optimistic about automation,
its impact on their work. So I think the
implication here and what I think we can
learn from this data is that if you
design jobs and this goes back to the
the control room environment. If you
design jobs to focus on high levels of
problem solving, workers in those
environments might be more open to
adopting new technologies and figuring
out how they can make it work. And our
explanation for this is if you have a
high level of problem solving, you feel
confident that you're still going to be
able to have discretion at work and
you're still going to be able to have
kind of a purpose and grow in your job.
And the way you can use automation is to
get rid of those pesky routine tasks.
That technology really can be helpful
for you in that way without being a
threat. Whereas workers here, technology
might might be helpful, but it might
also be a threat because you don't have
the problem solving that might help you
grow in your job. Okay.
All right. So, so I talked about, you
know, the role of people in in helping
make automation work and the role of
redesigning jobs. So, we can't just take
a job that existed in a manual
environment and a person with those
skills and necessity
intensive environment. That does not
seem to work based on our historical
evidence. So, what does work? What are
the skills compositions that we see um
successful? So this was a paper that
came out of what might seem like a very
different industry, but I think it's
relevant here. And it's it's hospital
systems. So over the last 10 to 15
years, hospital systems have invested
pretty significantly in automating the
routine tasks of administration through
technologies, a family of technologies
called robotic process automation. Now
there's some more AI involved in these
in these technologies. And what we found
in comparing different hospital systems
and their approaches to using these
tools was that a lot of their their uh a
lot of these deployments of new
technology focused on specific use cases
or focused on specific technologies but
they had difficulty scaling up across
the system. So in the mining context it
might be like you could provide a
control room environment for one type of
task or one type of operator but you
couldn't necessarily look at the whole
system in an integrated way. And we
wondered why that was the case. And we
realized that when the hospital system
designed jobs to work in an automated
environment, they they made one of two
decisions. They either really focused on
people with process knowledge, so people
who know knew what it looked like to do
that task well, or it focused on
investing people with engineering
knowledge, with a lot of technical
skills. And those people really knew
what the technology was capable of. But
rarely did they really build a kind of a
multid-disciplinary team that had both
process knowledge and technical
knowledge that could develop the kind of
flexible automation that scaled up more
successfully. And this was this was very
difficult because you could think of
these the process knowledge and the
technical knowledge is two very
different languages and it takes a lot
of time and it actually the people who
know both of those languages can demand
pretty high wages. So the challenge here
isn't necessarily to train the unicorn
type person who can do everything, but
instead to build kind of channels of
translation across those two different
types of workers. And and I I want to
emphasize two real I think important
skills for um these teams that I'm
talking about these multi-disiplinary
teams that can scale up automated
systems. The first set of skills is in
experimentation. And why experimentation
is important is what we talk about when
we're talking about deploying new
technology is a pretty dramatic change
to a system. And when you're changing a
system, you need to be able to
understand what's working and what's
not. And our best way of understanding
the impact of different changes that we
make is experimentation. So the the
skills associated with experimentation
are not just kind of how do you um do
the statistics to understand is there a
significant improvement in your
performance. It's really about
understanding what question you want to
answer in the first place. What are the
metrics that you want to improve upon?
And that requires process knowledge.
Whereas the actual running of the
experiment, the collection of data might
require technical knowledge. So this is
is the first kind of skill that requires
a bridging of these two types of
knowledge. And the second is
interpretation. And I'll come back to
this in a moment with with generative
AI. But one of the I think the misguided
uh arguments around generative AI today
is that you need to be skilled in the AI
itself. You need to know what's going on
under the hood. You need to have pretty
deep technical skills to be able to use
these technologies well. And what I
think that argument ignores is that one
of the key skills of being able to
interact with new technologies is to
interpret whether the data the
technology is providing is useful or
relevant to the key challenges that
you're trying to meet. So if you use
generative AI to try to identify a
better approach to a mining task, you
need to know quite a lot about mining to
understand if the generative AI is full
of it or if it's providing something
really uh useful and insightful. Okay.
So, finally, I want to say a little bit
about this this current wave of
technologies that's captured a lot of
people's interest and attention, what we
know about it currently and what we
still uh need to learn. So, first I
talked a bit about robots and and
robotic process automation and the
characteristics of those technologies
are quite a bit different from the
current uh large language model
technologies. So if we think about two
two features of a technology, its
reliability, its ability to do the same
task over and over again versus its
flexibility, it's it's the quickness and
dexterity with which it can move across
tasks. We have robots are very good at
doing the same thing over and over
again. And for a long time, kind of
before we applied some of these machine
learning tools, they weren't very good
at flexibility. So the role of of human
workers, the role of human machine
interaction was to add flexibility to to
robots that were quite reliable. But
with LMS, and many of you probably know
this from interacting with them, they
can answer all sorts of questions.
They'll answer almost any question you
give them. They'll give it you different
form factors back. They'll answer in
different languages. Um, but what the
challenge is is to get them to answer in
the same way, in a reliable way. And
oftentimes the answers might be
different and they're not predictable in
how they're different. So this is one of
the the big challenges. Now
you know one of the early questions that
we had when we started studying this um
kind of the role of generative AI and
reshaping work. We we gathered a bunch
of companies and we tried to understand
what experiments they were performing
with generative AI. Where were they
using it? And we heard a few consistent
things. We heard that they were using it
in customer service. We heard that their
software engineers were using these
tools. And then as we were asking our 50
or so companies about their use cases,
Enthropic, the company that uh makes the
Claude uh chatbot, they came out with
this really uh interesting study where
they took all of the conversations with
Claude from their non-commercial uh
users and they said they tried to link
these conversations to different tasks
and then they linked those tasks to
jobs. And what they tried to learn was
what what job what occupation does the
person most likely have who is having
this conversation you know what's the
nature of this conversation and what
they found apologies for the the size of
this but I can share these slides if
you're interested was that the high
concentration of the the chats with claw
the use of LLMs were in just a few
occupations they were in the computer
and mathematical occupations you can
think of that as just as coding so over
a third of all claude conversations were
coding related, about half were either
coding or research related
conversations, and then you get up to
twothirds if you add in kind of
marketing and writing tasks. So a a
segment of the workforce that's only
about 10 to 15% of workers was having
about twothirds of the generative AI
conversations. So as of now, what I want
to emphasize is that the the use of
these technology tools has been very
concentrated in a pretty small segment
of the workforce and a pretty small
segment of firms. Now
the other thing that I I I think caveat
I want to throw out about this
technology is that a lot of advocates of
generative AI, a lot of the generative
AI companies are talking about the
continuous improvement of these models.
They often share how the latest and
greatest model can do uh kind of solve a
scientific problem that the previous
models couldn't. They could do more and
more complex tasks. They talk about
reasoning.
But what they don't talk about is that
as these models have improved in some
dimensions, they've actually gotten
worse in in others. So this is OpenAI's
uh publicly available release about its
its reasoning models. And what what it
shows is both that what these reasoning
models can do that's new, which is which
is exciting. And it also shows that the
accuracy rates and the the accuracy
rates of these models have gone down and
the hallucination rates of these models
have gone up. So what we see is a real
trade-off that as these models become
better in certain domains, they become
worse in others. So I think when you
might hear from their advocates, you
know, this is the worst AI we're ever
going to have, these models are going to
get better and better. Hallucinations
are going to get lower and lower. I
think we really need to scrutinize that
and look at the data and ask why uh
hallucination rates continue to go up
even as these models improve. And AI,
open AI has been asked why this is the
case. and they don't have an explanation
partly because they can't always
understand why their models are giving
the answers that they do. All right.
Okay. So now I I want to you know end
with a few examples that I think are are
really promising from these technologies
and and I think might be relevant to the
industries that that you represent. One
is that a lot of the early use cases of
these technologies have emphasized the
ability to do certain tasks faster than
you might have been able to do them
before. So you can now uh you know write
u you know write code you can you could
program u you can write a program faster
than you could previously or you can
maybe write a memo faster than you could
previously with just a few prompts. But
what I think is important is that speed
is not always the right measure. So this
is a study of of doctors making uh
diagnoses with the benefit of chat GPT.
And what it found was that doctors who
had access to chat GPT actually made
their diagnosis slower than doctors who
made their diagnosis just based on their
memory and their training. But the
doctors who were slower also were mo
more likely to give a thorough and an
accurate diagnosis. So what we care
about the metric we care about with
doctors isn't are you the fastest, it's
really are you going to come up with the
right answer the highest share of the
time. So, I do think that we, you know,
that users of these technologies always
need to think, what are you using them
for? Are you using them just because
they're exciting and they're this newest
tool and, you know, I have a new hammer
and I'm going to go look for nails, or
are you using them to really get better
at the core purpose of your work? And in
this case, the core purpose was to
become more accurate. Second, I want to
emphasize that the the nature of how
people are doing their work is changing
when they have access to these tools. So
this comes from a survey asking people
about the different kind of tasks and
how they're doing them when they when
they start using generative AI tools.
And what it shows is that people are are
accessing really different parts of
their brain when they're using
generative AI than if they were doing
these tasks on their own. And I think
this is kind of intuitive and obvious,
but it's it's important that now that we
have some more detailed data on how um
the access to these tools are different
than even access to a search engine like
Google with how our brain is
functioning. So the most recent study of
this compares three groups. People doing
a research task on their own by memory,
people doing it with access to Google
search and then people doing it with
access to a chat GPT like tool. And then
they they looked they did a scan of
these people's brains as they were doing
the work. And what they found is that
that the the people uh who were doing
the research task on their own there
were all sorts of kind of neurons firing
with their in their brains all sorts of
neural connections but the people who
were doing the work with chat GPT had
very little brain activity at all. They
did the task quite quickly. Um but they
they weren't actually activating their
brain. And as a result, when the
researchers asked about the task they
had just done afterward, the people who
had done the task with chat GPT couldn't
really recall what they had just done.
They didn't really remember it. It
didn't sink in compared to the people
who had done it on their own. So again,
there there might be productivity uh tra
productivity benefits, there might be
quality benefits, but there are
trade-offs necessarily for workers and
how they're developing their skills that
I think we need to be concerned about. I
think we need to guard against. And one
way to think about it that that I like
is really thinking of these tools uh you
know like a new type of food. So we have
processed food this is really processed
information and just as processed food
can be healthy or unhealthy right some
processed food might taste really good
in the short term but actually have
negative health effects in the long term
but other processed food could be a
cheaper way of getting really essential
nutrition like vitamins. Right? So the
question is how does this how do we use
these tools to get us the essential
nutrition that helps us in the long term
and helps us grow as people and as
workers versus using this tool in a way
that leads to skill atrophy and and kind
of cognitive decay. So
I'm going to you know end here with a
comparison that I think is really
important. A lot of our data on how
humans can work best with machines comes
from early evidence from uh airline
pilots and and even military pilots kind
of the the cockpit environment that
became more and more automated over
time. So how do you design an automated
system? How do you design a control
room? A lot of that research comes out
of the study of um of aerospace. And I
think a lot of the kind of the core
lessons from about 50 years ago still
really apply and how we should think
about the interaction between humans and
machines. And the first is that you can
automate too much. And when you automate
too much, what that does is it reduces
the situational awareness of the person
such that they become worse at their job
when you really need them to be expert.
So when something goes wrong in the
mind, you need the operator to have
excellent skills and a complete
awareness of what's going on in the
system and you you can't automate so
much that their awareness goes down and
they don't have access to the right data
that they can interpret. So maintaining
situational awareness is really
important even if you have to sacrifice
some automation and and the example of
of cockpits for example, if you've been
in a cockpit recently, you know, they
don't have a bunch of, you know, tablet
screens that are perfectly automated.
the plane really could fly itself but
they've dialed back in the automation
particularly because they want the pilot
to be locked in and very skilled when
they need the pilot. The second is that
the you know good human machine
interaction really requires a balance of
the cognitive load. You don't want to
overload the human with information such
that they can't process it and they kind
of throw their hands up. But you also
don't want the the human to be on
essentially autopilot and just clicking
yes or clicking no and in response to
certain tasks that humans human workers
who are engaged in that middle range
find their jobs more fulfilling and are
also more able to you know maintain the
situational awareness that's required in
an emergency. And then finally, and and
I I touched on this that you really need
to guard against skill atrophy that in
order to use technology successfully,
the the organizations that we've seen
scale up their automation are really
learning organizations, they continue to
invest in the skills and capabilities of
their workers such that they can avoid
the potential trade-offs of these tools.
And finally, I want to, you know, if I
leave you with one point today, I I want
to, you know, make this, I think,
counterintuitive argument that the
success for an organization using
technology
is it has something to do with the
technology. Yes. But you know, your
organization and your competitor
organizations in many ways, they have
access to the same technology tools,
right? The a lot of the technologies
that organizations are adopting are
commodities and your comparative
advantage isn't with the technology
necessarily. it's with your people and
how your people can adapt the
technology, the skills they have to use
it effectively and the skills they have
really to translate it into your domain.
So that that's really critically
important here. And and and finally, you
know, the the image that we started with
with one person in a control room, we
know that that's not the best scenario
in part because one person alone rarely
can be as innovative and and successful
as many people working together. And and
this is the kind of the evidence of of
knowledge spillovers that we have from
all different types of industries, all
different types of environments that
when you get a lot of talented people
with complimentary expertise together,
we don't really know why it happens, but
great creative things tend to happen. So
even in an automated environment, having
people close together exchanging
information, learning from each other
really remains critical and and I I hope
will remain critical well into the
future. So thank you so much and I would
be glad to take your questions.
Thank you Ben for your presentation. We
have some questions for you now. Please
put this for the questions.
>> I think so.
>> Okay. It's okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Are you okay? Yeah.
We're going to hear questions now.
Ben Armstrong,
executive director of MIT. Okay, we have
some questions for you now, Ben.
The question is,
how can we move forward
in knowing the skills that will be
required
in an uncertain world?
So
again with the caveat that uh I have
very little capability in predicting the
future but I I instead would like to
think of preparing for the future. I
agree that there's that we have an
uncertain world in terms of what are
going to be the dominant technologies of
10 to 20 to 30 years from now. What will
be the dominant designs of those
technologies? you know, we have large
language models, but we don't really
know how we're going to be using them in
the long term. I think a lot of the ways
that we use computers and the internet
today, we couldn't have anticipated when
when they were first introduced. But
with that uncertainty, we also know that
there have been certain kind of skills
and important practices of organizations
that have been quite consistent
throughout time. And one of those um has
to do with creativity and
entrepreneurship. So if you look at
entrepreneurial practices around
experimentation and continuous
improvement going back to the 1800s, a
lot of the entrepreneurs and and how
they approached building their
businesses um in the late 1800s was
actually it's actually quite similar to
how tech entrepreneurs did in the 2000s
and how hard tech entrepreneurs like
some of the folks you've seen today um
are approaching their businesses. So
some of those types of uh skills and
approaches to growing a business and and
experimentation I think is the key skill
I have mentioned today are they seem
timeless at least they've been timeless
uh for the last 100 plus years and and
that kind of that reasoning from history
is how I think we could be best prepared
for an uncertain future.
>> Thank you Rodrigo.
The second question for you, Ben.
After visiting our sites, what do you
think about our sites? How do we
progress with more technology to be more
productive?
>> So, it was a it was a great pleasure to
visit um your site yesterday. I I told
my my wife and kids that it felt a bit
like being on Mars where there was a
sense of kind of exploration and it was
uh like nothing I had seen before. Um
and it was very exciting to see. Now
with that said, you know, when we were
watching the autonomous vehicles, and I
think it was different yesterday than it
normally is, um I saw a lot of the
similar kind of um similar challenges
with autonomy or or similar um maybe uh
a similar design to how we see
autonomous mobile robots deployed in
warehouses where sometimes they they get
on the same route and they're less
flexible than they could be. So, one of
the questions I have is how do you get
from in a mining environment, which I
know very little about mining, um, but I
I I know a little bit about automation,
how would you take a deterministic
automated system and try to make it more
flexible? And one way you do that is by
adding kind of new data and new skills
into that system and and kind of you
could do it with software, not
necessarily with with uh with new
hardware, which I know that that
hardware is very expensive and very
capable um, as it stands. I don't know
if that's a satisfying question, but I
I'm I I think I'm still processing and
learning from the visit, and I I look
forward to talking to some of the
colleagues here today to to put more
context around what we saw.
>> Ben Armstrong,
thank you for your answers. Thank you
for your words.
Armstrong