Welcome
back. So, it's my absolute pleasure to
introduce Dr. Ricardo Mororrow Pinto.
Um, he's an assistant professor of
neurology at Harvard Medical School. In
addition to that, he's a Brody who's a
member of the MPG program. He also runs
a lab um at the center for genomic
medicine at MGB um where he is focused
on neurogenerative diseases including
Friedri's itexia and Huntington
Huntington's disease and he'll tell you
more about um his research today. Thanks
Ricardo
m perfect thank you so much for the
invitation to present our work here. Um
so um just quick disclosure so as Julian
mentioned we're very much interested in
repeat expansion diseases and uh I'll
touch a little bit on on um Huntington's
disease which is a autotosomal um
dominant disorder caused by u a cagg
expansion in the htt1 in the htt gene in
exxon one and once you inherit uh an
expansion beyond about 40 cag repeats
you'll develop uh hingtons at some point
in your life and uh the disease is
primarily characterized by uh neuronal
loss uh throughout the brain but
primarily in the
striatum as you can appreciate here the
atrophy in in the brain and um
interestingly that there's a strong
relationship between the length of the
repeat and the severity of the disease.
So the longer the repeat, the earlier
you'll develop symptoms and uh you'll
also have a faster and more severe
progression. And this the disease can
manifest in a variety of different ways
uh primarily motor symptoms but also
cognitive and u and
behavioral. And an interesting aspect
about these repeats is that they're
unstable. So common phenomenon in
Huntington's disease is called
anticipation. So meaning from generation
to generation patients tend to develop
the disease earlier than their parents.
And this is primarily because the repeat
changes from generation to generation.
And as you can see here from maternal
transmission is sort of stable. So the
child will have more or less the same
repeat as the mother had. But if the
transmission is from the father, there's
a higher chance that it will expand and
it will become much longer and therefore
that the child will end up developing
the disease
earlier. But something that hasn't been
so well appreciated is also the fact
that the repeat is also unstable in the
brain. It it's not just in the germline
but also sematically in in the brain.
And you're seeing here uh a brain from
an individual that died not from HD.
This is a brain uh about 13 years before
the predicted onset. So there's no real
signs of um neuro degeneration in this
brain. But you already see some neurons
or some cells from what you can
appreciate here that have expanded
drastically beyond the two inherited al.
So this would be the wild type. These
would be the mutant alil and you can see
expansions all the way up to a
thousand. Uh and this starts in the
strium. This is a different brain late
stage uh heavily degenerated. Um and it
it starts uh you start seeing it
throughout the brain. This uh
instability is present in different
parts of the brain. Um and stratum in
this particular brain strikingly low.
But the hypothesis that at this point
you hardly have any neurons left. most
of the stridum is gone. Um so you're
you're not really seeing it. And I'll
present a couple of data. Some of you
you're probably aware of some of Carol's
work, but um there's been some focus on
trying to understand exactly where this
is occurring at the cell type specific
matter. Uh and two studies that came out
in the last couple of years, one by Nat
Hines group in Rockefeller, uh where
they did fan sorting. So they enrich for
different uh neuron different cell types
from the brain and size the CG repeating
each of these enriched populations and u
you can see that in medium spiny neurons
which are the the the neurons that are
primarily affected in Huntington's
disease accumulate these
repeats and and Steve validated that
with with a independent approach with
single cell level uh sizing the the the
neurons um um characterizing the the the
different cell types based on
transcriptional um information and but
realizing that these large expansions
are only present in medium spiny
neurons. But interesting what this
allowed um uh this single cell
resolution allowed to ask a different
question. How um different are these
neurons from each other? these medium
spiny neurons. And turns out they're
they're not that sick. They're not that
different. Uh neurons that have these uh
CAG repeats that are 40 that we would
consider pathogenic. They're
indistinguishable as they increase in
size and it's only once they cross a
certain threshold of about 150 cages
that become dysfunctional and then they
die.
So this is very very important because
changes completely the way we understand
the disease and how we approach it from
a therapeutic point of
view and and it makes a lot of sense
also to intersect it with genomewide
association data. So data from patients
um um all the way from the the last 10
years going up from 4,000s all the way
to 16,000 patients and and this is not
the traditional GI was this is not a
case control. These are all patients and
we're just looking for the effect of uh
um the effect on age of onset. What this
so these are would be modifier um genes
and we're starting to see a pattern.
Most of these are DNA repair genes. Um
you do find Huntington gene and I'll get
into that later. This is an interruption
in the uh in the gene. But most of the
other uh genes that are coming up are
DNA repair
genes. And this was very interesting
when we started looking at this because
this was actually something that we had
already discovered in the mouse. So in
genetic crosses with mice, we knew that
some of these genes were essential for
this uh sematic expansion. So when we
cross an HD mouse with an MLH1 knockout
or with an MLH3 knockout mouse, we were
completely abolishing. So this is um
expansion just a different way of
quantifying the CAG expansions. uh this
would be the inherited al this would be
expansion. When you knock out these
genes, you completely abolish the the
expansion. So you stabilize the
repeat. And this led us to build a model
at the time that was fairly incomplete
and uh but we with the poor
understanding we had of that model and
the the increasing number of genes that
were coming out of the GI was we wanted
to try to establish a functional role.
most of them we didn't really know what
function they had in Huntington's
disease. So we we designed um a crisper
screen an invivo crisper screen um where
we cross our HDMI with a
nozzogously and then we just have to
deliver the guides of interest in an
AV HD animal so that we allow expansions
to either uh occur
or stabilize them if we turn off a gene
that is um a driver of instability.
and and this is just a a validation
experiment. So we're seeing here that
these just different way of quantifying
this. We can convert this into a into an
index the rate of instability. So we
know that it is age dependent. It keeps
getting larger and larger uh in the
striatum. Um and um actually this is
data in liver at this point. uh we
leveraged the fact that AV8 uh is very
strong at transducing the liver and the
the instability is also occurring in the
liver. Um and we noticed that if we
knocked out the genes that were um
essential for driving expansions, we
completely stabilized the repeat all the
way to the same level that when we
started the experiment. Conversely, fan
one, which is a strong modifier that
came out of the the patient uh GI was we
accelerate the rate of
expansion. So here showing the the
result of the screen. This is data
coming from about 600 mice, total of 60
genes. Um and we we probed a variety of
different genes coming from the GI was
data set. Uh and a variety of different
DNA repair pathways and some of them
coming from the literature. Uh but so we
proed a these different 60 genes and
ranked them based on effect on sematic
expansions. And interestingly what we're
still find is exactly the same. It's the
mismatch repair uh pathway that is uh
either stabilizing or accelerating the
rate of
expansion. And
here at this point we were only doing it
in in the liver. It's it's a
neurological disease. We we um
collaborated with with Ben Everman. We
packaged this in PHP to to uh target the
the stryatum and we we could validate
these genes and in um in the
brain alternative ways of validating. We
actually for some of these they were
novel targets like PMS1. We generated
the the the mice and we we crossed them
um with our HD mice and we observed that
PMS1 is an essential gene. It it's um
it's not as strong of an effect as some
of the genes but it's significantly
reduced instability in u in the in the
brain.
Um and we we validated we collaborated
with Gazella lab to develop a cell model
of of expansions. So in culture the
repeat would expand in a in a short
period of time and when we knock out uh
these modifier genes we can either
stabilize it over time or accelerate it
and we can use it to validate our denovo
sort of hits.
still from the point of view of
mechanism exactly how this occurs um
we're very interested in in a gene MLH3
um because of of
um of its role as a as an
endonucleaz so we wanted to know because
there was still a question about does it
only require these proteins to be
recruited to the these secondary
structures or do you need catalytic
activity so uh we've used a mouse model
that had point mutation in the
endonucleus domain that's still
expressed it still forms a dimer but um
um question does it still promote
expansions and the answer is no if you
if you have no endonucleaz activity you
completely stabilize the repeat um so
interesting this also provides and it's
become clearer later but it provides us
a different way of how to target these
genes and and this is we just recently
published this but it's sort of uh uh
our current understanding of how this
occurs. So we in red here we have the
CAG uh repeats um during transcription
or during replication in neurons it
would be during transcription you'll
unwind um the DNA and you'll have um
propensity to form these slipped strand
structures these hairpin structures that
get primarily recognized by MSH2 MSH3 or
mutas beta and then recruit other
components of the mute the the different
mutel um components uh of mismatch
repair. We believe that MLH3 is required
to cut the opposite strand. Um and then
uh you'll have a polymerase delta which
is also a gene that I didn't have time
to go into that came out of our screen
to uh synthesize a new copy of the DNA.
And by doing so in both strands you add
uh additional
repeats and um as I mentioned at the
beginning we're very much interested in
repeat expansions uh and it's not we
primarily work on Huntington's disease
and ftheraxi but this is a group of as
many as 60 u uh different rare diseases.
Um so here that you've got the the cagg
CTG uh repeats that tend to form
hairpins the Huntington's disease spinal
cerebellar at taxia monic distrophe and
um fuks coral distrophe um but then you
have others as well that are um a little
bit longer so something I didn't mention
they can occur the variety of different
locations both coding or non-coding u
just in regulatory regions um they can
have a variety different lengths of CAG
repeats in Huntington's disease around
40 to 60 CAG repeats at majority of
patients but other diseases are in the
thousands that that have a repeat and
another interesting aspect is that
depending on their sequence they can
form a variety of different secondary
structures we believe that that's what's
u makes them likely to be uh recognized
by the DNA repair machinery and
expand but because they they all have
sematic instability We also want to
leverage can we identify a common
genetic uh therapeutic target that would
pro possibly be uh have therapeutic
value not only to Huntington's disease
but a variety of other repeat expansion
disease.
So we performed the same similar
experiments, similar screens um and
summarizing here just those results for
Huntington's disease from Friders taxi
which is a GA repeat and fragile legs.
We're doing this now in in spinal cerell
or ataxia one as well and we're trying
to combine this data to try to
understand in what directions this this
modify the the
instability and we've identified a few
uh want to caution that you know it's
tricky thing to target DNA repair uh
it's there for a reason uh we think in
this case it's actually misreping um but
to we need to be careful because some of
these are actually quite strongly
associated with with cancer particularly
colon cancer. Um but there are three
that are very minimal uh effect or many
very little uh documented um
implications for cancer. They're
primarily involved in spermatogenesis in
replication um in uh in biotic
recombination. Um but so we've
identified these three particular genes
that we're kind of excited and the field
is also uh excited
about. Um few examples on how we can
target these. I'll give you a quick one
on how to use a small molecule a splice
modulator something that was actually uh
under um testing for Huntington's
disease but with Huntington's disease as
being the target. So just as a
Huntington lowering strategy, one of its
offt targets is actually PMS1, one of
the the genes that we've shown as a
modifier. Um, and we can see that with
with this drug, we can reduce the level
of PMS1 and we can also reduce the
effect on
instability here. just sort of
validating the the therapeutic effect uh
of uh so transcriptional disregulation
and and also accumulation of mutant
protein. Um the when you knock out PMS1
you reduce the accumulation of the of
the mutant protein in the nucleus the
strumm and also you you sort of rescue
some of these transcriptional changes.
So uh sort of validating this
therapeutic um um
target. Um going back to MLH3 um we
we're particularly excited about this
because
uh knowing the the
the dependency on the endonucleus
activity and the fact that this gene is
expressed as two variants, one
containing the endonucleus and one
without through alternative splicing. um
collaborated with with Ed Grabzik to use
ASOS to sort of favor the splicing of
this gene towards the endonucleus
lacking
um
version. And interestingly, this is even
expressed uh um in in
some regions you have the endonucleus
lacking um version expressed at higher
levels than the one containing the
endonucleus.
and and and briefly u try to go through
this quickly because we've tested these
with ASOS and we could suppress sematic
expansions with ASOS but they we
couldn't use them so well preclinally um
we couldn't get them to target the the
brain as effectively uh even though
we're able to reduce sematic expansions
in the kidney um it
um it it wasn't as easy to to do with
NASO and uh based on our collaborations
with with David Lou and with Ben
Kleinstever we sort of pivoted um with
this strategy still keeping the same
target and the same mechanism but with a
with a different
approach and we hypothesized that given
how conserved splice acceptors are
across species we hypothesize that we
simply disrupt did this ag sequence we
would be able to um um alter the the
splicing of that region. So we as I
mentioned collaborated with with David
who's invented base editors and and
don't need much of an introduction here
and with Ben Kleinstever who has
engineered these uh enzymes so that they
can recognize a variety of different PAM
domain. So we can essentially target
different regions in the genome and not
necessarily limited to an an NG
PAM. So how did we do this? We
essentially tile the entire region with
a variety of different guides uh with a
variety of different ABS and a variety
of different
CBEs and uh fortunately we we identified
a couple that actually were seem to be
quite effective um in hex cells and this
is what we've been pursuing further with
in
u further validation. Importantly, we've
showed that a single point mutation um
is a is uh sufficient to completely
change the splicing. So, we no longer
have any uh expression of the transcript
that has the
endonucleaz. And in fact when we test is
in a in a in a cell line that has
instability. So you can see here across
a month of culture the repeat expands
when we have this single point mutation
we completely stabilize
it. Um next we've already started our
preclinical work. We have to generate
the mouse model. So rather than testing
this and and using guides towards the
mouse sequencing, we've um we've
engineered a mouse that contains the
human uh sequence flanking it.
Interestingly, and this is something
that curious biology just changing these
30 base pairs, we we all of a sudden the
mouse is splicing like a human um cell
would. So all of a sudden we now mice
normally just express variant one and
all of a sudden with this humanized
sequence there there's alternative
splicing performed very quickly
preclinical work with with some um I
would say not optimal uh AEV preps. Um
this is something that we still need to
to repeat but um we identified a couple
of animals where we had decent editing
in the stridum.
um we show that in this rumm we're
altering the splicing and more
importantly we're reducing the
instability by 40% even with these uh
sort of poor AV preps. So we're quite
excited about this um um and moving it
forward. Again important considerations
here is uh really terms of safety and in
terms of delivery. These are things that
still need a lot of work.
Um I'll uh won't touch too much here but
here just going another example of our
collaborations here at the broad uh and
giving you
um a different
strategy also targeting expansions we
know that individuals with interruptions
and uh in the middle of the cag repeat
develop the disease later. So um work
done by Janera here at the David's lab
hypothesized that if we were to use base
editors to introduce these silent um uh
CA interruptions within the CAG repeat
we would slow down
instability and in fact we do and um so
when we have about um 30 40% editing in
in the strumm we can reduce the rate of
expansions and also promote the rate of
contractions. Um, so just a a little bit
of a a cartoonish overview. Uh, we think
that throughout the life of an
individual, the CAG repeats keep
expanding in a cell type specific manner
until they hit a third certain threshold
where it starts becoming toxic and
causing neurodeeneration. you start
losing these neurons and upon a certain
time that will manifest as symptoms. Um
we from the genomewide association study
we hypothesize that there are certain
genetic variants that will change the
rate of that process how fast the repeat
expands or how slow it expands and it
will manifest as different ages of
onset. And so we hypothesize that if we
use a therapeutic to slow down or stop
sematic expansions, you will either slow
the progression or if you go before
onset and you're effective enough in
stabilizing the repeats that you can
effectively cure these
diseases. And so with that, I want to
thank um everyone in the lab, our
collaborators and and the funding and
letters to cures for support. Thank you.
As we mentioned, we'll do uh Q&A um
jointly. So, our next speaker is Dr. Jen
Pan. Jen is the director of
translational neurobiology here at the
Broad Institute in the Stanley Center um
where her lab focuses on um high
throughput evaluation of ion channel
physiology and next generation
therapeutics. Um importantly, she's also
an adviser to the Kacno 1A Foundation
whose leadership is in the audience
today. Um, welcome Jen.
Hello. Thank you so much Jillian um for
that introduction and I wanted to thank
Anna and Julian for organizing such a
fantastic symposium. It has been
inspiring to hear the messages, the
approach, uh the research and stories.
So uh today I'm going to talk to you
about one of my favorite genes 1A which
encodes a an ion channel. um a as an
example of how we think about rare
genetic um coding changes with
intermediate effect size uh is going to
contribute to the disease burden. How we
think about the um uh treatment
strategy. Okay, there we go. So uh I
wanted to start with a few words about
channelopathy. The monogenic medelion uh
uh mutations that causing diseases in
ion channels has been studied since the
beginning of the molecular genetics.
These are recurring mutations produce a
common shared disease phenotype and then
there are many reports of such. there
are very few mutations but once it
happens it produce very repeatable uh
very common uh disease phenotype and
then in the past two decades a China op
in complex polygenic disorders has been
discussed and has been discovered by the
G-W was um on the right here is a figure
that was published 15 years ago by Steve
Mccara and Peter Fishell and many others
they uh demonstrated that at that time
there might be missing heritability from
G-Wall studies. Uh are these rare and
low frequency coding variations in in um
with intermediate effect size in this
spectrum of the disease and um this is
what I'm going to focus on today. Uh so
why do we care about these rare and
intermediate um uh uh frequency
intermediate effect size low and rare
frequency uh rare coding uh varants and
so so fast forward 15 years to where we
are now our ability to detect them has
increased exponentially. So here is a
figure of how many um sea variants has
been identified in the past 20 years and
you can see with the DNA sequencing exom
sequencing we have starting to see
hundreds of the variants but many of
them with unknown uh function. So
annotating a large number of coding
variants are necessary um
to explore in a cohort in a a set
disease cohort sets has been become
accessible and we have increasingly able
to identify these low frequency coding
alals and channel opt is a great place
to start addressing the connection
between genetics and functional
consequences because ion channels they
have these assays to precisely
um study their function by
electrphysiology using patch clamp. So
you can get very detailed look at the
functional outcome uh the voltage
dependence of activation uh uh or lian
binding or kinetics of how they open how
they close and then in addition to that
annotating using this class of uh
proteins as an example uh annotating a
large number of them can be very
powerful to further um propel the human
genetic study of complex diseases as as
well as stratifying patient population.
Uh they're very critical to identify the
patient to go after the treatment and
design the precise um treatment. So with
that introduction
uh this is what I'm going to talk about
today. Uh these are
uh so here is outline. So first I'll
introduce what is a kac1a spectrum
disorder and then I'll describe to you
uh a a a couple of studies addressing
the missense misssense changes of
kakuana in a cohort of
neurodedevelopmental disorder and then
the results what can we learn from this
study in a cohort study of
neurodedevelopmental disorder and uh our
subsequent analysis trying to link the
molecular phenotype with the clinical
phenotype and then Lastly uh for a few
slides I'll talk about the strategies
towards a potential therapy and
potential nodal mechanisms underlying
these uh coding varants as um uh uh
powered by the letter to cure as a
pilot. So first of all what is keen1a?
KNO1A encodes a PQ type cal uh it's a
voltage gated calcium channel. It's a
2.1 voltage gated calcium channels and
then there are 10 genes encoding these
large transmembrane proteins. They
respond to voltage um changes and are
expressed throughout the excitable uh
cells in the body. Many of them are
expressed in the uh brain as you can
imagine because neurons communicate with
electrical signals. So keen 1A is right
here. uh it's one of the this is
family the cap one family cap 2 family
and cap 3. So kak1a is right here it's
expressed widely throughout the central
nervous system and also present in the
peripheral nervous system. It mediates
the neurotransmitter release at the
majority of the pressaptic terminals in
the central nervous system and mediate
excitability uh both neurotransmission
and at the uh soma for the excitability.
The reason it was was originally called
Ptype channel is because it was
initially identified in piking cells and
then back then that that was uh
initially called ptype channels and then
the structure of uh the let me see if I
can uh it doesn't play um the structure
of the kek1a has been
um published and then so this could be a
starting point for uh structural
assisted uh rational design and it's
also one advantage when we're going
after the precision medicine. So this is
a uh a table that I take from technoma
foundation. Uh there are many um
phenotypes or clinical manifestations
that have been annotated for people with
kag1a mutations.
Some of them has been well described for
example the hemiplatic uh familial uh
hemopleic migraine some of them are
sporadic and sometimes you see them in
the people harboring these mutations
sometimes you don't and it's spread
across uh quite a different domain so
it's very difficult to grasp in in what
is the connection between the mutation
or what type of mutation to the clinical
manifestation. So we started to ask the
question utilizing a um a published
result of the um neurodedevelopmental
disorder. So what we did in this context
is to take uh the axom changes in the
cacao 1A from a 31,000 trail patients.
Okay. So in this cohort 49 individuals
has contained misssense changes and only
four individuals with protein truncating
variants. So misssense changes are
dominating in this in this cohort. Uh a
few variants have been documented before
but the majority of them are with
unknown
function. Okay. Um so we take this
entire alic series of denovo mutations
of the kac no 1a and uh summarized here
including the 42 unique denovo variants
and this is coming from 36 unique coding
changes that I just described to you
from the previous cohort and we added
six additional novel denovo mischange
coming from the clinic in uh Dr. Hbiggs
in chop and then Dr. the jury at uh
Boston Children's. This con comprised of
42 unique denovo mutations. Taken
together, we also added eight most
frequent missense changes in the general
population and we wanted to include the
nomad mutation to give us a sense of
what the true wild type range of that
functional activity is. And then here is
a topology of the channel where um for
those of you who are not familiar with
this large protein, they're roughly
divided into four transmembrane domains
and each domain is uh uh composed of the
six trans membrane segment and then they
come together wrapped together to form
the central ionic pole um in the middle.
So here uh the the red dots represent
the disease associated missense changes
across the channel. You can see most of
them are located in the transmembrane
region and then the green dots are
represented um
here representing the nomad variants and
then they're mostly uh located actually
in the loop region and right here you
see some segregation of where the
mutations um coming
from and I I'll skip this slide and this
is describing the the overall uh how do
we choose this um the nomat varants. So
as I mentioned one of the advantage of
this class of um um proteins is that you
can study them with a huge uh amount of
precision. So the way we study them is
uh electrphysiology. These channels are
broadly broadly described in open state
and then closed state and inactivated
state. So typically they're sitting at
um closed state and then when the
membrane potential change they um become
open with open probability increasing
and then sometimes they go into
inactivated stage um where it's very
difficult for them to open again but
then they have to go back to the closed
state before they can open. So we can
devise the protocols to precisely probe
um their transition between the open
closed inactivated as well as the
kinetics of how they do that. And then
here uh I probably will show some
graphs. This is what what we call it the
the IV uh relationship current voltage
relationship. And then most often we
define how they open and how they
inactivate with this with this graph we
called uh voltage dependence of
inactivation and activation. This is
activation curve and this is
inactivation
curve. Um and then the technology that
enabled us to
query almost uh 50 plus variants in this
gene is a couple of technologies. One is
a maxiteon that can transact large uh
cDNAs very efficiently and another
technology that allow us to be able to
um patch on uh a whole chip of 384 well
plates. Um that is the huge incre
improvement on the typically very
laborious manual patch clamp. And then
we did that for all of these 50
variants. I'm going to jump through the
technical side and then the this is the
first result. Uh when we first saw this
we are very surprised. Basically you can
view this on the y-axis is how much of a
currents that we can see from each of
the variant channel and this is oh I
don't know why I don't have the label
but this is basically the wild type and
each of this bar represent one variant
and different color represent different
domains. So and then here at the gray
bars are all nomad uh variants. So right
here you can see nomads behave more or
less like a wild type. However, near
half of the variants uh from the disease
uh from this neurodedevelopmental cohort
do not show current density. We're quite
surprised by that because it wasn't
obvious because we thought if if just
losing half of the channel uh losing
half of the copy of the channel would be
the main uh contributor we should have
seen that in the PTV uh truncating
variant and hold the thought I'll come
back to that and here is um another
example just gave you some views of how
these variants behave and so these are
three uh different examples of of of the
variant that calls the gangoff function
what we call um in the sense where they
all shift the voltage dependence of
activation which is here to the left
hugely however they don't behave very
this very much the same as one of the
variant here which is a
V1393M also shifted voltage dependence
of inactivation to the
left at any rate here is a summary of um
the rest of the variants that we can
detect uh the currents. Um, overall all
but one coding changes induced at least
one significant change in one of the
five uh key biohysical parameters that
we interrogated compared with the wild
type reference channel. So half of the
channel disease associated channel did
not express and then for the rest of
them uh we characterize about physical
properties and then I wanted to draw
your attention to right here this is the
half point of activation. So you can see
with the remaining of the variants uh
nearly half if not more of the the the
remaining of the variants shifted the
voltage dependence of activation to the
left and and some of them shifted as
much as 20 millolts. This is this is
this is like uh um astronomically huge
for electrophysiology.
So um this is what we get um and you
know we're trying to understand where in
the structural domain that may
contribute to different uh deficits in
the biohysical uh u uh properties. So so
for example we we draw these radar plots
where um uh the pentagon each vertex
represent a property. So the wild type
is uh right at the zero uh line and then
you can see the nomad most of the nomad
fall right on the zero axis and
suggesting that across all five property
domains they're behaving more or less
similar to the wild type channels yt
type uh reference channels and then if
you look at the if you look at the
different domains so for example in
domain three a lot of variants
go hyperpolarized direction. So in this
case is basically allowing more calcium
influx um and and then compared to the
domain four where there is only one
pentagon plotted here because most of
the variants in domain four uh do not
express or uh with
undetectable current density that we can
measure.
So I'll skip this slide and we we start
to get some structural insights and
structural hotspot and of where when you
have a change then you start to modify
which aspect of the biohysical property
but I I wanted to share with you um of a
uh how how do we use this data set to to
compare with our missense prediction. So
this is done by sewway in Mark's lab. Uh
basically we wanted to test our
functional annotation. How does that
compare with ARA missense? So ARA
missense get um 39 of the 41 uh uh
impactful variants uh as correctly
annotated as pathogenic and then they
get one out of seven nomad rung on on
the other direction. So it's fairly
good. It's not perfect. It's it's it's
okay. And one of the things I wanted to
say about the alpha missense which is
depicted here is that that the alpha
sense despite its relative uh uh
accuracy in predicting the pathogenicity
it does not does not tell you the
directionality and as I I will show you
later both gain of function and loss of
function are implicated in the uh this
disease cohort and and then so
segregating them becomes very very
important. So after validating the the
the ARM missense and using our
functional data we use the ARSense to
look at additional disease cohorts. So
the results is here if we use the alpha
missense pathogenicity score you can see
that the kactton 1A for the missense
variants is uh significantly enriched in
the epileptic encphilosopathy and it's
not so much in the genet in the genetic
generalized epilepsy rather the PTVs are
slightly more uh enriched in the in the
GGE so right here it seems to suggest
that there's some segregation
between the PTVs and the misssense um uh
changes. So I'll skip this slide but I
wanted to tell you some uh because we c
categorize different domains of the
property and sometimes it's so for
example if you have reduced current
density however you still left shift in
the activation threshold. So we wanted
to have a method to have a combined
physiological output as a prediction of
how does it impact the neurono
excitability. I won't go through this
but we we did that and the reason we did
that is that we wanted to be able to
have a better uh look between the
cellular phenotype from these variants
the impact of the biohysical
uh impact with the clinical
manifestation. So to do that we um so
here is a three parameter we measured
and here are the four parameters that we
modeled using uh using this uh neuron
simulations and then I'll just um go
directly to some of the insights here.
So for example, we found that current
current density increase and voltage uh
voltage dependence of activation shift
is really uh significantly associated
with a severe form of epilepsy. And then
the the the the reduction of the current
density is more associated with episotic
atexia. Not necessarily at taxia but
episodic taxia and hemibbleic migraine
and is really only
associated at least in this data set
which is which is uh you
know 80 patients with 22 unique uh
variants is mainly associated with
voltage dependence of activation. And
I'll show you one uh example of how we
start to obtain more insights onto this
uh um variant property to clinical um uh
relationship. So what I'm showing you
here are two different types of uh
perhaps most frequent recurring
variants. Here is a A713. Here is uh two
very close mutations and that has very
similar property which is shown here.
All of them shift the voltage dependence
of activation to the left. However, the
difference between this two class is
that the
1349Q also shift the voltage dependence
of
inactivation. So as the result you can
see clinically they have slightly
different um manifestation. So for
example, A713 people who harbor A7 A713T
mutation
are you see more of them with this uh
very severe form of epilepsy but you
almost don't see them in the uh
hemoplegic migraine on the opposite the
R1340Q and
R1352Q have a expressed uh uh
manifestation clinically in hemopleic
migraine. So we wanted to do this
correlation to give us a better handle
on the um mutation impact and the
clinical
manifestation. So here is what I've told
you so far. We characterize a function
of 50 variants. 42 of them are denovo
changes of keen 1A where stricken by how
impactful of nearly every one of of
these denovo mutations. And then we
started to infer the genotype, cellular
phenotype and the human phenotype in the
caca uh spectrum disorder and hope to
delineate a little better correlation
for the physicians as well as for
understanding the disease
mechanism. And I would argue that um uh
understanding the function of rare
coding changes of this class of protein
may start to bridge the gap between the
monogenic disorder and complex uh uh
channelopathy. So where do we go from
here? And we're grateful very grateful
to to the support for the pilot um from
the letter to cure accelerator program.
So there are two key um directions that
we're going to go and we already started
in both directions. So one is to uh
identify the nodal mechanism in disease
associated with K1A uh varants uh and
spectrum disorders. We already
identified the two key phenotype one
molecular phenotype. One is a voltage
dependence of activation. The other one
is basically we do not see much currents
on the surface. So we're going after
both of them and I'll uh we're starting
to constructing the prototype um cell
lines that showing very sim showing
these class the the the prototype
representing the whole spectrum and then
the goal is to screen for modulators to
address potent these two potential modem
mechanisms for the kek 1A spectrum
uh mutation disorder. And then the
second study is to collaborate with uh
Chong lab as Wendy is collects a
detailed health information and medical
data from individuals with keen related
disorders for the natural history study.
She already collected 156 individuals in
her database and we're starting to
address all of the missenses in her
database. uh we already in this study
we're already performed we have 20 of
them and then so we're we're looking to
characterize the rest of them and then
to map back with the clinical um uh
details and potentially identify the
biomarkers and just very quickly here we
already constructed in
uh almost a dozen of the cell lines
representing the prototype of the two
potential nodal mechanism and uh we have
constructed ed a um cell line that we
can read out the calcium influx through
these channels um using a Gamp uh six
that tether to the membrane to increase
uh signal to noise ratio and we're very
excited that this will launch us to the
next stage of screen for the repurpose
library and and identify potentially
clinical ready uh compounds that we can
test. So with that I wanted to thank um
the four people who contributed majorly
to this project and collaborators um Wii
in the uh audience and then uh Wendy and
many of the support over the past few
years. Thank you.
All right. Next up we have Dr. Lee Rubin
who is principal faculty at the Harvard
Stem Cell Institute where his lab
focuses on mechanisms of
neurodeenerative diseases um and
identifying preINDD um compounds for
translational purposes um which he has
done successfully several times over the
course of his career. In addition, he's
an expert in modeling neurodeenerative
diseases um specifically from patient
specific differentiated neurons um with
a focus on Parkinson's disease, SMA and
ALS. Um and he's going to tell you more
about his L2C project. Thank you, Lee.
Thanks, Jillian. Um so, I'm really happy
to be here today and I'm going to talk
about a pro project that with the good
graces of Anna and Jillian and the L2C
program, we've been able to resurrect in
the lab. And I'm gonna in in particular
talk about a disease that probably all
of you have heard of, spinal muscular
atrophy. This was not so much the case
10-ish years ago, but it certainly is
now. Um, spinal muscular atrophy and
cystic fibrosis are probably the poster
children for studies of rare diseases.
They're not so rare in the sense of what
we're talking about here today. They're
about 20,000 or so kids with both of
them, I think, cystic fibrosis and SMA.
But it's a fairly well understood
disease and probably all of you know it.
I'll just quickly say right now. Um the
disease spinal muscular atrophy was was
and is referred to as a motor monogenic
motor neuron pediatric disease and it's
due to a reduction in the level of a
protein of slightly incompletely
understood function called survival of
motor neuron. Survival of motor neuron
is coded for by two genes. one of which
is SMN1 and the other of which is a
duplicated gene with a misssense
mutation called
SMN2 and it exists in various dis uh
degrees of severity um uh very very very
severe which is called type one until
recently kids with type one SMA died
before the age of one then type two
where kids would be um more severely
handicapped and finally the mildest type
type three where kids could live on a a
normal lifespan maybe they'd be in a
wheelchair later in life and what
distinguishes one from two from three is
the number of copies of the SMN2 gene.
So this is fairly well understood and it
led to without with incomplete
understanding of the disease. The um
hypothesis which is seemingly very true
that the more SMN protein you have the
better you are. And based on that
hypothesis as probably many of you know
there are currently three approved
therapeutics. One of which is a gene
therapy that delivers the wild type SMN1
gene. the other two of which are
splicing modulators. One is an ao
anticens nucleotide delivered
intratheally and the other is a small
molecule um splicing modulator in fact a
relative of branoplam that we just heard
from recently which was originally uh uh
developed by Novartis as an SMA drug.
Now given what I just said you may be
wondering why I'm talking to you today
about SMA. It's cured sort of cured. Um
and I'm going to tell you why um our
stubbornness about the value things that
we've discovered using an approach that
was somewhat different from everything
else that was used in the field which uh
uh Jillian already mentioned using IPS
cells from patients that had different
degrees of SMA severity how that led to
what we felt were very interesting
insights which is what I'm going to
describe to you today. So I'm going to
talk a little bit specifically about
SMA. I'm going to talk um in some detail
about SMA motor neurons and how they
behave. Then I'm going to talk about
other surprising observations that we
made using IPS cells made from the kids
with SMA and a general principle that
I'd like to put forward uh uh today
about broadening the way we think about
using IPS cells. Um uh and um I'd also
like to um uh uh bring in this idea that
in the case of SMA and this is I think
will turn out to be key to this program.
We hypothesize that the carriers of SMA
the parents of which there are 7 million
in the US are also many of them
phenotypically abnormal and might
themselves benefit from an SMA drug. So
it's a little bit specific but we're
trying to establish some principles
here. Okay. So, um uh what we found very
early on as having made iPSLs from a
bunch of kids with SMA, as I said, and
making motor neurons, it was certainly
the case that we could do what everybody
was trying to do at the time with any
disease, which is to say you reproduce
in try to reproduce in culture the thing
that you know about the disease. And
since it was called a motor neuron
disease, we tried to reproduce motor
neuron uh death starting from patient
cells. Well, this was relatively easy in
SMA unlike all the late onset diseases
like ALS. ALS is another motor neuron
disease, but it's genetically very
heterogeneous and and late onset. This
is early onset monogenic. Seemed like it
would be easy and in fact relatively
speaking, it was easy. So we could show
this from patient derived motor neurons
and even here I'm just showing you these
are just wild type motor neurons in
which we just um reduce the level of of
SMN and you can see that this kind of
rapidly induces the death of motor
neurons. Nothing um at all surprising
there. The thing that was surprising
though is that we looked at the cultures
in great detail by imaging and I'm going
to show you more imaging later on. Um
now done here what we observed was
unlike what we imagined that every motor
neuron in the culture would have the
same level of SMN protein this was not
true. In fact there was wide variation
in the level of protein in individual
motor neurons such that some had much
much lower levels of SMN than others. Um
and um it turned out that the effect on
motor neuron survival of reducing SMN um
or when studying patient cells was not
uniform um and and in fact what we
observed was um this so we plotted out
the individual cell levels of SMN. So
this is intensity and every culture
whether it's from SMA uh IPS cells or
wild type IPS cells had a distribution
of SMN. So as a population you could see
that SMN was really low in the
population. But even that severely
affected population still had motororns
that had relatively high normal levels
of SMN. And it turned out that the cells
that had low levels of SMN in one single
well had higher probability of dying.
And this was um seen by following the
cells over time and ultimately staining
them with uh uh um cleaved caspace um uh
antibbody. So the effect of reducing SMN
is preferentially on cells that happen
to have low levels of SMN protein.
Okay, that's
SMA. Now, we also observe the converse.
If we took motor SMA motor neuron motor
neurons and uh overexpressed SMN using a
viral viral delivery in those cells, um
SMN the SMN histogram would shift to the
higher
values and again that was associated
with increased survival. So increasing
SMN decreasing reduced survival
preferentially by affecting low SMN
motor neurons if you shift the profile
so that more cells have normal or high
levels the survival of those cells
increases. In other words in SMA it at
the single cell level the amount of SMN
that they have dictates their life or
death. So you can see this in as an
average but more importantly you could
see this at individual cells. So why is
that interesting? So it turns out every
type of motor neuron, every type of
motor neuron culture, no matter where
they, no matter where IPS cells came
from, ALS, any genetic version of ALS,
SMA, any type of SMA patient, wild type
motor neurons for which whoever the
donor is, we always see a histogram of
levels, it's always the case that the
lower the cells in the culture with
lower SMN die preferentially. And it's
always the case importantly that
increasing SMN in these cultures even if
they're wild type motor neurons even if
they're ALS derived motor neurons the
survival of these cells is always
improved. In other words as a summary
statement the protein survival of motor
neuron does exactly what the name
suggests. It improves the survival of
motor neurons regardless of where the
the source of the cells. Okay.
So it is even true and in fact I won't
have time to tell you about this. It is
even true if you take a wild type
culture of motor neurons and treat it
with toxic compounds. Toxic means that
it decreases the number of motor neurons
in the well. You often find compounds
that decrease the total number of
modinors while increasing the average
value of SMN in the well. And the way
that happens is even toxic compounds
many of which are shown here shift the
profile by selectively re um eliminating
the cells with low SMN leaving behind a
smaller number of cells but cells with
higher SMN. So the number goes down the
average SMN goes up. So under any
circumstance that we have tried whether
it's straight toxic compounds um a
disease phenotype of any kind if we make
motor neurons the higher SMN they have
the better they survive.
Okay. Okay. So um this I won't talk
about now but it leads you to wonder and
this is part of the new program if that
is true. It suggests the idea that a
compound that increases SMN might be
therapeutic for nonSMN motor neuron
diseases. Let's just say ALS. And if you
were thinking about that, you would also
have to think about what is the best way
of increasing SMN um in in those
cultures. And we act in our hands with
IPS cells, the best way of doing it even
compared to the approved splicing
modulator is by blocking the degradation
of SMN protein. That's part of our new
project and and I'll talk about it
later, but I won't show the these data.
Okay. So, I I think this was a
relatively simple story, but I've
summarized it here. There's cellto cell
variation in the amount of SMN protein
in every single culture we've ever seen.
Mouse, human, ALS, SMA. Um, higher
levels of uh SMN protein protein
increase the survival of motor neurons.
Full stop. Um, this suggests that
therapeutics that increase SMN may also
be able to treat ALS. So um that's
that's our hypothesis and again what is
the best type of SMN elevating
therapeutic that we believe would work
outside of the disease SMA okay now
there's a second part um to this and
this is kind of this question are motor
neurons really the only cells um
affected in in in kids with SMA now what
even though it's always been thought to
be a motor neuron disease There's reason
to wonder if that's really true and and
the one of the main reasons is the gene
is ubiquitously expressed and this is
from the uh broad gtex portal. Um and in
fact motors um do not have by far the
highest level of SMN. There are other
types of cells that have much much much
higher levels of SN. So it suggested the
possibility that there might be for
instance if kids were to live longer it
might be the possibility that you one
would observe other tissues being
affected. So um this uh really the our
interest in this stemmed from our
observation that when we made a bunch of
IPS cells from kids with SMA they were
pur potent in the technical using the
technical definition of pur potency
which is the the IPS cells made endoderm
misoderm and ectoaderm but they didn't
do it normally they had clear
differentiation defects and in fact
they're surprising defects. One of them
is they make neural ectoermal cells
including motor neurons much better than
wild type cells. So you generate a lot
of motor and they die quickly. So it's a
degenerative phenotype for motor neurons
but they're born perfectly nicely. On
the other hand, cells of endodermal
origin are not produced well from the
very same IPS cells. So just to kind of
illustrate that on the top left are
endoderm cells and you can see the SMA
ones are really uh defective in in their
production. Um skeletal muscle is highly
defective in its production from IPS
cells. I'll emphasize this now because
it's very clear that kids with SMA have
skeletal muscle defects independent of
the motor neuron defects. And in fact,
there are several clinical trials
underway now to just make muscles
stronger even in kids who have received
SMA therapies. So this seems to be on
the right track. And we also found some
cardiac defects. But the cells most
affected were endodermal derived. And
this shows um a figure from a recent
paper that we published in the journal
of clinical investigation with Crystal
Yo. And there were two interesting
things here. One is that we could
reproduce um hpatic a liver der endoderm
derived liver cell defects starting with
patient IPS cells but more importantly
it illustrates the other general finding
we had which is cells do not have equal
sensitivity to loss of SMN. So in fact
the cells that are most sensitive to
reduction of SMN are endoderm derived
cells and in this particular paper there
we showed a clear phenotype with
carriers hetererozygous IPS cells. They
clearly had a very strong liver defect.
So you didn't need to not you needed to
to reduce the protein level only 50% for
those cells to be affected. You didn't
need to go down to close to zero for the
cells to be effective. So this suggests
a range of sensitivity and also suggests
that if any of this IPS stuff is to be
believed. It also suggests that if you
look carefully at patients perhaps you
would find things that you didn't that
you didn't already know about. So I want
to say that one again. Everybody who
uses IPSLs uses them to model the parts
of the dis of a disease that you
understand.
But for IPSLs to be really believable,
you should also sort of imagine that
IPSLs could tell you things you didn't
already know if they're really truly
representative of the patients. So that
became kind of for us a big deal. Is
this, you know, it's just an artifact of
IPS cell biology? It's an artifact of
cell culture. And so we were quite
interested in this. And finally um after
a lot of struggling via um uh Zakohan's
lab at at uh Harvard Medical School was
um Scott Lipnik who was a computational
biologist in my lab at the time we got
access to an Etna electronic health
database with a patient dise ICD codes
patient disease diagnoses that were used
for billing purposes. These records are
not the best in the world. um but we had
60 million of them and from that we
identified about 1,300 kids with SMA and
I'll also mention by imputation about
2600 carriers of SMA. I'm going to come
back to that and we found sure enough um
before um neuromuscular diseases were
diagnosed in these kids. They had a
variety of other disorders listed
clearly on their health records
including cardiac and um endodermal
tissue derived disorders. So that was
kind of interesting. If you are if you
are imaginative enough or want to be
believe this enough, you could imagine
that actually IPSLs in fact do reproduce
aspects of of the patient biology under
the correct settings and we can debate
what those settings are. Okay.
So that's second part. Multiple tissues
may be affect may be affected well
clearly are affected in SMA patients.
And I want to emphasize one thing. I
don't know if physicians will agree with
me or not. SMA is a neurological
disorder. Neurologists are examining the
patients. The kid the thing the
condition that used to be killing kids
with SMA is um breathing distress. I
don't think the physicians are
necessarily wondering about other more
minor conditions that the kids have. So
I want to distinguish between biological
significance, things that are actually
happening that are interesting maybe to
some of us me um u versus clinical
significance, the things that need to be
treated immediately. Um okay. And that
um again inv oops um in vitro studies
indicate that some cell types are
actually more sensitive than motor
neurons and will ultimately give rise to
disease phenotypes especially now that
kids are living longer and that there
are effects that are easily observable
with e where where the cells have only
lost 50% of their SMA. So this leads to
this other question. Are carriers of SMA
really phenotypically normal? Um and so
that's the the second part of the
project. Okay. So what are we doing?
Part one plans. Um identify we're
interested in what regulates the level
of protein SMN protein in motor neurons.
So our plan is to separate the highest
10% from the lowest 10% and study uh
gene expression differences in those two
different populations. Um and then we're
going to use phenotypic screens um uh uh
to uh find compounds that let's say
drive more of the low cells into the
high expressor category and then
ultimately to test compounds like that
in different ALS models. And we've made
a good start already given that we had
to resurrect this project from zero even
in my lab and then transfer everything
over to here. But with the wonderful
help from Moing Gishere um uh and and
Masha Alen Mo that that um we've already
reproduced the fact that all of these
cultures do have these extended
histograms of SMN intensity. So that's
the core of the project. So it's good
that we were able to see that. We've
also um were able to show that if you by
imaging distinguish between the cells in
the well that have the highest 10%
versus the lowest 10% and then look for
by imaging other aspects of the cells
biology of those cells. You can
immediately see that there's a good
correlation between let's say
mitochondrial function looal function
and SMN. So the highest uh SMN
expressors also have the most intact
mitochondria and losomes. And that's
kind of summarized here. And again, very
reassuring that even by just straight
imaging, we can already pick up
differences. And um uh um Mary Rose
branch in my lab has come over here
together with the people at the fax core
and has stained um a fixed and permeed
motor neurons, stained them for SMN and
then separated them by fax. And again we
can easily separate the top well not
easily separate the top 10% from the
bottom 10%. So that's good. So that now
lets us move forward with the first part
of the project. Now part two which is
now computational and here we're working
with Ben Weissberg um and Heidi Ram from
the computational group here. Um, so
we're now able, unlike when we did our
first study, we can now call SMA
carriers just by gene sequencing
information, not the indirect way by ICD
code to get the kids and then
retroactively
identify the parents. So, we're
expecting about 9,000 um uh SMA carriers
in the UK bio bank. So that will really
allow us to power up and see whether or
not it's true that these u uh uh parents
are phenotypically um abnormal in any
way using again ICD codes and also other
informatic analyses of their health
records. And then we're going to use the
all of us uh uh uh cohort as the
validation set. Um and then if all this
turns out, we are ultimately interested
in finding again a therapeutic that
would treat the somewhat abnormal
parents of the kids or just people who
are SMA carriers. Okay, so um that's it.
Thank you very much. The people in my
lab um who did the work um really were
the middle three up front there. Mary
Rose is in the audience has been coming
over here to do the work. Rich has been
working with Mary Rosen. Chris next to
her on the left is our our computational
person. And again, I'd like to thank the
L2C program um and um people at the
Broad that we've been working with.
Thank
Thank you, Lee. I'd also like to invite
Jen and Ricardo up for a quick uh Q&A.
Uh a question to you, Lee. Um, it'd be
helpful in interpreting all of your
studies to know what the protein
actually does.
What's the status? I mean, this has been
going on for a long time for sure. Um,
so on the one hand, I always like to say
to um basic, you know, very good basic
scientists, it shows you just don't
really have to understand everything
about a disease before you treat it. But
on the other hand, it is really true
that it's a splicing modulator, but it
regulates the splicing of thousands of
genes. And people have always had this
idea that there must be something
especially important in motor neurons,
but nobody knows what that is.
I also have a question to Lee. Are you
able to access uh information on
patients responders and non-responders
and try to correlate it with their SMN
levels? Um I I want I haven't heard
about a large number of nonresponders to
one of the treatments. Yeah, partial.
Yeah, that's yeah, it's a really good
it's a really good idea. We we need we
need to look in that. I I presume so
number the patients switch therapies and
and I think there are two reasons. one
they weren't working that well and as I
guess think you know the timing of
treatment is so so so important the
longer you wait the less that gets
corrected um and and the other reason is
for example um there's a supplementation
of gene therapy with this the oral drug
some kids of course don't like getting
the anti-sense you know every 3 months
by intratheal administration so that's
the other reason for switching but we
could look into presumably how patients
have responded to the treatments we
haven't done that yet. It's a it's a
good thought.
Can I ask a question as well for you? So
going back to the the idea of uh for
example using risk the plan or brand
like do do you are you thinking that
maybe this is something that everyone
should be taking a little bit like at a
low dose maybe not everybody but that's
that's also but you know uh uh it's come
up every now and again. I would love to
start with the more severely affected
carriers just to see what how they
respond. Um so it is true as you as you
you're pointing out I mean since we've
seen this on um motor neurons as well I
I don't know if there are situations
like after traumatic damage for example
if the um nerve is cut to preserve the
cell bodies better maybe it would be
useful under those kind of circumstances
as well.
everyone for a fantastic session. Um the
speakers will hang out for a little
while to answer any follow-up questions.
Please be back at 1:15 so we can
continue with our program. Thanks
everyone.
[Applause]