Modern warehouse automation brings a lot
of productivity to warehouse facilities.
But it also brings a lot of new risks.
It can go from a cyber attack to power
and network outages or just technology
failure. The warehouse management system
or WMS, the central brain of warehouse
operations for many years used to be
running in a single facility. Now all
the WS's are being combined into a
single WMS. So that brings a lot of
efficiency, but it also presents a huge
risk. For example, a cyber attack can
bring down the whole network of
warehouses. One of the main things they
need to start doing is leveraging AI for
cyber security first. It can actually
prevent some of the attacks by detecting
those malicious hackers beforehand, but
it can also be used for an automated
response. So, if a cyber attack is
already happening, the AI tool can
actually be the one fighting that cyber
attack in advance.
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learnmit.edu.