So, it's my pleasure to uh to introduce
Andrew Garson uh who I had
honor and pleasure to work with
for for a long while at Morgan Stanley.
Um and Andrew is uh actually a MIT alum.
uh he got his PhD uh from in geo physics
uh from MIT. Uh and uh after that uh he
worked in a variety of uh uh roles in
financial senior quantitative roles in
financial industry and now Andrew uh is
head of quantitative strategies at
Mizukho in New York. So Andrew, welcome
and please take it away.
>> Okay. Uh thanks everyone. So I'm going
to have a quick talk today about sort of
linear uh models and rates in particular
which is area I work in. Um we'll just
have a quick overview. We're going to
talk a little bit about some basic
markets. Uh interest rates, what are
they? Um what are some of the more
liquid rates products, yield curves, you
know, a little bit about hedging, how do
you hedge your positions, uh P&L
attribution, and then end with a little
bit on E-rading and bonds. Uh I'm going
to caveat this is going to be a very
non-mathy presentation probably for this
class. So um that's probably my personal
bias is I don't find math necessarily uh
that illuminating in some of these
problems versus what problems are you
actually solving. As I told Peter, you
know, if I was you were talking about,
you know, how to build a house, we
wouldn't spend, you know, 80% of the
time talking about hammers. You know,
we're talking about how big you want
your rooms and how the connectivity is.
Uh I would highly encourage you to ask
questions. I'm going to ask Peter if
nobody else does if he can pipe in a
couple just because I'd like to keep the
discussion going and I'm generally happy
to yak on and on about any particular
topic that anyone uh is interested in.
So, so please uh talk away. Okay. So,
start with the basics. What are linear
products? You know, they're things that
are not nonlinear. Uh nothing too
surprises there. Um you know, some of
the major categories are things like
bonds, high interest rate swaps,
interest rate future, CDs. These are
sort of the more traditional relatively
simple products. These are not you know
codo squared or colable spread range
acrals or any of the super exotic stuff
that has uh been around for a while and
still continues to be done. You know the
modeling is in some sense relatively
simpler here. These are not you know
huge you know multiffactor scastic
calculus models you have to do in term
structure models and things. It's
relatively straightforward you know. So
the question then is you know why do we
care you know as quants? Why is this
interesting? You know anybody want to
hazard a guess as to why the stuff is
still relevant today?
Somebody take a guess. Look, you look
like you're thinking.
>> I was going to say it's still related to
important stuff like interest rates.
>> It is it's it's an important thing. It's
the core underlying. What is what are
some other reasons? Maybe you might care
about this.
>> It's traded a lot.
>> It's a very big market and a very liquid
market. True. A couple other ones are
it's also generally used for hedging of
the more complicated stuff and it's also
an input to all the more complicated
models which generally you start from
the simple stuff and you build your
models up. Um you know these are very
large these are the largest markets on
the planet. Um just a couple of
statistics in the last few years.
Equities is is you know getting close
now particularly with the sort of run up
in global equities last couple years. Um
bonds have something north of $120
trillion outstanding. uh interest rate
swaps are more like you know 500 plus
trillion dollars outstanding you know
just the main futures contract more than
10 trillion you know these are very
large numbers um you don't need to have
a huge profit margin and when a market
this size to you know do very well in a
market of this size that's very actively
it trades a lot um you know the daily
volumes treasuries approaching a
trillion dollars a day uh interest rate
swaps you know comparable uh again
futures something like four million
contracts a day and the sofur futures
which are the main uh short-term
interest rate contracts.
And then I think some some a lot of the
more complicated models start with the
simple stuff and then sort of build up
on top of that.
And again, I have a tendency to talk
faster and faster and faster if nobody
comes back. So I'm going to apologize in
advance and if you find me doing that,
somebody just uh tell me to stop.
um you know and again I as said they
mentioned they're sort of uh based to
the compllets and uh inputs to the more
complicated model you know previously I
think they were thought quite simple uh
I think the global financial crisis in
2008 sort of brought a number of factors
to the four that people hadn't
considered before uh in particular
around things like funding
uh and what was previously say a very
simple product so you know I'll pay you
a dollar in 10 years how to value that
became quite difficult and and subject
to a a lot of uh thinking and discussion
and um and interesting there's not a
unique answer to that um which is also
interesting.
Couple of the other things that came in
there was a lot of regulation that came
in after uh 2008. Um you know some sense
somebody said the regulators wanted to
make banking boring. Um and you know
it's not boring but they've changed
where the interest is in it. um and sort
of the super complicated exotic products
that were really uh very much in vogue
in the early knots and midnots really
those things uh ended poorly for a lot
of people. uh you sort of think about
the causes of the financial crisis at
least on on the market side a lot of it
ultimately uh boiled down to US
residential real estate uh which had a
huge runup and then an enormous crash
but off of that they'd been issued you
know a lot of very complicated
securization products uh very highly
levered and multi-layered uh and things
were you know very opaque and hard to
value you know this was not uh financial
modeling's finest hour
uh so I think there was a lot of
regulation that came in on top of that
in terms of model risk management and
that that really um sort of ended that
little that section of the business. So,
uh people went back a little bit to
basics and and started thinking a little
more about some of the fundamentals. Um
which I think was a good thing because I
think things were kind of silly there.
Uh and I remember talking to some of my
friends at a soccer game or something
our kids were playing and he was
mentioning they just done a mortgage
securization issue which I believe
defaulted without making a single
payment. So, this stuff was just so, you
know, so poorly supported and thought
out. Um, but because it was so opaque,
you know, you know, smiling fast
talkinging sales guy could push a lot of
the stuff to areas that really probably
should not have been involved in this
area. Uh, and you find little like
municipalities in Norway having declared
bankruptcy because they bought a whole
bunch of CDOS's from Iowa, you know,
strip malls or something crazy like that
and you sort of think, you know, how did
that happen? Um so I think there was
quite a lot of uh regulation came in
really to you put a little bit of fences
around some of this stuff which is is uh
you know it's quite powerful but you
know could be used for good or bad in
some sense. So
okay
so let's talk a little bit about what is
an interest rate. You know an interest
rate at its most basic um is a rate at
which you can you know either borrow or
lend money uh on a principal amount. So
in this case, I'm going to have, you
know, my interest I payment will be N,
which is a notional typically times the
rate R acrewed over whatever time I'm
borrowing it for. So I have, you know,
I'm borrowing $1,000 at 5% for a year.
In a year, I'll have to pay back $1,000
plus 5% uh times a year times $1,000,
$50 of interest. Um, relatively
straightforward. You know, how do I
value that in terms of what I'm willing
to pay for that today? you know, I'm not
willing to pay $1,000 for it because uh
well, let me reverse that. So, if I get
$1,000 in a year, how much am I willing
to pay for that today? And whatever I'm
willing to pay for today, I can invest.
And if you work out arithmetic, it works
out to be one over one plus the rate
times the time. So, at a 5% rate, I'll
pay something like $950 odd dollars for
that. Uh and then in a year get $1,000.
Now, this depends a lot on the
discounting rate. for example. So, what
rate am I going to discount at? Um, you
know, that's hard to observe. Rates I
can get for investing are easy to
observe. You know, you walk into a bank
and you look at the signs on the front
door, IRCDs, four and a half% rates for
a year. Uh, whatever. How much a
discount is is hard.
Um, typically, you know, in our world,
we're going to assume one of the, you
know, institutional rates, which is
something like a sofa rate or an OS
rate, which we'll talk more about in a
little bit in the future. Um but these
are sort of a standard uh assumption.
Now one of the interesting things
practically you find every person has a
slightly different rate that they should
be discating out because it depends on
where they can borrow money and that
that depends on your creditworthiness.
So you know you may have a good credit
rating and you can borrow money at 4%.
You know you no offense I'm not picking
you. You may have a terrible credit
rating so you have to pay 8% to borrow
money. You may have a medium one so
you're borrowing at 6%. So uh and you
know it all depends on the particular
issues of the issuer. So this this makes
it uh interesting because at this point
you know the uh a contract for you guys
to pay me a thousand bucks in a year has
different prices depending on who you
are. So there's no single price here
makes it interesting. Uh a lot of the
banks will deal with this because you
know it's kind of a pain in the ass for
a trading desk to have to manage you
know a thousand different counterparty
relationships each with their own
funding. So usually you'll centralize
that on a central funding desk of some
sort. They will then assume all of the
uh
individual traders can fund at a
relatively generic rate and the funding
desk will deal with all these horrible
little uh funding bases uh and small
collateral exposures and things like
that.
Okay, going back a little bit in
history. Um you may or may not have
heard of Liebore. Uh probably not
because it now is gone. But this was one
of the first really common use rates.
Stands for London interbank offered
rate. Uh it was developed I believe by a
Greek guy in the 60s uh as a method of
standardizing syndicated lending in
London.
Most bank lending to corporates is
floating rate lending. So you won't you
won't do a fixed rate loan for 10 years.
You'll do a rate that resets every
month, every three months at the then
current rate. And the question then was
what rate should we be using to set the
interest payments on these loans at? So
what he came up with is a notion we're
going to pull the banks as to where they
lend money shortterm and we'll take the
average of that you know kick out the
highs and lows and then that'll be a
standard rate everyone can use as a
reference index you know was a very
great very good idea incredibly
successful
first interest rate swaps which are
really synthetic versions of those came
out in the early 80s uh first swap I
believe was 1980 or 81 which is a
crosscurrency swap with IBM uh and then
the first pure single currency swap came
out the next here.
Uh these products had you know
phenomenal growth in the 90s and knots.
Uh currently there's something about 350
or 400 trillion of them outstanding as
of uh labor cessation and still continue
to grow a little more than that. Um so
you know very pro very popular product
very liquid uh very actively traded. You
know, liberate though, you know, again,
another one of the fallouts from the
financial crisis showed that it had some
issues. You know, liber was set by
polling banks. So, you'd go ask the
funding department at each of the big
banks. I think there's 20 odd people in
the LIBOR pool, were you going to lend
and borrow? Were you going to borrow
money from they would come up with a
number, they'd quote it. Note that it's
not based on actual transactions. So,
they're just making a number up. They're
trying to in theory if they're all good
players hitting it where they would
actually do the trades. But this is not
actually observable trades and I think
in the sort of late knots early teens um
group of traders of uh less than
honorable intent realized that this is
and this was a manipulatable rate. Now
you may have for example you know every
day you're going to look at how much
money you know these rates set every day
and based on your portfolio you'll have
some impact on that. Some of them you
can have millions of dollars a basis
point. A basis point being a hundth of a
percent. So if you can get that rate up
or down just a little bit uh in your
favor it can end up making you a lot of
money. So what they did was they
essentially all you know chatted with
each other and they were chatting with
whoever the people at their banks were
responsible for setting these rates and
convincing them look I need you to make
this a high rate today or I need you to
make this a lower rate today. Um and
they could you know you can move this
thing a little bit because it's not
observable because nothing trades. And
they, you know, they were doing that for
a while to their advantage. Um, this was
discovered. Number of them were in jail
for some time. There was very
substantial multi-billion dollar fines
to the banks doing this. But I think the
realization came that this rate didn't
have any support.
You know, one of the things is Liebore
is a um, you know, it's an unsecured
rate, if you will. It's it doesn't have
anything backing it like a repo or a
collateral rate. Um, and there's just
not a lot of transactions. Post 2008,
nobody wanted to lend unsecured because
you know you had a number of
bankruptcies. People like Leman's gone
out and you just you don't want to lend
to money who's nothing backing it. So uh
people weren't happy with that. And you
know some of the things in some of the
teners and markets I think had you know
three transactions in a six-month
period. That's not enough but you have
to quote this rate every day. So there's
just nothing fixing it. So that was a
real issue.
So the Fed set up uh or the Fed plus the
other regulators
uh I guess it came out of London
originally was the big driver for this.
the FSA there um because L being uh
London and Liber
really decided you know you needed a new
rate that was going to be defensible
backing up based on actual transactions
and a number of other criteria to make
it hard to manipulate so that you know
this would be a genuine real observed
rate and not something that was just
being made up uh by banks to favor their
trading desks.
>> See Andrew just a comment
li sound a bit esoteric at this point,
but at the time uh mortgages mortgage
interest rates were often quoted as
LIBOR plus a spread. And my experience
was during the the time of the knots and
the teams, you know, looking at
>> possibly refinancing my mortgage to a
lower rate because rates were coming
down and the lie board did not move much
at all during that period which was
rather frustrating to watch if anyone
understood why it was not moving. Well,
it was partly that and partly um the
libore to treasury spread which is the
difference between libore rates which
are the the bank rates and the treasury
rates which are government rates uh blew
out in that period around 20112
uh the fine institution I was at at that
point wrote off 8.4 four billion dollars
in structured notes because of that for
example um because they were hedging
their structured notes with LIBOR
products and assuming the two would stay
together and they just went uh most of
it came back in the next couple years
but it was quite unpleasant for a while
there and and uh made them want to
change how they were doing that. um you
know when we went through sort of the
liebore retirement you know when you
look at how much of what kind of
products are out there there's all sorts
of weird stuff you know swaps are the
biggest piece but then as you have
floating rate mortgages uh you have a
fair amount of corporate bonds out there
um you have some really bizarre slightly
esoteric stuff that is like you know I
don't know how you redo that when you're
going to go knock on somebody's door and
tell my mother that you know her library
plus 100 mortgage is now a sofa plus 150
I don't know what she's going to do with
that other than be confused and call me
and ask for help. I think but um so you
know so they really the labor had to go
because it was it was not not a good
rate anymore. Um and this is also true
of the equivalent libs in at least
Japan, Canada, US, Switzerland, Europe
and uh the UK I think all have uh
replaced their rates with something a
little more uh defensible. In the US,
it's called the sofa rate, which is the
securitized overnight funding rate. Um,
which is essentially the average of
overnight repo trades. So, a repo uh
rate is, you know, if I have a bond, I
can just buy it outright if I want to,
but it's not usually the, you know, an
efficient way to do. I can borrow money
against the bond. So, if I have I buy
100 million US treasuries, I can then
lend that to somebody, you know, post
that to somebody and borrow say $98
million of cash. He he'll hold my bond.
uh and then if we want we can swap it
back in again but the rate at which
you're going to pay in that borrowing is
known as the repo rate or reverse repo
rate depending which direction you're
going uh and that's at yeah a real rate
real money changes hands um US has about
800 billion of that a day of the main uh
repo facilities so that's something that
there's a lot of transaction data behind
you can you know look at it measure it
you know add it all up average it uh and
come up with the rate so that's what
they
Um, you know, uh, so far does have some
features that are not so fabulous. You
know, first of all, it's a daily rate.
Uh, nobody wants to have a loan where
you have to pay interest every day. It's
just a pain in the ass operationally and
and not good. You want to pay every
three months or six months or annually,
for example. That just makes it just
easier mechanically to deal with. Um,
you know, you can compound it into term
rates. So, we'll talk about that in a
slide or two. Uh another thing if you do
compound it into term rates so you do
like the average so for over threemonth
period and then pay that rate you don't
know the rate until the end of the
period because you haven't finished
doing all your daily uh features. That's
a bit annoying for uh people because a
lot of people want to know the rate up
front so they can just arrange you know
guess operationally
set all their payment systems make sure
the payments get there schedule that
have enough time to sort out make sure
they're doing the right rate. Uh and the
other interesting thing is it's sofur is
a secured rate. Banks actually prefer to
lend unsecured. Uh so I think when a
bank when a bank makes a loan so it'll
do a floating rate lend to a corporate
they'll give them $100 million.
Corporate will pay them the floating
rate say Libbor plus you know spread or
whatever.
Now if you think about what happens when
um bank credit goes bad. So if there's a
crisis, typically the bank spreads will
blow out, which means LIBOR will blow
out. And if the majority of the income
is coming from LIBOR products because
that's what you've loaned at, you're now
making more money. So you loan money at
Liber plus 50, LIBOR's now 100, you got
an extra 50 basis points of income
because your credit's deteriorating. So
it's sort of a rightway risk kind of
feature. um that is you know I don't
know if it's worth you know a whole lot
of the bank but it's a nice feature to
have that if bank credit goes bad you
end up making more income so people like
that
said Libbor has mostly been phased out
in the last few years um US ended lieore
last June so June 2023 they're one of
the biggies sterling went earlier um
Canada went two months ago Mexico is
going into this year uh and then there's
a couple features in yen that are also
happening I think uh early next year.
You know this was an enormous migration
and and uh you know you should hope in
your careers you never deal with this
kind of stuff because it is just painful
and tedious. Yes.
>> Do you mind introduced lending the
relationship between uh bank credit and
um the funding rate?
>> Okay. So I'm I'm a bank. My my majority
of my corporate lending portfolio is
floating rate loans which are going to
pay me an interest of liber plus a
spread fixed spread. So it it's going to
float. If LIBOR's higher, I make more
money. If LIBO is lower, I make less
money. I'm going to fund myself as
something that's typically not, you
know, less less uh floating than the
rat. So bank credit goes bad. So banks
get into trouble or somebody perceives
that there's a a systematic issue out
there with banking allot 2008 or a
couple other episodes, the liber spreads
are going to increase because, you know,
larger spreads, higher rates, lower
quality generally. So what that means is
the spreads are going to increase. So my
interest I'm going to earn on my loans
has now gone up which helps me because I
get more income. Make sense? Or
>> sorry.
>> Okay. Yeah. No, please again please. I'm
talking fast on a big range of topics.
So please jump right in. You're looking
confused or anything?
No questions?
>> No. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Um you know again
you hope in your career you don't have
to deal with this because it's a pain in
the ass. It's just an enormous
mechanical process. Uh there's been a
few of them around. Euro conversion was
another one in the late 90s we did where
you know all of the European currencies
converted to euros. Um
yeah I remember sitting in Canary Warf
at that one at like three in the morning
because we'd screwed something up and it
was like oh dear. Um but it all happened
in Y2K is another classic one. There's
been a bunch of other ones like that and
but it all happened and fine. So no more
library.
Okay. So as I mentioned sulfur is a
daily rate. you know, you don't want to
pay daily. So, you know, you can
compound it up. Two standard ways. I'm
going to do daily compounding. So, each
day I'll, you know, work out my discount
factor for that day, which is one plus
the rate over 360. And you just compound
those up. Uh, and then subtract one off
the end, and that'll convert it to an
equivalent term rate. Fine. And you can
pay the term rate. Or I can just do a
simple average. So, just average um the
sofur or average the daily sofers. In
this case, the little d's are the number
of days it applies for. So a rate
setting in Friday will apply for three
days over the weekend. A rate setting in
Monday only applies for one day. Excuse
that. You add it all up, pay that rate.
Um the majority of products in the
dollar market go on the compounding uh
sofa because it's just it's a simpler
rate to calorie. Uh it also doesn't have
the average and you need to make a
slight correction due to volatility
which is just annoying. You know, it's a
few basis points running so most people
won't care. But um if you're trading
this a lot as a market maker, you want
to get all this stuff right because the
bid offers are couple ten of a basis
point. So uh if you have something that
pushes you outside of that, you're going
to lose money.
You know, there's lots of other rates
out there. Uh term sofer is one that CME
created a couple years ago. Uh use they
actually fit something. They have a
little model. They do a best fit to all
the futures prices which are again are
very liquid, well traded stuff. and they
work out one month, three months, six
month rates and then publish those. It's
a set in advance rate. So I set it now
and it applies for the next three months
say so I'll fix a term so for now pay in
three months at that rate plus whatever.
Uh this one is is quite common in
corporate loans. Uh and again corporate
lending you know um the banks in
generally have much better systems than
the users. not always the case, but
they've been at this for a while where
if I'm a corporate, I don't necessarily
want to deal with a lot of the
complexities uh and sort of nuances of
this stuff. I just want to have
something fairly simple. Every 3 months,
I'll look a rate up on a screen. I'll
put that on my loan and I'll pay that
three months later. Yep.
I don't know if this is like if I'm not
understanding this correctly, but like
let's assume like we go back to like um
when rates were
kind of now, but like when rates were
there was more of a risk of rates um
going above 6%.
>> That like would directly influence how
like the duration of the the futures
contracts.
>> Is that my
>> sure I'm understanding like the cheapest
deliver for the the futures contract
changes because um like the price at 6%.
>> Sure. So at 6% your futures contract
will hit at 94 because the 100 minus the
price is generally the rate. Fine. Yep.
So then for in terms of thinking about
how in terms of think about how that
affects the term sofur like
theoretically um
>> like that would change the duration of
the like the cheapest deliver which
means that your term sofer represents a
different rate
>> term so it it is a slightly different
rate. Um,
so
okay.
So let let me doodle here for a little
bit if you don't mind. Okay. So that's
time that's rate. So what it is, the
futures will each set a block of say
three-month futures. We'll set an
average over a three-month rate. So I
might have a rate that does that.
Another future that does that and that
might have a little stub period in here
which you know can go back to that
future. So each future will be set and
it's essentially the average over the
term of the future. So what CME then did
was they did a fit of this model to the
futures contracts and they then
interpolate the daily rate say for six
months which will run from here to about
here.
So they look at that and they'll work
out what the equivalent six-month term
rate is based on
these rates to compute that.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, I think I think I'm not asking
this question. Oh, sorry. I think for a
second.
>> Anyway, so you know, CMA came up with
that. The loan guys like it. Again, you
know, end user corporates don't want to
deal with all the mechanics of daily
sets and operational stuff. It's just a
pain in the ass for them. Um, so they're
happy to let somebody else do that. Um,
you know, it's the usual set in advance,
pay six months or three months from now,
fine. that makes everyone happier. Um
the Fed however doesn't want this to
become a de facto new LIBORE rate. So
they actually have quite severe
restrictions on how much the dealers can
trade in it. Essentially dealers are
only allowed to trade it to hedge their
loan portfolio. Uh which also is an
interesting feature which means it's an
entirely one-way market because you know
banks issue loans. They have to hedge
it. It's all in the same direction. So
there's a very substantial basis between
sort of regular vanilla sofer swaps and
the term sofer swaps. you know,
something around four or five basis
points, which again, in a market context
where that's 20 or 30 times a bid offer,
it's way outside the bid offer range.
Um, there's another sort of older
version of sofur called Fed funds, which
is really average of of slightly
different Fed funds drawing similar to
sofur at still in wide use. And there's
a whole lot of other crazy rates, prime,
disco, you know, municipal or military
housing rates and all sorts of other
stuff. Disco is my favorite rate. Not
for any reason other than I like the
name but which is a Fanny made discount
rate.
Okay.
Okay. So now discounting rates. One of
the questions is how do you work out
what the discounting rate is going to
be? For example, what rate should you
use to discount you know a future
payment?
So let's assume we have you know a
simple case of a fixed payment f for
fixed at a time t. We're assume some
discounting rate and we'll value the
payment today. give a present value of
P. Now we have to fund this rate. So we
have you know we generally in in this
world you assume that you are not just
you know spending money out of your back
pocket. You're going to go borrow money
from somewhere and use it to purchase
this thing. So we'll buy P and we're
going to buy at whatever our funding
rate is. So whatever we can borrow money
at that's what we will do to fund it.
And now just think a little bit about
from one day to the next day. What are
the cash flows involved here? You have
two of them essentially. you have you're
going to have to pay money to borrow in
your you will have to pay interest on
your borrowing. So whatever interest
rate you've done for one day you're
going to pay that and then your
underlying asset which is the fixed cash
flow in the future will increase in
value a little bit because you're
getting one day closer to its payment.
Okay. So the interest paid you know the
interest is just going to be whatever
the present value of that is be it t not
times the borrowing rate um over 360. So
that's how much you're paying to fund
this. And the increase in value, it's
going to go up by yesterday's value
times 1 plus r over 360. That's sort of
the the compounded rate occurral factor
or the change in that is you know again
the uh value times r over 360. Notice
that the first and the third equation
have very similar forms here. The only
thing different are the two rates.
So this is actually going to imply those
rates have to be the same or there's an
arbitrage here.
So that means that your discounting rate
that you should be using to discount un
you know future cash flows is whatever
your funding rate is. So whatever you
can borrow money at that's the
appropriate rate to discount future
flows at.
Now if those rates are different you
know there's a trade. You can either
borrow cheaper than you can invest or
you can invest cheaper than you can
borrow and you do one or the other and
that'll come back.
This actually this is a very you know if
you only pick one thing away from the
hour and a half we're spending here
remember this because this is you know
funding and discounting are the same.
Okay let's talk a little bit about some
of the products just going to talk about
the vanilla ones. So the question is how
do I compute what I think um forward
rates should be and what projections of
those should be. So what I'm going to do
essentially is build a curve uh to do
that I'm going to start with by thinking
what are the easily observable
instruments in the market. What can I
see out there that I can think I you
know whatever my pricing uh model is
going to be these are the things it
needs to hit because I can trade these
things.
Some of the common ones we're talking
about are CDs which are certificate of
deposits. These are very short-term uh
bank lending borrowing. You know, you
can walk into a bank and buy a one-mon
CD at four and a half% if you want.
Maybe a three-month one, six-month one.
Doesn't go much beyond that. Maybe a
year, you know, again, fairly liquid,
quite common. Interest rate futures,
very liquid products, uh, can do that.
And finally, interest rate swaps.
Now, so for each of these, we're going
to work out what is the price of this as
a function of my discounting curve. So,
and then given that the cash rates, I
can invert that to find what my
discounting implied curve is. that
prices all these instruments back to
market.
So CDs, you know, nothing too hard here.
You know, I buy a CD, I get the amount I
invested plus the rate accured over the
time. The value of that is that forward
uh interest amount plus the forward
return of my principal discounted back
or inverted. I just get, you know, Z is
one over one plus R delta T. That's
again, that's a thing you're going to
see all over the place.
These rates are well observable. They're
a little little bit tricky because a
swaps test typically can't necessarily
trade them because these CDs are funded
products. I have to actually, you know,
buy them. I want a 100 million CD. I
need to give somebody $100 million. I
have to get that. Swap desks don't like
that. They, you know, they prefer
derivative instruments which are not
unfunded instruments because you just
have to put less cash up front and
everybody likes less cash up front
because it means you can do more,
leverage yourself up more, uh, and so
on.
Okay. Second one is interest rate
futures. Uh again, very liquid
contracts. Uh US ones trade on the CME
exchange in Chicago. Uh every country
generally has, you know, a relatively
active short-term rate. Canada trades on
Montreal. Um the UK contracts trade on,
I believe, the LME. The Euro contracts
trade on the Euroex. Japan contracts
trade on um Tokyo, I think, stock
exchange.
So, um two main contractors, a one-month
contracts and a three-month contracts.
They're slightly different, which is a
bit annoying. Three-month contract
trades on a compounded rate. One-month
contract trades uh on a average rate.
Three-month contract goes from ImMate to
Imm. IMM is international monetary
market, which was an old market in
Chicago that sort of set the standards
here, which is the third weddednesday of
every March, June, September, December.
Uh it's just when the contracts settle
and that's fine. The one month contracts
trade on a calendar month. So today's
contract started in September 1st, we'll
settle on October 1st. I think maybe off
by a day there. The futures settle at
100 minus uh the rate. So you know, if I
have a interest rate of 5% when I'm
settling a future, that'll be a 95
price. And so and again,
people just did it that way because they
like to know markets rallying, contracts
go up, markets selling off, contracts go
down. For bonds, price and yield move in
opposite directions. So yields go up,
prices go down and so on. So that's why
they set the uh 100 minus that line.
There's a small convexity adjustment
here as well dealing with futures
margining and I'm going to just wave my
hands and gloss over, but it's something
you have to be conscious of. Uh futures
do daily margining. It's a standard part
of a futures contract. So if I have an
interest rate futures contract and I you
know I enter in into it and generally
you'll enter into a futures contract at
no upfront cost aside from some initial
margin perhaps market moves up you know
futures contract goes from 90 to 91
they'll give me one back in margin if it
goes from 90 to 89 I have to pay one to
remar it so at the end of every day you
settle up the net move on that day and
they do this to sort of minimize credit
exposure between that but if I think if
I have an interest rate contract you
When the price of the contract goes up,
I'm getting money back. But the the fact
that the price went up implies rates
have gone down. So that means I can
reinvest my money and now at a lower
rate or if the contract goes down in
value, uh I have to fund that more
because I need to anti up more margin to
the exchange, but I'm having to do that
at a higher interest rate. So this sort
of correlation between the uh flows of
money and what it's going to cost me to
borrow or lend that introduces a small
uh valuation impact.
Okay, so let's talk about interest rate
swaps, which are probably the biggest
single uh product on the planet. Uh this
is basically an agreement, a custom
agreement between two counterparties to
exchange two sets of cash flows. In the
most uh simple case, one of these is a
fixed rate. So I'm going to pay you 5% a
year for 10 years. And the other one is
a floating rate. I'm going to pay you in
um compounded so far. I'll pay you
annually every 10 years. We'll do that
for 10 years. Uh and then we'll call it
a day. Uh there many many variations of
these structures. There's all sorts of
crazy stuff and you you know imagination
is the limit here. As long as you convin
somebody else to do the other side of
it. They're a tremendously useful
instrument. Um they're great if you know
if I need to hedge something or change
my risk profile. It's a very efficient
way to do it. These are all derivative
products means they generally don't use
balance sheet. They don't take a lot of
upfront capital. They're cheap to fund.
So they're quite popular uh for those
reasons
and I said they are the most liquid uh
interest rate product out there.
They're one of these things that you
know there's a lot of mechanics to get
it right. Um in particular you know if
you if you enter you know you work in
this field you will get very good at
data arithmetic which is sort of a
stupid thing but um I mean I remember
once I was interviewing a guy and he
just done a PhD in numerical methods I
think and one of the questions he asked
me which was a great question so you
know keep this in mind when you're
interviewing he said if I come and work
for you a year from now what will I know
now what will I know then that I don't
know now and I said you will know how to
do data arithmetic he looked at me kind
of funny but went away and they actually
gave a job and he took it and he's
fabulous guy and he came back a year
from now and said you know you were
right you know I know how to tell you
know between my birthday and today how
many days are there it's not a unique
answer to that one by the way just to
make it come depends on your conventions
um and I'm also going to guess in
interest rate swaps at least 90% of all
problems are date related that's the
first thing you want to look at do I
have the dates correct because you know
am I using the right holiday calendars
uh and holiday calendars again it's
another one of these things that's
occasionally annoying you They're they
change. We had Junth added a couple
years ago, for example. We had the
Queen's funeral added. Every time a
president or ex-president dies, there's
a holiday and just these, you know,
Canada had truth and reconciliation day
added recently. So, you know, you have
to make sure you build your models to
account for, you know, the fact that
holidays may be dynamic. So, I just put
on there a simple sort of standard
dollar swap roll out and you there's a
half dozen different steps to actually
get what are the acral periods and the
cash flows and the payment dates and the
reset dates. You know, you start with
today, you go to the trade date. It's a
forward starting date. From that, you
typically add two days. You go to the
effective date. You then add the tenor
of the swap to get the maturity date,
unjusted maturity date. You then roll
that back in increments of the payment
frequency. Get the unadjusted roll
dates. And then you adjust everything
based on a holiday calendar, which
typically be New York banking or
something.
Um, and again, you got to be really
precise on the calendars. Another one of
the questions I like to ask people is
how many distinct dollar calendars do
you think exist in terms of swaps
monitor which is a standard source for
all calendar data. How many dollar
calendars do you think they have? Any
want to take a guess?
So I have New York banking for example.
I might have New York Fed. I might have
somebody guess
no penalties for getting it wrong.
Okay, Peter, what's your guess? You've
been around for longer.
>> Let's see. Um,
I would guess maybe 150.
>> You're in the right ballpark. Last time
I checked, there was 294.
And they're all, you know, every
exchange has got its own calendar and
they're all different. Every major
business center has its own calendar.
And it's just, you know, if you get the
wrong calendar, you're going to price
stuff on the wrong date and you're going
to mispric things. Uh, and then winner's
curse rule says if you price something
wrong, you only get the trade when it
hurts you. So, um, and again, dates are
just an enormous pain.
Okay, value of the swap, we're going to
do it in two pieces. We'll start with,
um, the fixed side. So, fixed side is
relative forward. We roll out all the
cash flows. We work out how much we're
paying on what dates we're paying. We
then, you know, from our curve, get the
uh, uh, discount factors there. Sum it
all up. So in this case I've just got C
which is the coupon rate. Delta is the
acrual fraction. So if it's an annual
swap that'll be our round one notional
and then times the discount factor. Sum
it up. That's a present value of the
fixed side.
Floating side's a little harder but same
idea but instead of the um coupon rate
I've got the forward rates uh which are
little F. So I have to work out what the
forward rates are but you know we'll get
to that in the next slide. uh you know
some mechanics are about what is the u
what are the particular specifications
is it set at the beginning at the end is
it forward maybe a spread in there but
you end up with there sort of two
different uh curves you here I need one
curve to generate the forward rates from
and another curve to generate the
discounting factors from in the vanilla
swap those are both the sofur curve so
they're actually only one curve okay so
what do you want to do here
there's another bit of magic here that I
can actually generate an employee
floating rate from fixed flows only. So
if I assume I can borrow fixed rate
bonds, I can borrow one at a given at a
first date, invest it and pay it back at
a later date, invest it at the unknown
floating rate and then pay it back at
the end. Uh and I'm assume I'm going to
invest at a rate that's a fair trade. So
PV of that is zero. So I end up here
with, you know, the initial term there
is me borrowing the money. I have time
t0 me getting the interest rate at time
one and me getting the principal back at
time one. So given all that sums to zero
I can work out what the implied forward
rates from this discounting curve are.
So I use that plug it through the swaps
uh and now I've got a uh swap market. So
for an implied swap markets you know
generally when you do a swap it's
usually done at a zero PV or something
pretty close to a zero PV. So when I
look at the two legs and sum them up,
I'm making zero. I've got, you know, the
fixed side plus the float side. You
know, both just the sum of the fixed
rates times the discounting factors. Uh
and then, you know, subtracting the
float side giving factors, do some
arithmetic, and I get the uh what the
implied swap rate coupon is.
Now, this is useful because swap rates
are observed. I go to my favorite
Bloomberg screen, I can see all sorts of
swap rates. So that's what I have to
work out my zero curve to fit those.
Any questions? I feel like I'm just
motoring through this here right now.
So, yep.
>> Can we get these these slides? This is a
question. This is a question.
>> Sorry. What was the question?
>> I was going to ask if we'd get the
slides. I don't know if they posted.
>> I can certainly send them. I don't think
I have them, but
>> we don't have them.
>> There is there is nothing too top secret
in any of this. Um that's how you do.
>> See Andrew, one comment. Um I'm not a
fixed income expert, but um the zero
sort of present value at trade
initiation is quite an important uh
feature I think where it um encourages
people interested in either side of the
swap to be comfortable with uh making
the trade. Yeah, that's sort of the
so-called par rate, which is the rate
that prices it at par, aka for a swap,
that's zero. Um, you could price it at
something other than that. And, you
know, again, bid offers in this market
are usually a tenth of a basis point,
two ten of the basis point. So, it's
around zero. Um, you know, some of the
structured transactions will have swaps
that are way off market and then, you
know, that may get accounted for
elsewhere or that just may be where
you're taking your P&L out of.
Just another comment that the a long
time ago, this is like the late 80s, um
I was at the Sloan School and uh swaps
were becoming very popular. And one of
the reasons they were becoming very
popular was that certain corporations
could access sort of fixed rates at very
low rates and less uh creditw worthy
companies could not have access to such
good rates for borrowing but did have
access to floating rates and so these
corporations would sort of pair up uh
with a swap. I don't know to what extent
the swap market now is
>> it's I think it's well past that but
>> but at the time if I'm a lower rated guy
and I can maybe borrow short term but
nobody's going to l lend me money long
term because they don't trust you know
I'll be around in 20 years but maybe
they're they're comfortable that I'll be
here in three months and have another
guy who can then fund for 20 years
because he's a high credit rating. We
can both bore in respective countries
then do a swap. So I now have fixed rate
swaps and he has floating rate swaps and
depending how they want to manage their
treasuries that may be a great trade for
all sides. So yeah, again swaps are very
flexible. They let you move the risk
around in quite a flexible way and quite
a customizable way.
Okay. So let's talk now about the core
sort of uh valuation model really in uh
interest rate swaps which is the yield
curve. So we're going to parameterize
the yield curve. And a yield curve is
used to it's just to get a function of
the discounting as a function of time
which then feeds all of the other
valuation models. So, we're going to
parameterize it by a set of times and
zero uh zero coupon bond prices. You can
parameterize it in a number of different
ways, but this is one of the easy ones.
I also need to choose a method to figure
out what is my uh zero um disease if I'm
in between not points. So, maybe I have
annual knot points. So, I'll do a 1,
two, three, four, five up to 10 years
for my times and I'll have disease at
each of that. But suppose I need a four
and a half year discount factor. How do
I do that? lots of p lots of
possibilities here. Um first of all I'll
talk about in the not points you know
how do you choose which times to use to
your interpolate that simplest one which
is the most common one is you just use
the maturity dates of all your
instruments so I'm going to build it
with say one two three you know five
seven 10 years swaps I have not points 1
2 3 5 7 10 years use that that's easy
one uh there's other possibilities like
FOMC dates which we'll talk about in a
minute um you also have to be a little
careful on picking your knot points to
work well with your interpolation method
because some of them there's some you
can make bad choices here which will
give you unstable hedging.
We then are going to fit a set of market
observables here to get the Z's. So
given that we've chosen an interpolation
on knots, you know, we have hopefully n
knots and n points we can solve. Let's
talk a little bit about CDF spline. This
is a constant daily forwards. This is
one of the easy ones which you assume
that between your knot points your daily
forward rates are constant. So you end
up with a curve that looks like sort of
a skyline or a stair step or something.
Just an example there simple one where
you know in this case you can see what
my uh not points are. I think I have six
months a year uh two years, three years,
5 years, 7, 10 and 20 I believe and 30
and the forward rates are just flat in
between them. This perfectly good this
is really fast. Um this is a local
interpolation method which is one of the
key features. And what I mean by that is
if I'm looking at you know I want to
find a discount factor say there it only
depends on the value there and the value
there. It doesn't depend on anything
here or anything there. So I'm just
going to interpolate between those two.
>> Why do you not choose the not purity
based on minimizing error?
>> No on what?
>> On minimizing error.
>> How are you going to do that?
>> Like chubby chef.
you could um what you want to do the
thing in on the simple case is you want
to maintain a connection between your
not point and your calibration
instruments. So in this case I'm
choosing be maturities. You can do lots
of other stuff but you could for example
let's suppose you had this set of uh not
instruments to the not points here you
know if I choose uh say not points at 5
10 15 20 25 30 I'm oversp specified here
and I'm underspecified there. So you
need to choose it with regards to how
you're going to calibrate u particularly
uh and the other thing that comes out is
when I work out the simplest cases what
my hedges are. It's in terms of my yield
curve input instruments. So I want to
choose a good set of liquid observable
stuff that I can actually transact in to
do the hedging. There's a zillion ways
to do this and that's still you know 30
years in that's still a very active area
of research and discussion. So um lots
of stuff and and you know some of the
areas like some of the um uh computer
graphics for example has a lot of
advanced interpolation stuff you know
beastplines and beyond and all of those
are likely entirely uh relevant here
just haven't looked at it
anyway so this one gets you your very
characteristic shape so this is you know
probably the least smooth simplest fast
method so it's got popularities for that
on the other side the most smooth little
slower cubic splines. So in this case
I'm just going to fit a peiewise cubic
polomial here. So I'll work out all what
my little parameters are and then I'm
just going to you know sum it up. I have
four terms you know cubic in each
interval. I impose constraints at the
edge of the intervals on continuity and
smoothness and do that. Again this is
still a reasonably fast method is a very
smooth curve. Now this curve is not
local. This is a global curve and you
know if any of you go into interest rate
quant space you need to make up little
laminated cards saying I can have fast
local hedges or I can have smooth global
hedges and it can be anywhere in
between. But you know I've had this
argument for 30 years with traders. Um
traders always want you know if I'm
going to do a hedge of eightear
instrument they want it to be only seven
and 10 year hedges. They don't like it
when the hedges sort of spill over to
five years or 15 years. But you know
smoothness is a global property. So if
this is my curve and I'm you know I have
a point you know somewhere instrument in
this area and I'm um you know pricing it
you know it's affected obviously by
these two but if this point here was
down here I would have a different shape
through that area because I'm
maintaining smoothness again global so
what the global thing implies is that
I'm sensitive to points much farther out
from my maturity point and again this is
an argument you know we've had for
decades um some of the smooth methods
are better than others. Cubic spine is
probably the worst um because it is the
most smooth. I guess you could do a
quintic spine or something if you really
wanted to be uh sort of pathologic, but
uh that would be a weird thing to do.
Okay, so then how do I calibrate? You
know, I can write my error function. I'm
going to price each instrument as a
function of my my uh proposed curve. I'm
going to, you know, from that take the
difference between that and what the
actual observed price is.
So if I can then just if I have uh you
know n knots and n calibration
instrument I just solve that exactly you
know pick your favorite numerical solver
and off you go or in some cases you can
actually bootstrap it and be fast or if
I want to relax that constraint that I
have to have the same number of
calibration instruments as points. Maybe
I'm going to do a le squares fit. I can
just pick my favorite minimizer and uh
let it go and see what we come up with.
Now you can also include lots of other
stuff in your objective function other
than just the errors. So you know one of
the stuff we built with for example are
I want smoothness constraints. So I'm
going to underspecify a curve but then
I'm going to impose additional
smoothness constraints because I want my
curve to be smooth. That's fine. Uh I
can also drop the exact fit uh
requirement a little bit. You know there
is no single price on it. There's always
a bid offer. So maybe I'm happy with my
curve prices things to within a bid
offer. That's close enough. I can't
distinguish that from an exact fit and
any a number of other uh extra
constraints you can add here.
Okay. Now just one of the other ones and
actually you know when we take a look at
rates so this is uh sofer rates over the
last I think three or four years. This
doesn't look very smooth. All right.
This in fact looks very stairsteppy. And
what you'll notice here is the rates are
this is a little this is an interesting
spike cause for tax uh receipt issues
which caused a lot of concernation in
the industry at the time but we'll
ignore that for now. Um you know it's
generally flat and then it goes up. It
stays flat. It goes up. These are the
central bank meeting dates. So these are
when the FOMC gets together and decides
we're increasing rates. The rate the
daily rates will generally stay constant
until the next FOMC rate change. Um, you
can tell this graph actually needs a 50
basis point drop off of the right side
of that because they just cut rates last
week. Um, so this is this looks very
sort of like the CDF function for
example. So there's another curve model
that I think is probably pretty much uh
pretty widely used at this point in the
industry which is I'm going to build my
not points um based on the central bank
meeting dates because those are the only
dates that rates are going to change in
general or going to change materially
and I'll assume it's flat in between.
Uh so that's one again I think that
started six or seven years ago and it's
pretty far as I know almost everybody
uses this methodology now where you have
generally the central bank will publish
the next two years meeting calendar if
you really want to you can apply beyond
that but two years is about the stuff
you know uh and then we'll assume say a
spline beyond that um you end up with a
little bit of issues on how do you
choose your instruments there's eight
meeting dates eight central bank meeting
dates a year four quarterly futures a
year so you have a slight under
constraint raint issue here. So you need
to fill that in somehow. You can include
the one year sorry one month futures
smoothness constraint. You have to do
something else but that's fine. Um also
recently in the last couple years um
actual swaps between meeting dates have
started to trade. So basically this is a
bet on the implied rate you know after
this meeting date. So if you think the
Fed is going to cut it the next uh
meeting, which I think is early
November, you can buy a swap from
November through I think middle or late
December at this rate. And that's
essentially the implied rate after the
meeting. So I don't know what they're
think probably thinking is they're going
to drop 25 basis points. Fine. They
surprise people a little bit by dropping
50. Fine. But there's there's
instruments that will directly uh uh
probe that and reflect that rate. So
that's also something you can do.
Okay. Um, yep. So I said we can make a
hybrid curve and this works pretty well.
Lots of other stuff in curves and this
is still
very active area of research. There's
other features that you sometimes want
to account to. For example, turns um
there's an interesting feature where
there's dates that are significant
accounting dates year ends. For example,
generally corporates will post their
earnings and their balance sheets return
in assets on December 31st or you know
quarterly. So what that does is puts a
premium to borrow money over that rate.
If I'm a bank, I want to minimize my
balance sheet when I'm reporting what it
is because I'm going to be judged uh by
the investor community and things like
return on assets on total assets and
things like that. So I don't want my
assets to spike over year end. On the
other hand, money is money and if
somebody wants to borrow money over year
end for some other reason, I'll do it.
But I'm going to charge them a premium
for that.
So you find the curves actually
you know if I actually look at a curve
it might be like but then I'll have a
big spike you know every year so maybe
that's one year where this essentially
is the premium for borrowing over year
end so those you can include in curves
as well and you'll find um some of the
hedge funds in particular are slightly
nasty. So they'll do a trade where they
want to do one swap to this date and the
second swap opposite direction to that
date. So they're really just picking out
uh whatever you know curve building
you're doing over year end and you know
it's very easy to get that wrong and you
know you do it enough size and it's real
money.
So and the other way there al also other
sort of approaches you can do for
example do a PCA method you know one of
the things on the curve is I may build a
curve typically it's about 50 inputs for
a dollar curve you know there's widely
varying liquidity among all those 50
typically there's going to be about a
half dozen that are the super liquid
points and then the rest of the stuff
will slowly uh become less liquid so you
can if you want say look at historical
data work out what my factors are pick
the first half dozen factors which
represent sort of shapes of curve moves
have those driven by my most liquid
stuff and use that for a curve. Um that
works quite well in bond world for
example. So lots of other possibilities.
Okay, talk briefly about hedging.
So one of the things you want to do if
you're running a trading book of some
sort or asset management or something,
you want to know what is my risk? um you
know and risk generally in in the sort
of trading desk view of the world is how
much do I make or lose if my say rates
go up or down. So I'm going to use just
simple PV1 is my main risk measure which
is just a sensitiv basis point increase
you know nothing too I've got a
two-sided difference here just PV at
rates plus a bit minus PV at rates down
a bit normalized by two times the size
of that do this parameter and I get a
delta strip and that's typically what
I'm going to use for hedging that's what
I'm going to have limits put on me
former management you know it's what I'm
going to use and an assortment of other
things uh very standard approach and you
can do that for you
any parameter you want. You work out
just what is my sensitivity, but
generally a brute force bump and reval,
change a parameter, repric, take the
difference. You can get a bit cleverer
than that if you want to go to sort of
analytical hedge computations and things
like that, but the Gore method is still
the same.
So that's first order. I can also, you
know, depending on my product, you know,
everything has got a little bit of
convexity and depending on what my
trading style is, may or may not matter.
So I might want to do a gamma which is
my second order uh risk. Generally the
change in PV uh squared by D rate
squared.
Many definitions of gamma and at least
in in equity world it's a little
simpler. In interest rate world it's a
little more annoying because interest
rates I said you have a say a yield
curve that might have 50 inputs on it.
So my delta will have 50 computations.
Gamma is going to be that squared
because I need to bump each of them in
pairs. 2500 computations is very
expensive. So you probably don't want to
do that. So again, you can do a parallel
gamma or factory gamma, a number of
other approaches, or just use scenario
analysis. Lots of ways to get your
higher order terms uh in there.
Okay. Um as soon as you start actually
hedging in practice, you hit a whole lot
of uh practical issues that you had to
be aware of. Um you know, how much is
the uh higher order terms contribute?
You can have third order terms, fourth
order terms, cross terms, and so on. All
sorts of weird convexities.
How do I choose my bump size? You know,
the standard is a basis point, but
that's really just for reporting. And
this depends a little bit on your
numerical method and what you're doing.
So, if I'm in a Monte Carlo world, for
example, I have a Monte Carlo pricing
engine, I probably want to bump a little
bigger because there's Monte Carlo noise
because it's, you know, it's random
numbers, it's a little noisy. So, my
bumps are too small. My difference is
going to be quite small. some of the
other methods for example some of the
PTE based methods if I'm doing a large
bump I can see grid effects starting to
hit it so there's a lot of numerical
issues here and everyone's a little bit
different
said there's some sequential bumps
there's all sorts of little convexities
come in and I said you're exposed to
your interpolation method if I'm doing a
local interpolation my hedges are
concentrated around my maturity if I'm
doing a global one they're going to be
more distributed so this was something
that again you get into lots of
arguments with people about pretty
quickly
One of the other things to do depending
on your jurisdiction maybe a regulatory
requirement is to do your P&L
attribution. So, you know, I, you know,
come in in the morning, I've got a set
of positions, set of whatever market is,
whatever. At the end of the day, I go
home, I've made or lost some amount of
money. So, one of the key questions is
why? Where did that come from? Am I a
genius trader? Did I get the market
right? that I just have a lot of client
flow that I you know took a bit offer on
what happened. Uh it's also a very good
check on how well your model's working.
Uh which is interesting.
So you know the P&L I said from you know
yesterday close to today's close because
you can value everything. So how did you
get that?
You know generally there's three main
components and this is also something
that you will have arguments about till
the heat death of the universe on
particularly on the theta component. You
have a change due to the portfolio. So
did I buy and sell trades? Did I do
unwinds? Did things get assigned to me?
Do I have resets? Did I exercise
options? All of that will have an
impact. Uh there's the passage of time.
That's the complicated one. So I went
home, you know, yesterday and I came in
today. Market hasn't moved. But what
does market not move actually mean? Um
it's a very subtle effect. Um because
interest rate curves are a function of
you know time versus this. So when I
move this date to that date, what do I
hold constant and what do I let change?
And there there's more than one
intellectually defensible answer to do
this. Um so anytime I tell people you
just be very precise, make sure you know
exactly what you're doing. And again,
there's lots of defensible answers, but
you all have to agree on your notation.
And then finally, there's the more
common one that people think about,
which is move. So you know, I'm long a
billion bonds. I got a, you know, a PV1
of what is that? $10 million in 01 or
whatever. Rates moved five basis points,
I made $50 million. Well done me. Rates
went down three basis points, I lost $30
million plus well done me. Um, so market
impacts easily. Uh, and I said the
portfolio change is also one of these
ones. It's mechanically just a pain in
the ass. You know, you get introduced to
booking systems and all your operational
flows and things like that which are uh
can confuse things a lot.
Okay. Finally, you know, just still
bouncing between subjects. So, we still
got a few more minutes. Um, you know,
clearing is another thing that came in
post 2008.
One of the features in uh 2008 is people
became acutely aware of their
counterparty exposure. So, I do a trade
with you and you know, we do it at zero
PV initially. Time passes, now it's
worth $10 million to you. Great. You
know, this is not realized money. This
is money I owe you in the future. If I
go bankrupt, you lose 10 million bucks.
So, people become very aware of and if
you go bankrupt, I get a $10 million
freebie. So, you know, assuming I can
argue with your bankruptcy judge. Uh,
fine. So, there's a, you know, people
have been very acutely aware and Lehman
really brought that home because they
were a huge uh dealer. You know, they
had many, many billions, hundreds of
billions of dollars of derivatives with
people. Um, it by the way is why JP
Morgan is doing so well now because they
were the only bank still standing in the
fall of eight. So people had to replace
an enormous amount of Lehman hedges and
JP was the only one still actively
trading. Goldman's was in trouble.
Stanley was in trouble. Bank America
where I was just bought Merryill.
Merryill went bust. Um you know all the
City Group was having all sorts of
issues with guaranteed uh credit
exposures and things. So JP Morgan just
made out, you know, the bid offers went
up by about a factor of 20 for a month
or two there. And you know, they just
raked it all in. You know, good for
them, I guess.
not good for anybody else. So, um, so
one of the things the regulators decided
after that was people would have to use
clearing for vanilla swaps. The clearing
is a concept that's been around in
futures forever, but in in swaps it's
relatively new. So, what that means is
say I'll do a trade with you and we'll
do a trade fine. You guys, we agree in
the terms. We will then both assign our
side of the trade to a central clearing
house. Say CM CME and LCH London
clearing house and the CME are the two
big ones. So then both of us now face
say the CME and you and I are now
separated and we don't care what happens
to each other. You can go bust and you
know I'll be sad but I'm not losing
money. So um so that came in and
clearing houses are are generally big.
Um you know one of the worries is we've
traded off sort of small and large
potential disasters for a very small
number of enormous disasters. you know,
if LCH goes bust, you know, it's time to
get, you know, guns and ammo and head
for the hills because it it's going to
be just a complete disaster in the
financial world. They are so big and so
integrated with everything. And all the
members post various margins to them and
membership fees. So, no, they're pretty
robust, but if something did weird
happen, you know, it would be quite uh
unpleasant there.
Okay. Now, one of the things about the
clearing houses is the dealers are
required, but you you end up with this
now situation where a dollar I'm paying
to LCH is not the same as a dollar I'm
paying to the CME. You know, these are
these are not fungeable amounts even
though they're both dollars.
So, it's quite interesting because I
can't, you know, if I have a swap with
LCH and I swap with CME, I can't offset
these two. Um, I can in my books, but
not in terms of operationally and
collateral and everything. So what
happened uh probably eight or nine years
ago is quite a significant spread opened
up between these two. So this is you
know from 2017 I guess the tradition is
one of the big uh brokers. You know this
is the difference between if I want to
pay fixed on CME versus pay fix and LCH.
So again if I'm doing a 30-year swap
it's now three and a half basis points
between them. And again this is a market
where the bid offer is 0.2 of a basis
point. So you know the question is why
did this you know this persisted for a
long time. It's actually a flipped sign
recently, but this was around for years.
Anybody want to guess why this kind of
new? Why can't I just arbitrage this
soy? I'll go receive fix and CME. I'll
pay fix and LCH and I'll collect three
and a half basis points and, you know,
go by my island in the Caribbean. Why
can I not do that? Or why did nobody do
that?
Anybody want to hazard a guess even?
It's quite interesting and it's it's one
of the pretty core things in a post08
world which makes things a lot harder.
No guesses there. Yeah.
>> Like is there a spread?
>> Pardon?
>> Like is there a spread like when you're
long something that like you receive
versus when you're short that's like
different?
>> But why does that persist? Why can't I
just Well, you know, there's enough
people out there that are happy to make
money. Why can't they just take that
out? If you told me I can make three and
a half basis points running for 30
years, I'll do that all day and that'll
make me a ton of money.
Anyway, there's a couple reasons
the you have to post margin on both
sides. The clearing houses as part of
doing clearing require you post for a
swap. It's typically a percent or 2% of
the notional. So, you have to post money
to them on both sides. You're now double
posting margin that costs you and that's
the main driver of it. Some of the other
features are other products trade on
these these clearing houses and you can
net them. For example, CME is the big
futures uh counterparty. So if I'm long
a ton of of interest rate futures and
short a ton of swaps, I get at least
partial netting of my margin between the
two. Then there's a couple sort of non-
less economic things. Um this thing was
largely driven by some very large US
asset managers, people like PIMCO who
was ginormous that wanted to pay fixed
all day uh to hedge their loan
portfolio.
They are a little you know less trusting
of the LCH because the LCH is owned by a
consortium of dealers. CME is owned a
private company. So they their thought
was the LCH is going to be more
favorable to dealers because the dealers
own them. So if it comes down to a juris
a legal issue or something you're
they're going to be biased. Um the other
one is they want it to be in US
jurisdiction. LCH is in London L being
in London. Uh and they just want you
know they want to deal with the legal
issues in the US because that's where
they have their expertise and where
they're based. So a couple things again
it's quite interesting but one of the
things this introduces the fundamental
thing is that because of the margining
requirements there's a spread here that
can exist between things that would
formally be arbitrageable
and it can persist FX has all sorts of
these too and this is sort of coming to
the point that actually to correctly and
completely calculate the prices and
stuff you need to include a lot of
things outside of the core pricing of
the instrument how are you going to
margin it what capital do you have to
post it or is there any other kind of
things like this that are going to cost
you money that have not traditionally
been accounted for.
And I would say one of the huge sort of
quant efforts over the last 15 years is
to been work out what are all these
extra costs and how do I push them back
into the upfront pricing. You know, if I
if I do a swap for a very small P&L with
a counterparty and then it turns out I
have to post an enormous margin. It's
going to cost me way more than that.
I've just done a money losing trade. So
I don't want to do that. That you can't
do too many of those or you're not
trading anymore. Um so you have to
correctly account for all of these extra
costs and that's quite non-trivial um
just both mechanically in your system
side as well as sort of conceptually and
a lot of these things are portfolio
effects. So how do I then allocate that
to individual trades is not necessarily
super obvious.
Okay, good. Coming to the end at about
the right time. quick quick uh blurb
about electronic trading which is uh you
know if any of you guys get into this
area in your careers this is one of the
very uh sort of quite interesting very
hot areas. Um electronic trading has
been around in equities for quite a
while. Um my sort of standard metric is
equities is probably 10 years ahead of
foreign exchange which is 10 years ahead
of fixed income. And one of the graphs
there is from one of the data providers.
Um sort of the percentage of markets in
some of the fixed income products that
are traded electronically.
You know two basic. There's electronic
trading which I sit on my keyboard and I
go all computer does everything or I can
pick up the phone and I can call
somebody voice trading. Um so again
there's a sort of a spectrum here. On
the right, I've got the very liquid
stuff, you know, US equity products,
cash equities, those are all 90% plus FX
spot, all traded electronically
basically. And then I start to get less
and less European governments, US
governments, both predominantly
electronic, but you know, we're talking,
you know, 60 to 80% of the market here.
What you tend to see is a lot of the
smaller trades will go through
electronically for a couple of reasons.
You know, these are not market moving
trades, so people are happy to let the
machine do its thing. you know, if I'm
buying a million dollars of a treasury,
you know, that's not going to affect a
market that trades a trillion dollars a
day. If I'm buying, you know, hund00
million, maybe if I'm buying $500
million, I need to be careful because
that is going to move the market and
it's going to market against me and I'm
going to end up paying more than I would
otherwise do that.
And the other thing as I get down there,
so I sort of have some of the investment
grade corporates, high yield bonds, and
I get down to the left, which is really
not electronic, is things like emerging
market bonds and municipals. Um again
munis is one of these ones quite an
interesting market. Um uh before I was
at Missou I was at TD Toronto Dominion.
Um we acquired a MUN bond electronic
trading firm from Chicago which was just
tremendously successful. Uh and they
have about half of the electronic market
in munis. So munis is something that
there are huge number of bonds. There's
something like three and a half million
issuers in the country, which is the
states, um the towns, you know, bridge
projects, school boards, all sorts of
things that issue municipal bonds.
They're all a little different.
So, there's a lot of non-standardization
in the actual bond structures. And the
other thing, there's a tax advantage. I
don't know if you guys any of you guys,
you know, have a PA at this point or
hopefully in the future, not too much
longer. um you know muni bonds you don't
pay federal income tax on them which
means they're you know typically the
yields are about 70% of a taxable issue
because you get the same net after tax
yield this means it's a retail market
you know institutional investors don't
get the tax break so they are less
interested in unis retail investors
typically are not buying things in
blocks of 100 million they're buying
things in blocks of 5,000 or $10,000
something like that so the average trade
size is very small at TD they did you
know something like5 to10 10,000 trades
a day, but the average trade size I
think was $28,000, which in a government
market is is absurd. That's not even an
oddlot, but something, you know, the
janitor picks up at the end of the day
and just does something with
um so it's it's quite interesting, but
on the other hand, you do enough of it,
you can still make good money. You know,
emerging markets is another one where
the bonds are very idiosyncratic and
there's a lot of sort of very special
stuff. There's not really a generic
Chilean bond. you know, you have to know
exactly what it is, how is it paid,
what's the credit support, all of that.
So, these things are generally done over
the phone with somebody because, you
know, not not for the faint of heart
there, I would say. Um, but, you know,
as time goes on, you know, things are
slowly moving up here and, you know,
things are becoming more electronic. You
know, electronic is just it's faster,
it's cheaper,
uh, it's it's you're less sensitive to,
you know, people taking advantage of,
but you have markets, you can see where
the market is.
They're doing quite a variety of
participants here. Um, you sort of have
the trading shops. There's people like
XDX or Jane Street or Hudson River
Trading or folks like that. You know,
they don't have customers. They just
trade on their own account. They're very
good. They're very fast. You know, they
generally make markets in a lot of this.
Telling Peter a story I had at some
point. Um I was at a Thanksgiving dinner
or something with a big group of people
and one of the other people there had
just graduated from college with a PhD
in physics in microwave guides and he'd
been employed I think by jump trading uh
to work out the optimal microwave
transmission to reduce Chicago New York
latency because Chicago's where the
exchanges are New York where the
customers are and I just remember
talking to that guy and thinking Jesus
you know I think I was at Bank of
America at the time we are never getting
in front of this you know these guys are
just there are so advanced in this stuff
that you have to be very careful to pick
what you're doing. Um, so you know,
these guys are are super fast, super
good. This is a high frequency traders,
people like that. Then you have the
dealers, um, which are people like the
Bank of Americas or or, um, you know,
TDs, Morgan Stanley's. They generally
are trading, um, they're pretty good.
They're fast. They're not building their
own microwave towers. So, they're doing
that. They have customers, you know, uh,
customers are good. Customers want to
trade with you. The customers will pay
you a bit offer to do trade with you. So
you know I like that
and they're they're sort of you know low
latency but you know microsconds and not
nanconds and then there's the customers
who just want efficient execution and to
get sense that they're not being taken
advantage of and they're seeing a full
market and you know they're able to
decide what they want to do and there's
a bunch of other guys but those are sort
of some of the main uh market
participants here.
So pricemaking here it's it's you know
at least on on the dealer side which is
what I'm familiar with. I've never
worked at a prop shop, so I don't know
uh if those guys are much different. We
start by getting a good mid-market price
u either from liquidity providers if
it's a something that trades actively or
from a model if it's something that's a
little uh
you know, a little off the run. You're
then going to sort of skew the
mid-market price to what you're actually
going to offer the guy based on a whole
lot of stuff. Maybe risk, you know, what
is your current position on this
product? If this is a risk reducing
trade, you're willing to be more
aggressive just to get it off your
books. If this is a risk increasing
trade, you're generally going to want to
be a little more conservative because
it's going to cost you to manage it. You
know, who's the client? You know, is
this a good client that it's important
um you know, for you to keep good
relations with? You have other other
transactions as the firm which case
you're willing to be a little little
more aggressive with him. Is this a
toxic client?
It's quite an interesting study of how
do you evaluate client toxicity? And the
classic toxic client is again is some
sort of fast money guy will put out 10
requests to 10 different dealers for the
same trade at the same time. So if you
execute that, you'll then find nine
other guys have executed the same. So
your hedge is moved away from you. So
it's going to cost you more money to
hedge and you're probably losing money
on the trade. But how do you determine
if that's likely to happen or not? So a
lot of market microstructure things. Uh
also volatility. Um you know if the
market's in a particularly volatile
period, you're going to want to be a
little more conservative in your
pricing. widen out your bid offer
because the market might move away from
you before you can hedge. And then
there's a whole world of sort of
prediction models and um you know how do
you look at that and and you know what's
your estimate of where the next tick is
up or down and things like that and
there's all sorts of market micro
structure there. There's quite an
interesting area you can do. Um in
general the trading requires uh very
good integrated systems. You need to
have everything talking everything super
fast. you can't have, you know, one of
the bins of our existence at a previous
firm was the credit check. So, I had to
get a request from somebody to do a
trade. I had to determine if we had open
credit lines with them. By the time that
answer came back from our credit
systems, the deal had gone away. So,
that was a bit annoying. So, um, okay, I
think I'll end there and just open it up
for any more questions. I think we got a
couple minutes still, so I'm happy to
yak about anything as I said. So, um,
otherwise, I think we'll call it a day
there.
go skip through some
>> I guess like one of the main things that
people have been talking about recently
is just interest rates and like the
recent CL what is your like opinion on
the implications that changes in
u
just kind of understand like what type
of considerations that we can make
>> you know the biggest one from the guys
actually managing interest rate policy
is really inflation
you know, we've had a burst of inflation
here driven by things like the COVID
funds. You know, we pumped an enormous
amount of money into the economy um to
stop things collapsing in COVID and
that, you know, one of the ways that
showed up was inflation. Um Russia
invading Ukraine also popped energy
prices. So, that also popped inflation.
That's one of the big ones, you know.
Now, the downside is the Fed's trying to
balance that with employment. You know,
generally if rates are high, people are
not willing to borrow money because it
costs you more. you know, if I'm going
to start a business or something, I'm
going to want to um quite often borrow
money. The other huge connected thing in
that is home prices. Um you know, when
you look at, you know, in my lifetime,
what have I spent money on? You know, my
house is overwhelmingly the most
expensive thing I've bought. And then
also, every time you move, you know, you
buy furniture and paint and a new roof
and this so that's also a huge driver of
economic things. So, so I think in terms
of we've just I think just kicked into
an interest rate cutting cycle. U said a
few weeks ago they dropped it. Um, you
know, there's some arguments that they
kept the rates too high for too long,
but I think they started to cut. So, I
think the kind of things that you would
look to see is things like mortgages,
uh, home sales activity, business
startups, stuff like that. There's it's
quite pervasive in terms of how much,
how expensive is money is a huge driver
of a lot of activity. I don't know if I
answered your question or not, but okay.
So,
anything else?
>> Just one question with fixed income. uh
modeling y
>> uh I would guess that forecasting and
predicting rate changes would sort of
take a real backseat to sort of hedging
>> well again that's a subtly
>> it's a there's a subtly a subtly
difference here there's sort of two
kinds of fixed income research there is
the economics client-f facing research
which is a lot about that stuff here's
my prediction for the economy here's if
the rates cut this is what I think you
should do here's the positions and And
there's the internal area which is IM
which is more about pricing and hedging
of transactions which you know we don't
make any prediction. We don't care. We
just want to know how to hedge it under
that point. Uh we're good. So they're
sort of they're quite different in
outlook even though they're both sort of
fixed income research.
And I have no opinion of where rates are
going. If I did I wouldn't be standing
in front of you here. I'd be sitting on
my Caribbean island the pin coladas.
>> Could you could you also comment on the
municipal bond sort of what the
analytical uh challenges are there? A
couple of the challenges there are again
there's there's sort of a set of bonds
that are very idiosyncratic maybe the
project bond. So this is a bond where
the um the revenues come off of say you
know toll tolls on the Pennsylvania turn
bike they'll bond supported by that. You
know I don't know about you I have no
idea on the traffic in the Pennsylvania
turnbike and what that's likely to be.
So you know a lot of these things got a
big whack in COVID for example because
nobody went anywhere for a year so there
was no revenues to support them. So they
all got them. Um a lot of the other
munis um it's about what do you think
future tax policy is? So let's suppose
the average federal rate is I don't know
30% right now. So that means I'm willing
to take 70% of the treasury rate for a
mun bond. When I look forward I think
tax rates are going up or down. I have
no idea. I would suspect up but you
never know just given the deficit
situation but who knows. So there's that
kind of issue. Um,
a lot of the other issues when we're on
the trading and the quant side is, you
know, how do you figure out who's got
them? You know, so I want some I have
somebody who wants to buy a bunch of,
you know, double A New Jersey bonds. How
do I source those? So that's a lot of
data. That's one one of the reasons mun
are still very voice driven is the sales
guys know where the bonds are, so they
can get them out for you, you know,
whereas the machines just have no idea
who's got the bonds right now. So it's
hard to source the product at that
point. So that's some of the
complexities and
Thank you very much.
[Applause]