So, it's wonderful to be here and um
thanks so much uh to CIRC for organizing
um this day and um for the funding of
this project. Um I'm here representing
um Josh Tennibal and myself in this
collaborative work we um have done
together.
So we'll start off by pointing out an
interesting observation about moral
cognition that one of the most striking
features of the human moral mind is its
flexibility. We can make judgments about
moral cases that we've never seen
before. Is it morally permissible, for
instance, to get a haircut during a
global pandemic? Before a couple of
years ago, none of us had ever thought
about that issue before.
And there doesn't need to be a global
pandemic in order for the moral
landscape to change. There are new
technologies all the time, new
information, and new opportunities. And
we need to make decisions about how it's
morally acceptable to act in light of
these
changes. So what we do in our line of
work is we work at the intersection of
cognitive science and AI safety. think
thinking about the ways that the human
mind works, trying to understand that
with a certain kind of computational
precision in order to see if we can
inform AI safety, how AI systems can
navigate the human, moral, and social
world in a way that's morally acceptable
and safe. And the kind of ideal vision
of this program is that there should be
a dynamic exchange between these two
fields. that as we learn things about
human moral cognition that'll help make
AI systems safer. And then as we attempt
to build those things into AI systems,
we'll discover we actually don't
understand moral cognition as well as we
thought to originally. So th this works
in a kind of virtuous cycle as this
research program progresses.
What I'm going to do today is talk to
you mostly about the cognitive science
work that we did um writing down in
computational terms how you the human
moral mind works and then what I want to
do is sketch also how we think that what
we've learned about moral cognition
could be an important alignment target
for AI safety quite
broadly. Okay. So how does moral
judgment work? One thing seems obvious
just from a simple glance at our moral
world. Rules seem to be important. The
moral world seems to be guided by these
inviable rules. Often we use rules to
communicate moral expectations to one
another. We use them um to teach our
children how to act in social
situations. Um, there are rules about
the way we treat our experimental
subjects, what counts as honesty in
academic work, how we're supposed to
navigate complex um, relationships in
the workplace. Um, they're rules
everywhere and they often seem to be
written in stone and in fact sometimes
they literally are written in
stone. So why do rules play such an
important part of our moral lives and
our theories of morality? Well, there
are many reasons, but one of the most
important reasons is that they're
efficient. Our human minds are limited
in various important ways, and rules are
simple ways to articulate kind of
complex
ideas. So, def despite the fact that
rules seem like they have this rigidity
to them, there are also constant
exceptions. So, for instance, it seems
like there's one very simple rule about
stealing. don't steal. But on the other
hand, we also know that it's okay to
jump in into a cafe and steal a napkin
if you really need one. Yet, we also
know that you can't just take the whole
stack to refill your supply at home. So,
it seems like actually when we dig a
little deeper, we realize that we have
this kind of complex and subtle idea
about what the rule is, when it applies,
and when when it doesn't apply.
Um this is a a lovely example of this
sort of thing. So this is um the kitchen
from building 46 right across the hall
down the street from my old office when
I was postto. And if you zoom in here
you see that someone has written on this
bottle of soap do not steal. So the
question arises don't MIT graduate
students know that it's wrong not to
steal and certainly they do. So what was
this attempting to communicate? It seems
like basic somebody thought that um the
act of taking the do soap did not count
as stealing. So we have a vigilante um
soap um idea corrector who is trying to
tell you that because of the background
conditions here this actually does count
as a case of stealing. So the point here
is that we often have a fine grain um
idea about what rules are, but we can
sometimes go wrong with our use of rule
flexibility. Okay, so there's a lots of
mysteries about rules. Where do they
come from? What do we do when there are
no rules? How do we make new ones? And
how do we know when the rules apply and
they don't
apply? Rules are
flexible. And so we need theories in
order to understand what where and how
this flexibility
arises. So moral psychology has
typically used theories of moral
philosophy in order to get off the
ground in order to make models about how
the human mind works. And traditionally
in moral psychology we've relied on two
main theories of moral philosophy
deontology and consequentialism. Though
in our work, a central driving theory is
this these ideas from
contractualism. And so what we're
attempting to do is show that all of
these theories from moral philosophy can
be combined into a triple theory of
morality which explains not only where
rules come from but how they are
flexible and how they can be applied in
this flexible way.
So what that amounts to is pointing out
that the function of morality is
essentially to help us all get along.
But and that that is the core idea
behind contractualism that we can
understand what morality demands of us
by thinking about what everybody would
agree to. We can do this rational
negotiation for mutual benefit.
But the trouble is that is often
extremely difficult for the moral
situations that we find ourselves
involved in. We lack the time,
information, and processing power in
order to run this full um negotiation
that we would need to figure out how to
reach mutual benefit, the contractualist
ideal. So instead, we do a sort of
resource rational approximation of that
ideal. And what our theory proposes is
that the rest of the moral mechanisms of
cognition, things like using rules, um,
calculating outcomes, the things that
might come to mind when you think about
how we make moral decisions, what we
argue is that all of those mechanisms
are simply approximations of this
contractualist ideal. So what we've been
doing over the past year is actually
developing this theory and then positing
that this theory of how human moral
cognition works should act as a way of
aligning AI
systems. So I'll tell you more about the
specific ways um that we're studying
that in a minute. But what the broad
idea I want you to take from this is to
to understand that humans have these
limitations which is why we use rules
and other mechanisms in order to figure
out how to act in moral situations. AI
systems also have resource limitations.
They also have the imi limitations of
time, information, and processing power.
So if that's the case, we can use human
cognition as an inspiration for how to
have AI systems navigate the human moral
world as well. Okay. So how exactly do
we study this in humans? So I'll tell
you about a a couple of very specific
experiments um that we ran so you get a
sense of how how this sort of um
research goes. So we'll start off with
this question. How do we figure out when
the rules apply and when they don't? Um,
and this is work um with um Josh and my
awesome collaborators also um in the
computational cognitive science lab.
Okay, so we'll start off with what again
seems like a fairly simple rule, the
rule about waiting in line. So it seems
like there's one very simple rule about
waiting in line. Just get in the back of
the line and wait your turn, right? So
the way that we're going to be studying
this um is with in this like game
environment. And what the goal of this
the people in this game is is to collect
water from various water sources and to
deposit it in those buckets as quickly
as they can. So this is what happens
when things go well. People just pick up
water from the buckets and they just
kind of walk in this very orderly
fashion um all the way to the buckets
depositing the
water. Okay. And um sometimes one person
will get out of line and they'll go go
directly towards the water source, get
get the water and deposit it in the
buckets. So it seems like on the face of
things, what went wrong here is that
this person broke the rule, right? There
was a rule about standing in line. This
person got in front of the line without
waiting their
turn. But if that's the case, then we
have trouble explaining this particular
situation. So in this situation,
everybody is again waiting in line and
we see one person get out of line and go
directly towards the water source. But
in this case, while the person in some
sense broke the rule, in another sense,
we feel relieved that they actually
figured that out. After all, it seems
like what they did um benefits
everybody, including themselves, and
it's not clear why those people were
standing in line to begin with. So what
we want is ultimately a theory that can
explain the subtle ways that we
understand when breaking this rule is a
problem and when ultimately it's morally
permissible. So we um propose a
particular model of um how to go about
thinking about this and um it's an
approach that we've been studying for a
number of years now um called
universalization. Ultimately, we think
about this as a sort of um
contractualist heristic approximation to
an agreementbased ideal, though you
might have also heard of this if if
you've read any Kant. So, this is like a
a um a kind of Kantian model. And so,
the the thought is that when a person
looks at this person who's getting out
of line, they think um what would happen
if everybody in this situation felt at
liberty to get out of line? What would
that do in this universalized world? And
what they can essentially figure out is,
well, everybody would kind of be able to
find their way to the water and things
would actually go quite smoothly. This
would actually be a good world to live
in, a world where everybody broke the
rule in a case like this. But if you
contrast that to thinking about what
would happen if everybody felt at
liberty to get out of line in this case,
you realize you get a lot of chaotic
crashing. And that's just simply a bad
thing to do. So what we propose is that
people simulate this sort of
universalization reasoning to figure out
what would happen if somebody broke the
rule in this case. So what we do as an
experiment is we develop a whole series
of different maps that manipulate
various spatiotemporal features of this
sort of world. Um and we ask subjects
how morally permissible was it to do
that thing that that person did which is
always a case of getting out of line.
And what we can then do is model what
exactly would the world be like if
everybody gets out of line. So we have
this kind of agent-based simulation
where each of these people pretends that
no rule exists and just plans directly
towards the water source. And you can
see just as we anticipated everything
goes quite smoothly in this case and
things go badly in in other cases. Um so
then what we can ultimately do is build
a model that includes this
universalizability feature as well as
various other um features that you might
think matter for whether or not um this
breaking this rule is acceptable. Um and
ultimately we find that this is a good
way of understanding um how people are
making judgments in cases like this.
Okay. So here's one way that it seems
like people figure out how to break
rules. they think about what would
happen in this in this quite
sophisticated way if everybody broke the
rule in that
case. Okay. Um so I'll just tell you a
couple of more directions um that we're
taking with this project.
um one is to think about um exactly what
people mean when they communicate simple
rules. So for example um think about the
a park um where you might see a sign
that says don't walk on the grass and if
you're trying to figure out what that
rule means um similar to the case of
don't stand in line what does that rule
mean? You might think it just means
something like all policies that include
steps on the grass are prohibited. Um
but in fact, as as you'll see, um there
are lots of cases where actually it
might be okay to break the rule. Um so
while this path might be one that is
perfectly acceptable, also this path
might be one that's perfectly
acceptable. This being a hospital for
instance. Um, on the other hand, this
might not be um acceptable for somebody
to cut across the grass specifically to
go to um a coffee shop. And this might
not be acceptable either. This person is
headed to the hospital, but it seems
like maybe they actually don't need to
get there that
quickly. Um, what if the person um has a
pogo stick and takes this path to get to
the hospital? Well, they're not walking
on the grass, but it seems obvious that
that shouldn't be permitted either. What
if your dog has run onto the grass and
what you're doing is running over there
to try to get stop them from digging a
hole in the grass? What if you're a
gardener and you take this path across
the grass? So, all of these examples are
simply to get you to realize that when
we communicate a simple rule like don't
walk on the grass, you can actually
recover much more communicative meaning
than is simply articulated. So, one of
the one of the things that we're
positing this rule actually means is
something like, okay, there was somebody
who simulated a bargain of everybody in
the community who who brought their
needs to the table. And what they all
decided together is that sure, each of
us individually would benefit if we
managed to cut across the grass to get
wherever we were going a little bit
quicker. But if that were to happen,
then we would all lose the grass. the
grass would die and that would yield
this collective harm that is more
important than the benefit we would each
individually derive. And so what we're
arguing is all of that can be understood
by simply reading this sign don't walk
across the grass. And then what you can
do is use that simulated model to then
go and predict in these kinds of edge
cases or unusual cases whether or not
it's actually permitted for you to walk
across the grass in these in this case
given your simulation of what everybody
would agree to if they could talk about
it. Um so I'm not going to go go into
the specific like ways we test that and
the models we build and the data we
collect. Um but that's one of the the
kind of things that we're thinking about
right now. Okay. There's another um
couple of really exciting directions
here which I'll just touch on very
briefly. Um you'll notice that all of
the the studies that I've um talked to
talked about up until now um are done
with um in a very kind of western
context. So our subjects are um people
who live in the United States probably
think a lot like I think. Um, but what
we want to do here, especially if we're
trying to use this model of moral
cognition as a guide for AI alignment,
is to ensure that what we're studying is
something that's true of the human mind
and not just true of these particular
participants that we happen to talk to.
Um, so we have an awesome collaboration
going um with Nori Jacobe at Cornell who
has this pipeline where um he can
translate a um a set of stimuli into 80
different languages and run it in 60
different countries. So that's what
we're getting started on now. We're
using um this paradigm of water
gathering. Um, and when you kind of run
a a study like this cross-culturally,
you need to like really understand that
everybody understands everything that's
going on in the scenario. So, there's a
ton of checks to um make sure that that
happens. We translate the instructions
into lots of different languages and we
have various hypotheses about the types
of things that we might see depending on
how people how much people are using the
types of rulebreaking mechanisms that
we've introduced. So we have a set of
pilot data that's really exciting um
just in a handful of languages. But um
one of the main thing that we used the
CIRC funding for was to fund an awesome
student who got this started who has
since moved on to working on AI policy
in Washington. So that's an a awesome
opportunity for him, but we need help
with this project. So we're currently
hiring somebody who wants to um kind of
take up the mantle of this
cross-cultural work. Um so if that might
be you or somebody you know, definitely
um feel free to get in touch. This is an
extremely exciting project that's going
to have, I think, a big impact. Um,
okay. And yeah, with that, I'll take
questions. Thank you.
Questions for Sydney.
The first question that I have is that
lu have a genetic component to it like a
uh there are some rule that can be
inhaled. Uh so that will be a question
they have. Yeah. Does do rules have a
genetic component you ask?
Yeah interesting question.
Um really interesting question. Um,
so, oh gosh.
Um, yeah, I mean, in some ways this is
like one of the most foundational
questions of cognitive science, like
which parts of this sort of moral
cognition are um kind of embedded in our
minds in the architecture of our minds
and which are learned socially. Um, and
that's one of the things that we aim to
test with this cross-cultural study. um
are we going to see broad patterns that
look similar across cultures or do some
cultures just do a very different thing?
So the particular way you phrased your
question was are rules embedded in the
mind? Um and that'll depend a bit on
what you mean by a rule. So the thing
that we hope to find cross-culturally is
this mechanism of interpreting rules. Um
which is something like universalization
or a certain kind of like bargaining
simulation. Um though what I imagine we
might find is that those mechanisms are
used to apply to very different rules
that are designed um in in in different
cultures based on the context that they
emerge from. So I wouldn't be surprised
if we find rule similarity but simply
because environments are similar in lots
of places. But what I hope to find
cross-culturally is the same mechanism
of rule interpretation potentially. I
don't know. This is an empirical
question. Yeah.
Um, hi. Thanks. Um, I wondered if
there's a sort of temporal temporal
component to add to this. So, when do
you jaywalk or something? So it isn't
just your assessment now, but it's like
the rules are set to sort of be absolute
and yet people are making judgments
about under certain circumstances I'll
jaywalk, under other circumstances I
won't. And how you sort of fit that part
in.
Yeah. Um
yeah, exactly.
Um, so figuring I think like one of the
critical questions is to figure out what
counts as a morally relevant feature. So
when you say
um like time might matter, you probably
don't mean um is it like 12:00 or 12:01
or is it Tuesday or Thursday unless for
some reason that picks out something
important. Maybe the traffic laws are
one way on Tuesday and a different law
on Thursday. So what matters is figuring
out what is what is a morally relevant
feature of the context. How do you
represent that feature and how do you
then compute over it in order to get the
right answer. Did did I get your
question? Did I understand?
Yeah.
Uhhuh. Okay. Interesting.
Oh, okay. Okay. Yes. Okay. So, um
yeah. Okay. Yeah. So, that that's like
pretty critical to what we're thinking
about. So, um Yeah. Okay. So when rules
are are codified, they tend to like rule
makers tend to have particular
circumstances in mind. Um so for
instance, like somebody who's putting up
a sign that says no walking on the
grass, they might do that when they know
certain things about the community,
certain things about the health of the
grass and the sustainability of the
grass and what the weather is likely to
be, etc. But um if those things change,
then the applicability of the rule might
change. And as a person comes along,
reads the rule and understands the
context and the circumstances, they
might realize the rule didn't anticipate
my circumstance. And so I need to then
figure out what was the rule trying to
communicate and what should I do in this
case given my update about the context
and the relevant information. Yeah.
Yeah, that's exactly right. Awesome.
Well, I'm afraid with apologies to the
remaining questioners, we have to move
on. That's fascinating stuff. And maybe
you'll get an opportunity to ask Sydney
the questions sort of offline. Sorry
about that. Um, great. Thank you.