Hello. Uh, I'm Matt Carpenter and this
is this is Gaia AI. Uh, we are using uh
technology and sensors from uh our
team's time in autonomous vehicles and
uh applying that to build a forestry
management system from the ground up. So
forestry is a huge industry. It's
essential to the modern world and it
shows up everywhere in our daily lives
and it's getting broader all the time.
Uh from carbon sequestration to managing
for biodiversity while also mitigating
the growing risks of wildfires. There's
a lot going on in this industry. Uh and
the industry is also based on data and
methods that are over a century old.
Foresters going out into the field with
calipers and tape measures and this is
holding it
back. Our
system uses advanced algorithms like
SLAM AI specifically tailored for forest
environments to measure and map trees
below the canopy 100 times faster than
the current status
quo. We use this dense rich below canopy
data to train satellite imagery AI
algorithms to scale that information to
much broader areas.
We've worked with a dozen forest
management companies and some of the
largest carbon project developers in the
United States. And we're excited to
share that in 2025, we're collaborating
with the US Forest Service to scale
wildfire risk management across the
country. Our data is uniquely positioned
to measure fuel load on the forest
floor, which is an essential missing
piece to solving the wildfire crisis.
And this is the same information that's
necessary to evaluate the risk to homes,
utilities, and
properties, which also assists in
solving the forest or the fire man uh
insurance crisis as
well. Our AI will power the next
generation of carbon credits, wildfire
insurance, and nature finance. for
carbon credits. We will measure the
biomass within the forest as well as
proving additionality and also helping
forest managers understand the
trade-offs involved with participation
in carbon markets. For wildfire risk, we
measure both the uh the fuel load on the
forest floor, but also the height of the
canopy, which are the two main factors
determining the risk of extreme
wildfires. And for nature finance, we
will measure a wide variety of
biodiversity metrics, helping assess and
manage supply chains in an ever evolving
policy landscape around natural
assets. We've built the world's best
data collection system for this market.
Specifically designed to integrate with
our customers existing workflows. We
have a lightweight backpack for data
capture in the field, a mobile app that
allows for navigation and feedback, and
a web application for planning and data
analytics. This system allows our
customers to overcome the limitations of
the shrinking labor pool willing and
able to take on forestry fieldwork while
gaining the advantages associated with
precision agriculture.
If you're interested in using AI to
improve how we manage our forests for
carbon credits, wildfire mitigation, and
nature finance, we'd love to chat,
particularly with insurance companies
impacted by wildfires and sustainability
teams interested in building large
quantities of highquality carbon
credits. Thank you.
Thank you, Matt.