let's get started uh I'm a little under
the weather today so uh but don't take
my lack of enthusiasm my my slower style
today for a lack of enthusiasm about the
topic because today we're going to cover
one of my very favorite topics in
economics and the one I've bue a lot of
my life just studying which is social
insurance um so today we're going to
we're going to start back where we ended
we're going to ask we're going to start
back where we ended the last lecture
remember the last lecture we talked
about information imperfections we
talked about uncertainty and then we
talked about how why people would want
insurance and why people do spend
trillions of dollars or insurance but we
also mentioned the government also
spends trillions of dollars or insurance
and we asked why and the answer lies in
the problem of asymmetric information
now in the used car market example I
covered last time buyers know more about
the car they're selling I'm sorry
sellers know more about the car they're
selling than buyers know and that led
that asymmetric information led the
market to potentially collapse Insurance
markets is the opposite here the buyers
know more than the seller does but the
problem is the same so for example
suppose you want to start a new health
insurance company for MIT graduates MIT
graduates need health insurance uh so
you want to start a new company you
figured these are pretty pretty healthy
people health insurance will be cheap
indeed you figure you have data that
says there's 100 that out of a class of
100 graduates let's say you're going to
sell the 100
graduates 90 of them are very careful
people and they the only risk once again
like last time I was getting hit by a
car and for those 90 PE or for those 90
people there's a 10% chance that they'll
have a $10,000 bill
and a 90% chance that they'll have no
cost that's the expected cost for those
people for those careful
people now for the less careful people
or we often refer to as the sicker
people um uh let's do this with sickness
let's not do this with with car
accidents let's just say there's illness
you can get health we'll call these
healthy people the healthy types H have
a 10% chance of getting this sickness
and 9% chance of nothing happening the
sick
people the um and that's uh and then you
know the remaining 10
people the remaining 10 people out of
the 100 have a 50% chance of getting
sick and incurring a 10K Bill and a 50%
chance of nothing and that's the sick
people okay this is all data you
know this is data given to you that is
statistically accurate it's a separate
issue about what about when you don't
know the information we'll come back to
that but for now M you know this
information okay so what you do is you
say
look I then know the expected value of
buying Insurance to MIT students when I
sell to those 100 people my expected
cost if I sell this 100 people my
expected cost is what well my expected
cost for the healthy people is a th a
10% chance of 10,000 I expect to cost a
th000
for the healthy
people and my expected and they are 90%
of the
population okay so a th expect to cost
health people they're 90% of the
population and for the sick people an
expected cost of $5,000 because they
might get sick 50% of the time and that
happens 10% of the
time so by statistical simple statistics
my expected cost
is400 so I expect that when I sell
insurance I will pay out
$1,400 okay so I say well if I sell
insurance for
$1,500 as long as people a little risk
averse they want to buy it right $1,400
everyone want to buy as long as they're
not risk
loving if I I charge $1,500 then then at
least the risk unless unless you a
little risk averse they'll buy it and I
can make a profit so I roll in I sell
insurance for
$1,500 and I make a tidy profit I think
of $100 on 100 people each
$10,000 why am I
wrong why do I not in fact make that
profit why in fact might I lose
money why is that math wrong why if why
IFI were for
$1,500 might I in fact lose
money
yeah purchase yeah because I assumed
everyone buys it but I don't have the
power to make everyone buy it so who's
actually going to buy it well let's
think about that all the sick guys if I
charge
$1,500 this is an incredible deal for
the sick guys right the expected value
of the insurance is
$5,000 and I'm charging the, 1500 and
the risk of Earth so they're like this
is a great deal what about the healthy
guys well the expected value of
insurance them is a th and I'm char of
1500 so unless their risk premium is 500
or more they won't
buy so let's let's imagine some
distribution of risk premiums out there
in the population and let's imagine that
it's such that um only half the healthy
guys decide to buy when I charge
1500 I that half number is just a made
up but there's some distribution of risk
aversion some the guys are super risk
averse they'll easily they'll happily
buy 1500 some aren't very risk averse
they won't buy A5 00 let's say half buy
so now what do I pay out at the end of
the year what do I pay out well to my
sick
people to my 96 people I pay
out uh to my to my 96 people I pay out
on average
$45,000 okay I pay it on average uh
uh uh I'm sorry for my 9 sick for my 10
sick people I paid on average
$5,000 okay that that's why I pay my 10
sick
people that's my expected payout what if
my healthy people I said only only 45 of
the healthy people choose to buy right
so for those people I have a
45 times a $1,000 payout in expectation
so my
payout uh my payout is uh
$95,000 okay for $ 45 ,000 people okay
for 45 people but what's my
revenues well how many people have I
sold
to 60 people 10 sick and 50
healthy I'm sorry I i' I've sold to 55
people 10 sick and 45
healthy okay what's 55 time
150 well 55 time 150 is only 82 thou is
only 82250
so I have paid
out
$95,000 but I've only
collected a little more than $82,000 so
I lose
money therefore I don't offer the
insurance this is the flip of the car
example in the car example because I
don't know what's a what's a lemon and
what's not a lemon I don't buy the car
here because I'm not sure who's sick and
who's not if I offer at that price I'm
going to lose money someone off someone
offer it now you might say to me well
that's because you were dumb you chose
too low too low a price what if I just
rais the price to
$2,000 maybe that'll solve my problem
well at
$2,000 I make a lot more money per
person but what else happens at
$2,000 fewer Health even fewer healthy
people
buy so if at
$2,000 only 10 healthy people buy
instead of 45 I I'll still lose
money the point is this problem of what
we call adverse
selection adverse selection which is
only the
people on whom you're going to lose
money want to buy screws up Insurance
markets once again let me be clear on
this since only the people for whom it's
a good deal want to
buy and you lose money on the people for
it's a good deal you make money people
it's a bad deal right it's a bad deal
for the healthy if you charge more than
a thousand it's a bad deal for them
you're making money on them so
essentially what's Insurance doing it's
taking money from the
healthy exter healthy to cover your
costs on the
sick that only works if the healthy will
play If The Healthy won't play it
doesn't
work okay questions about
that so what happens in the real world
well if there's five possible outcomes
here five possible outcomes
okay outcome
one outcome one is the one good outcome
which is the health people are so risk
averse enough of them buy so if there's
enough risk
averse
healthy then you can make this work
right if more if if something like 70 of
the 95 90 healthy people buy I don't
know I forget what the crossover point
is we should add that to the not SP
there's an error in the notes just say
45 not 50 and we should add what the
crossover point is I don't can't do it
in my head but there's some crossover
point where if enough healthy people buy
I will make money at $1,500 or
$2,000 so the first outcome is it all
works out yes there's average selection
but it's not so bad because the healthy
are very risk
averse that's outcome
one outcome
two is the market collapses the market
fails why do the market fail because
because at any price the adverse
election is so bad I can't make money I
never get enough profitable healthy to
cover my unprofitable
sick so the market fails that's the
second possible
outcome there's a third
outcome I could just sell to
sick let's say I rolled in and I said
I've got insurance for MIT graduates
it's going to be
$5,500
well at that point as long as the sick
are somewhat risk averse they'll buy
it or if they're $5,100 if they're all
risk averse they'll buy it and I'll make
some money so I could just sell the sick
people at that high price no Health
people want the health people want it
great go for it I'm happy to have them
but that's just icing I then make money
on the sick as long as I set the price
above 5,000
so that's another thing I could do I
could just have a health insurance
policy for the sick priced at the price
for the sick and I know the healthy just
won't take it or if they do it's only
icing okay a fourth thing I could
do is I could just
discriminate I could say I'm going to
sell insurance at
$1,500 I'm G to test you when you come
in if I find you're sick I'm not going
to sell to you if I find you're healthy
I'm going to sell to you
turns out totally legal until the
Affordable Care Act passed so for most
of my life insurers were totally legal
to say if you're sick I'm not going to
sell you insurance or if you get sick
I'm going to drop you from insurance as
I hope you can see that sort of
undercuts the whole idea of insurance
well your insurance is to get healthy
people to cross upside sick people and
you drop people as soon as they're sick
then it doesn't really provide insurance
so insurers were totally free to do that
before the Affordable Care Act pass and
I'll talk more about that the last
lecture okay finally there's a clever
solution which I don't the math is hard
so I'm just give the intuition which is
you can
sell different
products that is what I can do is I can
sell two
products comprehensive
insurance for $5,500
and crappy insurance for
$1,500 as long as the sick people don't
want the crappy Insurance then what have
I
done I've solved the asymmetric
information Problem by getting people to
reveal their underlying health remember
my problem is I don't know who's sick
and who's healthy I know the Aggregates
but I don't who's sick and who's healthy
if people had sick and healthy stamped
on their forehead I'd be done but I
don't know that but if I offer a very
good product that's expensive and a
shitty product that's cheap
people will tell me their type by what
they buy the health people will buy the
crappy product sick people buy the the
other product and I'll make money on
both so that's another thing I do have
have you ever heard of an HMO that's
what an HMO is okay basically that's
what we've done with health insurance in
America to try to deal with this problem
has created
less high quality insurance for the
healthiest people that they can buy
cheaply okay so that's another thing we
can do
okay here's the key
Point all of
these are market
failures all of them you may say I know
that's a market failure but why is it
market failure if you just sell to the
sick why is that a market
failure
yeah L some people yeah there are trades
that with perfect information I would be
happy to make and they would be happy to
make them not being made so long as
imperfect information information
asymmetry leads to trades not being made
that most both make both sides better
off then that's a market failure so the
sick it's a market failure likewise if I
discriminate that's a market failure
because there's sick people who would
happily pay me $50 $200 for insurance
but I don't know they are so I can't
sell them at
50200 finally even selling different
products is still a market
failure the reason is because
what you can see from the insurance
model we set up last time is a typical
risk averse consumer wants complete
insurance they don't want partial
insurance they want to basically make
sure that their consumption is the same
no matter if they get hit by a car or
not and partial Insurance isn't as good
because once again the extra they keep
doesn't compensate for how much they
lose they hit by the car so incomplete
insurance is also a market
failure so the point is unless you
enough risk vers healthy the market will
not deliver the welfare maximizing
outcome okay questions about
that okay so now once again as I said
the principle that I teach in my classes
is the market knows best until the
market fails and then there's a
potential role for the government but
it's only a potential role for the
government and the reason it's
especially confusing here is there's
many different ways the government could
come in and solve this problem and in
fact governments around the world do
this in three different ways they solve
this problem three different ways the
first way so what about Government
Solutions the first way government
solved this problem is with
subsidies let's go back to our
example what if I said to everyone who's
an MIT graduate
I will give you $500 if you buy
insurance then the original product
would
work because the $1,500 I would charge
them like let's say I the government say
I'll give $500 well the F the insurance
I'm offering $1,500 so it's then a good
deal for both sides so they both buy it
so in substance one way to combat
average selection is through price if
you make it cheap enough the healthy
will
buy so subsidies just naturally offset
selection if I get a $500 subsidy in my
previous example it's a good deal for
everyone and everyone buys and we get
solution one we get this one everyone
buys
okay that's one
option indeed we use that option A Lot
in the
US in the US we massively subsidize
Private health insurance how do we do
that well one way we do it is through
our tax code here here's a interesting
feature of tax code if MIT pays me in
wages I get
taxed I'm not giving away too much
private information say if you add up
the tax rate I pay to Massachusetts and
to the federal government my tax rate
approach is 50% so I get to keep about
half of what I make okay but if MIT
gives me health insurance it's not
taxed so if MIT says to me John do you
want
$1,000 in health insurance or $1,000 in
wages I say wait a second if you give me
,000 in wages I get to buy $500 worth of
goods you give me $1,000 worth of health
insurance I get $1,000 worth of health
insurance I'll take the health insurance
and that is partly why most people in
America get their health insurance
through their employer we bribe them to
we bribe them to by taxing their wages
but not taxing their health insurance
that's a massive subsidy that cost us
government $300 billion doll every
single year big money that we're paying
to bribe people to buy private
insurance okay so that's one example of
how a government could come in and try
to solve this
problem a second
example is through a mandate any of you
followed Health Care policy debates when
you were younger remember this term of
the Mandate it was a big centerpiece of
the debate over the Affordable Care Act
which is what if I just say everyone has
to
buy I say healthy sick alike you have to
buy then basically I get this outcome
again because I force everyone to buy so
I know what the price is remember I know
an aggregate the price should be I just
don't know who's going to buy and who's
not so I force everyone to
buy everyone comes in and and I know
what price to set okay
now you might think well gee that seems
like a way better option than option one
option one costs the government a ton of
money option two cost the government
nothing other than just say buy
insurance but in fact who gets upset
when there's a
mandate which particular group is is
most upset when you mandate health
insurance the healthy who are not super
risk
ofe they are getting hit they didn't
want to buy insurance
at500 you're forced them to do something
they didn't want to do that's
politically very challenging as we
learned with the Affordable Care
Act okay which is that it's politically
very challenging to force people do
something they don't want to do in the
American political
system so in some sense you can give a
mandate at sort of implicitly forcing
the health to subsidize the sick that's
great because it gets the government out
of the way but it's essentially pissing
off the healthy non-risk averse people
and believe me during the Affordable Car
Act debate every single one of them sent
me an email okay people did not like
that feature uh of the Mandate in the
Affordable Care Act and eventually the
Mandate went away for that
reason okay we but we have mandates
they're not
new okay for example the oldest program
of this type in the country is called
Workers Compensation Insurance
that's a program that ensures you you
get hurt at work that's been a mandated
benefit of employers since the early
20th century no one's protesting workers
comp
mandates in Most states you're mandated
to buy auto insurance people don't
protest that they about how
expensive auto insurance is people don't
protest it so interestingly mandates are
not A New Concept brought up by the
Affordable Care Act it was just this
application they got people very
upset the final option for the
government
is you can just provide the
insurance cut off the middleman say
sorry John we're just going to have gov
care it's going to be whatever it's
going to be and if we lose money we lose
money because we're the government we
don't need to break
even we're just going to provide
it obviously you can combine it with
subsidies you say provide it we're going
to subsidize so everyone's in or you
just provide it and make it free this is
what most countries do most countries
say we have a national health insurance
system it's free take Canada
when you're born you're entitled to
national health insurance it's free you
just go there's no ad selection because
it's free when stuff's free there's no
aers
selection okay so that's another way you
could do is have the government just
provide it indeed that's what most of
the world
does okay questions about any of
that
yeah uh private insurers at all no
mandate tell private insurers because
when you mandate you're giving them more
customers
know government Health thing back then
like some private insurance because what
the government did is they wanted to
make a trade they said we'll mandate
insurance but you need to stop
discriminating that was the trade was
they're saying you're discriminating
because of adverse selection here's the
deal we're going to offer you stop
discriminating and we'll end your
adverse selection some people would
rather discriminate and they're upset
about
it okay good question now the bottom
line is this all sounds pretty good
we've got a problem we've identified
potential Solutions most governments of
the world are using some combination
Solutions what's the problem well the
problem is that there's another asmsc
information problem which poses a a
fundamental tradeoff and that's what we
call the fundamental social insurance
tradeoff and that other problem that
other a information problem is what we
call moral
hazard the other asymmetric information
is what we call moral hazard that's
basically the adverse behavior that is
encouraged by uring against an adverse
event when you Ure against an adverse
event you can cause adverse Behavior
so basically for example if families buy
fire insurance for their homes they may
be less likely to have a fire
extinguisher in the house they don't
need it because their house is insured
if it burns down if people have health
insurance maybe they're less worried
about taking
precautions okay I'm not feeling so well
today I de thought I'd come in with a
mask be okay but if I have health
insurance maybe I
wouldn't you know so basically maybe
there's risk people take and then
also take another example one of the
biggest Insurance programs in America is
unemployment insurance insurance you get
if you lose your job well if we insure
you for the money you lose when you lose
your job what's the incentive to search
for a new job remember Leisure is a
normal
good these are all forms of moral hazard
and the best and most fun examples come
in the context of workers compensation
which I already mentioned already that's
a $60 billion a year program that
ensures people for injuries that are job
related the problem is now you might
think well that sounds like really
sensible Insurance the problem is a lot
of these problems are actually hard to
diagnose and hard to figure out their
job related if someone is at a machine
you watch them saw their arm off that's
pretty easy if someone says I've been
driving all day and I have back pain and
I can't stand up that's
harder most of claims for workers
compensation today are mostly pain and
mental health those are hard things to
evaluate as a result
um and then on top of that workers so
you've got two problems workers
compensation one is it's hard to
evaluate if people are really
injured the other is if they are injured
they get a pretty attractive benefit if
you miss work and get Workers
Comp you get 75% of the wages you would
have gotten if you worked so you can sit
at home and get 75 remember Leisure is
normal people would rather not work so
you can work or sit at home with 75% of
your Wes but it's better than that
because your wages are taxed and workers
comp Isn't So for a typical worker after
tax their workers comp amounts to about
90% of what they take home working so
you got a program which says look
Leisure is a normal good I'm going to
pay you roughly 90% of what you'd earn
at work all you have to do is pretend
you're hurt that's a clear incentive for
moral
hazard okay so basically the idea is
that there might be moral hazard is
something like workers comp and there's
been a large really fascinating
literature this tried to measure
that sometimes there's fun examples my
favorite example was the woman who in in
what state what state I'm talking about
bad behavior what state am I talk about
Florida right come on so there was a
woman in Florida who was at her desk uh
while she was at her desk a sprinkler
had fell out of the ceiling and landed
on her desk and shocked her she looked
around bonked herself on the head with a
sprinkler desk with with the sprinkler
piece and claim workers comp but of
course you know the reason I'm telling
the story is All on
camera okay have any guys ever heard to
show Wicked Tuna it's about tuna fishing
out of gloss about a guy wrestles these
thousand two ton Tunas onto his boat
turns out the whole time I was on Wicked
Tuna he was collecting workers
compensation because he couldn't
work okay there are lots of fun really
fun examples but we care about an
economics is not stories we care about
facts and how do we test in empirical
economics whether moral hazards a real
problem but well the way we do it is we
say it turns out that what you get from
workers comp varies across different
states and over
time so let's say I'm in one state
Andrew's in another state Andrew State
randomly raises the benefits now there's
no reason Andrew should be more injury
prone just because the state rais the
benefits but if Andrew becomes more
likely to be injured when the state
raises its benefits clearly that's moral
hazard because there's no other reason
why just because the state rais benefits
Andrew should be more injury prone and
the evidence that is incredibly powerful
we talked about the elasticities the
evidence is that for every
10% that benefits go up people Miss 10
to 20% more work an elasticity of one to
two people are very responsive to these
benefits and that's C evidence of moral
hazard
okay um so
moral hazard exists but we might ask
look so what's the problem okay every
selection I explained the problem the
market collapses that's pretty bad
collapse we know is a bad word that's
bad what about moral hazard why is it so
bad well it's bad for two
reasons the
first is you
remove
productive labor
Supply let's just do some quick math to
show why this is
imagine that an individual is choosing
between staying at home is choosing for
the for the marginal hour do I stay at
home or do I
work well we know the way they'll make
that decision is they will
maximize their utility over consumption
and Leisure subject to some budget
constraint and we know that this will
yield the first order condition that
du DL or the margin utility of leisure
equals the
wage that will be the equilibrium
condition why because it's where
marginal benefits equal marginal costs
what's the marginal benefit of staying
home how much happier it makes you the
Marg utility of leisure what's the
marginal cost of staying at home you
give up your wage
W so an efficient market this is a very
important Insight by the way many people
talk about work as a virtue that is
wrong
work is not a virtue okay people should
only work until this condition is true
if you're someone who reallying hates
work because you're really disabled it's
awful you shouldn't work it's not like
God has said we must work okay the right
the optimal social conditions people
should work until this condition is
true which means no one should work all
the time that can't be true 24 hours a
day for everyone at some point you got
to sleep and some people should work
less or more than others okay that's
what's
optimal okay now imagine
that um and we
know that the wage in a perfectly
competitive labor market equals the
marginal revenue product of labor we
know that's where the wage comes from in
a perfectly competitive labor
market
okay so basically think of this from the
from the employer perspective from the
employer perspective I take Leisure
until the Val Leisure equals the value
of what i' produce at work okay so
basically what we want in society want
people trading off the value of what
they produce at work versus how much the
value they get from sitting at home but
now suppose I tell
you that for every hour you sit at home
you also get an amount
G well now if I sit at home what do I
get I get du DL plus G and I set that
equal to the marginal revenue product of
labor so
DL plus G
I said equal the margin product of
labor let's think for a second about
what this does to my leisure
decision this means I set my margin
utility of
leisure
above I'm sorry I set margin utility
leure below my marginal product because
G's positive I set my margin ility of
leisure equal to mrpl minus
G does that imply more Leisure or less
Leisure than what we know is a efficient
we know efficient is DL equals mrpl if
DL plus g equals
mrpl am I supplying more Leisure or less
Leisure than the efficient
outcome we know this yeah go
ahead more because remember as Leisure
goes up Margin utility goes down we know
we want Mar since G is positive to keep
it equ PL DL has to go down
doodl goes down by taking more Leisure
so by offering this benefit I've created
inefficiency I'm C to take more Leisure
than is optimal the optimal Leisure
would be DL equal mrpl but I'm making DL
equal to mrpl minus G so I'm causing
them to take too much leisure in other
words I'm getting in the way of
productive trades there's a productive
trade to be made here which is I work
you pay me but now I'm like it I'm
not going to work because I get G so
that's a productive trade that goes away
because of moral hazard and that's why
we care that's a dead weight
loss
okay there's a second there's a second
problem which is sort of minor but
important but which to remember which is
that how do we pay for social insurance
programs by taxing
workers the less people work the more
taxes we have to raise on everybody else
so it means higher tax rates
because if we're shrinking the base of
workers but we got to pay for all these
workers sitting at home that means
higher tax
rates and we'll talk later about why
higher tax rates cause
inefficiency so this leads us to the
fundamental
tradeoff with social insurance on the
one hand unless the government
intervenes there will be a market
collapse unless you get condition one
and we have lots of evidence condition
one has in met in most markets the
market will collapse and that is bad
that's a welfare loss on the other hand
by providing that insurance we create an
offsetting welfare loss which people
don't work as
hard what does that mean well that has a
simple
implication which is we should have
social insurance but it shouldn't be too
generous clearly the right answer is not
zero social insurance unless moral
hazard is like deadly I mean you know
this is just you're losing some product
this one people starve if they don't
have insurance so clearly want some
insurance but if we have too much we
might encourage people to sit at home so
the ideas we want in between want a
tradeoff want enough insurance we won
starve but not so much that we cause a
lot of moral
hazard okay and to see that let's talk
about the largest social insurance
program in America which is the Social
Security program
we have a number of social insurance
programs in America I mentioned workers
compensation if you get H at work I
mentioned unemployment insurance if you
lose your
job our biggest aggregate social
programs are for healthcare I'll talk
about them in the last lecture they're
called Medicare and
Medicaid okay but the single biggest
program of social insurance at about
$800 billion a year
is social
security Social Security is insurance
against the income loss that comes from
retirement soci is insurance against the
income loss of retirement it's ensuring
you to make sure that once you're
retired you have enough money and don't
starve let's talk about how it works
here's how Social Security works first
when you
retire you get a check from the
government
you get a check from the
okay that check is a function of how
much you made before you retired that
check is
Progressive what does that mean that
means that if you're very poor you get a
check that's almost as much as you made
before you retired if you're rich you
get a check that's about 30% of what you
made before you
retired so you get a check that
basically depends on how much you made
before you retire but in a Progressive
Way the more you made before you retire
the less you get back from the
government everybody gets something
everyone gets at least
30% but there's a range 30 to
90 actually I'm wrong it's at least 15%
there's a range 15 to 90 over which of
VAR so Bill Gates will get Social
Security start to keep picking on Bill
he'll get Social Security but only get
15% of his previous
wages uh or or or you know subit to a
cap so even less okay you get this check
until you
die it's what's called an
annuity this is an important term not a
lot of people know financially Savvy
people an annuity is the opposite of
life insurance we all know life
insurance life insurance is I pay money
while I'm alive and when I die my
descendants get a check a new is the
opposite a new is I pay money now they
send me a check as long as I'm alive and
then it ends when I
die so if I want to Nei tize my wealth
what i is I'd walk into a broker's
office I'd say here's my money I'm give
it all to you now and you're gonna send
me a check until I
die why is this
appealing it's appealing because we
don't know when we'll
die and as a result savings for
retirement is very imperfect
definitionally you will always save if
you you just use saving for retirement
always save either too much or too
little if you live longer than you
thought you'll save too little if you
die sooner than you thought you'll save
too much now if you care about your kids
that's a different thing but let's let's
talk about a childless
person okay so basically the point is
savings isn't perfect because you don't
know when you're going to
die annuities are insurance against that
uncertainty think about it just like
health insurance insures you against the
medical bill a UI isure you gu how long
you're going to live you turn out to
live a long time then your nity will
turn out to be a good deal youve paid an
AM and you get a check forever if you
turn out to live only short time rity
would be a bad deal just like with
health insurance Health if you turn out
to be healthy health insurance is a bad
deal turn out to be sick it's a good
deal but you still want it because you
want to smooth your consumption and
that's what annuities
do okay now that is the
benefit of Social Security that we make
sure sure that people have enough money
till they die they don't
unave that they don't unave and end up
without enough money because they didn't
think they're going to live that long
they live a long time and suddenly
they're they're they're
impoverished okay indeed one of the
reason we set up Social Security was
because there'd be all these
impoverished people especially after the
Great Depression the main motivation
social SEC is the Great Depression wiped
out a bunch of people's savings and
we're worried they wouldn't have enough
money to live till till their death so
we set up this
program on the other
hand there's a moral hazard element of
social
security which is remember how do you
qualify for Social
Security by
retiring retirement is a
choice Leisure is normal people would
like to be
retired so the more generous we make
Social Security the earlier you'll
retire because basically we're saying go
back to go back to the math over
here think about this not as a period by
period decision but a year-by-year
decision this year do I want to work
well this year I think gee how much do I
value Leisure if I sit at home versus
how much will I make this year as aside
should I work or not well now I'm gonna
be more likely to quit because if I quit
I Get Money I get if I don't
work so I've essentially put a thumb on
the scale for quitting I've put a thumb
on the scale for retirement so the moral
hazard aspect of Social
Security is it causes increased
retirement why is that bad well because
old workers are productive not that they
shouldn't retire but they should only
retire when this condition is true not
when this condition is
true okay they're retiring too early and
in fact there's tons of evidence from
very well crafted studies that social
security has a huge impact on
retirement okay there's a really cool
and basically the way they study this
offit is by looking at the fact that
social security has have certain ages at
which you a minimum age and when you
lower that minimum age all of a sudden
everyone retires earlier and you raise
people retire later in Germany the minim
age was
60 and the average reement age was
58 cou people retire early because they
have their own money they raised to 65
within five years the average retirement
age in the whole country of Germany was
63 think about that within five years an
entire country change went retired by
five years pretty phenomenal okay that
illustrates the power of moral hazard
illustrates the power and that says
there's a
tradeoff so basically the question is
how do you think about this
tradeoff well you write down an economic
model and you talk about the benefits of
insuring against longevity and the cost
of early retirement you come out with
some optimal social security number this
isn't what we do here we'll do that in
1441 if you want to follow up that's in
1441 write down a model we put both
these things in one model and optimize
and you get some optimal level of Social
Security turns out it's probably not
that far from where we are social SEC
average replaces about 45% of people's
wages across everyone that's probably
not a terrible number given this
tradeoff okay but the problem is this is
a much bigger issue in Europe than is in
the US because of a seemingly harmless
little tweak in the way we do social
security versus the way you do social
security so social care is an age of
early retirement the earliest of which
you can get your benefits so the way it
works in Social care in the US is as
soon as you're 62 you can start getting
a
check but if you wait till 63 we'll give
you a bigger check why because you're
going to get it for a fewer years your
death dat's the same see like at 62
you're going to die to 162 to 100 and we
give you X if you get 63 to 100 we're
going to give you X plus a little bit to
give you the same total by age 100 so we
basically have what we call in Social
Security an Actuarial
adjustment we basically look the longer
you work the more money will let you
keep because you're going to get fewer
years of benefits it's a
trade-off
okay the the issue is getting this
actual adjustment right can strongly
impact people's works decisions so let's
say Let's do an example let's say you
earn y percent per
year and Social Security replaces K
percent of that remember I said an
average social security rep about 45% so
K would be 0.45 or 45% in the US so
Social Security replace about 45% and
ignore the fact that rich people and
poor people are different Imagine One
representative person that
representative person earns Y and when
they retired they're going to get K
times Y where K is a number less than
one and let's imagine that you're going
to live until
80 live till
80 and you're deciding should I retire
at age 62 or
not should I 62 or work till 63 well if
I retire 62 what do I get from Social
Security well I get the present
discounted value remember I got to pdv
it because the money's coming in the
future okay of getting 18 years
of K * y i retired
62 I get it for 18
years and it's going to be in the future
so I got to pdv
it if I work till 63 what do I get if I
work till
63 well then I get y I get the
pdv of Y this year plus 17 * k time y
because I get it for one fewer
year so what's the difference between
these two the difference these two is 1
minus K *
y That's the difference between these
two if you work one more year you get
one minus K * y
more this is the questions about
that why is this important because this
k term effectively is a tax think about
it if I work one more year without
Social Security what do I get why if I
work one M with Social Security I get
one minus K times y why is that because
I'm giving up the money I could have had
by sitting at
home and my decision is always sitting
home versus working so it's a
tradeoff the bigger K is Imagine K was
100% imagine K was
one and Leisure is normal when anyone
work past 62 no why' you work past 62
you get the same thing if K is one that
means if I work I get Y and if I'm home
I get Y and leure is normal why would I
ever
work so the bigger K is the bigger the
moral hazard is the less is that of
there is to
work okay so what do we do in the US to
offset that we have a simple what I call
Actuarial adjustment which is we say if
you work till 63 we're gonna give you an
extra bonus
we're going to give you y + 7 * K * y
time 1.06
7 we're going to give you more and that
1.06 7 is calculated so that you're
indifferent so the average person is
indifferent yes they give up K but they
get more per
month and it's calculates the average
person is
indifferent okay so roughly speaking in
the US when you're deciding to retire 62
or 63 Social Security shouldn't affect
that
decision it's basically pretty neutral
now let's go to the
Netherlands in the Netherlands two
things are different K instead of being
0.5 is
0.9 B the second thing different they
don't have
this so in the Netherlands your decision
is do I work age 55 is early retirement
age your decision is do I work till age
and get
y do do I work my 56th year and get y or
do I stay at home and get K * Y which is
90% of
why okay people understand that that's
your decision but it's even worse than
that because how does the Netherlands
pay for this
program by taxing workers taxes you
don't pay if you don't work so if you
work you get why but you lose almost
half it in taxes so you get half y if
you don't work you get 90% of why you
make money by not working even MIT
students might find that
attractive as a result literally no one
works past age 55 in these countries we
essentially made it not in their
financial interest some people go back
to work off the books and sort of jobs
that aren't recorded so they can make
some money but that's why I see all
these old people sitting around cafes in
Europe having a great old time in the
middle of the
day because basically there's no
Financial benefit to working we're
essentially making you IND different
even working and nonworking once you've
reach the retirement
age so that is an
example of moral hazard that's an
example setting the benefits too
large so that the moral hazard benefits
the the moral hazard cost is enormous
rela to potential smoothing if the
Netherlands for example lower than 90%
or even just introduce a factor like
this that would offset things a lot so
the point is this is sort of a wonky
discussion but the point is this shows
you how the little wonky numbers that
policy makers fight about all the time
could have a fundamental impact on the
way an entire economy functions
literally by setting K to 0.9 and by not
having this Actuarial adjustment the
Netherland essentially taken every old
person out of the labor
force that's a pretty fundamental change
and that's something that policy makers
that's why I love policymaking that's
what policymakers need to think about is
essentially what are the unintended
consequences what I started the semester
with I want to ensure people in
Netherlands if they can't work anymore
but I don't want to take every old
person out of the labor force and that's
what they end up doing okay that's all I
got for today um hope you guys had a
good Thanksgiving and we'll come back
Wednesday