So our next speaker is professor will
Oliver. Will is a professor at MIT
electrical engineering and computer
science department. He's also professor
at MIT physics department. And Will has
been the faculty director for the MIT
center of quantum engineering since its
start in 2019. And since then he has
spearheaded MIT's efforts collaborating
with industry. So he's really the best
person who can provide us update on the
history, the current status and the
future outlook of quantum computing.
Over to you will
>> Yeah. So I'd love to continue that
discussion. Uh thank you very much Dana
and uh great to see you this morning. Uh
Will Oliver MIT and uh let's get to it.
So we're in what we call now the second
quantum revolution. The first one
happened a hundred years ago as you just
heard from Dana and that's when we first
realized that nature around us in fact
the world around us is fundamentally
quantum mechanical. Um and as I'll talk
about in a moment that led to several
very important uh technologies that
underpin our current well economic and
national security. Um but the quantum
wasn't really used in those devices um
at a fundamental level. This second
quantum revolution is now using the
quantum for purpose and that purpose is
sensing communication or networking uh
and computing. And so if we had to give
it a quick definition, quantum 2.0
utilizes quantum mechanics at a
fundamental level to sense, communicate,
process information in ways that are
just unobtainable by our conventional
means.
Now, when I think about quantum
computing in particular, I like to go
back and remember the history of
classical electronic computing. And I
will make it brief, but the main message
is that history doesn't repeat itself.
Certainly, it doesn't, but it often
rhymes. That's Mark Twain. Um, if we go
back to 1906, the vacuum tube was
invented, three- terminal device. It was
used initially for radio transceivers.
But 40 years later, we had ENIAC, one of
the first computers. Um, and it was
based on vacuum tubes. Of course, we're
not using vacuum tubes today. We're
using transistors. Those were invented
in 1947 at Bell Labs. 10 years later,
MIT had a computer called TX0 or Tixo
based on transistors. But it was
basically these devices soldered
together. To get closer to what we have
today, we needed the integrated circuit
in the late50s. But even with that, it
wasn't until the 70s that we saw chips
that you and I would recognize, I think,
as integrated circuits. This is the
Intel 404. Uh with Moors law, we
advanced and 25 years later, we had the
Pentium Pro. I remember using that one.
Um millions of transistors and that
still was 30 years ago from today. Today
we have wonderful machines, CPUs, TPUs,
XPUs. Um and the latest from Nvidia has
more than a 100red billion transistors
uh on the Blackwell. actually 200
billion transistors. So fantastic
achievement but look it took us 100
years to get here. Now quantum computing
in comparison is much uh more nent. In
the 80s people suggested if you want to
simulate a quantum system why don't we
use a quantum system to do that? Okay
that makes sense. Took us good 10 or 15
years to figure out what those
algorithms might look like. uh people
like Peter Shaw uh and his algorithm for
cryp analysis uh Eddie Farhey uh
Nishimuri from Japan and others started
to say okay look if and when we can
build this hardware there are some
important things we can do and that
turns out to be also 30 years ago and
here we are today starting to build
quantum computers we have them they're
just smallcale but the development is
accelerating and uh takeaway message
here is that look quantum computing is
It's transitioning from scientific
curiosity to technical reality. Um, but
we know that advancing from a
fundamental discovery
heroic, but but going from that point to
a useful machine is going to take time
and engineering. And that's the part
that rhymes with classical electronic
computing. Nonetheless, um, you need to
be in the game to play. And what I mean
by that is if you look at the Nvidia of
the world, TSMC's, etc., who are making
these very complex chips today. They
didn't jump in in 2015 once somebody
else figured out how to do it because
there's so much uh trade secrets IP
that's involved. This is part of the
reason that the PRC is finding it
challenging to stand up a
state-of-the-art fab and it will be the
same way with quantum.
Uh quick slide on cubits. Quantum bits
are the fundamental logic elements of
quantum computers and they come in
basically two flavors. One uh flavor is
the natural atoms that we have in our
periodic table. Um and one feature that
these atoms all have, they're obviously
very different, but they all have
electrons, protons, neutrons. And if you
look at the outermost shell, there will
be an electron there. And whether it's
in say the second shell or the third
shell, uh this can be construed as the
zero and one. That that's a bit
simplistic, but that's that's basically
what it is. And we tend to take elements
from these two columns although not
exclusively from there.
The other type that we have let's call
those natural atoms. The other type that
we have are electrical circuits that we
can design and manufacture uh in
fabrication facilities. And these um use
inductors, capacitors and something
called Josephson junctions arranged
together to form uh nonlinear
oscillators. Now when you take the
oscillator and you cool it down to very
low temperatures uh 10 20 millich
keelvin uh you can see that there are
discrete energy levels that appear here
as well. And now we're going to choose
the bottom one the first one to be our
zero and one of our cubits. Now this
this is a very simple example. You might
think of it as the hydrogen atom um or
hydrogen artificial atom. It's actually
called a transmon but we have a whole of
table of artificial atoms as well where
we've designed these for effect. Um and
and I'll leave it at that but these are
the two major categories. Quantum
technologies are based on natural atoms
or circuits that mimic those properties.
Now how is a quantum computer different?
Um I like to do a compare and contrast
with classical. So let's do that. Um
classical computers a bit of information
transistor for example. classical device
the current is on or the current is off
when it's on we call it one when it's
off we call it zero these are discrete
states and measurement is deterministic
and in fact transistors are almost
perfect um so if we set it in a one
we're going to measure it in a one set
it in zero we'll measure in zero quantum
computers on the other hand are built
from two-state systems that are quantum
mechanical we call them Qbits for
quantum bit and the way to think about
it is in terms of the planet earth and
Now, uh, if you're at the north pole on
the planet Earth, we're going to say
that's state zero. And if you're at the
south pole, that's state one. And those
are classical positions. A transistor
can only live at the north or the south
pole. And a cubit as well can be
classical. It can be at the north or the
south pole. But just like people, cubits
can be anywhere on the earth. And when
they're anywhere other than the north or
south pole, they're now in a quantum
mechanical superp position state of zero
and one, north and south pole
simultaneously. Now this is weird but
that's the what that's what quant
mechanics gives us. This is called
quantum superp position and one feature
of it is measurement becomes
probabilistic. So that if you're
standing on the equator you're equally
weighted 0 and one and you make a
measurement just like flipping a coin
you'll instantly snap to the north pole
and say hey will I'm state zero or go to
the south pole and say I'm state one.
And you could go to the same place on
the equator and do it again and it will
be completely random which one you get.
Might seem that it's hard to make a
computer out of this. Um uh and it is
indeed true that we need to encode
information in a fundamentally different
way. But we can do it. Now to give an
idea of the power of a quantum computer,
let's consider um let's consider this.
If you have n transistors, a number n,
you can form an exponentially large
number of states 2 to the nth power.
Let's take three that that I can I can
do in my head. Two to the third power is
eight. There are eight different ways I
can permute the zeros and ones. All the
transistors are zero. All of them are
one. Every permutation in between. If I
wanted to for some reason use each of
those inputs to calculate some out on a
classical computer I basically have two
choices. One is I can take one classical
computer and feed the inputs one at a
time and get the outputs 00 get the
output 001 get the output etc. Or I can
buy a really large number of computers
and try to do this in parallel. But
either way with an exponentially large
number of inputs I need either
exponential time or exponential
hardware. Now quantum computers
similarly n cubits can represent 2 to
the n classical states but they're
cubits so they can do a quantum
mechanical thing which is represent all
of them at the same time in a single
quantum superposition state and I won't
have time to talk about it today but
this leads to a quantum version of
parallelism and importantly quantum
interference and you can think of the
mass position state as being fed into
the quantum computer then a massive
superp position state comes out Now, we
haven't measured anything yet, but the
goal of the quantum computer algorithm
designer is to take this massive input
state with equally weighted answers and
then through the algorithm suppress all
of the wrong answers, leaving only the
correct answer by the end. So, when we
measure it, we get the correct answer.
That's basically how it works. So, to
take advantage of this, of course, we
need algorithms. And uh what I here at
the bottom are many of my colleagues
here at MIT who played an instrumental
role in developing these algorithms. I
won't read through this whole chart but
the left column shows the category of
algorithm and then we have the classical
time generally exponential in the size
of the problem n and then the quantum
time generally polomial in that which
means there was an exponential speed up.
So the one that we think will have the
broadest commercial uh advantage in the
nearer term is quantum simulation
simulating materials quantum chemistry
for example pharmaceutical development.
The second application would be one of
the originals, Peter Shor's factoring
algorithm, which attacks our current
public key crypto systems. We'll talk
later about switching over to a
different crypto system, but it's bas
basically because of this uh engineers
will recognize ax equals b that pervades
all of engineering and quantum computers
can sample solutions to large uh
matrices using quantum algorithms.
Optimization of course is ubiquitous and
whether there's an improvement or not
depends a lot on the problem that you
ask. Um do you need the answer like your
life depends on it or uh is a good
enough answer good enough? And depending
on how you answer that a quantum
computer will be more or less likely to
be useful and then search algorithms. Uh
this is over search algorithm and it's a
quadratic speed up. Okay. So so what
does it take to get commercial quantum
advantage? I think that's what we really
care about. And first off, there should
be no fast classical algorithm. If there
is, use the fantastic computers we
already have. Second is I need to know a
good quantum algorithm solves that
problem. There are many problems today
where I don't know how to do it on a
classical computer and I also have no
idea how to do it on a quantum computer.
And so you need to have a fast quantum
algorithm. And then third, ideally it
should be commercializable, useful. Um,
there are many algorithms that have
shown quantum advantage, but how to use
that for commercial advantage isn't yet
clear. And if we look at this overlap
today, it's still a fairly small region.
And and one call that I always make when
I give a talk is as a community, we need
to be developing more commercially
relevant quantum algorithms.
Now once you have an algorithm there are
two types of advantage and the advantage
is often construed as how long the time
to solution but it's also about the size
of the system the amount of energy it
will take to arrive at an answer maybe
other resources whichever one you prefer
they're to two terms a polomial in the
size of the problem n and an exponential
in the size of the problem n and quantum
computers can improve both so they can
either improve improve the prefactor
which we call a polomial improvement
that's where n goes to square root of n
that's Grover's algorithm for example or
you can reduce the exponential down to a
polomial that's called an exponential
improvement so if if the size of the
problem is upstairs bring it downstairs
and that is a tremendous uh improvement
uh in in these properties so that's
great um why don't we have them right
now and it comes down to two time scales
one is the coherence time and the other
is the gate time. So let's take them one
at a time. The coherence time is the
cubit's lifetime. How long does it
remain quantum mechanical? And so I can
my problem and I'm starting my algorithm
and as I'm taking steps towards the
final answer, the environment, you can
think of it as the wind blowing is
blowing me off course and and over time
my state of my system decays or blurs
and eventually is lost. Now the cubits
are still there generally speaking but
but where I ended up the answer I got is
the wrong answer because I was blown off
course. The time frame over which this
happens is called the lifetime or the
coherence time. The second is the gate
time. How quickly can I make steps? How
quickly can I run to the answer? And the
figure of merit here is the number of
gates you can do within the coherence
time you've got. Now the correlary to
that is long coherence times. That's
great, but it's not sufficient.
Technologies will have very very
different coherence times depending on
their technology, but it's really how
many gates can I do within that
coherence time. And when we think of it
in this way, we can compare different
modalities against one another. On the
vertical axis is number of operations
before an error. That is our metric that
we just talked about. And that's one to
one in what the community or the jargon
would be gate fidelity. So if I have one
error in a 100 that's 99%. One error in
a thousand my gate is better 99.9% etc.
And you want that to be as high as
possible. The horizontal axis is the
speed the clock speed basically how
quickly can I run my algorithm and of
course best performance is in the upper
right corner. Now some of the leading
technologies today are represented here.
For example trapped ions they're
relatively slow but their coherence
times are pretty good at least for the
single cubic gates. And so their goal
right now is let's get faster, let's get
higher cubit fidelity. Uh
superconducting cubits where I work,
we're relatively fast. Uh we'd like to
improve fidelity. Neutral atoms, you'll
hear about those in a moment. They're
somewhere in between. And there are
others like silicon quantum dots,
probably the closest to a transistor, NV
centers, nitrogen vacancy centers, etc.
many outstanding research efforts, but
in some sense you can see we're all
equally far from the upper right corner,
which is why we're still early uh in
this race.
Now, this is what commercial processors
look like today. Um in the lower left is
IBM's Osprey, more than 400
superconducting cubits, 3D integrated,
uh that uses technology that was
developed here at MIT. And in the upper
left is the willow processor.
Um that also 3D integrated but looking
down at the top we can't really see it.
These are both superconducting as is the
D-Wave system. In the lower right, which
is different type of quantum computing
called kneeling. In the upper right is
Quantinum's H1 processor which is a
trapped ion processor on an integrated
chip made of silicon. And in the middle
here is a Cera's Aquila processor. You
see a little dot of atoms in there and
we'll hear more about that in the next
talk. Now, in the lower bottom here, of
course, obviously this isn't a quantum
computer. Uh, this is the right flyer.
Um, it's often said, but it's not true
that it it's not the first time
humankind had flown. Just like these
demonstrations here are not the first
time we've ever done experiments with
quantum, but but I like this analogy
because um the right flyer is the first
time it all came together. There's a
person on board, self-propelled, took
off from the ground, flew for a
distance, landed again. and we see this
in hindsight say yes is the dawn of
commercial aviation none of us would get
on that plane um it's not mature enough
yet but but it is the dawn of commercial
aviation and I put it here because I
believe with these other processors
indicate similarly that we're at the
dawn of commercial quantum computing
we've demonstrated enough to show that
that's true in opinion and so going
forward we need to realize this promise
um and to do that we need to engineer
systems that are robust trust are
reproducible and extensible.
I'm running short on time so let me just
give this last slide um at a very high
level. I won't be able to talk through
the whole thing but the grand challenge
going forward is called quantum error
correction. We need to fix the errors
faster than they occur uh naturally due
to the environment. The physical cubits
we have today are up one in a 100 one in
10,000 error rates. But where we need to
be for practical applications is
something like one in a billion to one
in a trillion. Um, of course,
transistors are even better than that.
But we don't need to be that good. Need
to be in the blue. And the way that
we're going to do it is by forming teams
cubits. Rather than using just a
physical cubit by itself, we're going to
form a team. Nine yellow cubits. And
we're going to encode the information
across all nine. We call that a logical
cubit because it represents one cubit's
worth of information. but it's
distributed across nine. You'll also see
some blue cubits. Those blue cubs are
you can think of it as the referees and
they're going to raise a red card, a
yellow card. We have three errors and
maybe they have a blue card where that
tells us if their neighbors had an error
and go back and fix it. I apologize I
won't
explicit
it actually gets a little worse two
times worse two than a thousand go only
to 577 cubits my error rate has dropped
now to roughly 1 in a billion. So that's
an improvement of about 1 million. So So
I'll take that trade going from 1 to 577
to get a factor 1 million improvement.
That's what quantum error correction
shows and that's why it's important. Um
just to say Google for the first time
demonstrated this fact uh last fall
where they went from a size uh 17 to a
size 49 to a size 97. And each time they
did that, the error rate came down by a
factor of two. And in fact, it was
better than any individual on the team.
That's what we need to do if we're going
to realize uh the promise of quantum
computing. So, so just a few facts. Um
quantum computers are not going to
replace classical computers. First off,
we need classical computers to do the
error correction, but furthermore, we
need them to run the quantum computers.
We need to program. We type on a
classical computer and that program gets
implemented on a um on a quantum
computer. They will run in tandem. We
need more quantum algorithms. I already
said that. Let me say it again. Um on
the encryption side, quantum computers
are not going to break encryption today.
The quantum computers just aren't large
enough. We're going to need around 4
million cubits or more to do that for
today's encryption. But that doesn't
mean we should wait or be complacent. We
need to replace our current RSA type
encryption schemes with a new one that
was just released last year from NIST.
It's called Kyber or similar names. Um
we need to switch now so that the
information we're encoding now remains
secure not just today but in the future
when a quantum computer at a shore
capable scale becomes available and we
will almost certainly need error
correction to make this happen. Uh Donna
mentioned this but next steps if you'd
like to learn more um we have a series
of professional development courses um
feel free to contact me um uh these are
now from MITx pro and also we have an
industry membership group uh where we
work together with industry to um across
the board many verticals to address
problems more specifically in crop uh in
quantum. So if you'd like to learn more
please reach out and thank you for your
attention.
Thank you, Will. And there's always so
much to talk about and time is always
too short. So, we are running out of
time, but there's one question in the
Q&A panel. If you can type in the
answer, that would be great.