Good afternoon. Really nice being here.
So my name is Pong. I'm CEO of Movie
Systems. So at MOI we solve probably a
very different type of AI problem. It's
about large scale planning and
optimization out there in the real
world.
Um yeah. So really the problem core
problem we address is um people have
been using constraint solvers
optimization system to solve problems at
a local scale for transportation for
logistic for a very very long time. But
when you try to expand it as a world
scale and then you try to compress the
solution time down from hours to minutes
to sometimes second in order to
accommodate for this dynamic changing
disruptive world things will fall apart.
But really that's what uh where our
software address. So really what we end
up doing is developing a large scale
planning system that can ingest all type
of data from inventory for resources for
mapping for traffic. Anything end up
being described in either temporal
spatial or preferential constraints or
objective functions. Then we solve that.
We spend time to solve for the initial
solution but then continues to receive
updates in a streaming way. There is a
flight being delayed. Suddenly 200
passengers on board that flights their
bus route to different hotels in Morca
needs to be rerouted. We'll subscribe to
that and then start to identify the
impact automatically and then replan
either the route the pick up the drop
off the bus with who is going to get
seed all automatically.
So I want to talk through a um kind of
workflow we end up deployed our solution
with TUI the tourism company based in
Hanover Germany. So they operate about
12,000 buses of different sizes just
like the one in the vehicle serving over
25 million travelers on an annual basis.
You can imagine traditionally they have
a fixed solver that operates overnight
for about four to eight hours. Their
operation team defines a problem kind of
plug in all the bookings they receive
for the next day. The solver get a
solution. The operator team then push
that to a different place where they can
dispatch it to all the bus drivers. When
things fall apart, the operation team
has to go in manually reassign all the
passengers to all the vehicles and then
based on the flight, based on weather,
based on equipment failures. That's have
been changed completely now because we
are now our system is at center dealing
with all those hard planning routing
scheduling problems and then the
operation team suddenly become the team
that's just monitoring the results and
then providing guidance on how we want
to shift the different ways in the
objective function what type of digital
business logic we want to support. So
you can imagine from there the business
impact is very very significant. First
of all they are the largest travel
company in the world. So basically
everything has a huge multiplier but
also on that even if when you're just
looking at the operation metrics we're
definitely providing better plans
because we no longer need humans to
solve constraint optimization problems
on the spot. We also significantly
reduce really the solution time for the
teams to basically respond to any type
of issues. Maybe previously need 30
minutes for all the travelers impacted
by a flight delay to get any plan. Not
anymore. those things are really being
pushed out in near real time computed
automatically by our system subject to
all those different business
constraints. So coming here we mostly
want to look for opportunities to
basically expand our software's frontput
in the transportation logistic base but
also potentially go forward because we
know our software works really with any
type of temporal spatial preferential
constraints. So for us, every new
partners we on board to our platform, we
go through this three-step process to
make sure that we can truly get the
software and the model customized to
your problem. Making sure we capture
every single constraint that we need to
consider so that we auto solutions that
can be put into the field and execute
directly. So for us really going beyond
travel, transportation, we definitely
see opportunity in maintenance and
repair, disaster response, um shipping
as well as supply chain field, but
really any other verticals that may
utilize the type of large scale planning
solutions we have. We would like to talk
to all of you. Thank you.
Thank you,
Pang. Any
questions? Okay, I'll start. Um tell us
a little more about do you support cloud
uh native on premises and hybrid
implementations? Um yeah definitely so
the software itself is cloud native
because we actually need to utilize
right now it's in AWS the autoscaling
capabilities to solve for different
problem sizes very very quickly but you
can imagine everything ultimately got
packaged into either a data streaming
layer or a solver layer that we can just
deploy as docker images or containers
into any public or private cloud
environments. Any questions?
Cool. So, we'll have a booth outside.
Looking forward to talk with all of you
later. Perfect. Thank you.