I'm here today to answer a question the
question is why don't we use all our
brain cells well guess what we actually
do we just don't use them all at the
same time there are two major types of
brain cells the first are neurons these
cells are the ones we traditionally
think of as existing in the brain now
there's another type of cell in our
brain that we don't think about as often
those cells are called glea these Gia
are there to help the neurons do their
daily tasks so when neurons are talking
to each other they'll sometimes create
waste and Gia will help clean up that
waste the second example is we need lots
of different parts of our brain because
we do lots of different things with our
brain to help us walk we need our motor
cortex to learn and form a memory you
need a totally different brain area
called the hippocampus it's actually a
rumor that we don't use all our brain
cells we use them all we just don't use
them all at the same time for more MIT
moments from MIT open learning like
subscribe or follow