Quantum computing represents a
fundamentally new approach to processing
information. It's the only computing
model we know of today that's
qualitatively different from existing
computers. This difference and the
potential promise of a quantum computer
is reflected in the fact that simulating
a quantum computer using a classical
computer requires exponential overhead.
This means that as we add one cubit to
our quantum computer, the size of the
classical computer required to simulate
it will grow exponentially. representing
all of the quantum states of just 30
cubits would require at least a very
powerful laptop. Increase that to just
40 cubits and now you need a
supercomput. Double that to just 80
cubits and you would need all of the
classical computers we have on Earth.
Double that again to 160 cubits and now
you need all of the silicon atoms on
Earth. Even small increases in the
number of cubits translates to
exponential growth in the amount of
memory required to represent all 2 to
the n numbers that n cubits can store.
For more MIT moments from MIT Open
Learning, like, subscribe, or