I would like to introduce Evan H,
co-founder and CEO of Helix Carbon.
Evan, please go ahead.
Thanks. Great to be here and great to
great to see a good crowd here. So, my
name is Evan. I'm one of the co-founders
of a company called Helix Carbon. We we
spun out of MIT with uh my co-founders
Ariel First who's a professor in
chemical engineering and Dave Brown who
was a graduate student with me to to
really solve one specific problem which
is the the emissions impact of the
global steel industry. I think many
people on this call are probably
familiar with this, but it's a both
enormous market and enormous in its
emissions impact, right? And the vast
majority of those emissions comes from
the very first step, which is turning
metallic iron or sorry, iron ore rather
into metallic iron. And and the reason
for that is the way that we do this
process today. We take in some kind of
fossil fuel. We produce what's called a
reducing gas from that fossil fuel and
use that as a chemical reagent to strip
oxygen off that iron oxide. and then
gets emitted as CO2 and water vapor. And
so, you know, this CO2 is really coming
from this upstream carbon monoxide. But
it's actually quite difficult to get rid
of that carbon monoxide because it's
necessary as a chemical reagent. It's
it's providing heat for the reaction.
It's also providing carbon which you
know good quality steel obviously has
carbon by definition. And so switching
away from carbon monoxide is quite
challenging. So, how do you decarbonize
a process that inherently requires
carbon? That's the core challenge and
why it has been so difficult to reduce
emissions in this in this industry. And
so, we came up with a bit of a different
solution, which is let's actually keep
the carbon in here, but let's close the
loop. Instead of letting that CO2 get
emitted, let's pull that entire flu gas
that includes both CO2 and water back
into our electrolyer. We selectively
reduce the CO2 back into carbon monoxide
and the water back into hydrogen for
reinjection into the shaft furnace.
Right? And so it's a closed loop carbon
neutral process. But most importantly,
it requires zero process change at the
level of the furnace. From the
perspective of the iron making furnace,
nothing is actually changing. The
chemical inputs and outputs are
identical. And so this is compatible
across most existing iron making
facilities globally in a way that there
is not a technology solution for today.
And so that's really our core product is
this electrolyer that can take in not
just pure CO2 but actually this dilute
mixed gas flu gas which is really
important for the economics here. taking
that in directly, selectively reducing
the spent components, the CO2 and water
back into CO and hydrogen for
reingjection through to the shaft
furnace. And as you might imagine, you
know, this is plenty of applications
beyond steel. And so if this rings a
bell to you, we're happy to chat about
that as well. But we really see our core
focus for now as in the steel industry
for a couple of reasons, right? This is
novel because it's a drop in gas mix.
It's interchangeable with fossil fuels,
which also allows you to tap into a
pretty critical piece of this, which is
intermittency. You can run this
alongside fossil fuels to dramatically
reduce your emissions during times of
the day when electricity is cheap and
green. But for most geographies, you
don't have green power 24/7. And so you
can flip this on and off in a way that
is not available to most legacy
solutions. And it's also very flexible,
right? You can partially decarbonize,
you can entirely decarbonize. There's
really a flexible slider here
operationally because of that drop in
gas mix because it's something that you
can integrate day one without any
changes in your process chemistry while
producing green green steel. And so what
we do is we build electrolyers that sit
on site at our customers facilities
whether they're chemical plants or
particularly obviously steel makers. We
sit on site alongside them take in their
flu gas and produce the existing
chemical feed stocks and sing gas that
these sites already use. It allows them
to stabilize the production of these
feed stocks and and perhaps more
importantly stabilize the price, right?
Because you can tie it instead of tying
it to to volatile energy markets, you
can all of a sudden tie your economics
to 20-year PPAs for power. And so it
allows you a huge level of insurance on
your cost stack as well in a pretty
interesting way. And and finally, it's
drop in, right? We're not trying to
change any of the chemistries. It is a
drop-in solution. But I think more
importantly perhaps is is the cap
expert. And if you're trying to
decarbonize steel making, this is by far
the lowest capex solution because it
allows you to take advantage of legacy
innovations in fossilbased steel making,
which frankly has gotten really darn
good. And so that's what we're trying to
do here and and build upon. So we're
here to to to to share this with all of
you and also to to look for
collaborations, right? We're ready and
building currently some pilots here in
Massachusetts, but we're excited to
build additional partnerships sort of in
the 100 to 100 kilogram per day range.
as well as joint development projects to
really customize and test and validate
the solution for your specific plant for
your specific needs. And then finally,
if you're a user of steel and you're
looking to decarbonize, we're also
starting to explore green steel optic
agreements with many of the end
consumers in those spaces. So if any of
these describe you, you know, please
reach out and we we'd love to we'd love
to discuss. Thank you, Evan. Thank you
so much. Again, post your questions to
the Q&A tab and we'll try to get to
that. Um, what about the cement
industry?
Yeah, cement's good actually. Very high
concentration CO2, which is nice and so
that that's useful as a feed stock. The
I think the core challenge for us would
be what do you our whole model is we
produce sing gas and we want to use that
on site, right? And so it's for
industries where that is of chemical
value. And so the ones that come to mind
are really steel like we talked about.
There's also a broader suite like
polycarbonates, polyurethanes, acetic
acid, even pharmaceuticals as a broad
suite of industrial chemicals that use
carbon monoxide and or sin gas as a
chemical feed stock. And so we see those
as our as our sort of places to start um
before perhaps expanding to to other
industries as well. Absolutely. Okay.
Cement will definitely be of interest.
Um and then what is the technology on
the stack? Can you talk a little about
that or is that the secret sauce? It's a
little bit the secret sauce. Uh the
obviously there's there's innovations
both on the stack side, sort of the
design of the stack as well as on the
catalyst side. So the types of catalysts
that we're using uh one of the most
important pieces is resilience here. The
ability to operate in in mixed gases,
not just pure CO2. That's a huge
difference from existing systems as well
as to operate intermittently with with
no degradation. I think both of those
two are sort of the core technical
differentiators of of our system versus
the the current CO2 electrolyers out
there. Um, and I just saw Anton's
comment. So, uh, it's funny that you say
that. So, one of our first, uh, our
first partnerships is going to be at a
biomass pyrolysis facility. Um, but I
don't know if we've ever looked at bio
explicitly. So, I'd be happy to if you
want to reach out to
evanhelixarbon.co. I'd be more than
happy to chat specifically about what
you're envisioning. Uh, because I think,
you know, there's there's a much broader
suite of bio I'm I'm a chemist, right?
I'm not a biologist. And I think there's
a lot of those types of industries that
I wouldn't expect to see that have needs
that we can serve. Yeah. Fantastic.
Thank you, Evan. Thank you again, Matt
and Grace. And if you like to connect
with any of these startups now after
today, please contact your ILP program
director or us at Startup Exchange and
we'll all be able to help. Now, thanks
and back to you, Jose.