MIT actually announced the establishment
of MIT Generative AI and impact
consortium and today we are so thrilled
to have one of the faculty
co-directors
professor uh Vivik Filas who is a
Patrick McGovern professor in MIT school
of management. Uh he will give an
overview of the consortium and this is a
great opportunity if you have any
questions to ask the person who's
leading the consortium. The concern
itself is really to
explore the potential of genetic AI
across all industry sectors and foster
the collaborations between industry and
MIT researchers. Now let's welcome
professor Fas.
[Applause]
Okay. Uh, so I am I think the last thing
between you and lunch and so I'm sure
you're hungry after all of the uh the
exciting intellectual stuff you've been
exposed to. Um, and so I'll I'll be I'll
be relatively quick. Um, and uh
hopefully we'll have some time for
questions as well. Um, okay. So, uh,
basically you know you know we just sort
of talked about this Genai impact
consortium, right? What what is this
thing? Um so about a year and a half ago
uh this is in late uh 2023
uh President Cornblue uh organized uh
sort of an AI week at MIT. All right. So
it was a sequence of conferences uh
around campus very very heavily attended
where the idea was to kind of just
understand you know what what was
happening right like what what did we
think as as an institution about uh
generative AI. Um and one of the things
that kind of came out of that was sort
of the need to kind of have a consortium
an effort a centralized effort uh here
at MIT uh that would function on a few
different fronts. Okay. So one very
important front was the following. One
thing we recognized and you've probably
recognized this uh you know the in the
con in the in the conversations this
morning. A lot of the efforts happening
over here a lot of the research that's
actually happening uh you know in Genai
is not siloed. It's it's very sort of
cross-disciplinary by its nature. Okay.
Um and so one very important thing was
how can we actually do something that
brings every single school at MIT
together. Okay. uh this is so this is
not just an effort out of engineering,
out of computing, out of business or out
of science. Uh it's a much broader
thing. Um and so that was sort of one
goal. The other goal was uh impact,
right? So we said look uh this thing is
going to sort of transform pretty much
every industry that we sort of see
around us.
How do we make sure that, you know, from
the get-go, uh, we're kind of plugged
into this that we, right, that like what
we're doing is something we're doing
kind of handinhand, uh, shall we say,
with, uh, you know, things that will
have impact in the real world for real
companies. Okay? How do we kind of bring
them, uh, sort of into the fold? Uh, and
then the final sort of thing, the final
sort of desira was look, everything we
do over here, uh, this is for impact.
This is for the greater good. And so a
third sort of principle was anything
that comes out of this needs to be open
source. Okay. So these are sort of the
principles of this sort of genai impact
consortium. And uh you know uh president
Cornbluth uh you know gave us sort of
the following mission right. So she said
look uh hey what what what what I would
like right is that our community our MIT
community uh you know blaze the way
forward on important new sort of gen AI
solutions. Okay. Uh and so this led to
kind of the founding of the Genaii
Impact Consortium. Uh and what I'd like
to do today is tell you a couple
different things. So we just launched by
the way. So the idea is was very new,
right? So the idea h was middle of last
year, late last year actually. Okay. Um
we put everything together along with
the funding and our sort of initial
founding members who I'll tell you about
in a second. uh and uh over a very short
span of time. We launched in February uh
and we're at a place where we're very
soon going to announce an inaugural set
of research grants that will go to 40 to
50 different investigators around campus
uh to do work uh that we believe is
going to be at the forefront uh of Genai
that is at the forefront of impacting a
whole bunch of companies. Okay. So um
what what does uh the impact consortium
consist of? And by the way, you know, we
pronounce this acronym magic. Okay, so
MGIC, we call it magic. All right. So uh
uh in any event, right? So uh magic is
so so who are our founding members? So
as I said, we launched very recently. We
have seven founding members. I've shown
six over here. The seventh will be
announced very very soon. Uh one of the
things that you'll see okay is that
these guys run the gamut from on the one
hand open AI uh that needs no
introduction uh right to the other hand
uh to the other side you know Coca-Cola
and so you look at a company like
Coca-Cola and you ask yourself hey what
what is you know what does Coca-Cola
have to do with generative AI and it
turns out that Coca-Cola cares very
deeply about citrus greening okay what
is citrus greening I didn't know what
this was I learned what this was a few
months ago
uh but it's basically uh thinking
through how we keep our citrus crops
healthy. It turns out that with climate
change and a whole bunch of other things
uh this has been severely impacted and
so Coca-Cola says well hey listen maybe
Genai can help here. It can help with
precision agriculture. It can help with
thinking about uh you know how we
actually invent perhaps new strains of
of of of
of oranges, right? And things like that.
Uh and so as you can see this kind of
runs the gamut. OpenAI on the one hand,
you know, Coca-Cola on the other and a
whole bunch of different uh folks in
between. Okay. Uh what have these
founding members uh you know actually
done and what do they sort of get in
return? Um so the key thing for any of
these founding members is one they're
huge financial supporters uh you know to
this effort. Uh you know each of these
guys has committed uh you know a couple
million dollars a year for a period of
two years. the seven of them. It funds a
good amount of research. Uh you know
what what what do they get in return?
What they effectively get in return is a
seat at the table essentially
influencing in a very very strong way
our agenda. Okay. Here in terms of what
we do for research and you'll kind of
see how that that that works in very
specific terms in in in a second. Okay.
Um there's also uh you know a deep
connection with all the education
happening at MIT. One of the things we
heard from many of these founding
members uh was sort of the need to kind
of educate themselves as corporations
around how they ought to be thinking
about generative AI, how they ought to
be thinking about generative AI
strategy. Um and even educating their
workforces to some extent uh and we're
helping a lot with that as we sort of as
this grows uh you know we've kind of
closed at these seven founding members.
Uh we just sort of kept it at that. Uh
in fact our goal was five founding
members but it ended up being seven. uh
what we're going to do uh starting later
this year uh is sort of opening up uh
you know the gates to a broader group of
participation from companies. So there's
a whole bunch of companies on this list
uh that that didn't sort of make it into
this sort of founding pool. Uh but
really you know we call these innovation
members. This is going to start uh
beginning year two. So we'll start
recruiting these folks actively uh you
know later uh later this year. Um, and
the idea is to kind of grow the
membership here to something significant
where again really the the the back and
forth is that all of these folks get to
influence the research we're doing here
at MIT in a highly non-trivial way.
Okay. So, um, I'd like to do two things,
right? First, I'd like to tell you a
little bit about the leadership of this
initiative of magic. Like, there's a lot
of people at MIT involved in this and I
want to tell you a little bit about
that. Uh and then the second thing I'd
like to tell you about is what we've
actually done so far. Okay. So in terms
of our process of how we're making
research happen around campus, this very
interdisciplinary research that's impact
driven. What are we doing? I'm going to
talk about that. Okay. So in terms of
the membership, I know you heard from
Dan this morning. Uh but uh you know at
the top we sort of have a deans
oversight group uh led by uh our dean of
engineering Ananta Chandra Kasan. So
Ananta was in fact you know crucial in
really the idea of magic getting this
off the ground and a lot of the
fundraising and so on and so forth. Uh
right in the middle you have uh two
faculty co-directors uh myself and my
colleague Tim Kroska and CESO uh and
then there's a whole bunch of folks
around campus involved in a whole bunch
of different activities. Okay. Uh
ranging from effectively you know
education to undergraduate outreach to
really hiring and things like that.
Okay. U so that's kind of the leadership
and what I'd like to tell you about la
you know next is really what we've been
up to. Okay. What what have we been
doing? what is our you know what's our
2025 outline of goals to kind of give
you a sense okay so uh as I said we
launched very recently barely a month
ago okay so we launched in February that
was our sort of big launch event um and
essentially in February we reached out
to all of campus and we said hey look
we've built this consortium and our job
really our key job as part of this
consortium is to drive interdisciplinary
research across campus, right? Like high
impact interdiciplinary research. And so
we launched a call for proposals. Uh
that call of call for proposals I'm
going to tell you about in a second.
That call is going to fund 40 or 50 odd
research projects that'll get announced.
A first symposium and this is a
researchoriented symposium will happen
in early May. Okay. uh and then
following that in uh in later in
September we'll have a much larger
symposium again kind of focused on
research but much broader sort of impact
around that research okay uh so as you
can sort of see the center of all of
this is around basically doing high
impact research how has that worked what
has our process been uh right so this is
this is really what that process is okay
so one of the key missions of this
impact consortium is this you know seed
funding program that funds research. Um
the idea is we want to open source all
of the work that comes out of this to
the entire world. It's open to all, you
know, every lab essentially all sort of
um uh uh principal investigators around
campus, all researchers around campus.
Um and in particular, one of the things
I'll I've noticed in this first batch of
submissions that we got is that the
teams are very very multi-disiplinary.
Okay? And I'll I'll tell you a little
bit in a second about the kind of work
they've proposed. There's a whole bunch
of thematic areas associated with this.
AI for science, for engineering, for
business, for education, uh you know,
and so forth. And essentially what we're
funding is, you know, 40 roughly 40 uh
might be a little bit more than this uh
you know, one-year projects where the
idea is that these serve as seed grants
to get these projects off the ground.
And you know the money for a single
project ranges anywhere from 50 to to
300k with the median the sweet spot
being roughly around 150k for most
projects. Okay. Uh so what's our
progress so far? What have we done? As I
said this is like really fresh off the
press, right? Like everything's moving
really fast. We have to mobilize really
fast and so all this is really quick uh
and moving very quickly. So we had our
launch event in February. Uh we had
about 600 odd attendees to this launch
event. Um, and then March 7th, we had a
proposal, a call for proposals, right? A
call for these these these seed
proposals. We got 180 research proposals
from 180 different research teams around
campus. Okay, so this is like 180 labs
across campus that want to be part of
this. Okay, there's a whole bunch of
research that's represented over here.
Okay, uh, you know, there's folks that
care about doing generative AI and the
healthcare value chain. There's folks
that are thinking about generative AI
and how it's going to transform
education as a whole. Uh there's folks
that are thinking about generative AI
and bioengineering and chemical
engineering and so on and so forth.
Right? This relates somewhat to that
citrus green screening thing I talked
about but so much more. Uh there are
folks thinking about the transformation
of work. Okay. So as we sort of think
about really every job ranging from the
software engineer on the one hand to uh
doctors and nurses and whatever on the
other uh what are the problems gerine to
that kind of transformation and the
problems people are thinking about uh
sort of run the gamut okay from very
technological issues right to building
agents building robust agents so on and
so forth on the one hand um to strategic
issues right how do how do we think
about a workforce that's being
transformed what does one need to do
with a workforce that's being
transformed and so on and so forth.
Okay. Um so right we've gotten a whole
bunch of these as I said we'll fund
roughly about 40 to 50 of these of these
of these proposals. Um and our goal okay
is at a high level to make this
essentially the engine okay of high
impact genai research on campus here at
MIT. Okay. Driven by sort of the need uh
as I said earlier for highly
interdicciplinary high impact work.
Okay. The last thing I will say and then
I'm going to end over here right uh is
you know for those of you that are at
companies where this might be something
of interest to you um let me let me just
sort of give you a somewhat quick
picture of what this what it means to
participate in this program. Okay. what
does it mean for the company and what
does it mean for MIT? So uh you know
I've already sort of mentioned uh you
know the the inaugural founding members
that pro that part's done right we have
our group of founding members we've
formed that that part's over the next
step is bringing on these innovation
members that I that I've talked about we
have a very big list um what does this
you know what does this involve uh one
this involves uh for you the ability to
effectively deeply influence the work
happening on campus. Okay. Our founding
members contributed a whole bunch of
problems that they thought would be
valuable to them. I gave you one
example, the citrus screening, but there
was a long long list. Okay. Uh and to
folks on campus, this was very exciting,
right? You say, "Hey, like this is
something that's going to deeply impact
and influence the work at these
companies." It'll be the same thing for
the innovation members. Okay? So, in
essence, the big thing you get out of
this is the ability to deeply influence
work on campus. Okay? In a in a very
direct kind of way. All right. the the
financial sort of level for
participation is much lower uh you know
as as an innovation member um and as
such we're looking to to bring in a much
larger a much larger group and of course
you know I'm here representing MIT what
does this represent for MIT what this
represents for MIT is is our ability to
continue doing uh super impactful work
uh that is not siloed that is
crosscutting across campus um and that
speaks very very strongly to uh high
impact as defined by you know some of
our uh some of our partner members. And
so that's kind of what I had over here.
Um you know, I'm happy to sort of uh
happy to sort of go with questions.
Should I take them from here? Okay.
So, okay. So, the first question is why
can't AI generate reasonable images and
depictions with text that's not
distorted? Uh I think that's a
conversation for a different day, but
that's actually changed pretty
dramatically as of a week ago. Uh
there's a new model that OpenAI uh
announced. Let's see. How will magic
influence the integration of current
technologies to license, track, and site
copyrighted materials that have been
invested with or without permissions in
LLMs? Yeah. So, um look, um I think this
is a great question. Uh I think really
what you're speaking to over here
is it's a little bit of the wild wild
west, right? with what's happening with
uh with with large language models u and
it's sort of really disrupting a bunch
of value chains. So like yesterday uh I
spoke with uh the founder of a company
called Tolbit uh that basically is sort
of asking the question of listen you
know as a publisher and this question
really relates quite a bit to publishers
as a publisher right um you know it used
to be that uh there were very fairly
well-established value chains with how
you generated money for the content you
produced right broadly driven by
advertising and things like this in a
world where you go to perplexity or
something like that to get your
information. You know, how how do how do
things work over there? What what are
the economics of this, right? Because
nobody shows up on your site anymore.
How do we think about this? Um my belief
is that a lot of the work we do as part
of this, a lot of the work we fund
because of its crosscutting nature will
hopefully influence answers to questions
like this. The conferences that we, you
know, so a big part of our mission is
organizing a sequence of conferences,
right? Um and this is exactly the kind
of this is exactly the kind of topic uh
that some of these conferences can
actually focus
on. Thank you very much. Thanks.