[Music]
from the MIT energy initiative this is
what if it works a podcast looking at
the solutions for climate change I'm
Cara Miller and I'm Robert
[Music]
Stoner and today an exploration of how
the new Administration might change the
calculus around energy policy what
should we expect and how impactful might
the changes be we are joined by Chris
kid he leads the policy mission of mit's
recently launched climate project he's
also the associate dean of climate and
sustainability at the MIT Sloan School
of Management and as if that weren't
enough he is the former deputy director
of the MIT energy initiative Chris
thanks for being here thanks for having
me so based on what we know of
president-elect Trump's positions and
obviously it's not just that but
Republicans have a pretty broad power
coming up in the next Congress at a high
level what do you think the implications
are for climate policy yeah so I would
say that at least the biggest of the
Biden administration's climate policies
the inflation reduction act many
components of that act are at risk for
being repealed that act focused on
subsidizing clean Technologies and I
think the new Administration will be
looking at each of those subsidies and
trying to figure out whether or not they
want those to continue do you think if
you had to sort of look at that 30,000
foot View and you think about the energy
transition do you think this is going to
slow it down is it going to actually put
it in reverse and kind of go backwards
what would you say if you had to guess
it'll certainly slow it down um the
inflation reduction Act and the
bipartisan infrastructure bill you know
were key pieces of legis and when they
were passed lots of academics and
Industry followers uh measured the
impact of those acts as as being
substantial so if those are at risk then
clearly it's going to slow the
transition down but a lot of the a lot
of the heat was directed at Red States I
mean this was not only about a clean
energy transition it was about a just
transition and and and the Biden
Administration really popularized this
idea of of climate Justice and making
sure communities that had been either at
an advantage in the in the current
energy economy or or chronically
disadvantaged did okay in the new world
isn't that going to save it well
certainly in the data bear out what you
just said so the clean investment
monitor which sits at at MIT and was
pioneered by Brian De has measured that
roughly 80% of the inflation reduction
act subsidies are going to red districts
or red areas of the country so I do
think that's going to potentially save
some of those subsidies but there will
likely be a targeted approach by the new
Administration that will go through
subsidy by subsidy and probably ask two
questions do I like this technology and
do I like where this money is going so
the governor is like where it's going
well certainly some of them but you know
if we dive deep into the inflation
reduction we subsidized rooftop solar we
subsidized offshore wind hydrogen
ccus obviously the offshore wind is
purely going to Blue States because we
got the coasts still got the coasts
that's right and if I was a betting
person I I would not bet the offshore
wind subsid is going to survive but
there are other subsidies that are more
likely to survive whether that's the
subsidies on hydrogen or the subsidies
on battery manufacturing those those are
red State type subsidies yeah a lot of
really important manufacturing related
Industries being supported by those
subsidies that's right we now even have
a name for it there's there's an area of
the country called the battery belt
Kentucky Northern Georgia that area the
country is seeing a lot of
manufacturing enter those regions at
least we expect partly because of the
inflation reduction act I expect a lot
of people are thinking but wait one of
Trump's confidants at least as far as
we've seen has been Elon Musk who is
obviously famous for thinking about some
of these transitional Technologies you
know many many people own Teslas and you
would think he would want his goal would
be to incentivize the purchase of more
Teslas does it matter that somebody who
is not really super pro internal
combustion engines is on
it you know has the president's ear one
would think although this is where
economics teaches us to Think Through
the complete set of incentives so if I
was Elon Musk who has a dominant
position in the electric vehicle
Market I would probably be in favor of
getting rid of the subsidies because I
would be sitting there thinking my cars
will still be sold so I'm I'm going to
hurt my competitor
more than I'm going to hurt myself and I
think musk has kind of hinted if not
said that directly in some ways that he
doesn't really mind if the EV subsidies
go away and I think that's his rationale
that it's going to be much more damaging
to his competitors than it would be to
Tesla so it's you know we have this
Rising Tides raise all boats but so
lowering Tides lower all boats but if
they lower my competitor's boats more
than mine I might be in favor of it and
he he burned through just by selling so
darn many cars he he burned through his
initial subsidy limit didn't he that's
right there's that and there's also the
fact that our research suggests the
biggest limiting factor to EV adoption
now is the lack of infrastructure so the
vehicles are pretty close to cost parity
already it's the fact that an EV buyer
is afraid that they won't be able to
charge their EV easily that's keeping
them from from buying that EV and and
Tesla has an advantage on that with
their network but so do you expect then
the network for charging will get built
out it may through the bipartisan
infrastructure bill which did set
allocate I think roughly 5 to7 billion
do to building more Chargers that was
passed uh with bipartisan support so I
don't expect that to be repealed but our
work also suggests that 5 million doll
is not enough to get to get us to large
scale EV adoption I know you've looked
recently at the notion that the US has
really managed to achieve economic
growth in the last 15 years and has kind
of decoupled that uh from CO2 production
are we able to continue doing that do
you think that we will I mean that's a
really interesting thing because people
often think well these two things when a
country is growing there's more
pollution going into the air going ahead
what do you think will happen so if I
were to look at my crystal ball and the
Trump Administration has gotten rid of
several key subsidies in the inflation
reduction act I would not be surprised
that the economy continued to cut
emissions albe it much slower uh than it
would before and one actually positive
impact from the Trump Administration
terms of cutting emissions is I would
expect him to focus a lot more on
drilling for natural gas so that natural
gas is likely to speed up the retirement
of coal plants uh which has been the
major source of our emission reductions
over the last two decades so that'll
continue I just think we'll get a lot
less Renewables than we otherwise would
have but potentially a lot less coal
than we otherwise would have and just to
sort of follow up on the clean
technology I know you talked to uh
representative son Casten from Illinois
recently at MIT and there's this kind of
he talked about this dilemma in
manufacturing which is you know let's
say you're in the market for solar
panels you can have a factory in the US
where people obviously make more money
than they probably would in China so you
like americanmade jobs for Americans but
it's going to cost you a bunch of money
to put some solar panels on your roof or
you can get those solar panels for much
cheaper put them on your roof but the
manufacturing has to be done in China or
a lower cost for Vietnam lots of places
how do you think about that question and
what we're going to see going forward
obviously lots of talk about tariffs on
China but people also don't necessarily
want to spend a bundle to put solar
panels on the roof yeah that that's
going to be the conflict within the
Trump Administration so you know in
general trade
is welfare enhancing or or it increases
our aggregate level of of welfare or
earnings so if we move to this more
autarchy type World undoubtedly the cost
of building things is going to go up and
the question is going to be for the
administration whether or not they're
going to accept that higher cost for
having those jobs at least some types of
jobs more of them in the US but in
general We Believe trade increases the
wealth of the US but not uniformally so
the administration I I believe is is
making a bet that they can by reducing
trade with China or other parts of the
world our aggregate incomes will fall
but the incomes of key constituents may
rise that I mean that's a that's a
really key issue I mean everything
they're talking about doing or almost
everything they're talking about doing
seems to me to be sort of in
inflationary if we increase gas exports
we're basically connecting American
markets to Global markets and prices
will go up for Americans as a result of
that canceling EV subsidies so musk is
going to be able to raise his prices
because the other guys are going to be
more expensive we're we're eliminating
renewable energy subsidies we're
introducing tariffs on imported goods
largely from lowincome countries and
like like China we're repatriating those
jobs to a really high wage
environment so it's it's going to go up
but you try to look at the Silver Lining
bringing things out of China means we're
also bringing things out of an economy
that is extremely carbon intensive and
we're going to make them in a
environment here maybe maybe more in
Europe that at least for a while maybe
quite a while is going to be
comparatively low emissions isn't there
a chance then that the
repuation uh of manufacturing to this
country reduces Global emissions maybe
even quite dramatically yeah I I think
there's a few channels where that's the
case one is if China is producing less
stuff that stuff will get produced in
likely a cleaner Energy System that's
what you mentioned you also indirectly
mentioned two others uh which is we're
going to be raising the price of
stuff so we're likely to be buying less
stuff and that is going to put downward
pressure on consumption generally so
that too will push emissions downward
and then that there's the second order
effects which is we're going to be
moving things around less as well and
that might have a negative impact on
emissions and by negative I mean a
positive impact meaning on ships and
things fewer emissions yes yeah I mean
another way to reduce the emissions of
course would be to have a carbon tax and
I know you've right you've thought a lot
about that and would that be a more
efficient thing to do than and try to
you bamboozle everybody into uh doing
what we want them to do certainly in an
indirect way we might be moving in that
direction through Europe's carbon border
adjustment mechanism the cbam which is
kind of in a piloting phase right now
where at some point any import into
Europe will be adjusted based on its
carbon content and that is creating
pressure by
the countries that were exporting to
Europe to think about adopting their own
carbon taxes and it's also providing
some cover for US policy makers on both
sides of the aisle actually to think
about well if we're going to start doing
tariffs maybe we do tariffs based on
carbon content as opposed to just
Flatout tariffs which would then
potentially augment the impact that that
you mentioned Chris you know 15 years
ago more when you first came to MIT
which I remember uh you had a you had a
big old suburban with a license plate
that read tax CO2 which was I think
supposed to be your calling card as an
economist do you still have that license
plate and what are you driving
now so I do have that license plate and
I'll admit it's still on a very low fuel
efficient car it's on a Ford Bronco one
of the new ones I also have as the spare
tire cover on the back of it a graph of
the temperature rise in the globe from
1880 to 2023 so so hang on what are you
thinking well so look maybe this is why
I worry so much about how the energy
transition impacts uh Middle America and
parts of the country that academics may
not always concentrate on I grew up in
the Central Valley of California which
even though it's in California it's much
closer to Middle America you know I grew
up hunting and fishing and driving in
the back of pickups and and I frequently
have conversations with that area or my
old friends from from high school about
climate change and their skepticism of
the importance of climate change and so
on so that's where I constantly get the
feedback on you know how how does what
we're saying sell to different parts of
the country and the other point I often
make is you know the energy transition
not everyone has to
transition we need them to want to
transition and we're not going to solve
climate change through charity or
through forcing products on consumers
that they don't want we need to design
products that they want and use that are
cleaner than they otherwise would have
my Bronco Burns gasoline if Ford
produced a battery electri version or a
plug-in hybrid version I would be the
first one to buy it and that's a point I
also make is that we need to incentivize
the manufacturers to want to clean up
their act but they want to sell cars to
us so it at the end of the day it comes
down to designing policies where making
the decision that's right for society
and the person are one of the same I
have to ask you how often do people say
dude you have have like CO2 Emissions on
this graph and you're driving yeah
Professor dude but they may not know
that and you're driving to Bronco what's
going on here oh more than a handful uh
and it usually happens at the gas
station where somebody says isn't that a
little inconsistent with what car you're
driving and and then they get a five
minute lecture on no why no it's not
inconsistent and and here's why good to
know so if you see Chris's car in your
neighborhood make sure you have some
time if you start bringing this up
that's right the other great irony of
course that you're driving a Bronco is
they have huge engine problems if they'
made an electric version in the first
place that'd be a much more reliable and
better car yeah yeah certainly
maintenance costs and reliability
electric vehicles are a positive yeah
I'm I'm sort of heartened to see at
least some of the domestic car makers
kind of defending their EV Investments
you know they've built factories theyve
they have co-invested at least in
battery plants and so on retrained their
workforces you know now they're facing
four years where maybe the government
won't quite be the wind in their sales
that it has been but they can't go back
I mean they're not going to write off
tens hundreds of billions of dollars of
investment so maybe we just sort of get
over it and it's not so bad a Rob with
the with the optimistic but if it
works my wife hates me when I say these
sorts of things
you know our research does suggest that
we can reallocate money to be more
effective allocating it away from
subsidizing the vehicles to subsidizing
the charging stations so if the Trump
Administration was dead set on no longer
subsidizing the vehicles it is possible
that they could spend even less money
and at the same time get the same
penetration if they transferred more
money toward charging stations but I
haven't seen any discussion of that it
seems like all the discussion has been
we shouldn't support EVS in any way how
could we go
[Music]
backwards back beginning of 2024 you
wrote an opinion piece about how
essential it is that when we transition
in terms of energy sources we not leave
people behind
economically and there's been so much
examination and there will continue to
be about things Democrats did wrong how
did they underperform in the 2024
election not just at the presidential
level but uh you know in the Congress as
well and I wonder if you can just talk
about sort of that aspect of it the idea
that there is an energy transition going
on but that is not evenly felt yeah
that's been a frustration of mine for
quite a long time well before I wrote
that opinion piece we need to get Buy in
from all parts of the country and I've
written a quite a few papers that look
at the potential impacts of an energy
transition either on jobs households or
energy poverty is the most recent paper
and you know the impacts of the energy
transition are not equally felt and they
predominantly fall on the shoulders of
people living in Middle America and
people living outside of the
cities and this has two effects one is
if we do adopt policies like the
inflation reduction act and we're
actually quote unquote successful those
policies leave a bad taste in the mouths
of people living in in the middle of the
US but the second and potentially more
important impact is it creates an
environment where they're going to
resist those types of policy so and I
think that's what we're seeing in
Congress it's the coastal
Representatives that are pushing the
most for this energy transition and
we're not paying enough attention in
terms of Designing policies that do
disproportionately help Middle America
now we talked earlier about the
inflation reduction act where the money
is going to the red States but I don't
know if that's known I don't I don't
think that is widely known by policy
makers it's taking time for the
inflation reduction act to kick in and
and for the volume of those subsidies to
rise but did we get it wrong with the
IRA I mean could we have done better in
in being more inclusive of red States
and and poorer communities I think the
IR was a major step forward in terms of
just recogn izing that so under the
inflation reduction act we have energy
communities there are a few ways you can
become an energy community based on how
much fossil fuel employment you have
what what's your unemployment rate do
you have a coal mine or a coal plant
that recently shut down so that's the
first bill that I can think of that
explicitly differentiates communities
that have been hit hardest by this trans
transition and if you're an energy
Community your subsidies are are higher
than if you're not we've done some work
that suggests you know you could
certainly make it better I think they're
a little bit too much backward looking
and not forward-looking but it's a major
step forward in terms of recognizing
that the impact of the energy transition
is not going to be equally felt
therefore maybe the policy should not be
equally levied across the US I wonder
how much of this is also you know we
were talking about this before this idea
that a lot of money is going to Red
States and red State Governors but how
much is there a kind of skill mismatch
so you've given this great example
before which I really like and had never
thought about which is we saw a lot of
action from the UAW over the last few
years in terms of a strike unhappiness
with the way they were being paid and so
on but one of the real concerns for the
UAW is that as you transition from
building internal combustion engines to
building electric cars a different set
of skills is needed so I wonder if like
just because you're sending a check to a
red state does that mean that the people
in that state have the skills that are
needed or like outside people coming in
to take those jobs and maybe you can
talk about that a little no that's an
excellent point and I'm going to really
throw out a question because I don't
know the answer to this is are we trying
to protect
a geographic region or a person and
those are two very different objectives
right so we can if you think about the
inflation reduction act which is
providing bigger subsidies for specific
regions of the country so that's meant
to protect you know Appalachia or the
industrial Midwest but that's not
helping necessarily that coal miner or
that assembly line worker and I don't
think we have a great idea or great
policies to protect the people yeah that
are impacted so we could protect a town
and we'll no longer have the town
collapse because the automobile plant
shut down but that's not the same thing
as protecting the workers that were at
that plant and obviously it depends like
how we protect those workers depends on
where they are in their life you know it
might be impossible to protect that
65-year-old automobile worker there's no
chance he or she is going to be
retrained to do something or there's
very little chance but maybe that
25-year-old worker that just started we
could think about providing him or her
with the additional skill set that they
can transfer to another industry of
course that presupposes that they want
another skill set I mean Sarah Smarsh I
don't know she's the recent author of a
book called bone of the bone essays on
America by a daughter of the working
class has been talking about how you
know we have to respect the possibility
that workingclass people want to be
working-class people they don't want to
be reskilled they they don't want to
advance economically necessarily I mean
we're looking at it I mean not to cast
dispersions on your profession we're
looking at the situation Through The
Eyes of an
economist maybe we're getting it wrong
socially and not recognizing that people
have preferences oh yeah and I didn't
mean to imply that we're going to
necessarily change them from being
working class or a union worker or or
whatever but I I'm just thinking that if
I've been trained to be on an assembly
line and that assembly line which EVS
take I believe the number is 20% less
labor to build them you know can I be on
another assembly line or can I transfer
my skill set to installing heat pumps or
installing solar farm so we can keep
those workers potentially it pretty
close to where they were geographically
and skill set wise and and so on but we
need to realize that a lot of the
policies we adopt are really doing a
decent job at protecting locations
rather than individuals and what I don't
see are retraining programs or retooling
programs or you know that may not
require too much of a shift from you
know that assembly line to installing
solar panels or heat pumps and so on but
still require some level of retooling is
there any sort of research looking at
you know when a plant opens in North
Georgia and all these new jobs open up
are the people who are taking those jobs
inhabitants or do people come in because
we know like you know when there are
energy booms in like North Dakota lots
of people travel from wherever they are
which is not North Dakota to North
Dakota to participate and then might
leave again when like there's a bit of a
bust in the cycle or what I mean gold
rushes are kind of like that people come
from other places and so I wonder do we
know are those helping the people live
in Georgia or people coming from
wherever yeah I think it depends on the
on the job so the fracking boom you know
we actually have written a couple papers
on looking at who was attracted to that
boom and that's by and large you know
men in their 20s those are the ones that
moved to North Dakota but you're not
going to get the 50-year-old man or
woman with a family moving great
distances the moving costs are just grow
exponentially as we as we get older so I
think when that plant opens up in North
Carolina at least the more permanent
type jobs are just pooling predominantly
from people living already near that
area I wonder if you think think you
know there's so much sort of Monday
morning quarterbacking about the
election and about social issues and
about inflation to what degree do you
think the issue of the energy transition
and maybe maybe a mishandling of it or
maybe it could have been handled better
to what degree do you think that
factored in or mattered at all in terms
of the decisions people made I I don't
know the answer to that but what I will
say is I think the Democrats have missed
their opportunity and have not handled
it well and you know you mentioned a
2024 piece I wrote I can remember going
to I think it was a some meeting in in
Cambridge Massachusetts in
2018 in the heart of the Democrats and I
remember standing up there saying
Democrats need to start caring about
poor people again because I was
expressing my frustration with the
energy transition which is at that time
in particular everything was about
handing money to wealthy people living
in Suburbia whether that was rooftop
solar or EVS all of that was focused on
that demographic to get a $7,500 subsidy
for your EV you got to buy an EV that's
that's right that's right and and you
know maybe from a pure climate
perspective if if we just care about
maximizing carbon reductions in that
given year that's the right thing to do
because like you said said Rob you need
a lot of money to buy that EV you need a
roof to put those solar panels on so
you're already pushing toward the upper
part of the income
distribution but that might have been my
opic because I think it might have been
missing the fact that this is a
long-term game and we need to get Buy in
not just from Eevee or $775,000 car
buyers with roofs we need to get Buy in
from the complete country so simple
question how do we do that how do we how
do you design a policy that isn't
regressive as as the the transition
tends to be because it raises the cost
for energy which is a disproportionately
large fraction of poorer people's
budgets than wealthier people's budgets
how do we do this without always messing
with them yeah yeah well one way is is
what in the long term I think your
longterm point is also really important
right yeah you can't just have answer to
the short term well there you go that
was going to be my first answer and but
my I was going to make the point that
that's not a sustainable policy because
it's too expensive we briefly talked
about carbon taxes earlier we've shown
that if you structure a carbon tax
correctly 75% of lowincome households
bottom cortile households can make money
off of the policy the question is will
they trust that can we communicate that
to them but it's certainly possible to
design policies that actually transition
the economy and are a greater burden to
the wealthy consumers which I think are
are what we're looking for the question
is just how do we build the support for
those
policies another sort of aspect of this
whole transition and of sort of
convincing people
is the issue of convincing people that
it's expensive not to to change policy
or not to transition because there's a
we've focused a lot on like how
expensive it might be right maybe you
have to you maybe you had a job in a
regular assembly line and now you're
going to electric vehicles and that
might cost you your job we've obviously
we've seen a lot of hurricanes and
floods and people who live in Florida
know how expensive it is now to ensure
their homes but yet I didn't really see
that as a part of anything that any
candidate anywhere talked about not the
ones I heard there was little very
little discussion about climate I think
in in this last election cycle certainly
at the presidential level but you're
exactly right the costs of climate
change are also not uniform we talked
about the cost of the energy transition
not being
uniform and the cost of climate change
are going to fall predominantly on the
south and coastal areas of the country
and how we communicate that is a tough
one because a lot of the costs are in
the future even though we are starting
to see stronger hurricanes slower and
wetter hurricanes and more droughts and
more wildfires and and so on so the
concern though is by the time everybody
realizes how bad climate change is going
to be it's going to be not too late I
hate using that phrase but it's going to
be much later than we would have wanted
to heart's reverse that's for sure yeah
yeah do you think there's an effective
way to make that economic case because
when I think about the places that are
growing the most Florida Texas those are
also the places where insurance rates
are going up the most they are
Republican places people were worried
about eggs and the cost of eggs and meat
and like these sort of basic things that
they buy well if you own a piece of
property you probably ensure it yeah I
think that we are going to start to see
that and there was a recent paper that's
a NBR working paper that looks at the
reassurance rates and where they're
going up in in the country and it it it
is those areas that you mentioned as
well as big chunks of Middle America so
people are going to start to see their
cost go up the question I have is
whether or not they will connect the
dots will they realize that this is
because of climate change and not just
because rates are going up for
everything or or whatever excuse they
give and that's I'm a professor I got
into education for a reason so I I am a
true believer that education matters and
and work here but that's the education
that we're going to have to push out
there in so far as it's credible and
defensible so let's look ahead you're an
economist you care about climate policy
you think a lot about government maybe
first what do you expect when you think
about what the next four years will look
like at the intersection of those things
what do you expect to
see so I expect to see big chunks of the
inflation reduction act to continue so I
I do think we will continue to make
movements toward
hydrogen demonstration projects around
CCS or building more battery
manufacturing plants I also expect that
China is going to start sadly dominating
in key industries that I wish we had
more foresight to support and that in
particular electric vehicles so China by
far is already leading in that space and
the EV future is not going to be
squashed by the next four years the
Trump Administration is not going to
salvage the internal combustion engine
vehicle in the long term it might delay
EV adoption in the US and it might keep
us driving around in gasoline vehicles
but if you look at the rest of the world
they're already moving toward EVS so
this is a critical moment for our
automobile manufacturers to continue
their leadership in the automobile space
and my biggest concern over the next
four years is will'll be leapfrogged by
everybody else and that's going to
actually have very long-term
repercussions it really becomes a
competitiveness issue is the way it
sounds like we wake up in four years and
we're like oh well Trump isn't President
anymore but as you say China or whatever
other places are so far ahead of us on X
Y and Z we can't catch up
anymore yeah and the Trump
Administration might be able to s
Salvage you know John Deere or
Industries like that you know were
basically in homing that production but
they're not Global Industries at the
same scale as EVS or solar panels and so
on so if the Trump Administration is
going to really be
anti- clean technology then that's going
to put us four years behind on those
Industries and by then it might just be
too late so I mean as I I look at the
the nominees that that the president
elect is putting forward I'm I'm struck
by how their thinking is somewhat
ideological possibly not science-based
or science informed certainly not the
basis of science informed policy but
that's your thing so what's a guy like
you to do for the next four years you
just sort of retreat and and maybe work
on K2 education or is is there a role
for an outof work Economist or are you
out of work let me uh tag on to that
question in terms of not just what you
are doing for the next four years but
what do you think democrats should do or
think about for the next four years
there's a lot we can't predict but I'm
pretty sure they're not going to be in
power during the next four years but
what should they be thinking about so I
think there's bipartisan support
for
policies that reduce
emissions but the focus of the policy is
on something else and I'll give you an
examp example so we over the past few
months we've been through the new
climate policy Center here at MIT we've
been modeling several bills that
subsidize or promote or incentivize more
electricity transmission so those bills
if adopted would have a negative impact
on emission so we would get emission
reductions from being able to move the
electrons from the places where wind and
solar are most effective to where the
people live but what we've also shown is
those bills have huge impacts on
reliability and resiliency in the face
of storm so one in particular if you
were to pass that bill and have you know
we simulate a thousand storms across the
US that cut out generation because of
whether it's hurricanes or droughts or
and you can get 70% reductions in the
outages face by customers with that
additional transmission so that's a
bipartisan topic right we're all looking
for resiliency and reliability in our
electricity grid it has this co- benefit
that it leads to lower emissions there's
also the we talked earlier about the
Border tax adjustments based on carbon
content a republican in a Gulf Coast
State might support that because it
negatively impacts Chinese Imports but
that as Rob was mentioning might shift
the things we do buy to cleaner areas of
the world and that would have a benefit
from the climate perspective so I I see
the next four years looking
for co- benefits or looking for policies
that improve some other aspect of our
lives but also lead to lower emissions
and I do think there's a lot of room for
those policies do you think they're
going to listen to you is there a forum
or a some sort of channel that you work
through so the climate policy Center is
explicitly bipartisan we are actively
having conversations with both sides of
the aisle we're looking to work with
both sides of the aisle on understanding
what certain legislation or rules inside
of agencies might do to lots and lots of
outcomes so not just carbon emissions
that's our plan is to continue to have
those conversations maybe have more
state level conversations but I do think
there's scope here for passing
legislation that improves the climate
but improves other things that have more
bipartisan
[Music]
support Chris canle is the head of the
policy Mission at mit's climate project
he's also the associate dean of climate
and sustainability at the MIT Sloan
School of management Chris thank you so
much for joining us thank you for having
me thanks
Chris what if it works is a production
of the MIT energy initiative if you like
the show please leave us a review or
invite a friend listen and remember to
subscribe on Apple podcast Spotify or
wherever you get your
podcast you can find an archive of every
episode all of our show notes and a lot
more at energy. mit.edu
pods and you can learn more about the
work of the energy initiative and the
energy transition at energy. mit.edu
[Music]
our original podcast artwork is by
zeitler Design special thanks to all the
people at Mighty and MIT who make this
show possible I'm Cara Miller and I'm
Rob ster thanks for listening