The following content is provided under
a creative common license. Your support
will help MIT Open Courseware continue
to offer high-quality educational
resources for free. To make a donation
or view additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT Open
Courseware at ocw.mmit.edu.
Some content in this audio is not
covered under our creative common
license. For more information, see the
course materials on the MIT Open
Courseware website.
>> Okay. So, so today we've got uh a guest
panel uh of folks from uh the education
arcade uh folks from
news network uh which is actually very
closely related. Um these are folks uh
the the is the comparative media studies
uh research group over based in the in
the old media lab building where I'm
working right now. Um and you work with
the shadow uh teacher education program.
Um for folks who are unaware of of this
MIT actually has a teacher education
program. If you want to be like a
certified teacher uh to teach uh I guess
>> middle school math and I not middle
school, secondary math and science.
>> Um then that you can take classes and
basically get your certification or
apply for your certification at the end
of all those classes. Um but then they
also make games. They uh they they make
augmented reality games using uh
portable devices like like iPhones and
uh and PCs. uh games that run on flash
um together with campus to prototype
stuff before and uh focusing a lot on
games for learning. So the education arc
is the research group learning the
learning games network is kind of like
the spin-off company of the education
arcade that basically sort of works on
uh on projects that will be too
expensive to do inside universities
because universities are really
inefficient. Um anyway um maybe some uh
can you get start introducing yourself
I'm the latest in the group. So okay
yeah hi I'm Constantine. I come from
Austria. I'm at the moment researcher at
the education and um so I come from an I
I'd say I'd come from an I come from an
educational background. So I did my PhD
on on learning through failure, learning
through mistakes. And I kind of like
worked on on theories that explain why
we why we learn through mistakes and why
we most of the time don't want to learn
through failure. But in games we think
it's really funny or entertaining or or
challenging. So I was really interested
in how games um can be tools to um
understand learning and also is it
possible or this is like one of my
research questions. Is it possible that
people maybe learn who play games how to
cope with failure better like even be
more open to realize maybe sometimes in
life we make failure and our
expectations are not true or sometimes
not maybe they're wrong so I do um
research on a theoretical level with
that and um do um interviews with
players on learning demographies how um
learning experiences through games were
important in their lives and in in the
summer um I was um happy to um for for
and designing a game in the summer
workshop. Maybe they heard about that
anyway or not.
>> Okay, so it's just like I had um eight
weeks I was product owner on a team and
kind of like my theory was was used as
basis to develop a game a learning game
um called Afterland. Um of course it's
free online
um and I think our students did a really
good job on that game and it's it's a
platformer where um I will not tell you
what's about because then I would ruin
it. But there is twist.
>> Yes. And um and what I'm going to do now
in the next um year is um as it looks at
I I join game for a few months and do
research on how the game um is used by
players, how they learn in the game, how
they reflect on the game and I would use
I would work and hopefully even elderly
people on that.
Very good.
Hi, I'm Dan Roy. I'm a CMS alum. I did a
master's and finished in 07.
Worked with Philip a little bit here and
there. Um, mostly I worked with the
education arcade during my time at CMS
and with Scott
and we worked on a project called lure
of the labyrinth which you may have
heard of. It teaches middle school math
and literacy skills particularly to
But I believe to anyone who's interested
>> free online.
>> Free and online. Yeah. So go play.
Better than after.
>> Just trying to keep it interesting.
>> Is there a twist?
>> Yes. Well,
>> not as good a twist as we originally
wanted.
>> There was a twist in the development
process.
So that one was uh funded by the
department of education and that's the
it was a larger scale project but the
grant didn't go to MIT it went to
Maryland public television. So that was
part of the I believe the impetus for
the spin-off of the learning games
network is to have a structure that can
accommodate
the sorts of larger scale projects and
think about them in more sustainable
ways. But I'll let Scott talk about
that. Um
so
how did I get into this?
Um my interest in learning games is
mostly around engagement.
I feel like people who are extremely
motivated and enthralled with a
particular subject will find a way to
learn it and that a game may or may not
be the best way to learn anything in
particular.
but that there are many people out there
who struggle to get interested in a
topic if they're even trying and that a
game can be useful there. So as a an
exploratory tool say well I never really
thought about history but I like this
game and I want to spend some time with
it and I want to be good at it and it's
social
now I'm finding myself asking the kinds
of questions that other people are
telling me ask and I don't know what
label they want to put on it but I think
it's interesting and just sort of having
that kind of introduction to a topic
also I think games are helpful for uh I
guess I'd call it identity exploration
so for people particularly learners who
may not think of themselves as learners
or as competent learners that they can
sort of put that identity behind them
when they enter the game because you
know it's a game and anyone can play it
or maybe I'm particularly good at games
so I can play games and then I can
suddenly realize that I might be good at
other things as well or I might be
interested in other things that I
wouldn't allow myself to discover if
whether or not I was interested because
it was a risky sphere to enter.
So current projects, we're doing a
language learning game. Uh it's a casual
and massively multiplayer online game
with a grant targeting a population of
Spanish speaking high school students in
the US. Um and that is from the Hila
Foundation. And then we have a couple of
other projects going on as well, science
and some other stuff. So that's about
it.
So I'm Scottwell. I'm the research
director of the education arcade.
Research I share two titles, research
director and creative director. Um the
education arcade, but also one of the
co-founders of learning games network.
Um and I don't want to repeat too much
of what's been said except that I I at
the same time as as I do this for a
living, I still struggle with the term
educational game because it's not the
way I think of what I do primarily. The
first I before working in this set, the
first game I did was a commercial game.
It wasn't designed as an educational
game. It was designed just as a puzzle
adventure game. It happened to be about
math and logic, but that was just
because that's what we thought was
interesting. Um, it got marketed because
of changes in the marketplace as sort of
enterainment. But when I started in the
business, there was no such word as
enterainment. Most most games, if you go
back to the early 90s, were sort of
exploratory environments. I mean they
either either they were sort of twitch
games or they were exploratory
environments. I have nothing against
Twitch games but the exploratory
environments are all about thinking and
problem solving. And to me that's what's
interesting. No matter what domain
you're working in, whether it's
mathematical or whether it's historical,
it's still the process are the same. And
just to one slight twist I want to put
on what Dan Dan said. I think we are on
the same page. But because he led the
idea of engagement, it's possible to
think that I'm talking about games as
sort of an inducement to do something we
don't want to do.
And I think it's games are an
opportunity to discover how much fun
something is which is very different
from sort of we ah we tricked you just
mad but rather
this is really interesting. Don't you
like doing this and um you can do more
and then then maybe and that and that's
all that you get out of it that's fine.
If you later realize oh I like doing
that and that's math and I'm going to do
more of that. That's also that's even
better. And then I think it's not so
much because we just said it's fun. It's
because I think
the um very process I think the very
process of thinking and problem solving
is rewarding and I want people to
understand that better
and people do get that in games and I
just think it's important to tell people
realize if you enjoyed it in a game you
can enjoy it in life and maybe this
comes from my own realization but if
anyone told me if when I was in sixth
grade instead of them saying scientific
method and writing this list of dull
steps on the on the blackboard they had
said play this puzzle and let's talk
about how you solve the ple
that science. Um I think I might have
ended up working at MIT.
>> So anyway, um that's so so so talking a
little bit about finding about
identifying how you're going to make
how you're going to locate what's
enjoyable about the thing that you
wanted people to engage with. like how
can you talk a little bit about maybe in
a in a recent project or in past project
uh how you went about that process?
Let's let's let's talk about the the
things that you worked on. Um and maybe
sometimes it's more difficult than you
have some challenges. Maybe sometimes it
was just pretty obvious.
>> Yeah.
I'll take it
always.
I'd like to congratulate Scott on this
personal group.
So, with the language learning game that
we're working on at the moment,
there are approaches to language
learning out there in the world that
emphasize
vocabulary memorization or
grammar. Grammar meaning memorizing
tables of conjugations.
Um,
and
It's pretty much stripped of any sort of
meaningful context. So, and a meaningful
context could either be
a text, and I use that word loosely,
that is engaging. It could be a film
that you want to see that happens to be
in a language that you're trying to
learn, or it could be uh a means of
communication. After all, that's what
language is. So if you're thinking about
using language as a means of
communication, then of course you need
to think about what are you
communicating
and fortunately games are full of
communication between the game and the
player and the player in the game. And
if it's a multiplayer game between the
players in the game. So it was almost
like if you start from that philosophy,
it's almost a trivial exercise to say,
okay, well, what's something interesting
for people to talk about in a game? And
so you come up interesting game. And
instead of having the mechanic be click
this button to uh activate whatever the
nuclear missile, you have to you build
in collaboration. So I have part of the
piece and you have part of the piece and
we need to talk about uh when to use
what and which contexts and
on whom. And
so suddenly we're talking and it doesn't
even feel like we're learning a
language. It just feels like we're
playing a game. Uh and then if you're
doing it in a language that you're
attempting to learn, then there there's
the barrier there where you might want
to say something that you just don't
have the skill yet to say. So it's not
quite as simple as just saying, "Hey, go
talk." Um, but there's
slightly innovative ways that you can
give people tools to allow themselves to
express themselves in a fairly
constrained context. So, because you've
designed the game, you sort of break the
system, you know that people aren't
going to talk about absolutely anything.
Maybe they will in the chat, but
primarily in the game, you're
incentivizing their discussion around a
particular topic. So if you give them
tools to discuss that particular topic,
uh not only does it make the game play
more efficient, but that's also how the
learning can happen because there can be
some sort of selection mechanism whereby
I am able to say something that I want
to say but without needing to bring all
of the knowledge of how to construct
that on my own. You know, there's some
amount of oh, I can just recognize that
that's more or less what I want.
Uh, and then by seeing it repeatedly and
by seeing other players use the same
tools to communicate and knowing that
the communication in certain contexts is
is valid that I can pay close attention
to that and start to become familiar and
learn. But it's it's not a I have to
memorize it so that I can use it. It's
I'm using it and I'm using it so much
that I just naturally learn it.
>> Question on that.
>> So if you're trying to encourage me to
talk Spanish and you talk Spanish. We're
trying to work something out. Yeah.
>> What prevents you from just typing
something in in English and having you
read it in English?
>> Right. So, it depends on the game. Uh,
and in some games that's totally fine.
In other games, we have uh teams
moderate other teams. In other games, we
have some sort of communication tool
that's not free text entry. So it's uh
not so one extreme is here's a list of
10 sentences that you could say click
one of them and that's not the direction
we tend to go in but that's an example
of how to communicate something without
free text entry. So there could be some
sort of sentence construction kit, let's
say, uh where you have a pool of
different words that you can assemble in
a variety of orders to express a small
set of meanings.
And if you think about games like
charades or pictionary,
the need to communicate with constraints
doesn't stop us from necessarily
enjoying the game if we make it
interesting.
In fact, that's part of the game. Part
of our insight was thinking about our
own experiences learning languages and
sort of the game of say and this gets at
my sort of core idea which is to find
the game that's already there. So a game
that I always play when I'm travel
particularly
when I've traveled in France where I
speak the language sort of is how far
can I get into a conversation before
they figure out I'm not American.
So that becomes a game and sort of the
whole and and then and how how can I
have it or if I know someone uh who's
friends how much of a conversation can
we have in French that's again from at
that point it becomes kind of fun. So I
think we were just really trying to
access that and I think that really gets
back to your larger question when you
take on something new I want to know
where is the game already in this and I
mentioned it to Raj from my the first
game I did was math and colleague with
my who designed the game we both spent a
lot of time saying when we were kids how
do we play with numbers what kind of
things did we do what was interesting to
us with numbers we really try to access
our own our own play um and similarly
now uh I try to if I can try to meet
practitioners in the field and say you
know what do you think about in the
shower or when you run it where's the
because that's where the play is
actually happening um in the field and I
think that's where that's where people
who love their jobs it's the play in it
that they love about it and that's what
I think you try to access in any in any
service um so Dan talking about the
language one um we're doing a game with
the Royal Shakespeare Company if we can
get funding
around the Tempest and trying to figure
out how to make a game of it. And um I
realized that that part of the challenge
with Shakespeare is to some degree the
language too is sort of making sense out
of the language which is now somewhat
archaic but really interesting. And so
we try we made a game that's sort of a
um
puzzle that you assemble by finding
pieces of the play and associating
things. So you find a hedgehog and you
find some text that makes a reference
that somehow makes you think of the
hedgehog and you put them together and
you actually start building a visual
puzzle. So it's really sort of a
challenge of making sense of snippets of
text that gradually grow out and the
picture of the play starts to of the
Shakespeare play tennis starts to emerge
through the game play. So you a story
sort of appears out of the way a picture
appears in a jigsaw puzzle. So it's a
game you can play without knowing
without knowing without ever having seen
it. Um but that is sort of part of the
experience of theater is the way stories
emerge from I mean they emerge from
different pattern but still we're still
trying to make a story through
exploration
that was
maybe if if I if I talk about my
experience coming I think I come from an
area where we made really bad games like
we made there's this saying like
education games are like chocolate
covered broccoli like not healthy not
sweets you know and I think I come from
a background where um teachers or
educators were asked to build games for
somebody and what you had is content and
then it was like and I I I can say that
because I think most of my colleagues
didn't know better. They thought okay I
have content that content is good and
now I just make it a little fun and the
kids going to love it. And I think we as
you all sit here, we all know how um as
how quick kids realize that this is not
fun, you know, and um and I think um
there there are tons of bad games out
there um that that ruins the reputation
of educational games in that sense. And
coming here to MIT and working um with
Scotland and people like Dan
that I realized more the question is
more what makes us curious about a
problem about the learning content. Of
course, we can have the content in the
game. Sometimes we don't even have the
content. It's more abstract. We we look
for metaphors that kind of like, you
know, you you can understand how to be
interested in history without really
learning all the the the the real data.
Maybe you learn other history, but you
get interested in how history works. And
I think that's that's kind of like what
I learned here. And and I I realize now
that it's really useful that that um we
don't we don't use the chocolate cow
broccoli anymore. um we ask more about
what do we really want? Um do we want to
have something that is healthy or sweet
or something different? Let's cook it,
you know, let's not just combine two
things. And um and I think that's
something um that also like the good
educational games that are out there are
kind of heading in that direction.
>> You have counter examples from your own
work of like, you know, a something that
seemed fruitful but then kind of turned
out to be a dead end. uh
some you know maybe you're trying trying
to address some subject area and then
you're trying to marry some some
specific game mechanics you thought it
might work but it didn't quite
>> um I can talk about one that I'm it's
not resolved yet I'm struggling
I'm starting to work I'm doing a game
with a um professor here in ocean and
environmental engineering um about
microbes he does all this work studying
microbes in the which I I learned about
I mean half the biomass of the ocean are
microbes and we know almost nothing
about them because until people like him
which is one of the few built apparatus
to study oceanlike conditions in the
laboratory they had no way of knowing
what was going on with them. So, I mean,
that's interesting if if you get into
it. It's not something that a middle
school kid is dying to know about,
right? Um, although it could be I, you
know, so anyway, so we're doing a
simulation where we try, well, where you
the premise is that you've got a part of
the ocean that's dead and you're trying
to re-engineer it by putting plates by
introducing nanobots which you can
build. Um and these nanobots would
simulate the functions what microbes do
because microbes are doing at the
microbial level what does too which is
processing oxygen or rather plants and
you know plants plants and processing
either oxygen and producing CO2 and
energy or the reverse taking CO2 and
sunlight. Anyway, um so we so the
challenge we made a sort of interesting
playable simulation where you build this
stuff. But I I haven't figured out yet.
I'm struggling with
uh is it is it sufficiently
does the have we found the way to entice
you to do this stuff without having to
give you too much information? I mean,
I'm a big believer that a game this game
does not start with instructions. I
mean, because I don't believe games
should ever start with instructions, but
I'm still struggling with the
information we're providing along the
way. It's too much too much need this
now as opposed to and and I think the
problem is because simulations are very
wide open environments and it's very
hard to constrain a simulation enough
that the brain says ah now I understand
what variable I just used and and
particular because kids has have a
tendency to see simulations as black
boxes. So they'll throw in they'll
change three variables at once and not
notice that they've changed three
variables and not think about well which
variable wasn't. they just don't have
the they haven't got the habit of mind
to practice changing you know really
controlling the variables and if you
don't do that simulations do become
these black boxes and I'm still
struggling with how to how to not sort
of say mark down mark the kid down the
road and say okay now make this choice
now make that choice because that's
too constrained and not fun I want to
have have them have a lot of choices but
also help them understand the the effect
of the choices they made that's the best
way so I had to have just processing
I'm not speaking with a very clear way.
I can give you a bad example. So I was
working on this game like I wasn't
really working on that to my excuse. I
was beginning to work with these people
and then realized this is not the way
it's it's I want to go and then I
stepped out of it and I think it's u
it's a good example what you shouldn't
do. So this this um small town in
Austria is is um using their waste to
produce energy like renewable energy.
It's it's really it's interesting the
town is like somewhere in the
countryside nobody was interested. They
make so much power now that they can um
give power for free in their um the town
companies and the neighbor companies uh
the yeah neighbor companies in neighbor
towns. So a lot of people are interested
in how they do that and they thought wow
we want to be a cool town we make a game
instead of was providing the content.
But what they did they gave us all the
content and said this is what what you
should like teach to people and do it
make it fun and and in the end you know
like you know these people were sitting
together like okay what do people like
comics and you have to have a character
that is moving around and then we make
small multiple choice tests and
afterwards you get a reward and you get
the reward out and it says your name and
it says you are trained in that
discipline and what was interesting for
me that they built the game and the the
game's been bad and it's very sad and
it's horrible. But the funniest thing
for me was who was the target group like
and and they never talked about that.
They always thought who cares about
target groups? We make this game,
everybody's going to love it.
Everybody's so interested. The idea was
who decides if you can do that. It's the
major of towns. They say, "Oh, we we
want to have a company like that." And
so now we're talking about Austrian
European majors of towns and they are
normally fat and like to drink wine. You
know, normally they sit with another
major and have lunch and then they say,
"Wow, this works." And then they decide
to do it or not. But now they were
sending these games to the majors. They
didn't know at all what to do with this.
You know, they they they they couldn't
get into the game. Um and so not that
the game was bad, they didn't even think
about their target group. And um I think
that's one one um one aspect that
interests me the most is you have to
have the the context of the game and the
learning experience has to be suitable.
If this is not happening you know you
can play the most interesting game um if
somebody doesn't want to be like doesn't
get the problem doesn't get engaged to
the problem it's just you know it's just
um something happening is not really
interested in that. And um I think
that's that's a major problem that this
this example was totally addressing. So
>> So know know who you're designing your
game for and how and and how they tend
to get engaged with things.
>> Yes. I think um um
if I so I mean just to do a simplistic
example but it's one that's just as
applicable. If I wanted a game for my
mother who occasionally would play a
casual game, I wouldn't do a massively
multiplayer game with lots of stuff
going on. All these senior systems are
going to get into this massively
multiplayer game. I mean, in some ways,
it would be really great to come with a
massively multiplayer game for senior
systems because they're isolated. But
you also know that they're not they're
they didn't grow up with computers and
they're not going to be able to navigate
a 3D space. So I mean that's a that's a
simplified example of why it's
important.
>> What is really beautiful if if like a
game like like Remish the the cancer
game maybe some of you know that like a
cancer game actually it was actually
mentioned in
>> but it's probably one of the best
learning games out there. But the good
thing for them is people that play that
game have cancer and they you know so
you have the problem to the game is so
close that people will not play oh I
don't care about cancer no like they
care about cancer because they have
cancer the game is about cancer and the
way how chemotherapy works so the the
context and the engagement is
automatically um kind of like the
problem is solved but what about as as
Dan said what about a learning game
where it's about language learning um
are these people already interested to
learn the language. Do they come there
with a language problem or or do we want
to to introduce them to the problem or
or show that maybe they don't have to be
afraid to learn language or whatever.
this this question has to be addressed.
It's a very very early stage otherwise
you if if you'd stop design it and then
address the question it's
late
I do think I mean it's the question is
sort of about sort of the explicit
versus the hidden so if you played the
game Waker
that was really designed to introduce
basically
what an idea that people have struggled
with which are what position and
velocity graphs actually mean um but the
game doesn't mention velocity and it
doesn't mention graphs. And in fact, in
the same reviews that got lots of good
reviews when it came out, a lot of them
said that I had no idea this was
educational. Um
I
I would sort of I don't believe that
that's fine that people don't
necessarily know that as they play a
game that that they you're still
building up some conceptual knowledge. I
don't think that I think that some large
percentage of people who play a game at
that setting will probably they walk
away from the game and do nothing else
but three months later it'll have gone.
I mean that that experience for most
people will not be resilient not because
they didn't enjoy it but because they
got lots of interesting resil lots of
things going on in life and there's more
information coming out of something on
the other hand the kid plays that game
and then you sit down and have a
conversation about velocity and position
grass there might be some real
meaningful learning that occurs and so I
think it's really important to not
overreach in that sense um I try to
avoid although we slip into saying it
that our games teach anything because I
think teaching is a much more active and
explicit activities that our games do. I
think our games let people play with
things, let people learn things and then
just like if you write a you write a
book, the book doesn't teach anything.
The books the information it's available
and I think that's really sort of part
of what I think we have to be modest and
humble about as we do this stuff.
So, but that also puts on us the
challenge at an audience of thinking
about if if you do want some learning to
occur, where do you want the learning to
occur? is for people's personal lives.
Is it in a mediated setting like a
hospital or is it in a school that it's
really those are really critical
questions? It's not it's not just the
audience but the setting for the
audience
>> and who's introducing the game to them
for instance to the teacher doctor
>> right and while they play it like with
Labyrinth which is this middle school
math game that Dan and I worked on uh we
knew that if we didn't if we didn't push
in another direction the implementation
was going to be well we'll create this
game that gets played in classrooms. If
you've ever seen your all, if you
remember your own computer labs in
school, if that was your edge, which is
true, actually,
it meant every now and then you went,
you had to line up and walk down the
hall to this other place. So, what you
could only get to occasionally and it
took by the time you settled in your
chairs and booted up, you had maybe 20
minutes on a computer that it was time.
So, that was all, you know, if you're
designing for schools, you're talking
about a 20 minute experience once every
two or three weeks.
I'm not sure that was was worth thinking
about anything for that sense. So we
designed a game to be played online at
home and encouraged teachers to let the
kids just play it. And there was another
advantage of that which was to go back
to who introduces it. If you're playing
that even if we have a perfect 20-minute
game for the computer lab, if the
teacher's walking around, I mean there's
some I shouldn't say I've seen good uses
of that space, but there's some greater
probability that you're going to feel
like this is just a lesson. Whereas if
the teacher said, "Go play this at
home," there's some greater probability
that you'll sort of forget about school
and get playful. And it's not that
again, it's not that we want to trick
you when you're doing math. It's that we
want you to engage with the math in the
most playful spirit possible. And the
few the less we make it give the rapper
of scroll to it, the more playful you're
likely to be, even if we're not denying
that it's math or science. So that was
the other that was part of
you had said um that the cancer game was
really well evaluated. So, did any of
you have like stories or experiences
from seeing your games out in the world
that like like have you gotten feedback
from teachers who have tried this class?
>> No.
>> Yeah. No, no. Was it um Oh, um
yes. I from the from this this game I
just talked about about um renewable
energies. It totally failed. Like people
played them and didn't understand it,
hated it or or um before. So I think
like total failure. Um and I think I
think just to kind of like
to start with this this conversation is
this is a this is um problematic thing
because we hardly have any um we there
is very little um research going on on
evaluation of games because it's it's
also very hard takes a lot of effort and
and it also would take a lot of money to
re to evaluate the the research the
success of the of the game for learning
purposes. Um I I just know very little
studies that do that in the end. And I
think we just kind of like reach that
moment where where people start to think
that this is um an interesting way to do
it. And remission as I said is is
probably the only I I just like I hope
maybe you're correct in a second, but I
think that's the only game I would put
my hand into the fire for it. But what
but the question is what do they learn
in the game? They learned about self
agency. They learned that that they that
there is something they can do and they
they learned a more positive um
perspective and positive um relation to
medicine. They didn't learn anything
else, you know. It's like they didn't
learn like in the research because they
didn't change their illness.
>> Yes. And they and they didn't get
happier, you know. It's like not that
they said, "Wow, now I can Yeah. I
cannot they couldn't cope better with
their with their illness. They just took
their medicine." And so the doctors were
really happy with that. But you know,
And that's the stated goal of remission
actually is is this this is a it's a 3D
game where I think you play like a a
woman in space suit something um going
you know shock down and and and suddenly
someone blood bloodstream u but but but
say the goal of the game at least of the
people who are making it was to try to
encourage uh people who are suffering
from cancer to keep up with their
medication. uh you know just don't don't
don't
fall on your don't fail keeping up the
schedule of taking your chemotherapy
drugs basically and uh and again
designed to sort of show what happens
what what these drugs actually try to do
and some sort of like fictional or
fantastical I'm not going to say the
fictional yet all based in science um so
that's that's that's remission is this
famous
>> yeah so you can Google So um on
labyrinth the the original grant
included an extensive one-year
evaluation um of the game abuse and then
when Congress cut back the funding of
the larger program which is just one
small piece that got cut off and so the
research didn't happen. We're now
looking for a grant because it's being
used aggressively in Maryland schools.
So we are going to look for money but
generally there's less m as little money
as there is for developing interesting
engage is even less for researching them
and
and I think some of what I think our
work about is design research. We figure
out what we can learn by making the
games and we publish what we've learned
in the hope that other people will pick
up the ball. People who are have more of
a researcher bent
traditional sense we'll start doing the
research about it. I think we're on the
brink of that. I think with stuff like
the quest to learn school. I think
increasing numbers of educators are
interested in asking those questions. Um
I do have only anecdotal evidence but
the very first game that I did which was
this math and scienceoriented game a
math and logic oriented game um ended up
being not particularly well marketed um
and nevertheless sold a million copies.
And the anecdotal evidence I got was
that it was one of those rare cases
where parents would bring it in and
recommend to teachers or teachers would
recommend to parents or kids would come
home from school and recommend and and
there seemed to be this fairly broad
acceptance by both parents and teachers
and kids without without kids having the
sense that oh my teachers make them do
this and I hear that now that there's
original players in their 20s I will
hear from them and some of them say it's
what interested them in math and stuff.
So that's all anecdotal and maybe every
that's
but I think the million copies is
>> sure I'll just add a little bit to that
I also have some anecdotal stuff around
some of the other games but
the most interesting thing that I've
discovered
was with Labyrinth in a target audience
that I've seen play it that it was not
specifically designed for, which is uh
kids with some sort of um attention
disorder, whether it's ADD or autism or
something. and
seeing these kids engage with the game,
even engage with the game in a social
way. Uh, and be hyperfocused on the game
and be highly confident with the game
and
to really
calm down and adopt pro-social behaviors
that were not characteristic of them.
or that their peers or families hadn't
seen in them before. I think there's a
lot of power there.
>> The first two teachers I met who used
Labyrinth um said that they were seeing
performance from kids they didn't expect
to see in the program which is exactly
what I think we were hoping for because
we our sense was that lots of kids have
competencies and skills that they don't
show off in the format of school. School
being its own kind of game which only
certain people are good at. Um and so
having a be able to demonstrate
competency at a different kind of game
and let the teacher see it because part
of the design lab is that teachers can
track progress online.
Um that was one of our goals that was
that was
>> Chris
said it possible to look it up.
>> Yeah, sure. We've been talking about it.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Absolutely.
>> Doesn't actually exist.
It's just a notion that
>> other people can keep a little bit
while while we're setting it up. Um I
think talk ask a bit about prototyping.
So I mean in the process of um in the
process of designing the these are
mostly digital games that we've been
talking about all this time but I'd like
to talk about you know sort of the early
stage when you're working with paper or
um or simple digital prototypes. uh uh
how
maybe you can talk talk a little bit
about how you how that might be similar
or different from designing um uh other
kinds of computer games or even board
games? I mean do do you do do you test
it differently because you're designing
it explicitly for a specific audience?
Do you test it with instructors as well
as players or independent players? I
think it's always best to try to test
with your target audiences. The things
you've learned from
uh
um there's things you learn you can
learn from any audience particularly
usability which is important. Frequently
the flaw in a game is not the core
mechanic but the ease with which the
player can understand what they're
supposed to do. And you can test that
with that with any wide range of people.
anyone who you think is roughly as
computer or game literate as your target
audience. But I think if your goal is
sort of to interest kids, for example,
middle school kids like we were with
this game, just turn this on.
Um
um then you do want to because there are
questions about age appropriateness. Um
or uh sorry for let me mirror my screen.
All right. So we're about to get the
screen here. So this is just a login
screen. And this is not really this is
not the first screen you would come to
if you'd started again from scratch. But
um you get some more information about
but I've already logged in. So but
you'll notice um
oh let's just let me just log here.
So it's online. You can play from any
computer. That was important because we
were concerned about underserved
populations who either don't have
computers at home or
or who have less control over their
time, don't have a computer in the room
certainly or might do all their work in
in an after school setting or in a
library. So basically you can log in
from any computer. Once you have an
identity, you can log in from anywhere.
I'm going to briefly enter the game
space, but then we're going to actually
So here we're already in the middle of
the game. This is a puzzle adventure
game. And um the plot is someone stolen
my pet. I've tracked it down to this
underground factory that's being run by
monsters with the help of remember
there's middle schoolers with the help
of um a mysterious woman with kind of
bluish skin and wings um I've been given
a monster costume. So in the guise of a
monster myself
I can go around and sort of do jobs at
the factory find my pet figure out what
what the monsters are up to which is
indeed no good. Um, and uh, I'm in the
middle of this game, so I've already ran
some. There's a sequence of rooms, which
part of the game is just finding the
room where the puzzles are. So, for
example, we're going here.
Uh,
one of the wings of the factory.
There's 100 doors here, and I can click
on every door if I have to, but I have I
get map, which is itself a mathematical
tool to find where I want to go. Um
and uh and as I go through each each
room represents a different puzzle. Um
anyway, having said that, I want to
actually go back and oh the other big
the other big feature in an egg is that
um
you play on teams and you can
communicate with your teammates um
through this communicator.
Um, and the reason there is to actually
get kids reading and writing about what
they're doing with math because if you
want to help your teammates, but you
can't give each other the answers
because you'll see we're about to play a
puzzle. Um, every uh every puzzle is
every time you play it's a different
solution. So, you can't tell each other
the answer. All you can do is talk about
your strategies. So,
you're going to leave your game and go
to puzzle mode play.
This is like a shortcut.
>> Yeah. Shortcut to puzzles, right? You
don't have to play in the in the context
of the game. You play any puzzle that
you want. Um,
well, I'm going to try one. I don't I've
never played this with a group before.
So, usually uh usually I pick the same
game play because I get used to playing
with people. But let's just try this
one. This will be a real
I think I try level one.
>> Okay. So, you So, I'm trying to remember
what you know here. You have to
basically you're in the fac the shipping
area and you've got to come up with a
manifest to um ship the number of
objects that you've got. That's all you
know. Okay. You got to give it the right
you got to basically give them the right
instructions to ship it. And so, now
just tell me what to do here.
Quick.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Of course. And that's what you
know kids
up into the
>> drag. Okay.
>> Up into the slots up there as one zeros.
>> Okay.
>> Can we put that crazy fish head second
to the right on everyone in the equal
spot?
>> Yes, you can.
>> Yeah.
>> You want to try in the equal spot? Go
equals on this one.
>> Just tell me what your thinking was.
>> Well, it looks like we're trying to
build math equations and usually they
end with equals something
>> and you saw the Now, just so you know,
the equation that we're going to build,
you're right. And just as a short, this
is not about arithmetic. The equations
are simple. I'm not interested in
drilling kids at arithmetic. This is
really about the fact about uh number
systems and
that number systems are just symbol
systems. But there's also some algebra
that's going to go on as we start to do
this too. And at higher levels of the
puzzle, this gets into other basics. You
start doing stuff in base two and base
six which sort of dubtales with the
notion that that number that our
representation of numbers are
disembodied. So zero a one a one zero
doesn't have to always mean 10. It's
It's just a symbol. Anyway, so now what
should we do?
>> Pac-Man should be minus because the only
ones with six digits have Pac-Man as the
third digit.
>> Sounds good.
>> Okay. I'm not sure which one is
>> right. This guy
>> thing is if you look at the top left
then what is the twodigit number that
minus the last digit gives a single
digit number. So 24
>> so yeah
>> oh that's a good point. Yeah, it has to
be divided by
>> Yeah. Yeah. See, but but now what you're
really doing is thinking about the
structure of sort of math, which is
exactly what we want.
>> So, what you say that is divided?
>> Yeah.
>> So, I'm going to guess the banana is
four.
>> And you want to say why?
>> Four. Oh, because well, like using that
same logic, that first equation, it's
something
nxid x= some single number.
>> I'm guessing X is four.
>> By the way, I think by the way, you guys
have have avoided have not noticed a
piece of information which would make
your work even more um
>> what's that thing?
>> The thing at the top.
>> What's the thing at the top?
>> The thing at the bottom.
>> Oh, it could be two actually as well.
>> What are all the green things? Can we
click one?
>> Those are the things you're shipping.
Those are jars of stuff. Oh, pepper. Oh,
that makes sense.
>> Banana something banana
>> banana
>> equals
>> something banana.
>> So try banana.
>> Well, banana could actually be two cuz
doubles
36.
>> 5 * 5 is 25.
Oh, with in that respect that means the
little um the four.
>> Yeah, the four squares is times.
>> We try that.
>> Has to be 01.
>> By the way, every time you play the
game, the symbols are different. I mean,
the same symbols, but they're different.
>> Triple dash has to be Oh, no.
>> You're still missing a piece of
information, but that's okay. That's
what games are all about.
>> So, what's this thing in the top left?
Can we like put things in there and
press enter? And will it evaluate them
for us? Um, yeah, but right now you're
not done yet until decid.
>> Oh, triple dash is one because one times
banana is bananas.
>> Unless banana is zero.
>> But I can't
banana.
>> That would be a banana. six. I think
>> by the way, I've never done this game
before. You know, the fact that you're
naming all these symbols, which of
course they were just symbols.
[Music]
>> What am I telling you? I can tell that
you're wrong.
>> I think banana because it's banana
banana.
>> So, banana squared is equal to something
times banana.
>> Not as many times.
>> So, yeah, it could be 25.
>> It could be five banana. Now remember, I
didn't know the solution to this when it
came in, but I actually have enough data
to know that you're wrong.
>> No, it's on the screen.
>> Banana definitely is
>> five.
>> It's five because banana squared is uh
>> something is like anchor banana but uh
but flower banana divided by banana is
also an integer.
So if flower banana and anchor banana
are a multiple of banana, then banana
should be five and not six.
>> Yes,
>> because flower minus anchor time.
>> I love your math.
>> All right. No, that's good. So you're
saying it's what? I think it's
>> okay.
>> Well, it could work, but you could have
done it in a simpler way
>> or you could have surmised it. Not known
it, but surmise. Remember this wasn't
the first thing like subsequent times
you'd have other information you don't
have. So,
>> oh yeah,
the number of blocks
25.
>> Oh, so the maximum number is 25.
>> That's what you're actually
sort of short. So, normally in the group
I don't give away this much. So, give it
away. But in fact, you're making a ship.
That's sort of those that's the describe
the thing on the pallet.
>> So, anchor is 20.
>> Anchor's two.
>> Yeah.
>> Sorry. Two.
>> You call this the anchor. Yeah.
>> Anchors anchors to claw. Claw zero.
>> Wait, where's claw?
>> Claw is the one on the top left
>> of of the squares that are left.
>> Oh, you mean press circles. That makes
sense.
>> Yep.
>> Oh. Oh, that
>> that's zero. Has to be zero.
>> Wait, why is it zero?
>> Uh cuz if you look at the the equation
at the bottom,
>> wrong one. I'm looking wrong.
>> It's definitely
zero. Ninja star is four.
>> Ninja star is four
>> which contains epsilon is five.
>> Wait, dude.
>> Nine. No, I guess it is a sigma.
>> Sigma is nine. Sigma is nine.
>> Yeah, sigma is nine.
>> Uh, see
>> wait.
>> Okay. It shows the other
>> like the scythe is scythe is a plus.
Scythe is plus.
>> No, it has to be minus.
>> No, it has to be something.
>> And then uh the crescent moon dot the
banana banana is three.
>> Oh, that's banana.
The sticks is
>> No, I'm not talking about that one.
>> Look at the bottom.
No, I was talking about
>> the backwards thing has to be triangles.
>> That one the triangle
that one that looks kind of like the
last one.
>> But I'm just curious anyone who who was
having trouble and and this happens in
the group and so please anyone have
trouble following it as people were
making stuff up finding stuff because if
you did it's okay. In fact, sometimes
you got to play the game yourself for it
to make sense. So I didn't have said in
front of the crowd. I could have told
you. I actually think I could have told
you a lot about the game going into it
and there would still be a high
probability that when you started
playing it, you would have not absorbed
anything I'd say. That's my experience.
I can almost give it a wall away and
people still don't get it until they
play it.
>> So theta talks about the value of play.
>> Theta doubles upside down as eight.
No, not really.
Quickly enter that now.
All right.
>> Oh, so now you have to type in one times
whatever equals
>> you have to type in what this is. So
this actually is getting at an alternate
another representation.
>> So let's see
>> 8 + 9
>> 8 + 9 is 17.
>> All right, let's try that. And then here
you don't actually have to remember
just divide by six, right?
P
is the top right time. It's puzzle mode.
>> So 56.
>> Yeah. And by the way, it can take it in
either order.
library=
52.
>> I think there's only addition in this
level. There's only addition.
>> We actually come up with a way of
representing subtraction division plus
>> 2. Yeah.
>> Or we could do 10us 2.
>> Anyway, I just point out that that when
you were solving that, you were doing
10us. when you were solving for those
numbers, you were doing Algeb, you were
really sort of thinking about X and the
structure of the math and and the the
numerical quality of it and and like I
said, now this is simpler, but it's
still getting at the fact that that
there are multiple ways of representing
numbers and quantities.
>> Is there any mechanic to prevent like
brute force,
>> you run out of yes, those lights go out,
you run out,
>> but you do earn points along the way in
the game if you make some progress. And
so we we try not none of these puzzles
are brick walls because you can always
play multiple puzzles at once. You can
leave this puzzle go to another puzzle.
And if you do make any progress at all,
you're accumulating points for the end
of the game. You can actually get to the
end of the game story without having to
solve any puzzles. Takes a long time.
The rewards are there for doing well.
And there are rewards for doing well,
but there isn't punishment for not doing
well. There isn't sort of a we don't say
you can't we don't we don't make you
sort of stop in the tracks.
You can do it again.
>> Yes, that's right. You can do it again
instantaneously.
>> And there's no cost. There is no cost in
the game to having failed
repeatedly. It's not if you eventually
solve it, you end up with the same score
whether you solve it on the 20th time or
the first time. This um that's what
really problem solving about is not
about being the fastest. It's just it's
just about learning how to solve things.
Speed speed is underrated.
And in math it's much very you know big
kids think they have to be able to do
calculations in their heads. Anyway I
don't want to go any I mean it's just
more of this and higher levels we do
have come up with we came up with
representations of subtraction which is
that you have like a large number like
you have 10 jars and five of them are
empty so it's 10us.
>> How is division?
>> Um are they 10 rows of jars?
rows are empty.
>> Yeah, I think it's the same. I think
that's it. I think that's the same. Ah,
it's in the it's in the it's in a grid
pattern. Um
so,
>> and how would you do uh I guess uh
there's algebra in there, but do you
have any algebra such this like format?
Uh no no but what so what we encourage
is that so what comes with this is
material for teachers to relate this to
the curriculum and what we really want
to happen is the kids have played the
game before they get the subject where
the teacher introduces symbol systems or
base six or whatever it is that relates
to this instead of saying all right you
start up a new unit you are get you
again know nothing we're start you're
starting again at square one and have to
start all over again with something new
instead the teacher comes in and says I
want to introduce a new concept but it's
one that you've really already begun to
master and uh it's called basis. It's
called basis and it pulls up, you know,
the higher level of this game. How did
you solve this? What was going on in
this game? Um and they have a
conversation about what they already
know as a way of leveraging into
leveraging what I mean I arguably don't
know. I mean I don't I again I would
argue that the way we deal with bases by
the way is you have boxes, you have
things in cartons. So a carton of six
jars plus some leftover would be a
carton of six jars plus three left over
would be one three in basics.
So uh so anyway the point is that the
kids begin to build up this sort of
robust conceptual understanding and
hopefully with a play a sense of
playfulness about it so that when the
teacher talks about it it's something
they actually feel kind of good about
instead of here's one more here's one
more reason you'll ever be a
mathematician which I think math
education is largely designed to gate
everybody so that at the end of the high
school only 7% of the population thinks
they're good at math which means that
we've taken 12 years teaching 93% of the
population no better than math and they
should stop doing it and I don't know
why we waste 12 years we could just tell
everyone to kindergarten um but that's
sort of what we end up doing anyway I
think that's true with every subject
that's how you know the number is so I'd
like to turn it around where everyone
says there's things about math I can do
that
>> yeah can I talk a little bit maybe about
how that process
>> sure I also wanted that provide a little
extra nuance to one of the questions
about what if you just brute force your
way through it and the higher levels um
it won't tell you when you put a symbol
in a spot whether it's correct or not.
>> Yeah.
>> So which actually you can learn
something kind of interesting because
you can start doing something like
suddenly you end up with something that
doesn't add up. That's actually mean
you're learning something.
>> So
there's 10 puzzles or how many nine
puzzles and we came up with 9 plus x and
some of that x was uh
slated for implementation and we never
got there and some of that x was uh
puzzles or activities that we ended up
deciding deciding were not as compelling
as the others and our process for that
uh we did a hybrid approach with paper
and computer programing And in general,
the rule is if it can be paper
prototyped, paper prototype it. It's so
much faster. Uh but there are certain
kinds of activities that really can't.
So for instance, this one is perfect for
for paper prototyping. You just take out
a piece of paper and a pen and you
create uh I mean you have to create some
of these uh equations so that you then
have a system of equations to solve. But
once you've created some of those data
sets which would need to be done whether
it's a paper or a computer prototype
then it's trivial to put it in front of
someone with paper. So this is an
example of something where we would uh
for the first round test internally with
just symbols and numbers and then uh
probably we would do we might even test
that version with people in our target
audience. But probably we would try to
do some rudimentary art treatment
>> uh before we put it in front of people
just so there's a little bit of context
and it looks a little bit more like a
game. And then in general
>> and sometimes we try to if there's story
this one has less story about it but if
there's story as you are in some places
we actually try to act it out even I
mean you have to sort of get over your
resistance to doing that you sort of act
out the character in even if it's you're
the computer when you do and so even if
it's just a character giving a response
to something that the player does um you
try to do it in character you try to get
a sense of what because I think even
even in that kind of rudimentary form
you are engaging the player's
imagination
So you know whether or not they're
interested in this character or the ide
>> and like a dungeon master you need to
prepare because it's hard to be the
computer without also being the
bottleneck if you're a human.
>> Yeah.
>> So uh and in fact we've done some game
not represented here. We've done some
games uh that are real time that if you
want to prototype with people and then
especially on paper and you want to keep
things moving then you need to have more
than one person be the computer because
there's just too much to track for one
person do it all. Um or if you want to
do sometimes we do hybrids where we'll
do a computer prototype but there's
aspects of the game that are not
represented through the interface or
that logically we haven't modeled and so
we'll do you know players directing
human interactions with the computer or
uh I guess not players designers uh you
know
influencing
those interactions. So anyway, this is a
game that uh moved pretty much all the
way to final design on paper and then
went straight to implementation. Some of
the other games, so for instance,
there's a game um you want to show bats
maybe.
>> Bats. Yeah.
>> That's an example of a game that's a
little bit harder to think about playing
just on paper.
>> I just want to think we implemented this
early.
>> Yeah, we did.
So this is a game um about
modular arithmetic
>> and common multiples and that sort of
thing. So it's very hard to see on the
screen. In the upper left there is an
avatar.
>> There's you
>> and you know from the story that your
goal is to get the golden eggs.
and avoid this guy that that much you
know and you're in a factory where they
mix stuff. So
>> let's put
>> Do you move your avatar
>> one and two?
[Music]
>> What?
>> Oh
>> how about one in class? Oh, with 11. All
right.
[Music]
>> Yeah.
>> There is one flaw, by the way, in the in
the fence in the um interface. People
don't realize they're going to have to
click to get their guy onto that
>> thing. And it was supposed to start with
with it up right where he was so that
people
now. What should I try now?
>> Four.
>> What?
>> Six.
>> Or four.
>> Why? Four.
>> Six. Then you can move against.
Bam.
>> Four is stuck at the top.
>> Oh, can we move?
>> But you'll notice that these bats all
are different amounts. And so it's
really about modular arithmetic. So
what's 12 will take you once around on
one of them, but it'll take one and
third around on on another one. And and
you start doing simultaneous equations
to solve to solve this. This is this
level is hard. I I think maybe the
hardest puzzle we designed the whole
game is level three of this where you've
got to every step you've got to align
two bridges.
>> Oh, that's fun.
>> And yeah, it's it's serious work.
>> Oh, you're trying to avoid that monster.
>> Yeah, you kind of avoid the monster.
>> Oh, okay.
>> Which isn't always hard, but but you do
have you have to sort of keep in mind
sometimes it means instead of going
around once like nine, you know, instead
of going one on the nine thing, maybe
you go um 10 and that'll c and he'll
he'll always go on the grid that shows
up. So maybe that'll cause another
bridge to show up and get your way. So
this is really Chinese.
>> What?
>> Yes.
>> Anyway, again,
you know, you can play a game without
without think about math school math at
all. There's no school math in this
game.
>> But I think there are really interesting
things to think about.
>> But I think I want to highlight what you
just said with the character if he walks
or not. Like I think if we far it's
clear anyway, but You have to keep in
mind there are two forms of learning.
One one is learning the game, how to
play the game. The other one is the
learning like the the problem solving or
the puzzle in the game. And I I think
it's sometimes especially my experience
in educational games. It's so easy to
mix it. Yeah.
>> You know, because sometimes you make it
cool that it's educational game and it's
really interesting but but you know like
for inance the character wouldn't move
if you don't press the mouse button. So
he would always stand there in the
beginning and he would get that effect
you know. And I think the mixture of
both forms of learning is quite
interesting to keep in mind when you
prototyping.
>> Yeah. And it's actually there's two
there's two add that one is I never
think just because you want people to
think hard. I don't think the interface
should be the thing they have to think
hard about. It's always tempting to say
oh that's really good and t that's a
really hard thing to solve. How do I you
know how do I make them jump? But no, I
mean I think generally it should not be
hard to figure out how to make him in
trouble walk left or right or how to
open a door or you know unless that's a
puzzle and it's easy to delude yourself
that by making the interface hard. On
the other hand, there is this other
challenge which is that kids do have
different degrees of sort of literacy
around games and it's hard to figure out
the sweet spot of this. That's one I
don't have an easy answer for because
some large percentage of the audience
naturally knows, you know, try to get to
the edge, try to, you know, knows what
winning means. But there's some kids who
don't. And the question is, do you if
you make the game, if you bend over it
backwards, like if if tried to do I I
watched my mother play this and it was
horrible. Um because she just didn't she
just was totally clueless about where to
go with this. But I think if I tried to
set up the game to work for my mother um
you it would only work with all this
explicit instruction that so so they
hopefully with kids it's less of an
issue that they there's more I think
uniform game literacy but it's always a
challenge. No game appeals to everybody
and you do want I don't think we I don't
think those of us who make learning
games have a good answer to that. I
don't think we can ever make a game that
every kid will play with equal fervor
and we should never claim that you know
that we're going to get 100% on that.
>> Um,
>> one thing that I know that uh you've
you've noticed uh is the amount of
tolerance that kids and adults have for
frustration. You know, when when I seen
kids say, "I hate this game. This game
is too hard." And they will just keep
keep going at it.
You adults have this tendency to get
really embarrassed if they console the
first time.
>> It happens when you're uh 26
and you suddenly sit down and say,
"Well, I'm not very good at this."
People who were you may you may have
been a gamer all your life, but at some
point it's it's what having another
adult watching you. I don't know. You
know, there's some point in life when
you suddenly say, "Oh, I'm not good at
this."
I don't know why why it happens, but it
doesn't it hasn't happened.
useful.
>> Can you negative numbers?
>> Uh, not on this one. No, that's a good
idea though. It's initially thought.
Yeah, we didn't think about
>> Well, you could in modular arithmetic.
You could always do it as just put in a
larger number.
>> I I have a question for content because
so far we've been hearing from you guys
about coming more or less from a design
from a game design angle into playing
games for as a learning purpose and you
kind of came the other way around. You
came in from the education and pedagogy
side. Are there things to keep in mind
when you're working across disciplines
that you might need to know?
>> Yeah. Um, so I think I I think one one
one difference that I still have um or
see between the way I approach games and
the way educational games approaching
games is I'm I'm I'm more focusing on on
learning as an experience like more in
abstract form. It doesn't mean that I
wouldn't be interested in that but
that's not what I've been working on yet
here. Um so for instance in in after it
was so the re research question was how
can players overcome expectations that
are wrong and um and I didn't um so the
idea was not to use um educational stuff
like numbers or whatever but more can we
develop patterns in games that players
realize very quickly and are they ready
to give them up if they realize that
they that they think what they've seen
is wrong. So um for me it was very
interesting because I come with an
abstract theory inside and then u so we
were developing prototypes and it's very
interesting when you come from the
abstract idea to prototypes and I
thought paper prototyping is perfect
because it really you know like it made
me as a scientist come to the grounds
you know like because I can of course I
can read and all these people and say
wow um experiences this and that and
then you suddenly have pen and paper and
sit there and think about a game that
kind of like is is a metaphor for your
theory. And um so I think my so kind of
like my takeaway was that paper
prototyping was very healthy for me and
with the team to come down to the fact
what is really doable in the game. what
can we really I think and in the
beginning I was a bit like being not
that experienced in prototyping like wow
we can all do that later um we can do
the cool stuff when when we get to
programming but then I realized no we
can't you know if we cannot do it as a
paper prototype how should we do it you
know like in programming what what what
is changing you know and um and I think
for us it was very interesting we had so
I think one experience we had is we had
them develop different prototypes and so
I That was healthy for us not to make
one paper prototype and then think how
we can do it better. But that's what
what what education kit anyway makes a
lot of prototypes you know like and and
and to stay open and even if you spend
like three or four days on a prototype
if it doesn't work with others the
moment you show them and they go like
what like these are the rules are you
sure I don't get it you know and if you
explain the 10th time maybe maybe you
know it was a cool idea back home or
with your friend maybe it just doesn't
work you know and um so this kind of
like experimenting with prototypes was
very healthy for us and then coming to
the point and I realized for me it was
important that somebody coming in the
room and playing the prototype for five
minutes kind of like understands the
core mechanic. If this is not happening,
you know, like who takes the five
minutes to understand the core mechanic,
you know, nobody today.
>> Be like in this game like walking onto a
bridge.
>> That's right. That's right.
>> And um so yeah, I think coming from a
different perspective again prototyping
is kind of like the way to to to to get
in the game, you know, even as the
designer. Um because from then on, you
know what you're talking about. And I
had to lose a lot of my abstract
thoughts in the process. and then the
play testing you know so I so it was
interesting sometimes to see even if the
prototype is cool then you you have a
prototype and then people come in and
say I don't I don't get it again and you
go that can't be true you know it's so
easy but then you know you can start to
stick with your idea or say no if if
maybe I have to go down with the
theoretical aspect and and really look
what is suitable for the players so
another thing about prototyping it's
temp it's not focus groups So it it's
not a case of it's sure you want to do
as put it in front of as many people as
possible but you really want to I think
avoid stuff like what did you like what
didn't you like those kind of questions
because people want to be helpful and
sometimes when what people say they
didn't like is actually the part where
they were working hardest you know so I
didn't like that I had to jump over the
wall well in fact you have to jump over
the wall and and it may not really mean
that that that if you took that out they
would enjoy the game more in fact they
might not enjoy it at all so you have to
be really careful about and people want
to please you and they'll say, "Oh, it's
good." And some of that I think it's
really important that what you do with
prototyping is watch the player and then
trust yourself as a designer rather than
ask them what you should do because they
won't they'll try and be helpful and
they'll come up with wrong suggestions.
watch them and try your use your best
judgment as a designer as to what
they're reacting to and why they're
reacting the way they are and try to fix
it and maybe ask them try to get some
questions to try to maybe get some
access to their thinking but don't think
that they necessarily know what what was
interesting to them or what how or how
or what would make them happen. Don't
ask those questions. Those are focus
group questions and you shouldn't ask
them because it's not going to give you
the answers you want. You got to trust
yourself at some level as well. And
something that I also had to learn was
if you have the focus chest or like or
or the play test and and and then you
you realize there are problems and it's
really healthy to write down the
problems and then brainstorm different
solutions. Don't ever like when you
discuss it, try to come up with a
solution immediately because what
happens is you quickly develop one
solution and then you go in with another
problem but you don't realize that
sometimes you know like some problems
stick together or sometimes you realize
wow we have so many problems just
because of this little aspect we have in
the game why don't we just you know and
if you don't do that you start to you
spend two hours on solving a problem
then realize it was wrong or you never
realize it again. to kind of like seek
more to the problems and quick solutions
where you are still movable and not make
solution solution solution and then have
the same problem a few weeks later
again. Yeah, I just want to clarify
focus test and focus uh focus group two
two very different things you know we're
talking um the kinds of results you're
talking about focus testing which is
which is specifically identifying
individual problems in your game
>> and focus group is asking them what what
they like which is actually very not
useful for most product design in fact
uh games
>> one piece of advice because you're all
that I think is really important if
you're a smart college student like an
MIT student is that you probably learned
you probably learned in spite of your
education. You learned by having someone
sit in front of the class and tell you
what was going on and you somehow you
absorbed it. Um that's why you got here.
But lots of people don't learn that. And
it's really hard to avoid the tendency
in the game to just tell people what
they should know which is sort of for my
money like when you meet up someone who
speaks a foreign language and so you're
not understanding each other. So you
both start speaking slower and louder.
to no effect and I think that's what a
lot of education that's a lot of bad
education in general does speak slowly
aloud and certainly a lot of bad
educational games so so and just
remember that just because you got the
first time and someone told you doesn't
mean that everybody else it's not just
about explaining it better giving you a
different way of learning
questions
Just wanted to say something. You ever
heard of Fire Hose Game? Post this on
the forum. Uh so I told him I know a guy
works there and he said we got focus
group tomorrow night or PS3 central a
few months and they didn't want to go
tomorrow night 7 o'clock. for an hour
and a half.
>> That's that includes NK alums part of
people who haven't played the game
before.
>> Maybe
they're not.
>> Can I ask a question? Can I ask
questions?
>> Let me know in the next.
>> So the question I would have for you is
is did anybody of you have his in this
in this play biography educational game
that you played that you would say was
was kind of like an important experience
to you that even you know like I know
maybe it's embarrassing now with the
other ones are listening but does
anybody out there yeah like Sam Bon
whatever that game was best game of all
time
I mean it was it was similar in that you
you had like an avatar they taken around
and had to solve little puzzles that you
know underlying them was math and like
simple m equations, but like pizzas like
just divide up pizzas. Cool.
>> It was awesome.
>> We can't let that that's got me.
>> Oh, it is. I was going to ask you. I was
like I was like
you.
>> No, but
but and I think it's interesting to
think about if you had an experience
like that, what was it that made you
like the game? you know, like I think
it's worth very rich because a lot of
people have um have bad experience with
educational games and then think about
them when they design it. Think about
the the cool ones that have um there's
this series of games called thinking
things and one of them had a mode that
basically was kind of like programming
in that you could place different types
of units on a grid and then give them
instructions in a loop. So say go
forward then left and right and they
could they could paint a square. And so
what you could end up doing is with
certain configuration a certain set of
rules you could get them to draw
patterns and stuff like that. And what
used to happen is my dad would say can
you get um you know two like inverted
triangles drawn on the screen and then I
would like sit there and try to like
basically program without realizing that
it was actually a programming game. So
>> does that
made a game which is there's a bunch of
games that have done that. Um, the last
puzzles and beans actually did some of
that stuff, too. Um, and there's a
product out just now called that I'm
hooked on right now called Trainard,
which is on the iPad. The I
>> Yeah, I thought that be
>> what? I thought that would be your name.
>> Yeah. And and it really is about um it
really is a programming game basically.
It's kind of cool.
>> The iPhone version.
I was just going to say that two games
which are really informative for me like
in the educational context were Dinosaur
Discovery which is an ancient game
>> and I would have played it when I was in
kindergarten and I'm all most of the
people here
um and it was it was a an adventure text
puzzle game which was which was the year
and then where in the world is San
>> another classic game that I played back
when I think it was back when about the
time when the internet started getting
popular because mid9s it was uh math
blasters or something
>> Mario teaches typing that's
>> oh
Mario teaches typing
>> the incredible
>> machine
that's like thinking it's really
I love
>> and I think this this is a even this
romantized wow that back in the good
days you know like I really enjoyed that
game that's that's kind of like I think
where we all want to have to with
educational games it's not like oh my
god you know I have to play an education
game but more they can be really and I
think the best convers was it came with
an almanac they encouraged you
>> yeah to look use research search of fact
answers. In fact, it wasn't cheating to
look up the answers. It was smart to
look up the answers.