Thanks everyone. Um it's fun to be here.
We can keep this as like interactive as
possible. Um sort of just like you know
maybe don't scream it out but you can
raise your hands and happy to sort of
keep it interactive. Um sorry for the
title change. I'm now one of those
people who just sends a generic title
and abstract and then talks about what
I'm currently interested in. Um but no
I'm going to talk about this the same
thing just under a different title and a
different framing. Um and so sort of um
so so the title of this talk is sort of
at a high level I think connecting uh a
lot of sort of the type of work that
I've done my group has done over the
last few years which is sort of the
following which is so I I I sort of grew
up in the econ
the like sort of the fundamental
assumption right so like like the core
belief of the econs community is that
people have information and preferences
that sort of central planners do not or
central mechanisms do not and that it's
important to sort of uncover
those preferences or information in
order to do things right so we have
democracy democracy is good um and so
you know people vote on things um sort
of out of the econs community we have
things like participatory budgeting or
deliberative democracy and it's sort of
people are voting in complex spaces
right um sort of a lot of my sort of
early work as faculty was sort of on
crowdsourcing systems so in New York
city and in Boston things like 311 where
like you complain about potholes and um
sort of noise complaints and trees
falling down um and things that like
sort of you need the government to fix.
um sort of what I'll mostly spend today
talking about is also in Boston and New
York City um and many urban centers
throughout the United States and
throughout the globe. Um we have things
like school matching where sort of even
to get into elementary school or middle
school or high school um and then you
know residents you know med school
students residencies um you sort of um
the the student side submits a rank list
of their preferences over the other side
and then schools do the same thing and
then a central algorithm decides who
goes where
and like sort of empirically and this is
just sort of just like an empirical fact
that has been shown repeatedly in a
whole bunch of sort of contexts
including a lot of sort of uh my group's
work over the last few years. Um it's
just the fact that participation is
often low and is especially
heterogeneous in these systems, right?
Right. So, like in New York City,
participatory budgeting, um, where sort
of you vote for how much like your
neighborhood spends millions of dollars,
like does this school get a bathroom or
that school or like libraries or things
like that, sort of voting rates are
around 2% depending on how you count the
voting population. Um, and it sort of
differs by socioeconomics.
um and sort of these crowdsourcing 311
type systems sort of neighborhoods
request service at different rates in
ways that correlate with socioeconomics
even controlling for need right so like
even controlling for like how many
potholes there are um sort of u and you
know doing that controlling is that the
hard part methically but sort of ones
you can control for things like that um
sort of neighborhoods request service at
different rates um sort of in what I'm
going to talk about for most of today is
in sort of in school matching. Um
families might have heterogeneous
awareness of highquality options or sort
of things like you know their their
beliefs about admissions rates at these
schools and so on. And so so that causes
sort of differences behavior.
Um and so a lot of sort of the driving
belief of my group's work over the last
few years has been sort of like this is
a bad thing, right? And this is part
sort of probably um the biggest threat
to the legitimacy of I think the core
belief of econs right is sort of um that
sort of we need to deal with sort of
this heterogeneous behavior um if if if
we sort of want to sort of our systems
to grow
um and sort of I have um a paper in the
sort of the SIG comics changes the
newsletter. Um
>> could you just reiterate what you mean
what you mean by what exactly is the
biggest
>> Yeah. So sort of I think heterogeneous
participation and the resulting
inequities that result because sort of
in our system. So in what I'm going to
talk about today, for the most part,
it's going to be sort of um if
[clears throat] students or families
have um sort of different ability to
fully participate in the school matching
system, then sort of that leads to um
inequities in who gets into sort of top
high schools even sort of controlling
for who's eligible for top high schools
and sort of so sort of inequities and
inefficiencies caused by sort of this
type of participation differences is I
think sort of the biggest threat to the
legitimacy of these type of systems.
Yeah. Great.
Um and so um you know I probably won't
get very far in talking about the other
direction. So, but what I'm going to try
to do in this talk is sort of primarily
talk about sort of these sort of ideas
um in sort of behavior in and sort of
now um in RCT that we're um sort of
running and in sort of the New York City
high school applications context and um
sort of and then you know if I get there
overview a few other directions and my
hope to you is to convince you that one
sort of um the thing that I said on the
previous slide is true that
heterogeneous participation matters
Um two is sort of um there's a whole lot
of interesting work to do um from sort
of theory to empirics to HCI um
deployments RCT that kind of stuff
um and sort of not just sort of um
heterogene this is sort of maybe a more
technical point but sort of not just uh
is heterogeneous participation a thing
but sort of um you know one of the
mechanisms that we're going to talk
about is then give is sort of
recommendations to try uh um sort of fix
this issue and sort of their um
heterogeneous uh information provision
which you know various folks here have
also worked on um sort of also matters
right so you might need to give
different information um to different
people um and sort of I'll I'll talk a
little bit more about what I mean later
on okay so but for most of this talk I'm
going to talk about sort of these two
papers um the first one is written it's
not online yet, but happy to sort of
share share a copy um if anyone wants
one. It's 100 matching in New York City
um school choice application behavior
and the potential personalized feedback.
Um it's sort of exclusively a historical
descriptive paper um sort of with Kenny
Pang and Emily Rue were the lead um
student PhDs and then also with John and
Ava. Uh and then sort of the second
project is sort of our ongoing work um
sort of our our RCT sort of our our sort
of the interventional piece uh
personalized nudges under congestion and
the New York City high school match sort
of led by PhD student Erica Chang also
with Kenny John and Ava.
Great. Okay. So what's the context? The
context is that every year um about 70
plus thousand um eighth graders apply to
about 8 to 900 high school programs in
New York City. And historically this
meant that they could rank up to 12 of
these 900 plus programs and then match
their deferred acceptance. As of last
year um they can rank as many as they
want.
Um and then sort of empirically
um we know that there are disparities in
where students attend high school,
right? So the median black or Hispanic
student matches to a program um with uh
almost double higher fraction of
students who did not graduate high
school about 43 higher fraction who did
not enroll in college. Um and then lower
school impact or sorry lower school
performance which is sort of a
combination measure and then lower
school impact which is sort of trying to
do like the causal thing of the um sort
of the performance measure. So trying to
control for um sort of uh input
performance of eighth graders, right? So
sort of there are disparities and who
goes to school where.
And you know there's at least three
potential sources of disparities. Um,
one sort of source or two of the sources
you can think about are maybe sort of
supply side disparities, right? So like
where physically are the high performing
schools and sort of where do students
live, right? Like geographic segregation
um still exists. Um, and so you can
think about sort of geography and
location of high performing schools. Uh,
you can also think about admissions
policies, right? So um as I'll describe
in a little bit, New York City has sort
of um a fairly extensive and complex um
sort of way in that students are ranked
for admission. So many so about 200
school 200 of the 900 programs um are
screened schools which means they use um
grades and historically things like test
scores in order to um rank students um
and then admit by that. Um, and so, you
know, some other schools use geographic
zoning. Um, and then there's like all
sorts of other preferences, right? So,
you could believe that even if sort of
schools are physically accessible, maybe
they're not accessible because of
admissions policies, right? So, these
are maybe supply side um sources of
disparities.
Um what we're going to focus on in this
line of work is uh maybe the sort of uh
I don't know if demand side is the right
word but sort of application behavior
sort of component of disparities which
is controlling for and I'll be more
specific by what I mean in a little bit.
Um but controlling for geography and
admissions policies um disadvantaged
students may not apply um and match to
high performing schools. And you could
you can say you you know you and maybe
these differences exist for many
reasons, right? Maybe it's like a true
preference um sort of like true
preferences around sort of around
geography or true preference around peer
groups or all sorts of preferences over
sort of where they want to go to school.
Or you could uh do uh blame things like
a complex process, right? that like this
is just a hard process
in like applying to high schools in New
York City is like a hard stressful
process, right? So, like I said, there's
like 8 to 900 different programs. I
think this year it was over 900
programs. They're all throughout the
city. um each of them have sort of a
different set of maybe language courses
and AP courses and arts courses and
different sports that they offer and
different like after school activities.
Um and then New York City also publishes
like all of these quantitative metrics
for each school. So like performance and
impact um like I talked about earlier
and then also a whole bunch of like
survey data. So New York City for each
school publishes things like surveys of
families, parents, students of each
school. Things like how is this school
on like the school's relationship with
families or safety and school climate
instruction and performance, right? So
like there's like an incredible overload
of information and choices um that
parents have
uh in this process.
Any thoughts or questions so far?
What what is impact and performance?
It says that impact is measured against
expected outcomes. Yeah. Adjusted for
incoming student factors.
>> Yeah.
>> So running some kind of regression on
this.
>> Yeah. Great. So um how this score is is
exactly that. So it's like essentially
it's like I don't even think it's as
fancy as a regression. I think it's um
like literally like means amongst
comparable schools by incoming class. Um
there's like an a really great line of
work. So like folks here at MIT, so
Paragatic, Josh Angoras, sort of those
sort of folks u who've been thinking
much more carefully about like sort of
like much more directly causal inference
sort of ways to calculate this taking
advantage of the fact that the match is
random, right? So like that induces
randomness which sort of gets you sort
of much more like causal measures. Um
but that's not what's shown online.
Other thoughts or questions?
Okay, great. So this is like a hard
process.
Um, and I'll show this fun thing in a
few slides, which is like if you're
rich, you can, so like if any of you
Google New York City high school match
and you don't have a ad blocker, you're
going to see a bunch of ads for
consulting services to help you apply
for the high school match.
>> Yeah. Sorry, I'm just confused about a
lot of this because you know if the
thing that you're trying to um you know
test is about participation and so
economic
>> stuff then this is kind of a fraud
example just because like you're saying
there's so many complexities right and
also the whole school choice thing was
introduced you know kind of for a reason
there's this you know they want people
to think like uh you know especially the
lower socio economic classes have been
discriminated against, you know,
chronically.
>> And then, you know, this was set up to
try to uh essentially um uh devalue
public schools so that the rich would be
going private schools, right? And so,
you know, there's that whole thing. And
and and so sometimes people can be um uh
let's say cynical about whether the
participation process really has an
effect will really will give them more
educational opportunity.
>> Uh I I I would say that sort of like if
you go to the rhetoric of sort of like
you know Bloomberg administration
imposition of school choice. It very
much was like an equality of opportunity
argument, right? It sort of you should
allow people access to schools um that
are high performing that they might not
be geographically zoned to. Um, and so
part of I think what we're going to try
to think about is sort of um and you
know I I I think that's that's great.
Uh, and sort of part of what we're going
to think about is sort of how can we
help with the application process in
order to sort of like help maybe achieve
some of those equality of opportunity
>> aspects. Why is there that so the what
is it? Why is there that socio that
geographic difference you know? Yeah.
>> So, you know, I'm just not sure that,
you know, how much did you even if
everybody participated
forms makes all the choices, you know,
will that really will honestly
>> Yeah, great question. So like this is
what we're going to try to do and I'll
show you hopefully some results in a few
slides in which sort of trying to
compare at least a little bit um sort of
uh sort of disparities due to
application behavior as opposed to
disparities due to sort of geography and
other aspects.
Okay. And so this is new as of last year
sort of by done by a couple researchers
who were at MIT um Bola Cordini and
Cleman Zaido which is sort of as of last
year in New York City um you can see
your admissions chances at each school
at the individual level right so you can
see um in high medium or low sort of
discretized buckets um what your chance
is at an individual school Um, and we're
like they say that high means that you
have about a 99% chance of getting into
a program. Low means that you have about
a 1% chance and then medium is
everything in the middle.
Um
there there's a lot of I think um good
re yeah we can talk about the design of
sort of these um sort of buckets. No, I
think there's I think I think there's
some really nice reasons that you would
want to do something like this. we
should, you know, happy to talk about
the design um offline. Um but this is
sort of what the design is in New York
City, right? And and I think this is
great. So like I think sort of this is a
sort of a big step toward helping sort
of students um apply sort of apply to
schools, right? Because now you have um
sort of some personalized admissions
likelihoods,
right? Okay. And so empirically, not are
there just match disparities.
Yeah.
>> Um
>> I mean it's it's it's the centralized
system so they know everything, right?
But they what they actually use are
things like uh at this point literally
just discretized grades um zoning
information. So like as course as Burrow
and then some schools have like weird
like south of Hston Street and so like
like zoning um free and reduced lunch
eligibility um which is used for sort of
a version of affirmative action um and
then a few other criteria.
Great. And so what I'm showing you on
this screen is so in orange it's
students who are eligible for free and
reduced lunch eligibility. Um blue is
students not eligible for free and
reduced lunch and on the x-axis is um
sort of like the rank in the list. So
the first program they listed, the
second program they listed all the way
to the 12th program they listed. And so
then on the plot on the left is the
selectivity of the program they applied
to. So that means sort of on average a
student eligible for free and reduced
lunch applied to a program that accepted
40% of its students um in their first
list first point of the list. For a
non-FRL student this is about 25%.
Right? So sort of at every level um
students eligible for free and reduced
lunch are sort of applying to less
competitive programs. And then on the
plot on the right, you have the same
thing but graduation rates.
>> I have just a question about New York
City. Um for the y- axis on the right
hand side, is the twopart percentage
point gap in graduation rate like
meaningful? Like what's the range?
>> Yeah. So I mean at this point um New
York City sort of has like surprisingly
high or surprising to me um high
graduation rates in high school. I think
it's like over 85%.
Um yeah. Yeah. So, so this is like like
a substantial portion of the the
remaining. Yeah.
Um Yeah. So, sort of um yeah, same
disparity sort of if you look at either
by selectivity or by offer rate.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So like I think you can say
many reasons why this is happening. um
you know so some things that could be
happening is maybe these correspond to
their true preferences right so like
there's other things you know there's
other sort of characteristics of these
schools um around geography peer group
um sport you know all sorts of things
that you might have preferences over for
schools language programs and like you
know when you look at graduations and
selectivity this is what happens but
sort of there's other reasons to prefer
these schools
Um, so you can tell a true preference
story. Um, you can tell sort of an
admissions probability story, which is
um sort of uh and I'll get into this a
little bit is uh when you're limited to
12 schools, you you need sort of
theoretic it's deferred acceptance isn't
strategy proof anymore. You can't just
apply to your favorite 12 schools. You
need to do like a reach mat safety um
sort of approach. And so maybe this is
corresponding to admissions
probabilities. um or maybe this is
corresponding to ge like you know this
goes back to the first argument is like
around two preferences is maybe this is
geography right so um this by itself is
no is not evidence of like much right
all this is saying is there are
application differences and there's many
reasons one could believe that these
application differences arise
okay and so there's a large um there's a
large literature sort of on these type
of application differences uh on ranking
and matching disparities. Um but sort of
um sort of maybe uh one summary of it is
is that disadvantaged students are less
likely to apply and match to quote
unquote highquality schools even
conditioned on things like grades. Um
there's sort of a large emerging
um sort of line of work that sort of
trying to say that this is evidence of
mistakes that applicants are making as
opposed to just a preference story and
sort of so how do they do this? They do
things like they just run surveys of
families and they in these surveys of
families they ask them okay what are the
characteristics of schools that you
prefer? um sort of are you aware of you
know like they they test for awareness
like are you aware of these high quality
schools in your neighborhood um things
like that right you can also do things
like um just like look at like quasi
experimental things like okay New York
City in like 2014 um introduced certain
letter grades for schools that provided
students more information about school
quality how did that change behavior and
then when they took it back How did that
change behavior again? Right.
>> Well, so um that would be a mistake in
like whether I should have applied to a
place, but this says they're less likely
to apply to and match with the schools
that our grades. Is that
>> Oh, sorry. The match because of
application. Yeah.
>> I can't match. Okay. So, so we don't
you're not claiming that there's
evidence that having applied
>> Yeah. No, no, no, no, no.
>> Match.
>> No, no, no. And and like I think at this
point like applications are basically
fun like formulas for how students are
ranked. So like that would be
>> Yeah. Yeah. No.
>> No. No. That that would be very
surprising if true.
>> Yeah.
Um and yeah, sorry I couldn't fit this
on the earlier slide, but this is sort
of the like nice consult like Google
consult like all these consultants who
will help you apply if you can afford
it.
what's the evidence on like whether or
not the uh the families are likely to
strategy because you mentioned
acceptance algorithm like
>> yeah so that that's what sort of we're
going to try to think about um in this
paper is that like sort of even
reasoning on this reach safety sort of
thing
>> what
application designs
are
>> yeah so it used to be much like and and
I think this is just a paper to be
written At this point it's like over the
last 5 years they've simplified it a
lot. So like it used to be like each
school would run their own thing and
sort of like could sort it was like
almost the wild west in what could be
used. So like it was there were like
three performance features. Seventh
grade grades, eighth grade grades, test
scores and they were continuous features
that schools could use in however way.
They could also use um admissions essays
and things like that. Um some schools
would use things like did you show up to
an open house. Um and then sort of
increasingly they've centralized and
limited these things. So there still
exists schools that have auditions and
essays um and interviews and things like
that. But sort of among the quantitative
metrics at this point it's essentially
like discretized grade
and then lottery number within the
discrete buckets.
Yeah. And there's sort of similar
findings outside of New York City and in
college admissions around sort of um
mistakes that people make.
Okay. So what do we do in this work? Um
sort of get getting at sort of that
question which is like okay so you you
maybe need to reason about strategic
behavior a little bit in the in the
following sense which is so I'm gonna
show you plots like this. um sort of
repeatedly where the x-axis is my
position in the list like what position
in the list I I show I had a school and
the y-axis is like some measure of
school quality for simplicity in this
paper in this talk I'm going to only
focus on selectivity or like offer rate
where like lower offer rate is better
but sort of essentially all the results
hold for like any performance metric you
care to think about. Um
and so like in so like this is like a
visualization of a student's portfolio
where and sorry and the reason I focus
on offer rate is because it does double
duty then of both of like selectivity as
a imperfect measure of school quality
but then also um it's it's your
admissions likely or it's like an
unconditional admissions likelihood. And
so if for example you apply to 100%
offer rate school first then it doesn't
matter what the rest of your list says
right so you you sort of you can
basically ignore the rest of the list
right so this is an example of such a
student who applied to a 100% offer rate
school first match to that program and
it sort of doesn't matter that their six
ranked program um was selective sort of
even if they would have gotten into it
right so the first question that we want
to think about is how do empirical
portfolios differ from what they should
right and by should I mean sort of
there's um like you know you sort of
need to think about the theoretical
question of how should students apply
given short lists and uncertainty right
so given that you can only apply to or
at least historically up to 12 programs
um and there's like uncertainty about
are you going to get in
>> from understanding if there's no
constraint on list then you should just
like rank your favorite thing in a
>> strategically. Yes. Right. So deferred
acceptance is strategy proof if you can
rank all that you want. Um now like in
practice that's like in practice sort of
about half the students even with a
limit of 12 didn't list 12 and like even
right like in practice I think this is
going to remain an issue even if
strategically like I just think the
strategic lens is not the right lens to
look at this. Yeah. And then sort of the
interventional piece that hopefully I'll
get to um is how can we steer students
toward high quality matches.
>> Yeah. Sorry to uh challenge this but I
think there was a news news item that I
think it was sty.
>> Yep.
>> That you know out of thousand
there were you know eight black.
So it was just you know to a lot of you
know that indicates that there is some
sociological
uh discrimination that the low-inccome
uh uh you know students don't have an
equal chance when they apply for these
>> Yeah. No no I I I yeah I I I I'm not at
all contesting that. So so I guess
>> saying that that this is a mistake you
know to the applicants and sort of
blaming the victim.
>> Yeah. No it's okay. Sorry. Yeah. I I
totally do not mean to do that. Um I
think so there are definitely sort of um
I think admission policies and
geographic sort of things going on to
play. I think sort of what I'm trying to
do here is um sort of even even sort of
on the application behavior side is um
sort of you know I I I think even on the
application behavior side sort of it's
it by mistake I mean sort of um sort of
complex process
caused um and so sort of like how can we
like simplify or help in the
applications right so so I I don't sort
of I don't mean to say that oh it's
justified because sort of it's an
application behavior site. No, I just it
seems like this just worse I can just
say I'm not accusing you of saying this
but it just it's not it's maybe not a
very good example for you know studying
application strategy or something right
you know the the the the applicants are
are making a realistic estimate that you
know even if I apply to I'm not going to
get in right
>> yeah so I I think
>> yeah so so here what I'm going to do in
this work is I'm going control for what
you have gotten in and I can do that
perfectly and then I'll show I can tell
you how I will do that perfectly. Um and
and the reason Okay, great.
Right. So, right. Okay. So, maybe I'll
jump to this part, which is sort of to
to do any of this, you need some
estimate of would this applicant have
gotten in had they applied, right? And
uh what's nice about New York City is
for about 80. So, like I'm actually not
talking about the nine specialized high
schools. I'm talking about the remaining
like 900 programs, right? So the nine
specialized high schools including
styend like by law well three of them by
law the rest because by choice
essentially they use a single exam and
they run like serial dictatorship for
who goes where. Um I'm talking about the
remaining 900 that participate in the
deferred acceptance system. And of the
deferred acceptance system, um about 80%
uh use an application policy that is
perfectly formulaically knowable, right?
They publish it on an Excel that's
online. And so if you had all the
inputs, you could and we do to like 95
plus or 99% accuracy reverse engineer
would this student have gotten in had
they applied?
Well, but again, you know, if you talk
about eight black students out of a
thousand, that's a very small sample,
right?
>> Yeah.
>> Uh, yeah. No, I I think so. The the
features that sort of they use do not
use race.
>> No, Iconomics.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> The point of view of the applicants, you
know, there's only people like down to
that.
>> Oh, totally. Yeah. So, I think there's
many other sort of um like preference
based reasons you might not want to
apply or you might not choose to apply.
I think what I'm trying to say is sort
of um given the simulator, we can at
least in hindsight say would they have
gotten in had they applied?
>> And so the one% left in the Excel
spreadsheet formula is like who else is
sort of
>> Yeah, that's a good no. Well, it's it's
not like equilibrium effects like that
sort of it's like sort of this 5 to 1%
error still is even without those
effects. It's like it's like partially
rounding and then partially like they're
like even those schools have some
criteria that aren't in the data. So
like even those schools have like kids
of teachers
>> or sib No, no, that that that's sort of
not it's like kids of teachers siblings
like these priorities that that we don't
observe in the data.
Right. And then what I'm also going to
do and and again I think this assumes
away a lot of important things is for
the purposes of this work we're going to
assume that program quality metrics
capture preferences right our proxy for
metrics for for preferences right so the
um so things like selectivity graduation
rate college enrollment rate performance
impact in the paper we end up doing
things like safety and college and
career readiness and other things like
that as well
>> do you think geography at all
Yes. So, what we're going to end up
doing is we're going to compare where
could a student have matched compared to
where did they match um and where the
could have matched is restricted to be
no further away geographically than
where they actually matched. So, we're
going to take sort of um so yeah. So, so
we're going to think about like prito
dominance in terms of geography and sort
of these characteristics
um and
traditional things like things
getting some places are actually more
cumbersome than others.
>> Yeah.
>> Yes. Great question. And so like in the
first paper in the first paper where all
the analysis was on data we had on
Cornell like transfer to Cornell servers
the the most granular
geographic location we have for a
student is zip code which is imperfect
and um so and we use commute distance by
like zip code centers and sort of the
second piece interventional piece we've
been working with the public schools and
so on their servers we have we have
exact addresses which we convert to
census tracks
Um and sort of we use census track and
again everything is subway or like
commute distance. Yeah.
Okay.
And so um actually yeah let me just sort
of um summarize a little bit sort of the
empirical findings from the first paper.
So um what I'm going to so here again so
here I have different race or ethnic
ethnic groups on the y- axis I have
offer rate and in the different in in
the the sum of the bars it's sort of the
offer rate on average of the students
actual match right so like the average
Asian student matched to a school that
accepted about 50% of applicants
in the dark blue I have um their
counterfactual which is exactly what I
just said which is the best school
according to this metric that they could
have gotten into um that was no further
geographically by commute distance than
their actual match. And so for the
average Asian student, that's about 32.
And I'm just going to call um under
matching sort of this difference, right?
So where did they match versus
counterfactually where they could have
matched?
the fact that everyone
>> Yep. Okay. Great. No. No. So, so
>> um the first empirical paper um No. So,
this is like a one like like a one
change. Um in the second paper sort of
like the interventional piece that's
like the first order thing that we did
everything like sort of that that's like
this the core of the paper is you have
to deal with congestion that your
recommendations induce. Great.
So if there are better schools that are
closer, what like what information are
they or families do you think or like
it's just so
>> Yeah, I mean I I think there's just like
again like there's both true preference
stories and um sort of complex awareness
stories that you can tell sort of to
explain behavior.
Okay. And so then this is so this is
undermatching differences by race and
ethnicity. And sort of one thing to note
is the differences in where students
matched are on average much bigger than
sort of the differences between the
counterfactuals.
Right? So this is in this sense um sort
of um you know it's it's not I think not
a perfect comparison. I think mostly
because of this like equilibrium issue
in this plot um is sort of um if you
look at the individual student sort of
on average these are the differences in
selectivities and then um if you look at
sort of uh where they actually matched
and then the teal is if all you did was
resort a student's portfolio
according to offer rate right so um like
they had the school in their list. It
just wasn't it just wasn't before the
school that they actually matched to.
And then this is um I think for time
reasons maybe I won't get into it but
this is sort of basically the same plot
but now in a map of New York. Um
actually sorry I can always I can never
resist. Um like there's like if you know
New York there's like so many stories
you can tell from this point. like like
at this point over 5 years I've done a
lot of like empirical analys
quantitative analyses of inequities in
New York and every plot looks like this
right across papers. Um and so like one
one interesting thing is maybe so like
up here the northwest is Riverdale which
is actually a relatively wealthy
neighborhood um in New York City. Um but
sort of just to the south of Riverdale
is like Inwood, which is again um less
welloff and to the east of Riverdale is
the Bronx, which is also less welloff.
And if you look at Riverdale, if so on
the left plot, it's like the match offer
rate of student on average of students
there. And like on average, they're
getting into like, you know, schools
that accept 65 70%. Right? So like on
average students in Riverdale are sort
of getting into less selective schools
than maybe students in downtown
Manhattan,
right? But if you look at undermatching
is they're basically not undermatching
at all, right? They're basically getting
into the most selective schools that
geographically
they can get into. Right? So like
Riverdale is just far, right? It's like
really hard to get to anywhere from
Riverdale, right? So if you look at the
undermatching metric, they're actually
doing very well on the undermatching
metric, even if they're not doing so
well on the offer rate metric.
Okay?
And so then we might ask is where in a
student's list did is this undermatching
coming from, right? So is it so this is
another example. So this is a student
that was rejected from their first three
programs and then their fourth program
accepts everyone and that's where they
matched
right and what we show is if all we do
is analyses as a function of this list
very simple individual characteristics
um like functions of this that so I'll
show one example in the next slide
explain about 41% of the variance in
undermatching um Even though like
individual student characteristics, so
like race, ethnicity, grades, things
like that only explain about 4%. Right?
So like very simple functions of just
sort of looking at the portfolio
um explain under matching. So like as
one example, think about um you know a
student who doesn't what we say doesn't
apply to any reach program, right? So
their first program accepts even
historically basically 100% of its
applicants, right? So like if the first
program you apply to accepts 100% of its
applicants, it doesn't matter what the
rest of your list was because you'll
just never get there in deferred
acceptance,
right? And so this sort of behavior is
about um you know so here again I have
different bars for different race and
ethnicities and different colors for
eligible for free and reduced lunch or
not. And so um the average Asian student
sort of only about 5 to 7% of Asian
students sort of have behavior like this
where their first program accepts
everyone and whereas this is about sort
of either 17 or 25% of black students
depending on if they're eligible for
free and reduced lunch. Um and then
similar patterns.
Yeah. Um
I I guess I'm I'm trying to understand
why it would ever be a good strategy to
select something that to like put
something that's
>> again like I I think like there's true
preference reasons like people have true
preferences to go
>> to different schools.
>> There's like
there are cases in which someone might
be like say geographically in a location
where the only closest schools are those
that are like
>> Yeah. accepting. Okay.
>> Yeah. So, so, so again like like again
this is sort of I think like like
anything any plot like this had like
will not tell you anything about
students true preferences or geographic
constraints or so on right the these are
very simplistic views
>> like an associated question like you're
making the assumption that the more
selected school is inherently like
better in terms of the rankings like you
like maybe look at other variables such
as like school performance or outcome
Great. So like I so in in the so you
know I don't want to use terms like
better or worse. I in the in sort of in
the paper we use a whole bunch of
metrics that this school district uses.
So like selectivity um performance
impact um like you know some aggregate
measure based on survey data including
safety um graduation rate, college
enrollment rate, you essentially get the
same pattern regardless of what metric
you use. Yeah.
Okay.
Um, great. And so, um, the last thing we
did in this paper is, um,
actually I'm going to skip this because
I kind of want to get to the second
paper. Okay. Okay, so we did some math
and the upshot of the math is um we
calculated the quote unquote optimal
recommendation like the optimal feedback
you would want to give to a student in
order to most improve their outcomes and
expectation. Trust me that we did that.
Um and what did the model spit out? the
model spit out that essentially like for
most um black and Hispanic students, the
sort of the optimal thing to do if
you're optimizing for selectivity of the
match is to apply to a much more
selective program first. Whereas for
Asian and white students, sort of the
models recommendations are much more
heterogeneous, right? Like many of them
should be applying to more um
competitive first programs, but many of
them should maybe be applying to less
competitive um second, third, fourth
programs in order to even optimize their
own selectivity.
>> Also like the
>> Yeah. Yeah. This is sort of like
accounting for where they would have
gotten in and so on,
>> you know, that like you know that they
like
there may just not be schools nearby.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So I I can talk about the
details offline, but essentially Yes.
Yeah.
Okay. And so what do we do about this?
This is sort of what's been we've been
working on for the past few months u or
I think six months at this point, six,
seven months, which is working with New
York City public schools um to to sort
of um design nudges in order to nudge um
students into applying to high
performing schools. And I guess I like
five minutes or so. So I'll try to give
the punchlines. Um and so like how do we
define high performing schools or sort
of how do we per define um disadvantaged
middle schools is we think about middle
schools that consistently send very few
students to high performing high schools
despite having students who would have
been admitted to those schools. And then
high performing high school is defined
by our partners in the New York City
public schools. But it essentially is
some combination of graduation rate,
college and career readiness and safety
scores.
And then the question is is sort of
should we like sort of like are these
nudges effective?
But then we run into exactly this
problem of equilibrium effects, right?
which is each program is capacity
constrained and um suppose an applicant
has a high chance of admissions
according to the model that they see in
the portal, right? And we nudge a whole
bunch of high likelihood applicants to
apply to a school.
Well, then we're changing the
application behavior according to the
assumptions of the model. Right now
we're doing an intervention in a on to
change the data that the predictive
model was assuming. And so then if you
have too many nudges to the same program
then that's going to be self-defeating,
right? And so then the design goal of
sort of the methods sort of sort of like
the interesting methods of this piece is
how do we nudge students so that even if
some fraction of them were to follow the
recommendations then they were still a
good set of recommendations right that
we're not just nudging everyone to apply
to schools that then they're competing
with each other and now they weren't a
good set of recommendations in the first
place.
How we operationalize that in this work
is um we're only going to be nudging
high high likelihood applicants
according to this of sort of this
previous model and then we're going to
say suppose a high likelihood applicant
has some admissions probability at a
program according to that model. We want
to design nudges so that even if X
percentage of applicants follow our
nudges, so behave according to our
nudge, then still Y percentage of them
are admitted um in actuality and like
what X and Y are are obviously design
decisions that someone needs to make,
right? But this is sort of the goal,
right? So this is maybe one example um
of sort of X going from like 0 to 40% or
so and then Y sort of each line here is
a different program
right and we came we came to this
through simulation like using previous
year's data right so like in something
like this if maybe somewhere you know if
X is here then for this program that 95%
sort of actually maybe go down to 65%.
And that would be a bad thing.
>> I guess like a question here is like you
know you swap out high likelihood for
like you know another type of target. I
guess like one question is you kind of
like already know the score function
right of like you know absent capacity
constraints if I were this school would
I accept this app?
>> Yeah but we know that
>> uh would it be possible to like look at
something like that as your benchmark
instead where it's like sort of maximize
the number of students who pass that
that score.
>> Yeah. So you you could do many things.
Um the reason we went for this is this
is partially a communication constraint
is that students see the high likelihood
right students know students are told
whether they're high likelihood.
>> Okay. And so we have essentially
something that corresponds to coordinate
descent in um sort of for a given set.
So now we have an optimization problem
where we want to figure out the maximum
number of nudges we can send to a given
school assuming some kind of applicant
adoption right so let's just ahead of
time assume let's say 40% you know it's
the most successful RCT of all time that
40% of people follow nudges
>> oh
>> oh so this year we're sending emails
>> this year we're sending emails to the
applicant's parent to say sort of can
here is a high performing high school
near where you live that sort of you
have high admissions likelihood too.
>> One could imagine another nudge would be
they fill out an additional list.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So we we thought about many
potential designs sort of some of them
we're hoping to do next year. this year
sort of um you know software and various
constraints that this year it's the
simplest possible thing is it's an email
to students or to to their parents um
saying sort of here's a high school.
>> Yeah. Um you could do multiple as well.
Yeah.
>> Are you doing ranking amongst those?
>> No, we're just ordering I forget. I
think maybe random.
No, we're not doing anything like we're
just like listing potentially multiple
high school programs in some order.
Yeah. Yeah. So, this is just an email
and then they have to
>> Yeah. Yeah. This is certainly not the
perfect nudge. This is like a a year one
pilot and so we're hoping to sort of do
all of those in future years,
but yes. Um Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, so I
mean I think there are reasons to
believe that this year's nudges will be
>> not the most effective RCT in the
history of humanity.
>> Um yeah.
Um okay, great. So assume some kind of
applicant adoption. Then here again we
take advantage of the fact that we can
perfectly simulate the system. Um assume
adoption. So you change their
preferences from last year's data. run
deferred acceptance and just evaluate
acceptance probabilities among students
you told were a high likelihood. Rinse
and repeat um while you iteratively
adjust adjust these nudge caps until
you're happy, right? And so we ended up
with something like this.
Um once you have these nudge caps,
another integer program that actually
sort of then does the nudges in that
sort of now you have constraints for how
many nudges you can send per school and
you want to decide am I going to nudge
this student to this school. And so for
each student you have the list of high
performing high schools that are within
45 minutes of their home um census tract
and they have high admissions likelihood
at two. um run an integer program this
year again some heristic which is um
sort of um you want to maximize the
number of nudges but maybe not the sum
because that could be unfair and so
maybe you want to sort of encode some
notion of diminishing utility that you
would rather give one nudge to someone
than a third nudge to someone else right
and so this kind of encodes that
um I'm running out of time and so maybe
I can end
So this is um an active RCT we launched
in October um when the application cycle
started um it closes in December. Um,
and this was just like an incredible
amount of work by Erica, um, the lead
PhD student on this project over like
the last sort of like I mean really
started working on it in January, but
sort of since like May or June has been
embedded full-time um, and sort of in
the New York City public schools um, and
sort of like working across multiple
offices to like define high performing
um, schools and then have focus groups
and then we have to have translations
and communicate with superintendent and
middle schools and do all the RCT
infrastructure and sort of like make
sure the data science is correct. So
just like an incredible amount of work
and you know hopefully you know ask me
about the results in the spring
and I'll maybe end here. Um I think
there's like a whole bunch of
interesting uh methods questions as well
sort of in on especially and this is
what I'm really excited about
methodologically on like how do we think
about what makes a good recommendation
um in equilibrium right so like when you
have to think about these externalities
um both for this student and other
students um when you're sending many of
them
cool I'll stop