Hello everyone.
I can see a lot of you are here today.
Welcome. This is our
uh curriculum overview for the Master
Business Analytics program. My name is
Michelle Lee and I'm the director of
this program. I've been the director
since the beginning in 2016 when we
launched and right now we're in our 10th
year. So, it's our 10year anniversary.
I'm joined today by our colleagues Anna,
Jen, and Mina um in the admissions
office as well as our program office.
And u feel free to ask questions as I go
along. I'm just going to share a few
slides um and then you can ask me
questions um and we'll try our best to
get everything answered for you.
Um great. So I just wanted to start with
sharing an overview of MIT. MIT is a
really big place and Sloan is one of six
colleges um inside MIT. So we have the
master business program inside
management but we also have students
across our university in the science
department shass which is our urban
planning um and the college of computing
which is our newest college the
Schwarzman center um architecture and
planning and finally our engineering
flagship school.
Um so within the management program is
our business analytics program. It was
launched as I said in 2016. It's been
ranked uh the number one program in the
world um luckily uh since the beginning
and we are a STEM classified program. Um
it's a one-year onampus
full-time program. So we do not offer
any online components. students come to
campus and stay on campus um for the one
year.
This is the breakdown of our student
body. This year we have 80 students. Um
we've had a steady state of 80 since
2023. Um and we do not expect to grow um
in the near future. So next year we're
looking for a class of 80 students as
well. Um we have a good mix of countries
over 29 countries represented. Um very
high GPA a good balance of female to
male um and very technical undergraduate
degrees.
So the overall mission of the program is
to combine machine learning and
operations research to arrive at data
models and decisions to allow for
predictions and prescriptive analytics.
So the unique aspect of our program is
that we really do focus on optimization
in combination with machine learning. We
do teach deep learning, genai, we teach
statistical inference, but the core of
our program is lies in machine learning
and operations research.
This is a map of the one-year program. I
know this is a lot of text on one slide,
but all you need to think about is
there's the fall semester on the left,
the spring semester in the middle, and
then the summer semester on the right
hand side. The students take a really
full set of courses in the fall. There's
really no time for anything else. We
keep trying to add more courses, but uh
I think they're really maxed out here.
So, they're taking analytics tools,
which is programming in R and Python,
Julia, SQL, optimization methods,
machine learning. Um these are all our
foundational courses in machine learning
and AI. Um the analytics lab which you
can see is the 9 unit 572 course is a
more hands-on training course. So that's
more uh projectbased students work in
teams of three to four students with a
company. Uh and before this uh webinar I
was just uh talking to some companies
that have done a lab in the past for
example like Wayfair and um General
Motors and Disney for example. So
companies come and do projects with our
students, but students are also taking
our typical engineering type courses
like machine learning and optim
optimization
which are more traditional courses. So
you're in a lecture room and students
are taking um exams during the semester.
There's midterms coming up uh soon in
two weeks. And then they also have
weekly problem sets and um final
projects and final exams.
Um students do have to maintain a 4.5
GPA out of five. MIT is on a 5.0 system.
So a five is an A and a four is a B. An
A minus is still a five and a B+ is
still a four. So you just need to get
half A's and half B's in order to
graduate from the program. We haven't
had anyone come through the program who
have not graduated.
Okay. Again, if you're just joining us,
feel free to ask me questions and Anna
or Mina will let me know. There are
questions. I'll try my best to answer
them. Um, so one part of the uh the map,
the timeline that I just showed you is
the analytics capstone project. It is a
majority uh of the program. It's seven
months out of the 12 months. So, it is
really the defining characteristic of
our master's program. It's a required
uh industry analytics course where
students work in teams of two with a
faculty advisor on an industry project.
The companies pay for these projects and
they fund your tuition. So this the
students tuition is partially funded by
the capstone project and the students
then travel to the location of the
company in the summer to work on these
projects. At the end of the summer, the
students come back to MIT campus,
present their final projects, and attend
a graduation ceremony at the end of
August. For some sample projects, you
can visit our website. They're all
listed there, analytics capstone.edu.
Um again here's our required core in
very minute detail if you're interested.
Um again this is a curriculum uh
overview webinar uh and so we're trying
to go through the curriculum as much as
possible. There'll be other webinars
about career and capstone and student
life but this one is focused on the
curriculum.
Um so fall core uh the students are
taking the top list of courses. I know
it seems like a lot of courses and it
is. Students are working, you know, 60
80 hours a week on these courses. Um,
and then if those courses are easy for
them or they want to challenge
themselves even more, they can take one
additional elective course, any elective
that's offered at MIT at the graduate
level. Um, and then students can engage
in research.
Um if students are engaging in research
with faculty then they are not permitted
to take an elective in the January
period. Students are taking the
analytics capstone a communications
course. We also offer a data ethics and
data privacy course in the January
period. Um so MIT is broken into fall,
January, spring and summer where in
January there are no regular courses
held at MIT. So January is called
independent activities period and during
the whole month of January there is
special um courses offered and we offer
these four courses. Um but most of the
campus or the rest of MIT is not on
campus for that winter break. And then
in spring which starts in February
students are taking the capstone project
continued uh with their with their
required mandatory courses. And then
spring is the time where students can
take electives that interest them. So
they have to take at least 27 electives
and up to 40 maximum units. Um 27 has to
be approved technical electives and then
up to 21 additional units or 48 max can
be any elective that you want. Some
students also take electives at Harvard.
um cross registration is permitted
between Harvard and MIT. Um so Harvard
students can take MIT courses and MIT
students can take Harvard courses and a
lot of students do try to do that as
well. Um and then in the summer there's
only one course it's the capstone course
and students go either abroad or travel
to do their capstone.
Are there any questions?
No. Okay.
Um, here's a sample schedule for the
fall semester. Um, this year it's kind
of crazy because the first course 15681
only meets on certain days um because
the professor travels from Morocco um
every other week to teach the students.
So these are just this is a special
course. All the other courses you see
here are regularly scheduled every week.
Um so uh there are many gaps. Um you
know there aren't courses offered during
lunch but there are courses offered um
from 8:30 a.m. until
5:30 p.m. sometimes until 700 p.m. Um
and then Fridays are held for
recitation. So students do not have
lecture on Fridays. They have recitation
on Fridays and then other special
activities. Um so this is just an
example schedule of our students for
this fall. Of course, in the spring, the
schedule doesn't look like this. It's
very different based on what students
choose to take as their elective.
Um, and then there's some special um uh
analytics um events that we hold for our
students. For example, we have a class
ball retreat where we take the students
up into the mountains of New Hampshire
for two two nights and they go and um do
some teen bonding and go hiking and get
to know each other better. Um we also do
a spring trek to New York City. Um this
year it's going to be March 18th to the
20th. Um, and then we have um
some breaks throughout the semester for
our standard holidays. Um, there's a
fall Sloan intensive period and then a
spring Sloan intensive period as well.
Um, it's not really intensive. It's a
it's a strange name to call it. It's
just really a week where classes are not
in session and we do other activities
for the class. And like I said, um,
graduation is at the end of August each
year, which is different to other
programs that you may be applying to.
Um, most programs graduate at the end of
May or June, and ours, um, the students
graduate at the end of August, and most
students start working in the fall. So,
full-time hiring, they will start in
October or November or December.
Um, these are some of our faculty that
teach our courses. Dimmitri Bertimas.
He's the associate dean and now he's
also the vice provost. I guess we should
update this slide. Is a vice provost for
open learning at MIT. Um so he's in
charge of both all online education at
MIT as well as business analytics and
he's the faculty director of our
program. Um, Alex Yakiat teaches a lot
of operations research and statistics
and transportation um topics and he his
research is in transportation
um as well as um traditional O. Uh,
Rahul teaches the analytics edge course
and um he has a very famous um paper on
um soft compute that he is well known
for. So if you look him up, he's an
incredible professor as well as
researcher. Um Georgia Barakus, she's on
um sbatical this year at Harvard. Um but
she will be back next year um at MIT. Uh
she does re research in retail and
online platforms. She works with
companies like Zara, Wayfair um um all
the online platform strategy um pricing
strategy companies. Um and then Karen
Zang is our amazing professor who works
a lot on health care systems and um
social impact projects. Um and um she's
gone to
uh Africa to work on some healthcare
delivery systems um for those countries.
So amazing slate of professors and if
you are interested in doing research uh
com students do uh like doing research
with our variety of professors. Um the
maximum hours is 10 hours per week
because they're taking a very heavy
course load in the fall and spring. Um
and the research assistantships are
funded. So they will go towards paying
down tuition. It is approximately
$12,000 in funding if you choose to
uh conduct a research assistantship at
MIT. Um so that's very helpful for a lot
of students who um need that funding.
Here are some additional uh topics. So I
must say that the the research topics
have now um shifted to more generative
AI large language models and um less
traditional O topics but um that's
really what you're interested in. So if
you're you're saying oh I really want to
see um you know I really want to look at
food safety in in developing countries
for example that's up to the students to
say okay these are the faculty working
on these problems and that's who I want
to work with for my RA ship.
Uh this is a class profile of this
year's class. And if you join our other
webinars, we do have some of um our
alumni and current students attending
future webinars. I do encourage you to
um come and and talk to them. Um there
are 80 students and I think I went
through the statistics here so you don't
I'm not going to read them to you again.
They're on our website.
Um, and then I'll turn it over to Anna
who has any logistics about our upcoming
events, but you can scan the QR code it
um to register. Um, I do think there's
an onampus event where you can meet me
in person. Um,
it looks like it's October 7th and
November 12th, but I'm not sure. So,
Anna, take it away.
>> Yes. So, we have a lot of upcoming um
events directed for business of an
business analytics and these aren't even
all of them. Um so, definitely feel free
to scan the QR code um to see the full
list of upcoming events. Um and you will
get the chance to meet Michelle on
campus on November 12th for business
analytics preview day. Yeah.
>> Great. So, that's all the slides that we
had. Um, I guess we'll just turn it over
to you for any specific questions and I
can go through. Yeah.
>> Yeah. So, we did have a couple of
questions in the chat for you, Michelle.
Um, so one person asked um if while in
the program um are they also able to
take some action learning courses um in
addition to the capstone project?
>> Uh yes. So, you can definitely take
action learning courses as part of your
electives. Um so a lot of our students
will take um product management courses
because there's a product management
certificate. So you can definitely
enroll for product management lab or
other labs if it fits into your you know
you design your spring schedule. So
there's definitely options. And in the
fall some students have taken
entrepreneurship lab. So if you're
interested in starting your own company
in the future or if you have started
your own company and you need help
that's a great lab to join. Um and you
know that's you can definitely take
those classes.
>> Great. Thank you. Um, and someone else
asked if there are any opportunities for
students to do research while they're in
the program.
>> Oh, yes. This person must have missed my
entire um summary about the research
assistantships, but that's no problem.
Um, yeah, so you can definitely do
research. Um, tons of students do
research. I think over 40% of our
student body do uh does a research
um assistantship. So here is the summary
of the research assistantship. Students
apply in August um before uh starting
the program and
faculty will interview them and select
them to hire them as a research
assistant. Students work 10 hours per
week from fall semester until spring
semester and they're paid roughly
$12,000.
Thanks, Michelle. Um, and so we know
that today's session is geared towards
the curriculum, but someone did have a
question asking if there's any
prerequisite courses that they should
take that will help them um prior to
being in the MBAN program.
>> Uh, yes, there are many prerequisites
that we recommend. Um
the most important prerequisite is
linear algebra. You have to take some
linear algebra whether it's an online
course or a full um undergraduate course
in linear algebra. Advanced mathematics
topics. Um differential equations is
also great to have um because these
classes in the fall are very very
technical. They start with your basic we
we basically assume knowledge of linear
algebra of statistics of probability um
when you come into the program um and
then just some basic coding
computer science courses um if you take
like algorithms or data structures um
that will also help um in your fall
core. Um a lot of our students have
taken SQL or Java or C++ or or something
to show that they have good uh computer
science knowledge. So I would say math
and computer science are the most
important two requisite two
prerequisites.
>> Awesome. Thank you. Um and then we have
someone who is curious to hear more
about what alternative activities they
can do outside of the curriculum at
Sloan.
>> Oh yeah. Um there's lots of um so social
events, clubs, and activities. Um I'm
just showing you the 12-month schedule,
but within this schedule, students will
u participate in conferences. There is
the annual Sloan Sports Analytics
Conference, which is the largest sports
analytics conference in the world. I
went to the sports analytics conference
one year and I met President Obama at
the time and Michelle Obama was the
speaker the following year. So it would
it's a pretty big deal. Um and students
at Sloan can volunteer to organize these
conferences. There's other conferences
as well like the um I think there's an
Africa conference. Um there's a
technology and AI conference. There's a
product management conference. Um but
you don't have to do conferences.
There's also there's social like sports
intramural sports. We just had Sloan
Olympics. I mean the problem isn't that
there's not enough activities. There's
the problem is that there's too many
activities and students can't decide
what to do because there's too many to
choose from.
>> Thank you. And then another question um
was related to capstone which we will be
having a webinar um that focuses just on
capstone um so stay tuned for that but
the question was how does selection of
the company you work with for capstone
how does that process work? Um, sure.
Yeah. So, uh, you can see some of our
companies on our website, uh, if you go
to the website on this link here,
analytics capstone.edu,
we have returning companies each year.
So, each year we have about 40 40
companies and
many companies return year after year,
but we're also always looking for new
companies to come on board and and host
a project for our students.
Um, so it's just a submission process.
companies will submit a project and
we'll evaluate it and select them to be
part of the 40 each year.
>> Also got a question, Michelle, um about
health care and if students have can
take any healthcare analytics type
courses while they're at Sloan.
>> Oh yes, you can definitely take
healthcare courses. We have a lot of
healthcare the intersection of
healthcare and
u data science or healthcare machine
learning. There's actually a machine
learning in health. There's a course
that's called machine learning in
healthcare. You can Google it. It's
online. It's machine learning in
healthcare offered by MIT where students
work with doctors at hospitals to solve
a data science problem. It's more like a
project class. Um, but there are many
healthcare classes offered in MIT and
you can take them as part of your
electives list. Um, and you can also do
research in healthcare. Uh, for example,
Dimmitri Bertimas, one of the faculty I
I showed you before, has done a lot of
research in oncology and diabetes
research where he's helping doctors
classify certain symptoms um of patients
into different diagnosis.
>> Thank you.
I don't know.
>> Sorry.
>> Um, we had another question um asking
what the typical class schedule looks
like for MBAN students. Um, and so if
they spend most of their time inside the
classroom and what sort of amount of
time they have to do other activities.
>> Yeah, that's a great question. So, this
is a sample class schedule from this
fall. Currently, the students in this
class are doing this schedule um for the
fall semester. So, you can see there are
a lot of gaps in their schedule where
they're not in class, but a majority of
the learning does not happen in the in
the classroom. Actually, most of the
students come out of lectures being
really confused or, you know, very um
agitated because they're worried that
they didn't understand everything in the
lectures. And that's normal. A lot of
the students will learn in study groups
or outside the classroom where they
where they go to office hours or they go
to recitation and seek help from the
TAs. Um so I say like 80% of the
learning comes outside the classroom. Um
and then there's also speaker series
during lunch hours where
different clubs or the dean's office
will invite speakers to come and and
talk to the students. Um and then
there's the group work. So students are
always doing projects together. So when
you're doing projects, it's usually late
late at night or early in the morning or
during the gaps. So that's where the
learning happens.
Thank you. See what else we have.
Oh, there's a question about work
experience. You don't need to have any
work experience coming into the program,
but if you do have work experience,
that's not a negative, it's a positive.
um especially if the work experience is
related to data science or machine
learning or AI. Um so we don't have a um
like
I guess um requirements for number of
years of work experience.
Feel like there's more questions now
that I answered some.
See?
>> Okay.
Uh,
there's some questions about linear
algebra. So, yeah, if you're a finance
major, you can still take linear algebra
or math matricy math or differential
equations online. You can, you know,
there's tons of online courses you can
take to show us that you know the
content.
We did get a question on how classes are
structured. So if they're more project
based, case study based, if you could
answer that. Oh yeah, it's a mix. So a
lot of the courses are traditional
engineering courses. So for example,
machine learning is you go to lecture,
there's problem sets every week, there's
a midterm or and a final one or final
project. This year there's two midterms
and no final, but there's a final
project. So that's the that's the
traditional machine learning and um
analytics edge classes. The other
classes you can see here at the top is
the analytics to action. That's a more
communications course and business
course. So it's case study based. It's a
past fail course. So all you have to do
is attend. Um then the analytics lab is
also a project course where students
really um just learn by working on a a
analytics project with a company. So
they work with the company and the
company gives them you know a guide on
what they're expecting and the students
are ex you know doing the project and
getting a grade at the end of the
semester based on what they have done on
the project.
Thank you.
Um,
so there's lots of questions about GRE
and GMAT and so this is an optional
component when applying. Um, Michelle,
people were asking what is your
viewpoint on if applicants have taken
the exam? Um, should they still submit
scores?
Um yeah definitely if you took the exam
if you took all the trouble to take the
exam yeah go please submit the score
because I mean if it's a good score if
it's a bad score then you know maybe try
again but definitely if you took all the
effort to take the exam tell us how you
did um but it's not required we put a
lot of weight on your transcript. Um so
make sure your transcript looks good and
you have good grades on your transcript.
Um that's really the deciding factor.
>> Students asked if you know of any
favorite courses that students take um
that is related to business analytics.
>> Uh well you know that's a always fun
question. I I think you'd have to ask
the students what their favorite courses
are and in the past the best courses are
the courses taught by the best faculty.
So the question really is who's your
favorite professor? And I'm not really
able to say that later on a recorded
webinar, but there's, you know, more
favorite professors than other favorite
professors. It's just based on who you
like and who what kind of teaching style
you like. So you can go and see like who
are the high most highly rated
professors. And chances are whatever
course they're teaching is an amazing
course. Um, given all that said, um, one
of the favorite most favorite elective
courses our students have taken, no
matter who's teaching it, is power
negotiations.
It's a MBA course that's highly soughta
and our students can take it in the
spring. So, power negotiations will help
you with any future business deal or
even negotiating buying a car or, you
know, your salary or um, offers, all
that. So, a lot of our students love
that course, Power Negotiation.