from the MIT energy initiative this is
what if it works a podcast looking at
the energy solutions for climate change
I'm Cara Miller and I'm Rob
[Music]
Stoner so we talk a lot on this show
about different technologies that can be
used to create or store or distribute
clean energy but we probably don't talk
enough about the fact that in order for
any of that science to take effect a
thing usually has to be put somewhere in
some community and that involves
discussion it involves negotiation and
not infrequently it involves Larry
cesk I am in the middle quite often I
play the role of mediator cesk kind is a
professor of urban and environmental
planning at MIT and he's the publisher
of the public interest technologist he
says the story tends to go something
like this a developer has an idea for
renewable energy project he thinks
people are going to be thrilled about
this project and he's got a business
plan mostly he's aiming at getting a
permit from the state sighting agency
but he does usually have to go through
some local review so he needs to have
all the answers that are going to come
to the questions that he's asked at
these hearings so he hires really
expensive
Consultants many of them not from the
country that he's from who are working
from Air photo materials I mean the
consultant may never have been to the
site but they're preparing a detailed
plan for how on that 3,000 Acres there
going to be a wind farm or a solar
facility I'm guessing you can already
see the problem and The Clash that's
about to come somebody locally will
stand up and say did you guys look at a
map when you picked this site do you
know that you're proposing this in an
endangered habitat that's on a map that
EPA caused us or the department of
interior caused us to put together you
had several thousand acres that you were
considering and you put the proposed to
put this
there and the developer turns to their
consultant they rais their shoulders I
don't know what they talking about and
at that point Who's ever running the
local or state review process says uh we
need a break so you might have hundreds
of people sitting in a room susine says
just waiting and the business people
have quietly already bought land because
they didn't want the price to get bit up
in anticipation of a big industrial
project in Europe Europe the government
has a plan for where energy production
needs to be located and increased and
it's related to where you're going to
hook the local facility into the larger
Energy System here these are all private
individual private judgments someone
says I think I'd like to do a wind farm
I think I'm going to need about 3,000
Acres I guess that means they won't be
in the suburbs I'll probably be more in
the rural area well certainly won't be
in the city I need a lot of acreage and
so they shop around they talk to some
people they come up with a plan in
detail so that they can assure their
investors that we we have a legitimate
plan and we're going to get a license or
a permit and we're following all the
rules and we've commissioned an
environmental impact study and
environmental impact law says you're
supposed to have a public discussion
about what aspects of impacts you're
going to study and how uh that doesn't
always happen with energy facilities
because once again there's really no
interest in letting the community know
so you're setting this up in the context
of what sounds like a first public
encounter where the the developers
trying to get this done everything's
been secret until then or it's been
controlled by a Communications company
that they've hired and they're about to
announce this and they announce how
wonderful this new facility is because
it's going to help with the energy
transition and we promise they say we
will meet all the minimum requirements
environmental and otherwise by local law
and state law and federal law and uh
what percentage of the time would you
say that this kind of thing comes up at
you know your local town meeting or
whatever and they say this is here's the
plan we're going to have a we're going
to have a whole bunch of solar panels
out in this field here and we haven't
really talked about it before now
because as you said we don't want to
drive out the price of land but this is
the plan and it's going to be great what
percentage of the time does the do the
people in the town meeting say sounds
good to us never
okay because they haven't been given
enough information right the one thing
they say above all else is let us see
the plants they're not for or against
anything at that point they're just
saying uh it's kind of weird that you're
talking about something at a scale
that's going to change our whole
community and you haven't shown that to
anybody have you shown it to the elected
officials and not the public and
conceivably they have but mostly they
use someone a straw to go in between to
talk to the the the head of whatever
board the local zoning board and say uh
you guys aren't against
renewable energy facilities are you so
they say well it looks to us and we
looked online and we heard that there's
all kinds of problems for people who
live near wind farms like the the
shutter effect that thing is going round
and round and at night uh they hear it
and they can't sleep and they have
headache we've read this we know this
because you can find whatever you want
uh on the internet
and the developer says oh we've chosen a
distance that's best
practice and they said well like what if
it turns out that this really makes our
house
unsellable if we want to move right it's
our single biggest investment in our
lives buying this house are you are you
going to buy it at the current market
value before the horrible things happen
that you're causing um well no U we're
not required to do that and then
somebody else says well like how many
jobs are going to be created during
construction and after Construction in
terms of this facility and they have a
exact number how many of those are
reserved for people who live in the town
now oh well we Pro we'll consider all
good applicants no no but you you're
you're not going to guarantee that these
permanent jobs or how many people are
going to move here during construction
or after and how many kids are they
going to add to the school system and
what taxes are you going to pay anyway
like are you going to pay an industrial
property type taxes and they say things
if they're in New York state they say
things like well we're going to make a
payment in lie of taxes and those
initials are pilot we're going to have a
pilot agreement and it's going to start
with we don't owe anything because it's
great
for us to be building this here as part
of your Economic Development they said
but what how is it help our Economic
Development you're putting this thing
out here in the rural area so the people
in the city can have green electricity
and maybe at a few cents a kilowatt less
right what do we get out of it do we get
free electricity in our community oh no
no no we don't we don't do anything like
that well why should we support this
what's one
reason it it stands to create
environmental impacts because we have no
evidence that it
won't it's going to prop affect property
values in the area and various kinds of
ways and we might lose all the value of
the largest investment that we have what
water are you going to use during
construction or after does that come
with the land I'm never going to be a
developer so how do you resolve this I
mean You' got all these they're going to
buy all the houses I'll skip making the
whole list it's a very long list of
potential costs right the big rigs on
there local roads and all this yeah you
you yeah I I it's a long list of
potential right adverse impacts and the
developers not
responsible for those impacts unless
they somehow exceed
minimum State not local state
standards and you can't know that so you
have a study done a forecast and the
forecast doesn't have the data that it
really needs you know about making
models it so you you you plug in some
realistic numbers from some other
counties and near buy and you make a
model and you forecast and you say uh
we're doing everything possible to cre
to meet minimum standards now all of
that story says that the prevailing View
and policy in
America
is if the gains to the gainers outweigh
the losses to the losers it's good
public policy you should go ahead too
bad for the losers the whole region is
going to have have stable renewable
energ stable price renewable energy for
at least 30 years and that's so it's a
small amount times a million people in
the region there's like 30
landowners in this tiny rural
Hamlet one of those bad things might
happen to them but um hey you got to
break some eggs if you want
to bake and uh they say but that's not
fair why should we bear the cost for the
region well we're not breaking any
minimums so if you step back here it
sounds like you're describing a
situation obviously you see a lot but is
it also a situation that ultimately ends
in things falling apart often that the
person comes in and says I want to do
this and it like does not happen we we
last year did it 58 case studies of
community controversies over renewable
energy facilities in the last five six
seven years across from Hawaii to Alaska
to Maine to Puerto Rico um I would say
right now we're down about
20% of the megawatts that could be
running if the projects that had been
planned and financed have been able to
go ahead all of them and there's energy
to do it except that people in the group
that are adversely affected
and people who will side with them
because of the
unfairness not letting them know until
after the decisions are basically made
not compensating them for likely losses
not mitigating adverse effects as long
as you meet minimum standards that the
state sets people side with them and say
well I'm in favor of renewable energy I
want to do something about climate
change but this not fair they're right
to say it's not fair now very quickly so
fast forward to what gets this problem
resolved very
simple hold harmless anybody local who's
adversely or likely to be adversely
affected as part of the cost of planning
and implementing the facility what does
that mean pay them it it it means offer
contingent compensation should buy
property value insurance for them you
won't lose your property value I didn't
you have a $200,000 house they don't
know what's going to happen it does fall
to 100,000 it's okay they're protected
it's like they never they it's like the
property Val you get what would have
happened if this facility had not been
built in that market okay that's just
one example they could say we're going
to make you 5% owners of the facility
this town and you're going to get less
expensive electricity as long as you
live in this town this much below what
everybody else in the region is being
paid you could make them part owners and
then they would be represented amongst
the stockholders not just the
stakeholders at the annual meetings if
they didn't think the place was being
run properly and they would bring that
local perspective you could have and
this is my primary focus these days a
community benefits agreement signed with
the local Government after there was a
facilitated or mediated negotiation with
representatives of all the relevant
parties not decided by the development
who was relevant and they
negotiate and reach an agreement that
becomes a binding contract when it's
signed by the municipalities and
submitted by the developer along with
their application to the state
regulatory agency so you're describing a
process that's very very different from
what you set out for us initially there
is this initial confrontation right but
what we found is in the places where
projects were stopped and the developer
went bankrupt and they sold their rights
to build a facility to a next person
what's the first thing the next person
did let me sit down with all the people
who are upset with my predecessor and
make sure I tend to all those problems
and then the project can go forward let
me fix this process in the way the
bankruptcy had to have happen first yeah
it's not a mystery have the discussion
before you have the confrontation yeah
rather than make the
confrontation the regulations
changed to require it and also it it
sounds like even though initially
developers might be reluctant to say
well I'll help you get insurance on your
home or I will make you a part owner
I'll help this community benefit it
sounds like in General you must not
think that extra $100,000 here or there
is going to bankrupt the developer
because you're saying like hey get out
in front of this and say like let me
give you some percentage as the town or
let me help you to lay your concerns now
this going to cost some initial money
from the developer but it doesn't S save
it's G to save the money but it's gonna
save the money it's the cost of
contention it's the opposite of the
Pennywise pound foolish approach you're
going to be in court for five years that
five years rates are going to change
competition is going to move in in the
next town over all kinds of
uncontrollables that you're investors
are going to say uh-uh we're out because
you this happened while we were waiting
around dealing with the disastrous
reaction and what has happened in the
last three years which is exactly the
opposite of what I'm saying is
California and New York
and Michigan have changed the sighting
law and
said no more local review of these
decisions it's going right to the state
we're
preempting any conversation at the local
level so they're putting into law this
sort of they have decision about the
right they're saying oh my God we're
being delayed people at local levels are
opposed let's exclude them from the
conversation cuz we all know the gains
the gainers outweigh the losses to the
losers and the projects really ought to
be going ahead like really California
saying we sick of these little towns
saying like no you can't have and New
York yeah yeah yeah New York York and
California and Michigan okay and now my
own State here in Massachusetts the
governor created a commission to
streamline the sighting process what she
meant was she heard from her Pals
governors of New York and California
that this is what you should do just
exclude local and what you have in
Michigan when they change their law like
California New York is the developer
should talk to local
interests and if it makes a sincere
effort and can't succeed in finding
anyone to talk to then it should make a
contribution of a couple thousand
dollars to that
town that's not very far that's that's
what they've taken out of everything
that's happened and writing this wasw
last year and I'm trying to say that we
know a lot about Community benefits
agreements and how they should be
structured and who should be part of
negotiating them and the one thing we
know most of all is that they are
informal agreements that are not binding
and enforcable on anybody if they are
made between Town's people land owners
and the developer because those towns
people do not have legal standing to
join in contract and so unless the
municipal government signs it and unless
the state is willing to see that it's
enforced you can have any conversation
you want with anybody you can promise
anything you want and then ignore it and
that has happened and that is why
Community benefits agreements which were
made previously have a bad name so this
is fascinating to me so you what is
going to happen in a situation like
California where there's some renewable
energy project they go to some small
farm town or ranching town or whatever
what they're just going to be like we
want it here and the state's going be
like yeah and the township we going to
be like Noe they're going to sue and
then what happens it's happening now
after the law was passed a year and a
half ago they're they're going to be in
court for at least a decade we have
tribes in the west who are suing because
the Bureau of Indian Affairs and the
Bureau of Land Management told the
developer here's some land uh we we hold
this land in
for the tribes and it would be great and
they didn't consult with the tribe
there's law that says you have to
consult with tribes if you're doing
anything on their land I mean there's US
law and federal law no matter they
didn't consult they proposed it and as
soon as it's proposed and the tribe sees
it they said that's sacred land you got
6,000 Acres you pick the spot that's a
sacred burial area if only you had
talked to us the way you are legally
obligated to and they said well we
talked to somebody I know we did and we
can't change this now because the
financing is all in place da d d d da
and then you're in court and those
projects don't go forward there has to
be a conversation the worst case is
projects that go ahead and the the line
from the electricity producing facility
to the transmission system goes over the
tribal land and they still don't have
electricity for the tribal properties
man is that a problem throughout Africa
and other developing countries but if
you said from the beginning we make sure
you have electricity and you're not
going to have to pay for it because
we're using your community's resources
for at least 30 years to make this solar
facility Wind Facility whatever it is
but there no discussion of this sort and
so the tribes have litigated in many of
the western states saying if you had
talked to us we would have told you
we're not saying we don't want any
change and I want to come to this
nickname for this whole problem nimi
that people are talking about not in my
backyard not in my backyard and you know
nimbyism is about upper middle class
folks saying we don't want
change that's the not what I'm talking
about I'm talking about the inevitable
distribution of adverse effects on a
small number of people who in my mind in
terms of fairness ought to be held
harmless they not necessarily have to
make money out of it but they at least
should be held harmless in terms of the
environment the social impact the
longterm cost of electricity to them and
so on and the the RS are not based that
they're based on gains to the gainers
outweighing the losses the losers
minimum environmental standards reviewed
everything else it's too bad and what's
happening is the people for whom it's
too bad are winning the sympathy of the
people who are
nearby who are saying you know I'm not
against this facility at all but I'm be
damned if I will let my neighbors be
treated this way this is
undemocratic but the reason to be
optimistic is if you you look at the
cause of the
contentiousness it's painfully obvious
what needs to happen to eliminate that
contentiousness and that cost which is
somebody if it's the private developer
then so be it although I hope they are
regulated by the state or even better
the federal government and they have to
talk with the people who might be
adversely affected before they make
deciding technology development related
decisions and I know that threatens to
raise the price of the land that they
have to secure the rights
to that's far part of the cost I also
think they could turn what I'm saying
back the other way and say you know if
we look at prevailing prices in the area
you're telling me that you want me to
pay you that much that's twice what you
could get from any other source and the
person says yeah well I don't have
anybody else and you're sitting here and
you got a lot of money and then that
person could say you know you're going
to make it necessary for me to move to
the next County and your community is
going to lose the
following and I'm going to make it clear
that it was you who's lost all that
benefit to your community so if there
were really benefits that had to be
negotiated I think it could be used by
the developer as a counterweight to what
they worry about about revealing things
[Music]
early so this is you know we're we're
talking
about energy infrastructure and and you
know ultimately as you say they can move
to the next County if they can't strike
a deal with the county that they're
initially interested in stuff can be
recited there are other sunny places
other windy places what about mining
it's you know it's really really Central
to the energy transition we need a lot
more copper we need a lot more aluminum
and iron for steel mines can't be
recited so easily what what's happened
how does how do you deal with
that same
principle whoever's in charge of giving
the license away for the subsurface
mining which is usually in the capital
somewhere and then some private
developers show up with a bunch
of equipment and nobody's talked to the
locals and they take out their
guns and they say you can't just come
here and start digging get out of here
and we mean
it and then the developer in in their
comforable headquarters back in the
Capitol calls the person that gave them
the lease for a vast amount of money
that goes into the federal Kitty
and said you need to send the
Army and that's what's happened is it
really absolutely
where pick a country that's where that
you've had mining you had to have the
federal government impose its will on
the locals it's not the dev largely in
Africa that we're talking about no
America it it it because the right to
take anything below the surface you need
a license and a permit from the national
government the national government makes
the deal gets a whole bunch of money
right the developer thinks they can now
go start work right nobody talked to the
local community because it's not
required again because the gains to the
gainers in this case small number of
wealthy government officials gainers uh
outweigh the losses to these peasants
locally C can you give an example of
whether you've been involved or not of
this happening in some specific Place
most of the work that we do as
mediators uh is
confidential um we don't want the Press
uh the media around we want people to be
able to speak without worrying what
their compatriots are going to say about
them the agreement is informal and then
when that informal conversation is done
then it moves into a formal context
where the developer now makes another
proposal to the official Regulators so
Chile they don't have minerals they
don't have oil they don't have gas have
coal and it's a big long country and the
capitals at the top and a lot of the
stuff that they may want to build and
make and do is in the South and they
have to run huge country long
transmission lines and when the
government changed uh three governments
ago they said maybe we should be asking
in each region what's their idea of how
they can contribute to meeting energy
demand and need in the country and that
of course comes on the heels of many
years of dictatorship where the market
made all these decisions now you had
several administrations trying to do
that they chose to produce renewable
energy in each region in a different
way and they chose to have the regional
councils that were set up with multiple
interests
involved deciding where when and
how and what percentage of the benefits
including the sale of the electricity
would go back to the people in that
region what's a country that approaches
this in a way that you think I really
like that approach this is my all the
countries I've heard about in thinking
about where you put a Wind Facility and
and how you do this the right way and
how you get byy in who does it well
almost every Scandinavian country okay
and tell me what they do so all right so
at Landa and Finland what do they do
they they draw the line between public
and private is in terms of aspects of
decisionmaking and they have more
overall planning long range planning
ensuring fairness at the national level
and then they
decentralize to local or subnational
units for us would be States or counties
responsibility for doing the stuff it's
not socialization in terms of taking
over the doing of the stuff it's
nationalization and more emphasis on
public and public private partnership
for
planning we we don't believe in planning
in the United States we don't have
planning I teach happen to teach in the
planning department but that's another
story and then when if you plan then you
can say sustainability is the outcome of
a lot of stuff happening separately we
have to look at how all those things
relate okay so you know we were talking
before about little towns where people
like what you want to put what here and
like that could affect the how if you
live in little town in Finland how do
you feel better with the same kind of
Wind Facility right nearby how they do
it there two parts to the answer to that
the first is what people expect to
happen in their lives is they expect to
be treated
fairly and they believe if you say
what's your attitude toward the
government right right now you would
have in the US majority of people say we
don't trust the government we don't
think the government operates fairly we
don't like it because we've polarized
that discussion and it's Lo lost trust
and faith in government that trust and
faith exists in those places so there's
starting with a comfort level about well
if something's going to happen it's
going to happen because the decision was
made in a transparent accountable way
designed to maximize the public interest
we believe that we know that I'm not
arguing there's no corruption I'm not
arguing they don't make some mistakes
because they lean in One Direction or
another at the moment because of
political benefits or gains but in
general the public starts with an
expectation that when government does
something it's done in a fair
accountable transparent way aimed at
maximizing the shared or common interest
of the public okay so part one
expectations then the processes that
they rely on are to create citizen
advisory councils for everything okay
and they don't pick it's not a blue
ribbon committee chosen by the mayor
it's ensuring that all the different
interests I work with indigenous groups
in Scandinavia they have lots of
concerns that they are not being treated
fairly right but they're in a discussion
they're in a dialogue they're at the
table they may not be happy with h the
balance of not of of what's happened and
they certainly have good arguments
historically but
contemporaneously there's a public
advisory process at the local level
which is taken seriously and the law in
the
EU the law about public engagement is
really clear we don't have any law about
public engagement in America so I think
you told me you're an optimist but I
feel like a lot of what we've talked
about worries me because you know you
can do we talk so much to scientists
sort of moving something out of the lab
and then we have to think about how do
you manufacture something and you know
it's scale but then there's obviously
this whole other piece of it which is
then you have to put it into practice
somewhere and somebody lives near there
wherever there is don't you worry that
at least in the US we just like we just
don't have a decent process for doing
this and and and you were mentioning
before like we're maybe way below
capacity on what we the energy we could
produce
because basically fights between the
people who live here and the and there
and the and the uh
developers when not if when the
University
redefines its role the way we have as
providing a neutral space and Joint fact
finding capabilities and teaming up with
non for-profit providers of facilitation
Services the question of who's going to
help make this happen in each locality
is solved you think universities are the
place like the neutral place that you
know we're not used to thinking about
the university in that role but over the
last 3 years I've been part of an effort
to create in universities cyber security
for critical Urban infrastructure
training programs and we just started
one in MIT we said we'll teach students
to facilitate cyber security Improvement
at the local level and we'll offer our
services free to any
municipality that doesn't know what to
do or doesn't know how to proceed and
we've been doing that for five years and
Google came along and said that's a
really good idea uh I see youve formed
an association of 12 universities that
are now doing the same thing in cyber
security offering not for-profits and
communities assistance in dealing with
their vulnerabilities to Cyber attack
which are growing dramatically and which
raise huge financial loss
possibilities and they said here's $20
million find another 20 places which
we've done so now there's an association
of all these this is in less than five
years there's the possibility for any
municipality to get free assistance from
a university that has technically
capable people but cyber security
adjustments are not primarily technical
problems they're primarily local
political decisions about who's going to
have control over what what's the change
in the chain of command when you're
attacked who's going to be in charge
what money are you going to spend to
staff security it's not it it's a whole
new line in the budget oh my God we
don't have any money to do that and it's
very controversial to make the obvious
improvements that are going to protect
and and we go to communities that have
been attacked and had to pay huge Ransom
because they were victim of Ransom and
they didn't do anything after they're
absolutely every bit as vulnerable as
they were the day they were attacked
because they still don't have the
resources they don't have the capacity
but the idea is higher education
University I view what I'm doing in
training these folks as the same thing
that a law school does when it creates a
legal clinic or a medical school does
when it creates a a medical clinic we're
creating cyber security clinics now
we're doing a renewable energy Clinic
we need to formalize and allow the
process because it isn't
normally in this hyper politicized
context where nobody trusts the
government or vast numbers of people
don't trust the government they don't
trust the university either vast
majority of people do no longer trust
the university and when I say we're
going to play a neutral role and provide
a neutral space and make our scientific
and technical stuff available equally to
all sides oh yeah right and we have to
prove it right it funny I mean rule
making improving process it's like the
least sexy part of government stuff um I
have an MIT question for you so you work
alongside all these technologists many
of whom are very interested in trying to
create clean renewable
energy do you think people are aware of
you know what that sort of Last Mile so
to speak looks like that like here they
are really hard at work at trying to
change the planet and they've come up
with something and it it's going to be
great do you think they know what
implementation is going to look like or
are they very disconnected from that I
think they have been disconnected I
think they are becoming more aware
because they're hearing from the
sponsors of their
work uh you got anybody over there that
can be part of your team on How to Build
a Better wind turbine who could figure
out how the hell we get permission to
build the facility once we have the
better turbines and we now have a new
climate initiative with a new president
um that I think is going to ensure that
work on a fair transition or a just
transition is what happens not just do
we have the latest model for forecasting
the adverse effects going to be if you
don't do what we
say I have confidence because I see in
the hiring of new staff even in science
and engineering when you look at the
BIOS which you know 15 new people just
hired in the engineering school you look
at those bios 2third of those people
have in fact as part of their background
done work where they could be part part
of a collaboration that's new we had
talked in the beginning about a really
interesting example in the
US of you know sort of factionalism and
whatever I mean I think a little bit
about the cape wind thing because it's
here it's in the Massachusetts area
but do you want to talk about an example
that might be really interesting about
you know looking at how uh there's this
sort of factionalism when some sort sort
of energy project comes to town I have
to be careful because all of my
interventions guarantee anonymity okay
uh but but imagine a place that's real
uh in Massachusetts okay uh on the shore
and it has a newly elected town
government and the town government is uh
really concerned about the future of
offshore
wind and what it means to this town
big cables have to come across their
land to get connected to the
transmission system will all the tourism
that they currently have be lost because
all the views out the hotels are going
to be
obstructed by floating turbines right so
this town is saying uh we don't want to
wait around and see what
happens we want to have some way of
being in conversation
with offshore wind developers we have no
power over offshore wind developers but
we want to be in conversation with them
we want to be in conversation with the
state that's ultimately going to give
permissions and the federal agencies
that are going to have to give
permissions and we want to be able to
draw together people from all across our
town and have them be involved it isn't
going to be one meeting it'll be an
extended task force and we want to be
able to do it in a way that's open to
the rest of the public so that it can
become excited about and become part of
this and that we this isn't an offensive
play this is a how can we be part of
this in the way that we accept yes as I
I I chose to take your question to model
something that I know is real and this
leadership is interested in neighboring
towns and how it could perhaps involve
them subsequently in a collaborative
discussion which might ultimately lead
to to representation of local interests
in offshore wind in coastal
Massachusetts so they've come to uh the
clinic and we are in the process of not
only negotiating with them about what we
can do to staff and help them do this
but we're trying to put them in touch
with people at the appropriate federal
agencies who also are concern concerned
about what the future of conversations
going to be with local governments on
offshore wind in New England and we
we're trying to say that the uh federal
agencies should fund this locality's
efforts to staff and do all this work it
shouldn't just depend on our being able
to volunteer students in one course
especially because I think based on what
they're proposing we might be able to
recruit
at this early stage a whole slew of
Municipal leaders if this first one and
what they're doing could be presented in
the right way and if resources for this
could be coming from the federal
government and once the federal
government expresses interest I promise
the state government is going to follow
and want to be part of it and offer some
funds probably federal funds that it has
uh to assist so even in the context
we've been talking about everybody's out
to protect themselves reduce their costs
you have the opportunity for leadership
to not be against or for anything but to
create a different kind of dialogue
aimed at consensus facilitated
appropriately supported through joint
fact finding and maybe even
intergovernmental from its beginning and
when it devel developer comes to this
town I assume they haven't yet they have
okay they have um so how's that going is
it better because the town had sort of
talked through here's what we are the
old leadership of the town is the old
leadership and the new leadership is the
new leadership because the old
leadership didn't talk to the developers
in a way that majority of the community
was happy about I'm just going to leave
it at that okay they're what whichever
stand they took that's why they're not
the leadership anymore it was explicitly
about this issue so so is the new
leadership and a more adversar has a
more adversarial stance of the new
leadership says we're going to tend to
the interests of the whole Community oh
okay and we are going to prepare
ourselves okay the new leadership is the
the prepping the people who are prepping
um the old leadership just took a stand
and is that going to result in a more in
I think it's going to make the developer
obl incredibly happy okay and they're
not being asked to fund this process
that's the last thing that we would want
but they can tend they can be part of it
okay but there's no discussion going to
happen of their project at this time
this is a great example to conclude with
I think they are framing the the the
future of how they're going to have wind
if they're going to have wind in terms
of the benefits that it will bring to
the community in a way that works for
the developer and that seems to me the
sort of recognition of costs and
benefits and not winners and losers but
everybody
winning but I would also point out that
because we're looking at the subject or
hopefully we'll be looking at the
subject in
depth in its
entirety there might be a possibility
that wind would come to this in this
mici ofate not just about what offshore
wind means to
them what wind power means because we do
have examples I mean city of gastra mass
95% of all public electricity costs are
covered by one turbine that is built on
Industrial land wow that that
municipality built it's gigantic and it
was very controversial but it was done
in the way that I
describing and they everyone in town is
very aware that that affects their tax
[Music]
rate Larry seskin is Professor of urban
environmental planning at MIT he's the
publisher of the public interest
technologist at MIT Larry thank you so
much thanks Larry thank you both and I
very much appreciate you're doing the
whole series I think it's
terrific what if it works is a section
of the MIT energy initiative if you like
the show please leave us a review or
invite a friend to listen and remember
to subscribe on Apple podcast Spotify or
wherever you get your
podcast you can find an archive of every
episode all of our show notes and a lot
more at energy. mit.edu
podcasts and you can learn more about
the work of the energy initiative and
the energy transition at energy. mit.edu
[Music]
our original podcast artwork is by
zeitler Design special thanks to all the
people at Mighty and MIT who make this
show possible I'm Cara Miller and I'm
Rob Stoner thanks for listening
[Music]