good morning everyone and welcome to the
first day of our MPG
2425 season um my name is Nicole
rockweiler I'm a postto in Steve MCC
Carrol's lab um myself and Michelle we
co-organize the mpg primer and we're so
glad that you guys are tuning in today
remotely or in person um just wanted to
give a few slides for housekeeping um
information so as you have already can
tell we're in a different location this
year and this is just to make it easier
so we can transition to the seminar
meeting uh so we'll be here in this room
every week unless there's a a room
reservation issue but you can always
check our calendar um and then also just
to be cognizant that there's another
seminar right after this we're going to
end at 9:20 feel free to stay here if
you want but if you want to move over to
get your next breakfast and get a good
seat for the prime for the seminar um
just uh feel free to do
that um and also just want to tell you
today and forever we really encourage
you guys to ask your questions this
primer is for you if something is
unclear you want to know more please ask
your questions either at the mics or put
it in in the Q&A on Zoom um and then
lastly we put these meetings online
afterwards on YouTube so they're open
meetings um and then again this year
we're going to start something new we're
going to try to put these uh PDFs of the
slides on the broad website that's
publicly available so if you want to
share with colleagues um it's another
resource for
you um one more bookkeeping thing about
today uh today we have our primer our
seminar at 9:30 and then the next event
today is a happy hour with food and
drinks uh it will be at 4: to 5:30 in
the Terrace just across the the side um
um and if I didn't mention both food and
alcoholic and non-alcoholic
Beverages and then uh another update
we're trying a lot of new things this
year we are officially on Twitter as
broad MPG so if you want to learn about
our primers when the videos go up read
about papers from our community as well
as job postings um please consider
following us and also tag us with your
research so that we can follow you um
and share your
work um and you might notice one less
person in the room right now uh Lauren
who was our program manager she actually
stepped down from the position so we are
actively looking for a new person uh to
be the operation SP specialist for MPG
and TGG uh the job is officially posted
um there's this IO link here um if you
have any um questions about the position
or know someone please let um myself
Heidi Mark Michelle um know and also in
the interim while Lauren's out there's
this um email address that you can send
if you have any questions um about MPG
in
general I'm G to go o I'm going to skip
the description I'm going to post it on
slack later today but please if you know
anyone we would love to um have them on
board uh so just to give you AE of
what's coming up in the beginning of
this primary season we're going to
really focus on basics of population
genetics so next week we're going to
have an intro to pop gen and the
following week we're going to do um more
pop gen topics such as population
structure stratification and AD
mixture and uh lastly I'm pretty sure
this is the last slide um today we have
a lovely um introduction to our for data
analysis by nil and Michelle's going to
introduce her great thanks good morning
um it is my pleasure to introduce nil
aigon nil received her PhD in
bioinformatics in computational biology
at UNC Chapel Hill in 2023 during this
training under the mentorship of Dr
Jason Stein she investigated genetically
altered cell type specific Gene
regulation during human neural
differentiation she began her postdoc
research in the bokum lab in May
2023 and in her postdoc she's developing
algorithms to explore the genetic and
other molecular co-occurrences driving
cancer progression and Drug resistance
um but today she's going to be talking
to us about data science with our um an
introduction so with that I hand it over
to
Neil thank you so much yeah today I
would like to share with you some
introduction uh for how to use R and
data science um in general so I'm really
happy to be here today yeah today we
will go over uh certain some basics in
art and how to use them in specific
genomic analysis and this is our outline
uh we will learned basic data structures
data how to manipulate data INR how to
uh define specific functions um how to
use control structures how to perform
regation analysis and how to visualize
your data um and some uh still there
specific specialized our packages you
can also use for genomic analysis in
addition to what we go over today
so to be able to give you an
introduction all of these topics I would
like to start with an interesting
genomic question uh so that we can
introduce certain data set and how we
can answer specific questions by using R
so this question includes um some qtl
work in from my pphd study um so in that
as you all familiar with genome white
Association studies discover many in
genetic variant that are associated with
variety of complex human traits one
interesting fact is that those variants
are mainly found in noncoding part of
the genome um and that makes uh hard to
explain uh their function so one
potential mechanism is that a genetic
variant can be located from water of a
gene that may interfere binding of uh
transcription regulators and that will
uh change the C accessibility in that
area and accordingly based on the um
having different variant excuse me
different Al of this variant we can see
changes in expression as an outcome so
by performing expression quantity to tra
Locus ensured uh equal analysis we can
try to understand if the individuals
that that have AA genotype has a higher
gene expression than individuals with CC
genotype and in this case we perform a
statistical test and understand if this
relationship is significant so let's say
we are interest in performing expression
quanti local analysis and these are the
oops let me go how can I go
further oh okay here we go
so let's say we drive uh some data sets
from this to perform this analysis such
that we perform um RNA sequencing by
collecting hundreds of individuals and
drive cell lines from them because we're
interest in cell have specificity and we
profile we perform jic Prof transcrip
profiling across the cell Lines by
performing R sequencing analysis and
here is the data set we can see for Gen
expression in this case each Dr
indicates different genes and their
corresponding expression value across
those cell lines coming from different
individuals and you can see that those
values corresponds to normalized gen
expression
value and we can also look genotypes of
the cell lines dve from the individuals
in this case you can see the variety of
genetic variants listed on the roow and
their corresponding genotyp information
across cell lines for instance one
indicates that in my case I call effect
Al as a minor Al um and if an individual
has only one minor Al We call we can
call as a one if it doesn't have any we
can call this a zero if it has two of
the minor Al we can call two so just a
numeric interpretation of how a
genotyping data set u can be done for a
qtl in any typ type of um variant
Association analysis in addition to that
we may have a metadata which includes
information from the cell lines which
can be further useful for us for example
let's say we sorted cells based on a
certain marker by using tax machine and
unfortunately there are two different
tax machines very available that's why
it ca some batch effect that's what we
can call them tax Miss A and B and uh
those individuals they provide as sell
lines for us can come from may have
different genders male female and you
can also store their ages um as well
so oops Yeah to be able to um import
this data set and work on them in R we
first need to understand uh data
structure potential data structures in R
let's look at them a little quick
vectors are the base six um El Basics
units have to represent data structure
in R it basically includes a list of
elements and by using C parenthesis you
can define a new Vector in this case I
Define a vector name a u which includes
eight numeric individ components and
this is how you assign a variable in R
by using equal Dash operators and and
this is how the it looks like and you
can also check what type of data is by
using class function in R again as you
see that it go on numeric values in
addition numeric values we can store a
character U or other words stct string
components in a vector in this case
these are different Gene names as you
can see and there's a character
vector and majes is a 2d form of the
vectors in this Cas you can store a
multiple information from multiple
vectors um as an example here you have
two different vectors A and B that
includes numeric values of with three
different components by using C cbind
function in other words column bind
function you can bind this vector by
column that result in this 2D U
information and we can check the
dimensions of this matrix by using dim
function again
uh and alternatively you can define a
fun matrix by using Matrix function in
this case you provide a vector as a
first first parameter of this function
and you can actually uh there a type
here is three um and you can say that
how many rowes you expect in your Matrix
and if they were order if there are
order by row or
column um so to be able to access
elements or slice or subset a matrices
there are certain ways so for this we
can use square brackets B for our um um
object in this case our Matrix object
called as M so let's say we want to
interested in to access Elements which
located second row and First Column of
this Matrix for this we can ident we can
Define first element before comma
uh as the row information and the second
one as the column information
alternatively um we
can get for example slic The Matrix so
that we can get only the First Column
and then all the information from the
rest of rowes we can uh basically uh
leave empty the first item and second
place can be the number of the um column
you're interested in
data frames uh are a little bit more
complicated version of the matrices um
difference between mat and the data
frame is that you can store a variety of
um uh different the different uh not the
same data set but different structures
uh different classes excuse me for
example you can store both numeric and
character information in the same data
frame such as for example let's back to
the our previous example we have cell
lines uh indicated by your identifiers
here and uh the text machine which is
use to sort them and gender information
and age information by using the data.
frame function you can define a data
frame as you can see you can place each
of those U vectors and they result in a
mix of information coming from numeric
values and character
values again you can SL device or softs
set data frames by using a similar
strategy we use for matrices uh by using
a square brackets and writing the name
of the um um columns for your interest
for example let's say I want to get the
values from First Column to Second
column by keeping all information from
the all rows I can put one column and
two and this will result and this will
give me the information from the first
uh uh First Column second column and
also we can select information from the
um first and excuse me second and third
rows across all the columns so this now
we will place our interest uh range to
the first place and then um leave the
empty in the second
item and alternatively how we can call
certain columns from data frame can be
can be performed by using a dollar sign
for example each uh column has a name in
our data frame and by using a dollar
sign we can pull information from fax
machine and that will result in as you
see in a vector it's a character vector
and Str Str is another function you can
learn what type of data set you have
within your vector or in general in your
data
frame and uh lists are will the final
data structure I will introduce you here
today um this is a even more complicated
version of the data frame which includes
uh a vector a character and even a
matrix written a same um same object so
in this case I included a numeric Vector
called numbers and a strength of work as
genetics and a matrix uh which has two
columns and three rows in the same list
and eventually you can see that all of
them can store in the same uh
object uh to be able to extract the
elements of the list you in this case
you need to use double square brackets
for example if I want to reach the
Matrix within this list I can use a
double square U uh brackets and also
writing the um index of
this where this Matrix is stored in the
list
which is three and as you can see again
I can look for this by Str Str I can
learn what type of a data I have here
that indicates that I have a matrix
which include numeric values and also
similar to data frame you can use a
dollar sign to extract an element as
long as you have a name for it within
your list uh and again you will um
extract your um Matrix information
within that list by using dollar sign
Matrix
comment
so after learning the data structures
let's look at how to manipulate data in
R and we will go over that by asking
some very simple um questions and before
going that I would like to introduce you
tidy Words which is an collection of
different art packages that is designed
for data science usage and can be used
for data manipulation as you know this I
said something different here which is
package so let me first introduce what
is package what does it mean in
R so um in addition to certain function
which you can find in B bying base R
without need for any other um help I
would say you can perform many tasks but
however there are also um packages in R
they can be add on all of the
uh base our functions and that allows
you to perform additional tasks so you
need to install this R packages as you
need and there are three major uh
resources you can install this packages
one of them is curan and by using
install. packages function you can
install um your package of interest in
this case for example tiders um can be
uh installed in that way uh bioconductor
is another place uh which includes our
packages that is that are specified for
biological
functions um and by using biom manager
you can install this packages as well um
so biom manager another our package
which allows you to install um packages
store in the bioconductor so that's why
you first need to get the bio manager
bio manager from curan and then you need
to install packages from bioconductor by
using the help of Bio manager and GitHub
is another place um you can also
um um you can also get the data for that
you can use Dev tools which is another
our package uh because uh you know this
a very Dynamic field and every day
people generate their their own art
packages and they don't prer going to um
you know apply by conductor for each
time that's why they just place them in
GitHub because it's free open the public
so basically you can if you are
interested in to use their own packages
you can uh download them from GitHub
based on the um addresses they provide
you so one important thing here
installing a package is only a one-time
task once you install a package in your
R you'll no longer need to do that
however you need to do each art session
is you need to load them for this you
can use a library function and every
time once you want to use a pack some
some functions from a package you need
to install excuse me you need to load in
your environment by using this Library
function so let's go back to um data man
manipulation part again so in this case
um we going to answer U such a question
like cell lines in our data set were
sorted by FX machine a so for this first
we need to import the data set of
interest in our R environment for that
we can use RIT CSV function because I
have a CSV function it can be an Excel
function you can use a different um
um excuse me Excel document you can use
a different function for that specified
uh or you may have a text uh file in
this case you can R table or you can use
a f function which is coming from data
table package which is very um helpful
once you have a big data set it's
required High memory um as an
alternative so to be able to um read
this data set first we need to Define
where is the data set this is um how I
store my data set a meta called the
metad data and then you write the name
of file and once you uh read this file
you need to assign another variable so
that you can work with uh as a object in
your our environment so we can look at
what is inside in this metadata object
by using head function uh that will give
you the first six row um so you don't
need to um look at the whole full data
set for example again you can see the
cell line information and they
corresponding fact machine gender and
age so now if you go back to our
question that is uh we want to learn uh
which sell lines were sorted by fax
machine R fax machine a excuse me what
we can do is we can use um this uh
specified functions from uh tiders uh
more specifically de lier so now I would
like to introduce you this operator
which looks AIT complicated is call as a
pipe so that allows you to use an output
from your previous step as an input for
your next in this case I will use a
filter function so that I can get only
row which has a a in their fax machine
information
so that's why I uh uh Define it in here
and then that
resulted uh in subset this uh metadata
so that only the only information is
kept where cell lines were sorted based
on tax machine a as the Second
Step what I would like to learn is I
want to learn which cell lines actually
have this information that's why I only
need that column that include the
selling information to be able to
perform this task I need an additional
command again I add my pipe here and I
will perform that by using the select
function So within the select function
I'm writing the name of the column I'm
interested to extract and that will
result um in sell lines that were sorted
based on text machine
a so let's ask another question that is
um I'm going to learn what is the age
average of females versus mail donors
from which cell lines were generated for
that again my data set metadata is here
I want to group by group them based on
their gender so that I can get a gender
specific information by using Group by
function and then from the separated uh
stratified data based on gender I want
to calculate um average of the um
age to be able to perform that I can use
a summarized function and with the
summarized function I will write um um
my function interest in this case that
is gaing the mean calculate the mean for
the column of interest that is H and
that will resulted uh average uh age for
females and males
um what else I can do for example I may
also be interested in adding additional
information for this metadata let's say
ancestor information uh and we have a
list of ancestors for each of this
donors that we got the sell lines from
um which is a an object called ancestry
character vector and um to be able to
add this information to my data set I
can use mutate function again after the
pipe and I can um put in a name for this
variable within my um um for my for my
data frame uh by using uh by using the
variable name on the left side of the
equal sign and then I will put my Vector
name here so that result in new column
called us ancestry which includes the
information from each of the cell
lines so since I created a new data set
probably I want to store it or exported
from R to be able to uh do this I can
use right CSV function if I want to save
this in a CSC format or I can save as a
text format by using the right table
function so these are the uh basics for
how to you can manipulate the data based
on your specific question of interest um
however we may need to do additional
tasks in this case we may need to use um
we may need to Define some functions by
ourselves and we need to perform this
complicated uh settings like going
through all the data set and that's why
we need to learn some control
structures so first look at this uh
another question that is they are
specifically interested in if the
expression of egfr gen um is greater
than five at Le 5% of the cell lines so
to be able to perform this task first we
need to read the Gen expression data and
you can see the first fourth rows and
fourth Columns of this expression data
here as you can see so so first I need
to obtain expression values
from egfr egfr G there are alternative
ways to do that first what since I know
that this is a first row I can quickly
call the information from first row
across all the columns from this object
expression um data object or
alternatively if I don't know there is
the egfr in store um I can learn it by
asking um by using the V uh
function so and
then I try to understand uh actually
which of the cell lines have gen
expression value bigger than five again
by using the V function that will give
me the location of the cell Lines within
this um first row that has a value
greater than five and to be able to
learn how many of cell
lines uh has this information I can use
length function and that will gives me
the number of the cell lines that has
egfr expression greater than five and I
can calculate the percentage in the end
and eventually it is 96 res in that 96%
of cell lines um having a Hy expression
value so this is important for us
because mainly we want to learn
um coverage so so that we can have
enough expression values to perform CU
analysis or any type of differential
expression analysis so on so that is why
we probably need to do that across
transcript on across all other genes and
how we can do that so we cannot make
this one by one right for each row um
and every time when you write all of
this um
commands it looks U it's not efficient
first of all and also it looks U very um
not not regulated not arrange very well
so what you can do is actually you can
define a function which can perform all
of the steps within and you can just
provide um specific information in that
function and then it will eventually
give you the answer of the question
you're interested in for example in this
case we can define a function by using a
uh function name is function and X will
be your input of your interest and again
I will replace all of the commands I
show you from the previous slide within
this uh our function and then it will
return the percentage of the cell lines
um that has a certain expression value
greater than certain expression value in
our case this is five so I call this
function as get
coverage and um to be able to um perform
this task across all of the genes I can
use a for Loop strategy um and for this
I Define a for Loop that will go over
each of the row of this gene expression
Matrix and after I extracted information
from each through for example in this
case I Define it here and I will provide
it as an input for my function get
coverage I Define previous so what is
important here is for this is something
new for us I put a minus one here so
that I can export the First Column which
include information from the Gen um name
so that I can get only the numeric
values and J indicates the row that will
first one by one through this for Loop
for example it will first get the
information from the first row and then
second and third so on and I Define a g
g name as well so that I can store this
information and to be able to store this
information in the end at the beginning
I Define an empty data frame called as
coverage values and every time I extract
the information for
uh coverage and also Gene name I store
them in a little data frame and I added
this information to the previous one uh
previous information the previous Ro by
using the rbind row bind function
basically I bind this information from
this little data frames um by by row and
eventually that result in a object
called as coverage values that will the
information from each gene um and your
corresponding
coverage so after that after I Define
the data frame by using uh again some
data manipulation tools I can filter
them based on their coverage will be
greater than five and I can select only
the gene column so that I can learn
actually which genes has High
coverage so there's actually more
efficient way doing that um instead of
using the for Loops um and apply family
functions can be can perform this task
for this we can use apply function and
we uh provide our data set here as a
first item and second item um will be
direction of the calculations we're
interested in in our case we're
interested in um uh compute the coverage
per row right in the direction of this
arrow and we provided this input for the
get carage function each time so
basically instead of writing a for Loop
uh by providing an apply function you
can let your algorithm pass through all
of the rows and uh in your data frame uh
by using a one called line so in this
case
each um rowes will go to get coverage
function and that's will result in the
same um
um coverage
information um there are other functions
called L apply and S apply so uh there
are differences based on what type of
input you can provide and what type of
output you can get in apply function you
can
um apply function can be applied for for
either matrices or data frames um so uh
one more one more information here is um
for examp if you want to parse your data
frame or Matrix through columns you can
replace by two um and L apply uh can be
used for uh inputs that are list and
output again list s apply also can be
used for either list vectors um matrices
and it will result of um uh this data
structure as an output as well so it
depends on what type of a um task you
want to perform you can uh look for
other apply family functions and they
are very efficiently uh passed for your
grou um now let's go through regression
analysis that is the actually the
initial question we are interested in so
that was we want to look learn how um
what is the um variation uh in the gene
expression data is how much of them is
explained by certain um variants so in
this case we can um perform regression
analysis understand their relationship
between the genotype and the gene
expression in this case we
Define um gen expression as a depend
dependent
variable basically by using a genotype
information that's our independent
variable we can predict um values for uh
Y which is Gen expression value in our
case and to perform this task we try to
fit the data points in a line and as you
see here you call the regression line um
the data
points do not perfectly fit the line so
that will introduce an error term um and
this line basically
selected based on a criteria that
minimizes um the square sum of each of
this error term coming from data set
that indicates their distance from the
fited line so after this U line that
minimizes the square sum is selected uh
we see two different
uh variables one of them
is it's for better coefficients it
included two information one for beta
zero that is intercept basically that is
the point uh the y y value that
correspond to x value which equals zero
and beta one which is actually more
important for our cases that is the
slope of that line that indicates how
strong a relationship between your genot
type and your gen
expression so and regression analysis uh
tests the significance of how this uh
beta value beta one value is different
from
zero and we can perform the linear
regression analysis by using R um let's
say I'm interested in see the
relationship between EF gen expression
values versus this RS um 14 and and with
76 uh genetic variance first I read my
uh data sets and then I extracted the
corresponding values for EGF egfr gen
expression and genotype value for the
snip and I form a data frame which
include information from What gene
expression and genotype and also
additionally I added gender and age
information so that resulted in in a
data frame where you can see the
expression values for egfr and their
corresponding genotype value for uh this
specific snip and uh gender and the age
of each of the cell
lines so by using LM function I can
perform this task and uh basically my y
now will be in the left side of the
tilta my X will be the on the right top
of the um uh tilt and I Define uh those
variables by using their column names
and I tell them which data I want to use
within this data
parameter and U by using a summary
function I can get an information of
Statistics so U for the beta one we can
see the uh estimation values as uh 27 in
this uh second row of the First Column
and then you can see the corresponding P
value let's say I want to
add gender information uh to this model
meaning that I want to control for the
impact of gender on gene expression and
then I want to see the relationship
between an expression of genotype for
this simply I can add gender after um
plus sign and as you see here again I
will look for the corresponding
statistics for the
genotype and
P value and beta coefficient of slightly
change now after you add this so there
are some cases your data can be
significant after you add for um this
additional information we call them
co-founders um basically the um ideal
way is checking their impact on G
expression first and then decide uh if
you want to edit your linear model so
that you can perform a robust Q analysis
sure uh yeah this is a b and then what
is the number above that the nine what
is the oh this one yeah what is that
this is intercept this is the beta zero
this is how okay yeah basically
generally we are always interested in a
beta coent key value uh so that we can
report them to show the significance of
our relationship
um yeah and then let's visualize uh our
data set finally by using GG plot so um
I also want to show how we can look for
the line relationship excuse me um and
gplot is a very helpful function for
data
visualization um for this you use ggplot
function and you write the name of your
data and then you can uh select the
columns which you would like to uh Plot
show within this a e s corresponding
athetics function so what I want to do
is I want to plot information genotype
versus expression values that's why I
put this column names and I use jum
Jitter function here uh so that I can
get a scatter plot which U uh sort of um
since I have a group of values from 0 1
two for x-axis but I want to separate
this data points I use uh kind of a
rotation by using a g function instead
you can use a g point that will allows
you when you have a wide range of X Val
versus y AIS that's um kind of having
equal number of elements as well uh I
Define a color of this data points here
um and then I Define size B
um excuse me size of the points and then
I name the uh labels exic y labels here
so if I want to add um gen stratify them
based on the gender information what I
can do is I can add a color parameter
within this a e Statics function it will
color those data points based on gender
or finally I can uh add a box plot on
top of it by using the jum box plot
function in addition that there are
variety of other function that allows
you different visualizations like for
examp bar plot you can use J Bar for
density plots you can use J density or
histograms because jum
histogram let's go to the final part of
our talk today so as we mentioned at the
beginning uh by conductor is are one of
the uh place you can uh get lots of our
packages to be using
um to answer different biological
questions um it's a huge uh storage area
that includes above
2,000 uh different um our packages uh I
just like to highlight you uh one of the
a few popular ones first one is dc2
first that can be used to test
differential gen expression analysis you
can um use the dc2 uh package name dc2
for that uh it will perform a differen
expression by using negative binormal
distribution um and you can see this is
a famous volcano flight uh not Volcan
but mean expression versus log to full
change plot um after you perform uh this
um analysis it's an algorithm generated
by um Dr Mike and their
colleagues um another package which is
very I found very helpful is a g
profiler too um instead of using uh this
webbased tools you can perform Gene
enrichment analysis genology analysis by
using this Tool uh basically after
performing your differential expression
analysis you can um extract the genes
which show up regulation and which show
down regulation and then by using list
of genes as an input for a function
called as ghost within this package you
can find uh which Pathways they were
significantly enriched and it can even
perform uh some visualization for you um
summarize uh what type of uh enrichment
um results you
have finally uh this is from uh um my
own study uh with my colleagues uh we
performance crial analysis and to be
able to look at the results um we use
some visualization tools
uh this looks a very complicated graph
here if I can summarize for example in
this case we are interested in um how
and eqtl for coming from certain cell
types for the CPW Gene um is associated
with u education attainment and Global
surface area gas so for example to be
able to make this beautiful and
complicated graph a variet or our
packages exist uh which includes Jus
biomart um and also genomic ranges that
will allow you to Define your um genomic
Locus with an object and you can play
with
them so yeah thank you so much all of
you for having me today and I will be
happy if you have additional uh
questions and if you don't have anything
right now you can also reach me
afterwards uh this is my email I'm in
the cancer program uh living in the
fourth floor um yeah I will be very
happy to talk about about my research
and our in general
okay thanks NE that was great I know for
me I'm used to looking at art tutorials
with the built-in um data frames like
cars so it was really nice to see it in
a genomic context um do we have any
questions in the
room yeah yeah I can bring you the
microphone or you could come up and
stand by one do you have any experience
working with data that doesn't fit in
memory and how you would handle that
yeah that's a great point and for those
cases uh instead of using my generally I
don't use my local machine at all for
any analysis uh we can have a system
inro called Uber that allows you to
access High memory uh computer with the
high memory uh basically you can get an
interactive job um you can Define how
much memory you want and you can handle
data set with uh those additional
computers not your in local machine
yeah the eqtl the last
plot the last plot for showing the locus
and how do you know about this snip is
uh the the location in your plot oh yeah
uh I'm having the information from um
have genotype data store that's a
software plink that give me the VAR the
variant is uh you can you can also look
at them in r as well because we know the
there is the jum location of each of
variant um and but you can actually put
this information within a g range object
in each time for each variance uh and
basically you create a numeric values of
the location of each variant and the
genome are these um all Snips correlated
with each other and the inod to the the
one gen oh yeah that's a great point so
in this case I tested Association of all
the variant within the stomic locus with
cvw Gene only one gene thank you yeah
sure I'm wondering if you have
suggestions for um people new to R in
these analyses and using chat GPT or
copilot to try to help them with their
coding or like words of the wise yeah um
definitely they are helpful uh but as
long as you don't know what function
does it can some dangerous and time
consuming um for a starting point I
would definitely suggest going uh some
uh art tutorials online first and once
you're familiar with um you can also uh
look for chat but I think you should be
able to judge what chat un does because
sometimes uh it gives you a mix of
functions um all the general it can be a
very helpful starting point as well uh
but yeah as long as you have a good art
tutorial sort of a script save somewhere
you can copy paste it from each time um
change it based on your um question so I
trust tutorial more than chat
actually all right well if there's no
other questions let's thank our speaker
again
[Music]