Welcome to the AI and open education
initiative speaker series. My name is
Sher Seagull and I am the collaborations
and engagement manager at MIT Open
Courseware. I'm also one of the planning
committee members for the AI and open
education initiative at MIT open
learning in order to meet the moment of
remarkable growth of artificial
intelligence and to examine its benefits
and challenges to the field of open
education. Last summer, MIT Open
Learning solicited rapid response papers
from stakeholders around the world to
articulate how generative AI might
accelerate or hinder the promise of open
education. An international jury of AI
and open education experts reviewed 147
submissions and published nine
thought-provoking papers by 32
researchers on the open platform PubPub
which you can find via the link in the
chat. The initiative and today's speaker
series webinar is generously funded by
the William and Flora Hulet Foundation.
We want to thank Hulet for their ongoing
support. Today's session is the second
of two webinars in the initiative
speaker series. Our first webinar topic
was professional education and the
judicious use of AI. Today's webinar
topic is AI literacies and evaluation.
An overview of today's structure is as
follows. First, I will briefly introduce
our speakers. Then our respondent will
contextualize this moment for us. Third,
select co-authors of the two spotlighted
papers will provide a highle overview of
each of their papers for less than 10
minutes each. And this will be followed
by a discussion with the authors led by
our respondent. And finally, we will
open the discussion for your comments
and questions.
I'm thrilled to introduce today's
speakers. Nick Baker is the digital
learning specialist and former director
of the office of open learning at the
University of Windsor. and he is our
respondent today. Nick was a founding
board member of eCampus Ontario, a
government-f funed nonprofit
organization that provides support for
digital teaching and learning,
educational technology, micro
credentials, and open education for the
publicly assisted post-secondary
institutions of Ontario, Canada. He
works at the intersection of open
educational practices, AI, and
accessibility. His work also entails
higher ed policy and change management.
Some of his publications are in the chat
for you.
Angela Gundar and one of the co-authors
of today's two spotlighted papers is the
CEO and founder of Opened Culture. She's
previously the the chief academic
officer of the online learning
consortium. She's also online faculty at
the University of Arizona's College of
Information Science and she teaches
courses in new media, instructional
design, game design, and AI. Her
research focuses on open remix
practices, open culture, digital
literacies, narrative digital learning
practices, and emerging technology for
language acquisition.
Josh Herren is the director of
professional learning at the online
learning consortium. He is a researcher
with opened culture and a doctorate in
information design from Clemson
University where he also teaches
interdisciplinary courses. His research
and work is largely in new media,
instructional design, and digital
leadership.
The featured papers for today's webinar
are in the chat now for you. Josh and
Angela's paper is titled AI Literacies
and the Advancement of Opened Cultures.
Our next two co-authors are Hannah Beth
Clark uh from the Oak National Academy
in the UK. She's a teacher and senior
leader in London Secondary Schools for
the last 15 years. She's experienced in
curriculum design and impactful teaching
in the classroom. She leads the quality
and safety work of AI tools at Oak
National Academy. Our second co-author
from Oak National Academy is Margot
Dowand. She recently completed a
master's in pure mathematics and then
pivoted into AI and machine learning.
She's a machine learning engineer at Oak
National Academy focusing on evaluation
and designing agent-based systems. Their
paper is titled auto evaluation a
critical measure in driving improvements
in quality and safety of AI generated
lesson resources. Now I'll pass the
baton to our respondent Nick Baker to
contextualize this moment for us.
>> Thank you. And for those for whom a
visual description is helpful, I'm a
light-skinned male uh middle-aged male
with short brown gray hair and short
gray facial hair and glasses. and I'm
wearing a blue shirt and headphones. I
wanted to start by acknowledging that uh
I have the privilege to live and work on
the traditional lands of the three fires
confederacy of the Ojiua, the Ottawa and
the Potawa Tommy. Thanks so much to Sher
and the team for the invitation and the
incredible work that MIT is doing to
advance open education um and all the
open practitioners involved in the AI
and open ed initiative. We're at a
fascinating time in history where
incredibly powerful technologies are
kind of within the reach of almost
everyone and societies around the globe
are trying to figure out not only the
implications of this new wave of
artificial intelligence, but how best to
steer its power towards good things for
humanity because that's certainly not a
given.
There's a lot of potential for AI to
help solve some of the persistent
challenges that we've had in the open
world for decades. how to keep resources
up to date, how to adapt them to local
context, adding local case studies,
providing enough ancillary resources to
compete with other forms of educational
content and so on.
AI can be harnessed to work on these
gnarly challenges. Uh, but it can also
present quite a few challenges of its
own.
There are many concerns that remain
about the quality of AI outputs, biases
and inaccuracies
um that they might contain the potential
to reinforce inequity in existing power
structures and so on. Projects such as
the ones that you're going to hear about
today are critical to addressing those
concerns.
It's clear that there are now a new set
of literacies and competencies that are
emerging in response to the almost
unimaginable growth of AI, which is a
technology that's causing us to question
our understanding of knowledge, how we
create and share it, and even what it
means to be human and sensient. Um, as
our first speakers are going to point
out, many of the competencies we need to
work with AI are actually pretty closely
aligned with the values and approaches
of openness and open educational
practices. With AI evolving so quickly,
technical skills and knowing how to use
a specific tool is rapidly outdated as
knowledge. What we need is to develop
literacies rather than just technical
skills to handle the complexity of the
transformation of knowledge work um in
this new AIdriven environment that we
find ourselves.
As Angela and Josh are going to note in
their paper, we need to place AI
literacies above um AI tools themselves
as central to fostering cultures of
openness in the education in education
globally. There are many questions that
we need to address at the intersection
of AI and openness. And I'm really
excited for this opportunity to have a
chat today with four of the authors of
two excellent rapid response papers from
the AI and open initiative um who've
been obviously thinking about these
questions really deeply. So I'll pass
the baton back. Fantastic. Thank you so
much. So I will kick us off with our
first set of papers, our um co-authors
Angela Gund and Josh Heron uh for their
highlevel overview. Thank you.
>> Thank you for the warm welcome Shira and
Nick. I have to thank you for that
beautiful and profound grounding and
context for us. I know that in this um
iconoclastic moment where um my
colleagues are also going to present
their paper, you're going to see a lot
of connections and uh findings that link
together and hopefully spark new ideas
for you. Um so I'd love to kick off in
that spirit. Uh and typically when I
talk about research findings, especially
from my team, I like to ground them
around narratives because that helps us
to apply theories and put them into
practice. So today I'm going to talk a
little bit about the night sky to kick
us off first. Growing up um and honestly
even now I've always been fascinated by
looking up at the stars and you may be
the same. And whether it's out here in
the desert where I live in Phoenix,
Arizona where the visibility is crisp
and clear or even just catching glimpses
between city lights. I always find
myself drawn to that vastness and the
way that constellations take shape. And
each star alone that we look at is
impressive, but it's the way that they
connect that creates something
meaningful. Whether it's a constellation
that orients us or even helps us to find
our way. You can go to the next slide,
please. Metaphors from the natural world
always creep into my work, especially
within education. and the phenomena
surrounding the vector of AI is really
no exception and the connections to the
metaphors about stars that I'm going to
share here. Um, folks are grappling with
what AI in education means for them in
their roles and for their students and
in Josh and my research and the research
of our team. We've seen this uh from
educators not only uh through their
perspectives but their practices. And
one of the biggest challenges that my
team and I have seen is this quest to
define AI literacy as a singular thing
to find one perfect framework that will
explain how we should think about AI in
our work as educators and honestly it
feels a little bit like chasing a black
hole. Go to the next slide please. So
when it comes to AI literacy, there's
been a bit of obsession with finding the
one framework to rule them all. And this
framework is imagined as an ultimate
guide, a singular model that can define
what it means to be literate in AI
across all contexts and applications.
But in the same way that a black hole
forms when a massive star dies and
collapses under its own gravity, we've
seen the same collapse happen when we
try to define AI literacy as a single
fixed entity of either literate versus
illiterate. And instead of illuminating
the way, this binary rips through
diverse perspectives. It crushes our
context specific practices and
compresses all that richness that we
know exists within education into a
dense unyielding point. When we focus
too much on creating one
all-encompassing model, we risk losing
the nuance, dynamic, and open nature of
AI literacies, and we risk creating a
closed singularity of thought that
doesn't reflect the varied ways
educators and learners actually use and
think about AI. Next slide. So for the
past two years, my team and I have
conducted research on AI literacies,
most recently in a study commissioned by
UNESCO IIT. And in parallel to that
study, we ended up talking to open
educators around the globe about the
competencies and skills needed to use AI
for education as part of our rapid
response paper. And just as the stars
offer more than one just more than one
bright point in the sky, the findings
from these educators have really
illuminated for us that AI literacies
aren't about finding a single guiding
light. Instead, they're more like a
constellation. They're a pattern of
skills, mindsets, and competencies that
when we connect them together help us
navigate the complex realities of AI
within education. And to map these
constellating sets of literacies, my
research team and I identified eight
dimensions of AI literacies, which is a
combination of both skill sets and
mindsets that reflect the multiaceted
ways that we engage with AI. Um, these
dimensions, if you look at them in just
a second, are going to maybe seem
familiar to some of you, and that's
because they're an open remix of the
foundational work of my colleague and
friend Dr. Doug Belshaw, um, who wrote
about digital literacies in the early
2000s. and they're aimed at creating a
more nuanced and pluralistic vocabulary
for AI literacies in education. So with
that, I'm going to have my colleague and
friend Dr. Josh Herren share a little
bit more about the study, our conceptual
framing of literacies as pluralistic and
socioulturally situated. And he's also
going to share the findings of our
inquiry on what those constellating sets
of AI literacies were that emerged from
our study.
>> Thank you, Angela. Yes, and I will echo
it's an great opportunity to be here and
um share these results with you all and
but also invite you into the
conversation. So, as Angela mentioned,
we held dozens of conversations uh as
part of this research uh team with
educators from around the world about
what they were seeing happening with AI
in their context and how it was being
used or not used as part of these um
parallel uh purposes and goals uh that
they had personally and professionally
and institutionally.
And uh as these studies ran in parallel
uh with one another from UNESCO and um
the work for this paper, we coded the
data and noticed that findings were very
close to what we are seeing in learning
environments more broadly. And that is
that we need an interrelated
competencies, skills and mindsets uh to
build instruction rather than knowledge
of just one tool for one purpose. Um,
and we also knew that these literacies
were about more than tools because
they're about culture. And again, we see
uh so much of this in in the uh digital
learning space. And Angela has uh framed
it as the three C's u coming out of
focusing on people, objects, and events.
It's how we collaborate, how we create,
and how we connect to our community. And
from there uh with the remixing of Doug
Bell Shaw's um dimension uh digital
literacies the dimensions of AI
literacies were born and we'll get to
the next slide and uh share the
definition of what are AI literacies. Uh
and yes, we are intentionally using
plural and there's much to be said about
that and much you can read about why
we're we're doing that uh plural
uhization of the term, but they're
simply put a collection of skills and
knowledge that a person needs to
understand, use, and critically evaluate
artificial intelligence.
They work together. They're
interconnected. And you'll see how that
plays out in in just a moment when we
talk about uh the ways that certain uh
connections uh work out within uh
various regions. They can be expressed
in different ways across diverse
contexts and modalities. They give us a
way to talk about our abilities and how
they can be applied in a rapidly
changing world of education. It's
something that's still going to uh last
next week uh and next month and uh and
has held up for the past year and a half
or so that uh the dimensions of AI
literacies have been used in a variety
of contexts. So they're flexible and
grow with the evolution of AI over time.
And next slide we'll show you the
dimensions.
Uh we're not going to read through all
of these. uh you can uh check those out
at uh the the link there. Uh but each
dimension is essential in its own right
and uh there it's not meant to be a uh
deficit or a gap focus. It's meant to
see where are the strengths at where can
we lean on one another uh and reinforce
one another uh as we build this
constellation and make it useful. uh
they help us map out the broader
landscape of I AI allowing us to move
from one context to another with a sense
of direction and purpose which I know uh
feels hard in the current age of AI and
so as Angel said we're not looking for
one perfect model we're inviting you to
think about AI literacies as a dynamic
constellation this interwoven set of
skills and understandings now on this
next slide you'll see that we're
spotlighting three and um that's because
we saw all uh in in our findings uh
certain literacies uh pop more than
others and so uh constructive AI
literacies and critical AI literacies
were particularly um strong and and
those asked that we use AI tools to
rebuild, remix and generate new content.
So folks were interested in how do we
use these tools? What can they do? Uh
and we saw that connection again to
critical literacies. this idea of are we
using them ethically, equitably, uh are
we uh validating outputs for accuracy?
Are we rushing into uh the usage and and
the trust of of what we're seeing? And
also very concerned about the
environmental impacts. I know that's a
big conversation that we're all having
right now as well. And particularly in
the global south, we saw uh cultural AI
literacies as a an important uh
component and and it's something that we
saw pop uh throughout the study as well.
But this idea, how can we use uh uh AI
to support uh points of engagement from
the tools and the environments
recognizing multilingual support and uh
the contextualized multilingual
collaboration? And then on this slide
you're seeing here, these are uh some of
the ways these interconnected literacies
work together. Uh you'll see that uh
each region has a set of interconnected
uh literacies that uh folks in our
conversations were um curious about,
concerned about, interested in. uh we
won't read through each of these but you
can get a sense from from uh this slide
uh that these uh regional approaches
underline the need to embed cultural
ethical constructive AI literacies into
open ed education in particular and this
integration empowers educators and
learners to navigate AI critically and
responsibly while maintaining the values
of openness
and then in this uh next step slide
we're uh just shining a light on a
pluralistic view uh we're asking you to
join in the conversation uh submit a
case example to help us as we continue
the research on AI literacies by
surfacing these regional perspectives
and practices and then uh you're invited
to u participate in uh the uh events and
courses on uh open culture and the many
resources available to you through uh
this collaboration. And with that, I
believe I'm at time and we want to say
thank you so much.
>> Fantastic. Thank you so much. Up next,
we have Hannah Beth Clark and Margot
Deland to talk about their paper.
>> Great. Again, thank you so much for
having us. Um, at Oak, we've been doing
lots of work on evaluating quality. Um,
and this was a really exciting project
to be able to showcase some of the work
that we've been doing. Um Margot and I
are representing two of the 10 authors
on this paper. Um and we come from a
cross functional team um representing
software engineers u machine learning
engineers um sort of members of our team
working from an education perspective um
and Margo's background is in machine
learning mine's in education and so
hopefully we can provide sort of both
sides of that perspective to you here.
Um so just to give you a bit of sort of
introduction into Oak and and a little
bit more about what who we are as an
organization. Um we were set up during
the pandemic as a response to schools
closing because of COVID. Um and over
the summer holidays produced 10,000 free
resources. Lots of teachers came
together to produce those um that were
free and accessible for pupils to use
and access from home. Um and following
the pandemic, we found that pupils and
teachers were still continuing to access
those resources. And so we received some
government funding to be able to remake
those resources um to a really high
quality and standard. And they're all
available on an open government license.
Um we we hope that by making those
available to teachers and to pupils um
we're able to sort of um improve pupil
outcomes, close the disadvantage gap,
but also help other organizations to
innovate in that space using highquality
underlying curriculum material.
So what do we have on offer at Oak? Um
first of all, we have really high
quality teaching materials and
curricular for teachers. Um we have an
interactive uh platform for pupils.
That's for any pupils that might be
learning from home for any reason or
should we get to a point of school
closures due to extreme weather or um
hopefully not another pandemic, we'd
have a sort of um remote education back
stop. Um and then finally um we've been
experimenting with AI building an AI
lesson assistant um which is called ISA
and the name comes from um AI lesson
assistant but its meaning is um oak tree
in Hebrew and from strong roots in um in
Scottish Gaelic which we felt was really
appropriate for for the use case. Um and
we're going to talk specifically today
about our AI lesson assistant Isa.
Could you just go one back? Sorry.
Thanks. Uh yeah, perfect. So um we were
in a really strong position to innovate
with AI. Um and there were sort of four
things that put us into this position.
The first was we have an incredibly um
rich high quality corpus of content. We
have nearly 13,000 lessons and resources
um that have been created by expert
humans and quality assured um by subject
experts that we were able to use to
innovate in this space. We also had lots
of expertise in curriculum design um
from from the lessons and resources that
we'd been creating. We had as an
organization an agreed definition of
quality um which was really useful for
building our prompt. Um and finally we
had cross functional team made up of all
of those different sort of parts
including machine learning engineers but
also lots of expertise from the sort of
education perspective.
Um I'm going to give you just a very
quick brief glimpse into ISA. um
hopefully on the next slide. Um if
anyone wants to have a go with using
ISA, you're very welcome to. Um but ISA
is designed to take a teacher through
planning a lesson step by step. Um
allowing them to personalize that
content for their specific learners. Um
sort of embodying best practice in terms
of pedagogy and cognitive science um to
support them in producing really high
quality lessons and resources that are
going to be useful for them in in the
classroom. And we've intentionally
designed that so that's a co-planning
process for the teacher. Um it's not
just doing all of the hard work for
them. It's asking for their feedback and
their review as they go through. And
after this lesson's been created,
they're able to download adaptable
resources that they can then use within
their classroom. Next slide. Thanks. So
what makes ISA different from other AI
tools? Um firstly, we've got um you can
just pop them all up, Shar. Thanks. Um
firstly, we've got an incredibly
detailed UK specific prompt. Um, we've
codified best practice in in pedigogy
and cognitive science to ensure that the
outputs of ISA are incredibly high
quality. Um, we use retrieval augmented
generation and content anchoring to
bring in that content from our human
created corpus of content. We've got a
whole range of additional safety
guardrails um to ensure that our tool is
really safe for use in the classroom.
And finally, we're keeping the teacher
in the driving seat and we've ensured
the outputs of our tool are really
useful.
So, we've talked a bit about ISA. We're
now going to move on to talk about auto
evaluation. Um, and we want to start off
with the problem here. So, uh, next
slide. Thanks. So, the problem for us is
that, um, AI generated content is, um,
sort of rapidly, uh, being launched into
the market and it's really important
that this specific content is being
evaluated and we wanted to place
ourselves as sort of leaders in this
space. um making sure that there was
importance placed on the quality of
content that was being produced and how
this could then be used in the
classroom. Going to hand over to Margot.
Thank you Hannah Beth. Yes. So with our
focus Oh, back to the previous slide
please. So with our focus on evaluation,
not only can we highlight areas for
improvement, but also it means that
whenever we make changes to ISA, whether
that be new versions of the prompt, uh
using different model models or
adjusting parameters, it allows us to
take a really datadriven approach and
really evaluate the effects that those
changes have. Next slide, please. Now,
the way that we do this is with auto
evaluation, also known as like LLM as
judge, where we essentially ask an LLM
to evaluate content for us using a
prompt. Um and we've designed our own
auto valuation tool which allows us to
do this at scale. So we have 24 uh
benchmarks 24 of these tests in the form
of prompts uh which are a mixture of
tests based on both Oak's pedagogical
rubric for example increasing quiz
difficulty which looks at if the
questions in a quiz are getting harder
um or like common quality issues for
example Americanisms which we hope to
avoid. Uh and what we ask the LLM for is
a score either one to between one and
five where five is ideal or a boolean
output true false if it's well suited to
the test as well as a justification so
we can really track the LLM's reasoning
and we get the justification to be
output before the score due to the
predictive nature of Genai so that
hopefully the the justification
influences the score and not vice versa.
Next slide please. So yeah, it's all
good and well having all these LLMs, you
know, outputting all these different uh
evaluations for us, but unless they're
uh aligned with expert humans, how can
we really trust them? So our goal for
this paper was to get our auto
evaluations to align with expert humans,
i.e. teachers. And the prompt that we
chose was answers are minimally
different, which just looks at what we
call the distractors of a multiple
choice quiz question. So the incorrect
answers, compares them to the answer,
and basically sees if it's too obvious
or not. Next slide, please. And we chose
this one because we ran around 5,000
lessons through our auto evaluation tool
and picked one of the ones where the LLM
was um judging very harshly. So you can
see in the second row the scores are
quite low. Um and out of the ones that
was judging harshly, this was quite a
digestible task. We didn't have to
present the teacher with too much
information. Next slide please.
Um yeah, so what we did so we ran auto
evaluation a number of quiz questions.
Um, we took these same quiz questions,
gave them to the teachers, making sure
they each saw questions over across a
range of quality. Um, we collected 311
of these. Uh, we then conducted thematic
analysis on the scores and well on the
justifications for particular scores.
Um, as well as pulling out
representative examples, took that
information, threw it back into the
prompt, and then compared the alignment
before and after. And next slide,
please. So, it worked. So we found a
statistically significant improvement in
alignment between our auto evaluation
tool and the human evaluations. Um the
three overarching categories that we got
were what makes a good distractor
essentially was plausibility,
commonality and structural coherence.
And not only were we able to improve the
auto evaluation prompt, but through
being able to define what makes a good
distractor, we could improve the ISA
prompt itself. But perhaps the more
important finding um even though
alignment's great is that the
justifications the LLM gave ended up
aligning more with what the teachers
were thinking. And so it could be the
case that um the LLM is really a more
consistent evaluator. Um so as long as
it's in line with the themes that's uh
that's the goal really. So yeah, next
slide please.
Great. So um we obviously published this
paper a few months ago. Um but we've got
lots of other areas that we're working
on um that sort of build on this
specific part of auto evaluation. The
first is we're looking at our safety
guard rails. As I mentioned earlier, we
have a number of additional safety guard
rails to ensure our tool is safe for use
um and the content that's provided is
appropriate for use in schools. Um and
so we're using our auto evaluation tool
to help us to ensure that that aligns to
human uh human judgments on that. We
also um are hoping to build in live
evaluations so that the auto evaluation
tool is um is reviewing the content
that's being produced as it's being
produced rather than async um and is
able to provide the teacher with
feedback on on areas of the lesson that
they might want to go back and improve
as well as going back through and making
automatic updates. Um and then finally
we're looking at um some agentic
approaches. um first of all agentic
approaches to this sort of auto
evaluation um challenge but also to um
different sections of our of our tool
and how we can build that in to to
improve efficiency and um and quality of
our outputs. Um we're really excited to
answer some questions at the end. Um but
if you have any other further questions
after this then please don't hesitate to
get in touch. Our email addresses are up
on the screen.
>> Wonderful. Thank you so much. that we
will now enter the discussion between
the respondent and the co-authors before
opening up to your questions. Again,
make use of that Q&A function to let
your comments and questions and concerns
and enthusiasm be heard. Um, and we will
circle back to them. So, I will stop
that and now we have Nick in
conversation with Angela, Josh, Hannah
Beth, and Margot.
>> Awesome. Thank you so much uh for that
wonderful work and uh for sharing it.
And I want to start with you know just a
small question for Angela and Josh
because I know you love these little
questions. Um one of the things that you
point to in the paper is um the idea
that that literacies are socially
socially constructed. They're culturally
constructed and that they vary around
the world. you noted that um but we also
know that the concept of literacy has
been used harmfully throughout history
in a number of different kind of
settings and I'm wondering about the
idea of AI literacy if if we don't get
to the point where the stuff that you're
pushing back against in considering it
as a multi- as a pluralistic kind of
approach to literacies if we think of it
in this binary you either have it or you
don't might we see a world that pushes
is that where AI literacy becomes
another kind of tool for preventing
people from access having access to
things and and might um might openness
be an antidote to that?
>> I I love this question. I could probably
fill up a full couple of hours talking
about this both from a challenges and an
opportunities perspective. Um there um
have been many many many conversations
around us validating the outputs of AI
and really looking at whose privileged
uh whose power is on display based on
the outputs but also how are we thinking
about training these models um around uh
what Josh had mentioned before around
the ethical uh pieces the equitable
pieces and the and the impact and um
when we think about AI literacies uh
within this plurality.
What it does is it also allows us to get
back to our values and those values are
defined within communities. Certainly um
the open community has very specific
values that we're that we're using and
that we are um talking about within our
perspectives and our practices both. So
yes, I I think that while we're in this
very uh tense space and in this tense
moment in time, having conversations
around vocabulary, which was our hope
with uh creating a taxonomy and not a
framework is the way that we can start
to chip away um at what is in support of
our values. uh whether it's how tools
are used but also how tools are created
and contextualized and what that tool
usage means from a community or a
cultural aspect. Um we have to start
with that dialogic moment before we can
get to determining okay and now is how
we actually um use these tools uh from
from sort of a more technical or
operational perspective.
Wonderful. Um
I think
uh a question for Hannah Beth and Margo
then uh you were working with a pool of
content that kind of belonged to a
particular community.
um you know and I'm wondering whether
uh that made a difference in how you
trained that model and kind of the the
quality of the output that you that you
saw. Um, also wondering a little bit
about uh one of the things we talk about
in the open community is as as a
challenge is we've openly licensed
material for the good of everyone and
lots of these uh AI companies come along
and hoover it up as a um as a part of
what they do. And in this case, you have
a a a group of content that was already
designed to be used by that community.
wondering how you thought about kind of
consent and and uh using that content
for training the AA tool.
>> Yeah, that's a great question. Um Marggo
might be able to jump in on some of the
sort of more tech technical aspects of
this. Um there was a question in the
chat about whether we're using a sort of
underlying large language model and at
the moment we're using GPT40. Um we've
tried to make the tool as sort of model
agnostic as possible so that we can move
to different models or potentially move
different aspects of to different models
as we go forward.
Um, but we're not at the moment training
a model underneath. We're using
retrieval augmented generation to bring
in content from our corpus um to improve
the accuracy of of the tool. Um, and I
think for us it was that sort of
situating it in our local context was
really important. We wanted to make sure
that it was designed um for UK schools
um specifically for the UK and that
context here and our national curriculum
um but also for for that sort of
specific age range of pupils and and
making sure the content was really
appropriate for them. I think there's
nothing more frustrating as a teacher um
as using an AI tool that then produces
something that's totally irrelevant to
what you you need to teach as part of
your curriculum. Um I think for us we
were in a really fortunate position
where we had this huge corpus of
content. Um and again that's sort of
available for others to make use of
which is really exciting. Um but that
was very specific to our use case and it
enabled us to sort of innovate on top of
that. And I think for other
organizations in other countries and
other regions, um, thinking about how
they're going to, um, sort of source
that high quality underlying content to
use within their tool is really
important, um, for them to be able to
sort of, you know, make sure that that's
aligned to their context and their their
outputs.
>> I one of the things I noticed that was
really interesting in your paper as
well, Hannah Beth and Margo, was that
um, on that first run through
the AI evaluation agent was kind of
harsher or stricter than uh than the
human evaluators.
And I guess a controversial question for
you is it possible that the AI was
actually applying or better at applying
assessment theory in that situation to
um uh to the design of multiple choice
questions in this in this case. Um, and
I wonder what the implications of that
are down the track if people to were to
use these, you know, perhaps less
critically than than with your technical
knowledge or uh, you know, our other
authors as well. How how does that
what's likely to happen if we kind of
unleash these tools on lots of people
um, who may not know what underlies
them?
Just to add a little bit of context for
people who haven't read the paper, the
things that um the LLM was sort of
overly focusing on um before we changed
it was um you know uh focusing on how
deep the understanding it was testing
was for each of the key stages. Um and
whilst that's a good thing to focus on
and it should be sort of keystage
dependent um and we still gave the
teachers the key stage and we still gave
the prompt the key stage now um it
wasn't a thing that the teachers
themselves were overly focusing on. So
even though it might be valid and maybe
the LLM was doing a genuinely good job,
um we decided to have our standard of
quality based on just what the teachers
themselves would tend to focus on. Um so
yeah, even if the LLM was doing a good
job, um and maybe that's something to
look into like what it tended to focus
on and if that was um applying some
sorts of things that we didn't think
about. Um I think we wanted our standard
for quality to be based on wholly what
the teachers were doing.
I think it's also worth saying that um I
think at points the the LLM was applying
those evaluation criteria with more sort
of um consistency maybe than our humans
were um it enabled us to work out some
categories that that even from the
thematic analysis of human
justifications um that I think if you'd
asked a human what made a good multiple
choice distractor they maybe wouldn't
have identified themselves. Um, but we
were able to pull that out either from
the justifications from the LLM or from
the justifications that were given by
the human and then feed those back into
our into our AI sort of prompt and back
in both for the auto evaluation and for
the um prompt that was helping us to
generate those lesson questions. Um, but
I think it's really important as an
organization to have decided what your
sort of measure of quality is because
you can obviously look at multiple
choice questions and what high quality
looks like from lots of different
aspects. Um, and for us, we wanted to
just make sure that that auto evaluation
was really aligned to what our human
evaluators, our expert teachers were
saying. Um, so that we could start to
generalize some of the the findings of
that to make improvements to our tool
and and to sort of evaluate quality on a
bigger scale.
Angela and Josh,
to some extent it sounds like, you know,
when uh this reminds me a little bit of
your your idea of the the black hole,
right? That the the potential for some
AI is to kind of crush the complexity of
human nature into it and and what uh
what Hannibbeth and Marggo were looking
for is ways to maintain that uh
complexity.
What kind of things were you kind of
seeing from the people that you were
talking to when you're asking about
competencies that they were looking for?
Um were they imagining that as a
challenge? Were they were they trying to
hold on to that kind of rich human
complexity?
Yeah, I think that um one of the most
common things that we saw in terms of
the conversations that we had with the
educators, especially the open
practitioners, was that they were
grappling with the complex uh mixed and
nuanced emotions that existed within the
communities within which they were
serving. Um we've seen this uh
historically show up within um open
education as well when we talk about
lensure and you know in the beginning
some of the early conversations around
licensing were hey let's make everything
open be as open as you possibly can be
but what we found is that in certain
geographic areas of the world it was a
privilege to be uh at a certain level of
openness or even that you might feel
that you could be open in a particular
moment in time in a certain way, but
based on bad actors, based on changes in
the world, based on politics and the
climate within which you were living, it
was no longer safe for you to be open or
your values or feelings may have changed
around what openness could be for you.
We're seeing the same thing with AI.
We're seeing that um any sort of
monolithic approaches that we're taking
where we're trying to um determine how
everybody collectively feels and we see
this even with students. You know, all
students are using AI to cheat. uh you
know those sweeping judgments that we're
making don't really reflect not only the
the complex feelings that folks have
around AI and its usage um but also how
those feelings are changing over time
especially as AI is evolving and
changing. A tool that you may support
one day uh may not be one that you
support later on. So, um, I I love the
work that Hannah Beth and Margot are
doing and along with their team because
they're really bridging that gap between
the the operational piece and the the
building of something tangible and
active, but also creating space for
folks to talk about how do we feel about
this usage and how is this usage
changing how we think about AI?
And I just to add to to what Angela said
there is is this idea of the technology
is not going to be the determiner right
um that it's it is a discourse-based um
plurality of experiences and as the map
showed um folks were interested uh in
different interconnected literacies um
depending on the region they were in but
also I would even say it depends on what
classroom you're in right um as to how
open and how vulnerable even the faculty
member is on um how AI is being used and
and their openness to it and uh so I I
think that's uh an interesting way to um
look at that question of you know what's
the technology going to do rather than
it's one piece in a conversation and
even you know uh this idea of
prioritizing it as an object over uh
what we bring to the table uh is uh
troublesome right but I do love the you
know what what's happening with Ayah
here is the perfect example of how
you're iterating based on something like
the literacies and competencies. So uh
love it.
>> I hate to interrupt but there's so many
juicy questions coming through the Q&A
that are relevant to a lot of the things
that people are talking about. So if
it's okay with the group I'll go ahead
and start introducing those into our
conversation. Uh the first question
we'll highlight is from Pablo Chiaza and
the question is in teaching that
requires hands-on practice such as
technical skills like carpentry, welding
and blacksmithing, how do you think AI
can combine theoretical and practical
teaching and provide feedback on it? And
this question is for anybody.
>> Maybe I'll I'll open the floor with this
one. Um I think it's a great question. I
think um at the moment within ISA we've
focused uh initially on sort of
classroom based lessons with our design
of the tool um but but actually we've
done lots of experimentation with people
who are working in all sorts of
different context and it will plan
really great lessons for um in the UK we
have alternative provisions where pupils
um aren't able to attend mainstream
schools normally because of a behavioral
reason um and the curriculum won't
follow a sort of traditional
um national curriculum subject that we
have here and they might be doing things
like ship building or planting gardens
or all sorts of other types of um
activity um and Isa will take the
principles that we've we've sort of um
codified into it and enable um teachers
to still produce really high quality
lessons that that they can deliver in
those contexts. Um I think as with
everything uh the more um highquality
examples that you can give AI tools of
of what sort of exceptional practice
looks like in that area the better the
outputs will be and so I think it's a
really exciting spa space that will
hopefully um develop lots as we go
forward. Um there was also a sort of
mention of how do we then provide
feedback. I'm assuming that that's maybe
on um on outputs of of what people are
doing. Um there's a really interesting
uh sort of experiment happening at the
moment with um uh a government funded
project where they're looking at
soldering and soldering of um different
sort of uh technical devices I think um
and they're using AI to provide feedback
to the pupils on their on their
soldering and um how they've gone about
implementing that. So I think we'll see
lots of innovation in that space going
forward. But I think that really high
quality um examples that we can give to
the AI model is is really integral
there.
>> Just super briefly, I want to plus one
that and add that uh Josh and I in
addition to coming from a teaching
background, we also come from an
instructional design background and some
of the early conversations around AI
were, you know, how can AI replace
teachers? How can AI replace or will it
replace instructional designers? But um
what we're seeing from the research and
from practice is that AI actually can be
used as a tool to enable us to get to
the higher order thinking, the active
learning and the experiential learning
that we've been begging our field to get
to for for quite some time. So thinking
through what are the assessments that
we're creating, what are the intended
learning outcomes, and how can AI be a
co-partner, a coach, a mentor, um that
guides us into that active learning and
that learning that is um getting us to
the the deeper funds of knowledge that
we've we've wanted to hit um is is
absolutely uh on the table, on the
horizon, and we're seeing more and more
educators heading in that direction.
The um the next question I see Angela
you wanted to answer live and I think
it's a fascinating question. I think we
could open it up to everybody as well
and that's from an anonymous attendee
who asks if one intends to develop some
curriculum to develop AI literacy among
students and faculty given the
dimensions it would have to be very
comprehensive. What do you see as the
starting point and what could the
minimal starting point be?
>> I I adore this question. I know that
when you're looking out at what needs to
be done, it can feel like a massive
challenge and and pretty deflating. Uh
but one thing that I always guide people
into doing is starting from a place of
strengths, looking at current strengths
and then moving into intended outcomes.
So when you think about AI literacy's
development uh not only amongst learners
but also amongst faculty and the leaders
the administrators um getting to know
your stakeholders in which AI literacies
are appearing naturally in their work
perhaps have been happening um
undercover and surfacing them uh is a
really empowering way to start and then
from there uh we recommend that you move
towards which AI literacy ies can be
incorporated naturally through
professional development through remix
practices uh to lead to that uh AI
literacy's development over time knowing
that there's never going to be a finish
line there's never going to be a moment
where we say oh we're done let's
high-five uh we're all we're all
literate um there's no baggage that we
have to carry in terms of a point of
perfection or completion uh because our
AI literacies development is ongoing And
um we put the link in the chat earlier.
We should put it in there again, but uh
as part of the findings of this
research, we actually put together um a
free miniourse that's online. Anybody
can take it. We have educators from all
over the globe that are taking it that
really gives you some practical ways to
get started on just this question, not
just the theoretical pieces that I
shared just now.
>> Fantastic. Marco and Hannah Beth, is
there anything you want to add for that
question or Nick?
just I think it's going to become a
really important part of the curriculum
across schools and I think sort of
starting that really young and making
sure that that's part of um sort of how
we're teaching pupils to use sort of
technology safely and and responsibly is
is really important and so it's really
exciting to hear that that work's
already happening.
Our next question comes from Diego
Viauses who asks, "How can we encourage
the use of AI in the social sciences
among those who oppose it due to its
gender and cultural biases?"
And this is a wild card for everybody.
>> I'm happy to I keep on jumping in all of
>> No, kick us off. I think that would be
great. Do it. Yeah, these are great
questions.
um we build the environments that um
that we live within. We've built these
structures over time. We've imbued these
structures with our biases um with our
um both on and unknown or known and
unknown discriminatory practices. So the
work here is not um avoiding and sitting
back, but it's being proactive, being um
open about the challenges that exist and
exist for you specifically. Um, I I
definitely wear my identity into all of
the work that I go into as a bipok woman
from the global north, uh, native
English speaker, and I I let all of that
be known in all of the work that I put
out there so that I can signal to other
people that they can and should be open
about their perspective. So, we have a
call right now um to to do better. And
again, um, the open community has very
mature practices for doing this work,
for creating content that is culturally
affirming, uh, creating content that
supports the diverse perspectives and
lived experiences of all of the
stakeholders that are involved in
education. Um, so this is a time for us
to lean in and the only way that we can
signal to other people that it's safe to
lean in is if we're doing that
ourselves.
I think
>> I love the Sorry,
>> sorry. I say I think that it highlights
why evaluation is so important in the
first place. Like cultural bias is
something that we evaluate for and so
doing that allows you to be proactive
and sort of um check as you go.
I was just going to add to to that piece
that that both of you spoke so so um
particularly about is this um need to be
proactive but also um vulnerable. Uh
Angela used the word safe, right? It's
safe uh to to talk about uh what we're
bringing to the table. I remember when
we were putting together um the UNESCO
report in in particular, Angeline had a
lot of conversation about what we were
bringing to the conversation and trying
to represent a global perspective,
right? And I think that's u part of the
important pieces behind the scenes is
that you are proactive, you're thinking
about that intentionally and that um uh
from the classroom to the strategy
level, right? folks are uh open about
challenges and opportunities, gains and
losses uh that happens within any uh
digital transformation.
>> I'm noticing that there's um there's a
couple of other authors from the
initiative that are posting some really
wonderful questions um in the chat that
we are answering by text or that are
being touched on. So, I'm going to go
ahead and ask our team to put um the
links to those other author's papers in
the chat for people to read from Jo and
Dan Magcguire as well. Um our next
question, there's actually two questions
related to this and I'll read the one
from Roia Mosur. I apologize if I'm
mispronouncing your name. And the
question is, as an EFL language teacher,
I wonder how I could possibly benefit
from AI.
Well, I was going to I I've sort of
answered a very similar one in the in
the chat. Um Angela might have more to
add to this, but um we've been talking
lots about this as being a a great use
of ISA and um and sort of the ability to
enable teachers to adapt their content
for um pupils who are speaking um other
languages within their their classroom.
Um at the moment lots of those are
requiring a teacher to have the sort of
knowledge and expertise of the
adaptations that they'd want to make for
those those specific pupils. Um, but
we've been talking lots about how we can
codify best practice in that space, but
also in the sort of SEND space to make
those adaptations easier for teachers to
use, um, and enable us to sort of
showcase best practice in that area. Um,
but I feel like that's a a huge sort of
piece of work that we're we're just
starting to explore at the at the edges.
Um, and so it's really exciting that
that's that's, you know, the
conversation that you're bringing up.
Um, and we're really keen to have
feedback. So if you if you've seen
things that work really well or if there
are things that you'd like us to have a
go with um sort of implementing, please
get in touch with us. We'd be really
keen to hear from you.
So I am going to circle back to one more
question um that was raised that I'm
curious how you would say it even though
we've been talking kind of around it and
touching on it and it's this question
from Joel, one of the other co-authors.
And then we're going to invite the
initiative's principal investigator uh
to join the conversation, Christopher
Capazola, who's also the senior
associate dean of MIT open learning to
um to join us for the last five minutes
in our conversation. Joelle's question
is, in what ways do you think AI tools
might redefine the role of teachers in
education?
And Nick, feel free to tackle this as
well since I know you grapple with this.
I kick us off.
>> Yeah, recently a teacher. Um I was
teaching until last summer. So this is a
very um sort of poignant question for
me. I think um there's been lots of in
the UK definitely lots of conversation
about whether AI is going to replace
teachers or sort of take over their
role. Um, I think those of us that sort
of look at it with that lens are
probably um, sort of thinking about the
aspects of what makes great teachers as
being something quite different to what
I would consider. Um, I think lots of,
um, great teaching is about the human
connection that you make with pupils and
and that supports pupils in sort of
progressing and um, sort of achieving
things during their time at school. Um I
think AI has the the capacity to be able
to support teachers with some of the
things that take them lots of time. Um
lots of people are leaving the classroom
in the UK. Workload is really high.
Teachers are maybe teaching five or six
lessons a day um across different year
groups potentially across different
subjects and planning really high
quality content for all of the pupils in
their in their classroom is really
challenging. Um, and so I think my hope
is that that the use of AI will help
teachers to do some of those tasks that
don't require um, sort of their
expertise. Um, and that will free up
their time and capacity to be able to do
some of those more human aspects of
teaching that we think are really
important. I don't think it's great use
of a teacher's time to be, you know,
formatting a worksheet or translating
something from one language into
another. But I do think thinking really
carefully about how your pupils are
going to access a concept or how you're
going to support a specific pupil who
maybe have some additional needs is is a
really integral part of teaching that
often we just don't have time for
because we're running from one activity
to another. Um and so I hope that that
that's sort of the direction that AI
heads in.
>> Thank you. Other thoughts that anyone
else wants to add?
ju just that uh I would say that we're
in a a moment in time where us
considering this as an opportunity uh
beyond just a challenge to respond to
allows us to get to a future of
education where AI is positioned to
allow us to do the work that we got into
education in the in the first place to
get to that deeper learning uh to
building those systems of care uh and to
really innovating in ways that are far
more inclusive than we've been able to
be up until this moment. So, I'm excited
to be on this journey with all of you.
>> You're here. Thank you so much. So, in
our final few minutes, I'm bringing in
uh Christopher Capazola, who is at um
again our senior associate dean at MIT
Open Learning, the principal
investigator of the AI and open
education speaker series. He's also
faculty of history at MIT. Uh so, Chris,
what are you noticing in these last
couple minutes? And Nick, feel free to
join us as well.
Yeah, I would just uh say that in
response to Shar's last question,
Hannibbeth and Angela's answers were um
you know were just uh spoton and really
sort of um uh addressing that
intersection between AI and open
education that motivated us to launch
this uh this paper series. And I've had
the privilege to work with the with some
of the authors and and with our uh with
our editor Sarah Schwepman and with the
the whole team here at Open Learning to
kind of launch this. And this webinar
really captures what exactly what we
were trying to do, right? Um the last
hour has been really both technically
rich and also culturally thoughtful. Um
and I was really struck by that, right?
That I think we're into a phase now u
you know far beyond where we were in you
know 2022, right? where where people are
now talking, you know, really talking
shop about tools, but also, you know,
asking and demanding answers to some of
the hard questions um about how these
systems will work in the real world that
we're moving into. Um so, you know, just
huge thanks um to, you know, to to the
authors, to the respondents, to about,
you know, 150 200 people who uh you
know, tuned in for this. The other part
is that we really wanted to create a
global community of practice. Um and so
I am really excited um that people are
tuning in you know and I hope that
people will go to the pub pub platform
you know use uh use its interactive and
open features to kind of carry on this
conversation as we move forward because
I think many of us are kind of craving
uh a place to have that conversation at
the intersection of AI and open um and
and third you know we called them rapid
response papers for a reason um first of
all to thank our authors for for writing
them um you know rapidly uh but also we
know u that they will uh very soon be
out of date. Um so we hope that they
will be out of date because we are
advancing um really fast both on the
technical improvements and on the
cultural uh and political thought that
that needs to happen. Um and that's
exactly what the the open ed community
uh has tried to do over the last 20 to
40 years. Um and it's also what what the
the technical community brings to this
conversation right now. So a huge thanks
all around and um and you know the
reward for for doing a lot of uh great
work is is to is to do more great work.
So looking forward to to the to more.
>> Fantastic. Thank you so much Chris and
thank you to all of our co-authors and
everyone that participated in the
initiative and to our respondent Nick.
Um we put some ways to stay engaged in
the chat. We're just so grateful for the
work that's being done and this um
public engaged conversation that we are
having. We look forward to having more
of them in other forms uh in the future.
So I will pass the baton to Nick Baker
to sign us off and to thank everyone
again.
>> Thank you so much. Uh this hour went so
quickly. Um I I want to just say a
couple of things. one is I I love the
metaphor of the of literacies as part of
the night sky as you know that there's
just such a huge richness of it and I
think it's important because we tend to
talk about AI as this monolithic thing
as well but the reality is that that
this is a language that we use to
describe lots and lots of different
things that are sometimes connected and
sometimes not and they all require us to
think about it a little bit differently
um especially in the way that they're
that they're applied to our societies.
And the last thing I want to end with is
um Andrew Maynard talks about this idea
of a playground versus a play pen. And I
think we're I I like this idea of us
working in a playground as opposed to a
play pen where someone else has control
of of what we're allowed to do in there.
And there are times when we probably
should be put inside a play pen
sometimes for the decisions that we
make. But the playground is this kind of
rich space where different perspectives
and values come together where there are
some scary parts of the playground.
There is a boundary, you know, roughly
around the outside and there are some
teachers there to help us figure out how
to navigate working with each other in
that space. And I think that's what um
AI and openness coming together um kind
of forms at this point. So, thank you so
much for for all of your work and for
continuing this great conversation.
>> Wonderful. Thank you again, everyone.
Um, and we'll see you next time,
whatever shape and form that may take.