One thing we're noticing is that we are
very quickly moving from LLMs and chat
bots to AI agents. And this is going to
open up an entirely new way of
collaborating with AI and producing
productivity, performance, creativity,
and other types of gains from
investments in AI. So what is this
agentic age? What are these AI agents?
Chat bots can produce text. Image
diffusion models can produce images, but
AI agents can reason and they have
multimodal capabilities to access
information on their own, to access the
web, to make decisions, to take actions.
They can essentially do almost
everything that a human can do. This is
the next era of human AI collaboration.
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learnmit.edu.
[Music]