I didn't get any new topics that people
wanted uh throughout the day so I'm
going to go through some topics that
people have uh T talk asked about
earlier in this semester and um that I
think are are kind of fun and so they're
sort of the the most fun things that
from my perspective maybe I have a six
sense of fun uh that that we didn't
fully cover so one of the first things I
want to talk about is a cool little
two-part um uh you what do you call this
a fable a moral uh moral story um that
has a little conclusion at the end and
something called Gap fill I'm pretty
sure I've talked about this a couple
times in different places but I'm pretty
sure I did not do this this semester did
I no good good okay because there
there's three points in the semester
where this could have gone one is
anytime we started talking about David
Hon's work um and this is one of the
very cool papers he's the second author
Paul Von hipple a very uh very well
established uh scholar and of Music
perception and cognition um did this
study in around fall 2000 published in
Fall 2000 so it's about uh 25 year 25
years since they did this and it's a one
of these really cool things that got me
into this field U so when I heard about
this I was like this is why I want to
use computers to do things so um has
anybody ever uh you all have some
encounter with species Counterpoint
because you did uh you read the um the
David Luen article on an interesting
Global rule for Counterpoint so it's
dealing with sort of 16th century
musical style and how we can recreate it
and one of the rules that I was taught
when I learned uh species Counterpoint
is that if you take a big leap and you
go up you've created a gap and the most
natural thing for your musical line to
do is to go down after that fill in the
Gap Gap fill uh some people spell it as
one word some hyphen some as space it
doesn't I don't really care Gap fill
similarly you leap down a lot and you
should go
up and um so I immediately looked at um
a piece by Giovani palestrina uh one of
the most important composers in this
period that species Counterpoint is
based on uh around 1550 1570 or so um
this is part of one of his masses and um
here's the score you see it but I've
also kind of colored things in that uh
green notes are upward leaps that need a
downward um thing after it so um things
and then the Blue Notes a downward leap
that needs an upward motion and all
around here it's all stepwise so it can
go any direction it wants so if Gap fill
exists then then uh and every time
there's Gap fill fulfilled every time it
works there's um a little uh pink or
Peach Dot and every time it's not
there's a big yellow Dot and you can see
there are no yellow dots up there so
this is what this sounds
[Music]
like do that one more time so you can
hear it
[Music]
I just had to add the last note
otherwise it'd be kind of out there um
so Gap fill seems to be a thing
composers do this but um the really cool
thing that uh that hippo Von hippo and
hiron did was that they realized that
there's two things happening when you
leap up a lot one is you've you've
created a big leap right the other is
that you're higher in your voice
range so
um if if I'm down here and I leap up and
then I leap up then I Le up you guys are
going to bet that eventually I'm going
to come down right yeah uh you can't
really go up forever and so what they
were wondering is does it have to do the
fact that eventually when you get really
high the only place to go is down
especially if you're talking about vocal
music or well I mean even on a piano
eventually you got to come down so they
looked at um what the median what the
average pitch across a whole piece was
and marked it as specific and then
thought that hey there's um there's four
kinds of leaps and can't um there's ones
that start at or above the median and go
even higher that's when I was doing this
and I yeah up there then there's ones
that start below the median and go above
it there's ones that start below and
reach the median and then like I started
the ones that start below and after they
leap up they're still pretty low so
there's still below the
median and
that there might be something besides
Gap fill that explains things for
instance let's say you bought two
domestic continental US
flights first you flow from San
Francisco to New York City now you have
another
flight just take a guess uh you've gone
from well instead of up and down we'll
say west east you've gone from west to a
big thing on the East and now you board
let's say a random flight after this
it's it's pre 911 you could just board
random flights you all don't remember
that World um
so what do you which direction do you
think you're likely to go you you're not
in the international section west or
east west west why because there's so
many more options of going west from New
York than there are from um
yeah then there are East I guess we
that's that's a little too far for
Portland I mean but yeah you can kind of
get the picture um and so if
you're if you're already above the
median you have a lot more choices going
down than up and what they
predicted was that um a lot of these
things would happen even by chance that
if you went um if you you jumped up up
above from a normal note and and you big
do a big J Jump Up you're probably above
the median and you're going to Gap fill
just by the concept of regression to the
mean and so I went and um took that
exact same piece from uh pal I guess
I've been doing the same thing I did
with a bcde e f for a long time of just
taking pieces and scrambling them
remember when we were doing the
similarity one I just scrambled all the
notes so here's the exact same Melody
[Music]
scrambled and again everything that that
demands by the theory of Gap fill Motion
in the opposite direction than where it
just came I've marked um with a green or
blue and I've marked with peach when it
works I've marked with a big yellow dot
when it doesn't and in this scrambled
and this was the first random run I did
I didn't run it a whole bunch of times
until I got one that worked it works
perfectly so there what they argued was
that this concept of Gap fill as
something un in music could actually
just be explained by regression to the
mean and I thought this is really really
cool um the thing I noticed looking at
this article for the first time you uh
in the mid what do you call them the a
the 2000 to 2009 something was looking
at the data that they had um to do this
and so they had um some uh songs Leader
by Schubert they had European folk songs
where do you think that came from from
anybody European folk songs and Chinese
folk songs that's always that's the ESS
in data set so they had this data sets
been around for a while and they had
some other things South African and obj
uh Native American folk songs and um you
can kind of see when uh when you're
going all the you're already high and
you go even higher then the odds are
you're going to turn down when you're
here you you're going to come back down
right and so that's very statically
significant and when you start in a
normal range and end in a high range
you're still probably going to go down
and they saw that a lot this is not just
down this is other direction but I'll
assume for a second that everything is
leaping up but then when you get right
to the median you kind of see that you
go about 5050 in either direction and
when you um when you start low and you
go up but you're still
low the that um more often than not you
just continue going up there is no Gap
fill or or it's kind of reverse Gap fill
or some something like that um so I'm
you know somebody uh developing music 21
and I I kind of look at these numbers
which are probably from like 1998 or
something now it's 2010 2012 I'm
teaching here doing this type of stuff
and I look at their sample size they
have you know 60 86 examples of
something like this and 101 of something
else because it took a long time to
encode music then it still takes a long
time but we've gotten things better
there's more data sets out there so I
thought about running it for um think it
was originally to think of as a problem
set for this class to to you know let's
validate Von hipple and Hon's work um
but it turned into a little bit more and
it turned into uh a paper that my friend
Mark who's probably going to watch this
at some point we do still need to finish
publishing it we've presented it many
times but
published uh species or species on
various rules for species Counterpoint
that uh don't seem to actually exist in
the literature uh
because when we ran the same thing you
can see we have a a lot more data
examples and when we looked at the
Chinese folk songs we also saw the same
thing that Von hipple and hiron did that
there is a lot more evidence for R to
the mean regression to the mean than
there is for Gap Phill and when uh we
looked at the European Essen data set we
still saw the same thing and all these
things so um I get got to do the nice
validation study that I thought we would
do and I thought would' make a nice
assignment for us all and everything
until I looked at um music before Bach
the music of the era that we do species
Counterpoint on why we have species
Counterpoint exercises and it turned out
there that for these uh weird pieces
where you're jumping up above the mean
or something like that that Gap fill
happens more often than regression to
the
mean and so for these like low going to
here and then you would expect
regression to mean you should still go
up there did seem to be a period where
people were actually doing Gap fill and
so that was was pretty uh was pretty
neat and um so it just shows that
sometimes and you get a new data set you
should be
reexamining existing
theories um but Von hipple and hon did
cover their butts at the end they said
that their conclusion and I agree with
them completely so so they are actually
and I are actually in agreement on this
that their conclusion applied only to
the sampled vocal repertories that they
were looking at um that that other
repertories may contain an excess of
post skip reversals Gap fill uh given
the centuries of Western composers who
have been taught to write Gap fill it
seems inevitable that some of them have
actually done it in their compositions
and now we can kind of see what eras
composers were actually doing it though
I I think it's kind of interesting that
the era that um started teaching how to
write music with gapville is closer to
this period to Bach Mozart and
everything talking about how music of
that past worked so they weren't
actually doing it in their own music but
they had observed something um in the
past and just shows for the 10 millionth
time when we think we're Smarter Than
People of the past were quite often
wrong questions on Gap fill or this kind
of work or or discussion points doesn't
have to be a
question cool eh do it again somewh
something between yeah um can you talk a
little bit through the numbers like what
yeah what exactly does like how do you
measure significance exactly yeah I
can't I can't remember this is why I
needs a little bit of time to come back
to this how did this I think it was the
um uh Scholars T Test um do you know
what that is what the significance
basically how far is this difference
between these two things um how far is
it compared to random chance so one of
the one of the things that um it doesn't
work this isn't a statistics class and I
am not a professional statistician but
um but one of the ways you can often
test something is U if your null
hypothesis if your hypothesis going into
experiment is that um you know that Gap
fill doesn't exist that there shouldn't
be a difference between a gap fill and a
random motion or motion toward the the
um toward the mediant regression should
say regression to mediant I suppose than
to mean but we don't know that and so
one of the things is that
significance goes um the amount of
difference between two hypotheses
necessary to say that something is
highly significant goes up uh the the
amount of difference in percentage uh
goes down a lot as the number of
observations goes way way up um and one
of the places I saw this on was on uh
the article I wrote with Sophia sun on
the lyrics uh emphasis you know like uh
various are there high notes on
anticipation or surprise when you when
we're talking about oh anticipation is
higher than discusted we're talking
about an average I think those two were
about one semitone the difference
between F and FP this is not a huge
difference but when you get um you know
880,000 or I suppose that one was around
10,000 observations one semitone starts
becoming pretty significant um so that's
one of the ways that sometimes you can
um if you look at if you're just looking
at like 10 pieces you might see that
well six of them do this and four of
them do the other thing that's probably
not going to be a significant difference
because if you flip a coin 10 times you
might get sick heads and four tails or
something um
yeah the numbers for Gap fill and
regression so I guess the median those
are instances where this happens in the
pieces of that specific um sometimes can
it do both I guess like if if it starts
above the above R median it will
technically be both if it just goes down
right yes so you can okay but some of
them are one or the other right and and
so the ones that cross over um I think
it's only the ones that reach to the
median or that don't reach it that end
up having um being in the observation
set okay because all the rest should
always be the um should always be the
same they should be the same the whether
uh that is to say if if you
start if you start middle or start
middle high and go really high and then
you go even higher well then you've
broken Gap fill and broken regression to
the mean and if you go down then you
fulfilled Gap fill and regression to the
mean so you haven't learned anything
about your hypothesis so I think these
were um only very um various these um
particular cases where the two
hypotheses would res uh result in
different directions
predicted yeah great question great
question now we're getting on I just
need to give more time
any other things
this isn't a statistics class so I'm not
going to go into um things like this but
there one of the one of the mistakes
that people who dabble in statistics uh
but whose main work is on Medieval music
music theory programming all these other
things we often get wrong is uh
something called a multiple comparison
test and that is to say the more if I
did looked at you know 7,000 repertories
and I'm only reporting the top 10 or the
10 best or something like that um then
my significance level needs to be much
much much higher and sort of general
rule if is if um who's heard of like P
value 05 or 5% yeah as sort of a
standard thing so if you look at five
different things in uh you know five
different hypotheses start with a P
value instead of 05 divide that by five
is
01 um and so this was uh a criticism on
some of the um some earlier work that I
did where I was looking at you know
there's uh what is it 10 different um 10
different emotions or sentiments that
can be compared with nine other ones so
I'm doing 90 comparisons for each uh
attribute so I should be whatever 05
divided by 90 is some somewhere around
01 we just looked at the number of zeros
compared to the number of of hypotheses
um yeah so so look out for things where
people are reporting
p
046 as significant because it's lower
than 05 but not not very much but on the
other hand when you get something like e
to the 45 you have 45 zeros before some
digit that I don't even care what the
digit is there's 45 zeros and that's
what's important um that ends up being
pretty good I like that the um European
folk song we can actually do even better
than um than uh you know they were
giving two two stars for um for their
work because they only had this many
observations um but now we can give them
a lot more observations and say yeah
this is absolutely right um one once you
get uh in 64-bit numbers once you get uh
more than 308 zeros it just gets rounded
to zero which uh ends up being a lot of
zero division errors cool
I'm going to move on to the second um
second topic uh a little bit briefly and
it's something I feel I rightly should
feel apologetic for um we're moving into
an era where uh where we where where
people here in New England in Boston at
MIT in the United States are recognizing
finally that Western Europe is not the
only place that does music or culture I
know big big big shock so why has this
class been primarily about western music
in fact we can start um looking at other
music as part of a music theory class
there was just earlier this semester I
think I emailed it to somebody it might
have been Vincent even who just came
came in um some maybe sure a new book
that just came out it's I think it's
like 600 Pages all on
computational approaches to Indian art
music uh that's say um music that's
that's sort of in a high tradition that
is not folk music or modern popular
music and if you think about you or
Bollywood or something like that if you
think about if you can write 600 pages
on Indian art music you could probably
write 600 pages on computational
approaches to any of those things too um
and I'm really looking forward to seeing
uh what one of my colleagues uh down in
the um in South South as are doing but
uh one of the things that's comes up
here oh no I didn't highlight this is
that most of my training my personal
blinders I I'll say bias my although
maybe it is also that has been that I
was always interested in musical scores
and now there's large parts of music
theory that are interested in things
that are not score-based and most of the
rest of the world's music is not
primarily score based just as shockingly
most um most western music today is not
primarily score based I mean it is
really really great when you go see your
favorite uh heavy metal band and they're
all page turning for each other so no no
that doesn't happen we're you know we're
much more of an oral culture today so
yeah so it says basically that um there
are no standardized tools yet such as
hum drum or music 21 for Indian art
music scores and that still get need
Collections and of scores whatever it is
if we're going to be using these tools
and I want us to always be trying to
break out of the chicken and egg problem
that I've done this semester with you
we'll do another Buck cow I I really my
apology to you all everybody is that I
wanted to deemphasize more of those
things and music 21 Version 9 has a
bunch of other substitute scores that
are designed for us to be using and uh
it's just has continued to be too buggy
to recommend for us all to use in this
class not the scores the surrounding
code um so we don't want the chicken and
egg problem that well we don't study
this music because there aren't enough
scores in there well why don't we encode
a whole bunch of scores well if we did
that there's no software to analyze it
right so these are some of the problems
that are there um so um they're
absolutely WR that these tools the
authors of this book editors that these
tools don't yet exist um
but we wanted to those of us who are
building music 21 first and many of us
in scores we just never got there this
is um one of the slides I know I haven't
changed my font in a long time um from
the original funding presentation to get
funding to take music 21 from a little
hobby europ project and to make it a
bigger one and we talked about these are
probably things doesn't exactly work
like this but you know these were the
types of things music 21 was going to be
able to do generic intervals specific
chromatic is Step you all have worked
with this by now um but then I thought
well you should be able to apply a
context to any object and transform how
that object Works uh so you could apply
13th century France con uh con oh I
didn't even make this consistent in the
um you this is all pseudo code in 13th
century France this major third would
not be called a consonant only perfect
intervals that's why they're called
perfect or consonantes in fact this
lower note wouldn't even exist there is
no a flat back then so we could do that
and then we could apply other things
like 20th century Harmony apply an
octatonic scale and count the number of
um notes in this and we' get three
instead of two and that one we can kind
of do but I did think about oh wouldn't
it be great to be able to take this
interval which we started with calling
it major 3D and convert it into the
Indian farara and get seven shuti as the
interval that these types of things
should be able to be done and a lot of
the basic design decisions some of the
things are over complicated in what
you're trying to do were in order to
enable more of these U things or that um
we can apply an IND okan pentatonic
scale and say the a flat to C is a step
it is not a skip is a leap because there
is no note between those
um or one of the last things in there
that um you know one of the things music
21 will be able to answer um I suppose I
never put a timeline on that so maybe
I'm still uh telling the truth you know
is that West African cultures often hear
the same rhythmic pattern and as having
different strong beats different parts
of the Bell pattern um what can we learn
from analyzing more music to try to
figure out what Clues give uh different
of um of strong beat among different
listeners so these are all ideas that
computational music theory should be
able to
do so we wanted to get there originally
a whole field has wanted to get there uh
to be able to do some of these things
but we're not there yet to really have
cross-cultural symbolic music um an
analysis but I want to keep trying I'm
going to be
spending this is a summer coming up for
me I'm going to be trying to this has
really inspired me to make sure that at
least one more of these things are
possible so that's that's one more the
second of three things I wanted to talk
about today um discussion ideas anybody
know of anything very cool happening in
this sort of
world oh I meant to talk about there is
a project taros that um is specifically
a music theory uh toolkit for looking at
music throughout the world it's a little
bit um uh older it's one of these things
that you need to find your Java virtual
machine to work uh properly on but it's
very cool set um of tools for uh for
analyzing especially scales and scale
usage through the world that doesn't re
that doesn't rely on saying oh well that
not's kind of like an A and that notes a
c but 20 cents high no no those are
notes these are not alterations on some
you know platonic correct note that just
happens to be the Western scale so I
think any conceptual system for
nonwestern music needs to start with
anything that is fundamental in that
system is a fundamental object that
maybe we can translate them to um to
other systems objects like western music
but first the manipulation should happen
in the space that people are actually
conceiving I know it's very B leury
today for me but
um I don't want you to have to do too
much more work while you're doing many
other things so I'm going to talk about
um the last really cool area that I
think there's still so much for music
theory to be doing in order order to get
us more scores and that is improving
Optical music recognition so Optical
music recognition process of changing a
musical score into something that a
computer can understand a symbolic score
and this is uh done what is my name
bigger on this I think we reset the that
that is not supposed to happen I think
there was something I think it was in an
auto shrink um uh mode sorry about that
sorry Mara uh doing amazing things out
there at du lingo um okay um one of the
opportunities is and this is from a
presentation I'm reusing slides I don't
update them every year uh because from
2014 um
that um that back when imslp had about
300,000 scores I think it's over double
that now and so we'd love to be able to
convert all of them into music so I
always you know might as well start with
AA Klein KN music by wolf amas Mozart
late 19th
century and so if we want to convert it
over this is um use from the
state-of-the-art in 2014 it's gotten
better but not a huge amount better so
this is the original score of of one
part and this is what the optical music
recognition score came up with so you
can see uh oops we've lost lost some
notes Here uh somehow we have another
rest here and a whole bunch of dots at
the top and on the other hand you know a
lot of it looks kind of kind of right
but how do these errors add up
especially rhythmic errors um and
misidentified part names cffs can lead
to Big differences in perception so I'm
just going to remind us for the first
couple bars of what I CL music knock
music should sound like this is actually
it shouldn't sound like this this is a
un unretouched finale performance from
um music EX
okay y'all recognize it good so I don't
need to play more let's listen to a
little bit of what happens when you play
back the state-of-the-art optical music
recognition
[Music]
oh
I have no idea how it got what
instruments should be
playing
anyhow so one of the things I've been
talking about especially since our sound
discore lecture we didn't really do uh
uh image discore lecture uh is how music
theory knowledge can um work with
inaccuracies in omr fortunately some
other people have been thinking about it
this is one um I should be citing my
sources I can't uh remember exactly
where it came from one uh pipeline for
how scanned music can end up as a music
encoded data file staff line DET
identification object location so on but
uh just like we saw in the sound of
score things musical semantics and
musical knowledge can be used to go back
and forth in sort of a two-way Pipeline
and that was the idea that almost
everybody knew but but very few musical
semantics have been brought in to um uh
to to what we're uh doing so here's some
things that errors that music theory can
fix um you might have a pitch out of
context and would figure out what we
have
misread probably that was intended to be
a sharp and now it's been read as a
natural instrument or cleff
misidentification I mean this is
something that you don't need very much
programming to figure out Uh something's
wrong
the correction isn't necessarily the
easiest thing should it be uh change
that to a tuba or change the cluff to um
to a treble cluff not sure but we can
definitely point that out if we have
music theory knowledge um to point
something in um and then metrical
inconsistencies is what we focused on
because metrical inconsistencies have a
really really nice thing that pitch
inconsistencies don't there's um there's
no answer key to whether you do it right
or wrong but there is a check sum to
check see if you've probably got it
right or probably got it wrong and that
is the time
signature when everything that you've
recognized does not add up to the time
signature maybe it's a pickup bar maybe
it's some other weird thing but most of
the time you've gotten something wrong
right so um we want to talk about um the
Rhythm replacement and what we're doing
all
has begins with the assumption that
context will give you an idea of the
correct Rhythm so here's that measure
that was screwed up and here it becomes
very obvious that we have a DOT that's
been
added given this context but now we're
going to come up with a different
conclusion same middle
measure but now what's wrong is almost
is very very likely that we've lost a
flag
on the first eth
note so we have the assumption that the
context will give an idea about the
correct Rhythm and that requires a
certain amount of rhythmic repetition
and metrical stability throughout a
piece or across parts um there's some
20th century music John Cage Pier bz uh
Ruth Crawford Seager Gregorian chant
that can't do it but most music doesn't
behave like that most music works like
inin and KN music so we're just tripping
out all of the um Melody and just giving
the computer a score that looks kind of
like this it be a separate problem if
there's a note deleted to try to figure
out what pitch put it in but we're
trying to figure out well at least what
Rhythm it is so this is iined knock
music the opening with just the
rhythm so first thing work looked at was
distance that the probability measure
offers a solution based on its location
and score something called distance
probability um so distance can be
partwise or horizont vertical or
horizontal what do I mean by vertical um
probability measure so we're just going
to look at this third measure at the top
of in music where there's an added well
there's a there something doesn't add up
here the computer doesn't yet know what
you all know that there's a DOT that's
been added dotted eighth note but it
could be anything
right so yeah there it is much so one of
the things to do is to look at the
rhythms in all the other parts at the
same
time what we can do is build a histogram
of for the violin how often across the
whole piece now again this is being
built based on the incorrect possibly
incorrect o omr so you're learning from
you know from uh error PR scores to
build other error prone scores perhaps
but you hope that that this is act just
a little bit close to reality so the
violin mostly violin one mostly has the
same Rhythm or has closest the same
Rhythm violent 2 and the cello but for
the most part it's doing its own thing
when we look compared to the viola you
can see hey when the viola is wrong 80%
of the time if that measures like the
other measures uh the the cello might
have the same
Rhythm so that gives the probability
based on a horizontal a vertical and
then the other thing you can do is look
left and look right to see if that same
rhythm is somewhere over there in this
case it's not because uh it should have
been but there's another mistake in the
first measure and we can look throughout
the whole score not just a what's cool
about the horizontal thing is that
scores tend to be wider than they are um
tall other words more measures than
there are parts so you have more things
to do and we can look I'll skip over the
violin I think it's more interesting to
look at the cello um that obviously each
measure is always exactly identical to
itself so you have a one probability of
one it's going to be but then um you can
kind of see in a lot of the classical
things the the most often similar
measure is two measures on either side
not one because of this sort of four bar
structure and um the other thing that I
learned from this is anybody know Sonata
form uh yeah exposition
development recapitulation at some point
later the music comes back and so you
can kind of see this temporary spike in
that if you can't get it right look 97
measures later and you might also get it
right so the computer can learn just
from the scores what all the
probabilities for this particular piece
are and then hopefully apply them to put
it in so now we know what measures what
the probability of any measure having
the same Rhythm would be ahead of time
but then we need to look at second
probability what's the probability that
that measure that each other measure
might have the solution based on how
often certain errors happen and here's a
chart that I think we need to keep
looking at and keep judging but it was
the only one that I knew of at the time
where somebody looked at what the
probability that something uh that any
given musical object would be recognized
properly so 97%
99% some of them I don't believe
anything that says 100. that means not
enough data right but you know uh a lot
of things so we can look at uh
various uh probabilities the natural is
that's quite quite quite
low so then um this is where there
should have been some gigantic formula
with regressions but it turns out all
you need to do is find the probability
that of each measure being the same find
the probability that it would how how
many changes you would have to make and
multiply those two probabilities and
take the max value so and yeah it is
that simple um so the workflow normally
take a PDF turn it into music XML we
kind of stuck ourselves in to in the
middle take uh run it through one more
time I would love to be able to send it
all the way back into the omr pipeline
and say no reject that now rerun the
recognition with this being a
possibility but didn't get to that um
then had a whole bunch of scores where
we had um not not as many as I would
like but we had scanned Optical music
recognition music XML and we had the
correctly encoded one and we can look at
the number of differences before run
through the model and then look at the
new number of
differences um all of this code is in
music 21 in case you want to use it to
improve things how everything works and
the music we looked at again too many
canonical
composers average about 19% decrease in
error which made us very happy in a
field where um usually you're trying to
improve by 1% at a time or something and
Got U well and Mora Church earned the
best uh grad student paper award which
was great because she wasn't technically
qualified because she was still an
undergrad but but um yeah so it worked
worked pretty well um here and some of
the pieces got as high as 36% error
reduction so what happens you have all
original score we've marked what's the
errors we correct that and then post
correction it's correct if we got the
same Rhythm not if we um not necessarily
the right pitch because we didn't work
any time on that so these are all the
places to be looking
at here here's what the optical music
recognition software got
wrong and um the correction so it got in
this case three out of five corrected
see them all there um but the what what
really um came out of this work for me
that seemed very important was that we
are evaluating the quality of our work a
little bit wrong so there's um
that we need to be looking at Optical
music recognition that allows for
musical semantics to go back and forth
into things um that was a prop possible
implementation for how you can um make
it faster to do things but um so there's
proposals for judging how good Optical
music recognition software is that you
feed in a bunch of scores and you see
how you know how well does it do but
some of the standard scores being used
are ones that uh if we had to run our
software through would run terribly on
so this is one of the ones that you
should be able to recognize but this
particular score has no motivic
repetition I mean I I've never even
played it let me let me play it just
here how unusual that score is
[Music]
so it doesn't really behave like a
normal score and there's even things
like if if I my Optical music
recognition saw that c when it just
recognized this key signature I would
say you probably got it wrong that's
probably a c natural or you've got your
key signature wrong because there's no
reason why you would write a sharp there
immediately
there are other things that are in the
test beds I still think we need to do
like being able to recognize properly
this measure and I get that it's trying
to test can you recognize a whole bunch
of rests but if I saw this from an
regular regular piece of music I would
say those are probably notes in here
right because there's no reason to not
just write every measure like
this and then other things if you get
really smart you could okay well that's
a pedal Mark and that's a cleff Mark I
don't know a single Alto cff instrument
that uses one staff and has pedals so I
would send it back and say you got to
change one of these things in your
recognition um so I think in our quest
to try to give simple tests that can be
run very quickly we're ending up
optimizing our models for things that
don't resemble the music that most of us
learn um yes so there's still a ton of
work to be done on music theory and
semantics in Optical music recognition
choices and this is something that's
getting a little bit harder now with the
rise of most people who are trying to
work in this field now obviously want to
use machine learning artificial
intelligence and deep learning models um
which will be great once we get more
ground truths encoded and we can do
things right now that's the hardest part
of having more things lined up so that
the computer can learn but um it's it's
going to be harder and harder as long as
we're just using black boxes to be able
to um to get this uh in into there uh I
think uh you all have actually met the
world's expert in doing this his name is
Gus sha he h was here um when we moved
in another place yeah so there are
people who are trying to figure out a
way to add uh not just not just in
Optical music recognition but in any
sort of artificial intelligence working
with scores how that we can we can still
use these big deep learning models but
still but incorporate music theory into
that so that's the big challenge for our
time questions on this yeah what do you
think the state of using deep Lear
endtoend deep learning for
optical yeah so what do I think this the
state of the-art of using endend deep
learning for optical music recognition I
think it is a place um with great
potential it is not nearly as good yet
as the things you can buy um smart score
sharpy uh the things that are there but
it you know it's has a lot of potential
and one of the things most of the work
that I've seen on it is missing are the
skills that you guys have here um I saw
okay I'm going to forget you're going to
tell me to put this back up in a second
I just need a couple extra lines I I
actually saw a model um
where uh it was using generated scores
which are a little bit different because
they're always the same so you take an
output from finale or M score or
something you create a image file and
then you know exactly where every note
is because you wrote it and everything
so you can generate a million ground
truths and stuff like that and so it was
you know running through a whole bunch
of scores and
things and this particular one it had a
particular uh reinforcement learning
problem that it successfully identified
where all the notes were and where all
the staff lines were it was getting
incredibly incredibly good but could not
break around 80% on then recognizing
what the note was why because they had
trained it on this is a this is D this
is G this is F this is B flat
uh this is B flat this is e actually
we'll make it even even even
better put that
there that's an e
sharp so these are all being
recognized the fourth will also be right
yeah that's oh sorry thank you yep um
thank you very much Adam but now imagine
you're the PO computer that's having to
predict okay a I got it right d i got it
right oh sorry I didn't mean that G and
ignore that G I got it right uh I think
that's
F because it's only looking at sorry
camera and people on this side because
it's only looking at this amount of data
whereas it needs some way to know that's
sharp um yeah this this one could get
right is B flat and then again it was
saying uh I think that's G
flat I think that's C and I think that's
D because the training data had
prioritized treble cff and once it's
here has no way of getting back to here
what what should the computer be trying
to
predict on this
basis anyone take a guess B based on the
amount of information you're trying to
get the computer what would be uh an
essentially incredibly good prediction
model yeah maybe just have it predict
like which line or space yeah what's
yeah I see a quarter note on
space
three I see a 16th note on line five and
then when you put all that together then
have a separate detector trying to
detect all the cffs or it can be the
same one these things are pretty smart
but yeah and try to do that and then
only afterwards connect those two data
to other things so that that was that
was really nice that um that that was
about I think four about four years ago
that that this was shown to me as sort
of the state-ofthe-art I think that
they've gotten better since then but
there's still if if these kind of
mistakes were still being made four
years ago I imagine that there's still
many um stumbling blocks that you can uh
put in for and I I think a team from
here now with the knowledge that we have
uh could you know in a year-long project
produce a real State ofthe art tool yeah
Misha with some of the best uh like
language large language models they use
like attention based models y so in this
case this actually might um fix this
problem because it would really
priortize Stu at the beginning of the
measure and and ignore the adg when
evaluating half sharp yeah yeah some of
you who are also taking um uh Aran Go's
interactive music systems had um had a
lecture from one of the experts Anna
hang who is um an expert in the
attention models and the the sort of
things where you sort of have a memory
and thinking back about what's what's
important earlier in the data and so uh
I think that that her work um and that's
over at Google um project magenta I
think that that could have a lot of of
impact on the field and there's other
people um naming naming a few people
doesn't mean that these are the only
people doing great things is just ones
people who I seem to know but none of
these people are are working
particularly on the optical music
recognition problem so again we need to
someday have 21m 384 where we have a
whole semester to just take our projects
and do something bigger uh but we don't
have something like that
yet because that would be a great group
project right we going to do all
this any
other question
yeah you know are there any classes I
know like that no right now and Paul are
you
senior you're junior there may be by the
time you uh leave or M we are looking at
creating more classes on U on artificial
intelligence and music and and these
kinds of problems um yeah so there's
there's prob um but definitely well I
suppose if you're junior yeah we're
already too late right we're in the
second semester it's just been so cold I
still feel don't feel like it's Spring
end of semester there but yeah there
there should be more and and there are
other schools that offer um some of
these things and and various workshops
that you could go to on some these
techniques but we're all we're all still
learning we're all still trying to
create um the musical equivalent of for
those who have done machine learning
know the handwritten to to to to data
set the classify thing which everybody
does as their first artificial
intelligence thing to here's all the
different ways to's been written now
here's a new number what is it um we
still need that data set for optical
music recognition here are 10,000
quarter notes on space three from all
different things and now can your system
do that
cool else
well I'm going to give you time to
either work on your projects or stay
here or take advantage of the fact that
um you know finally I didn't make it uh
use up every inch my time so just um
this is the end for my teaching in this
class uh and next week I'm excited
because I get to learn a lot new now
I've been learning from youall but I'll
get to learn a lot more so I'm looking
forward to that um I'll have office
hours uh as soon as I'm done here and uh
look forward to to projects so
thanks thanks oh oh that's nice that's
nice thank you