so uh now we're going to talk about um
something related to agents really which
is uh reasoning in search with deep Nets
the common theme Here is again we're
building up that that Tech stack that
once you have really powerful you know
Foundation models and large language
models and generative AI then what can
you do on top of that what can those
Systems Support how can you build that
into something that will start to do
kind of multi-step inference and
Analysis of data and it might be an
agent or something that looks like
gentic that's doing that but it also um
could be a more kind of classical um
algorithm that's just going to do what
we might call search like searching a
search tree for example um and that's
what we'll talk about in this lecture
and the kind of payoff of this lecture
is I'm going to tell you how um these
models that you've probably seen in some
headlines recently work so if you saw
this big thing about deep seek this this
new model from a lab in China has made
the headlines yesterday and that I'll
tell you how that works and uh there's
another model called 01 and another one
called 03 these are the latest greatest
models from open a this will be how
those work as well okay so this is
bringing us right up to the you know the
very current thing that's
happening
okay cool so what what has changed you
know in the last five years of
AI so suppose you have a question that
you want an AI to answer we have our
chat Bots that can answer we had them in
2020 as as well some earlier versions
you know one was called gpt3 in 2020 and
essentially these language models in
2020 what they would do is they would
give you not the correct answer to your
question but they would give you what a
random person on the internet might say
in response to your question that's how
they're trained right um I think you
talked about this earlier that large
language models you download a you know
big Corpus of data usually you know a
lot of websites a lot of text on the
internet and they're trained just to
predict what would some say next what
would the next word be on that internet
so they give you kind of a random answer
where random means a random person how
they would reply on the internet okay
but AI in 2025 is quite different
instead it gives you uh a good answer
not a random answer and by good we mean
it might be the correct answer an
accurate answer an unbiased answer a
fair answer good in certain ways now
it's not perfect but it's it's better
than it was in 2020 so what what made
the difference and this lecture is about
the technology that made that difference
went from 2020 to
2025 okay so um in particular in this
lecture I'll talk about two different
paradigms one is called learning that's
what we've um seen mostly so far
although um Antonio's talk definitely
got a little bit into the more reasoning
and agentic um style of things um and
learning is about um learning or it's
about finding or estimating the
distribution of your data from examples
of how people talk online uh come up
with a model of how people talk online a
model of the distribution of all the
different ways that they could talk so
the distribution of random answers that
are randomly sampled person might give
uh so today uh now we're going to talk
about reasoning which is trying to find
not the distribution or random answer
but the best
answer okay so that's the key
difference okay so here's kind of a
chart um of my own kind of mental map of
learning versus reasoning and all the
subcomponents um in the space there's a
lot of different ways paring this uh a
lot of you might have different
backgrounds from different fields these
words are highly highly overloaded so
don't think that they have a precise
definition they do not okay so the word
inference uh for example in statistics
means what in um my language and most of
kind of modern machine learning language
is referred to as learning so going from
data to a model of the data St
statisticians might call that stat
statistical inference I would call that
machine learning um other people might
call that amortised inference so there's
you know different name for the same
thing so it's really a little tricky to
get around these naming issues there's a
lot of conflicts and debates in the
field about people just using the same
word to mean two different things and
thinking they're talking about two
different things but they're not um so
try to like get below the surface I'm
can give some you know synonyms here um
okay so learning goes from like a data
like the internet to a model of the
internet a model of the distribution um
of data and this is really related to
what K Ming talked about with generative
modeling being trying to fit the you
know identify or fit a distrib to data
from finite samples find the
distribution that explains all the
samples okay reasoning on the other side
is um there's different ways again of
characterizing this but I will
characterize it as going from a
distribution or model to a decision or
prediction so now that I have all the
random things somebody might say online
can I find the best thing they said that
what what an expert would say what is
actually
correct okay and reasoning might go
under different names um inference uh
prediction thinking cognition control
these are all like related to
reasoning okay but the spectrum is is
essentially um now in kind of modern
systems being broken down pretty clearly
into the different phases of training a
model so we have the pre-training phase
this is um the fitting the language
model to predict the next word in your
Corpus that you mostly talked about uh
and then you have the uh what's called
the posttraining phase and now at
companies there's these teams that call
themselves posttraining or mid-training
or you know retrain like they just start
having different phases of training but
basically um there's a gray area I'll
talk about that in a minute and the
other end of um the spectrum is the kind
of reasoning or deployment phase which
I'll also refer to as search okay I'm
using a lot of different terminology
here but they all link together okay so
pre-training is usually uh generative
modeling or representation learning
where you have a lot of data you try a
base model to just model the data
predict the next token
uh given the previous tokens now that
gives you this base model of like the
internet if you're training a chatbot
okay then you can do some adaptation uh
in the middle but at the other end of
the spectrum is how are you going to
actually use this in practice so when
you deploy this on your phone and you
ask your phone a question you know
what's the weather today and like tell
me where I should go have a picnic it
will do something and up until 2020 or
so the thing that it would do in deep
learning was very very simple it would
do just a forward pass through this
autor regressive uh model so it would do
a forward pass predict the next token
sample that token repeat and that was
all it did that was the deployment phase
the search was this really really simple
greedy process um okay but now well well
I'm exaggerating like 2020 of course
people had other ideas too but that was
roughly how these systems worked uh now
they work a little bit differently and
that's starting to change okay now we
can instead take our system at test time
at employment time and query it multiple
times and try to um say here's the 10
different answers we would give now can
I pick the best of those 10 answers
somehow or Ensemble the answers and come
up with a better
prediction okay and then in between
there's all these other phases which are
kind of a blurry uh you know this blurry
uh line between this pre-training the
base model and at deployment time
searching and reasoning on top of it uh
and those include methods like taking a
model and updating it so transfer
learning and fine-tuning uh or or at
deployment time you can also update the
model you can say do these things like
in context learning where at at
deployment time you provide some con
context to help guide what the model
will do so the model's behavior is being
manipulated and updated by that context
but that context is provided at test
time not at training time okay so this
is kind of the pipeline there's teams at
these companies pre-training the base
model uh fine-tune the base model toward
uh to be better on the type of data you
care about uh and then deploy it and let
users prompt and uh add context and do
continual updates at test time and
finally do kind of classical search
algorithms on the very
top okay so we're mostly going to focus
on this very top part and then there's
this interesting connection that comes
in which is that there's something
called reinforcement learning down here
so what is reinforcement learning
reinforcement learning is updating the
the model uh changing the kind of the
learning process
by doing search so you're going to
search for good Solutions if you find a
good solution you will update the model
to do that do that thing that was good
you get a reward for finding a good
solution so you should do more things
that are like that good solution so I'll
talk about that at the end okay so um I
think there's this you know very
important essay in AI from a few years
ago called The Bitter lesson many of you
might have heard of it which says that
uh you know for all our cleverness U
most of the you know AI methods that
have driven progress have come down to
simple methods that scale well and uh
that's really been uh one of the
dominant stories of the last uh decade
or so of AI is these kind of scaling
laws like come up with a simple method
that can absorb data and compute to do
better and better uh and don't try to
over-engineer or be too clever about how
you do it and what Rich Sutton who wrote
this essay pointed out is that there's
two two simple algorithms that seem to
scale arbitrarily in this way and one
was learning and that was kind of the
story the last decade deep learning and
making bigger networks trained on more
data but he actually mentioned the this
other one search and so uh he you know
already identified that 10 years ago or
five years ago uh as being the other big
component and it's just in the last um
you know year or so that it's become a
big component in kind of deployed
systems that we're all starting to use
okay um here's a blog post from openai
from about six months ago on their 01
model and they were just pointing out
uh Rich Sutton's bitter lesson uh again
they were saying there's kind of two two
scaling laws that they've identified one
is the learning scaling law so train on
more data uh you get better performance
and the other is a search scaling law
which is at test time do more thinking
more inference at test time uh and
you'll get better performance so the
first is training time compute and the
second is test time compute uh the first
goes under the name learning the second
goes under the name
search okay so what is search okay so
search is basically the more um
classical approach to AI which we used
to do before machine learning became
dominant so uh search can be used to
describe how uh deep blue the IBM chest
plane computer worked uh what it did is
it would kind of look forward over the
tree of all the possible moves it could
make so it could say I will you know if
I move my Pawn up then Gary casparo and
plans might do this and if he does that
then I'll do this if he does that I'll
do this if he does that this you keep
going right and you do that for all
possible path paths through the game and
then at the end you find okay this this
set of moves will guarantee a victory by
doing that search or it will make it
likely that I have a victory okay so
that's how deep deep blue works there
wasn't really any deep net involved
there wasn't any you know learning uh
per se involved it was just it would
expand the game tree of all
possibilities um some number of steps
into the future and pick the best um the
best initial move along that
tree okay that worked that beat Gary
Kasparov um search was also a huge
component in other gamling landmarks in
AI like Alpha go uh so Alpha go actually
had both the learning and the search
components but the search was this Tre
search again where you kind of do
exactly what deep blue was doing you
kind of Imagine uh all the possible
moves that you could make and all the
opponents responses and then once you
get to the you know you search a few
steps ahead but once you get to the um
oh there we go okay once you get to a
leaf of that search tree then you have a
neural net that looks at that leaf and
says is it good or bad so you kind of
combine this neural net with this search
tree so already people were thinking
about com combining search and learning
back then okay so um let's let's
introduce a few equations I won't make
it too technical but we're going have a
little bit of math um so what I mean by
learning I already told you it's fitting
um a distribution to data but in
particular we usually think of it as
fitting a uh a probability model P that
will um say you know I I'm going to have
um learned that my data can be well
explained as samples from um probability
model p over um x's and y's I'll think
of uh y's as being the the kind of
outputs and X's as being the inputs to
my
system okay so inference is saying now
once I have that model I'm going to
observe some input X and I want to um
not not output just what's the
probability of Y or like what make a
random prediction I want to take the max
I want to say what is the most probable
y given X okay so this is this argmax is
is inference or search so search more
generally might be um taking a scoring
function it doesn't have to be a
normalized probability it could be any
kind of score function that just says
you know it's a scaler that says how
good is this XY combination and then
take an observation X and try to find
the Y that will will make that score the
highest that's the general idea of of
search and this maximization taking the
max that is the search that's looking
for that Max of that distribution or
that
score
okay so let's see a few methods that
that um people use in practice right now
I'll talk about best of end beam search
and and Chain of
Thought
okay so again reminder about yun's
lecture we have Auto regressive language
models and what those do is they just
predict the next word a sequence okay so
once upon and then we we will make a
prediction we'll actually get a whole
set of possibilities we'll say it could
be once upon the lake but no instead
we're going to say it's Once Upon A this
more probabil it's a so we'll sample
that and we'll keep on repeating so this
is how autor regressive models generate
language okay and so yeah right we don't
want to just tell a random story we want
to answer you know find the the argmax
the most the best story or the most
probable answer to my query uh and the
observation here is that um the
underlying probability model of Auto
regressive models uh is this the joint
distribution of all the words in some
kind of answer to a query is equal to
the the product of the probability
probability of the first word times the
probability of the second word given the
previous word times a probably the next
word given all the previous words that's
the underlying probability model behind
Auto regressive large language models
and if you want to find the best
configuration so you want to find uh you
know the answer to your question X which
is the the best set of words that answer
that question so the
argmax of that distribution meaning
meaning let's say I'm trying to model
you know expert expert data here so I
really want to find what what is the
most likely thing the expert would say
um that does not
equal the ARG Max of each of these
individual terms okay so the best
configuration the most likely um you
know according to probability model the
most likely output is not the same as
what you'd get if you just do this autor
regressive greedy sampling where you
just take the argmax of what's you know
the best first word in the sentence and
the ARX and the next word in the
sentence and so forth so um this way
that we usually in 2020 would decode
from a language model it's just a crummy
way of maximizing the probability and we
have better ways of doing
it okay so one of the better ways turns
out to be extremely simple it's called
best of end sampling and this just says
run your language model end times and
uh it will give you n different you know
sentences or anwers sheer query if it's
like you ask it a question it gives you
n different answers and you just simply
uh evaluate under the probability model
that is given by the auto regressive
model which one is the most likely and
you out you say that that's the best
okay so let me just um make it uh uh so
here here we have the x's and the the Y
is again uh the x is meant to be like
your question and the Y is the answer so
I ask a question I want to find the best
answer I want to find the the most
probable answer I can evaluate the
probability of any string but how do I
generate the string that maximizes that
probability I can't just sample the
argmax step by step instead I will
sample um end sequences evaluate the
probability of these end sequences and
take the best okay so I'll sample let's
say my question is
um what what what is
so the answer might be a stimulant that
enhances cognitive function and the
model will say that has you know7
probability it might be a simulant that
improves thinking 05 probability a
chemical that makes you feel more awake
point8 probability under some uh
probability model this Auto regressive
model that's been fit to to data um and
so I will say that this this is the
sentence I'll have sample three times
and the best of the three samples will
be this one and that's the one that I
can
output okay so this is a very simple C
procedure um through an autoaggressive
model uh we can also do something a
little bit more sophisticated which is
called tree search and a particular
variant called beam search and that is
we're not going to just search for you
know three independent Different Strings
but we will construct our search in a
tree fashion kind of like Alpha go or
deep blue so what we'll do is we'll
we'll first take the
um sorry we will First Take the first
word and then we'll say there's the
language model the autoaggressive model
says there's two likely next words and
given if I go up this Branch the next
words that are likely are these two
words but I'm not going to just take the
the best the best one I'll I'll expand
this tree of possibilities and then once
I've expanded the tree to some depth I
can look at which path through the tree
has the highest probability according to
the probability model okay so that's
kind of like deep blue looking through
the game tree and saying which path
through the tree LED to me winning okay
and in this case you know mild stimulant
was the best one okay sample multiple
sequences um and uh pick the the
sequence with highest likelihood at the
end and Sample them in this tree
structured fashion expanding the tree
only on the high likelihood
paths okay so then a really interesting
thing happened which is that yeah people
kind of thought we need to have these
search algorithms in order to decode
from these powerful models and make them
better um uh but the bitter lesson of
you know machine learning comes back
again in in multiple ways it it says uh
well maybe we can't be too maybe humans
are not clever enough to come up with
the right search algorithm so what if we
could just ask the model to do search
maybe somehow from the data on the
internet there are enough examples of
search like behavior that the model has
internalized a representation of what it
would mean to int intelligently uh solve
a search Problem and then rather than
explicitly ask uh coding that we'll do
treesearch through the model we can just
tell the model hey I want you to do Tre
search and maybe it will just work
because it's been fit to data that shows
exemplifies tree search and this is the
big discovery that went under the name
Chain of Thought from a few years ago it
says that if I just ask the model uh
like let's say I want to I want to solve
the problem what is 4 * 5 + 10 if I ask
the model to do that it might make the
wrong answer it might get a bad sample
of what a random person online would say
but if instead I say you know I want you
to think really hard and I can in
particular here say I want you to use
beam search so we know how to do beam
search over this model but we could just
at tell it just prompt it hey I want you
to do beam search it turns out it knows
what beam search is and the dot dot dot
here indicates that this is you know the
chat gbt uh model um and there's a whole
um sequence of thoughts before it gets
to this this point but I just cropped it
and it basically says oh okay you want
me to do beam search so the way I would
do that is first I'd break the problem
into these two parts and then I'd make a
search tree and then I'd go da d d d da
and it actually writes out that whole
that whole procedure it is doing beam
search in its um natural language
output um so it's kind of an emergent or
learned version of beam search and it
doesn't have to be beam search I could
ask it to do best event search I could
ask it to do Monte Carlo Tre search I
could ask it all these things will know
something about those your your mileage
will vary because it only knows whatever
existed in its training data on the
internet
uh but this kind of works and in fact
you can even just ask it hey I want you
to solve this problem I'm not going to
tell you how but I want you to think
really hard and think really long about
it the famous line was you prompt the
model with let's think step by step and
then it just starts doing this emergent
reasoning process it doesn't have a name
it's not beam search it's not tree
search it's whatever kind of emergent
thing it it it Associates with the
phrase lets things step by step and
sometimes that might even outperform
classical no and search algorithms
okay so this emergent search H you know
the trade-off here is it can be more
powerful than what humans and more
clever than what humans were able to um
discover by their own Theory but it
doesn't have the same guarantees we have
on classical algorithms where we've
proven things about them we really know
how they work this is just the model
discovered its own stuff and we're using
methods like Antonio's interpretability
methods to try to understand you know is
the model actually reasoning correctly
or incorrectly we don't really really
know that's an ongoing part of science
we just it's like an alien or you know
creature that has discovered something
that humans don't know how to fully
characterize so that's the trade-off
this is a little bit less safe less
robust but can potentially be power more
powerful
okay so the really cool thing about this
search perspective is you don't just
have to stick with probability as the
thing you care about you don't just have
to say I want to find you know the
argmax of the data distribution you can
actually search for um strings that
maximize other functions any kind of
scaler reward function that looks at a
string and says is it good or bad you
can optimize that with search okay so
here's a here's a case let's say I want
to say give me a description of caffeine
but I don't want you to Output like what
the internet thinks is the most likely
description I want you to Output what
some model of fun thinks is the you know
the most fun statement okay let's just
say I have it doesn't matter what the
scorer is the scorer is just something
that takes a string as input and outputs
a number a scalar a score okay and
there's you know there's a lot of these
it could be a cat versus dog classifier
in this case I'm just saying we have
trained some other model that will say
how how fun does this sound right so it
says no that's not very fun uh you know
Nature's tiny cheerleader jumping into
your bloodstream with pom poms okay I
asked a language model to make that for
me I didn't come up with that uh and
that's more fun okay and then maybe
emojis are the best and so that like the
thing that optimizes the fun is is the
set of emojis and I can do best of un
sampling sample you know end different
uh possibilities and then say oh the
best one with the highest score is this
one
okay uh I could do scientific accuracy
maybe I have a model of you know what
would you know somebody in a journal
paper how would they describe this uh if
I have a verifier or a score function
that can uh measure how scientifically
accurate the statement is then maybe
you'll get a different answer that
maximizes that
function um and in particular the
scorers that are really working well
right now we don't quite have great
scorers for scientific accuracy or for
uh funest but we do have really really
good scorers for formal languages and
proofs so for Math and for programming
we have what are called verifiers so a
verifier is something like like in math
it would be a proof Checker so it's very
hard to prove a theorem but it's often
very easy to check that a proof is
correct right you probably did this in
math classes you probably read a theorem
and you're like oh I can check that's
correct but how did they come up with it
it's impossible uh or you know you have
to be really smart uh in programming we
have the same thing it might be really
hard to write a function to um output
the fibon I mean this isn't a hard one
but this is just an example it might be
be somewhat challenging to come up with
a function that outputs the Fibonacci
sequence uh but maybe you can check uh
the Fibonacci sequence quite easily by
just you know checking if um each next
each next number is equal to the sum of
the previous two numbers okay so uh
write me a python python code to compute
the Fibonacci sequence the way that the
verifier will work is the llm will
output two possibilities or end
different possibilities it could be best
of end samping one of them turns out to
compile and be correct and I have a
verifier which will check the syntax
right we know how to check Syntax for
code that's what compilers do uh they'll
throw a syntax error and then I'll say
that was incorrect or maybe it's a logic
error and the verifier could check the
logic it could be like a proof Checker a
formal uh verification system and this
one turns out to be the wrong code and
this is the right code and so I'll
simply select this okay put a box around
that and my model when I query it online
when I talk to uh gemini or chat GPT or
any of these things uh this is what the
latest systems are doing under the hood
they're trying multiple completions uh
multiple you know if I ask it to code
for me it will try multiple things we'll
check which one is correct um so
different systems working different ways
but this is one of the ways that some
systems
work okay the key idea here actually
might if you you know have a background
in um CS Theory you might remember that
uh there's this fundamental idea that
for a lot of problems verification is
fundamentally easier than generation so
there's this class of problems the NP
class of problems where uh they are
efficient to verify but people think
they're not efficient to uh generate the
solution so you can solve the uh you
know a problem like uh the traveling and
salesman problem I can I can I can solve
that but it's it's really hard it might
take exponential time to to find this
like path through all the cities to
maximize my profits as a Salesman but
once I have found the path checking it
is really easy I can do that in what's
called polinomial time okay so uh
verification is fundamentally easier
than generation for a lot of problems
and whenever that's the case then this
strategy is a good idea you use a
verifier to guide the
generation
okay so um I'm not going to fully
explain this this is a snippet from a
paper but I I've given all these
examples of language models that are
autoaggressive outputting the next
character or the next token given the
previous ones but I want to mention that
all the other generative models or many
of the other generative models that are
popular today like diffusion models and
and vaes uh you can do similar things
with if I have a diffusion model which
is what this diagram is showing I can do
the same search procedures but not
through the autor regressive sequence of
words but through the no den noising
steps
um did did King talk about diffusion
models somebody yeah he did okay so um
you saw that and it's like in diffusion
models you start with a A you know noisy
image and you make it less and less
noisy but you normally do that by this
just like in Auto regressive models you
in 2020 you did that by just kind of
greedily like remove the the you know
estimate how to remove the noise and
just uh make that decision and then
estimate how to remove more noise and
make that decision but instead you could
search over all the different paths
through this denoising space and check
and and find the best path that will
lead to the most likely output and so
you can do these same types of search
with diffusion models just like you can
with auto regressive models so don't
worry if you're more of an image
processing person the same ideas apply
okay most of them were developed first
in autor regressive language
models oh and sorry here's the the paper
if you're interested in reading more
about
that okay so um so far I've only talked
about discrete search um because I was
focusing on language models which are
discrete models uh but you can often
also do continuous search so what is
continuous search I'll give just I'll
give an example from some of my my work
from a few years ago um so this is going
to be an example of trying to take a uh
continuous model which maps from some
underlying latent variables Z to
imagery and then we will take the output
so everything is continuous here pixels
are continuous valued you know it's a
continuous valued function so the nice
thing about continuous valued functions
and variables is I can do my search not
by looking over like discrete trees of
possibilities and what we might really
want to call reasoning and like thinking
but instead just with gradient descent
so it turns out that search with
continuous models can be done with just
the same old vanilla Machinery that we
used for a lot of deep learning which is
gradient descent okay so here's my image
generation process and then I'll um
take that output and I'll put it into a
model of a human's preferences so I have
a model of a human this is another
continuous function I'll get a score and
so I'm just going to try to change the
you know the latent variables the input
to my generative model to make a image
that humans like in some sense or that
optimizes human
preferences uh so this is related to
what's now become famous as
reinforcement learning from Human
feedback uh but I'm going to show an
application a slightly different
application which was not trying to make
an image which uh you know humans give
an up vote to or a down vote to but
instead we're going to have a model of
human memory and we had this model of
human memory because some years ago we
ran these experiments where we would um
see what images people tend to remember
and what images people tend to forget
and we ran these like psychophysical
experiments so uh people watched online
sequences of images and now and then
they would repeat and when they would
repeat the person was instructed to
press a key and we found that some
images were was really really easy to
recognize when they repeated this way so
we called them very memorable in fact
this guy right I'm sorry to show you
this this photo because you're never
going to get be able to get out of your
head this is the most memorable photo
that we ever found okay so you you
should remember that photo come back in
a year and we can chat um okay so here
are the some memorable photos here's the
most memorable guy and here are some
forgettable photos it turned out that
people everybody just remembers people
that was the main conclusion of this
work okay but we Revisited this in this
kind of can we do you know search over
this you know the uh variables in a
generative model to optimize
memorability to see what it looks like
for an image to become more memorable
okay so we're just going to manipulate
my generative model to make outputs that
a model of memorability will think
causes the image to be memorable this is
work with Laura and
Alex okay so um here is a input photo
and we we you know here's here's the
model the the details don't matter too
much but basically we tried to
manipulate the inputs that control the
appearance of of the image uh so that
the generative model called Big Gan here
would output something that a neural net
which was called memet a memorability
assessor here would think uh is
memorable so we simply would uh find how
to how to tune this model to make more
memorable images and if we tune it up
the dog Zooms in and becomes really cute
and if we tune it down it becomes kind
of blurry and hard to recognize and
is predicted to be less memorable you
can run this um in a new psychophysical
experiment and find out that indeed
people remember this photo a lot better
than that photo
okay um you can do this for Aesthetics
or emotional veillance or other whatever
type of human perception or you know
score function you want and that's kind
of the point is once you have a good
generative model you can search the
model to produce um images or sentences
that maximize whatever score function
you want uh so here's a just you know
some more fun examples here's the
original images and then this is making
them less memorable more memorable the
um snake becomes kind of like a perfect
circle when it's more memorable um this
is making it less aesthetic more
aesthetic so the dog you know the
saturation goes way up it's related to
memorability but not identical uh and
this is emotional veilance this like a
sad dog and a happy dog um so you can
kind of get a probe into human
perception that was how we pitched the
paper back back in 2019 19 um but now
more recently uh this type of technology
is um is very commonly used in language
models under the name rhf for optimizing
toward you know what What sentences what
answers humans would find um positive or
negative
okay so you can do continuous search uh
by gradient descent if you have a
continuous
model um another thing you can do is
what I told you about train of thought
and what is train of thought it's like
emergent search it's just just ask for
search so Chain of Thought is like just
ask for symbolic search hey let's think
step by step hey I want you to do
reasoning I want you to do Tre search
you can just just ask the model to do
that and if the data distribution
exemplifies that type of thinking it
will know how to do that if the data
distribution does not exemplify that
kind of thinking then it might not um
could we just ask for continuous reward
can we just ask just do gradient descent
to optimize for human preferences okay
so here here's just a
this is not really a formal experiment
just a kind of fun playing around with
some of these models a few years ago so
here I'm just I'm asking for a painting
of a waterfall and it's it's okay right
but let's say can I just ask it to be um
you know higher reward painting so I'm
going to say no no I I don't want to say
how reward maybe it doesn't know how
that to interpret that but I'll just say
I want a beautiful painting of a
waterfall it's a little more beautiful
okay what if I say I want a very
beautiful I'm asking it for an even
higher reward it's a little more
beautiful what if I a very very okay
it's starting to get pretty good okay a
very very very very very very beautiful
painting of
waterfall okay this is like 20 varies
now and that was about the max that it
got to okay so people have continued um
to play with things like this you um
there's a fun kind of meme one of these
which is called make it more you just
you take an image and you say make it
more and then it will just like
exaggerate the things in the image you
can just repeat this process it's like
just asking it to do this this reward op
optimization uh or beauty optimization
in this particular
case okay so um the last section uh of
this talk will be on reinforcement
learning okay reinforcement learning is
a huge field so I'm not going to do
everything but I just want to give you
the gist of it so what is reinforcement
learning in the context of reasoning and
language models and modern AI uh I think
of it like this I think it's using
search to um feed back into training so
remember we had the verifi that checks
if my program is syntactically correct
and logically correct and that can help
me to pick the correct um the correct
output to my language model but there
was a problem with this verification
approach which is that I had to run the
language model twice to rule out the bad
incorrect answer and I in general I
might have to run it many many times to
do search over all the possibilities of
outputs to find the the best one so how
can we make it so that it will just
directly output the right answer and not
have to run it many many times
during the deployment of the system and
so reinforcement learning does that it
first does search right so what is the
idea of reinforcement learning the the
basic idea is you try some random thing
if it works you do it again if it
doesn't work you move on and try a
different random thing that's the basic
idea of reinforcement learning so
reinforcement learning is try some
random
thing uh and try a few different random
things so search for all the different
random things that you know might be
good or bad find the one that's good and
then reinforce that and remember the one
that's good so what is remembering or
reinforcing the one that's good that's
training the model to preferentially
Output the one that was good so you
simply search for random different
possibilities try to try to find a good
solution once you found a good one you
bake that back into the lm's weights
itself you do training to preferentially
Output the good one and not the bad one
directly okay so after you have found
the good solution you just do supervised
learning that's the learning phase of
reinforcement learning it's just
supervised learning you found a good
behavior you output the behavior is to
Output this correct code and you simply
supervise that whenever I see an X my
llm should output the correct good
behavior
y okay so reinforcement learning is not
that fancy it's just adding some search
finding good Solutions and then
reinforcing them with basic supervised
learning Antonio also talked about this
he called it synthetic data it's just a
different name for the same thing this
is like good synthetic data that was
generated by
search okay again you see that all the
concepts are related they just go under
different names reinforcement learning
synthetic data they're to me they're two
names for the same
thing okay so using search to improve
learning but then you can also use
learning to improve search once you've
updated the model to make it more
powerful and more directly output good
Solutions then I will I can guide my
tree search I can you know guide my
search process to you know it's going to
be trying random things that are more
likely to be correct and then I can
repeat and refine the process okay so
this is making it a little closer to
what you might have U seen if you've
ever taken a reinforcement learning
class uh it's usually applied to games
gameplay and you have this game Mario I
want to find the policy that will you
know win the game Mario so I train in my
network pi to you know output jump when
I'm next to the um next to this tube
here okay so reinforcement search for
random actions sequences that lead to
high reward and then train a network of
policy that will tend to do those
winning moves and three repeat guide the
search process using the policy not to
try random things now but to try things
that it thought were pretty good and
search
intelligently okay that's like the beam
search right we're expanding the tree
not just um in all directions but
preferentially toward the the things
that we think are the right direction
the highest likelihood
branches
okay okay so this reinforcement learning
loop with search and learning search
learn search learn that Loop is now uh
become uh that's the big innovation in
01 R1 this latest crop of models that
are coming out one of the papers that
really popularized this is called star
so uh it's an old idea of course uh Rich
suton you know he was writing about this
in the 1980s or whenever but um the
model that popularized this recently is
called star uh and so this is a diagram
I won't fully describe it but basically
uh you have a question the language
model will uh generate an answer but it
will also generate like a chain of
thought that led to that answer and if
the answer is correct then I'll I'll
discard it ignore the hint part that's
kind of a detail if the answer is sorry
if the answer is incorrect I'll discard
it if it's correct I'll put that Chain
of Thought back into my training of the
language model so the language model
will preferentially output that Chain of
Thought they call it a rationale here uh
that language model will preferentially
output that chain of thinking that led
to the correct answer and now um okay
sorry for the lights um okay now you can
see better I suppose so so let me
summarize it on on this slide because
star now um I highlighted R1 because we
actually have the paper so I know this
is how that works I don't know if this
is how 01 and 03 work but people think
this is how they work too so you search
for chains of thought that solve a
problem by randomly sampling different
chains of thought randomly sampling
letting the model chat to itself and
think and see if it comes up with the
right answer or not find the ones that
came up with the right answer and and
fine-tune the language model to Output
thinking of that type with supervised
learning and then repeat and now the llm
outputs better chains of thought which
are more likely to solve problems you
train this on more data on more problems
and it just self- improves uh and at
deployment time you could also do
additional search on top if you want you
could do tree search and all the rest on
top or you could just not and just do
feed forward inference on top and in
fact the interesting thing about R1 this
new deep seek paper is that their
procedure is extremely simple they don't
do any test time search uh they have a
RL um approach which is called policy
gradients which is like the most vanilla
RL approach there's no uh process
rewards there's no critic function
there's no it's extremely simple so it's
like it's it's very interesting that
like you can you can skip like half of
the theory of reinforcement learning and
or most of it and and understand R1
which maybe it turns out that that's
just um you know one point and we're
going to get better than that but it
also could be some kind of simp you know
bitter lesson again or it could be
something about like intelligence is you
know the algorithm that can you know
solve these problems is simpler than we
thought that just might be how the world
works okay so I'll end there and um yeah
thanks for coming today we'll do a Q&A
session now
[Applause]