great thank you so much for having me
today my name is karita I'm the founder
C of the 3D architect so I'm affiliated
with the MIT visiting scientist so we
are manufacturing technology startup
located in Boston here and also s City
in
Japan the problems we are tackling is
about how we can enable sustainable
society and in this topic this is the
two challenges we are fac we are working
on right now the first one is that the
data center cooling power consumption so
as you have seen a lot of discussion
today data center um has other like
Demand right today and it could consume
30% of the world electricity by 2030 and
with within this 133% of electricity
consumption actually 40% comes from the
data center cooling so the heat or heat
disspation is a huge and Urgent problem
today in the data center and another
problem we are looking at is the green
hydrogen production in order to achieve
that net emission by 2050 we need adapt
200 million t hydrogen by 2070 however
the hardle here is that the cost of the
hydrogen production we need to reduce
the hydrogen cost by the fact of the
pipe by 20 stud and it looks like two
different problems here but as a
manufacturing startup we see the
underlying common issue here that the
inefficient fluid flow which comes from
actually the manufacturing um inability
to optimize the design at micrometer
scale so one of the good example is a
heat sink used for the data center
Cooling and that has a typically the fin
structure which has a 0.1 mm Fin and if
you we know that already if you can
decrease a fin stickness or interval
between FS we can increase surface areer
so that we can improve the cooling
performance or if you can make more
organic structure optimiz structure so
that we can make a more improved um
cooling performance however we don't
have a way to manufacture such a design
so the state of the art manufacturing
can only offer 0.21 mm scale of the
design control today and it's same for
the green hydogen production the water
electrizer is using right now the
randomly oriented gas division layer and
if you can optimize that structure we
can also improve the um energy
production on cost as well or decrease
energy production cost as well so to
tackle this challenge what we do here is
that we invented a completely new way of
making Metals which is a listography
based metal 3D printing and this can
offer 10 micrometer features with a
desired structure so that we can offer
ultimate performance at scale so what we
do here is that we use offer shelf
rography based 3D printer or any
rography based device that could be used
for the semiconductor manufacturing but
we use that machine for making Metals so
we have the pro G materials which can be
you know manufactured by that type of O
sh 3D printer and we make a 3D
structureal gel and you have the
conversion technology that can convert
from Gel to metal completely so that by
using this o shelf rography Bas printer
which is typically used for making a
raisin or plastic we can create high
performing metal and allo parts and we
working with a globally mulle company in
this two uh industry spaces and one of
the use case is that heat sink or Li
heat sink we are working with a Japan
heat sink manufacturer here today so
compared to the traditionally
manufactured heat sink we can offer 10
micr meter features with the optimized
structure so that we can offer almost
60% cut of electricity cost for the
cooling and also we can offer you know
by the nature of the 3D printing
technology the customization at low cost
and at the scale as well another example
here is that the gas diffusion layer for
the water electricity system so as you
see from the left pictures people use
this randomly oriented structure for the
on Division and you haven't know that
for the decades if we can control know
this structure we can improve the
improve the performance but today we
only can offer this design you know
basically by Design cat so that we can
manufacture the same structure in the
reality here and people select us a
couple of reason the one of the reason
is that we can improve the out output of
the green hydrogen production by 30%
with the same cost and also we can lower
the cost of material as a by Design and
also one of the interesting aspect is
that now today we can offer the Val
design structure so that you can tell
what parameter you want to chune to
improve the performance of the elect
system for example porosity po diameter
or any other parameters in the design
space so today we are seeking the some
partnership for the green hydrogen
production water electrizer and liid
cooling the example is that liquid
cooling heat sying or coold plate works
for the Vaper Chambers and imion cooling
system and also we think we are seeking
collaboration on the water electrizer
system and Al fuel cell as well and we
are transitioning to the mass production
scale right now so we are seeking as a
chemical company that can produce the
our G material at the scale as
well so we if you are interested please
come byy my Boost we have some products
that has a very fine featured product
thank you so
much thank you Kai