Our next speaker is VJ Gapali. He is a
senior staff member at MIT Lincoln
Laboratory. So, let's give a warm
welcome for VJ.
>> Uh, it's a pleasure to be here today.
So, I'm here. It's pretty funny because
I've never used the title for this slide
before and then I found it on the ILP
website and then I said, you know what?
Let's just run with it. It looks uh
looks like a good title. So, it's the
first time giving a talk with this
title. Um, but it's actually very true,
right? And so, a little bit about
myself. Um, I've, uh, been at MIT for
about 12 years now. Uh, and then over
the past couple years, I've actually
gone out and done few companies that are
focused in this world of AI. And a lot
of our research has been on how to make
AI more efficient. And it essentially
comes down to being able to orchestrate
and schedule things more efficiently.
And we can do so much more with what we
have if we just do so carefully. And so
this has clearly gotten a lot of
attention these days of the power
challenges that are associated with AI.
Um we started a company about four years
ago. This is like around COVID time when
it was tough to get access to Nvidia
GPUs. And what our company did was we
were one of Nvidia's partners. And so we
were able to get supply chain and we
were essentially able to put a bunch of
Nvidia GPUs onto the market. And at that
time that was the big bottleneck for AI
just you couldn't get enough processing.
And now we're at the next phase of okay
now we can get these processors but how
do we actually secure the power uh in
order to run these processors? And so
you're starting to see this even in the
industrial world where large some of the
larger cloud providers are now moving a
little left or right depending on which
side you sit on but moving into the
power side as well because we need to
get that and this is a critical
challenge not just for cloud providers
but for really anyone and I think most
of the speakers have already highlighted
some of the very real challenges. It's
not just AI computing but a whole bunch
of other things that are coming in and I
think we've we've probably seen some
versions of these stats uh today itself
but how quickly AI's energy use is using
what the environmental impact of AI
looks like and even just your small
interactions with an AI system how much
energy it can use
but we often talk about AI and we focus
on this training of large language
models
And as we've looked at the life cycle of
these models, it turns out that a lot of
the energy or the power that is being
used or the energy is really going into
the inference. The amount of people that
are using these systems has scaled
dramatically. I mean, you get it stuffed
down your throat. Even if you don't want
a genai answer, you get one. Um, and so
if you look at the cost parody, about
200 to 500 million inferences is roughly
equivalent to a single training. And you
know, you can think about just in a
given day, you probably do hundreds of
these inferences, just you individually
and everyone else. And so, as we're kind
of looking at these larger systems, it's
really a delicate balancing act of how
do we make sure that the power we're
feeding into the system and the power
that we're consuming across the system
are um are being balanced out and are
being used effectively with each other.
So I don't know why this little symbol
popped up already but uh there's really
a few things that our group here at MIT
and I wanted the last one is a company
that we just started uh a few months ago
in fact and wanted to talk about that.
First is can we just reduce the overall
computing? Right? In order to meet that
balance between power demands and what
we're generating, let's keep the what
we're generating constant because in the
last 10 years, we've only created as
much new energy generation in the United
States as what we're projecting data
centers to use in the next couple of
years. And so it's taken us about 10 to
13 years to put new energy generation
online. And by most of these growth
projections on data centers, even
picking, you know, one end of the
Australia, as Elsa said, um we're still
looking at having to increase the amount
of power that's being used by these
systems by nearly what we've done in
about 10 years of energy uh generation
in the US. So the first thing we can do
is just reduce the overall amount of
compute that's needed. That seems pretty
obvious. Uh the second is to reduce the
energy intensity of the computing we're
doing. So, this is kind of like getting
a car that's more fuel efficient. Can we
travel further with that kilowatt hour
of energy that we're using? Similar to
can we travel farther with a gallon of
gas that we're putting into our car. The
next one is to use lower cost power. Uh
this is really and cost here can mean
many different things. If you are a
person who's looking at the environment,
lower cost could mean lower carbon
power. If you're interested in just
saving money, it could be cheaper power.
Uh if you have other things, it could be
lower water power. It's so opportunities
are endless. And then the final one is I
think one thing that we've really been
looking at these days. Our systems are
broken. They're siloed. We need some way
to bring all the way from energy
generation all the way to where it's
being consumed. We need to bring these
different pieces together. And that's
really about optimizing energy systems,
grid and data centers altogether.
So I'm just going to give you a few
snapshots. This is many many years of
research and so I'm kind of like
cherrypicking a few results um and a few
aspects of the research. But if anyone's
interested in this line of work, please
feel free to reach out. We would love to
love to find more partners. This is uh
uh something that the more the marrier.
So the first thing I talked about is
reducing computing energy demands. Uh so
this is a snapshot that we run an annual
survey of AI accelerators and
processors. This is a 2023 snapshot. A
latest one was just released a couple
weeks ago um at the le Hback. That was
actually last week. Um and what we're
doing is tracking essentially different
hardware accelerators. So on the x-axis
is see if this works. On the x- axis is
peak power. So this is how much power
that processor is using. And on the y
ais is the peak performance. This is how
many operations per watt can that
processor have. And what we've seen is
this cool uh trend over the past few
years where if you looked at the 2019
version of the survey, most of your
processors were sitting at the one terop
per watt line. So over here, wrong
button. So right over there. And we've
now seen a jump to about 10 terops per
watt. So we're we've been able to get
better hardware uh over the past four or
five years. It's almost like Moore's
law, but not really. Um because most of
the tricks are on precision and uh you
know different types of computing that
we're now supporting. But nonetheless,
right, so one of the things that you
might be able to do is use some of this
newer hardware. And so the challenge,
however, is how do we actually schedule
these different types of hardware? How
do you select for a given operation
whether you're going to use the Nvidias,
the AMDs, the Cerebras, the Gros or
maybe all of the above and how do you
choose that given that you might keep uh
changing things around. So this is some
research that we've done where we've
applied Beijian optimization to the
problem. We've essentially defined a
cost function that can find a hard
optimal hardware configuration in order
to meet some quality of service
constraint that you might have. So it
your quality of service constraint here
could be you want to deliver this many
tokens per second uh with a P99 latency
of some number you know 100 milliseconds
for example and what we can do is take
that information we can take information
about the AI hardware as well and then
find a dynamic pool or an optimal
configuration of hardware that can
minimize cost and we've applied this for
example to AWS and Azure where we can
then lower your cloud bills without viol
violating your quality of service
constraints that you have. And this has
been something that's really exciting.
Uh has huge opportunities from energy
reduction to power redu to power
reduction uh carbon reduction and even
cost reduction depending on which way
you're looking at this. So here's just
uh some highlights of these results and
written a number of papers about this
topic if you're interested in learning
more um of applying this towards a uh
recommener model. So a system like what
you would find you know you like these
shoes you might look at shoelaces as
well. uh and we've applied these to a
number of different types of models and
you can see that very often just by
applying this technique um if we want to
maintain the 99th percentile uh we can
still see reductions about 10 to 20% and
if we're willing to adjust our
constraints ever so slightly we can jump
up in terms of the cost savings and here
it's dollars and cents that we're saving
you by nearly 30% just by using this
optimization engine in the middle so the
next thing I want to talk about is how
we can introduce the energy intensity of
computing. And I'm just going to give
you one really uh quick highlight about
this um because it's it's so simple that
it really doesn't need much time to
explain how to do it. Uh we about uh 5
years ago were running into a challenge
with our data center uh and our so we
have a data center that's based out in
Holio, Massachusetts, which is about 100
miles west of here next to a
hydroelectric dam. And so we ran into a
problem of our data center starting to
heat up and we weren't really sure like
how to avoid that apart from turning
things off and you know the MIT
community loves to compute. So turning
it off is not really an option. So we're
really thinking about well what else can
we do to keep these systems running and
so one of uh one of my colleagues who's
an avid gamer just bought one of these.
How many people here are gamers before I
make fun of gamers?
I suck at games. Um but he bought this
like crazy rig. It was a um GPU. He had
water cooling like on this system at
home and you know he started to play
this and he was like I don't know
somebody correct me if I'm wrong but it
was like going at 130 frames per second
and I started to ask him like can you
actually see that or can do you know
what's going on? He's like what's the
frames per second that you you can
perceive? And it was something like 90
or 100. And so like any good scientist,
he comes back the next day, he's drawn a
plot with uh power versus frames per
second. And we found that you can reduce
the amount of power to that GPU. That
was an ampier class at the time. Uh you
can reduce the amount of power by about,
you know, 20% 30% reduction to the power
and still have a frames per second that
is visually looks the exact same to you
or me. And then we said, gee, I wonder
if we can apply that to AI. And so we
did. And so we applied that to our
supercomputer that's running out in
Holio and we have been applying this for
the last couple of years and we have
seen some really really interesting
results. So the idea here there's a
simple setting that you can change where
it says how much power you can just
limit it to some percentage of the
total. We found that you know about 80%
of the max capacity seems to be a good
number. And we've applied this uh across
and it turns out that that one little
change was able to reduce the uh amount
of energy that our data center uses by
somewhere between about 10 to 30%. And
the most exciting part of this and
coming back to the previous talk was a
reduction in the operating temperature
of our GPUs. So we were able to actually
over a year long we saw about a 30 to
40° Fahrenheit reduction in the
operating temperature of the GPUs which
means less cooling intensity less
cooling needs and greater hardware
reliability all while saving you money.
So come on right why aren't you doing
this already? Um, it turns out though
nowadays you can get this uh and in fact
as you're buying if you buy some of
these high-end Dell boxes that are out
there, these XC9680s, these have 8way
H100 or B200 or 300 uh processors. They
now power cap by default and I was all
excited because I thought they cared
about the environment and I think they
do, right? uh to be clear, but it also
turns out because of the hardware
reliability aspect of this means less
warranty calls, you're generating a lot
of heat in an 11U box of a computer. And
so this power capping is now kind of
making its way across and we're finding
a lot more people actually using this
technique uh in order to maintain better
operating temperatures.
So the next one is what I call using
lower cost power. And for those of you
who look at energy systems, who use
energy systems, there is a wide variety
in cost. And you'll see I'm using the
word just cost, it can mean anything. If
you look at carbon emissions, you can
see swings within just a given day, the
carbon intensity swinging by 30 to 40%.
Your time of if you're looking at demand
response or time of use pricing, again,
huge variations in the cost. and why are
we then creating our AI systems to not
care about this or not pay attention to
this. So this is a research area that we
kind of think about which is bringing
the environment into software systems
and I think this in my opinion is
probably one of the most exciting
directions for people to be looking at.
Our AI systems today act the same
whether it's hot or cold outside whether
it's sunny or it's dark or whether it's
windy or it's not.
Why? Right, our AI systems, they are now
becoming such large users of power and
energy. Need to start being aware of the
environment around them. My car has more
connection with the environment at this
point than these large AI systems do.
Even though the power of these things
are quite large and so we started to
think about what would that mean, right?
What are some easy ways to incorporate
the environment and make our software
more environmentally aware? And so one
of the uh aspects is bringing in signals
from the environment into the way that
the software program actually operates.
And we've applied this to a number of
different AI problems. One being
computer vision where in the case of a
computer vision algorithm if it's highly
carbon intense or very expensive power
outside we can use a smaller model for a
small period of time and maybe switch
back to the larger model for the other
times on in the world of generative AI.
Maybe we just give shorter answers
during times of peak intensity and kind
of give unconstrained answers during
other times. And it sounds really really
simple and it turns out it's extremely
effective. uh in the world for the
computer vision algorithm that I just
mentioned uh we had looked at applying
uh this technique right so here we were
using different models of yolo which is
a computer vision algorithm
uh applying this over a 48 hour period
we saw a reduction of carbon emissions
by nearly 80% with a reduction of just
about 2 to 3% in the overall accuracy
when compared to sort of the the
non-normalized system and and as I
mentioned we did the same thing and we
applied it towards uh generative AI
problems and here again instead of
giving unconstrained answers we gave
what's called the generation directive
saying keep it short or let it go and
the results here were even more
promising what we found is that we were
able to reduce carbon emissions by 70%
and the answer quality actually was
almost unchanged uh because a short
answer is not wrong a short answer could
just be better. And so we're working
with some companies to make this. Now,
if you How many people here like use
OpenAI's API or Claude's API? Anyone
here? A couple of people. You pay per
token. And so, if we can give you
shorter answers, it also means that your
token rate goes down. So, we're working
with a few companies that want to
incorporate this into their uh system to
almost give a short answer first and
then let people ask for longer answers
afterwards. And then if you can do so
somewhat strategically, you can actually
apply these during types of during times
of peak demand. Uh and then so there's a
really nice cost as well as uh
environmental aspect to this. So this is
sort of just one example of you know
ways to make your software systems
themselves more environmentally aware.
And I'm hoping that we see more
companies starting to do this. Although
it's always seems to be an uphill battle
with getting people to even give
rudimentary uh information about what's
going on in their systems. But we'd love
to get these type of tools and see more
people building tools like this cuz I
think you know I think most of the
speakers have highlighted this AI
systems are no longer just a side
project that's just happening somewhere.
uh but this is now a a part of that
we're planning grid capacity because of
AI doesn't you know shouldn't it kind of
happen the other way around where AI
should also be modifying itself based on
energy and power needs
so the last one I wanted to highlight
this is uh relatively new uh and this is
a company that we started recently
called BayMP compute uh which is focused
on that joint optimization as we kind of
walk through you know how energy is
created
all the way to where it's being used.
They're all different silos and
different organizations that run these
things. And because of that, there's a
lot of inefficiencies that come along
the way, right? Everyone's kind of doing
their part within the silo, but it's the
connections between the silos that are
that are often a challenge. And the one
place where this all meets, where the
computing meets the power, which is in
the data center, is actually one of
those areas that hasn't been studied
that much, right? I think there's some
lots of really like a lot of the talks
today talked about various components
that can go into the data center. the
actual operation of the data center is
something that's often looked past or,
you know, not really concentrated on.
And so I like to think about this. This
was data centers up to about a couple of
years ago. You had a nice lemon tree,
had a lot of lemons in it, put a
lemonade stand under it. Cool, right?
You can just make lemons and keep moving
on. And where we are as of the past
couple of years is a bunch of people
took that same lemon tree, but then they
put four stands under it. And so there's
a little bit of competition for these
lemons and you have to either squeeze
that lemon harder or you have to try to
plant another tree which is going to
take years for lemons to start coming
out of that tree. I don't have a green
thumb but I'm assuming it takes a couple
years for lemon trees to take off.
Anyone can correct me please. And so
this is sort of a trend that we're
seeing across the world. It's not just
in the US. US data center vacancy rates
are under 1% in some of the hotter
markets. And so people are, you know,
skipping the line by creating, you know,
off-grid data centers, but that has a
scalability problem. Also has a huge
sustainability problem because the only
fuel source you can put online that
large and that quickly tends to be
fossil fuel-based. And so you're looking
at Abalene, Louisiana
um and and many other places that are
coming up with these uh and you know
Tennessee most recently that are coming
up with these huge natural gasbased
uh data centers and these are hundreds
of megawws trying to go up to a
gigawatt. So the amount of power that
these things are using are quite large
and even in terms of the market needs
right there's about over a4 trillion
dollars in data center spend and that's
growing quickly. Um if you're trying to
connect a new power source to the grid
it takes over six years. So it's like
the idea of planting a lemon tree in
order to get more lemons to create
another lemonade stand. That's a long
process. And we're looking at, you know,
and I know almost every speaker has had
a version of this plot over here. Uh oh,
it shows up over there. Nice. Um these
changes are occurring in the next 2 to 3
years. So planting a lemon tree is not
going to work all that well for the next
few years. And with all these vacancy
rates uh where they are, it's becoming
uh very difficult to to use it. But even
when you go inside a data center, it's
not like all that power is just feeding
AI, right? The power is going to a bunch
of different things. And so you're
wasting, not wasting, but you're using a
lot of power on systems that don't
necessarily adapt to workloads. And
we've designed our data centers to
really satisfy peak demand. And we're
not really looking at average demand.
It's like, you know, if you have a 100
amp breaker at your house, you've
designed your entire, you know, you try
not to charge your two electric cars
plus run your dryer plus put your oven
on and the stove all at one time. That's
what our data centers are doing today.
they are putting everything on at the
same time like a gee I don't have power
well what if you tried to orchestrate or
move some of these things around and so
that's what our company is really
focused on is using machine learning and
AI in order to help balance what power
is coming in with the power that's
coming out and it turns out there's a
lot of levers that we can adjust within
a data center uh that will give us the
opportunity to um really kind of make
that balance happen right so in your
house you might maybe run the electric
car charging in the night. Uh maybe
you'll schedule the uh dryer to run at
some other time. Maybe you have battery
backup in your house and you're going to
use that to supplement power during high
time of use pricing. And so it's sort of
the same concept here at a much much
larger scale that we're applying to uh
this problem of data center control. And
if anyone's interested in in kind of
talking about this uh afterwards, more
than happy to spend some time discussing
that. But the basic idea is you know we
can uh we built an optimization engine
that can take real time data that's
coming off various elements that are
sitting in the data center. So hardware
that you have in the data center. Uh we
can predict uh certain things such as
when you're going to hit a peak or uh
when you're likely to run into problems
and you can dynamically adjust the
various components. So at certain times
you might adjust HVAC, certain times you
might adjust battery, certain times you
might adjust the IT equipment itself if
that's a possibility. And you can also
change the optimizations. We talked to a
lot of people that really kind of want
to do different things on one day.
Sometimes they, you know, they're
feeling good about the world and they
want to adjust for carbon. Other times
they're, you know, PE firm just took
over, so they now they want to adjust
for money. Um, and so we want to be able
to let them do all of the above, right?
And so we can but how this operates uh
can change and you know even in some of
the more conservative estimates that
we've seen we're seeing a a fairly large
capacity unlock. So that means if you
are if you feel that you have a data
center that's tapped on power we may be
able to help you kind of raise that bar
a little bit uh by essentially raising
the waterline of what you operate at. So
I'll save this uh for another time. It's
just a simple demo video of of this
going on um which I don't know if it's
working or not. Yeah. So just you can
configure different portions um and and
that. So I I wanted to make sure I left
some time for questions which is a
rarity when I speak. Uh so I kind of end
it here but I think that there are huge
opportunities. Uh some of this comes
down to just how can we be flexible with
how things are working. I think we have
one question over there. Um, so it just
comes down to flexibility and how we're
able to leverage flexibility within the
world of AI, whether that's on what
computing platform,
what precision I'm using, uh, when I'm
running it, or just in terms of how I'm
operating my data center. But thank you
very much. Look forward to connecting.
>> Maybe two short ones. the first one like
the power cap example you gave I wonder
did you have to trade anything off like
performance or anything else to get the
>> yeah so so the biggest change was time
right so it's you're essentially
reducing the number of floatingoint
operations you can do per second so it
does take a little bit longer uh so in
the cases that I showed over there
you're seeing a 15 to 20% energy
reduction so for you know let's say
serve serving a thousand LLM inferences,
but the time taken would increase by
about 2 to 3%. So your 100 milliseconds
might become 102 or 103 milliseconds,
but that's roughly what that trade-off
looks like. So we were looking at where
it's, you know, 15 to 20% reduction in
energy with maybe less than 5% increase
or decrease in throughput. But the
answer stays the same. No change to
that. Okay, maybe one last one like in
terms of uh like if data centers pay for
provisional power kind what incentives
do you think they have to actually
reduce power consumption,
right?
>> Yeah. So that the second one is actually
very interesting because they're
extremely incentivized to reduce power
consumption because that means they can
sell again, right? So they're sitting
under a lemon tree that's got no lemons
left and somebody's coming and saying,
"Hey, there's a software solution that
can give you more lemons." Uh so they're
actually quite interested in that
because right now if you're a data
center company that's, you know, 1%
vacancy rate, uh you really don't have a
growth path that does not include major
construction and capital projects. And
so if someone's able to come in and say,
"Hey, look, we can uh really help you
tune the power that you have and that'll
allow you to get more customers." That's
actually something that we're seeing
people quite excited about. And we tried
to keep this as uh
there's no huge changes. You don't need
to go buy new infrastructure to make
this happen. This is using what's
already there. Just optimizing the way
that they actually operate and helping
schedule and time them.
Um in one of your last slides uh about
the dashboards uh of Bay compute there
was one of the uh the the first one
there to predict the peak demand um of
the the compute loads. Um how does that
work or h how do you do that?
>> Yeah. So certainly when you're saying
predicting it does make a few
assumptions that you're not like put on
a brand new customer in there like
yesterday and then we're trying to
predict that. Uh so in the most part
there is a lot of like known variance
amongst different workloads that people
have oop sorry ah that people are using.
So for example between 9 to5 their so
we're we're seeing this sort of like
patterns that emerge. So assuming no big
changes obviously if you're a colo and
you just replace three customers that
prediction may need to be reworked but
there's a lot of patterns in the way
that people actually use these systems.
And so that's what in terms of the
workloads themselves that though
combined with like the environmental
factors which may not follow that same
seasonality. I mean there is still
seasonality but may not like on a
day-to-day basis follow the same path.
So that's the part that we're trying to
really predict. It's kind of bringing
those pieces of information together.
>> U Thank you. I really like your lemon uh
analogy. Right. So for the for the four
approaches you mentioned reduce the
demand, reduce the intensity and and the
cost, right? So consider a a typical
like large scale uh data center
operators.
Which approach do you think is you know
serves like a more of a lower hanging
fruit that they were easy to implement
for them and also like easier from time
time frame and cost frame? Uh which one
is you know what's your thought on that
one? Yeah. So that's a that's a tough we
have to think about how many people
there are in this and everyone's got a
slightly different uh so you have for
example like my uh you know company
radium we're a cloud provider we don't
own any data center we put our equipment
into collocation facilities across
across all over the place but we don't
own the actual physical buildings in
which they run. You then have some
companies which kind of move up one some
of the hyperscalers are like that where
they have the equipment plus they own
the building or at least they control
the building and its operations. Then
you have some that are coming up even
more recently that are all the way from
power you know from energy generation
all the way to the data center they run
and this is like you know Tesla being or
sorry XAI being a good example of that
where they're generating power and
they're using it themselves and so for
every one of them uh there's a different
uh answer if you want to say that uh for
let's say the most restrictive case
which is maybe a collocation data center
provider so probably the one that we
have at the that we showed at the end
which is that optimization is probably
the lowest hanging fruit for them. If
you're a AI company that's making things
available, the software integrated with
your AI is probably a very powerful
technique that you can use because you
may not control the actual
infrastructure itself. And so yeah, I
think it's a little bit of the usual uh
academic response of it depends um
applies here as well, but really which
community you're coming from and what
levers you're allowed to to dial or what
what what you're allowed to adjust.
>> Yeah. So I um I really like I was blown
away by your uh your methods in tackling
the inferencing stage of uh AI and uh
using that to save energy. I think it
was really brilliant but uh at the same
time like using the lemon tree example
uh where you have more than just one
stand. So if you reduce like the service
uh quality or the service level then
it's easy for people to switch to
another AI that's one of the tradeoffs
or the constraints. Uh so like how did
you determine the optimal point to which
like uh you serve people at this like uh
level and also not making people like
move away from your uh products.
>> Yeah. So, and just uh um a lot of the
techniques were developed by folks in my
group, so credit really goes to them. I
just get the opportunity to present some
of their work. Um but on the you know,
coming back to the lemon tree stand,
right? Uh I mean, if you're a Tropicana
and lemon cost skyrocketed, what would
you dilute your lemonade a little bit?
Um so that's sort of like reducing the
man, this lemonade thing is continuing
this analogy. It's like adding a little
bit more water into it is like slowing
down your processing a little bit. Uh
but there's some point at which
customers are going to be like this
tastes really bad. Um and so that's the
so for some of the experiments that we
ran when we came up with that what we
call the P99 tail latency we actually
took that from published works of what
you know a Google or an Amazon when
they're deploying things at scale what
they're striving for. Um and you can go
to something like uh replicate or
together to look at what the latencies
of large language models should be in
terms of that's the product that they
offer. they've usually put an upper
bound on that. And so we sort of took
the numbers from there. We try not to
invent those numbers ourselves. And what
we did then say is look, if you're
willing to adjust 1 or 2% off of that,
right? While there is a race to produce
faster uh lower latency throughput, if
you're allowed to relax that by 1 or 2%.
You suddenly open up. It's, you know, we
have this in the data center world, but
many data centers try to provide three
or four nines of uptime. And I think
there's somebody from uptime institute
over here they can correct me. Um if you
can remove one of those nines you
suddenly have a lot of options
available. And so the question is you
know can we work with and I think we're
getting to the state because power is so
difficult to get your hands on where
people might be more willing to be a tad
bit flexible if that means faster
compute faster access to power.
Okay. Thank you.