all right well it is a pleasure to be
here today uh and this is obviously such
an important topic and it's a you know
great group of people that's talking
about this and hopefully we can work
together and come up with some great
Solutions on addressing this so as y
Yuri mentioned I wear a few different
hats today I'm going to be talking a lot
more about the work we've been doing at
MIT uh in both understanding but more
importantly mitigating the environmental
impact of AI data centers Computing but
I'll also add a little bit of flavor as
a person who uh also moonlights as a
chief technology officer and attempts to
buy space at different data centers and
set up heavy compute in order to make
customers build larger bigger systems so
I'll I'll go through my slides and look
forward to any questions that you have
I'll try to get through things quickly
so we can have a robust discussion
because there is just so much Nuance in
this topic and there'll be times where I
come off as a real defeatist and like oh
sucks uh and then there are times where
there are some h GE opportunities and I
think with this group of people here
there are some really interesting
opportunities even in the world of data
centers and Computing and being able to
bring all of these pieces together and
there may be some uh interesting
conversation that comes off of
that so let me just start with a little
bit in case uh you're not as familiar
with the environmental impact of AI and
what's causing it so the first is over
the past few years there has been a
rapid growth in the models that we're
using that power a lot of the services
that we're now using so when you take
something like gp4 or GPT 40 those
models are hundreds to thousands of
times larger than models that we were
using maybe just a few years ago and
while it's not exactly directly linearly
proportional but there is a pretty
strong correlation the larger the model
the larger the energy use that's both on
training it as well as on inference or
when actually interacting with these
models and in fact by some of our
estimates we've seen that just in the
last 5 years we've seen an over 100x
growth and everyone keeps predicting
that oh well this is the last year when
it's not going to grow again then
someone comes out with the new 10
trillion model uh 10 trillion parameter
model so this growth seems to still be
growing and as we look at different
types of models moving away from text to
video to image those models are growing
larger and larger so is the energy
impact of that and I I help found our
supercomputing Center at Lincoln
laboratory in MIT and so we also track
where Computing performance is going and
that growth has not been as steep uh and
in fact if we look at some of our
estimates our growth is maybe about 10x
every 5 years and so we have this huge
need of being able to map the the
tremendous amount of computing and the
increase in Computing demands with our
Computing systems which are not
necessarily growing as fast and in fact
that Gap is growing further and further
apart now the solution that a lot of
people have had is well just throw a
much larger system at the problem and
while that does satisfy uh you know
getting you this works that does help
you over there what it does not do is
solve an energy uh crisis or growing
problem that we're seeing in that space
and here are just some other uh I call
these like wild ass guesses because
really don't know um but this is what
you know you talk to to folks across you
know the iea and groups like that these
are some of the estimates that they have
um So currently data centers uh are you
know about 1 to 2% of global energy
demand I've heard people comparing it to
the airline industry so we use about as
much energy as the airline industry or
we have as much emissions as the airline
industry which is reasonably large and
that number is expected to increase
between this super accurate 8 to 21% uh
by 2030 right and a lot of this is
because we really don't know right
there's a lot of things that could occur
that could change this Trend in a in a
very significant way but I think what we
all agree upon is that this is going to
grow to be a pretty sizable amount of
energy use and a growing contributor to
uh emissions across the world there's a
lot of water that's being used by these
systems you have to cool them somehow uh
and as you're getting uh larger and
larger Footprints and Tighter and
Tighter spaces you need more and more
aggressive cooling technology so you
have a lot of water that's going into
these and we often just talk about the
operational side of these data centers
which is how much energy we're using to
power it on but we forget about is that
this new hardware comes at another cost
and we often refer to that as the
embodied carbon footprint but this is
how much carbon has gone into the
manufacturing of these processors and we
actually don't know anything about that
I actually lead a subgroup within uh an
organization called the open compute
project or the ocp and all we ended up
with is we don't know uh and we had
contributions from these different
organizations and there's a little bit
of people don't want to share there's a
lot of we don't know the full supply
chain and where it comes from but this
is another contributor and so while the
arguments often made that hey let's get
you know using a more efficient
processor right going from a V100 to an
h100 in theory should reduce the envir
operational environmental footprint we
don't know what the embodied cost of
that is to figure out when those
crossover points occur but I like to
think about this as you know I think in
a very conservative Way by using just
some of really simple techniques we
should be able or shave off you know 10
to 20% of this energy demand which would
then translate to roughly 1 to 2% of the
global electricity demand which I think
is pretty exciting and this is without
doing anything uh too crazy or too
wacky and the reason for this is and we
talk about this growth is because of
training and inference and there's a lot
of anecdotes and I have a few over here
you know training gpt3 emitted what 500
metric tons of carbon dioxide equivalent
um you know some great papers that have
come out using GPT 4 for every 100 words
consumes three bottles of water uh if
you have some of the work that we did if
you do about a million tokens of GPT
right which is about a bucks worth of
compute uh that's like driving a gas car
5 to 20 miles in terms of carbon
emissions um you know another great uh
anecdote that I love is every time you
mess around with stability or you try to
create an image on that uh that's like
charging your cell phone and so on the
training side while the numbers are
large on an individual case and so 500
metric tons of carbon dioxide obviously
is quite large and you look at some of
these newer models multiply that by 10
to 20x um the inference side is probably
the one that's going to cause us a lot
more trouble and heartache in the future
just for a couple of reasons one is the
scale at which it happens right charging
a cell phone you know making an image
how many millions or billions of times
does that action occur or how many
people are routinely interacting with a
large language model uh or creating a
new video right like using Sora and what
is the environmental impact of that and
a lot of this is we need to measure it
we need to get a better understanding so
there's some great anecdotes that you
can work with but at a large scale it's
still not fully
understood and I like to think of this
even beyond the environmental impact
it's always great when we're able to you
know and coming in from you know the the
startup side there is this huge
opportunity where we can reduce the
energy and environmental impact of AI
and also have economic incentives to do
so so this isn't a huge capex that you
need to invest to cut down your energy
emissions but you can employ some of
these techniques and cut your Opex cut
your cut your own bill and so there's
this great opportunity to align our
incentives in terms of making money
along with helping the environment and
this it's very rare that you see a
problem where you can do good and make
money at the same time and so I just
wanted to mention that uh for those that
are looking to move this up to chain uh
but it's often there's another argument
that you can make uh where you're able
to talk about cost savings uh or imp
Improvement of Roi rather than just
saving the environment which you know I
love to talk about the environment but a
lot of people you know it's it's a nice
end uh piece but not the first
one so I can tell you from my experience
I can't buy data center space anymore I
I often in the market for 1 to two
megawatts of power right we have
relatively small so we're not doing
gigawatt size deployments but it's very
tough to find them uh most Enterprises
including probably many of you here are
severely overpaying for the resources
that you're using you have overr
provisioned probably by 5 to 10x because
you don't know what you're uh
necessarily using and what the actual
mapping between the hardware and your
workloads are so you're often buying
something that's much larger and you're
grabbing it because you can and then
there is a a a break in this value chain
because all of these individual pieces
are separate from each other and there's
no interconnectivity across all of these
so you have energy companies that are
trying to work with data centers who are
then trying to work with AI companies
and none of these groups are actually
sharing information with each other and
so they're all making these sort of
Oddball assumptions that are not true
and everyone's dropping a lot of
resources on the floor because of
that but there are a few things that you
can do about this right so first of all
if we could get the energy Data Center
and uh AI companies together there is
this huge opportunity for cross
optimization across these and this is
some work that the hyperscalers are
doing so you're thinking of you know the
Amazon and the Googles but not something
that most other companies uh have the
ability because they don't actually cut
across all of those components as well
the second is that we can use
intelligent energy reduction and
scheduling systems uh I think this came
up in the in the last talk but a lot of
things are not time sensitive and you
can have some huge carbon savings or
environmental or Energy savings if
you're willing to move shift times or
shift Geographic zones also think that
you need to be able to make your
software uh and AI carbon aware there is
a huge variation in carbon uh emissions
and carbon uh uh impact through the day
through the year there's some great
opportunities there to make your
software platforms under understand that
and work with it and I'll give an
example of that and I think that there's
also you know using AI to help the
climate as well is another opportunity I
just wanted to highlight one which I
think is super cool this is actually a a
company that was working with our
startup they uh designed a model called
climate GPT uh and what they did is they
took a bunch of scientific literature
and they trained a model and they had
two sort of levels of impact here one
was they were able to achieve the same
level of performance with a model that
was about a tenth of the size of a
larger model which wasn't fine-tuned or
specifically trained on this data set
and the second is it is one of the only
models that's trained with scientific
data from the ground up in uh actually
answering questions related to climate
change and so helping shed a light and
answering questions uh with scientific
uh papers and references so people can
actually use that for for their
work all right so I just want to do a
quick thing on you know how do we even
measure the carbon footprint of a data
center uh I will uh you know uh be the
first to admit that this is high level
uh this is not meant to be super
detailed uh but if you kind of look at
the total carbon footprint of your
system at a high level you break it up
into two pieces which is what I call the
embodied from most organizations that
would be your ghd protocol scope 3 uh as
well as your operational footprint which
again for most organizations that are
not running these systems themselves
that's your scope to emissions within
the embodied footprint uh you have
things like chip
manufacturing um storage and memory
manufacturing component networking all
of those different so think of all of
the materials transportation all of that
falls into embodied and on the
operational side is your how much energy
is actually being used by your compute
or your data center what's the carbon
intensity of the grid what is the
specific application usage and how is
that varying over
time if you're trying to calculate the
operational footprint it's usually one
of the most common ratios you'll hear is
something called Pue or power usage
Effectiveness this is the amount of
energy that goes into operating a Data
Center and it's often a ratio that's
called Pue is often shared I have my
qualms with that particular metric but
it's it's a very common metric that's
used to indicate how efficient or
inefficient a system is one of the most
efficient data centers you'll you'll
come across will be close to about one
um probably a little bit over that and
then your global average is about 1.58
which means about 50% of the energ is
going towards non-computing tasks such
as cooling or other ancillary tasks that
a data center might have and so we talk
to a lot of organizations and like oh
that's easy I can cut my operational
footprint to zero and how how are you
doing that so they want to use renewable
energy or there's a lot of accounting
tricks that people can also do in order
to make that happen and I think that's
certainly a worthy Endeavor I do like to
argue though that at any given time
moving to Renewables is somewhat of a
zero sum game in that you using more
renewable for your data center just
makes it either more expensive or less
available uh at that given time so it's
not reducing the carbon emissions at
that moment it makes you feel good and
it is a demand signal to the energy grid
that hey we would like to invest in this
so I think it's absolutely worthwhile
but we think that that's shouldn't be
the only answer and in fact we think
that the aim should be to reduce the
energy use and not just shift to
renewable energy
and the other piece which I talked about
earlier is the embodied footprint uh so
one of the efforts that we've been
trying to to work and you know this is
with the open compute project uh is
actually lead a group in trying to
standardize some of this information it
turns out that it is possible to
calculate the embodied carbon footprint
to some level of accuracy um however
there is no standardized metric and so
we often make these very uh broad
assumptions about oh you must be in this
energy Grid in so that must be the or
you must be using this etching process
so that must be the footprint of that
what we're trying to work with the
industry in the community is to see if
we can standardize some of these terms
so that we can make more of these Apples
to Apples comparisons because a lot of
organizations would like to know hey
should I be upgrading my uh processors
or should I keep it at the same here's
how much usage I have and here's the
carbon cost of a new one uh that's the
kind of information that we're trying to
get off of organizations still I think
work to go there um but there is an
opportunity and especially for people
that are buying a lot of processors to
tell your vendors that this is
information you want it's again it's
about creating that demand signal uh and
ensuring that while there's been this
arms race of building larger and larger
systems can we actually convince them to
like hey just pause for a second and
give us some of this additional
information all right so I I know I just
covered a whole bunch of stuff there
real quick um but now I want to talk to
you about all right AI sucks it's bad
for the environment okay there's a lot
of ways that it it hurts us but are
there things that we can actually do to
reduce this footprint and I'm going to
just pick a few things over here there's
obviously dozens of things or hundreds
of things that you could possibly do in
this space I just wanted to talk about a
few things that we're doing within my
group at MIT to actually reduce the data
center footprint a lot of this was
actually was created by necessity about
a few this is somewhere Co so what four
years ago now we had a huge heat wave in
the summer and we were struggling to
keep our super computer running um and
the cooling demand was growing very
quickly uh and so we started to think
about can we do something for ourselves
because this is is kind of nuts right uh
it was one of those hot jues and so we
started to investigate different
techniques and that sort of kicked off
this whole area of research which we
absolutely you know dog food ourselves
uh but has also had value even outside
of our
organization and so you know some really
highlevel ways right if you want to
reduce your data center footprint what
can you do reduce the amount of compute
that you have okay there's obvious many
ways in which you could do that you
could reduce the energy intensity of the
compute right so you're trying to do the
same task but maybe make it a little bit
more energy efficient replace that uh
bulb with an LED bulb for example or you
could use lower carbon power maybe I can
Tri shift my uh training to a geographic
location that has less carbon intensity
or maybe I could find a time of day
that's a little less carbon intense if
it's a short task or maybe I could
switch in a a cheaper model instead of
uh using this huge model at when I'm at
these carbon intense
times so I'll just give you a couple of
really quick examples we have a lot of
papers that we've written about this
topic most of the software is open
source uh and happy to to share this or
have a discussion after this as well
so I just want to talk about the model
training process that many of us go
through and the example that I'm going
to use here was used for a drug
Discovery problem and so we were
training you know graph neural networks
uh for material Discovery and Drug
Discovery right so you're trying to find
you know what molecules or what
materials do you put next to each other
uh in order to make a viable drug or a
viable material given certain properties
that you'd like to satisfy traditional
way we do this is we take a thousand of
these candidates and we run them all and
see what happens and oh yep that that
one model was really good let's keep it
the rest yeah sure I learned a lesson
but I I I really didn't need that
information and so we had this idea that
look there's a lot that goes on in this
training process could we not determine
much earlier that your models are
unlikely to yield success and so we
built this tool called training speed
estimation in which we actually track
the loss curve of the models that we're
training so instead of training now
these hundreds or thousands of models to
convergence or to completion we actually
train them partway usually about 10 to
20% but we track how the loss curve is
progressing and we can make some pretty
good predictions about what that
endstate converged accuracy is going to
look like so what that allows us to do
is only after about 10 to 20% of the
runs be able to eliminate essentially
all of the runs that are unlikely to
yield high performance unlikely to yield
good performance to instead f Fus our
computation on that 10 to 20% of the
models that are likely to yield higher
performance and so what that allows us
to do is quickly shave off about 80% of
the
compute with no impact to the end model
because again we're trying to highlight
that one or two different models that
are of value to us and so we've applied
this to a variety of problems and it's
actually given us some some really
exciting results uh and so this is a
graph neural network called schnet uh
which is used in material Discovery uh
what we have on this plot over here is
if you look at the this never works uh
on the uh xaxis here is the true loss so
if we actually ran this model to
convergence what would the loss be and
on the y- AIS is the predicted loss
after about 20% of the runs and so if we
were doing perfectly you should see all
the dots line up on that green line but
you can see that most of the dots are
right around that green line which means
in most cases we're able to pretty
closely predict what that true LW
would be with only about 10 to 20% of
the runs I think in this particular use
case it was 20% of the runs and so what
that allows us to do now is focus all
our computation just on these four or
five models that are in that lower box
right because they're still within that
error margin so we don't want to just
pick the top one but we can pick now the
the just three or four that are in that
little box where we believe that the
true loss and the predicted loss will be
as close to zero as
possible right so that's just one way so
you can think of that as let me just how
do I reduce the Demand right how do I
just reduce the amount of computing I
need to even build my models from now on
right so that's one approach uh another
thing that you can do is reduce the
intensity or the energy intensity this
is the replacing your bulb with an LED
bulb equivalent of uh things right so
one way you could do that is to make
your existing Hardware just magically
use less energy or less power um uh the
second thing that you can do is probably
use more efficient hardware and there's
I think both are are excellent
opportunities depending on what you're
trying to do we were really surprised
that that first one which is just making
existing Hardware use less energy
there's a very simple way of doing that
we just limit the amount of power that
goes to our processor we just tell it
I'm sorry you want 250 Watts we're going
to let you we're not going to let you
cross 150 watts for example and
obviously using more efficient Hardware
means newer systems that are better
designed for the workload uh that you're
trying to
process and so one of the super simple
techniques that you could like go home
and do today is something that we call
power capping uh and what we do here is
basically limit the amount of power
that's available to a processor and we
thought this is there's no way this can
work this is way too easy turns out it
works extremely well and we've been
running this on our supercomputer for
about two years now we've had a group
complain and it happens to one of the
groups we collaborate with so they
caught us but no one actually noticed
that we did this when we turned it on
and what we do by default is we actually
limit our uh processors our gpus which
is the vast majority about 70 to 80% of
the power goes to our gpus within our
system we we limit those to about 60 to
80% um of their total power so rather
than letting them go to to 100% we kind
of limit them and in many cases 150 to
250 Watts depending on which processor
we're using uh We've applied these to a
variety of both training and inference
uh and not only does it reduce the
overall power and energy consumption of
the workloads but it also reduces the
operating temperatures and we did a we
actually had an economist on the team
last year and did like a year-long
analysis of this power capping and how
it worked on our system um we were able
to show that uh we our gpus on average
run about 40° Fahrenheit cooler uh than
you would find if you didn't have this
technique installed or this technique
running and what that also allows us to
do is obviously reduce our cooling costs
but more importantly improves the
hardware reliability because running
your processor cooler means that they
can last a little bit longer which means
now our embodied carbon footprint goes
down so it's this wonderful little cycle
that we're able to see doing this uh and
we've you know applied this to a bunch
of problems and it's just it's it's
funny how this is such a simple
technique it was funny because I was
talking to you know we buy a lot of uh
pretty beefy gear in my startup right so
these are six U boxes that usually have
about
kilow in them power capping is Now
default when you're buying these dgx
type boxes because it turned out the
warranty Replacements because the
reliability was so bad so some of this
research is actually helping uh people
like y they actually come in with a
default power cap because what was
happening is one of the gpus would often
get unseated it turns into a warranty
thing and so they come with default you
can obviously turn it off it's a simple
setting uh that you can undo if you want
but we're seeing that people are
starting to actually send these boxes
out with some of this capping now
installed because it really does have
minimal impact uh to the workload but it
does have a very large impact to the
hardware and for those who are wondering
like how does this work it's like
driving a car uh at least that's the
analogy that we saw you can there's two
ways to get your gas mileage right if
you're trying to make a certain distance
you can go fast slow fast slow or you
can drive at a somewhat constant speed
and both might get you there about the
same amount of time but one of them has
far better efficiency and sort of the
same intuition behind what's going on
here but it has to do with like thermal
power caps and aggressive clocking that
the processors
have and then another thing obviously is
you could just find more efficient
Hardware if you're using a processor
that's 15 years old there's a good
chance that a modern processor will be
able to perform the same task at a much
better rate and this is a um this is a
survey that my group at MIT has been
running for the past four years where we
track various Hardware accelerators and
what we have is the peak power here as
well as the Peak Performance in Giga
operations per second
um uh and what we're able to do is
basically track these Trends and so if
your processor is on this line you might
find more performance by moving up one
of the lines if you're able to uh if
you're able to do that for your
processor There's an opportunity here as
well to replace older Hardware with
newer Hardware that is just inherently
more efficient that can perform more
operations per watt of computation
and then I just finally wanted to talk
really quickly about the final one which
is using lower carbon power um it turns
out if you're not familiar that your
carbon intensity varies significantly
over time and location so this is a
couple of plots over a 48 hour period
just showing the carbon intensity of two
sites one's in the United States the
other's in the United Kingdom uh over
two times of the year and you can see
that there is this probably not a huge
surprise a hot summer day tends to be
more carbon intense uh than a cold
winter day if you're in Boston and you
have you know hydroelectric and solar
and stuff like that so what we were
thinking about is can I actually like we
got to do something about our software
right like our software doesn't know any
of this our software pretends that it's
all the same can our software actually
start to use this in designing in in in
the way that it operates and so we built
a couple of tools uh one of them is
called Clover and the core idea is this
if it's super carbon intense outside use
either a lower quality model
slow down your answers do something
about it and if it's not carbon intense
it's a nice day you know great
Renewables you got a good mix Going On
sure use your use your model and that
actually has a a fairly large impact and
it's this is just the starting of This
research area to be completely honest
but I think the opportunities are very
large so we did one experiment with
computer vision uh and so this was an
object detection problem uh we took a
few different models one model was I
think YOLO V8 which is you know
state-of-the-art computer vision model
for object detection you know beats
humans all of that stuff and then we
took another model which is probably a
few years older not as good but
reasonable but definitely a smaller
model less energy intensive and what we
did was we took that data that I showed
you on the previous slide uh of the
energy intensity and said look if you're
in that Peak energy intensity period use
the lower quality model if you're not in
that Peak energy intensity time use the
full model
and what we were able to show in this
experiment is that we can reduce the
carbon intensity for different types of
operations by about 80 to 90% so it's
the carbon emissions with an overall
reduction and accuracy of this model
over a 48 hour period by about 2 to 4%
and you could obviously adjust these uh
up and down a little bit if you're like
well I can't lose 2% I can only lose 1%
sure you could do that also and you'd
still see uh similar you your uh carbon
reduction might go down a little bit but
it would still be non-trivial or pretty
significant and obviously large language
models are the coolest things and so we
did the same we took the same idea and
applied it to a large language model
except here we were using actually open
Ai and what we did was instead of using
different models because we don't
necessarily have access to that we gave
what's called a generation directive
where we told the system hey instead of
uh giving me you know I can ask who is
the president of the United States I can
get an entire essay or I can get a
couple of sentences each of those has
very different different uh energy
consumption right remember the 100 words
is like three bottles of water um so you
can get 500 words you can get 50 words
and there's different bottles of water
that go for that and so we did the same
thing with uh with Chachi PT or open Ai
and a couple of other models as well and
we uh said if it's very carbon intense
limit your response give me a short
answer if it's not en if it's not carbon
intense go for it right give me give me
whatever and we measure that again and
so even here we were able to see about
70% carbon reduction with minimal
accuracy loss as measured by some of
these benchmarks like mlu and trivia QA
and things like that and so again
another opportunity if you're designing
these systems to think about can I
introduce carbon intensity uh as a as a
parameter that I'm also optimizing
around so I just want to end here
because I think I'm way over time at
this point
um we need more data this is a lot of
this has been done in our own system
which is certainly not uh represented of
the world right we happen to work with
you know some exceptional researchers
that are also very aware of the climate
impact of their work and they're willing
to make many of these tradeoffs in order
to make things more sustainable or less
uh environmentally um you know damaging
and so we would like to work with the
wider community in collecting these data
sets building benchmarks building
challenges around this problem because I
think that's where the community needs
to go I'm hoping that the era of bigger
and bigger and bigger models starts to
slow down it at least and we start to be
a little bit more uh you know start to
think more about well can we get the
same answer but add a little bit of
intelligence um to make it more energy
efficient so I want to uh just
acknowledge a number of folks who have
contributed to this work uh really any
mistakes I made are mine uh they did all
the the great work to be honest and look
forward to uh interacting with you all
and please reach out to me if there's
any opportunities to uh connect or
collaborate always always welcome that
thank you
[Applause]