And now I would like to introduce Seleno
which is redefining health span through
precision biio manufacturing. Presenting
on behalf of Seleno is Willie Reeves.
Welcome to Willie. Good afternoon
everyone. My name is Willie Reeves. I'm
the head of public engagement at Celeno
where we are building a technology stack
to scale biommanufacturing of
personalized cell tissue and eventually
organ therapeutics. Uh, Selenino's labs
are right down the street at the engine
and the engine accelerator is one of our
series A
investors. Aging contributes to a wide
range of reg of degenerative conditions
like those that you see on screen. There
are literally hundreds of millions of
patients all around the world waiting
for cures for conditions just like
these. Now, at Celeno, we want to shift
the healthcare paradigm from treating
symptoms with chronic conditions to
truly reversing and curing underlying
diseases. And our vision is to transform
medicine to extend healthy lifespan for
billions of people across generations.
And we do this with autonomous optical
technologies to scale self-sourced cell,
tissue, and organ therapeutics.
Now, we're building a healthier future
where you can have bespoke living
medicines tailored to you as much as a
custom suit made from your very own
cells. And the way this process works is
that you start with a blood sample and
then we reprogram those blood cells into
IPS-CED or induced pluropotent stem
cells. And then those IPS-C's can become
virtually any cell type in the body as
you can see here. So there's a
tremendous potential to treat, reverse,
cure a huge r wide range of different
conditions. And a couple of other things
about these therapies. They are
autotogus. They come from your own
cells. That means you don't need a donor
match. You don't have to wait around for
years trying to find someone who's a
match to you. And this really opens up
the opportunity and the window for a
maximum number of patients to be able to
receive these therapies. All that sounds
great, right? But to get to these
therapies at scale, what we've got to do
is solve the manufacturing issue that's
currently the bottleneck across the
entire industry. Now, this is how autous
IPS-C therapies are made today. It's a
van very manual processes. Scientists
are sitting there looking individually
under a microscope saying, "Okay, this
cell colony looks good. That one looks
bad." They say things like, "This cell
colony looks fluffy." That is not
reproducible. It's not scalable. And
then to remove the unwanted cells, they
use a plastic pipet tip scraping away
with in some degrees 1900's technology
to remove all the unwanted cells. This
process is inefficient. It's not
scalable and it will never meet the
demands and needs of patients all around
the world. So what we are doing is using
very different approaches that I'll
explain in a moment because these manual
approaches lead to also extremely high
costs. It can be on the order of a
million dollars to generate a single
cell line with these approaches. So
instead of manual manufacturing, Celeno
has an optical biorocess that's driven
by an AI pilot system. So the system
makes decisions about which cells are
good or bad based upon our proprietary
machine learning algorithms and then
instead of scraping away with a pipet,
we have a laser that can go down to the
single cell level and zap and remove any
unwanted cells. So what this allows us
to do is really shrink the
infrastructure required for
manufacturing for a patient from one
whole clean room individually for each
patient to a cassette like this one.
This is a Celeno Nebula cassette that is
holds about 10 million cells for a
patient dose. And what this allows us to
do is this is your cells your cure
inside of a closed system. So all of the
cell management, the liquid handling,
the laser process, all of that happens
inside one of these cassettes. So what
this allows us to do is parallelize
manufacturing for potentially hundreds
or thousands of patients in a single
facility. And this will help us to bring
down the cost of manufacturing for
personalized cell therapies by an order
of magnitude if not
more. Now we like to say at Celeno that
our scientists are in the loop not in
the lab. We do have some people pop into
the lab, but what can what you can see
here is for example, this is Katherine,
one of our skill biologists, and she's
sitting at her computer reviewing data
from the AI pilot system. So, our
scientists can log in to this
proprietary platform that we've built
and say, "Okay, I agree with this data,
or maybe I want to make a little change
in the AI pilot system." So, what this
allows us to do is really move from the
traditional way. So a very highly
skilled stem cell scientist can
traditionally manage about 20 cell
clones per week. But with our autonomous
system, we've already been able to 17x
that. So they're moving toward 340 cell
lines per week and counting. So what
this lets us do is unlock creativity,
unlock efficiency for scientists to
focus on highlevel critical thinking
work, not manual pipe heading.
Now, we are really excited to build a
global network of regenerative medicine
foundaries and we're starting that right
here in Boston through our collaboration
with the Mass General Bighgam Genes and
Cell Therapy Institute. So, we're going
to build the world's first autonomous
IPSC foundry right at Mass General
Hospital and the first clinical
application there is working with Dr.
Jeffrey Schweitzer who's a neurosurgeon
and we'll be working on IPSC derived
dopamineergic neurons for Parkinson's.
We've also got some other collaborations
announced with Matriself on spinal cord
injury as well as with Carus Bio who I
actually met with two years ago during
an MIMIT ILP trip to Japan and South
Korea. Uh and they are working on
cardiovascular
disease. So from a partnership
perspective, we are interested in uh
collaborating with any companies working
in the personalized cell therapy space,
especially using induced puropotent stem
cells and we're relatively a therapeutic
area and disease agnostic really looking
at chronic degenerative conditions.
Thank you so much. Really appreciate
everyone's time today.