let's get
started so we're going to number the
classes as if when you have a
substantial thing to do over the weekend
as you did this time um that that counts
as a class when you watch me talk uh on
a screen so we'll call this class four
even though this is the third time we
get together and um last time we were
together I suppose this should be
penultimate class if I'm numbering the
other one we talked quite a bit about
what is a note right and um let's just
take a second to review because uh there
were a couple people who weren't here on
Friday um what what are some of the
things that are complicated when you're
talking about what is a
note quick hand and shout when it's
quiet or
just does it need a pitch does it need a
duration does it does it need a pitch
does it need a duration great um
what was the problem when I
went you couldn't tell if notes were
slur you couldn't tell if notes uh not
so much slurred you can tell what's the
other word he's looking for tide yeah
goes that could be four tied notes right
um depending on if we think of the
notation as one domain as our definition
of the note or if we think of what we
hear as a domain domain good anything
else that screwed up um our easy
conception of what a note
is remember or make up your
own you had 14 notes in a gando we
had yeah go
ahead well for us you have two notes and
you have to kind of between the two yeah
what was what was that called else yeah
John Trill a Trill yep Trill is one of
them and the other one that we talked
about was yep tremolo tremolo how many
notes does it take to write a Trill on a
on a St a standard
score one how many notes does it take to
write a tremolo two how many notes are
there in a trill
whole Gob right a lot lot of them as
many as you can put in yeah so so these
kinds of different representations we
did a lot on today we're going to be
talking more about not just what is a
note but how can we represent a note or
how can we represent something else for
a computer um you know
what I made really nice handouts that I
put online and didn't forgot to put them
out so I'm going to keep one for myself
and we'll try to do a group here going
this way a group here going this this
way and um in the back where I see
people the least um I see the fewest uh
name tag so if you don't mind I'd really
like to get to know everybody by by name
there's um some discussion of various uh
configuration problems and a few
Solutions and a few things still left
unsolved um on canvas if you'd like
stick around after class or um and we'll
talk through some of those things and
the was another question um who raised
it Hannah um no um about whether or not
the standard library is okay so the
standard Li and that includes things
like math and regex and things in Python
that some classes don't let you uh
import yes if it comes with python when
you download it you may use it on
anything so I'll unlock the entire
standard Library so go ahead and import
math within the math Li Library some
people saw that there's a particularly
useful function in the math Library what
what's
that log log yeah the log when you're
dealing with frequencies and things
you'll see that the logarithm function
uh so if anybody reimplemented the
entire logarithm function um uh you
know uh you you we we can talk about uh
getting a life no no no you did great
super we can give extra um points on
that but but yeah um if it's something
that you have to download via pip
then always ask beforeand uh but I do
want to say at the end of the semester
when you have final projects it's
anything goes so if you can find it on
the Internet or you can build it uh you
can use it okay we're going to start uh
we're not as talkative as we were on
Friday Friday we were very very
energetic so maybe we'll we'll start
with um talking amongst ourselves um I
want you to you have one bite how many
bits are in a bite eight good so you
have you have eight positions where you
can have ones or
zeros um and I want you to try to
encode pitch and
duration so the two things that in one
representation one definition of a note
are two of the fundamental parts of it I
want you to try to encode a note in one
bite and then talk about what kinds of
things you've had to decide you're not
going to represent in order to make that
possible I'd like to do this in groups
of two so um it's very yeah everybody is
either at a desk with somebody else or
not at a desk with somebody else so if
you could just uh make that the group
and we'll give it about uh about three
minutes okay let's let's come together
and let's um see we'll we started middle
of the alphabet last time let's uh who's
a group um involving somebody with a
name toward the end of the alphabet I
don't think we have any z's X's y's
Vanessa and Adam either way I had
started this you guys would be going
first um what what's something that you
uh comp that you decided to encode and
what something you decided to compromise
on I think we decided that it was more
important to like preserve information
about Pitch than it was to information
okay so that's always
um a choice the so we're going to have a
lot more information or all the
information on Pitch rather than on
duration good so we we have to make a
compromise that even though I said these
two things maybe one of them is more
important than another great um going
alphabetically
backwards oh we should have started with
Vincent and Jake sorry uh yeah I think
what we decided first was that like M
group pitch is most important and so we
decided to like prioritize uh encoding
like the 12 discreet chromatic Western
pitches okay so we we've decided to
limit to Western pitches which is
already a compromise um losing all those
great microtones and we said we want 12
of them great how many how many bits is
it going to take to encode 12 distinct
things let's let's do
fingers good I see a lot of fours
because why why is it four uh Somebody
explain um anyone want
to yeah Jordan uh 2 4 is 16 so 2 to the
4 is 16 and what's I have to do with 12
you can have that many like combinations
I guess permutations you can have that
many permutations into there um what's
two to the um 2 to the 3 everybody eight
eight so it's said yeah that eight is
less than or well no is less than 12 is
less than or equal to 16 therefore we
need 2 to the 4th so we need four bits
for that so we have four bits in one
thing for um for pitch class is that a
term that everybody knows it's not a
term taught in all of uh of 301 first
semester Theory it's um well say sort of
encoding c as zero C sharp or dlat as
One D as two or also I suppose C double
sharp or e flat um we don't really care
so we're going to use four things for
pitch class something like that
great and uh anybody else use um do
something like this any other groups
Jason and okay so quite a number of
groups um let's see uh yeah we'll go
with Phil and Angelica's group what what
did you do with your other part oh we
try to like up with duration so
sacrifice the like octave PES uhuh just
encod the duration so how many durations
can you encode with what's
remaining 16 16 what are some durations
that that you might have chosen to to
encode or we'll go move on to uh uh Lila
Leela Lila lla and John um we could do
whole notes half notes dotted four notes
Etc whole notes half notes dotted
quarter notes uh explain a little bit
more to your Etc oh yeah so you can have
like your basically like whole half
quarter then you like add the Dodge CU
we have 16 bits to work with Okay whole
half quarter and E eth and so how many
how many bits is going to take if we
just stop there only two only two
because we have two to the two squared
is four right so we can put that into
there and then if we want to encode if
it has a DOT or
not is that another bit so then we have
dot or not what happens if we say h we
just put one more thing in we'll put in
16th what do we get as a
problem can we squeeze that into four
bit into two bits no so once you decide
that you're going to be able to encode
16th you might as well go and do your
32nd 64th
do we want to do 128th or breath double
whole note they're both both pretty
uncommon so so we're slightly wasting
some space on some pretty uncommon
things but we get the dot um so that's
three think about doing just 16th notes
as your base and then you can have all
like multiples of 16th okay you can have
multiples of 16th so you have 16th as a
base and then how um if you had like the
number two or one I guess you'd get like
Z would be note or I guess or maybe not
maybe You' want like maybe you'd want to
be able to have zero time but if you had
zero is 1/6th note then one would be
26th notes would be an eighth note and
then you can do like dots and stuff and
you can do all of that stuff and you can
encode up to something that has 16 16th
notes right with that way um which would
be a whole note so that's that's pretty
that's pretty great way um it does mean
we are spending quite a bit of uh energy
dealing with things that are uh a little
bit unusual but yeah anybody have any um
any ways that we didn't talk about very
much second El yeah uh we thought that
it was important to encode octave
information too uhhuh um so we spent six
bits encoding like the 6 or 64 of the
midi note numbers okay and then two bits
on duration 64 mini notes so now we have
octave good 64 out of the 88 keys in the
keyboard um you decide to do just the
outside ones right and leave out the
ones in the middle okay good and um and
then two bits for uh for duration so we
get maybe whole half quarter eth not too
much more
great um super this great thinking
exercise why might you want to do that
well there's some people who use
oops that's the most confusing slide in
a while
there are quite a number of people who
are very interested in um not even one
bite but six bit
encodings and
um for instance in the Braille music
code one of the important things is
being able to encode um the seven dionic
notes because the dionic notes tend to
be used much more often and maybe
somewhere else you have something that
tells you the key signature the seven
dionic notes and eight durations in six
bits um how do they do that how do they
get eight durations they've doubled up
and said look if you're on 128th note
you're really unlikely to move to a
whole
note so that contextually you take
advantage of the fact that it's very
rare to have a whole note and then a 64
note
um and if if it's really really really
unclear fortunately they put in a space
uh the Braille music code it puts in a
space where um there's an end of a
measure so if you're really unclear like
I I wonder if these are all 128 no no
the measure ended okay they're they're
probably the long notes so that's one
one reason why you might be thinking of
very efficient encoding
um many things are lost there we'll take
I don't want to spend as much time on
this but get back in your same group and
talk about what you could do if now you
had three bytes on
average to encode your notes so that if
we have a typical score and I'll leave
you to think what a typical score uh
looks like that um you could be doing
sometimes you take a little bit more
sometimes a little bit less so just talk
through you don't need to come up with a
full representation
like this for it but just what are some
of the things that you might
add okay let's come back together what
are some things we use this enormous
Bounty of space of three bytes to do
that you didn't do before um let let's
just go go around you can say pass but
we'll start over here in second row and
go um I guess left to
right we say day for okay great we're
we've stopped leaving out o Ive for
everybody right um another
group Dots Dots okay we have dots in
here
great articulation articulation o yeah
um it's every note needed
articulation so this is where average
might come into play right you might
have something some sort of a flag
somewhere some condition that says uh
more information to come and then you
can use additional space great
articulations other things uh we said do
like
Dynamics volume Dynamics or
volume
mix
volume just in case I forget to mention
it at some point a lot of people in the
computer Music World call the Dynamics
of volume the
velocity uh which is which really tells
you that the um that the piano was the
first instrument they were thinking of
encoding because it's how fast you hit
the note um how fast you hit the key on
the clarinet doesn't really make it any
um any louder um but velocity Dynamics
volume velocity uh good continue on I
guess you could do something like what
you just said for the flag where like if
it's an extreme range of a note or
extreme duration then you say like oh
this is an unusually long extreme
cases to follow right or something like
that to
follow and yeah so that could be these
could be little
Flags suppose do people think flags look
yeah flags look better going left don't
they good um other continuing around
other things to chose that aren't on
here so I think one thing was I guess
like time signature and stuff
because um it encoded with like just the
reference of the musical half notes yeah
information isn't necessarily stored
within
the I actually made um yeah I put in and
anything else on this slide that I
didn't put on the other one because yeah
I thought maybe time signature could go
in key signature other things to go at
the beginning what what else comes at
the beginning
piece so chout out key signature time
signature
Tempo name of the piece name of the
piece metadata name of the piece
metadata very
important who wrote
it Metadate sorry that was that was
yesterday's metadata now metadata um
yeah
CL good um quickly go through the front
row if you have something that you'd
like to throw onto this uh we'll
continue uh
was that Adam did you you guys just
smoke right no no did you because you
you you shouted out when I said anything
else you put in your encoding
Vanessa ties
good that lets you build a lot of things
Jordan Misha
anything
triet
triplets
yep
triplets yeah and I was just um
what's the generalization of triplets if
they're
not three anyone know term for tuplets
or tuplets or t more often tuplets in
the British pronunciation tlets more
often in the English um
pronunciation good um anything
else why would we want and so here are
some examples by the way of how the
braille code
uses an average of one B but allows for
or one cell six bits um but allows for
other things so if you have accidentals
we can be adding particular marks to say
hey there's going to be something else
coming next look up what this extended
Mark is or sometimes there is a sign
that you can use for saying hey I know
you'd think that I'm all in 302 notes
I'm probably going to jump to a 16th
note but actually I'm going to jump all
the way up to a a half note or something
so there is there are some cautionary
signs for that um and beams and things
of that sort can be put
in um yeah Adam is there a morse code
for music notation Morse code um not
that I know of not that I know the
Braille by the way music code
predates the um Braille text Lou bral um
invented the music code first first and
then decided to do it with text uh
before in part because um text is
already a little bit easier to read with
raised Impressions whereas music was
just impossible to read with raised
Impressions so there was more of a need
for reading music than there was um for
text at the
time um and just for a second let's just
think what could you
do that you couldn't do with this if you
had about a megabyte per
note that's a million
bytes people have thought of this all
the time and you've probably done it and
you're not even thinking of it you've
probably used a megabyte encoding per
note already
today I know that John
has
just I
see have like different like features
for like the output of the notes so like
like a stere mono sound stereo mono
sound or yeah you're getting getting
yeah Fidelity the Fidel just the the
audio wave of the note you can encode
the exact you know why do you need to
encode um is this a c or saying when you
can just hear it and you can also be
encoding with that yeah the Fidelity the
mono thing you're encoding the in exact
instrument how it was performed you're
losing generality right because you're
encoding one performance of a particular
piece and not um every performance but
maybe maybe you can do one megabyte plus
um plus an average of three bytes to
also store what the note was supposed to
be so so we'll be able to get the best
of all worlds um okay what do we have
why do I care about efficiency it's in
part because we're at a point where um
we can start storing a lot of
information about notes uh you know most
of us don't bat an eye anymore at the
notion were streaming in high def or 4K
or what whatever and you know gigabytes
of billions of did I said billions
before I meant Millions four billions of
bytes in an hour just to watch a movie
so why do we care about if we can store
one extra um thing in the note it's
because um almost entirely based on
history this is one of the earliest
encodings of um of a musical piece of
the dissertation from 1982 but this is
going in the 60s and things and we
started with um with Punch Cards and
punching cards takes a long time so the
more efficient you can get with your
encoding the fewer cards you're going to
need and this has left consequences on
us um for today by the way I always
thought that oh punch card you can you
know you get 1 2 3 4 5 six seven 8 nine
10 you know you can you get 10 bits of
information it turns out you punch too
many holes in a punch card and you try
to put it through the punch card reader
and it jams so you actually have a
limited number of ones you can do per uh
bite or per per row in a punch card but
we're still so we're still having to
deal with some of the choices that were
made um in order back when computers
might have 4 kilobytes of of memory or
16 kilobytes of memory for every single
thing so if you want to store um you
know 16 kilobytes of
16 16,000 bytes
you if you're storing 10 bytes per note
you only store 1,600 notes you can't get
through a whole piece but if you can get
it down to two matters and so we have a
lot of ways that are very compact
representations there are still out
there and that we're only over time
feeling like you know we can expand a
little bit this is your first file your
first encoding format that you've seen
in this class I believe right besides
stupid weird ones I make up on the on
the Fly this is um called Muse data this
was one of the first U major projects of
encoding uh yeah of encoding a lot of
music into things made uh by Walter huet
of huet Packard Fame and um let's try to
guess what some of the things might be
in this what um let's let's start with
something really obvious what do you
think this
means rest okay
good we're obviously already in a period
where we can afford four bytes to write
out rest rather than putting R in so
that's this tells you that this is a
little bit later than other things that
were happening um somebody else take a
guess what something else might
be y go ahead Z does q s for quarter Q
might s for quarter um let's see we we
we might find something that will help
us with that El I'll go easy measure
starts for measure and measure stands
for measure and one stands for one and
two stands for two right um is there
anything that would let you think that
QQ cube in one measure might be the
right
thing yeah t time signature T time
signature 34 right um every everybody's
notation teacher always told you never
put a slash in a time signature when
you're writing on the page well in
computer stuff we always do because we
have nothing better to separate them
good Q's that
um you think these are notes notes good
good interesting thing is that they end
up encoding the duration
twice uh since this one I've tried to do
long time you know what do you think
that is and it's almost impossible to
get so you have the quarter note and you
also have something that says a quarter
takes
two something ticks maybe some things
like that and so you encode it twice
once
what's the difference between this two
that each quarter is two of something
and that this is a q who needs what for
what yeah what's printed on the page
versus what's played what's printed on
the page and what's played so that you
don't need to convert between Visual and
um and and time duration and this is a
function um in almost all modern uh
storage things uh still today
it's also helpful for um there are some
very weird cases that U that you'll run
into in one of the readings later where
composers have used durations to mean
something slightly different from what
uh they actually what they generally
are okay um so this is some of the
reasons why we went through efficiency
you're going to be um on the second
problem set the one that um you'll get
on Friday which will be done in groups
you're going to be coming up with your
own representation system for some sort
of thing that is music except for the
thing I'm just about to talk about
common western music notation so
something else besides normal scores
that we see all the time and you'll need
to make the same choices decisions
mistakes maybe that um that pioneering
people did uh in the 60s and 70s and um
hopefully um learn something about what
trade-offs happen along the
way so we're going to be talking uh oops
this slide's a little bit out of order
should be here this slide should be um
about something in the class which is
called common western music notation
often abbreviated to leave out one word
uh one letter either common western
music notation common music notation
common Western notation some like that
um this is an example of what I think
most people would believe is common
western music notation it uses notes
staves clefts things uh left to right
means earlier to later up to down
means higher to lower right so that
here's a whole bunch of high notes and
here's a whole bunch of low notes
right no except for that there's certain
there's certain things that we say only
within a particular staff is higher and
lower and then we have divisions and we
move on to other systems and stuff so um
yeah so these are things that uh are
standard in common common western music
notation uh that was a piece by uh
Joseph bong the chaler Des s George this
is a piece by uh clar Shuman her Piano
Trio um Trio for piano violin and cello
and see some things that we consider to
be common western music notation
including
slurs ties Grace notes beams all these
types of
things common western music notation can
represent a piece of music in multiple
ways this is an ARA from uh Wulf Kong
Mozart's Opera Don Giovani um
song in that IIM May by Dona and um we
have the top of each of these systems
voice part Italian translation to
English two two staves for
piano and then the exact
same music in some way here's her part
here except for the English is gone very
helpfully replaced with German and um
her nice trouble cff was nicely replaced
by soprano cff for ease of reading for
all of us because she's a soprano and
the piano is gone replaced with take a
guess what are these parts
for orchestra or Orchestra yeah so we
have we have um strings we have other
things going
on one of the questions would
be when we have multiple representations
of the same piece how do we translate
from one to another is there a way that
we can go from this exact moment to that
exact moment and what kinds of
relationships would make that
possible um so jumping back to clar
schuman's Piano Trio um there are some
things that are that violate particular
Norms of common western music notation
such
as well I mean there part of it but they
violate the basic basic principles what
are these things up
here not not Grace notes um let's say
a a quarter note takes one tick a half
note takes two ticks of some sort an
eighth note takes half a tick how much
does a Grace note
take yeah usually half the a lot of time
usually half the aot of time so so if I
put a that that's that's very true in
one sense so correct absolutely correct
it's also not true in another sense so
if I have
44 and I put in a dotted half note and
then I put in a Grace note that takes
half of that so it's one qu so I still
have enough room
for that amount of space right can
everyone see from back here that's a
dotted what's what's wrong with this
representation Adam the grace note also
eats away at the actual time for the
note the grace yes so the grace note
steals
time from the note that it's next to or
it seals it sometimes from the one
before um so in terms of how how many
Grace notes can you how many Grace notes
can you put in a 44 measure let's put it
this way
this trick
question 16 no you can put as many in as
you want because the Grace notes just
steal time so for instance here we're in
68 so we have two dotted dotted um
eighth note beats and we have a dotted
cordin note so we have a dotted cordin
note here and the equivalent of a dotted
cord note here and we can squeeze in
five gra notes there s 8
doesn't matter but where conceptually do
you play that and if we have this notion
that in Western uh common western music
everything that happens at the same time
is vertically aligned I hope your theory
teachers taught you that that's most
important rule in
general how do we know where to align
these notes with the Grace notes so
that's um that's one violation thing the
limits of common western music notation
are not strictly defined this is a very
common p uh genre of music from uh
around 1700
1687 Elizabeth CLA jaet de ja de um very
interesting piece a lot of things that
look like common music notation until
you start
getting what is
this what are
these all the symbols of common western
music notation but used in a different
way these are um unmeasured preludes so
certain places that should be played in
time and certain other things that some
most people believe um these tell you
play these notes for exactly how long
you want I kind of figure some other
people think maybe improvise something
on those notes
but it's common western music notation
but it becomes a problem for the
computer what's the problem for the
computer when it's all handwritten and
so there's all kinds of ambiguity can
you you can tell that okay this is going
going and that's an A and that's a you
know that's an A and that's an e and
that's a c and oh that's either a d or
an e right we can conceive of a note
that is hard to read does your
representation have a way of of notating
that so um musical um handwritten scores
also tend to contain lots of things that
um that don't that violate common music
notation I saw a bean manuscript once
where he was just going along going
along on two states then it became
obvious that the top part was just going
to repeat sorry the bottom part was just
going to repeat what it was doing so
goes along and just use the top one next
time he's drawing the next system and he
needs another staff oh and there's this
empty staff above so he go goes ahead
and uses it so you can be jumping
forward and backwards in time in the
same thing there are small almost every
composer um uh of of significance has
made uh their own tweaks to uh common
music notation this is by uh the 20th
Century composer Igor trinsky later in
his life he started to ask why do we um
when you have instruments that don't
play very much why do we waste all the
staff putting them out so it's really
easy to see what's resting if you just
start the staff where they come in and
end it when they
end a little bit um there limits of
common western music notation come out
in certain uh pieces this was I think my
freshman uh composition assignment uh
when I was trying to be a composer where
I've used some things that look like
normal notes but then at this point I
didn't want to calculate what the Tempo
was so just hold it for about 2 seconds
hold this for about 2 seconds and then
get to this point and this part should a
chill Rondo so we'll just show about how
kind of end like a 64th note is that
part of common western music notation it
wasn't 50 years ago but there's quite a
number of scores that do it
now a lot of the music being written
today are stretching common western
music notation quite to the limits this
is uh uh Kate soer who's uh was a peer
priz finalist a few years back teaches
at Smith college one of her pieces from
uh part of iik SE her Opera um she
herself said it um where moves back and
forth in the voice between sung and
spoken and uses these other symbols to
tell you how much uh to open and close
the mouth and something a little bit odd
about the violin
lots of things odd I'm thinking about
the staff itself it's not a usual cluff
for the violin now we violin in
percussion cff with four lines what do
you think those four lines represent
what does a violin have four of strings
strings so just what string to play on
you'll figure out the
notes uh this is a piece by um Brian
ferow part of a compositional group
called new comp lexity uh which if we
look just at the first measure there's
almost nothing that violates common
western music notation principles that
we learn in our Theory classes but they
kind of take it to the extreme so for
instance first measure is 28 where um
we're going to put in in place of four
what the four 16th notes of 28 we'll put
s16th notes in within that um for most
of these we're going to put 21 30 second
notes in the place of the first 20 of
them or 2 and then within that we can
have triplets so that tuplets can be
nested almost indefinitely and there's
no reason why our time signatures have
to be powers of
two so people are playing with things a
lot okay Professor stop talking about
the weird music this is all all strange
new music it's no nobody in the great
past like Mozart would do things like
this so this is we go back to Mozart um
this is again Don Giovani the end of the
First Act it's very cool moment if you
don't know the Opera they go to a a very
very rich Ball and it's kind of like um
going to a club today with multiple
rooms and multiple multiple you know um
people uh DJs or whatever doing things
and so here at this big ball we're going
to have in one room in 34 a stately
Minette for the upper upper classes they
like their 34 dances at the time and
then in another room we're going to have
a dance in two four for sort of the
middle class uh cuz they like those
things and then for the farmers and
things uh we're going to have uh they
like they like their trible time 38 5 68
Dances all
together at the same time the bar lines
when you say um well let's start at
measure 22 you go I'm sorry my measure
22 or her measure 22 because you don't
have a concept that measures um are
Universal this is um I think this is now
this is Revel or DBC I think it's I
think it's DBC the dance D um very very
common everything looks great everything
looks great
until what does that
mean we're in treble cff and trouble cff
but we have a base cff um just just for
this one note does it also go here no
you can tell what this is what that
means just
better not to write a whole another
staff just for one note right but you
can have two CS simultaneously on the
same staff you can also uh there are
examples from Bach of two time
signatures uh in the same staff or
changing time signatures mid measure and
what does that mean so almost every
composer has pushed the limits in some
ways of conventional music
notation jump back to clar Schuman one
more time there's certain things that
might be very obvious to us but that can
be very difficult for uh encoding in
such a way that it's completely
unambiguous for a device as stupid as a
computer such
as where in the measure does this
begin you all are musicians you all know
that this line is continuing up to here
and that's why there's something empty
here and empty here
but how would you ever how would you
teach a computer to make that kind of
abstraction that lines can move from
staff to staff and therefore don't need
to be um filled
in so um any questions on this sorry on
on any of these things or any discussion
points and Adam we'll start with you
that rest supposed to be what is this
rest this at the beginning of the
there's a oh this one here uh this is
because your professor did not print a
PDF but took a really fast screenshot
from finale and so it's even it's even a
new thing that um our user interface so
this is the user interface that says um
this is a hidden rest until we get to
this note that has to be added onto here
super great no one's ever ever seen that
but yes the user interfaces also end up
being part of our conception of of
notation
today
good other points
or so where does common western music
notation end where does other things go
and um sorry
and what might we want to represent
that's not common western music notation
so this is a a type of thing I work on
from time to time this is um church
music from uh I think the early 17th
century or or late late Sometime Late
17th century maybe um and looks very
much like ours but
just the note shapes are a little bit
different common western music notation
just with a little little twist maybe
not sure but it's not too far off all of
our notation goes back and back and back
in time or it has come from things
decisions beave for let's start with
this is Western music notation this is
the first um music notation of Western
Europe from about the 9th century um
this is the chant for uh the mass on
East on Christmas day um and what these
things do is they tell you how many
notes there are and if they go this case
one 23 um and they go start low go high
come back down about the same the same
higher note same thing we have up down
most of these go up and down here we
have one two three notes going down
three notes going down um the height
means
nothing it is
music might we want to represent this
and how might we want to and some of the
things people are always wondering we
have pages and pages and Pages thousands
of pages of Music in this
notation how is it helpful for somebody
to know how many notes to sing and
whether they go up and down but not What
notes they
are right so that's something a lot of
people out um wish we had met yesterday
be a little bit more obvious um this is
a piece from around
1420 uh B cordier um piece B bons uh in
the shape of a heart there something
about the the shape of the piece is that
something we want to represent where
we're making our
representations about the same period
it's a piece in the shape instead of a
heart in know shape of a harp hard to
say um where it's basically the music
notation of its time except that it's
sideways but um we're writing on the
strings so we need twice as many strings
and we don't write anything on the
spaces getting back to more modern music
some of the things that
definitely violate almost every
principle of common western music
notation but use some of them this is a
Cornelius cardu piece Treatise which
uses a lot of notational symbols a lot
of things that look like music
notation but it's up to you to interpret
them done differently every group
performs this quite
differently if you're going to have a
graphical score where you use music
notation elements but they don't mean
anything maybe a musical score doesn't
necessarily need to have any uh elements
at all Earl Brown's folio from uh
December uh yeah uh December what is it
1962 that's all things that have come
out of the West um Japan China every uh
many cultures around the world have
developed their own notational systems
um and then there are notational systems
that have been made to try to study the
physicality in this case of Inuit throat
songs of um without using anything that
might have the cultural baggage of
Western mation so we start notating the
um the actual you know the the
spectrograms is that a form of music
notation and so how would do that um one
more of of
taure just giving a sense of some of the
notations that might be happening in the
world in addition to notations that um
that have been sort of created uh over
time by people um there are invented
notations that tend to that have been
found to be very useful times this is
something called tubs if anybody has
taken the time unit box system I think
was invented around the 1970s I'll look
up exact uh time later but the notion is
kind of like I did with the um bits
things that you can specify what the
smallest tick you want to notate is and
specify when somebody plays or if you
need to specify different things they
might play you can put that in the Box
this has become a very uh useful and
used system uh especially uh in the
notation of West African
music lots of notational system
representations have been created uh
many of which have not been successful
this is the turntable list notation
system because there's nothing that's
greater and cooler than spinning at a
bar while reading music notation right
but it's it is a way of notating what
somebody did for reproduction later
let me see if I let me see if my sound
is working before doing this I'll be
very disappointing I should have checked
that ahead of time give me one second
[Music]
so um but not all notation and
representational systems end up being
very successful I think this is super
cool I don't know why I made a joke
about it I think it's really Innovative
uh the website has been down for about
six years now so I assume uh it did not
take
off one of the earliest um mechanical
notational representation systems that
that's still very influential is the
player piano role or we just call it the
piano role now where the actual punching
of the of the notes on the staves
becomes a very important uh part of how
um well it encodes the notes so we get
again the same kinds of Notions of up
and down though side and side for height
I guess sort of height turns sideways
and as the role progresses there's a a
cursor there's this technical name for
it I can't remember in piano roles um
that is reading at that moment what um
what should be happening and or what is
happening at that moment there are other
ways of controlling usually on the side
what the dynamic of the entire piano is
but usually not of encoding what the
dynamic of any individual note is and
quite often written along the side
though there will be the lyrics of the
song written kind of like um when you're
driving and it says like you know slow
Crossing pedestrian Crossing you WR read
upside down so you learn to read it that
way so that you can sing along with what
the piano is playing very cool
multimedia questions about about um
things going forward or discussion or
just things you're thinking about um
because you're going to be thinking
about something to represent that isn't
common western music
notation over the next week yeah Adam
that abstract painting that you showed
up the notes that reminds a bit of line
writer line writer oh yes the um the the
game where you're riding on the you draw
all the things and then you get to see
how the um how the motorcycle jumps
around is that one us some people have
that composition in which line riter
motions are synced to a piece of
classical music very very very cool nice
yeah I want to see that at some point
yes is this just kind of like a big View
music books yeah P um it is but um often
something that you could also attach to
your home piano so that you you have
your home piano early on and then later
they become or I might have my
chronology reversed but then they become
um sort of things that um that become
standard loone objects um but there were
there were um things that allowed people
to feel more like they were playing the
piano um by having you um pedal it and
control the volume so you could do and
control certain levels of softness kind
of like using a Betty Crocker Bake Mix
to bake your cake you get feeling that
you really did something to make the
music but not the really hard Parts um
yeah cool yeah these These are
interesting we have um some of these
over at the Lewis music library which
I'm going to be talking more about uh
later as we um go into representation
things but the Lewis music library just
over here um
has put as one of its um sort of
long-term Visions to try to get um all
of the different technologies that have
been used to encode and playback music
over time so there's wax cylinders and
piano rolls and stuff and real to reels
and trying to make it so that there's
some that are very valuable and need to
be preserved and some that um we can
just play with and you do wouldn't want
to have a problem but if you did end up
breaking the real tape it's okay we got
we got more um yeah so definitely if you
haven't been to lisis music library uh
check out what they have
there they also have a theramin if you
want to play with that and and you might
be using them at the end of the semester
when we make some videos because they
have a nice podcast video recording um
space for editing there okay so we've
been thinking uh a lot about the common
western music notation in sort of in
general terms now I want to think about
uh a little bit computer representations
I don't know why I didn't write the word
computer
representations and again these are
slides that I'm borrowing from a
composition package named uh Bel Bon
exactly the named after that um piece in
the shape of the heart um things so we
talked about this extremely fast on day
one but I want to slow down a little bit
more um the two main ways that people
have ch chosen um generally to encode
common western music notation for the
computer are in terms of the container
based thing the Box based so you have a
big box that might be the whole score um
you know some kind of a uh thing and
then you have smaller boxes that um you
know that might be Parts within those
you have measures and quite often um
voices become things inside that and
then going all the way down to
notes so this um representation the
other second one that is uh very common
is the time sliced based container so
everything that happens at a certain U
moment in musical time is it in its own
slot some people would not put um these
in three different slots because or
these four things that in four different
slots because all of these things happen
musically at time zero right they the
clef um you know there there is no um
note or anything that there's no
conceptual notion that the clef comes
first and then the time sign then the
key signature comes then the time
signature comes then the first note
except that we have to write them in
certain order on notation but all of
them are present at the very beginning
of the score
so I want to start talking about some of
the reasons why you might want to use
one of these and why they're all bad
choices every choice you make is going
to be a bad choice at some point so
thinking about um the part-based
representation you can immediately see
certain problems uh anyone know an oia
sta what you use that for Somebody
explain that so Adam I think we've been
really great but I want to hear a few
more voices
right
now anyone ever heard that term AIO
staff
no it's a little
stuff no no pianist violence see it
quite often especially when you're
starting when you're playing a conero
sign is in a really hard
part yeah Hannah alternative way to play
that yes it's an alternative way to play
that measure this this is a hypothetical
one because I don't think that would
ever be an alternative way to play this
but quite often if it goes too high um
for some people especially for singers
actually singers see O is a lot because
uh if something's not in your voice
range some things they'll write a
different different part yeah so you
have a staff that just appears for a
minute we said that our top level thing
might be the parts beyond that sometimes
for a piano thing you might have the
part and then staff one and staff two
but here we have a staff that just comes
up and if everything is in a box and one
of the lowest boxes is a
measure you have these
problems what do you do when you want to
say if everything's in a box that a
crescendo goes from the beginning to the
next how how might you solve some of
that
computationally when everything has to
be in a box and think of a box as like
an array or a to yeah go
ahead have like a flag start something
in one box and then CL yeah so
everything could have a start and an end
or certain things might maybe a note
doesn't need to have a start and end but
yeah you might have a flag for starts
and ends so there are some ways around
it um other possibilities
anybody yeah go ahead maybe just put
them a higher level up like they don't
belong inside measures maybe they belong
inside Parts yeah so you move move up
one level that's great um when you do
that um that works quite often but then
you have a second problem that comes up
and that don't worry this problem was
going to come up anyhow um especially
once Mozart brings his three bands to
the page but you have maybe here's your
part and you have your measures and
things and now you want to elevate the
crescendo that went across two measures
you want to El elevate it up to the next
part the next thing
um let's assume that these are some sort
of arrays so we're putting commas them
then you might have the problem maybe
you put it here maybe you put it here
but suddenly the array is no longer
sequential in other words that certain
things can appear at points that are out
of line and so we s call this the
forward backwards cursor
so that we're at a certain point but we
need to look back or to look forward in
order to see what's happening at that
point but it's also a very good solution
and it's something that happens quite
often so two great Solutions any
other doesn't even have to be that great
those are like the two industry most
standard uh ways of getting around this
I can plant a better
thing okay good that's that's fine I
should have said those are two of the
three great industry standard ways and
one of you would have come up with a
third way and invented something new
never never say that there's no more
possibilities to MIT student um here is
one of the the problem that we were
talking about this earlier with a Time
based system that Grace notes which take
up no concept no no number of ticks in
the time signature but of course take up
time um to play and take up space on the
page how are they engraved and they they
end up being one of the great problems
of the time
method so you could say hey I'm great
I'm not a bagpiper so I don't use Grace
notes bagpipers use Grace notes all over
the time so I can do the timebase system
or somebody else can say look my my
piece is forte from the beginning to end
I'm never going to have a crescendo I
don't need to worry about I can use the
part
system the one of the things this class
CL is not just is not computational
representation but it's computational
music theory and Analysis eventually
we're going to be diving into our
representations and doing musical
analysis on them right and there's
certain things that we often like to do
um we said uh first class Yahoo is
written a parallel fifth almost every
hand went up um that's we call Voice
leading where we're looking at how
certain chords or certain voices at one
moment move to something at another uh
anybody have a have a professor who
frowned on this do we know it yeah um
overlap they sometimes call this where
the bottom note has jumped above the
place where the top note had recently
vacated in certain styles of music it's
not um very
idiomatic well let's analyze how would
we find overlap in the part base system
in the in the Box um system in the
container system we'd probably have
there's one container for this part or
measure and then there's going to be one
container for the up stemed notes that's
a voice one container for the down stem
notes we need to know if at this moment
um at at this moment this note has
crossed over the previous notes in the
other container so we have to be able to
jump back back and forth among
containers and that's it's not very good
to do so the time slice we want to look
at everything that's happening here and
then everything that's happening
here and then it becomes a problem of
yes but but how does this note in the
First Slice relate to the second so for
voice leading problems uh to jump to the
conclusion there neither system works
well they both have problem they both
have big conceptual difficulties that
make voice leading one of the one of the
hard problems that uh always needs to be
solved specifically for music before any
deeper analysis can happen and it means
that generally speaking you're going to
be writing a system from moving from one
representation to another from a time
wise to a box wise and how to move back
and forth and have your system be able
to have multiple representations it's
one of the major
problems last little topic for today and
I think we're done with slides so I can
put this
up um is just some of the terms that
you're going to come up actually two two
little things I'll always make sure
because I don't like to keep anybody
late I want to cover the last uh last
item on there um you will get problem
set two on Friday after you turn in
problem set one it will also will be a
onewe assignment um there is one assign
one reading uh to add on it's about I
think 15 pages or so but uh 20 pages but
most of its pictures um uh that you'll
find on canvas it is a article by
Nicholas cook uh who's one of the main
people in this field called uh
computational comparative and
computational musicology and it is um
it's one of the foundational texts in
this field um so I want read it it's
little it's uh 18 19 years old now so
it's a little bit out of date you'll see
some of the encoding some of the ways of
writing computer code are are are a
little um archaic now but what it says
is still really really good um so you'll
find that online and we'll discuss that
there's certain questions uh to start
thinking about you don't need to write
out answers to them but but maybe sketch
down an answer to one or two of them so
that you can um be quite participatory t
on uh on
Friday and um if you've haven't been
reading very many uh scholarly articles
or this is your first time uh reading an
article written for academics I have
like a little six-minute optional video
on how I read these articles that maybe
even if you are a master at uh you know
great at doing this it might still be
useful to see how a professor um doesn't
read from the beginning to the end um in
one set so if you want that
um that could that might be particularly
useful so we have about four minutes for
the last topic and the one thing that I
want uh that you'll probably want to
look at the outline for I usually put
the outline for you to get later but um
something and it's
about the different um music
representation some of the different
terms that we're going to be using a
lot um has anybody taken uh uh more than
one or or a couple philosophy classes
and come across this
term philosophy class what about in a CS
class computer science anybody ever see
I'm not going to ask for a definition
right now unless you want to do it yeah
great um so ontologies are sort of
this ontology is the study some people
say of essence of meaning of what it
means to mean something general uhu
philosophy and computer science have two
slightly different definitions of
ontology so you're going to start seeing
the word ontology in a lot of
representations it has to do with
representation for for
philosophy and this is I mean really
philos
so um your
you're getting a lot about um what are
the limits of something that Mak
something no longer something so we did
a lot of philosophical ontological
discussions in the fir today and on um
and last class right um what's what's
something that we were trying to play
find the limits of so
much when something is no longer
something a a note yeah WR that there so
what's some things when is a note one
note when is a note two notes when is a
note six notes right we pl with that um
when is common western music
notation no longer can does that apply I
kind of you know uh did the the Frog
boiling in hot water trick like kind of
slowly slowly slowly moved out until
finally it's like wait a second
Professor that's a whole bunch of STS on
a page right um but but we got there
very very slowly how do we put a
dividing line um so it's a philosophical
definition and then and that's and we're
going to be using that one in this class
because this is also a humani class
we're be thinking about those types of
things what is the limit of something
what is a note what is um C if a piece
of music is every note and every um and
every duration that's in there how many
notes can you get wrong and still say
that you're playing you know uh B to
Vince uh how C your
Sonata 10% 5% one note wrong and it is
not the piece these are some of the
things that that the philosophical
definition does we're not going to get
to the second half here but so just
we'll end with the computer science
usage which is also very very cool and
related and that would be what are all
of the
objects yeah disle
objects names
relationships used in a
representation so on on ontology of a
file of of your computer's file system
might say that there are documents and
there are
folders can folders can documents go in
folders yes can folders go in documents
no can documents go in documents no can
folders go in folders okay so we're
starting to make some kind of
representation of something can a a
document appear twice somewhere in your
hard drive diff different operating
systems yes no they're ways of doing it
um so these are all the decisions that
make up the systems and objects and
representations in use we're going to
start up again on Friday by talking
about some of the ontologies that we've
already been creating some of the
relationships and some of the different
ways starting to get back into
programming we haven't really done that
for a little bit in class um some of the
ways that we might represent the
relationships between notes and pitches
and durations and so much
else e