Thank you so much. Welcome to 61200,
6120, I don't know how you want to
pronounce it. Anything goes. Either way,
welcome. Um, really looking forward to a
great semester with all of you. So, a
couple a couple salient points.
structure-wise, schedule-wise, um we
have lectures on Tuesday, Thursday, 2:30
to 4, which I suppose you know if you're
here in person, uh we have recitations
on Wednesdays and Fridays. Uh we do take
attendance at recitations. It's worth
10% of your grade. So, we highly
recommend that you go both for your
grade and also it's some of the most
useful time that you'll have this
semester. Um you'll be working with your
peers to solve problems in small groups.
You'll have a TA there to offer advice
and suggestions. Uh it's really valuable
time. Um and I highly recommend you go.
I guarantee you'll get a lot out of it.
Um
since it's such a valuable time and such
a limited resource, just two hours per
week. Um we have what we call warm-up
problems, which are just quick
multiplechoice problems right there on
Canvas um to get you thinking about the
lecture material a little bit. They're
not meant to be hard. They're not meant
to be stressful. Um, but we do want you
to think about the problems a little bit
and answer them and get the answers
right. Um, getting the answer right is
not as strenuous as it sounds because
you get infinite retries and instant
feedback up until the deadline. As so as
long as you remember to do it, you're
going to get full points. Um, you could
if you want just option A, click, nope,
that's wrong. Option B, click, nope,
that's wrong. Option C. We don't
recommend that. Ideally, it's in your
favor to actually think about the
problem a little bit. might even be a
little faster. But the point is to be a
reminder to think about the lecture
material a little bit before you come to
recitation. What we want to avoid is
everyone shows up to recitation and
says, "Wait, what are we covering today?
I don't even know. I wasn't able to go
to lecture. I don't know what was
covered. Can someone fill me in?" Um, I
would prefer that we that we do the
catching up before recitation. So, by
the time we get there, we know what
we're going to talk about. We can ask
any questions we have. we can start
working on the problems and use that
time as productively as possible.
Um, so that's recitations and warm-ups.
We have problem sets. We'll have weekly
problem sets due on Monday nights. I
hope everyone turned it in yesterday.
Um, they'll be released on Tuesdays. Oh,
I got a thumbs up. Where did you send
that?
Um, we'll release problem sets Tuesdays.
They'll be due on Monday nights 11:59
p.m. Uh, so as Monday night as we can
get. Um,
and I want to say a few words about
these problem sets, uh, about the
structure and about the collaboration.
We want you to collaborate. We want you
to work with your peers. We want you to
get help from us in office hours and on
piaza and things like that. We want you
to solve these problem sets
collaboratively if you so choose. Um, we
do have we are signed up for pet
partners. So once a week, shortly after
the problem sets go out, um the pizza
partner site will match you with other
problem set solvers that have similar
schedules. So if you want to find a
group that way, you're more than welcome
to. We'll set it to go off a couple days
after each problem set releases. So just
be sure to sign up on time. If you miss
the first round, you can sign up in the
second round. Or you can come to office
hours and find friends there. You can
work with friends at your dorm. However
you want to find partners, go ahead and
do it if you want. And we encourage you
to solve these problems correctly.
Sorry, collaboratively also correctly,
you know. Um, not the worst Freudian
slip. Um, we encourage you to solve
collaboratively. Figure things out. Some
of these problems are challenging. Some
of them have tricks that you're you
might not see immediately and you have
to figure out what's going on. However,
there's a second step to this to the
problem set process that I want to call
attention to, and that's the writing
step. One of the main goals of this
course, one of the main exports for this
course is proof writing. The ability to
write precise, concise, correct
mathematical arguments. And that is a
skill that we will be practicing and
developing all semester.
And everyone has a slightly different
style. Everyone thinks about these
things differently. Uh, and the act of
just constructing a proof, even if it
all makes perfect sense in your head,
the act of translating that into a proof
on paper that's able to be read and
consumed and believed by others is its
own special skill. And we want you to
get lots of practice with that. Keyword
being you, not your group. So, go ahead
and solve the problems collaboratively.
Whatever notes you've generated, that's
fine. Keep them, study from them. But
when you're going to write your problem
set, put those notes aside, please, and
piece things together yourself in your
words, showing your understanding. So
solve together, write alone. Just to
emphasize this one more time, the reason
I'm spending all this time belaboring
this point is something I like to call
the P versus NP fallacy, which just says
that reading and understanding someone
else's proof is easier than constructing
that proof yourself.
And it's really tempting to think that
these two tasks are equivalent. Like
when you're studying for a test, you
read through our problem set solutions
like, "Yeah, that makes sense. That
makes sense. That makes sense. Great.
I'm convinced that doesn't immediately
translate to I therefore could have put
it together myself.
So understanding a proof and writing a
proof, two different skills. We want you
to get practice with both. Any questions
about that? About the intent behind our
collaboration policy.
Awesome.
Um let's see. Late problem sets. Last
thing I want to talk about, we do accept
late problem sets. We accept very late
problem sets. Um so we put a lot of
effort into making these problem sets at
least trying to make these problem sets
both interesting and useful. And so we
want to incentivize all of you to work
the problem sets as much as you can um
in as many ways as you can even if that
means it's late. If the schedule doesn't
line up you had to miss some problem
sets. We want you to be able to catch up
by doing the problem sets. So, we allow
late problem sets up to and including
the last day of classes.
Um, if you forget to do problem set one
and you you remember, oh, in the last
week, maybe I should go back and and
solve those problems.
Probably would have been more useful to
do it before the first quiz, but you
know, better late than never. Um, you
can still turn in that problem set late
for half credit. More precisely, our
late problem set policy is that for the
first 50 hours, um the late penalty or
the percentage of points that you will
earn from your submission goes from 100%
if it's on time down to 50% if it's 50
hours late and 1% each hour for those
first 50 hours, those first two-ish
days. And then after that, it stays at
50 for the rest of term. Uh that also
means that if you're if it's 11:45
and you have one problem left, you you
know how to do it, you just down to the
wire for writing it down or you want to
take another hour or 30 minutes or
something to think about that problem.
Go ahead and be a little late. It's not
a big deal. If you're 1 hour late,
you're still going to get 99% of the
points that you would have otherwise.
It's worth it to take that extra time.
It means that there there isn't a sharp
cut off between before the deadline and
after the deadline. It's not a big deal.
Don't worry about it. We want to reduce
stress for everyone involved. Any
questions about that?
Excellent. All right. Like I said, lots
more details there on the course
information policies um PDF on our
Canvas site. And with that, let's let's
talk about some math.
So, as I said earlier, the one of the
main skills and tools that we want you
to have coming out of this class is the
ability to write proofs and read proofs
and evaluate proofs. Um, as one of my
colleagues says, this class could have
been called proofs, proofs, and more
proofs. We're going to talk about proofs
a lot, especially today where we're
going to start with what is a proof?
And I'm going to write that down because
it's important enough. What
is a proof?
And I'm going to give a starting answer
and we're going to elaborate on this a
little bit. Here's uh question and
answer.
It's a method
of ascertaining truth.
A proof is how you show that something
is true.
And we as a society have lots and lots
of methods for determining what's true.
Uh I'm going to give you a couple. For
example, we have uh we have experiments
and observation and the scientific
method. Um that is how we determine
what's true in the physical sciences. Uh
we have sampling.
If you want to know who's likely to win
an election, you pick a random sample
and you ask who they're going to vote
for and you generalize.
Um, we have legal proceedings.
You hold a trial. Huh, two different
L's. Who knew? Uh, you hold a trial to
determine what happened and who's
culpable. That is how we determine truth
in those cases. Who can give me some
others? How do we determine truth?
Yes.
Investigation.
All right. Yeah. Investigation.
Absolutely. Um
investigation.
Looking for evidence. Um looking for the
the most likely explanation that fits
the observation. So actually pretty
similar to some of the other ones. Yes.
asking questions.
Asking questions. Absolutely. Um,
cool. Let me give you um a couple more.
Um,
authority. If your professor says this
is true, then it's true, right?
Please don't do that.
Uh, we make mistakes all the time and we
want you to call us out on that.
Um we have religion.
This is what our religion says. This is
what our deity says. Therefore, it is
true and it is how I should um live my
life. These are the values I should
value. Um we have like inner conviction.
I just feel like it should be this way.
Like deep in my gut I know it's true. It
came to me in a dream.
Sometimes
that is how things work. Um so lots of
different ways of determining truth,
lots of different meanings of the word
truth in those situations. Um and as
mathematicians we have our own
procedures for determining truth. Um and
that is a mathematical proof.
So definition
A mathematical proof.
Is a verification of a proposition
by a chain of
logical deductions
from a base set of axioms.
A mathematical proof is a verification
of a proposition by a chain of logical
deductions from a base set of axioms.
And there are three terms inside of that
definition that we're going to focus on
today and tomorrow. We'll break them
down one at a time and hopefully make
this make more sense. Let's start with
proposition. What is a proposition?
Definition.
A proposition is a statement
That is true.
Oops. Or false.
Today is Tuesday. Proposition.
Yeah, it's Oh, that is true. Yeah. Okay.
Um, today is Thursday. Proposition.
Yeah, it's false, but it's still a
proposition.
Um,
[Applause]
let's see examples. 2 + 3 = 5.
Yeah, proposition.
2 + 3 = 4.
Still a proposition.
Here's one.
For all n in the natural numbers,
n^2 + n + 41 is prime.
This is new notation. Let's break it
down. This says
for all. So for every n that is in the
natural numbers, this what's called
blackboard bold capital N is the natural
numbers.
Also known as the set zero, 1 2 3
and all the way up. starts at zero,
starts counting upwards. Um, outside of
this class, you might see um people
trying to convince you that zero is not
a natural number. Uh, they're wrong. At
least for the purposes of this class, 0
is always a natural number.
Um, all right. So, every natural number
for every natural number n, n^2 + n is
plus 41 is prime. Is this
a proposition?
Yeah, it's a statement where it at least
makes sense to ask is this true or
false.
There's a related concept by the way. So
this thing in here just n^2 + n + 41 is
prime. Is that a proposition?
Let me give a an even easier example.
Um oh my examples were already on that
board. Um, sorry.
[Applause]
Even easier example. P is prime.
Is that a proposition?
I'm seeing some thumbs down. I'm seeing
some thumbs down. Yeah, it's not a
proposition.
Not a proposition.
Because it's sort of incomplete
information. What P are we talking
about? If you tell me a P is seven
prime, that's a proposition. Is 12
prime, that's a proposition. So this is
sort of a proposition with a variable
that we need to fill in before it
becomes a proposition. This is what's
called a predicate. This is a predicate.
And I was bringing back the old board so
I could write down that definition.
A predicate
is a proposition
whose truth depends
on variables.
So it's sort of a parameterized
proposition. Once you tell me what the
variables are, then it's a proposition.
And we just saw an example up here.
I hope no one's getting dizzy from all
the boards moving around.
We just saw an example here where this
inside
is a predicate that depends on n. And
this for all is able to take that
predicate depending on n and wrap it up
into what is now a proposition. It says
that this predicate about n needs to be
true for every natural number. And now
it's a proposition. It's either true or
false.
Is it true or false? Let's see if we can
figure it out. We know it's a
proposition, but is it true? Is it
false? Um, well, let's let's do the
natural thing and try some examples.
Okay. Well, here's n here's n ^2 + n +
41. Is it prime?
Great. So, natural numbers, remember,
start at zero. So when n is zero, this
is 41. Absolutely prime. When n is one,
this is 43. Still prime. Looking good so
far. How about two? I think we get 47.
Also prime. And if you check 3, four,
five, six, prime, prime, prime, prime.
It keeps being prime. Um, what if we go
all the way up to like 39? We get 161.
If my notes are to be believed, which is
also prime,
this is looking pretty convincing,
right? There we go.
And in some fields of study, just doing
a sufficient number of examples would be
enough evidence for it to be true or
effectively true or as good as true.
Unfortunately, for us mathematicians, if
we say for all n, we need all of the n,
just these 40 examples isn't enough.
Um,
and of course, if you go one more,
um, did I write this down? Oh, here.
Let's jump to 41. 41 looks like a good
example cuz that's going to be a
multiple of 41. Multiple of 41. Multiple
of 41. Uh, turns out what you get is
41 time 43,
which is not prime.
And so we found an example where this is
not prime and therefore this proposition
is false.
If it's supposed to be true for every
natural number to disprove it, all we
need to find is a single counter
example, a single number n that doesn't
satisfy the required conditions. Does
that make sense?
Cool. Turns out if you go to 40, I'm
pretty sure you get 41 squared, which is
also not prime. Um, so 0 through 39 are
are really um the most you're going to
get in that run.
All right, let's look at another example
of a of a fun proposition
just to get more familiar with this.
Let's see. Goldbox conjecture.
Let's see.
Every
even
number greater than two
is the sum of two primes.
Every even number greater than two is a
sum of two primes. For example, can we
do 12?
Who can tell me? Um, let's see. Yes.
7 + 5. Excellent. 7 + 5 prime plus
prime. So, 12 is a sum of two primes.
The claim is that every even number
starting at four can be written as a sum
of two primes.
And it's called a conjecture because we
don't know if it's true.
I love u I love in math and often
especially in number theory you can
state these very simply uh stated
conjectures, theorems, questions that
are just beyond human understanding.
They're beyond the scope of what modern
mathematical tools are able to tackle.
And it's really pretty that right here
is beyond the cutting edge of math.
We've already gotten there first
lecture.
Um
yeah, really pretty problem and in fact
in I think 1995 it was highlighted in
the globe as one of the biggest unknown
questions in math. Um right here goldbox
conjecture.
Um for example 20 can be expressed as 9
+ 11.
Oops 9 isn't prime.
Okay. So, have we have we disproven
Goldbox conjecture?
No. Why not? Yes. Yeah. It's 17 plus
three. 20 is 17
plus three.
So, really pretty question. Wish the
reporting had been better, but we can
forgive them.
Um, are there any questions about
propositions and predicates so far?
Yes.
You said P is not proposition. Yep.
Um it's Yeah, that's very good point.
That wording is maybe not great. Um
um is a proposition
that depends on variables. Um except
that
it depends on variables.
Um, it becomes a proposition after you
give values to the variables. Yeah, I
agree. We should we should fix that for
the next go around.
Um, all right. Now that we have
propositions and predicates,
really useful thing is to be able to
combine them into bigger and more
complicated and new propositions and
predicates. And we have a couple what
are called boolean operators that help
us do that. Um, for example,
if A and B are propositions,
propositions,
we have what's called not A.
This is a new proposition.
Um, it's sometimes written instead as A
with a bar on top. It's sometimes also
written as that weird right angle symbol
next to the A.
These all mean the same thing. They're
just different notations for the same
thing.
And this is just the proposition that A
is false.
A is false.
So you read it as not A and it means A
is false. We can clarify this with
what's called a truth table. So here's A
and A is a proposition which means there
are really only two two possibilities.
It's either true or it's false. And so
let's write down both of those options.
It can be either true or false. And then
we can look at not A
and ask what is not A when A is true.
Well, not A is supposed to flip it. So
not A is false. And when when A is
false, not A is true.
So this truth table can be taken as the
definition of not.
Yeah.
So,
truth
table and let's do some more interesting
truth tables.
Uh let's use two propositions. Now, if
we have A and B,
um well then there are four
possibilities.
They might both be true. A might be true
and B is false or false and true or
false and false. And our truth table is
supposed to cover all the possibilities.
So we're going to have four rows this
time. And let's look at A and
B. This is a new operator
and it means what you think it means
because it's also an English word. A and
B means that both A and B are supposed
to be true. So if A and B are both true
then A and B is true
otherwise it's false.
A and B means both A and B have to be
true.
Likewise we have A or B
which means at least one of A and B has
to be true.
So if they're both true that's fine. If
only A is true, that's fine. If only B
is true, that's fine. The only way for
this to fail is if both A and B are
false.
Uh, so I want to emphasize this is an
inclusive or. It's fine if both of them
are true. It just means that at least
one of them has to be true.
Um, notationwise,
A and B
is also sometimes denoted A and this
little wedge symbol B.
You can remember it because that looks
kind of like a capital A for and, but,
but you don't put the cross in. But
honestly, if we're looking for clarity,
I think that's a lot clearer, especially
because A or B is also often denoted
with the same symbol upside down. And I
don't have a clever pneumonic for that
one. So if you're trying to remember
which one to use, just use these. That's
my advice.
Um, but back to this or. I said this is
an inclusive or. So it's totally fine if
A and B are both true. Um, in English
that's not always what we mean. Uh, and
or not. These are words in spoken
English as well.
And when we're talking about math, when
we're using these words in a math
formula, we mean exactly what's written
here. But when we use these words in
English, we don't always mean that. Um,
spoken colloquial English or other
spoken languages are imprecise and
context dependent. And that really makes
it difficult to communicate precise
things.
um especially given the fact that as
humans we communicate math using spoken
language. We're trying to communicate
precise things with an imprecise channel
with an imprecise language. So, as an
example of how bad this can get, um
let's look at this word or.
Say you're you're at a nice wedding. Um
the waiter comes around and says, "Did
you order the chicken?
or the pasta.
And when the waiter asks this question,
they're trying to communicate some set
of allowable responses,
right?
Um, okay. So, are you allowed to say, "I
ordered the chicken." Just the chicken.
Yeah, seems reasonable.
Pasta. You can say, "I ordered the
pasta." Can you say
I ordered both?
Probably not. Um the the catering
company got all the RSVP cards in
advance and everyone was told to pick
just one, so they did. So if you tell
the waiter you you picked both, first of
all, you're lying. Second of all, stop
trying to make their jobs harder. It's
hard enough. They have hundreds of
people to serve.
So, probably not expected to say that
one. Likewise, you're probably not
expected to say neither.
I mean, I I could go back and forth on
that one, but let's say everyone filled
out the RSVP card correctly. And so, the
waiter isn't expecting a neither. So,
here,
chicken or pasta, they were they were
allowing this response and this
response, but not these other two
responses.
This is not how we defined or in a math
sense.
This is what's called exclusive or. You
have to pick one or the other but not
both and not neither.
So this is what mathematicians would
call exor for exclusive or.
Okay. So after dinner the waiter comes
around and again and says you can have
coffee or tea.
Excellent. What responses are they
expecting this time? Can you say just
coffee?
Yeah. Can you say I want tea? Yeah,
absolutely.
Can you say I want both?
Waiter's going to look at you sideyed
and say there's only one mug in front of
you and I am not mixing them. This is a
fancy venue. So, no. They're probably
not expecting an answer of both. Can you
say neither? I don't want coffee or tea.
Yeah, that's fine. Not everyone wants a
hot drink. Even at a fancy restaurant,
not everyone wants a fancy wedding. I
apologize.
Not everyone wants a fancy drink, a hot
drink after dinner. So now you can ask
for coffee or tea or neither, but not
both.
Surely that's how we define ore in a
math sense, right?
No,
the these two are swapped. This isn't
or. This is what mathematicians call
NAND. It's the knot of the and
nand.
Okay. Well, waiter used the word ore
twice. Let's try one more. May maybe
they'll get it right this time. You
order you ask for the coffee and they
say you can have cream or sugar.
Can you ask for cream? Yeah, absolutely.
Can you ask for sugar? Just sugar.
Yeah. Can you ask for both?
Yeah. Some people like a a really sweet
and creamy drink. Um, both.
Can you ask for neither?
Yeah. Some people like black bitter
coffee inexplicably.
Um, so all four of these options are
valid. This use of the word ore also
doesn't mean what mathematicians mean by
the word or.
This one means anything goes. I'm just
telling you what your options are. I
don't have a math term for that.
True. Yes. Um, so three uses of the word
or. None of them mean what or means.
Isn't language fun?
The moral here is first of all when you
see these in an actual formula with
other predicates and quantifiers and
whatnot um we mean exactly what's
written here. If we use it in a sentence
ideally we also mean what's written here
but we might mess up as well and slip
into colloquial context dependent
English. And if you're ever confused,
ask.
Um, if you're right and we we messed up
the wording, we will thank you and fix
it. If you're wrong and and we meant
what we wrote, well, now you have
confidence that that is what we meant to
write. Uh, and we are both parties are
happier because of it. So, please ask
for clarity if you're ever unsure of the
wording we use, whether it's these
specific words or anything else. Any
questions?
Wonderful.
Let's look at one other operator. We've
looked at and and or not. Exor and NAND.
Those are I mean they're there. They're
less important. I would master those
three first. I want to look at one more
that's really important both for this
class and for proof writing and that is
implies.
Implication.
We're going to write it as a
implies b.
Sometimes you'll see it written as a
arrow b or a double arrow b. There's no
difference. These are all notations for
the same thing. For this concept of
implication, a implies b.
Um, and when read aloud, I recommend
reading it as a implies b
or equivalently
if a
then b.
If a then b. This is already starting to
look like a programming language. Um,
and if statements in programming
languages are exactly doing what
implication in math is doing. So let's
talk about what that is. Um, as before,
we can figure out what these terms mean
uh by drawing the truth table.
So, we have A and B.
True, true, false, false. True, false,
true, false. Okay. A implies B.
If A and B are both true, does A imply
B?
Seems Yeah, seems pretty intuitive.
Yeah. Okay. If A and B are both false,
if false, then false. Again, seems okay
to me.
All right. If A is true and B is false.
If true, then false.
Does that sound good to you?
I saw a couple headshakes, couple nods,
more headshakes, though. Yeah. If true,
then false. That's kind of the whole
purpose of this wording. If A is true,
then B is true.
So if A is true, then B better be true.
And if it's false, we're sad.
Yeah. Okay. Last case. If A is false and
B is true, should this be true or false?
Think about it for a second
and let's take a poll. Who thinks false
implies true should be true? Raise your
hand.
Who thinks false implies true should be
false? Raise your hand.
Um, who just wants the answer and
doesn't want to think about it? Raise
both hands.
Okay, the both hands win.
Um, it was about an even split. Um, this
answer is not so intuitive. Um, in this
sort of abstract setting, if A then B.
Well, what what does it mean? What do we
want it to mean?
I claim, however, this what?
Last line. Oh yeah, sorry. Thank you.
This should be true.
Thank you. See, I do make mistakes.
It's not so clear, but I claim this is a
task that you are all familiar with in a
different context, in many different
contexts. So, let's make it concrete.
Let's pick an example. Let's see.
On Wednesdays, we wear pink.
Said differently, if it's Wednesday,
then wear pink. Wednesday implies pink.
Wednesday implies pink.
Now, it's an implication. And let's go
through the cases and see what's
happening. So, if it's Wednesday and I'm
wearing pink, am I obeying the rule or
violating it? On Wednesdays, we wear
pink. Yeah, I'm doing what it says. On
Wednesdays, we wear pink. Great. Okay,
so that one's fine. If it's Tuesday and
I'm wearing that color, whatever it is,
uh, and not pink, let's hide this. Um,
if it's not Wednesday and I'm not
wearing pink, am I obeying the rule or
violating it? Yeah, I'm obeying that
rule. That's fine. If it's Wednesday and
I'm wearing blue,
am I obeying the rule or violating it?
I'm violating it. On Wednesdays, we were
pink. I'm supposed to wear pink. And if
I'm not wearing pink on a Wednesday,
I'm not doing what the rule says. And
now we get to the confusing case. If
it's Tuesday,
not Wednesday, and I am wearing pink, n
obeying the rule or violating it.
Thumbs up.
Anyone think I'm violating it? No. In in
this way, in this concrete setting, it
makes total sense that on Wednesdays we
were pink. On all other days, I don't
care. Anything goes. I only have an
opinion on what you're wearing on
Wednesday.
So, we're going to define this to be
true. False implies true is true. As I
said, confusing in an abstract setting
makes more sense if you think about it
as obeying a certain rule. If it's
Wednesday, you have to do something
specific. If it's not Wednesday,
anything is fine. Yes. Question.
So, with the example of like Let's say
you're wearing you're violating.
What if you're like
wearing pink as well?
Yeah, good question. What if it's
Wednesday and you're wearing blue? So,
that's what we called the true and false
case, but what if you're wearing blue
and pink? Um, yeah, that was uh that was
a less precise phrasing on my part. I
should have said you're wearing only
blue.
Um, I assume if you're wearing pink and
some other colors, I think that is okay
here. I don't know. I'd have to watch
the movie again.
Um, anyway, implication is confusing.
Let's talk a little bit more about
implication. Um, in English, when we say
A implies B,
often there's a connotation of
causality. A causes B.
And often there's a connotation of time.
A happens and then after that B happens
because of A.
So like B is after A is a consequence.
And that is not neither of those is what
we mean. There's no causality. There's
no time.
How do you put a time on um Goldbox
conjecture? when it was conjectured
maybe, but that's not what we mean when
we say gold box conjecture implies
that I'm wearing pink on a Wednesday.
As mathematicians, when we say the word
implies,
we mean this truth table and only this
truth table. There's no additional
connotation. There's no causality.
There's nothing else. It's just this
truth table.
Does that make sense? it can be hard to
sort of flip that switch and redefine
this term that we're familiar with uh
from somewhere else because it does mean
something different now. It means that
uh and if you see this in class, even if
it's written in a paragraph, you should
assume we mean that first.
Was that your question? Please.
Um so clarification on the on sort of
the concept of time. If A then B. Do we
need to know whether A is true or not
before we decide about B? Um I would
recommend thinking about A and B as two
separate propositions. They each have
their own truth value. A is either true
or false. B is either true or false. We
don't necessarily know what they are now
or in the future, but they're still
propositions. A might be the Goldbach
conjecture where we don't know if it's
true or false, but it's still a
proposition. It's still it's still going
to be true or false. We just don't know
yet. Likewise, we can always combine
propositions A and B into this bigger
proposition. If A, then B. A implies B.
It's just a new proposition where once
we know whether A and B are true, we'll
know whether the implication is true.
Does that make sense? Cool.
Um let's see. So another example of
implication
[Applause]
you might be familiar with
less than three. This is a pre-eoji
heart means I love you.
Got some chuckles. I don't know why I'm
I'm showing my age maybe. Um so less
than three means I love you. What I have
seen
I have seen occasionally
less than four as an intensifier. Like I
really love you. I love you more than
three. I love you four.
And this irks me. I hate this. Not
because I'm against love,
but because this is the stronger
mathematical statement. Less than three
implies less than four. If we know x is
less than three, some number x, well,
then we know that x is less than four.
And in fact, we know more information
than that. We know it's not pi,
right?
So this implies that. So this is the
stronger statement. So you've weakened
it. You love me less.
It should be like less than two or
something, but only mathematicians would
get that. So, I don't actually recommend
sending that to your Valentine, but
that's always bothered me.
Uh, let's do one other quick example.
Um, who's familiar with Decart? I think,
therefore I am.
Excellent.
Um, so I think, therefore I am.
I think, therefore I am.
Um, and this this sort of has two claims
to it. It's not only saying that
thinking implies amming, um, but it's
also saying that I think. So it's
asserting that T is true and T implies
am.
Yeah. So that's Dart. What I have seen
that bothers me is a shirt and a pillow
and a meme. And you can go off and buy
all of this. I don't recommend giving it
money. Um, I do not think, therefore, I
do not am, which I find hilarious, but
also frustrating. Um, so I do not think
implies
I do not am. Yeah.
So, it's also claiming I don't think. I
don't have an opinion on that. But it's
making it's saying this implication. Not
thinking implies not amming.
And it irks me because that's not
equivalent.
It's not equivalent to daycart.
If let's go out on a limb here and and
let's assume big ask. I know. Let's
assume that my shoe doesn't think. My
right shoe specifically,
but it still exists. Let's assume. If my
shoe thinks and doesn't uh sorry,
doesn't think but still exists,
Daycart's fine with that. False implies
true is fine.
But the meme isn't. Not thinking is
supposed to imply not amming. But my
shoe ams even if it doesn't think. So
these two statements are not equivalent.
It should be I do not am therefore I do
not think which gets zero hits on
Google. We need to fix this question.
All right. That's a great comment. Let's
see. Um, let's go back to the front.
Um, what your colleague suggested was we
can write A implies B by combining the
earlier operators.
Oops. A implies B is equivalent to
um, and can you remind me what you said?
It was or not and not
okay B or
uh not A
and
not B. And the claim is that this is
equivalent to A implies B has the same
truth table as A implies B. In fact, if
you if you check it, we can simplify it
even further. We don't need this extra
clause on B.
B or not A.
this is equivalent to a implies b.
Um, what this is really saying is that
the only way to violate this, the only
way to violate a implies b is for a to
be true and b to be false. And so if
either of these is true, then you're
fine.
Yeah, absolutely. There are
relationships between these operators.
Um, really nice observation.
Um, but going back to Decart for just a
second, um, we looked at
A implies B and we also looked at, um,
not A implies B. Let me look, let's look
at some others. B implies A.
Not B implies not A.
If this is our statement, A implies B.
If we flip them around, B implies A.
That's called the converse.
That's the converse of the original
statement. And this one here, not B
implies not A, that's what's called the
contraositive.
Uh, and the one we saw over there with
um what not A implies not B, that's
called the inverse.
You don't really need to know all of
these terms. It's just nice to know
they're there because
A implies B
is equivalent to one of these two and
it's not it's not the the nice one. A
implies B is equivalent to its
contraositive. Not B implies not A.
Wednesday implies pink. So if you're not
wearing pink, it better not be
Wednesday.
A implies B. Not B implies not A. So
these two are equivalent.
And also the converse and the inverse
are equivalent for the same reason.
They're contraositives of each other.
Um so that day cartme was using the
inverse when they probably meant to use
the contraositive. I I assume because I
assume they thought that deeply about
it. Um that is everything I wanted to
say about implication. Does anyone have
more questions before we move on?
All right.
[Applause]
Now, very briefly, I've mentioned sets a
few times and I've used set notation a
few times.
So, let's let's go ahead and make that
more precise because we're going to be
talking about sets all term. I just want
us to have that common language to fall
back on. So, a set
is a collection of objects.
Um, I'm not going to be more precise
than this. If you want to dig into that,
into set theory, into the foundations of
mathematics, it's really interesting.
There's a lot of stuff there, but that's
not what we're doing in this course. A
set is a a collection of objects. Um,
let me give lots of examples. An example
is the set that contains six, one, two,
and zero. And we're going to write sets
with these curly braces. Crucially,
um, when we when we're talking about a
set,
the order doesn't matter.
And there's no such thing as a repeat.
All I care about is which things are in
your set and which ones aren't. So this
set is exactly equal to 2 1 6 0
because they have the same four
elements. This set is exactly equal to
six uh yeah 6 1 2 O.
It's kind of weird to write O in there
twice, but technically it's okay. I
don't recommend doing that. Um, but this
has the four numbers 0, 1, 2, and six in
it. And so do these other sets. They're
exactly the same set. Yeah, we already
saw n the natural numbers. This is the
set 0, 1, 2, 3, and so on all the way
up.
Um, yeah, we also have the set that's a
blackboard bold Z.
um which includes the integers the
natural numbers and their negatives 1
and minus one and two and minus2 and so
on all the integers
integers.
Um a couple more useful ones we have Q
is the set of rationals.
So fractions you can get by dividing
some integer by some non-zero integer.
Uh, we have the real numbers.
That's a that's a bold R. Blackboard
bold R. Um, and we also have C, the
complex numbers.
Complex numbers.
So those are five sets that we will very
frequently talk about. Uh, let's give
some more examples of sets. There's the
empty set.
which is written
as a circle with a slash through it.
It's also sometimes written as an open
curly brace and a closed curly brace
with nothing inside.
Yeah, these these two mean the same
thing. They're just different notations
for the same thing. The empty set is a
set that contains nothing. It is a set.
It is a thing. It does exist. It just
has zero elements. Whereas this set over
here has four elements. This set over
here has a has infinitely many elements.
These other sets have infinitely many
elements as well. But is it the same
infinity?
Not not always. And that's a confusing
thing. Come ask me if you're curious. Um
let's see one other set I wanted to give
an example of. Let's call this one A
just so we have a name for it.
Uh let's define B is what did I want to
write? Yeah. two,
three, four, and empty set.
B is a set with three elements.
It has the number two as an element. It
has this set as an element and it has
the empty set as an element.
Is three an element of B?
We would write this as three is an
element of B. There's that notation
again. Is three an element of B? No.
It's inside one of the elements of B,
but it's not one of the elements itself.
So, no.
Uh, so we have this notation. Oh, no. I
just used that. Let's move over here.
Eraser help.
Found it.
We have this notion of being an element
of a set that we uh have already talked
about a few times. uh you can also ask a
set to be a subset of another one. So x
in a
means x is
an element of a
a and then this new symbol this is a a
sideways or this is a curly c uh with a
line underneath it. A is a subset or
equal to B.
A is a subset
or equal to B. Not the similarity to A
is less equal to B. Um less equal
doesn't really make sense for sets, but
this one does. Subset means everything
that's in A is also in B and B might
contain more besides.
For example, the set that contains um
two and one.
Is that a subset of A
was over there?
Yeah. Everything that's in here is also
in here. Totally fine.
Um
let's see. Is the empty set a subset of
A?
Cool.
All right. I got some thumbs up. I got
no thumbs down. I got a lot of blank
faces. I'm going to assume that means
yes. Yeah. Um, everything that's an
element of the empty set should also be
an element of a.
Well, it's kind of weird, right? Because
there are no elements of the empty set.
So, and we can't really check this this
rule for any elements of the left. So,
it kind of feels like this shouldn't be
true because there's nothing to
instantiate. There's there are no
elements here to talk about.
Um, but a better way to think of it is
prove me wrong.
Show me an element on the left that
isn't an element on the right. You
can't.
You can't violate the rule and therefore
the rule is satisfied.
Yeah, a little bit confusing, but um
when you look at it the right way,
hopefully it makes sense. All right,
just like we were able to combine um
propositions A and B, A or B, um we can
combine sets. We can look at like a
union B. This is the union
which is the set of elements that are in
A or B or both.
Yeah. So in this case A union B
for our example it certainly includes
six and one and two and zero. Uh and
also well it already has two so we don't
need to write that again. And it has the
set three four and it has the empty set.
So everything in A or B or both. Um and
remember I don't have to say the or both
because or is inclusive by default.
All right. Uh we can likewise do a
intersect b
which is the elements that are in both.
So the intersection
in this case a intersect b
is well what's in both a and b? I think
it's just the two. There's a two in both
and nothing else is in common. So that's
going to be just the set containing two.
There's also the set difference
A minus B, sometimes written as A
backslash B.
Uh, and that's the set difference.
It's the things in A that aren't in B.
So it's a but take away everything in b.
So in this case it's going to equal
six and one and not the two but we still
keep the zero.
Yes.
Yep.
Good question. So the question was,
we've already said that the empty set is
a subset of everything.
So shouldn't it be in both A and B and
therefore in their intersection?
Really good question. Um and the
difference is that we have two different
meanings of sort of in. Um we said that
the empty set is a subset of everything
but not an element of everything.
So the empty set is an element of B
because it was written as one of the
elements, but it's not an element of A
because these are all four elements of
A. There's nothing else in there. So A
is a subset, sorry, the empty set is a
subset of A and a subset of B, but it's
not an element of both.
Great question. Thank you for asking.
Yes.
Why can A have two zeros?
Um, why can a have two zeros if there's
no repeats? Good question. Um, it's
because it doesn't actually have two
zeros. Um, I just wrote the two zeros.
Each of them says zero is an element of
this set. By the way, did you forget
zero is an element of this set. Uh, so
it doesn't have two. There's no way for
it to remember it has two. Um, but
sometimes in some weird cases it might
make sense to write a to write a set
where the same element is written twice.
Um, and so there's that example.
All right. Yes. Question.
That's a great question. So if a if a
also had a three and a four in it. So
let's let's pretend this also has a
three and a four in it. And then we ask
about a minus b. We take away from a
everything that's in b. Everything
that's an element of b. So would we be
removing the three and four? So if we
have a six and a one and a two and a
zero and a three and a four
and we subtract
the set what was it? two and three four
and empty set. And the answer is no. The
three and four don't go away because we
want to take all the elements of the
first set that are not elements of the
second set. And three and four are not
elements of the second set. They're
they're nested too deep.
Um three is not an element of this set.
This whole set is an element of this
set.
Yeah, make sense? Cool. So this
difference would keep the six and the
one not the two would keep the zero and
keep the three and keep the four.
Awesome.
All right. Similar to sets we have oh
sorry before that um one of the reasons
I'm talking about sets right now beyond
the fact that we need to talk about sets
um is the fact that sets and
propositions and predicates
are very closely related and they can
both be useful for the other.
Um specifically I want to talk about set
builder notation.
And that is where you take a set and you
you describe a subset of the set by
using a predicate.
So for example uh we can look at the set
of all n in the natural numbers
such that n is prime.
So we have this predicate of n over here
on the right and we're pulling out all
of the elements of this set the natural
numbers but only the ones that satisfy
our predicate.
So this is set builder notation. You
have elements of a set such that this
predicate is satisfied. This is the
notation we'll use. Um and this set of
course will return the set of primes.
2 3 5 7 not 9 globe 11 and so on.
Very useful. We're going to use that all
the time.
All right. Similar to sets, we have
tupils.
This is an ordered list of elements.
And repeats are okay.
And it's written with parentheses
instead of curly braces.
For example, the tupole 6 1 2 0
is a sequence with four elements.
This is not the same as 6 1 2 0 0 which
is a tupole with five elements.
Right? As sets they're the same. They
have the same elements, but this one has
repeats. Um, so they're different. And
likewise, neither of these is equivalent
to 2 1 6 0 because the order is
different even if the elements are the
same. So a tupole cares about the order.
Um, by the way, last I checked, um, 2160
is identification, estimation, and
learning in mech.
Not the same even though they have the
same digits.
um doesn't really make sense to ask for
the intersection or the union or the
difference of tupils.
Uh so we're not even going to try.
Any questions about sets or tupils?
Nice.
All right, let's go back to the
definition I probably deleted already.
Um, a proof is a verification of a
proposition by a sequence of logical
deductions from a base set of axioms. I
hope I got that right. We've already
talked at length about propositions, one
of those three terms.
Let's turn to the next one, axioms.
Uh, we've used both of those boards onto
this board.
Nice.
An axiom.
Let's see.
Is a proposition we assume
is true.
You you might have heard when you're
writing mathematical proofs, you
shouldn't be assuming anything. You have
to prove everything. And that's not
quite true. We need somewhere to start.
We need some foundation to build up
from.
The trick is to declare all of them in
advance. These are the axioms I'm using.
And if you assume these axioms,
then these proofs tell you other things
that also have to be true. So the axioms
are the things you start with. We take
them to be true. Sometimes people say we
take them to be self-evident, but I
don't like that phrasing because
they're they're not necessarily true in
some um holistic sense. We just assume
them to be true for the sake of the math
we're doing now.
uh and in fact you can often have axioms
that contradict each other as long as
you're not using them at the same time.
Uh for example,
let's see for example we have the famous
um
uh Uklid's
parallel
postulate.
So, Uklid in like 200 BC or whenever he
was alive, maybe 2000, someone can tell
me, um, wrote a book, The Elements,
Uklid's Elements, that chronicled all of
Uklitian geometry. That's why it's
called Uklitian geometry. He literally
wrote the book on it. Um, and at the
beginning of the book, he had five
axioms. Postulate is another word for
axiom, a little little outdated, but
still there. Um and the parallel
postulate, the fifth of the five axioms,
um famously for centuries, millennia,
people kept trying to prove that
actually the parallel postulate doesn't
have to be an axiom. You can prove it's
true if you only assume the first four
axioms.
So it doesn't have to be an a, it can be
a theorem. And people kept trying and
kept trying and kept trying. By the way,
the statement of of the parallel
postulate is that um for every uh point
P
and line L um that doesn't contain P
P not in L
there exists
a unique line
L prime M
through P
parallel to L.
In picture, if you have a point here and
some line that doesn't go through that
point,
then there's a unique line
parallel and going through your point.
Here's P. Here's L. Intuitive, right?
Makes sense.
uh and Uklid took this as an axiom and
and went with it. But can we can we
prove this based on the other four
axioms and turns out thousands of years
later we finally know the answer? No.
No. Um this is not a theorem. It does
not follow from the other four axioms
because
we know what happens if you change the
axiom.
Um things do happen in a meaningful way.
Uh for example, instead of saying there
is a unique line,
a unique line, let's change that to no
lines.
There are no lines through your point
parallel to your line. The concept of
parallel lines doesn't exist.
If we use that axiom instead of Uklid's
version and the other four axioms that
Uklid um did
um you can get spherical geometry.
In spherical geometry
um your your plane your canvas is a
sphere instead of a plane. A line is a
great circle.
It's a circle whose center is the center
of the sphere. And a point isn't just a
point, but it's a point and its
antipode, the one directly across from
from it on the sphere. And if that's how
we define points and lines, then there
are no parallel lines. All great circles
intersect each other.
Um, and we get a meaningful geometry
that we can prove stuff with, that we
can prove different things with than
Uklid could.
Since we have a different set of axioms,
we're going to have a different set of
conclusions, but it's still meaningful.
Likewise, if we replace this, instead of
no lines, we do infinitely many lines.
Well, there's another version of
geometry that does that. It's hyperbolic
geometry.
um lots of ways to draw it, but
sometimes it's drawn in a circle. But
now, now a line is a part of a circle
that's perpendicular to the boundary. A
point is just a point.
But now if we have a a line and a point
not on that line, well, parallel just
means they don't intersect. So, well,
here is a line through P that doesn't
intersect L. Well, here's another one.
And here's another one. There are lots
of them. Infinitely many lines through P
that don't touch L.
Um,
and so this is a different kind of
geometry that satisfies a different set
of axioms.
And so, no, you can't prove the fifth
axiom from the first four because you
can change the fifth one and get new
conclusions that make sense and aren't
contradictory.
Now, I've said a couple times we can
change it uh and get a new system of
geometry.
Well, sort of you can imagine you can
always change your axioms to some other
set of assumptions
and make a mathematical theory out of
it. Does any set of assumptions work?
Are they all as good as the others?
Well,
there are a couple things that can go
wrong. There are a couple properties you
might want your set of axioms to
satisfy.
A set of axioms
axioms
is consistent
when you can't
prove
that false
is true.
And we kind of need that, right? Um let
me see if that's how we defined it.
Yeah. Yeah. If no proposition can be
proved and disproved,
um we we kind of need true and false to
be different things because remember
false implies anything you want. That's
sometimes called the principle of
explosion by the way. Great name. False
implies anything. So if false is true
and false implies anything then then
everything is true.
So we don't want to be able to prove
that false is true because then our
theory is is uninteresting because
everything is true and everything is
false. So we definitely want a set of
axioms that is consistent.
Ideally, we would also have a set of
axioms.
set of axioms is complete
when every true let's see um yeah every
true proposition
can be proved
from the axioms
right we want things to be true or false
and we want proof to be the metric by
which we decide whether something is
true or false. If we can find a proof
for it, it's true. Um, ideally if it's
not true, we'd be able to find a proof
for the opposite for the not of that
proposition. Right? So, sort of the
baseline things, the two things you
would want in a set of axioms that is
nice to work with. You would want it to
be consistent, you would want it to be
complete.
And then Kurt Girdle comes along and
says, "Nope, can't have both.
There's what's called the Girdle
incompleteness theorem.
That's go olla d.
Girdle was able to prove that you can't
have a system of axioms that is both
consistent and complete as long as it's
complicated enough to just do
arithmetic, addition, and
multiplication.
can't have both.
We certainly want to be able to add and
multiply numbers,
which means we have to pick consistency
or completeness. And I know which one
I'm picking. I'm going to pick
consistent so that true and false have
meaning. what this means and this is
kind of a this kind of messes with my
head a little bit. What Girdle's
completeness theorem in sorry
incompleteness theorem tells us is that
there are true statements in math in
whatever set of axioms we're working
with there are true statements that
cannot be proved
you're never going to be able to
disprove it but if you want to prove it
you have to add more axioms
but then once you add more axioms that
bigger set of axioms now has other true
statements that can't be proved with
those axioms
um So conceivably we might ask you to
prove a problem in homework that can't
be proved from the axioms even though
it's true. We're not going to do that.
That's mean. Um conceivably goldbox
conjecture
might be true but unprovable
maybe. I don't know. Uh question.
Yeah. Excellent question. And if
something doesn't have a proof, how do
we know it's true?
Um, that is a really good question and
and that's also getting back into the
the set theory and logic and
underpinnings of math that are too in
the weeds for this course. Um, but I'm
happy to discuss it afterward if you'd
like.
Um, last thing I want to say about
axioms, every mathematician needs a set
of axioms that they're working with so
they know what they're allowed to assume
as they're proving new things. Um,
What a we use in this class.
Roughly speaking, all of high school
math.
Let's say that any fact that you think
is general enough and familiar enough
and simple enough to be included in
basically every high school math
curriculum, you're allowed to assume it
and go from there. Um, ideally, we ask
you to identify it. Write down fact.
Right. write the theorem you're stating
or the theorem you're assuming like the
product of two even numbers is even.
I know this from high school and then go
ahead and use it because ideally at
every step in a proof we know why each
thing is true and if sometimes the
reason is that's an axiom I'm assuming
it we should say that.
Are there any questions?
All right, that's all I've got. Be sure
to go to recitation tomorrow. Um, you
can check your time on Canvas. You can
switch your time on Canvas. We look
forward to seeing you then. Thank you so
much.