I'm going to introduce now my colleague
Ariana Rodenstein who is program manager
at the MIT startup exchange and she will
continue with the next part of this
presentation that will include two of
our startups in the area of
sustainability. So Ariadna
Jose thank you so much good to be here
and welcome everybody wherever you might
be today. So, we'll move on to the more
fast-paced lightning talks. Again, I'm
Marat Natenstein, program manager with
Startup Exchange. And to shortly, you're
going to hear from two very exciting and
very different startups, all members of
Startup Exchange. They are um working on
uh very novel uh solutions for problems
that could really be applied um and that
um we find in the real world as you will
see. and also especially at a time when
sustainability efforts and cost
reduction are crucial. But first I will
give a brief introduction of our
program.
So MIT startup exchange was created to
support MIT connected startups as they
grow expand and solve some of the
world's greatest challenges and we do
this by fostering partnerships and
collaboration between the startups and
industry primarily members of the
industrializ program as I mentioned our
ILP who are represented by so many of
you here today and also the MIT
innovation ecosystem and
beyond. Sorry, the
um the startups in our program have a
very strong connection to the institute.
They may be based on MIT licensed
technology or founded by MIT faculty,
staff or alumni and they may also be
vetted by some of our MIT peers
including the engine start nano and cel
startup connect
plus. Our program has around a thousand
startups and they usually join at pilot
stage or beyond and of course they may
represent any sector and any geography.
Here you can see in bold some of the um
trending technologies of the startups
and those to be represented by the
startups presenting to you today. Of
course we start with AI and ML big data
and analytics and sustainability.
So when it comes to value, everything
that we do at Startup Exchange is really
to provide exposure opportunities and
connections for the startups with
industry and we do this in a very
customized approach. I hope everyone
will be taking advantage of the benefits
that you can see here on the screen.
These include when we launch calls for
startups, we call these opportunities
and they're based on a corporate's
um priorities and internal challenges.
And startups can apply on our website
and if selected, they can work with you
as an ILP member to help you solve a
problem that you may be facing in your
industry. We also host one-on-one
meetings, virtual demo days, other
webinars like today, and conferences
locally and internationally. And for
these we have startup lightning talks
and exhibits and we also create
workshops and trainings sometimes in
conjunction with our peers. And so with
that let's hear from the startups. Um
each speaker will present for five
minutes and then we will have Q&A for
two minutes. So I ask again that you
pose your questions to the Q&A tab and I
will get to as many of those as
possible. Let's keep this interactive
and dynamic.