My name is Kik. I'm visiting scholar
here at MIT. I'm actually assistant
professor at poly techchnical university
of Madrid. And my background is actually
on engineering. I am aerospace engineer.
Uh I did my PhD on numerical methods.
But uh after my post dog I decided to
start doing things that really
passionates me and that's how I end up
doing something related with music. No.
So I'm relatively new in this field and
today I'm going to show you an algorithm
that I came up for pattern detection in
music which is what I've been working on
for the last year and a half more or
less. So as running example uh I'm going
to use the most listened song of the
history which is uh Baby Sark.
>> So I don't know if I can play it. Yeah.
At least it's the most listened song of
the history of YouTube.
>> Baby Shark doo doo doo doo doo doo. Baby
Shark doo doo doo doo doo doo. Baby
Shark,
>> Mommy Shark, doo doo doo doo doo doo.
Mommy shark, doo doo doo doo doo doo.
Mommy shark,
>> pretty much like that all the song. This
is the melody. So what's the problem of
pattern detection in music? Okay, we
would like to have a tool, an automatic
to tool that help us to identify over
the score or over a corpus like the
important musical ideas there. No. So
I'm highlighting here some fragments.
Have a look first at the blue fragment
over there. There are three fragments,
three occurrences of them. All of them
are exactly the same. They have the same
notes with the same pitches and same
durations. The only difference is that
they occur at different moment of the
score. But it seems logical. It seems
reasonable to group them as the same
musical idea and say that they represent
the same the same pattern. No, we can
call them uh we can put them a label
blue pattern. Okay, for the green one is
a little trickier because the occurrence
number two and the occurrence number
three are exactly the same. Okay,
probably makes sense to group them
together. Occurrence number one has a
different durations for the notes and
the occurrence number four is even
trickier because
they just serve with the rest that it's
three notes also and the lyrics. No, but
it's pretty different. No. So that's one
of the main difficulties of the problem
of pattern mining in music that even
though uh objects that we want to group
together because in our mind represent
the same musical idea over the table
they might look pretty different and
there are two mechanisms involved here.
The first one is something that we have
already studied the transformations. So
if we have a a music fragment, if we
apply the mathematical transformation
over the notes there, we obtain other
fragments that under some circumstances
our mind will process them as
equivalent.
And how to deal with this
computationally from the point of view
of a pattern mining algorithm? My
approach was to use the concept of
viewpoint. I'm going to show you an
example of what is this about but for
the moment it's enough to know that it
it's it have a double task know on the
first hand um it directly takes into
account this transformations you will
see it in a minute and probably more
important it simplifies the
representation because one of the
constants in this course in this classes
is that music is something complex no it
has like complex logical structures
among among the elements of the score
and if we find a way to simplify that
representation would be helpful for from
the computational point of view. So the
viewpoint representation is pretty
simple. It's just I'm going to
substitute a complex tune like this one
by a single sequence of symbols. So
actually here I'm showing three
viewpoints representation. The pitch
viewpoint it's the sequence of these
symbols 83 83 83 85 it's the MIDI note
then we have the duration and the onset
time I'm going to highlight there a a
fragment so you can see the different
viewpoints representation for that
fragment and it's nice that idea of
constructing the score by overlapping
layers of information no that's the idea
formally a viewpoint is a mapping
between the current event, the current
time slice and all the former ones into
a symbol. Usually an integral or float,
but could be others. Those there are
derived viewpoints
and perhaps for your own particular
music application, you need to develop
your own viewpoint representation.
Uh and here is clearly highlighted how
the transformations could be directly
taken into account by using this
technique. You know for instance if you
apply uh the octave transformation to
that pattern there that fragment you
obtain that one over there which one
which by the interval uh viewpoint
representation
uh will have the same symbol. So for
sure any pattern mining algorithm that
is trying to uh find this sequence uh
will see that that one is the same. No.
Is that enough to deal with the concept
of dissimilarity in music?
Unfortunately, not. So have a look at
these two occurrences of the green
pattern of baby sark. There is no
viewpoint representation that can take
us from one to the other. So someone
said at some point okay it would be nice
to have a kind of measure uh a
mathematical tool that help us to
evaluate how different two fragments
are.
like uh the aim here is that okay if I
use that matrix with this guy and this
guy I would expect a lower value than
the one that I would obtain when taking
this guy and this guy no because they
are uh more far no they represent uh
farther ideas. So in computer science
they use what is called the distance
functions. is in a general scenario is
that you can give to a function two
objects two random objects for instance
me myself and this computer and it
returns a non- negative real number
evaluating the degree of dissimilarity
between the two objects in the context
of sequences because we are using
viewpoint representation so now this
fragment will be a sequence for instance
let's see let's think that I'm using the
duration viewpoint point. So in the
literature we have like plenty of
distance functions. This was very a very
trending topic in music information
retrieval like 15 years ago more or
less. There were many studies and papers
trying to figure out which was the best
distance function depending on the
style.
The lestain distance function perhaps is
not the most advanced one but is one of
the simplest one and probably the most
used one and it accounts for the number
of substitutions
or insertions to go from one sequence to
the other. So uh to go from the sequence
0.5
to the sequence 0.52
we just need a single substitution. So
the leven distance function between the
fragment two and fragment four is one.
Okay. Probably the leven distance
function between this guy and this guy
it's I don't know two or three at least.
No. So cool. Now we have like all the
ingredients needed to understand the
inputs and outputs of my algorithm. We
have a corpus or a piece of music. We
have also the viewpoint representation
that the user want to choose and some
parameters at the input. The minimum
support is the minimum number of
repetitions that we uh require to a
pattern to be considered frequent and to
be included in the result list. These
two guys the minimum length and maximum
length are the parameters to control the
lengths of the patterns that we want to
mine and some parameters to control the
degree of dissimilarity
from the former slide. And the result is
yes like the list of frequent patterns
together with the position. This is an
example with the piece of the former
slide. Now I'm selecting the interval
viewpoint
uh and those parameters over there. And
this is an example of the output that we
might obtain. So we have a yellow
pattern that has four occurrences. and
have a look that each of these fragments
are at most distance one from any of the
rest. No, taking the Levenstein distance
function and we might have for instance
also this guy the purple pattern and
this green one which is of length four.
So yeah in a real case the pattern
structure might be complex as you see
because you have nested patterns you
have many overlapping I won't go into
the details on how I implemented the
algorithm just a brief overview uh I
divided in four steps the one is the
creation of a an initial database a a
vertical database it's called sometimes
where I just take a sliding window of
length minimum length the minimum length
selected by the user and I just create a
database of do all the patterns together
with their positions within the score.
Then in the next step I compare every
pattern against all the rest trying to
uh see if they satisfies the distance
constraint. No. And in that case I group
them together into uh what I call metric
patterns which are like groups of
fragments of music. you know at this
stage it's safe to deate the entries
that doesn't reach the minimum support
constraint like they don't have enough
occurrences to be considered frequent
and finally as here I still have
patterns of length equal to the minimum
length and we actually want longer
patterns so the last stage is
overlapping different patterns to form
longer ones
okay and to finish this I'm going to
show you some results this is the last
slide
Uh I'm actually already using this I
started using collaborating with these
research groups like seven months ago.
This has a a research group from
another university of Madrid. They got a
good amount of money of the European
Union to study the Italian operas. They
have a huge database with many features
for each piece and in particular they
are interested in the emotion that the
piece evoke. So here we are trying to
find some correlations between the
emotions and the pattern structure of
the different pieces. These two other
projects are pretty similar. The number
two it's on a corpus of folk music from
a very concrete region of Europe in
around the Pyrenees. And the second one
is the
a database of just solos. So here we are
building classifiers like similar to
what we did in the last uh class. Here
I'm showing like uh the number of
patterns per style for the different
styles in this uh corpus. uh but perhaps
here uh we can see a cool thing of the
algorithm that it returns also the
position of the patterns not only the
fact that a piece contain the pattern no
so here I'm plotting it's called
coverage this variable but it's actually
like the
probability function of encountering a
pattern within a solo no so I normalize
the length of the all the solos by style
and the thin line is the average for the
solos we You can see for instance that
the concentrations of of patterns tends
to be at the beginning and not in the
end. This is intuitive because like the
impro improvisors usually start their
solos like in a more organized way
taking thematic material from the
original melody and then they start to
do more crazy stuff. No. Then I'm also
trying to build up a pattern dictionary
of uh in an Iris corpus. These are the
five most frequent patterns in the
subset of minor rs in the corpus that
I'm working on. So I don't know for a
performance that is interested in
playing this music perhaps the takeaway
of this is okay you might want to start
studying these patterns no because they
appear quite often in the in the corpus.
So better to first master them and for
the future with Michael
we want to study uh how the algorithm
performs in a nice corpus of early music
that he has and also we want to analyze
some solos of Charlie Parker who was one
of the most mathematical improvisers of
the history and also for the close
future I would like to see if this tool
can be helpful for plagiaris detection.
No, I suspect that two pieces that uh
are very similar share also some
similarities in their pattern structure.
And that's all. Thank you very much,
guys. Any questions?
[Applause]
>> By the way, just so you get a sense for
your final things, that was 12 minutes.
So, a tiny bit longer than what you have
as a maximum.
Cool.
>> If any of you are interested in a
particular thing of the algorithm, just
drop me an email and we can talk about
it. Okay.
Thank you.
>> So, what I want to do is I want to
immediately start by putting some of uh
thoughts to work. So, uh get with a
partner next to you. You can um you can
do that if over here we need a group of
three or unless you want to participate
with a friend or or jump over there.
Well, jump over with uh with yeah with
uh with Jordan if you do. Um and here
are um six melodies. I'm going to play
um each one of them. I'm going to play a
a bunch of times also. So I'll tell you
which one I'm playing and you're going
to So and you can talk during this or
wait till just after playing. You're
going to tell me which melody is the um
is most or least similar to A.
[Music]
Okay. And this is and and
this is B. And I want you to know say
why
[Music]
This is C.
And I'm going to play A one more time to
get it back into our heads.
[Music]
And now D.
Oh, and by the way, this isn't a right
there isn't a right answer one.
Great.
Now E.
And now A one more time before doing F.
So this is A again.
[Music]
And now F.
Oops, that's F and E simultaneously,
which is very different. Now F.
[Music]
Great. Talk amongst yourself. I want a
ranking from your group. So, somebody
write it down.
>> And I want to know why.
>> Okay, let's bring it all back together.
Let's bring it all all back together.
So, look at look at your look at your
list and we'll we'll count like normal
human beings. whichever one is the top
in your list is one, whichever one's
second to stuff. And we'll we'll vote by
fingers first off for the general
ranking. So when if you hold up the
number of fingers that um you know, if
it's closest, it's pulled up one finger.
If not to, you know, whatever. And pull
palm means I have no idea what that is.
Okay.
B.
Oh, B's doing pretty pretty well. Okay.
Not a lot of twos. A couple ones. C.
Okay. A little bit more variety. Hold
them up so other people can see also.
Yeah. Look around the room. It's not
just for me. Great. Great. Uh D.
Oh, okay. We got a variety. No. No.
Whatever. Great. Uh E.
Oh, that's still see some palms or
things. Great. And F.
Okay.
Oh, we have one one four. Good. Good.
Uh, what did you what you what you you
put it down? What do you guys Those who
put uh F as four, what' you put as five?
>> D.
>> B.
>> D. Okay. D. Good. Good. Great. Um,
somebody who had who had uh C above B,
justify your answer. Who who had C above
B? There were a couple people. Yeah. Uh,
go ahead, Jake. First.
Yeah. Groups. Yeah.
>> C was basically just a transposition
whereas B like B changed a lot of the
rhythms a bit. Like B H B I think fits
the exact pitches a little better, but
or aside from a couple places where it
has some accidentals, but it changes the
rhythm quite a bit. Whereas C is just a
transposition. So for relative pitch
especially,
>> yeah, we waited transposition on. Okay,
good. Good. I'm already hearing words
that I that I'm liking and stuff. Great.
Um, somebody who had it the other way
around to justify your answer. Who who
had it the other way around?
Who had a bunch of people had B above C?
Yeah, John.
>> For like the kind like styling feel that
A had. Um, because are similar between A
and B is why we put a bit higher
relative C. And when you take
transposition into account, only part of
C's coming transposed. So it doesn't
even feel like it's like a full
transposition.
>> Great. Only part of it transpose. Yeah.
Yeah. It kind of gets back on for a bit
and then comes back off. Great. Uh okay.
Who had who had D um who had D1 or two?
Anybody? I can't remember.
Yeah. Why' you have a one or two?
>> Um because it basically has this. Sorry.
It has all of the same notes in the
right position or or basically. Yeah.
Yeah. All you have to do is remove notes
and then you get the same thing and I
think with a few exceptions but that
never happened in
>> Okay, great. Who had uh D very low?
>> Yeah. Go ahead.
>> Sorry. Sorry. Can you speak a lot?
>> Okay.
>> Great. Um, and who had um did anybody
have E above um above four?
>> Okay,
we have EX3
and we put it there because the pattern
was very similar. I even though the
melody wasn't all that close, we figured
that count.
>> So, so when you say pattern, what the
rhythm the rhythmic pattern is about the
same? Good.
That's an inversion, right?
>> Is it an inversion? No. No. That would I
would I do that?
>> I can't, by the way, I can't remember
where melody I I think melody a comes
from uh here on uh book and then gives
there's uh some some search book and I
should I should have my notes better and
I'll try to make sure it gets annotated
later. Um that had three other melodies.
I tried this in the past and it was so
obvious everybody had the exact same
ranking. I had to agree with them, but I
think this is better for making some
arguments. Good. Who um who had F
anything but F? Actually, somebody who
gave F5. Jonathan, why would you did you
give F5?
>> Yeah. Why'd you give it five?
>> I mean, it didn't have any noticeable
similarity. Like at first it seemed
closer to like E in like it might have
been inversion, but then not really.
is also completely different or not
completely but like it's fairly
different.
>> Great. So, um I'm just going to point
and we'll get some um some uh just what
your ranking is. So, so say them from
thing. Matthew, what was your your
>> alphabetical order?
>> BCDE F. Okay, good.
BCDEF
>> BCE DF. Great. Great. Um, what's it?
>> Yeah, CBDF.
>> CBD EF. Good. Any anything that feels
like you're not being represented on the
Hannah, what's your group?
>> Um, I think I put CBD.
>> CBDF. CBDF. Great. Super. Now, what I
want you to do, we're not going to get
through all of the exercises today, uh,
but I think this is the most important
part. What I want you to do is think
about what ways,
um, start thinking. I'll give you a
little bit of things. What are some ways
you can make sure that your computer
system that is going to classify things
by similarity follows your intuition of
what is similar and not somebody else's
intuition for what is similar. So that's
going to be the main theme for the rest
of this that we are intelligent people.
We are intelligent musicians. We are uh
make these choices and yet we are making
differences on how far and how similar
they are. So in fact I'm going to blake
the screen and say the one the one uh
takeaway from today's lecture I hope and
from Kiki from all these things is that
there is no right answer for the
similarity between two melodies between
the si similarity between two pieces.
There may be wrong answers. I will not
deny that that if if somebody said that
uh that f was uh closer to I don't know
than the same thing with one note
changed or something I would you know
think that that might be wrong then your
problem program might be malfunctioning
but there isn't a right answer and a lot
of it the what different between good
answers are what we think of u as
important when thinking similarity there
is a yearly competition I think it's
been suspended since since co so I don't
if it's restarted but um for the
algorithm that can that can classify
songs as the most similar and here is a
place where I would say what are your
ground truths how do we trust that you
have gotten it right and are we just
trying having to recreate the views I
won't say biases but the views of the
people who organize the um the
conference and you know what's that
going to do for us okay so I want you
start thinking that um and I will tell
you what f is beforehand.
F is one that a lot of computers
programs in fact what I like went aha
during one of uh Kiki's uh al algorithms
that could F is one that a number of
algorithms especially older ones will
classify as the most similar
because what is F unlike any of the
other lines F has every single note and
every single rhythm if I did it right I
was doing it in my head. Every single
note and every single rhythm from A just
order didn't matter.
A is the counter set function, the
unordered version, the the P. Well,
yeah, the permutation does not matter
version of F
or F is the permutation does not matter
version of A. Did I get it right?
>> Right.
>> That looks right.
>> Looks right. Okay.
So, I'm going to go quickly through some
things I think you've probably seen
before. Some some ways of measuring
distance. You all learned this in some
point. The um uklidian distance between
two points. Take the square root of the
x terms. Take square root of the y term
add what difference squared plus
difference squared square root. Right.
Yeah. Square root of x^2 plus difference
between x and difference between y.
So anyone seen this u thing where the
distance between these two points 3
comma 2 and 7 comma 8 is 10 who's soon
taxi cab distance Manhattan distance uh
we'll go with we'll go with taxi cab
since not all of us have been to a
Manhattan and had the joys of taking a
taxi there and stuff what why this here
the distance was 10 here it's approx
that's not a negative sign this
approximate sign approximately 7.2.
Why is the distance greater here?
Somebody who's
>> triangle inequality. What's talk talk
English to me for a second? Talk talk
like you're talking to the uh your cab
driver and who's who you're explaining
to this. No, cab drivers are really
smart. Talk but who may not have heard
the time inequality. What what is
represented by the term Manhattan
distance or triang or um taxi cab
distance? What's the notion
intuition?
>> Go along the axis.
>> Go along the axis or that go along let's
let's get get more literal. Let's one of
the things that we science don't do so
well is step back into the real world.
What is the distance traveled? What
constrains the taxi cab from not hitting
distance of 7.2 but instead 10? Yeah,
>> you go straight up and down to the side.
>> You can only go straight up and down the
side. You can only go on Let's go even
further back. What can What in
Manhattan? If you don't want to get
arrested, you can only drive on
>> streets. And the streets in Manhattan
goal
>> Yeah. They're orthogonal. There are
these little lines. So, you are
constrained in where you can go. So if
there are constraints on your distance
and the most common one is you can go up
down left or right um can't always do
that in Manhattan but um because of one
ways but you know let's assume that we
have certain constraints you can be
brought down good I wanted to make sure
that we all have that and so that we can
start thinking about um
that first off that what operations are
allowed determines the distance metric
What operations are around determines
how far the distance are? What are some
operations we do in music?
That's the question. What what
operations do we allow and not allow?
Adam,
>> we can look at MIDI.
>> We can look at MIDI difference between
notes. So therefore, we can take notes
and bring them
higher and lower, right? We can we can
raise and lower notes. What are other
things we can do?
What are some some things you've ever
done with a piece to make it a little
bit different or interesting?
>> Yeah,
>> you can subdivide or combine.
>> You can subdivide or combine notes.
Maybe you can, maybe you can't, but
yeah, quite often you can. This context
where you can um other Yeah, other
>> you can change durations. Great. Super.
Super super. Um, how about this? What is
which of these two chords are closer to
the first one? The first one's going to
be C major
versus
[Music]
another little similarity problem.
Second one was G
major. The sorry the the first chord the
first one it was G major second one I
went from C major to
>> C augmented great C augmented triad so
those are two things which one who votes
that from going from C major to G major
is closer
who votes that C major and C augmented
are closer
people. Okay, great. So, a lot of it has
to do with your thought um about, you
know, well, one one you're the
augmented, you're only changing one note
and you're only changing by a half step.
The minimum distance in our
Manhattanized musical world of MIDI and
piano keyboards, right? That is their
minimum distance is one half step there.
Not for all music in the world. Great. C
major to G major, you're also just
moving one. If you think of something
this way, you were moving one distance
in what space?
>> Oh, what's that word?
>> Circle.
>> In circle of fifth space, C and G are
about as close as you can get without
being the identity. C and F probably the
other way. Although, I don't know, maybe
it's a one-way circle of fifths. You
only go around uh one direction or
another. Great.
based on the time. I don't not going to
go through all these other measurements
of distance that people can do. Who has
heard of Earth Mus distance? That is the
amount of work that it takes to move one
mound of things over to another place
and um sometimes you optimizing
depending on how um how much it costs to
move distance and how much it costs to
move material. Um you can end up with
different results.
Um, I always, this was one of the charts
I think I showed early in the semester,
uh, is here's one place where Earth
mover distance might be a good use of
things, uh, of distances. And then, uh,
Levvenstein or edit distance is one that
was mentioned in, um, do you use it in
your work?
>> Yep. So, that's that's what you're
talking about. Um so the idea of how to
change the word Hondaai into Honda um
and uh no no international East Asian uh
politics uh please for a second and um
we'll you can think of every time okay H
and H are the same so it has a cost of
zero or we can delete the H and start on
O and we have a cost of one but we can
kind of find the pattern of as we change
we're going to insert a Y after the H
we're going to substitute a U for an O.
This should be symmetrical the other way
around different operations. N is the
same. So that's good. D is the same. So
it doesn't cost anything. So our cost
function goes here. And so we're trying
to find the minimum cost from going from
one end to another. Uh we don't have
time to go through all of the algorithms
for this but uh Levvenstein distance
edit distance has a lot of good um
qualities that makes it useful for a lot
of musical similarity tasks uh just so
that you know you can say your professor
at least uh put the algorithm up on the
head for a second. But more importantly,
I think a lot of times is thinking about
um the particular costs of things in a
musical spa in a musical world. So for
instance,
is deleting what we're trying to think
about two pieces, two uh melodies. Um
one of them deletes the first note.
What would you call the cost on that?
Maybe maybe one. But then if it doesn't
make up the rhythm, the total rhythm
later and everything from here on is
going to be off and it's one line within
a orchestral piece, that might be a
higher um cost. Maybe um some and the
classic debate is whether changing a
note is that the same or changing a
letter uh um in something like this. Is
this the same? Does this cost one or
does this cost? Well, one way you can
change a letter is you delete it and
then you add a new letter back with a
cost of two. And these are these are
things that come up quite a bit in
similarity search. Um, and just really
want to say that it comes up a lot in
music. Don't borrow your distance metric
from somebody else. Different ones might
be used for different situations. So,
the distance between dog and gate. Um,
well, we can substitute d for g. Um, I
don't know, maybe or maybe we add other
things, but I'm going to assert that in
different some situations the distance
might be two between dog and gut. What
we do is we use the substitute uh
closely related pet function for cost of
one. So dog becomes cat and then
translate English to Spanish might cost
one. And if you think about large
language learning models and things, you
might want to have functions like this.
And in fact, um this is not a digital
humanities text class, but if it were
and we were doing computation, we'd
definitely be talking about an algorithm
called wordtovect, which uh was one of
the uh earlier successful algorithms for
trying to predict what words are similar
to other words, what words are synonyms.
So you can create a kind of cost
function for uh that is for this word is
a synonym for this one that has been
substituted that is lower than this then
this sentence is different from this one
because um it's using a completely
different concept.
Um I'll skip that.
So when we're thinking about um these
distances and these weird things like
substitute dog for cat on low cost,
substitute cat for gateto at low cost.
What's the term that we spent a lot of
time, maybe even too much time if it
felt like at the time talking about
earlier in the semester that helps to
think about things that are not the same
but might be closely related to each
other
>> equivalence.
>> Equivalence or equivalence classes. Yes.
So, one of the things you might want to
do is define what equivalence classes it
could be. I mean I I think last other
times I've given the exact same melody
up an octave and everybody immediately
said oh that is basically the same
thing. So everybody was very quickly
putting in an O equivalence class
things. So I wanted to make sure that we
had that and um yeah and so once you
have these um these distances we tend to
go through and this is if you're in a
biology class you'll spend a lot of
computational biology a lot of time on
this sequence alignment uh a kind of
distance metric where you're trying to
find the minimum distance between two
things that you believe might represent
the same type of thing or you might say
it's innocent until proven guilty. we'll
first try to see if they can be changed
into another thing at a low cost and
then discard once we realize the cost
cannot be u minimized. Um I will say
that algorithms that can be
shortcircuited that you can prove at a
certain point you can't do better than
this cost will save speed up a lot of
your um run times because once you know
you might say um you know that there's
no way that this could be more could be
better than um 20% or could be yeah
there's no way that this could possibly
be better than 90%. % similar to this.
So, I'm going to stop looking at the
rest of the piece or whatever your cut
off. Um, one of the classic uh things
for sequence alignment is trying to find
uh this is Google's uh data set they
released at the height of Britney Spears
um popularity of all the number of
searches that they believed were uh
trying to find the top left one, Britney
Spears. Um, actually really really
impressed that that the number of
correct spellings um of a hard name to
spell uh outweighs the rest. Anyhow,
that's not what I'm talking and um the
people who are who are really really
good at this and like anytime I'm trying
to figure out a similarity sequence
alignment or similarity task that I
don't know is to look at the people who
are trying to align um base pairs in
biology or trying to align genes um so
that um because they have many many uh
many many options
Okay. So, I'm just going to keep
pounding this term in and as many
different ways I can do uh all the
things that we're just working like
Honda Britney Spears uh jeans those are
all strings but we work on notes and and
clefts and things like notes and stuff
but things like that. So, how do we get
them in? Uh so, this is great to get
this from two different people. Same
thing. We use things called hashes which
are very similar to uh the concept of
viewpoints um to the rescue. So that try
to convert things note hash and note we
might say that here our equivalence
class is all notes that are names with
octave and so we might hash a stream by
just joining all the hash notes for all
the notes in there. Um, you will find in
music 21 if you're working on it,
there's a bunch of tools for this
already there in music21.sarch, a module
that we have not talked about now and we
will not talk about again, but if you're
doing a lot of searching, it's probably
worth reading the um reading the uh
module reference for it. I think that
there might be a user's guide, but I
can't remember if I finished it or if it
just trails off after a few words. So we
might take a a string a string convert
it to a stream that's hard to say very
fast and um translate it and we might
have some sort of hash function that
tries to make everything into um into an
asky character.
Um though there's no reason that
everything needs to be turned into a
string like name with octave. um in a
lot of ways uh and um strings are just
arrays of ints
if you know we're talking about that the
um
that the you know that a is it lower no
lowercase a is generally represented
internally as anyone remember number
remember number remember number remember
number remember number remember number
>> what's that
>> 96 97 or 96. I can't remember. 96. Yep.
In capital A. Is that one 60?
>> 65. Okay. So, some people some people
know these. I used to have them all top
of the head. So, all the letters you're
doing have a particular representation.
And mo back in the bad bad days of the
60s and 70s, different computers would
have different representations for this.
And then we all agreed on the same
representation for uh letters. And then
we remembered that there are other
things in the uh um other characters in
the world. That looks too much like an a
how do I do a jin or something or an
alpha beta things like that. And and
then for a while we had a big problem
that they weren't all converting the
same thing. Anyhow, degression aside,
maybe we'll get to the point where we
can start converting things besides MIDI
numbers and notes into something um more
standardized because right now the MIDI
numbers is basically the only
standardized notes, which is probably
why MIDI keeps um uh being used for a
lot of computational projects.
So the hard part is always finding out
what numbers we should use to represent
a note.
So if we're going to convert name with
octave and we want to make a string and
then we want to make it a number and
then we want to have a whole bunch of
numbers. What have we just recently seen
that looks like a tool to take a score
or a part or something and works like a
hash or a viewpoint that tries to
convert it to a bunch of numbers.
Not asking you to think too far back
but farther back than today.
Yeah, I'm
>> getting a feature representation.
>> Get extracting features. Getting a
feature representation. Yeah. So feature
extraction and this kind of viewpoint
searching are very go hand inand with
each other. So if you're it's partially
why on you know once you finish up a
search function you're just going to
want to probably try to see if um AI or
machine learning can do it better
because you have everything ready to go
for it. But sometimes what we extract is
different from others. Um I want to give
a little bit of a caution that um uh
great uh back then course six you had to
do a little final a final project called
the UAP and we thought that making these
viewpoints making a hashing system for
music 21 for comparisons would be a nice
um would would be a nice senior project
and then we both realized that no it's
uh it's a lot bigger than we thought and
a lot more complex than we thought and
so it needed to be an MN And Emily Zang
was great at creating this and great we
did a really great Menge project and
then we realized no this this really
needs to be a PhD project. We did not
continue on. You can work there are so
many difficult parts of um hash
algorithms because you want to think
about things like um yeah we'll not get
to it. um going all the way back to the
beginning. Um
how can we create a viewpoint or
something that allows D not to be
totally totally different for anybody
who didn't put D as the last of all
possible results?
What kinds of hash what kinds of numbers
would we need to represent a piece on to
make D not the worst
and to really make sure that F isn't the
best. So that's going to be our last
five six minutes of class. I want you to
talk five minutes of y'all talking with
each other and five minutes of y'all
talk and talking to me. So what kinds of
what kinds of feature extractions? What
kind of hash function? What kind of
viewpoints? These are all slightly
different concepts, but they're all in
the same area. What kinds of equivalence
classes will you need in order to make
this happen?
Go ahead.
Okay. I hear I hear words um continuing
but but less frequently. Let's talk
about what are some of the ways that um
that people thought to create a strategy
that doesn't make D and F about the
same.
>> Yeah. Go ahead.
>> Look at the sequence of like local
maxima and minima.
>> Local maxima and minima. Okay. I think I
know what you talk about, but let's give
me a little example. What um let's talk
about A. What do you what do you
>> So you could maybe argue that the C is
the local minimum and then the F is
higher than both of its neighbors. So
it's a maximum and then the D is a
minimum. The E is a maximum and then the
D and C after that are not really
anything until you hit the A on the 16th
note.
>> Cool. So yeah, we're just looking at
every time the direction changes of the
pitches. Great. And compare that. So
beginning A has D F D E here we have D F
D tiny bit different D F but then going
down to a little bit different but it's
at least giving some numbers we have um
yeah does always the question is does
your current streak end when you hit a
rest or not and maybe it depends on how
long the rest is. So good. Other other
strategies?
>> Adam,
>> I would look at where offsets are the
same and then check if their notes are
the same or not.
>> Great. So, we're gonna look at offsets
that are the same and see if notes are
the same or not. That works really well.
And what I'd love to do if if this were
um what do you call the the generalized
adversarial problem set, the GAN problem
set, where one one team has to solve the
problem, the other team has to keep
giving them things that break that. Uh,
and I think it was a great idea and I
think it would work in general, but I
could generate something like um where
all I insert is let's insert a 64th rest
at the beginning and then put all random
notes and you're going to end up with
and then maybe we'll put one note that's
the same at the end and you could end up
with 100% of the notes on the same
offset are the same. Uh I think you I
think we we would really work in the
real world but but we might want to
always think about something like that
too. Great great idea John then
>> ours kind of builds up on Adam. So
>> you kind of start kind of builds up on
what Adam was saying.
>> Um but first you like take a look at the
notes and kind like kind of do like a
set kind of like crossover between like
a set of D's and A notes and then like A
and S notes. So both those would still
like show up like relatively high and
then like compare the offsets which we
want to like take half of it but still
keep D relatively high.
>> Okay.
>> Super. When we're talking about offsets,
are we talking about um what kind of
offsets
>> like um where in the guess like within
the two measures?
>> Great. Yeah. Where in the two measures
where in the measure um we sometimes
want to do global offset from the
beginning of the measure, but then you
can't identify similar phrases or all it
takes is put a repeat, put the first
four measures, repeat it once and
suddenly the whole rest of the piece is
different. So yeah, that's great.
also similar but a little duration based
I guess like if you just start at time=
0 and go all the way through the piece
like anytime the two pieces have the
same pitch if you score so like the F
that they both have on beat two would be
like a quarter point because
>> the F the F that they both have on beat
two would be a quarter point because
>> shared duration is only for that 16th
note.
>> Gotcha. So we look at shared.
Great. I like that a lot. Did anybody
try to come up with equivalence? Yeah.
Yeah. The contour ends up being a kind
of a new equivalence class that we
hadn't talked about which kind of works
out in thinking that everything that
doesn't change directions is a kind of
passing tone even though not in the
proper music theory term and so can kind
of be ignored.
By the way, I the one I use quite often
is I'm just going to look on down beats
or strong or on beats and ignore
everything else. Um, and that would
works pretty well for a lot of a lot of
things.