[Music]
there's nothing sacred about the
six-foot rule in some cases it's
inadequate and in other cases it's
overly conservative problem with any
measure quantitative measure limits one
variable is it's neglecting the
interaction between these variables if
you have really high ventilation maybe
you can have more people by analyzing
the available spreading data from Super
spreading incidents where the physical
characteristics of the rooms are known
to come up with quantitative guidelines
to say as a function of the various
parameters in a certain space what is
the actual risk it's not enough just to
qualitatively say oh you should open the
windows or you should increase
ventilation well how much what if we
already have a lot of ventilation do
anym and how many people can really be
in that room safely and for how long the
devil's in the details if you can't put
a number on these things then nobody
knows how to act for more MIT moments
from MIT open learning like subscribe or
follow