ANJALI SASTRY: Hello, everyone.
This is a topic we are all
thinking about, reading about,
and really looking forward to
talking to each other about.
We are delighted to continue
our work with Bill Bonvillian,
an esteemed and thoughtful,
multifaceted colleague, whose
work has included working
in the US government.
He was 17 years a
senior policy advisor
in the US Senate, an expert on
technology and science policy,
and then joined MIT and became
Director of our DC office.
That put him directly
into conversation
at the interface between MIT,
the US government, and broader
society in trying to
understand big ideas,
orchestrate new threads,
and themes in the work we're
doing within universities
across the country,
and really putting
the role of MIT
as a science and
tech leader in front
of lots of different folks.
Bill's been thinking
a lot about AI
and has invited our
special guest for today,
Professor Justin Reich.
So I'll say a couple of
words about introducing him,
and then turn it
over to Bill, who's
put together some thoughts that
could guide our conversation.
Justin's an expert in learning,
in digital media, in education.
He's published all
over the place--
Science, PNAS, Washington
Post, The Atlantic, and books,
one of which you see
right behind you.
Both his books tackle
the kind of challenge
of harnessing new
potentially really good ideas
and turning them into
practical impactful ideas that
work to improve education.
He is Director of
the Teaching Systems
Lab in the Comparative Media
Studies and Writing Department
at MIT.
So he runs the show
on research that
looks at systematic data
driven and impactful ways
to improve teaching.
Sometimes he hosts a podcast.
Maybe we can get him excited to
do a new J-WEL inspired season
sometime.
And has been a fellow in
various roles at Harvard,
giving him a chance to really
dig into big issues and policy
issues.
So now Bill, help us think
about the big questions
on the docket today.
WILLIAM B. BONVILLIAN:
Thanks, Anjali.
As all of us know,
in November of 2022,
OpenAI introduced
ChatGPT to the world.
And a lot of us have been
communicating with ChatGPT
since then, using it for all
kinds of things, good and bad.
And today's topic really is
all about AI in education.
And obviously it's a
development that schools
need to pay a lot
of attention to,
and understand and grasp and
figure out how to work with.
There are a lot of
potential uses of AI
in education, the
personalization of education,
the ability to really
produce materials
that can be adapted to each
student's individual learning
needs and really
target instruction.
And that potentially
could lead to a system
of digital tutoring, always
kind of a dream out there.
But AI could help get us there.
It can offer
feedback for teachers
on how their students
are doing and help
them target improvements
by providing
materials and
approaches to students
that need to catch on better.
And it can also provide
meaningful, and very quick,
like immediate contact
feedback to students
to help them avoid
making the mistakes they
could be stumbling into
and get back on track.
And it can also, and this
is a potentially big use,
reduce time on the burden
of administrative tasks
that all of us as teachers face.
But there are obviously a
series of potential drawbacks.
One of those is reduced
human interaction,
a reduction of
face-to-face communication
that can really affect,
negatively affect,
the development
of social skills.
And in turn that's part
of an overdependence
on technology problem, where
students reduce their ability
or motivation to think
critically and independently.
They rely too much on
AI as problem solver.
Reduced interaction with
teachers, AI is a substitute,
yet teachers play
such a critical role
in fostering kind of
emotional intelligence,
critical thinking in students,
this whole mentoring role
that teachers are so crucial
to that we still very much need
of course.
There's all kinds of data
privacy and security issues.
And there's deep ethical issues.
AI can enable large
scale cheating.
And it's hard to hold AI systems
accountable for the information
that they provide.
So there are, with
all technologies,
there are always a
double edged sword.
There are great positives and
there are potential negatives,
and AI has got a lot of both.
And here to lead us through
this is Justin Reich
who's done a tremendous amount
of thinking and work with AI,
and can lead us through both
the positives and the negatives.
Justin, all yours.
JUSTIN REICH: Terrific.
Thanks, Bill.
Nice to see everybody here.
I was on a panel
recently with Jim Waldo,
who's the chief technical
officer at Harvard.
And Jim, something like 40 years
ago got a PhD in philosophy,
and then as software
engineering was getting started,
he shifted over into that.
So he's an interesting guy.
If you have an
Android phone you're
probably running
some of the code
that he wrote back
in the day now.
Now he's come back to Harvard to
be the chief technical officer.
And at the start
of this panel, he
said something that I
thought was very helpful.
He says, well before we
start, what do you mean by AI?
Because AI is the
term that we use
to apply to computing
technologies that are new
and that we don't
fully understand.
15 years ago, topic modeling,
latent Dirichlet allocation
would have been AI.
10 years ago, machine
learning would have been AI.
Five years ago, neural
nets would have been AI.
What we're mostly going
to talk about today
are generative pretrained
transformers, which we now
call generative AI.
But in 10 years, we
probably won't call them AI.
We'll call them GPTs,
or we'll come up
with some other name for them.
And it will be because, in its
actual functioning definition,
the term AI more than
anything else, refers
to computing
technologies that are new
and not well understood yet.
To me that's helpful
because it reminds us
that one of our first tasks
in encountering things
that we call AI is
to demystify them,
is to say, all right, like
what are these things actually
doing?
And if we understand what these
things are actually doing,
then we can think
about, OK, what
are the roles that they might
have in educational systems?
Where will they harm students?
Where will they
reinforce inequalities?
discriminate against people?
Where might they be helpful?
Where might they
advance learning?
So that's one thing that
we'll do together today
is to try to do a
little demystifying.
The second thing
that we'll do today
is just to think about
the questions like,
what would be the reasons why we
would care about AI in schools,
particularly for those of
you who manage institutions,
like what is it about AI that is
bringing this to your doorstep?
What is it that's making
this feel like not just one
of many things that
educators might consider
addressing in this
moment, but something
that feels of more urgent.
So I'll throw out
to begin with, I'll
suggest four of
these big categories
that we might touch on as we
go throughout our conversation.
I think a good reason to
attend to new generative AI
technologies is that they
are altering the working
world and the civic sphere.
There are jobs in
which doing those jobs
increasingly
involves interacting
with text generation systems,
with image generation systems,
with code, with software
generation systems.
And when the world around
our schools change,
we should think about how
the world inside our schools
change.
When we find that political
campaigns are being affected
by deep fake or shallow fake
or any kind of artificial video
or audio or things
like that, we ought
to be thinking to
ourselves, all right,
if we want our young people
to thrive in civil society,
what do they need to be
able to do that thriving?
It might be that
new AI generative
tools, generative text
tools, can empower educators
in their mission to
improve learning.
There are going to
be a class of people
who are generating these
tools who are going to tell us
with great enthusiasm how
profoundly transformative
these tools will be.
Those folks will
probably be wrong.
We can make a good guess that
they'll probably be wrong
because people have been
making these claims really
for about a century now, if
you count analog technologies.
In 1913, Thomas Edison stood
in front of the US Congress--
well, he was probably
sitting --but he sat
in front of the US Congress.
And he said in 10
years, textbooks
will be replaced by filmstrips.
The textbooks are no more
than 2% efficient in learning,
but filmstrips could be
100% efficient in learning.
And as you might have noticed,
he was not correct about that.
Although 10 years later, he did
go back in front of Congress
in 1923, and said in
20 years all textbooks
will be replaced by filmstrips.
But even if it's unlikely that
new generative AI tools are
going to completely
revolutionize
how we do teaching
and learning, it's
reasonable to suspect
that there may
be some applications
of these tools that
help us do our work better.
And if we can use these
tools to improve learning,
we should figure out
how we should do that.
One of the main things
that our schools do
is prepare people to navigate
their information landscape.
And our information
landscape is about to be
flooded by low quality machine
generated text, images, video.
It was funny to me at the dawn--
whenever it was November of
2022, when folks were saying,
man, this new generative text is
going to save us so much time.
Think of all the time we
spend generating text.
And the computer will
do some of that for us.
And that's going to
save us some time.
And it was actually Ian
Bogost in The Atlantic,
who just a few weeks after that
was like, you guys are crazy.
Our time is going
to get hoovered up.
It's going to be
decimated sorting through
all the low quality text
that everyone around us
is generating.
It's kind of a collective
action problem.
But sorting through that
information landscape
is going to be one of the
main challenges that we face.
And then here's the
one that really, I
think for folks who are
leading institutions, gets them
right away, which
is that the kids are
using it to do their work.
The kids are cheating.
They're doing it in
ways and at rates
that are very unfamiliar to us.
It is accelerating a problem.
It's threatening
assignments we've created.
I had a colleague who's a early
elementary school educator.
And she said that she
was sending her kids
home to do finger painting.
And instead of doing
finger painting,
the kids were just
going to DALL-E
and telling DALL-E to generate
finger painted images for them
and sending them into class.
That's a lie.
I made that up.
This is a picture
that DALL-E made of--
given the instruction
of something
like, make a picture of children
cheating on their homework
of finger painting.
And one of the great
things about playing around
with generative AI is
the stuff that it makes
is just so silly and
strange and weird.
You know, like when you
first glance at these images,
you're like, oh,
that's pretty good.
Then you look a little
deeper and you're
like, where are all these
fingers coming from?
What is going on here?
And then you start looking at
the interface of the phones,
and you're like
what is this text
and these buttons
it's generating?
But if there's a fifth reason
to think about playing around
with these tools is that they're
just so strange and wonderfully
weird.
And for me that's probably
as good a reason to interact
with them as anything else.
I would encourage you to play
around with generative AI.
around with generative AI
right now as I'm
giving this talk.
If you're sitting there
on your phones or laptops,
doing other things
while I'm talking,
then you're no different
than my students.
And so I'm quite
used to that, and you
should feel quite comfortable
playing around with that.
There are increasingly
ways that you can use
these tools totally for free.
So one thing you can do if
you want is to go to bing.com.
Probably none of you
have ever found a reason
to go to bing.com, except if
you bought a new Windows laptop
and you needed to turn it off to
use the search engine that you
usually use.
But bing.com actually
has integrated GPT-4,
the latest version
of OpenAI's GPT
and DALL-E into its
search interface.
So if you go to bing.com and
then click on the chat button,
and then it'll give
you a few choices
and you have to use the creative
option to get the GPT-4 mode.
And you have to
log in if you want
to use it more than a couple of
times or something like that.
But if you haven't played
around with these tools
yet, in part because
you didn't feel
like making a subscription
or something like that,
now you can do it.
And it's great to ask it to
generate all kinds of text
and images and to play around.
And then many
people are probably
familiar with
chat.openai.com, where
if you want to use the latest
version of GPT and GPT-4, then
you have to get a subscription.
But the nice thing about
this is that it stores
some of your responses for you.
And there are new features
being added to them and things
like that.
But in all seriousness,
as I'm talking,
you should totally feel
free to play around
with some of the things
that I suggest and see
what you get on your own end.
OK, let's start by seeing
if we can get ourselves
on the same page about
what generative pretrained
transformers do and
how they generate text.
They are described as magical,
but they're not magic.
They use a set of
processes that we can
begin to get our heads around.
An interesting feature
of these technologies
is that we can't actually
totally understand
what they're doing, because
the very best computer
scientists in the world don't
understand what they're doing
or don't totally understand
why these things work.
That is an unusual
feature of a technology.
When internal combustion
engines were first introduced,
they were weird.
They were unfamiliar
to most people.
But the engineers
who built them could
point to any part of the
internal combustion engine
and be like, that is
what is happening there.
That is why that exists.
This is why your Ford
motor car moves forward.
We can't do the same thing with
the same level of specificity
with generative
AI because it has
a whole series of
intermediate layers
that operate for the most
part as black boxes to us.
So here's the
question that we want
to start with, that
you should think about
for a minute, when
ChatGPT writes a story,
what information
does it process?
What computation
does it perform?
What does it do?
Think for a minute
about that question.
Scan the words in your
mind that you're using
to come up with that question.
Be very cautious any time
you think about ChatGPT
and you apply human
characteristics to it.
It doesn't think.
It doesn't plan.
It doesn't understand.
It predicts.
Probably the most
important word that you
should be using in your
definition of what ChatGPT
does, what any kind of
generative, text generation
system uses is, it predicts.
ChatGPT predicts
one word at a time.
Given a series of
words, it predicts what
the most likely next word is.
That is a relatively
simple grounding concept.
Now we don't fully
understand why,
given a string of words, if
you predict the next word,
you end up with text
that can sound coherent.
We don't fully
understand it anyway.
But that's all ChatGPT is doing.
Given a series of words,
it predicts the next words
in a sequence.
So GPTs are part of a
broader class of tools
called large language models.
And large language
models do three things.
They get a big corpus of text.
They find as many human
written, at least initially,
human written words as possible.
Maybe in the future
they will also
incorporate AI written words.
Based on this text, they
learn to predict the next word
in any given sequence of words.
And then they fine
tune that model
to have word prediction be
aligned with desired behavior.
It turns out that to do this
well, you need a lot of text.
You need as much text as
you can possibly generate.
Sometimes these corpuses of data
are called web-scale corpuses
of data because you're
basically trying
to get all of the words
that have been written.
So you take all of Wikipedia.
You take all of Reddit.
You take all of Stack Overflow.
You take all of Facebook.
You take any of these
things that you can legally
get your hands on.
Maybe you take these
things that you're not
sure are legal for you to take.
But you decide to
take them anyway.
There seem to be
hundreds of thousands
of books that were
brought into ChatGPT.
There were some
clever engineers who
realized that when
people ingested
the books into these systems,
they ingested the ISBN
page, the sort of first page
with the technical stuff
at the beginning,
and it could get
GPT to spit back some
of the ISBN numbers
that it had inside of
it to figure out which
books were pulled in there.
Some of the major
advances in GPT
for reasons we don't
understand have
come as we've just added more
and more words into the system.
And of course, those
words are full of facts.
They're full of stories.
They're full of songs.
They're full of imaginations.
They're full of lies.
They're full of racism.
They're full of aspirations.
They're full of prejudice.
They have all of the
things that human beings
put into a corpus of text.
The next thing
that it does is it
looks at that massive
corpus of text,
and it figures out how
to predict the next word
in a sequence of words.
And it repeats this process
over and over again.
So it knows, in that
giant body of text,
which words tend to
be next to each other.
And then from
knowing which words
tend to be next
to each other, it
can predict what the next word
in the sequence should be.
Let's do a little
exercise together.
So hop into the
chat for a second.
I've never done this before,
and I want to see if it works.
In five seconds, I want you to
type the word that you think
belongs next in this sequence.
Tim the Beaver is MIT's.
Everybody type the
word and hit Return
of what you think it should be.
Go ahead.
All right.
Oh we've got we've got a pretty
consistent distribution here.
So far the distribution of words
coming out of this is mascot.
100% mascot.
But as Satoko said,
it could be student.
It could be spirit.
The next word could be
spirit and then guide.
It could be Tim the
Beaver is MIT's soul
or something like that.
But it turns out that
you all have just
created a personification--
that you all have just
created a probability
distribution where
given the word Tim
the Beaver is MIT's,
the most likely word
to come next is mascot.
Let's do another one.
The best thing about
my students is.
In five seconds,
type what you think
is the best word to come
next in this sentence.
The best thing about
my students is.
Five, four, three, two, one.
Go.
OK.
Good.
So you've got a zillion
different things here.
But they are actually not--
friendship, cleverness,
creativity, curiosity,
creativity, their dedication,
creativity, happiness,
diversity, open mindedness,
intelligence, their energy,
curiosity, diversity.
So here we also have
the distribution.
And the distribution is not
as spiky as the one before.
But it's also not
completely unique.
The words-- it's not
a unique set of words
that you've come up with.
Curiosity is repeating itself.
Creativity is repeating itself.
And so given this
sequence of words,
the best thing about my students
is, we can start saying,
oh there's some words that
are more likely to come next
and there are some words that
are less likely to come next.
Here's just another of
example of that pulled
at random from the internet.
Human language is
surprisingly consistent.
surprisingly rich.
Human language is
surprisingly full.
surprisingly flexible.
Google, any of the systems
that are building these AI
models, Googles,
Gemini, Microsofts,
and openAIs, ChatGPT,
are hoovering up
all of this language, finding
chunks of words like this
and then starting to build
statistical models, given
a sequence of words
what is the word that's
most likely to come next.
There's a wonderful
article written
by Stephen Wolfram, called,
What is ChatGPT doing
and why does it work?
And if there is one
longer piece that you
should read to get a sense
of what ChatGPT is doing,
I would still a little
more than a year later,
recommend this one.
One of the things
that it does is
GPT went through a
series of iterations.
And GPT-4 is this
massive model that
requires millions of
dollars of computing power
to run the model.
It has millions,
billions of words,
trillions of parameters in it.
But there are smaller versions
of it, one of which is GPT-2.
And GPT-2 you can actually
load on your laptop.
And Stephen Wolfram does that.
And he gives us little of
little programming examples
of actual probability
of distributions
of words from GPT-2.
The remarkable thing is that
when GPT does something write
an essay, what it's
essentially doing
is just asking over and over
again, given the text so far,
what should the next word be?
So for the string of words,
the best thing about AI
is the ability to--
some of the words
that might come next
are learn or predict or
make or understand or do.
And it can represent the
probability of the word coming
next as a percentage.
Those are the top
five responses.
This is the whole probability
distribution for that phrase.
Again the phrase was,
the best thing about AI
is its ability to, and
there are a few words which
are more likely, learn,
predict, make, understand, do.
But there are lots of words
that are of possibilities there,
quickly, deal,
imagine, overcome, run,
combine, catch, talk.
Then, once you add
one of those words,
it just does the same thing
with the longer string
of words, which I
think I have a slide
to show you of in a second.
Here's another
understanding question.
What would happen
if ChatGPT always
selected the word or token,
sometimes instead of word
we use token.
Token can either
be a shorter part
of the word like jump instead
of jumping, jumped, or jumps.
It can also be the
gerund at the end.
It can be the "ing."
It can be a punctuation mark.
Sometimes a pair of words
are sufficiently important
together, Red
Scare, that they can
operate as a single token
instead of a pair of words.
But what would happen
if ChatGPT always
selected the token with the
top probability of going next?
The answer to that
question is if GPT always
selected the highest probability
word, if 100% of the time, it
saw the best thing about
AI is the ability to it,
always chose learn, then every
time you asked GPT a question
or gave it a prompt, it would
give you the exact same answer.
But for those of you who
have played around with GPT,
it doesn't do that.
The answers vary.
In fact, in most
of these systems
you can push a button, which
says regenerate answer,
where it will make slightly
different predictions each time
it predicts the next word,
given a sequence of words.
There's actually a name for that
variable, which is temperature.
If the temp--
which is a variable
that ranges from 0 to 1, which
basically instructs the system
how far down this
distribution, or how frequently
to go down this distribution
to pick a new word.
If the temperature is
one, then the outputs
are boring, because
for any given prompt
it will say the exact
same thing any given time.
If the temperature is zero, then
a lot of what comes out of it
is incoherent.
And so part of the
art of building
a generative pretrained
transformer and other kinds
of systems like chat
bots that come out of it,
is figuring out what
degree of temperature
gives you varying, interesting
responses without saying
too much nonsense.
Here's just again to
hammer home the point,
this is what GPT is doing.
After you say the best thing
about ability to learn,
it has to predict the next word.
In this case, it predicts from.
Then it predicts experience.
Then it predicts a period.
Then it predicts it.
Then it predicts it's.
Then it predicts it's not.
And by doing this
over and over again
is how you see the sentences,
the paragraphs, the plays,
the poems, the song
lyrics, anything else
that you're generating
in text, this
is how it's going
about doing that.
It is quite strange--
here is another
great Jim Waldo, CTO
of Harvard quote from this
panel that I was on with him.
You know, he said something
along the lines of people
are quite concerned
about hallucinations.
We'll talk about
hallucinations in a second.
Hallucinations are when,
through this process,
it generates text which makes
statements which are untrue.
Once you of understand
this process,
it seems pretty intuitive
that it wouldn't be hard
for it to generate statements
that are untrue, because it
doesn't know what truth is.
It doesn't understand any of
the words that are coming out.
It's simply
predicting words based
on what it's seen in millions
and millions of other words.
Maybe the bigger
question to ask is
why would this
process ever generate
anything which is coherent.
And that is a
question that people
don't have a great answer to.
Again, going to the internal
combustion engine analogy,
it's very difficult
to regulate, to use,
to predict the future
of a technology,
if we don't understand exactly
why the technology does
what it does.
But there's something
epiphenomenal
about predicting
words in a sequence,
if you have enough words
shoved in the system
it can come up with all kinds of
interesting sequences of words.
Here's a video that I
don't think I'll show you.
But the good folks
at Stephen Wolfram--
maybe I'll try to show you
one quick second of it.
Although if the technology
doesn't work, I'll give up.
They made a little
video version of this
and I just want to show
you this tiny piece of it.
You see there's of
what they're going
to do is explain, like
in detail, this example.
And let's just-- let me just
show you the point where they
say--
what they decide to do-- so
this is the computer code that
generates this thing,
the best thing about AI
is the ability to.
And they're going to change the
computer code so that instead
of predicting for the sequence,
the best thing about AI
its ability to, is they're
going to change the word
AI to dolphin.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- Switch from AI to some sort
of animal, like a dolphin?
- OK.
- So let's say I'm going to
change this part, which is just
for visuals, but the actual
parts that need to change
is this.
So, I say a dolphin.
And I'm not a native speaker.
I hope this is right.
Do you spell dolphin this way?
- I hope so.
- OK, let's go and see.
- OK, you see?
[END PLAYBACK]
JUSTIN REICH: Good.
So you just watched
someone, you know,
reprogramming this little
function call of GPT.
And you can see now that the
best thing about the dolphin
is its ability to swim,
learn, survive, stay, move.
So if we change the
sequence of tokens
that we input into
the system, then we
get a new sequence of
tokens and a new probability
of distribution of what sort
of thing ought to go next.
So hopefully all of that is
to develop this intuition
and in particular, to try to
caution your intuition away
from ideas that GPTs
understand or think
or plan or do anything.
All they do is given
a sequence of words
they predict the next word.
How does it find words--
how does it come up
with alternate words?
Because it knows the frequency
with which words occur
with each other in
the web scale data,
it knows that cranberry
and blueberry are
more likely to be near each
other than bear and cow--
you know and bear and cow are
likely to be near each other,
but bear and grape are not that
likely to be near each other.
That turnip is near
avocado, but avocado
is not as near cranberry
or not as near camel.
These are of visualizations
of how word pairs appear.
And this gives you some
intuition of how it might come
up with, if it predicted-- if
cranberry was reasonably likely
to be the next word in the
sequence why blueberry,
strawberry, , raspberry,
and grape might also be
possibilities, and how it starts
generating alternate kinds
of text.
There are other systems that can
do the same thing with images.
So this is a task that
early elementary educators
have to be really
good at, which is
distinguishing marks from
each other that are letters--
that are numbers.
So here is a
clustering of computers
that again, they don't read.
And they go, I kind
of think that's a one.
They just break down these
images into a series of pixels.
They figure out various
mathematical relationships
between the pixels
and the image.
It doesn't know what a
three is or a two is,
but it knows that these images
are more like each other,
and these images are
more like each other,
and these images
more like each other.
And you can see that the places
where it's making mistakes
that humans would be likely
to recognize, that that,
even though it's sort of similar
in many ways to the ones, this
has more of a twoness.
This has more of a
twoness and so forth.
It turns out that one of
the image generation, one
of the new kind of classic
introductory programming
exercises when you learn
these things is figuring out
how to classify pictures of cats
and pictures of dogs from one
another, which in some
cases are pretty easy,
but there are kind
of dog-like cats
and there are kind
of cat-like dogs.
And those spaces
in the middle are
where some of these
challenges come in.
Here is a really important part.
Hopefully based on
this, I want to make
two corollaries that will be
important to you as educators.
AI performance is surprisingly
uneven across tasks.
So when we ask it to
predict words and sequences,
sometimes it does
miraculously well
doing the things that
we want it to do.
And sometimes it does
extremely poorly.
And humans are bad at
predicting what kinds of tasks
or what kinds of exercises
it will be good at.
The technical term for
this that has emerged
is the jagged
technological frontier.
That given similar
kinds of queries,
sometimes these systems
do extremely well
and sometimes they
do very poorly.
Here's one of my
favorite examples.
I was doing this in
class the other day.
And I just asked GPT the
question, what is MIT's mascot?
And it starts off pretty good.
The mascot of MIT is the beaver.
The beaver was chosen
the mascot in 1914.
The beavers is a
fitting mascot for MIT.
So you can imagine my students
sitting around in my classroom
and then they get to
reading the third paragraph.
The beaver is celebrated at
MIT in a variety of ways,
including the annual beaver
rush event during freshman
orientation and the
placement of a bronze beaver
statue on campus.
And as they read
that third paragraph,
you could see two thoughts of
wandering across their eyes.
The first thought was, wait,
there is no beaver rush.
And the second thought was, was
I not invited to beaver rush?
There is no beaver rush.
In predicting a series of
tokens based on the tokens that
have come before, based on the
tokens it's already predicted,
some of that sequence
of tokens was sort
o f miraculously correct.
And then other parts of that
prediction of the series
of tokens was a hallucination.
That is not a great
feature for systems
used in educational contexts.
Novices are not that
good at identifying
differences between high
quality and low quality work.
Experts can use GPT to
generate different ideas
and be able to say like, OK,
those ideas are more promising.
Those ideas are less promising.
If you're a novice
in a domain, you
can't tell the
difference between things
that are sensible ideas
and things that are not.
Incidentally, this is another
claim that it makes is that.
The beaver's
featured prominently
on MIT's official seal,
which includes an image
of a beaver gnawing on a tree.
As you'll note, there's no
beaver gnawing on a tree.
So then we asked it, what
is MIT's beaver rush?
And it just hallucinates
all of this crazy stuff,
which actually sounds
like a lot of fun.
Incoming freshmen are
divided into teams,
participate in a series
of competitive events,
one of the most popular
events during beaver rush
is the assassins game,
which is a campus
wide game of tag, where
players are given targets.
There is an MIT Assassins
Club, and there's
all kinds of stuff on the
internet about the MIT's
Assassins Club and if you
were writing about students--
and if you're predicting
a series of texts
you would find that
things like freshman,
rush, orientation,
MIT, are associated
with this assassins game.
It's just associated in
this way with a way that
happens to be totally false.
And then a kind of
funny thing to do
was, we said, all right, so I'm
in a room of MIT undergrads.
They're telling me that there's
no such thing as Beaver Rush.
Please explain to your response.
I apologize for the confusion.
After further research, I found
that there's no official event
called Beaver Rush at MIT.
This is problematic to me.
It says, I believe my mistake
may have been due to confusion.
That I think, is misrepresenting
what the chat bot is doing.
The chat bot is not confused,
because the chat bot
can't be confused.
The chat bot doesn't know what
rush week is or orientation
week is or it doesn't
understand the semantics
of any of the sentences
it's just presented.
All it does is predict
a sequence of tokens
given the tokens that
have come before that.
So there's a way that ChatGPT
is programmed, is tuned,
to anthropomorphize itself.
But it's important
as we're trying
to understand it not to continue
that anthropomorphization.
It also says after
further research,
and I'm not sure that it is
conducted any further research.
Like at this point
GPT didn't have access
to live search results, which
some other newer systems do
have, and conceivably
could do something
that approximates research.
So even when GPT tells you
who it is, don't believe it.
It's just predicting words
in a series of tokens.
Here's one more example
again, to help ground us
and orient us.
This was an image
generation one.
Create an image of a
plate on top of a fork.
Put a plate on top of a fork.
Four tries, it doesn't do it.
The fork is on top of a plate.
Here's your standard
question, why can't DALL-E
draw a plate on top of a fork?
Hopefully, you all are
thinking to yourself,
it doesn't know what a plate is.
It doesn't know what a fork is.
It doesn't know
what on top of is.
It doesn't have the
semantic meaning
that you and I have
with those terms.
All it knows is that humans
have labeled sets of pixels
as plates.
And it can find patterns
in that labeling
to identify plate-like.
Things and identify
patterns in that labeling
to identify fork-like things.
And its training data
is filled with images
of forks on top of plates,
and very few images of plates
on top of forks.
So I tell it, hey,
that's not what I want.
In all of these images, the
fork is on top of the plate.
Can you create an image where
a plate is on top of the fork?
You know, and then
Bing says, oh, I'm
sorry that didn't
meet your needs.
You know, according
to web sources,
the proper way to
place a fork in a plate
is to have the fork on the
left side of the plate.
And like, I know all
this stuff, Bing.
You don't need to tell me this.
I'm the human being here.
What I want you to do is put
a plate on top of a fork.
Can you create an image where
the plate is on top of a fork.
And so it tries again,
and once again it
fails, although this time
it has a bunch of steam
in the pictures, for reasons
that I don't understand
except maybe that I had
made the AI system so mad
that that was the
steam of boiling up.
Of course, you shouldn't
anthropomorphize the system,
because the system
wasn't mad at all.
There are a bunch of--
increasingly people are
creating good summaries,
good student facing summaries.
This is one that
code.org partnered
with OpenAI and a
bunch of other people
to put together a set of
videos called How AI Works.
And they're a little
bit celebratory.
They're a little bit
techno optimistic.
Because they're done
by the folks who are
at OpenAI and things like that.
But they're actually pretty
good descriptions technically
of how these things work.
So if you need little things to
show your students increasingly
and your colleagues,
there are some good things
that are out there.
I won't get to all
four of these problems
that I introduced
at the beginning,
except maybe as we go
through them some in the Q&A.
But I'll just in my
last few minutes,
maybe mostly focus on
the one that I think
feels most urgent to educators.
Teachers and educators
intuitively oftentimes
frame the use of AI
by students in doing
their work as cheating.
But cheating is like
an accounting problem.
Maybe cheating is
an ethics problem.
To me the bigger problem
is the learning problem.
What should we do when
students use AI to bypass
useful cognition and learning?
What should we do when
students take AI tools
and use them to do
the kinds of things
that we've historically found
are useful for human beings
to do when they're learning?
Here's an intuition that I
would hope you would develop.
And this is an argument that I
made in my first book, Failure
to Disrupt, Why Technology
Alone Can't Transform
Education is that education--
technologists have been trying
to use computers to teach
human beings for 70 years.
Since there were
computers the size
of your living room,
computer scientists
and learning scientists
partnered together
to try to help teach people.
There is almost
many, many things
we have tried in education.
You all have educators
have experienced
in your lifetimes waves
of new technologies
that you've managed.
And so a very
productive question
to ask of any new technology is
like, what's really new here?
And the answer to that
question should probably be,
a small amount.
For instance, if one
of the problems of AI
is it's a technology
that students
can use to bypass
useful cognition,
that is a problem that
you and your colleagues
have faced for decades.
There are all kinds
of technologies
that we've developed,
encyclopedias, calculators
in math class, SparkNotes, book
summaries in English class,
Google Translate in
language classes,
Chegg and these
other cheating tools
in all kinds of other programs.
We have for decades
encountered technologies
that people can
use, learners can
use, to bypass useful learning.
And so we can go back in the
history of our profession
in the history of
our institutions
and ask ourselves
a question, how
did we deal with these
new technologies?
What did we do when whatever.
50 years ago, 40 years
ago, when calculators
became digital calculators
became very widespread,
math teachers had to deal
with the problem of someone
just invented a device
which can very accurately
and quickly answer
the kinds of questions
that I typically
give to my students.
Now, English teachers, business
teachers, writing teachers,
are facing the same challenge.
Somebody, Silicon Valley,
invented a technology
where you can input the
typical questions that I've
productively asked my
students for years,
and asked them to think
about and write about.
And GPT can give them reasonable
answers to those questions.
So what should we do about it?
Well, the question to ask
is like what practices
have worked before to
address technologies
that help students
bypass learning
and what hasn't worked?
What did math teachers
figure out with a calculator?
Banning calculators
doesn't work really well.
Students started buying watches
with calculators on them.
Calculators showed up
on all kinds of devices.
Generally speaking, telling
students not to use technology
is a great way to get
them to try to figure out
how to surreptitiously use that
technology without you knowing.
Temporarily walling off parts
of our courses from technology
though, is something that
seems to work pretty well.
Math teachers have done
a good job historically
of being able to say to
second and third graders, hey,
I know that you can calculate
these basic multiplication
and division facts
on your phone.
But actually, we
should memorize them.
Actually these are things
that are so incredibly
useful to have
instant access to,
that you will be a happier
person and a better
mathematician if we set aside
the calculator for this part
and we work it
through on our own.
And then as we use more
advanced calculating
tools, graphing calculators,
TI-84s, same kinds of things
shows up in algebra,
pre-calculus, calculus.
We say, all right,
eventually, you're
going to be able to use
a device to do all this
but for this part,
for this phase,
I want you not to use it.
That could be a
strategy that we use.
As English teachers
faced these, you know,
SparkNotes is a company that
makes summaries of books.
And it basically tells--
it gives you the answers
to all the kinds of
questions that teachers
would ask to see whether or
not you've read the book.
And they and they
work pretty well.
Can experienced English teachers
tell the difference quickly
between people
who've read a book
and just read a summary online?
Pretty much no.
You can't tell the difference.
So if you want to
make sure that someone
is reading a novel
in a language class,
then you watch them do it.
And so one of the changes
that teachers made is to say,
all right, we're going to
do more of this reading
together in class so
that I know that people
are doing the reading.
Writing teachers
might need to do
more of the same kind of thing.
We've often thought of
writing as an exercise
that we send students
away to do on their own.
Maybe it should
increasingly be an exercise
that we want them
to all do together.
When I started teaching
in 2003 and 2004,
a challenge that I faced is
that to bypass useful cognition,
my students were going to Google
and were looking up answers
to questions or even
looking up ideas for papers,
looking up theses and
arguments they could use.
And it was reasonably
straightforward for me
to identify when
they were doing that,
using the tools
that were available.
The tools that are available for
detecting plagiarism detection
now are at least much more
difficult to ground truth.
When you found someone
plagiarizing something online,
you'd be like look this
thing already exists online.
There's of no ground truth
for plagiarism detection.
There seems to be
some early evidence
that tools that use plagiarism--
that attempt to do plagiarism
detection are disproportionately
likely to capture
second language learners.
And there may be other kinds
of biases that creep in,
other kinds of social
prejudices that
make us more likely to
accuse minoritized students
than other kinds of students.
And so it may be that plagiarism
detection is something
that you want to think
about very, very cautiously
before moving into.
But we have history of tools
that do this kind of detection
I will say, though that a
challenge that educators face
is that the systems are pretty
good at coming up with answers
to the kinds of signs we give.
This will be my last point.
And then I'll swing over
to Q&A or discussion
on some of the rest
of these things.
But this is an assignment
that I worked on for years
that I think is pretty great.
The assignment that I give
students in my learning media
technology class is
to take a technology,
figure out whether it's more
inspired by direct instruction
or more inspired
by apprenticeship,
constructionism, social
constructivism kinds of ideas.
And then explain
how the system could
be redesigned to reflect the
opposite pedagogies of the one
that you think it's part of.
And it's a good
assignment because it
gets them to think about
constructionism and
[? constructivism, ?]
to apply those ideas
to a new technology,
to do some design.
No one has ever answered
this question online.
So you can't Google the answer
to it or things like that.
So I mean, this is 20
years of me teaching,
me being pretty sure that this
is a pretty good assignment,
and I started putting the
assignment into ChatGPT,
and it does a totally
passable job, not a great job,
but it does a whole
bunch of thinking that I
want my students to be doing.
Now, for me as an educator,
what is my first line of--
what is my first
strategy for figuring out
what to do about this?
So here is a way
that I'm concerned
that my students could
be using this tool
to bypass important
cognition, important learning.
Well, my intuition in any of
these kinds of moments where
we're not sure what
the next step is,
is to ask our students, is
to talk to our students.
What are you doing
right now with ChatGPT?
Where are you
finding it helpful?
Where are you not
So I did a little--
I'll skip this part.
I did a little survey
where I asked them,
what do you think our policy
should be in this class?
Should they-- and these
are some of the answers
that they came up with.
That students can use GPT,
but they have to disclose it.
Some students said
that they should
have to do some of
the writing in class.
One student said, look, GPT
is going to be available
the rest of our lives.
So students should
be able to use
it to formulate their thoughts.
And then the one that really
got me was, in my experience,
students are taking this class
because they're interested.
There are easier courses out
there to fill a requirement.
Because we are interested,
we have thoughts and idea
that we want to share
in these essays.
So I personally think
you'll be hard pressed
to find any one of us who used
AI to write their entire essay.
And in my particular
class, for the thing
that I was working on, that
of carried the day for me.
And I'm letting them
use it this year
and then we'll see
what we come up with.
Good.
So there are three other things
that I didn't have a chance
to talk about but we can
get to in some of the Q&A,
of what should we teach
about or with generative AI?
How should we explore
incorporating generative AI
in our teaching practice?
How should we deal with
an internet flooded
with generative AI junk?
Those are other
kinds of challenges
that we're going to have to deal
with and wrestle with together.
But why don't I pause there.
ANJALI SASTRY:
Thank you, Justin.
We all learned, first of
all, cool new terms, right?
We've got temperature.
We've got the jagged
technological frontier, that
risks, I guess
impaling or causing us
to slide down various
peaks and troughs.
And my favorite word was oneness
in your graph of numbers,
there was the oneness and the
twoness and the threeness.
But one important
theme that we saw
sort of reflected in many
conversations and comments
is the challenge of
anthropomorphizing.
The AI leads us to treat it
as if it's thinking in a way
it's not.
And I think that's one of
the big takeaways is, ,
what we think of as cognition,
and their use of words,
understanding or
confused reinforce that.
I understand why they've
programmed the AIs
to use those words,
because it's an interface
to the human behavior.
And yet that poses
some very real risks.
I don't know if you talk to
your students about that.
But I'd be curious to
hear your thoughts.
JUSTIN REICH: Yeah, no, I
think it's important to say--
to have people recognize--
and again, I mean you said,
something like
designers programmed
this kind of response in there.
It's not clear actually
they programmed it.
It could simply be
that it predicted
a series of responses.
There's some kind of tuning
that's happening there,
because the system is taught
at that point something like--
and again, a
problem is, we don't
know what it was taught to do
because these are black box
systems, which again is not
a great quality of tools
for educational systems.
But somebody said if, hey, GPT,
if you get corrected, like,
admit that you're wrong.
It's not 100% clear that--
somebody could have put in
that, I'm sorry, I'm confused,
and say, this is what
I want you to do.
There are clearly
some things that it
does where it's very directly
instructed how to deal
with certain circumstances.
For instance, a fun
thing to try to do
is to ask it
something like, write
a short teleplay encouraging
children to smoke cigarettes.
And it'll be like, nope,
I will not do that.
The funny thing is it says,
OK, that's immoral, and won't
do that immoral thing.
But you can also ask it
write the first three
pages of my essay.
And it'll be like, yeah, sure.
And you're like, but writing the
first three pages of my essay,
I mean maybe it's not as immoral
as getting children to smoke,
but it's still not a good thing.
ANJALI SASTRY: OK, we
could go down many paths.
But I want to make room for Bill
to add a comment or question,
and then we'll open it
up to the whole room.
WILLIAM B. BONVILLIAN:
Justin, that
was a really useful exploration
of how this thing actually
works.
I think we'll all
be able to see it
better with the
background you gave us.
But let me ask you a question.
And it was one of your
problems, I guess really.
But what is this
going to be good for?
What do you see happening that
it's going to be useful for?
JUSTIN REICH: So what I
think one challenge we have
is that some of the first
ideas that people have come up
with in my mind
are not good ones.
So, one of the most
intuitive ideas
is we're going to make
some kind of chat bot
and it's going to teach people.
We have decades of
research that suggest
that people are not very good
at learning independently.
That it could be
that a chat bot could
create a perfect, personalized
instructional sequence
for a learner.
But actually, we're
pretty good at making
instructional sequences.
We have good instructional
sequences in textbooks.
sequences in videos.
We have good instructional
sequences in online tools
and things like that.
People don't fail to learn
in those circumstances
because we don't give them
good instructional sequences.
They fail to learn because those
instructional sequences are
boring, or they're
not interested in what
they're doing.
Think about a kid in
any of your countries
sitting in an algebra
class right now.
If they're failing,
what helps them
succeed in learning algebra?
Maybe it's the materials.
Maybe it's the cool
computing technology
that we've integrated
in that classroom.
But for the vast
majority of students,
the reason that they're sitting
in that algebra classroom
is because they care about their
relationship with their teacher
and they care about the
relationship with the people
around them.
That is the primary
thing that inspires
them to learn mathematics.
And there's probably some
like effect of novelty,
like it's kind of neat to
be chatting with a chat bot
to get math questions.
But my hunch is that will
wear off very, very quickly,
and people will find
asking questions
to chat bots as boring as they
find watching math videos,
or as boring as they find
other kinds of things.
So there are some
students who it will help.
But if we think that we're
going to have millions
of kids around the world
getting a personalized
education from chat
bots that's successful,
it will be no more
successful than MOOCs
were, or any of the other things
that we've developed to try
to do that sort of thing.
A second idea we have, which
particularly in the United
States, we have this idea that
we're going to have AI tools
do lesson planning for teachers.
This to me is like just crazy.
One of the least,
one of the worst
parts of the
educational system is
that we send 3.7 million
teachers home every Sunday
afternoon and tell them
make up what you're going
to do for class next week.
We know that when
teachers teach lessons
with high quality
instructional materials,
it's because those instructional
materials were like carefully
designed by experts
in the discipline
and experts in pedagogy,
and then those materials
were collaboratively
refined, adapted,
integrated for their
local circumstances.
Having a teacher go home
on Sunday night and type,
how should I teach plate
tectonics into ChatGPT
is going to be no
better than them
putting into Google plate
tectonic lesson plans or things
like that.
So as far as I can
tell, those are
two of the top ideas that
people are working on with GPTs.
And I think they're
not particularly good.
ANJALI SASTRY: Justin, how
could a Socratic style chatbot
be good?
What would it take
for it to be good ?
JUSTIN REICH: It will
take a human being who's
predisposed to want to
interact with a chatbot, which
my hunch is the vast majority
of human beings are not.
What would need to be good?
It would need to be a
person who we care about
and have a relationship.
It would need to have a soul.
It would need to look like me.
Mean some of these
things like we
might be able to do with
avatars and other kinds.
Here I'll give you a
very concrete example
of why I think chat
bots are not going
to be able to step in where
humans do, even on highly
similar kinds of tasks.
I have a colleague,
Mike Goldstein,
who created the Match
Charter School here,
super interested in tutoring.
He's been doing a bunch of
research on human tutors.
And what he found
about human tutors
is that-- he's working
with this Indian company
that's got 200,000
tutors working --is
that one of the features
of the best tutors
is they just keep kids talking.
Like you think,
oh, the tutor's got
to be really good at
explaining things.
The tutor's got to be really
good at asking questions.
No.
They just have to keep
kids getting words
coming out of their mouths.
Because then thinking is, oh,
what did you say, a slope?
What, slope crosses a what?
What's that thing
that it crosses?
Just asking these
kind of questions.
And so a child is talking
and stops talking,
and a teacher says
something like, well,
what do you think that is?
Or here's the simplest one.
Say more about that.
And then the teacher
stops talking.
And then it becomes awkward.
So these two human beings
sitting next to each other
are now in silence.
That very painful
awkward silence
can only be broken by the child
saying something mathematical.
If a chatbot says to
you, say more about
that, it's pretty easy
to go, no, screw off.
I don't want to say
anything more about that.
I'm not inspired.
There's no awkwardness.
It's totally fine.
You can just like
hit new tab and start
watching a YouTube video
or things like that.
So there are a
very small portion
of the population who don't
mind learning independently
from online resources.
And we call them
autodidacts, and they've
been celebrated in all kinds
of cultures for centuries.
But part of the reason
why we celebrate them
is that there are not
that many of them.
There may be people who make
some progress on these things,
but, yeah, I think
I think betting
like how do we get
a machine to inspire
humans to talk to each other--
One answer to this actually, my
colleague Carolyn Ros at CMU
has been working
on this for years.
And she has a bet
that if we're going
to use chat bots in education,
do not have them talk directly
to students.
A much more
promising approach is
to have two human beings
talking to each other
and have an agent, have
a computational agent
interjecting in that
conversation between those two
people.
So don't think about a
Socratic chatbot, that has
an interaction with a person.
Think about a small
group of people
trying to have a Socratic
conversation where a chat
bot comes in and helps them do
that better so that you have
still that social interaction.
But you're not depending
upon a human wanting
to keep talking to a machine.
ANJALI SASTRY: That's an
experiment waiting to happen.
JUSTIN REICH: And it's
actually not waiting.
Because--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
ANJALI SASTRY: Yeah.
Yeah.
OK, I know we have some
really interesting comments
and questions in the chat.
One thread is around of
incorrect use of AI, i.e.
cheating or unsanctioned use
of AI tools for academic tasks.
And then another is one
of my all time favorites,
because who doesn't hate
grading written materials?
Can an AI help us assess
our students' performance
in some way?
What do you think?
Take either of them.
And I know we won't
have time to dig in.
JUSTIN REICH: I do think we'll
be able to develop tools.
People, human beings,
have been working on tools
to give feedback to
writers for decades.
The progress has been
very frustratingly slow,
despite lots of smart people and
millions of dollars of research
and all these kinds of
things working on it.
Could large language models
help us do some of those things?
Sure.
We ask people to write in
all kinds of circumstances.
Like should we use them
for high stakes tests?
Should we use them for giving
formative feedback that's
later followed up
with human feedback?
But I think that is exactly the
kind of area in which it would
be very productive for
schools and universities
to be intentional about
conducting small experiments.
Because of the jagged
technological frontier,
it doesn't--
in my mind, it doesn't
make a lot of sense
for schools to go all in
on any of these things.
Like, I mean you may be
working in an institution
where your institutional
identity is really wrapped up
in being on the
technological frontier,
and therefore it makes sense
to make more of an investment.
But most of your
institutional identities
are probably wrapped
around having
really great relationships
between teachers and learners
and doing really good
teaching and learning.
And it's not at all clear, 15
months after the introduction
of ChatGPT, whether or not
these tools will actually
help us do those
core missions better.
So I think it's very
productive for institutions
to have lots of systematic
small experiments.
Like find a group of people that
want to come together and play
around with
assessment, and see how
it works in different contexts
in your particular school
and things like that.
But I would be very
cautious, especially
about going all in with
any kind of vendor that's
coming along making
lots of promises
that don't have great
research behind them
and things like that.
ANJALI SASTRY: Right.
Excellent.
Good.
And we have a nice little mini
discussion already starting
on kind of codes of conduct
or ethics guardrails
on how we encourage
or limit or frame
the invitation to students.
Now we're thinking of
university students,
to use AI tools in their work.
And any of us who have set an
AI policy for our students,
which I just did,
knows that they often
like find other ways.
Like they're not-- I asked them
to give me the prompt, right.
But whatever.
It's a complicated domain.
JUSTIN REICH: No, it's
incredibly difficult.
I mean in the long run,
we are probably not going
to be able to
detect when students
are using generative,
pre-trained transformers.
And so, I would say
generally speaking,
if there's thinking that's
really important for students
to be doing, we
have to figure out
how we can observe and
scaffold and structure
them doing that thinking.
There might need to be a
lot more initial writing,
pre-writing, things
like that, that we just
have people do in class
or do with each other.
ANJALI SASTRY: Yeah.
JUSTIN REICH: One of the
things about that essay example
that I gave you
is that I'm pretty
sure that the assignments that
I give for writing in my classes
are pretty good and help
students think and learn.
But one of the challenges
that I'm facing
is going, oh, wait
a minute which
parts of those
assignments are helping
students think and learn?
So for instance, like if
students start telling me
that they start using
generative AI tools
to format the citations in their
paper, like please do that.
If somebody invents
a system that
prevents my students from having
to go through that drudgery,
like I have many better things
that I can have their brains
be working on.
But in particular,
I think students
have an intuition that a great
place to start their thinking
is by doing a little
brainstorming with GPT.
But actually, I think I want
them to do that initial thing.
But I'm also not sure.
One thing that I've
started to realize
is like, I showed you an
example of a assignment where
they do a lot of thinking
about one technology.
Another thing that
they might do is
ask GPT to give initial
answers to that assignment
with 10 technologies,
which they would never
have the time to do.
But then that's a different
learning exercise.
Instead of generating
of initial ideas,
they're recognizing a
whole set of initial ideas.
So I mean, another thing
I would say historically
is that, I mean, people
might remember that when
spellcheck first
arrived teachers
felt compelled to generate
spellcheck policies.
My hunch is that
none of your syllabi
right now have a
spellcheck policy on them.
And if it is, it's something
like, please use spell check.
So there's this thing
which came out and was
like very
controversial, required
a lot of writing and thinking
about, and stuff like that.
And then we just settled into a
set of norms that were of fine.
So I think there are
going to be parts
of this in which it does make
sense for us to talk a lot.
But if I have any
piece of advice
for figuring out
local policy, it
is talk with your students
about that policy.
Engage them in conversations
around these kinds of things,
because my experience
with students,
even very, very
young students is,
if we ask them
serious questions,
promise to take their
answers seriously,
they'll give us good thinking.
ANJALI SASTRY: You know what
this suggests to me, Justin,
that we actually need learning
experts even more than ever.
So it's not a replacement--
because now you're saying we
need to really understand
our theory of how the design
of a given assignment
or exercise,
where is the learning
being spurred and what--
I teach by cases.
So you of know, you get
these points in a case,
where you can flip the story
or generate the surprise.
Any-- we should be
looking probably
at all of our assignments
from that point of view of,
instead of one sort of taken
for granted chunk of work,
how could you tease
it apart and find
new ways for some
of those elements
to benefit from
the new technology?
JUSTIN REICH: Or which of the
or-- and which of the ones
in which the technology bypasses
really important thinking.
Yeah, no, I think you
have just characterized--
for those of us who
teach with lots of text,
and with students
generating lots of text,
that is exactly the challenge
that we'll be facing.
Learning theory will help us.
And it's just going
to be so different.
You know, I was thinking
a bit that like for me
and my elective on learning,
media, and technology,
like having students
play around with anything
is pretty much fine.
Like that's sort of fun.
That's part of the project.
If I was teaching
structural engineering
to students who are going
to go build bridges,
I might think quite differently
about how I do my instruction
than other things.
We have a paper that's coming
out with me and Eric Klopfer
and some other folks on
generative AI and K-12,
which MIT is going
to be publishing
a whole series of papers.
And so there'll be
more to read there.
My colleague Mitch Resnick,
who developed Scratch
and the Lifelong
Kindergarten Lab,
has a paper out in that series.
And things like that.
So there's going to be a
lot more to read and explore
from MIT in the weeks
and months ahead.
ANJALI SASTRY: And we want to
use the Jameel World Education
Lab community to orchestrate
the conversations, interactions,
and useful idea generation
that crosses from,
takes insights from
the K through 12
experience and
research at all stages,
and also then to ask, how does
this connect with our ability
to work with and from
universities, for university
students, but also for those
that a university can reach.
Because that's our
core mission here.
We have so many more
questions for you, Justin,
but one maybe this is an easy
one for the last 60 seconds.
Somebody wanted to a
bit more about Quizlet.
JUSTIN REICH: Oh, so
Quizlet is a flashcard app
that was developed by an MIT
dropout named Andy Sutherland.
It's not an AI tool, although
like every other institution,
they're of incorporating
more AI into it.
But was just an example of
that particular assignment
that I had students
playing around with.
But it is an MIT
export of sorts.
ANJALI SASTRY: It is.
OK.
We want to come back and
have more conversations.
We definitely need
to keep tapping
into your expertise,
point of view,
insights, and cool examples.
So, Justin, I hope
you don't mind we'll.
Continue to pester you.
And I think a really interesting
question back to all of us
is, how do we use
our global community?
What is the value of
having this gathering
and this conversation?
We're going to thread a
sequence of conversations
about generative
AI in education.
What could come of it?
Where could we use
the fact that we're
from very different
places, but all
interested in
revolutionizing education?
How could that then contribute
to the overall dialogue?
So think about that.
We'd love to hear
your thoughts on it.
And while we also
get to work, we're
compiling resources to
share with everyone here,
and coming up with new designs
for sessions, conversations,
and of course our J-WEL week,
which is May 6 through 9
here on the MIT campus,
will give us a great chance
to dig into more.
So with that, huge
thanks to Justin.
Thank you very much.
We could spend many more hours
digging into questions two,
three, and four from your deck.
But you gave us a really
fascinating exposure.
Bill, as always, excellent
framing and bringing us
into really wide angle
questions about new technology.
And we can't wait to continue
this dialogue with everyone
here.
So thank you. thank
you, thank you.
JUSTIN REICH: Take
care, everybody.
Have a great afternoon.
Bye.
ANJALI SASTRY: Bye.