Hello. Hello. So, um if you're not if
you're not uh sitting down, now would be
a good
time. Uh welcome. Hey, Doug. Um welcome
to the uh third annual um uh envisioning
the future of computing uh prize finals
dinner. And uh yeah,
indeed. So we solic solicited um MIT
students of every stripe to uh submit
essays on a tech and ways in which this
tech could uh work to our our collective
good and pitfalls for us to avoid. Um as
um in previous years we've had a
wonderful array of submissions. We had
67 this year and they were judged
anonymously by intrepid courageous um
otherwise they're going to be credited
now by Jason Jackson, Mazio Cassami,
faculty Brad Scout, Nikostrakis and
Amando Solo Lazama. Thank you
[Applause]
judges. And um they selected from the 67
they selected some honorable mentions
who are um who get um spiritual
gratification and material gratification
for a thousand dollars. Um, and they are
here tonight, several of them. Andy
Coup, Alisa, could you stand up? Um,
Andy, uh, El Alysia, Jonathan Ziang,
Carrie Shen, Kristen Edwards, Lillian
Bluestein, Nathan Clus, and Ky Simeon.
Uh, well
done. Your papers will, I'm afraid, be
available on the website for all to
peruse for eternity. So um you get the
$1,000 in the credit but you also get
yeah that um and uh wonderful. And then
uh what's going to happen today is the
three finalists are going to give
presentations and um a larger committee
um composing uh of the people that we've
been talked about so far and some jolly
come lately jud judges um coming in to
like snatch the glory once the grunt
work has been has been done as ever. Um
Kieran Setia, Dan Hutton Locker, Asu
Oglar, and Agugustine Rayo. Thank you.
Thank you
[Applause]
judges. And what's going to happen?
We're going to see a presentation from
each of the finalists. It's going to be
13 minutes long and then there will be a
9-minute question period. Um well, I'll
hand the mic. Rules for the question
period, only one question, no
follow-ups. We're going to try to get as
many questions in as possible and keep
it clean and
uh and yeah, and then the judges will um
retire. I'm thinking the retiring will
take place at around 8:15 or 8:10 and
then we'll come back at 8:20 and we will
have a winner and the presentation of a
winner. So, we'll hopefully be done in
about an hour and 45 minutes this whole
thing. So, please stay for the
announcement of the winner.