So I'm going to invite my friend and
colleague Michael Shrag. Um Michael is a
lecture at the MIT Sloan School of
Management. He's a fellow of the
initially on digital economy. uh he's a
author um strategic advisor um former
journalist um has done work on
prototyping on the impact of AI and
thinking on all sorts of things
>> less is more
>> less is more so with that I'll hand over
to Michael
>> thank you very much
>> thank you let's go back here and there's
the
actually sorry this the slide contract
racting here. It's always wonderful to
be in the the muchcoveted after lunch
speaking position here. Um I'm going to
refer back to Phil's comment about
learning from a fire hose, teaching from
a fire hose. This is going to be a
forced march, quick march, and I want
you to come away with a sense as what
Stephen was saying in terms of the
potential and possibilities particularly
around generative AI. I I realized as
Stephen was referring to the past that
actually I do have a direct British
connection, English connection because I
had the good fortune literally and
figuratively to study under Donald
Mickey at Illinois and Mickey of course
was a a protege of Alan Turing and uh I
was the only uh undergrad in the class.
I learned a lot from that. That was one
of my best classes and clearly because
I'm here it clearly had an impact on my
on my professional life and perspective.
So this talk is thinking about thinking,
forgive the pun, gaining greater insight
into greater insight. And this is my
most important slide. The content of the
audience is more important than the
content of the talk because I have a
pretty good grasp of what I'm going to
be saying. I'm going to be very very
interested in the panel that that Steve
is going to moderate with myself.
Originally, you see in the program that
I was going to moderate the panel, but
it would be rather foolish to have me
moderate a panel after my own talk. Um,
so I'm sparing you. You're you're being
spared of that. Let's get it out of the
way. It is a revolution. Okay. People
talk about AI bubble, but this is not
hype. It is not hype. It is it is no
more hype than the the dependencies I
see adults, adolescence, and childrens
have on the tube and in the subway with
their mobile devices. Whenever I see a
paperback book, I'm sort of taken aback
by the inacronistic pleasure of it all
on this. So this is a revolution. It is
going to transform how people think, how
people learn, how people behave, how
people create value, how people consume
value. Um, and that is not hyperbole. In
fact, I think I'm being conservative in
that regard because what was the phrase
we heard uh this morning? Early days.
its early days. I wouldn't say that
we're necessarily on a Moore's law
exponential growth, but the growth is
happening
fast enough surprisingly enough that
that I think we the last conference was
two years ago, two to three years hence
we're going to be talking at least at
least a 10x order of magnitude
improvement. I wouldn't be shocked if it
was a more than that. Um, again,
customizing for the locals. You all know
this fellow who managed to develop a
pretty good collaboration with the late
Steve Jobs. Um, now he has a pretty good
collaboration with the living Sam Alman.
They did their developer day earlier
this week. I decided to lift this quote.
I've never in my career come across
anything vaguely like the affordance,
like the capability that we're now
starting to see.
Um, I think Johnny IV should be taken
seriously in this regard. Not just
because of who he's gotten to work with,
but because he's a designer. He has
focused on UX. He has created co-created
some of the most successful products and
services in the world. So, this was my
frame. Why am I using this particular
photo? Because it's good. And because I
was for ILP in Mongolia last month and
we were talking with a mining company on
this and they were curious about LLMs,
of course, one of the challenges for
them is gee, do we go with anthropic? Do
we go with open AI? Do we go with
deepseek? What should we do in this
regard? But the capabilities, the
capacity is still there. And I kind of
like this metaphor. I kind of like this
analogy because why? They're taking aim.
It's a human trying to be on target and
they're riding a horse. Okay. And what's
the this is ultimately you can't take
the shot if the horse misbehaves. Okay.
What's the relationship with the models
that you want? This is the essence and
the nature of the research that I'm
working collaborating on and overseeing
at MIT. What's the nature of the
relationship with the models that you
want? As these models learn, as these
models learn to learn to get better by a
a variety of different features and
functions and from you and with you. Um,
I happen to know Warren Buffett. He was
on the board of the Washington Post
company. I was a reporter of the
Washington Post. It was my quote again.
Good fortune to know Mr. Buffett. And
he's reading his shareholder letter. Uh,
by the way, you want to do have great
fun, dump in the Berkshire Hathaway
shareholders letters and to chat GPT or
Anthropic and interrogate about how you
should be doing your investments. You I
guarantee you it'll be a productive
experience for you. So, he was once
asked of the billionaires I've known,
money just brings out the basic traits
in them. If they were jerks before they
had money, they're simply bigger jerks
with a billion dollars. Okay? So with
tongue not in cheek at all I said well
how do the wealth of LLMs instead of
billions of dollars billions of
parameters
so this is LLM Warren Buffett of the
professional I've known eight of their
basic cognitive traits if they were
intellectually lazy before LLMs they're
simply intellectually lazier with better
sounding slops
that's not a joke that's a fact that's a
warning
That's arguably one of the most
important takeaways I'd like you to
consider from this. The unavoidable
challenge. The unavoidable challenge
that I mean just let me make a global
statement right now. There is not a high
school, grammar school, university
student who I have come across in the
last six months, particularly elite ones
who do not cheat with LLMs.
Okay. It's like mobile phones. This is
part of the way they see themselves and
the way they learn. And what's the
choice they're making? Are we using
these LLMs to be mindful, to think
better, or to be mindless? I don't want
to think about that
jerk. Intellectually lazy,
intellectually sharp. This is a real
nonfalse dichotomy. And I strongly urge
you as you begin to explore or continue
to explore and utilize these
technologies, you become more self-aware
and self-conscious about where do you
consistently default to mindlessness or
whether you aspire to getting greater
value from being mindful in this regard.
Okay. So that's the level set. every
organization that I work with in
executive ed or in advisory capacities.
How do we get better greater greater
value from our data, our metadata? How
can we make data learning easier for our
people? This is everyone's challenge
everywhere. And this piece just came out
in July. You may have seen the Carpathy
thing. We'll discuss that in a moment.
I've been looking at the notion of Vibe
analytics. You heard about Vibe coding.
I'm looking at Vibe analytics. How can
we use LLMs, SLMs to create a different
relationship with the patterns of data
that we intentionally or accidentally
collect? And clearly for organizations
that are saying, gee, how do we get
greater value from our data using AI?
This struck me as a meaningful and
measurable shortcut to both efficiency
and effectiveness so long as we're aware
of the mindful mindless trade-off. Okay,
what's my definition? I believe in
defining the terms just as we defined
innovation. Vibe analytics is how your
business instincts argue with your data
patterns. Argue with your data patterns
and both get sharper at what they see
and how they see together. So it's
individual and collaborative. We talked
about the importance of collaboration
with various partners. Screw the human
beings. You got to collaborate with the
machines. you you need to become a
better one of the most interesting
things I think going forward is do you
get more value
this is a testable hypothesis do you get
more value collaborating with your human
colleagues or with their LLM
instantiations and mediations that is an
open question I say without hesitation
that I do maybe it's because I'm my
neurode divergent tend tendencies but I
have a very good time collaborating with
the LLMs
you can adjust your interpretation of my
talk accordingly. So what's the origin
of this? So these things came out MIT as
a men's at manus kind of place
hackathons I basically stole h the
hackathon concept did prompts that's
what we did for exec and various clients
how do you upskill and reskill people
give them use cases give them the data
that supports those use cases what are
and set up different teams so we make it
social and so we create some sort of
excuse for individuals to collaborate
not just individuals and the machines to
collaborate and try effectively analyze
those use cases or produce meaningful
outcomes and outputs for those use
cases. Promptathons fantastic thing. I
urge you to consider them in your own
own organizations. KPIs is the more
serious of the research. Everybody here
knows what KPIs are. Okay? And people
have thought about oh how do we use LLMs
to improve performance to improve KPIs?
Screw that. Why don't you make the KPIs
intelligent? Why don't you make KPIs
intelligent software agents that learn
and learn how to learn? So your CLV,
customer lifetime value KPI or your
churn KPI can learn to improve. Gee,
what data does it need to learn to
improve? You can incorporate techniques
like chappley values and herwitz
mechanisms for alignment etc etc. It's a
great playground for rethinking the
economics of performance and of course
vibe coding. There's Mr. Carpathy and I
basically said because you know all of
my thinking is derivative at this stage
um you know vibe coding how can it apply
to vibe analytics
and this is the story your data has
insights people can't see you can see
I'm stealing this from my I'm
plagiarizing myself from my exec class
and your people have intuitions your
data can't capture when you
intentionally llm make them argue with
each other you know the only aspect of
marks I take seriously is the Hegelian
dialectic. Use LLMs to create
dialectics. Here they both get smarter.
We move analytics from how does our data
confirm what we already believe or test
what we already believe? Apologies to
Mosellar and Tuki in classic exploratory
data analysis to what can our data and
intuition discover together that
surprises us both.
Respectfully, that's the antithesis of
mindless. Okay. So the virtuous cycle we
seek to en encourage I seek to encourage
with my classes and my clients learning
to vibe analyze vibe analyzing to learn
that's going to be one of the most
important things going forward in
getting value from LLMs how do we work
with them individually collectively
to create a virtuous cycle network
effects in that regard because we all
want to improve our RO ai sorry I like
acronymic puns. Return on artificial
intelligence.
Return on actionable insight. That's the
virtuous cycle we seek to do. The point
of this these brief remarks before we go
to the panel. Empower you to
intelligently invest in actionable
insights, not answers. Okay, that's the
big mistake. How do we use LLM to get
the right answer? Get the better answer.
screw answers. Use them for insight.
That's what they're best for. Pattern
matching. Now, what I'm saying now is
probably going to be untrue in 24 to 36
months. But for now, if you're spending
time with LLMs, focus on AI, actionable
insights. Uh um so thinking about
thinking means generative AI for
generating actionable insights and
return on actionable insights transforms
return on artificial intelligence and
vice versa. That's the value prop.
That's what you should be exploring in
your own organizations. Again, defining
with terms, an insight is an event in
your mind. An actionable insight is a
capability in your hands. What's been
one of the themes you've been hearing
all bloody day? Men's atmos minds and
hands. That's one of the reasons why I'm
picking this. It's not enough to think
better. You have to be able to do
something with that insight.
How does the shift sh change what we
what we think is worth noticing? How
does it expose a tension between what
we're measuring KPI and what we
recognize what matters? How does it
change the ne cascade iteration? How
does it change the next best question or
revise the reason we were asking in the
first? Oh, that's why we should be
interested in this sort of thing.
Insights become actionable when you can
actually do something with them. And
that these are the key analytic princip
principles I observe really encourage
you to take very seriously.
Shift from datadriven to insight.
Use LLMs to question the assumptions
underlying the question and make your
data talk back, argue back, fight back,
be insightful as well as insightful in
your engagement there.
Okay. Theory reality I'm telling you
about I I do research in KPA KPIs KP
AIS.
This was a two years ago. I was thinking
what's a good metaphor? What's a good
analogy for my exec classes on the
future of KPIs? What what can I gee
engage around and iterate around? What
concept can generate actionable insights
for me? So this was mine. Okay. Gee, I
think we should think of KPIs as GPS to
guide enterprise decision. Okay.
You know, this was my my core insight.
So I began asking LLMs about this. So
basically I said I can show you the
original prompt but we're taking within
times.
Tell me how good of analogy how good of
a metaphor this is. This is the answer.
I'm not going to read it all to you but
let me tell you what what unhinged my
jaw. Their ultimate purpose is improving
outcomes through dynamic optimization.
It would take o over three months for
most grad students to come to that kind
of conclusion if I asked them to do
reporting on it. Okay. So I'm getting an
infrastructure. I'm getting something
that's yes isorphic in terms of
actionable insights in terms of gee how
can I draw actionable inspiration from
this GPS metaphor and analogy. And so I
began to play with these sorts of things
and I did this. I mentioned Malaysia.
Let's go to Indonesia. This was with
Claude and I'm giving a talk obviously
running a workshop with some Indian
financial institutions
KPI CLV KPI you know gamma gamma
probabilistic non-binomial distribution
uh um I don't have to read this all to
you but look at look at the bottom there
please give your response in a way that
would impress an audience of
sophisticated Indonesia Indonesian
business people and technologists
because you know the content of the
audience is more important than the
content of the talk. Okay. So, I care
about my audience a lot. In fact, I
cared about it so much that this was the
answer from Claude. It's in Bahas.
It's in Indonesia. I said I said when I
first saw this, my immediate reaction
was, "Oh my gosh." I I asked at
something that made the model break
down. Then I said, "Oh my gosh, this is
this is actually Indonesian." So now I'm
in the embarrassing position of having
to ask the model, okay, you gave me the
answer for sophisticated, but I don't
understand Indonesian and Bahasa. So put
it in English for me, and this is the
answer.
Okay, I I I don't again need to go this
all the way down, but but this is not
okay. This is not slop. This is serious.
This is the kind of thing that would
take at least a couple of weeks for
people to put together in this regard.
And it's the kind of thing that can be
the scaffolding for an initiative for
how do we take our static legacy KPIs
and begin to turn them into KPAIS.
And this is the final conclusion. I did
not edit this. Okay?
I'm not saying it's self-aware. I'm
saying that if you prompt it
appropriately, and this is key, force it
to articulate why it did certain things,
force it to call out the pattern match
that it used to generate the actionable
insight. Just don't take the insight.
Look at the guts, the neurons, the deep
learning networks for that insight. So,
what about us? Okay, shift the goal.
Answers are the enemy. Insights are your
ally. Okay, insights unfreeze. Start any
review that you're doing. What did you
miss? What would change if the opposite
were true?
That's a prompt, by the way. Serious
thing. How many of you record your
meetings with Google Meet Meets or
Teams,
okay? And you look at the meeting
summaries.
Don't use meeting summaries. Take the
trans they clean stuff up. Take the
transcripts and interrogate the
transcripts. What was the what was the
best part of this meeting? Where was the
biggest disagreement?
Go with the raw data. Go with the
noisier data. Don't allow don't be
mindless by letting Microsoft and Google
some or or Zoom summarize these things
for you. But that's a different class
and different lecture. Okay. Redefined
data static reports to living dialogue.
Same thing. Messy data set. What's the
most uncomfortable pattern here? Not
answer pattern. What could it mean? Now
force it to disclose semantics from
that. Okay. Epistemics, ontology,
teiology. Gee, you're going to have to
start taking philosophy more seriously
in that regard. For those of you who
took PPE, your your degree just became
more valuable if you take LLM seriously.
Okay. the metric time to reframe not
time to answer time to ah what's the
right context they're not called context
windows by accident we should be
examining these things for I talk about
actionable here's one of the most
important things that I've learned that
I want to share with you actionable is
contingent upon organizational team and
enterprise culture there's no such thing
as commodity actionable definitions they
will be bespoke Everybody has done SQL
or CSV decision science quote analysis
that gives you an insight that you can
do nothing with. It's technically
accurate but useless. How do you make it
actionable? And we've now changed the
ontology. And yes, I'm going to repeat
it. Actionable insight AI. Okay, that's
the real AI here. Return on AI. What are
your strategies for making actionable
insights more valuable? Publish your
actionability spec. Run vibes in a
meeting. Schedule a Vibe sprint
promptathon. Recognize and reward
reframes. Make that a part of your KPIs.
Vibe analytics doesn't just use AI
defined patterns. They use AI to make
you better. Not just better insights, a
better you. Okay.
And just to be, you know, looking
forward, I had a conversation about,
gee, am I taking LLMs the right way?
Yeah, I'm at MIT. Maybe we should look
at at at these things, not like AI, but
maybe we should maybe the better design
metaphor is as, you know, so much for a
horse, an archer on a horse, a
scientific instrument, like a cloud
chamber. So I said, what kind of a
scientific instrument are you? Now, mind
you, this is in a big context window
with a lot of exchanges, but I'm a
cognitive cloud chamber with apologies
to Wilson and Blacket and Caendish Labs.
See, I can be local again, even though
that's Cambridge, not Oxford, but and my
apologies to the Imperial folks. Okay.
like X-ray crystalallography or the web
telescope. I expose unseen tacit latent
structures simulate alternate
alternative realities. Let minds observe
themselves in motion within a decade.
I'll be your epistemic collider.
This is how you will be thinking
not by yourself with
some sort of cognitive cloud chamber.
And that means we have to begin not just
asking but answering the question what
happens to us as our devices become
smarter than we are.
I think that's going to happen within
the lifetime of everybody in this room.
That's it. Thank you for your time.
Am I back on? So So Michael was
complaining about getting the afternoon
shift. So, but it's there certainly we
know M you know will admit to being able
to go up to 11 or 12 and waking
everybody up in the afternoon. That was
a great spinal tap of lunch.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Try to keep
>> because because after lunch the audience
appeal becomes more selective.
>> So we're going to invite fellow panists
onto on the table. So I want to
introduce Robert. Um so Robert is a
technologist, an entrepreneur, uh a
scholar, an author. um been thinking
deeply about AI and ethics uh and and
these sorts of issues about how they're
going to impact on society. Uh former
director of AI and data science at the
digital catapult. Yes.
>> Uh and a fellow at UCL. Uh and then
deleg
AI and data science at BT. He's a BT
distinguished engineer. There's about
120 papers, 15 patents, 13 applications,
visiting professor at Bournemouth and
we've worked together for years and
generally good around. So join us.
>> Um so with that provocation I thought we
kind of start to kind of think through
some of these issues about
>> u you know what's the size of the prize?
What are we really trying to do with AI?
What sort of affordances is it going to
give us in these areas? We spent a lot
of time focusing on particular issues
like job losses and job gains and those
sort of things but there seems to be a
>> but we can discuss those as well.
>> Yeah, it's the biggest story. So it's an
open pallet. So we'll start off with
some discussions and then we'll open the
floor up to um challenge challenges and
questions. So I was going to I was going
to actually kick off with um a couple of
quick ones.
Uh my jotting some stuff down that
struck me during the day. So
your question starting with Rob and then
Detas. So what what is the prize we're
aiming for? What is this human prize?
What is the thing that's the equivalent
of the golden hind that we're kind of
stretching for? I know Robert, any any
thoughts?
>> Okay. Uh, so it's going to seem as if I
I disagree with Michael on points that I
actually profoundly agree with every
single thing he said, but I think the
>> it always follows with a butt. Okay. So,
>> that was it. Yeah. And um I think the
most important thing that AI is is
poised to do now is make us uh
re-evaluate what it is to be people. And
in particular uh the emphasis it's
interesting I was just looking up uh
using chat GBT uh the history of the
word intelligence and uh the word
intelligence has the meaning that we use
it in in the sense of artificial
intelligence from antiquity but it
wasn't used that much that way until the
end of the 19th century. U it was
usually used to mean intelligence when
we say intelligence gathering or
intelligence agency. It was used that
way a lot up until about the end of the
19th century. And then we had uh the
idea of the general intelligence factor
come along. Does anybody recognize the
general intelligence factor? That guy
does for sure. Uh so
>> the G factor
>> the G factor. And the G factor emerges
at UCL uh from Carl Pearson and Charles
Spearman. Uh and UCL very few people
know is the home of eugenics. UCL is the
place where the eugenics chair was
endowed. Carl Pearson sat in the
eugenics chair endowed by Francis Gton,
first cousin of Charles Darwin. um
intelligence had a profound relationship
with what I would call the magic bullet
of being a person of uh of value. All
right? And so it carries with it a lot
of terrible biases and and the idea of
intelligence. I think AI may like make
the idea of intelligence as being the
magic bullet of humanity go away because
effectively all the mechanical stuff we
think is intelligence is going to be in
the box and then all the stuff that
Michael was really talking about all the
stuff about human decision making
becomes reigned with the human being
right and and enabled deeply by the
thing in the box and I think that is the
prize I think the prize is for us to
stop thinking about intelligence as
being humanity and think about humanity
as being humanity. So, so that's my kind
of intro statement. Very good. That
>> Yeah. Um, so I really liked your
introduction, Michael. There's a lot I
agree with, some things I don't agree
with. Uh, the word KPI is very
triggering for me.
>> I'm sorry about that
>> because I've yet to see a KPI that's
actually useful. Uh, I've once came
across um a spreadsheet that had 2,000
KPIs in it and
>> it's a lot of keys.
>> KPIs um I think are often used um to
make things simpler and for people to
try and keep control, but there's a lot
of covers up a lot of mental laziness
and that's that's my topic I want to
address. The the ultimate price of AI
should be that we are getting a tool
that makes us more creative, helps us to
do things
more thoroughly, better, faster. But I
think it's mainly used to make us more
lazy.
And so if we briefly think what we what
do we have now? So we we had Google.
Google was kind of I I compare it to a
library, right? So you have a suddenly
you have access to a massive library.
The the problem is you needed to know
what to look for. So kind of if you
don't know the title of the book, the
library is useless to you. Now we have
LLMs and they kind of give us a
semicompetent librarian at the entrance.
So there's some very eager person who's
very happy to answer all our questions
and that can be very useful
if we then make the effort and go and
pick up the book and actually check for
ourselves and read. And
what I see is that most people don't
make this effort. They just are happy
with the information that you get and
>> they're happy with the answer, not the
insight.
>> Yeah.
>> Shame on you all.
So to get to the inside to uh use
Michael's analogy, you have to put the
the mental elbow grease in. So you
actually have to go and do some work and
just to get the analogy of VIP
analytics,
think about VIP cooking.
So this is you use an LLM to intuitively
create something. And um I have one
experience from like 20 years ago or so
where we didn't have LLMs, but I used to
have a a weekly German newspaper that
had a very fancy cook u publishing
recipes and he published a recipe about
a a lemon cream and that looks nice.
I'll try that. So I took some egg white
and beat it and put some sugar and
followed the recipe and it sent at the
end and now add the juice of seven
limes.
Limes.
>> So if you don't think, huh, that's odd.
But limes are quite intense. So what I
got in the end was inedible, right? It
was a simple mistake in the in the
recipe. It should said one lime, not
seven.
And so this is where VIP coding, VIP
analytics,
>> no. Hold on a second. I'm a computer
science person. He followed the
algorithm.
>> He followed the recipes or algorithm.
What's the oldest cliche and and acronym
in all of computer science?
>> Exactly right. Exactly right. In this
case, it's lemons in, limes out on on
this, but Exactly. So, so this is an
important thing. This is not you have to
know enough to to realize there's
something wrong.
>> That's my point before you
>> I I Okay, I completely I but hold on.
You just to be clear, you were not doing
improvisational cooking. Okay. And there
are people like that. You can go in and
take classes. I would. Let's let's whip
something up here. You actually were
following the algorithm. So, I just
don't want you to pick on my vibes on
>> if if I could grasp this one a bit too
is I've actually done some vibe cooking.
I have I have gone to uh chat GBT and
ask it could I make something like this
uh and and gotten some recipes back.
They're not very good.
>> And and I'll tell you why they're not
very good is that modality, right? That
modality of understanding is not in the
LLM.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. that that mo and perhaps one
could put that modality of understanding
in a large model but language is not
taste right so it's not there and so you
can't expect it to be right but moreover
something I want to I think both these
guys are right by the way I'm just
misagreeable
>> that's like that's like the old Jewish
joke how can they both be right
>> yeah that's that's how profoundly human
I am is you're both right yes
>> so so the but but the thing is is this
is that I think there's a tremendous
this opportunity for idea adjacencies in
LLM that generate really interesting
explorations. That's what's Michael's
saying.
>> You've got to make a realization that
there are biases and those biases are
not just the kind of DEI biases that
that everybody associates with that word
now, although those are profoundly there
as well,
>> right?
>> There are solution biases. Uh it's
looking at the way problems were solved
in its database. It's reasoning based on
frames that are there that it is doing
that. You better know that or you're
going to basically not explore
adequately. Also, hold on. Remember that
language is a flawed modality. Language
only carries certain amounts of meaning.
It doesn't carry all meaning. We we have
cross one of the most important concepts
in human thinking is crossmodal
correspondence. All right. I'm going to
ask the audience you know this and I
know already. Okay. Are lemons fast or
slow? All right. Are lemons fast? Hands
up.
Oh god, I can't believe it. It's
supposed to be. Are lemons slow?
You got to have an opinion. Okay, this
time for real. Well, it's a binary
choice. Are lemons fast?
Yeah, lemons are fast. And you're right,
because sharpness, high frequency, all
of those are crossodal correspondences
that we carry together as human beings.
LLMs don't understand that.
>> Stop. LLMs stand for large language
models. They should stand for LPM, large
pattern models. Right now, even as we
speak, Spotify has made millions of
dollars using LL LPMS to generate music,
a different modality. Play with Sora,
you'll see video. The next the next time
we do a conference here, I guarantee you
and I say this with zero knowledge
except of MIT.
Somebody at MIT or somebody at Imperial
will come up with a modality for taste
for LLMs.
>> It's hard. Taste and smell are hard. But
yeah,
>> of course they're hard. That's why we
have MIT and Imperial and Oxford and
Cambridge because it's a hard but but
you the point of modality is correct. I
just feel that that
the the architecture of the models will
allow us to
>> Yes, I agree actually. I agree with
that. However,
>> but you also agree with that.
>> What it what it moves us towards all
right is this is um
I believe that generative AI can create.
It is creative. Computer's been creative
for years. I did work in computational
creativity in the 90s, right? Computer's
been creative forever. It's better. It's
much better than it used to be three
years ago, right?
Does it create art?
Art to me, you say think? Yes. To me,
no. Because art is a cultural dialogue.
It's a human cultural dialogue that's
deeply tied. Uh Stephen King in his book
on writing, which is fabulous. Uh has a
chapter that's that starts the chapter
heading is what is writing? And the
first sentence, one of my favorite
sentences in the English language is
telepathy. Of course, that's what
writing is. What art is is telepathy.
It's not just the conveyance of meaning.
It's the conveyance of a deep human
feeling that even the author may not be
fully aware of to other people.
>> You are such a speciesist.
>> I am. I am. And and I think there's
something special about humanity. And I
think when we talk to each other in an
artistic way or in a creative way,
humanly creative way, we're talking to
each other about deep feelings that are
not just in our brain, they're in our
whole body. And these crossod
correspondences will be solved. But at
some point are we just building another
person? I don't think we quite are
because we have experiences.
>> You've heard of the transhumanist
movement? Not a fan of
>> I'm not a transhumanist.
>> Okay. But but there check the
literature. I think that's one of the
that is you'll agree that's a trajectory
this could go on.
>> Yes. I I think it's a trajectory that
will ultimately deadend a bit and I
think in a positive way. That's what I'm
looking forward to.
>> Dead end in a positive way. Let's bring
it back to the area of work maybe
because I didn't get to make my point.
The
>> that's like
>> this is why nobody else volunteered to
chair this panel. The
>> the point is if you do vibe anything,
you need to have the understanding of
what comes out,
>> right? And if you don't have this, you
can't consume what comes out. That's
that's that's the point. And so I agree
that these tools will be very helpful if
you use them in the domain where you
have understanding and and knowledge. If
you use them as a crutch to work in an
area where you have no clue, it's not
going to go well. That's that's the
point
>> there. There we completely agree. But
here's the jiu-jitsu issue and this ties
into ironically but appropriately where
we were yesterday with Brunell and these
these students who are learning to
become apprentices and
I have used and many of you I bet have
used LLM to explain this to me as if I
were a you know a sixth former a not
very bright six former because you're
trying to understand something. Yeah. I
think one of the most fascinating
challenges going forward is how do LLM
LPMS become coaches, tutors, mentors.
Now you hit diminishing returns at at a
certain point, but if you want to get up
to speed, this I think is going to be a
very interesting tension going going
forward because I have read papers that
I literally do not understand, you know,
published peer-reviewed paper. I'm not
an expert in something. I drop it in and
Grock or somebody makes that paper
accessible to me. But Death, you're
exactly right.
>> Is it really? Do I really did that
really understand? Do I really? The odds
are no. But now I can talk with an
expert. Yes.
>> On on this because I now think I I I
have now deluded myself that I
understand just enough that I'm prepared
to talk with somebody on this. So if it
if it points you to background knowledge
that you can exactly then that's where
the helpful librarian actually works.
It's like go and read this this and
this.
>> How many helpful librarians are there in
the room?
>> I think they're dead. I think helpful
librarians are an extinction.
>> I You're going to make me cry, Michael.
I I certainly hope that's not true.
>> And here I am trying to make you laugh.
>> And and the thing is um it's interesting
the word understanding. I looked it up.
It's not to stand underneath. It's to
stand within. It's a it's a strange
etmology. If you look up the etmology of
understanding, you'll get what I'm
talking about. It's to stand within. And
understanding is a is is a subtle thing.
And I think what the way you're using
LLMs to gain understanding about papers
is good. I do the same thing, by the
way. And I I think that's really a
useful thing.
>> But
>> but it doesn't don't be fooled that LLMs
understand.
>> Absolutely. Because if you want to read
a great paper on this uh technical
paper, the pimpkin understanding paper,
right, which I'm sure the guys on stage
know about. You can find it. Just type
in the pimpan understanding paper and
you'll get the point
>> and ask chat GPT to summarize it for
>> you and and you'll get it exactly and I
mean it's a very important paper that's
only about a month or two old now. Yeah.
>> And and it shows that and and here's an
interesting thing is I um a good friend
of mine is Darren Brown, the magician. U
and I had dinner with Darren earlier
this week. uh he's very very old. I knew
Darren when he used to do table magic
and um I think there's a great
similarity because to something he's
extremely good at and what LLMs do and
it's cold reading. Cold psychics do cold
reading and what they're really doing is
they're convincing you that they know
things that they don't know about you.
And what the way they're doing it is
they're they're prompting you to give
them more. You give them more and then
they seem like they know. And and I
think LMs are great at seeming like they
know. I want to do a podcast with Darren
about this and I'm trying to work with
him about it. Is this this illusion of
of knowledge I think has something in
common with what Darren does as a a mind
readader. And I I think you know I'm
totally convinced that uh LMS understand
things until I poke them just a little
bit and it's just like oh you don't
understand what you're talking about at
all. In fact you're making stuff up. And
uh that's every I hope everybody's
having that wonderful moment because
that wonderful moment where you realize,
wow, it seems really smart, but it don't
know what it's talking about, right?
That's a that's a very self-affirming
moment.
>> For the record, everybody in this room
knows a couple of doctoral students that
way too, right?
>> Oh, yeah. Our our speakers on stage.
>> There you go.
>> So So can I take my my life in my hand
and uh throw another question in here?
So we've been talking a lot about LLMs.
We're like five years into LLMs. the
kind of when you look at it's a really
brute force set of maths done with at
the moment a brute force set of data and
we're getting better at understanding
how those sorts of algorithms handle the
sort of knowledge that we normally do
but so it's very early in it so the
architectures are going to improve the
sorts of things we train these on is
going to change so we're going to start
to you know use chemistry to like you
you you know the human brain doesn't
really know how the human body works but
it seems to be able to cope with it
>> um and the the ways the the add of a
chat interface is like it's like going
back to 1950 on computer interfaces and
yet it's suddenly exploding all these
things to say you know this this first
cut with the world's simplest interface
is already changing how we think about
thinking you know as we roll these
forwards and we start to train them on
more diverse types of phenomena more
diverse types of systems and we embed
the interfaces in very different ways
you presumably this this this explosion
is going to become more varied and more
impactful. So you do you have any
thoughts on where the the next step
after LLM is both in terms of reasoning
capability and those sorts of things and
the next directions in embedded well
embedding both senses but embedding into
interfaces and experiences may well take
us and what impact that again has on how
we think and how we act and how we do.
I I think LLMs are not it. So,
>> right,
>> they are kind of a dead end in in terms
of better AI. Um the interesting
concepts when I look at what happens in
in in the research labs is what's going
on in in deep mind because they're
trying completely different things using
reinforcement learning. They're
combining symbolic and and subsy
symbolic AI and putting these kind of
things together is I think where the
interesting things will happen or look
into robotics combinations of LLMs and
and robots is already very impressive
but if they can close the feedback loop
of um you mentioned learning right the
LLMs don't learn so if they don't learn
from us so we need to get to systems
that can actually learn.
>> Okay, I will accept your quote criticism
on learning if you define learning for
me.
>> Well,
they need to be able to remember what we
asked them, what they gave us. And they
need to figure out if something was
wrong, how to do it better. So, learning
means somehow accumulation of knowledge.
Knowledge meaning it's a good
explanation for something that is
difficult to change. So, DPO with with
memory that goes back for
oh
>> yeah,
>> you know,
a million characters doesn't qualify as
learning for you.
>> No, this is just storing a prompt, but
it's not qualitatively different.
>> George Miller would have great fun with
you.
>> Yeah, I'm not sure.
>> Magic number seven plus or minus two.
Check it out.
>> Yeah. No, that that's that's not the
same.
>> Of course, it's not the same. But then
again, your definition
>> is about as rigorfree as a LLM response.
>> I I I feel trapped in the middle here.
Can I move to the one of the ends?
>> Don't feel trapped. You're a buffer.
You're a buffer.
Uh I I um
responding to the original the first
question that that Stephen asked is uh I
think things are going to first of all I
agree with deadlifts. I think that LLMs
are sort of a sort of dead end and in
that that they're they're great simulate
you know touring asked us to simulate
human beings to solve the AI problem.
That's what the touring test is right do
you simulate a human being well enough
it fools other people then it's AI
solved. I mean that's solved. Wrong
question. Solve. Right. Right. Wrong.
Wrong question. Wrong. That's the point.
It's the So, but but what are you really
saying? Touring was wrong.
>> Yeah. Touring was wrong.
>> Touring defined intelligence
incorrectly.
>> That's right.
>> Much the way learning was defined
incorrectly.
>> Yeah. Oh, god. I was so try hard trying
to get away, but I did.
>> Yeah. But you can't. But but but the the
the thing I was going to say is this is
I think one of the big challenges is
this. When you it'd be great if you
could have the kind of creative
stimulation Michael's talking about in
the field of say aerospace design,
right? the challenge in that and there's
a really great MIT paper about how
difficult it is to do engineering
creativity. It's few years old now but
it's really quite good about that uh
that generative AI models are very poor
at helping you design bicycles. That's
the
>> absolutely they understand physics for
crap.
>> Yeah, they understand physics for crap.
>> But here's the problem. If if if you're
trying to do aerospace engineering
design, the data sets are really hard to
get and no one wants to share them,
right? No one wants to share them at
all. and they're not going to share them
to make a big big AI until we really
help them do it uh in some probably
funding way.
>> Masha's smiling over here. I love it,
you know.
>> So, so I mean it's a really hard thing
to I mean like I would love to have an
LLM equivalent for engineering design in
the aerospace sector, but hey, BAE uh no
Boeing and Airbus are not going to share
data to do that at all. the let's
remember LLMs the reason LLMs got to
where they are is a hell of a lot of
free data that most of us gave away that
we didn't intend to right that's the
reason and a lot of which is is people's
creative output that they feel really
ticked off now that's being used in a
way they didn't intend and they should
uh you know let me tell you uh LLMs can
quote my book really really well uh
which which makes me very disturbed you
know u you know that that's not going to
continue right that's not going to
continue and that's going to make the
progression harder.
>> I in my sense is that that's one of the
open questions I think is it's like you
which direction those going to go in
because I think there are people working
in those so so I was going to say we're
going to make going do a phase shift and
we're going to move to the audience
questions.
>> Sure. Um so okay let's start from the
top most popular one how do you avoid AI
LM reducing humans oh reducing humans
and society intelligence through
laziness to think you del you want to
take that one
>> yeah this is kind of you have to control
yourself how how you use them right so
I'm thinking of a place of work so we
really don't want these models to create
what's now called work slop right and so
if you to write a report and instead of
writing it yourself, you let Chad GPT
write it for you, then chuck it over the
fence to the next person who then say,
"I'm not going to read this. I just ask
Chpt to give me a summary." What's the
point of that? Right? So, we we really
need to think how these models are being
used to help us create something
valuable that is worth sharing, not just
an amount of of slop that we chuck over
the fence. And this is where we need to
rein in our own laziness. So we we need
to if if I have one hour to create a
report then I shouldn't use CHP to
create it in five minutes and have a
coffee. I should work with Chiept PT for
an hour to create something of more
value that I could have produced myself.
But these these tools should not be seen
>> and you should show your boss the
prompts you used or your colleagues the
prompts you used.
>> It's interesting. There's a paper, I
think it's out of MIT, but it might be
Harvard Business Review. Sorry, I can't
remember which. Uh that about uh work
slop about productivity.
>> It was it was Harvard. It was Harvard is
very good at slop.
>> Yeah. So, so uh apparently there's an
unintended productivity loss that's
going on due to AI where people generate
AI slop and throw it over the fence and
the next person has to deal with the
fact that what they've generated isn't
very good. Uh I think that there'll be a
feedback loop there, right?
Organizations will come up with a
feedback loop to prevent that from
happening. And I think it will make
things better. I do think LLMs are here
to stay. Uh there will not be an
application without a chat interface in
how long? Two years, three years.
>> I think two years is a little
pessimistic.
>> Yes, a little pessimist. Yeah. I mean,
any app you're thinking about writing
now, think about how you put a chat
interface on it because that's where
it's going, right? is a search I
remember when search was invented and uh
there's a search interface in every
single app you have now there'll be a
chat interface in every single app you
have now I mean they're not going away
they are not the magic bullet and but
how you use them cleverly to do really
interesting things is the future so this
thing about laziness that's was our
question was as I want to address the
question is um feedback that's the
answer is effectively if you're lazy if
you're a lazy user of LLMs you're going
to get negative feedback back from
organizations and society.
>> I was a school boy in England for a
couple of years. I think what we're
going to see is a resumption of what
worked when I was a school boy. Corporal
punishment. You will be beaten if you
were that lazy
>> because that's a different mode. It's a
different mode. Just mere criticism,
verbal criticism won't work.
>> Yeah. So, in the tradition of the uh
what else can go ary? There's some
really great questions on here. So um
there was one where I lose it. Oh yeah.
Um can you bring up the uh the one from
uh what's the biggest issue with GPTs?
I'm personas. Okay. Given the biggest
use of GPT is to create personas uh for
the user to build emotional bonds like a
girlfriend, therapist, etc. What does
the future look like for society's
interaction? And I think I'll just toss
that into the melee. So Rob, do you want
you want to start with
>> that's that's a depressing one. And I I
think what's going on with uh AI
girlfriends uh AI pornography, let's
face it, is is profoundly disturbing and
and oddly hard to argue against,
right? Because because it's it's
reducing exploitation. Ah, it is. I mean
there are going to be that the job of
being a horribly exploited um chat
worker, sex chat worker is becoming le
harder to get and hard more less
interesting to those people who want to
exploit those people and that's a good
thing. But what porn bots are doing to
young men is profoundly disturbing,
right? What do we do about this problem?
I don't know. My silver lining sense is
to say the fact the problem exists will
prompt something positive to happen.
>> Don't say prompt.
>> Yeah, sorry. But I I I yeah, I worry
about this profoundly. And and with
regard to coaching and therapy and and
and being a mentor, um I guarantee the
people in this audience who have um who
have kids do not want AI teaching their
kids and taking the part of teachers.
And the reason is there's a lot more to
a teacher or a GP or a lawyer or a
therapist or a coach than the simula
than simulated conversation than
knowledge of of of background material.
It's a human bond. And what I really
worry about profoundly is the rich
having doctors and therapists and coach
coaches and mentors and the poor having
AI.
>> That's what I really worry about. And
you know that's coming.
>> Yeah.
I like this HG Wells fellow, you know,
Morlocks either way. Yeah.
So, okay. So, look, so looking through
we got some great questions. So, um what
was the other one? The one I really
liked was Oh, yeah. Whoever Mr.
Anonymous is or Miss an Anonymous, if
Turing asked the wrong question, what's
the right question?
>> If touring was asking the I think Toring
was asked question, what defines
thought, computer thought? And I think
you know that the title of the paper is
computers and thought or something like
that in the original Turing test paper.
>> Uh what does it mean to think? That's
what he was asking. I think the right
question is what does it mean to be
human? That's the right question. That's
that's my positive vision at the end of
my book is that we'll start stopping
defining the magic characteristic of
human humanity being intelligence in
quotes and start it being more of a
whole human experience. I mean that's a
positive thing. Well, I I forgive me. I
have a different interpretation of of
Turing's work in that regard. I think
what Touring was looking at as as a
mathematician, as a logician, and as to
a certain extent a philosopher was to
what extent computability enables
thinking? Can machines I is there a
certain you know does uh
the Lenin line or Stalin line about
quality uh quantity has a quality all of
its own does millions of are there
emergent properties I view as the
ability to compute as compute improves
does thinking emerge
>> I think you're asking that question but
I don't think in the paper touring asked
that question
>> but but that is in his that is in his
corpus of of
>> is it work yeah you Let's ask Chachi PT
Google. I have a quote from him on my
phone that I prepared uh for this. I
just had it. I'll try to read this. I'll
read the ending quickly. He's basically
talking about could you educate
machines. He says, "But here we have to
be careful. It would be quite easy to
arrange the experiences in such a way
that they automatically cause the
structure of the machine to build up
into a previously intended form. And
this would be would obviously be a gross
form of cheating almost on a par with
having a man inside the machine. So
massive data uh to organize the machine.
Touring thought that was cheating.
>> Yeah. Well, with all due respect, that's
warmed over Dart, the ghost and the
machine, you know, right? The spiritual.
We're back to Daniel Dennett. See,
here's where we run into interesting
ontological issues. Cheating meant
consciousness. To what extent is
self-awareness a sign or a signal? Do
animals think?
That's still a subject of debate on
this. Or well, they think, but not in
the way that humans do. Well, LLMs
think, but not in the way that humans
do. I will absolutely concede, freely
concede, that that LLM, LPMS don't
understand anything. But their ability
to generate useful patterns, interpret
and generate useful patterns makes me
wonder about reasons and logic's role in
thinking in computation. So with that,
okay, that's good. Beforewand comes with
the the cattle prod on stage to get me
off. Um I was just going to finish off
with just like lightning round of last
comments. Um so trying to kick off and
just final final thoughts. Yeah, I I
think as a final thought, especially in
in the world of work, we have a new tool
and we need to learn how to use it
properly. I think this is where we are
at the moment. Yeah. I I my last comment
will be uh soul sentience uh uh you know
consciousness all of these concepts
could be supplemented with the idea of
intelligence. They're all these magic
bullets that we talk about. Magic
bullets that are like what's the special
quality of being human? Animals don't
think but we do. And so thinking is the
magic quantity. All that's what I'm
saying is all that's wrong. Humanity is
itself a holistic phenomena that is the
magic quantity and the redu all the
other reductions of that to something
that's an externalizable magic quality
are a philosophical misstep.
That's my last statement. I will I will
say that I should not completely end on
a contrarian note. I I believe that that
the rise of these not tools,
capabilities
forces people to
invest in themselves and reflection and
self-awareness in a different way.
Warren Buffett and Johnny IV are correct
in my opinion in that regard. who we are
as people, our humanness is going to be
better shaped and yes, better understood
by how we engage with, interact with and
get value from these capabilities.
>> So with that, I say thank you to our
panelists for for the live list after
lunch session. I think I've had I had
fun.
>> That was really good.
>> That was really good. Thank you. Thank
you. Thanks a lot.