welcome to the AI generation from
research to impactful use cases panel
and we will address today with you
technical advancement uh the challenge
of the mod of the curent Innovation and
any question you will have so I will be
the moderator my name is OD Oliva very
French apology for my accent I've been
at 20 years and I have two lives two
their lives first I'm a senior research
scientist I have a lab uh that actually
focus on human machine intelligence for
the past 20 years and this is really
very sci-fi thinking for me like right
now we are thinking about how can an AI
with your minds but then the day today
my other life is actually to take care
for the schatzman College of computing
of how the research done at MIT can
Bridge with our industry and with all of
you and in that uh role um I lead uh in
the leadership of the college so I'm the
director of the Strategic industry
engagement I'm also the MIT director of
the MIT IBM Watson AI lab we are going
to talk today about it and I call it the
MIT AI Hardware program so uh when I was
invited to put this panel together I was
really thrilled because we are going to
have three
formidable panelists today you're going
to know how to say in French some of the
English words um and uh really you they
all have life that I would like to have
so I would like to welcome intra deep
gosh who is the Chief Executive Officer
of fujit research of America thank you
please come join
us
oops um I would like to David to David
welcome David Cox vice president of AI
model at IBM research and the IBM
director of the MIT IBM Watson AI lab Hi
how are you since
yesterday dear
colleagues and um I would like to
welcome Ramin asani who co-founder and
CEO of liquid AI a startup that you
founded with the famous Cel director
Daniel arus and you're also a machine
learning research affiliate at Cel very
very happy to have the three
so we are going to have about 45 minutes
uh together and I took from the previous
talk that the audience um will walk away
ready to ask the right questions so we
have the right panelist for this and uh
so I'll start with uh so few question
for you and your introduction but what I
was thinking is that I think I see here
oh no why not I think myself then I'm
going to see your question and maybe we
can make this more lively and have you
asking question during those 45 minutes
but first let's know about our three um
panelist here so a would you tell about
yourself and what you're doing thank you
OD uh so um uh I am Indra Kos my people
called me IG and I had Fujitsu research
of America so Fujitsu as you know is a
Global Information Technology Company
and U they have a big research Wing So
currently we are 1,000 strong and uh
they are as like the company spread all
over the world and uh so we have lab in
Japan of course and then we spread to
North America and then Europe and the
latest one is in the hotbed um of
Bangalore so so we uh do research in all
the cting age it techn techologies I am
in charge of U the research activities
in North America which comprises Canada
and United
States and uh AI is a huge part of our
uh work right now in fact I would say
the total amount of budget that we have
in research more than 50% is now devoted
to research in Ai and uh out of that uh
generative AI of course is the new kid
in the block I've been there for two
years and we are doing active research
in all of that and uh Fujitsu being a um
businessto business company mainly uh
our generative AI research focus is also
on Enterprise AI so we are going to
discuss a little bit more about that we
have some uh tools uh some resources uh
some new research areas that we target
towards uh kind of helping Enterprises
uh as we go through the panel thank you
David great so I'm sorry David Cox I'm
the BP for AI models at IBM research I
actually wear two hats at IBM research
one is I lead IBM's own internal llm
development efforts so we're training a
model series called granite and we're
actually going to have a big release uh
next month so stay tuned for that uh and
then I also am the MIT director 's my
counterpart where we have a research lab
where IBM is investing close to a
quarter billion dollars over 10 years to
uh co-develop sort of Leading Edge Ai
and I've been doing that for about 6
years and as a confession I'm a
recovering academic uh so before I
joined IBM I was a professor at Harvard
for about 10 years and my mom's very
proud of me that I finally got out of
school um I don't have the heart to tell
her that my office is still on the MIT
campus only about 20t across the street
from where I did my PhD here but uh it's
a it's a really exciting environment and
it's a really exciting time to be in AI
IBM does a lot of things in the AI space
we have a Consulting arm that helps
develop Solutions we have software we're
infusing generative AI into all of our
products and have been for quite some
time and uh so we we really Spread
spread the gamma and including also
Hardware uh and everything from
traditional Computing like mainframes to
AI accelerators and also Quantum
Computing yeah so hi everyone Ramen
Hassani i u I'm the CEO and co-founder
of liquid AI I started this company
about a year and a half ago spawn out
out of MIT the company
is building found new type of foundation
models building on a technology that I
invented uh during my PhD um also at MIT
and um so the technology itself was
basic it's called liquid neural networks
it's like a alternative type of neural
networks we started looking into brain
of little animals and then we
identified what are the core comp
computational blocks that are missing
from today's AI systems such as the
Transformers that powers today's gen
systems and then uh we thought that okay
so let's build these kind of neuronal
circuits you know like this new type of
AI systems and then see how powerful
they are and then study their properties
so we started building these um liquid
neural networks liquid for flexibility
okay the the whole system is going to be
a very different system than a
Transformer and a GPT system and it has
a lot of attractive properties so
property number one is that it is going
to give you the best and goes beyond a a
little bit beyond learning theory so
what that means that means like you're
going to get a very good out of
distribution kind of um performance what
does that mean that means if you let's
say you're driving a car and you have an
AI actually drive that car autonomously
you if you deploy these kind of system
on top of this you know car let's say
all of a sudden there is raining like
happen like you know it starts raining
the system would be a lot more robust to
these kind of properties so liquid is
for flexibility and robustness okay and
then uh we started with the field of
Robotics we then applied this technology
into let's say modeling Financial
systems and modeling uh uh sequential
data like in the space of uh Healthcare
and user behavior and a lot of other
space and and we soon realize that we
have like a general purpose computer
that gives us a very high quality and
robustness kind of properties and then
this was quality number one quality
number two is that these systems are
brain inspired so they are very
efficient So based on the mathematics
that we designed these kind of systems
we built very efficient algorithms that
you do not need to spend that much power
for example today at the company we
built uh Foundation models language
Foundation models this same quality as
what meta actually released like let's
say llama 370 billion parameter with the
same kind of capacity llama spent 48,000
gpus to develop that kind of quality of
models we spent 300 gpus to develop them
all so the massive reduction in the cost
of development of gen if you change kind
of the substrate uh with this new type
of technology and then the third and the
last thing that I wanted to mention is
we are coming back coming from a control
theory background and and and dynamical
systems and Robotics you know my I I my
supervisor P Supervisor was Daniela ruse
who is the director of Cel and um you
know like she's a roboticist and and you
know like we have been thinking about
real world and implications of AI in
real world when you want to deploy a
system an intelligent system in real
world you need to make sure that you
have a lot of control on this system so
it doesn't go Rogue so you need to have
reliability you need to ensure that
system is safe so that is basically
another angle that we have we have a lot
of control into the design and
deployment of gen systems which is kind
of sometimes you can call it
explainability interpretability and
aspects of like having visibility into
how networks are coming into decision
making so with this three kind of value
proposition we started a company and we
are a headquartered actually in the IBM
building here right next to uh on the
other side of the street uh the pi
building actually and um we are 40
people Massachusetts base we have um
onethird of the team is also in palato
but um happy to take whoa whoa thank you
for uh that um very deep uh description
so actually on this topic let's go to
the technical advancement and challenges
that you saw ra me you you you talk
about a few but for IG and David um so
in your in your business uh what are the
challenges you see in
training deploying at scale and
maintaining uh those large model David
yeah there's a lot of challenges uh in
every part of this ecosystem and then
there's another layer of challenges if
you're an Enterprise if you're a big
business on how you do that responsibly
and then if you're in a regulated
industry there's yet another sort of
layer of challenges so um you know the
today's uh technology requires enormous
compute to train so we we typically have
thousands of gpus burning for months at
a time that's just standard practice
with the technology we have today uh
that's obviously a huge energy problem
it's also a huge supply chain problem
Nvidia you probably have seen nvidia's
market cap growing and there's a
worldwide shortage and you know like my
CEO has to talk to somebody to Jensen to
like strike a deal and good things so
it's a it's it's an interesting moment
we're in where it's there's you know any
any technology we can get that could
reduce that would be very very welcome
the amounts of data we're using are
astonishing um you know a year ago we
trained some of the models we use
internally on one and a qu trillion
tokens so tokens like a word or a word
part uh that felt like a lot at the time
and when I was a PhD student working
with little neural networks unimaginable
quantity now we routinely are in the
tens of you know well over 10 trillion
tokens of data that means we're
basically slurping up the entire
internet and all kinds of data coming in
and that's evolving and that introduces
all kinds of interesting governance
risks right because in many cases this
is more data than a human could read in
a lifetime in fact if you read the data
in a typical llm training set it would
take you 350,000 years to read it all
just sitting there if you just sat down
and tried to read it so we can't read it
um so in some cases there are companies
that have sort of played fast and loose
and just said we're just going to take
it and let the lawyers figure it out
later that doesn't serve our customers
so well so we put quite a bit of effort
into making sure that we understand
exactly what's in our models we're using
AI based filtering to remove things that
could be objectionable this is an
ongoing process and we have we built a
platform that we can have traceability
back from from any model we produced to
back to every last individual word that
went into that model or image in the
case of our multimodal models um so
that's a big Challenge and then when you
deploy these things um you know
everybody's excited about the
capabilities of the things and it's
amazing um I I didn't think I don't know
about you I I didn't think we would be
here I've been doing like AI research in
one form or another my entire adult life
and I didn't think we'd be where we are
this fast so it's amazing and everyone
sees the potential but one of the
defining characteristics of large
language models is that they're
unreliable uh we're in this new
Computing regime where it's really hard
to be really
certain that the system will do what you
need it to do and that it won't go off
the rails hallucinate which is you know
produce a response that it sort of
generated out of thin air it's not the
right answer or produce bias or negative
responses this is a new attack factor
for adversarial players so a malicious
actor can uh do all kinds of different
attacks against an LM um there was a
comment in the previous talk don't put
private data in something that has a
public interface that's because
increasingly researchers are figuring
out how to uh sort of pull out the data
like trick the model into giving up
something it shouldn't give up um
there's lots of ways to break the
alignment do this things called prompt
injection attacks so that's an
interesting evolving space that
companies are having to to to to deal
with and it just amplifies all the
issues that you had with AI before if
you're going to take a model and
customize it if you're going to take a
model and have it do a retrieval
augmented generation or rag sort of
pattern pulling in data you have to
validate it somehow so a lot of this
landscape is evolving uh this is the
place where we play at I BM all the time
so we have governance products that will
help you manage those things and and we
think that's going to be really
important particularly in in regulated
Industries and I think it's safe to say
there are places where we are seeing AI
deployed at scale we deploy it already
in many of our products but many
companies and I'm sure many of you in
the audience are kind of at that uh MVP
po kind of stage like like a little
tiger team went and said hey look what
we did we built prototype but then and
uh there was a mentioned of banks as
well banks have lots of these and then
you get to their model Risk Management
Department which in a big bank is like a
reporting directly down from the CEO
independent arm that has to like say is
this okay or not and I think we're in a
phase now where everyone's trying to
figure out how do we deal with that how
do we be confident how do we build the
right guard rails and and and models
around that and that on top of the fact
that the technology is changing all the
time you know right now it's
Transformers you have an alternative
architecture we have a couple
alternative architectures that we're
working on as well and like nobody is
quite sure what's going to happen but
the world is changing so fast and
companies are trying to build you know
do something sensible with this power
and everyone feels like they're being
left behind so it's it's a really
interesting environment I've never seen
either in Academia or in industry I've
never seen anything move this fast uh so
it's exciting and hopefully you're all
excited by it um but also really
uncertain and and interesting and
exciting time yeah the pace keep all of
us
Young no it's making me older don't um I
I want to add basically the other things
so he already uh mentioned David about
all these challenges of putting it u in
the private setting we had an additional
challenge about language so all these LM
models initially were all mostly trained
on English and so when you put that
model in a context of Japanese language
the accuracy was really poor so
initially Fujitsu did a lot of work
fine-tuning these models on Japanese
language so that the accuracy becomes
much better so that was one of the
challenges that had to be addressed and
on top of that whenever you are talking
about Enterprise the first thing they
say was okay we want everything on
premise okay we don't want to send send
our data outside in the cloud we are a
sensitive company we don't want and so
you if you have to train an llm on
premise I mean with the current
technology the amount of investment that
you have to do to create such a huge
system that you just tell that to the
customer and then immediately they
switch off we cannot justify so then we
had to create some other kind of
solutions so one as David mentioned was
rag so rag is retrieval augmented
generation where you create some kind of
a knowledge graph of the private data
which is on premise and then you use
your uh llm model which has been
pre-trained but it takes input from
those kind of models which are on
premise to enhance your answers in the
private setting so in that way you kind
of um have the best of both words but
it's not without issues and there are
some things that some research is still
going on to make this uh rag more
intelligent and to give more accuracy to
the kind of uh uh answers that you're
are getting yeah so so I would say these
two main challenges how do you keep it
within the uh organization uh not
disclosing the data to train the model
outside and then of course uh the
language barrier has to be
crossed thank you so I have a question
for Ramin and then we will start looking
at the question from the audience so uh
Ramin in your explanation of liquid uh
Ai and uh the innovation of the startup
tell us about energy consumption because
I think we're all thinking about the
planet so yeah
absolutely well as David also noted like
these systems like they require like
different aspects of scale you have to
have in mind like okay so everything
started by the fact that you know you
make them
larger they get better and better you
know by better and better I mean they
become more reliable and they give you
like more reliable answers you know and
when I say bigger there are three
dimensions of scale you know that we
talking about one is the size of these
models the other thing is that how much
information they can process at the same
time or in other word working memory of
the device so that would be a context
length and the third angle is the data
that they consume the amount of time
that you you you the number of tokens
basically you you spend to actually
train these Tok train these systems so
across this tree when you start like
scaling the models you get better and
better and more reliable systems so that
directly Demands a lot of um you know
energy to consume and as I mentioned
like uh meta just spend like you know
two clusters of 24,000 gpus each like
for development of the Llama series you
know and that's a huge kind of system
that we we seeing and it's and the trend
is actually not slowing down you know
about three months ago like Kevin Scott
of Microsoft actually went on stage and
showed like a scaling graph as long as
you're scaling across the three
dimensions that I mentioned it is there
is going to be power consumption of this
system and then the underlying system so
far the Transformer architecture or
attention is actually something that is
working you know it's it's it's elegant
it's simple you can scale it so there is
very hard to beat the performance of
this elegant architecture that's why
just the the matter that people are
scaling it it just seems to be solving
problems like Beyond complexity Theory
even you know now people were saying
like Transformers from the mathematical
formula it's a simple mathematical
formula that that can do like it's
literally matrix multiplication you know
like when when we think about it and we
scaling that you know and then so
there's there there's not going to be
like stopping of the consumption of
energy there this trend is going to be
continuing the thing is we just have to
get a little bit more creative and the
fact that a lot of people worked on
alternative models you know from the
base like changing like the landscape
like into Transformers or something
called computationally or quadratic in
computational costs that means the more
information they process it is becoming
like quadratically harder to process
those information so you can build
systems that H that have linear time
complexity these are like even one of
the questions there is like State space
models you know or ssms right so you're
talking about this structural State
space models that are out there these
are linear kind of models you're
reducing the complexity of attention
that's why like you can consume a lot
less especially as you're processing as
you're scaling the models you are
consuming a lot less kind of energy
compared to the Transformer architecture
the drawback of this alternative
architecture is that in computer science
there is no free launch right so that's
that means if you're making something
simpler or making a linear kind of
system you're losing on expressivity so
these alternative architectures they had
a hard time to catch up with with the
performance of a transformer
architecture so you might actually get
into like more more energy efficient
Solutions as a result of like
architecture research better kind of uh
arrangement of the hardware status and
everything so just to control the
technology itself but what I want to
tell you is that you're losing also
accuracy so there has to be a balance or
if you want to enable the next
generation of kind of AI systems or the
foundation models you really have to
think about how can I maximize also for
expressivity because quality at the end
of the day is going to be the winner you
know and these AI systems are getting
better and better again as I said as you
scale them you need to get into the
point where you know efficiency and
quality can can come together that was
the idea where we wanted to combine kind
of um ideas from dynamical systems like
core 200 years of kind of mathematics
that enables dynamical systems to bring
in into learning theory to design
something new and this became kind of
liquid foundation models so on the on
our kind of technology and our impact on
on these things so I can tell you that
the systems are in the order of 10 to 20
times more energy efficient compared to
uh uh Transformers on the deployment
side on the development side and on the
deployment side they could be between 10
to 100 times faster and cheaper kind of
to to to to use them but on the and on
the quality they're going to surpass the
quality of Transformers that's the
difference between liquid and and ssms
or any other alternative or because it's
not just also an architecture it is the
the the the entire kind of package that
you're using in order to really like
build a gen system you know there is the
matter of what kind of algorithm do you
use for training what kind of
posttraining kind of strategies do you
have what kind of how much how do you
Cate data how do you uh think about
causality you know like in in your data
so there's a lot of things that you can
do to really improve the quality of the
final system that that comes out and at
would we do that so in a week from now
we're going to announce the first series
of we have we have never actually
published a liquid foundation model or
lfm which is going to be a replacement
for gpts basically and these are for the
first time in a week from now you're
going to read about it we're going to
release to the board there is going to
be API access through perplexity if how
many of you guys knows what is
perplexity so perplexity is like another
AI startup that is working on a search
algorithm so it's going to be on the
perplexity and Lambda and and and we are
also working with a couple of others to
really get confirmed and we're going to
give access to everyone to test this new
generation of models that even on a
smaller kind of size they maximize kind
of their capacity of learning it's
higher quality and at the same time
being that efficient so reducing the
energy cost sorry I went oh no no this
is this is fascinating uh Innovation is
really uh everywhere okay we'll have you
uh coming back um after a few weeks
weeks um so all of you actually we have
excellent question here on the board
let's go with the first one and it's
related to uh what you were saying Rin
but let's go with David and um IG so
what's the best way to measure the
impact uh of model uh in production on
the business yeah um
so one thing that I think we sometimes
have a tendency to do when there's an
exciting shiny new object is we
we believe that it requires radically
new rules and it it for for measuring it
for thinking about how to use it and
that can certainly be true and there's
elements of that but the other thing to
remember is you're still running a
business and you know what is your
return on investment what is your
investment what is your return on that
investment um on the on the power
question actually just get back to that
for a moment uh I don't know if you know
this but like even a decade ago we were
projecting that our year-over-year
energy cost energy usage for computing
was increasing at a rate such that by
the year 2040 we would exceed the power
budget of the planet Earth we're still
on track we're going to run out of power
there won't be enough solar radiation
from the sun we can collect nuclear
power plants we can commission stuff we
can dig up out of the earth and burn to
keep up with this habit now that's bad
um we don't want to do that uh and of
course we won't you know we won't we
we'll just top out at some point um but
but this is actually a nice case where
the negative externalities with respect
to client are actually climate are
actually perfectly aligned with the
negative of the internal uh issue of
cost so if you're if you're specking
data centers I don't know if any of you
are uh specking out data centers these
days it's all about megawatts like where
can I get this many megawatts of power
everything is about power power
basically is like the clearest um
surrogate for cost and many of these
systems are actually people are doing
poc's and they go straight to the
biggest model
and then somebody eventually like this
you know they and then they come to me
and say oh my God like how are we
supposed to afford this is is this
actually even cheaper than the human
labor that we're replacing with this so
I think there's um you know there is an
element of understanding the costs of
the system are you targeting a high
enough value application and and do you
have the metrics in place to measure the
cost takeout you're doing or the new OP
Topline opportunity that you're bringing
um and this is really tricky also for um
any of you are some of you making
decisions about what to do with
generative AI in your businesses right
now none of you are doing that okay or
you're shy um you know the benchmarks
that are available in the community are
largely driven by academics and they're
also driven by a small number of players
so so like you like how do you choose
what model do I need a 70 billion
parameter model do I need an 8 billion
parameter model do I need a 405 billion
parameter model for this task um and
then you look at these benchmarks and
you're like oh well this MML thing that
seems to be high and people usually use
that as a circuit for for knowledge like
how much knowledge does the model have
but if you want to score well on mlu
that means you need to be able to do
college level physics and does your HR
chatbot really need to know Advanced
physics like is that important or not um
you know Mt bench this is a multi-turn
chat like how good is it at chatting if
your model cannot talk like a pirate you
will not get a good empty bench score
role playing is one of the major
categories of empty bench I would argue
that it's undesirable for your chatbot
for HR issues to to speak like a pirate
so the benchmarks we have right now are
woefully misaligned with the needs of of
businesses um we and others are working
to try and help correct that so like you
give you something that you can latch on
to but the number one thing I would say
as you're doing model selection as
you're scoping out your applications is
to actually first and foremost get good
at evaluation like Define define the
business case Define what the
opportunity is like if you if you
succeeded beyond your expectations how
much cost would this take out what
Topline opportunity was give and then
what's the cost and then how would you
measure it to know that you're getting
there along the way and one of the
things we find that many of our clients
of of IBM and then even our own internal
teams struggle with is even just
understanding like having some data that
says like am I doing the thing I want to
do um the other thing you have to in
that evaluation piece which I think is
super important everyone needs to like
develop a competency in evaluation um
and or you know work with ecosystem
players to provide you products to give
you that capability is also
understanding what's the risk of Black
Swan errors um because in some
Industries you know if if it's a fun you
know it's helping you know your kid
write their college essay you know if it
makes a mistake no big deal you're going
to edit it if this is giving advice on
policies for your company um the courts
are already starting to rule that you're
liable for that so there was an airline
in Canada that had a chatbot and
somebody asked it what's your refund
policy and the model just blissfully
hallucinated a policy which is not the
correct policy and the Court ruled that
no your representative you can't just
say the AI did it that's like the dog
ate my my homework but for business and
for AI so you need to understand all of
those things so I think um you know you
really just need to be very strategic
and holistic about understanding
understanding how to measure and that's
all going to decide you know in the near
term how this technology is going to is
going to impact your business you really
think about that you know it's it's
really simple it's like how much how
much money you're going to get how much
money is it going to cost do the
balancing yeah and go from I just wanted
to add like a 30 second kind of um idea
about these benchmarks as well like how
how do you Benchmark these things it's
also important like to understand these
benchmarks are designed for general
intelligence we're talking about future
versus today so if you say value of gen
today it's not going to be measured by
those by those benchmarks that you're
actually putting together we talking
about general intelligence right like
with the test of mmu for example it's
like for for for systems that want to be
generally good you know solving the the
homeworks of your kids and uh giving you
Financial advice at the same time so
this is basically the area where uh you
know like like the big big companies
like openai and and Tropics of the world
are actually moving towards you know so
that's why like The Benchmark design and
everything is kind of driven by that
right so but today you want to have like
more special like if you want to use
today as action systems like system that
you want to put them in production not
system for productivity for productivity
you can use any of these chat Bots but
if you want to have an action system A
system that takes action in especially
safety critical applications you want to
have like dedicated kind of benchmarks
internal kind of evaluations set so that
you can make them reliable and you would
want to have like safety mechanisms in
place so short there's a short-term
long-term play in gen you need to always
be aware of yeah um I actually looking
at the question and related to uh the
one we just had um do you have example
of use cases in your
organization where the model or AI had
an impact yes yes of course so basically
uh in Enterprise AI we have been
targeting various use cases that
enterprises want one of them is uh uh
understanding uh internal knowledge so
so you have uh these millions of pages
of uh manuals and uh kind of written
statements uh maybe legal documents and
many people who were working with them
might have left the company and then
somebody want a query answer that you
know can uh can I do this and in order
to do that I mean you you need somebody
previously would have to go through all
those relevant documents and basically
come and after maybe one week give you
an answer yes this was done in so and so
date on so and so time but now with this
kind of uh generative AI models you can
actually train them or use this kind of
rag type uh schema inside your company
and they can actually provide you with
an answer and also a reference as to
which uh place they got that answer from
in just a few seconds so that's a huge
increase in productivity so that's one
of the things that people want they want
to distill all this uh internal
knowledge uh quickly uh uh so that they
can get answers the other thing uh that
people were uh uh looking at is this uh
uh Network logs so there is a network
out outage and there is an expert who
looks at all these logs at various nodes
in the network to figure out exactly
what happened and now if you can train a
model on those logs and the incident
that happened before then now it can
actually tell you oh in in maybe a split
second that this is what actually
happened you need to change change this
node in the network or you need to make
this kind of corrective action so these
are some of the things that um uh
actually people people use in the
Enterprise yeah thank you um I see at
the top one of the question I want to
know David what is your prediction for
the impact of quantum Computing on AI in
the short and long term okay that was M
my bad I said the word
Quantum um so Quantum Computing is
coming I mean IBM we have uh some of the
very best and largest quantum computers
in the world today um Quantum general
purpose Quantum Computing isn't here yet
and but it but we are getting into this
age of what they call Quantum utility
where we can actually do things with a
quantum computer that you couldn't
possibly do with classical computers now
one misapprehension I want to just
disabuse every one of all at once here
on mass I'm going to do do my part for
this is that a quantum computer isn't
simply a faster computer it's a
different kind of computer so computers
compete with bits zeros and ones um
quantum computers compute with cubits
and they just have fundamentally
different properties to them so they're
amazing for things like if you want to
simulate a material you can't beat a
quantum computer because materials at
the level of sort of atoms and electrons
and and interacting obey Quantum you
know quantum mechanical laws it's not
like the physics we're used to at the
length scales that we as humans occupy
and we're going to have huge
implications in the field of Material
Science for instance from that you know
new materials that can sequester carbon
and all kinds of things are going to be
amazing from that um they can also do
machine learning you can do Quantum
machine learning um but I would say at
the stage we're at right now like don't
just assume that when we get quantum
computers that's going to magically
somehow speed up what we do with AI it
it'll work in certain very particular
domains and be interesting but um we're
not going to we don't see a world at
least not at IBM where our clown
computer is just like the solution
actually what we're building is hybrid
data centers that mix classical
Computing Quantum Computing and then
increasingly optimized AI acceleration
Hardware because it's just different
enough um you know gpus are the game are
are s of the dominant architecture today
we actually have something internal with
an IBM which is actually a nonv noan
architecture that can can run uh llms
and other deep learning extremely fast
um and we'll see continuing Innovation
there but what Quantum is really going
to win is something where it's like no
matter how many computers you have it's
just the problem the algorithms we have
won't get you there so a classic example
of something when we do have a general
purpose on a computer is uh factoring
prime numbers so a lot of our
cryptography depends on taking two
numbers very large numbers they prime
numbers multiplying them together and
then it's very easy to verify if you
have those two original numbers if
that's right but it's it's very hard to
go the other way with a classical
computer like the algorithms that we
have for that scale in an unpleasant way
like it like and it's to the level of if
you had the fastest Computing chips and
you tiled the Earth with them it
wouldn't be enough compute because it
just scales so poorly and what quantum
computers do is they can they can
actually they obey different rules and
they can have a different scaling so all
of those kinds of cryptography aths are
going to be broken uh eventually
thankfully we have postquantum
cryptography actually IBM contributed
several of the algorithms to this we
have other ways to do it that aren't
that are resistant to that kind of
quantum algorithm but um but I I don't
think we're going to see some like bang
moment where it's like oh now we have P
computers now we're just going to do the
AI thing with that now the other
direction is even more interesting
though because a Quon computer is a
really complicated analog system there's
lots of different ways to do a quic
computer but like kind we have you have
like a cryostat which is a really really
really cold refrigerator it's got heal
it's like the cold like close to
absolute zero and you're putting
microwave pulses into it AI is actually
really great for controlling that analog
system see people are using AI
Technologies to to came the Quant the
cubits and that's that's a very
effective and interesting place and we
and we will we are starting to see Niche
applications particularly the financial
sector is really interested in certain
kinds of AI algorithms not like whole
llms but things more like Quantum kernel
machines like for classification and
doing very very high value kind of
things that maybe a quantum computer
could be useful for but um so lots of
things are going to change and be
interesting but I don't think it's a one
+ 1 equals you know five kind of thing
that we're going to see anytime soon but
I've had to eat my words about l so I I
reserve yeah so so at Fujitsu actually
we do uh a lot of research in Quantum
machine learning so there's a team under
me who actually does some research on
that and uh yeah as uh David said I mean
the the speed up that you get in uh U
Quantum machine learning is not
exponential so you don't uh hope to uh
get to anywhere with a few number of
cubits so you are probably looking at
maybe hundreds of thousands or even
millions of cubits before you can see
the impact of that speed up on like AI
training or AI inference and that kind
of stuff so we are currently at around
a, noisy cubits so we are nowhere near
that so in the short term I would say I
mean the applications would be quite
limited and the impact on AI but in the
longer term yeah there will be uh
definitely an impact into training
because currently the llm models I mean
training from scratch you're looking at
months sometimes and so if you can even
speed that up uh by a polinomial time uh
in computer science jargon then you will
be bringing that down to maybe weeks or
days so that would be a huge
impact so we just have a few minutes uh
but I would like to jump into the future
um and actually so I spend the
weekend try reading and trying to find
information about strawberry
so if you don't know what strawberry is
it's the nickname of uh the the new
model that openai put available for a
lot of us to play with it's also called
thing o1 but what intrigued me is that
so I'm a I work on cognition human uh
cognition and it seems that one of the
old Mark of intelligence is actually
reasoning so I would like to ask the
three of you uh final words on what will
be the next
next breakthrough that you think we
should see or AI should do in order to
move
towards system that are more
intelligent any you want to start two
minute each yeah I can I can getar this
so this is not the the the most uh uh
interesting thing that came out like
there is a there is another model after
this one strawberry from open AI it's
like gbd 5 actually the one that
actually coming out that one is like
pretty impressive this one is still um a
good system it's a reason it's a f first
uh you know like you can you can do
computation as I told you like when you
train these models you train them on
enormous amount of data right so you can
you can spend that amount of data
training like training a model or you
can take like a well- trained model not
that large and then try
to search opportunities that this system
from the knowledge base that it actually
created at inference time to actually
create like more reasoning more
scenarios you know if this happens then
that happens you know and then this and
then try to actually encode all of this
you know input reasoning and thinking
kind of passes and then try to make a
decision so that that kind of
exploration and then trying to find out
the answer to a question by exploration
like deploying search and you know and
this this kind of thing at test time
this is something that the strawberry is
actually doing right so they're doing
test time uh kind of computation you
know so they're increasing the capacity
of compute on the test side and you know
like basically balancing between the two
you know you can spend a lot of time
training a Model A lot of data or you
can change the narrative and and and
just you know train at test time you
know like that's that's basically the
the the discovery that they had so this
seems to be a nice way for for AI
systems to memor you see before that AI
systems were memorizing uh data input
outputs now they're memorizing reasoning
so it's still in in distribution so it's
it's still what I would say is not like
something that goes beyond distribution
kind of learning you need something more
than that and that could happen in the
future thank you David your two minutes
so I mean anytime one of these models
comes out I have a team that goes and
tries to reverse engineer what what
exactly they did and and what we should
do about it and and what we should think
about it and and I think that piece
around being smarter about what you do
at inference time I mean that's
obviously a big part of it but I think
it's part of actually a larger Trend
which is don't assume that we're going
to have this Magic model that just is
all knowing and all being and all
thinking the pattern we're seeing much
more and more is actually embedding the
llm in a system of other tools and um
you might remember alphago this was a
reinforcement learning system and they
could play go it beat the the champion
in the in go and everyone said oh this
is fantastic reinforcement learning has
has really gotten us there a big part of
that system was something called Monte
Carlo treesearch which is actually a
classical uh you know AI like old school
AI kind of technique and you know
there's there's there's a lot of that
happening I think behind the scenes with
a lot of these these models and I think
even more than that what we're going to
see is treat an llm as a new tool that's
embedded in a larger system and when you
get to the issue of control this becomes
really important because I might not
just want to rely on a Model just to
give me the answer I might have a policy
that says hey if some employee asks this
question about this HR issue I I
shouldn't take what the model says I
have a thing that the lawyers wrote and
I need to I need to show them that and
sometimes we have this posture that as
all knowing model is going to know
everything and the reality is it's going
to be part of a system that includes
classical traditional Computing
components going to include classical AI
methods things like Monte Carlo
treesearch but also probably things like
planning and other kinds of reasoning
and we're going to have hybrid systems
that are are are more controllable and
and more powerful that harness the magic
of the LM but but don't don't rely on it
exclusively thank you so uh basically uh
the reasoning is very important in case
of auditing and governance so whenever
you have an AI system in in your uh
product and it makes make some kind of a
decision you would like to know if the
decision is wrong where actually did it
go wrong and that is very important
because you are liable right like like
he said about that GP uh that chatbot
which gave some hallucinated answer you
you don't want to get to that uh point
so whenever there is this kind of poor
reasoning or the the training is not
enough so that the llm has some
different uh Notions of knowledge or
there is bias in the data you want to
know all these kind of things so that
you can correct for that so the so you
don't run into all these real life
issues so these are the reasons why I
think this reasoning part of that llm is
very important all right well that's the
end of our session uh thank you everyone
for your question thank you uh for um to
be here it was uh very Illuminating okay
well see you next time