(regal music plays)
(upbeat music)
(Professor Wallace laughing)
(music continues)
- So, on Friday, we talked
a bit about scheduling,
and you'll really need to maintain one
if you want to work effectively as a team
and manage that path to
your first prototype.
I'm David Wallace,
a Mechanical Engineering
Design Professor At MIT.
Goals are essential, and
I mean precise goals.
That's because meeting goals, milestones,
is how we measure getting things done.
A systematic set of goals
that build upon each other
are the path to success.
(chick chirping)
Have you heard of the
phrase one-hit wonder?
It's the idea that we've done
something great, it's a hit,
but we have no idea how we did it,
and we can never do it again.
We don't want that.
Having a set of well-defined
goals, a process,
is the ticket to succeeding
over and over again
without being overwhelmed.
Goals keep us on track.
So,
This is how I explain the concept
in our MIT Mechanical
Engineering Product Design class.
May I introduce the Chicken Chart?
The Chicken Chart is actually
just a developmental timeline
for the gestation of a chicken,
but it's a really great metaphor
for product development,
or really completing any project.
So let's take a closer look at the chart.
So here we are.
Roughly 19 days, depending
on when your lab is,
and we pretty much have an idea, right?
A very nice, fertile idea.
We have a fertile idea, kind
of like a chicken embryo,
and we have limited resources.
That's the yoke.
It's money, people, equipment, time.
Time is a big one.
And there's a lot of growing
to be done along the way.
So the yolk, the resources
have to be metered
in just the right amount,
so it's utilized to the fullest,
but we don't run out.
(chick chirps)
On the gestation timeline,
we go through a series of checkpoints,
developmental milestones.
The first milestones focus
on exploring opportunities,
needs, and pitching high-level
ideas for new products.
And we're talking hundreds of ideas.
Next, we have the sketches and mockups,
where things begin to slowly take form,
and, like the chicken,
things can be pretty ugly.
The idea is there, but
it's not fully formed.
Then, when each team
lands on the one big idea
that they'll present together on stage,
things really start to take shape.
- [Team] Woo!
- [Professor Wallace] They grow,
and you really start to see
what the final prototype
will eventually look like.
(upbeat music)
Having these goals to hit along the way
helps us to constantly keep ourselves
and our progress in check,
whether they're massive milestones
or the many smaller goals in between.
But whatever the goal may be,
all of them are essential to the task,
all keeping us on the
roadmap to a good product,
a product that is magic for the users.
And if all goes well,
we'll have the most beautiful
chick we can create.
But if we don't hit those milestones,
well, we may be fried.
(chick screaming)
(Professor Wallace laughing)
So, think about something
that you wanna do.
What is the end goal?
Really define it.
Think about the goals
that will lead you there.
Frequent small goals that build a path
to your final outcome.
(students cheering)
What resources do you need,
or just what do you have to work with?
Put it on a timeline.
You have a plan, stick to
the plan, and always deliver.
That is the chicken chart.
We will be putting this in the lab.
Goals are essential.
They really are your friend.
Play seriously.