Okay. Well, we can get started. So, in
the first class, we talked about like
what what is a projection estimate and
what is projection theory and tried to
give a little bit of motivation for it.
Um, and today we'll start getting our
hands on things and looking at examples
and proving theorems. Um now the the uh
cleanest setting in which to get started
is finite fields. Um and although most
of our class will be working in RN um
I'm going to start there because the uh
proofs are very clean and the examples
are very clean and it's also it is also
interesting in itself.
Okay.
Okay. So here's our setup.
So I'll have fq the finite field with q
elements. Um and then uh theta will so
then I'll I'll have a map pi sub theta
from fq^2 to fq. These will like be our
different projections from fq ^2 to fq.
And it's defined by
pi theta of x1 x2 is x1 * theta or x1 +
x2 * theta.
Okay. So here theta is also in f.
Okay.
Um so now our setup is that we'll have a
set of points x in the plane fq ^2 and
we'll think about projecting this set of
points in a bunch of different
directions. So then we'll have a set of
directions which is called d.
So d is a subset of fq and think of it
as a set of directions.
I'm going to imagine taking this at X
and projecting it in all of these
different directions that are in D. And
we'll see um how big the different
projections are. And um the the thing
I'll measure, I'll call it S, which
depends on X and D, is the size of the
biggest projection.
So it's the maximum
theta in D of the size of pi theta of X.
Okay. So, so one thing we study in
projection theory is we like to
understand for different sizes of X and
D, what can we say about S.
Okay.
[Applause]
So, let's look at a couple of examples
and then after that I'll put I'll tell
you some theorems what we know and some
conjecture what we think might be true
based on the examples.
Um
so the first example is a square grid
or integer maybe it's good to say
integer grid.
Um so for this example let's suppose
that Q is actually prime. Um
you could do similar things if if Q is
not prime. It's just easier to write it
down. Okay, so our set X is going to be
the set X1 X2 where X1 and X2 go between
one and M.
So even though we're over a finite
field, you can think of this as a square
integer grid.
Okay. And then we were saying last time
that if you take this a square grid, an
integer grid, and you do a projection in
a direction that's kind of a rational
angle, um then you get a small
projection. So that's what our set of
directions is going to be. Our set of
directions is going to be the set of a1
over a2
where a1 and a2 go from one up to some
a. So n and a are parameters that we can
play with. There are many square grids
many choices.
All right. So now let's figure out what
is s of xd. So what happens when I
perform a projection of of uh uh of x at
one of these angles?
So if theta is in d
and I take pi and if I if x is in x
um so if I take pi theta of uh of x1 x2
then I get um x1 plus a1 over a2 x2
and I'm going to put it over a common
denominator. So it's a2 x1 + a1 x2
over a2.
All right. Now in this situation, we're
imagining that theta is fixed and we're
varying little x and big x. So we're
going to try to see how big is pi theta
of big x. So I want to see if a is fixed
and I vary x1 and x2, how many different
numbers do I have here? So the
denominator isn't important because it's
not changing. And I want to know how
many different numerators I have. And
the numerator is going to be an integer.
And it has size a * n at most plus a *
n. So it basically has size a * n. So we
see that the size of the projection of x
is at most a * n. So this less than with
a squiggle here means there's a constant
factor that I left out. Here it's a
factor of two, but in general squiggle
just means there's some constant factor
left out.
Uh okay. And S is the biggest of these.
So S uh of XD is around a * M.
Okay. Um
so then uh you could do a little algebra
to see how S and X and D relate to each
other. Um and if you do that you see
that uh d is around s^2x.
Okay. So that's how it works in an
integer grid.
And there's one more example um that
that I thought I would mention which we
also mentioned last time. It's an
example that comes from sub fields. So
if Q is not prime um then FP is an
interesting subset of FQ and FP squ is
an interesting subset of FQ q^2.
So this is called the subfield example.
So let's say that Q is P ^2. There are
similar phenomenon if Q is a higher
power of P but the um the the
computations are a bit different. Um so
if Q is P^ squ um our set X is going to
be FP^2
sitting in FQ ^2. So the size of X is P
^2 which is Q and our set of directions
is going to be FP which is sitting in
FQ. So the size of our set of directions
is P which is Q to the 12.
Um and then if theta is in D
then
X1 and X2 are in X then pi X1 X2 is in
X. Pi theta of X1 X2 is X1 + X2 theta.
All those things are in the sub field
FP. So this is in FP.
Um so therefore
the size of pi theta of x is at most p
in fact exactly p. Um and so that's our
s.
[Applause]
Okay. Um and this example coming from
subfields is more extreme than the
example coming from grips. Um so if you
were to take this value of x and this
value of s and plug them in here
uh to make a sort of a fair comparison
in the grids we would have only one
direction if we did that. But here we
have many directions. So this thing um
has very small projections in many
different directions even more so than a
square grid.
Okay.
So those are a few examples and
and based on that I can tell you a
conjecture that we stated also last time
and also I can tell you some of the
things we know about this conjecture
some of the main results.
Um
okay so first I'll say the conjecture.
So if uh Q= P which is prime
um and we're in this setup
and S is smaller than around X over two.
um then we can't do better than the
square grid.
Okay, so let's explain all the
hypotheses in this conjecture. Um so why
do we have this? Well, if you take any
set D, S of XD is is obviously smaller
than the size of X.
So if s was allowed to be the size of x,
then d could be everything and there
would be no no meaningful upper bound on
d. So we have to insist that it's
somewhat smaller than that. Um you you
could ask about the range in between
here and x but there's something to say
but it's I think not not super
interesting. Um so we look at this
regime.
Okay. Um okay and we have this setup and
why do we also add here that Q is a
prime? Well, we have to add that because
of example two. If Q is not a prime, you
have that example. And we just saw that
this is false.
And this conjecture is plausible in the
sense that there's no counter example
that you no one has found an example
that beats the square grid. And
basically, no one has found an example
that even is well.
Okay. There are very few examples that
are competitive with the square grid.
And they're all small variations of it.
Um, okay. You also might wonder uh what
happens if Q is not a prime. And I
haven't seen anyone write down a
conjecture for that. Um, I think roughly
speaking what people believe is that the
all of the interesting examples should
be of this type or that type or maybe
you can combine them a little bit by
taking sort of a grid of sub fields. Um
so it would be a reasonable little
project if anyone is interested to try
to write down the known examples and and
make a conjecture about what happens.
All right. Now this conjecture is open
um but let's start to talk about what we
know. We'll we'll we'll I'm going to
state some theorems for you and we'll
prove the theorems and uh maybe more
importantly we'll introduce some of the
basic techniques in in projection
theory. Okay. So we're going to talk
about two techniques today. One of them
is a double counting argument that has a
combinatorics flavor and the other is a
for analytic argument that's based on
orthogonality
and this is what they give.
So theorem one which is based on double
counting
says if uh we're in this setup
and s is smaller
than x over two um then the number of
directions is smaller than around pass.
Okay. Um, now if S is around X over two,
this is actually sharp.
Um,
hold on, let me look at my notes for a
second.
Okay, actually I wrote that in my notes,
but I'm not quite sure it's true. Let's
just go on and I'll tell you theorem
two.
Um
so theorem two is based on what I'll
call a forier method or orthogonality or
something like that says if we have the
setup and this time if we suppose that s
is smaller than q / 2
then
d is smaller than s * qx.
Okay so let's digest this statement a
little bit. um uh so the projection is
always a subset of fq. So s is always
smaller than or equal to q. So this
hypothesis says that it's it's it's
significantly smaller than that. The
projection is significantly smaller than
the whole space.
Okay. And then we get this bound. Um and
this bound is most interesting in the
case that s was actually close to q over
two because in that case this q and this
s are about the same size. So this is
around s^2x
which matches the grid example.
So this is actually um sharp
if s is around q2.
Okay, I find that quite striking and
impressive. This is a great example. Has
an interesting intricate structure and
we're wondering whether it was sharp.
And at least in this one regime uh this
theorem is shows that it actually is
sharp.
Okay. On the other hand, S could be a
lot smaller than Q. Then we get some
bound here and we don't have any example
that that matches that bound. Um
I guess no I should also say this works
over any field. So if you plug in
example two, it's actually also sharp.
Um and so it's also sharp in example
two.
Um,
all right. But there are a bunch of
there are a bunch of choices of the
parameter you could make where it's not
clear that this is sharp.
Okay. So, the big goal of the class is
to introduce these two techniques really
and we'll use them to prove these two
theorems. But maybe it's a good place to
pause and check if people have questions
or comments. Yeah,
>> it's um in the first theorem, are you
assuming that it's prime?
>> We are not assuming that it's prime. Um
right. So that's right. We're not
assuming it's prime in either theorem.
And so where it says setup, it means
we're assuming this.
Yeah, that's right. Um okay. And so that
raises a point that it appears that the
true answer to this question uh depends
on whether Q is prime or not prime. But
neither of these techniques depend on
that. they work for all Q and they're
sort of not able to notice whether Q is
prime or not prime. That will eventually
be a big theme. We won't get to it
today, but eventually we'll try to find
some techniques that do notice whether Q
is prime or not.
>> Yeah.
>> Um for the premise S is less than or
equal to size of X / 2, how easy is it
to construct some other examples that
satisfy that element of the grid?
>> Yeah. Okay. So the question is um uh you
know can can we find
how how many examples can we find which
obey the hypothesis so that this theorem
says anything about them? Um well I
think it's not super hard because we're
allowed to take D to be small.
Um so uh
um
so you know if D is just one direction
then you could easily arrange the points
so that their projection in one
direction is quite small and you have a
lot more flexibility than a grid and if
you'd like the projection to be small in
two directions um then you would want
some kind of cartisian product but it
wouldn't have there's still a lot more
cartisian products than integer grids.
And then as you add more directions, it
gets more rigid and and and we we can
start to think about it. We can think
about it uh later on. It's it's a neat
question how many examples we can come
up with. Yeah.
Okay. Other questions.
In example one, you said Q = P prime.
Um, can Q be a prime power?
>> Yes. Right. Right. So, okay.
Yeah. So, the question was up in example
one, we assume that Q is prime. Um, are
there examples similar to that if Q is
not prime?
Um, so okay, so if N and A are smaller,
if Q is P to the R and you choose N and
A smaller than P, you can just use
what's on the board for Bane.
Um, if you wanted to choose N and A
bigger than P, it doesn't really make
sense in FQ. Um, so I think that there's
a fix for that, but I didn't have time
to think through the details before
class.
Um
yeah. So
homework for one of us.
Okay.
Okay. So let's start proving some
things. Um so first we'll do the double
counter.
Okay. So suppose that pi we just look at
one direction where this projection is
small. If s is a lot smaller than x, it
will look something like this. Um so
here's the space we're projecting onto
and we'll have some points.
Uh and this is our projection map. So
here we have x and this arrow is the
projection map pi theta.
Um and then and then down here we have
pi theta of x.
Okay. And you'll notice that for each
point in the projection or at least for
most points in the projection uh we'll
have many points of x that are going on
top of it.
Okay.
So, so we're going to pay attention to
that. Um and the first thing we'll say
is that um
if s is smaller than x over two then we
have a lot of points going on top of
each other. Um uh so for every theta in
our set of directions,
the number of pairs x1 and x2 and x that
got projected to the same point
that should be at least around um s * x
/ s^ squ.
Okay, so let's digest that. First of
all, I'll warn you that I changed
notation. So x1 and x2 are each points
in x. Those are not the components of
anything. Um, okay. And so why is this?
Well, imagine first that these uh each
that each point in the projection has
the same number of pre-im images. So
each of these points has about x over s
points of x sitting above it.
And then the number of ways to choose
two of them um would be x over s^2.
And that would be true for each of these
s points. So that would give us uh this.
Actually, let me add here that I'm
interested in two different points that
got projected to the same point.
So this is still true, but because I put
two different points here, that's where
I needed to use uh this hypothesis.
Okay, so that was some intuition why it
might be true. Um, then you might
wonder, well, maybe they're not evenly
distributed. Maybe some of these points
have more pre-im images than others. It
turns out that that only helps you. I'm
going to make it an exercise. It's kind
of a standard combinatorics exercise.
So, it's exercise on your first problem
set uh using Koshy Schwarz to
Okay,
cool. So, there are a lot of points
getting collapsed together in these
different projections and we're going to
put it all together. So the key object
that we're going to count is the number
of directions theta and distinct points
in x uh so that they have the same
projection.
Okay? And they have to be a lot of those
because for every direction there are a
lot of them. So the number of these is
at least x^2 s inverse number of
directions. The x^2 s inverse is just
that simplified and that was how many
there are in each direction and there
are d directions.
Okay.
So now the point is that it's hard to
have this many collapses
um because if you take any two pairs of
points in X there's only one direction
in which they get mapped on top of each
other.
So that gives us an upper bound on on
this star. So but for any points x1 not
equal to x2
the number of theta so that
pi theta of x1 = p theta of x2
there's at most one and that gives us an
upper bound for star
is upperbounded by x2
once you choose x1 and x2 there's only
one choice of theta
Okay.
Um
so this key quantity is sandwiched in
between here and here. We have x^2 s
inverse d is less than star is less than
x^2.
And you simplify this a little bit and
we get that d is less than s. That's the
proof.
Let me summarize it without the
equations. The key object is this object
star. U let's call let's call this the
set of coincidences. A coincidence is
when you have two points in X that get
mapped to the same point in by pi theta.
And if many projections are small, there
must be many coincidences.
But there can't be that many because if
you take two points X1 and X2, there's
only one direction that makes a
coincidence. And that's what we're
using.
Okay. Any questions or comments about
double counting?
Okay, let me show you the second
approach which is based on uh I called
it a forier approach or based on
orthogonality or based on cancellation.
So this approach begins with an image
that uh that that I want you to have in
mind and that you know we could try to
work on this image in many ways. Uh so
it's the overlapping lines image.
Okay. So suppose I have a bunch of
points that have small projections in
many directions.
Okay. So if I project this down it has a
small projection
And if I look at the so maybe I'll call
this pi theta 1. If I look at the pre-im
images of these I'll get some lines
in uh in a certain direction that
corresponds to theta 1. And so I've
covered my set with uh not too many
lines. So down here there are at most s
points. So over here we have at most s
lines. And I'll call this set of lines L
theta 1.
Okay. So to summarize uh
if pi I guess pi theta of x is less than
or equal to s then I get a set called l
theta
uh is a set of at most s lines
uh that are that are I guess
perpendicular to theta. Um and that they
cover my set X.
So now if I have many small projections,
I can do this in many directions. And so
I'll have sets of lines in different
directions and I'll cover X many times.
So I can do this
for every theta in my set of directions.
Okay. So I'll do one more. I was meaning
to bring some colored chalk, but I
didn't I don't have colored chalk today.
So I'll do my best. Uh so let's say this
is a dotted direction and
when I project in the theta 2 direction
this
so this is um
uh so this would be l theta 2 in in
dotted lines. Okay, I'm not going to add
any more directions to the picture, but
in your imagination, imagine that this
set of points there are lines going many
different ways that are uh covering the
set of points.
Okay, so in our second method and maybe
in a lot of things that we do, we're
going to imagine these lines and work
with these lines as a way of
understanding the projection estimates.
Okay.
So, let me add a little vocabulary about
this.
So, we've defined L theta. L our whole
set of lines is the union over all the
different directions of the lines L
theta. So, that's a set of lines.
And um
so if L is a line, I'm going to write L
of X as an abbreviation for the
characteristic function of that line 1
sub L of X.
And think about what happens when we add
up all these characteristic functions.
So f ofx
is the sum over all the lines in my set
of lines of L of X.
Okay, so take a moment to visualize that
I have lines going in different
directions.
Imagine their characteristic functions
and add them all up. So when I add them
all up at any given point, it will tell
me how many different lines to my set of
lines went through that point.
Um, and so if if x is in my set of
points, then f ofx is the number of
directions. If I take a point in my set,
this point is going to lie in one line
in every direction.
If I take a point that's not in my set,
uh, it's not very clear what's going to
happen. It won't necess not obvious it
will be in any lines, but it might be in
some lines. We don't know much about how
what f is doing at those points that are
not in my set x.
Okay, great. Um, okay. So, we're going
to get at projection theory by trying to
study this function and in particular
trying to uh study the set where the
function is big. That's going to be our
second approach. Um, and we're going to
study the set where this function is big
using for a analysis or andor using
orthogonality.
Okay.
So orthogonal.
Okay. So um so L L of X remember is the
characteristic function of a line and
I'm going to decompose it into pieces.
So um okay so there are Q points in a
line and there are Q squared points in
my whole plate. And so the average value
of L of X is 1 / Q. So I'm going to
separate that out. That's 1 / Q plus a
piece that I'll call L sub high of X.
That H is for high. We'll talk about
that name more in a sec. So this is the
average value
of our function. And therefore the
leftover piece has mean zero
has value zero
and not value zero it has average value
zero as mean zero. Okay. Um and I also
will think of this as the zero frequency
piece and the high frequency piece in
terms of fora analysis. We can make that
precise. We'll do that a little bit
later.
But as a depending how much for analysis
you do, you may or may not like this
intuition. But this is a constant part
and this is like a higher frequency
oscillating part.
Okay, those are just words. So we
decompose it like this.
Now the key observation
is that um well oversimplifying just a
little bit. these high high frequency
parts are orthogonal to each other. So
here's a precise statement.
So if L1 uh not equal to L2 are lines,
so I have two different lines,
then
the sum over all of the points in the
plane of L1 H of X, L2, H of X
is less than or equal to zero.
Okay. Now when when we prove this lema
in a little bit we will see that it's
almost always equal to zero. So these
functions are almost always orthogonal.
Once in a while they're not orthogonal
but then it's negative. That that part
isn't that important anyway. So so
roughly speaking these functions L1H and
L2 are orthogonal.
Okay. Now how does that help us?
Well,
let's think about f ofx. f ofx,
remember, is the sum uh over all the
lines in our set of lines of L of X. And
so, we can break it up this way also.
When we add up the constant parts, well,
we'll just see what we get. We get the
number of lines divided by Q. And then
we have to add up all the high frequency
parts. So plus the sum l in our set of
lines
of lh x. So this thing here is the high
frequency part of f. I'll call it f subh
of x. For now you can think of that as
just a name.
Okay.
So this part we understand quite well.
Know exactly what it is. And so as
understanding this function boils down
to understanding this part. And for
understanding this part, we can use this
orthogonality. We've written it as a sum
of pieces that are each pretty simple
and they're orthogonal to each other.
And so that lets us figure out or
estimate quite well the L2 norm of this
FH.
So after the key lema, I guess there's
the L2 estimate.
[Applause]
It says the sum x in fq ^2
of fh of x^2.
Well, um that's the sum l1 l2 in l
of the sum x and f2
l1 h of x l2 h of x
Okay.
And because of my orthogonality in the
key lema, almost all of these terms are
less than or equal to zero. Namely, if
L1 is different from L2, then this sum
is less than or equal to zero.
So then I'll just keep this the terms
where they're equal to each other.
[Applause]
Okay.
Now, this sum here is easy to do uh
because I just have to think one line at
a time and all the lines will be
equivalent to each other. So, it's just
the number of lines times whatever this
is.
This thing also is not very hard to
compute. Um, but
let me say that this is actually smaller
than if I uh did the whole L of x squ.
I mean, you could you could just compute
it and write down what happens though.
But anyway, but um if you take a
function and you subtract off its mean,
then the L2 norm is smaller than for the
original function. So anyway, so we
could write this and then we can compute
this even in our heads. So L of X is one
at Q points and otherwise it's zero. So
this thing here is Q. So we get the
number of lines times Q. So that's our
L2 estimate.
[Applause]
Okay. So now let's finish um the proof
of theorem 2. There's theorem two up
there. Um, we have this hypothesis that
S is a lot smaller than Q.
How does that matter? That controls this
term,
right? So, you know, if D was only as
big as L over Q, uh, then um, this
complicated thing wouldn't come into
play and and F could be that big
everywhere.
Um,
okay. So, let's see how that works. So
the number of lines in my set of lines
is s * d because I have d directions and
I have s lines in each direction.
So this uh
l over q is uh s * d / q
and I have a hypothesis that s is at
most q over two.
So that implies that when I take this
ratio
um L / Q is less than half of D.
>> Yeah.
>> Um equality L equals S * D. Does does
that assume that every uh so set of
lines has the same
like every L is the same size because I
thought that they could be different
sizes.
>> Yes. Right. That's okay. That's a good
technical catch. So um Right.
Right. So in each direction I have at
most S lines. Um but
it might be okay to work with that but I
find it slightly confusing to keep track
of and you can always add some extra
lines and the lines will still cover the
set X. Um and so
[Applause]
so I don't know I don't know that this
is crucial but the what I like to do is
to say that there are equal to s lines
and they cover x and and we can say that
and then it makes this computation
clean.
Okay. Um
okay so this l over q is less than half
of d.
Now remember that at each point uh in x
f ofx is d and f ofx breaks up as l over
q plus the high frequency part and the
the what we just saw is the l over q is
less than half of d. So the high
frequency part is the majority uh of of
f at those points.
Okay. So we conclude that for every x
and x um the high frequency part of x is
at least half of d.
I'll just write greater subd.
Okay. And now we can comp compare this
with our L2 bound there.
Right? So
um so we can say that the sum over all
of the
that the sum over all the points
of fh of x
squared. Well that should be at least as
big as the points at x times the number
of directions squared. So in this sum
some of these points are in my set x and
at each of those points this has size
around d. So that contributes this much.
Plus there are other points which I
really don't know what they're doing.
Okay. And then we have the upper bound
the L2 estimate that we just proved over
there that is upper bounded by the
number of lines time q which is s * d *
q.
Okay. And now we just rearrange this and
it will give us some information about s
and d and x and q. Um,
so I'm going to get the D by itself. So
I divide by that and I divide by that.
I'm left with D is bounded by S * Q /X.
There it is.
Yeah,
>> just going back and forth between
analysis. The mean value here is taking
over like talking about the mean over
the sex.
>> Yeah. So when we say the word mean,
yeah, when I say the word mean, okay, so
the question was when we said mean
value, the mean over what? Um,
[Applause]
so let me put that up here.
So if I have a function g fub^2
c then when I say the mean value
of g what I mean is um 1 over q ^2 sum
in x and f q ^2 of g of x. So it's the
mean over the whole vector space.
Other questions or comments about the
proof?
Okay. So, so
I am also working on digesting the
proof. Um, so the proof is all about
breaking up f as this constant part plus
this high frequency part. And the proof
is saying that in a certain sense the
high frequency part is actually kind of
small compared to the constant part.
So, I wanted to draw that out because I
feel like it helps my intuition about
what the what the proof is saying.
Um,
so, so let's look at this L2 estimate.
So, our L2 estimate was that um the sum
f ofx^2
x in the whole plane
was bounded by the number of lines times
Q.
Um, so I want to think about what this
means and uh, it helps me a little bit
to replace the sum by an average. So I'm
going to divide both sides by Q ^2.
So if I take 1 / q ^2 some x and f q^2
f h of x^2 then that's bounded by the
number of lines divided by q.
Okay, so this is an L2 version of an
average and by Koshy Schwarz that
controls
uh let's see yeah so then so so the if I
took a square root to get an L2 norm I
would have a square root over here and
by Koshy Schwarz
I would get that the L1 average
um
has a bound
and the bound is now the square root of
number of lines over Q.
Does that look right to everybody?
Okay. And so a bit informally, you know,
there might be some points X that are
different, but on average for a typical
point X, the high frequency part only
has the size square root of L over Q.
Whereas the low frequency part, the
constant part has size L over Q at every
point. Here
let's call let's call this constant part
fnot that's your frequency part right so
for comparison the size of fnot of x is
always number of lines over q so the
conclusion is that if the number of
lines is uh much bigger than q
then this is way bigger than
Um so then
the high frequency part is much smaller
than the constant part on average.
So it's telling us that whenever I add
up a lot of lines has to be
significantly more than Q lines
then that sum is pretty close to being a
constant function.
At a typical point, the difference from
being constant is extremely small. And
there may be a few points where the
difference from being constant is
bigger, but but there's a pretty strong
bound on them.
Okay. Any questions or comments about
this? um orthogonality proof.
>> Yeah.
>> The inequality fater.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Okay. So, so to recap a
little bit, we have these lines going in
each direction and we have d directions
and we add up all the characteristic
functions of the lines. So that's called
f and each point of x is in all is in
the line in every direction. So f ofx is
d.
Now we broke up f into two pieces. The
constant piece which was number of lines
over q and then the mean zero piece or
high frequency piece.
Um, and I claim that the constant piece
is small. The constant piece is less
than half of D. And that would mean that
the high frequency part should be more
than half of D. And why is the constant
piece small? Well, this L is the number
of directions times S. Um, and we
plugged it in and we used the fact that
S is at most Q over2. It's one of our
hypotheses. That's what fell out.
Okay.
Um, okay. Now, I called this early on
the Forier method. We didn't actually
mention the Forier transform or for a
series of anything. We didn't have to.
Um, we did use orthogonality
crucially, which is an idea that I first
saw in 4A analysis. Um, but it is
possible to rewrite this proof using the
the 4A transform. um and um it is
uh I think it's worth doing even though
we didn't need the for transform this as
we keep going and do more sophisticated
things in this spirit it helps to have
the 4 transfer
okay um
I guess the other thing is we didn't
prove the key lema
okay actually why don't we let's so I'm
going to uh prove the key lema And I'll
show you two proofs. One of them is sort
of direct and the other one is based on
the uh for a transform. Okay.
Um so I think we can erase this board
here. We're just going to talk about the
key lema.
Okay. Um so I'll call this the direct
proof of the key lama and then we'll
also have a forier proof.
Um okay so actually two cases in the
lema. So the main case is that L1 and L2
are not parallel.
Okay. And in this case the the high
frequency parts are orthogonal.
So sum of x L1 H of X L2 H of X in this
case is exactly zero. The the less than
zero comes from the parallel keys.
Okay. Now there's a lot of symmetry in
this problem. And so we have the two
lines that intersect. We can make a
linear change of variables and a
translation so that one of them is the
x1 axis and the other one is the x2
axis.
So after change of variables, L1 is the
actually I'm going to say L1 is the X2
axis and L2 is the X1 axis. I know that
looks a little silly. Um but yeah,
somewhere there's going to be a any is
that a point?
So
So over here is L2 and over here is L1.
All right. Now and we do that
if I take L1 high of a point X1 X2
um
it only depends
okay so okay so the function L1 of X
only depends upon X1 if X1 is zero L1 is
one if X1 is not zero we get zero then
we're subtracting a constant function
from that so it still only depends on X1
so This is a function g of x1
and its mean zero. So the sum over x1
and fq of g of x1 is zero.
Okay. Similarly l2 high of x1 x2 only
depends upon x2 and it's g of x2.
This is the trickiest bit. Let me make
sure that looks okay.
So remember L L1 is one if X1 is zero
and it's zero otherwise.
And then we're subtract. So that's a
function that only depends on X1. We
subtract off its mean. We get a a new
function that only depends on X1.
I guess it's 1 - 1 over Q. If X1 is zero
and it's minus one over Q if X1 is not
zero. That's what G is.
Okay. So now when we sum L1H
of X1 X2
L2 H of X1 X2
well it's the sum over X1 X2 of G of X1
G of X2. And now we can just break up
this sum.
It's the sum on x1 of g of x1
times the sum on x2 of g of x2
0 * 0.
Okay. Does that look okay to people?
Okay. Then there's the minor case that
they're parallel and um
okay, I don't have anything super
instructive to say about this case. They
might as well both be p parallel to the
x2 axis.
It's not hard to compute it by hand. and
and you'll see that it's negative.
So I I'm going to not do it on the board
because I think it's not very
illuminating.
Okay, so that's one way to prove the key
lema.
Uh but the key lema also the whole setup
also has a nice relationship to for a
analysis and and you can use we can also
use for a analysis to to prove the key
lema and if we do it that way we can
sort of justify in a precise way saying
that something is the zero frequency
part or the high frequency part.
Okay.
[Applause]
Okay. So let me remind everybody how
fora analysis works over finite fields.
Okay. So um
I have a
for analysis based on having some like
group homorphism from your group into C
star. So I'm going to call it E. So E is
a map from FQ to C star. Think of it as
FQ with addition. So this is a grouping
group. That's an aelion group. Complex
numbers with multiplication. This is a
homorphism
and I want it to be non-trivial. does
not send does not just send everything
to one.
Okay. So for example, if Q= P is prime,
then it would be E of X is E 2I I X
over P.
And if Q is not prime, it takes a little
bit more doing to write down a
homorphism, but there but there is one
that's not true.
Okay. Um so now suppose I have a
function on fq to the d.
It has a fora transform. Um so the for
transform of c
is defined to be sum over q and fq to
the d f ofx d ofx
c.
So this x c this is a dotproduct. It's
just x1 c1 plus x2 c2 and so on.
So that's the 4 a transform and it looks
more or less uh like how you know how it
looks in uklidian space.
Okay.
So this c also lives in um
inf.
There are two main really fundamental
theorems about transform. One of them is
forier inversion and the other one is
planer theorem as orthogonality and in
the finite field setting they work out
in the following way. So theorem one um
for a inversion
f ofx is the sum c in fq to the d and
here we need to take an average
f of c e of x dot c.
So it looks like 4A inversion in
uklitian space although there's this
average here maybe worth saying that
there are several reasonable conventions
that you might put about you know
somewhere in this setup we need to
divide something by some powers of Q and
there are several reasonable conventions
and you see different conventions in
different places um but anyway this is
one that I picked um and I I never
remember it so I always take the
function one and comput it for a
transform and check that this works and
that tells May I have this factor?
Okay. And theorem two is planer.
So that says that if I take the sum
over fq to the d of f ofx g of xar
then that's equivalent to a sum on the 4
a side. And there's also a
normalization. So that's 1 / q to the d
sum x and sum c
and f q to the d f of c g hat of c bar.
So again if you compute a simple example
you'll see that this is the right
normalization.
Okay.
So now if you take the characteristic
function of a line you can take its fora
transform and something interesting
happens that represents uh important
connection between I don't know between
lines and the 4A transform and and
therefore between projection theory and
the 4A transform. So okay so here's what
happens. So suppose L is an athine line
in FQ ^2
or or really the characteristic function
of the alpha.
Okay. So then it has a perp so L perp is
the set of C. So that um c do x1 - x2 is
zero for any x1 x2 in the line.
So in uklitian space this would look
like this. So
so here's my line l
uh this is x space
and then over here in c space I would
have
l.
Notice that L perp always goes through
zero.
So here's here's my X1 and X2.
So this direction here is a tangent
direction to L and then these are the
perpendicular directions.
All right. So
proposition
if you take L hat of C and you take its
absolute value there are two cases
one of them is that you get Q and that's
if C is in LP and the other one is you
get zero and that's if C is not in LP.
So the for transform of a line first of
all has is very sparse. It's zero almost
everywhere. The only places where it's
not zero are on this perpendicular line.
Okay. So, um I think it is a good
experience to uh compute this out and
check that it happens. When you write
down this sum,
the sum
will reduce to a geometric series and
then you can sum the geometric series
and you can see exactly what happens.
So this is an exercise
on the homework.
Okay. And now um okay so we also do this
thing of subtracting off the mean
and and that has a very natural
interpretation in for analysis.
Um let's erase this.
Okay.
So,
so if you have a function g from f q to
the d goes to c, then we can write g as
1 / q to the d sum over c g hat of c e
of x c. And one of these frequencies is
often very special, namely the frequency
zero. So I'm just going to break up this
sum. It's 1 / q to the d g hat of zero
plus um the sum over the nonzero c 1 / q
to the d
g had x c e of x.
All right. So if you think about what
this is, ghat of 0 is just the sum of
the values of g and then I divide by
that I get this formula here. That's the
mean value of G.
So this is G knot and it's the mean
value of G.
And this thing here we'll call G high.
G high is G minus its mean value. So it
has mean zero.
Okay. So that's what we did with our
lens. This is the zero frequency part of
L and this is the nonzero frequency or I
called it high frequency part of L. So
from from from the for analysis point of
view that that's what that's what these
things precisely mean.
Okay. Now we can put this together
to give a a new explanation of the key
orthogonality lama.
Um
where should I put it?
Yeah. So we we gave one proof of the key
lama over here. We can do now another
one.
All right. So let's give the forier
proof
of the key lama.
uh we'll still do the main case
which is that L1 and L2 are not parallel
and that's where we get literal
orthogonality then we get that the sum
of L1H of X L2 H of X is Z
how will we do it we'll evaluate it with
planer Wrap.
Okay. So that's planer theorem 2. And
now I have the high part here. What does
the high part mean? The high part means
I crossed out the zero frequency.
So this is 1 over Q ^2 times the sum on
nonzero C
L1 hat of C L2 hat.
So if if you compare the for transform
of L1 and L1 high, the only difference
is the zero frequency. I take I take the
zero frequency here and I throw it out.
All the other ones are the same. So this
is the same as this.
Okay. Now I'll make a picture. Um so
here in in X space I have a line um
I have a line L1 and I have a line L2.
What happens in for space C space? Well,
there's uh L1 per
and then there's L2 per
and L1 P and L2 per intersect only at
zero.
So here I'm summing over nonzero
frequencies.
So if C is non zero then C is not so
either C is not in L1 per or C is not in
L2 per
because those two those two purps they
only intersect at the origin.
Okay. But this function is only
supported when C is in L1 per and this
one is only supported when C is in L2
perp. So at every C in this sum, one of
these guys is zero. So this is
or to put it a little bit differently,
uh these two functions have disjoint for
a support.
So they are orthogonal.
Okay,
so those are these are the two main
classical techniques of projection
theory. The double counting argument and
the forthagonality argument. Um they're
each not that difficult. Um, but it
actually is really pretty hard to go
beyond them even though there's a lot of
situations where they're they're not
sharp. That's a that's a theme that
we'll get to. Um, but before we get to
that theme, we'll explore these for a
while. Um, and we'll see that uh a bunch
of people have used them in fact in
different areas of math to do some
different different things that things
that I think are interesting.
Um,
so the next thing that we'll do is the
the more analytic setting of working in
R2 instead of over a finite field and
having balls instead of points. And I I
sort of waved my hands about it uh last
class about exactly what we would try to
prove. Um and um uh so in our in our
last 10 minutes I'll introduce the setup
with balls and I'll tell you what are
the analog of theorem one and theorem
two and this conjecture.
Um
okay and then we'll see we'll see the
proofs of all that next class and we'll
see the proofs are morally the same as
these proofs in finite fields but with a
little bit of extra technical issues
from uh from working in uklitian space.
Okay.
Um.
All right. So, let's do a setup with
balls.
Setup in R2
with balls.
All right. So, our set X is going to be
a set of disjoint
unit balls
in a large ball.
And then D, our set of directions. I'll
think of it as a subset of S1. So, this
is a set of directions that we'll do
projections in.
and they will also be disjoint and what
I'm going to put here is that they're 1
/ r separated.
So you take so these these um you can
think of d as a set of angles and any
two angles are at least 1 / r apart from
each other. The reason for that is if
they were closer together than that the
two projections would basically be the
same in terms of how they what they do
to a set of unit balls in in a ball of
radius r.
Okay. So that's x and d. And then our s
s of xd
is the maximum over any direction in our
set of directions of the size of the
projection of x in that direction. So
this is a one-dimensional set. It's
basically a set of unit intervals. And
and this this absolute value is its
length.
Okay.
All right. So, we could ask just in
terms of the size of X and the size of
D, what can you say about S and how does
it compare to the finite field case? And
we saw last time that it's rather
different from um the finite field case
because of an example where X is very
clumped together.
Um okay, so let me put up here a couple
of examples in our new geometric setup.
Okay. So, example one
is a square grid
that's spaced out.
Okay. So, it looks like this.
It's going to be an n byn grid.
And um I'm going to it's inside of an R
ball, but I'm going to make it as spread
out as possible. And so the distance
here is about r.
So that's my sax.
Okay. And d could be the same as before.
It could be the directions
with slope
um a1 over a2 where a1 and a2 are
integers going from one up to a.
Okay. And if you if you compute how big
the projection is, it's the same as
before.
A * n the same that's the same thing we
got before at the beginning of class.
except that the projection is never
bigger than r. You know, you project a
whole ball of radius r, you get an
interval of length r. So, it's never
bigger than that. So, I'll put the
minimum the same.
Okay, there was one scenario. This is an
integer grid, which was an important
example before. But another thing you
can do is you can take these points and
clump them way together.
So example two
is a clump.
So I take a ball of radius n and I fill
it with unit balls.
So we still have the number of balls is
around n^ squ but they're much more
clumped together.
And when you do that, pi theta of x is
only around n. You know, you project
this set x in any direction, it'll be an
interval of length n. And so that's true
for everything.
And if you compare these examples,
you'll see that this one uh has has a
much smaller has much bigger s than uh
sorry, much smaller s's than than this
one. This example is much more extreme
than the grid.
Okay,
so it turns out that just asking the
question, if you know the cardality of X
and you know the cardality of D, um what
can you say about S? Uh we we'll answer
that question. That's a somewhat
interesting question and and we'll
answer it. Um but it's not the most
interesting question. the the phenomenon
there's a phenomenon that's more
interesting which is that as the points
get spread out you get stronger
estimates.
Okay. So what does it mean that the
points get spread out? We need to have
some rules about it or you know how do
we make that precise that they're spread
out. Um so being clumped together means
there are a lot of points in a small
ball and we can quantify that in the
following way.
N subx of R is the maximum over any
choice of center
of the size of X in the ball around
center C with radius R.
So you can see that this quantity would
be quite large in this example
especially if you took little r to be n
and it would be a lot smaller in this
example. So that point is more spread
out.
Okay. And it turns out it doesn't just
matter how our set of points is spaced.
It also matters how our set of
directions is spaced.
So we'll talk about that also. So n subd
of r is the maximum
um over any
actually I'll give this another letter.
I'll call it row. Any arc
um of length row
in s1. So we have the directions as a
subset of S1 of the number
of the directions in the arc.
So for you pick a particular parameters
a size row and you ask how many uh
directions are there in in an arc of
size row. So that's this thing.
Okay. Um so you could describe the our
goal in projection theory in uklidian
space in the following way. Given some
information about this thing and that
thing try to estimate um uh s and d and
x.
Um
you can phrase it that way. Um and then
there's a whole world of questions
because there's a lot of different
things you could assume about nx and n
uh d. There's one particular scenario uh
one particular set of assumptions that
has been investigated a lot and it seems
it's not the only interesting one but it
seems to be uh important and and uh a
good thing to focus on.
So we could say that X is a alpha
dimensional
set of balls.
F
the total number of balls is around R to
the alpha
and N sub R of X is less than little R
to the alpha.
This numerology is sort of consistent
with how fractals behave.
Okay. And there's a and then you can
make a similar definition for D.
Maybe people feel it's not so I know
people might feel it's not so clear why
to focus on this particular set of
conditions. We can talk about it. Uh
okay. Anyway, so
so the final thing is that if you take
this set of conditions, then we can do a
version in uklidian space of the
conjecture and theorem one and theorem 2
and all the numbers match up and we can
prove a version of theorem one that
looks just like that with this double
counting and we can prove a version of
theorem two that looks just like that
with for analysis
and we have a conjecture that looks just
like that.
Um and um the the big recent result that
I hinted at in the first class is that
that that the analog of that conjecture
is proven.
Okay. So at the beginning of class on
Tuesday, I will write all those things
down and then we'll um and then we'll do
analysis in R2 and we'll and we'll prove
theorem one. Theorem one prime and
theorem two prime.
Okay, great. We'll stop there. Have a
great weekend and I will see you next
week.