hello everybody can people hear me in
the back is it working cool okay so um I
believe that uh last time we started uh
counting and you saw the uh the sumr in
particular um so let's uh let's take a
look at a quick example so I've got a a
very standard deck of playing cards here
as you can see uh how many kings and
queens are
there eight why is
that yeah so the the the answer was that
there are four suits uh for for each
rank we've got therefore Four Kings Four
Queens nothing is both a king and a
queen so you can kind of just add them
together right you've got eight cards
that are either Kings or Queens okay uh
what if the sets are not disjoint so
what if I instead wanted to count the
number of cards that are either hearts
or face
cards so that then what do I
do so I've got uh you know 12 face cards
here my my hands are a little bit too
small for playing cards but you know
hopefully you can roughly see right how
many hearts are
there yeah 13 Hearts so 13 hearts in one
hand
12 face cards in the other so uh
25 no what's gone
wrong can anybody tell me what's gone
wrong
yeah yeah I've got two kings of Hearts
here so I'm I'm cheating uh okay so what
what do
yeah exactly so the answer was you know
I've got three cards that are both
hearts and face cards right so these are
the three cards that I've counted twice
right I've got uh two each of these
three
cards so if I just like discard one copy
then I'll be fine right so I subtract
off everything that's in the
intersection uh so I had 25 before
subtract off those three and I end up
with 22 that are either hearts or uh
well these cards are too big maybe I
should have actually brought standard
cards uh I've got 22 cards that are
either hearts or or face cards okay does
that make sense to
people okay so this is what we call the
uh inclusion exclusion role or the
principle of inclusion and
exclusion so often abbreviated as uh Pi
for principle of inclusion exclusion
okay so if I have two two sets A and
B and I want to compute their Union
right uh the size of this Union oh well
this chalk is terrible um
sorry the size of their Union is going
to be the sizes of the individual
sets minus the size of the
intersection
okay does that make sense to everybody
maybe a little bit easier to see if we
uh draw a picture right
so hopefully people REM remember uh ven
diagrams from uh from grade school yeah
maybe no well this is a ven diagram
couple of overlapping circles so maybe
we've got hearts on one side and we've
got uh faces on the other right but then
we've got some things that are in the
middle so this can be our set a this can
be our set B and here we've got King of
Hearts
Queen of Hearts and Jack of
FS okay so if we want to compute the
size of the Union right we're going to
take the things that are like only on
the heart side the things that are only
on the face side and then the things
that are in the intersection we only
want to count them once right but that's
counted in both of A and B right so
we're going to add together the sizes of
A and B and then subtract out the middle
okay does that make sense to
everybody okay so what happens if we
have three sets
any
ideas well can we do something similar
so let's draw a three-way vend diagram
this
time okay so we've got a here B here C
here so is it true that whoops a union B
Union C
C is equal to the
sum of the individual sets minus the
parway
intersections oops that should be a
b is this
true yeah
yeah okay so your classmates's
observation was that uh these
intersections themselves overlap right
so if we think about how many times
we've counted each each item right
everything here we've only counted once
okay that's that's fairly
easy uh what about the things in these
uh kind of weirdly shaped segments right
so those appear in you know two of the
individual sets and in one of the par
wise intersections so we've also counted
these
ones okay but now we've got a problem in
the middle right how many times have we
counted this well we've counted it once
for a once for B once for C and then
we've subtracted it once each for a
intersect B A intersect C and B
intersect C Okay so we've counted this
zero times in
total okay so what we actually want is
to add back in the three-way
intersection
okay and that gives us the correct
formula okay does does that make sense
to
everybody
yeah okay so let's take a look at an
example
then uh how
many uh numbers uh K in the range from 1
to
n are co-prime with n
how could we figure this
out and those of you who already know
the toen function don't invoke
that how could we use uh the principle
of inclusion exclusion to compute this
any
ideas tentative hands
maybe yeah see
okay so the idea was look at uh you know
which which numbers uh share prime
factor with n okay so for Simplicity
let's assume for now that n is the
product of say three primes PQ and
R
okay so then how could we figure out how
many things share a factor of
P
yeah you div y right yeah so they're
going to be uh n/ P that share a factor
of of P so let's say that
uh let's call the set a
subp the uh set of numbers and the the
subset of these numbers that that share
a factor of P okay so they're going to
be n/ P of those what about the things
that share a factor of
Q same thing right so similarly we can
define a sub Q to be the the set of
numbers that share a factor of
Q and then we've got this and similarly
a subr is going to be the set of things
that share a factor of
R
okay now what exactly are we trying to
compute what we really want is the
complement of the Union of these three
sets right so we're trying to
compute the size of n
minus a union
AQ Union a
r okay
okay so now we can use inclusion
exclusion we're trying to compute the
union of this set right that's going to
be the sum of the sizes of the
individual
sets right minus the oh I did this the
wrong way around didn't
I uh oh no I didn't that was the right
one so the the sum of the individual
sizes minus the sum of the parse uh
intersections plus the sum of the
three-way intersection okay so what are
the sizes of these
intersections what's the size of the
intersection of AP and AQ
yeah yeah so the answer was n/
PQ right so p and Q are distinct primes
if something shares both a factor of p
and a factor of Q it has to be a
multiple of
PQ okay so they're n/ PQ of
those similarly we have n / p
r and N /
QR what what about the three-way
intersection how many things share a
factor of PQ and
R
yeah yeah it's just n itself so minus
one
okay and if you do some uh you know
messy algebra this turns out to uh P
minus one Q - one
r -
one which is also equal to n * 1 - 1 /
p uh 1 - 1 /
Q 1 - 1 /
R
okay so hopefully it's not too hard to
see how this could generalize right uh
to get you know the more general form of
of oil
totient okay does this application make
sense to
people any questions
yeah oh that's just the assumption that
we made you for the sake of
example
okay so that's inclusion exclusion with
uh two or three sets but more generally
you can kind of continue the pattern
right so if you have say n sets uh A1
A2 all the way up to a
subn and you want to figure out the
union of all of these
right so as we did before we're going to
add up the individual sizes of the uh uh
of the individual
sets
Okay then we're going to subtract off
the pawise
intersections
okay then we're going to add in the
three-way intersections
right and we're just going to keep on
going okay until eventually we get to
you know plus or minus the size of the
nway intersection so A1 cap A2 Cap all
the way to a
subn
okay and the the sign on that last term
will depend on you know the parody of n
okay does that make sense to
people so perhaps a more formal way of
expressing
this is the
following so suppose we have some set
u uh which we're going to say is a union
of
uh n
sets Okay so this is going to be our
universe of discourse okay uh and so
this means that you know by
convention if we intersect no sets right
this is just going to be uh
U okay so just like if we Union no sets
we start with nothing and then you know
start unioning in more things and we
should get a union of sets
if we start with everything and then
start intersecting we should get an
intersection of sets so that's that's
where this convention comes from
yeah oh uh this this notation this
notation both oh okay so this is kind of
like the uh the big Sigma right so uh
just how this represents like an nway
addition uh this represents an nway
Union and this represents an nway
intersection
right uh so we've got this is saying
we've got a union of n sets like A1
Union A2 Union A3 Union a n
okay uh and this is saying you know
we've got an intersection of n sets but
n is zero so by convention we just take
that to be the entire universe
sorry uh the the question is why are we
setting both the union and the
intersection to be U uh this is just how
we're defining youu this is a
convention right so if if you intersect
no sets right you should get everything
just like if you multiply no numbers you
should get one it's kind of similar to
that right like you know you start with
everything and then you intersect one
you should get the set that you that you
intersected in
right okay so this is just a convention
uh if you prefer you can just write in U
itself and and what I'm about to write
that might make it easier to understand
sorry about
that
uh
okay so the theorem is
that uh
if you look at all subsets of the
numbers up to n right and you take uh
the like ey way
intersection of these
AIS right and then multiply it by minus
one to the size of
I this should give you zero
okay so now if you want to think about
this in the case of the
2way inclusion exclusion
here right so this is saying uh you know
zero equals like we move the the union
over to the right hand side okay or I
guess we're moving everything over to
the left hand side based on what I've
written okay yeah
okay uh so this formula is basically
what we were doing here like we're we're
kind of taking uh eyeway
intersections and we're you know
flipping the sign on on successive you
know sizes of I right and we're just
kind of moving this Union over to the
other side right so we get
zero okay
so if that formula is is too much you
can think about the previous formula but
uh
yeah okay so the the question was the
like what is the difference between big
and little I so big I is a set of
indices little I is an individual IND
index in that
set okay
so we're summing over you know all
subsets of the numbers up to n
right and then for each of those subsets
we're taking the intersection of the
relevant
AIS right so over here we've got a is
you know just it corresponds to the
subset just
one B corresponds to the subset 2 uh a
intersect B corresponds to the subset
you know 1 comma 2 and a union B
corresponds to the empty subset okay so
these are all of the subsets of uh the
integers one and two does that make
sense
question uh size of I right because I is
a set yeah so the question is why do we
have absolute value here that's the the
cardinality
okay so how could we prove
this well let's look at some X okay so
say that you know we've got some element
X of our universe
how many times do we count X on this
left hand
side like how many of these terms does
it appear
in well it's going to be in all of the
terms where X is in you know all of
these uh AIS okay so if we say like I
subx
is the set of
indices with uh X and
AI
okay right it's going to be in the uh I
subx
set it's also going to be in the in like
every subset of I
subx okay
does that make sense do people see why
right if x is in sets one and two right
it's going to be in the uh in the in the
intersection where we've got you know I
is 1 two it's also going to be in the
intersection where I is one or where I
is two or where I is
empty
okay but now how much does it contribute
to the left hand side for each of these
well how many subsets of I subx have
even size and how many have odd
size
yeah yeah it's half each right so for
the ones of odd size we're contributing
minus one to the left hand side for the
ones of even size we're contributing
positive one to the right hand side or
to the left hand
side right so because they're half and
half those all cancel
okay
[Music]
so X
contributes +
one to left hand
side for each even
size
subset of I subx
and it contributes minus one to the left
hand
side for
each odd siiz
subset okay so when we add when we add
all of those together we get
zero okay so every element of our
universe contributes zero to the left
hand side
so we get
zero
okay does that make sense to
people
yeah uh yes we're we're looking at the
uh sorry question was are those both
supposed to be left hand side we're
looking at what x contributes to this
sum okay like how many of these terms
does it contribute positively to how
many does it contribute negatively to so
whenever the uh size of I is even it's
going to contribute positively if it's
contained in that intersection whenever
the size of I is odd it'll contribute
negatively when it's in the intersection
okay
yeah uh
sorry the the question was how do we
construct a big I so that the
intersection is the empty
Set
uh okay let let me let me see if I'm
understanding um you are trying to find
an I such that uh this is empty or such
that this is empty
this one okay so we don't care uh we are
looking at the sets that contain X so
they should never be
empty
okay like we're we're kind of looking at
uh you know what we had here like how
many times have we counted
X
okay so if this is still confusing uh
please review the lecture notes or uh
you know it's not important that the
proof is not important the most
important thing is you know knowing how
to use it right so you want to add
together the the uh the single sets
subtract off the the parse intersections
add together the three-way intersections
Etc
okay so let's move on to the second
topic for
today Pidgey hole principle
okay has anybody heard of this
before yeah okay uh so the pidy hole
principle it gets its name from you know
Medieval Times you have uh a bunch of
you know Pidgey holes that are supposed
to contain pidgeys uh but what if you
have more pidgeys than Pidgey holes
right what
happens well two of them have to share
right two of them get squished okay so
that's basically what the uh what the
pidal principle is saying if we have two
sets A and
B where uh the size of a is greater than
the size of
B
and F from A to
B is total right then F cannot be
injective
right so if a is our set of pigeons
right B is our set of pigeon holes and F
is saying you know pigeon a lives in
pigeon hole B
right uh this should be a total function
right like every Pidgey should have a
home right we don't want to have
homeless
pidgeys uh so it's a total
function right but that means that it
can't be injective meaning that there
have to be two pigeons that share a
pigeon
hole
okay so let's look at a couple of
[Applause]
examples do we still have 26 students in
the room
nice not too many students have dropped
okay so there are more than 26 students
in the room so at least two of you uh
share the first letter of your first
name right uh so we've got well at least
students and 26 letters of the
alphabet so if we map every student
right right to the first letter of their
first name right that's a total function
so it can't be
injective okay so two students must
share
okay does that example make
sense
right okay uh what if I've got n
differently colored pairs of socks
right don't worry about
it how many socks do I need to pull out
of my drawer to ensure that I get two of
the same
color
sorry yeah the answer was uh n plus one
right so in my case
two so if I've got n socks or sorry n
colors of
socks need n+
one to guarantee a
pair okay so I've been a little bit
handwavy with this
one when you're trying to prove
something with the pigeon hole principle
you generally need to be very careful
about what your pigeons are what your
pigeon holes are and what the map
between them
is
okay so what are those three elements in
this case
maybe we could phrase it instead as you
know if I have n plus one then it
guarantees a
pair
yeah okay so a is the set of socks
and B is a set of
colors and the map is going to map the
sock to its
color okay does that make sense to
everybody
okay uh does anybody know what the
population of Boston
is are you looking at the lecture
notes oh
okay yeah about 650,000 as of you know
however many decades ago these lecture
notes were written um I don't actually
know that that was very long ago it
could be current
[Applause]
is anybody a uh human biology nerd does
anybody know how many hairs humans
have so it turns out humans
have less than about
200,000
hairs okay
so what does the pitch and hole
principle tell us
here any
ideas getting some face Palms
yeah oh good point so the answer was at
least three uh humans in Boston have the
same number of
pairis okay so as stated all we know is
that you know at least two bostonians
have the same number of hairs right so
does that mean that there's somebody
with the same number of hairs as me
not necessarily right uh so we know that
there exists two bostonians we don't
know who they are right uh this this is
non-constructive right it it only tells
us of
existence uh but your your colleague
also brings up another good point uh
because this 650,000 is so much larger
than the 200,000 we can actually say
something stronger right like all we
need is is 200,000 plus 1 right that'll
give us a a a of two
bostonians right we've actually got more
than three times that number right so
there are more than three
bostonians who have the same number of
hairs so in fact we can conclude that
there are at least four
bostonians who all have the same number
of
hairs
okay does that make sense to everybody
yeah
did ah so the the question was how did
we get the four
right so this is what we call the
generalized pigeon hole
principle okay so up here right we just
said you know if a is is larger than
b but if we have the stronger condition
that if a is larger than K *
B right right then we've got a K plus
1way Collision not just a two-way
Collision
okay so because you know we have 650,000
which is more than three times 200,000
we've got a 3 plus oneway Collision not
just a three-way Collision does that
make sense
yeah yeah uh I suppose we could include
zero but I guess there're everybody
knows that there're are bald bostonians
so maybe we exclude that um but yeah
every natural number from uh from one up
to 200,000 was is going to be our B and
our a is going to be the set of all
bostonians right and we are mapping a
person to the number of pairs that they
have
okay okay so you can like you can
basically always use the generalized uh
pigeon hole principle if you would you
know just like strong induction will
always work whenever whenever weak
induction
does uh you could always set k equal 1
right
uh but like the the proof is basically
the same um and if you use these to uh
to to prove things about functions uh
the proofs can often be you know very
short very simple uh but they can Al
they can also sometimes require some
cleverness okay so it it may not always
be obvious what a b and F should be okay
so here here's a slightly more involved
example okay so we have an 8 by8 chest
board and 33
Rooks does everybody know how uh how
chess works you know
vaguely okay so Rooks can move along you
know ranks or files right ranks or files
sorry um so we would like to place these
these Rooks so that uh no five or so
that any set of five right uh they don't
all attack each
other or no I I phrased that wrong uh so
we want to find five of them where none
of them attack each other right so
basically we want them all to be in
distinct uh rows and files so if we've
got you know something like
this right if we have a rook here a rook
here and a rook here those three do not
attack each other okay so we're trying
to find a set of five like that right
like no two of them share a column or a
row does the uh does the setup make
sense
okay how could we do
that rather how could we prove the
existence of such a
set maybe it would help to draw out the
chessboard let's
see one two
three
four five six
7 one two three
four five six seven
okay there's our wonky chest board
okay so how could we do this any
ideas
yeah okay so the answer is if we place
four Rooks they cover at most 2 to the
five
squares
uh is that
true uh I don't think that's true right
like if we place Rooks in these four uh
squares right they're going to cover 3/4
of the
chessboard okay uh yes
uh that's
right
pardon uh so what what is your solution
then oh oh sorry I think you may have
misunderstood the problem um you know we
we have 33 Rooks right we're trying to
find a set of five that don't attack
each other we're we're given the
placement right we're not allowed to
just Place five Rooks if we could place
them then yeah we could we could you
know place them along a diagonal and
then we've got eight right so like you
know some of these have have Rooks we
don't get to control where
right right and we're trying to find
some subset of these uh some subset of
five of these that don't attack each
other
does the problem setup make
sense maybe yes no
yeah okay so how could we use the pigeon
hole principle
here well perhaps let's start with the
easiest element what should our pigeons
be what are we trying to make Collide
yeah Rooks yeah so our pigeons are going
to be the Rooks and I've lost my
Eraser
okay
now what should our pigeon holes
be right we want
we want to set it up so that if we get a
five-way
collision right those five Rooks do not
attack each
other
yeah yeah so the answer was you know
we're placing these Rooks on the chest
board so let's make the pigeon holes the
uh the squares of the chest board
okay so you are off to a good start
that's a good idea uh the problem right
now is that we've got uh fewer Rooks
than squares on the
chessboard okay so what we really want
is a five-way collision right so we want
to ensure that we have more than four
times as many Brooks as pigeon
holes okay so is there a way that we can
modify your
solution uh to make you know fewer
things where Collision is still good for
us so can we can we subdivide our
squares so we have
yeah
sorry okay the the answer was squares
that don't have rope Rooks um that's not
going to be very helpful right like
we're we're assigning Rooks to Pigeon
holes so the the you know the map should
map Rooks to you know occupied squares
of of some
sort but how could we maybe split up the
chessboard into eight pigeon holes right
if we have eight pigeon holes 33 Rooks
right that's more than four times as
many so we get a five-way
collision what could our eight sets of
squares be
yeah colums okay so if we have five
Rooks in a column is that
helpful now all of those Works attack
each other
then you're getting close though
yeah yeah so the answer was you know
diagonals but then offset
them okay so I'm going to number all of
these squares so so everything numbered
one is going to be our first pigeon hole
okay so if we get five Rooks along the
main diagonal like all of them are going
to be in different rows and different
columns so they won't attack each other
okay so that's good right number two is
going to be offset by
one but then we're also going to wrap
around down
here okay so once again we've got eight
squares that are all in different rows
and different columns so if we get five
on you know two squares they also don't
attack each other okay and we can
continue in this way right three goes
along
here and then these two squares
Etc
okay so now we have uh eight pigeon
holes 33 Rooks so that's more than four
times as many we get a five-way
collision uh whichever you know number
of square has that five-way Collision
those are five Rooks that don't attack
each
other
okay does does that make sense to
everybody so it took a little bit of
creativity to come up with the pigeon
holes
here but once we have that the proof is
fairly straightforward
okay so let's change gears a little bit
and move on to uh the last counting
technique for
today which we call combinatorial
proofs or double
counting
oops okay okay so I like to think of
this as somewhat similar to uh I believe
you've seen the baction rule earlier
right so if you have two sets and you
can come up with a baction between them
then those two sets have the same size
right well similarly if you have two
sizes and a single set that shares those
sizes right those sizes must be equal
okay so basically this is a proof
technique where we take a set and kind
of count it in two different ways okay
and that can give us some nice
combinatorial
identities so for
instance we have this identity have
people seen this one
before
no okay so if you uh if you sum up and
choose k for you know all K from 0 to n
you just get 2 the
N so if you haven't seen it before it's
you know perhaps a little bit
counterintuitive right like we've got a
summation of you know a bunch of things
involving factorials but it turns out to
be some nice uh
exponential
okay so how could we prove
this how could we come up with a
set that we can count you know both as
this expression
and as this
expression any
ideas
yeah so the solution was count length
and binary sequences
okay so how does that give you each side
of the uh of the
equality
okay exactly
yeah so the the right hand side is
fairly straightforward
right right if we're counting length and
binary sequences like every uh position
you can either have zero or one right so
product rule gives us to the
n and for the left hand
side we're going to partition based on
how many ones there are in our
sequence
okay so our sequence could have any
number of ones from0 up to n
inclusive okay so and all of these are
disjoint right if it has three ones it
can't also have eight
ones okay so by our sum rule we can just
sum up all of the sizes of those
sets what is the size of the set of
sequences that has say three ones
anybody how many binary sequences of
length n have three
ones n choose three yeah or more
generally you know they n choose k
with
k1s and you know K from one through uh
from zero through
n form a partition of our
set
okay so if we sum up all of these
binomial coefficients from 0 to
n right
we're also going to get the the number
of length then binary
sequences okay does that does that make
sense to
everybody okay does the proof technique
make sense to everybody right we're
we're taking a single set and we're
counting it in two different
ways right and each way of counting
gives us a different expression so those
two expressions must be
equal
okay so the key here you know is
choosing the right set to
count so as it turns out that's actually
a special case of a uh of a nice
theorem uh so we we've been using
binomial coefficients quite a lot right
these uh n choose K uh terms does
anybody know their
eponym any
ideas has anybody encountered the
binomial theorem
before no okay well let's take a
look Okay so
okay
so this here is what we call a binomial
right uh you know sum of two
monomials uh and the binomial theorem
says that if we take a binomial raise it
to the N power right then we get you
know basically the same thing as we had
on the left hand side over there but you
know we've got these uh powers of X and
Y
okay and you know by convention 0 to the
0o we just say that that's equal to
one
okay so the uh
uh the proof
does anybody know how we might prove
this it's fairly similar to what we just
did well what happens if we expand out
the left hand
side what do we get
yeah okay uh so the answer was we got
the coefficients of Pascal's triangle uh
you've skipped a couple of
steps more immediately what do we
get like say if n equals 2 what do we
get
we get XX plus X Y plus YX plus y y
right like we've basically got a bunch
of binary sequences of x's and
y's
okay so this gives us a
sum of 2 to the N uh
terms of the
form uh and I'll call it you know B1 B2
up to
BN where each
B is either X or
Y
okay so now how do we get Pascal out of
that
so you're talking about coefficients
what are these Coe like what are the
coefficients of where are we getting the
coefficients not quite of X and
Y so we're going to want to group like
terms right so both multiplication and
addition are commutative so we can kind
of fiddle around with uh each of those
terms and you know put all the X's at
the beginning and the Y's at the end and
then we can also rearrange the terms so
that you know we put like terms
together okay so we can group them into
a bunch of
uh terms of the form at x k * y nus
k uh and then multiplied by su
coefficient C
subk
okay so now as your colleague was saying
right those C subk are going to be you
know the entries of Pascal's triangle
they're going to be the uh binomial
coefficients okay why is that
well how many terms are there of this
form well it could come from putting the
K x's in you know any K places from
among the uh uh the N possible places
right so you've got n choose K possible
places or possible ways to place the X's
the Y's will be the the remaining ones
uh and each of those gives you a
different term
okay so C
subk is going to be n k similar to
above does that make sense to
everybody so if we specifically put in X
and Y are both equal to one then we
recover what we had uh originally
you may also have uh encountered uh a
form of this theorem where y equals 1
have have people seen that before like 1
plus x to the uh to the
N possibly maybe
not okay well it is a useful theorem the
coefficients on the terms are the uh you
know n chose K the binomial coefficients
and you know this is where their name
comes
from okay and uh more generally you can
also get the uh multinomial theorem in
the same way right if you have uh you
know X Plus y+ Z for instance raise that
to the nth power uh you start getting
multinomial coefficients instead of
binomial
coefficients okay
yeah sorry I'm moving all the way over
here I didn't plan this up very well
okay so for the multinomial theor right
if we have a multinomial here like we've
got mx's instead of just two right
uh if we sum all those up and then raise
it to the N power we can use essentially
the same proof to show that this is
going to be the sum over all uh
sequences
K1
K2 all the way up to K
subm uh where these all sum up to
n of the multinomial coefficient and
choose K1 K2
up to
km of you know similar to the uh x to
the k y the N minus K term we had over
there this time we've got a product of M
things
okay so essentially the same proof right
uh you know if we uh uh if we think of
the uh the binom coefficients right as
you know multinomial coefficients where
we've only got two
things right you can kind of see how it
expands right
uh we're going to look at you know all
possible ways that you could you know
Place x1's x2s x3s
Etc uh among the N different
terms
uh and each of those is going to give us
a different term that we can then
combine uh when we're grouping like
terms does that make sense to
people so the number of those the number
of ways that you can you know permute
those uh those nend
things that's just going to be this
multinomial coefficient here
[Applause]
okay are people happy with the uh
binomial multinomial
coefficients and the binomial
multinomial theorems yeah
uh
so the the question is uh what what does
this mean um is this the notation that
you saw in the bookkeeper uh
recitation uh perhaps not if if not this
is uh equal to n factorial
/ K1 factorial K2
factorial all the way up to km factorial
okay so it's kind of an extension of the
binomial coefficients right with the
binomial coefficients you just have you
know two k that sum to
n uh and we also kind of simplify the
notation by just you know dropping one
of the uh dropping one of the ks because
it's redundant in that
case uh but you know for the multinomial
coefficients we have you know a bunch of
KS that sum to n instead of just two uh
we're going to divide n factorial by you
know the product of all of them
okay does that does that make sense does
that answer your question
okay any other questions about binomial
multinomial
theorems
yeah sorry oh question what is the pi uh
so this is an analog of Sigma but for
products instead of sums so we're saying
you know x i to the Ki like multiplied
over all possible I so X1 to the K1 * X2
to the k 2 time X3 to the K3
Etc
okay so Pi for
product any other
questions okay so why don't we move on
to another useful identity that we can
prove using a uh a combinatorial
proof
oops and choose k
equals n -1 choose Kus
one
plus nus one choose
K okay who has seen this before I know
that at least one of you
has few hands
okay uh so uh we could prove it you know
algebraically just you know writing them
out with factorials and you know doing a
bunch of fiddly garbage uh but that
seems a bit difficult so let's use a
double counting proof instead
okay how might we use a double counting
proof to prove this
identity what set could we try and count
any
ideas
yeah yeah good answer okay so the the
answer was uh you know once again we can
look at binary sequences of length n but
this time we're going to restrict it to
Binary sequences of length n that
specifically have
k1s okay so
count uh binary
sequences of length
n with
k1s okay
now how many of those are
there does that give us one of our two
expressions
easily if so
which
yeah
sorry yeah so essentially by definition
right like this is equal to the the size
of this set is going to be and choose k
okay
so let's call this set
s okay how could we also make S equal to
the right hand side
does this give us any ideas
yeah
answer
yeah yeah so the the answer was
essentially we're going to par our set
okay so what are we partitioning on well
we're going to look at the last bit of
the
sequence
okay
[Music]
so okay so so we've got two cases right
the last bit can either be zero or one
it can't be both right so we've got you
know we've got a
partition okay that means that we can
use the sum
rule we can count each of these sets
individually and then add their sizes
together that'll give us the size of our
original
set
okay so how many length and sequence
with k1s have a one at the
end
yeah
so the answer was n minus one choose K
minus one
okay so let's partition this
s s0 Union S1
s0 or let's call it S Sub B is
the set of binary
sequences with n1's uh
sorry n
Bits
k1s and B at the
end okay
so S Sub
1 is going to have size n minus1 chose
Kus one right if we know that we've got
a one at the end right we've got K minus
one additional ones that we need to
place right where can they go into any
of the first n minus one
positions
okay so there are n minus one choose K
minus one ways to choose those
and what about
s
yeah
yeah this is going to be n minus one
choose K and why is
that yeah if we've got a zero at the end
right we still need to place those k1s
somewhere right so now we've only got
nus one places where we can put them but
we still have k1s that we need to place
okay so there n minus1 choose K ways to
place
them
okay so these two cases are exhaustive
right you can't have uh like you can't
have a sequence that ends with nether a
zero or one it's a binary sequence right
they're also disjoint you can't have
both a zero and a one at the end so this
forms a partition right so by the sum
rule the size of s is going to be the
size of s not plus the size of
S1 which we just established is I guess
I flip them
around nus one choose K plus nus1 choose
kus1
okay and as we established at the
beginning this is also equal
to and
K okay does that make sense to everybody
do people have any questions about uh
either this Identity or uh combinatorial
proofs
yeah yeah the the question was is there
any reason we uh didn't you know write
out the definition of n k using the
factorials simplify things uh because
I'm a lazy folk and I don't want to
um yeah so that that kind of depends on
so the the the concern right was that
this uh you know maybe this takes a lot
longer than just uh you know putting
your head down and going through all of
the messy
algebra um yeah at the beginning it it
probably will right like uh if you are
not familiar with this proof technique
right it may not be obvious you know
what set you should be counting or how
you should be counting it uh but as you
get practice right uh it could be much
easier than you know just trying to to
bruteforce it and uh I think in in uh uh
possibly in recitation and homework you
will see other
identities where it may be less viable
to you know actually you know go through
the messy algeb
right
um so you know yeah this is kind of a
silly example and it's one where you
could definitely solve it in in other
ways uh and in fact you know those of
you who have seen this identity before I
imagine you probably did prove it in
other ways right uh but it's just kind
of illustrative of of this particular
proof technique does that does that
answer your
question
okay uh any other questions comments
concerns
okay
so as your colleague was hinting at
earlier this kind of gives us the
following
so I imagine many of you have seen
Pascal's triangle before but if you kind
of just you know write out all of the
binomial coefficients uh in like rows of
a
triangle so like this is uh n = 0 n = 1
Nal 2 Nal 3 and then you know successive
uh entries in a row are going to be like
n choose zero n choose one n choose 2
Etc okay so if you write all of these
out right what we just proved is that
every entry of this triangle right is
the sum of the two entries above
it right so if we take this four and
this six here they sum to 10 okay that
is uh that is essentially what this what
this identity is
saying
okay uh so this is what we call you know
Pascal's
triangle um we also showed that the sum
of all of the numbers in a single row is
going to be a power of two right it's
going to be uh 2 to the n
like if we sum everything in row five we
get 1 + 5 + 10 + 10 + 5 + 1 =
32 okay that was uh I think we proved it
over there yeah top of the uh top of the
rightmost
board
okay and
um you will see uh I believe in homework
that that if you sum the diagonals you
get the Fibonacci numbers right so if
you kind of uh let's see so go like
that right if you Sum along these
diagonals you get the Fibonacci numbers
uh is am I correct is that still a
homework problem or
uh maybe sorry I've not actually looked
at your homework uh full disclosure
uh it's a fun exercise if you want to
try it
um but I will leave you with one more
fun
exercise prove
that uh the sum from k equals 0 to n and
choose K
squared is going to be 2 N choose
n
okay so if you look at all of the
entries of a row instead of just summing
them up directly Square them and sum
them up you get you know the entry
that's kind of twice as far down in the
middle okay so see if you can prove that
using a uh a double counting
proof uh so that's all we have time for
today um if you have any questions
comments concerns please feel free to
come up um otherwise good luck on the
exam um yeah