okay today we are going to continue our
discussion of producer Theory remember
to set the stage I said producer theory
is like consumer Theory with one extra
step with consumer Theory I gave you a
budget constraint I gave you preferences
you could solve for what consumers were
going to do you were done
with producer Theory I can't do that
with producer Theory I give you a
production function which is like
utility function I give you input prices
which are like the prices consumers face
for pizza and cookies but there's no
income in some sense the income is
determined by the firm's production
decision firms get to choose how much
they want to produce so instead of one t
one relevant tangency between isoquant
and an isoc cost we end up with many
relevant tangencies which creates our
supply curve if you remember the supply
curve is the firm's marginal cost curve
above the point where it might shut down
okay so we did as we said we developed a
supply curve but that only tells
us uh so Bas supply curve tells us at
any price how much a firm wants to
produce we match that with the demand
curve and we get equilibrium we'll dive
back into that next lecture but today I
want to talk about an important
feature of the comp competitive
assumption remember to nail down the
supply curve we drew that supply curve
only for a particular Market assumption
remember with Supply Theory what's going
to drive the outcome is going to be the
Assumption of how we assume firms
compete we are now working within a
particular assumption on competition
which is the extreme Assumption of
perfect
competition okay where basically
consumers are totally indifferent and
fully
informed and therefore each firm faces a
perfectly elastic demand curve the
market demand isn't elastic necessarily
but the each firm face a perfect elastic
demand curve okay now La we're going to
now extend what we did last time from
the short run to the long
run in the long run we developed a short
run supply curve in the long run we're
gonna add one
wrinkle okay one basically extra
assumption to perfect competition so
talk about perfect competition in the
long
run we're going to add one extra
assumption for the long run which is
we're going to assume free entry and
exit that is in addition to the
assumptions we made last time of full
information and identical Goods we're
going to add one more assumption which
is free entry and exit that firms in the
long run are free to come and
go that assumption which seems pretty
harmless okay firms seem pretty free to
come and go as they like okay will
actually lead to an important
conclusion what we'll find is in the
long run when do firms enter firms enter
when there's a profit to be made when
the firms exit remember because there's
no shutdown in the long run it's just
about whether profits are greater than
zero or not so when the firms enter if
pro profits are zero greater than zero
when the firms exit if profits are less
than zero what does that mean in the
long run profits are always
zero so we're going to show you how in
Long Run perfect competition delivers
the Stark implication that long run
profits in the market are zero not short
run short run you can make money but in
the long run if you're ever making money
more firms are going to enter until
profits are driven to zero okay so to
see this I want to go to a particularly
old example relevant for my lifetime not
yours which is the market for personal
computers Circa
1990 okay the mark so and I DW this now
this is the first of many times in this
class we're going to do sort of go back
and forth in side by-side diagrams so
figure 8.1 I'm going to go through
slowly but please if it's not clear ask
me questions okay now we are going to
look at the market for personal
computers this is just when personal
computers were starting to take off
there are only a few firms there was
Dell Gateway you probably even heard of
them they were a big personal computer
firm back in the day there were a few
firms firms that produce PCS but it was
a pretty New Market in
1990 okay pretty New Market okay and
what we're going to assume is we're
going to assume this is a perfectly
competitive
market and we'll assume that that all
the producers are identical that any new
pc company is identical the ones that
came before it you can already see why
these are silly assumptions and we'll
talk about that later but that's how per
that's the kind of assumption we make in
perfect
competition okay now so what you have is
in the left hand side of figure
81 you have a
firm's production decision you have
their marginal cost curves so this is
say the firm is Dell okay one of several
firms that producing PCS in this market
you have their marginal cost curve which
is upward sloping okay you have their
average cost curve which is curved which
is a which is a parabola because
basically they first pay off their fixed
costs and then they have Rising marginal
cost remember the marginal cost curve
intersects the average cost curve at the
minimum of average
cost so that's the firm's that's the
firm's production decision now I want
you to carry that over so where's the
firm could produce in the short run
they'll produce where the market price
little
P1 equals their marginal cost so once
again focusing on the left hand side of
figure 81 The Firm will choose to
produce at the point little
q1 they will make a profit because
marginal cost is above because they'll
make a profit because marginal cost is
above average cost at that point they'll
make a profit of the entire lightly
dotted area called Pi
1 okay questions about that this is the
firm's production decision okay they
will choose price equal marginal cost
which happens at Point little q1 that
will deliver profits which is the
difference between price and average
cost
times the number of units produced and
that'll be the lightly dotted rectangle
Pi
1 now if we take that over to the market
with only one firm in the market they
will then have some supply curve
S1 in the market that supply curve if
the price is little
P1 and the supply curve is S1 then the
mark produce big
q1 okay so basically there's a big q1 is
a quantity produced in the
market okay but now flipping back to the
left hand side of the diagram what's
happened there's lots of
profit what does lots of profit mean
with free entry and exit that means more
firms will enter the
market as more firms enter what happens
to supply curve we learned this last
time as more firms enter the supply
curve flattens because as more identical
firms the supply supply curve gets
flatter it's just from S1 to
S2 so the supply curve flattens at a
flatter supply
curve at a flatter supply curve now um
you're going to get uh at a flatter
supply curve you will now get that
they'll be more produced at a lower
price so you'll get Q2 big Q2 but the
price will fall to to
P2 what happens when the price Falls to
P2 will now go back to the left hand
side when the price is P2 D now only
produces little
Q2 because the they produce where price
equals marginal cost they produce little
Q2 and that leads to a much smaller
profit Pi 2 so once again let me go
through the math they choose originally
little q1 at P1 that you shift to the
right creates a supply you've got a
supply curve that yields profits of Pi 1
due to those profits more firms enter
the supply curve flattens as Supply
curves flattens the price Falls shifting
back to the left that delivers a lower
profit note that little Q2 is to the
left of little q1 but big Q2 is to the
right of big q1 why is
that yeah more firms remember because
little Q is what Dell's producing big Q
is what the Market's
producing well but there's still profits
so what's going to happen more firms are
going to enter
and firms are going to enter until
profits are zero because as long as
those profits are positive firms can
enter so we've shown how entry drives
profits down but there's still profits
being made Pi too so some other company
will say hey this is still a good
business to be and they'll enter and
they'll enter until profits go to
zero because if profits are greater than
zero there's incentive to enter so firms
will enter until profits go to zero
now let's imagine a different
Market the market for mainframe
computers you guys don't even know that
term when I graduated MIT in 1987 our
graduation speaker was was uh Kenneth
Dell Ken I'm sorry Ken olssen Ken Olsen
who founded deck which was the big main
he was it was an MIT base he was an MIT
guy started this company called deck
they were dominant huge companies they
made these huge mainframe computers and
he gave this speech in
1987 about my graduation so first lesson
of graduation speeches if any of you
should ever give them I haven't given
one but if every should the position is
you don't spend the whole speech just
talking about how wonderful you are well
that's what he did spent those spee how
wonderful he was how deck was incredible
how awesome they were five years later
they're basically out of business why
because they got wiped out by PCS
because people went on maybe 10 years
later they're essentially out of
business okay because they got wiped out
by PCS okay well so let's look at the
market for mainframe computers and let's
look at a big company that produc frame
computers
IBM okay so mainframe computers they
were just big they're what we call
servers today but you basically we sort
of gone to transition almost back to
that model but we sort of went to a
decentralized PC model now we're back to
sort of a model where there's PC is just
a node onto some onto the cloud think in
that area you had a you had a you had a
terminal it wasn't a standalone machine
it was a terminal onto a Mainframe okay
so it's sort of a different version of
what we have today so IBM was making
those IBM was poo pooing PC just as much
as deck was and they were originally at
S1 there's a supply curve S1 with a
price q1 with a quantity big q1 now what
happened was people stopped wanting
mainframes so they were losing
money okay IBM had invested big in
mainframes they didn't believe the PC
was going to work and they were losing
money because people didn't want main
frames anymore so at their original
supply curve S1 which involved IBM and
deck and all these
companies there's money being lost so if
we go to IBM's case so basically S1 was
the market supply curve S1 intersected
demand at Big q1 at a price of P1 if you
take that over to IBM's curve P1
intersect the marginal cost curve at a
point where they produce q1 little q1 on
the leftand side of figure A2 so I've
now moved to the left hand side of
figure A2 I've been producing little q1
at little q1 their profits they're
negative because marginal cost is below
average cost they're losing money now
there's still above the shutdown Point
look look they they haven't reached the
bottom of their marginal cost curve if
the price fell far enough they'd shut
down but it hasn't they're still
producing they're just losing money
because they still they're still because
basically remember last time as long as
their variable costs are below the price
they still want to produce so in this
case they're still producing the
variable cost still below theice price
they're just losing money what happens
when you lose money firms exit like deck
firms exit that that that steepens the
supply curve just like firms entering
flatten supply curve firms exit that
steepens the supply curve okay you
steepen the supply curve that raises the
price and at this point I've drawn it
raised the price to P2 where IBM is
basically making zero profits so the way
I've drawn it okay we've gone from q1 to
Q2 that's raised the price to P2 at P2
price equals marginal cost equals
average cost and profits are
zero this is the lesson that we derive
which is entry will happen till profits
are zero and exit will happen to profits
are zero so what does that mean profits
are zero in the long run okay so what
that means is that the long run go to
figure
83 okay the long run supply curve is
flat each firm will be pushed to produce
to the point where price equals minimum
average
cost each firm will be pushed to produce
to the point where marginal cost equals
average cost so basically entry and exit
will drive profits to
zero we know that profits are only zero
when marginal cost equals average cost
if marginal cost doesn't equal average
cost as profits or losses so profits go
to zero profits margin cost equals
average cost and we know that only
happens at minimum average cost that's
the point where marginal cost equals
average cost there's your little proof
okay basically profits go to zero which
means marginal costs have to equal
average costs which only happens at
minimum average cost so in the long run
every firm produces at minimum average
cost that is every firm produces at
maximum efficiency
they minimize their cost so they
maximize their
efficiency so the long run supply curve
is flat at the minimum average cost
remember we assume firms are identical
so every firm is identical minimum
average cost okay so the long run supply
curve with perfect
competition with identical
firms with free entry and exit the long
run supply curve will be at the firm's
minimum average cost and profits will be
zero
okay questions about
that now you might say to me um John uh
that seems a little bit odd because um
profits aren't zero Apple makes ungodly
amounts of money tons of companies make
ungodly amounts of money so you've
really kind of I I I you know I I I
bought your pizza cookies thing but this
is getting ridiculous I can't buy a
model where companies don't make profits
there wouldn't be a stock market you
know they're basically what's going on
well two things are going on the first
thing going on the easiest an remember
the companies can still make profits in
the short
run okay so still short run profits but
you know you look at many companies
General Motors has made profits for
decades and decades and decades they'
blipped up and down but it's not like
they only make profits in the short run
there are plenty of companies that
around a long time making
profits so it can't just be that they're
around because they make profits in the
short run so basically what's going on
what's going on is that there's not free
entry and
exit Okay well no I'm sorry let me back
up that was too extreme what's going on
is there's a number of complications to
this simple model and we got to Dive
Right into them because this is really
sort of an unrealistic prediction it's a
good extreme it's a good teaching
example you will come back to it in
problem sets and exams to remember that
are all the assumptions of perfect
competition Long Run profits are
zero but in reality they're not so let's
talk about why there's really three
reasons why long run profits might not
be zero the first is limited
entry I assumed the profits of the PC
industry got driven to Zero by entry but
that's not true because in particular
there exist in the world things we call
barriers to
entry there are costs which are barriers
to entry in particular the ultimate
barriers to entry is sunk
costs because once someone's in the
market hav paid the sunk costs if you're
looking at entering okay think about a
doct you be a doctor if you make doctors
an economic decision you want to go look
at how much money you'll make compared
to the cost you'll sink into med
school well if profits are sufficiently
clo being a doctor aren't very big
you're not going to sink 300 Grand into
med school you're gonna say forget it so
as long as profits aren't too big you
won't go become a doctor so profits
don't profits can't be enormous but they
can be driven not all the way to zero
they're driven to the point where unless
you can pay off your sun cost you don't
want to do it okay so basically entry
will happen not freely but entry will
happen only if you can make enough money
eventually to pay off your sun costs
orse you won't you won't do it there's
lots of these barriers to entry
that are basically exist in the world
with Pharmaceuticals it's
patents even in the little market that I
described our perfectly competitive
example Market outside the Eiffel Tower
maybe if you try to set up another
blanket someone will come beat you up
okay and you've got to decide is it
worth the punches I take to make the
money and if the answer is profits are
truly zero you won't take the punches
you just won't set up your blanket okay
there's basically lots of barriers to
entry in the real world if there's
barriers to entry
then firms will not enter till that
point the profit goes to zero they'll
stop at a point profit they're still
positive okay so that's one example of
why you might end up with positive
profits in the long
run the second example is a little more
complicated but important which is firms
are not
identical and in
particular firms May differ at what
their minimum average cost
is and if firms differ what their
minimum average cost is you can end up
with the lowest average cost firms
making
money okay so basically you can enter
you can end up with the lowest average
cost firms making
money okay so to see this let's look at
figure 84 which is sort of confusing but
it gives sort of an example if there's
time in section we'll do sort of a more
complicated example but this is sort of
a simple
example this is an old example some a
real empirical study that was done a
long time ago of the marginal cost of
producing cotton in different countries
so here we're just assuming flat
marginal cost curves okay we're ignoring
just assume not output slow just assume
it's just a it's just a constant
marginal cost a flat supply curve a
constant marginal cost of producing
cotton you might say well in that case
obviously with free entry profits are
zero but in fact it turns out that cost
is different in different places it only
cost 71 cents a
kilogram to produce cotton Pakistan
because I mean I'm sure that's changed
now but Labor's cheap things like that
there's it's good good growing
conditions for
cotton
Argentina their lowest cost they can
produce cotton their minimum average
cost is a dollar eight Australia is a15
all the way up to the United States
where it's a$1 56 to produce a kilogram
of cotton okay so just assume in this
case bear with me think of margin class
is just one number it's a constant
number okay and that marginal cost is
higher in the US than it is
in Pakistan now what happens in this
market if the demand for cotton is 1
billion kilograms per year who makes the
cotton how much profit did they
make and what's the price let's say
demand is 1 billion kilograms per year
what happens who makes the cotton what's
the price and how much profits they make
anyone you got this you know the answer
yeah Pakistan makes it at what
price they make it at 71 cents and
therefore what's their
profit zero right price equals marginal
cost equals average cost if marginal
cost is flat average cost is flat so
price equals Marg cost equals average
cost so in a world that's the example we
just did in a world the perfect
competition profits are zero
yeah well basically that's a great
question because presumably within
Pakistan there's multiple companies
competing and if one company tried to
sell for higher than 71 the other would
come in and sell for 71 okay it's weird
to think of a country level supply curve
but that's s the logic but now let's say
the demand curve is such that there's
five billion kilograms demanded
if demand is five billion what is the
market
price if the demand for cotton is five
billion what's the market
price
yeah right this is a supply curve this
Red Line supply curve demand equal
Supply at
156 so what are profits in the US at
that
price what are profits in
Pakistan 85 cents
so in a
world where there are where to meet
demand you need to draw on less
efficient firms the more efficient firms
can make
money okay this is a confusing Point
let's go back and remember what drove
the last example I'm saying was the
assumption that all firms were identical
that led to this flat Supply cover at
long range average cost but in fact when
firms aren't identical as some are more
efficient than others the more efficient
firms can still make money even in the
long run
as long as demand exceeds their marginal
as long as demand exceeds their part of
the supply curve they can still make
money okay so another reason why there
could be profits in the long run is
because particularly efficient firms can
make profits if demand is sufficiently
high okay questions about that
yeah
yeah oh Pakistan well the point is
Pakistan will make more but think of
Pakistan's supply curve as such it's a
great question think of Pakistan's
supply curve as such that after they've
made 1.7 million kilograms of cotton
their cost just goes through the roof so
that's sort of the way we think about it
but you're right they could make more
and make even more
profits all right okay so that's a
second reason why you could end up with
long run profits the third reason is
quite different
the third reason hint it's something
we'll start talking about in a few
lectures which is that input
prices may depend on
quantity or or they do input prices
depend on
quantity that is as you produce more the
cost of buying inputs could
rise okay so to see this I'm now going
to skip ahead something we'll talk about
much more in a few lectures which is
let's look at the market for labor
remember so far in this class we've
taken labor the wage of Labor as just
given from God but now we're going to
talk about where that comes from it
comes from the market for labor so let's
go to
figure uh
85 figure 85 is the kind of figure we're
to start working with in a few lectures
it's the classic Supply demand figure
quantity on the x- axis price on the y-
AIS the difference is the quantity is
not the number of cookies it's the hours
of work or number of workers and the
price is not the price of a cookie it's
the wage the wage is the price of Labor
so this is a demand and supply curve for
workers why not you can draw demand
supply for anything so like any demand
supply curve we have a demand for
workers the demand for workers is that
downward
sloping okay why is the demand for
workers downward
sloping okay it's downward sloping
because as the price of Labor goes up
firms want less of
it right we've know this if you go back
to your underlying production theory if
you solve for optimal those isoquants
and isocost we know is the isocost shift
that's going to change your production
mix you're going to end up wanting as
the ice as labor gets more expensive you
want fewer
workers okay so therefore as the price
of Labor goes up they want fewer workers
that's why the demand is downward
sloping why is the supply upward sloping
can anyone tell me why is supply of
labor upward
sloping
yeah exactly the assumption is and I'll
teach you a few lectures it's only an
assumption I like the the celebration
there that's good good good good answer
um I the it's only it's only an uh an
assumption but the Assumption we're
making here is as there's more wages
more people want to work as wages go up
people want to work harder more people
want to work there want to work harder
supply curve slopes up and you end up in
some
equilibrium L1
W1 now imagine that people suddenly want
more of a
good well if they want more of a good
and that's in some other diagram that's
not in this diagram it's the labor
market diagram there some other diagram
people want more of a good good if
people want more of a good you need to
hire more
workers how do we represent that here
well that means there's an increase in
demand for
workers that means there's a shift
outward in the demand curve to D of
Q2 okay once again people want more
rivets or whatever we're producing to
produce more rivets you need more
workers that's a shift outward in the
demand for workers what does that do
well that increase the number of workers
but it also raises the wage the price of
Labor
with an upward sloping supply curve
you're going to find that if you want
more workers you're going to have to pay
more to get them right so think of the
firm's decision I want to make more
rivets I need more workers well I'm in
equilibrium my current level of workers
they are are happy at the wage I'm
offering I'm getting the right number of
workers if I want more workers I'm have
to raise the
wage well if I raise the wage that feeds
back to my marginal costs and that leads
to something like figure 86
okay so basically when I was producing
before I was at
MC1 and
ac1 now I want to produce more and I was
producing at little q1 at Price P1 I
want to produce more I produce little Q2
well for this little Q2 I've got to
raise the wage if I raise the wage that
raises my marginal average costs so I
shift to the new mc2 and
ac2 and my costs are higher
so now you actually see an upward
sloping supply
curve that as the wage goes
up costs go as as you I'm sorry as you
produce more your costs go
up because you have to pay more for your
inputs so what happens is my my marginal
cost shes from MC1 to mc2 so I have to
sell at a higher price to break even to
get to that point where margin cost
equals average cost that that efficient
point at E2 I've got to charge a higher
price so now you see an upward sloping
supply curve so this is a perfectly
competitive market notice firms are
making zero
profits okay in both E1 and E2 the firms
making zero little E1 and little E2
profits are zero how do we know because
marginal cost is equal to minimum
average
cost yet even though they making zero
profits when you want more Goods the
price has to rise and that's because
they have to hire more workers and
that's the key distinction between cases
one and two in case three in case one
and two barriers to entry or firms not
identical leads to Long Run profits
greater than
zero but in case three long run profits
are still
zero it's important distinction in case
three long profit are still zirm firms
are still producing at their minimum
average cost every firm is it's just the
supply curves upward sloping so I I I
said this a comp this is a complication
which doesn't explain law that's why I
backed off and said there's long run
profits there's still not long run
profits but there is a long run upward
sloping supply curve so what I concluded
a few minutes ago is a long run flat
supply curve meant Zero
profits here we're actually in a long
run upward sloping supply curve in zero
profits why because we have to pay more
for labor as we produce more so a long
in the long run now this once again
still unrealistic because we know
profits aren't zero in the long run it's
just showing you can't assume as someone
might ask you to in a problem assume
that because as long one Supply curves
upward sloping there's profits to be
made that's not necessarily true here's
a case where there's no profits in these
cases the long one Supply curves upward
sloping and there are profits being
made okay that's a lot that's confusing
let me pause pause for questions about
any of that any of that
stuff
yeah I right now I'm just uh the Lark
supply curve is upward sloping by
assumption I'm talking about creating
upward sloping in figure 86 so comp
piure figure 86 to figure um
83 okay okay in figure Figure 8 three
you see that every firm produced their
minimum average cost you I could have
drawn a whole bunch of firms here they'd
all be at that same price or a whole
bunch of quantities say all the same
price now what I'm saying in figure 86
is no as the quantity goes up you got to
pay you get a higher price even though
profits are still zero okay good
question
yeah uh once again we don't have income
substitution effects here because it's
not um it's not the income substitution
effects come from sort of cons come from
underlying consumer preferences these
are firm decisions so we're not getting
income and substitution effects the way
you care about one two verse three is
ask are there long run profits so if you
if you want to ask which is the right
case this's an easy test are profits
zero in the long run profit zero in the
long run then either our base case is
true or this so we have four total cases
we have our base case and then we have
these three complications both the base
case and this third complication
delivers one prediction which long
profits of zero these two deliver a
different prediction which long and
profits are greater than zero now
differentiating between each of those
pairs of cases that'll involve
additional
testing okay so for example
differentiating between the base case
and this case you differentiate
empirically by asking do wages rise as
quantity
Rises differ in these cases you
differentiate by asking will our firms
identical or are there some costs Etc
okay good question other questions yeah
that's an awesome Point Apple's Apple's
$8 millionar $8 billion dollar per
quarter profits not bad uh are
accounting profits what are economic
profits that's a great question and that
is much much harder uh now to be fair at
one level it's harder let's it's not
like accounting profits are easy because
Apple gets to make up their
numbers okay so let me give you a simple
example of what Apple does um Apple by
the way makes $18 billion in reported
profits uh to their stockholders to the
US government they report profits of
zero they report $8 billion to their
stakeholders but to the tax authorities
to whom they pay taxes they report
profits of zero essentially why well
because they play a game where they
pretend they have a company in Ireland
with two
employees they CLA but Ireland has low
taxes they claim that all their profits
are earned in Ireland how can they do
that only two employees they claim that
their profits come from intellectual
property intellectual property is housed
in Ireland with those two
employees okay so accounting profits are
not necessarily right either you know
accounting profits are not so clean but
economic profits would be very very hard
economic profits economic cost is also
very hard to measure there is measuring
firm profits and that's why in some
sense many of us would say well look
there's an easy answer to economic
problem there's tax firms that make all
the profits the problem is what are
profits and it's very hard to measure
both economically and for accounting
reasons great question other
questions yeah in the figure 85 where
there's like you talked about how the
demand cve shift or the cost of the
wages shift based on the demand cve
shift which is in relation to the market
demand but then does the supply curve
ever shift adjust for the increased cost
well no but the supply curve is
determined that's a good question supply
curve is determined by the workers's
preference for how they want to work
nothing's changed that it's just it's
just the supply curve is just how much
more do I want to work when the wage
goes up and that's just fixed that could
change and we'll talk about that in a
few lectures in fact we'll tell you a
few lectures why it might not even slope
up it might slope down and that's good
about then the our big income and
substitution effects fan here will have
uh we'll have some to talk about uh
question like assumtion of like comp
also workers that mean the long run all
workers make no profit wonderful
wonderful point and we will come back to
that as well when we talk about well do
a whole lecture on how workers make
their decision how to work and we'll
come to that point okay great questions
all right well let's follow up on the
Apple
discussion to talk
about something that once again let's
let's let's interject the real world
here for one second and
ask do firms actually maximize
profits we assume that we assume fors
maximized profit there's no reason not
to or the logic is pretty impeccable but
in fact we see a lot of things that
don't look like firms are maximizing
profits so for example uh in
Amgen lost 3% of their market value in
7% over the past five years yet their
CEO made $21 million
in 2008 the CEO of abomi and Fitch who
stock V had dropped
71% was paid $72 million that's a lot of
money based off ABS good ABS right and
then finally here's um then we have the
case of Leo apecer who was CEO of hulet
Packard for 11 months and it was so
disastrous they F fired him after 11
months and he made $13
million okay so the question is
if firms really maximize profits how can
be paying all these outrageous amounts
of money to employees that don't
necessarily seem to be doing such a good
job and there's two answers to that one
answer is well look we don't one answer
is the opportunity cost we don't know
what would happened if those CEOs hadn't
been in place maybe they would have lost
120% of their value maybe they would
have done even worse maybe these highly
paid CEOs are worth it look a great
example is Michael Jordan Michael Jordan
there was an academic study which
measured the value of Michael Jordan
Michael Jordan was the highest paid
player in basketball at 1 Point $32
million a year someone did a study based
on the ad revenues that are generated by
increased viewership when Michael Jordan
was on TV and based that he was worth a
hundred million a year so he was
actually underpaid at 32
million okay so basically the point is
just because someone's paid a lot
doesn't mean they're not worth it okay
we can't just look at some some page and
say they're not worth it that's one uh
explanation however that one doesn't
seem to work and the way it noce the
work is a super clever test that was
done by Professor Sloan at Shore and a
now a new professor um in the computer
science department sen mull Nathan they
did a very cool test they said um uh
actually Mel and Mar betron to Chicago
what they said is look let's look at
what happens to how much CEOs of oil
companies get paid when the price of oil
goes up when the price of oils goes up
oil company profits go up but it's not
due to anything a CEO did the price of
oil is determined by a World Market no
one CEO can have any influence on the
price of
oil so if the profits go up because the
price of oil goes up CEOs shouldn't be
rewarded for that they did nothing and
yet they find that when Pro oil prices
go up CEOs get massive raises in oil
companies that can't be that they're
doing a particularly good job that's got
to be something else okay so what's the
something else the something else is to
recognize that firms are not just some
blackbox little little Q function or F
function firms are actually a
complicated set of what we call agency
relationships a complicated set of
agency
relationships what do we mean by that we
mean that when you think of the firm in
this course we're thinking about
something like someone working for
themselves or pair of Partners where the
workers are the
owners but most firms most of the goods
in America not most firms most of the
goods in America are produced by giant
corporations and the key Hallmark of a
corporation is the
separation of ownership from
control corporations are owned by
disembodied set of stockholders but the
decisions are made by employees managers
who work at those
firms and that separation of ownership
and
control leads to a fundamental challenge
which for which uh uh my former
colleague B Holstrom won the Nobel Prize
was one7 won the Nobel Prize for
documenting this fundamental tension
understanding it which is when you have
the owners different from the
managers the managers don't don't have
necessarily the right incentives to do
what's profit maximizing for the
owners so here's the example I like to
use okay imagine you're a corporate
manager and this is a world you may be
in someday but imagine you're a
corporate manager at a pretty big but
not massive company it's big enough that
you don't yet have a private jet but all
your buddies the bigger companies have
private jets and they rag on you
mercilessly like you ler you don't have
a private jet You're Nobody da D D D D
okay so you're like I need a private jet
the problem is you've done the math and
it's not economical of a private J you
can fly you can fly first class anywhere
you need to go for less than a cost set
of private
jet but you've noticed that if you
change things a little bit so you flew
only at the busiest times and only most
expensive Airlines and you did the math
then the cost of flying commercial would
be more than the cost of private jet so
you make a PowerPoint for your board you
make a PowerPoint and you show the
owners look we could save money by
private jet now the owners could take
the time to reverse engineer your
calculations and figure out that you
cook them a little bit but they're not
going to they're a bunch of disembodied
people owning tons of stocks they're not
going to take the time so like yeah you
make sense get a private jet and now you
can hold your head up high with your
buddies because you got your private jet
that is not profit maximizing profit
maximizing was to fly commercial but
it's what made you happiest as the
manager what makes the manager best off
is not necessarily what makes the profit
the highest
and in that
situation you can end up with profits
not being
maximized now it's firms recognize this
and they set up something to deal with
this they have something called a board
of
directors board of directors what the
board of directors are it's a set of
representative of the shareholders that
keep an eye the idea is look you've got
millions of shareholders in a company
you got this manager so the million
share company a set of 20ish people who
keep an eye on the manager they should
be doing the calculations they should be
watching it to make sure the manager is
serving their
interest the problem is Boards of
directors just don't do a good job
they're L be why because the people on
the board of directors is largely chosen
by the
managers and it's just their corporate
buddies it's a lot of retired CEOs who
liked having private jets and think you
should have one
too okay so board of directors doesn't
end up doing necessarily what they
should a great examp example was um
Richard Grasso was a great American
success story he went from working in
the shipping department at the New York
Stock Exchange to running the entire New
York Stock
Exchange great success story when he
retired there was a lot of controversy
because he got $187 million as a
retirement package it's pretty good okay
and there was a lot of press about
that's outrageous and they went to the
board director Bo director said we had
no idea we were just told it was this
retirement package with a bunch of
options and stock pieces and stuff like
that it looked pretty good to us we
couldn't unpack it we no idea to have
$187
million okay because it's in the manager
incentive it's his whole life's work to
maximize his happiness the board of
directors it's something they're doing
part-time while they go play Golf the
other times okay so at the end of the
day the separation of ownership and
control is real and costly and it means
that firms might not not be doing things
to maximize profits and that's LED once
again the whole point of this course is
to sort of not solve all your problems
economic problems but to peque your
interest in the field this has led to a
huge part of the field of what's called
Corporate Finance which is how do you
set up
contracts to align the
incentives of owners and employes this
led for example to the birth to the
revolution in stock options many many of
you will know about stock options you're
hopefully hoping to get them from your
company you go to the idea is that when
you get hired they'd only pay you in
cash they give you some stock and what's
the idea of stock options it's not
actually stock what they do is they give
you what's called an option which means
that you have the right to buy the stock
at today's price or at some strike price
why is that valuable well it's valuable
because the stock goes up then you can
buy it at today's price and sell it at
some future higher price so a stock
option the idea is it's something which
is worthless to you if the stock value
goes down but valuable if the stock
price goes up so let say you go to
workday for a company where the stock
value is 100 they say we're going to
allow you to buy a th shares at 100 if
the stock price goes up to 200 you buy
those thousand shares for 100 and sell
them for 200 you just made
$100,000 and the idea is well that will
give managers the
incentive to raise the value of the
company that will align the incentives
and that's why they became so popular
the problem is they've led to disasters
and they've led to disasters because of
the exact kind of accounting discussion
I was having a few moments ago which is
that managers can do actions which raise
the short-term stock price but aren't
necess in the long-term interest of
profitability of the
company okay and this the classic
example of that was the company Enron
which went bankrupt when you were young
okay Enron basically a bunch of managers
a bunch of stock options what they did
is essentially set up a Ponzi scheme
where they had Enron sell its
subsidiaries they had Enron sell an
unnamed subsidary that was also owned by
Enron a good and it looked like Enron
was booking big sales but of course
Enron was also booking the purchases but
it was all the sum of the subsidiary and
Enron stock price went through the roof
and these guys got super rich and tried
to run away from the company some did
some got out but some didn't the company
went it got exposed and the company went
bankrupt and but you know I don't think
any went to jail some of them got
penalized a lot okay so basically the
problem with stock options is they work
in theory in principle they can lead to
even more bad behavior which you can end
up with people trying to then go further
to try to manipulate the stock price to
maximize their income the point is that
this is a very hard and fascinating
Enterprise and there's always room for
thinking creatively about how do
you align the interest
I even talked about the interest of the
workers we're only talking about the
interest of you know one rich guy versus
another rich guy okay there's also the
interest of the workers and how do we
think about contracts that also bring in
the interest of the workers is another
interesting question it's a fascinating
area and one which you can learn more
about if if you study the field of of
corporate finance and think more about
those areas okay questions about
that all right let's stop there um and
uh go see our Kel's tomorrow night and
I'll see you guys in class on Wednesday
okay