Hi everyone. Um, biomedical imaging data
sets can exceed hundreds of terabytes.
So, computer vision algorithms operate
on them one chunk at a
time. There's extensive work in
multiscale representations of image
content, but is far less common to use
lowresolution information to guide how
the algorithm queries high resolution
information. We were inspired by uh the
cascade detector framework in face
detection. So we applied this framework
to biomedical
microscopy. We constructed a statistical
model to analyze the performance
trade-offs uh under such a framework and
we confirmed in a variety of public data
sets that cascade detectors can detect
sparse objects um in a fraction of the
time as their single resolution
counterparts with little to no uh
decreases in accuracy. So, hope to see
you at poster 23.
Thank you. Up next is Salvatore.
Hi, I'm Salvo. I am a post-docctoral
researcher at the Overstart Lab at Dana
Farber Cancer Institute. Currently,
acute leukemia diagnostics relies on
multiple tests that are time and
resource intensive. We developed a
framework for rapid epigenomic
classification of acute leukemia using
DNA mutilation, machine learning and
nanopore sequencing. And we validated
our approach in both retros
retrospective and prospective cases even
doing realtime
classification. Uh we are shifting acute
leukemia diagnostics from several days
to hours. If you're curious, you want to
know more, please find me at poster 24.
Thank you.
Up next we have Utsavv.
Thanks. Hi. So my name is Utsv. I'm a
postto here at the Ericon Schmidt Center
and at my poster poster number 25 I'm
going to present our algorithm Gaston an
interpretable deep learning algorithm
for learning topographic maps of gene
expression. So similar to when you're
hiking you have a topographic map of
like uh a mountain where each point
denotes the height. We derived these
topographic maps of tissue slices where
at every point in space we have a
coordinate that we call the isoepth. Um
and this uh topographic map is based on
this new mathematical model of spatial
gradients um in sparse and
highdimensional data. And using these
topographic maps we can do things like
finding spatial trajectories of cells um
inside tissues, finding spatial gene
expression patterns that separate
different um gene patterns in cancer and
finding spatial gradient patterns in
other tissues like the liver and
intestine. And so come to poster 25 if
you're interested. Thanks.
Thank you. Running right along. Seb,
you're up next.
Good morning. I'm Seb. Um so this
project started with a simple
observation that um cell annotation
models trained on atlas level data
sometimes struggle to generalize to new
data sets that they've not seen during
training. And I was wondering why this
is the case. And one of the things we
notice is that often those models are
trained with standard cross entropy
loss, meaning that they treat cell type
labels as being independent. Yet we know
that cell types are actually not
independent. They follow a hierarchical
structure. And we were wondering how can
we modify this loss function to encode
this relationship between cell types. Uh
so we came up with a mathematical
formula for that. And we've applied it
across models of increasing complexity
from a linear one to an MLP to more
sophisticated transformer. And what we
see is an improvement on their
performances. Thank you.
[Applause]
Next we have
my hi.
So hi. So we use single cell data along
with the spatial data and we have
produced a wonderful uh rag
or wonderful rag or regional agency
graph showing that the PMC's that are
the foundational bone of the development
of skeleton in sea
chains do have a special patterning code
and For
more and for more insights, please do
join me at poster number 27. Thank you.
Thank you. Welcome Navami.
Hi everyone. My name is Navami and I'm
in the MarkX lab where we're interested
in modeling how mutations to viral
proteins impact different aspects of its
fitness including ability to infect a
host cell, replicate or escape a host
antibbody. And in this project, we're
studying the best modeling approaches to
apply to 40 um pandemic threat viral
pathogens that have been identified by
the WH as a priority for research and
intervention. Um to do this we curate 50
deep mutational scanning assays covering
um a range of viral proteins and we
assess the performance of models that
fall broadly into two categories.
Alignment based models and protein
language models. From this we identify
confidence metrics based on the quality
of input data that are predictive of
model performance. And we use these
metrics to highlight pandemic threat
viruses that are that critically require
additional sequence or structural data.
Um if you'd like to more see more um
come to poster 28.
Thank you. Up next is
Ye. So genetic variations and its
interaction with the environmental cues
are all contributing to the development
of the metabolic diseases and these
effects are highly associated with the
adocides dysfunction.
So in order to explore the fundamental
mechanisms as well as to link the
genetics to biology uh we performed uh
we leverage our population scale solut
gene bank to perform the put natural
genetic variation screen in 118 donor
adocide villages under disease related
stimulations and as well as under the uh
uh single cell resolution. So we will be
able to identify hundreds to thousands
of uh sales state and the context
specific eqtls with potential links that
link to our uh adopite uh adopite
function. Uh we also will be able to map
the distinct cell states and their
stimulations to the relevant disease
heritability. We also observed uh the
pornogenic disease risk is associated
with adogenesis levels. Uh my name is
Iwang. Uh I'm a a posttock from Manina
Clauser lab. So come and chat with me uh
at the post 29 if you are interested.
Thank you.
Thank you. Up next is RT.
Hello everybody. Um so as we know that
GVS
associates genotype variation with
phenotype and if you have uh uh data
sets with gene expression and genotype
you can predict gene expression
variation using uh genotype variation
across individuals. So if you integrate
the two essentially you can associate uh
genotype driven gene expression with a
phenotype. And as Angel pointed this
that ancestry uh background ancestral
background of people in these cohorts
could have an impact on uh observing
these relationships. So we train uh Grex
models on uh different ancestries uh for
brain tissue and integrate that with
mismatch ancestry gses of psychiatric
disorders. If you want to learn more on
how that helps, come to poster 30. Thank
you.
[Applause]
Up next is Anu.
Hi everyone, I'm Anu as final year CPSD
student at Georgia Tech. So humans like
to whisper to their close friends. Turns
out cells do the same. We present cell
whisper uh inference of contact mediate
cell signaling from spatial
transcrytoics data set. There are two
main innovations. First uh it has
stronger confounder awareness leading to
much lower false positive rates and
second we are the first to study gap
junction communication which is very
important especially in brains and there
are other we als we saw exciting results
on mouse brain and pathogenesis of
Alzheimer and we are the first to have a
novel latent variable model that works
directly at the quadriplet level. So see
you at uh poster number 30 uh 31 and
let's discuss and collaborate. Thank
you.
[Applause]
Thank you. Up next is V.
Hi everyone. I'm a post-doal fellow at
the Schmidt Center. So this work is
about identifying cancer drug
combinations that work synergistically.
So this means that their joint effect
kills more cancerous cells than when
administered independently. Antagonism
is the opposite effect. So combination
therapy is a bedrock of cancer care. But
we just don't know what these do
response surfaces look like. Instead,
what we have access to are these coarse
cell viability assays on a fixed grid of
concentrations per uh for a chosen uh
drug pairs. Uh the theory of bliss
independence says that two drugs just
don't interact. So basically their joint
effect is just the sum of the individual
effects. As for the model, we uh
represent we mathematically represent
the dose response surface as the sum of
this bliss independence deterministic uh
effect plus a nonlinear unknown uh
interaction surface that we model with
Gaussian processes. What makes this
entire model multitask is that we take
these grid concentrations, we we we
flatten and stack them column-wise per
cancer cell line, per drug drug pair in
this gigantic matrix and then we model
across columns and rows leveraging cross
coariance between uh cancer cell lines
and drug pairs. In order to chat more,
I'll be at poster 32. Thank you so much.
Thank you. Up next is Max.
Hi everyone. I'm a PhD student here with
Caroline Shiva and we're interested in
mechano genomics. So as we age uh the
kind of physical properties of our
tissues change and in particular
fibroblasts that reside in our tissue
can kind of sense and respond to changes
in mechanical signals thanks to a
signaling transduction pathways. These
signaling transduction pathways kind of
induce changes in gene expression which
kind of lead to cell state transitions.
And remarkably, fibroblasts are actually
quite plastic and they can kind of give
rise to diverse phenotypes. This kind of
phenotypic phenotypic diversity is
actually quite interesting because it
kind of suggests there's some underlying
like gene regular mechanism that kind of
govern cell fate decisions. And so we
were kind of thinking about how
fibroblasts adapt to the tissue
environment. And so what we observe is
that kind of uh cells in different
tissue contexts actually have different
3D chrome constructures. And so
basically what we're proposing in this
project is a pathway level mechanism of
gene regulation through which 3D
interimal contacts po cell state. So if
you're interested please see me at
poster
33. Next we have Tara.
Hello. I'm Tara. I'm a first year postto
fellow management center. Um and our
poster is about um how to learn how
dynamic DNA regulation affects sulfate
as you heard a little bit about before.
And uh we want to learn the regulatory
interactions as well as the trajectories
that the cells are on. Um and we wanted
a framework that would link these
different measurements in this case DNA
and RNA measurements uh through their
physical interactions but also give us a
way to assess uncertainty and our
different hypotheses of different
mechanisms in the system. Um so the idea
was to combine an explicit structure of
so RNA processing kinetics with flexible
machine learning. um so that we could
learn potential DNA based regulation
over time, how that affects the
downstream RNA processing and then where
your cells in your system are along the
potential trajectories. So if this is
interesting to you, please come by
poster
[Applause]
34. Next we have
Dora. Hello everyone. I'm Dora and I'm a
um postal and shim center. So um today I
want to u present a work that is
basically a model that we believe
actually nerves how cell interacts and
fally assemble into tissues. So we take
this self-supervised approach in which
we mask some cells and we ask the model
to use the unmask cells information to
predict this unmask cells cell types and
on top of that on top of that sorry uh
we actually come up with this
hierarchical model in which each single
layer you can think of as representing
some spatial units of different
resolution from single cell couple of
cells to tissue modules made up of
thousands of cells and we then optimal
interactions within each single layer as
well as across different resolutions and
finally get the output at the cell
level. So it turned out this model works
uh pretty well as shown in the bottom we
see that actually for example for this
uh for this tissue patch even though we
uh ask the model to only use 20% of the
information it can reconstruct 80% of
the cells accur accurately. So if you
wanted to learn more, find me and poster
certified. Thanks.
Next we have
Mining. Hello everyone. I'm Minshing, a
PhD student from UPAN applied
mathematics. So I will introduce our
project, a unified model for self
segmentation and classification. So
Selta classification annotation uh is a
important uh task for the spatial armies
data analysis current methods usually
based on the two-step approach which is
the self segmentation followed by the
cell tai annotation. However such
approach will let the full semantic
comprehensive
understanding of the tissue images. So
we propose a model called cellotype an
end to end transformerbased model for
cell annotation with three highlight
features the improved precision wide
applicability and multiscale
capabilities. So if you are interesting
in the segmentation or annotation of the
imaging based spatial or data welcome to
the poster number 37 for discussion.
Thank you.
[Applause]
Thank you. Up next is Yuni.
Hi, my name is Yuni. I'm a um third year
PhD in UCS MIT. Um I'm here to talk
about um uh like trajectory inference.
So what we do is um we know we want to
know uh how what's driven single cells
RNA change but we cannot track any
single cell because we have to kill it
to see what's inside. Um one of the
often used method is so called
shreddinger bridge or dynamic optimal
transport. Um the idea there is to let
let's learn the trajectory that that
most close to a brain motion. But if
shinger himself is here he will oppose
that because he actually written that on
what life feed upon is negative entropy.
So you cannot do the minimum entropy
thing. So what we do is we relax this
assumption of everything has to look
like a brain emotion and we ask for
things to look close to a family of
reference which could be biologically
informed and in many uh benchmarking
tasks we outperform the existing method.
Thank you.
Thank you. Up next is Maria.
Hi everyone. I'm Maria. I'm a second
year PhD student uh postdoctoral at the
at Smith center. Well uh the the idea is
that here we are interested in
identifying molecular qu quantitative
trait loi. The question is how can we
use gene expression in order to
understand complex trait trait genetics
and our approach here is going to be uh
through expression quantitative trait
locus which is a method in order to
identify associations between
genotype and expression levels. So in
our case we're interested in the uh
genetic variation uh which is going to
be accounted for as snips also known as
uh single nucleotide polymorphisms and
we wish to identify their pairwise
association with z expression variation
in order to see to learn which snips are
actually uh important and tend to
regulate this uh kind of variation. So
that's the problem from the biological
point of view. But of course uh there
are quite a lot of cavits. Uh one of
them is the fact that we have high
dimensional data. Usually the number of
individuals is of orders of hundreds to
thousands and then uh gene expression
levels tens of thousands and snips
hundreds of thousands to millions. So
it's quite hard to uh kind of do that in
an elegant statistical manner. Uh we are
overall we are interested towards uh
doing the uh the task of variable
selection. That means that we are
interested in identifying which of those
snips are actually regulatory with
respect to the gene expression levels.
And another uh interesting and I guess
that it's uh well known to most of you
uh another keyword here keyword here is
pleotropy in the sense that there's this
two-way association in between varants
and uh gene expression levels. So that's
us and next is
Sophie. Hello, my name is Sophie. I'm a
student at the University of Toronto and
I'm excited to share yeastiff, a model
that learns how cells divide. So we
start with live cell images of yeast um
each visualizing a specific protein in
the cell. And kind of our fundamental
question we're trying to answer is what
can we teach a diffusion model to learn
about the cell cycle process allowing it
to generalize to new and untested
conditions. Specifically, we're focused
on multi-roin visualization which is
challenging to do in live cells due to
spectral overlap. Now, as you can see on
the right, we are able to generate
highly realistic single cell images, but
more interestingly, we're able to
generalize to multi-roin cell images,
which is something the model has never
seen before. And we're currently scaling
this to many, many more proteins. And we
kind of hope this work can serve as a
visualization tool to help kind of
researchers and people better understand
the cell cycle process and also help
identify or test new hypotheses without
having to run every experiment in the
lab. And if you're interested in
learning more on how we did this, you
can find me at poster 42.
Thank you. Our last speaker will be
Petar. Okay. So, um, hi everyone. I'm
Petar. I'm uh postoc at the Schmidt
center and uh in the Gats lab. So, most
of the transcrytoic studies that we're
that we discuss about generally is
concerning the coding genes. um and
often um other molecules are overlooked
and some of those molecules are small
non non-coding RNAs and they can have
different kinds of roles. They can be
involved in translation which is the
tRNA and it's very very well known. Um
they can be involved in splicing uh or
guarding um guarding the the integrity
of the genome during u um in germline
cells. Um and most importantly uh the
the most known ones are micronas which
are important in gene regulation. And so
um the GTEx project um sequenced a lot
of um um a lot of different tissues ac
across many different individuals. Um so
um and that used polya capture. Uh and
then um then for the same donors uh so
the these are 9 900 donors across 54
tissue types and a total of 20 almost
20,000 samples we now have subset of
them with a different protocol that uh
profiles small uh non-coding RNAs. And
so uh with these kinds of overlap
between the two data sets, we can look
at one of the highlights is that we can
look at genetic regulation
um of small RNA expression. And then we
can also look at how um the uh
regulatory effect of a EQL on a small
RNA can propagate to a coding gene for
example and then subsequently to a
complex trait like a G-W was trait. Um
and then um here we have an example in
thyroid where uh two micronas are
regulated in SIS by a variant and then
through um kind of um instrumental
variable analysis collocicalization and
other um evidence we can show that that
these micronas are in actually mediating
the trans effect of the of the snip on
the coding genes that are that are all
involved in growth. And finally we can
also show that that um that this all
makes sense when we actually look at the
effect of the snip on um growth g was
like kite. So for more uh more vignettes
like this and more overview of this data
set please come to poster 43.