hello computational music
researchers we're going to continue our
study of corpora and what we can do with
the Corpus of music by talking about
some research that I did with Sophia H
Sun who was a visiting student at MIT in
2006 to 2017 and graduated in 2018 from
Wellsley College we've published our
work as emotion painting lyric affect
and musical relationships and a large Le
cheet
Corpus so this is work that's about
looking at a large musical Corpus and
also looking at words and how music and
words
interact words and musical moments are
generally both felt to have intrinsic
emotions
but while the emotional context of text
is determined at least in part from the
semantics that is the meaning of
individual words and sentences the
emotional content of individual musical
parameters is far less well
defined this lack of definition is
especially acute in written musical
scores that are separated from the oral
and visual components of particular
performances or
recordings so a major question for music
perception or the psychology of music is
is do particular musical features such
as consonants and dissonants beat
placement and Pitch height when they
separated from the performative elements
do they still carry particular emotional
meanings such as acceleration or
sadness it might not be possible to
answer such a question directly but we
can approach the answer indirectly by
asking are there musical features that
are used in conjunction with texts and
are associated with particular
sentiments or emotions with such
regularity that we might believe that
the musical features themselves are used
to to strengthen the effect of these
affects and emotions or do they indeed
carry that affect or emotion
themselves the problem with making such
connections with the traditional musical
analysis is that there's no perfect
correlation between any musical feature
and any emotional state
we might think at least in Western
common practice tradition that words
conting Joy would tend to be higher in
Pitch than the notes around them or the
notes preceding it and it's easy to find
examples to confirm this theory in
Schubert's Gretchen on SPID Rod or
Gretchen at the spinning wheel one of
his leads every single time the word
hers which is the German for heart
appears or
smile or zor magic your cuse kiss it's
always at the same pitch height or
higher than the preceding note and
always in the upper register for the
[Music]
singer so it might sound like this is an
easy connection but then a little bit of
Elvis enters into your head but
I
can't
help falling in
[Music]
love in this song by Elvis originally
written by George Weiss and others
called can't help falling in
love we always hear the words love and
darling below the previous note even in
an expression as magistic or the full
word painting as
falling even that is set with a rising
motion so this says that individual
pieces some here and some there might
have clear relationships among text and
emotion and musical features teachers
but across a large Corpus the aggregated
experience of listening to common
practice or folk or popular music is far
more
muddled to clarify this we can turn to
Corpus studies especially computational
analysis of large repertories of musical
encoded data sets whose sheer volume
makes it impossible for human
researchers to analyze all these pieces
manually with comput methods for
extracting connections among music text
and emotion we can find statistically
significant Trends in music a
relationships that stand out from a
large Corpus even if the magnitude of
the trend itself is quite
small Sophia's son and I used a
repository of lead sheets that is
Melodies with lyrics and chord
symbols there were n about 1900 songs
189 9 5 in total that were in English
language that the encodings seem to be
high quality and that there were no
duplicates this is a repository called
wikip phonia that used to be freely
available on the internet and
unfortunately their license expired and
now uh is only available to those who
had downloaded it
beforehand in these 1900 songs there's
about 200,000 notes and a little bit
less than that in terms of the the words
and 70,000 chords so this is a big
repository to look
at we also used a second Corpus but this
one not a musical Corpus this is an open
crowdsource database of 14,000 common
English words that was made Mohammad
anney of the national research Council
of Canada and each of these words has
been coded according to the aects that
they have for instance words with the
affect of anticipation include skewed or
recreational or Zeal Holiness intimately
harbringer
birthday something I think we all
anticipate or plan and we can also look
at words that have that effect and that
effect alone so for instance if we look
at uh discust we see slim dong barf
diarrhea gratuitous
heartworm things that all only have this
particular affect together with a small
list of what we call stop words these
are words that have no affect and appear
too commonly such as the and
us she he about 60% of all the words in
the Psalms could be classified according
to affect or not having affect in the
stop list
mutal and there are at least
2,000 in instances of each affect and
some with over 12,000 that appeared in
the scorpus so there were in the
repository there were 2853 songs that
had anger in
them also in the in the Corpus were
25,000 words that were coded as being
mutual and then of those plus stop words
there were about 12,000 words that we
can be pretty sure to be neutral
and then 100 sorry 123,000 that could be
believed to be neutral and then
183,000 is all of the comprehensive uh
words that did not fill foot fit into
one of these 10
aects sun and I use Music 21 to
automatically label every instance of
the word in the data set alongside one
value that we are measuring at the time
so for instance this is the song Green
sleeves uh also known of at Christmas as
What Child Is This and in this excerpt
every word except for U the word alas
was identified by the composer by the
computer as being somewhere in the data
set but only two words in this excerpt
had a particular aect that had been
identified they a identified love as as
joy and positive and wrong as
negative so then we looked at
particular values that we could measure
for instance the one that I talked about
earlier about Pitch height so we're
going to look for each word look at the
first syllable How many semmit tones
above or below the previous note does
that word appear so my is two semitones
or a whole Step Above AAS uh love is two
semmit tones above
my going forward wrong is four semitones
below
me with measurements like this we can
test the first Theory do positive words
rise in pitch and negative words descend
in
Pitch here
is our graph of the results
for for this particular measurement what
we call the relative pitch measurement
and what we can do on the left are the
10 aects or emotions that we were
looking at anger anticipation discust
fear Joy negative positive sadness
surprise and trust and we can look at
words with that connotation compared to
the neutral words that had been
identified in the National research
Council Canada data set and we can see
that uh for instance looking across at
the Top Line um to the
highlighted to the highlighted figure
that anger was a little bit higher well
there's a plus sign so it was higher
than the neutal thing but the
0.89 is the P value that is our
confidence how often would such a value
happen by chance and um you subtract
from one so 1 minus .89 whatever it's
about 10% chance it would happened um by
chance that all the words for anger
would be higher and usually we don't
think of P values that are below 0.95 or
95% uh chance or 5% chance of happening
accidentally we don't think of those as
uh having meaning in fact when you do um
what we call a multiple comparison set
where we're looking at a lot of things
that once we really want P values that
are much better than 05 01 001 and so
on and so in this chart anger doesn't
have a particular color on the NRC
neutral set there's no no Stitch
significant value there nor does
anticipation disgust or
fear but joy on the other hand is
labeled with a uh sort of a darker blue
meaning that this is statistically
significant the three stars show how
statistically significant so words with
Joy are higher than neutral words
negative words didn't have any sort of P
value but positive words had a slight
positive uh correlation they're a little
bit higher but if we go down surprise
was a strong thing so words with
surprise were higher than other
words we can look at other parts and for
instance on the right um side this
triangular chart we can look at how each
affect correlates with another a effect
so we can see that surprise is slightly
statistically significantly higher than
words about anger or slightly
BS about
negative the column just to the right of
the yellow highlighted chart are the
stop words compared to the A and and
every single emotion or word is higher
in Pitch than a stop or you know just
think about when I say the it's pretty
low we don't tend to put this kind of
high emphasis on stops so I'm going to
show some of the things that that came
up comparing these affects to neutral
words because this seems to be the the
most fun and um interesting part of the
research so all of this this whole chart
will get reduced to a
single column in this chart and so we
can see the relative pitch that Joy
positive and surprise are
higher here is the key for the chart so
I don't show how much higher or how much
lower in pitch or how much more positive
or negative just the mag just the
direction in terms of the colors so blue
colors tend to be high in some way and M
and brown colors are lower and then the
intensity of the shade shows the P value
um so the first things that are shaded
happen only 1% chance um that they're
Happening by chance and then the next
shade is uh 1110th of 1% then going down
100th 1% 1,000th 1% one uh 10,000 1% and
you can see on the right as 10 to the -5
-6 7 you'll see some of the charts were
really showing things that are
absolutely positively not by chance
things with 10 to the -200 or or
more one of the things that we thought
was really interesting we looked at the
beat strength of every note so we
compared to the prevailing time
signature which is quite often 44 and
we're able to figure out what's on the
beat and what's off the beat and one of
the things we can see looking at the
blue parts that words conting joy and
positive emotions are really much more
common to happen on the beat similarly
with surprise and trust but looking at
things that happen off the beat or on
weak beats that's where you put the
words for anger or syncopate disgust or
fear or negative emotions tend to happen
on weaker
beats similarly we can look at the
length of notes that um almost nothing
has um a a positive correlation that
that say that is longer than you would
expect but these negative emotions anger
disgust fear and and just the general
negative tend to be on shter
notes so that we're we're really um just
sort of spitting out these short
emotions intriguing ly when we look at
the overall pitch the the pitch of a
note compared to the average pitch of
the entire song there's basically no
correlation we don't tend to
sing happy things high and set things
low only a little bit with positive
Happy Joy surprising things do we set
them a little bit higher than what was
happening
before did look at at
consonants What
notes with what words are set to notes
that are part of a consonant chord we
remember these are lead sheets so we
have the melody the words and also the
underlying chords we can see some of
these U negative emotions anger but
especially sadness and sub um are are on
more dissonant thing um notes than the
dissonant chords than the prevailing
peace but also
somewhat surprising Joy maybe that's a
way you emphasize joyful words or
surprising words you put them on
slightly um slightly more dissonant
words looked at two ways of classifying
the mode of a piece so major or minor
and um we looked at do certain emotions
appear more in songs that are in minor
versus in major and this is something
that I at least have always been taught
and I think many of us have been taught
that you know minor pieces are sad maybe
minor pieces are sad but their words
aren't any sadder than major mode pieces
There's no distinction between major and
minor uh when we look at the whole
piece so instead we used um and by the
way we will be looking later in the
semester and how we can computationally
measure the key of a piece U when we get
to Carol uh Carol Crum hansel's
work so we thought maybe you know maybe
it's not the whole piece but maybe that
these you know sad emotions appear in A
Minor section or piece using a lot of
minor chords within a larger piece so we
looked at the local mode just the mode
of the four measures on either side of
uh I think the support measures on
either side of a word and there we found
a very small correlation
but it was exactly the opposite we
expected in a local um section we use
Brown to represent minor in this case
and blue to represent major joy and
positive emotions tend to appear a
little bit more in locally minor
pieces what it might be is that there's
not this connotation of sadness or
negative or anger with minor but about
not knowing where you are so we looked
at the tonal certainty how how clear is
it what key we're in and here we found
some correlations that were negative
that is to say anger and negative words
tend to appear a little bit more in
tonally uncertain
passages now this isn't necessarily a
guide to composers for what to do but
what composers have done what people
have done in the
past so what did we learn by doing all
this words conting joy and surprise are
higher in Pitch than the surrounding
context but negative connotations such
as anger or disgust are not lower in
Pitch than a neutral
word positive words are not highlighted
with consequences if anything it's
slightly the
opposite in one measure of dissonance
however words conting sadness are more
common but negative words appear more
often in passages of tonal
uncertainty finally mode has almost no
correlation with the emotion of words
whether we're talking about the mode of
the pieace or whether the chord at that
moment is major or minor though surprise
and anticipation do get minor chords
more
often it may be that this connection of
minor with sad is one of these cases of
a purely musical connection that is to
say we've learned to hear minor music as
sad regardless of what the words are
about and this is something that as a
music historian I know hasn't been true
all throughout music's history uh there
were times when uh a pure major cordin
was considered harsh or a little bit sad
and that's not the case today but but
maybe when people do consistently report
in music psychology surveys that they
hear sadness in minor
pieces that there's something happening
that's not fully explained in the words
so there's always more research to
happen and I just want to thank you for
allowing me to share what Sophia son and
myself have found