Good evening everybody and welcome to
tonight's Broad Discovery Series event.
I'm Tom Olrich and I'm the associate
director for science communications here
at the Broad Institute. It's my pleasure
to welcome everybody in in the room and
everybody online who's joining us this
evening. For those of us who are joining
us for the first time, the Broad
Discovery series explores the genetic
and biological roots of human health and
disease, the mechanisms that govern how
our cells and bodies function, new
technologies that are changing what's
possible in science, and new advances
that could be translated into treatments
for common and rare diseases. It's my
pleasure to introduce our speaker for
tonight, Shomo Raichodri.
Shomo is an institute member here at the
broad director of the center for data
sciences and the JS Coblin MB Brener
distinguished chair in rheumatology and
immunology at Brighamin Women's Hospital
a professor of medicine and of
biomedical informatics at Harvard
Medical School and he also is a clinical
rheatologist.
Shomo's lab studies the genetic risk
factors and mechanisms that underly
autoimmune diseases like rheumatoid
arthritis. And tonight he's going to
talk about how that research is
revealing a lot about how the immune
system and the genome as a whole work
basically.
This evening also marks the 2025
Elelliana Hector Memorial Lecture
presented in memory of Elelliana and
with the support of the Elelliana Hector
Memorial Fund. Aliana was a gifted MDPhD
student and a member of the Broad
community. And I'd like to take a moment
to thank her family and friends and
loved ones who are watching us this
evening.
If you have any questions for Shomo, I
encourage you to flag down one of our
micr runners during the Q&A portion of
the evening. And if you're watching
online, uh, please drop your questions
into YouTube chat. I'll do my best to
work them into the conversation as the
evening goes on.
If you're a Brody or a scientist with a
deep technical question for Shomo, I
encourage you to approach him after the
Q&A or during the reception uh so that
members of the community have an
opportunity to ask their questions. And
speaking of the reception, I invite
everybody here in the room to join us in
the Broad Discovery Center right out
here outside the auditorium after
tonight's talk uh for a short reception.
And I also encourage you to explore the
uh museum's exhibits and interactive
elements. Shomo, take it away.
[Applause]
Okay. Um, thank you everyone for uh sort
of joining me uh after after your busy
days. Um, so um today I'm going to talk
about uh autoimmunity in in general and
the specific manifestation of
autoimmunity which is uh uh immune
arthritis and rheumatoid arthritis. And
uh I'm going to be presenting that from
the perspective of someone who thinks a
lot about the genome and how the genome
works. Um so um the immune system I
think for most of us when we think about
the immune system we think about B cells
and T- cells um and and we and and it's
true that those are very important
components of the immune system but the
immune system is actually uh broader
than that. It's a system of cells,
tissues,
organs and processes that protect um
that protect us against external and
internal threats uh that lead to
disease. Um and and typically its most
important role is is obviously protect
us from pathogens such as viruses and
bacteria. Uh but it also protects us uh
well sort of protects us from foreign
tissues. For example, we get a
transplant um or damaged tissues. For
example, when we develop mutations that
lead to cancer, uh the immune system
works to prevent that. Um uh and it
involves a whole range of of organs uh
including the organs that house T- cell
to B cells such as tonsils and legones.
Uh but it also involves other organs
that you don't normally think of as
imunologicals. for example, the skin uh
or the gut wall which protect you from
um the the bacteria and the other
pathogens that live you know on the
other side of of of us.
Um we are becoming increasingly aware of
the important role that the immune
system plays in so many different
diseases. Um infectious diseases again
uh is something we think about most most
commonly in terms of the immune system.
autoimmune and autoinflammatory diseases
which is going to be a focus uh in this
talk. Uh we've over the last 10 years
realized important role of immune system
in preventing and treating cancer. Um
and uh and now there's emerging data of
the role of immune system in
neuroscychiatric and
neurodedevelopmental diseases in
metabolic diseases and cardiac diseases
uh and the list goes on. Um in many
instances the immune system is not the
major player uh in in all of these
conditions. Uh sometimes it's a it's a
secondary role uh but immune system is
very targetable through therapeutics. So
sometimes the role it plays is exactly
the role that we can uh go after uh with
the drugs that are being developed.
Um so um they're really a sort of a
dichotomy to the immune system when we
think about it. Um they're they're two
uh separate components and obviously
there's some overlap but the exchange
are the innate immune system and the ad
that domain immune system um the innate
system is the part of the immune system
that's non-specific. So when you first
get an infection um it's the part that
responds. It doesn't really uh remember
uh and doesn't really have memory um in
in the sort of typical sense of memory.
um and it acts quickly and broadly. Um
and it's sort of your first line of
defense and it includes things like
barriers. Um the adaptive immune system
uh is a little bit more specific. Uh
when you get a particular infection or
still pathogen that you experience or
encounter, it's the adaptive immune
system that learns it, protects you from
it. It's the part of the immune system
that we activate when we get a vaccine.
Um and it acts more slowly than the
innate immune system but acts with more
precision and protects you from when
that threat occurs again.
Um and again a lot of the times if you
think about these uh components of the
immune system in terms of the cell types
that that are the muscle behind them for
the innate immune cells there's cells
like uh the neutrfil the eosinaphil the
macage and for the adaptive immune
system uh they're the T- cells the B
cells the positive cells the cells that
make the antibodies um the B cells um
and those those play the part role um
and uh and as we think about
autoimmunity is really the adaptive
immune system that we're going to be
focusing on. Um, so I'm going to make a
subtle uh distinction between
autoimmunity and autoinflammatory
diseases. So autoimmune diseases are
diseases when your immune system attacks
an organ because it mistakes it as a a
threat. Um, and then there's there's a
wide range of autoimmune diseases where
the immune system is going after a
particular multiple organs and that
really um is your adaptive immune system
gone wrong. The auto-in-flammatory
diseases are the ones where your um your
innate immune system is is
malfunctioning. Um a lot of those
diseases have a systemic component uh
can be accompanied with systemic
inflammation or or chronic inflammation.
And the reality is most of the diseases
that we call autoimmune or
auto-inflammatory uh really live
somewhere on a continuum.
Um so the autoimmune diseases is where
where I'm going to be uh focusing on
today. Um these are um diseases that can
really affect every organ system. Some
of them are very specific. For example,
thyroiditis affects the thyroid organ.
Uh ulcerative colitis is a disease where
your immune system is attacking very
specifically the the the colon. Um and
then there are other uh conditions that
are more non-specific such as systemic
lupus or systemic vasculitis where the
immune system is really uh attacking
multiple organs uh all at the same time.
um these conditions are are individually
rare. So if you think of a condition
like systemic lupus or or type 1
diabetes, they affect one in a thousand
or three in a thousand individuals. Uh
some of these conditions are a little
more common such as psoriasis which is a
imunological disease of the skin which
affects about three in a 100 uh
individuals. Uh but if you put it all
together about one in 20 individuals
have some type of autoimmune disease. So
they're um in aggregate um uh in
aggregate more common uh than than we
think of them as.
Uh the disease I'm going to spend a lot
of my time on and I've spent a lot of my
career on is rheumatoid arthritis. Um
rheumatoid arthritis uh is a condition u
that's kind of a relatively new disease.
I mean it was really described for the
first time in 1800 and that was when a
medical student uh in France in the year
8 of the French Republic um or the year
1800 by our calendar uh recognized a
condition uh that he called athena gout.
Uh he basically looked at nine
individuals um and understood that these
individuals had a a type of gout that
was different from the typical gout. It
affected women predominantly. It had a
chronic core, so it wasn't sort of
coming and going the way gout typically
does. Um, and it affect multiple joints
um all at the same time. It was
polyarticular.
Um, today we know that rheumatoid
arthritis is a disease that affects uh
about one in a 100 individuals. Uh, it
leads to systemic destruction uh of of
the joints and the hands and many other
uh joints. Um uh and there's a
particular tissue that's really
important in the synovium called the uh
or in rheumatoid arthritis called the
synovium. So you see this uh thin
membrane that surrounds the healthy
joint. When people have rheumatoid
arthritis, that joint becomes inflamed
and engorged um with uh immune cells um
and that uh engorged tissue then works
into the joint and solely destroys it.
um uh the disease can lead to systemic
uh complications um such as lung
involvement um uh and and and it can
affect uh other other organs uh as well.
Um so before um I go further into this,
I'm going to present how I thought about
the immune system u maybe when I was
like a medical student. Um, and I think
I think maybe a lot of us uh, well,
maybe I won't speak for anybody else
besides myself. Uh, but but when I first
thought about the immune system, I sort
of thought of it as something you either
have more of or less of, right? That
there's uh, individuals in the middle
who are immunompetent. Um, and either
because you're on a problematic drug or
or your immune system is somehow
compromised, you might move to the left
and be imunompromised and and therefore
you might get an infection. Uh or you
might be uh someone who has an overly
active immune system. Um in which case
you have um an autoimmune or
auto-inflammatory disease and what you
really want to do is somehow um get to
the middle. Um
uh this view that I had was really uh uh
challenged uh when I was a young medical
student uh before I knew I would do
anything with uh immunological diseases.
Uh when I had an attending doctor uh
called Hal Holman. Hal died last year.
Um Hal is um and again when he was my
attending I'm not sure I appreciated
this about him but he was really one of
the founders of of the field of of
immunology and he kept talking about
autoimmune diseases as uh a condition
where one thing can blend into another
or that there can be different
components to it. Um, and I really
didn't know what he was talking about
um, until I came to understand that he
was the person who originally uh,
described a a condition called mixed
connective tissue disease. Um, and this
was a particular imunological condition
where you could have one of or multiple
of many uh, manifestations such as
arthritis, uh, myasitis um, renal
disease uh, and and you can see the long
long list here. Um, and every patient
can look a little bit different. Um, and
I think that's a kind of general
principle of of autoimmunity. Um, that
it's not just really one flavor. It's a
lot of components that can fit together
in complicated ways. Um uh Hal was also
a remarkable guy in that uh his career
at different points was derailed by his
political activities including uh uh
being blacklisted by um uh by the
McCarthyists and and and uh losing his
job as as the chair of Stanford uh
medicine uh because uh of his protest of
the Vietnam War. So he was a very
influential guy in a lot of ways to
those of us in the medical community.
Um
uh so autoimmunity um is very difficult
to diagnose uh and also to treat. Um uh
as I mentioned uh many of our patients
have multiple autoimmune um symptoms uh
and they don't neatly fit into these
categories that I told you about uh in
the beginning. Um another thing that's
uh uh interesting about autoimmunity is
that in the last couple decades we have
a large armamentarium of different
therapeutics. we obviously need more uh
but it can take us years to find the
right treatment for the right patient
and a lot of times uh we don't know if
we have our patient on the best possible
therapy um and uh and there's some
consequences to that um because as we
search for the right therapy our
patients are facing in the case of
arthritis joint damage or damage to
their uh other organs they can have
reduced quality of life um and uh for a
lot of our patients they end up being
managed on steroids which can work but
have a lot of other complications
associated with them, including an
increased risk of of of heart disease.
Um, so I thought I would just uh tell
you about a few uh few quick cases uh uh
a couple of my my patients. Um, so this
is a a woman that I met about 7 years
ago. She was 59 at the time. Uh, when I
saw her, she had complained that her
hands were stiff and swollen, which is
typical of of inflammatory arthritis. Um
she had taken medications like ibuprofen
which helped a little bit but not that
much. Uh and she had a family history of
rheumatoid arthritis. And on the on the
right here you see her hand and you can
imagine how painful that thumb uh thumb
must have been. Uh we did some tests um
and her tests were actually were
actually negative for rheumatoid
arthritis uh but positive for lupus. But
despite that we treated her for
rheumatoid arthritis because that's um
that's what her clinical picture looked
like. a disease that mostly affected the
hands um and mostly affected uh her her
other joints to a lesser extent. Um
so uh this is uh sort of uh her five her
next five years uh with me. Um and
without getting into all the details,
she basically went uh on eight different
treatments in a fiveyear span. Um and
and since this slide, she's continued to
cycle through other treatments and each
one works to some extent but doesn't get
her all the way better. And again, this
is the one of the challenges of our
patients that were sometimes struggling
to find the right drug for them.
Um, this is another patient. Um, this is
a uh 34 year old woman that I met about,
um, 13 years ago. Uh, she originally
presented with a certain amount of
stiffness in the morning. Uh, she had
presented to her primary care doctor for
tendinitis. She had had some episodes of
sort of a flare of of her tendons. uh
she was managed uh with prennazone to
get her wrists uh better. Um so when I
saw her I saw that her skin was
involved. She had psoriasis in her skin.
Um her she tested positive for lupus and
tested positive for inflammation. Uh but
I treated her for seriatic arthritis
because I thought likely uh it was
likely the case that the disease of her
skin and the disease of her joints went
together. So the same imunological
derangement that was causing her skin to
be involved was also causing her joints
to be involved. Um
uh so um for the next 10 years this is
what happened. Um we started her on
prennazone and got her off. We put her
on an anti-inflammatory something like
ibuprofen a little bit stronger called
nebumatone. Um she tried to stop taking
it a few times but flared. So um so she
was persuaded to get back on it. Um and
and then after a while even though she
was uh on that medication she started
developing uh more swelling um in her
shoulder and her pinky. So we started a
stronger medication called laflunamide.
Um in 2020 her mom became my patient
because her mom also had the same
condition. Uh diseases like this can
sometimes be familial. Um and in 2022
she went to the emergency room because
she had some shortness of breath and and
some uh chest pain. They were worried
about a pulmonary ambism and they did
this CT scan on her and you can see here
that there's some things that you
shouldn't have in your lungs. She has
these big masses over here. Um and um
and initially the thought was that this
might be some kind of uh some kind of
malignancy. Um the clue was um the first
clue that uh it was something else was
when we looked at our inflammation
markers. Um you can see in 2019 they
weren't that high. they were in the in
sort of the 10 to 20 range, a little bit
higher than normal. And as we went
through time, you can see that that
inflammation level really climbing up
high on her. And so after after doing a
lung biopsy, what we came to realize is
that she actually had those masses
weren't a malignant mass, but they were
an inflammatory mass. She had a
condition called sarcoidosis, which is a
type of infiltrating inflammation. We
treated her initially with prennazone
and then we put her on another very
targeted drug called infleximab and
right now she's doing fine. Um but but
there's also this question of how long
will this drug work for her? Is it the
right drug? Um so a lot of these um u a
lot of these choices that we make to
keep our patients well are a little bit
um um arbitrary and based on experience
and based on clinical data but not
really as based on the science as as as
we would ideally like.
Um so so I so I would say actually the
um uh the our view of the immune system
my view of the immune system is that
it's much more complicated than a simple
you know you don't have enough or you
have too much because it can manifest
itself in lots of complic complex ways
causing complex symptoms um and um and
and we and the immune system probably
has many dimensions. It's not a simple
spectrum. it's probably highly
multifaceted with many different
components and each component itself can
be disregulated leading to different
disease manifestations. So if you go
back to this uh picture of all these
different cells, you can appreciate that
each of these cells themselves are one
of those components. And then if you
take a particular cell like like say the
T- cells and you zoom in, what you see
is that when you uh take a T- cell and
look at the spectrum of tea cells um uh
even those tea cells are not a monolith.
Uh there's rather multiple functional
categories each playing a different role
in the immune system. some of which are
honing in on specific antigens and and
going after it and coordinating the
immune system to attack others which are
actually more regulatory in nature
trying to trying to keep the other parts
of the immune system in check so you
don't have too much of a a reaction and
we'll come back to the regulatory tea
cells later on
um and um that complexity is actually
something we can exploit so uh we um so
there's a an upside to this complexity
uh which is that we can develop drugs to
go after these different components So
um for example, if you think a dis
disease or a particular type of
inflammation is being driven by B cells,
well maybe you should use a medication
like ocrolusamab which is used in
multiple sclerosis also used in lupus
because it deletes B cells. Um if you
want to do something about TE- cells
because you think the inflammation is T-
cell driven, you might use Abotaccept
which which blocks uh T- cell
activation. Or if you want to enhance
TE- cells because you're trying to
trying to fight a malignancy, you might
use Prolysmab which activates TE- cells
so that you're killing uh your tumor. Um
and and sometimes what you want to do is
block the way particular immune cells
are communicating with each other. In
that case, you want to really go after
cytoines uh and block uh those cytoines
which serve as the uh messages between
cells. So anti6 which I'll come back to
later on or toolsimab blocks that cell
cell communication.
Um so um a lot of the uh goals that I
have or the goals we have in the lab is
to try to define the modifiable
components of the immune system. Um and
the strategy that we've taken is is
first to really focus on human data. Um
there's a lot of animal models of of uh
uh immune diseases which have been very
useful over many decades as we've
developed different different drugs but
um but people are are different from
mice in some ways some small ways um and
uh and so trying to find the things that
really work for humans and human disease
is is very important to us. Um the
second is uh is what you might call
human immunology which is to really
define the key uh uh tissue cell
populations really find those cell
populations those immune cell
populations that are active in inflamed
tissue and try to try to modulate them.
And then the third thing is to focus on
causal biology. uh we focus on genetics
because it's inherited and the genetic
differences in different people that
predispose you to a particular disease
have to be causal because you're born
with them and you have those changes
long before you have the disease.
Um so um so so this is the idea so that
you know on the left we're we're uh
looking at genetics to define causal
biology in humans. uh on the right we're
using human immunology to define the
essential compon components of tissue
inflammation. And the idea is if we can
find that causal biology that's working
in a specific cellular context or tissue
context, then we can really develop
tissue specific or cell type specific
therapies that are both effective for
inflammation but also safe because
you're not just turning the whole immune
system down or turning the whole immune
system up in case you're trying to
trying to activate it.
Um so um so I'm going to start uh this
next part of the talk by really focusing
on tissue and tissue inflammation. Um so
as I mentioned uh I had a cartoon of
this before for rheumatoid arthritis
what we really pay attention to is the
synovium. It's this thin membrane that
surrounds the joint. Uh and you can see
it uh not so well on the left because
that's a healthy knee. Um so it's it's a
barely visible membrane. On the right
you can see the synovium. It's all that
red stuff. So that small membrane has
now become inflamed uh and is really uh
really digging into the joint and
causing problems. Um so one strategy
that you might think would be you know
useful is to really try to understand
what those cell states are in that
inflamed synovium. Maybe if we
understood what those cell types are,
what those cell states are, those would
be places that we could target for
therapeutic uh therapeutic benefit. Um
so um the the work I'm going to describe
is uh is is really um a project I've had
the pleasure of being a part of but is a
large um um uh you know national even
international uh consortium of of of
many different institutions and many
different individuals. Um and it's
called the AMP RA Lupus Network. It's um
driven by the NIH and and by private
funders as well. Um and I just want to
acknowledge some of the key people uh
fan Helena Parnia who who led a lot of
the analyses uh that I'm about to show.
Um so this project uh was conceived um
you know sort of uh around 2017 2018 and
at this time what was happening was that
single cell technologies were really
taking off. Um so it was now becoming
possible uh to uh look at individual
cells and measure all the genes and how
active they were in individual cells.
And as you can see that technology was
really looking at like you know one to
10 cells uh a decade earlier and now we
were able to look at 10,000 100,000
cells all in one go. Um and so we wanted
to apply that to rheumatoid arthritis.
Um and um this is some of the data that
came out of that study. So uh we assayed
uh inflammatory tissues inflammatory
synovium from rheumatoid arthritis
patients uh to get a data set of 300,000
cells and what you see here are the
major cell types. So no surprise it's
inflamed tissue. So you see B cells, T-
cells, myoid cells and K cells. But you
also see some of the tissue cells, the
endothelial cells and the fibroblasts
which are also interacting with immune
uh cells uh to to kind of propagate uh
propagate inflammation.
So um one of the first things that we
saw uh which was a little bit surprising
to us because um all of these patients
had the same disease. They all had
rheumatoid arthritis. But when we
started looking at their inflammation
and simply asking how many T- cells are
we seeing in a given sample? How many B
cells are we seeing in a given sample?
We started to see that there's some
individuals that have a lot of myoid
cells, a lot of macrofasages. There are
other individuals that have a lot of T-
cells and B cells. Those are in the
middle. very creatively we call them T
plusB. Um some of them have a lot of T-
cells and fiberblast we call them T plus
F. Um so we actually found six different
groups um of of patients. Um so this was
a lot more heterogeneity in terms of
tissue inflammation than we expected to
see. Um so this exercise and cell
counting is really interesting. But what
what about if you just like look at the
tissue? Do you see the differences that
we see when we count cells when you
actually look at the at the biopsy
samples? Um, and here we're looking at a
at a simple H& pathology slide. At the
top you're looking at the F individuals,
those individuals that have a lot of
fibroblasts. At the bottom, you're
looking at the TB individuals, those
individuals that have lots of T and B
cells. And these are just two
representative samples. And right away,
you see that these two things don't look
the same. The bottom has a lot of
purple. That indicates a lot of
cellularity relative to what we see in
the top.
Looking a little bit deeper, we can
stain them for uh for T- cells and B
cells. So you see the bottom really
lighting up with T- cells and B cells uh
with the light blue indicating T- cells,
the purple indicating the B cells. And
you can see sort of clusters of those
immune cells uh uh occurring together.
So it's not just that you have a lot of
these cells, but they live in the tissue
in a very particular way.
If you stain for fibroblasts, you also
see something interesting. So if you
look at the individuals that have a lot
of fibroblasts, they don't just have any
kind of fibroblast. They have a lot of
these click five positive fibroblast.
And you see where they are. They're
surrounding um they're surrounding uh
the tissue. So these are what we call
the lining fiberblast. So it's a very
particular kind of fibroblast that these
individuals have. So again pointing to
this kind of interesting hetrogenity
that we have in these samples. So our
first thought was like you know maybe
what we're seeing is people with more
active disease, people with less active
disease, maybe the people who have the
fibroblast rich uh RA, maybe they just
have less active disease. and the people
that have lots of T- cells and B cells
maybe have more active disease. That's
not actually what we saw when we looked
at these samples and we looked at their
disease activity of of the individual
patients. We saw that they were all
actually pretty active. Um so the
differences in the tissue uh didn't just
go with how um how affected or how
active an individual patient was.
But are there implications for
treatment? Uh that's also a really
important question. uh and we worked
with uh with some of our colleagues in
the UK. We looked at some clinical trial
data uh and they had samples that were
treated with multiple imunom modulatory
drugs. One that went after B cells, one
that went after uh anti-IL6. They had
133 patients. And we were able to take
their patients and figure out which of
these categories their tissue would fit
into. And what we saw is that the
likelihood that you'd respond to
treatment did have something to do with
what type of inflammation uh your tissue
had. Specifically, we saw that the
individuals who had a lot of fibroblasts
um they were less likely to respond. And
this isn't a surprise because that
fibroblast proliferating um tissue
inflammation, that's not the kind of
thing that our drugs go after. Our drugs
go after B cells and T- cells. Um, so
this is a a a category of patient that
maybe we're not treating uh as well as
we should.
Um, so now we can look at each of those
six major cell types, the T- cells, NK
cells, fibroblast or stomal cells, and
we can look at the hetrogenity within
them. And what we see is that within
each of these populations, there's a a
wealth of heterogeneity. Um, so I'm
going to look at T- cells because u
that's one of the most important cell
types for us in the world of u uh
autoimmune diseases. Uh, and what we see
here is that there's uh, uh, 24 uh
different um, uh, T- cell types. You
might see that the number only goes up
to 23. That's because in our lab we
start counting from zero. Um, it's a
computer science kind of thing. Um, so
um, uh, so really a lot of interesting
hetrogenity. And one of the questions we
wanted to ask is are the T- cells that
we see in people that have a lot of T-
cells and fibroblast different from the
T- cells that we see in individuals that
have T- cells and B cells or different
from the people that we see that have T-
cells and myoid cells. Are they all the
same TE- cells or are there differences?
Um, and it turns out that these six
flavors of inflammation not only have
different amounts of TE- cells, but they
also have different kinds of T- cells.
So the people who have lots of T- cells
and B cells um you can see that they
have a particular kind of T- cell which
is these T3 T7 T peripheral helper
cells. For the people who have T- cells
and fibroblast they have they don't have
an enrichment for those kinds of T-
cells. They have other T- cells that are
enriched. Um so um so it's not enough
just to know that someone has a lot of
T- cells but also the type of T- cell
they have can can vary. Um and those T-
cells up in the upper left corner are
really interesting to us. We spent a lot
of time thinking about them. uh those
te- cells uh as you can see have a lot
of expression of IL6 receptor or IL6R.
Um, so these are the individuals. These
are the cells that we're sort of going
after when we use toolsab that anti-6
drug I told you about. We think of it as
something that disrupts communication in
the immune system. But actually what
you're doing is you're disrupting
communication with a particular type of
tea cell. So that drug is actually a lot
more specific than we maybe give it
credit for. What about fibroblasts? Um,
so these are not cells that we normally
think of as immune cells. They they make
up the sort of structure of of the
tissue. Um and what we see is that
there's multiple uh fibroblast uh
population. So there's the F uh type of
inflammation with lots of fibroblast,
but there's some people with a lot of T-
cells and fibroblast, other people with
endothelial cells, fibroblast and myoid
cells. Are they all the same? Uh and
again, we can do the same kind of
analysis. And what you see is that these
F-1 populations are really enriched in
the individuals that have the uh the
most fiberblast. So people who have the
most fiberblast in their inflammatory
tissue, they don't just have a lot of
fibroblast. They have a specific
enrichment for this particular type of
fiberblast called the lining
fibiberblast. So just tuck that away
because I'll come back to that in a in a
few minutes.
Um so so hopefully I've convinced you
that tissue inflammation in RA and
probably in other diseases isn't
homogeneous. It's rather heteroggeneous.
uh uh we looked at cell populations in
RA senovial inflammation in this case
and we found that different patients
have different types of cell type
heterogeneity um and that hetrogenity
may have something to do with treatment
response and different cell states track
with different inflammatory subtypes and
there's some potential there because
that might mean that different drugs may
be most effective against specific
cellular uh subtypes and maybe certain
patients would do better with certain
kinds of drugs than other kinds of
patients.
Um, so now I'm going to switch gears and
and talk about the genetics. Uh, up
until now I've been talking about uh
tissue immunity. Uh, but uh but but it's
hard to know when you look at inflamed
tissue what's causing the inflammation
and what's responding to the
inflammation. The genetics maybe hopes
to help us untangle that.
Most of the time when we talk about
genetics um casually we're talking about
mandelian genetics. So so these are
diseases that kind of run in the family.
So uh you know you can imagine your
typical mandelian disease um is one
where uh your one of your parents uh has
the gene and uh a child inherits it and
they maybe have the disease as well.
That's a a dominant uh genetic disease.
So these are kind of familial uh
genetics which are highly predictive. um
uh rheumatoid arthritis, most autoimmune
diseases and most complex diseases are
complex uh genetic diseases which
involve hundreds of thousands of uh of
different genes and often have a pretty
large environmental component. Um each
gene or mutation makes a tiny uh plays a
tiny role uh in disease risk. Um and the
genetics is only somewhat predictive um
of of disease.
Uh one of the key metrics we use is uh
is sibling risk. So we ask um you know
if if a if your sibling has a the
disease what's your relative increase in
risk. So for disease like rheumatoid
arthritis which is present in about one
in a 100 individuals if you have an
affected sibling your risk goes up to
about four in 100. So we would say the
this metric this lambda s is about four.
Um and you can see that uh for all of
these diseases there's an increased risk
if you have a first-degree relative or a
sibling that has this uh condition
suggesting that there is some kind of
genetic basis to it. It's not 100 or a
thousand. That's what we would see with
a more familial uh genetic disease.
Um we've been working on the genetics of
rheumatoid arthritis for like a really
long time. We've been uh been doing this
for about 20 years now. um and uh in
that time we found 150 different um risk
alals or 150 different uh risk lossi.
These are regions of the genome that are
driving uh risk of rheumatoid arthritis.
Um it's really a global effort. Um our
lab is has been lucky to be a part of
it. Um but as you can see uh in our our
latest study uh which we published in
2022 um we uh had uh global
representation uh capturing five
different major ancestries. Study had
about 40,000 cases and 240,000 controls
uh that we analyzed.
Um and I won't talk too much about the
HLA locus. The HLA locus is a critical
component of the machinery that displays
antigens to tea cells. Um and if you if
you look at the whole genome and um here
each spot represents an individual snip
or genetic marker uh what you see is
there's this like massive tower um in
chromosome 6 and that's the HLA region.
So it's a really important player in
rheumatoid arthritis risk. Um and uh we
had fine mapped the signal to an
individual spot in an individual protein
which we think is really important for
how the immune system recognizes
antigens h and how it interacts with te-
cells to activate them.
I'm going to spend most of the time
today talking about the other LOSI. Um
so um for all those other 149 uh LOSI in
the genome only about 10% of them are
what we call coding alals. These are uh
changes in the DNA that actually change
the protein. Uh 90% of them are outside
of genes. And we think they work by
altering how uh the gene is controlled
and how the gene is regul the genes are
regulated. Um most of these uh changes
are changes in individual base pairs. Uh
it's a single uh uh change in a single
spot in the genome. Um and what we've
noticed is that these snips are very
often close to genes. Many of these
genes are important for T- cell biology.
Um and they they very often sit in
regions called regulatory regions that
control uh the function of those of
those genes.
Um
now um one of the reasons uh one of the
things that we think a lot about is that
these snips are really hard to
interpret. They're really hard to make
sense of for a couple reasons. One, if
you find a given snip that's associated
with disease, it's not by itself driving
the risk necessarily because there's a
whole bunch of snips nearby that are all
correlated with it that are inherited
together in a block. So it's very
difficult to know whether the the single
variant that we're reporting on is the
driver or if it's a marker for some
other signal that's nearby. Um
the snips are often as I mentioned in
regulatory DNA. So they tweak expression
of a nearby gene and they influence how
genes work. So trying to understand
those regulatory mechanisms have been a
really important focus of our our lab's
work. Um and some of the snips turn the
uh activity on uh activity up for a
gene. Some of them turn it down. Um, but
one of the other uh things that we think
a lot about is some of these snips
matter in very specific cells or cell
states. Um, and we often don't know what
the right cell type or cell state is.
And so we spend a lot of time trying to
figure that out.
Um, so for um any given locus um uh we
need to define what the driving snip is.
And as you can see this is this is kind
of a typical region and each of these
points represents a a genetic change or
or a snip. And you can see there's a
whole row of red uh uh changes there.
Whole row of red snips. Those are all
correlated with each other. So you can't
just simply look at that and know which
one is the one driving disease. Um so
it's really important for us to think
about the downstream gene, to think
about the downstream functional effect,
and to think about the cell state that
it matters the most in. Um and all of
these problems are interlin with each
other. So it's a little bit like a like
a Jenga uh puzzle where uh you know if
you don't solve all of them in some
sense at the same time the whole thing
can fall apart. So so that's um yeah so
that's that's my life. Um so so um so we
take uh two uh overarching uh
approaches. Um one is a statistical
approach and then the other is a
functional experimental approach. And on
the statistical side, we're analyzing
human data from patients from healthy
individuals to look at how these genetic
changes uh affect uh the activity of a
gene or an activity of some kind of
molecular fingerprint. On the right
side, we're interrogating cells trying
to change the DNA to see what happens to
figure out what the functional effect of
an individual genetic changes.
Um so I'll walk you through u one
example. Um so uh this is a a
statistical computational technique uh
in this case. So what we're doing is
we're fine mapping a locus. Um this
particular locus is called um DNA1L3. So
we see this particular snip uh that was
flagged in a large genetic study. And
when we dug into it, what we saw is that
that snip actually fell right in the
middle of this gene called DNA1 L3. It
actually stopped the function of the of
the protein. It actually was a
disruptive mutation. it changes the an
arginine to a cysteine in that protein.
Um and and so we uh felt very confident
that this is the causal uh causal gene.
Um now when you go back and look at that
single cell data I told you about what
you see is that this gene is very
specifically expressed in lining
fibroblasts. Um so not only is this gene
important in in uh causing RA, it's
important in the right context uh which
is a very particular fiberblast
population um that that we sometimes see
expanded in some of our patients with
tissue inflammation. And you can imagine
if you wanted to target this particular
gene, you would want to do it in those
individuals maybe who had the most
amount of these lining fibroblasts
because because that's that's where the
action is. Um and this is what I showed
you before. Uh this is that same
population that's expanded in our CTAPF
individuals. Uh but most ch losi are
more challenging. So uh most of them 90%
of them are uh non-coding change. They
don't change the protein but they
control how the protein is regulated. Um
and so we need to really think about
regulatory elements um and and how they
work and in which cell states they work.
Um so um so here we use expression
quantitative trait lossi or eqls and we
use let gene expression be our guide. Um
and so so if a snip is regulatory maybe
you would think that that uh snip is
sitting there in a promoter or enhancer.
You can see here I have an a to change
and that's disrupting how a
transcription factor or the regulatory
machinery interacts with the DNA and
maybe that has an effect on gene
expression.
Um and for for for example for a
particular snip this is an RA snip uh
which is near the BLK gene. You can see
that as you have as your uh genotype
goes from GG to GC to CC the expression
of this particular gene BLK is
negatively affected and maybe that's the
mechanism for how individuals with two C
alles get a little bit closer to having
an autoimmune disease.
And as I mentioned the challenge for
this is that this regulatory machinery
may change from cell to cell from cell
state to cell state. So finding the
right context is really important to
understand how these snips are are are
working. Um and again as I mentioned for
te- cells there's this complexity um and
as I showed you when we look in synovial
tissue um it's a very rich complexity
with all of those 24 uh different cell
states.
We've been really interested in using
statistical and computational methods to
understand this kind of complexity. And
here's a here's an example of a
particular snip uh that we've been
interested in. It's an RA risk alil. And
when we looked at single cell T- cell
data, we see that this snip doesn't have
much of an effect uh on gene expression
in the blue cells. Um so you can see in
the in the lower left, you know, if you
uh depending on which snip you have, you
have only a small change in gene
expression. But in other cell states, uh
the red ones, you can see that the snip
is really affecting gene expression. So
again, you would think that this snip is
modulating risk in these particular uh
cell states. Um and in fact, if you look
at all of the variants that alter gene
regulation in T- cells, and here we're
looking at about 6,000 of them, not all
of these are are disease alles. Uh but
what we find uh is that uh many of these
snips about a third of them 2,000 out of
6,000 um have cell state specific
effects. Um so they're doing different
things in different uh cell states. So
the therapeutic implication is that if
the goal is to target these genes, then
it may be particularly effective to
target the right cell type and the right
cell context and maybe in the right
patient.
Um so um so now I'll talk a little bit
about the functional uh some of the
functional approaches that we take. Um
so one of the things we've been really
interested in is trying to um you know
after we've prioritized causal variation
with these uh tools after we think we
have the snip that that we think is
driving disease we want to really
confirm it. Um and uh and we think it's
really important to functionally confirm
the molecular effect of these disease
alals. Um and and the approach we take
is is this gene editing approach. Um, so
the idea is that you have a snip, it's
sitting in the DNA. Uh, maybe that snip
is having an effect on a downstream
gene. We really want to prove it. Um, so
what we might do is do gene editing to
change uh to change the identity of that
DNA in this case from an A to a T. And
then maybe what we'll see is that the
expression of a downstream gene
increases and then we understand what
the molecular effect of that DNA change
is.
Now in practice, it's a lot more
complicated than that. When we try to
edit cells, we're not always successful.
We edit a minority of the cells that we
try to try to go after, particularly for
immune cells. So, you might be looking
at a population of cells, and you might
only be successfully editing one of
these uh in the middle. Um, so we
developed a method called Minecraft
Seek. Um, uh, when we tried to publish
it, uh, some of the, uh, the journal
told us that there's apparently a video
game, uh, called Minecraft. So uh so
they asked us to change the name uh so
that we don't detract from the
popularity of the video game. Um so what
we do here is we take our cells, we try
to edit them, some of them get edited
successfully, some of them don't. And
then what we do is we sort those cells
into a into a plate and then we assay
every individual cell. Um and when we do
this, we are looking at the DNA of the
cells to see if we've changed um uh
changed the DNA successfully. And then
we're looking at other molecular markers
uh to see ho how the effect of that alil
is on other uh other parameters. So each
cell is its own experiment here um
because in the population some are
edited some are not uh and then when we
define the downstream uh effects of the
alals we can simply compare the cells
that we edited in the same experiment to
the ones that we didn't. Um so so here's
a particular uh snip that I think is
really interesting. Uh this is a snip
that causes type 1 diabetes, asthma,
lupus, and rheumatoid arthritis. It
plays a role in a lot of autoimmune
diseases. It's near a gene called IL2.
Um and when we apply this technology uh
and we look at aector T- cells, um we
see that what whatever uh version of the
snip we introduce that it doesn't really
have an effect on IL2 protein. uh on the
other hand when we look at regulatory T-
cells the kind of te- cells that reduce
inflammation what we see is that this
snip uh actually increases the
expression of IL2 protein so individuals
that have the protective T alil they
actually have a higher expression of
CD25 but they do so um specifically in
the regulatory T- cell and not the other
kind of T- cell. So what does that what
does that mean? So um so the results
prove that the RA protective alil
increases IL2RA.
Um but the alil that drives reduced risk
acts in T- cells uh in in T- rags but
not other T- cells. Um and the
provocative idea here is that this
indicates a cell state specific
mechanism. So if you want to develop a
therapy towards IL2 or IL2, you really
need to think about which TE- cells
you're going after and it probably
really needs to be specific for
regulatory T- cells. Um and such a
therapy may be uh most effective in
those individuals that have
dysfunctional many dysfunctional T-regs
uh operating in their inflamed tissues.
Um so I come back to this. So um so
hopefully I've I've convinced you um
that it's useful to think about genetics
um and the immune system together. um
thinking about observational immunology
data finds a lot of the changes that
occur in the tissue that might be
important and the genetics helps to get
uh us to causal mechanisms that we can
we can maybe target. Um so um so before
before I close um I hope uh you know
we've answered some of these questions.
Can we use genetics to define
therapeutics for autoimmune diseases? Um
I think the answer is yes. uh the
genetics has already pointed to many uh
useful regions of the genome that are
already being used therapeutically. So I
think there's a lot of promise there. Uh
can we define very specific mechanisms
for those therap
[Applause]
Thank you so much, Shoma. That was
fantastic. If there are any questions in
the audience, like I said, we've got mic
runners who just raise your hand and
they'll come over with a microphone so
that you have an opportunity. Uh and
again if you're watching online um
please type your your question into
YouTube chat and I will try to work it
into the conversation. Um just real
quick so how did you get involved and
interested in this kind of work? You
know what drew you to rheumatology and
and autoimmune diseases and
autoinflammatory diseases and what sort
of inspired you to start researching
them and also on the clinical side too?
>> Yeah. Um you know it's it's a a bit of a
strange story. So uh when I was a
medical student I mostly used to think
about um you know statistics algorithms
modeling data um and um uh when I
started doing my clinical work I I don't
think I had any good sense of what kind
of clinical work I'd want to do and
maybe I wasn't even sure I want to do
any kind of clinical work at the time.
Um but um but I found the autoimmune
diseases really interesting um in part
because they don't follow any rules. Um
so it sort of made me use a different
part of me um which is you know the more
um you know intuitive uh approach to a
patient you know making decisions based
on a physical exam by by listening to
the patient's story. And I actually
found that very appealing probably
because I was spending so much time on
algorithms and statistics and such
things. So, so um so yeah, I found
basically it was it was that I found the
patients really interesting.
>> So the cells the diseases are rebellious
and so are you.
>> Maybe maybe over here. Yes.
>> Hi. Could you speak to the concept of
timing in terms of like for example
therapeutic targets over the course of a
disease where earlier on there might be
a different target you're looking at
versus later on the cell state might
change looking at a completely different
kind of beast in terms of therapeutic
targets.
>> Yeah, I think it's a great it's a great
question. Um you know uh and I guess
maybe I can talk about it a little bit
in the context of rheumatoid arthritis.
So um you know if you talk to
rheumatologists in the pre- therapeutic
era right um uh now I think we have so
many therapies that it's it's a little
bit difficult to know what the natural
history of the disease is. Uh but if you
talk to people in the pre- therapeutic
era they would talk about a thing called
burnedout RA um which probably wasn't
really burned out but the idea was that
you know the the sort of swollen hot
joints that you're seeing early on that
over time you don't you don't see that
right? So there is some kind of change
um you know in the immunology um in
terms of tissue inflammation at least in
in RA um and we certainly do see
individuals where you know they do well
on a drug for a little while and then it
stops working as well for them.
Difficult to know if they've you know
developed some kind of tolerance to the
drug. Sometimes people develop
antibodies to the drugs, but sometimes
it could also be that the disease is
just evolving and the particular drug
we're using no longer works for that
patient because the disease has shifted
into something else. Um, so I think it's
a really uh really important question.
It's probably not a one-sizefits-all
answer because obviously different
diseases are different.
>> Thank you Sha. Fascinating uh
presentation and very impressive body of
work. Um I was particularly struck by
that slide which you showed uh
hetrogenity of cell composition in the
sinovium across multiple patients in the
six groups that you've defined. I was
wondering um you know for those patients
on average given the 150 genetic loi or
risk lolli that have been identified on
average how many risk side of the
patient carry
um and whether that is different across
these genetic uh these cellular
heterogenity based groups that you have
identified and if it is indeed this
multisellular and you know
multifphenotypic
why do we still think that single target
agents, therapeutic agents will work for
any patient when they have multiple
snips and multiple cell types involved.
Thanks.
>> Uh great great question. So um so the
150 uh LOSI they're all common alals,
right? So um so at every of those 150
you can imagine that people have zero,
one or two risk alals. Um it's pretty
much if you add them all up it's like a
bell-shaped curve, right? Um so you know
in some sense most people have half the
risk alals and half the protective
alals. Um and some people have a little
bit more and some people have a little
bit less. Um there are some individuals
who will have an extreme number of them.
And you know for those individuals you
can imagine that the risk goes up from
you know half a percent to 1% to 2% to
3%. But the genetics for most autoimmune
diseases aren't really that predictive.
um you know in the sense that um you
know a 23 and me test probably is never
going to get to a point that it's going
to really tell you who's going to get RA
um you know so if you have a twin
sibling an identical twin sibling that
has rheumatoid arthritis your risk of RA
goes from half a percent to about 10%.
So that's like perfect genomic
information, right? And it's still not
that predictive. So it's useful in terms
of understanding mechanism, less useful
in terms of, you know, doing doing
predictions about what's going to happen
to whom. Um
the single target versus multi-target
strategy is a really interesting
question and one that I think has dogged
our field. Um you know I I think many of
us uh including me think that there's a
tremendous benefit to you know going
after multiple bi biologics at the same
time. Now as it turns out you know some
of this is just about drug development
right that that you know u before we had
antibbody types of targeted therapies.
We had non-specific therapies which were
small molecules. Many of them we still
don't know exactly what they do or why
they work. Um you know rheumatoid
arthritis we used to treat with gold
shots. I think we still don't know why
we did that. Um, and whether you know
there's controversial how well it
worked. Uh, a lot of a lot of belief
that it did work. Um, I wasn't around
for that era. Um, so I think the
targeted therapeutics are great because
we know what we're doing. We know we
know what we're going after. Um, it's
probably true. It's definitely true. Um,
that using multiple targeted
therapeutics in an individual may be
beneficial. Um, and now we're starting
to see data on seroriatic arthritis
where that's the case. The downside of
it is that going after two major
components of immune system is scary,
right? Um, and you may be, you know,
each of them may be synergistically
working to make your patient
particularly imunocmpromised. So my
argument is that what you probably
really want are ter targeted
therapeutics that are very specific.
That's a good thing, but uh but spec
going after specific molecules in
specific cell contexts, right? So you're
not taking out like an like two massive
pillars of the immune system. Rather,
you're taking out two pillars but you
know in in some very specific places um
so that you'd have the benefit of
getting the tissue inflammation down
without wreaking havoc um you know in
terms of immune susceptibility.
Hi, thank you so much for your talk. Um,
I had a question on the environmental
component of disease. So, you mentioned
that environmental factors will trigger
you know genetic susceptibility and I
was wondering to what extent can we
prevent those factors and could you
enlighten us on what those factors are?
Yeah. So, you know, some of those risk
factors are known and some of them are
are less well known. Um I maybe I'll
talk about two of them that I think are
pretty pretty clearly established. Um uh
one is smoking. Um so, you know, smoking
is bad for you for a lot of reasons. And
from an autoimmune point of view, that's
another way in which it's bad for you.
So, um uh for rheumatoid arthritis, the
the your risk of uh RA more than doubles
uh if you if you smoke cigarettes on a
on a regular basis. Um so that's a
modifiable risk factor. Um another risk
factor um that I can tell you about is
uh with multiple sclerosis now we've
come to realize that there's a a viral
trigger. Um for most autoimmune diseases
there's been a sort of ongoing debate
about whether viruses trigger it uh or
not and to what extent uh it might. Um
and it's it's very difficult to to you
know do the right epidemiological
studies or the right clinical studies to
really separate that out. But in the
last three to four years I think the
evidence for multiple sclerosis being
caused by Epstein bar virus has become
overwhelming. Um and so um so Epstein
bar virus is one that we think probably
causes u multiple sclerosis. Um
it's a little difficult to know what to
do with that one because most of us have
been infected with uh Epstein bar. Um
and maybe um the the problem with
autoimmunity is not that you get
infected with it, it's that you get
infected later in life with it than
earlier in life. Um so so there's some
interesting questions one could ask
about, you know, whether we should be
vaccinating everyone for EBV to prevent
multiple sclerosis or whether we should
be exposing everyone early on so they
don't get it later on and and and be be
put at put at risk. Um so those are
those are two um two risk factors that
um that I can I can speak to with
confidence.
>> We did have a question from online which
I need to find again.
Ah what do you see as the benefits and
challenges of personalized medicine for
rheumatoid arthritis? you know, from a
farmer production angle, it's easier to
massproduce drugs um than to like come
up with individual treatments or small
batches of treatments or like antibodies
that might work for one small set of
patients and not another set of
patients.
>> Yeah. So, you know, I think for
rheumatoid arthritis, we're actually
incredibly fortunate that there are, you
know, dozens of of I mean, there's a lot
of different treatments for RA right
now. Um and and this is something that's
really changed from back you know from
when I met Hal uh as a medical student
there there really wasn't a such a
spectrum of diseases. So we can go after
B cells we can go after tumor necrosis
factor we can go after T- cell
activation. Um so often the challenge is
really um there's a subset of
individuals we certainly aren't treating
and we need something better for them.
Uh but for the rest of the individuals
there's a huge question of how do we
find the right right medication. Um, so
I don't think that involves creating
lots of individual, you know, treatments
for individual patients. It involves
simply matchmaking the right patient to
the right drug. I think one of the
barriers for us is that um because so
much of um what we do in many autoimmune
diseases including rheumatoid arthritis
is huristic, right? You see a patient,
they look a certain way, they're sort of
active, you try a drug, you work your
way down a ladder. um you're not
actually collecting the data that you
need to make that decision. You're not
getting the biopsy of the joint. Um and
we don't to make matters worse, we don't
know what to do with that information if
we got it. Um but you know, I think some
of the data I showed you shows that
there's information there um that maybe
we could exploit. Um and maybe that
could help us make some rational choices
so that we're not spending, you know,
years trying to find the right drug for
for a lot of our patients.
Well, thank you very much, Shomo. Thank
you also to the Elean Hector Memorial
Fund for supporting this evening's talk.
Thank you and also like to again
acknowledge Ellen's family and loved
ones who are watching us this evening.
Thank you all to everyone in the room
for coming out tonight. Uh I again
invite you all to join us for a
reception in the Broad Discovery Center.
And please uh keep an eye out for the
fall um the fall event in the broad
discovery series. We're working on who
our next speaker is going to be. That
news should be released shortly. Thank
you again and have a great night.
[Applause]