I'm going to introduce our next speaker.
Our next speaker is from MIT Lincoln
Lab, which actually isn't on the main
campus here. Is about 25 miles west of
here. Uh yeah. Um has an even uh bigger
a larger uh R&D budget than the campus
uh proper itself. uh doing a lot of work
in homeland security. Uh so we thought
it was be a great idea to uh bring in
Dennis Ross who is a group leader of
artificial intelligence technology and
systems at MIT Lincoln Lab and he's
going to talk to you about how AI and
machine learning are affecting security
and software. So let's hear for Dennis.
All right. Uh good morning everybody. Uh
my I'm glad everyone's in a good mood
because you might not be after this. Uh
a lot of this talk is going to be uh
some of the challenges that we're seeing
uh out in the world. Of course, as
software engineers, you're kind of at
the front lines of all this. So before I
get started, just out of curiosity, how
many of you work in cyber security in
some way, shape, or form in your daily
job? Okay, so a handful here. Uh how
many of you work in AI
security? All right. Now, everyone that
didn't raise your hand, you're probably
going to have to at some point very,
very soon because you're on the front
line of all the stuff you're about to
see, uh, and we're going to talk through
a little bit here. So, uh, my name is
Dennis Ross. I lead a a group. We have
about 60 or 70 folks, uh, working in,
uh, building AI technologies, delivering
them usually through commercial
partnerships or direct to the government
in lots of different areas. Uh, Lincoln
Laboratory, we sit in Lexington,
Massachusetts, although we do have a lab
down on campus as well. uh and we're
about a billion and a third a year of
R&D and we do a lot of work across lots
of different domains. I represent some
of the AI and cyber pieces and then
we'll jump around a little bit about
some of the challenges and trends we're
seeing. Uh personally, I am a
mathematician by trade. I'm sorry, an AI
researcher by trade because I like to
get paid more. Um but generally
speaking, I'm working with folks that
are software engineers, uh front-end
designers, psychologists,
astrophysicists. It's this weird mix of
all sorts of different skills that it
takes to build really interesting
software against some very hard
problems. Uh so as we go through this,
if you have a really burning question,
let me know. But I do want to save time
at the end to have some discussion. Uh
and I think it might be a little bit of
a different view than we've seen so far,
which have been some fantastic talks
this morning. Uh looking at some of the
specific security implications. So
before I get into much else, I just want
to explain a little bit about our group,
who we are, what we do. Uh so in my
group we work across four major areas
specifically in things like multimedia.
In fact the first uh packet over IP came
out of our group well before I was there
uh sometime uh about 60 years ago. So
this is a really longunning series of
efforts which have looked like analytics
signal processing which again we're just
calling everything AI now. Uh but we
have a long heritage in looking at what
multimedia especially voice looks like
over time. cyber security uh especially
building things to be more secure and
finding the uh ways to quickly automate
uh threat hunting uh patching
vulnerabilities all those different
aspects that go into cyber uh fall into
a group and we've been doing these two
things for a very long time. What we're
seeing is the emergence of some new
areas which are based on those core
technologies uh specifically in things
like what we're calling information
deterrence, information operations. Uh
our group doesn't work in things like
social media. uh we don't really work
with sort of population level areas but
more in how do we look at trends how do
we look at what kind of messaging is
going out think more like voice of
America versus Facebook something like
this uh and then the last part here is I
actually operate the laboratory's AI red
team and AI blue teams uh where we go
out and try to find uh all sorts of ways
to break and fix AI models uh the key
here is almost all this is in software
which of those interconnected systems do
we find vulnerabilities this looks like
cyber honestly from the most part. Uh,
and what you're going to see throughout
this is I'm going to talk very loosely
between cyber AI software, they're kind
of all the same thing to me, right? It's
a big bucket of stuff that is all driven
by code. So, the kind of vulnerabilities
that we're seeing, the kind of ways in
which we can exploit and then defend and
patch these systems, it doesn't really
matter if we're looking at an AI system,
a cyber system, or some of these sort of
run-of-the-mill um, vulnerabilities and
software. We're going to go about it
basically the same way.
I'm not going to brief everything you're
going to see on these slides. I actually
wanted to make them as something you
could sort of take away with you, some
compendiums of interesting information.
Uh you're going to see some companies on
here, which is a no- win endorsements.
It's just a by the way, here's some
companies doing interesting things in
the space. Uh but I've arranged this
talk around some core areas specifically
in what are we looking at for AI for
cyber defense? How can we secure some of
these AI systems? And what are some of
those emerging threats? And again,
software engineers, we're talking
software. I'm just going to use one of
these three words, mathematician, right?
Up to isomeorphism, they're all the same
thing. All right. What we've been seeing
though is cyber security and AI
software, all of this stuff is just
coming together all at once. And if we
actually want to get to a place where
we're building systems that are secure,
safe across all of our industries, we
need to start thinking about this from
the lowest levels of software design,
data design, all the way up to the sort
of finished systems and humans
interacting with them. So hopefully by
the end of this talk, everyone will be
deputized to go be a cyber defender, be
an AI defender, even if the language you
speak is in software. All
right. So this may be something you've
thought about a little bit. Maybe you've
seen uh other versions of what are these
sort of attack defense patterns? Uh how
might we actuate particular effects that
we care about? What I want to lay out is
similar to how we think about cyber, AI
is itself an attack surface, right? And
there's lots of ways to get after it. We
use this very loosely and say, "Oh, of
course these systems are vulnerable.
There might be things that we can do to
uh induce a bad effect, maybe release
some bad code, whatever those different
things are." But really, there's a whole
bunch of different areas we can be
talking about. Are we going after uh
ways to attack a cyber system? Are we
going after an information system? Are
we going after the AI? Are we just
looking at the downstream effects? So,
the reason I want to lay out this way is
you might be able to actuate via cyber
or electronic warfare uh methods to
induce some sort of effect in the AI
space or maybe you're using AI to induce
some sort of effect in cyerspace. Again,
I don't really care which one of these
ways we're going. Just useful to think
about what is our actual attack surface.
I feel like we generally speak and say,
okay, well, we care about threats, we
care about vulnerabilities, we care
about software issues, but we don't tend
to be very specific on no, no, but
seriously, what is the way someone could
actually do this? What are the ways that
we should actually be defending against
it? Uh, in the cyber world, you might
have seen lots of the like common uh
vulnerability uh like CVES, things like
this where we're trying to rack and
stack. We're trying to provide more
information. Uh but what I'm trying to
get at here is there are other ways to
categorize these to look at what are the
actual risks to you and the systems you
care about. Now in your commercial
companies you might have very different
attack surfaces. You might care about
very different things. Uh but try to
think of this all of your problems and
frame them in a way which is how might
someone exploit them and what might
those downstream effects be. All right.
I'm going to build a lot of charts here.
I'm not going to read a lot of charts,
but these are uh things that you can
take away uh use maybe in your
day-to-day uh space for the cyber
defense. Has anyone heard of DARPA's
AIXCC challenge by chance? Actually
lower than I was expecting. So, uh DARPA
stood up this grand challenge very
specifically to say, can we find and
patch automatically in software
vulnerabilities? So, there is a a set of
open challenges. There'll be all sorts
of links in here later you can see. But
this is using lots of systems, LLMs
especially to be able to look at code
bases, common open source uh toolkits,
libraries, and actually injecting
vulnerabilities into them to then do
things like capture the flag exercises.
And then we're seeing the uh competitors
do things like use an LLM that they're
fine-tuning to find the vulnerabilities
and LLM put in. But you know, that is
sort of the way the world goes right
now. Everything is an LLM. So what are
we taking away from this? This is a
system and a a set of exercises that are
set up to be able to generate
interesting vulnerabilities, to be able
to generate capabilities for defending
them and automatic patching. So the
dream is that in a a world in the
future, you're going to focus on the
things you heard earlier. You're going
to look at that modular design. You're
going to be a software architect. You're
not going to have to worry as much about
what is the cyber security of your
systems. I don't think these things are
ever going to be foolproof, but these
kind of challenges are ways in which you
can start to see how are we actually
measuring uh the safety of these
systems. How are we actually looking at
vulnerabilities and what are ways to
automatically patch them? Uh I think the
finals of this are coming up maybe this
summer or so. Uh kind of a multi-million
dollar prize for people to be able to do
automatic capture the flag as well as
creating some of these patches. So I
encourage you to reach out and look at
this. But what are some of the things
that come up with this? If you're doing
things like, "Hey, uh, chatbt, I have a
common open source library here. Induce
some sort of buffer overflow attack."
Now, I could also just give that problem
to a bunch of undergrads and they'll
probably induce that for me, right? Like
there's all sorts of ways to put bad uh
code inside of these code bases. uh but
trying to do this in a controlled way
where you can automate it at scale using
generative AI is really tough because
what it tends to do is I can break
anything but then it's very obvious came
from a computer or maybe the effect
never is u reachable inside of the code.
How do you actually dial it in to be
something that's interesting that is
looks like the baseline code uh and is
actually a challenge to find but also
represents actual threats we see. So
these are the kind of uh challenges
we're seeing come out of this DARPA
exercise uh and trying to build all the
tools around that into existing software
workflows to be able to do things like
understand the risk, understand uh what
these vulnerabilities are actuated by to
be able to build patches or detectors
against it is very difficult. So I'd
encourage you all to look at some of the
papers coming out of this, look at some
of the software flows. But in general,
this is the kind of things you're doing
day-to-day if you're starting to use
these LLMs, if you're starting to use
generative AI, which I'm all for. These
things are great. You are inducing
potential vulnerabilities inside of your
systems. Uh so from this at the bottom
uh we're seeing and I'll try to move
between both sides. What we're seeing is
people are building these kind of tools
uh to go provide these automatic
patches. They tend to be LLM based but
there are ways to do this. Now, I
wouldn't trust this to fully fix the
system right now, but I also wouldn't
want my defenders or my software
engineers not to be using these tools to
try to do what they do faster. I'm
actually okay if this doesn't find
everything, and I still need to have a
red team that is going to go for these
really, really, really hard to find
vulnerabilities. It's a defense and
depth approach. So, this is just another
tool you should start getting
comfortable with. Again, I don't think
software is any different than AI is any
different than cyber. You should be
thinking about this. What are some ways
I might be introducing vulnerabilities?
And at the same time, what are some ways
that it can fix my crappy code? I
mentioned a mathematician. I didn't
learn how to code until I'm like, oh, I
can do external graph theory with code
instead of drawing them all in my
notebook, which happened when I was
doing my like actual dissertation,
right? I learned very late uh how to
code. So, my code is crappy, but that's
okay because I'm able to uh make it
better with some of these automated
tools. Uh we've talked a little bit
about Copilot today. I'm not sure if
anyone has used it for the more sort of
agentic type approaches. I know it's
come up a few times. Uh but now instead
of just saying generate me code, it's
working in sort of broader ecosystems.
It seems sore cyber security ecosystems
where instead of having to produce code,
you're trying to produce insights across
lots of different data sets. Uh so now
imagine that if you're actually looking
at your entire industries your entire
company's uh cyber security posture for
example lots of alerts are coming in
lots of data are coming in how can you
actually understand this in a way that
lets you take any action right you can
go patch you can go do things that are
general hygiene uh you might even
automate some of those but what are the
ones you should care about what are the
risks that are actually happening to
your system and how do you actually do
this without uh burning out all of your
IT and cyber defense people well when
you start looking at these kind of
challenges it's really tough because
every system is different. Every network
is different. Uh the logs might look
slightly different. Even though these
LLM like approaches are pretty good at
learning context over time, your system
might just not look like what's in the
training data. And we see this all the
time, especially in the government side.
Uh how do you also make sure that we're
not just doing what you heard a little
bit earlier, which is I'm only seeing
things I saw before, right? Novel
attacks happen all the time. Well, my
argument here is use these tools to find
the things that have been seen before
and then spend your security analyst
time to find more interesting things
they haven't seen, which is a really
hard problem. Uh, and then if we look at
some of the ways in which we can use
this to do interesting things uh from
sort of the software side is how do we
actually use these AI assistive tools as
an assistant, right? I don't need it to
automate my job away. What I need it to
do is help find interesting context for
me, summarize some things, run some
queries for me, pull the data before I
need it. Think of this as that sort of
assistive mode where instead of just
saying, "I need the AI to know exactly
what to do because I defined
everything." Just let it be clippy,
right? Looks like you're trying to do a
hunt. Here's some interesting data.
Looks like you're trying to scrape this
pcap file. Here's a way to extract out
that entity you care about. And it turns
out these tools are pretty good at it
already. So, the reason I want to talk
through this one a little bit is we have
a way to uh use these agentic like
systems. Okay. Move around a little bit.
Hope they don't fall on a chair. uh to
help automate some of our workflow,
answer offload some of this work, and
actually make us better because we don't
need to be cyber defenders on a whole
stack. In fact, you're going to see a
whole lot of this, especially at the
bottom. How many of you that work and
understand data flows, network flows,
how things are actually connected inside
of your apps are thinking through the
what are the actual say nation state
level attacks that my company might be
facing for someone trying to steal my
IP? That intersection is really small.
So, what are some ways to actually
bridge those gaps through these assisted
technologies? Turns out copilot works
pretty well for this. Many of the other
generative tools already do. Uh so we
have to start thinking about how are we
training our folks to actually look at
these different tools, offload and
define the kind of work that they should
be doing and then hopefully push forward
our defensive
posture. Uh again I have a couple
companies in here. This is an
interesting one. Uh but it's not
endorsing this particular one. Uh but
for Resilient, how do you actually look
at ways to understand what is your risk
inside of your system? This is sort of
the normal thing we talk about uh for
cyber security which is what do I
actually need to care about? What is
going to attack me? What is going to
lead to exploitation? So these kind of
uh there's a ton of companies in the
cottage we'll say security industry that
have done this for cyber for a long
time. What we're starting to see is
people really relying on generative AI
uh to be able to do things like rapid
exploit development. If you have a
vulnerability, can they show proof a
concept right away that says yeah this
is something you need to worry about.
Can you generate network artifacts that
your uh defenders can look at and say,
"Yes, I can see this on my network or
something similar to it. Maybe this is
actively being attacked because the fact
of the matter is we're never going to
fix everything." So, if you're not going
to fix everything, what are some ways in
which you can prioritize those defenses?
All right, I recognize these are really
slide dense, it's not going to get less
dense. Uh, and I'm not going to brief
all of these, but I want you to be able
to take them away if they're interesting
to you. Uh, on this is some different
initiatives across industry and the DoD.
uh as an FFRDC, fedally funded research
development center at MIT, uh we sit at
the simplex between industry,
government, and academia. Uh we like to
say we're the best at all of them. The
secret is we're just really do a little
bit of all of them at the same time,
which is the special sauce. Uh so we sit
in a lot of these different areas. Take
a look at these. You can read them
after. Uh but there's many different
initiatives that are playing across both
industry and government right now. I do
want to highlight, especially on the far
left, which you've heard a lot today,
industry is already using LLMs for a lot
of code generation. I think the 47% was
thrown around earlier. Uh my guess is
some industries that's even higher
depending on what you're actually doing.
This isn't going away. The number of
people we've hired in our group, the
first question they ask is you have
co-pilot, right? Even though we're
working on these weird government
things, like I can use that,
right? It's it's not going away. Be
aware of that. Tailor to your use cases.
see how this can make you faster and
better while uh not ignoring some of the
risks. I did want to point out one thing
on the uh government side specifically
is red teams have been around for a long
time, right? We've looked at systems, we
probe for vulnerabilities. Many
companies have their own red teams for
their business use cases. We're starting
to see this being very explicitly
tailored to breaking AI systems. How do
we defend them because we can show what
those actual vulnerabilities that we can
actually are. Uh so this is a major
major trend. And there's a ton of
movement in the government space and the
industry space to catch up to be able to
make sure we're actually looking at real
vulnerabilities. So do think about those
as you're bringing in those tools. Talk
to your security professionals. Think
about what it actually means for your
product. Think what it means for your
company and think about what those uh
exploits might be. We'll talk about that
in a little more detail on the next
slide. Uh again, I'm not going to brief.
Oops. Sorry if I lazed somebody.
Um same thing here. There's a collection
of interesting things going on in
academia, uh, as well as some links of
some interesting papers, uh, blogs,
other posts you might want to see.
Again, I'm not going to brief all of
these, and I'm happy to share all the
slides. You're welcome to take pictures
of them, but I can send you a copy, uh,
if you want to click through all this,
but just things I found over the years
that I think are rather
interesting. All right, switching gears
a little bit. Let's talk about uh, the
defense across some of these AI specific
systems. How many of you have used
something on hugging face? Right. I
mean, I use it all the time. It's a
really interesting repository of a bunch
of AI
models. How many of you used a pickle
from hugging face? A pickle file in your
Python. Good. Right. Keep it
low. It's not great. There's all sorts
of ways in which uh exploits have been
known to propagate through things like
pickle files in Python or of course
there's other methods in which uh
exploits can come through. How many
companies do you think are using models
on HuggingFace right now? How many
governments do you think are using
models in these open- source
repositories right now? It's a lot. So,
what are we doing to make sure we
understand some of those risks? We
shouldn't ignore them, right? This is an
amazing thing that we can share openly
across the entire world. Advances in AI.
I'm a huge advocate for that. Let's
share all of our model weights. Let's
advance this as much as we can. But
there are going to be malicious folks
out there who are trying to either steal
IP and do cyber effects or other things
inside of your systems. what is the way
in which we can robustly understand what
some of these risks are as well as
building guard rails to protect them. So
as you see more and more reliance on AI
uh code completion turns out some of the
models uh you can buy right now work
really well and there's really good
fine-tuned ones on hugging face that do
a really good job at exactly those very
specific things you want to do and say
crypto maybe worry about that a little
bit
right as a side note. So actually last
talk great way to use crypto. Try that
one instead. All right. Uh there's also
an interesting industry popping up now
that's looking at ways to actually
analyze these systems. What are some of
those risks and vulnerabilities inside
of uh these models? How can we actually
scan them? And we don't actually know
what these things look like sort of
broadly. Uh as software engineers, we
might say, okay, we can think about this
as a code base. We can validate it, but
what if it's just much model weights?
Like what are the things that we
actually need to understand about this?
How do we educate uh the software
engineers in the room to be able to
understand what these risks are? How do
you even poke and prod to know what you
might be exposing your systems to? And
that's really tough. So there are
companies who are doing this now. You
likely have some inbuilt solutions in
your own uh companies. But do think
about how do we actually figure out
what's going on inside those models and
what some of those risks are. And I
think there's a lot of ways that we can
uh help defend things sort of from the
ground up. And then lastly uh picked on
meta there's a lot of other folks who
were looking at AI safety security or
other permutations these words depending
on what's uh popular in a particular
day. Uh but how are we looking at ways
to defend these systems? Uh so it's
definitely in something like OpenAI or
Meta's business model to not release
ways to build a bomb from an LLM. Uh to
not induce self harm because you're uh
you know idealizing suicide or something
else dangerous psychology
psychologically speaking. How do you
actually make sure you can detect that?
What are ways that you can build in
guardrails? What are ways you can log
it? And what are ways you can stop it uh
maybe from propagating across other
industries as well? So think about what
that might look like, what those
guardrails are. These right now are
really done boutique. It is people who
are trying to break the models, doing
interesting test harnesses, trying to
induce bad behavior. Uh but hopefully we
can build those guardrails back in and
as a way to defend these systems across
everybody's um ecosystems. Again, not
going to brief all these. Feel free to
take a picture, but we'll send them. Uh,
across all of this, there's a lot going
on in this this realm. Some of the AI
security uh work in the last couple
months has dwindled. Uh, but I think
it's in people's business use cases and
uh business interests to make sure that
their models are safe and secure and I
don't think that is going away. So,
think about some ways in which we can
push that forward. Uh, there are some
great government frameworks. Uh, NIST
has some, NSA has some. you can look at
how can you secure these systems and
how's the government think about it. Uh
similarly lots of interesting things
going on. I do want to highlight the
watermarking and fingerprinting work.
This is a really critical way which you
can own your IP, watch how it travels
around, watch it for if it's stolen and
ways to make sure that things are
behaving as expected inside of systems.
So I would encourage you to read more
about that uh as you're using these AI
systems even for code generation. Right?
What are some ways to know that this was
made by a trusted system versus
something that someone just downloaded
online?
All right. Uh, the last bit I want to do
is talk a little bit about some of the
emerging threats. Uh, sorry, I missed a
title there. How many of you have heard
of shadow
AI? It's a fancy word with a cool logo
that I found from some random website.
Uh, it's just people in your company
using AI improperly. Maybe you're
inducing vulnerabilities in code. Maybe
you're an insider threat. Remember, an
insider threat doesn't have to be
witting. they might just be a bad coder
or they might be doing things against
company policy. There's a lot of ways we
can tell people are misusing IT systems.
There's not a lot of ways we can tell
people are misusing AI systems. So, as
you're enabling, say software
development to become much more
automated. What are some of those
guardrails? What are some things you can
do to make sure you're not losing IP,
that someone didn't accidentally put in
something that leaks your entire
codebase or induces a vulnerability you
don't know about?
Uh there's also we've talked about this
a little bit uh lots of work happening
right now to try to evaluate how well
these things are generating secure code.
Uh in particular I take the approach
that if I would let an undergrad build
it and put it into my system what level
of vetting would I have done to make
sure I trust it. Do the same thing with
LLMs. We already have good practices for
working people that are getting up to
speed in uh programming. So just don't
trust it to be great. That's fine. Build
some systems of verified. We heard about
some of the formal methods earlier, but
you can think about the normal unit
tests, the normal things that we do as
well as things like fuzzing to try to
find some of these vulnerabilities
before they hit your system. And then uh
lastly, I do in particular want to call
out open AI uh for sharing a lot of this
thread information with the broader
community, watching as things are
emerging. Uh what are some of those risk
and vulnerabilities and how do you
actually provide fixes? If they said
nation state X is attacking all of our
systems with this capability that it's
you know generating code for crypto,
right? Pick your thing. How do we fix
that? What are some ways to put that in
disparit AI systems and disparit
software stacks? That's really tough.
So, uh, take a look at what some of the
frontier models are doing now and how
they're sharing information. And I
encourage you, uh, to not make the same
mistake we did in cyber, which is when
you see risks, just hide it to yourself
because you don't want to share all of
your your sort of bad news. All right,
same thing here. Lots of stuff going on
in this space. I want you to think
through them all. Go read them at your
leisure. Because we have five minutes
left, I want to take some questions. I
know that was a lot. Uh, hopefully we're
a mix of uh, seeing risk as well as
opportunities. Hey, I was wondering
where do you see the most attacks coming
um aimed at AI systems? Is it actually
where the processing is happening or is
it where systems are connecting to AI to
get answers? So right now uh many of the
attacks are actually just like say for
LLMs at the prompt level. What are some
ways to jailbreak to extract information
that we don't care about? Uh but we're
seeing sophisticated thread actors start
to go against software stacks, right?
You take the low hanging fruit first. If
I can make open AAI give me my training
data that was in a very special uh
protected data I care about just do
that. But as those things become more
defensive cat and mouse they're going to
go after software stack. You're going to
go all the way down the processor level
extract the information you care about.
So right now think about open APIs
things that are touching AI systems
defend those secure those write good
code around them but the whole stack is
going to be vulnerable. Um prompts can
be very valuable to train the AI models.
How do we protect our um prompts that we
feed into the system to
Yeah. Uh I that's a really good question
because you might share more information
than you expect by just what you're
asking of these models. I'm a big fan of
crypto. What are some ways that we can
do things like multi-party computation
uh share you know just encrypt
everything. How do you have
cryptographically secure channels that
no one system knows all the pieces of
the thing you ask but you can still
mathematically show you can answer the
question. uh there's some work in NPC
probably adds 15 20% overhead which is a
lot but if you really have a sensitive
application that might be some way to
help protect that information uh
otherwise normal cyber security posture
applies right keep those queries safe uh
make sure they're stored inside your
enclave have some pretty good uh normal
practices for securing them
is there any guideline around when we
work with the third party but they are
using AI and when we are interacting
with them how do we ensure like you know
what kind of you know safety practices
there like is there any guideline these
are the things we must do yeah I don't
ever trust anyone maybe it's just a
consequence of my job so um I'm okay
with using things from untrusted sources
so having some best practices for what
are those unit tests what are the things
that are critical for you what are the
kind of uh outputs you expect put in
those firm guard rails if you see things
pop out that are unexpected don't run
them for example if
uh eliciting code from these models. Uh
but generally if you just take a zero
trust approach, I think that's probably
the safest bet because we should work
with untrusted partners. That's great,
but let's just not even if it's not
malicious, let's not assume that things
won't have bad effects in our systems.
One more question. Okay. Oh, maybe two.
No. Can you talk about quickly about um
containment? So, if there's an
exploitation, how do you can you know
have things change and how do you
contain it and shut down systems in a
way that's stable? Yeah, I'm a very big
fan of maintaining uh fine-tuned models
for your business use case that might be
kind of crappy as in you train them on
gold standard data that you trust, you
believe is not exploited. Of course, it
might be that you can roll back to. So
maybe you're using the frontiers, maybe
you're using other systems, but you have
a way to say whoop something's happening
here. Let's jump back to an old version.
Let's jump back to a trusted uh version
or a gold version uh to be able to push
that forward. Uh in terms of putting in
guardrails, that's really tough right
now. I don't think there's a way to do
it that definitely gets rid of the
exploits because these are
nondeterministic systems. Uh but usually
if you have older models you can roll
back to and it you might have to keep
going if that risk persists but that's
one good standard way.
So we build a lot of u application by
using open source and now we see the CVS
also available and as as you mentioned
now uh with the help of LLM uh people
are probably easily can create the
payloads. So what is the trend are you
seeing in um uh what you say increasing
amount of payload for CVS is there any
trend which is like uh payload means it
is becoming easier or yeah I do think
it's becoming easier uh but it as you've
heard earlier it's not necessarily the
most novel ways of doing it. Uh so
you're going to get the strip kitties
you're going to get advanced actors who
can do what they already could do faster
which isn't great but defenders can also
do the same thing. What you're not
seeing is a lot of eliciting of really
interesting, difficult zero days that no
one else would have thought of before.
Uh so I I think it's kind of the the
normal cat and mouse. It's happening
faster, but we can also find them and
patch them faster, too. So maybe I'm
slightly optimistic there, which good
note to end
on. All right. Okay. Let's hear it for
Dennis. Thank you.