[Music]
have you ever watched in awe as lonel
Messi scores yet another impossible
goal what you may not realize is that
without the biologic medicine human
growth hormone or HGH that small boy
from Argentina would not have reached
his full potential as one of the
greatest footballers today scientist at
jentech cloned HGH in 1979 and then in a
remarkably short 6 Years genentech's
first product approval from the FDA came
in growth hormone for children with
growth hormone deficiency I was so small
they said that when I went onto the
beach or when I went to school I was
always the smallest of all I was like
this until I finished the treatment and
I then started to grow properly for more
MIT moments from MIT open learning like
subscribe or follow