Okay, I'll go ahead and get started.
Good afternoon. My name is Aspen Hopkins
and I am going to be presenting joint
work with my collaborators Isabella
Struckman, Kevin Kleimman, and of
course, Susan Sylvie. Um, and today
we'll be talking about AI supply chains,
how stakeholders, markets, and the
complexities of AI shape harm and inform
redress.
I want to start with a fairly direct
provocation which is that AI supply um
AI systems are increasingly the result
of fragmented development across
multiple organizations contributing
models, data and AI
services. And these kinds of composed
systems are embedded throughout our
daily lives. Consider an example of a
patient going to an ER complaining of a
stomach ache.
In the ER, they tell their provider some
details. The doctor discusses the
symptoms and makes some observations to
direct next steps of their care. This
conversation is transcribed and
summarized by a voice enabled AI
assistant which updates the electronic
health record of the patient. This might
sound familiar.
These notes are fed into an upstream or
downstream sepsis model which flags
high-risk patients for escalation to
support triage. This information is then
fed back into an EHR system with
information about the patients
risks. This interdepend interdependent
system I just described is an example of
an emerging phenomena we call AI supply
chains.
We can redraw this system view to
emphasize which components are doing
what at any given
time. Going back to our example, it
turns out that the patient displayed
symptoms of sepsis, but was not flagged
in a timely manner. If I were to ask you
which component in this AI supply chain
is most likely responsible for this
failure, you'll probably say the sepsis
model. After all, this is the AI
component that is actually monitoring
for sepsis.
and you would be sort of correct, but
also incorrect. I'm here today because
this problem is not as clearcut as we
might think initially. It turns out that
a few days ago in our example, the
voicetoext app had a system update. The
update overall improved quality and
accuracy of patient summarizations.
But for a subset of doctors with
specific accents, it actually
experienced a regression, a distribution
shift from its expected behavior. And
this introduced unwanted distortions in
the EHR record like mistransating
keywords. Information about this update
wasn't necessarily shared with the
sepsis model developer and in fact that
developer might not be aware of the
voicetoext app in the first place.
The challenge is that the crisis that I
just described isn't necessarily a
technical failure on the part of just
the sepsis model
provider. This is an AI supply chain
failure. Harms like poor patient
outcomes, the sepsis model provider
losing customers over ineffective
products, loss of hospital reputation
are all the results. But who is actually
responsible? And how can AI supply chain
participants fix it? Can they even do
this without the help of the upstream
voice to tax
app? I'm here today because AI supply
chains are humanmade. That means that we
can design them. But to do so, we must
ask who participates in these systems?
What happens when harms occur? And how
do power differentials and market
structures shape our ability to respond?
Poignantly, there is no one-sizefits-all
in AI supply chain
configurations. This makes generalizing
interventions exceptionally
difficult. There are also many
stakeholder roles. There are
infrastructure, data and model
providers. There are user and consumerf
facing developers. There are
intermediary AI services. And of course,
there are users and consumers.
AI supply chains are not just technical.
They are institutional arrangements with
many stakeholders that have incentives
shaped by contracts, limited
coordination or accountability, and that
often play multiple roles. What this
means is that even those who cause harm,
failing to capture the census, for
example, may be constrained in
responding due to position or to market
incentives.
To restate this, stakeholders in AI
supply chains operate with unequal
bargaining power. Variations in power
and influence shape outcomes. And this
becomes most evident when we examine not
the harm itself, but how a responsible
party responds to a
harm. In our work, we contribute a
typology of redress. We ask, how do we
respond to harms? Now that we've seen
some examples of harms that can emerge
in an AI supply chain, we need to think
about how do we fix
them. We describe five different cases
of responses. Recognition in which you
acknowledge that a harm occurred.
Recourse in which you stop the harm.
Repair in which the harm is corrected.
Reparation or compensation. And
prevention in which we learn from and
then ensure that future harms are
mitigated by adopting new policies or
processes.
These forms of response are common
across domains but they operate
differently depending on who you are in
the
system. So when I ask will redress
happen we have to note that it's not
just about issuing a fix or a refund.
It's more complex. It involves
determining who can act what's
technically and organizationally
possible and whether there is enough
agreement among stakeholders to make
something happen. In other words, we can
re define redress as possible when two
things hold. That the redress is
achievable physically, technically,
legally, and that there's minimal
consensus, meaning the relevant parties
agree to act or can be compelled to.
That's where things get tricky in AI
supply chains. There's not systems where
any one company owns and operates
everything. They're fragmented, built
from models, services, and
infrastructure spread across films with
firms with different incentives and
levels of control. So when a harm
occurs, say a patient is misprioritized
or a hospital loses trust in a system,
the path to fixing it is often blocked
not by malice, but by
structure. The question then becomes,
what shapes what is achievable? What
makes consensus possible or impossible?
and supply chains. The answer is market
structure and institutional
arrangements. The ways that AI services
are sourced, built, delivered, whether
they're vertically integrated,
horizontally, modular, or fragmented
into
microervices, directly shapes what kinds
of redress are even on the table. And
often the same features that make AI
scalable or cost-effective also make
harm harder to trace and fix. In our
work, we examine this across three
common
configurations. Um, I'm going to focus
on the vertical integration because of
time constraints. So, let's look a
little bit more closely at how a harm
and redress plays out in this setting.
In a vertically integrated market, one
firm owns the full stack. In our
example, this might mean that the voice
to text app, the sepsis model, and the
EHR system is all owned by one company.
Perhaps you can think of examples
In vertically integrated markets, that
firm gets to decide whether the harm is
even recognized. Recourse, the ability
to avoid or disable a harmful component,
is limited because you can't remove one
piece without necessarily leaving the
ecosystem. Repair is sometimes easier
because the firm controls the whole
stack. So, you can choose what to fix
and you can choose to holistically fix
it. But fixes are prioritized based off
of business interests and not
stakeholder needs.
When it comes to rep uh reparation or
compensating people who are harmed,
things get murkier. Without
transparency, firms can minimize or
obscure their role in the harm, making
it difficult for affected parties to
even ask for compensation, let alone
receive it. And prevention, making
changes to avoid future harms, is often
only prioritized when there's external
pressure, say from regulation, public
outcry, or reputational risk.
Across the board, market structure
doesn't just determine who builds what,
it constrains how and whether harm is
addressed. So, if these supply chain
specific harms aren't caused by one
actor or one broken model, but by the
way the system is organized, then the
fix itself can't just be technical. It
has to be structural. And that brings us
to our final point, which is
intervention is possible, but it has to
be targeted and it has to be
intentional. When we say designing AI
supply chains, we don't just mean
choosing what APIs to use or how to
fine-tune a model. We mean shaping the
institutional context in which these
systems operate through law, governance
and market mechanisms. This can look
like regulation which forces
transparency, traceability or
auditability.
um licensing standards, procurement
criteria, especially in public sector AI
that demands evidence of recourse or
repair mechanisms, contractual
frameworks that clarify accountability
between firms, and yes, tort law, where
harm can't be avoided, there must be
pathways to
compensation. The point here isn't that
one solution can work everywhere. Harms
are fundamental to risky business and to
new technology. Each of these
interventions can target a specific
structural barrier to redress for all
stakeholders and together they can help
build systems where it's possible to act
before harms
cascade. The final point I want to leave
you with is that AI supply chains are
not natural. They are made. And that
means we can design them differently. We
can design for transparency, for
interoperability, for feedback channels
that let stakeholders identify harm
early and to do something about it.
We have to look at the entire system,
the actors, the markets, the
institutions, and ask who has the power
to respond when things go wrong, who's
left without a voice. Because in an AI
today, those answers are often, frankly,
structured long before the harm
occurs. Thank you.
Thank you, Aston. questions for us.
Uh sorry I missed. Yeah,
thanks. Um there is significant body of
work on digital supply chains. Uh what's
different? What's what does AI bring
into into the into the mix which is
different or substantially new? Yeah,
that's a wonderful question. And I think
this is a question on many people's
minds. Um so we have a bunch of work
that we actually didn't include in this
presentation. Um some of it talks about
what's new to AI from the supply chain
perspective. The other side is what's
new to supply chains from the AI
perspective. I think one of the
challenges with AI specifically is that
you are operating off of um
distributions. So you're learning and
producing distributions rather than
modular components that have inherent
traceability which you do have in in
digital supply chains like software.
Software is traceable. Um granted that
was designed for but in many cases it is
hard to take two different probabilities
and understand where the probability
it's like the the output that you get is
itself comes from. you have issues of
like no onetoone mapping or you have
things like collapsing distributions and
and it becomes exceptionally challenging
to do this traceability that we care
about or it becomes computationally
expensive um and therefore you have to
have ownership over the model or
whatever it is.
Great. Other questions?
Yeah,
I should also say that Susan's in the in
the audience and is very respected when
it comes to regulations. So ask your
questions as well. Yeah. So uh the
question that I have is regarding
thinking about this uh supply chain that
you outline like uh there's a different
uh stakeholder uh along this uh supply
chain and how can you bring when you
talking about design it seems uh to be
that design in a relative uh isolate
environment when you talking about
design but then the impact is actually
uh there's multiple stakeholder multiple
like party involved and how can you
ensure that their incentive their
interest uh kind of align with uh this
kind of uh design process I'm
particularly thinking about in this kind
of uh environment of the hospital uh
healthcare related that probably a
strong interest uh from insurance
standpoint so for example hospital want
to make sure that uh the kind of uh case
happen early introduced is very little.
So that the in premium won't be
increased uh uh next year something like
that and uh that kind of incentive
probably would uh help you uh kind of
try to make uh optimize of uh design. I
I see um to interpret your question I
feel like there are two or three parts.
Um the first was that it's hard to
design for systems that have um very
complex incentives that may not
necessarily align right. Um Susan has a
body of work on regulation and on um the
common place of law, how you know when
law is written, it is actually
interpreted. Um often there has to be an
adjudication process. The point of our
work is actually to highlight that these
um misalignments and incentives and
perhaps more critically um the power the
relationships and powers across AI
supply chains can
push away some of the necessary
uh pieces of the conversation. And so
and so like I think your comment around
insurance being a narrative that we can
align around I'm I'm not sure that I
necessarily agree per se. I think that
it can surface some of the challenges
and the question that I would have then
is the people who are designing these
mechanisms for
ensuring more transparency and
communication around updates. how they
do so in a way that does not center only
the insurance company but also looks at
these
um more modular components. I think
Susan has an answer though. Thank you.
It's on. Hello. Oh, sorry. Uh thank you
for that very fine question and it is a
very
complicated question and situation which
you by your your question illustrate
that it is very rare to be able to
create a system of traceability and
accountability with so many stakeholders
with divergent interests and that is
basically the history of government
regulation.
There is not a way for the market by
itself to be able to do that. The market
requires minimally a system of contracts
and tors to enforce it. But that relies
on the resources of the individual
actors in a complex supply chain.
They're not going to be aligned. So the
comments that Marise made at the end of
her presentation just before on almost
the same example of a problem in data in
the hospital. She made the point that it
is only through the
collective resources and information
collect collected by government agencies
that one can see across the competing
interests and
compromise to some sort of set of
boundaries and responsibilities. Though
as Aspen puts up, short of government in
the past industries have
self-regulated. This one has
not. There there are some attempts to um
particularly in the agentic space. Um
there's something that the Silicon Bros
are excited about called model context
protocol. It is an example where a
system is being designed already with
that comment that I had earlier. Um that
the structure is in place before the
harm necessarily incur occurs and so you
know participatory design maybe is one
solution to this.
Thank you. Any further questions?
There's also a lot of very interesting
technical problems. Um, if you're
interested in those, please chat with me
later.