Thanks for the introduction, Elena. So,
yeah, I'm excited to be here for the
first uh computing and sustainability
seminar in the LID seminar series for
this academic year. And I'm excited to
be here to talk to you all about
foundation models, a uh really promising
new tool set to help us understand the
natural world. But I'll also be talking
about some of the challenges that we
still have to overcome before we really
can start to automate biodiversity
monitoring at scale with these new
approaches. And there's a really strong
sense of urgency around figuring this
out because as you probably know
worldwide plant uh biodiversity is under
threat from rapid anthropogenic changes.
This includes things such as land use
change like the 30 years of
deforestation you can see across the
Amazon on the left. But that also
includes rapid climate warming which you
can also likely see here on the right
from the retreat of the Columbia glacian
Alaska over the similar 30-year period.
These widespread changes have led to
radical losses in biodiversity
worldwide, including estimates that half
of the world's plant biomass has been
lost since the beginning of
industrialization and that animal
populations have shrunk by almost two
3/4 in the past 50 years alone.
These severe threats led to the adoption
of the conic Montreal biodiversity
global biodiversity framework in 2021
2022, excuse me, at COP 15. And the
these goals include target one of trying
to reduce loss of areas of high
biodiversity to near zero by 2030.
Target two of restoring 30% of the
world's degraded ecosystems to enhance
their ecosystem services, ecological
integrity, and connectivity. And target
three to conserve 30% of the world's
land, water, and sea to ensure that
important areas for biodiversity are
effectively conserved and managed.
However, to actually achieve these
goals, we need to actually know and
accurately assess where the world's
remaining biodiversity is located. And
additionally, how it is changing, which
is a challenging task.
Indeed, anthropogenic biodiversity
change is so widespread and happening at
such astonishing rates that our
traditional methods for monitoring
biodiversity on the ground such as surf
such as vegetation surveys, radio
tracking, and census counts to name a
few, they simply cannot keep up. And in
fact, there are so few experts for
collecting and identifying these species
and this data and so many regions at
risk around the world that we're quickly
reaching the point where we are there
are entire new species of insects,
fungi, microbes, and plants that we're
losing before they've even ever been
identified.
Therefore, for us to truly
comprehensively track the world's
biodiversity anthroposine, what we
really need is new automated
biodiversity monitoring methods, ideally
ones that can also leverage novel data
sources.
However, traditional approaches to
automating biodiversity are often data
constrained across many different
dimensions. So, for example, if we're
trying to enable comprehensive
wall-to-wall monitoring of biodiversity
at fine tempmporal scales and spatial
scales, we have products such as the
Neon network. Neon possesses a rich suit
of thousands of automated and
semi-automated insitu measurements that
are taken daily to yearly.
um but they have fewer than 100 sites
total across the entire continental US
which makes it difficult for us to make
inferences from this data at fine
spatial scales between these sites.
Similarly, species distribution modeling
approaches which use which are used to
try and predict species distributions
that find spatial and temporal
resolution nevertheless end up not being
at the spatial resolution we need to
understand how species are changing in
response to land use change because
these models are built often times with
low resolution climate variables like
you can see here in the top center.
These climate variables fail to capture
fine scale landscape patterns like the
vegetation transitions you can see for
the exact same geographic area in the
bottom center of the slide. Similarly,
we do have high resolution in space and
time methods for detecting deforestation
like forest watch. But these approaches
only have the spectral resolution for us
to capture major changes in forest
structure. Essentially deforestation or
no deforestation which gives us no
signal on what species may have been
deforested in these areas.
and in general miss more subtle changes
in vegetation community that are
happening as climate change starts to
become even more important on natural
communities.
Additional modeling challenges include
the scale at which these changes are
occurring and the drivers of which these
occurring are very mismatched.
For example, climate warming is
consistent in global scale but happens
at a very slow pace for many for many
species. For example, you can see here,
this is the the creeping up of a tree
line in Sweden over 100-year time
period. So, as you can see, obviously
the tree line is moving up as the
climate warms, but it's moving only
about 100 meters every 100 years. On the
other hand, land use change is very
heterogeneous. It's very spatially
concentrated and very rapid. So, if we
return to our example of uh
deforestation
in the Amazon, we can see that the the
the deforestation is very rapid but very
patchy as well. There's still places in
the forest that are being maintained
even after deforestation has been rot on
all sides.
There are yet more challenges when we're
talking about ecological modeling
specifically when we're trying to
understand commal communities. One
additional challenge is habitat
fragmentation like this Ontario boreal
forest. And you can really only best
resolve the effects of habitat
fragmentation at very spine spatial
scales. So as you can see here only a
few hundred meter resolutions is the
difference between no forest and a
healthy community.
Additionally there's challenges with
community turnover. So this is a Swiss
alpine grassland. You can see here on
the right. What the issue with community
turnover is is that population
fluctuations between individual species
may ultimately cancel each other out
when measuring with traditional
biodiversity statistics. Therefore, we
may miss changes that are happening at
the community level as these
fluctuations cancel each other across
species. Therefore, when we're really
trying to think about monitoring
progress towards the Kig Montreal
Accords and trying to synthesize across
all of these change drivers with our B
biodiversity monitoring methods, it
becomes clear that we really need new
sources of data and new models and
methods to work with said data in order
for us to comprehensively track these
changes in the 21st century. So, this is
where the idea of foundation models
comes in. So, foundation models are a
new datadriven machine learning paradigm
that have led to rapid advancements in
the sciences of just the past few years.
Things such as protein folding, climate
prediction, and the now ubiquitous
language modeling that we all know of,
which powers products like Chat, GPT,
Claude, and Gemini that are being used
by millions daily.
And so, the central tenant of foundation
models are deep learning models trained
on lots of large scale albeit noisy data
such as text, images, and speech. These
data are then we take a a deep learning
model and then use a shockingly simple
objective to try and learn the
representation of these of this data. So
for example for language modeling it
would be simply predicting the next word
in the sentence for this example which
would be dog. Through these seemingly
simple tasks, these models nevertheless
learn complex statistical patterns
across these large collections of data.
Patterns which end up being widely
generalizable and adaptable for many
downstream tasks such as chatupt's
ability to answer questions, follow
instructions, and caption images from
just a few examples.
These exciting advancements along with
other recent successes across the bi uh
across biological domains such as
sequence foundation models like ESM3 and
EVO have made it a question of when not
if similar approaches will lead to major
breakthroughs in ecology and
environmental science.
And indeed there has been a recent rise
in these biodiversity focused foundation
models just in the past few years uh and
especially building out these foundation
model scale data sets. So we have things
like wildlife insights and I naturalists
and other sources as well from acoustics
data to remote sensing. And so my
research really centers around how we
can start to build these biodiversity
foundation models and how can we start
to curate these data sets in a way that
we can use them ultimately for automated
biodiversity monitoring in the
anthroposine.
So towards that goal today I'm going to
talk to you about some of the
opportunities that we have for adopting
a foundational model approach towards
this task but also some of the
outstanding challenges that lie in our
way. So first I'll start with the
opportunities which ex includes
exploring how these foundation models
can be actually used to detect the biode
change at fine spatial and temporal
resolutions. And so for that in the
first chapter I'll present the biosphere
which is a model from my PhD that we can
use to predict plant species occurrences
from satellite imagery and citizen
science data and use that to ultimately
detect biodiversity change across time
and space. However, many areas of the
world lack large volumes of reliably
labeled data like what we use in order
to train deep biosphere, especially in
the global south where a lot of the
world's biodiversity is located. So, in
the next section, I'm going to talk
about the opportunities that we have to
leverage both ecological relationships
and self-supervised learning to improve
foundation models representations of the
natural world. Lastly, we're going to
switch gears a bit and now we're going
to focus on some of the challenges,
these outstanding challenges towards um
operationalizing the datadriven approach
of foundation models, which includes
that the patterns that these models
learn by nature reflect the biases of
their training data and biodiversity
data especially contains many known and
strong biases. So for this last section,
I'll discuss div shift which is a new
framework and data set for quantifying
the impact of biodiversity specific bias
on foundational model performance. So
just to kick things off first, let's
dive into the potential that we can have
for building foundation models for
biodiversity monitoring. And as y'all
might remember from just a few slides
earlier, one of the few central tenants
of foundation models is the need for
data and the need for lots of data. But
thankfully across the natural world, we
now have open and citizen science
initiatives like I naturalist and eird
which are generating tens to hundreds of
millions of biodiversity records yearly
across the globe. Similarly, for high
resol high resolution environmental
predictors, we also can turn to remote
sensing data which has high spatial
resolution as we can see here on the
left. You can actually start to see the
individual tree troughs of old growth
redwoods in Northern California, but it
also has high temporal resolution as
well, which we can see with the return
of wetlands after a marsh restoration
project in northeastern California on
the right.
So in order for us to leverage both of
these data sources for this we first
curated a new machine learning optimized
data set of over 650,000 plant
observations taken from I natural NG
BIFF across the state of California
which is what you can see here on the
left. We then pair these I naturalist
observations with highresolution remote
sensing images from the national
agricultural imagery program and further
also include pointwise climate variables
since climate is an important predictor
of species distributions to aid in
training and enable simultaneous
modeling of multiple species
simultaneously. We also impute nearby
species information turning this into a
weak multi-lel setting. So as you just
saw the climate data that we're working
with and the remote sensing data that
we're working with come at very
different spatial resolutions. And so
for us to better handle these different
spatial scales, we also worked on
building a new two-headed neural network
architecture which we colloally refer to
as deep biosphere which is able to
extract 2D spatial patterns and using a
convolutional neural network from the
remote sensing data and ensembles them
with pointwise predictions of the
climate data using a simple multi-layer
perceptron which you can see along the
top in this diagram. We also, as you may
see, include higher toxinomic
information during training for both for
species including their genus and
family, which helps to improve overall
accuracy, especially for rare species
who may share information with the with
more with species with more observations
from their genus and family.
However, because the biodiversity data
that we're using to build this data set
is largely from opportunistic citizen
science campaigns, what this means is
that most of the remote sensing images
in our data set are lacking labels for
most of the species that are actually
present on the ground. So, as we can see
here, on average, only one or two
species have been identified in the I
naturalist app for every image in our
data set. even though we know that there
on average more than 100 species are
present in any given 250 meter square
foot area that represents one of the
images in our training set.
But given that there's over 200 2200
classes in our data set, what this means
is that when we're using standard binary
cross entropy loss, which is the typical
loss in a multilel supervised setting,
the fact that there are many more
species than there are absent than there
are present in a given image means that
we're biasing our network to learn what
species are absent. But again, because
there many species have not yet been
observed on the I naturalist data set
despite actually being present on the
ground, this means that when we're
learning species absence, the number of
pseudo absences overwhelms the number of
actual true absences on the ground in
the signal that the model is learning.
And so the model will be biased to learn
what species are absent versus what are
not present, but only for observations
that have lots of data. And this is
again a problem when we're dealing in
this imbalanced data labeling setting.
So to help deal with this imbalance,
what we introduced is a sampling aware
binary cross entropy loss which
essentially rescales the loss
contribution of present versus absent
classes for every sample depending on a
given area sampling effort. What this
means is that areas with few I
naturalist observations. The model is
then focused on learning the species
that we do know are present versus areas
with a high sampling density, we're
going to focus learning on those species
that actually are most likely absent in
in that given area.
So after hyperparameter tuning and uh
many ablation studies we ultimately
found that by combining our new
architecture loss function pre-training
data set which we colllocally referred
to as deep biosphere in general this
outperformed a broad array of
traditional species distribution
modeling appro approaches including
classic climate only approaches like max
and random forest which you can see here
in dark blue but along with remote
sensing only deep learning methods like
in the inception light the inception net
model which you can see in light blue
and additionally the remote sensing only
component of deep biosphere which you
can see in yellow.
Deep biosphere significantly improves
modeling performances across species and
geography as measured across dozens of
accuracy metrics including recall or the
number of species is correctly correctly
predicted as present and which you can
see here on the left which we improved
accuracy by on average 47% over the
baselines. We also check we also
compared against area under the receiver
operator characteristic curve which we
can see here in the middle which is a
measure of precision varying under
various um um detection thresholds which
again shows a sustained and significant
improvement for all species including
the rare species with h which have fewer
than 100 observations in our data set
and other metrics that are common to the
machine learning community like top 100
per species accuracy which we can see
here on the right which again shows a
sustained and significant improvement of
4 to 65% per species.
But when we're going from just improving
accuracy and accuracy metrics to
actually using an approach like deep
biosphere for for monitoring
biodiversity
um we'll focus on a case study first to
see how these methods can unlock new
monitoring potential focusing
specifically on the northern
California's redwood forests which you
can see here on the left. Um redwoods
contain uh there's only less than 5% of
old growth redwood forests still remain
in their natural habitat after 20th
century clear cutting. And you can see
some of this 5% of remaining old growth
redwood forest is this thin band of dark
olive running along the right side of
Redwood Creek which you can see here.
These tall old growth trees are so
easily visible that we can actually have
humans annotate them and they can
accurately detect these old growth
groves from satellite imagery. However,
if we take deep biosphere and we impute
it um make predictions across this image
to generate a species presence map for
redwoods, we see that the predicted
presence of redwoods is much more um has
a much broader extent with the model
than compared to the human annotations
of old growth redwoods. But if we
actually do take the National Park
Services fine scale vegetation map for
the area, what we see is that most of
this area is indeed covered by redwood
forests, but it's covered by redwood
forests of two different ages.
Specifically in red is the old growth
groves that our human annotators are
very good at detecting. So this area
right here. But additionally these areas
in blue are redwood groves but these are
groves regrowing after clear cutting in
the 20th century.
And so what we see is that deep
bossphere was indeed the only modeling
approach that we tested which was able
to consistently predict all redwood
containing pixels as accurately
containing redwoods and in and showed an
average improvement of 75% over all
other methods. But beyond large
charismatic overstory species like
redwoods which are easy to see from
remote sensing imagery. If we want to
start also looking below the canopy we
we can also see that deep biosphere can
also detect where understory species
were more likely to grow based on the
relationship with their overstory
species
ex including examples like rubasar sinus
pacific blackberry which we can see here
on the top from this example and as well
as redwood sorrel oxalos orana here on
the bottom. These two species show very
strong associations with either old
growth redwoods or new growth redwoods
and weak associations with the opposite.
And so then if we take deep biosphere's
predictions for these two species and
project them across this landscape as
well, we see that deep biosphere on
average predicts rubiser sinus more
often with a higher predicted
probability than oxalis orana in pixels
that are mapped as secondary growth
redwoods and vice versa for oxalis orana
in the old growth redwoods. This is
additionally matched to field validated
studies of the relationship between
these species in these sporests areas
with additional case studies from
traperal species in southern California.
In general, we see the deep biosphere is
able to pick out these patterns not just
of the oversource species but also the
species that we can't directly detect
from remote sensing imagery that they
are associated with which is exciting.
Now, when we're talking about
biodiversity monitoring, we're talking
about trying to detect change, right?
And so when we're trying to think about
predicting spatial biodiversity change,
we can again leverage Deep Biosphere's
learned features in order to map spatial
change across the landscape. In this
case, what we're doing is we're
comparing local change and deep
biosphere's predicted presence across
2200 plant species here on the right.
And what we see is that if we actually
then compare how those change how those
pro probabilities change across
individual points in the landscape, we
can actually measure the intensity of
spatial turnover across the highly
heterogeneous Marin County, California
here on the left. So this is the map for
this area um developed with deep
biosphere. What's exciting is that these
spatial turnover estimates correlate
strongly with independently measured
maps of vegetation trip across the area,
which means that regions of high spatial
turnover on average do have more unique
vegetation types in that given area. Um,
suggesting that these are areas that are
exhibiting strong spatial turnover.
Now towards predicting temporal
biodiversity change with a biosphere.
Again, we're going to focus on a case
study, but this time in the 2013 in the
Sierra Foothills of California,
specifically the 2013 Rim wildfire.
If we you which you can probably see
hopefully has a pretty strong a pretty
um obvious burn scar um here using
imagery taken from 2014. If we aggregate
changes in deep bossphere's predicted
presence for all 2200 species, but doing
so across time, so essentially comparing
predictions from imagery taken in 2012
versus imagery take before the fire to
imagery taken in 2014 after the fire, we
see that in on general the areas with
predicted change tend to visually
correlate with areas that have a higher
amount of burn scar um left over after
the fire. from the remote sensing
imagery on the left. We can actually
then see that these uh these estimates
not just visually seem to agree but also
uh empirically agree as well with
independently measured empirical burn
severity metrics which you can see here
on the left. Um oops sorry. And so this
shows a promising example of how we can
use these methods potentially to track
high resolution changes in natural
communities across space and time.
If we start to look more broadly across
the landscape to explore deep
biosphere's potential to capture
biodiversity change at ecosystem scales,
we can also map the short-term temporal
change across the entire state. And if
we actually zoom into the uh Sierra
Nevada region, eco region of the of
California here in the middle of the
state, we can see that there appears to
be a band of increased difference along
the western foothills of this of the
Sika region across the western foothills
of the of the Sierra Nevada
specifically.
Interestingly enough, this is actually
an area that is undergoing what we call
vegetation climate mismatch. And so the
plants that are living here, the
communities that are present um are now
out of equilibrium with their climate.
It is too hot and too dry for many of
these species to exist, but the forest
hasn't fully transitioned into um a
grass parkland like ecosystem.
What's exciting is that if we actually
map out Deep Biosphere's predictions of
change across time, we see that pixels
that are mapped to have high vegetation
climate mismatch from this independent
study have a significantly higher
predicted change when when looking at
deep biosphere change prediction
features change predictions providing
further evidence that biodiversity
foundation models can be used to
potentially track biodiversity change at
continental scales.
So to summarize, deepphere is a new
foundation model like approach for
mapping species distributions across
space and time. Deeposphere can detect
the presence of thousands of plant
species simultaneously from remote
sensing imagery and can further estimate
their changes in space and time at high
resolution. All from large scale noisy
citizen science observations and remote
sensing data. Oh, forgot to click there.
Sorry about that.
So next we'll talk about how we can
leverage both ecological relationships
and self-supervised learning to improve
foundation models of the natural world
where biodiversity data is sparse much
sparer than what we see in California.
This is important because public
biodiversity data is not distributed
evenly worldwide.
If we take our research grade I
naturalist observations availability by
continent we see that the vast majority
of I naturalist observations actually
come from above the tropic of cancer.
While the we know that the vast majority
of the world's biodiversity is actually
found below the tropic of cancer in
subsaharan Africa, South America,
Southeast Asia, etc. And in fact, if we
focus on California, specifically the
example that I just showed you, our
focus um area of study for deep virus
here, we see that I naturalist
observations are more than 10 times
dense in California than the rest of the
world combined. So, in the face of such
little highquality label data, what
other sources of data could we
potentially leverage instead? Well,
thankfully the internet has lots of
images of the natural world taken all
over the planet with public sources like
Google Street View and Lion 5B topping
over 5 billion images of the built-in
natural world. This then motivates uh
the question of how can we actually
leverage these photos of the natural
world even if we don't have explicit
labels of what species are present in
them.
But even if we lack specific labels,
nevertheless, biogeography can still
help. Specifically, the ecological
insight that species form and function
are shaped by their local environment.
For example, many clarkas, which is a
type of plant as you can see here on the
bottom, have evolved traits that have
enabled them to survive in the hot and
dry southern chapel ecosystem of
California. Similarly, tamarisk, which
is a a tree species you can see here in
the middle, it has also evolved traits
that have helped to expand across the
dry desert southwest of the United
States. And in general, we can see that
the closer species and a region are to
one another, the more similar they look
and vice versa. This is a relationship
that the wing can then exploit in our
model pre-training process.
Leveraging this ecological relationship,
we developed contrast of image remote
sensing pre-training or crisp for short,
a new representation learning
pre-training strategy that learns a
joint representation space between
ground level and aerial views of plant
species. For crisp pre-training, what we
do is we first pair each I naturalist
ground level image with a remote sensing
image from the same location. We then
pass these through um an encoder and
then for both the ground level and
remote sensing image and then based on
this ecological insight that ground
level and remote sensing views from the
same locations should look more similar
than images from other locations. We use
the clip loss which we can see here on
the left to train both the remote
sensing and ground level encoders so
that paired ground level and remote
sensing image embeddings are more
similar than unpaired image embeddings
which you can see along the red
diagonal. So we want our images from the
same location in green to have a more
similar representation from images taken
from different locations.
However, since users can upload more
than one photo to an a given I
naturalist observation at a time, some
images in a batch may be from the same
location.
So for this what we do is we um expand
the crisp loss to include any other
observation taken from the same location
as considered to be a positive in this
case. So for this example, we can see
that the first and the fourth images
were taken from the same geographic
location. So then when we're calculating
the clip loss, we're going to consider
those paired images as well to be
positives in this case. We want those
representations to be similar too.
Lastly, since the ground level and
remote sensing views may not be equally
informative as expressed by the 1/2 and
the base crisp loss, which you can see
here in yellow, we also introduce a
parameterized version of the clip loss
that differentially weights the
contribution of the ground level and
remote sensing loss components
respectively and dynamically learn this
as training evolves, which then enables
the model to learn from the most
informative data source throughout the
pre-training process. Most importantly,
you'll see at no point during this
pre-training process do we actually need
labels of what species are present in
these images. All we need is an image
from the ground and an image from above
in order for us to train our model.
For us to empirically test this
approach, we also developed the new
nature m nature multiv- view data set
which contains almost 2 million image
eye naturalist observations from across
California for more than 3 million eye
naturalist observations. These images,
which you can see here on the top, are
then paired with remote sensing images
from National Agricultural Imagery
Program for over 6,500 plant species
from across California. Now, you might
remember I said California has a lot
more naturalist data than most places in
the world,
um, which is represented by the box in
gray. So for us to more closely map to
the biodiversity data availability for
the rest of the globe, we also test the
model's downstream accuracy using
progressively smaller subsamples of
these 2 million research grade images.
And these subsamples roughly m match the
data densities similar to other
continents like Oceanania, Europe,
Africa and Asia respectively.
Challenges of this data set include that
it covers a large diversity of
phenotypes and habitats as we can see
clearly from the imagery. But it also
has a strong taxonomic imbalance as
well. So if we plot the number of
observations per species, we see that
most species have few observations and
few species have a lot of observations
in our data set. Lastly, our data set
has a strong geographic skew where most
observations come from just one eco
region which is near which contains both
LA and San Francisco despite not
covering covering less than half of uh
California's land mass.
So with these challenges in mind,
nevertheless with the nature multiview
data set, we're able to test the model's
performance on a wide variety of
downstream biodiversity monitoring
tasks. The first being species
recognition where the models are tasked
to identify what species is present in a
given ground level image as we can see
along the bottom. So if we compare the
crisp pre-trained encoder fine-tuned on
on progressively smaller subsamples of
our labeled data to in comparing it to a
variety of self-supervised and fully
supervised machine learning approaches,
we see that crisp pre-training often
improves downstream species recognition
accuracy especially on the smallest bits
sorry splits of data that mimic I
naturalist availability in the in
continents such as Asia and South
America.
For these data density splits, we see
that crisp pre-training improves
performance on average of 23% when cons
comparing all examples equally. As you
can see here, up to 14% when comparing
accuracy per species, uh sorry, up to 7%
when considering accuracies per species
and up to 14% per eco region.
So with improvement gains concentrated
again on the most lowest density data
splits, what this implies then is that
the crisp pre-training process provides
the most downstream benefit with the
least amount of label data.
Similarly for species distribution
mapping, which is where a model is
trying to predict what species is
present in a given remote sensing
imagery, we see again that crisp
pre-training often improves downstream
species distribution mapping performance
as well. And again, most clearly for the
smallest data densities.
This is especially true when we're
considering the rarity of species when
we're calculating accuracy, which is
important in our longtail longtail data
scenario. Again, where most species are
rare and few species are common. If we
further break down this per species
accuracy into frequent, common, and rare
species, we see that the biggest jump in
improvement is actually for the rarest
species in our data set. These are
species with less than 200 observations
in total from our original data set. And
yes, even though the overall accuracy is
low for these species and especially for
the lowest splits, we again see the most
important thing is that the improvement
over the baseline accuracy of on average
0% is significant because these rare
species are the ones that often times
that we want to monitor in a
biodiversity monitoring setting. So any
improvement whatsoever is important in
this space.
Scaling this approach to continental
levels, we also tested crisp downstream
transferability using the auto arborist
data set which provides both ground
level and aerial images for over 3
million urban trees across 300 general
from 23 cities in the US and Canada.
Pre-training with the crisp pre-training
with crisp on this data set also leads
to uniformly higher downstream
performance on cities unseen during both
pre-training and fine-tuning and for
cities coast to coast. So these are the
three three cities from three regions of
the United States, Central, West, and
East.
More qualitatively, if we actually
visualize the remote sensing encoder
from the pre-training process and do so
for a random subset of images across the
state, we see that in general, images
that are closer to one another
geographically tend to look more similar
in embedding space, but not always. Such
as this example from the central basin
arranged in the sonor and desert. Even
though geographically these areas are
far apart, their vegetation structure
and species composition are actually
quite similar both visually and in
embedding space. We can also visualize
the ground level encoder across the tree
of life by mapping the average embedding
per genus and again see that more
closely related species visually appear
to have more similar representations
such as these two gymnosperms from my
original example um from the remote
sensing encoder. But these embedding
similarities are not just driven by
simple features like color but also more
complex phenotypic traits like similar
flower structure for broodier. You can
see here that these flowers are all five
leveled and have this this veination
coming off of the the center of the
flower but also the succulent pads of a
punch and ferocus in the cactier family.
So even without an explicit signal for
so in the training process
um using a crisp pre-training approach
the model um is able to learn these
ecological relationships just like
chatpt's next word prediction
pre-training task can model a wide
variety of linguistic phenomena without
explicit training signals for them.
So to summarize, Chris multimodal
pre-training improves downstream
classification accuracy for a diverse
array of natural world tasks and also
enables us to leverage natural world
imagery even if no labels are present
for set images, showing the power
promise of foundation model approaches
for biodiversity monitoring even when
label data is scarce.
Now we're going to um oops, I forgot to
click again. So now we're going to
switch gears one more time and dive into
some of the challenges that um that
still nevertheless uh face these
approaches for biodiversity monitoring.
And we're going to start with the fact
that biodiversity data, the data that
underpins the most of these these models
and approaches contains many
well-documented biases.
And even traditional biodiversity
monitoring and uh modeling approaches
have challenges of dealing with these
biases
and in in also leave foundation models
in general with a worse understanding of
the natural world. Specifically in the
realm of computer vision, these these
biases are are are even more complex
typified by this example of a butterfly
for my naturalist because what we're
trying to do is we're trying to figure
out what the model is trying to figure
out what species is present in image.
But sometimes images will actually
contain more than one species at a time.
So for this example, it's unclear what
from the model's perspective which
butterfly it should predict because
there's two butterflies that are clearly
visible. But for us, it's very obvious
which one matches to a species
observation.
Um,
so to to try and concretize a bit some
of these different biases, the volunteer
collected biodiversity data that I've
been showing you from from products like
I naturalist and EIRD. These types of uh
products are especially biased as well
across five specific axes that we'll
explore today. This includes spatial
bias which means that observers tend to
prefer easy to access green spaces in
urban areas. Temporal biases such as
non-ecological spikes from biiob blitz
events or on the weekends. Observer bias
which means that most observations come
from a small but dedicated group of
users that tend to observe more species
in more diverse habitats. Taxonomic bias
which includes a preference for larger
and more charismatic species when people
are taking observations. And also
finally sociopolitical bias where who
has access to the resources, time and
areas to collect biodiversity
observations includes skews towards
wider wealthier and older observers. But
for us to actually go from knowing that
these biases exist to quantifying their
effects on model performance. We then
developed a new framework called
diversity diff shift or diff shift for
short that cast these biases as a
distribution shift problem. Essentially
given D which is our observation sampled
in a biased way from the broader
biodiversity across the landscape J what
we're going to do is partition D into P
A and PB depending on some known bias in
in in our data such as for example for
temporal bias observations tend to be
taken on the week versus the week or the
weekend versus during the week work
week. What we can then do is compare the
the distribution shift in label space
between PA and PB to changes in a deep
learning model's performance when
training on one partition and testing on
another and quantify how different the
how different the distributions are in
label space using genten Shannon
divergence between the labels in PA and
PB and vice versa. We can then compare
this label divergence to the model
performance as well and even to expert
derived me measures of um abundance for
get different communities in these
examples to help us ground how much
performance change is expected
ecologically versus unusual
to help test this approach with real
world volunteer collected biodiversity
data. We again focus on on North America
and we collect specifically the diff
shift North American West Coast data set
which is over 7.3 million images of more
than 7,500 plant species again from my
naturalists across 11 states across the
western US. These observations cover
seven of the world's nine terrestrial
biomes and include some of the coldest,
hottest, driest, and wetest places on
Earth. Additionally, it covers a a high
variation in socioeconomic status as
well, including California's GDP of over
3.6 6 trillion the 2024 uh 2023 to Baja
California surge GDP of only 13 billion.
Um for this analysis what we do is we
partition the div shift knock data set
across the five biases that I introduced
earlier. And for the sake of time I'm
only going to cover three of the five
biases that we introduced but if you
have questions I'm happy to talk about
the other two later in the Q&A session.
So for the first bias, we're going to f
focus back on spatial bias, which
includes again a skew towards more
observations tend to be taken in easy to
access metropolitin parks rather than
hard-to-reach wilderness areas.
We can see this very clearly in the div
shift knock data set from this histogram
that you can see here. Different knock
observations, what we can see here on
the bottom, have a significantly
stronger skew towards more modified
areas as measured by the human footprint
index versus if we compare that to the
total land mass of all the areas of the
states that are included in the div
shift knock data set, we can see that
these areas tend to be overwhelmingly
wilderness thanks in large part to
Alaska's large um geographic extent.
For this partition, we therefore
partition the div shift knock
observations into as the human footprint
index describes wilderness and highly
modified observations. So blue being
highly modified and orange being
wilderness regions. As we if we actually
dis um plot out the number of
observations we have per species across
these two data sets or these two
partitions of our data set specifically,
we see that there is nearly
uh 10 times more data from human
modified regions as compared to
wilderness regions for nearly three
times as many species, which really
highlights just how underrepresented
these wilderness regions are in
volunteer collected biodiversity data
sets.
Applying the div shift framework to this
partition, we see that on average
training on observations from less
disturbed habitats in orange. So these
two parts you can see here tends to lead
to a uniformly worse performance than
training on observations from both area
from areas of high human activity in
blue. This is using testing test
observations from both human modified
and wilderness regions. This is again
likely due to the significantly larger
size of the modified training portion.
There's simply more observations for the
model to learn a good signal from.
However, if we actually only look at
species that are most common in
wilderness regions, as we can see here
on the right, instead of all species in
the wilderness partition, we see that
the wilderness train model here on the
far right does actually outperform the
highly modified model, but only for
observations from wilderness regions for
these wilderness associated species.
What this suggests is that the growth
form or the environment of these
wilderness associated species is highly
unique and that the model is leveraging
them to make accurate predictions and
really highlights the need that we need
more data in these underststudied
regions.
Switching gears, we're going to now talk
about space uh temporal bias,
specifically the bias introduced from
the city nature challenge, which happens
every year during the last weekend in
April. Um, which introduces this large
spike in observations from observers.
Volunteers during this week are
encouraged to maximize the number of
observations and also the unique species
that they collect within this week. So
again, if we plot out the label uh the
the data for each of these two
partitions for observations taken during
the city nature challenge versus
observations taken from the rest of the
year, we see that while the majority of
photos on our natural list are taken
from outside of the city nature
challenge, a sign uh a significantly
higher number of species are are
observed during this time as we can see
again. So more than half of the species
from the rest of the year are observed
in just this one week.
So for this partition, what we
hypothesize is that these observations
from the city nature challenge may be of
higher quality due to the changes in
user behaviors. Users are really focused
on collecting as many observations as
they can. Hopefully those observations
would be of higher quality if they're
really focusing on using the app within
this week. So for this partition again,
we compare observations from the city of
nature challenge to the rest of the
year.
However, against our expectations, what
we see is that the model trained on city
nature observations actually shows an
uniformly worse in domain and out of
domain performance than model trained on
the model trained on observations from
the rest of the year. And interestingly
enough, the model trained on
observations of the rest of the year
also classifies images from the city
nature challenge better than the model
trained on proper city nature challenge
images as we can see here in the left
side histogram.
And in fact, if we break this accuracy
down by day, we can indeed see that the
city nature train model in purple is
overfitted. It has a significantly
higher accuracy during the days for
observations from the days of the city
nature challenge, but then shows a
strong decrease in accuracy that is also
scaled with the number of species seen
in a given day,
implying that the model has actually
overfit to observations from the city
nature challenge.
Conversely, the model trained on
observations from the rest of the year
has a significantly higher and
consistent accuracy no matter how many
species were observed in a given day.
This suggests that user behavior is in
fact altered during the city nature
challenge, but is not necessarily
altered in good ways and in fact in ways
that allows the model to cheat on
observations for those um uh uh during
that week at the detriment of
generalizability.
So for the last axis of bias that we're
going to look at is the observation
quality bias where most of the volunteer
collect and biodiversity data that we're
working with tends to come from a small
group of high interest users. So if we
actually break down the diff shift knock
data set by naturalist user. So each of
these yellow dots is a user from our
from um from I naturalist we start to
see two different user behavior patterns
emerge. We see in yellow our equin
infrequent observers tend to obser
observe only one observation per species
and then move on to the next species
whereas frequent users highlighted in
blue here on the very end. These users
tend to observe species more than once
and they tend to end oftentimes in
diverse habitats.
Noting these two different patterns um
of user behavior, we then partition the
div shift knock data set into two
categories by observer engagement
specifically into casual users in yellow
versus engaged users in blue.
What's interesting here is that there
are only 521 engaged users which is
again this blue p partition here. But
these 521 users have collected over
three times the amount of data that the
75,000 users in the casual category have
collected. really um which really goes
to to highlight the the the
long-tailedness as well in the user um
engagement um side of our data as well.
So if we compare the out of distribution
test set performance for models trained
across these two partitions and then we
bend them by the number of observations
per user, we see that models trained
with engaged observations and tested on
casual observations have a significant
and sustained outofdistribution test set
performance on obser on observations
from casual observers.
Interestingly enough for this engaged
train model we see a strong negative
relationship between the number of
observations a user has taken and the
engaged model performance. This suggests
that the I naturalist observers who use
the app least frequently. So the
observers down here
um tend to generate the most easy to
identify data and the most generic kinds
of observations focusing likely on the
most common species that the model has a
very easy time to identify.
Um alternately if we uh look at the
model trained on click
here we go. If we look at a model
trained on casual observations, then
tested on observations from engaged
users, we see that there's a a strong
positive relationship. The click is
still not working. Here we go. Come on.
So even though casual train the casual
train models performance is worse, we
see that the more photos that a user
takes, the higher the accuracy. This
suggests that the most engaged users on
the I Naturalist app take the best
photos for species identification. These
users know what features and what
phenotypes to focus on when identifying
species in the field to make those
individuals more easily identifiable
later on from images alone.
So ultimately these findings imply that
from spatial bias volunteer collected
data is simply insufficient for us to
use these models for the wildest places
on Earth. From temporal bias that we
really should use more than just
bioblitz data and that there's some
challenges with the way data is
collected during these events. For
taxonomic bias, which I didn't have time
to get into today, we see that the
commonness of rarity means that the
modeling choices that we want to make
when we're training models really
depends on the downstream use cases of
the of the actual products we build on
top of them. For observer bias, when
possible, we want to consider discarding
data from those most infrequent users
and focus on power users when possible.
And lastly, for sociopolitical bias,
which I also didn't have time to get
into, we see that sparse data confounds
performance degradation by distance. And
so when possible, it's best to use
expert curated validation data in low
density areas to assure ensure that our
models are making accurate predictions.
So to summarize, one of the biggest
challenges that still faces biodiversity
foundation modeling is bias and
biodiversity data. And so now we've seen
that this bias driven this bias driven
distribution shift does indeed affect
biodiversity foundation model
performance, but in unexpected ways. So
in the face of these challenges and but
also these opportunities where do we go
from here?
So looking forward towards building
biodiversity foundation models that can
have real world sustainability impact in
the biodiversity monitoring space. We
need to engineer models with three key
traits including
centering ecology and ecological
principles. when building these models.
Two, a global focus with an eye towards
accuracy in the global south. And three,
making sure these m models are safe and
reliable enough for deployment and high
stakes real world decision-making
scenarios.
With these three key traits in mind,
there are still some significant gaps
remaining towards building these reli uh
biodiversity foundation models that are
reliable enough for automated
biodiversity monitoring tasks.
If we return to the foundation model
paradigm and the encology setting, we've
seen that there are even more rich data
modalities for us to pull from than what
have traditionally been used in the in
the foundation model setting. We have
things such as camera trap imageries,
bio acoustic satellite data, genetic
data, etc. However, these data
modalities are sparse and heterogeneous
across space and time. Therefore, for us
to further center ecology and
biodiversity foundation models, we
really need to focus on building better
pre-training strategies as this part of
the foundation model pipeline.
Alternately, the idea of one model to
rule them all across so many modalities
and so many biological scales may not
necessarily be feasible or even
ecologically correct. And so, we may
need different pre-training strategies
in different foundation models depending
on our different downstream monitoring
tasks.
Additionally, we should also focus on
better alignment strategies when
thinking when all modalities are not
necessarily universally present,
including recent work like Taxabine in
order for us to align modalities when
data gaps exists and but nevertheless
utilize data at scale.
Lastly, for the integration step, we
want to incorporate a global focus. And
so we really need to think about the
fine-tuning strategies and other um
fine-tuning strategies and especially
validation that centers performance on a
global scale and emphasizes accuracy in
the species rich tropics
and and including a critical eye towards
when and when not to use these sorts of
approaches depending on the different
biases etc that are present in this
data. So taken together, these
directions will help us to build better
biodiversity foundation models that
better represent and ultimately protect
the natural world and with the goal of
helping us to see and track the forest
for the trees. So with that, I'd like to
thank you all for listening and I as
Elena mentions, I'm starting a new lab
here u next year at University of
Michigan and so I'm in the process of
recruiting PhD students. If any of this
work seems interesting to you, please
feel free to reach out. That's all.