the MIT energy initiative presents
climate goals may take longer but we'll
get there Mass state Senator Mike
Barrett describes State's progress on
tackling global warming remains
optimistic despite short-term delays
written by the MIT energy initiative the
covid-19 pandemic inflation and the war
in Ukraine have combined to cause
unavoidable delays in implementation of
massachusetts's ambitious goals to
tackle climate change state Senator Mike
Barrett said Wednesday April 19 2023
during his presentation at the MIT
energy initiative Mighty Earth Day
colloquium but he added he remains
optimistic that the goals will be
reached with a lag of perhaps 2 years
Barrett who is Senate chair of the
state's joint committee on
telecommunications utilities and energy
spoke on the topic of decarbonizing
Massachusetts at mit's Wong Auditorium
as part of the Institute celebration of
Earth week the event was accompanied by
a poster session highlighting some of
the work of MIT students and faculty
aimed at tackling aspects of the climate
issue Martha broad mighty's executive
director introduced Barrett by pointing
out that he was largely responsible for
the passage of two major climate related
bills by the Massachusetts legislature
the road map act in 2021 and the drive
act in 2022 which together helped to
place the state as one of the nation's
leaders in the implementation of
measures to ratchet down greenhouse gas
emissions the two key pieces of
legislation Barrett said were
complicated bills that included many
components but a major feature of the
road map Act was to reduce the time
between reassessments of the state's
climate plans from 10 years to five and
to divide the targets for emissions
reductions into six separate categories
instead of just a single overall number
the six sectors the Bild delineated are
Transportation commercial industrial and
institutional buildings residential
buildings industrial processes natural
gas infrastructure and electricity
generation each of these faces different
challenges and needs to be evaluated
separately he said the second Bill the
drive act sets specific targets for
implementation of carbon-free
electricity generation we prioritize
offshore wind he pointed out because
that's one resource where Massachusetts
has a real Edge over other states and
regions because of especially shallow
offshore Waters and strong steady
offshore winds that tend to be strongest
during the peak demand hours of late
afternoon and evening the state's
Coastal waters are an especially
promising site for offshore wind farms
he said whereas the majority of offshore
wind installations around the world are
in deep water which precludes fixed
foundations and adds significantly to
construction costs massachusetts'
shallow Waters can allow relatively
inexpensive construction so you can see
why offshore wind became a Lynch pin not
only to cleaning up the grid but to
feeding it into the building system and
for that matter into transportation for
our electric vehicles he said
massachusetts's needs in addressing
climate change are quite different from
Global averages or even us averages he
pointed out worldwide agriculture
accounts for some 22% of greenhouse gas
emissions and 11% nationally in
Massachusetts the figure is less than a
half of 1% the industrial sector is also
much smaller than the national average
meanwhile buildings account for only
about 6% of us emissions but 13% in the
state that means that overall buildings
transportation and power generation
become the whole ball game for this
state requiring a real focus and terms
of our thinking he said because of that
in those climate bills we really
insisted on reducing emissions in the
energy generation sector and our primary
way to get there lies with wind and most
of that is offshore the law calls for
emissions from power generation to be
cut by 53% by 2025 and 70% by 2030
meeting that goal depends heavily on
offshore wind clean power is critical
because the transmission and
transportation in buildings depend on
clean power an offshore wind is critical
to that clean power strategy he said at
the time the bills passed plans for new
offshore Wind Farm installations showed
that the state was well on target to
meet these goals Barrett said there was
plenty of reason for Massachusetts to
feel very optimistic about offshore wind
everyone was bullish well Massachusetts
is a small state 44th out of 50 because
of its unusually favorable offshore
conditions we are second in the United
States in terms of plans to deploy
offshore wind after New York he said but
then the real world got in the way as
Europe and the UK quickly tried to Pivot
away from natural gas and oil in the
wake of Russia's invasion of Ukraine the
picture changed quickly offshore wind
suddenly had a lot of competition for
the expertise the equipment and the
materials he said as just one example he
said the ships needed for installation
became unavailable suddenly worldwide
there weren't enough installation
vessels to hold these very heavy
components that have to be brought out
to see he said about 20 to 40 such
vessels are needed to install a single
Wind Farm there are a limited number of
these vessels capable of carrying these
huge pieces of infrastructure in the
world and in the wake of stepped up
demand from Europe and other places
including China there was an enormous
shortage of appropriate vessels that
wasn't the only obstacle prices of some
key Commodities also shot up partly due
to supply chain issues associated with
the pandemic and the resulting worldwide
inflation the ramifications of these
kinds of disruptions obviously have been
felt worldwide he said for example the
horn sea project off the coast the UK is
the largest proposed offshore wind farm
in the world and one the UK was strongly
dependent on to meet climate targets but
the developer of the project oread said
it could no longer proceed without a
major government bailout at this point
the project remains in limbo in
Massachusetts the company aveng grid had
a contract to build 60 offshore wind
turbines to deliver 1,200 megaw of power
but last month in a highly unusual move
for a major company they informed
Massachusetts that they were terminating
ating a contract they had signed that
contract was a big part of the state's
overall clean energy strategy he said a
second developer that had also signed a
contract for a 1,200 megawatt offshore
Farm signaled that it too could not meet
its contract we technically haven't
failed yet in meeting the goals that
were set for emissions reduction Barrett
said in theory we have 2 years to
recover from the setbacks that I'm
describing realistically though he said
it is quite likely that we're not going
to hit our 2025 and 2030 benchmark
but despite all this Barrett ended his
remarks on an essentially optimistic
note I hate to see us fall off Pace in
any way he said but he added the truth
is that a short delay and I think we're
looking at just a couple of years delay
is a speed bump it's not a roadblock it
is not the end of climate policy
worldwide demand for offshore wind power
remains extraordinary said Barrett
mainly as a result of the need to get
off of Russian fossil fuel as a result
eventually Supply will come into balance
with this demand the balance will be
restored to monitor the process Barrett
said he has submitted legislation to
create a new independent climate policy
commission to examine in detail the data
on performance in meeting the state's
climate goals and to make
recommendations the measure would
provide open access to information for
the public allowing everyone to see the
progress being made from an unbiased
Source setbacks are going to happen he
said this is a tough tough job while the
real world is going to to surprise us
persistence is critical he concluded
that I think we're going to wind up
building every windmill that we need for
our emissions reduction policy just not
on the timeline that we had hoped
for the poster session was co-hosted by
the MIT Abdul LA jile water and Food
Systems lab and the MIT Environmental
Solutions initiative the full event was
sponsored by the MIT climate nucleus