My name is Lauren Golden, not to be
confused with one of our speakers today.
Um, I'm one of the co-chairs of the MIA,
the models, inference, and algorithms,
uh, seminar series here at the Broad in
the Eric and Wendy Schmidt Center. Uh,
and it's my pleasure to, I guess, kick
off a new semester of MIA talks. Uh I'm
really excited here to um I know start a
new a new semester here, a new you know
a new academic year. Uh and I think it's
going to be a really good time. Um we
have a lot of interesting talks lined up
this semester and going to be continuing
on into the the spring as well. Uh we
have uh our first set of speakers here
and I'm gonna have Sebastiano introduce
them as our host today.
>> Hi, good morning. I'm Sebastiano
post-docctoral fellow here at the Eric
and Wendy Schmidt Center. So, welcome if
you've not been to the MIA talks before.
Uh there are two talks today. One from 9
to 10 by David and another one from 10
to 11 by Lauren. Um it's an interactive
meeting. So if you feel like you have a
question, uh raise your hand. I'm going
to come around and give you the
microphone. It's important you ask the
question in the microphone for people
online. Um and yeah, I think that's it.
So usually, so essentially always the
seminar runs on uh Wednesday. Next week
actually it's an exception where the
seminar will be run on Friday in the
broad auditorium in the first floor. Um
yeah so without further ado I think we
can let David speak. So Davidid is a
grad student at the poly techchnic of
terin in Italy. Um he conducted a
research stay at MIT last year for six
months where he started collaborating
with Lauren and with the Xvivo group
more generally. Lauren will say a few
words about that later. um and uh he's
interested in deep learning both
theoretical and more applied. Today he's
going to cover more the applied side of
it. Um and the title of his talk is up
there infrastructure and modeling
challenges in single cell omic. Um the
floor is yours.
>> Thank you. Thank you very much for the
introduction. So thank you all of you
for being here. Um yeah before before
starting I want to thanks like my
collaborators with which this work
wouldn't be possible. There is Seb,
Peton, Shri from the broad institute and
Lauren Nava from Microsoft research. So
these works have been done with them. Um
so what I I will be talking about is um
one infrastructure challenge that we
will we have seen in deep learning for u
single salomics and in particular about
data loading and so I will present our
solution which is called SC data set
like to overcome this problem and this
like then I will give I will do like a
small break if you have like questions
about this first part or even like
interrupt me at any point and then I
will be talking more like about uh
modeling challenge. and I will present
hierarchical version of across entropy
loss for cell type annotation and then
after that I will leave the stage to
Lauren that will talk among other things
about um how the size of the data and
the type type of data can influence the
training of um deep learning uh models.
So why deep learning and I think the
reason is uh we have seen in the recent
years that deep learning is
revolutionizing any field for example
computer vision and now natural language
processing. I think all of us it's
basically using a chatbot at at a
certain point during the day and we have
seen deep learning also uh
revolutionizing biology. We've seen uh
with alpha fold and now we bolt uh
protein structure prediction protein
binding and all this kind of stuff.
We've seen that we have a models for
that now can uh process like the whole
uh DNA sequences. And so the natural
question is like can we expect the same
stuff on single cell omics in particular
we will talk in all examples about
single cell
but most of the things will apply to any
kind of single salomics that we will
that you can think of and the real
question is why we don't have something
so powerful on single salomics yet and I
will try to give like two answers to
like two of the problems that we might
have in in this field and so the first
one is what I call an infrastructure
challenge and to talk about this um
there there is a like a brief background
which is on on the fact that we are
using we will be talking about Python
and PyTorch because this is basically
the standard for deep learning and also
we have a good suite of tools for like
doing data analysis on on genomics data
and on um computational bi biological
data and so we have scampy SCVI tools
which is a set of like um probabilistic
models so Python is is a really nice
scenario and in particular the de the
developers of this like uh consortium of
tools have developed this data format
which is called the undata format uh
that is very handy to have annotated
data. So you have the x matrix which for
example in sia seek represents uh the
expressed genes per each cell and then
you can annotate with like information
about the cells information about the
genes and so forth so on and it has some
nice properties. It it supports like
sparse cell by gene matrices which is
usually the case for single cellic data.
So we will have just a very small
portion of genes uh measured during
experiment. It supports on disk data
sets which means you don't have to load
everything in memory when you want to
access your data and this is actually
pretty useful for a very big data set
and it supports sharded data set which
means you can have different files which
are easy to distribute in different
systems and then you can concatenate
them without the need of recreating a
new file and like waiting for merging
this kind of stuff.
Um and if we want to do uh deep learning
on this kind of data, we actually have
just one native solution that works on
top of this undata object which is
called the unloader which was developed
by the undata. Um the problem with this
solution is that uh it's extremely slow
for deep learning application to the
point that basically all the models you
can you can use on them consume data
faster so process data faster than the
time you take to fetch uh samples from
this. in particular if you want to do
like random sampling from disk which is
usually the case for deep learning
application.
So we can um ask like a couple of
question saying okay what could be like
the solution to this problem. This is
basically how we thought about the
problem and we went through it and the
first question is okay what if we load
the entire data set in memory. Uh the
problem with this solution is that
nowadays we are getting with very big
data sets like the last perturbation
data set. The biggest one is the tower
100 million data set and like it will
take uh several like terabytes of RAM to
do this. So maybe some like data centers
can do this but if you want to do this
on your laptop you definitely cannot do
this. So this is not a viable solution
for like small labs and people that want
to try this stuff on its own. Um so the
second idea is what if we stream the
data from disk because like instead of
sampling what we can do we just take
continuous continuous cells from disk
which is actually faster than sampling
from this because of reasons that we
will talk about later. The problem with
this is that I will give a as an example
like the tow 100 million data set. But
for this data set we have that the data
set is plate organized or in general
when you do an experiment usually the
data that that that you have out are
organized by the experiment. And so in
this case what happens is that each
plate is composed of about like 7
million cells. And if you train this in
a streaming fashion, what happens that
the basically the model will just
remember the last plate it was trained
on because we have a catastrophic
forgetting and so it will erase all the
information before that and we will
actually see this happening later.
Um and so the like the the third
question could be like what if we change
format like we've seen that data format
is pretty nice but what if we change it
and we have a bunch of different reason
not to do that. The first one is it's
pretty costly to do this conversion like
uh if we are getting a very big data set
it could take like several days and
several time to do this kind of um
transformation. Um the second one is
that we usually increase the storage
usage because data was like thought to
be used for this kind of sparse data and
for example um if we if we take the 100
million data set uh on and data files we
get more or less 300 gigabytes of data.
If you transform it to the phase data
set version which is also available
online it's more or less two terabytes
of data and sometimes you have also peak
storage usage which is much higher
during the the the conversion
and uh even if we do that usually we
still have slow random sampling because
this is how the disk work but since
you're basically doing the conversion
some people just say okay let's do also
a pre-shuffling while we do this
conversion and so some people solve this
problem like that um and finally like if
we want to do some analysis is after
this or like if at any point we want to
do some transformation like
normalization of the data we have to go
back to and data format usually because
like all libraries works on this kind of
format
and yeah just last to mention it doesn't
work with many tools for example if you
want to do probabilistic inference with
SCBI tools usually it accept data format
doesn't work with other formats or at
least you have to to wrangle around that
um and so like the question we were left
with is what we if we reink the way of
sampling from the disk
And uh what we actually want is like a
fast way to do random sampling for from
disk because this is usually how SGD and
other strategies works. But actually if
we can do fast quasi random sampling
where we will quantify this quasi
randomness. Uh this is actually pretty
good if like if we can get good
performances with uh a good speed and to
do that I will present you two
strategies uh which are called block
sampling and batch fetching.
Um so to start with I will make just an
example of like a training procedure.
Usually you have your model and you set
up set up a certain mini batch size.
Let's say that this is 64 which is just
a a standard um size for for training.
Um this means that in like normal
setting you will be sampling 64 cells
for from 64 different location in the
data set. Now if the data set is on disk
this means that you have to do like 64
random accesses to disk which is pretty
costly. Um so what we what we thought
about it like we thought about it and we
introduced this block sampling and what
we do is basically we define a block
size and this block size um tells us how
many contiguous cells we want to sample
from this for example 16 and now if you
want to um create a mini batch of like
64 cells you can sample from four
different locations use like taking 16
continuous cells from this and this is
just basically a trade-off between the
disk throughut that you can get and
actually the diversity of the mini batch
that you're getting. So not not much in
here. Um but now we can combine this
with this other idea which we call batch
fetching. And um the idea is that we can
ask the disk for more data at once. So
instead of like one mini batch or one
cell, we can ask more than that. For
example, we can ask for 10 mini batches.
And why we want to do that, I will give
you two reasons for that. So the first
reason has to do with disk optimization
and in particular the disk can do uh can
serve batch requests in an optimized way
and to give you a sense of what does it
mean I can give you an example it's a
simple example with with an elevator
this is just one of the many
optimization that this can do for
example let's suppose we have three
people that have to take an elevator and
the first one has to go to floor two the
second one to floor eight and the third
one to floor five now we can serve those
people sequentially and what happens
that we first go to floor two then to
floor to floor eight and then back to
floor five or like even if we can take
one person at a time we have to go back
to floor zero each time which is even
worse. Um and with this strategy we
basically travel 11 floors um in total.
Now if the elevator knows that he can he
has to go to all these three location
before what he can do he can stop at at
floor five middle way and like serve all
three people and now we just traveled
eight floors and then there is basically
a similar idea for disk if you know all
the data that you have to access it can
optimize the way he accesses it and
serve you the request
and the second uh reason is what we call
in memory shuffling and um the idea as
we said is for example we want 10 mini
batches worth of cells instead of one.
So we are actually asking for um 640
cells at a time. Uh and we are still
using the idea of like block size of 16.
So now we are accessing 40 different
random location in the disk. Um but now
that we have the cells in memory, so
like we suppose that we have enough
memory to handle like 600 640 cells. Now
we we can shuffle the cells in memory
which is pretty cheap because everything
is in memory and we can rebuild the mini
batches after that. So now each mini
batch instead of having cells coming
from four location we'll have many more
location like 35 36 depending on like
how many how many mini batches you you
choose to start with.
And so what we're actually doing is
basically trading the memory consumption
of your uh of your computing system for
an increased throughput for the batch
request and for for more mini batch
diversity with this inmemory shot.
And this is basically the full picture
of the whole algorithm. We have um a
certain data set. We generate just the
indices of those data set which are
integers. So they can stay on disk on on
in memory. We can then split in blocks
that we define with a certain block
size. We can shuffle them. And now we're
shuffing just the indices not the actual
data set. And we can reconcate them in a
single vector. And then we can split
them based on the on the um on the size
that we want to fetch from disk which we
call fetch factor. So mini batch time
fetch factor. And then we can just ask
the data from disk shuffle the resulting
data in memory splitting mini batches in
memory and return the split batches.
This is the whole algorithm.
And then the question is okay how does
this algorithm perform and um this is
basically a plot of the throughput of
the algorithm um compared to like the
choice of block size and fetch factor.
And on the bottom on the on the black um
dotted line you can see unloader which
is more or less 20 samples per second
which is not not that much for deploying
application. And like in this plot if
you go up to 64 um fetch a fetch factor
of 64 and a block size of 64 we can get
almost uh a thousand samples per second.
So this is actually a um 4 480 400 sorry
48 times speed up in single core set.
Now the other thing is that unloader
doesn't support very easily
multipprocessing. you have to like uh
wringle with the source code while in in
our solution you can use multiprocessing
in PyTorch data loader. So we also
compare to that and we have basically
more than two order of magnitude phase
and what does it actually mean for
example for the tow 100 million data set
it means that just to go through the
data set without any training with
downloader you will take two months and
with this solution you just take 11
hours and this is without training and
anything else
and uh like previously we talked about
this uh quasi randomness in in the
process and we quantify this with this
term like mini batch diversity and we
did two things. The first thing is uh
compute this in a mathematical way which
uh which is mini batch entropy. So what
we did is again considering the 100
million data set as we said this is
plate organized. So we have 7 million
contiguous cells per plate. So we
basically took the plate labels of each
cell and we measured the average entropy
of the mini batch that we were creating.
So mini batch of 64. Now if you do a
standard streaming strategy basically
you will take cells coming always from
the same from the same plate except for
like 13 times on the on basically on the
change of from one plate to the other.
So the average entropy will be zero. Uh
well if you take random sampling you
actually computed
like the average entropy of random
sampling with mini batch size of 64 and
you get a 3.63.
Um
and now what we did is okay let's
compare our solution with this these
values. So you can see on top the
performance of of uh random sampling and
you can see on the on the very bottom
the performance of basically streaming
because this is not really streaming but
is uh a mini batch size of 64 with a
block size of 64. So we are taking 64
continuous cells. So that's again a
batch entropy of zero. But you can see
that as we increase slightly the fetch
factor, we can actually achieve almost
the same batch entropy that we will get
with random
um sampling. And yeah, so and this is
just a mathematical way to like quantify
this. It's completely test agnostic. You
can like you can validate this with with
any data set. But we also tried to do
some real world uh evaluation on this.
Uh and we did it on the tower 100
million data set. So what we did we
trained a simple linear model. We didn't
want to like have conf confounding
effect from like a parameter tuning the
choice of the model or anything else. So
just a simple linear model and we
evaluated the F1 score on four different
tasks. The simplest one we can think of
set line classification. Oh just like
just to mention the power 100 million
data set is just this perturbation data
set where you have 50 cell lines 400
drugs then you have also doages with
that we ignored and you have all
combination and see how the perturbation
perform. Um so we basically just took uh
like the SERNA seek of each uh of each
cell and we classified the cell line was
coming from the drug and the mechanism
of action which is basically a broader
classification of like the drug effect
and this is was like the the labels were
done by the authors of the 100 million
data set and those are the performances.
So we actually compared four different
solutions. The first one is streaming
that we presented. The second one is
streaming with buffer where buffer here
means we can also have a a kind of
buffer as we presented for the inmemory
shuffling for the streaming strategy.
It's just that all cells will come
continuously and this is actually a
solution that some libraries uh do for
example a phase have a streaming with
buffer strategy. Um so you can shuffle
locally the cells but actually we know
that if we don't want this effect of
plate we will need a buffer of 7 million
cells or more. So this is just a buffer
I think of a thousand or 10,000 I don't
remember by heart. Um and then on the
far right we have the random sampling
and then we have one of our solution
which is block size four and patch
factor 16 which is actually the solution
where where before we presented an
improvement of of two um order of
magnitude. So we can even go higher than
two order of magnitude but we will get
less performance. So we we took
basically the best solution for from
both and you can see that like
regardless of the actual performances
you can see that the streaming and the
streaming with buffer basically go go
hand by hand and then we have the random
sampling that goes well with our
solution. Those are the pairing of the
performances
and yeah uh so we put everything
together in a package. You can access
the GitHub on on the right with a QR
code. We called it FC data set and this
is basically a drop in solution that can
go on top of any collection like we
thought about it for the anda format. It
actually work with any collection. you
can work with uh aphase and there is
also this Nvidia biono which is another
uh solution from from the Nvidia team to
work with uh within data format and the
way we we went to work with any solution
is just we um exposed for for methods uh
that basically give you the opportunity
to index your data set however you like
it there is a function called fetch
callback and batch call back and then
you can transform also the data on the
fly so you can define everything you
want for the data set you can install
with standard pip. So pip install SC
data set and we also compare this
solution to those other loading
solution. So the to a phase which where
like you can get the power 100 million
data set on a game face and then to this
Nvidia solution that was specifically
meant for like uh single cell data and
so on the right you can see that
basically the standard throughut is 20
sample per second for a loader. Then you
have a eight times speed up with dug in
phase over unloader and you have a 12
speed up uh of biono overloader while we
get a 48 speed up. But as we said this
can be used on top of any collection. So
you can even combine like a phase with
the data set and get even more. It's
just that you will lose a bunch of
things. For example, um in case of
aining phase and bionimo, those are not
undata like we wanted to maintain the
compatibility and also like the handling
of metadata is much harder to do within
phase and biono while for for unloader
also for our data set. You can actually
return undata object. You can return
pytorch tensor. You can return whatever
you like for your task and like now we
support also weight as sampling. That's
something that a lot of people asked
for. So you can also train on imbalanced
data sets and you will get uh the same
performances you get now.
Um yeah so just to recap like we wanted
to handle this problem of like having
data loading uh like handling the data
loading bottleneck for large scale deep
learning and so we think about this we
proposed this SC data set um solution.
So now you can train on this large data
set on your laptop basically. And uh how
we went for it, we basically trade pure
random sampling with quasi random
sampling and we show that basically with
um uh if you choose the parameter well
you basically get the same performance
of random sampling but you have two
order of magnitude improvement.
So I think this is a good time to stop
if you have any questions about the
first part. Yeah.
Hi. Um, nice to meet you. Great talk.
It's really, really interesting. So, um,
I'm from a pharma company. We worked on
a lot of data sets, single cell data
sets coming from, uh, clinical or real
patients. Um, so, um, while and it is
great that you can actually get to load
sort of very big data set that we're
getting. However, I'm just slightly
concerned whether the way that you
quantify entropy assumes um
a level of sort of diversity between the
plates for which has been tried to be
experimentally controlled. So the tower
data set they're trying to
experimentally make it as similar as
possible with the least plate effects.
So have you tried in a data set where
has you know patient samples in which
the sort of the batch effect between
patients will be kind of at a very
different distribution? Do you think
that the sort of the fetch the ability
to use the quaseron and sampling won't
make the batch effect worse?
>> Um so we didn't try any other data set
because like we we did the setup for
this large scale data set. Uh I think
that uh um like even in this data set
even if it was controlled there was some
technical artifact because we can see
the difference in performance. If the
like if this uh artifact is even more
pronounced one one what what one can do
is just like increase for example the
fetch um the fetch factor and so you
will use more memory or or you will slow
down a little bit the throughput and
like you will handle this in this way.
would you suggest um sort of quantifying
the entropy factor before sort of
addressing? So
>> exactly like for like it's very easy to
quantify because it's just a
mathematical formula. We use the label
entropies um like the plate label
entropy because like we knew that the
data set were were organized by plate.
But if you have any other way of
organizing your data maybe by cell line
then you can use the cell line label or
something like that. It's just that it's
not super easy to like find a universal
way to measure like how quasi random you
are doing. So it's either on downstream
task which depends on the model and the
task or it's with a mathematical formula
on some labels of the data.
>> Thank you.
>> Um yeah thanks for the talk. In my
experience the bottleneck was always GPU
calculation. So you you you of course
everyone always monitors their GPU usage
while training uh their models and um
using multiple workers per GPU. Um it is
I I didn't found it hard to keep the
usage at 100%.
Um so I I don't know why I have a
different experience so that data
fetching was not a bottleneck for me. Uh
related question I have is in your test
uh in the Tahoe data set did you measure
real u real time of the training of the
model like in these bar plots you showed
with random sampling uh block fetching
>> and streaming. Okay, so
>> what's the difference in time it took?
>> So this this was just about the loading
um of the data. We actually have tests
on like training a model on top of them
and the the the like the time that
doesn't change because like in our
experiment the GPU basically had zero
utilization most of the time. So even if
you put on top a training of the model
just get the same performance.
>> I see because the model is small.
>> Yeah, we didn't use like a very large
big model. Yeah, that's also the case.
Also
um just to add on that I think it also
depends on the server that you're using
for example because we have been other
people where instead of having a
baseline of 20 cells per second they had
200 cells per second. So maybe 200 cells
per second with a very large I don't
know foundation model the transformer
model maybe it can work like that. So it
depends also on the system you're but
for example in a laptop is pretty hard
that you will get this
>> on a
laptop GPU isn't enough to train a
foundation model.
>> Yeah. Uh I mean we will also talk about
like do we really need foundation models
and stuff like that. So yeah this is
just a way of like if you want to
experiment with some models even if it's
not that big you can do it and even with
bigger models we don't want the the data
loading being the bottle. So like in our
cases if you want I don't know if you
trained on and data format or you change
format but
>> I use data but I didn't use end loader I
always write a custom data loader in
>> okay yeah that's also another
>> and then I use multiple workers per GPU
set it to four if it's not 100 uh set it
to eight and then it's it always uh
>> yeah yeah so like what we did is
actually we wrote a custom solution but
since basically every developer is now
writing its own custom solution we said
okay let's make this accessible for
everyone.
>> That makes sense.
>> But yeah, you you had to write your own
data load. Makes sense now. Okay.
>> So, which this which type of disk did
you test did you use in this test?
>> Sorry. Which which disc did you use this
experiment?
>> Oh, this is basically uh an uh ride of
five SSD. So, this is done on solid
state disk. Uh we didn't try on our disc
because we didn't have them on the
server. we expect even larger difference
in performance because their disc
actually have a physical um latency. So
this is actually the the worst case
scenario to show improvement to this.
>> Yeah. And why uh second question why so
I didn't understand why you get a speed
up when you turn on like parallel
computation is if this is IO bound why
does it give you improvement? Oh,
because probably we can uh um probably
because we can go
uh where is it?
Like probably we can go even higher with
them and so you don't have to use
multiprocess like if you increase even
more the block size and you increase
even more the fetch factor probably you
can go even a little bit higher. So
that's and probably you will get this
like you can get this on single core if
you increase this number enough probably
the pro the problem is for example for
the fetch factor this will actually use
a lot of memory in the tower we have
6,000 um um measurement for each cell if
you have a batch size of 64 then is 64x
64 by 60,000 so if you if you start
getting higher you will use a lot of RAM
so there is also this um uh this issue
but yeah I think that in single core you
can you can get it there like doing this
stuff. The other advantage advantage of
using multiprocessing is that for
example PyTorch use this prefetching. So
you have multiple worker that prefetch
and organize your data. If you have a
transformation that takes time whatever
it is like uh it will do it in parallel.
So there is also this this thing
we basically with this number we it like
also the CPU bound of doing this
operation.
Okay, I think we can move on and then
leave other questions for the end. Um,
okay. So now I want to talk like about
uh one modeling challenge that we
encountered and like uh our little
success story on that. Um like the
general idea is like we really want
those foundation model or single cell
omix data or on biological data but so
far we didn't see a really um like good
models on that in the sense that there
are a lot of works showing that linear
baselines or some very simple uh model
actually outperform those very big
foundation model trains for uh for days.
Um and so we asked the question of why
this is happening and one of the many
answer that you can get is uh basically
we want to actually harness the
structure of the biological task we're
trying to model and the problem with
most of these models is that they are uh
like at at least at this like two years
ago they were blindly inherited from
other fields. Now we are moving towards
this um these more biological um
meaningful models and for example we can
take the transformer architecture from
like NLP and like if you want to do out
an auto reggressive framework what you
have to do with genes you have to order
like you have to give an ordering of the
genes that you usually don't have and
then you maybe predict like the next mo
most expressed gene but this is not
actually the like the way you should you
would model the task. Um so we actually
want to build model that the structure
and uh we took this idea and we applied
to a very simple example which is cell
annotation which is actually a
downstream task that most people do like
to test if everything works out and also
most lab want to do like to annotate
their cells. Um so what is cell
annotation in particular automated cell
annotation. The idea is that you have a
data set and as we said before we will
think about measurement and you want to
put a label for each measurement of some
kind. Uh and like to do this in an
automated way what we can do is we can
use some deep learning model to do this.
And so what we will consider now is auto
scale cell annotation.
And in particular we will focus on the
uh um Celix gene atlas.
And in this case basically what we have
is this uh wonderful work that tried to
basically benchmark a lot of different
methods on this annotation which is
called SCAB. And what they what they did
they they took their own model which
which was the best one which is called
it's basically a a different version of
tubnet and they compared to a lot of
different models a linear one an MLP and
also like some foundational model
fine-tuned for to do cell annotation um
and so when when we've seen the results
of a sit basically two things uh
actually uh catched our attention um the
first one is that um the difference
between the linear
model and the tablet model is basically
four four percentage points which is
very small because we are not even like
near the one. So this task is not even
solved is not even solved. We are around
0.8 and there is this little difference
between a simple linear model and the
transformer architecture which was their
best best performing model. Uh the
actual linear model also perform like
some foundation models fine-tuned on the
task. Um so that's the first thing and
the second thing is the way they did
this split which we called
indistribution test set. So what they
did is basically they divided the data
set in uh different patients. So you
partition for patient you will have some
patient in training and some patient
test. Now if you want to do annotation
in a real lab what will happen is that
you will have your own data set and you
will you would annotate all of it. You
don't train on a portion of it before.
So we actually wanted to consider a more
like realistic scenario which we called
out of distribution data set where we
actually took whole new studies to like
annotate and so what we did we we kept
the original data set that SCAB used and
we added a bunch of studies. Now those
studies was was chosen with the same
rules of SCAB. So we have the same
sequencing technology and we have a
subset of the original cell types
because we didn't have the chance to
cover all of them. And so we have 21 new
studies and like we we basically found
out two things. The first thing is that
the performance of every model dropped a
lot like from 25 to 32%. And the second
thing is that in this scenario uh the
linear model actually outperformed the
tabet model. So like like we also seen
before with other papers like those
those very big models doesn't seem to
perform really well when you test them
in um in some scenarios. And so um we
actually asked like why is it this the
case and to understand this we we first
need to understand how uh we do the
prediction and what is considered a
correct prediction.
So in the in this cell annotation task
what we have is basically we have a cell
ontology of labels and what what happens
uh especially for atlases even if those
are basically harmonized is that one lab
maybe put a more broader uh label on a
on a cell and some other labs put a more
granular label. So some labs maybe it's
not really interested in lymphocytes and
specifically lymphosy. So you just put
lymphocytes and some others like
distinguish between T- cell and B cell.
Some others like for CD4 positive T cell
CD4 CD8 positive and so on so forth so
on. So we actually have this kind of
hierarchy that we want to learn and so
let's let's make an example. Let's say
that we have um uh a true label given by
our data set which is a lymphocy. That's
that's all we know. Now what we can
consider a good like a correct
prediction from a model that learns on
this kind of hierarchy. Of course it if
it predicts that it's a lymphocy this is
a correct prediction. Now if it predicts
any of the subtype we have to consider
this right because we don't have the
knowledge to say it's wrong because we
just have the more broader prediction.
Uh and anything else is basically wrong.
If we predict something broader or
something different is just wrong. So
this is basically the set thing we are
we're into. uh and so what we actually
want to do is learn on those directly
graph that represent the structure of uh
of labels in particular those labels are
basically set inclusion. So you have
that when you have a an arrow you say
that uh you have a subtype which is uh a
subtype of of the of the parent uh node.
So we know that uh annotations have
different granularity but what what have
been done so far is that uh we treated
this task as a classical like uh
classification task and so we trained it
with cross entropy even like in this
study they trained it with with cross
entropy loss. Yeah really quick question
uh if you could go back to the hierarchy
there. uh you you note that you you
don't like uh you consider Luca site to
be the the more general label to be
incorrect but the more specific label to
be correct and I'm I just want to note
that I think that like or I mean I I've
had to deal with this problem myself and
I've had to come to the think to myself
like when do I do I think actually a
more general or a more specific label is
more correct or not and I could imagine
a situation where if you don't know a
specific label you would prefer
something more general where like
>> or a if you label something a T- cell
and it's actually a B cell that might be
worse than labeling it as something more
general. So I was curious how you if you
could comment on you know that sort of
value structure.
>> Oh yeah. So I mean there are a couple of
reasons. The first one is that uh also
for example I set up did did it this way
and the other reason is that like you
have a model and the model will just
take a like
six sequence and it will have to give
you a a label. Now this label that it
will give you cannot depend on the on
the label that you've put on. Like if it
is a T- cell and it knows that that it
learns that is a T cell you you may have
end up with a lymphocy because you you
didn't want to to go deeper but the
model cannot know that. So uh like from
like the classification task that we're
trying to model we have to give the
benefit of the DP to the model because
we we don't have a more more specific
label. The other solution is just
basically throw away all the broader
errors.
But what what we'll we will actually see
is that even if we focus just on the
leaves, we actually get better
performances with this method. But yeah,
that's a good question. Thank you.
>> I think that what they're implying is
that sort of uh and this might be an
analyst step, but you might want to
penalize the wrong label in a different
way and just wrong and right. So from a
bological standpoint again it's not part
of this but it's essentially the the if
if you can insert penalty in whatever
training you do um there are there are
biological penalties that you can sort
of see who's worse than others that's
all.
>> Oh yeah actually this is the point of
what we want to to discuss. So this is
just how do we evaluate things. So this
is basically how do we compute the
accuracy of the system. Now we will
discuss like how do we penalize the
model to do that. uh and basically the
standard strategy is that you treat
everything independently. And so if you
if you have a T- cell and you are
predicting it with a B cell would be
considered wrong but also if if you have
a more specific subtype of a T cell and
you predict that but your label is T
cell will be considered wrong because in
a classical cross entropy loss you don't
have any kind of structure in the data.
So for the model everything is
independent and that's basically the
problem that we are having. Um so our
solution to that was actually reflect
the kind of structure that we have in
the evaluation task. So we like if you
now look at all the nodes you don't have
a real probability distribution anymore.
But what what we wanted to achieve is
basically if you have some kind of um
probability scores on on some uh on some
nodes then your parenting category need
to have at least the same probability
distribution. uh you can make it equal
or you can make up make it at least like
having a little bit of room for like
something that you haven't seen or some
something else but basically this is um
this is the strategy. So we want to make
sure that uh if we put 0.5
uh probability on on gamma delta t cell
then we have at least that's for a
general t cell. Then when you train with
this kind of objective what happens is
that the interpretation of the vector
you are getting is different like you
are still predicting over the whole all
the nodes but now when you look at the
row probabilities without this
aggregation the interpretation is that
if you have some probability over a T-
cell you should interpret this as this
is a probability of being a T- cell and
not being any of the childs because
otherwise the model would have put
probability on that well in the
classical way you cannot give this
interpretation.
Uh I will I will actually show you an
example of synthetic data. You can
actually follow the the notebook on on
the link. You can download it. Do
whatever you like. Um so we just come up
with a random uh custom uh direct graph.
We make sure that it wasn't simply a
tree. And we have five leaves in this
hierarchy. Four on the on the same line
and one slightly before. And basically
what we did we generated some synthetic
data where basically each spot
correspond to one leave. Um and then
what we did is basically um the color
assigned to to to each cell was either
the leave or any of its ancestor.
So uh the actual generation process is
that each of those five spot correspond
to one of the leaves. But we we puted
labels following the hierarchy. So for
example in one spot you can have both
the label of like the leave eight the
leaf eight or even like its parent four
or one or zero but not the other
and what we did we trained a very simple
model it's actually a two layer MLP the
simplest you can get with a cross center
and hard no parameter tuning like it's
just like I think 100
100 um uh parameter model something very
easy and what we get out of this is with
cross entropy you an accuracy of um 0
almost 0.6 when hierarchal cross center
you almost get one. But the cool thing
about the to example we can actually
easily visualize what does it mean from
in the in the trudy space and so what
happens in the cross entropy case is
that since all labels are basically
independent one from another uh the
model get confused and doesn't know
which label assigned to each spot. So
maybe if you if you get more of one
label than the other probably this will
take um um this will take the whole spot
since the model is very simple. You can
go more granular but basically you will
never be able to like assign the correct
probabilities. While in our case what
what what you will see is basically each
spot get the label corresponding to the
corresponding leave uh leaf and the
reason for that is that if I give in the
model a high probability for example to
the leaf eight I'm also giving the same
probability to the leaf to the node four
one and zero because we are up yes
okay because we are basically up pro
propagating this probability. So now the
model doesn't get confused anymore and
basically almost every prediction falls
down to the
um okay and now like yeah now we can
show some results on on the actual like
uh atlas scale um data set and so first
of all those are the results of three
model those three models are deep
learning models that are trained end to
end from the SCAB study we kept exactly
the same upper parameters that they
found optimal we just changed change the
loss. We didn't run another
hyperparameter optimization. So those
can be also sub-optimal as results. So
you can see on the on the gray bar the
the cross entropy um um performance
which was the one dropped by basically
25 points and then on the right the
hierarchical cross entropy performance
which is basically 12 to 15% more
performant than the than the
corresponding cross entropy loss. Then
what we did we also analyzed like how
does it like this is basically a bulk
measurement per model. We actually
wanted to see how does it work for
example for each cell type. Uh so those
results are for the MLP model. This and
the next one all for the MLP model. We
have very similar results also for the
other models. So what we can see is
basically so those are the 80 cell types
that we found in the out of distribution
setting and every um significant
improvement is basically an every every
significant change is an improvement
over the the cross standard cross
entropy. We just found one of two cases
for the linear model where there is a a
sign like statistically significant
decline. But we also have to say that
the linear model is very simple. But for
the MLP and the tablet, every
improvement, every statistical change is
an improvement. This is for cell type
and also we looked at the at actual
studies since what you want to do is
just give you a new study and so we
wanted to see if for each study we
actually get an improvement and that's
also the case like every statistical
change is actually an improvement over
the the previous um result and I think
that's it that's a summary you can look
at the paper on the on the QR code and
yeah like we proposed this hierarchal
cross entropy loss and we have shown
that this improves out of distribution
generalization
on every cell type of any study. We also
have um some other plots on like tissues
disease. We basically have uh uniform
improvement over any kind of
categorization you you will get. And
also this idea can be extended to any
scenario. Uh there are not many
scenarios out there outside of biology.
But if you have some labels even for
like image classification where you have
this kind of set inclusion relationship,
you can also do that. like if you have a
a label that is an animal then you can
do this kind of uh play with like cat
and dog belonging both to animal. Um and
this is in general a big opportunity for
designing new architecture and training
strategies for biological task because
we have shown that no matter the
architecture you choose like a simple
linear or more complex transformer you
basically get improvement if you model
the task correct and I think that's it.
Yeah, thank you m Thank you very much.
>> Thank you David. Time for questions.
>> Um hi again great great work. Um and I
I'm I'm very very happy that people are
starting incorporating biological sort
of thinking and how they actually model
it because it will make a huge
difference. Um I guess what I have one
question about sort of your comment
about the fact that you can only reach
only reach about 84 um% accuracy. Um one
of one of the issues that we practical
issue that we're having is that you know
we need to find a ground truth when you
look at a cell access is like somebody
annotating that cell. So you're
basically uh using the ground truth on
partial truth and like it's literally
partial truth. So I even doubt that you
ever get 100% because you'd have to sort
of verify multiple wrong I say. So
that's that's one thing. Um and two I
think uh you know we practically
speaking um we actually use a signature
based nonAI model to annotate the cells
in which you basically use but we use
hierarchical
cell annotation which basically means
that every cell that we annotate doesn't
have one label which is flat but
actually has like a tree annotation.
Yeah. Um is there any way you can train
on that first of all?
>> Uh I think it depends on how do you do
you implement that. Uh I think that in
SCB paper they they compare to cell
typist which I think works like that.
I'm not sure but I think those are
basically um logistic regret like a tree
of logistic regressors. So you do you do
this kind of job and they show that
basically they outperform also that in
their study. Uh I mean one can think of
training or something like that depends
on how you define the model I guess. And
secondly, I know this this goes all into
the biological expertise and maybe this
is outside of your realm of interest,
but for example, one of the one of the
uh sort of improvement that you show in
the last was like T17 cells if I saw
correctly. And I think I mean from a
from an application point of view, it'
be really really interesting if you're
actually able to prove that those cells
have the phenotype that you're looking
for. Uh so that you kind of like you
kind of run an experiment in which you
do single cell sequencing and you do
cytoine labels or cytoine measurements
and then you run your and then you try
to identify them and see whether you can
actually tell apart like the functional
state which is what's really sort of um
hard to define in these com in these
very sort of fine grained sort of T
cells and B cell states.
>> Anyway, great job.
>> Yeah, thank you for the suggestion
>> over here. Thank you so much. It's a
very very cool topic. Um
some of what we've seen in in the lab is
that it's very hard to uh annotate cells
that are have very low cell numbers
especially with the cross entropy. Do
you see the biggest improvements here in
the performance of the model in those
cells that have very few numbers in the
the training set?
>> Um have to look at that.
>> Uh so you mean like rare cell type get
better improvement?
>> Correct.
>> Um I think it's uh we had some plot I
think it's pretty independent on on the
rarity of the sub type. uh it has more
to do. So basically when you when you
have this um uh
hierarchy that that is basically derived
from like the cell types that you have
it's just basically you take the
celltology and then you take the
subgraph uh induced by those cells. It
uh it actually happens that some cells
are disconnected from this graph because
you don't have maybe the parents in the
the annotations. So we saw the biggest
improvement where you actually have
distraction like for example for the
isolated nodes you don't get much
improvement because it doesn't make
really a difference because you don't
have this um this hierarchy but for
other things I would say is pretty
independent for example the
>> thank you
>> do you think if you trained on a mixture
of let's say coarse and fine labels but
then only evaluate ated on the finest
grain labels you had, you would still
see the same lift with the hierarchical
loss compared to the same
>> would you still see the same boost from
the hierarchical loss compared to the
standard?
>> Uh yeah, I would say so. Uh so we also
have like the kind of um plot of the um
like like 2D plot of how the cells are
organized. uh as I said this is also
independent mostly independent I mean
there is a little bit of skewess but
mostly independent from leaves or
internal nodes and basically as you can
see we have where is it we have
basically an improvement over all cell
types this also includes the leaves
which are most of them I would say like
half of them will be leaves so yeah you
I don't know if it would be exactly the
same maybe maybe two points less two
points more but basically you will see
>> the reason why I asked is I'm thinking
about the case where your label is
lymphosy in the training data and the
model predicts T- cell but the true cell
is a B cell and they can become overly
confident in its predictions at the
finer grained labels I could see that
maybe hurting performance at certain
levels of the hierarchy at test time
yeah but like what's the alternative in
the sense that like with the cross
entropy it even if it doesn't get like
overconfident if you predicts the
broader one is still not correct for
from our point of view like from the
>> yeah
in its sense of what the finer grain
labels are, those points end up becoming
like noise, right? Because it see it
predicts a T- cell and it thinks it's
correct even when it's actually a B
cell. So that test you're only focusing
on the finer grain cells than I could
say maybe being less certain about the
finer grained classifications.
>> I'm not sure.
>> I I can see the point. I would say like
what we have served is that like on
specifically siblings usually you get
better performance.
>> Okay. Interesting. Okay. Cool. Any
other question for David?
>> I actually have one. Uh you mentioned
briefly that your uh you said the the
linear model showed I think maybe the
least improvement or something like
that. And I was curious about that
because one of the things that I I like
to do sometimes is I like to have a
linear model for things because you can
just check and see what it is. Like why
does it think this? Um they're very
interpretable and I was you know so I I
like to try and give them some credit
whenever I can. I was curious if you
could comment on you know the the
failure mode there a little bit more.
>> Uh I think we didn't really um analyze
that. So what you're saying is that for
example in this case the linear model
without proenter is outperforming the
tablet
>> or I mean I think you mentioned at some
point that you saw more declines.
>> Oh yeah yeah. So yeah it's basically the
same but probably here it's easier to
see. Yeah, like when you evaluate an out
of distribution, you basically see that
the tablet drops 32% in performance and
linear 25. We actually didn't analyze
like the model failure like we didn't
check into the linear model. But like if
I have to guess why this is happening is
because the tabet model can pick up like
um biases in the data more easily. So
maybe pick up like lab specific
technical like technical artifacts and
so this can be translated from patient
to patient while in the linear model
maybe you cannot do that. So in out of
distribution this drops performance more
than the other but we didn't really look
right okay so let's give David a round
of applause.
[Applause]
Um so I suggest we take a five minutes
break and we start again at 10 with
Lauren's talk. Um so yeah see you in
five minutes.
So it's my pleasure to introduce uh
Lauren Crawford principal researcher at
Microsoft who co-directs a group here
also up the broad called project Xvivo
is going to tell us a little bit more
about it. Um and today the title of his
talk is when more isn't better
rethinking scale in single cell
foundation models. Lauren, the floor is
yours.
>> Awesome. Uh, thanks everyone for coming
and hanging out for the extra hour. Um,
so a couple things. Um, I hope this talk
is a little bit of everything. A little
bit of like shameless plugs for our
group. Uh, a little bit of, uh,
internship calls for MSR. Uh, and then
also science. Um, the title is a new
working title that I decided to use just
for this talk. Um, there's going to be
some negative results, but I don't want
you to take this as like I don't like
foundation models. Um, I hope you see it
as a a a place for opportunity, let's
call it that, for for future development
stuff. Um, so for those who don't know,
I'm a I'm a researcher at Microsoft
Research. I always kind of start these
talks particularly in groups like this
because I don't know if everyone knows
what MSR is. Um, Microsoft Research is a
global organization. Uh, we have labs
stationed all over uh the globe. Um, and
you might ask like what is it that
people at Microsoft Research do? And the
answer to that question is like kind of
a lot of stuff, almost like everything.
Um there are people who are in yes
computer science but also people like
myself in in biology. Uh there are also
people like in in quantum physics and
things like this. Um I am part of what
they call uh the bioml machine learning
group. Uh which is a subgroup of a thing
called health futures which is a the
life sciences and biological arm of
Microsoft. Uh people primarily stationed
in uh Redmond but also in uh uh here in
Cambridge and then also in in real
Cambridge, UK. Um and so the biomel team
uh is uh kind of spread out across
different uh both roles and also
disciplines. Um so you have people who
are uh both applied scientists, people
are researchers and we also have an an
RA program uh for people who are just
coming out of undergrad which is also
really nice. Um so what is it that we
all kind of do? Uh so you know broadly
speaking uh bioml kind of covers
different scales of biology if you will.
You have people like Kevin Yang who are
working on protein language based models
on this like kind of molecule stack. Uh
people like myself working in cells. Uh
people like uh uh Kristen Severson and
uh uh Alex Lou working on this like kind
of tissue level thing with things like
histopathology. There's also like things
like microscopy and they also have
people uh working on this kind of uh
patient uh stack here. Um for my for
myself I'm a my background is I'm a
statistician by training. I was uh I
worked uh kind of on interpretable
machine learning. My research program is
kind of this idea of how do you
understand how non-additive variation
plays a role in complex traits and
diseases. Um you can think about that in
statistical genetics. So this idea of
you know I can study how gene A's effect
plus gene B gives rise to a trait but
also how gene AA's effect times gene B
gives rise to a trait. Um and can we use
uh ML to kind of look over large search
spaces to understand where these
interactions occur or don't occur. Um, I
was also co-advised uh and some by
someone in pharmacology cancer biology
through my PhD at Duke. And so I've kind
of gotten back to my roots and really
thinking about this on this cancer
stack. So thinking about problems in in
cell biology very similar style of
questions this idea of now not gene A's
affect gene and plus gene B on a complex
trait for patients on the patient scale
for things like heightened body mass
index but things like uh how do I
understand how interaction between genes
or pathways play a role in my
therapeutic resistance. Okay. Um, so a
little bit of background about like what
our group does. Uh, our group being this
idea of like project Xvivo. I'll kind of
give a a shameless plug about our group.
You know, we're really thinking about
ways to move beyond um, you know, DNA
based measurements and really thinking
about cell state as a marker for cancer
therapeutics. So for those who may not
work directly in this area, you know,
DNA is kind of the cornerstone of
precision cancer medicine, right? this
idea of you know a lot of patients
tumors have you know diverse backgrounds
that are kind of measured by uh DNA for
v these patient alterations when it
comes to drug discovery uh you know we
use a lot of patient models uh cell
lines and organoids uh where we we study
the fidelity of these models based on
also DNA and then when I think about how
to stratify patients right I also think
about this with relationship to uh
whether or not a a a drug might be
actionable or not actionable based on
again these like DNA uh uh mutations and
so This idea is that this pipeline sort
of works really well um only if we think
about the future that's relevant to drug
response being DNA based encoded right
um so you know how well have we kind of
done in this paradigm well there have
been a lot of cases where this has kind
of been a success right we think about
leukemia's breast cancer being one of
these but there are a lot of challenges
in this space as we currently uh sit
right there are only 40% of patients
that kind of uh fall within this regime
where m majority of patients still have
like an actionable single alteration
Right. And the big challenge here is
that you know there's we have limited
responses due to both heterogeneity and
or development of resistance that can
happen both because of genetic mechanism
but also something that might be non-
genetic right and so we as these
patients like how many of these
dependencies are can be explained by
just like single individual features.
Um
and so you know if I think about this
you know cancer phenotypes kind of have
this really diverse set of inputs right
um you know I just kind of gave this
notion that we kind of sit here on this
DNA uh code you can think about that as
like this static mutated blueprint right
what's really interesting though as you
kind of move down uh this trajectory
here you kind of have this idea of you
know RNA is kind of this dynamic
interpretation of what happens with the
cells right it kind of captures in some
uh sort of tagged way or correlated way
you get some sort of idea of you know a
little bit of measurement that kind of
is correlated with what's happening on
the DNA mutation scale also things that
are happening epigenetically but also
things that kind of interact with our
environment right and so if I think
about uh you know where we are you know
we can kind of think about this idea of
cell state being these groups of genes
that uh are expressed by a cell that
kind of capture both you know cell
function as well as like an
environmental uh phenotype and so the
current pipelines are here but what you
know what we're asking in our group in
Xvivo is really this idea of can we
search for state based lethality on this
uh uh via this uh cell state like based
measurement right and so for a little
bit of background again shameless plug
about our our our group you know we have
great tools to do this but we're really
asking questions like how do we measure
complex cell state attributes and so
XDivo is a is a collaboration between
Microsoft and and the broad um with a
close collaboration with people at Dana
Farber where we're really trying to
bridge this gap between biology and
machine learning um with a diverse group
of both experimentalists, computation
biologists and also AI and ML experts,
right? And it's co-led by myself and Ava
Amini at at Microsoft as well as uh
collaboration with leadership from Peter
and industry um in this audience here
just and a lot of lab members actually
throughout here um that are that are
more than happy to chat with um we
actually are we have we're coll-located
in terms of of of both geographic but
also like in space. So, for those who
don't know, Microsoft Research is
actually down the street. I have no idea
which way we're facing, but we're on One
Memorial. Um, and so we're not that far
away. Uh, we also have lab space here at
the Broad on the fifth and and sixth
floor. And I'm sure people like uh Pete
and Shri and and also Andrew and others
will be more than happy to take you
around that space if if anyone's ever
interested. Um, and so XV kind of has
two broad aims if I were to put them in
different buckets. Um you know the first
is this idea of what's the real fidelity
of of cancer cell states. You know one
question that we kind of ask is like how
does the environment affect cell state
and therapeutic response. Um and the
other aim which is a big part of this is
this idea of building foundational AI
maps or these like kind of stateto
function maps. I'll get into that a
little bit. Um and really asking this
like fundamental question which is like
can we learn a foundational uh AI model
of cell state? Okay. Um there are really
cool stories that kind of happen with
both of these aims because it's the MIA
talk. We'll just focus on this latter
half right. Um so in this talk today
what we're going to focus a lot on is is
this idea of single cell uh
measurements. Um so you know instead of
thinking about a bulk who people are
working in space instead of thinking
about like an average expression readout
from a given sample we'll think about
sequencing across uh individual cells to
get this idea of like cell type
heterogeneity. Right? So for those who
are more quantitative, you could think
about this as like a large scale matrix
where the my rows are different cells
and then my columns are the expression
values of those goodness. Right? And so
this idea is like we want to build
integrative approaches to measure and
understand biology um at this single
cell resolution. Okay? Now what's really
cool about this uh era that we're in now
uh is that you know I there was a point
in time where getting single cell data
was was really hard to find and and and
you had different sources that were kind
of scattered all over the place. Now you
have these like atlas scale level
efforts where you can get these data um
at at uh high throughput. What's really
nice is that this problem of working
with single cell biology is both equal
parts computation is also like and also
biology. So for the again more
quantitative people in the room you know
some calculations that we used to do
back to the envelope is like this idea
of like for in terms of data points you
know if I think about this from like a
multiomic uh study you know if I just
were able to get data on DNA mutations
for 500 cells across 225 uh genes as
well as thinking about RNA expression
across 500 cells and all 20,000 genes
and I had some kind of idea of
interactions across environment you know
your data space can explode quite a bit
where you could be working with like up
to like 44 million data points like per
per biopsy And so these tools that like
valve presented earlier are are quite
useful in thinking about one how you
load data in at a scalable way um but
also making sure that you don't just
have to be at a place like Microsoft to
make an impact in this space right um
and so with all this data uh sets kind
of exploding in nature you know one
thing that people have really been
started thinking about is like you know
obviously like how do I start to apply
AI to these types of methods right and
to these types of data sets and so we'll
kind of go through a little bit across
like some of these uh AI def models and
then we'll kind of see what we've found
in working with these methods um in our
own in our own group. So just take a
step back you know this term foundation
model has kind of popped up everywhere
for those who may not know what this is
effectively means you know foundation
models are just effectively AI models
that can do a a diverse set of
downstream tasks. So, you know, very
fundamentally, you know, I might have
some data set. I might train an AI
model. You're going to hear me say these
terms quite a bit throughout this uh
over the next uh 45ish or 40 minutes is
thinking about this idea of uh you have
you split task into two different
regimes. Uh we'll start with the bottom
this idea of zero shot. So, what we mean
when we say zero shot is I take a data
set, I uh train an AI model with it. I
take that model, I freeze its weights.
weights were just trained on a
pre-training data set and I apply it to
something out of distribution or some
downstream task without ever updating
these model weights. So that's zero
shot, right? I've trained on something
and I try it down stream. Uh finetuning
is a little bit different. Fine-tuning
says I train AI model and then I take a
little bit of data from maybe the task
of interest. So I'll take a little a
subset of that data. I'll update my
weights with respect to this uh uh data
that has my um task that I'm trying to
do. And then I'll then I'll train that
take that updated model uh and then
apply it to my prediction. s idea like
fine tune, right? And you can imagine in
a lot of different areas of science, you
know, where both fine-tuned prediction
and also zero uh zeroot uh discovery
capabilities are like are wanted, right?
Um and so, you know, let's you know, how
do these models kind of work? So, if you
think about a model like GPT, just again
so everybody's on on the same page, you
know, um a lot of these use what they
call a mask language uh uh modeling
pre-training objective. Okay, what that
means effectively is I take a sequence.
So let's say a set of text, we'll call
this like let's say like learning about
AI is awesome. What you'll do is you'll
kind of tokenize this sequence. So
effectively what you do is you'll you'll
take uh you'll find some representation
with respect to like an encoding for
each part of the sequence. Um the
masking part means I'll just go in and
I'll mask part of the sequence and I'll
throw the masked tokens into my model
and I'll ask the model to then fill in
the gaps basically, right? And I'll
judge how well it does. is based on some
sort of loss. And so we heard David do
talk about earlier about this idea of
cross entropy and I'll ask how good was
the model at making the prediction and
fill in these given gaps and I'll do
this all over again. Now the same kind
of regime of kind of the background of
what's happening in all of our phones
and things like this now is what we try
to do is take the same kind of regime
and apply directly to single cell
biology. We can we'll talk through like
why we think this is great or not great
but effectively you could do the same
sort of thing naively with something
with single cell. Um so I could do is I
could take a set of genes and their uh
and their expression values the same
sort of idea. I can mask
a part of the gene and its uh expression
and I'll ask the model to kind of fill
in the gaps with this given uh um thing
and I'll ask the same kind of questions
how well was it able to do in fill in
this thing of a given sequence. Now
naturally if you're thinking about this
about the difference between this
setting and this setting is naturally uh
I have order and sequences here where
you might ask this question like how do
I think about how to nicely order genes
and again these are these are to be
modeling choices that people are
starting to do but naively we don't
necessarily have that nice structure to
to to naturally think about how to do
this uh um well so you know where has
has AI kind of had a lot of success
um in our space well you in a few
different places, right? Um, and so if I
think about different bi uh biological
modalities, you know, the first things
that kind of come to mind are things
that kind of have natural sequence like
structure in terms of their data, right?
So if I can think about uh DNA sequences
or protein sequences, there are a few
things I want people to take away from
this slide. One is this natural idea of
going from text to sequences. It's nice
to have this nice ordering of my data.
Um, there's another thing that's quite
important is this idea of the reference
training data sets. So one if you think
about particularly like with protein
sequences and you think about the
success of something like alpha fold and
others is you know I have uh both real
data sets where I can think about uh
where to pull millions and millions of
sequences from but I also can leverage
synthetic data as well uh because I
understand the biological processes that
kind of generates nice sequences and so
I compare both uh uh real sequences and
synthetic sequences uh to to train
models with with high accuracy. So
that's the first kind of thing is like
this training data set scale is massive.
The second thing is that the underlying
task and function are often tied to uh
biology and things that I can also uh
test and also that people who are
internally like really care about,
right? This idea of like in protein uh
language models, the idea of like can I
generate models that can now identify
new antibodies or new enzymes, right? Um
in DNA language models, a lot of times
we ask questions like can you find
enhancer regions around the genomes? Can
you identify promoter regions, exxons,
so on and so forth? And so we had these
really nice underlying function and
tasks that kind of like are also
biologically driven.
Single cell is not necessarily or
expression is not exactly in this same
exact space. Um we have a growing set of
training data sets. Um you know we can
have geneontologies and gene sets. We
have this idea of single atlases. Uh we
can leverage pathway information from
different databases. Um and we have
different tasks that people kind of do.
So if you split out the different tasks,
the three majorish tasks that people
think about or again I left one out here
which is if I think about fourth is you
know we can annotate new cell types
which is the idea of what what David
went through earlier in this in this
talk. You have this idea of batch effect
correction. So this idea of like can I
use uh uh foundation models to kind of
integrate across different data sets and
you also wanted this idea of
perturbation effect prediction right
this idea if I've trained a model on
cells from one tissue can I then predict
its effect right in an unseen tissue or
unseen state right or if I' if I've
trained a model on a given drug can I
predict in a in a tissue can I predict
the effect of a different drug right on
that same tissue right and these are not
necessarily the same as as some of these
you know, a lot of these uh analyses, as
a lot of you pointed out in the last in
the last talk, is this idea of like, you
know, how well will I ever be able to do
this when the idea that the labels that
I now train on are coming from human
annotated uh uh labs, right? Um and so
some of these tasks are are quite hard
and as a lot of people have kind of
point out, we'll get back to a little
bit, this perturbation effect prediction
question is like quite challenging. Even
though I think that actually might be
like the gold standard that we're all
trying to work towards.
Cool. But, you know, despite all of
these uh uh things that hasn't stopped
our field from trying um like we've been
trying um that there's probably a new
foundation model that came out this
morning that I haven't seen yet, right?
Like every single day there's a new
group that claims that we have a
foundation model biology. So, I just
picked four here. Sorry if I left off
your favorite one. Um but there are a
few things that I kind of want to uh get
at. versus I picked four different
models here that are all kind of
different in terms of how they end up
doing their their model architecture and
their training, right? Um the gene
former has a different scheme uh where
it chooses the order and it sequences
based on uh uh sequences of genes based
on like the uh the magnitude of an
expression uh vector and that's how it
does its ordering. um UC kind of tries
to leverage it has like a universal cell
embedding idea that leverages um uh uh
both uh expression data as well as data
that comes from uh protein language
models um uh embeddings SCGPT has a
different architecture SC foundation a
different architecture so the things
like SC similarity and every model
claims to be foundational in the way
that they they do things in terms of
performance so it's hard to kind of uh
for those who are thinking about
research it's hard to to gauge who's
better and who also because not every
model is publicly available. So like if
you you kind of have to take things at
face value because people don't always
release code to then end up going and
and retraining their models to really
have this kind of really head-to-head
comparison. The second thing I think is
like also quite important is is this
number here. It's the number of cells
that each of these models actually
trained on. And I'm going to circle back
to this but I kind of want to put this
bug in your ear. The first thing is that
you know uh you know gene corpus uh for
gene the gene corpus for gene former was
trained on 30 million UC was on 35 or 36
million here SCPT 33 million SC
foundation was 50 million there was
actually a recent paper that was trained
on over 100 million cells right so the
the size of these training corpuses
continue to grow um and the size of
these models also continue to get bigger
right and so there's one kind of
question I put in bug in your ear which
is like why do we keep doing this but
I'll we'll We'll get back to that in a
second. Um, so one thing that we started
asking ourselves and I'll take you
through the story of how we got here is
a couple years ago we started asking
ourselves like what is the actual zeros
capabilities of these models? I can
imagine if I trained a model on
something and then I fine-tuned it with
respect to a given data set that was
that was kind of aligned with the task I
wanted to do. I can see a model doing
kind of well there. But what if the
model is actually zero shock capability?
if I train it on a a certain data set
and I tested it on another data set
where I could no longer find fine-tune
like how good are these zeros
capabilities and so a couple years ago
we had this idea of like let's start
asking these questions and this was kind
of led by um an intern at our um MSR um
Kasha who asked these like kind of three
fundamental questions one which is do
these models learn the distribution of
data well do the embeddings uh capture
desired biological variation um from
these models and do these models from
these embeddings correct for undesired
technical variation when they come from
different studies or different
technologies. Okay. Um and so here's
this first kind of result that we did
that kind of started us down this this
path. Um so here's an example from SCGPT
where we're looking at its uh uh
pre-trained objective where the idea is
to predict uh uh unseen genes and it's
um mass objective. Okay. So uh this side
is going to be where we do this when we
look at just the uh training data set
with respect to mass gene expression
prediction. Um and here on the right
hand side what you're going to see is
the same thing but we do predictions
from using just cell embeddings right
and ideally if you were to do this
really well what what SGPT does actually
is it takes to make it kind of discreet
it takes the expression of every data
set um aligns them and then puts them in
these bins. And so what it's actually
doing is predicting these bins. And
ideally what you would see is a nice uh
diagonal, right? That if I was
predicting, well, I would have low bends
for these uh uh uh these cases uh here
for the lowly expressed things and it
kind of scale up for for the highly
expressed ones. And what you're kind of
seeing is not this at all. Um I'm kind
of just here just like kind of
predicting this sort of mean. And here
on this other side, if I do with cell
embeddings, I'm I'm I'm not doing so
well here for these lowly expressed
things and a little bit better for the
for the highly expressed So you might
ask like how does this now translate to
performance?
Um and so here's an example of what we
kind of did where we thought about
training data sets um where we wanted to
uh uh uh predict gene expression using
these uh this different model. Here
we're going to focus on um SC GPT uh
trained on uh different types of data
sets.
The uh this is the light axis is going
to be mean squareed error. So a lower
number means uh better performance. The
first model you're seeing is our
baseline. So what we do here is I we
what Kasha did here is she just took the
mean of every single cell in my data set
and that's my model. There's no
training. Okay. And that's how well uh
that model does. Now what we could do is
now I can say what if I gave uh um SGBT
just straight noise like I gave it like
random numbers like there's no there's
no real data here and I train it on just
like random data and then I as a predict
did you just un expression
reconstruction? does quite poorly with
that when I feed it noise which makes a
lot of sense right I didn't actually
give any train data sets the rest of it
actually is when I give the data the
model actually real data so what happens
when I train the model on uh on on cells
coming from the kidney cells coming from
the blood or cells coming from just
humans so regardless of tissue um and
you can kind of see none of these models
are that much better than me just using
the mean this like mean model as my uh
predictive model Um so then okay not
great. So then the question becomes
again we're we're looking for
opportunity. This is not a bad thing
about these models. Um there's a chance
to grow right. So then we start asking
the second question which is okay what
about the the other kind of thing of
annotation by cell type or uh am I doing
well of getting rid of technical
variation. So for the first case you can
kind of guess based on talk how well
this is going to go. Um not fantastic
for some of these models. So um on the
on the far left hand side what you're
going to see is um all these genes from
this corpus um kind of annotated by uh
uh uh different uh cell types. And u on
here you're going to see is a highly
variable gene model. That's a kind of
baseline where we take just the highly
variable genes as our our model and say
how well is this at predicting a given
cell type. And you can see how well you
can kind of do by kind of getting this
nice clustering and this embedding on
this map of um certain cell types
together. Um here we use harmony which
is again it's like kind of data
integration one. Harmony does quite well
at this task. SCVI which is a basic
autoenccoder also does this uh uh very
well and then gene former and SCGPT
struggle a little bit in uh in uh
dissecting different cell types. Again
not surprising given our last talk but
you might have this question of what it
is that that gene former and SCGP are
actually learning. So let's look at the
same plot but now let's color code by
sequencing technology. Um so again on
the lefth hand side you have this idea
where uh everything here is separated
out by sequencing tech. The idea if
you're really good at integration is you
should look something like harmony where
I have the all these tech technologies
kind of integrated together. You see how
well uh harmony does and SCVI is not
terrible at this task and effectively
gene former uh as a as a stark example
is like just learning batch.
Um so it's just learning sequencing
tech. And so what we started to think
about was okay well out of these three
things that Kasha kind of showed you
know how well is this model like
learning the distribution very well like
it's not doing so great at that is it
are these embeddings capturing
biological variation like somewhat and
you know really these embeddings are
just kind of correcting for they're not
really correcting for undesired
technical variation at all and so we
started and we put this paper out and um
I was kind of nervous about it um but I
I ironically other people had also
identified very similar things actually
people in this building on right below
us right where there have been a lot of
papers since then that have come out
which have kind of noticed very similar
things right that you know single
cellation models tend to not do so well
as well as as linear methods um
particularly if you think about
perturbation prediction I like this idea
of one PCA kind of rules them all um
there's the recent papers that came out
even this year in nature methods this
idea of like I could just take a linear
model and and um uh that tends to be a
better model than than having all these
other type of methods. Actually, we'll
circle back to the finding of this paper
that we actually see in our studies as
well. Um and and and there have been
more papers that have come out since
then. Uh kind of all kind of around
similar ideas. Now, if you think about
this, one thing you could ask is how do
I fix the architecture of these models?
And that's one question that we could
talk about. But one question came kind
of came to mind to me is going back to
this data question. Um so I have this
kind of reality here. But one thing I
kind of asked is is data abundance or
diversity somehow bottlenecking these
things like is training data kind of the
issue like is it not the architecture
what we're actually training the data on
you can think about this this idea of
like I like to think about this in three
different parts where it comes to these
different methods you know I have a I
have the architecture which to me is
kind of the car itself I have the data
which is kind of the gas I put in the
car and I have the task which is like
what I drive the car on in terms of road
and challenges and I really thought
about this idea of like are we putting
the right data right gas in the car to
really make this thing go. And so we
really asked this question of like can
we construct nice training corpuses to
do this? And if you remember I said that
all these models were trained on 50
million cells, 30 30 million cells, 100
million cells. There was someone um I
didn't maybe hear this that said they
were going to create a corpus that had
500 million cells and it was like whoa.
Um but like how much information are we
getting per cell, right? And so we asked
this question and this was kind of
co-led by a student of mine um Allan as
well as uh Mattie Hughes and and AA
who's now a scientist here um where we
asked this question of can we kind of
think about how much these data kind of
saturate or or kind of like scaling laws
with respect to data in these different
corpuses. So what we did is like three
different experiments that or a lot more
experiments and I'll show you a little
bit but the idea of this was if I took a
model if I took data sets from SCAB so
SCAB has 22 million cells and I
downsampled them to a fraction of their
sizes. So I took all 22 million cells
and I downsample it to have 1% 10% 25 50
and 75% of its data and I do this in
three different ways. Right? The first
way I'm going to do is just uniform down
sampling. So I'm going to take all 22
million cells and I'm just going to down
sample to these different fractions. The
second way I'm going to do is just try
to preserve some sort of diversity. So
the and the and the second way I'm going
to do is I'm going to down sample but
we're going to try to preserve the
labels that I know these these cells
have. So if I have a different cell type
I'm going to try to keep the proportion
of cell types as in the original data
set but just down sample them so that I
have 1% 10 all the way to 75% of the
data. Okay. The third idea I'm going to
do the same kind of downsampling but I'm
not going to use the annotated labels
from the data. I'm going to use uh like
I'm going to use what we call geometric
sketching which is this idea where I can
uh do like effectively clustering and
I'm going try to preserve around the
centroidids of each cluster a certain
proportion of each cell. Okay. Now on
the right hand side what I'm going to
show you is a result of running a model
on these different fractions. So on the
x axis you're going to see an increasing
proportionate data size. On the y- axis
what you're going to see is model
performance. And what you expect to see
is that if I see more data that problem
performance should go up. Right? That's
not exactly what you see. So what you
see on the lefth hand side is uh so
these are my different schemes all kind
of colorcoded together. Uh this is by
running gene former. What you can see is
a very clear story. This model kind of
saturates at 1% of the data.
You might ask like okay how much does
this actually replicate across different
things. So what we do is we take the
study we're going to do this in many
different ways. So I'm going to take
these 22 million cells. We're going to
do these kind of random down sampling
schemes across these different
percentages. We're going to do this over
many different models and increasing
complexity. So models going from just if
I just had if I did my model was PCA all
the way down to something more complex
like similarity, right? And we're going
to do this um over uh uh different
parameter sizes and different inputs,
right?
Um we have four different tasks that
we're going to run.
Um the first are a set of zeroot tasks
where we're going to think about cell
type classification and batch
integration on uh these different data
sets
and we're also going to have a set of
fine-tuned tasks. Uh one be cell type
classification and the other being
perturbation prediction where I'm going
to take we're going to take Tahoe and
split it up into four different
fractions based on different drugs and
different tissues within all these
different drugs. Right? Um and in total
we're going to have about 6,400 total
experiments across all these different
things. This is a this is this is pure
review. Um basically
uh so we're going to do this over many
different experiments or and then there
are some uh side experiments I'm not
going to show. We'll just we'll show
results for for a lot of these. Okay. So
the idea of like the saturation idea was
really this this idea of like if I take
a pre-trained model and I have an
evaluation data can I identify a
saturation point? Effectively what we're
going to ask is at what percent of the
data do I see that the model is no
longer kind of increasing in performance
anymore? like it's saturated, right?
So, we do this on a bunch of zeroot
classification tasks. So, here what
you're seeing are our different
subsampling schemes, the uniform random
case, geometric sketching, cell type
reeated. Um, you're going to see these
different data sets on each fraction
here across every single different
model. And what you can see is that
overwhelmingly a lot of times models
tend to saturate at at 1% of the data
and I don't think any more than than
25%.
On this given uh cell type annotation
task if you want to fine-tune it's like
way worse like I don't need any data
really like I just need 1%. Right? Um
and in some cases I might need 10% but
most cases for a lot of these models
particularly the more complicated ones
like G4 similarity I just need 1% of the
data.
perturbation prediction is actually
really interesting one. Um I kind of
want to take a little bit of time to
walk through this. So we also did some
perturbation prediction. So here you're
looking at R squar. So a few things. So
this is R squar. Um the dotted line here
is no is a no change model. It's the
model that says like what if I just my
perturbation prediction was like I just
predicted like no change from the other
state. Um what you're seeing here are
the different colors here. So the these
different color schemes are like the
cell type reweed geometric sketching and
then random. This non-p pre-trained
thing is me just saying what if we just
like randomly initialized the weights
and then we just did fine-tune
classification on this randomly
initialized model. And that kind of gets
you like most of the way in terms of
like the ultimate model performance,
right? Um again if you want to ask like
where does things saturate across all
these different things, the answer again
is pretty overwhelming. it just
saturates a lot. Um, so we had a we had
a we had actually really great reviewers
here that kind of pushed us on like
these different tasks and these
different questions across these
different experiments asking like, well,
could it be this, could it be that? Oh,
yeah.
>> Uh, quick question. So, it seems like
you started out as the smallest data
fraction you subsampled as 1%. So, did
you try subsampling kind of below this
and seeing
>> at 0%? Yeah. like taking like no data
like let's just like randomly initialize
just like random like
>> yeah I guess for this one it had
comparable performance but you can
imagine that like for 0.1% or like 0.01
01 right that's
>> we stopped at 1% because every time I
did a new fraction it like it ballooned
in number of things but that's a good
question like how low could we have gone
we do we have a set of experiments in
the new sample which is like not an
archive but I'm happy to send you these
results that are on like we do a 0%
thing where we include like no data
which was a a suggestion that a reviewer
gave us um and I'm happy to send you
those uh as like where they kind of
compare on those cool yeah thanks Yeah.
>> Oh, this is exploding. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Uh sorry, just on the last slide, um for
the pipation prediction task,
>> um it says hel held out cell types. So
you validated on cells that you like
cell types or distribution cell. Did you
also do it for like seen cell types or
>> uh not seen? So we try. Yeah. So there's
there are some that are seen. So we do
this in like a few different ways. So
what we do in Tahoe is Tahoe has a bunch
of different small molecules that are
trained on um across different cell
lines. What we do is that we Tahoe is
kind of tough because again place for
opportunity. Uh Taho is kind of tough
because a lot of these cell lines don't
actually see any effect across any
drugs. So we do is we try to hand we
cherrypicked a little bit where we look
figure four shows E distance between the
untreated and treated cells. We took the
four topmost of those and then we looked
at which cell lines those drugs actually
had an effect in. And then what we do is
we train on the drug where had some sort
of large effect and held out a random of
the other like four in that group.
>> Um
>> you hold out like an entire cell line.
>> Oh well entire cell line.
>> Okay. So that's even harder then. Yeah.
So is there a version of the task where
you can like hold out a portion of the
cells from the cell line and I think
that's way easier.
>> Yeah. Yeah. We didn't do that here. We
did the the extreme case again for this
like data explosion kind of question.
But I would imagine that you would see
these things kind of go up if you were
to do Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> We picked the hardest of the the task of
like if I were an ideal setting, could
we can we mirror that like ideal kind of
setting?
>> Yeah.
>> Learn.
>> So they're all basically uh a flat line
around R square of 7. I assume that's
the similarity between the average
training cell type and the held out cell
type, right?
>> Yeah.
>> So that's um Yeah. So you don't need a
model for that.
>> And and when you're training cell types
are closer to your test cell type, then
the line will shift up and when it's
>> I'm going to get to some sort of that.
Yeah. But you should see it like shift
up a little bit and we're going to get
to a little bit. I'm going to go back to
training days in a little bit, but
>> real quick. Yeah.
Is the no change baseline when you're
computing these means is it using the
same test train split same test split.
Yeah.
>> So it's only using one like as you go
along it's using 1% to 100%.
>> Yeah. Yeah. just choosing the same
>> uh some of the ML field like people
argue that the value of training this
foundation model is really to learn is a
this universal embedding and to be able
to do some unseen perturbations. So for
the baseline being compared I think one
limitation is that they cannot be
transferred to the ancertibbations. So I
wonder do you have any insight about
whether their claim is true or not
whether they can really perform an
perturbation wells for the foundation.
>> Yeah my hunch is my hunch is hard. My
hunch is like no. I I'll get to like
some idea of like where I think we can
go for this. Actually this is a really
good segue. I don't know if anyone has
like any burning questions, but maybe
it's a really good segue of like where I
think there are opportunities for for
this. Um, so we saw this saturation one
one thing that a that a reviewer asked
us to do is like okay for the models
that you can completely mess with their
architectures. How much does
architecture play a role? This is
actually quite important for like this
question which is you know if I were to
take something like SCBI and scale it.
Um, so one thing that we do here is I we
take the number of layers and parameters
in SCVI and either cut it in half or
scale it up to be double its size and
four times its size. Um, and these were
the baselines that some of these models
were struggling to to beat before the
HVG baseline, the PCA baseline. One
thing that's really interesting, again,
this is on cell type annotation. So take
this with, you know, uh uh we didn't
want to we wanted to do something that
was zero shot and and not something that
was fine-tuned. Um but you do see this
nice kind of scaling thing that kind of
happens with SCVI. Um with a caveat that
at some point with with model size are
saturation still kind of occurs with
this idea that like once I go from like
two to four, I don't really see any more
like real benefit from moving like too
large of a scale. So there are a few
questions that one could think about
going from here. The first is what David
and and just talked about before with
the work with Seb, right? The idea is
like maybe if I think about biological
priors or biological architectures, that
could be one case. So for those who are
a little bit new that weren't here
before, you know, David talked about
earlier about this idea of like if I
move out of distribution, at least for
the cell type annotation setting, you
see this drop off in performance. And
one thing that I could think about in
terms of recovering that performance is
having more of like a biologically uh uh
driven training opt uh objective
function, right? Um, and so this idea of
moving from just think about cross
entropy to something that's more uh um
uh you know this like treel like
structure where I think about this
hierarchal cross entropy might be able
to be a solution to improving model
performance across all of these
different methods right and one thing
that uh that I talked about was this
idea like you know if I can see this
nice improvement across the cell types
where does that improvement come from um
and one thing I want to highlight here
is it really kind of comes from this
idea of like connectedness across is
different true right so one thing I
thought I didn't talk about was this
idea that like you know where you see
drop offs in performance tend to be
these places where I have little
information about the connectedness
across the different cell types I think
someone had asked this earlier about
where I see this massive drop off a lot
of times it happens where I have these
isolated points so there's this one
question of like how do I recover that
well where there could be some
architectural someone gave a really good
suggestion about like a treel like
method um when I think about uh even
building these models from the very
get-go but But one thing that um at
least like when Pete and I looked at
this, the one thing that we thought
about was this idea of like well the
other thing that really is a cool
opportunity here is like the more data
we collect so that this tree become this
tree structure becomes more connected.
So I know how different cell types are
related to each other, the better these
models can also get. There's also like a
data driven question here as well which
is like data can also start to think
about improving these different models.
One thing I think is very
underappreciated about like s like uh
chat GPT is this training training
corpus, right? like everyone kind of has
a lot of the same architectures now. We
all know like what architecture are
available. The one thing that's kind of
like a secret sauce is this idea of what
training data sets go in different
models. And that tends to actually be a
big separator for a lot of data sets.
One thing that people think quite a bit
about in in language models is you want
data in your training corpus that are
both related but also have unique
information so that your model can kind
of teslate across like these different
uh uh uh types of knowledge and this
idea of how you upweight and downweight
certain resources so that a model can
then learn and then uh uh generalize out
of distribution. That's like a just a
true like AI is a science like this is a
true science that kind of goes into a
lot of these methods. So, if you take
that that idea, you can think about,
well, what do I need to maybe think
about when it comes to to training
corpuses? And and we thought about this
last summer uh with this student um uh
Aay who who interned with us uh also uh
um from the area. We thought about can
we leverage like biological uh knowledge
to really think about how to build
training corpuses where I have it's not
about the number of cells, the
information per cell. So what you want
in your data set are cells that have uh
uh large sources of information per
cell. Like a bit of information per cell
is the measure that we should be
thinking about. And so as one example of
this to kind of show how we might build
really good training corpuses, we took
this really big example. It's a really
baby example where we said if I took a
data set that was trained on just blood
cells
um and then I took another uh and I
trained a model on that and I took
another model that was trained on half
of these blood cells but also half of
this uh data set coming from this uh
transcription factor at so the same size
of data but I just split in terms of how
much data is represented across these
two groups. How well do these models
train or how well models perform out of
distribution. So let's do a very simple
example. If I want to predict if I take
these two models and I say let's now
predict the expression of blood cells
these models both should perform kind of
the same right so the x ax the y axis
you're seeing here is reconstruction uh
uh correlation these r squared values
again we have the blood model and the
blood plus tf model train on different
data sets but kind of performed exactly
the same but that's because this this
data is actually in distribution right
now I can ask this question all right
what happens if I train on neurons so a
set of data that this model has not seen
out different cell type that's far out
distribution how well this model
performed and you get something that
kind of looks like this. Now, two things
to kind of recognize. The R squar is bad
for both models, but you can see that
magnitude of difference that I kind of
get as almost this like value ad that I
have from having a set of diverse data
again very small but of the same size
versus just having something of all one
type, right? And so they started asking
us like, you know, what if you were able
to now build data sets where I knew I
was kind of like information poor and I
started to build data sets that now have
have extreme value. again not thinking
about size but a bit of information per
cell. So you might ask like how well
does this does this kind of finding
generalize out of distribution and it
actually generalizes quite well this
idea like whether I trained and tested
uh those data sets on like something
that came from the heart or the kidney
or or again the set of neurons having
this like data sets that are more
diverse against effectively these TF
atlases tend to express data uh express
uh cells that have that just express
different types of genes. So we can
think about this as like a proxy for
more information, right? That value add
of having that TF atlas is is quite nice
and you can kind of do um this was
trained with a linear uh um decoder. So
you can actually go back to the model
and ask are there parts of the latent
space that I just can't reconstruct with
a neuron uh in these neurons that I can
just reconstruct with these blood cells.
And there's actually a lot of it where
the transcription factor atlas kind of
has high explanability that is lowly
explained by just this blood model. And
so you can kind of start to get this
notion of like where I should start to
think about different things. Now to tie
this all back to Xvivbo actually like
this is what the kind of stuff that
we're thinking about. So you might ask
this question like can I start to
engineer state heterogeneity for cancer
knowing these value ads that you get
from data for um uh for AI models and
the answer is that you that you can. So
you know what we're doing in in XDivo is
doing these kind of like stateto
function mapping ideas where we're kind
of engineering heterogeneity right this
idea of like you know we're taking these
like transcription factor libraries
across different cell lines screening
across different perturbations assessing
things like fitness and we're trying to
identify both common and tissue specific
cell states and how they map to
different perturbations. Right? And so
we kind of have this like nice uh uh uh
uh different axis if you will where you
think about um as we traverses these
different planes of engineered hogenity
across different hallmark perturbations
and how this might scale across
different tissues. Now if you if you're
like if you're looking at this um you
know we want to build these AI models
that kind of learn across all these
different data. If you're looking at
this, the ideal case um when we first
started thinking about Xvivo and first
started pitching this um if you are you
know a leader at at uh at Microsoft
looking to support this or someone you
might say like do you have to build data
that that basically for every cell
across every plane here? Do I have to
have a data set for everything here?
That seems like a lot of money. Um is
that the ideal state that we're going to
that we're going to do? Interestingly
enough, that's actually not exactly what
we've learned is that that's not exactly
what you need. So, one one key finding
from AJ's paper was that you can learn
parts about one side of this plane and
that'll give you a lot of information
about another. Right? So here here's the
full table of all of AJ's experiments
where he took these different models
trained all on either using like a blood
baseline model and then uh thought about
uh if I train a model just on blood or
just on bone marrow or can bone cancer
perturbed seek and TF atlas but then I
also combine them. So I trained it I
combined these different data sets each
with blood. how well does it do in in in
testing the uh generating the expression
for things coming from neurons uh uh uh
different cancers uh bone marrow and
also in blood. And so what you're seeing
here is uh the relative logful change of
each of these models with respect to
this blood model, right? And for a lot
of these you get this really interesting
point where you know if I train on just
blood and I add other data sets like
they're not actually going to be better
than me just doing this distribution.
And we also got some very interesting
ones which are like if I train on uh
blood and I want to test on certain
cancers. This is healthy blood I train
on uh and I test on cancers. I actually
do kind of well with just the blood on
its own. And then there are some cases
where I'm just totally out of
distribution where like the blood model
has no shot and I have to add a like
unique data sets in order to improve,
right? And so you you can take uh
settings from this with coupled with the
idea that we can actually like engineer
representations of of models to
represent certain cancer models where
you know the transcription factor idea
was this idea like I can take these uh
orphs and kind of overexpress certain
transcription factors to to basically
engineer uh uh cells that express a
certain signature of a state that I have
desired. And we can do this uh across,
you know, uh uh many different
transcription factors and have this idea
of like how close is a given
transcription factor getting me to a a
certain phenotype of interest. And you
can couple that with something that we
that we've done with AJ's work. So if I
go back, you know, this this looks like
a scary uh uh uh uh endeavor where we
have to do a lot of different
experiments and I and I don't pipet um
and so uh so how do we actually get
information from here? But what we
learned from AJ's work is that you know
there are a lot of cases where I might
load something about one sort of
perturbation in a certain state and it
actually might give me information free
about something in another place. And so
if we can kind of learn how to traverse
this plot uh in a in a uh you know more
computationally uh nice way which is
stuff that we're doing now thinking
about how to actually quantify where I
might be information for you know we can
do this in a much more efficient way and
effectively that's what XVivo's whole
thing is about um kind of tie this whole
thing up together you know we're
thinking about how to build these
different um uh uh maps uh create new
data and the really important thing that
we're doing in our group is thinking
about not using all of it because I
don't actually need all of it triaging
the things that just help us the best,
train models, learn about them, and
interpret them. And that should lead us
to our next best experiment, and we can
continue this cycle all with this idea
of eventually trying to think about uh
state-based therapeutics. Um, so to wrap
up in the last couple minutes, I'm happy
to take all the questions that you have.
Um, you know, we have these two
different aims. Um, really what we're
doing in the first aim is really how to
learn and optimize in silicone and
engineer corresponding XV models. And
the second is really thinking about how
to build out these uh new states of uh
function data sets to learn effective
foundation models um in the future. Um
so with that um there are a lot of
people that are involved. I'm sure I
don't have all the names that I should
have on here and I apologize for that.
Um but people have been nice enough to
give us money and support and I'm happy
to take any questions that you have.
Thanks.
Oh, and here are some references in case
you want to. Yeah,
>> thanks for the great talk. Uh, so I had
a question about your batch effect
correct uh correction evaluation with
the umaps that you were showing. Um, so
I was wondering if you've looked at
embeddings from different layers, but
you so you could imagine that certain
layers learn things about bats, certain
layers learn about cell type. Um, so
yeah, I'm curious if you've
>> Yeah, we did that with gene former. Um,
so if on the gene former plot, you will
see this thing that has like gene
former-6L that looks like that that
particular layer. We did that with other
layers and saw very similar type of
results. We didn't do that for all
different models, but you're right,
there could be questions where certain
layers correct for certain things or are
better at certain things. That's a
that's a really really good caveat.
>> Some of the questions we had online.
>> Yeah.
>> Um, so one question we had was um from
uh Stephen Fleming. What do we mean by
perturbation effect prediction using
SCVI? I was not aware that SCBI did
perturbation effect prediction.
>> Doesn't it's fine-tuned. So we take the
embeddings from SCVI and train a model
on top of it. And then uh yeah.
>> All right. Thank you.
>> Hi Lauren. Uh thanks a lot for the
wonderful work and uh your team shows
that uh the data saturates at 1% for
these foundation models and uh showing
that the gas is enough. But I I want to
hear your insights on this is like uh is
the car actually designed to take this
type of gas pretty well. What if we are
pouring this gas into a Tesla while a
U-Haul truck or a Ferrari can actually
do the work? And because actually the
scaling law probably exists but the
current this transformer-based
foundation model was designed poorly not
even optimal to take this type of single
cell RNC data right bing ranking
discretiz discretizing the originally
sparse data further so uh what do you
think it's like if we find another
better architecture maybe we still can
scale better and considering that GPD
actually the miracle happens after 3.5
after taking million of parameters.
>> Yeah. Okay. I have two two like thoughts
here. The first is yes. Is a transformer
the best architecture? Um sorry if
anyone loves transformers. I'm not sure
if transformers are the best
architecture for a single cell data.
Actually there have been there's been
work on this floor I think from people
who have thought about alternative
architectures that could be uh better
and have shown like really promising
performance from that. I think
Caroline's group has thought a lot about
this this question. Um, the second thing
that I've thought about a lot is like
are these tasks too simple in the
setting of like are we saturating a lot
just because we're not actually take
advantage of we're not we're we're not
posing questions or tasks that are hard
enough. Like there's a there's a there's
a task complexity idea here that like
with the right complex enough task,
you'll hit something that now activates
needing a very complex model. And cell
type annotation or some of these other
questions just aren't that. And so we're
like not really aligning task with like
how complex the models are. And so
there's a question of like we had an
intern think about this last sum this
past summer which is like can I start to
think about task complexity and should I
think about scaling laws with respect to
like to that um and I don't I think that
might be a I think that's a really
underexplored um area of like can you
align with more biologically difficult
things um yeah
>> thank you so much
>> I think that might have addressed some
of the other questions we had online
recently so one
Uh one was uh from Sam Zimmerman um
essentially asking you know if these
models did better on their tasks would
you see that the models perform better
the more data it has? Do you expect to
see this an improved data scaling when
you if if you were to have a um a more
complex task? And a related question
from uh Brian Plowski, would it be fair
to say that this is another way of
confirming that these models don't
perform better than the mean? Or for a
model that is actually better than uh
than the mean at perturbation
prediction, would you expect the same
type of saturation?
>> Yeah, I Okay, that's a good question. I
don't know about the mean model. um the
the no change model is probably as close
to that. Again I want to be I want to be
optimistic here and say like maybe this
that you can see something there have
been interesting so so um um Alain's
group at Harvard had this paper where
they show so two things I think are
interesting about scale of qual scale of
of data and and model scaling with
respect to that data is Alain's group
had a paper that showed that there was a
data squaling scaling uh uh feature with
respect to data quality and they kind of
had some measure of data quality and
showed that as data quality went up
according to the measure. You did some
you did see some sort of scaling law.
One uh underappreciated p uh figure that
I thought was in Fabian Ty's group uh
with uh Till Richard who interned with
me last summer. he thought about um he
has this paper called uh self-supervised
learning and there's an underrated
figure to me but I think a reviewer
asked him to put in and it's like this
really small panel but they show like
this scaling law with respect to donor
diversity that I think is like also kind
of an underrated thing this idea of like
moving up in scale and thinking about
diversity across donors whether just
like individual cells that you kind of
get across this thing might be a really
good feature to kind of index on um and
so yeah I think there's there paths
forward, but I don't know if we've done
enough research to be comprehensive
about it. Um, but yeah,
so I was wondering I wanted to follow up
on the question from the other
gentlemen. So, so, so one explanation
also could be that the data is somehow
redundant,
>> right? That the subsampling. But it
seems kind of that your answer to him is
it was suggestive of that you believe
that somehow we can't detect or we can't
really reap the benefits of this large
data. So c can we somehow be sure that
the data is not redundant that just 1%
is not containing all the information
that there is?
>> So okay yeah it's a great question. I
think so I think there is some level of
okay this is actually really nice. So
>> we need more data.
>> No we've been thinking about this a
little bit. Um I've been thinking about
this in a multimodal setting with with
till. Um so there have been some really
interesting work uh of people in u other
areas of machine learning thinking about
this idea of which data sets do you get
where you get like unique information
versus redundant versus synergistic. And
I do think there are methods for which
you can really start to think about how
to quantify that a little bit better. I
think what we've been doing thus far
have been using like these metadata
labels as a way to think about oh we've
seen enough of this. do I need to see
more of this? And I don't think that's
like the right scale to do that with. So
I do So I will say that the way that we
did the 1% down sampling may not be
reflective of this idea of like truly
trying to preserve like unique
information. It may not be as simple as
looking across clusters or looking
across um uh cell type labels. So it was
just in the way that we did the
downsampling. I do think there are other
ways to preserve uniqueness um uh or in
some cases like increasing like the
interaction so the synergy across
different data sets to improve model
performance we just didn't think about
it in this kind of framework this is
like more like recent work that we've
been thinking about but yeah um I I
think they're paths forward we just in
that work we didn't uh quantify it in
that way
>> I have another question from uh the zoom
chat uh we have from Amaro in a setting
where most perturbations don't do
anything. I think it's not possible to
learn uh a model that does well because
most of the gradients are computed from
changes in cells that are random or not
related to the perturbation. Uh I guess
that's more of a comment, but I can also
phrase that as a question.
>> Yeah, I yeah I no I I totally agree.
We've we've also thought about this idea
of the difference from the idea that
like you know a lot of drugs might do
something and so you have like you kind
of kind of discern between this idea
like things change versus things that
like meaningfully change and so um you
know that's another question of like you
know can we start to generate data sets
where you have this sort of meaningful
change and kind of detecting that I
think that's more of a biological
question um that you know we are working
closely with our XVO to start to try to
define. But um yeah, a lot of these
things end up being noise, which again,
I don't think it's a place like Taho's
fault, right? Like I think if you had to
start somewhere, you're like, I'll try
to perturb a bunch of different things
at scale and kind of see what happens. I
think that's just kind of the result of
um yeah, you don't get a lot of signal
from somebody.
>> Your evaluations seem to be at the level
of of pseudo bulk, but you also look at
the scaling with respect to cells. You
think maybe that is also a fallacy given
that information you get from single
cell is at the distributional level
>> uh suitable in what way sorry
>> you do r squared which I assume is at a
suitable level same with setup
annotations right these are um not
considering the whole distribution well
>> oh yeah that's a great question yeah
that's a great point yeah I mean I don't
I would argue that I don't know if R squ
is the greatest I think what you really
want when you think about like
perturbation prediction effect is like a
more distributional based like metric I
seven and I talk about this like all the
time like yeah it's just the one that
people always think about and people use
a lot but I agree like this idea of R
square can be conflated or deflated
based on like how well you're doing on
the cells that change or if you're
overindexing on the cells that don't
change and so you can have a misaligned
uh metric in terms of performance versus
like what the model is actually doing
across individual cells. Yeah, I think
about that. I mean if you have a thought
there um but I know people have been
thinking about better metrics for to
kind of capture the more individual cell
type thing. Yeah,
>> I have one last question from the uh
Zoom chat. Uh could a hybrid model uh
from Anthony uh could a hybrid model
that trains on both genes and expression
value and base pairs themselves unlock
some of the limitations of expression
ccentric models or are these two data
types just too different to be useful in
pre-training?
>> I mean maybe I think that's a really
good point. I mean like I get this
question a lot which is like do we like
at XV people think RNA is everything or
the end all beall like I think no I
think multimodal things are the way that
everyone's kind of moving the really the
real big question is how you start to
integrate across modalities right and
like one one strategy people have had is
I can just take one model trained on one
thing and then train a model on top of
that I think UC sort of leverages some
of this kind of strategy I don't know if
that's the way to kind of go because you
kind of lose what you really want to do
is capture the interaction across
modalities which I think is like the
challenge like how do you do that? But I
do agree like I think in incorporating
um other modes is is to get a more
holistic view of what you think cell
state might represent is yeah a a good
pathway forward.