every time I see that video I get very
inspired but anyway good morning I'm
gatri shasan executive director of MIT
corporate relations which comprises of
the industry liazon program and startup
exchange welcome to this today's Nano
Summit and I want to thank all our
district uish speakers panelists and of
course you the audience for joining us
today the field of nanotechnology is
revolutionizing industries from Health
Care to manufacturing energy and Beyond
as we gathered today you will hear about
how we are at the intersection of
breakthrough research and real world
problem solving applications to shape
the future at MIT we are committed to
pushing the boundaries of innovation and
nanoscience
and nanoscience is at the heart of all
this and making it happen the MIT
Industry liazon Program plays a key role
in fostering collaborations between
industry and Academia and specifically
at MIT we try to bring um programming
that will bring all of mit's research um
excellent research Innovation students
and educations to you for you to uh
explore and connect today's event is
more than just for you to attend a nano
Summit right it's more than a summit it
is an opportunity for you to collaborate
engage in meaningful dialogue form
Partnerships and explore how
nanotechnology can be leveraged to
address Global
challenges think about how you can
contribute to the growing Nano ecosystem
and what opportunities lie ahead in
collaboration I would like to thank the
event um and communication teams and the
event organized ERS for all their hard
work to making this Summit happen and be
successful with that I look forward to
an inspiring day of insights uh
discussions and opportunity to shape the
future of nanotechnology together I
would like to now hand it off to
Professor Vladimir bulovic who is the
director of MIT Nano to take it on and
show you what's going to come today
unfold for you today thank you
well thank you gatri for introducing the
event thank you so much for being here
I'm hoping that as the day progresses
you find yourself more and more excited
and asking what's yet yet another
discovery that you want to be exposed to
uh MIT n is extremely proud of Hosting
many different kinds of communities
there are about 40 different departments
labs and centers that utilize the tools
of MIT Nano to advance their next
Frontiers so what you're going to see
today is only a glimpse into a set of
opportunities that the world is about to
see we had to focus and so we focused on
five separate topics to show you off
today the first one is indeed looking at
the options of sustainable materials
solutions for Next Generation
Technologies sustainability climate
issues have been one of the top topics
for the world and indeed MIT through the
leadership of Sally cornbluth has
embraced it as one of the top topics MIT
needs to spend its time on we want to
tell you some of the perspectives from
the nanoscale as led by Des Plata um
that will go ahead and expose you to
various ways of thinking about what
climate needs next what can we do as
Technologies indeed to strongly affected
that will lead us to a short break
followed by a discussion of how do the
Technologies of MIT really reach the
world as an institution our business is
very simple uh we need to make impact on
the world through the demonstration of
new technologies new ideas and indeed
training of the people that can affect
the grand needs of the world but that
transition of the grand idea that is
imagined at the laboratory to something
that everyone can use a million people
can use in their hands is a journey and
that Journey needs to be understood just
as much as we need to understand physics
and chemistry and biology we need to
understand entrepreneurship and the
scaling up of an idea from the instance
in in the lab 2 million people
benefiting from it second session will
focus on that and the manager of star.
Nano program at MIT Nano Joyce Vu would
lead that second session we'll have a
little break uh where we have a chance
to expose you to variety of startups
that have been Associated through the
use of nanotechnology with MIT Nano and
other intellectual centers of MIT and
then we'll start the afternoon session
by focusing on nanom medicine for all
Professor Sangita bathia will lead a set
of incredibly distinguished individuals
who will tell us about where nanom
medicine is heading and how can you
personalize that nanom medicine thanks
to the benefits of nanotechnology that's
upon us the afternoon session continues
uh with our colleagues from Lincoln
laboratory we have asked them to tell us
about their Visions for the next
generation of computing and led by Mark
Gawker uh you will find a whole series
of opportunities that indeed through the
advanced technology Division and other
divisions of Lincoln have indeed been or
are about to be deployed into the world
uh for the tremendous benefit to all uh
we'll conclude uh on an extremely
important session that Dr Brian Anthony
will lead on modeling of matter
rethinking how do we utilize the AI
machine learning to indeed reach the
physical scale and impact the physical
scale discoveries I'm extremely excited
for what you're about to see I'm going
to even have the benefit of
participating as an engineer and a
scientist in one of the sessions coming
up that's also exciting to me in its own
right but thank you so much for being
here and I will start the session uh by
asking deser Plata uh to join us and uh
indeed kick off the very first session
of MIT Nano the Nano Summit thank you
for being here
[Applause]
is