My name is Tony Chen and I'm the CEO of
Manolan. We're a data intelligence
company that's making aquaculture or
ocean farming more predictable. I'm a
core 6 computer science alum from MIT
and you can see from the photos water
whether it's the pool or the Charles has
really been a central part of my life
since my time there. Um and at Manolin
the problem that we're focused on is how
to help aquaculture scale sustainably.
So aquaculture and again that's fish
farming is the fastest growing food
system in the world right now. One in
seven people rely on fish as their
primary source of protein and production
needs to double reliably in the next
coming decades. But despite all this
importance, it's honestly the least
modern form of of industrial agriculture
or modern agriculture. There's huge gaps
in farming systems, nutrition, genetics,
biotech, and the industry still lacks a
ton of the infrastructure that crop and
land farmers take for granted. Things
like commodity markets, insurance, and
real-time risk analytics. So, in order
to really scale responsibly and
efficiently, we believe that aquaculture
needs a data foundation that can make
farming more predictable and decisions
much more measurable. So what we've
built is a data platform that integrates
a combination of fish health and
oceanographic data. We process data
sources like satellites, ocean sensors,
machine vision cameras, and onfarmm
operational records to help our
customers basically make smarter
decisions. We package these insights
through two integrated platforms. On the
farming side, we have watershed and it's
our intelligence platform that helps on
providing better models to farmers. And
on the supplier end, we have Harpoon,
which is our supplierf facing research
and customer support platform that
powers large-scale observational studies
for feed, genetics, biotech, and health
companies. And what we're really working
on here is accelerating the feedback
loop between farmers and suppliers
across the industry. Behind all of this
is a proprietary data engine that
restructures raw farm data into the most
detailed health and performance
timelines across the industry. And what
it really helps us understand is what's
working and why. And here are a couple
example of how that translates into
actual real world impact. So one of our
customers is Veramarus. And they produce
omega-3 oils to replace fish oil in
feeds. And the goal of this is to reduce
impendence on wild capture fisheries
like anchovies where a ton of that fish
oil gets applied in fish field feed.
They use algae as their kind of conduit
for how to produce these oils. And
through our harpoon platform, we
actually conducted one of the largest
real world EPA and DHA studies ever run
in salmon farming. We analyzed thousands
of farming cycles to determine the
optimal levels of fatty acids that
maximize survival, growth, and harvest
quality. And in addition to the
sustainability importance of this
research, it helped Veramarus improve
their relationships with their customers
and trust the benefits of their product
even more. In another example, and this
is on the farming side, we've helped
Hoffsath and Cargill improve their
performance against sea lice. So sealite
is a parasite, but it's one of the most
challenging and expensive issues in
salmon farming. It impacts fish welfare,
regulatory compliance, and obviously
profit margins. And through our
predictive models, Hoff was able to
anticipate pressure weeks in advance of
sea lice coming to their farms and they
were able to time up treatments much
more effectively. For them, this
contributed to over $5 million in direct
revenue gains and simply they were able
to bring more fish to the market.
So for this group, we have a couple
different asks. So and we work with a
lot of different partners, but we have
three different areas. One is if you
provide a product, whether it's a
biological product, a feed solution, or
a health solution in another industry
that may be applicable to fish, we'd
love to launch some more of these
solutions to help our customers.
Secondary, if you guys have any sort of
data sets that may be helpful for our
models, we're always in the market
looking for ways to improve our
predictability towards our customers.
And then the last piece is launching
fintech or insurance solutions. We have
the data to power it. We're always
looking for partners who can again help
us launch some of these solutions into
the market. So if you're working in
these areas or are simply curious about
the potential, I'd love to chat. Thank
you guys for your time. And again, I'm
Tony.
>> Thank you, Tony.
Again, please post any questions to the
chat or the Q&A tab, whatever's easier.
But let me start by asking talking about
the scaling. Um, which markets unlock
the next major phase of growth for you?
Yeah. So, in our industry, much of fish
farming doesn't happen in the Western
world or in the United States in
particular. We actually started with
oyster farmers and right now primarily
work with salmon farmers in Scandinavia.
But as far as scaling kind of towards
the rest of the world, there's there's a
couple different species that really
matter. One is salmon farming uh kind of
around the world and again, Scandinavia
leads in that. Um seabbass farming in
the Mediterranean and then shrimp
farming both in South America and
Southeast Asia. Those are kind of the
top markets for us as how we see
ourselves growing.
>> And um how do partnerships with feed
genetics and biotech suppliers
accelerate the growth compared to farm
only strategy?
>> No. So I mean if you imagine kind of
ocean farmers, there's millions of them.
A lot of small holders in shrimp in
Southeast Asia, South America. Um and
then the large players kind of in the
salmon industry. But suppliers, it's
what I've come to learn kind of in our
time in the industry are largely
US-based. So, a lot of the
pharmaceutical companies, the feed
companies, the uh some of the companies
that I listed on our slide decks, um
they're the ones that that operate kind
of as suppliers around the entire world.
So, those partners really can help us
get into a lot of those markets. um the
same kind of chemical manufacturers that
work in animal feed are the same ones
that are working in fish feed and
they're really kind of conduits for how
we expand around the world is through a
lot of these partnerships.
>> Great. And just to also touch on other
sectors, how um do you see new uh the
model evolving with new capabilities
touching on finance, insurance, risk,
all of that? Yeah, I mean in our heads
this is this is just it's a natural
progression for the industry right now.
The industry is just growing very
quickly and we don't pay attention to it
much because it's largely volumes are
coming you know from internal not export
markets and third world countries is is
where a lot of this is happening but we
know financial institutions reinsurance
companies we're all trying to build
products into those spaces. Um this is
one of those industries that's growing
very quickly um and and needs those
solutions because the way that those
industries are scaling you can imagine
on small budgets don't necessarily look
the cleanest. Um but that's one of the
problems that we're trying to solve when
it comes to the fintech and financing
solutions.
>> Thank you Tonnie. Appreciate
>> it.