Wonderful. Well, thank you both. I just
reflecting on on what we just heard. For
those of you who are out there in the
world, it is almost as if we were
sitting in an office in building 62 here
at MIT listening to collaborators and
worldclass researchers on corporate
innovation brainstorm together about
what this new aspect of uh of
geopolitical driving of corporate
innovation will mean. And and we're so
fortunate to have that. And I thank you
both for your time. As you and the world
reflect on what you've just heard, as
you continue your day or start your day
or finish your day, I'm sure you will
have other questions and thoughts about
what you've heard. There are probably
some questions we couldn't get to.
Although I know Dr. Phil is a world
expert at pulling those things in. Um,
you can certainly consult Fiona and
Phil's new book. That's a great
reference for a lot of this. You can
also come to us at the MIT industrial
leazison program. Um, at a very granular
level, our job is to help people find
answers to questions when they don't
know where to go at MIT. It is what
we're good at and we're happy to do it.
If you're a member of the program,
certainly that is our duty to you. And
if you're not a member of the Cobra
program, we would love to do that job
for you and very much more. So again,
please do check out our website
ilp.mmit.edu.
You can contact me directly through
LinkedIn or you can certainly contact
Fiona and Phil as well. Um all of us are
discoverable through the MIT website. So
let's treat this as a beginning. These
things are not going away and we're
going to discover a lot more as the
world continues to evolve in a complex
direction. But for now, thank you again
for coming and thank you Fiona and Phil
for participating and we wish you a good
day.