okay ready for last hour okay before I I
start was this too slow too fast too
slow too
fast okay I have an idea everybody close
your
eyes okay now you have to say too slow
too fast or good okay no you need to
close your eyes everybody close your
eyes okay too
slow too
fast good
good okay okay thank you hands
up oh what is it all good all good pass
okay uh okay great um okay so I want to
say first uh one thing I forgot to
mention about the sump of protocol that
we're actually use later it has a nice
property which is look at what so the
ver the PO sends polinomial low degree
polinomial what is the verier S the
verifier just SS random field elements
so really Randomness he chooses random
like log F bits and send them over okay
this is called a publicly a public coin
protocol public coin meaning the coins
of so each round the verifier chooses
coins and just sends them publicly to
the approver like here my log F coins
here they go this defines a field
element and that's my field element okay
uh this kind of Public public coin
Protocols are very useful because we can
later as we'll see in this class we can
use cryptography to eliminate this
interaction from this protocol so the
fact that it public coin will come back
to it okay but just notice the verifier
message is truly random okay uh one more
uh J yeah sorry just want is there are
there also protocols where theover
has good so you okay the qu so as I said
we mentioned the verifier has to be
randomized if it's not randomized the
interactive protocol has no power the
question here was does the prover need
to be randomized is it helpful if he's
randomized and the answer is is he I
mean it doesn't help him to be
randomized because you can always fix
his coins the verifier doesn't it's the
uh okay when does the when is it helpful
for the Prov to have Randomness when you
want to hide when we do zero knowledge
where the goal is kind of to hide thing
then the verifier has random coins that
the verifier doesn't know and that any
but in this case the verifier is not
we're not trying to protect the verifier
so why is Randomness is helpful from why
why is it important that the verifier
uses Randomness because the proof or
need send the poomi he should not know
which element T the pro the verifier
will say if he knew and which point T
will be asked then he can cheat he'll
give you a false pomal that happened to
coincide with a true poal and that point
T there D such points so he can choose
it he can choose the fake polinomial to
kind of coincide
the power comes from the fact that the
prover doesn't know this te so we don't
trust the prover and we use Randomness
kind of
against the verifier is trusted we're
not trying so it doesn't help the Prov
to use Randomness in a sense or in other
words you can just fix if you can fix
his Randomness once and for all for all
time think of him as kind of a
non-uniform prover and and that's it the
the verifier is not going to change his
behavior depending on because he's
honest it's the ver is always honest
it's the prover malicious prover that
we're worried about and therefore the
prover doesn't help him to he doesn't
need Randomness because you can always
hardwire the best Randomness possible to
him and now he's just a nonuniform kind
of machine as a circuit as opposed to
kind of a randomized machine so in this
context Randomness to the Prov is not
not needed the randomness of the
verifier par amount So when you say
public coin does that mean the can't see
those FS no public coin means that the
verifire doesn't hide anything he so
okay of course okay of course the prover
uh good question thank you the prover he
doesn't he never sees the coins in
advance so if he saw the coins before he
said anything he can cheat but the
verifier never hides coins to himself so
public coin means when the verifier said
the verifier just sends random coins so
I got I'm the verif
you you guys gave me a univer polinomial
a degree polinomial I choose coins a
field element that's kind of random
coins I send it over I don't keep any
state I don't it's all my messages are
just random you give me another poom
I'll just send Randomness that's the
definition of a public coin protocol
okay so public coin protocol just
means so no some check is a public coin
protocol which me means that
verifiers
messages are truly random just random
bits or if it's a
uniform I just had Randomness truly
uniform that's that's what public point
is yes um I guess like is it known what
happens if the pro does know all the
randomness in yeah yeah if the prover
knows all the randomness in advance he
can cheat why let me tell you how how
I'm going to cheat so I'm a cheating
prover let's say before you started
before we started you gave me all your
T1 up the TM actually even if you just
gave me T1 I'm golden why I I faked I
said the sum is B it's not beta it's
beta it's something
else now what all I want is to find a
pol a univariate
polinomial that sums to Beta so it's not
the true polom it sums to Beta but it
agrees with a true polinomial only on
T1 because once once it agrees with T1
from now on I need to prove a true
statement because I need to prove this
which is actually a true statement so
I'm good so if I knew T1 I can always
kind of come up with such a polinomial
the thing is I don't know what T1 is so
actually I want to give Jim actually
asked me a very good question in the
break and uh like he he I want to give
kind of Jin's geometric interpretation
of the soundness proof okay so let me
give you kind of a geometric
interpretation of why this protocol is
sound what's happening in this protocol
so here's the geometrical interpretation
we have a little box H to the m you can
think of it this is kind of the little
box H to the m I want to prove to you
that this low polinomial if you sum over
the value in this point this point all
these hm points it's beta now let's look
at the big F I have like this big
F
right okay now what happens if you were
incorrect if you cheated me then the sum
you you sum over all the points let's
fix this point here H like the one one
possible H1
maybe what you gave me is false what you
gave me is the sum is either false on H1
or an H2 somewhere it must be false
because it was true on everything will
be true so you give me something that's
false on one of them I don't know which
one now so what I know but but now I'm
going to use air cration to say well if
it was false on one of them it's false
on a random Point
T1 so now I forget about this sum I just
look at T1 and I know that the sum only
over the rest of the like the dimension
two it's false on
T1 and now again false and T1 that means
H2 one of them must be false I go to
kind of a random point in the extension
and there with Hy probility it's false
and kind of this is how I bop around
from kind of Dimensions T1 T2 Third
Dimension T3 T4 and so on up to the
point that I get a random point in kind
of after to there okay so that's kind of
a geometric interpretation of what's
going on
okay okay any any
questions for we okay so we saw this
subject so let's see where we are we
introduced this interactive interactive
proof model we saw subject protocol
seems kind of very specific let's try to
see why why it's very interesting the
subject protocol so first before
a as first thing let me give you an
example where where the Su check is is
useful and here's the
example let me show you that sharp set
has an interactive p i is the set of all
languages that have interactive proofs
so let me prove to you that sharp sa has
an interactive proof that's an example
this will use the Su check protocol by
the way let me just mention all the
examples that I'm giving you are not
just examples okay I'm teaching
something through it so don't just
example I'll I'll kind of forget about
it okay um they're specially crafted
okay so what is sharp set sharp set
we're giving a formula uh
fee and we're asking what is the number
of satisfying assignments to this
formula that's the question that's the
uh
a so so so Fe is you you think of it as
a Boolean formula we given a Boolean
formula let's say Fe is over like it
takes H sorry over let's say n
variables and buing formula I just think
of like it's and and
or and we have
not okay and the question is what when
how many assignments over 01 to the n
make this formula accept that's the
question okay so by the way um when we
say formula we mean it's a binary think
of it as a binary
tree so a formula is just a binary tree
each gate you can think of it as an and
or an or and then the final final leaves
are kind of all kind of XI or not XI
okay so Fe is of the following form it's
let's say and and then you can have or
or and so on so forth and the end it has
like X3 not X7 and so on so forth okay
so you can think of the size of this
formula is the number of leaves because
after to factor of two it's like the
number of gates the number of leaves
it's kind of the same uh okay so and
note just note many Le X3 may appear
many many many times because I really
opened it up to a tree okay so each
variable here can appear many many times
so this is what a formula is and sharp
side so now I want to say that let's say
Fe and K is in sharp
set it's in the language if and only if
Fe has so the number if you look at all
the x's in
01 to the end that of X is
one this set equals K okay if there's
exactly K satisfying
assignments okay questions about this
language threat we're good okay I just
want to point out a formula is different
than a circuit in the sense that the
formula is a tree it's a binary tree a
circuit is kind of an arbitrary uh ayli
directed acylic graph okay in particular
in um in a in
circuit kind in the formula you need to
kind of recompute everything so if this
gate uses a value and this gate also
uses the same value you need to
recompute it you need to compute it kind
of twice in a circuit can do things much
more efficiently okay so there's also
circuit set that's a sharp circuit set
that's a different problem here we
talking about sharp set for formulas
okay for
trees okay so uh I'm going to give you
actually so so this is a
uh known to be a very hard problem you
know I'm giving you like think of three
set you know going be complete now look
at the number like 10p but number like
how you know how many satisfying
assignments it has it's considered a
very hard problem um but uh you know if
you think about it's really surprising
that you can give an interactive proof
for it which is really nice and moreover
the interactive proof is really just the
subject that's all that's all it is so
I'm I'm going to show you how I embed
this kind of question into a
su okay and not that this is just a
Boolean formula where's the polinomial
where's uh you know I'm going to make a
some check but to have some Che I need a
polinomial and this is just a Boolean
formula so the way the idea is to use
I'm going to use Sun check for this IP
and the way I'm going to use Sun check
is by a technique called arithmetization
which we'll use okay so I'm going to so
the idea of using subject or the idea
behind this
IP is to
arithmetization
Fe okay so I want to prove to you that
Fe Kam is in sharp set I want to I want
to use a su Che protocol that's the only
protocol I know and I want to use it but
I need a polinomial so how I need to
polinomial and the sum over this
polinomial what is this polinomial it's
going to be an arithmetization
of the S formula so how do I ariti the
idea is very very simple I'm going to
convert any so this is a bull this is
booing all over 01 yeah I have and and
or everything is over 01 I'm going to
convert an end
gate
into Mal
gate okay so actually fix any finite
field you can make it very very B so
you'll have good soundness so okay with
respect
to field finite field F so fits any
finite
field okay can be very
large I'm going to convert any Mal any
and gate into a multiplication gate so
malt is
just take X and Y and just output x * y
in the
field okay but in particular what it
means if it there's anything time Z is
zero and 1 * 1 is one it's exactly an an
and gate okay if I have an
orgate
into so this is a bit more problem so
this is going to be so actually let me
say maybe I'll write it so I'm G to
write
and of XY I'm just going to write as x *
y
and I'm going to write
or of X and
Y any idea yeah X Y X Y exactly exactly
X Plus y That's idea but of course then
it's two I mean so I subtract x * y
exactly okay so of course zero goes to
zero if only one of them is one you get
one and zero nothing and if both of them
are one then this one is one so it takes
care of good and then that the
not not I go into not of X is simply
what exactly one - x so now I have
actually an arithmetic circuit okay so
this arithmetization allowed me to go
from a circuit into an arithmetic
circuit or from a formula sorry into an
arithmetic circuit and now note let's
look at the
first note that each a
gate is now an arithmetic Circuit of ss
at most three right it's a tiny circuit
like this is so each gate really I is
only con blw up by only a
constant and now really what I want to
do the subject over my protocol what I
want is to look at so let's denote the
arithmetization
by so if we denote
Ari
metiz
formula by
flda okay so F that goes from F to the N
to F it's just addition multiplication
can Define over the big F yes I'm wor
that since or now like has X twice and Y
twice since you said it has to be a tree
like you have to like copy and paste why
in order to like plug it into that okay
actually I don't care we'll see you're
saying what you're saying wait why is a
middle why is I start all I cares that I
started with an arith with a formula I
don't care in the middle what I do with
it so right now it's not a formula
anymore yeah oh
sorry good thank
you good thank you very much
thank
you great well you guys are good thank
you okay so let's denote the
arithmetization
in
01 is equal to
K why that make sense the only thing we
need to be careful with is what is the
degree of this
thing so now let's just argue that the
degree is not too
big okay but if if I convince that the
degree is small then we're done we just
do a su check and this is exactly what
you want to prove
okay so let's just make sure that the
degree so n here like the number of R is
going to be n there's going to be a
degree D we just need to ensure that D *
n is much much much smaller than
F which governs I I put here the which
govern the
soundness okay so let's just see the
degree so here's a
claim the
degree of
flda is a most or let me write it
differently the sum let's look at the
degree for each variable okay the sum of
the
degree I for variable I of
Fe so we have n variables X1 of to xn
each one has some
degree the sum of these degrees I'm
going to argue is a most
s s being the number of
uh S
size of Fe which is defined to be this
is by definition the number of
leaves in
Fe okay so let me argue that the size is
um
is the most uh Fe is the the degrees the
most the Su of degrees the most s or the
size
okay by the way before actually I do
that just to make sure because I
actually noticed that I lost over too
quickly I said that you know this is all
we need to prove but I just want to make
sure is it clear that
flda and 01 to the
N is actually equals to
fee yeah that's very important because
we want to make sure that we're actually
summing over the actual fee like in 01
because we want to
prove uh sharp set of the fee formula
right and the reason is as we said is
that on
01 we really behave like the and and or
so of course outside of 01 who knows
we're over a Big Field who knows what's
going on but on Z1 we behave exactly
like the end and or like the original TR
therefore this this Ari arithmetic
formula is actually equal to the
original formula and 0 one to the
end yeah okay so good so this is what we
want to prove now let's just look at the
degree
yeah good good good this just means this
is the
degree of x i in Fe so I'm just going to
so so yeah or in other words I'm I can
argue that each variable has the real
most s but I can argue something strong
the sum of the degrees of all the
variables that most s okay know that s
is polinomial here okay we have this
that's the input the input is the h a
sad formula it's polinomial so as long
as this is the degree you know we're
happy the communication complexity the
verify complexity is going to be n the
number of variables D which is like s
polinomial uh and pol in the field so
it's po so the verifier is going to be
polinomial okay now we care about you
know now there's a notion of binomial
time verifier okay but if the degrees
are most s s is bomal we're
good okay so why why is this the degree
so to prove that this is the degree the
proof of this
claim is by
induction it's actually a pretty
straightforward proof and it really uses
the fact that fee is a Formula that the
original fee is a the formula
um so let's
see
so so the prove is just by
induction and here's how Okay so uh
we're going to prove by induction on the
on the depth of this uh formula and
and so okay if we have just one
gate then okay it's clear the degree is
just one uh so that's
fine
so if number of Gates or the depth if
you want is
one then of course the it's the degree
is going to be less than the size is
degree is just one that's if you just
have a single
gate uh and now if you have more General
so now suppose you have a circuit of the
form let's say add or malt it doesn't
matter or and you can have like F1
suppos Fe is F1 and or or I don't care
F2 okay this can gener the end but of
course it could be also an
or then how do we arithmetization
[Music]
F1 tlda times F2
tlda or in the case of this is for end
if for or if it was
or then it would be F1 TAA plus
f2a
minus1
time2 right all of course over X1 of X
over X1 of
X yeah okay so let's at I want argue
that the arithmetic version is of the
sum of the degrees of all the variables
that most s so let's see let's look at
flda if F Tilda was if the original Fe
was end of F1 and
F2 then flda is just the multiplication
by definition we replac and with
multiplication of the F1 tlda polinomial
times F2 2 ta polinomial
but what do we know here here the degree
of each the so now let's suppose okay
suppose F1 let's say it's of
size
S1 and suppose F2 is of size
S2 okay just now what we we know that
the sze of Cs is equal to S1 + S2
because it's a tree so there's no kind
of uh everything is open so the left
side of the tree is S1 size of S1 the
right side of the tree is size S2 the
entire tree is the size s which is S1
plus
S2 so now what is the a so what can we
say in this case so let's let's focus on
the on the and the or is exactly the
same so what can we say about about the
sum of the degrees so sum of
degree the the degree of the I ele of of
x i in
Fe is equal sumon I what is the degree
of the the I variable in Fe it's the
degree here plus the degree here when
you multiply things I need to some the
degrees so it's the
degree of x i in T1 tlda plus the
degree of variable I in C2
right when have two polom multiply the
degree adds but this is
just S1 + S2 by
induction by the induction
hypothesis okay so the the degree here
the sum of the degrees is like the size
of the formulas we actually don't really
care about the sum we care about the
degree itself but this kind of shows you
at least the degree of H one is also
most the size of the formula and
therefore the Su so now when we run so
let me put this back up so we run the
sum
check on this polinomial and we
get
the the communication complexity and the
verify run time will be n or the number
the number of variables here n times the
degree which is s essentially the size
of the input right that's s and polog
the field okay so you just need to take
and similarly uh and the verify yeah the
degree which is s the completeness is
always one and the soundness importantly
the soundness of this protocol
is n the number of variables the degree
which is s divided by the size of f so
all we need to make sure is to
arithmetick ER those you
want okay any yeah
questions
yeah you can go okay so when you do the
sum check like when the sum is happening
is that like necessarily a sum over the
field or can it be like any sum over
like a different field like if you're
like original field is just like I don't
know some field so okay just note in
this specific problem I don't have a
origal fi actually that for this
specific sharp set I'm over 01 there's
no field it's not an algebraic it's a
Boolean thing it I don't have any any
polinomial any algebra any field nothing
I just have zero one and I have and and
or Gates and to prove that to prove that
you know the number of satisfying
assignment in the Boolean cube is K I
choose a field of my liking and I
arithmetization
omals as as having additional
multiplication Gates and I think in my
head I think of this circuit as this
formula as a polinomial so I choose the
field it's not part it's not actually
the problem I I I am purpose kind of
chose a field so that I can do the Su
check
protocol right yeah um but I guess like
what I'm asking is like when you like
for the sum in the sum check like like
let's say you like not for this problem
oh I see I see you're saying you're
saying look let's say you have a some
check problem someone give you some
check problem and you're not happy with
the field the field is not good enough
for you or it doesn't give you enough
soundness can you can you amplify can
you work over a different field is that
what you're asking or I guess what I'm
asking is like if you have some check
and like there is some field like let's
say you're working mod like some large
prime or something good but then like
the S like will the sum that you're
doing be like also over that field
necessarily like can you okay so so when
I do a S check over the field everything
will be over that field yes everything
will be over the field however that said
if I'm not happy the P if you're saying
so I got a s Che protocol with certain p
over you know over gf2 a gfp with is so
everything is mod P with certain P now
yes everything should be over this field
now you can say well this p is not that
great because it's not that much bigger
than n * D and I'm not really happy with
this field or maybe even it's smaller
than n times B for all I know it's not a
good field not big enough then what do I
do so I'm saying it's okay don't worry
just take an extension field instead of
working over P you can you work over
kind of gfp to the N so you can take a
field of science P to the N for any end
that you want like and you're only going
to pay kind of polom or linearly with
this n so uh and then you can amplify
your sounds okay I was just wondering
because I was wondering what like what
happens if the K is like larger than the
size of field oh I'm going to choose the
field could be much Bigg okay okay I see
yeah I'm going to choose the field
otherwise you can't yeah I I'll need to
choose the field to be much bigger than
okay yeah so like oh sorry I I forgot
you okay yeah um this is kind of Rel
point but we need to choose a field that
have like really big characteristics and
we need to like choose a really big
prime number we can't just do like we
can't just it to the end oh because K
can be like two to the end
[Music]
that's bigger
than yeah no but the question is can you
no but the question a
well okay if okay in our case you can
just choose the field to be as big as
you want in in the case where you're
giving a su check of course K of course
the sum is in the field it's it's
something about the field you're giving
you're giving something about the field
so K will always would be in the field
but for the sharp for this specific one
I'm thinking of yeah you choose a k
that's bigger however I'm not 100% sure
that let me
think can you use small
characteristic can you Chinese yeah
that's what I'm think I'm not sure if
you can't use some Chinese remainder
trick and use over a small
characteristic I need to think about it
but anyway in this case just choose a
after the gfp for a large p and that's
bigger than K yeah sorry did you have a
question oh ask is this the only know
how to
this is easy what do you mean you want
easier I so no I think I think this is
the simplest way so let me say let me
just say so you know we put H sharp set
into IP in this way you can ask what
about let's say sharp circuits at which
is the same thing but we're giving a
circuit so we're given a circuit and you
want to know how many satisfying
assignment does it have over zero1 to 10
it's the same thing except for fee is
now uh it's not a tree anymore it's a
directed as graph so uh and it turns out
that it also has an IP because it's in P
space you can go over all possible X's
X1 up to xn and check if it's satisfying
or not in it's small space so it's in P
space and so you can ask okay so what
about this now you can't do some check
because the degree won't be small so
actually you can do it but that's much
much more complicated and requires this
kind of degree reduction thing that's
kind of how sham proves IP equals speed
space it's the some degree reduction
there that really complicates matters so
you need that for a circuit set but for
set because it's so low degree
immediately kind of it's kind of nice
and that's all you do uh yeah you should
be where's the
Gratitude I guess re interpretation of
problem question suppose is you know
suppose you're given another problem say
permanent or something right so I want
to I guess not formally defined but I
want to direct kind of without reducing
to kind of uh you know like so for I
mean I want a direct uh protocol it's
not very well defined yeah so I have to
say almost all the protocols I know for
IP go through
some they were trying to prove
okay so I'm not familiar with that but I
think the main ones go through uh uh
some
Che what I remember is like it's sort of
like sun but they're also like looking
at
any any other questions about sharp set
yeah the someck protoc is like I believe
it's operating over a field like all the
summation
goes so does that mean that we to be
safe to make sure Ure correctness we
must sure that the field has
characteristic greater than the number
of satisfying Solutions yeah two to the
uh two the two to the end yes yes but
the verifier runs in time log in this
circuit so in the in the log in the s in
the size of the field yeah log in the
size of the field so the field can be to
the then yeah requirement you can't fig
small character yeah so I yeah okay I
would so the what we should do is take
take gfp large large field like large
characteristic I'm not sure you can take
small characteristic actually I need to
think about it because maybe some
Chinese remainder theorem can help you
oh but that
[Music]
what said we run this protocol over very
small primes make sure that the answers
are all the
number exactly exactly
you don't want to sometimes actually I'm
not so sure right because the
computational complexity is going to be
S of is probably going to be smaller
instead of log a big field size to the
power three or something right you have
sum of log small size fields to the
power okay so by the way just note about
the the pro runtime here of course it's
large because he needs to find the SAT I
mean what can you do he needs to at
least count the number of satisfying
assignments it takes two to them at
least right to find them and then okay
so so far we gave some examples so where
are we right we talked about IP we
showed the magical amazing Su Che
protocol and we showed how to use the Su
protocol to give an IP for interactive
proof for Sharp set in some sense maybe
you're not so blown away at this point
because actually Sharps aent like a
formula is really you can
arithmetization is not like wow we know
all know that and is like multiplication
and and and the and and or can be
written as like small arithmetic thing
so it's actually an arithmetic circuit
so it's it's it's it's actually gives
yourself a lgre pom so some since it
calls for a subject it is a subject like
without much change it's like already it
presents itself almost as a
sub so maybe you're not convinced of the
generality of of the Su and the next
thing I want to do is kind of show you
actually uh completely different thing
that doesn't seem to be at all low
degree or anything and try to to uh show
you how you can use the S Check and
actually this takes us a kind of a nice
uh way into the idea of uh of doubly
efficient proofs so so far when we
talked about interactive proofs our
Focus was the verifier is efficient he's
poal time the approver can be whatever
and indeed in the protocols both some
check and sharp s of course the pro runs
in exponential time he has no choice he
needs to do the
computation
okay the idea that so now let's kind of
shift gears and talk about the notion of
a double efficient
interactive so the notion of a double
efficient interactive proof the idea is
actually you know what you don't so the
main idea is we care about the run time
of the proof so the pro is not all
powerful it kind of brings us kind of to
real life okay it's very nice that the
verifier is for nor the Prov is all
powerful but guess what all powerful
doesn't exist everything is limited to
some extent there's more powerful and
less powerful but there's not all
powerful so what we want is yes the
prover is more powerful than the
verifier otherwise we don't need it the
verifier doesn't need him but even the
pro is not all powerful so in a doubly
efficient interactive Pro we want to say
the prover has a problem at hand and he
should not spend too much overhead in
convincing the verifier that the
solution is that he that his solution
that you know let's say that X is in the
language okay and and this is kind of
interesting even if the problem so when
we talk about doubly efficient
interractive proofs we even care of
problems in P so often when we talk
about contracted proof we think even
let's say the problem is polinomial
time so I have Al I I want to argue
prove some pomal time uh you know the a
link anguage but I want the verify let's
say the time to to determine this
language is I don't know n to the 4th I
want the verifier to be linear
time okay so the idea is I I there
should always be a gap between how
powerful the PO is and the verifier is
weaker but I really care about both I
care the verifier should be very very
efficient and the PO should not should
also be somewhat efficient okay that's
the idea so okay so what is a doubly
efficient in trative proof
so a dou let's say for for example l in
some D time T so can be computed in the
teristic time
T again you can think of T even to be n
the fourth okay can be polinomial
is is an IP
where the Pro run time the honest Pro
the honest provers
runtime is
only polinomial overhead in the time of
determining the language okay so it
takes time T to determine here is the
time of most
Po and the verifier on
time should be much much less see
ideally we want the verif to run in time
like
like almost linear or quasi linear we so
n poly log n let's say which is denoted
by
O Okay so ideally want the verify TR in
linear time or quasi linear
time and the P should not have too much
overhead actually IDE po should also
have just linear
overhead okay but definitely by
definition it should not have more than
pomal
overhead and and sorry yes yes thank you
and this is T n is the instance size yes
so of course the verify needs to read
the instance but not do much more than
that okay so it's just interactive proof
we care about both the pro and the
verifier okay and uh yeah and and so let
me mention that these like things that
people actually care about because they
use it in these blockchain protocols and
so on and so they really actually a lot
of work that's done on this and I think
in the lecture notes of Justin Taylor
I'm not going to refer to these sections
we won't cover them but they the exist
sections where he really talks about the
exact kind of parameters the exact
numbers the exact implementations and so
on so forth because this these are
things that actually people care about
because they want to run it so actually
we really care about you know the
overheads here in in practice case okay
so now so so far we said the Su check is
really it's this of course it's like it
seems like outside the realm even of
double double double efficiency but
actually now let me show you a specific
example which again we is beyond just an
example because we'll teach use it to
teach something uh where it's actually
in p and I I'll show you an interactive
proof for for this problem okay uh using
the suck protocol a dou efficient
interractive proof of this problem
yeah like t d good yeah yeah yeah so
take any problem any language for which
membership in this language can be
decided in time to okay so D I'm there's
a deterministic algorithm that runs in
time T what T is it can be anything you
can think of t n to the 4th n to the
10th I don't know uh ENT to the log n uh
quazi po whatever all I care so of
course the PO needs to needs to compute
if he's proving something he needs to
know that it's true so he needs to do
this determin of computation so of
course he needs to run in time te but
should not run in much more than T and
by not more theorists say poly T applied
people say linear in t the real appli
you know say not more than 128 whatever
but um yeah depending how far you are in
that Spectrum um okay so a good so now
let me show you how a doubly efficient
interractive proof for counting the
number of triangles in a graph okay
that's the
example next week I'm going to show you
actually interactive proof for all for
dou interactive proof for all low depth
circuits so I'm going to generalize it
by a lot but let's start with like an
example okay
so let's say we're given a graph G and
we want to count the number of triangles
in the graph okay so given
G so we want to interactive proof for
counting number of
triangles in a graph
G with vertices V and edges e okay so
okay I want to cast it as a doubly
efficient sum Che protocol kind of sub
protocol but so notice this this is a
problem in P I can go over all possible
three vertices triple to
vertices and check if there's a triangle
so I can I can check this problem time
ENT to the
third I want that my verifier to be
linear so I want to Pro the runs in time
not much more than ENT the third uh or
let's say polinomial time to convince a
linear verifier that this graph has a mo
has let's exactly K
triangles and I want to cast it somehow
in the subject protocol so how do I do
that so I first I need to come up with a
polinomial right I that's kind of I need
to embed a polom here no there's nothing
polinomial like here talking about
graphs okay so remember how origin I
told you everything is a polinomial
everything can become a polinomial this
is an example that kind of shows you why
you take anything and make it a
polinomial so what is the idea let's
look at the
adjacency uh Matrix corresponding to
this graph okay that checks if there's
an edge between pair of
vertices now we can write this Matrix as
a function
f that goes from let's say V like number
of vertices times number of vertices to
01 takes a pair of vertices I'll put
zero if there's no Edge one if there's
an edge let's denote the number of
vertices here by n so sorry I denoted
there the input length by n close enough
it's not really the input length the
number of vertices but it's denoted by n
okay so now we can think of the
adjacency Matrix as a function so think
of the adjacency
Matrix let me write it as a function
f that goes from 01 to the log n I'm
going to assume that N is a power of two
goes from so it takes a I'm going to
think of a Vertex so v as I said is of
size n write it here so won't be in my
way I'm going to think of the function
as taking a pair of vertices where
I I represent a Vertex as a vector in 01
to the log n okay any number of n like
binary representation of the I think of
the vertices it's numbers between one
and N I'm thinking of the binary
representation and I output 0 one
whether there's an edge or whether
there's no Edge between this vertices
these two
vertices okay so this says one if and
only if there exists an edge
between the two
vertices okay now suppose you want to
argue that the number of triangles is
let's say
k so what do you need to prove you need
to prove that the sum over all i j and k
in N or let me even make myself in 0 one
to the log in to make it easy for myself
because I'm representing in binary so
for any three
vertices let's count the number of
triangle so when when is there's a
triangle
if I and J are connected this is one and
fjk is connected this is one and f i is
connected this is
one they all need to be connected in
order for it to be a triangle
okay so now not if if they're now I get
so if it's a triangle I get one if it's
not a triangle I get zero because one of
them is going to be a zero so I want to
count the number of
triangles and I want to prove check that
this is
K almost almost I lied a little
bit I kind of overcounted because
there's permutation igk jki so I need to
divide by one over six is the number of
way to permute any JK any I JK is
counted like all
permutations so this is what I want to
prove okay I want to prove that the
sum of all possible triangles i j k i
kind I counted each I JK here
essentially six times so I need to
divide by one over
six the number of the sum the number of
triangles is
K okay almost at least I have sum it's
getting to look like a su check but
there's no algeb there's no Algebra I
just wrote in numbers I mean I took
binary representation but at least you
know I have uh I I have some sum so if
if I had some Al nice algebra here if
this was all over a finite field and
let's say this F was also low degree
then I can use some check okay so again
suppose this was over a finite field and
suppose this F was very low degreee and
the field was large we have good
soundness
I want to prove sum of this big
F is K
Sun so I just need to kind of tell you
how how do I get uh how do I add
algebra where do you know to make this
degree low degree and and uh where did
the finite field come from and so on
I'll do that but before I'll do that
also note there some here
is only over 01 to the 3 log n right so
it's actually remember the problem was
the Pro run time is very large it's h to
the m times the time it takes to to
compute one function and times this m
this m is going to be is small but the H
to m is the problem but here H to the m
is just two to the 3 log n 2 the l n so
it's prob so if I'm able to put like a
some check like a algebra here the I I
will get double the pro will still be
pomal time which is what I
want okay I just the question is how do
I put algebra
here okay so this is
where so I'll say a little bit about
this this and then we'll break for today
and continue next
week but the way there's a generic way
to convert any function into a into a
polinomial okay and the the way to do it
is via technique called Low degree
extension so
if you actually remember the way we
start I started class with an example of
the matrix
multiplication and if you remember in
the matrix multiplication there also
there's no polinomial it's a matrix you
know nothing but what we did the
randomized algorithm that we showed we
thought of a row in The Matrix as a
polinomial so we took a row which
consists of n elements and we thought
about it as a univariate polinomial of
degree
n remember we thought of like the row as
like coefficients of the polinomial so
we thought it was a polinomial of degree
of degree n minus one I guess n elements
one is the free coefficient so degree n
minus one so we started already the
class with an example that I have a row
nothing no algebra nothing arbory row of
Matrix and we converted it to a univ
poomi of degree n like the length of the
M of the
row what we do here is a very similar
idea but in the multivariant setting
okay so what we can do we can take we
could have taken any n element that Row
for example or in this case like the
elements are all the kind
of for any F any F you can think of it
it's like a matrix right it's like N
squared elements if you want for any two
elements whether there's a a edge or not
an edge so you can think of N squared
elements doesn't matter we can take any
set of
elements and convert it either to a UNIF
polinomial as we did before of that
degree or that's not good for us because
here's the degree is going to be N
squared it's already like the verifier
runs in the degree and more it's not
going to be efficient enough but the
idea is we can convert it to a multivari
polinomial with much much smaller
degree okay and that's what's called the
multi the low degree extension so
whereas before we just did a univariant
polinomial so we had to kind of put the
co the the N elements kind of as
coefficients each one kind of added a
degree if you will if we put it in a
multivariate
polinomial so if we think of it like as
a polinomial over let's say h to the m
then we can stack inside H to the m we
can stack attack n points we can make H
and N much each H and both H and N to be
much much smaller than and that kind of
what we're going to do so let me let me
explain this uh uh more more
precisely
um
okay okay so here here's the theorem
we're going to use for for this
so take
any for any function non polinomial can
be arbitrary like the adjacency Matrix
function for any function f there it's
like from 01 to the 2 log n but let me
take it more generally from H to the m
to
01 again in this example H is just 01
and M is like two long n because we have
there two log n but let me give you
something more generally so take any
function okay this is essentially any
set you can think of this this is
any
set of this or this is kind of
equivalent to any
element and 01 to the H to the
m right so it's just a string of Len of
binary string of length H to n so take
any binary string of length H to to the
m okay just tells you for each element
into the M what the value is z or
one so for any function and any finite
field F that contains
h of course in that example 01 F
contains any
and any F contains zero and one so
that's not a
problem there
exists a
unique what's called Low degree
extension I'll explain what this means
in a second it's a function f
Tilda from F to the N to f
such that so in what sense is it low
degree extension first it's an
extension namely F Tilla if you look at
an an H to the N for the element in the
little Cube it's exactly
F so it extends it extends f f was an H
to the m f till up is an a bigger uh
Cube it extends on the small cube they
agree the second second thing is that
it's low degree so it's a low degree
extension extension and a low degree
what how low so uh
flda is of
degree hus one in each
variable okay so again
what is the theorem the theorem is you
can take any set if you want you can
take any set so let's say of n numbers
take any fix so take any set let's say
fix any
uh any
Vector let's say w and let's say 01 to
the
N you can always embed it you can think
of w
an equivalent way to think of w oh sorry
I didn't mean I meant to say sorry as a
let's say W1 up to w
n in 01 to the
N you can embed it you can think of it
as a as a
function from H to the N to 01 as long
as H to the m is n so you can you have a
long sequence of zero ones fold it into
a nice kind of uh you know
a cube of size H to them so essentially
should think of the H
representation of of n okay the H
representation so you just kind of H to
the m is equivalent to the set you can
think of a projection between that and
the all the numbers between 0 one
between one up to
n and now the claim is actually you can
take this St so this is let's say h by m
you can kind of extend it to a bigger
function
Tilda over F this is over F to the
m such that it has degree H minus one in
each
variable so just note if we think of of
M as being one the univariant
case is exactly what we had before if
you had just a string of like size of
size uh if n is one H essentially is
like n okay I take n i just just expand
it in this way to a degree
n but then the degree is very large
that's not good like the verifier runs
in time the degree that's all
so I make the degree much smaller how do
I make the degree much smaller I add
more
variables so the idea
is ADD many more variables now in each
Dimension the degree is only
H because now I don't need the size of H
is n but H to the N is
n and now in each Dimension the the
number of elements is like H so and the
Anita mention the degree will be H minus
one instead of n minus one like it was
in the univariant
case I'll prove all this but this is
just kind of a high level idea okay so
again the high level idea we'll go into
the proof next time of the theorem but
the high level idea is we all know by
the kind of the the univarate case that
you can take any string of length n and
coded as a univer function of degree n
minus one by there's two ways of doing
it either by thinking of the string as
the coefficients that's one element one
way to do it and another way to do it
which is how the load extension works is
by thinking of the string as the value
of the polom in let's say polinomial
value on one two three up to n let's say
one up to n is in the field so think of
gfp here what we do we take your
points we take a polinomial f for which
your points are sitting in this small
cube so let's say you have a vector of
size one up to n we'll put here W1 W2 W3
wh all the W's will put
here and then the theorem says there's a
way to extend this entire thing into a
bigger polom of degree H minus one in
each in each uh variable
such that that the if you look at the
polom on this Cube it's exactly what we
had before so you have your kind of uh
vector or your you know your function
from H to then to 01 here and the and
the rest it's just extended and then
extended in a way that the degree of
each variable is H minus one okay so for
example if if you want H to the m to be
n would you can take for example is H to
be log
n the degree is only log which is great
and you can take n to be even smaller
than log if you do the math it's going
to be log
n over log
log and note that the verifier runs in
time that depends on M M H and D and D
is going to be also H so all of it's
going to be
polyon which is
great okay so next time what we're going
to do is is prove the slow degree
extension theorem and then show how to
use it uh first for the triangle that
would be pretty immediate and then we'll
show how to use it uh for kind of a
general low degree low low depth circuit
okay thanks