uh I am Miki Kato program director ofp
and I will moderate this first you know
afternoon session talk so first I would
like to introduce Dr Ben Armstrong he is
the executive director and research
scientist at industrial performance
center and also he is a co-lead of the
works of the future initiatives he talk
about productivity Improvement in
manufacturing and adaptability of the
new technology and Workforce practice so
Dr Ben
Armstrong hello everyone I'd like to
start by sharing the story of four
factories the first pictured here is in
Denver Colorado not far from a major
American city where wages are high but
at this Factory they make products very
inexpensively they make a variety of
composite products from bicycle wheels
to backpack frames and they make these
products so reliably and so
inexpensively that they actually
outcompete Taiwan and China the dominant
producers of these Goods they end up
exporting their goods to to China this
is only a small shop about 50 people and
nonetheless they're growing dramatically
both in productivity and in size here's
a a second Factory this Factory is in
Los Angeles another large high-wage uh
place and what this Factory is doing is
they're producing one of the first lines
of all electric boats these boats have
been called Teslas on the water and it's
no surprise really that they call them
Teslas in part because uh the founding
team has modeled their production
strategy on Tesla's Roadster which
emphasized not necessarily quality but
speed to Market so they developed their
first prototype electric boat in just a
matter of weeks and then their first
several product lines were on the market
and fully sold out in only a couple of
years um without much Capital actually
uh it wasn't a very Capital intensive
process either so another very uh
fast-moving and high growth uh process
this time with a a a slightly larger
team but to go from from zero to a
standing product that is sold out now
long into the future they've done it
very quickly and effectively um the next
Factory is closer to MIT it's in a rural
community in New Hampshire where it's
hard to find skilled labor skilled
technicians but nonetheless this Factory
produces machine cutting tools that they
export all over the world and the
factory itself is fully owned by its
employees so this employee is named Sam
Seer he makes a high wage and he also
earns a cut of the profit each quarter
that comes out from the company so when
the company considered to adopt new
robots to improve productivity or to um
experiment with new technologies on the
factory floor Sam was very supportive
and what he did in order to learn about
those processes is he went to the
internal University at the company in
this rural area where they trained him
how to operate these new tools and then
finally here is a a company in Ohio
which is in the traditional rust belt
for former manufacturing Powerhouse of
of the United States it's only a 20%
Factory that makes a a high mix of low
volume Goods for the Aerospace and
defense industry as well as the
automotive industry and this Factory
despite low growth all around it in the
region has tripled its productivity in
the last seven years and also tripled
its output they've become one of the
most competitive factories they have
almost um doubled the productivity of
their industry competitors now okay so
the question that I have really the
question that drives my research and the
research of our group at MIT is a what
makes these factories so exceptional so
competitive and high performing and B
how can more factories operate like this
in the United States how can they
compete in high wage environments with
other factories around the world that
face all sorts of other different
challenges so today I want to offer
first a set of hypotheses about what
makes these factories so special
and then I want to talk about some of
the early Clues and Investments
happening in the United States that are
trying to replicate the success of
factories like these okay so I want to
focus on three factors that make these
factories different from other factories
in the United States and I'll say in a
moment I think a lot of factories in
Japan as well the first is that each of
these factories has a different risk
profile than the typical high-wage
manufacturing environment so over time
as I'll I'll explain uh manufacturers in
the United States have become more and
more risk averse less willing to invest
in New Capital Equipment and less
willing to invest in process Improvement
that isn't a slam dunk that isn't very
easy to map out and in very low risk so
what each of these factories has done is
they've actually had big projects that
have failed before they found process
improvements that could succeed and
they've also raised risk Capital either
from private Equity Funds or in one case
Venture capitalists
that allowed them to grow at a very
rapid
Pace the second piece that has
differentiated these factories is their
use of Technology it's not just that
they have robotic automation or Advanced
five AIS machines it's that they've used
software to customize a lot of their
equipment and then finally they have
internal skills to use that technology
effectively in one case the case of the
the bicycle wheel manufacturer that I
mentioned first the the idea behind the
factory is that anyone can buy or build
an automated solution but not anyone can
use it at its full productive capacity
and that's where the skill comes in now
I want to link this to you know many
environments where I'm sure you work in
Japan so yesterday I was with colleagues
from the University of Tokyo and we went
to a factory about an hour and a half
west of here that produces had
traditionally produced Automotive
components uh piping as a supplier for
one of the large Japanese oems and
recently a shifted to produce components
for Semiconductor equipment and um and
medical devices and one of the really
interesting pieces of this company was
that similar to the companies that I
study in the United States this company
had a very active skill development uh
process internally their employees had
required training hours to have each
year the employees were also co-owners
of the company they had 50% of the
profit share um each quarter and finally
the employees were also skilled at
machine building so this company made an
active decision to build all of their
own internal equipment program at
themselves that was going to be a fourth
of the cost of relying on externally
built equipment and that was these
internal skills that I think made made
this company one of the most competitive
and they they had a wall full of awards
that differentiated them from from their
competitors in Japan so I think that
there are common threads here between
American manufacturers on the frontier
of productivity and Japanese
manufacturers as as well and what I've
learned from these American factories is
that what it looks like when you combine
these three elements is that you really
merge the teams that are doing product
development and re product development
and research with the teams that are
managing production and this is an idea
that really comes first from uh Tesla
and SpaceX as well as from Amazon which
is not in manufacturing but I would say
manufacturing adjacent and the Amazon
fulfillment center network was
established by it turns out an MIT
alumnus who uh has a background in
chemical engineering so the flow through
that fulfillment network is is operating
at a same the same idea that you're
going to be able to run experiments on
the factory floor similar to you would
run in an R&D lab and you're going to
take risks that then you can easily and
quickly translate into um real
production steps that are actively
producing something new now at Tesla as
many of you I'm sure are familiar with
this often can go can go wrong and
they've made a lot of choices that have
led to to Quality defects by collap ing
the R&D team into the production team
but nonetheless it represents a very
different model of how to approach uh
manufacturing excellence and it's
allowed them to scale very quickly and
to learn very quickly so now when I I
study um you can think of them as the
cousins of Tesla or the the
grandchildren of Tesla the people who
worked at Tesla or SpaceX and have now
spun out a company there's one actually
here exhibiting these companies exhibit
a similar sense of experimentation so
Arc boats which I mentioned has a very
uh Common Sense where their R&D team is
actually located on the factory floor
and they can see the projects they're
working on right next to their stations
all right why do I think this is all
important to understand and to exemplify
it's important in part because this is
so different from what the modal
manufacturer in the US and I would
venture to say the modal manufacturer in
in Japan looks like and here's here's
why I say that so here's you know if I
were to kind of capture the arc
Manufacturing in the United States in
one chart this is this would be it and
I'll I'll show you uh roughly what the
chart in Japan would look like uh in a
moment but if you think about it it's
I'm going to break it down into two eras
you know roughly before 1984 and after
and I'll take a moment to walk you
through this so here I'm plotting the
red Capital expenditures so investment
in technology over time the yellow you
know production employment workers on
the factory floor productivity and green
value added so output minus input in
blue and then finally production wages
adjusted for inflation in the pink now
what we see in the era of mass
production in the United States really
production conglomerates where you have
a lot of companies that are producing
not only a high volume of goods but also
a high variety of goods so you have many
companies that are producing uh cars and
trucks but also producing defense
equipment and producing consumer
products etc etc they have a wide
variety of skills under roof this might
sound familiar because I think there
were were uh commonalities both in
ownership structure but also in
diversification with uh modern ketsu and
what you see also is after you know 1947
there's an kind of a positive and a
growth equilibrium among these
categories workers are earning higher
wages productivity is going up quite
sharply along with the investment in new
technology and something in the early
1980s really changes actually few things
change in the early 1980s um Capital
expenditures after that point are mostly
flat adjusted for inflation there's no
real growth in technology investment um
employment goes down quite sharply
productivity goes up that's really just
associated with this decline in
employment because value added stays the
same it actually goes down a little bit
overall so what's What's Happening Here
I think a few things are happening one
there's a series of changes both
regulatory changes but also changes in
management strategy in the United States
that lead companies to become far more
risk averse and less willing to invest
in growth in part because there's new
competition early on in the 1980s there
was competition from uh Japanese
manufacturers with at that time lower
wages but really operational excellence
that was leading American manufacturers
to figure out how to respond and what
really happened at this point was that
financial markets changed how they
valued manufacturing companies
and American manufacturers changed the
Paradigm of how they thought about
production many of you know this trend
I'm sure better than I and it was a
really a shift from the idea of flexible
mass production to what was actually
termed coined MIT lean production which
was modeled on the Toyota production
system so what lean did in the United
States was it helped at least in the
short term companies become more
productive essentially to do the same
with fewer employees that was what
productivity looked like in the US
environment now why I've become
interested in this is this last part
here since 2010 American manufacturers
have actually become less productive
overall that a lot of these Investments
over time and in continuous process
Improvement um that had delivered
productivity are no longer doing it and
American manufacturing has more demand
than it's had in the last four decades
but nonetheless we can't improve our
productivity so this is really the
puzzle driving American manufacturing
right now American manufacturers have
become less productive over the last 14
years but our our political environment
and the global economic environment has
more demand than ever for local
manufacturing near uh production centers
there's a need to produce more like the
four companies I mentioned at the
beginning now you might be wondering
what if I were to plot these same
figures for Japanese manufacturing over
time what would they look like so lucky
enough my colleagues at University of
Tokyo shared those plots yesterday I'm
happy to forward them to you they're all
in Japanese so I can just understand the
the lines in the line chart but I'll
I'll plot them roughly here so these
figures before 1990 look very similar
where there's if you take about 1960 to
1990 there's uh employment growth
productivity growth and output growth
that's that's quite dramatic among
Japanese manufacturers and what happens
after 1990 this is with the onset of
competition from China that was how they
explained it was that the US faced
competition from Japan in the 80s Japan
faced competition from China in the 90s
and then the US faced competition from
China beginning the 2000s so it's a nice
you know ping pong effect um instead of
the flattening of these curves or the
decline of productivity what Japanese
manufacturing has experienced is a kind
of a bode curve where it looks more like
a root curve so where us has been 0%
growth in Japan it's been between 10 and
20% so there's a similar challenge of
slowed growth but it's just been it's
been less severe in Japan is this these
are the data from from my colleagues so
I would say there are some parallel uh
challenges here now one of the questions
that I think is is reasonable to ask is
how have why haven't American
manufacturers been able to extract the
same benefits from lean and the Toyota
production system as their Japanese
counterparts now you might be familiar
with this this is how you uh Toyota's
production system is communicated to
American firms this is often considered
kind of the House of the Toyota
production system with several main
components and after talking to a lot of
firms that would consider themselves
lean in the United States what I find
really interesting is that every
American firm I talk to has a different
definition of what lean is some Focus
just on reducing waste it's essentially
an optimization function of how do we
get zero waste some focus on inventory
and just on the just in time being a
pull versus a push manufacturer and then
others focus more exclusively on Joka on
continuous Improvement through respect
for people and on kind of the skill
development side so lean means a lot of
different things to different
organizations in the United States now I
don't really think that's the problem
here I think the problem is more readily
that in the United States there's none
of the kind of the foundation for the
house that is present in Japan so you
might be familiar with these works and
these were really important works for
American manufacturers and American
Scholars to understand what was
happening in Japanese manufacturing and
why uh Japanese manufacturing was
growing so quickly um in the 1960s and
70s but really this this whole house was
underpinned by industrial policy and
also a corporate governance system that
allowed Japanese manufacturers to manage
risk and and be able to continue
diversifying in ways that us
manufacturers couldn't so if we contrast
that with the trend in the United States
which said you know in
1980 60% of manufacturing conglomerates
had you know Diversified portfolios were
producing a diverse uh portfolio of
goods and by 1990 0% were Diversified
the shift in financial markets was
really to support pure playay
manufacturers that could do one thing
very well and that the market could
price very easily because a lot of these
uh a lot of these organizations were
publicly traded so this has LED over the
last 40 years for public markets in the
United States to be less and less
willing to invest in asset heavy
businesses and that's helped drive a
trend toward offshoring even if
offshoring wasn't the right long-term
decision for a lot of these
manufacturers because they were
sacrificing some of their core
capabilities okay so this is the the
risk component when we talk about how
the the four Factories at the beginning
were more risk tolerant it's in contrast
to this trend which has made a lot of of
American manufacturers more risk
averse the second piece is is technology
and you might imagine and even be you
know directly familiar with a risk
averse mentality leads uh a lot of
Manufacturers to avoid investments in
new technology unless they're absolutely
necessary so one of the the Striking
things to me is someone who who who
studies Automation and its effect on
work in manufacturing is that despite
all the uh robotics research happening
at MIT actual robot adoption has been
quite flat in most countries even
countries that have a a strong
background in robotics so for the last
10 years uh this pink line is the United
States I should do probably red white
and blue um but it nonetheless it's pink
so last 10 years our robot installations
have been flat there's no real growth
and scale up of robotic use in
manufacturing these are industrial
robots um in Japan it's a little better
um like like many of the figures in
manufacturing but there's actually been
a decline even you know this was numbers
ending in in 2020 but they're pretty
stable after this there's been a slight
uptick overall in Japan and the one
anomally here is China with a large
scale up mostly due to government
subsidies in manufacturing now you may
wonder you know can we really trust the
data from China here this data is coming
from um actually robot manufacturer so I
think we can trust it but we can trust
it only to a point so I would encourage
you if you're interested to read the
work of a a sociologist at at Harvard
named yaah WL who has gone to factories
in China to study how they're using
robots and what she finds is a lot of
the robots that were subsidized by the
government end up in the corner of the
factory collecting dust partly because
the government provided these incentives
without an actual demand for the robots
and partly because the manufacturers in
electronics assembly for example were
expecting these robots to be able to
hand delicate electronic components but
the robots don't have that level of
dexterity yet so this is a kind of a
mismatch between
um Form and Function at the
moment okay one of the the issues here
you know you okay so now we have flat
robot adoption maybe that's because of
risk what really is going on so we've
had data now from you know this is from
a large robot manufacturer and we also
have some some data from a US Census of
businesses and how they use robots and
what we've noticed is that one of the
key problems here is not only that
there's only a small percentage of
American factories that adopt robots in
the first place robotic automation this
is not just robots it's also other types
of specialized equipment I'll show it in
a second but it's that only about half a
little a little more than half of the
companies that adopt robots uh buy a
second robot we refer to this as the
second robot problem that we know for
these firms when they scale up their use
of Robotics they hire more people they
become more productive they become more
profitable and yet they're still in the
very small minority of overall
manufactur uring firms so this is a
question of you know what's happening
here why is it so difficult for firms to
automate at
scale um I'm going to pause it that one
of the big challenges here is that a lot
of the firms that could make use of
robots but don't end up purchasing them
don't have the internal skills to use
these robots effectively so these are
again data from us manufacturers um
showing their different their purchase
of various you know Advanced or even
pretty basic equipment and then this is
data from job postings at manufacturers
so these are hundreds of thousands of
production job postings fewer than one
in five of those jobs requires any
digital skills at all that could be
operating Microsoft Excel to writing
machine learning algorithms they're
they're it's very rare in the United
States to require um manufacturing
workers to have digital skills and
that's really holding back the adoption
of new
technologies okay there are there are
deeper problems in the manufacturing
Workforce um this these data might seem
familiar because they're actually
they're similar in uh European countries
and in Japan is that the the
manufacturing Workforce has aged
dramatically and it's not only aged it's
also it's stopped hiring so there's a
big gap between old manufacturing
workers and young and this is just a
visualization of that so the red is the
distribution you know reasonably healthy
distribution of workers in an industry
it Peaks at you know late 30s early 40s
that's where most of the workers are and
it's relatively normally distributed now
what happened when you when you don't
hire manufacturing workers for the
better part of 20 years that Peak just
moves over and then you have a gap in
knowledge and experience and
Manufacturing and then it's only been in
the last five to seven years that firms
have had an uptick in hiring one of the
Practical challenges that some of you
might face firsthand and what we hear
from a lot of firms is that a lot of the
knowledge among workers here is not
codified anywhere there's no clear way
way to transfer that to this younger
generation without necessarily the
experience or even the the language and
understanding to absorb the knowledge
from the most skilled technical workers
so one of I think the big challenges for
institutions like MIT and institutions
like let's say the university and and
the firm that I explained is to figure
out a way to codify and somehow deliver
these skills to the next generation of
workers um this isn't easy and and this
is one of the reasons why this this is
so challenging um over the last you know
uh 15 years or so there's been a an
increase in demand for manufacturing
workers but also an increase in turnover
so the tenure of manufacturing workers
is becoming shorter the time that they
have to gain the skills in order to
operate new technologies understand to
process very intimately is getting
shorter so this is I think an even
bigger challenge for firms when they try
to develop skills one of the the paths
that American firms have taken with this
short 10-year environment is to say
we're not even going to try to look for
highly skilled workers instead we're
going to take any worker available and
we're going to try to train them
internally this is a challenge when your
average worker might only stay at your
firm for one to two
years
okay this is this is I think a challenge
that's underlying a lot of uh the other
problems and it's a lot of firms they
might complain that they can't find
workers because this generation isn't as
inclined toward manufacturing as the
previous ones or um in some cases it's
the that the workforce um itself is
focused more on um other Industries but
they don't deal with what really is a
root cause problem and that's wages so
this is quite different in in Japan
where there's still a significant wage
premium for manufacturing jobs but in
the United States this green line is uh
wages for careers in let's say working
at a grocery store working in a
warehouse non-manufacturing jobs and the
gray line is manufacturing jobs so in
1960 and even into the 70s and ' 80s
there was a very significant premium
work for working in manufacturing if you
had a high school education or even an
associates degree less than a four-year
degree you could make between 20 and 40%
more in manufacturing than you could in
alternative careers and today you can
make 2% more in in manufacturing in the
United States than you can alternativ
it's pretty much the same in places like
Massachusetts
California um it's negative you actually
can make less on average in
manufacturing than in other careers
overall so one reason for a Workforce
shortage or a lack of skills is that
manufacturing jobs aren't really paying
that much now you might imagine this is
a chicken and egg problem if they're not
demanding skills um they're probably not
able to pay justify paying that much
particularly if they're uh losing
productivity over time okay now I think
the question is what what do we do about
this what are paths to encourage
companies to be more growth oriented
more risk tolerant to improve technology
adoption and skill development now I've
noticed partly through study of
companies like the the four that I
introduced that there are there are
really three models and I want to
highlight a few here so one is a return
to some version of conglomeration where
we have I would say a pseudo
conglomeration in the United States
through private Equity held firms uh but
the challenge of private equity uh
corporate governance is that it's
relatively short-term that the the goal
of the private Equity Firm is to P is to
acquire an asset and then turn it over
at a higher value not to invest in the
long-term sustainability and health of
that asset one of the differences of of
a company called rebuild manufacturing
which has a connection to mit's uh
leaders for manufacturing program is
that it's set up as a holding company
similar to danur which some of you might
be familiar with and they have
explicitly said and you know I think to
some people's Chagrin that they want to
be like an American ketu that they
really are explicitly modeled on a
Japanese form of conglomeration and they
have tried to internalize some of the
principles of of lean but with a
different orientation toward technology
and skill so one of the portfolio
companies of rebuild is the Colorado
firm making bicycle wheels that I
mentioned uh at the top they have more
than a dozen other factories throughout
the country now and are growing quite
rapidly so the second model of dealing
with risk is a venture capital model a
startup model that um has served America
American companies well in software and
there are now multiple growing Venture
Capital firms that are financing
startups like the boat startup I
mentioned which is a in the eclipse
portfolio um over
time the part of the uh motivation for
Eclipse comes out of experiences at
Tesla rivan and SpaceX where a lot of
their Partners come from and to support
uh Founders who have come out of those
organizations and learned key principles
about experimental manufacturing um
while at these companies and then
finally one of the the real Trends in
the last 20 years has been there's been
an upsurge in foreign investment in the
United States so similar to how um lean
and the Toyota production system helped
spread through Partnerships like numi
between GM and Toyota in California as
well as just direct investments from
Honda Toyota and others in the United
States uh there was a lot of knowledge
and a lot of I think uh skill that has
spilled over due to foreign direct
investment so just to visualize this for
a second here's a plot just of a billion
dooll factories so very large Factory
projects over the last um you know 20 or
so years and what we've seen since covid
and is is and this trend toward the
localization of of manufacturing is a
tripling of billion dollar Factory
projects that are foreign owned so to
40% of all new large Factory projects in
the United States are from foreign owned
companies and you can imagine you
overall manufacturing uh Capital stock
in red pretty flat but the foreign
direct investment position has more than
doubled during that same time so there's
really a higher presence of foreign
companies why is that important well the
foreign companies that can afford to
make large investments in the United
States have a significantly higher
productivity than their American
counterparts they pay higher wages and
they invest more in technology so the
the hope at least is that these
companies will induce um more
risk-taking and a more productive
orientation of their American peers
through
competition okay now the other thing
this is a really core to the research um
within my my group is how do we
encourage more investment in technology
and induce more skill development within
manufacturing I think part of the
challenge here is that the typical model
for a adopting Technologies like robots
um in the United States has been to try
to use these tools to drive more
productivity but to drive more
productivity at the expense of the
workers who have been involved in a a
routine process over time so there's
more productivity but the tradeoff is
that jobs are more commodified and lower
quality and one of the results of this
process when it's taken to its logical
end is that automation projects end up
being brittle and at times failing so
you know we have a project um that if
you're interested I'd be happy to talk
about um looking at failed Automation
and trying to understand the root causes
of failed large automation projects like
Tesla's model 3 um there's a a large
tool Factory um run by Stanley Black
and& Decker that ended up failing in
Texas and then kind of the original um
which was actually inspired by GM
president's uh Roger Smith's visit to um
to Japan in the 1980s was the factory of
the future he called it uh where the
term lights out manufacturing came from
from and it was a factory that
ultimately um ran into a lot of
technical Pro problems and ultimately
shut down um so I think there there's an
alternative here though an alternative
that that creates automation that's more
flexible that relies more on workers in
higher quality higher skilled jobs now
what does that look like you know one of
the things we wanted to do is we wanted
to ask workers what they thought about
an automated environment that could help
them build more quality jobs we didn't
just want to ask CEOs so we did a um a
survey of 9,000 workers in nine
different countries about half of the
workers were in the US and then half of
the workers were in Europe and Asia we
surveyed 500 workers in Japan and I'm
happy to share you know uh the the
differences but what we what we realized
through that survey and I'll I'll share
some details in a moment is that uh
redesigning jobs can be really critical
to getting workers on board with an
automation project and one way to to
help workers get engaged is through
targeted incentives so I mentioned at
the beginning with those four firms the
employee ownership or employee um profit
sharing was really critical to
supporting employees who wanted to work
with new technology and wanted to
develop the skills to use it effectively
so here are some of the results of that
survey first one thing we were really
surprised by is that when we asked
workers how they related to automation
what impact they thought Automation and
Robotics would have on their jobs they
were mostly positive so when we asked
how does automation affect your your
safety and comfort at work you know
workers were 30 more 30% more positive
than than negative similarly when we
asked them how does automation help you
develop new skills grow in your career
workers were far more positive than
negative they were even you know
although somewhat divided slightly
positive about um the effect of
automation on their job security that
they thought automation might make them
more secure versus
less now what I want to share is that
this this wasn't present for all workers
or all countries so in Japan workers
were actually quite optimistic
about the impact of automation but in
the US they were the most pessimistic
workers that we encountered actually the
only workers with pessimism overall kind
of a net negative score on job security
or pay were in the US so American
workers are actually have a much more
negative orientation toward technology
overall than workers in let's say
Germany France Spain or or J um or Japan
now we want to understand why might a
worker be pessimistic toward new
technology might why might they resist
Automation and one hypothesis we had was
that workers in more routine jobs jobs
that might be most vulnerable to new
technology they might be more uh
resistant so we tested it we asked
workers what type of tasks do you do um
as a part of your daily routine and and
we tried to uh see if there was a
relationship between these questions
about
automation so here's what we found to
our surprise we found that the level of
routineness in a worker's job didn't
actually matter that much for the
perception of automation it was their
level of problem solving their level of
kind of the creative input that they
provided into the manufacturing process
that really made a difference so here
are workers in manufacturing Environ you
physical environments with high routine
tasks but low problem solving and these
workers are very pessimistic they're
negative toward the impact of automation
on their wages negative about the impact
of automation on their job security but
when you take the workers with the same
routineness but they do more problem
solving they say that problem solving is
a core part of their work they're among
the most optimistic and our our kind of
you know hypothesis we don't have a
clear explanation for why this is the
case but our hypothesis is that if
workers have enough problem solving
enough cognitive work that they're doing
they're less threatened because their
core tasks of their jobs aren't readily
automatable whereas they have work that
might be drudgery that they want a
technology to take care of that those
high level of routine
tasks okay now finally I want to share
one thing that I'm kind of I've been
inspired by while talking to to
colleagues here and trying to study you
know Manufacturing Systems all over the
world and it's a system of skill
development that is a public good so in
the United States we we've struggled
over a long time because we've invested
in higher education as a public good and
we've invested in in uh K12 education as
a public good but vocational training
has never been a focus of um of national
public goods investments in the United
States whereas they have been in places
like like Germany and to some extent in
Japan so when I talk to colleagues about
how this company that I mentioned
earlier to the West making parts for
medical devices how they had a skilled
Workforce that with a high school
education people could be building
custom machines they said well in
Japanese high schools you graduate with
a level of mathematics and Engineering
understanding that the gap between you
and someone in college isn't that
significant that you can collaborate
with engineers and you have a shared set
of language and principles that's not so
in the United States however there are
some experiments that I find very in
inspiring and they're in some I'd say
unlikely places so this is just an
example of a machine tool company
actually the largest American Machine
Tool company called H which is based in
in Ohio um they've partnered with
regions around the country to develop
essentially you think of them as many
technical colleges and one that they
developed I would say among their most
successful is in Easter Eastern Kentucky
and if you've never been to Eastern
Kentucky I imagine not many of you had
it's a very uh struggling part of the
United States it used to produce coal um
there's a lot of problems with drugs and
there's a lot of crime um but what this
organization has done is they've taken
people who might have been struggling
used to be coal miners um had families
that are very low income and they've
brought them into a manufacturing
environment and treated them as if they
have a lot of mechanical skills and
talents to offer offer and ultimately
through just a several month training
process they find every single person
who goes through the program a job
actually a high wage job mostly in
Machining professions working with
robotic automation at a network of
companies in the region and this is I
think an exciting story because it's
among the You' think of the hardest
populations to train and position in in
these types of jobs but nonetheless this
organization has done it with now
hundreds and hundreds of students from
all backgrounds and all ages
so I I look forward to you know figuring
out ways to replicate this type of model
um to support more skill development at
other manufacturers in the United States
so thank you so much for your time and
I'm happy to take your
questions I'm going to read these
questions like the previous speakers as
you mentioned manufacturing jobs are
with low wages also the salary in Japan
is too much lower than the United States
for the same job title and duties
in your opinion how do you keep
employees motivated to keep progress so
what I would say about wages so maybe
I'm looking at some of the different
data the gap between Japanese production
wages U and American production wages
isn't that big the gap between
engineering wages I think is much more
significant however what what I'm going
to focus on is this High variation in
wages within American manufacturing so
the four companies that I talked about
at the beginning all of those are very
high wage firms I was emphasizing where
they're located they're operating in
high wage environments and they're still
competing so how I look at these
examples is they prove they're kind of a
proof of concept that you can find a way
of producing with high wages and high
prod with high enough productivity to
justify paying your workers well and
motivating them to
contribute could you speak to possible
transition ideas is while workers are
being reskilled unskilled which would uh
make the break in employment more
attractive so so this is um a challenge
that in the United States we faced a lot
in the 1980s and 90s where there were
and even you know the 2000s when there
were a lot of layoffs particularly from
offshoring uh due to NAFTA or China's
entry into the WTO so there was a
program that has since been been uh
studied and and found to be uneffective
called the the trade adjustment
assistance program where the idea was to
Res skill people whove been laid off
from manufacturing jobs um luckily we
have a high demand for American
manufacturing workers there's you know
anywhere between 500,000 and a million
manufacturing jobs that are open
unfilled at any given time in the United
States over the last several years so
the idea of being reskilled I think
there there could be someone who has a
job in manufacturing and is being um
trained at the same time so that would
be a smoother transition
the other point I'll make here one of
the reasons we think Americans are so
resistant to automation or pessimistic
is because there isn't the same level of
job security and government support a
social safety net for American workers
so if we look at places like France
where we wouldn't necessarily anticipate
workers to think differently about
automation French workers are so much
more optimistic about the impact of
technology on their jobs and I think one
potential explanation is the social
safety net in France is a lot stronger
so workers are less worried about being
laid
off with the new Trump Administration
it's a great start to any question um
what do you think of future the future
of American Manufacturing in the short
and long term and how would it affect
other countries manufacturing such as
China or
Japan
so as as I imagine everyone knows Trump
Administration is very new it made a lot
of promises uh during the campaign about
how it would um impose tariffs on other
countries um these
tariffs I'm still skeptical that they
are going to be imposed in the way that
the Trump Administration promised I
don't want to speculate now what I can
say is that the tariffs in 2016 looked
really bad on paper and actually did
affect certain industries but how the
administration implemented the tariffs
was to offer many exceptions so really
what they created was a lot of
personalistic power for the government
that so they can control which companies
got exceptions to the tariffs and which
didn't so the tariffs on paper might
look bad and then you see all the large
uh companies that are importing from the
com the countries with tariffs getting
exceptions so they don't face tariffs at
all so it's more of a I think a
personalistic strategy there um I have a
lot of uncertainty about this as well
I'm following it very closely um clearly
the the words of the current
Administration are that they care about
manufacturing and want to see it grow uh
I don't think that tariffs are the way
to do that um so I am a bit concerned if
if any of the the proposed policies come
into action uh in a serious
way continuous training will help with a
skills Gap how much continuous training
is needed as we need workers and lack
the ability to always be thinking about
training okay so the continuous training
is important and what I think is is let
me let me step back and say the issue
with training within companies is that
you know there are some old papers that
lay this out very effectively that
companies will always systematically
underinvested training partly because
they don't want to train workers who end
up um going to their competitor firm and
using all the skills they developed at
the company so companies we can't rely
on companies alone to give workers the
skills that they need particularly in an
environment with high turnover so what
do we do I think that's when I talk
about public goods that's what I mean
that really there need to be public
goods for training that can support all
workers in a certain industry or all
workers in a certain area such that they
have the skills to support to to uh
provide a pipeline of very uh capable
workers in uh in a particular region so
these are I think Regional training
ecosystems and Regional training
infrastructure that can be that can help
solve the problem that the question uh
posed
thank you very much