Hi everyone. I'm Caitlyn Infantino. I'm
the co-founder and CRO of Blue Sarah.
Um, and today I want to invite you to
think about how ecom could be better for
everyone from the customer experience
through the brand experience.
Quickly
quickly, I want to introduce our team.
Uh, George Manley serves as our CEO. He
draws an extensive experience in CPG
sales, fundraising, and property
development management. Um, his
background has equipped him with a
strong financial acumen and a sharp
ability to navigate complex
uh, contract negotiations.
Tim Owen is our CTO. Uh, he's got a deep
background in predictive modeling and
machine learning. Tim built um, a
successful software company called Data
Robot from the ground up. It's now at
about a $7 billion valuation. Uh, data
robot enables everyone from larger
enterprise customers to smaller business
owners to effectively build their own
predictive modeling. Uh Tom spent many
years at Saks Fifth Avenue as GMM and
Katherine Havasi um as a former MIT PI
um and on our advisory board she's done
something um with customer feedback um
in the CPG space as well.
I suppose I should tell you about myself
for a minute. Um, I have a uh a
background in uh the shoe industry, but
um I really sort of cut my teeth in the
startup world selling foam to shoe
companies from everybody from Nike to
Jimmy Shu.
So, a quick story. This is how Blue
Sarah came to be. Uh it's birthday
season in our house, a couple of kids
and I'm just trying to buy one simple
thing, towels with ears and tails and
I've got five web pages open to do it.
Um
our ecom activity is spread out all over
the web. So even if you do get it done,
you've got emails coming into your inbox
one after another trying to figure out,
you know, where your shipping's coming
from.
There's counterfeits coming in. I just
spoke to a guy who returned $2,000 worth
of light bulbs. And consumers and brands
want an alternative to Amazon. So, you
know, I didn't like the product search
results. I didn't like how I had to get
it if I didn't want to just buy from
Amazon. I wanted to put one towel from
the company store and one towel from
Pottery Barn into one cart and check
out.
So, talked with a bunch of people about
this and did a ton of product research.
There's 81 billion views on #shop small.
There's a subreddit with 3.2 million
people for buy it for life. There's all
these different factions on the internet
looking for an alternative way to shop.
Here's the solution. With AI, we can
offer fast, intelligent, personalized
search results. We can eliminate
counterfeits. We can allow you to keep
multiple carts in one place and check
out from multiple stores with a click of
one button. We've put ads in a silo so
that you can go there when you want to
use them to be inspired to find
something different. But when you're
searching for something, all of that is
driven by your preferences and your
search activity. And then obviously it's
voice controlled and um completely
intuitive. So I'm going to show you a
quick demo.
Can you hear it?
Dare to imagine your customers shopping
online in a new world of product search
results. Let me show you how your
customers will be shown your brand and
your products exactly when they're
looking to buy them. There are no paid
promotions in this part of the app. The
customer drives the discovery.
Customers will be able to find your
products in store, too.
These are the carts where customers can
build and save all of their shopping
projects from all over the internet in
one place.
When the customer checks out, your brand
receives 100% of the margin and your
brand is the merchant of record
>> because our customers understand that
the inspiration tab is only for ads.
Your marketing content will be your
customer they're wanting to sold to.
They're in the mood to window shop.
By sharing your ads with friends, your
customers make inspiring marketing and
products they love go viral. They can
purchase right in the app where you
still receive 100% of the margin.
Adding content to Blue Sarah is free
during our beta. Easy because we accept
the same formatting as men.
At Blue Sarah, we love the hardworking
and creative designers, engineers, and
marketers who bring us the products and
so enhance our lives. We want to put the
customers and the brands back in
control. Join our free beta and together
let's create a new solution.
>> So, here's what we are what we need.
Now, we're calling on all industries
from shirts to pants to hammers to Bose
headphones. We'd love for you to join
our free beta and upload your meta
formatted ads to our inspiration tab.
It's free and it's going to be free for
at least the next six months is what
we're thinking. Um, please connect to
our APIs and upload your instore,
online, and wholesale account inventory.
Um, we can connect your APIs as well if
that's more convenient, if you want to
give us permission. Um, that will save
us compute
um, and and help with, you know,
timing, latency,
um, and then, you know, integrate for a
faster seamless checkout. Um,
and give the blue Sarah bot permission.
That's what we need.
>> Thank you, Caitlyn. [sighs]
So, um, let me ask you, how are you
different from any other ecom market
place?
>> 100% of the sale goes to the brand.
Every time we put your ads in front of
people who are looking to see them in
the beginning when the when the customer
first comes everything they see is is
driven by the preferences their
preferences what we already know about
them and what they're looking for that
day. So we can deliver um better search
results that aren't all paid promotions.
So it it'll drive your customers to the
correct products much more efficiently
and then when they're looking to be sold
sold to they'll go to our inspiration
tab and enjoy your marketing.
Um zero paid promotions um in that first
part of the app and then you know I
think what really makes us different is
that we're a service to the customer and
the brand. It's a completely different
economic setup than anything that's out
there today. Yeah. And so tell us a
little more about how the brands can
integrate.
>> Um initially we'll be scraping all CPG
websites for products and product
attributes. Um the the best way to
integrate is to first of all give our
bot permission and then we welcome the
opportunity to connect to your APIs so
we can grab your product catalog um
and you know can advertise directly with
us.
>> Okay. And one final question as we wrap
up. What is um your business model
and the revenue stream?
>> Yeah. Um we charge our customers $5 to
check out from any cart. So as you saw,
like if you're, you know, shopping for
your kids back to school, you could put,
you know, pants from Zara, underwear
from Lucky and Me, pajamas from Gap, all
into one cart, check out with one click,
and that cost the customer $5. The
revenue stream is um will be down the
road through advertisements.
>> Okay.
>> Yep.