It is my pleasure to introduce our first
speaker Matters Versa who is a research
collaborator with the MIT digital
currency initiative and also the chief
scientist of Radius. Welcome Matters.
>> What are you going to talk to us about
today?
>> Um thank you very much Jim. Um uh today
I'll give a brief introduction to uh
postquantum uh
um so um first uh what is cryptography?
Cryptography is communication in
presence of adversaries kind like if we
didn't have adversaries there would be
no need for cryptography. But we do have
adversaries like let's say there's uh uh
two people Alice and Bob and Alice wants
to um
uh uh send a a message to Bob um and
because she's sending it over untrusted
network anyone on the pass on the
network can read and uh modify it like
this would happen like if you were for
example at a coffee shop. Uh so there is
a standard technique that Alice uses and
like we all of all of us rely every day
which is just use encryption. That way
uh only Bob can receive Alice's message
but everyone else on the path from Alice
to Bob is left in the dark.
But here's the problem. Uh quantum
computers an upcoming technology uh
break most of encryption methods used
today.
uh in particular uh uh this is a quantum
threat as applied to cryptography.
There are two quantum algorithms that
matter for cryptography.
You might have heard of them like one of
them is called Grover's algorithm and it
basically weakens symmetric ctography
like hash functions or uh uh encryption
algorithms like AES and it gives a
quadratic speed up like if previously it
required 2 to 128 uh uh operations to do
a search now it requires 2 to 64
and because this speed up is just
quadratic it means there is a simple
solution it just suffices for us to
double the parameter sizes we used
smaller keys Now we all just like use
little bit larger keys but um that's not
again like life-ch changing.
But the second algorithm by Peter Shore
invented here at MIT uh is devastating.
It breaks most public key crypto
cryptography used today such as RSA
crypto system which relies on hardness
of factoring of large composits
elliptic curves and similar and it gives
exponential speed up. While uh n bit
integers can be uh factored in just
polinomial time
and like uh those terms mean that this
is a real threat to today's systems
unlike for Grober where you could just
double the parameter sizes you cannot do
that for short algorithm uh like you you
really like if if if quantum computers
get built that can execute short
algorithm then much of today's
cryptography is toast
but how far away is this and uh I'm a
computer scientist. I'm not a physicist
but u I'm going to consult a physicist
remotely. There's a great resource by
professor at your water loss which gives
a landscape of quantum computing and it
basically looks like this like there are
two main parameters for quantum
computers. One of them is how many
cubits are there and uh second them is
like how good are the cubits meaning uh
like what is the error rate and
generally can like uh uh like for for
most powerful computations you want to
be kind of like up and to the right you
want like a large number of uh very high
quality cubits
and if you can see kind like this is a
how quantum computing landscape was in
21 and now it's 22 and now it's 23 three
and now it's 24 and it's very clear that
we are advancing up and to the right
exactly as would be necessary to
implement a short algorithm to break
break crypto systems like RSA
and um
oh and and now we arrive at 25 and we
actually see something else uh like not
only we have attack from below like we
get like better quantum algorithms we
also have uh uh quantum computers we
also get like attack from above Like
people have figured out like
optimizations to source algorithm and
like when the two lines meet like what
where computers are there and algorithms
are there to uh to be run on them we
have breaks.
So uh so it might really be that we have
more uh type phenomena. uh uh quantum
computers just get better and better and
algorithms themselves are a moving
target
and global risk institute uh did a
survey of leading uh quantum computing
uh professionals and uh these experts
estimated likelihood of quantum computer
being able to break crypto systems like
RSA and in five years kind of like the
low values of the estimates were maybe
like 5% chance an optimistic one was 14
but in 20 years the situation completely
completely flips like uh the pessimistic
estimate is that it's more likely than
not 60% chance that quantum computers
will be able to break our say in 24
hours.
And fortunately there is kind of like
good news. The answer is uh postquantum
cryptography. There are algorithms that
are resistant to quantum computers. They
are based on different mathematical
problems like problems that we used and
loved uh just like elliptic curves or
RSA function are vulnerable to quantum
computers but other mathematical
problems like latises or codebased
cryptography is not.
Um and in 2016 uh national institute of
standards technology announced a
competition uh for selecting postquantum
algorithms for protecting uh Americans
data. 92 algorithms were submitted and
after multiple rounds of evaluations
uh NIST announced seven finalists to be
standardized and then like a couple
years later final versions of first
three standards are out there
so that's good news but like it's not
like this process would would have been
uh uh without challenges like in 2009
Cloudflare and Google collectively did
experiment where they changed the way
encryption works when you visit a
website to in incorporate a postquantum
algorithm called psych. Psych was um an
excellent uh believed to be excellent
performance giving algorithm with like
structures that's impervious to uh
quantum attacks and um in fact even
advanced to round four of N competition
but just a couple a couple months later
there was a catastrophic break in psych
even without using any quantum computers
it was just broken an ordinary laptop
so and this kind like like highlights at
a certain best practice to use hybrid
approaches like use classical algorithm
together with a postquantum algorithm
because like had Cloudflare and Google
just used psych and wouldn't paired it
with as a classical uh uh curve 25519
algorithm like all of the traffic would
have been broken but because they used
hybrids they used classical and
postquantum together uh they at least
retain the classical security
so question is kind of like well how
urgent it is like maybe it is coming uh
uh in 20 years but uh why upgrade now
and here there are two main quantum
threats. The first one is uh forging or
impersonation. You can break
authentication protocols in real time.
Remember like when Alice was talking to
Bob maybe uh somebody in the middle
could uh uh use their quantum computer
to impersonate Bob without Alice
knowing. And like people give all kinds
of like arguments. Well, maybe large
scale quantum computers never get built.
Well, that's a possibility or or maybe
we'll see signs and and then we'll
upgrade kind like let's let's wait and
see. Um but that doesn't work for the
second quantum threat which is so-called
harvest node decrypt later uh attacks.
Adversaries can today decrypt uh uh can
uh record traffic to be decrypted later
when quantum computers are available
and upgrading later wouldn't protect
today's traffic and unfortunately it
even breaks perfect forward secrecy uh
uh that's based on current pre-quantum
methods as they rely on ephemeral key
exchange um and key eraser.
So
really to protect against harvest now
decrypt later attacks we should upgrade
now.
So here are the key takeaways. Number
one uh quantum computing is pro
progressing steadily and it is very
likely that existing cryptography won't
remain secure indefinitely. Upgrading
now would pre prevent those attacks
where somebody just records traffic and
then 20 years later when quantum
computer is there like decrypts it and a
lot of information is still sensitive 20
years in the future. There are good news
that the postquantum cryptography
standards are here and the best practice
would be using hybrid approaches as they
protect uh risks inherent in new
software and new constructions risks as
we saw with site
and then there's also like a call to
call call to action which is uh leads to
our next uh talk like you could use this
upgrade uh as a catalyst to revaluate
and modernize system architectures not
only to switch to something postquantum
secure but maybe switch to something
else entirely.
Thank you very much.
>> Great. Uh thanks so much uh matters uh
for an enlightening presentation. Uh
we're going to continue on to our next
speaker right now and then after uh
after that we'll bring Madar back on and
we'll have about five minutes for Q&A.
So uh prepare your questions of the
folks that are out there. With that, it
is my pleasure to introduce our next
speaker, Dan Arinoff, who is a uh
research affiliate with the MIT
Department of Economics and like matters
is a research collaborator with the MIT
digital currency initiative. Welcome
Dan.
>> Thank you Jim. So to take the baton from
Madars
what what we see over time the
horizontal axis is is a time dimension
are advances in the technology of
quantum computing that Madar spoke about
and also progression and regulatory
rules in in the I'm restricted to a US
content because I'm I'm not sure what's
happening outside the US but um it the
NSA uh national security agency um
announced in 2015 I think it was or 16
that it was going to change all of its
systems and requires its vendors going
forward to adopt postquantum standards
and then the National Institute of
Standards NIST at that time announced an
intention to develop postquantum
um standards and then we go to 2022 as
Madar pointed out the first postquantum
standards were uh approved by NIST and
this is an ongoing process for both you
know messaging, keys and uh data
security and also the uh Congress passed
the US quantum computing cyber security
act which sets a timeline
excuse me for federal government
agencies and all the entities that they
interact with to adopt these standards.
So effectively the entire regulated part
of the US economy is going to be uh is
going to have to adopt post-quantum
standards and that's like regardless of
what one's opinion about the real threat
of quantum computing is you can think
there is no threat at all you still have
to adopt the standards. Um so that's
something businesses are going to have
to contend with particularly in
financial services and healthcare.
So now we go to so what are what what
methods are available? Um the two most
prevalent and promising methods are
multi-party computation and fully
homorphic equip uh encryption and both
have been progressing over time. We'll
start with multi-party computation. What
is it? Well, suppose we're computing
Alice's credit score and there are
different vendors with information and
there's a desire or a requirement that
their information not be coming that it
be private. Um, rather than sending it
to a trusted party, cryptography is
based on on removing trust and relying
on math. In the case of multi-party
computation, each vendor would would
chop up its its uh information that it
has on Alice into chunks and it would
send independent chunks to one of a
group, you know, each chunk to a
different server that was part of the
multicomputation pool. And so all the
vendors do that. So let's say you have
three vendors, you have three computers
doing multi-party computation. uh the
vendors each vendor chops this
information into three parts distributes
it to the vendors each each computer has
the function to compute but it's
computing on partial data so this is not
penetrable by quantum computer there's
no numbers to factor and then they
combine the outputs and you can then
make the in you can then get the result
from the output you can control who gets
to who has the key to see the outut put
you can make it resilient so that if
there's fake data coming in or some kind
of an attack it's resilient to that. So
this is a lowcost resilient method.
However,
it relies on on uh there being no no
collusion between the computers doing
the computing. If they if they if they
collude, they can decode and break the
system. So there's that that human
vector of attack that that is out there.
The next method is fully homamorphic
encryption. With fully homorphic
encryption, you're encrypting data.
And the encryption has the desirable
property that you can compute on it. So
for example, Madars and I can each have
a number and we can add, we can
multiply, we can compare our numbers by
just looking at the cipher text, the
encrypted data. We don't have to
decrypt. We can send our information to
a central processor encrypted. That
processor can compute over our data
never seeing it. And yet we can verify
that the computation's being done
correctly. Better yet, the methods that
are used for fully homorphic encryption
are res are quantum computer resistant.
And the reason is that they rely on on
random noise to protect the data. And
there's nothing a qu a quantum computer
can't penetrate random noise. So all of
that is very good. It's very promising.
Um it's and and it's very new. The
drawback is it's very expensive in terms
of computation.
It's not feasible to deploy at scale
yet. And so um uh it there's a lot of
research being done, significant amounts
here at MIT, but but it's not ready for
prime time. And therefore the method
that's currently relied on is generally
a trusted execution enclave. And what
that is is you have an it's it's is you
have an enclave around a processor. So
your data is coming in encrypted. In
Alice's case, all these different
vendors send their encrypted data in. It
gets decrypted, you know, by the machine
inside the enclave, computed on,
re-encrypted, sent out. This is
resistant to quantum computing attacks.
Um, however, you're now relying on your
hardware for security. The value of
cryptography is that when it works, when
it's impenetrable, it's math. There's no
way around it. It's it's it's
unbreakable. Here, because it's hardware
dependent, there can be flaws in
hardware. There can be human
malfeasants. Um, and so there's an
ultimately an element of trust that's
reintroduced in the in the trusted
execution environment. Finally, all
these methods can be deployed on
existing computer systems which is which
is beneficial.
Okay. So, um
next we have the progression of of AI
techniques of neural networks and
computational power that we're all you
know I'm sure aware of and using um over
time. But at the same time there's
there's this question of how do you
combine these advanced techniques with
the requirements of privacy? Privacy in
medical records, privacy in financial
records. So let's go back to Alice's
credit score. In fact, let's go back to
how do you compute a credit score? One
way is the current method which is you
send encrypted data to a vendor that you
trust um you know not to not to reveal
the contents but to make it trustless
um you can use cryptographic methods and
one of the most promising is called
federated learning. What we would do
here is now suppose there's there's
several silos of data on a large group
of people and we're trying to compute a
credit score function. So you would have
a central computer send like a a an
equation structure, a model structure to
each silo and each silo would compute
its function on that data. So it would
come up with its own let's say mini
credit score model on on the slices of
data that it has. It would then send
encrypted the parameter estimates back
to the central computer. The central
computer could then aggregate those
together. Maybe just averaging across
the the the neurons of a neural network
or whatever the model is.
And then you iterate back and forth. And
by doing that you can actually compute
um efficiently compute a or not
necessarily efficient compute you can
get an accurate um developed model um
without any of the underlying data being
shared because all that's being shared
are the parameters and you can of course
even disguise the parameters using
methods like FHE.
Um, and now we get to Alice's credit
score. And there you've got the model
set up and each vendor can send their
pieces of Alice's information and use
the methods that we talked about before.
Um, and so this is this is um this is
something that has a lot of promise.
And so to to summarize
um regulated institutions will be
required to adopt postquantum privacy
and security regardless of the reality
the ground truth of of whether quantum
computing is is going to be a real
threat. And there are methods available
but they're not cost feasible many of
them for atscale deployments
cryptographic methods. And again we
desire cryptographic methods because
it's trustless. It relies on math. It's
the most when it works in the right
conditions, it's the most secure um
thing that you can do. Um so a fallback
is trusted execution enclave, but that
opens a vector of attack through the
hardware. uh and finally we can apply
post-quantum techniques to decentralized
learning in the way that I described
where the data the underlying data is
never being combined and within each
silo um you can use the methods we
discussed earlier that can protect
against um postquantum or quantum
attacks. So that that's all I have.
>> Thank you Dan. uh great presentation and
uh we're going to move to the uh
question and answer portion of your
talks and uh so both of you can feel
free to tag team on a few questions that
have have come in. Uh so I'll just uh
start off with the first. Uh do you
believe that firms will need to scrap
the existing tech stack that they're
using in order to adapt to postquantum
security?
Um
>> well it's always kind like a a good and
um standard practice to do inventory of
uh of your software assets and hardware
assets and in this case also like what
underlying cryptography uh they use and
um of course um vendors will provide
updates uh uh but uh uh uh your
institutions might want to adopt like a
particular strategy. for example, a
vendor might choose not to use hybrids
and you might choose to actually do use
hybrids because uh uh that's a more
prudent choice.
>> But I think I think it's also the case
that that these methods we're talking
about are classical computer that is
existing computer type infrastructure or
methods that can that use classical
computers to defend against quantum
attacks. So they're they're not methods
that require that you have to yourself
you have to have a quantum computing
base to protect your data. You can use
the existing you know technology
um in principle to to achieve
protection.
>> Okay. Uh another question in for uh from
our Q&A function. Uh and and uh do there
was uh do you have any comments? Um
there was an announcement a couple of
days ago about uh 12,000 laser tweezers
uh that achieved uh 6,100 cubits and uh
do you think that that would ex expedite
uh the need for more uh uh postquantum
data security?
Uh well it's always kind of like like
when when you see those announcements
there's like uh I think the prime number
is the number of cubits but uh there's
also the second number is the error rate
and kind like uh because like ultimately
what happens is uh uh like to implement
uh quantum algorithms you implement them
on what's called logical cubits. You
apply quantum error uh correction uh uh
to deal with faulty physical cubits. And
so like maybe you have a ton of physical
cubits but uh you cannot implement
quantum error correction and it's like
not not not that useful but but if you
can and it's interesting because it
seems to be a modality where people are
uh not working a lot on uh the Twitter
specifically then um it sounds promising
but I I I hadn't seen this. I would want
to uh look at the error rate uh not only
the cubit count.
I believe this announcement came in from
Caltech. So, uh um I I guess being
academics, we're we we we put a lot of
um um credibility behind when when
another a peer institution makes an
announcement like that. So, it is
>> somewhat exciting. Uh okay, another one
coming in from uh our audience. And with
deep learning and AI, do you believe
that hardening your authentication for
your endpoints is necessary?
Uh, and I would I wouldn't see um a
reason why
why why it wouldn't be kind like like
the unfortunately there's this like
insecurities there's this kind of like
generic principle that like attacks only
get better. So if there's an attack that
doesn't rely on on on on deep learning
on AI and that can uh uh harm your
endpoints then this attack will will
continue to exist and uh uh uh so yes I
would believe that it's it's still very
much relevant.
>> Great. And uh one one final question. Um
it it appears that uh the cryptographic
methods that we're talking about here
today are relatively new. Um do you
believe that there is a particular
epicenter of research for for crypto?
>> Well, MIT is kind of the birthplace of
modern crypto and Madar was trained by
one of the uh founders so he could speak
to that.
Well, uh there many premier institutions
and I'm happy happy to agree that like
MIT is um is one of them and like to to
answer like the substantive portion of
the question which about can like u many
of those things are indeed newer like uh
say like practical zero knowledge proofs
or practical polycomomorphic encryption
has only taken off in in the past decade
versus like other branches of
cryptography we've seen in industry for
for many decades.
uh but um also there is kind of like a
the field uh is has developed like
maturity and there's like a lot of
investment in those technologies. So
they are really progressing quite
heavily and like many of those things is
kind like it's not uh 10 years away
technology. It was 10 years away
technology 10 years ago. So
>> great. Well, we have to move on now. So,
thank you both uh Dan and Madars uh for
uh presenting this morning.