Um so uh yeah I'm going to talk about
the notion
uh that we call generative computing or
generative programming. Um and it's
really about um uh embedding software
within AI workflows. I probably should
say around uh embedding workflows within
software. Um, and I hope you're going to
already start liking this mushroom here
because it's going to appear in at least
half of my slides and you're going to
understand in a minute in soon why. Um,
there you go.
Okay. Yeah. Okay. So, just before I
start talking about uh generative
programming, just uh where I'm coming
from and maybe that will explain why why
I'm here. Uh, so I'm part of the MIT IBM
uh what's on AI lab. Um this is the
building literally outside the door when
you come out on Main Street just across
the road. Um we are at the 30th floor of
that building. Um uh the lab was founded
uh about 10 years ago. Um and the idea
is to bring together researchers from
IBM and MIT and and really truly working
together. Um in fact in the almost 115
years that IBM existed, this is the
largest investment that IBM has done
ever in any academic institution. Um
here are some statistics on publications
and citations and and so on. We support
students. We have summary internships.
Um and part of the research that I'm
going to show now some of it came out of
of those collaborations.
So um in the last uh several decades
there are you know several different
paradigms of programming that emerged
and there are two very extremes. uh one
is good old coding um which is also
known as imperative programming and here
a coder which up until two three years
ago was just a human now it's AI or
human plus AI or just human um writes a
code so it just writes instructions step
by step how you should perform a task
now the coder whether it's a human or AI
can benefit from seeing a few inputs and
output examples but it doesn't really
need them as long as it have a good
specification and then it just writes
the code and and really what we're doing
here we're instructing a generalist
computer like my laptop or a server uh
to perform a single task and we do it
using code right and I say a generalist
computer because the computer can do
many tasks if I give it another piece of
code it'll perform it on the other
extreme we have statistical machine
learning um which is a form of inductive
programming here we have no
specification at all or the
specification is given us by many many
examples of input inputs and outputs and
I don't really know what the
specification is. But then there's all
these learning algorithms that we
developed in the last few decades and
they then they come up with a model or a
formula and that's how the computer
knows what to do. So again we're
instructing a generalist computer to
perform a single task but now we do it
through a model. And now came a new cool
kid on the block and that's genai. Um
and J gen ji is actually very
interesting because it has two stages.
The first stage we use inductive
programming to compute a new model which
is a generalist model. So we give it
many many inputs and outputs and they
come in different forms at different
stages of the training. The pre-training
the inputs are prefixes and the outputs
are the next token and then later during
instruction tuning we give it just
instructions and outcomes of these of
performing these instructions and then
that's a very long process. It can take
months and a lot of compute. Um and then
we get this generalist model. But once
we have it, it's like a little computer,
right? Um so now we can program it. And
I call it natural programming, but don't
worry about that. That that's going to
go away soon, that word natural. And we
do it by prompting really. So really
what we're doing here, we're instructing
a generalist model again to perform a
single task. And we use natural
language, English or whatever language
uh you want. Um, and that's great,
right? Because now we have people that
never studied computer science, never
been, you know, trained on programming.
They can now program a computer and
yeah, all off we go to the races and
there's a lot of excitement and all
these, you know, and AI is going to take
the world and people are developing
beautiful apps and it's all great, but
not so fast, right? So there's um this
famous uh MIT
uh research that actually Puma didn't
say but he is one of the authors um this
you you probably most of you have seen
this that 95% of AI pilots in the
business fail and there other evidence
that there are issues and then we we ask
ourselves so okay so what's what's what
really is going on here
and in order to understand what's going
on here let's see what agents really are
and agents are just you know glorified
prompts and and another title for this
slide should be well we're rediscovering
that programming in natural language is
actually really difficult. So there's
all kinds of problems that can can come
up. Uh so when people write these
prompts they often do it by themselves
but more more often they actually use
other ALMs to help them write these long
essay prompts. Uh but then you end up
being you know having these long essays
that there's no way you can maintain
them. Maybe you can maintain them
yourself, but if you work as part of a
team, then another team member will have
no idea what to do with that prompt. Um,
it's very easy to break. If I add
another constraints, how do I know that
it doesn't contradict a different
constraint? Um, then there's security,
right? We we we all know that LLMs
hallucinate, they make errors. Um, here
I'm begging the LLM that if there's
password, just don't reveal it. But once
I say the word password, if you know how
the transformer works, it works by
attention. than the word password its
tokens will probably if there is a
password the tokens of the password
their representation will probably
include the password in it and then I'm
just praying that the attention later on
when I generate other tokens will notice
that I say do not include and we'll kind
of suppress it but it's kind of security
by prayer and then there's all these
essay prompts and they really what
they're doing they are encoding in
language very complex language age uh
steps in a control flow but then it's
very difficult to be sure that this is
really going to the model's really going
to follow it. So with that I want to
pose a question for all of us is if LLS
are a computing device then why are we
forgetting about decades of computer
science research and software
engineering practice. The first
programmable computers were developed
during World War II. So that's more than
80 years ago. So we have decades of
experience and that experience gives us
a lot right. So we have tooling like
debuggers for example. We have best
practices unit testing abstraction
boundaries code reuse. We have paradigm
and design patterns like divide and
concore and map reduce and recussion and
dynamic programming and and we've got
thousands and thousands of algorithms
like sorting and clustering and
constraint satisfaction and you know any
any problem in the world. We've thought
a lot about that. So why are we
forgetting this? Whereas in Gen AI we
have prompt engineering and I'm putting
engineering quote unquote because it's
really mostly trial and error
and this I don't want to dismiss prompt
engineering uh because actually works
great right if somebody you know as I
said people can sit in their attic and
create beautiful apps and that works
great but it doesn't work when you work
with large teams sophisticated business
use cases it just doesn't work so let's
see what we using what we're losing by
not thinking of geni I is just a mode of
computation. So obstruction boundaries
right prompts as we know they're very
highly tailored to the model that they
are that I developed them for. Know that
in the previous example I said if there
are passwords ignore them but maybe for
other model it will say ignore if you
see passwords if you put the sometimes
it completely changes the performance of
the of the model. So they're really not
uh you know you can't transfer them from
from one model to the other and it's
very hard to encapsulate specific
functionality. So agents as as pruma
said you know we can use them as
microser and they can we can reuse them
as agents as a whole entire agent but
it's very difficult to extract from
these essay prompts like low-level
functionalities that can be reused
between you know on one agent can use
this you know this little functionality
I can put it in another agent and so on
and so forth. We all know that LLMs are
unpredictable and they're stochastic in
nature. So if it's a stochastic
computation device, we need to account
for that. We need in our design
patterns, we need to address that. Um
and finally, there's no real
methodology, right? We forgot about
methodology. As I said, it's all trial
and error. If I come with this 10k essay
and you ask me why did you do this? I
can't say why. It just worked, right?
So really what we want to do is come up
with I want to give it a name first. I'm
going to call it generative computing. A
generative computing is is is not is is
is a way to work with LLMs. Um but work
it in a method methodical way. Um so
what I'm going to do now generative
computing will combine code and
prompting. And what we we we really want
to try is to bring as much as we can
from computer science uh everything that
we've learned and and we have a lot of
experience and use it in generative
computing. And if we need to adjust
something because of the the model that
we're working with, then let's do that.
But let's do it um in a way that we
understand why.
So with that, I want to introduce
project MA. So Millia is an open- source
Python library that we've started
developing
maybe four, five months ago when we open
sourced it in the summer. Um Malaya is
actually a type of mushroom. It's
edible. Uh the they're they're very
pretty. They kind [clears throat] of
grow in bunches around barks of dead
trees. Don't ask me why we call it
Malaya. Um so let me give you a little
bit of a kind of a sales pitch and then
I'll give you an example of a design
pattern with Malaya. Uh so Malaya is is
really lets you use LLMs uh but less
lets you use it inside or more like
writing a a software which will give you
predictability, maintainability,
composibility and security.
And crucially, and you'll see it more in
later on in my slides, what we what
we're doing, we're taking control flows
out of the prompt and put them in in
software in code. Um, and as a result,
and Purduma talked about that too, in
the context of, you know, web of agents.
So now I'm talking about in the context
of a single agent. The prompts are now
becoming shorter. So instead of this
essay prompt, I'm breaking down the
prompt and but because I took the
control flow out of the out of the
prompt and [clears throat] I'm using
small calls to the LLM and now small
language model all of a sudden have a
power of a large model that was maybe
the only thing that could understand
this 10k uh long essay. And we say when
we work when we program in Malaya if
your prompts are more than one or two
lines or if you think too much how to
word them then you're doing something
wrong. should be easy and these short
prompts are also much more likely to be
portable from one model to the next.
I want to emphasize that malaya is not
an agent framework. It's a way to build
agents but it's not a way to orchestrate
agents. You have nand for that you have
lang chain you have other things. So you
can in you can incorporate malaya or
malaya programs in any of your favorite
agentic framework. You'll also see some
examples of inference scaling. Uh for
those who knows what inference scaling
is, um it's also another library of
inference scaling, but it's definitely a
framework where we can build and use
inference scaling in a smart way and
methodical way.
And finally, because it's software, we
can package libraries of functionalities
that have AI or LMS in them. And then we
can work as teams just like we, you
know, we work with software, right? So
we can have libraries and one one team
can write this library, another team can
write this and they can talk with each
other. They define APIs and so on and so
forth.
So let's talk about design patterns
within uh Malaya and and this is
probably the most important design
pattern that I'm going to show you and
and and it comes from the fact that we
all know that LLNs are intrinsically
unpredictable and often wrong. There's a
famous quote by Winston Churchill that
says it is remarkable that airlines can
understand and produce flu fluent
natural language. It is even more
remarkable that they are wrong five or
50% of the time
maybe 50% chance that Churchill said
that or he would have said it if he
would have been here today. So you got
my idea. So the consequence is that we
need structure that make uh that make it
a first class concern to check if it uh
to check our work and implement ways to
repair it. The analogy here is quantum
computers and quantum computers because
we know that the nature of the computing
device is that cubits are not uh uh are
not stable then we need to incorporate
error correcting codes inside our
computation. The same here.
So this is the pattern that uh uh that
kind of the main pattern in Malaya but
there are other patterns we can talk
about and we call it instruct validate
repair or IVR IVR this is a a simple
program in Malaya it's just a little
agent that can write an email um and the
first thing is we need that because we
are now instructing a computer to
perform a task so it starts with an
instructions right an email you can get
some inputs invite them to the end of
end of summer intern party
and then we also have requirements.
Okay, the requirement says the email
should be this and that and don't do
that. Yes, do that. Um within that
construct that you see here which called
m.instruct
when we have an instruction and
requirement under the hood when we going
to call the LLM and get back the output
under the hood there's going to be a
validation process. The user doesn't
need to know how that work. The default
will be using LLM as a judge, but it
doesn't have to be LLM as a judge. In
fact, some of the requirements can be uh
checked with code. You don't need LLMs.
For example, if there was a requirement
here that says that my email should
include at most 100 words. I can just
write a Python program. So, I can come I
can bring a requirement with its own
checker and and this all this happens
under the hood. Once we have an answer
if something was right or wrong, I can
do exception handling, right? I can know
if something went wrong, okay, then I
need to do something about it. Maybe I
tell a human to write the email or maybe
I send it to a larger LLM.
But before I give up, we also remember
that there's an advantage of the way LM
work. LM are samplers, right? So LLM, if
I raise the temperature, if it's not
zero of the LLM, then it just samples
from my token. So I can try again. So I
can have all kinds of repair strategies.
One of them is rejection sampling. So
here is a strategy that we implemented
in MLS. Again the user doesn't need to
worry about it. They just write that
piece of code that line of code and that
says try three times and until if you
succeed within three times great. If not
then say I can't do it within my budget.
So here's what happens under the hood.
Um so we get these instruction
requirements and the strategy for repair
and this breaks down
to several different calls. One the
first one will of of course will be
execute call the LLM to perform the
instruction with these requirements. The
instruction and the requirements that we
saw they were written in natural uh
language in English but that's not
necessarily what the LLMs will see. of
course it'll see that language but
there'll be some additional things and
maybe we'll add some structure and you
know the we'll kind of adjust it to the
way the LLM is used to see instructions
and requirements but again the user
doesn't need to worry about that and
then there's validation as I said
validation can come in many different
forms default is LLM as a judge um and
then there's my strategy you know I can
do all kinds of things here I'm asking
it to rewrite so I'm giving it the
output and the requirement says okay the
requirement failed on that output try
and fix it or I can just sample without
giving it out. Just resample without
knowing anything why it failed before
and I can do it several different times.
So you can already see here all the
things that I mentioned before. There is
abstraction boundaries here, right? So
the the way I run the LLM, the execute,
the way I run the instruction does not
depend on the way I validate that,
right? So these two things are separate.
It just needs, you know, a common
interface between them. Um so there's
abstraction, there's code reuse. I can
use the same validation technique to
validate something else and so on and so
forth. You can already see how I'm using
the regular computer science way of
thinking in developing my agents.
Whereas if I write that in a prompt that
would be a mess as you can imagine.
Um and there's many different ways I can
implement any anyone any parts of this.
And again the user an advanced user can
write their own but you know a simple
user that doesn't want to deal with it
doesn't have to worry because a lot of
it is already implemented. So it can be
just simple prompting. It can be an
adapter lura for those who knows and if
you don't I'm going to talk about lura
soon. Um so now we can take this to the
next step and we can apply all kinds of
traditional classical algorithms to
natural language tasks. We call this
verbalized algorithms. And here's an
example. So suppose you want to you have
a you have a list of customer complaints
and you want to deal with the most
severe one first. So you want to sort
them according to severity.
Now this is a natural language task and
I can just take an LLM and feed the list
of let's say 100 complaints that I have
feed it in the whole the whole thing in
one prompt. Now the LLM most likely not
only it won't be able to sort it
correctly, it will probably hallucinate
some other may may drop some complaints
and hallucinate some others. But now
let's make an observation. If I take any
any of your favorite sorting algorithm
like merge sort or bubble sort all they
do is really they have some control flow
but they just repeatedly perform pair
wise comparisons between the elements
that we're sorting. So here's an idea.
Let's use an LLM just to do the pair
wise comparison. This is an oracle. Um
and the rest of the algorithm we'll just
write in pi python. Python is great at
it. So we did that and and here are some
some results. This is the paper. Um so I
I want to emphasize so what you see here
the baseline is just feeding everything
in a prompt and all the other columns
are different implementations of the
verbalized algorithm idea. And I I
really want to emphasize you can see in
both models. So we ran it on two quen
models. One is a small model and one is
a kind of mediumsiz model. And both of
them we see really nice improvements.
But but really huge gains are for the
small model. Um the the numbers here are
just correlation. So correlation between
the ground truth sorting and the sorting
that the algorithm outputed and zero
means it's completely random. So the
small models completely get gets lost
with with the list. The list here is is
of size 25. So it's 25 um I think like
Amazon reviews or something that we that
we're sorting. Um but it get very nice
results better than the 32 billion
baseline quen just with 1.7 billion
and we have uh we're developing which is
a constantly growing library of
verbalized algorithms for sorting subm
modular set maximization clustering so
on and so forth
also opens the door for very interesting
research of you know all these
algorithms we now need to make them more
robust because the oracle is an LLM so
it's not reliable but potentially I can
actually Maybe if I have a time I'll
speak about it a bit. Potentially we can
actually quantify the uncertainty. So
how can we do that and make our
algorithm more more robust.
So really this is the message from this
part of my talk. My main part of the
talk is don't put the control flow in
the prompt. Okay are really bad at
following control flows even basic ones.
I mean and often this is where agents uh
fail
uh like Python handle the flow
divide and conquer.
So I have how much uh I see here nine
minutes is with the questions.
Okay. Uh maybe I'll do this fast. So
it's more technical. Um so if you know
whatever it's just be a few minutes. Um
so I just want to get give you some
examples of what happens under the hood.
um just to show you that we're not only
talking about the high level but but
also Malaya is is translating things
into the inner working of the model to
make everything efficient. Um and here
I'm going to touch of that that notion
of MLA session. So when you start MLA
you start a you write a you kind of
start a MLA session and there you you
specify all kinds of things in
particular you you determining which
serving framework like VLM you're going
to work with which model or models are
going to be associated uh with this
program and and also we have with this
model we have some uh implementations of
what we call intrinsic functions. So
introducing functions are all kinds of
capabilities that we want to inject into
the model and and and again it's back to
the code reuse just things that that we
want the code to know how to do. We
mentioned requirement check that's on
the top right here. We mentioned the
requirement checker. This is a very
important capability that appears in IVR
all the time. So we want kind of a
specific piece specific module that is
very good at it. I mentioned uncertainty
quantification. I think this is really
important for LLM. So, so we actually
have um a module that doesn't serve
dewantification. We have guardrails.
This is guardian. So, there's something
that checks guardrails for profanity and
things like this. We have a bunch of
things for rag. Um these are things that
are not part of malaya, but malaya can
use them. So, we we we're releasing
these things separately separately on on
hugging face.
Now, some of these things can be
implemented in Python, but most of them
are actually learnable modules. uh but
we don't need to retrain a whole module
uh model just to do that. We do that by
using efficient adapters uh also known
as loras. So let me take you again going
to be technical let me take you a little
bit into the what happens what is a
lora. Um so a lora is is an efficient
way to tune a model to do something
specific. Um and the way it works it
looks uh we look at the way transformer
model attention the main piece of
transformer architecture works and the
way it works it's really just many many
matrix multiplication. So you have your
input that's X and you take every token
and X and you generate
three things. The these things are
vectors. It's just list of numbers. Uh
one is query, one is key and one is
value. Um and you do that by multiplying
uh the input the token by some
projection matrices. And this is the the
entries of those matrices. This is what
we're learning. This is the model. So
during the learning phase, this is
really what's happening. we're adjusting
these the entries of the matrices. Um,
and what Laura does instead when I want
to do something when I teach the model
something new, something very specific,
rather than retraining all these
matrices from the beginning, I'm just
I'm fixing them. I'm not touching them.
I'm just going to train another matrix
on the side. This is these are those
deltas here. Um, and this matrix has
less parameters. It's low rank. Let's
not get into that, but it's it's less
parameters. Um, and after I train that,
I just add these two matrices and that's
how I perform my computation.
And that's very efficient. It's really
nice because they're very uh small these
deltas. So I have kind of a tiny module
in tiny compared to the whole model and
I can have many of them and I can store
them. I can bring them up and bring them
down and run them and so on and so
forth. But there's something that people
don't talk about that much. there is
something inefficient in the way we use
Lauras and this is the the so so the
model the way the model works is you get
a prompt um and then you run an answer
okay so you you kind of perform all
these computations by the base model and
let's say now you need to perform some
evaluation let's say a requirement
checking okay so if I now need to run a
lura for requirement checking I need to
recomputee everything that I did until
now because that's what the low rise
knows how to do. It knows how to work
with things that are the w plus the
delta.
And we came up and again I'm going to
I'm going to skip that. I'm just going
to very quickly we came up with an idea
which actually very simple. We were
surprised that it hasn't uh been
observed before and we call that
activated Laura which is trained to work
with both of them. So it knows how to
work with the original representations
of the base model. But once it starts
computing the actual things that I
wanted to compute, then it adds the
deltas and it works amazingly well. I'm
going to yeah, I'm going to have an
example. But it has like amazing uh you
know speed ups and evaluations. Of
course, the speed up get better and
better as the prompts grow longer or if
I need more and more uh activated Lauras
to run. And with that I'm going to
conclude. So what I I I talked about the
way why why we want to bring computer
science back to be you know at the
driver seat. Uh showed you how to build
agents with software using best
practices design patterns. Um we have to
understand that the LLMs are stoastic in
nature. We have to design for that and
we compile I show you how we compiled in
very efficient way models behaviors. I'm
just going to conclude this fits this is
this is not a kind of new thing you have
to throw everything that we did before
with with genai. Um so this fits with
your own framework. So what we're doing
here we we're creating these runtimes
that orchestrate multiple LLM calls
combining them with other software and
you know control flows that are done in
Python. We do that using Malaya. So that
gives us kind of the program programming
abstraction and methodology. But then
you can just plug this in in your
endpoint if it's lchain or open AAI API
and so on and so forth. And with that I
can take questions.
[applause]
That's excellent work. I really like
this. And then there's obviously a lot
of work going on to think about how do
we combine code and models together in
different topologies. So there's two
ways of thinking about Malia. One is
either as the user interest this is how
we write the applications or as an
intermediate layer that gets written by
other natural language is on top of. So
do you primarily see this as the way
we'll program or as an intermediate
layer within the programming stack where
we might be alternating code and models
and code.
>> Yes. So I'm thinking as as a layer
between you know the agentic and and the
LLM. So this is really how we we talk
with LLM. That that's how I'm thinking
about it.
Okay.
>> How do I Okay. Um I wanted to ask a
question. You um sort of paraphrasing
what you Here I am.
>> Oh
>> yeah. Yeah. Paraphrasing your discussion
which was good. Um you focused on
uh that the uh agents are glorified
prompts.
>> Yeah.
>> And you then pointed out that there was
a intrinsic ontology problem which was
the basis for I thought what you were
saying was the the brittleleness of of
that. So I I uh so I'm sure you've
thought about this but uh did you take a
schema approach and then the scripts
were sort of part of the runtime so that
the schema sort of solves the ontology
but I I I I didn't see how the how the
semantic or ontology problem was solved
but you certainly gave an example of one
path. So I I just wanted you to sort of
address those two two questions.
>> Yeah. So I think when you have a task uh
you have again to think about it from a
programmer point of view it's like what
is the specification what is the control
flow
which parts in the control flow I need
the LMS which part I don't need the LM
so I don't know if in your words maybe
that's the schema maybe that's why you
refer to the schema and then just write
the code and where are pieces that you
need to call the LM yeah well you need
to write a prompt right I'm not we need
some stage somewhere you need to write
natural language so you need to write it
but as I said it has to be something
small if it's not small. If it's not one
or two lines, you're doing something
wrong. You can probably break it
further.
I hope that answered the question.
>> I think I saw a hand around here. Is uh
another question.
Okay, then let's uh give a hand for Dan.
>> [applause]