Good evening everyone and welcome to the
Nexus and the MIT libraries. Uh my name
is Mark Sarco and I am a librarian here
in Hayden and uh I will be introducing
tonight's speaker. So
Eric Robsky Huntley is a spatial data
scientist, GIS analysist and geographer
at MIT. Eric is a lecturer in urban
science and planning in DUSP, director
of the spatial analysis and action
research group and lead systems engineer
for the data and feminism lab. They are
also founder and principal of
okography's research and design, a
missiondriven GIS mapping and spatial
data science consultancy.
Eric is interested in what they call
quote mapping up which involves using
data science and mapping methods to
analyze dominant actors and
institutions. Their current research
focuses on identifying shared ownership
of property owning LLC's in
Massachusetts using spatial network
analysis and building interactive tools
and visualizations to make this
information accessible to tenants,
activists, and local governments. Please
join me in welcome Eric Robsy Hudley.
Uh, thanks for being here, y'all. Um,
I'm glad some of you have moved up. I
was about to do a bit where I refused to
speak unless some of you did. Um, and
you've made I can't do that bit anymore,
so thanks. We'll just knock that off the
list. Um, so this is this is sort of an
interesting uh format. Um,
uh, yeah. Yeah, sure. This is this is an
interesting format in the sense that I
am kind of introducing a film before you
see it. Um meaning that I don't want to
this isn't I'm not going to give you a
critique of the film because I want you
to form your own opinions. Um you don't
know what you think of it yet. Um if I
reference things that are actually in
the film,
uh you may or may not hold them in your
head until they show up. Um, so I think
what I'm going to try to do here is kind
of uh in relatively abstract and open
ways, try to give you things to key into
as you watch the film that might make
that might change the way you view it.
Um because I think that we're looking at
an artifact in such a rapidly changing
landscape that much of this film, even
though it it came out two years ago,
it's only two years old. Um already
reads as being somewhat out of date, um
for reasons that are both probably going
to be obvious to you and those that
might not be quite so obvious. Um so the
first thing that I would say is that um
I sat down to watch it last night. Um I
am last minute perpetually and I was
sitting there with my partner and we
were watching this film. Um and the
thing that jumped out at me first um was
that it was falling really heavily on a
trope that many of us probably remember
from the months after chat GPT first
launched. Um, ChatGpt. Anyone any nerds
in the room? Um, chat GPT
beta the platform that the tool went
live when approximately.
Anyone?
I'm so glad you don't actually know
that. Thank you. Um, that's good. You
pass. Um, it went so uh, chat GPT went
public uh, no in the sense of the tool
becoming available uh, November 30th,
2022. Um, by January it had hit 100
million users. Um, and so around between
November and January was when we started
to see this particular thing emerge. And
the thing I'm referring to is this. Um,
you begin reading an article. You sit
down to watch a film. Uh, it unfolds. In
a film, it might be a minute. In an
article, it might be two paragraphs. And
then at the end of that second
paragraph, uh, record scratch.
What if I told you this was actually AI,
right? Um where the grand reveal was
that you've been engaging with this tool
this entire time whether you knew it or
not. Um and throughout this film um you
see fairly extensive use of at this
point relatively uh again it shocks me
that I have to say this but slightly out
ofd um generative AI models producing
imagery. Um so for example we see um we
see uh what AI thinks that uh say forced
weager laborers in western China might
look like when they're returning from
the lithium mines, right? Um, we're
seeing uh what it might look like to be
in a uh to might be in what what it
might look like to be in a um uh a data
labeling uh workplace uh where it sort
of we're led to assume relatively
vulnerable populations in say subsaharan
Africa are labeling exploitative data
exploitative visuals that are posted to
the internet for meta whatever it is um
one of the big tech companies. So, it
falls back really hard on this this what
I think of as kind of a dated gimmick
where it shows you AI and you're left in
a really mystified place where you don't
know how exactly how to engage with it.
Um, it's an image. It's speaking to you
in a way that is recognizable as an
image. Uh, you're engaging with it in a
way that is close to how you might
engage with the real thing, the actual
artifact, the actual photograph,
whatever it is, but you're at a distance
from it. And I think I I have some
questions actually about how the film
uses sort of these these um AI generated
images, but I actually want you to think
about how you respond, right? What is
your how do you understand your ethical
obligation in a way that is affected by
the use of AI to produce these images as
opposed to what would be more
traditional journalistic practice of you
know embedding doing these kind of
long-term trust building journalistic or
or ethnographic approaches and and
really kind of coming from a place of uh
more grounded research in the course of
of um film making or or writing. Um,
another question that I have. Okay. So,
um, I'm a I'm a geographer. Um, I am a
uh, GI scientist, which is geographic
information scientist. Um, and what that
means is I'm in some ways a ctographer.
Um, how many of you have met a
ctographer before, right? Ah, yes, I
know. Wonderful. Um, um, uh, okay. So in
the film um much of your narration is
going to be carried forward by not the
narration much of the sort of um
argumentative arc of the film is going
to be carried forward by a
self-described cgrapher. Um we meet uh
this this uh guy named Vladen Jober
Joler Joler I can't read my own writing.
It could be one of the two. Um and um
his his role in the film is to take us
through the sort of you could say the
back end in some ways. He's he's being
given the the task of saying um this
tool that you see this robot that's in
front of you this interface that's
presenting itself um it's actually when
you run a query when you when you um uh
when you give chat GPT a prompt right
when you give DeepSeek a prompt how does
that how does that relate to the entire
universe of things that sit behind the
technology right so how does it how does
your prompt to chat GPT uh trace outward
through your sort of standard uh HTTP
requests um and actually bring forth
sort of muster forth this whole world of
resources of metals and labor and blood
and all of these things that that go
into however quietly um the the tech we
use in our daily lives. Um and I'd
actually I' I'd encourage you to think
about um the fact that this is a
self-described cgrapher. Um cgraphy is
mapmaking, right? Uh ctography is right
parttoraphy. So it's drawing the world,
writing the world. Um and um the uh uh
the uh actually geography is writing the
world. Cgraphy would be writing the
sheet actually. It's sort of sort of a
strange word for what it is, but the the
um but it's a mapmaker, right? Um, and
in the sense that we're dealing with
these maps that exceed sort of your
traditional latitude, longitude pieces
of of uh, you know, traditional
mapmaking, um, I'd really kind of
encourage you to think about how how you
think about the uh, interaction between
tooling and supply chains and
technology. I think the thing that the
film is fairly successful at is drawing
out both how um drawing out really how
these individual pieces of technology
trace immediately outwards into these
these enormous networks of of resource
and and the like. Um, and then I guess
the the last thing that I wanted to say
that's and maybe this is where it starts
to feel the most um uh dated to me is
the the implications that it traces are
to it feels a little constrained
actually. Um it it deals with the supply
chains, right? So where do the where do
the um rare earth metals and lithium and
these sorts of things that go into NVIDI
NVIDIA chips and whatever it is, where
do they come from? Who extracts the
metal? Who refineses it? Um who labels
the data sets? These sorts of questions.
It doesn't really get, and I think this
is the 2023 part, it doesn't get into
the downstream effects on 2025 labor
markets in developed and elite
economies. Um, I don't know how many of
you have been watching the job outlook
for CS graduates recently.
It's not it's not what it once was. Um,
and for me, one of the fascinating
things about AI in the past year in
particular has been watching how it's
reshaped a lot of these previously
rarified labor markets. um to the point
that actually we're starting to see some
ripple effects where junior developers
while they're not being entirely
replaced um by uh by AIS by any stretch
of the imagination
sufficient quantities of that work are
doable by AI that they are hiring fewer
at slower rates and the responsibilities
are shifting to editing existing code
rather than writing novel code at the
very sort of simple um when you're doing
very simple things in the course of a um
developing a codebase Um,
and then I think frankly, I don't know,
and this is maybe my own thing. Um, I
was, um, I was watching this
documentary, and this is maybe a very
like public DMI place to say this, my
partner's pregnant. Um, and I I was sort
of like scanning outward, right? I' I've
been thinking very few in a few very
futurity saturated kind of way recently.
And I've I've had a switch flip in the
last six months on AI in general where
I've gone from being a skeptic to being
some actually, frankly, kind of a
doomer. Um, I'm I'm becoming less and
less open to the idea that there's much
good that comes out of consumerf facing
AI. Um, I'm really fairly skeptical of
of a lot of this and I I don't um my my
take on it has suddenly started to be
much more like, well, if it doesn't say
what it says it can do, we probably
shouldn't invest in it. And if it does
say what it says it can do, we
definitely shouldn't invest in it. Um,
and that's that's sort of become my
position to some extent, frankly. Um and
um I guess to to me um I've I've started
to I've started to um this film like so
many things in the in the ether puts me
in mind of a class that I've always
wanted to teach at MIT and I don't think
it really belongs in my department. Um
but if someone if someone is a
department head and is interested in
this, let me know. I can do it. I don't
know. I'll do it for free. Um, I've
wanted forever to teach a class at MIT
that's just called what if we didn't.
Um, alternative title, nah. Um, and the
premise of the class would be taking
very seriously that the best thing to do
with a piece of technology would
actually be to not do anything with it
at all. Um, in STS, this is sometimes
referred to as the inevitability
hypothesis, right? That the minute
something comes out of Pandora's box, it
can't be put back in. There's nothing we
can do to refuse it. Um, and I actually
think this is a moment where we're at
something like a really historical
turning point and maybe the the best
path forward is to find these little
ways of just frankly refusing. Um, I'm
um I uh you know and and and uh
enrolling in my class called What If We
Didn't? Um the uh thing I wanted to uh
close with. Um I have a favorite uh I
have a favorite ASAP rock song. He's a
rapper. Um, and uh, this is from a this
is from a um, it's from a song called
uh, Mindful Solutionism. Um, and it goes
like this. Uh, uh, you could get a robot
limb for your blownoff limb. Later on,
the same technology will automate your
gig. As awesome as it is. Wait, it gets
awful. You could split an atom
willy-nilly. If it's energy that can be
used for killing, then it will be.
Landmines, agent orans, leaded gas,
cigarettes, cameras in your favorite
corners, plastic in the wilderness. We
cannot be trusted with the stuff that we
come up with. The machinery could eat
us. We just really love our buttons. Um,
technology, focus on the other 3D
printed body parts, dehydrated onion
dip. You can buy a jet ski from a cell
phone on a jumbo jet. T E C H N O L O G
Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y Y
It's the ultimate. And he closes the
song with a rousing chorus of if it's
out of the bag, then it's out of the
bag. Now that is a powerful cat. Um and
uh this is a powerful cat. Um so thanks.
I don't know. Are we ready? Let's do it.