Our
collaboration with MIT and other key
players in the field of innovation
allows us to drive new solutions that
the minister said and Ivana Regala
mentioned this also and all this shapes
the future of mining, the exter exchange
of knowledge, research and finally to
create a dynamic and changing ecosystem
capable to adapt two new times and very
collaborative and that's why we are all
here this morning and we are also
followed by streaming from AMSA
and uh and all and it's time to listen
to other experiences and with this we
would like to welcome Eduardo Gerido
the director
of uh the industrial leazison program of
the MIT
Good morning. It is a pleasure to be
third year.
I thank Minister Williams for her words
for being present. Iana regard franco
the communication team for enabling this
wonderful event that I hope you will
enjoy. What you can see on the screen is
the Stata Center. This is the host of
the MIT AI center built by Frank Gary.
As most of you know he's the architect
of Guggenheim in Bilbao.
Now Let's start with this seminar.
MIT
has five schools. The engineering school
is the
renowned the renowned one. But there are
also very important schools such as the
school of sciences, architecture and
planning that is the number two in the
country. The school of business slom
ranked
among the first five of the country. We
have a school of humanities, arts and
social sciences with a series of
departments. But I want to highlight the
department of economy generating Nobel
prizes. among them the most recent ones.
There is also a department of political
sciences. MIT also leads in political
sciences and recently we have the
Schwvartzman College of Computing
Recognizing the significance of AI and
it in everything we do today.
>> Let me give you some figures. MIT has
over 1,000 full-time professors
and over 5,000 almost 6,000 researchers.
28% of them is women.
Almost 6,000 researchers, some of them
are visitors. MIT
dedicates $880 million yearly to
research without considering
1.2 2 billion dollars de dedicated by
Lincoln lab also managed by MIT which
works exclusively with the federal
government another figure in 2023
MIT received uh several patents almost
20% focus or dedicated to research comes
from the industry MIT doesn't make any
sense without the industry we exist
Because of the industry, we've had
several Nobel prizes. 13 of them are
teaching
and we have almost 12,000 students.
Twothirds are in post-graduate and one/3
in pre uh graduate levels. The school of
engineering has an enrollment ratio of
4.3%.
Four out of 100 applicants were
accepted. it is very difficult to be
enrolled to be allowed in.
So uh in the undergradu we have a high
percentage of women and 42% in
postgraduate.
MIT has several initiatives of research
covering the entire institute but I
would like to stress on the these three
ones. The first one climate and
sustainability.
There is a climate project at MIT. The
second one is life sciences MIT heels.
And the third one is computing and AI.
This is the MIT generative AI impact
consortium recent initiatives
across the institute. Particularly the
climate project is the most important or
significant project launched by Sally
Conrod.
MIT over a decade
should become the university that is
more prolific in terms of solutions
related to climate change not only
technologically speaking but also in
terms of performance and policies.
There are six missions.
The first one is decarbonization
of energy in the industry. We believe
this is key having new alternative
sources of emissions and clean energies.
Recently in May, one month ago, an
initiative was launched which is the
initiative for new manufacturing.
This is also an institutewide effort
aiming at creating innovative
jobs related to manufacturing
because we do believe that today it is
very important for the industries to be
based on the USA as well as in other
countries.
We feel very proud
of the collaboration with Antoagasta
Minerals. They are an innovative
company. MIT doesn't make any sense
without the industry. As I said, the
interaction creates knowledge, mutual
learning. This is not about coming here
to teach. We come here to learn as well.
This is a birectional path. With
antagusta minerals, we have developed
many things and we have learned a lot. I
will not go into details. Uh but the
goals are zero waste, decarbonization,
automated and remotely operated systems,
the community engagement is also key.
Mining for us is critical. Everybody
says that if we want to move towards
effective decarbonization to migrate to
electric trucks, we need copper.
So, we are aligned and I am happy to be
here today. You will hear from two
professors, Jose Pateco, the use of
sensors and digital twins to control and
improve processes and Ben Armstrong who
will talk about the work of the future.
I think this is very interesting because
it combines two important aspects for
MIT technology and humans. Thank you
very much.