When I was a freshman at MIT, uh we
lived in a fraternity house on the
Boston side. And to get to class, you
had to go across the Mass Avenue Bridge,
which is a long bridge. And our pledge
master said he wanted us to measure the
bridge. And he made all 14 of the
freshman stand up and looked at us and
said, "Smoot, you're the shortest, so
we'll do it in Smoots." How many uh
Smoots was it across the bridge?
364.4. four and an ear. When we got to
the last expansion joint, it came up to
about my knees. So, we did 04 and
decided that since we knew there were
errors in the measure that we'd be
honest engineers, and put a Greek E,
which means error measurement. And then
we decided that most people wouldn't
know what that meant. So, we wrote an
ear because maybe that's about the right
amount of error. For more MIT moments
from MIT Open Learning, like, subscribe,
or follow.