Hi, my name is Maddie Clark and I'm a
member of the admissions team here at
MIT Sloan School of Management.
Applicants should apply when they feel
that their application is at their
strongest. We strongly encourage
international applicants to apply by our
round one deadline in order to have
ample time for the various onboarding
processes, including the student visa
process.
Sloan is looking for accomplished
professionals who are ready to take
their careers from success to
significance. We're looking for folks
who are strong communicators and have
demonstrated leadership and impact in
their professional careers. For the
Sloan Fellow's MBA, we require a minimum
of 10 years of experience. We're
especially interested in candidates who
have general management experience.
Ultimately, we're looking for candidates
who can contribute meaningfully to the
Sloan classroom and who will go on to be
principled innovative leaders in their
communities, organizations, and
industries.