Our next session is about AI and
uh it's called interdisciplinary
research around AI. Our first speaker of
this session is an MIT major, MIT senior
uh in computer science, economics and
data science and she has studied AI
safety and AI safety and she's going to
introduce some MIT student uh le
activities around how to control the AI
risk. Let's welcome uh Audrey.
[Applause]
Hi everyone. My name is Audrey Lurville
and today I'll be talking to you about
AI risk mitigation and sharing students
perspectives from the MIT future tech
group and the MIT AI alignment group.
What could go wrong as we develop more
powerful AI? This is a question that I
and some others at MIT are working to
address.
Why is this question relevant to you?
Could you raise your hand if you work
for a company currently developing or
deploying
AI? Could you raise your hand if you
work in academia or the government and
you're wondering how AI will impact your
um field of
interest? Now, could you raise your hand
if you're simply a human being who's
been seeing how AI has been improving
over the past few years and you're
wondering what's going to happen? Well,
AI is clearly going to impact all of us.
We can imagine many futures where AI
will help us reduce um the big problems
that we're faced with by accelerating
scientific knowledge and lowering uh
barriers to knowledge. However, we can
also imagine many futures where AI will
exacerbate exa existing issues or even
lead to a loss of human control if we
lose control of these powerful systems
that we've
built. So, why did I start working on AI
risks? I'm a current senior at MIT. I'm
majoring in computer science, economics,
and data science. And I have a
concentration in international
development. I grew up all over the
world in France, Argentina, Japan,
Brazil, Mexico, and the US. And for a
long time, I thought I would work in
economic global development. But three
years ago, I learned about some of the
potential risks that AI poses. And this
completely shifted all my
priorities. I'd like to take a few
moments to see if you can think of three
different risks that AI poses.
Can you raise your hand if you could
think of three different risks from
AI? Okay. Can you continue raising your
hand if one of the risks you thought of
was existential
risk?
Okay. So, you may be wondering what is
existential risk? Existential risk
refers to the fact that AI may cause
human extinction or lead to irreversible
limits on human potential and humanity's
future. for example, by humans losing
control of AI and AI starting to take
all
decisions, especially if you're hearing
for this for the first time. It may
sound a little bit extreme. However,
many AI leaders and um executives in the
field believe that this is an outcome
that we shouldn't dismiss. In fact, in
2023, the Center for AI Safety released
a single sentence statement. Here it is.
Mitigating the risk of extinction from
AI should be a global priority alongside
other society scale risks such as
pandemics and nuclear war. Since then,
over 350 leading AI scientists, some of
whose names you can see on the image,
have signed this
statement. Existential risk is what I
learned about three years ago, and this
completely changed my life. I also
learned about the two types of advanced
AI. You may have heard AGI floating
around there, or artificial general
intelligence. There's many different
definitions out there, but a common one
is general purpose intelligence
comparable to humans on many points. The
step above that is artificial super
intelligence or ASI which surpasses
human intelligence in essentially every
domain. AI is already superhuman at some
tasks such as playing games like chess
and go. Um and current AIs are getting
increasingly better at different tasks
such as software engineering. We can
imagine that ASI will provide much
better biologists, better physicists,
and better inventors.
I'd like to argue that the continued
improvement of AI poses some serious
risks to humanity's future. My argument
can be broken down into three parts. The
first is that we're building
increasingly capable AI agents. The
second is that AI doesn't always do what
we intended to do. And finally, AI could
plausibly take actions that endanger
humans. Allow me to walk you through
these points. The first is we're
building increasingly capable AI agents.
Well, the main factors that go into
improving AI are energy, data, and
hardware, and there are no no very
strong bottlenecks on these. We also
have abundant funds going into AI, as
can be seen in recent large-scale
investments such as the Stargate
project. Third, AI is currently starting
to work on AI R&D, which means AI is
accelerating its own improvement.
Finally, the competitive pressures and
the potential gains are too great for
organizations to completely desist from
working on AI.
I'm going to show you two graphs that
illustrate this point. The first is work
from meter that was released in March of
this year. This shows um the length of
tasks can do um that length of tasks AI
can do is doubling every seven months.
Along the x-axis you have model release
year and along the y-axis you have the
length of tasks that AI um can get 50%
success rate on. So this metric the 50%
task completion rate is a good proxy for
tracking progress in model autonomy over
time. And as you can see um model
performance is showing exponential
growth. Next this graph shows the test
scores of AI systems on various
capabilities relative to human
performance. The different colored lines
correspond to different benchmarks. So
different capabilities that we're
interested in such as reading
comprehension or predictive reasoning.
Along the x-axis you have years and
along the y- axis you have AI
performance compared to model to human
performance. Um human performance is
used as the baseline. So it corresponds
to that gray horizontal line at zero.
And once the colored lines go above that
gray um baseline that means that AI
performance has gotten better than human
performance. And as you can see over the
past couple years AIs have pretty much
surpassed or come level with humans on
many different capabilities.
My second point is that AI doesn't
always do what we intended to do. And to
illustrate this, I'd like to share some
work from a lab I'm a part of at MIT
called Future Techch. Future is part of
CEL, which is MIT's computer science and
AI lab. And Future Techch studies the
economic and technical foundations of
progress in computing. Under the
direction of Neil Thompson and Peter
Slatterie, we've built the most
comprehensive repository of AI risks um
by synthesizing 56 different AI risk
frameworks. The result is what we call
the AI risk repository. A living
database of over a thousand AI risks
categorized into two taxonomies. We have
the causal taxonomy which looks at the
if, the how, the when, and the why these
risks occur. And then we have the domain
taxonomy. So every single risk is
divided into seven different domains and
23 different subdomains. Future Tech has
also built an AI incident tracker which
records the details of different risks
that um of different incidents that
occurred that are linked to
AI. This is an example of the domain
taxonomy we have for AI risks. So the
seven main domains are discrimination
and toxicity, privacy and security,
misinformation, malicious actors and
misuse, human computer interaction,
socioeconomic and environmental harms,
and AI system safety failures and
limitations. This risk repository is
completely free and it can be used by
anyone right now if you just access our
website. Um you can browse through the
different types of domains and you the
different taxonomies and explore
different risks linked to AI. The
Brazilian government for example has
already used this repository to inform
its AI act which is one of the largest
pieces of legislation that a country has
worked on to try to shape how AI is
being used inside its borders.
So back to AI doesn't always do what we
intended to. What do I mean by this?
This is known as misalignment in the AI
risk repository. This corresponds to
subdomain 7.1. AI pursuing its own goals
in conflict with human goals or values.
So AI doing something that the human
designers didn't actually intend or
plan. Um, every domain has a more
specific and detailed description if
you're interested in that. And we can
look at the AI incident tracker for an
example of misalignment. A very common
one um that appeared in 2023 is GPT4
which pretended to be a blind person to
hire a remote worker to solve a capture
test for it ones where you have to pick
like the number of palm trees for
example and the whole point of capture
is that it can't be solved by AI but two
years ago this already happened and we
can think of many different examples of
AI behaving in unexpected or deceptive
ways. We can try to train out examples
of misalignment that we catch when we're
training AI, but it's really hard to
guarantee that we aren't selecting poor
AI that's just really good at hiding its
misbehavior from
us. So far, we've seen that AI systems
are getting smarter and that they
sometimes pursue goals that are in
conflict with what their human designers
want. Now, to my third point, AI could
plausibly take actions that endanger
humans. What do I mean by this? Again,
I'm going to use the AI risk repository
to highlight categories of risks of
three categories of risks that endanger
humans. The first is misuse. In the
repository, we find this as cyber
attacks, weapon development or use, and
mass harm. An example from the incident
tracker is Amazon recommending explosive
producing ingredients as frequently
bought together items for
chemicals. Second category of risk is
systemic risk. This is AI possessing
dangerous capabilities, by which we mean
deception, weapons development and
acquisition, manipulation, cyber
offense, or AI development. An example
of this was a taser manufacturer which
proposed um AI enabled drones that were
equipped with tasers that would
supposedly defend um US high schools
against school
shootings. Finally, the third category
of risk is gradual disempowerment. This
is defined as loss of human agency and
autonomy. An example of this was Madison
Square Garden in New York, which used
facial recognition to identify and then
deny entry to lawyers that were involved
in litigation against them, including a
mother who was just trying to go see a
Rockhead show with her Girl Scout troop.
So, the examples that I have right now
might not seem too serious. However, you
have to remember that these are
incidents that already happened. They
involve AI that we have today that is AI
that is not super intelligent. So you
can imagine that as AI capabilities
improve the severity of these risks will
evolve
adequately. Now you may be thinking okay
there's maybe some potential risks from
AI but for every new technology there's
bound to be some alarmist and lites.
However the people who created and who
are currently building AI are also
worried about these risks. Let's hear
from them. Here's Jeffrey Hinton the
godfather of AI entering award laurette
in 2023. The existential risk is what
I'm worried about. The existential risk
is that humanity gets wiped out because
we've developed a better form of
intelligence that decides to take
control. Now, here's Sam Alman, CEO of
OpenAI in 2015. Development of
superhuman machine intelligence is
probably the greatest threat to the
continued existence of humanity. Okay,
that was 2015. Well, in 2023, he said
the bad case, and I think this is
important to say, is like lights out for
all of us. Finally, Dario Ammoday, CEO
of Anthropic, in 2023. My chance that
something goes really quite
catastrophically wrong on the scale of
human civilization might be somewhere
between 10% and
25%. Okay, hopefully I've convinced you
that AI risk is something we should be
pretty worried about. So, we would hope
that quite a lot of people are doing
work about this. Well, NGO, the Emerging
Technology Institute, actually counted
the total number of English language
articles on AI published between 2018
and 2023. Then they counted the articles
that were specifically about AI safety.
Can you guess the percentage of all AI
articles that were focused on AI
safety?
2%. Yeah. So AI safety work only makes
up a tiny fraction of work on AI. Now
let me tell you about some of this 2%
research. What are we doing about these
risks at MIT? Well, at Future, we're
starting a new initiative called the MIT
AI risk index. The idea is that for
every single risk in the risk
repository, we're going to provide a
risk profile with an assessment of the
risk, relevance for different types of
organizations, and then the most
promising mitigations. We're going to be
doing this by evaluating how over 200
different organizations are responding
to the different risks that they face.
And then we're going to work with
hundreds of different experts to help us
evaluate these risks and responses. This
is an example of what a risk profile
would look like. So you have the name of
the risk at the top. You have the
description, expert risk assessment and
relevance to ecosystem actors which
would be AI developers, large companies
deploying AI, government and consumers.
And then finally at the bottom you have
the most promising mitigations with
details. I'm also a part of the MIT AI
alignment group at MIT which is known as
MIA. MIA brings together over a 100
different students and researchers at
MIT that are conducting research to try
to reduce the risk from advanced AI. We
work on both technical and governance.
So that means um policy research related
to AI safety and some of our published
work can be found on our website. Maya
also organizes weekly meetings as well
as educational programs for students to
develop knowledge and skills in AI
safety which brings hundreds of students
from MIT every
year. Maya also plays an active role not
only in the MIT community or the Boston
area but beyond. And last month four
Maya members actually went to DC and
presented to policy makers at a
congressional exhibition for advanced
AI. and some of them are in the room
right now if you want to talk to them
about it.
Um finally
um some Maya members are working on a
new initiative called the MIT AI Safety
Institute or Macy and the idea is to
foster better collaboration between the
different labs and individuals that are
working on AI safety at MIT but might be
kind of
isolated. Okay. Based on all of this
interest and work that's being done at
MIT on AI safety, I truly believe that
MIT stands to be one of the global hubs
for independent review and work on AI
risk
mitigation. What are the next steps for
you? If anything I've said during this
talk piqu your interest, I invite you to
read more about AI risks. A good place
to start is the International AI Safety
Report. This was compiled by almost a
hundred different experts from all
around the world and published in
January of this year. and it's a good
overview of different risks from AI. I
also invite you to browse through the AI
risk repository and the AI incident
tracker from Future Techch. Finally, I'm
happy to answer any questions on the MIT
AI alignment group or on the Future AI
risk index which is currently open to
support and collaboration. Thank you
very much for your
[Applause]
time first.
Okay, one of the questions is, how do
you justify prioritizing AI existential
risk over immediate harms like bias and
misinformation given the lack of
concrete evidence for a doomsday
scenario? Hopefully, I've convinced you,
and if you're not convinced enough, you
can go into the AI incident tracker that
there is at least some evidence um that
we may have existential risk um in the
sometime in the future.
Um, I guess what I'll say here is that
quite a lot of attention, especially in
the mid2010s, was already being paid to
bias and misinformation and there's
enough people working on it. Even if
there's only a really small chance that
something really catastrophic could
happen, um, it's sort of like with
nuclear weapons, you want enough people
working on this and thinking about how
we can have global coordination on this
to ensure that even if there's only a
small chance this will happen, it won't
happen. hopefully. So, we have some
people working on this.
Um, okay. I can't figure out how to pass
questions, so I'll just answer this. As
a student, what is your opinion on how
the industry can help you cope with the
legacy of AI we are leaving you to
figure
out? It's pretty exciting. It's a good
moment to be studying CS and economics
at MIT.
Um, I think it's a problem that we all
have to face. As we've seen, everyone is
concerned in some way or another.
Um, it's really a unique moment in
history and I guess I'm glad that I get
to work on it or even talk to you about
it and even have maybe a very small say
in it by doing research on this. Yes.
Thank you very much.