good afternoon everybody it's great to
be here I'm Sid proein
M90 and I'm a firsttime CEO I've uh been
CTO for many Ventures and I think the
key thing I've I've Loved about it is
bringing together data from multiple
sources in fact I my first job was at
John Hancock Financial Services put
together a database of 12 uh different
product lines that have been separate
for 100 years and the insights we
produced were amazing that pattern is
one that really continues and what I'm
here to tell you about is swirl for the
Enterprise helping turn that painful day
to scavenger hunt where you spend time
going from tab to tab saving stuff
rewriting it organizing it that
scavenger hunt is AI is going to end it
we're going to get answers and insights
and the key is AI infrastructure
software let's take a step back you
might have heard a lot about the death
of AI or seen articles about how we're
in the trough of disillusionment it's
very hard to make it work the problem is
that most AI Solutions want your data
they want you to copy it in now if you
have just a single Silo of data for your
application that's pretty
straightforward but if you have a data
sprawl like the large Enterprise if you
have a data sprawl like the large
Enterprise it's very very impractical
there are security issues there are
compliance issues and actually those
Loom a bit larger and there's always the
question of resources do we really need
to copy nine pedabytes of data how
expensive is that going to be the answer
is about a million and a half dollars
swirl is AI INF infrastructure software
you install it in your environment it's
not a hosted service you can deploy it
anywhere Edge uh your own networks your
any cloud provider it provides a secure
connection between your choice of AI and
your backend data sources uses your uh
integrates with your single sign on so
there's no new uh permissioning of data
there's no bulk copying and it actually
gives you the power to turn an AI into
an assistant what does a conversation
with your data look like and why would
you want one the answer is it saves a
huge amount of time and it follows the
very natural process of being
interrupted by questions right and one
question needs to another so I got a
question recently what do we have for
cyber insurance I asked swirl and by the
way you could do this with a UI an API
or Microsoft teams or slack one of the
great things about AI is it's Omni
channel so after I clarified some
questions about my intent I was trying
to find swirls policy less than a minute
later in total I got the answer this was
open AI gp4 via swirls rag against as
you can see my one drive or SharePoint
not only do I have the answers but I
have the citations so I can verify that
this is correct and these insights are
personal I'm the only person in swirl
who can see this right because I happen
to have this document was sent to me and
I purchased the policy swirl produces
personalized
insights our secret sauce if you will is
swirls reader large language model you
may not have heard the term it doesn't
hallucinate it's only good at reading
and evaluating text and finding relevant
portions great video online you can
check it out swirl ranks Google and does
a better job of finding the right
answers if you search right now go to
Google search for red hat acquires the
number one answer is all about IBM
acquiring Red Hat why well it's popular
and you know they spent a lot right on
that PR and SEO if you ran that through
swirl it will pick up results 7 eight
and N from Google which are about red
hat acquiring company
llms and AI care about word order and
that you're actually on topic that's
contextual accuracy swrl can do that
same conversation or answer questions
and produce insights using any of the
AIS on the left-hand column and any of
the data platforms Enterprise
applications and web services including
structured data like thought spot
snowflake postgres new databases like
pine cone older ones like solar and open
search you know stuff I love from that
world also Information Services whether
it's open sanctions or something like
blockchain now who's using swirl I'll
give you some examples a global life
sciences firm their supply chain group
essentially stop using a ticket-based
data science team with a two-e SLA they
self- serve using swirl now across cbra
thought spot atlassian snowflake many
others their internal study showed a 7.5
hour per week savings 7.5 hours per
person per week a local University us
this world to search across multiple
catalog
a global retailer is combining the
ability to ask product and HR questions
like can I take a return with you know a
tear in this area again massive Time
Savings so swirl we're here looking for
people who want Enterprises who want to
do proof of values we guarantee results
and uh we're happy to do povs for
anybody who wants to engage with us
we're looking for folks with at least 5K
employees also US government agencies
that may be interested in airgap
Solutions swirl can be deployed anywhere
it's a great solution for that last
Point software solution developers who
build solutions for similar clients love
to hear from you we're easy to embed
thank you so much