- Welcome.
Thank you for gathering.
It's truly a pleasure
to introduce Keith Lynn
who is a member of Lockheed Martin,
part of Lockheed Martin.
Lockheed Martin is an organization
that recently joined the
industrial consortium of MIT.nano.
They also recently joined
Industrial Consortium of MTL.
And together our organizations
indeed are looking at ways
of furthering our depth
of interactions with Lockheed Martin.
As a part of that, we have asked them
to send us the very best
person they have, (laughing)
and that's Keith,
who can tell us very deeply
about the connections
that we possibly could
establish between us
and, indeed, Lockheed Martin as a company.
Let me just give you a
few snippets about Keith.
Keith Lynn is a senior manager of space
and strategic high performance
computing solutions,
and the site leader
for Lockheed Martin's Microelectronics
R&D Fabrication Center.
Since taking this position in 2020,
Keith led numerous efforts
in 3D heterogeneous
integration technology,
high temperature gallium
nitride electronics,
flex hybrid packaging, antitamper devices,
and engineered biological materials.
Keith works closely with
Department of Defense stakeholders
and Lockheed Martin's program offices
to conduct operations analysis
and mission analysis modeling,
an important step for understanding
how new technologies improve
the utility of platforms
in the field.
Keith frequently collaborates
with semiconductor companies
and Fortune 50 technology
providers to foster integration
of commercial technology into defense
and security architectures.
As such, Keith is member
of the Lockheed Martin Strategic
Collaborations Initiative,
overseen by the CTO,
Chief Technology Officer.
In this capacity, Keith works closely
with the organization's
director to form and implement
joint technology development agreements
and critical technology partners.
And hence he's here to think
about what can we do together.
Keith, please take over and tell us more.
- All right, thank you very much.
Thank you.
(audience applauding)
So as Vlad mentioned,
my name is Keith Lynn.
I've been with Lockheed Martin
for I think 16 years now.
I got the 15 year commemorative
pin a couple months ago,
so 15 and some change.
And I've loved Lockheed Martin so much
that I've stayed there my
entire professional career.
And I feel like I've worked
15 different jobs in 15 years
because the technology evolves so quickly
and there's so many
different technology facets
and mission facets in Lockheed
that it never becomes dull.
But I have to say, I'm finally
starting to feel old now.
I'm 37.
And I never really felt old
'cause it was so dynamic,
but now I am, because
I'm finally seeing things
come full circle in the industry.
They say the defense industry
is very cyclical as it is.
But I remember when I was very young
and very bright-eyed, fresh outta college,
the first thing I worked
on was nanotechnology,
which was the hot, up and coming thing.
Back then it was mostly carbon
nanotubes and buckyballs
and everything like
that was the big thing.
And now here we are again,
nanotechnology is the new technology area
that I think is gonna
revolutionize the industry,
many industries.
And it's not that it
was and that it wasn't
and it was again,
it's what constitutes nanoscale
technology is evolving.
And now we're talking
microelectronics that are nanoscale.
Microelectronics is a
bit of an outdated term.
And I'm excited to see it come back
and I'm excited to see that,
I dunno if you know the
hype cycle ideology,
that things are big hype
and then they fall into a
trough of disillusionment,
then they become popular again.
But the whole time people
are steadily working on them
to improve them and bring
new applications to fruition.
I feel like we're at that point
with nanoscale technology.
And I'm gonna talk a little bit
about how I think that's
gonna impact my industry
and the challenges we're
currently trying to solve
where we look to consortiums
like MIT.nano for solutions
in collaboration with universities
and with commercial partners.
So Lockheed Martin by the numbers,
for those of you who don't
know Lockheed Martin,
we are a global security
aerospace and defense company.
Our largest customer is the US government.
And we employ somewhere
around 60,000 engineers.
Ebbs and flows, but it's
a very large company.
You know, a lot of people come up to me
and say, "Oh, you work at Lockheed,
you must know so-and-so."
30% chance.
You know, I've been around a little while,
so maybe 35% for me.
But the company does a lot of things.
There's a lot of people
across many, many locations.
I was just having a conversation
a minute ago about my site
here in Greater Boston only has 10 people,
but I manage 20 people in Denver
and I have about 200 affiliates
between the Bay Area,
Huntsville, Alabama, Utah,
and a few other places.
So, you know, in a post-COVID world,
it doesn't make as much of a difference,
but we are everywhere.
And we operate four primary business units
that you can see here.
Aeronautics.
MFC, which stands for
missiles and fire control.
RMS and Space.
Space is pretty self-evident,
RMS not so much.
RMS does radar systems,
they do surface ships, they do submarines,
they do some helicopter subsystem.
So that's a hard one to
just understand by the name.
But we like to say that
we cover all domains,
land, air, sea, space, and
now increasingly cyber.
In addition to our core enterprise,
we operate multiple subsidiaries.
And we maintain very large supply chains
with many small business
and commercial suppliers.
So we like to think of
ourselves more holistically as,
you know, the enterprise
plus the affiliates.
So everything we do, every,
you know, the F-35 or satellite system
will have a huge tail of
suppliers and partners
and facilitators that make
the whole thing possible.
So it never just stops at Lockheed Martin.
In addition to that, we
operate internationally,
I think the last chart shows
what percentage of our business
that accounts for.
26%, that's growing.
International is becoming
more and more prominent.
The way that we engage
internationally is changing.
It used to be more hands off.
Now it's more direct engagement
with foreign governments.
And we maintain outposts and partnerships
and affiliations across
a number of countries.
The silhouettes are shown there.
I can tell you that UK is quite large
and Australia and Canada
are also quite large.
Sometimes when we do
international business,
it leads to some really
interesting scenarios.
I like to talk about this one
'cause it's kind of funny.
And this chart probably
makes no sense to anybody.
But one of the things you
do in the defense industry
when you do international business
is something called industrial offsets,
which means that a percentage of the value
of every defense sale has to be matched
with other investments in-country,
and it has to be collaborated
with the governments of those countries.
One example that I worked a few years back
was for the sale of F-35
aircraft in Denmark.
We went to Denmark, we
talked to their ministries,
and they were very interested
in applying some of the sensor
technology from the aircraft
to other industries.
And one in particular
was cold supply chain,
which is really prominent
in the dairy industry.
And their dream was to
have that technology
make it into the US agricultural markets.
So in order to facilitate
this airplane sale,
we had to go back to
the US, talk to the USDA
about where we could apply this technology
to make a big economic impact.
And I remember going to Chicago
to meet with the Dairy
Management Institute.
It's the nonprofit that
does the Got Milk campaigns.
And I'm sitting in their boardroom
and I have representatives
from USDA and the DMI
and a couple other
affiliate organizations.
And we ask them, you know,
"We wanna help solve a
major technical challenge
for the US agricultural industry.
What are your top problems?"
And I remember very distinctly,
he sits back in his chair
and he rubs his chin
and he goes, "Cheese
smugglers." (laughing)
And we just kind of stared
at him for a second,
said, "I'm sorry, could you repeat that?"
And he said,
"Cheese smuggling is a major
problem in this country.
You know, everybody thinks
we have an illegal immigration problem,
but we have an illegal cheese problem.
And many, many people get sick
from bathtub queso fresco."
And I said, "Okay, bathtub, explain."
And he says, "You know,
well, it's like bathtub gin
back during the Prohibition.
People make queso fresco in their bathtubs
and they run it across the border.
And we gotta catch them
before they get it into the supply chain
or else many, many people could get sick."
So that's what I spent
six months working on.
And this was all to sell aircraft.
So this is why I stay at the company.
There's a lot of creative things
that are more art than science.
And if you're someone like me
who likes to have a creative side,
then there's always
something that you can do
that's fun and rewarding
and lets you see some interesting places
and meet some interesting people.
All right, so where are we
today in the defense industry?
Well, Lockheed Martin
and our CEO Jim Taiclet
has set out a strategy
called 21st Century Security.
And this is meant to
address the evolving world
that we live in, which is itself
driven by transformational technologies,
moving towards more of
a digital landscape,
moving to a world where more
assets can do more computation
and communication with each other
and rely less on a hub and spoke model.
So these are the imperatives
that we have set forth
to pursue over the next decade or so
to help bring modern technology
into the way that we operate
from a national security standpoint.
Networked platforms,
this is, the graphic here
you can see talks a little bit to that.
Aircraft talking to
satellites, talking to drones,
talking to ground
platforms, talking to ships,
talking to infantry on the ground.
It's all connected.
And it's not just passing
raw data back and forth,
it's collecting data,
processing it, interpreting it,
sending that information
to another platform
without having to go back
to a central terminal.
So we call this edge computing
and distributed computing.
And this is a major challenge right now
because this is not traditionally
how architectures are designed.
So you are dealing with
legacy communication protocols
like Link 16, which is
used on F-16 aircraft,
that was not at all meant
to operate this way.
And it's tried and true
and they are not gonna get rid of it,
but yet it somehow has to
fit into this architecture
and operate in ways it was
never intended to operate.
So very difficult challenge.
We're also looking at
how do we put more advanced
computing on these platforms
so that we can do more
of that edge processing
and we can reduce latency
and we can reduce size,
weight, and power, or SWP?
So you can not just
have your best computing
on your largest aircraft,
but you could put them
on very small drones,
very small CubeSats and PicoSats.
That's another challenge.
And not just getting the technology there,
but putting the technology
in an environment
where it's not intended to operate.
So it has to experience extreme
fluctuations in temperature
or shock and vibration to put it in space,
or radiation environments
where it has to have countermeasures
to mitigate the effects
of ionizing doses of radiation.
So commercial technology is here,
and defense technology
can sometimes be here
because the gap to bring
that technology into the
relevant environments
is quite difficult.
And there's a quite high bar
that the government puts on
quality and trust in
anything that they field.
They don't like to wing anything.
It has to be extremely high fidelity,
that it will work as intended
because there are high stakes.
So that is something
we're always trying to do,
to close that gap.
And historically, some of those systems
originated within the defense industry
and we could just continue to work them
specifically for our applications.
Today it's not the case.
A lot of the leading technologies
are coming from commercial companies.
This is not their core market.
They're not spending their money
specifically to enable our mission.
We have to figure out
how to work with them
to take commercial technology
that's meant for your iPhones
or for 5G telecommunications
and make them fit into our needs.
And that is why, as part of
the title of this presentation
and something that you'll
see repeated again and again,
we're doing all this work
with commercial companies
to figure out the right impedance match
to form those lucrative partnerships.
So back to this slide,
now talk a little bit about
my role in the company.
I'm part of Lockheed Martin Space,
so the one on the far right there.
And in addition to sitting in Space,
not literally, figuratively,
I work with the corporate
offices at Lockheed Martin.
This is the CTO has his own
division at our enterprise,
which oversees strategic initiatives
for the entire corporation.
So you can think of each business area
as really focused on their
swim lane, on the products
and the missions and the
customers that are relevant
for aircraft or helicopter systems
or rotorcraft, satellites, et cetera.
Corporate looks at things that maybe
don't fall above the line
for any one of those groups,
but are important for
all of them holistically.
They make those strategic investments.
So some of the strategic partnerships,
some of the university engagements,
and then some of the tech
initiatives that don't always
get talked about in the business
areas like microelectronics
fall in the corporate purview.
It's very difficult to
talk to the program manager
of the F-35 about transistor architectures
and gate-all-around and
FinFET versus traditional.
They don't care.
They care about how far can I fly?
What's my ceiling, what's
my weapons payload,
what's my, you know, radar,
electronic warfare capability?
You know, you have to be able
to translate the nitty gritty
into the so what, who cares,
how does it affect the mission,
how does it keep the pilot
safe, et cetera, et cetera.
So understanding how to
do that is difficult.
It's taken me quite a
few years in the company
to figure out the value prop to go from
extremely deep technology
to things that are gonna move the needle
for our national security.
And being able to work
at the corporate level
on the finer detail technology
and then pull that back
into the business areas
where we can talk about mission capability
is extremely important.
So that's why I've made
it a point to straddle
between those two groups
within the company
so that I can be a Rosetta Stone
and translate between mission
speak and technology speak.
And this is just a little
more detail about what I do.
That's me, if you didn't notice
that already. (chuckling)
And these are some of the
things that are in my purview.
Between my facility here,
I'm essentially general manager
for our high mix semiconductor lab
in Billerica, Massachusetts.
And I oversee some engineering
groups out in Denver.
And I manage a hypersonic platforms group
in King of Prussia, Pennsylvania.
So everything from gallium
nitride, thin films,
flexible electronics, specialty coatings,
we even get into engineered
biological materials.
So we source materials
that are derived from modified bacteria
and we apply them to
various optics and coatings
and things like that to determine
if they can improve performance
over non-biological source materials.
Or in the case of things
like rare earth elements
where there's a supply chain problem
or there could potentially be a problem,
we look for alternative
sources of material.
On the computing side,
this moves a little bit
away from microelectronics
and just more into solutions,
where we're doing a blend
of COTS procurement and custom design.
We look at high performance
compute solutions
and architectures.
So you know, if we want to have,
again, starting with the mission speak,
if you want to have broader
coverage of EO-IR observation
of certain latitudes on the planet,
and you wanna be able to
communicate that information
with a certain latency
to your airborne assets
or your ocean based assets
in the South Pacific,
then you need to figure out what type
of data you're gonna be getting,
how much noise you have to filter out,
how fast you have to process it,
what processors are capable of doing that,
how many of them do you need?
Do they have to be co-located?
Can they be distributed?
How do you communicate between
them if they're distributed?
What kind of environmental
conditions do they have
to be modified to survive, et cetera.
So it's a very complicated thing
to walk it all the way back
to knowing exactly what your
technical solution has to be.
And that's what our network architecture
and distributed computing
groups are actively doing
with our program offices
and with our customers.
Hypersonics is a very interesting area.
It is the motherlode of extreme conditions
that you don't find anywhere else
in terms of shock,
vibration, heat, ablation,
plasma fields, all kinds of things
that are new engineering
challenges you have to work around.
I have a slide on this a little later,
so I'll go into that in more detail.
But again, another interesting area.
And the things we develop there,
we also find have relevance
in other places as well.
So usually when you work on
the most extreme of extremes,
you find utility in other places.
I mentioned microelectronics.
We still operate platforms
that have been in use since the 1960s.
And many of them still use compute systems
that are from the 1960s on
180 nanometer CMOS or above.
That's because they were
qualified extensively
back in the day,
and we know they work and we
have plenty of data to prove it
and we continue to use them.
But that mentality cannot persist forever.
So we are very actively looking at ways
to modernize those
capabilities, to not lose any
of the trust and assurance
we currently have,
but to enable our customers
to onboard new capability
because we have more
sophisticated technology
to bring to bear.
And the CHIPS Act has been a
major help from our government
in facilitating collaboration
with the semiconductor
industry to make that possible.
So we're now working
directly with foundries
with assembly and test
capabilities or OSATs.
We're working with catalog part suppliers.
There's been a catalyzation
of support from the industry
for the last year or so
and I think in the next
couple years going forward,
where we can really make strides
and understanding how
we modernize technology
without compromising any of the benefits
of those legacy systems.
I like the quote here, "We go
from airplanes with computers
to airplanes just being flying computers."
I think that's probably
an oversimplification,
but it's quite true.
The electronics in aircraft in years past,
and if you look at the percentage
of total development spend
that is accountable to
electronics in aircraft,
for most of aviation history,
it's been minimal, under 10%.
Now I'd say it's over 40%, closer to 50%.
So they really are flying computers.
I mentioned that collaboration.
These are just a couple
headlines I pulled about areas
where we've been working commercially.
The first one up here is IBM.
We have quite a large
partnership with IBM,
done a lot of work with
Red Hat specifically
to bring AI development
and AI deployment to the edge
in a more efficient process.
We've worked with
NVIDIA, this is maybe one
of our longest-standing
commercial partnerships.
And one of the major areas there
that we've gotten a lot of
progress made is in deploying AI
for some missions like firefighting
and search and rescue
in the Canadian forests.
These are areas that get a lot of support,
especially in states like California
and in Alberta where there these problems
are pretty prominent.
And they're actually,
not only are they solving a challenge,
an environmental challenge
and a challenge that affects human lives
on the civil side, but
they're also quite pragmatic
for implementation
in some of the defense
environments as well.
So this has been a very
lucrative partnership for us.
Third one there is Global Foundries.
I believe that's our CEO there
with Senator Chuck Schumer
and the, I believe,
CTO of Global Foundries
up in Malta, New York.
This is one that I've been part of.
And we are now working
with Global Foundries
on a number of initiatives
to understand the future of
embedded CMOS technologies
and how it can apply to
the defense industry.
Another one you may have heard
of is with General Motors.
We actually worked on
a lunar rover program,
the next generation lunar rover.
This was a really fun
collaboration where, you know,
GM is investing heavily in
electronic automotive technology
and we have a legacy
working on lunar vehicles
and lunar support systems.
And they seem like a mutually
beneficial partnership
for multiple reasons.
There's a lot of information you can read
about future lunar economy
and service models around,
you know, you don't have
to bring your truck to the moon with you,
you go to the truck and you rent,
it's, you know, Avis
on the moon basically.
So not only is technology transforming,
business models are as well,
so that's a pretty interesting one.
And then lastly here, we just
had some public announcements
around working with Microsoft
and figuring out ways
to leverage cloud in more
government environments.
Traditionally it's been
challenging to do cloud
in a fully secure way.
Companies like Microsoft
are changing that.
And once you pull that technology in
and you start to leverage
it, it opens up many doors
of capabilities and collaboration
and workflow efficiencies
that the government
hasn't traditionally seen.
So that's also very exciting.
Not as sexy as a moon rover,
but equally important, if not more.
Okay, nanoscale innovation across domains.
So the two disciplines I
showed on the previous slide
where I do most of my work
over the last few years
are satellite systems
and hypersonic flight.
And I mentioned that they
have a lot of common,
you know, inflection points
or they have some
technology that overlaps.
Although the environments
are kind of different,
you see innovations happening in a lot
of the same areas like
structural materials,
manufacturing processes,
internal and external sensing.
So the types of payloads
and the types of things that
they need are roughly similar,
but the exact details of the
challenges associated with them
will vary from one to another.
And I'll just mention that, you know,
satellite isn't a monolithic term.
Neither is hypersonic flight.
There's many different
classes of satellites,
there's many different
satellite orbital bands,
there's new ones coming online
that I'll talk about in a minute.
Same for hypersonic.
There's multiple hypersonic missions,
multiple vehicle bodies,
multiple, you know,
offensive, defensive, surveillance,
all different types of things.
There's talk about hypersonic vehicles
replacing satellites at some point.
So you know, inside each
of those two categories
you see lots and lots of variation
in what needs to be done.
But at a high level,
those are the two areas
where I'm focused on delivering
state-of-art technology.
About hypersonic flight.
Hypersonic is a term, roughly
means to traveling Mach 5
or a mile a second or faster.
This is something that's been
of increasing importance
over the last couple years.
You probably see a lot of talk
about hypersonic capability in the press.
It's not a capability
that the US has alone,
it's not unique to us is what I'm saying.
It's something where other countries
are developing this at a very fast basis,
and we are as well.
And I think in terms of priorities,
that there are government lists,
microelectronics and hypersonics
are number one and number two.
They trade places time and time again.
But I believe last time I
checked, that was the ranking.
So what are some of the
challenges of hypersonics?
At that speed
you're going to experience
temperatures on your surface
in excess of 1000 C.
There are points where that is higher
and there's points where it's lower.
I can tell you from some of
the things I'm working on
that it's higher
if you're anywhere in
this nose cone region here
up until about the yellow ring there.
And even inside, underneath
all of your thermal protection
and heat sinks and everything like that,
you're still looking at operating
temperatures around 500 C.
I could tell you that mil
spec electronic standards
are maxed out at 200 C.
So we're talking about
putting things in places
that they're not meant to survive in.
So that's a major challenge.
And commercial companies don't want to say
that they can operate in those conditions.
They don't want to supply
you if you tell them
that you're operating on those conditions,
because there's no guarantee on how well
the devices will perform.
In fact, most thermal models
for electronics in those
conditions tap out at 200 C.
So you see the same
performance predictions
at 300 C and 400 C as you would at 200 C
because they just stop, you
know, modeling after that point.
So this has been
something we've discovered
and we're working on.
There's benefits of having the ability
to put things like sensors
and compute capability in
those parts of the vehicle
versus having to put them
near the back of the vehicle
where it's cooler,
or having to surround them with
massive titanium heat sinks
that add weight and affect the performance
of the vehicles themselves.
Another challenge
is that you're gonna
generate a plasma field
when you're traveling that fast.
You're gonna have all
these ionized particles
surrounding your vehicle
and making a sheath.
And that can interfere with your ability
to do things like infrared sensing,
RF communications.
So you can go blind in
terms of your navigation.
You can go blind in terms of communication
with other assets.
And you lose the ability to
sense in certain spectrums.
So there's a lot of work
going into figuring out
how you mitigate that
either from a signal correction standpoint
or possibly even just
mitigating the plasma field
at certain points,
weakening it so that you
can communicate through it.
Ablation and phase change.
So material really starts to
fall apart at those speeds
and at those temperatures.
And you see more and more investment
going into metallic alloys
and manufacturing processes
that can withstand those
temperatures without ablating.
You start to see problems in joints.
So if you don't make your
vehicle air shell monolithically,
those bond points where one
part overlaps with another
are vulnerabilities.
So we're looking at ways
of shoring those up.
And we're looking at new
materials for things like radomes
that allow you to
integrate more seamlessly
so you don't have weak points.
And those materials themselves
have to also be able
to withstand those extreme conditions,
and that has been problematic.
Some of the areas where the
innovations are happening,
in summary, microelectronics,
metal alloys.
So we're actively looking at
new species of metal alloys
that can meet both the extreme temperature
and extreme environment conditions,
but also are scalable for
additive manufacturing processes.
So it's as much a logistical challenge
as it is a technology challenge.
And then things like
sensors, piezoelectrics,
they're all being looked at.
Energy harvesting is a big one right now
because you have all that heat,
you might as well figure out
some way to put it to use.
This one just talks a little
more detail about sensors,
communications, airframes, and simulation.
So I think I touched on all these.
There's a little bit here about why
each one of 'em is important.
So I mentioned putting sensors in places
that are extremely hot.
This really boils down to the ability
to track moving objects
and to have higher fidelity
on your own positioning.
And specifically when you're
not gonna be able to use GPS,
which could be caused by
environmental conditions
or manmade conditions.
But the more you can
look where you're going,
which requires you to be
in very hot environments,
the better off you are in
performing your mission.
If you have to look backwards or sideways
or you have to do turnarounds
and things like that
to see what you're trying to do,
it compromises your ability to perform.
Communications, again, the plasma fields
and human effects,
jamming, things like that.
We have to be able to be self-sufficient
in terms of navigation and IMU capability,
higher precision, things like that.
So this is another area
where a lot of investment is being made
and a lot of calculations are being made
about what kind of
capabilities are needed,
what thresholds have to
be overcome, et cetera.
And we have some partnership
activities going on there.
Airframes, right now
a lot of carbon-carbon
materials being utilized
because of its thermal performance.
But there are limitations in how quickly
and cost-effectively you can
produce using carbon-carbon.
It's known that metallics are much better
for scalable 3D manufacturing,
but there are some challenges around
the characteristics of some
of the more readily available alloys.
There's also some,
this is more forward thinking
and strategic than tactical,
but there's some challenges around
where certain alloy
materials are sourced from
and whether that could
or couldn't be a problem
in the future based on some
geopolitical conflicts.
So all these things get factored in.
We wanna make sure that
in a worst case scenario
the United States has the ability
to manufacture the
hypersonic aircraft it needs
to perform to spec
and without any kind of
supply chain shock or hiccups
that would throw a wrench
in the whole thing.
The last one here I didn't talk about yet,
but I think it's maybe
one of the most important,
and I see this a lot with my team, is that
we make all this progress on a technology
and we get to a point where we need
to test it in a relevant environment.
And then we wait and we wait and we wait.
And then we pay a lot of money
and we do a test and we get
a little bit of data back
and we're not satisfied,
then we wait and we wait and
we wait and we do it again.
And this is because the ability
to test in relevant
environments and in situ
is a bottleneck.
And the rate of technology development
far outpaces the supply
of testing capabilities.
And the reason we can't do
what we do in other fields,
which is just offload some
of that early validation work
to simulation, is because the
fidelity of hypersonic models,
multiphysics models
and specifically
computational fluid dynamics,
doesn't allow us to get
the fidelity we need
to make that triage.
We have to do real world testing.
And if we could overcome that,
then we could more effectively triage
which technologies move forward,
and we could cut the queue down
for these testing
infrastructures from, you know,
something very large
to something much more
compact and manageable.
I think this is a major
area that the industry
has to be investing in
at the same time that the
government is taking action
to increase the supply
of testing capability.
So we're approaching it from
both a supply and demand angle.
But I think having
that higher fidelity simulation capability
will pay many dividends for the industry.
This is another interesting one
I wanna talk a little bit about.
This is on the satellite side.
So for many reasons, both the practicality
of operating at lower orbital altitudes
and some of the challenges
that are emerging,
things like space debris
becoming a problem.
We're seeing a push to move
to a new orbital band
called VLEO or very low LEO.
LEO stands for low earth observation.
These are the lowest
flying satellites in space.
And they're usually the
ones that are doing things
like remote imaging
and taking pictures of the
Earth, things like that
because their altitude allows
them higher image resolution.
450 kilometers, 350, 450
is like the rough range
that this new VLEO band would operate at.
And it's kinda in that gray
area of, it's not quite space,
it's not quite the atmosphere.
So this one's really fascinating
because your traditional satellite,
like this one I have here
that is like a flying box
with solar panels won't
survive in that environment,
because there's so much atmospheric drag
that it needs to be more aerodynamic.
And there's a high
concentration of atomic oxygen
that leads to really fast corrosion.
So if you put something
like a traditional satellite
in this orbit, it would just destabilize
and de-orbit very quickly.
And if somehow it didn't do that,
the payloads would start corroding
and it would become useless very quickly.
So fortunately for
things in this low orbit,
the operating model is more charitable.
So they don't have to survive 10, 15 years
in extreme radiated space.
They can survive for a few
years and be smaller and cheaper
and we can put up new ones for less money,
because, you know, to go
to higher altitude orbits
requires more fuel, and
basically your launch costs
are just significantly higher.
But that doesn't solve
the problem of being fit
to operate in those environments.
So we're looking at things like
how do you build a satellite
that looks more like an
aircraft and is aerodynamic
and has enough thrust
to maintain orbit in a dense atmosphere?
Traditional electronic
propulsion from solar
on satellites won't cut it.
So we're looking at different
methods of doing that.
How do you mitigate the
extreme corrosive effects?
How do you deal with higher electron flux
which messes with your instrumentation?
It also messes with your drag profile,
your solar energy harvesting.
So there's a lot of things
that are changing the way,
it's not just satellites
in a different environment,
it's a whole new class of vehicle.
Here's some of the areas
I'm outlining for VLEO.
Propulsion, as I mentioned.
So something called
atmospheric breathing
electric propulsion or ABEP
is becoming prominent.
This hasn't traditionally
applied to aircraft,
it hasn't applied to satellites,
it's something specific to this domain.
And a lot of work is going into modeling
what the ideal payloads
are gonna look like,
what their size-weight
profiles are gonna be,
what their expected lifetimes are,
thrust performance, et cetera.
So we can understand how
to design a complex VLEO satellite system.
Aerodynamic control is another one.
So there's much more perturbation
that's gonna be incident
on these platforms
than in higher altitude bands.
So a traditional satellite
is not meant to have
that level of fidelity
of attitude correction
and awareness of slight
perturbations in its orientation.
So we really need to up the
sensing game on these platforms
so that they can auto correct themselves,
they can detect a slight
change and correct it
before that change grows
and now they're off their orbital track
or they really get in trouble
to a point where it's not salvageable.
So you have things coming
off a satellite like antennas
and arms and solar arrays
and things like that
that are also very sensitive
to increases in drag
and can bend and snap and break.
So we have to be thoughtful about how we
interlay those payloads onto the aircraft.
One of the areas that my team works on
is flex hybrid electronics.
So taking something that's
traditionally a rigid structure
and making it flexible so
it can withstand more drag
and it can be conformed
around different parts
of the vehicle, maybe wrap
around the edges of the surface
that need to be more aerodynamic
and still perform as needed.
So a lot of changes going on there.
As well as the anti corrosion aspect.
So not only do you have
to resist the drag,
but you have to be able to survive
for the one to two year operating lifetime
without degradation.
And a lot of the laboratory
experiments we've seen
with atomic oxygen are, it's really nasty.
So understanding how we can either build
with different material or
coat with different material
to mitigate corrosion or
slow its effects to the point
where it's negligible
over a two year period
is gonna be extremely important.
Not only understanding what
those coatings might be,
but also how we apply
them in an effective way.
And then lastly, you know, you can tell
that this is something that
I'm really passionate about
is simulation again.
So anytime you operate
in a new environment,
you're gonna get so far and
then you're gonna hit a wall
because, as I mentioned, your
ability to test and qualify
is gonna be your rate limiting factor.
And the more you can apply
modeling and simulation
with sufficient fidelity
and you can explain the fidelity of that,
the faster you're gonna be
able to break through that wall
and you're gonna be able to
transition more technology.
I like to think that the people
who use the technology are
probably the biggest skeptics,
because they don't want to take any risk
because there's really high
stakes of what they do.
And the burden is on us to show them
that this new technology
not only meets their needs,
it doesn't compromise anything
and allows 'em to do things
they couldn't do today,
which keeps the platforms
and their stakeholders, if
there's humans involved,
in even better condition.
So the more we can pull
the thread from technology
through mission analysis
and show the outcome
and explain that outcome
based on the simulated,
the models that go into doing that,
the easier it's going to be.
I think I'm reaching the end here.
I just wanna talk a little bit about ways
to collaborate with Lockheed Martin.
So probably the easiest
way is to work with us
on government funded initiatives.
So the government constantly
puts out opportunities
to develop technologies,
to conduct basic research.
Everything from what we call 6.1,
which is fundamental research,
all the way through high
technology readiness,
so things that are ready
to go into production
and be fielded.
There's different agencies
that focus on different parts of that.
But our job is to shepherd technologies
all the way through that process.
So on the lower TRL or tech
readiness level, we work a lot
with universities,
then we work with small
businesses that are trying
to mature technology,
then we work with commercial
companies that have matured it
and are trying to put
it into manufacturing,
high volume manufacturing.
And then we work as systems
integrators on the backend
to figure out how these
piece parts come together
to form the components
of a larger apparatus.
So the DOD, NASA,
now the Department of
Commerce with the CHIPS Act
all have solicitations that
come out throughout the year.
And Lockheed Martin as
a defense contractor
understands federal
acquisition requirements.
We understand the language
and the contracting modalities
that the government uses.
And we are usually there
to lead those efforts.
But we don't do all the
performance ourselves,
we partner.
So we are always open to collaboration.
And we do countless engagements
with business every week
to understand what they're trying to do,
what the technologies are,
what value they create.
And if we have a winning
opportunity there,
we know that it aligns to
something the government needs,
we're very active in
partnering to pursue some
of these research opportunities.
The other, for larger
companies, is to shape
what we call Joint Technology
Development Agreements
or JDTAs.
This is something to do with some
of the like, larger companies
like Microsoft or Global
where we spend a lot of time talking about
what we want, what they want,
what our win-win
scenarios might look like,
and how we message that,
how we deploy capital
to make those common interests possible.
These are a lot harder to stand up,
but when we do them right,
they have huge power
to change the way technology is deployed.
So I doubt that's gonna
apply to many people here.
But that is another way
that we are focusing
heavily on partnerships.
SBIR, STTR, these are the
small business opportunities.
So these are ones where Lockheed
actually can't participate directly
'cause they're specifically
for small businesses.
But we have a very large
apparatus to advocate
for small businesses.
Many of our suppliers
are small businesses.
Many of the unique
technologies that we work with
come out of small businesses.
And we are very active at
providing letters of support,
being minor performers on
small business-led pursuits
and contracts, where we
maybe do some testing
or we help evaluate a technology
and espouse on the relevance
of how this would help
support a larger system
or help support government missions.
So that one is very applicable, I suspect,
to a lot of folks here.
And we have people whose
sole job in the company
is to maintain portfolios
of small businesses
which we support
and monitor for future
supply chain integration.
So that is, I would encourage
anyone here to reach out,
if you have a small business,
you support a small business,
and you're looking for ways
of aligning more closely
with the primes in the defense industry.
That's not unique to Lockheed,
that's something that the
entire defense industry
has made a point of supporting.
And I know it's very important
to our government as well
that the large companies
support the small companies
and help usher them along and
pull the technology along.
And then finally, as university research.
So MIT has been a longstanding
partner of Lockheed Martin.
We have our University Research Initiative
that is funded annually.
We also have a few other, that's
a corporate led initiative.
We also have some of the business area-led
university initiatives.
These are just standing programs
where we allocate research
money to university efforts.
And then you have specific
programs that are more ad hoc,
when, you know, they need
a technology for program X
and it's coming out of a university,
they can just go directly fund
research and development there.
But this makes up a major
part of our R&D backbone.
And it is one that Lockheed
takes a lot of pride in.
I mentioned I've been around for a while.
When I first started here
was the Nano Initiative and
the MIT Energy Initiative.
Since then I've done work
in artificial intelligence
and with CSAIL and some of
the other groups out of MIT.
Now working with the
folks like Tomas Palacios
and Brian Wardle on materials
and microelectronics
and now being part of MIT.nano.
So where Lockheed is focusing
at different points in time changes.
But knowing that we
have a partner like MIT
is something that we maintain
a consistent level of participation in.
So, and I'll end on that note.
You know, my team and my
colleagues at corporate
are really excited about
being part of MIT.nano.
And we see it as a catalyst
for even broader collaboration
on all those different modalities
that I just mentioned there.
So with that, I'd like to thank everybody
for putting up with me for
the last 40 minutes or so.
Hopefully you learned
something interesting here,
or if you didn't, just enjoyed the time.
And if you have any questions,
I'm happy to field them now.
Thank you.
(audience applauding)
- So any questions for Keith?
- I saw a hand there.
- Yes, please.
- So I have a question about the shortage
of actual testing facilities
that you described.
And what is that arising from
and what's the solution to that?
I would think that that would
be a really high priority
for Lockheed Martin to fund that,
'cause that's really the bottleneck
getting something to market.
So I was just curious about that.
- Yeah, hypersonics have not
traditionally been an area
where, I mean, it's
pretty much a new domain.
So a lot of the
longstanding test facilities
that you see at national
laboratories, things like that,
are not oriented for that.
Some of them are, we have
like high speed sled testing,
and you can do some laboratory replication
of the environments,
but it was never designed
specifically for that.
And now all of a sudden it's
a domain everyone cares about
and we can't innovate fast enough.
So the demand is outpacing the supply.
Same thing for in situ testing.
You know, we're developing the platforms
to travel at hypersonic speed.
At the same time,
we're developing additional
hypersonic platforms
to test the things that
go into the other ones.
So it's kinda like, you have
to innovate on your measurement
at the same time you're
innovating on your solution,
which is why the government
is investing pretty heavily
in things like sounding rockets
that are surrogates for hypersonic flight.
And there is a lot of
investment going into updating
and refreshing, expanding
those lab infrastructure capabilities
so that the supply catches up.
- Other questions?
- Thank you, this was such
a great talk and overview.
- [Moderator] One second, sorry.
- Oh, I'm sorry.
Yes.
- Yeah, thank you for the
great talk and overview.
I was curious, so you mentioned,
like high temperature microelectronics
being used in hypersonic
and other applications.
And in those situations you have,
some of the integrated circuits
aren't designed for that temperature.
So do you feel that there's
any one particular area
that's of focus?
Is it the power amplifier,
is it the sensor?
Do you think it just needs
an entire reevaluation
across all the materials and devices?
- We're looking at all of them.
So the low hanging fruit I would say
is the analog components.
So things that are sending
and receiving signals.
It's more most advantageous
to have those at the point
where they can have
the best field of view.
You know, if they're communicating
or sensing another asset, you
want to have them unimpeded.
'Cause if they're are impeded, you know,
I'm trying to sense you, but
I can only look over here,
then I have to turn to look at you,
which creates problems basically.
So it makes my profile bigger,
it throws me off my course,
I burn more fuel, all
kinds of things like that.
So those RF components
are low hanging fruit.
But there's a lot of work,
as you start developing that
system and designing it,
you know, okay, the power
amplifiers are okay,
low noise amplifiers, high
noise amplifiers, switches.
Now you're trying to
take that analog signal
and convert it to digital
signal and do some calculation.
Now you have extreme noise
from the heat over your lines
so you're looking at better cabling.
Then you're looking at your mixing
and everything on the back end, right?
And you start to think,
well, what if I pulled
more of that forward?
Then I don't have to send
signal over a long cable
where I have more noise incursion, right?
So very quickly you go
from the low hanging fruit
to realizing this would
be even better if I pulled
more of that digital mixed
signal stuff upfront too.
So we can't just focus on that.
We have to look at the
entire microelectronic chain,
and then figure out what
the optimal distribution
from a geographic location
perspective is on the vehicle,
and then innovate to make that possible.
And then in parallel to that,
you know, the power devices
and actuation devices,
we're also running the
models right now to show
that these are gonna become bottlenecks.
So those are being developed in parallel
even though they're separate
from that sensing chain
that I just talked about.
So it's one of those things where I feel,
from my perspective, I see
a lot of parties waking up
to this challenge at the same time.
And some of them are gonna
rally around the thing
that is their core competency.
So you might have RF groups
rallying around that,
power device groups rallying around that.
And that's great.
We're trying to take the perspective of,
we're standing on the
hill seeing all of it
and we're trying to bring
all the pieces together
to make sure the things
people are focusing on
come together holistically
to help us reach that end solution state.
- I do wanna ask whether
AAA applies on the moon
if you're renting a car.
(Keith chuckling)
It could be for afterwards.
We have a lot of startups around
MIT.nano where I, you know,
I work with Vladimir.
And I'm curious if you
could expand a little bit
upon what criteria
maybe you're looking at,
if you were writing letters of support,
what that might mean, in case
there's anybody in the room
who would be interested in that.
I thought a little more detail
might help us understand
when to approach Lockheed
about an opportunity.
- Yeah, so the one challenge
that we see the most with
working with small businesses,
working with commercial
businesses in general,
because of the nature
of the defense industry
is we have to make sure that
there aren't export control
issues around something.
So if you're working on a technology
and you don't have a
workforce with US citizens
that can work on things that
are potentially classified
or sensitive, that is
gonna be a problem for us.
So there are certain things
where we just need US
nationals supporting it.
This is purely mandated
from the government.
It's from a potential security standpoint.
So we're just following guidelines there.
But in a lot of cases we
do work with companies
where there are certain
subsets of the workforce
who can work with us on
specific applications.
And that's fine.
We just work with 'em to make sure
that the right firewalls are in place.
I would say that's the biggest hurdle
or the biggest thing that would stop us
from doing everything we want
to do with small businesses.
But it's one that we often work around.
And there's a couple companies
we're talking to right now
that are MIT spin-outs.
You know, we don't just
work across the board.
We find specific things
that are applicable
and we align the right
people on both sides,
and then we can actually
start working together well.
So I'd say taking the
time to figure that out
and, you know, knowing, okay,
you want to approach Lockheed
to talk about your technology
for hypersonics, right?
Make sure that you can talk to us
about how you can work
with us on that technology
without violating any export
control or sensitivity issues.
- Other questions?
Other questions?
A quick question on,
you haven't mentioned
radiation-hardened electronics.
I assume that's also an issue.
- Yes. (laughing)
Definitely an issue for space, absolutely.
For strategic systems,
so things that are domestic intercepts,
things like that are also required too.
Think about, like ICBM defense,
missile defense capabilities,
they have high radiation requirements.
So it's not just space.
But yeah, in my discipline
that's a big deal.
So looking at doing radiation hardening
by design is expensive and time consuming.
So you have to build redundancies
and things like that into
your hardware and software
to mitigate radiation effects.
If we could figure out how to do that
on the packaging scale,
so your electronics stay as they are
but you just package them differently
and the packaging stops
radiation from permeating,
that would be huge.
But we haven't cracked that nut yet.
It's, you know, hasn't
substituted rad-hard by design
or rad-hard by process.
Same with thermal management.
We're getting into a lot
of challenges with thermal.
And thermal's traditionally addressed
at the structural level,
so you have heat pipes
and things like that
that wick away heat.
We're finding we have to move
more towards the packaging
and the devices themselves,
processes and design changes
in the die of the electronics
all meant to keep the
device from overheating
or to efficiently move heat away
so that it can continue to operate.
Otherwise have to throttle down devices
and we lose performance, so.
- So if we could do electronics
without any semiconductors,
that would be kind of good.
- That would be ideal.
(both laughing)
- We do have ideas.
- And you could
produce them at scale.
(both laughing)
- Oh yeah, oh yeah, yeah, yeah.
Last question, given the time,
we already spent a lot of it.
So you mentioned one of
your favorite examples
of how to utilize an offset,
and how to engage in essentially
any project at all possible,
just to make sure that other businesses
of Lockheed can indeed
do their performance.
And you mentioned the cheese smuggling
as being one of those specific ones.
Any other ones come to mind?
'Cause it does sound like the opportunity
is completely open there.
If we can suggest to you
a fantastic technology,
has nothing to do with any
of the ones you mentioned,
that could be grown into
a business in some country
that might be focusing
on cheese or otherwise.
- Absolutely.
It's one of my favorite
facets of Lockheed because it,
you know, the door's
really open for anything,
like you said.
And some countries not so much, you know,
their priority is if
we're gonna buy airplanes,
we want to make parts of
those airplanes in-country.
Others it's more, you
know, it's less specific
to the thing they're buying.
They just say, we really
care about desalination
or we care about agriculture, aquaculture.
So one of my other examples
is we actually created
a spin-out called Forever
Oceans that was in, you know,
we spun it out, our venture
fund invested in it.
They did mobile aquaculture.
So they would have these geodesic pens
with GPS tracking technology,
and they would put little
hatchling fish in them
and they would set 'em
adrift in the ocean.
They would follow the ocean gyres
and make this large circle.
And by the time they came back,
the fish were fully adults.
And they found that
by having them in the open ocean like that
and with that high fidelity tracking,
they were healthier fish.
You know, there was, it was a big deal.
And countries in the Middle East
and southeast Asia were
really interested in this.
So again, nothing to do with anything
with our core business,
but yeah, there's a lot of
opportunities like that.
- How's the company doing now?
- They're doing great!
Yeah.
(Vladimir laughing)
I think they are a supplier to some
of the really high end sushi,
you know, like Nobu, place like that.
So it sounds like they're doing great.
And the CEO got to move out to Hawaii.
And you know, what a hard life out there.
(Vladimir laughing)
- Keith, thanks a ton.
- Yeah, thank you.
(audience applauding)