My name is Tomás, and I'm a
high school student in
Chile. My story with MIT CW
began when my classmates and I were developing
a
school innovation project: a
phytopharmaceutical first-aid kit. This kit was going to be
implemented in
school nursing units, allowing us to
address students'
health problems. The
problem we encountered while developing this
research was that we lacked
the necessary
pharmacology knowledge. That's when the
MIT CW course on Principles of Pharmacology came along.
This allowed me to gain a foundation in
pharmacology, and, I believe even more importantly, to
share this knowledge with
my classmates. I think what I
value most about MIT CW is the wide variety of
content available; for me, it's the ultimate
expression of the democratization of
knowledge.