Welcome everyone. Today I am joined by
professor Rama who is a professor of
practice in AI and machine learning here
at MIT Sloan. My name is Michelle Lee.
I'm the director of business analytics
and we're really excited to have a
conversation with Rama and his journey
here at MIT. So to start Rama, could you
please uh introduce yourself to the
audience and tell us about how you
arrived here at MIT? Yeah, sure. First
of all, Michelle, thanks for having me
here. It's great to be here. Um, so I'm
actually an MIT alum myself. Um, I grew
up in India. Then I came to MIT for
graduate school. Uh, I got my masters in
PhD in operations research here. Uh, and
then I went on to industry. I spent a
number of years at Mckenzie. Uh, and
then I got bitten with entrepreneurial
bug. Um, so I was essentially an
analytics entrepreneur for 20 plus
years. Um, I was involved in a bunch of
startups. uh all all these startups the
common thread was that they would
identify an interesting business problem
uh which seemed amendable to a sort of
an analytics data modeling sort of
approach uh we would build a solution we
would take it to market and then we
would you know try to convince people to
use it and get value from it after doing
it a bunch of times um I had the
opportunity to join the faculty here at
Sloan uh as part of the operations
research and statistics group uh so at
Sloan I'm a professor of the practice as
you mentioned uh and I teach courses
broadly in the data science, machine
learning, deep learning areas. Um, and
my uh research really focuses on how do
you take predictive AI and generative AI
and make it really useful and practical
for business decision makers and
technical leaders in businesses. That's
really my primary focus. I do advise a
number of large companies and a number
of startups on how to essentially build
intelligent products and services. Wow.
How did you get started with Gen AI?
because genai hasn't existed for that
long, right? Um what was your path
there? Well, actually um as I mentioned
earlier, I teach courses in deep
learning and data science, broadly
speaking. And one particular course that
I've been teaching for about four years
now is a course called hands-on deep
learning. And as folks might know,
generative AI is actually built on deep
learning. It is in fact an application
of deep learning. And so since we were
teaching deep learning uh we got exposed
to generative AI very early on. We were
sort of teaching about generative
modeling and generative AI well before
Chad GPD hit the mainstream. Of course
we like everyone else were super
surprised uh at the reaction that Chad
GPD evoked in the public. Uh and and
since then uh we have just been tracking
the research we have been following the
applications. we've been seeing the
diffusion of this technology into sort
of businesses and so on. And so I have
essentially sort of um gotten sucked
into this rabbit hole in a big way. Um
and so I spent a lot of my time keeping
up with the technology and then
specifically thinking about all right
this sounds really cool and exciting.
How do we make it practically useful to
businesses? Uh often times executives
come to me and say uh you know things
are changing so fast uh should we you
know stand on the sidelines and wait for
the dust to settle or should we sort of
dive in and see what's going on? How do
we dive in without taking undue risks?
So these are all questions that to
answer properly you need to be standing
at the intersection of the technology
and business and therefore bring a very
pragmatic lens to the world bank. So
that's sort of what I do most of the
time when I'm not teaching. Uh but uh I
hope that gives you a sense for how I
got pulled into Gai. Yeah, that's great.
And well, you are teaching you're
teaching companies for example. Could
you give us an overview of your course,
the hands-on deep learning course and
how it evolves over the semester and
what do students experience in the
course? Oh yeah, absolutely. Um so
hands-on deep learning is a very
interesting course because first of all
it's a course that's situated in the
business school yet it actually is quite
programming heavy so one might think on
the surface that you know business
school students MBA students perhaps uh
you know are not that interested in
programming uh but what I saw in the
early years when I joined the Sloan
faculty is that there's a fair number of
people coming to Sloan in the various
graduate programs who are sort of not
content content with just reading about
things. They actually want to build
things. And so we felt that there was
indeed demand and value for having a
course which not only teaches you how
these things work but actually shows you
how to build things that work. Every
lecture ends up being you know maybe
half of it is sort of a traditional
lecture and then the the second half
ends up being you know we will
essentially you know fire up a a Jupyter
notebook or a collab notebook and then
do some live programming in front of
everybody. Um and I think and they can
see the the the model or the system
essentially taking shape before their
very eyes and that has a very huge
impact on people particularly those who
may not be very used to programming
because they can see that you know even
people like me who have been programming
for a long time we will make mistakes we
will course correct we will sort of
figure it out as we go and I think all
of it is part of the ethos of the class
um so I actually tell students in the
very first lecture that my promise to
you is that if you have a great idea for
a product or service you You don't have
to call your techie friend for help. You
can roll up your sleeves and build the
000 word version of the thing yourself
and then you can go from there. So in
some sense the course could literally be
called AI for builders uh as opposed to
just AI for managers and I think it is
for that reason uh for instance that
like the MBAN students find it super
interesting because MBAN students are
builders um you know they're not content
with just reading about things. They
actually want to build things. Uh they
want to make a difference to the world.
Um so that's really what the course is
about and I guess the final thing I want
to add is that um the course is
extremely action-packed in the sense
that we go from zero to the cutting edge
of AI in literally 12 lectures uh which
means that things happen at a dizzying
pace number one uh and number two um you
know very often we have these live demos
in the class where you know we will
build these things in front of everybody
else and then we'll just put it to the
test in front of everybody. No canned
demos. These are all live demos in the
wild. And I think that's all part of the
mix that makes the course very exciting
to not just the students but also to the
people like me who teach it. Could you
give us an example of a live demo? Oh
yeah, sure. So uh for for instance when
I teach um how to do uh image
classification which is a computer
vision problem.
uh you know what what we do is we
actually you know we web scrape uh you
know 100 handbag images from the
internet another 100 handbag images of
shoes sorry image of shoes from the
internet and then we say okay with these
200 images can we actually build a shoe
handbag classifier and we build it from
scratch in front of everybody and then
once I build it and the and the model is
ready say 20 minutes in I invite a shoe
or a handbag from the class so we
actually have students come in with
their shoes or their handbag and they
literally you know put in front of the
camera and see if it works. Uh
fortunately the last four years it has
worked every single time but I will I
will confess that till it actually works
I am a little nervous. You never know
right. Yeah. Very cool. And is
everything can you talk about the
technology stack is everything done in
Python? Yes. Uh the course is 100%
Python. Uh we uh do everything using uh
Google Collab. Okay. Uh which gives you
access to GPUs. Uh we also actually you
know allow the students to subscribe to
not the free tier but a paid tier. Sloan
will you know take care of those costs
so that students have access to more
powerful GPUs for their work. uh and we
so far we have been using a keras uh
which is a very popular uh deep learning
framework and I want to say that the the
final project the students complete in
the course they're very exciting and I
I'm always super thrilled to see the the
way in which students take the things
that they've learned in the classroom
and then apply it to actually build
something which is you know very
significant and often substantial. Uh
and in the past students have talked to
me about actually taking what they have
done in their final projects and
creating a startup out of it. Well, you
would be the perfect person to talk to
about startups. Um well, I I' I've done
my fair share of startup mistakes. So,
yes, I have something to offer certainly
on that front. Um so, what do you see
for the future for Gen AI and deep
learning? Yeah, that's a very difficult
and profound question, Michelle. So
first of all I do think that there is a
lots of things going on in deep learning
that have nothing to do with generative
AI and those applications are in my
opinion you know unaloyed good things
meaning you know if you if you look at
things like uh protein folding right we
have solved protein folding alpha fold
uh and there are so many incredibly
beautiful and successful applications of
deep learning so that is going to
continue to accelerate I have no doubt
about it and I'm all for it now
generative AI is different in the sense
that um incredibly powerful, very
versatile uh and we are seeing massive
impact, positive impact from genai uh in
terms of you know uh healthcare and drug
discovery and things like that. Um but I
think we should also be fully cognizant
of the fact that um you know given its
ability to do various knowledge work
tasks uh that there might be negative
impacts on employment and jobs and the
economy. uh of course we also we have
heard about the fact that these are very
energy guzzling systems so there's going
to be an impact on carbon and emissions
in the environment so so I think with
generative AI I think massive positive
impact is certainly possible but there
is some possibility of negative impact
as well and we as decision makers and
builders and modelers and so on I think
we need to sort of have a very holistic
360 view of what's going on so that we
sort of make the right decisions and
steer things in the right action
generative AI can do a lot of things
which um I feel that maybe students
don't have to learn anymore um so you
know Arvin Aran of Princeton had a great
framework for thinking about this and he
talked about how there are essential
skills and incidental skills we should
look at what we are teaching and we say
okay what is essential and what is
incidental and we should make sure that
students absolutely learn the essential
skills that they don't short
shortcircuit their learning by using
genai to sort of do those things but the
incidental stuff I think it's fine they
can use ji for it and now what is
incidental what is obviously the
important question and I think the
answer varies from discipline to
discipline but I think we all have to
really think about it carefully u and so
for instance if you take something like
machine learning um generative AI
systems can essentially you upload a
data set it can easily do random forest
or gradient boosting or any of the
standard methods um so the question
becomes if If you want to just use these
systems as opposed to build these
systems, do you really need to know the
nth level of detail of all the ways in
which these algorithms work? Or should
you really be focused on how do I get
the right data to feed these systems?
Once the system builds a model, how do I
actually uh evaluate the model? How do I
test the the kick the tires in the
model? How do I make sure it's ready for
deployment? How do I make sure it's not
perpetuating bias? How do I make sure
that it doesn't collapse with the with
one wrong example when you start to
deploy? Those are all very important
questions. So I think over time we're
going to gravitate towards um you know
these kinds of very important things
which are not quite amenable to LLMs and
genai yet um and make sure that we
reflect that in the way we teach. Great
well thank you so much for your time
today um and thank you for listening to
Rama and see you next time. You're very
welcome Michelle. It was great to be
here and I enjoyed the conversation.
Thank you. Thank you. Hi everyone. Thank
you for watching. If you like this
video, check out our other videos in the
series where I interview influential
professors at MIT Sloan. If you would
like to learn more about the Master
Business Analytics program, we also have
a playlist where you can see more videos
about the admissions process, student
life, and the program overall.