My mom has really been my rock.
A woman who didn't have –
who has an elementary school education,
but so wise in so many areas of her
life. A role model for me and many.
She has been an inspiration,
certainly always pushing me
to strive for more. To aim for greatness.
To never settle.
My name is Erika Ramirez.
I currently live in Texas,
but I'm originally born in Caracas,
Venezuela.
I am first-generation to attend college.
Education was seen as something
definitely to aim for, to do.
My parents
didn't have the ability to do so.
So my parents always – were always focused
and made it a big deal
for us to stay in school,
to go to school, to go to college,
to aim for greater and higher.
I remember I was married,
I went to school half of the time.
I worked half of the time. Then kids came.
So then I took a big pause in school.
And then I was a mom, a full-time mom.
So it was not
until my kids were a little older
that I went back to school
and I had to finish school.
It was kind of me paving the way,
you know, as I navigated motherhood and,
you know, being a wife, being a full-time
mom, full-time
wife, and and working
full-time and going to school full-time.
My kids are back home in Texas,
and I'm here,
I travel back and forth every weekend.
So I see them on the weekends.
It's intense.
And I think, I hope
that they appreciate what mom is doing.
I think that they do because I hear them
talking to their friends,
you know, in the background, like,
“Oh, mom goes to MIT.”
“Mom is, you know, stopped work.”
“And she's going to school full-time.”
And, you know, “Mom is in her mid/late 40s.”
“And, you know, if she can do it,
we can do it.”
So it's inspire them to know
that really there's no age limit.
You can do anything
you set your heart and mind to.