so okay so let's start so so I'm J and
uh uh so today I will give the lecture
about Starks for batch NP or batch
argument so uh okay so so this lecture
is about a bch argument um
and uh it has many different names such
as barks
so or you can also call it snarks for
batch
andp so um so B is are very basic
Concept in computer science so basically
if you have multiple items and you want
to collect them together then you can
call this collection a batch so uh there
are similar ideas in for example in
programming so there are concept like uh
batch processing and the so it's a very
uh common concept so in this lecture uh
we will talk about uh the batch argument
so it's it's a notion of batch in the
proof system
so uh firstly let me this uh Define what
is a b
argument so definition um so a bars a
bar is uh is a two of
algorithms
um so it consist of a uh generator and a
approver and a wifire
algorithm and uh with the following
syntax so at the very beginning the
generator will generate some CRS so it
will take some security parameter as
input and generate some
CRS and both of the approver and the
wifire is given access to This Ss
throughout of the pro of the
protocol so instead of proving one
statement time the batch proof allows
the prover to convince the verifier that
a batch of the statement is true so for
example uh so let's fix uh uh MP
language l so the L is uh Define as
follows and the prover tries to convince
the wif fire that uh a list of instance
from X1 to XK
so the pro has this list of statements
and he wants to convince the wifire that
all of those statements are in this this
MP language
l so this is the statement the prover
wants to convince the
wif and uh the proof is a single R
message
pip and also the prover also has the NP
winess for this uh uh X12 XK so let's
denote the NP witness as W12 WK so those
are the NP
witness
okay so now
um so as a so we say such a proof we say
such a bar is sync if it satisfies the
following
property so second is is defined as uh
the size of the proof is uh smaller than
the total length of the
widness so can anyone see why we require
this yes yes right exactly uh so we
require this this because uh a trivial a
trib uh proof system uh could we could
have the approver to just send off the
NP witness to the warier then the proess
will be K times w
so second this require this and uh and
as any proof systems we require the
completeness and the soundness
so so completeness requir uh for any
only study generated proof it will
always be accepted and uh the
soundness okay and
the and the soundness is defined as
follows
so the S says uh if if the statement is
not true then any cheating prover
shouldn't find a cheating proof so it
means uh so so if this is not
true then for any uh nonuniform uh PBT
cheating improver we have the we have
this
property so we
require so the cheating Pro is uh given
the CRS send by the CRS generator and we
required to send a proof Pi star so Pi
star is the cheating proof and we
require the probability that the proof
is accepted by this wi fire is
negligible
so I guess you already learned about the
concept the definition of the proof
systems this just a recouple for the
definition so do we know uh so uh any
questions about this definition
so uh now some of you might wonder why
we care about such a proof system
because such proof system is clearly a
subass so such a statement is clearly a
subass of MP so why we care about them
so the so the reason is as suggest
mentioned so batch is a very basic
concept so this is a just a notion of
batch uh batch the notion of batch in
the proof systems and the similar
concept has been studied in other areas
in cryptography such as signatures so
there is a uh signature scheme called
aggregated Signature so it allows you to
aggregate multiple signatures together
to a short signature then you only need
to verify the short signature to ensure
all the signatures can be verified so so
there is
also a smilar notion uh studied in
interactive proofs and it's called a
batch interactive proof
and uh so such a such a bark also has
many applications uh so in the next
lecture so yo will tell you how to use
it to build snars for all
ofp and
uh uh in fact there are many
constructions of snars 4p up to now so
from various assumptions and uh uh there
are different construction but all of
those constructions are uses this spks
uh as a building block in it
and uh indeed yeah is sound or is that
possible uh that's a good question so
there's a reason work shows if you can
get
statistical uh so you can get statical
Parks then you can build some witness
some some statistical witness in
distinguishability yeah you can yeah so
we don't know the we don't know the
exact answer yet
uh and uh so and actually there is a
technical reason why we study such a
bark why we study bark so this is the I
will briefly mention it but I will not
go into detail of this uh lower Bond so
this is the work by gent and
weeks so they show that uh I will not
describe exactly the uh impossibility
result so they show some impossibility
result about snarks in general
so they show it is
a it is impossible to
uh impossible to build
a to build a snarks for uh any for any T
hard
language uh with proof size
uh significantly less than log T so so
what does it mean uh so so here we say
uh a language is T hard if it takes T
time to decide this language so for
example uh for General MP language with
uh winess lens W then
[Music]
um then usually you all take two to the
W time to decide this language so by
this uh impossibility result they they
are saying it is uh very hard to build
snarks for General MP language uh if the
proof size is uh significantly less than
W so basically snar 4 MP is very hard to
build and uh and here the impossibility
is only holds for very good assumptions
so they call they call those assumptions
falsifiable assumption and basically uh
good assumptions such as uh learning
with arrow assumption are foral viable
so so I want to mention this because
um uh indeed if you want to so if we
consider barks then the language we are
then the this language the language we
are proving
sorry so if we want to consider barks
then the language we are proving is the
following language indeed so the
language Pro tries to convin verifier is
the language L uh product K times so it
simply of all of X1 to
XK such that all of X1 to
XK is in this language l so so what's
the time to decide this
language uh do anyone
else St yes yes right right uh great so
that's correct so to decide this
language we only need to uh take K * 2
to the W because you only need to uh
decide whether each XI is in L or not
and if one of them is not in L then you
then you know this language you know
this instance is not in this language
so so the point is if you take a if you
take this T in inside this uh into this
G WIS impossibility it shows that it is
very hard to build snar for H proof size
significantly less than log T but log T
is uh uh is roughly roughly the size of
w
so so it only shows is is very hard to
build a snark for proof that
significantly less than W but this is
signicantly enough so I mean if we can
build a snar with uh if we can build a
box for with proof size W it doesn't
contradict to into X but it is still
succinct because W is already uh
significantly less than K *
W okay uh any
questions okay so in this lecture uh the
main the we want to prove is the is the
following so there exist a contstruction
of bars
uh for learning with
arrow and uh the proof size is
uh
yeah so the proof size is
a part of uh sorry
so the proof size is dominated by
the the proof size is dominated by the
uh circuit the relation circuit size so
roughly you can think uh if we consider
3 sat8 instance then almost this uh this
C is almost the same as the lens of w
because the circuit is shallow yeah and
the and the verification time
so uh right so so the proof size is
almost uh close to the close to this W
because the log K term is small yeah and
the verification time
is
yeah so the verification time is K times
uh one of the instance
uh and uh plus some addition term so the
additional term so the first term only
depends on the total length of the
instance so which is K time
x so because we have K instances and
each of each of the instance has l
x so the additional term doesn't depends
on the uh instant side the total length
of the instant size so it only depends
on log
K uh the size of c and the Lambda
yeah so so the uh so in fact there are
more structure about the wifire
algorithm so in uh the wifire the
verification algorithm can be decomposed
to two parts the first part will only
take the all of the instance as input
and pre-processing it to Output some
very small state then the uh so after
the pre-processing the online phase will
take the state from the pre-processing
algorithm and it will verify the pro in
a very short time so the online phase
doesn't depends on the it doesn't depend
on
K I will come to this point
later so this is the m Ser I want to
prove uh so next yeah
sorry the number of lines the
of of yeah so you want
to K so K
much it's K much ler
than uh lens of oh right so K is you can
think K is a is a polinomial in W yeah
usually yeah because you want the pro to
be a polom algorithm then you can only
consider polinomial K
so so Pol W then this construction is
only exct if like the Pol in C is
small uh right yes
yeah uh right so in fact there is a so
there is a way to generically put of
strength this to uh remove the
dependence on the S on the size of the
circuit to make it even smaller to make
it only depends on the winess size and
so but that we I use the uh the things
in the next lecture by so you can
yeah okay so any
questions okay so uh so next I will show
you
how to construct this
bars uh so the if I directly show you
the construction it will be very
complicated so I will show you uh a
first initial attempt to do the
construction and gradually added the
building blocks to the construction
okay so the so our starting point is the
Kens protocal uh actually it's a
simplified version of K
so so initially uh the prover so the
prover has uh
K so it has a k instance and winess so
W1 to
WK sorry X1 to
XK and uh the pro is going to use uh PCP
to generate the PCP for all of those uh
uh for all of those uh instance so he
applied the PCP Pro algorithm to it and
obtain a PCP proof which is a long
stram so this is the first uh first PCP
proof for X1 and W1 uh and he does the
same for the second instance and witness
server so
PCP so do do any of you remember what is
PC key
uh or do I need to recall
it okay so so PCP is a
so a quick uh quick recall what is PCP
so PCP is
uh so
PCP
um so uh let's see PCP uh for
NP so PCP for NP is a pair of algorithm
uh so the prover so the prover has some
X and W which is the MP instance and
witness and he can uh generate long
proof long PCP
proof and the so this is the pro
algorithm for PCP and there is a PCP
wire fire so the wire fire will read uh
so this PCP string is some binary string
so it contains zero and on and the Wii
will sample some uh random coordinates Q
so the let's say the size of the PCP is
L and the Q is a subet of indices
so the so the uh PCP wifer will
check uh it will take
the uh the instance X and the query
queue and the PCP uh in the in the
subset queue and to where to and then it
uh decides to accept or reject okay so
that's the PCP
and uh we require the uh so the complain
says if x and W is in the language then
the proof should be accepted by the Wii
and the sound n
says so the sound says um so for any X
so if X is not in L then uh for
any so for any PCP string uh PCP PCP
star
we have the the probability that the Y
accept is some funed by some
constant so the randomness is over q and
the is B by some so so here uh we can
always do some parel repetition to
amplify the winess
sorry to amplify the
soundness so if we do the par repetition
Lambda times then the any so we can
amplify any constant uh s this Arrow to
L to Lambda so then we can set it to be
uh two to the minus the order of
lamb and the cost of doing this is to uh
is to blow up the size of the query by
uh
Lambda right so so we can so we can
always assume with the generality that
there exist a PCP for NP well the uh quy
complexity is roughly Lambda times
uh polog
C and the the sun this arrow is Du to
the uh roughly two to the minus B so we
will use this kind of
PCP uh with this query complexity and
the yeah there are PS with the size
of need po C term Oh you mean this term
yeah uh so that uh that's a good
question so it's possible that you can
get rid of the so for example if you
have a very good query complexity then
maybe you don't have this term uh but in
this work I I only so we will need some
additional structure about the PCP and I
only know at least I know it holds for
the
algebraic construction from this r m
code but I don't know if it holds for
General other constructions
PCP
so all right so I'll use this PCP uh so
now now we have K PCP streen and uh we
have a wiif
fire so can you remind how
big right right uh good question so so
the so this is so let's say this is a p
P for NP language L and the NP language
is defined in this
way okay so it has a relation circuit
C right and the the then the lens of the
L so L of L is some part in
C the circuit
size uh again it's possible that you
have use some more efficient PCP
construction to uh I think there exist a
PCP such that this L is almost uh almost
uh near near near in the size of the
circuit
yeah so
okay so we are use this PCP and uh uh so
we use some H function and we will put
the H key in the CRS so the CRS will
contain the H key let's say it's
HK and uh we are going to uh look at so
this PCP are uh so there are binary
strings for each coordinate uh there
binary values in each coordinate and we
are going to use this has function to
has each column of this
PCP of those pcps so that means I will
take the first bit of each PCP string
and the concatenate concatenate them
together and has them using a h
function so I I apply a h function
function here
uh
so to the to the First Column and I get
some H value
H1 and I will do the same thing for the
second
column uh and I can so I can get
H2 so for each column I will har it and
uh so basically so for
the for each column I to get some H
value so if the length of the PCP is L
then I get L values
okay so and this variant of uh K
protocol work as follows so I first send
all of the uh H values from H1 to
HK uh sorry H1 to HL for each
column and uh then I will have the
wifire to send one single piece P
query so a PCP query uh remember is a
subset of
indices okay so so this is one single PP
query for so I mean it's a PCP query for
one of the state one of the PCP string
and uh finally I will uh open the quar
column for this H function for those H
function
okay so so what do I
mean
so so this is uh so you can view this uh
uh PCP string as a matrix so this Matrix
has a uh uh L columns and uh uh K rows
right so and for and for each for this
one single PCP query uh it will query
some of the position so suppose uh it
querries this second position and the
last last position then I will open the
corresponding column for this qu
position so so let's denote the uh so
let's denote the First Column
as as column one and the second column
as column two Etc
then the the third round message will
contain all the all of the uh column
Q where this Q is in this uh quir is in
this
subset okay so so this is essentially
the same as Kon uh except that I don't I
don't use uh uh merco tree to commit
them I use uh I use a h function to
directly
uh H each column
separately Yeah question use to
H1 uh H1 uh so at this point I do not
use the m commm so I directly send them
to the
wifire so
okay so I sent them in the first message
so by sending them I already fixed the
PCP Matrix intuitively
so then uh after the so after I fix them
uh I have the wifi send the the PCP
query and uh I have the pro to answer
the same PCP query for all of the
PCP yeah follow the third message here
is
that SC okay yes yes good uh good
observation
so so this is the initial protocol
so right
yeah does
sending all those key blocks is that
small enough for the verier uh sorry is
it uh you mean k this yeah when you open
the column is that small enough for the
verifier is that enough for the verifier
no small yeah it's a so good so the so
the size of Q is only uh you can think
is almost the polog in the size of the
circuit C so so the so the Q is very
small you can think so for each for each
for each row I'm going to open uh for
each row I'm going to open C positions
so I have K rows so the third R message
is almost K * Q which is uh almost K it
gr always
K
yeah so the right so so what does the
wif fire do so the verifier will uh it
will first so the verifier will first
uh verify the opening is consistent with
the hash so it will verify
has and the the verification process is
uh the Wii just recompute the hash for
this C position and see if they are
consistent with the first round message
so it will hat the
use some H function uh applied to the
qued position and check if it the same
as uh HQ for for each of the
Q in this uh in this qu subset and
secondly the verifier also need
to uh verify the PCP so the W will run
the PCP verification for this uh for
each of the statements from X1 to XK so
it's around the PCP verification for
XI and
the right and for the same quy que and
the PCP answer PCP answer for the is row
is
the for the is stemma Xi is the piece is
the I coordinate of the of this column
vector and uh you take the collection of
all of the uh such position in
Q yeah so that's the initial
protocol but but this protocol is a
interactive protocol so to build a snark
we need
to uh make it non-interactive so so I
think last lecture before Thanksgiving
uh so so the that lecture is about the
correlation inable hash and how to use
it to build a non- interative proof from
interactive proof so let me recall what
is correlation in trable
hash
uh so uh correlation in trable
has
uh so I will call it a
c c for a relation I
for a
relation for for a relation R so R is a
subset of x uh times y so X here is
the uh right right okay so for for some
in some subset of X and
Y
uh is is a t of
algorithms so the T consist of a key
generator
a key generator and a
c
and
so and it satisfies the following
property so for
any uh other uh nonuniform PBT
adversary uh we need we need the
following
condition so so the adversary is first
the given the has key generated by some
uh let's say this this is c
key generat by the key gen
algorithm and the adversary is required
to Output find the some input X such
that
uh the pair of the X and the hash of and
the say has of uh
X
so so the par of them is in R so this
invent is bonded by some meable
amount
yeah so this is uh what you learned from
the last lecture so this is just a
recap and
uh
yes so given uh and also recall so given
such a h function how do you compare an
interactive proof to a non-interactive
one so the idea is you start with some
uh so given any three round public coin
uh interactive protocol so public coin
means second round message is a uniform
random
string so suppose you have such a
protocol then you can compile it using
this H function to obtain a non-
interactive one
so the proof consist of the transcript
of the of the protocal so proof is just
RF and uh beta so beta equals the S of
the S key and the
arpha and the
gamma
so uh and uh okay
so and we need to recall how do you
prove the soundness of the of the is a
non- interactive
protocal so to prove the soundness uh
how do we use this correlation inability
to prove the soundness so to prove the
soundness you need to First Define a
relation and the relation is the
relation R so it consist of the all the
first run and second run message Alpha
Beta such that there exist Sol around
message that can make the wi fire accept
so you define this relation for the
interactive protocol and uh um right so
in two and then so for any proof for any
uh so to prove the soundness we need to
consider this x the case One X is not in
L and uh yes for X is not in L and
suppose any cheating prover let's say we
have a cheating prover it output a
cheating proof so cheating proof
uh so the CH let's say chover output CH
improve Alpha star beta star and the
gamma
star and if the proof is accepted then
this means uh so if this proof is
accepted then this means uh this beta
star equals the
C of alpha
star under the c key so I I ignore the c
key here and uh and also this uh yeah
and this also the original verification
passes so so let me so here is a
different verification so and the
original
uh verification
passes so this means this alpha alpha
star and the beta star is in this
relation and this is how you prove the
soundness uh because so if a cheating
prover exist then you uh reach a
contradiction with the correlation
intractability because the cheating
improver also output input and output
pair uh such that this uh such that this
beta equals the H of alpha but uh it
satisfies this relation
R uh so this is from the last last last
lecture any
questions okay so so here uh I want to
emphasize here that uh there is a
condition in this proof so the condition
is uh so we need this uh for for such a
say to exist we need the the uh this
relation r
r it needs to be uh
sparse so what do I mean
uh or evasive so so sparse here means uh
for any fixed Alpha the fraction of the
beta that can make this pair Alpha Beta
is satisfies this relation is a
negligible fraction so it
means uh of beta such
that Alpha Beta is is
R if you divide it by the all the fra
all the the size of Y then we need this
to be
negligible so this condition is crucial
for the for the S to exist the reason
is uh do any know do anyone know why
this is the
case so so let's consider our extreme
case so so let's say uh if if there
exist uh so let's say if there
exist let's consider extreme extreme
case so let's say if there exist some
alpha alpha Z some fixed Alpha z uh
which is in the input input
space such that uh all of the all for
all of the beta this Alpha and the
beta is Alpha zero beta is in is in this
r
then it means that uh then for any H
function it cannot be correlation in
triable for Sr because any H function
will output something something some
Beta And it satisfies this
relation so so this condition uh so at
least we need this fraction to be less
than one okay
so the problem is uh if we want to apply
the C constru
here uh it's not clear whether we can
define a relation uh that is sparse
so so let's modify the construction
using this C
parad okay so the conu we all
replace replace the second message
Q so instead of having the wifi send the
Q we uh we have the prover comput this
queue by itself using the C
and uh so the so now we apply the S to
all of the first round message h12
HQ uh sorry h12
HL and we put the say key inside of the
CRS okay
so next I will uh Define a relation R
and try to prove the soundness
so yeah can you see what changes you
made again just yeah is
good so the changes is uh instead of
having the approver to send a message to
the verifier and have the warier send
back a challenge I'm going to have the
prover uh not send this H1 to
HL so the Prov directly apply a c to H1
to HL and obtain some query so you can
Pro so the prover can proceed to the S
round and uh finish the s
so the proof well consist of the
transcript of the protocol which is the
all of the H1 to H and the and the thir
message okay yeah um what assumption are
we making for like we need the the
output space of the C to be like some
sense that the verifier would query or
something right right uh good question
so uh so in fact we need the the PCP to
be a public coin so yeah that's the
that's the implicit condition so so so
so the uh so in the general case the PCP
quari may not be uniform random so you
need to uh so in fact there is some uh
PCP so the some query sampler that take
some uniform random string and it will
uh compute the actual PCP query so yeah
so we're also kind of assuming that the
output of C is like kind of uniform
disted or like super random uh yeah I
mean so uh okay so so in the general so
in fact uh so this is just some
uh uh some way to describe the the how
you generate the query so in fact the
PCP query is generated by using the
using some uh query some query generator
or some
sampler so the sampler will take some
uniform Randomness R and the generator
PCP query so what you do is you you take
the say output of the S as the as the
randomness and then you generate it from
it to get a PCP
query
yeah okay so so next I will try to prove
the uh security of this uh
construction try to prove the soundness
so complet is easy to show you just uh
you can do it yourself yeah so for the
sound and I will only prove the
soundness here so
yeah
whatever indes for PCP we
generate probility
onep
uh for the PCP yeah is complet this one
oh right right yes yeah we we assume
there um yeah we we choose uh PCP with
perfect correctness yeah yeah good
question okay
so so let's let's first attempt uh let's
first try to prove the uh
solness so the initial attempt is to
define a relation R similar to the
relation r as before so we just Define
it as uh the relation R consist of all
the pairs of H1 to H HL and uh the query
set Q such that there exist uh so there
exist a s message so so gamma here is
the S
message such as the wirefire accept
uh and
[Applause]
uh so so if so this is the initial
attempt to prove the soundness so we'll
do the same thing so this R is the the
same as the relation R we defined for
the C here uh except I just replac the
alpha beta gamma with the with this
protocol okay so but the issue is with
this relation is not clear whether this
relation is a spar relation the reason
is
uh the reason is that I remember so so
this uh right the the reason is that uh
this H function must be a compressing H
function so if we choose a comprising h
function then for any H value H1 to HL
there might be multiple pre-images of
the PCP so for one PCP so let's say we
have one pre-image of the PCP which is
pcp1 to PCP uh k then for those PCP you
may have a a queue that can make them
accept you may have a one que to make
them accept but for other pre-image of
the PCP it may have another q that can
make the uh query accept so uh so if you
know this relation we take the union of
all those all of those PCP queries so
it's not clear uh it if this reation has
sparity less than
one
yeah uh so so what we will do is we will
choose a special H function and uh uh so
the this spal H function is still
compressing but it will show us uh still
has some information about this
pre-image so now I will Define this uh
uh special H
function so the so the H function is
called uh somewhere statistical binding
hash so
or I will call it SSB so it's a yeah so
it's a SSB so such a function is defined
as follows so it has a
so SSB is also a two of
algorithms so it has a key generator and
some SSB has
algorithm uh with the following
syntax
so uh the key generation algorithm will
sample some
key and the the key generator will also
uh it will take some security parameter
Lambda as input and also it will take
some index I as
input
okay such that uh
and then the uh SSB hash algorithm will
use
the SSB key and uh it will take some
message X1 to xn as input and output
some has and we require the following
two property so the first property is
called a key in distinguishability
or a key hiding uh okay so key is
distinguish
so it says that uh for any uh two
indices uh so i1 and I2 in this n so
the the key generated by the using the
first IND indices is IND distinguishable
with
the with the key generated by the second
index index
and the second property is called uh
statistical
binding so statistical binding says
um so it basically says the H function
is binding for the
position uh I so it says uh for any
uh right so for any X1 to
xn and
the X1 Prime P XM Prime so
if if the SSB has of
them is the same
um then then we have this XI equals XI
Prime okay so it says the H value will
bind the value at the I position of this
input
XI uh so so here the k k i require the
so here the K is generated in this way
for this index I
okay uh any question yeah can you
explain why that relation might not be
sparse all right so it's not clear why
this uh it's not clear whether this is
sparse or not
the the reason is that uh
so so here uh the reason is that uh for
so because this has so H1 to HL are the
har values so so you can think uh so
initially we have this pcp1 to PCP K and
we H them to a sucin h value H1 to
HL but the the size of has is much
smaller than the
pre-image so so for for a fixed h12 HL
there might be multiple uh pre-images so
and for one for one pre-image it may
have some for for example for this uh
for this fixed one pre-image it may have
some uh quy set queue that can make all
of the query be
accepted but uh but there might be some
other uh PCP pre-image for the for the
same h12 HQ so let's say it's some pcp1
to PCP K
Prim okay and uh and they they may also
hash to the same same has value so if
this is the case then for those set of
uh pcp1 to PCP K PR they may have some
other query set QPR that can uh make the
make make each of the pcp1 Prime to PCP
K Prime be accepted so so but if this is
the case then of then this q and Q Prime
need to be so they are also in this
relation R right so so if this is the
case then both of this uh then you know
this h12 HL HL and Q is in this R and
uh and the Q Prime is also in
R so so you can do this do this argument
for each of the pre-image of this H1 to
HQ and and the issue is there are many
many many pre-images so the the is very
compressing right so the number of
preimages is much larger than the uh
than than the size of the que all
possibilities of que so yeah yeah in
order for a cheat to like take advantage
of
this they would have to like find a
collision like that right right so why
are we worried about this uh good
question so it's not clear whether so
for example if you take a specific H
function it's not clear whether the uh
prover can leverage this kind of back
but uh it's also not clear how to prove
the soundness so yeah
so okay so next I will show you how to
build such
a yeah any question okay so next I I'll
show you how to build such a SSB uh from
FH so
so the construction is uh very simple um
so do you remember uh what is FH so FH
is some uh public key encryption where
you can given a separate text of M you
can homop evaluate on the SE Tex uh for
any function f and to get a SE text of f
of M so that's the F so to build SSB uh
we we do the following so from the F
okay
so for the key generation uh so for the
index I we're going to generate FH
separate text of
I and uh right yeah so and we we Define
this seate text as the SSB
key okay and uh to use this uh separate
text to Hash X1 tox
uh
and the idea the idea is we're going to
homomorphically pick the iest position
uh under hood of FH for those X1 to X1
so so what we will do is
um um we will do the homic evaluation of
some function f uh and F has X1 to X and
Hollow in it and uh we'll do this homk
on the on the separate text
I and this is our H value so here this F
is defined as follows so FX1 to X1 given
index I it will output the
I I coordinate so intuitively you just
pick the uh XI under the hood of
F and uh so yeah so okay so here so this
is a has function because the size of
the H value is just a separate text so
the size of has value is po po
LDA yeah and the key in this in
distinguish ability follows from the
security of f because the index I is
hiding and the
the yeah so the second property this
statistical binding you can you can show
it directly because it the because the
has value contains
the uh the homic incretion of
XI
yeah uh any
questions okay so I uh so later we will
use this SSB but we we use a additional
property so this property is called uh
uh extion so so intuitively this
separate this uh uh H value it contains
the sep Tex of XI
so uh so in fact it contains
F and if you know if you know the secur
key of FH you can uh even decrypt this I
from the hash value so we need a uh
extraction
and it's just so extraction property
says that there exist an
extractor so extractor is a PO algorithm
and uh moreover uh moreover so in the
key generat algorithm I will add a TR in
it so the key generator will also output
some trap and uh there is some extractor
such
that uh the extractor will out will take
the trap door as input and also the
value as input and it will extract
something okay and we and we further
require the extractory has correctness
which means for any X1 to
xn if you has it under key
K and you uh so let's say s h is the has
of the X1 to X1
then the extracted value is consistent
with the XI with XI then this
uh okay so this is the extraction
correctness so if if the key uh if this
has key is for the for the is
position it's gener if the H ke is
generated for the is
position okay so now uh so now we will
we will go back to the
construction so now we have this SSB
hash from uh F we'll go back through
this construction and modify the has
function this H function we use so
the H function we use will we will use
this uh we all use SSB
hush and the SSB key is uh we will move
it to the we'll move the We'll add the
SSB key to the CRS
so so this is SSB
key so now we will use this SSB has to
has each column of the PCP Matrix to
this PCP
Matrix and the uh all the other things
are the same as before uh any questions
okay uh yeah maybe the we also need to
when we verify the H we also use SSB to
recompute the each column and the
verify uh
um when you're doing the
SS right exactly so in fact in the in
the actual construction uh in fact you
don't even need I because FH is separate
text in the actual construction is sudo
random but you can you can uh you can
put any index ey there
yeah so
okay so if we now if we use SSB has to H
each column uh of this uh Matrix what
will
happen so so let's say the uh so let's
say if the SSB H is generate the H key
is generated for some index I
star okay so then uh intuitively this
means uh this SSB is binding for the the
i i row of this
Matrix the reason is that uh for each
for each for each has value we Has It by
we obtain it by hasing the some column
of this Matrix has has for example the
first has value is obtained by has the
First Column of this Matrix and now if
the SSB is binding for the is coordinate
so the is coordinate now corresponds to
the is row of this Matrix the first
coordinate of the is row of this Matrix
and the same is true for other columns
so for each column we will B the is
position and that means uh this SSB is
binding for the is
row
so for for the I I start
row and intuitively you can think uh H
h12 H will contain the all the full
information about the is r of this
Matrix uh because the h12 HL they
they're just FH SE text
so it contains the actual value of the
is row okay uh any
questions right right a good question so
let's let's uh continue uh let's
continue this proof
so
uh
okay so we want to prove the soundness
of this uh snark so how we how do we
prove it so to prove the soundness we
need to show for any uh X1 to X XK such
that uh
X1
uh XK X12 XK is in L doesn't
hold then no cheating improver can break
the
snark
so so we start with the statement uh X1
to XK in language doesn't hold but what
does this
mean so the key so the key observation
here is that uh so if this doesn't hold
then there exist some index I let's say
it's index I star some index I star such
that uh uh this XI star is not in L so
it means that uh if you want to prove
the soundness you only need uh if you
want to prove the soundness there is one
statement x i star that is not in this
language and the goal is to just catch
this I star then we can prove the S
this okay so we only to use the one
statements is not in this language and
that's how we use
SSB so so remember SSB can find the is
position is coordin is row of this PCP
Matrix so the iow of the PCP Matrix is
the PCP for XI so
that's yeah so that give us some this so
that's the
intuition
so you're Bing is the one langage right
right uh good question so so the proof
so the formal proof goes like this
so so the good question so the formal
proof works as follows so so in the
first in the first hybrid
HZ uh we have a adversary uh
so suppose we have some adversary P star
that can break the construction break
the soundness of the construction so
what it will receive so P star will
receive the uh
CRS some some CRS star some CRS and it
will output some cheting proove P star
and the verification of the the proof
will be
accepted so uh right so the
verification uh of the proof will be
accepted and uh this happens with
probability greater than some
Epson
Okay so
so in the next hybrid uh I
will so in the next hybrid I know there
is a a index I star and the x i x i star
is not in the language so well so this I
star is
fixed right so I can switch the CRS so
in the hybrid H1 I will switch
the switch CRS so to this s generated by
SSB generation this using the I
star so let's let's denote this by uh
SSB okay so by sorry
this
[Music]
two k i star SSB uh Ki star
okay and and I can argue if this is the
case then we still
have uh
so this this new CRS let's call it CRS
star so CRS star will contains this uh
this SSB Ki star in it and it will
generate some Pi Pi
star and it still has
the property
as so this is greater than one minus
negligible so so so this is true because
uh so this just follows from the key in
distinguish ability because the key is
hiding
okay so now in this hybrid we switch the
uh so you can so intuitively you can
think
the you can think uh given so given any
cheating proof uh in fact the is RO of
the PCP is already fixed so next we will
reach a contradiction using correlation
in trable
hash okay
so
so so clim if the wirefire is accepted
so uh so the claim is for any proof for
any
proof uh the cheating proof uh has this
H1 star to HL star and
the Q star and the gamma
star so gamma star is the Solon message
I denote it as gamma
star so this is a information
theoretical claim and the claim is just
if the if the Ching proof is accepted
so oh sorry
is then it must be case that this Q star
uh sorry then it must be case that this
H1 to
HL star uh Q
star is in this relation
R uh so here I need to so R is uh is
almost the r above but uh I want uh
redefine a new
R so R is well contains of the h12 H
HL and the
Q so so given h12 HL I can extract I can
use the extractor to
extract to extract
PCP right because the that's from the
extraction of the SSB so so so this PCP
is the PCP for the I start
position and then I Define this R
so as follows so I
require uh I require the PCP is
accepted for XI
yeah so I requ so in this definition of
r i first extract the is
PCP and then I check if the query que is
uh query queue can make this PCP be
accepted for the is is uh statement X
start
okay so yeah any
questions uh is this
clear
so so intuitively uh in the third round
message if the proof is accepted then
anything uh so in the in the third round
message the Prov need to give some
Columns of the qued position so at the
so so for all of those columns if you
look at the is is star row of it it must
be consistent with the extracted
PCP because the because the S because we
have the SSB extraction
correctness yeah
so
yeah so we Define the r in this way so
in fact is the almost same as the r
Above So now uh now I can so to prove
this claim is just a the prove of this
clim is just the argument I set up set
just now so uh so for any cheating proof
if it's uh if the verification of the
proof is accepted then from the
correctness of the uh
extraction the
so uh from the correctness of the
extraction uh uh okay maybe let me write
it so if the
if if P star is
accepted then from the uh SSB extraction
correctness
we know this
uh PCP iar so the PCP iar we exract from
the from this H1 to HQ uh sorry H1 to
HL uh
so so let's say it's some PCP I start uh
PCP star
then uh if you look at the uh Q's
coordinate okay so if you look at the
q's coordinate then it must uh okay so
let me writing this
way the column star so column star are
uh
yeah
so where the thir round message are just
the columns so
yeah okay so that's the soundness
proof oh so okay so that's the proof of
the
clamp yeah any question
in the
hybrid how do you identify which I
start you need to know which statement
was good question so this uh this
soundless proof is uh nonuniform so it's
a non-adaptive so the sunless proof
start with fixed X12 XK so for any fixed
X12 XK you know uh there exist I star
that x i star is false so you know there
exist a fix the I star so that x i star
is false is not in
L yeah so that's given so you can you
can think it's given to the reduction in
a nonuniform way
yeah okay so so the okay so this is from
the extracted so if you extracted
some uh so this is from the SSV
extraction correctness uh you have this
we have the consistency between the
between this PCP extracted and the proof
uh in the Sol round and if the proof If
this cheating proof P star is accepted
uh so then we can we can use the fact
that this P star is accepted so if it is
accepted then then we know this uh uh
this Q This queue is a this que can make
this PCP uh PCP star be accepted
yeah so then that's complete the uh
complete the the this clan
and the final differ it can you can uh
so it's then you can use the correlation
intractability of the
C yeah so P
star
so so if the proof is accepted then
this
is the the extract PCP from this uh from
here it will make this PCP verification
accepted
yeah okay uh let's have a break yeah