It is my pleasure to kick off the
starting the lightning talks with
today's first presentation introducing
Kate Rosner of Medis. Medis is applying
AI and machine learning to revolutionize
drug discovery and delivery. Welcoming
to the
stage Kate Rosner.
Hi everybody and thank you Trisha and
ILP for hosting us today. Um my name is
Kate Rosner. I'm going to be presenting
a quick overview of Medis's
capabilities. So, uh, Medis aims to
integrate artificial intelligence,
machine learning, molecular dynamics,
and high throughput invivo screening to
develop novel genetic medicines
particularly um in the pursuit of uh
easing delivery issues. Uh, we are
founded in 2019 by three MIT alumni. Um,
and this mission has allowed us to raise
over $300 million through our series C
round. Uh, Jacob actually this morning
gave a really good introduction into why
AI is a really good uh application or
why LMPS are a really good application
for AI and machine learning. Um, there's
a really large design space when it
comes to LMPS. You can design chemically
each individual component of the LMP,
but you also can optimize the LMP
particle as a whole by adjusting the
proportions and ratios of the different
uh components within the particle. So
that creates a really large
combinatorial explosion problem makes it
really difficult to design these LMPS
optimally with just traditional
experimentation or
DOE. So we use AI, machine learning,
other computational tools to solve that
problem. Um this all begins with our
lipid library. It's over a million
different lipids. Um not just ionizable
lipids. Um but it also includes other
components of an L&P. Um this is all in
silicone and it was uh generated denovo
by machine learning algorithms. Um
obviously we can't synthesize millions
of lipids. So we have uh insilic AI and
molecular dynamics filters to allow us
to quickly screen through these lipids
um and other LMP components to identify
which would make the optimal LMP for
delivering to a target um tissue of
interest. And then finally we use
artificial intelligence to uh predict
the optimal formulation as well to best
tune these um LMPS for efficacy to
delivering to these difficult to reach
uh tissues.
Like most LMP companies, we began with
developing liver targeting LMPS. So we
have liver LMPS that uh have better
delivery than Madna's lipid 5 which is
kind of like the industry gold standard.
Um and this uh portfolio of liver LMPS
that we have actually supports our
internal pipeline which is primarily
focused in oncology. Um so this MTS 105
is one example of our pipeline. Um it is
an liver targeted LMP that encapsulates
mRNA which encodes for T- cell engaging
SCFVS. Um this is for the treatment of
paceellular carcinoma. Um in vivo we've
seen significant tumor shrinkage with
this therapeutic and we actually have
finally dosed in um humans in an
investigator initiated trial um that is
still ongoing. So that's very exciting.
But beyond the liver, we've also
developed um an extra hypatic targeting
L&P portfolio um that is allows us to
target a number of difficultto-reach
tissues with our LMPS. Um so we have CNS
targeted L&PS that can be administered
by intratheal or ICM administration. Um
in the slide you'll see we have um ICM
administration of uh TD tomato mRNA. RNA
scope shows that we're seeing really
widespread distribution throughout the
brain including to deep brain regions.
Um we also have lung targeting LNPS via
IV administration. Um we have seen
better delivery and more specific
delivery to the lung uh versus the liver
and spleen. Um in comparison to sort
LMPS which are the basis for recodes uh
foundational
technology. And finally, our kind of
like breakthrough really unique
technology is IV administered skeletal
and cardiac muscle targeting L&PS. Um,
these give us a lot of opportunity to
potentially help patients with
significant with diseases with
significant unmet need. We're thinking
like musculardrophes or
cardiomyopathies. Um, it's really
exciting data. So, I know it was a lot
to get through in a very short period of
time, but I'm open to hearing from any
of you. Please come find me at the end
of this. I'll be happy to talk more
about what our um company is doing. Um
something I wasn't able to get to here
is we actually have an AI empowered mRNA
uh platform as well. Um and we are
always looking for external
collaborators um on any of the
technology that I've shown you today. So
thank you all.