What do I wish candidates would ask me
when they're applying to MIT Sloan?
It's tough to say, but I think that the
biggest thing is what do what are we
looking for, right? Exactly. How can
they stand out in the pool? The reality
is is that we're not looking for
something specific. There's not a magic
part of the application that's going to
make you stand out. It's you that's
going to make you stand out. We want to
get to know you as an applicant and you
need to showcase that throughout each of
the application components, being
thoughtful and careful with how you use
your examples throughout all of the
different cover letters, resumes,
videos. We cannot wait to get to know
you. The question is, do you belong at
MIT Sloan? The answer is yes, you belong
here. There is no one MIT Sloan student
that we're looking for. We intentionally
create this environment that has people
of all different backgrounds, lived
experiences that can bring their own
perspective to the classroom and to the
community. Whoever you are, whatever
your background is, you belong here and
we can't wait to meet you. A question I
wish applicants would ask more often is
which part of the application is often
overlooked by candidates?
Not only are we looking for evidence of
your success through the essay
questions, the letters of
recommendation, your transcripts, and
your resume, but there's also a lot of
hidden real estate in the application.
There's lots of short answer textbox
questions in the employment section, in
the academic history section, even in
the academics and awards section. So,
make sure you spend a little extra time
making sure that all of the things you
include in your application complement
one another, not just repeat one
another. I want you to know that this is
just the beginning of the admissions
process. The application provides you an
opportunity to really highlight your
strengths and experiences and how you
might contribute to this loan community.
The admissions committee will review all
applications and invite a selected group
of folks to interview with us. In an
interview, we have the opportunity to
dig deeper into the experiences that
you've highlighted in your application.
As we get to know you through the
application and interview processes, we
look forward to learning more about what
makes you you professionally and
personally.