As you know, machine learning is
transforming healthc care but at the
same time risk amplifying the biases.
Our next speaker, Professor Mazia
Gasami, uh, associate professor in MIT
ECS and MIT Institute, Institute of
Medical Engineering and Science will
address next topic. Let's welcome.
Hi everyone. This is a 25m minute talk
that will be done in 15 minutes. So, I
hope you had coffee and you're awake.
I'm going to talk about ethical machine
learning. I'm going to focus on
healthcare, but these lessons apply
really broadly to any human-facing
setting. Okay. My lab is the healthy
machine learning lab. We focus on
understanding whether we need AI in a
health setting. If we do, developing a
robust health model and then
understanding how humans might use that
model in practice. Let's go through an
example. Let's say some doctors
approached me last year because they did
and said that they wanted to make a
triage system for Mass General. Okay, so
it's Friday night. They want to make
sure that when somebody comes in and
they take a chest X-ray and it's going
to be hours before a doctor can see them
that they can be triaged and go home if
they're healthy. This is important
because we have SARS, COVID, MRSA, all
those good things in the hospital. So,
can we do this? Yes, we can. There's
this pipeline that every single person
who's ever trained a machine learning
system walks through where you get uh
you define a problem, you get some data,
you uh create a label for yourself, and
then you optimize your model and deploy
it. And we already did the first thing.
We're doing this model-based chest X-ray
triage system. So, let's do the rest of
them. Data is easy. We have over 700,000
publicly available chest X-rays in the
United States alone that you can train a
model on. Check. We want to optimize for
a no finding label. That means I looked
at this chest X-ray and there's no
pneumonia, no pneumthorax, no nothing.
There's no finding. They're healthy.
They can go home. Okay, I'm going to
train a denset that's a kind of
convolutional neural network. And when I
finish this optimization, I get to
report my metric, which is an AU, right?
And that goes from 0.5, which is random,
to one, which is perfect. If your
model's perfect, then the graduate
student messed up. Make them do it
again. So 08 is pretty good. 085 is uh
something that we're very proud of. This
is a nature medicine paper. That's
great. The problem is we're not the only
people who have done this. This is
actually broadly done in a variety of
settings across uh different healthcare
subsp specialties and the FDA actually
clears these models to be used in a
medical setting. Okay, that's really
exciting. But it also leads to questions
about the deployments and how we're
evaluating whether those deployments
work well for everybody. By show of
hands, who here would be very excited to
have this state-of-the-art nature
medicine model triage them at Mass
General on Friday
night? Really? Didn't you hear about AI
all day? I thought I thought you guys
are believers. No. Okay. Okay. Well,
different crowd. Wow. Okay. Um well in a
normal setting many of you would have
raised your hands and then I in fact
would have said uh but for those
skeptics among you of which there would
have been few um they did not set me up
well for this uh that I would say okay
but for you skeptics maybe a reason that
you're skeptical is because you worry it
might not work on a person like you and
a way that you can check that is by
looking at the false positive rate for
this model in different subopuls. Why a
false positive rate? Because a false
positive in this setting is under
diagnosis. It means that you falsely
positively said that one subgroup was
healthy when it was actually sick. And
when I audit my state-of-the-art model,
I find that's true for female patients,
young patients, black patients, and
patients on Medicaid insurance. Okay?
And so, if you belong to one of those
groups, maybe you wouldn't have raised
your hand and said you felt comfortable
using this model.
Um, and so it's very important as we
look at these models where often in many
human facing settings, not just
healthcare, one number gets reported for
performance across a very large
population, that we make sure we
understand where these models might
fail. And I'm going to walk through a
couple of examples of how you can do
these audits and what the implications
are. The first one is when you're
collecting your data. Now, if you've
ever trained a machine learning system,
you know about this uh particular hack,
which is machine learning models like
human students are lazy and they really
like to use shortcuts. But shortcuts are
actually not great um in all situations
because again, they make you lazy. So,
in this case, if you see a cow on grass,
you know it's a cow. If you see this
mole on skin, you know it's a benign
mole. But, uh or or sorry, a non-ben
mole. Uh, but if you see a cow on a
beach, most state-of-the-art machine
learning models think it's an orca, not
a cow. And if you see uh the same mole,
that's exactly the same mole, but I've
put some markings on there. Those are
the markers that dermatologists usually
use when they're watching a mole to make
sure it's not growing. Now, suddenly,
it's changed its classification for the
mole, right? And so, this is this cow is
no less of a cow because it's on the
beach. And this mole is no more or less
benign because of these markings. But
that's not what the model thinks. And
this is a very well-known thing in all
vision machine learning systems that
they rely on these shortcuts, these
contextual biases. And maybe this is
cute in this situation because you and I
can all look at that and say it's not an
Orca silly model. But what happens when
we look at healthcare data where humans
can't actually tell what those spirious
shortcuts are, but machine learning
models can use them. What do I mean? We
wrote two papers a couple years ago
where we showed that if you take all of
the demographic information out of
somebody's notes, a machine learning
model can still tell their demographics,
but human doctors cannot. Even worse, if
you take chest X-rays, no radiologist we
evaluated could look at a chest X-ray
and estimate somebody's self-reported
race, for example, because there's no
biological reason you should be able to.
But machine learning models can. Why?
Because X-rays are a form of radiation.
If you self-report different races, you
probably have different levels of
melanination. What does melanination do
to radiation impacts it slightly, right?
There's like slight protective effects
of having more melanin. Um, and while
our eyes can't do a band pass filter and
notice that there's a slight difference
in the noise spectrum at the high end of
the frequency range, a neural network
can do that trivially. Why is that scary
and important? Well, if we think about
the fact that models can uh use
shortcuts to make bad decisions
sometimes. And now think about shortcuts
that are invisible to us but perfectly
obvious to machine learning models.
Where does that take us? We wanted to
actually motivate this in uh three
medical vision settings. So we're
looking at chest X-rays, dermatology,
and retinopathy screening. And in each
of these cases, we're going to train a
deep learning model to predict a
clinical outcome. And then we're going
to test what happens when it learns more
about whose demographics are whose. And
so here we see that yes, all of these
deep learning models when we train them
to predict a disease can actually
predict who you are, your demographics,
your age, your race, your sex. And the
more you can predict that, the higher
correlated that is with doing worse in
those subgroups. Put another way, the
more I learn to predict who is female in
a chest X-ray when I'm predicting
pneumonia, the worse I will do at
predicting pneumonia in female patients.
Okay?
Can you fix this? Yes. Beloved by all
economists, this is a paro plot uh which
was demanded by a reviewer. So here it
is. Um on the x- axis you can see this
is the overall AU averaged across the
population. And on the y ais this is the
level of fairness gap. So where do we
want our models to be? Bottom right hand
corner very very like performant on
average and then very low fairness gap.
Right? And you can see for the one I
have boxed predicting cardomegaly in
patients of different ages, right? The
uh normal models that people usually
train with empirical risk minimization,
those are in sort of that teal color,
which is bad. That means that on average
they do great, but if you're an older
patient, they won't work for you.
They're very unfair. But you can see if
we use some of these distraust uh
distributionally robust optimization
techniques like group DRRO you can get
those dots those model performance
results that are all the way in the
bottom right hand corner which is great.
So you can preserve most of the overall
performance very little change and then
you can reduce this fairness gap by
almost all of the 20%.
This is what happens when you use modern
machine learning techniques that are
aware of these distributional changes in
a data set in Massachusetts for training
and then you test it in data from the
same hospital in Massachusetts, new
patient data from Massachusetts. What
happens when we train the model to be
fair in Massachusetts and then use it in
Stamford? Well, suddenly it's not so
fair anymore. And so whereas right now
what happens is the FDA certifies your
model to work well across the United
States, across the world, that's not
actually true. That's not something that
works for certifying results. So if you
want a model to work well in your
situation, in your school, in your bank,
in your hospital, you actually have to
test that it works well in your
distribution, in the selection of humans
that it will be operating on in your
setting.
I'm going to briefly talk through some
of this algorithm section. Uh not all of
it. Um the first thing you might want to
know is whether this is an AI problem.
It's not an AI problem. This has been
happening for a very long time. This
happens with logistic regression models.
And so uh what people have known for a
very long time is that if we use a group
attribute a demographic attribute in a
risk score even a simple score like
logistic regression you can get worse
subgroup performance even though overall
your model will be better. So here if I
try to predict sleep apnnea and I use
sex and age it's 1% better on average
but it is worse for younger male and
older female patients. Why does this
happen? And this happens because we
either have model misspecification, your
model is not high capacity enough to
capture some interaction between a
feature, some attribute that exists, or
because you've selected a model to do
best on average. And if it just so
happens that it does that on average by
destroying performance in a smaller
subgroup and they all happen to be older
or female or black, so be it. Okay? And
this gets worse when we think about very
large billion parameter vision language
models like diffusion models, right?
That can do image generation, zeroot
classification or zeroot retrieval
because while they can do all these
things and that's very technically
fascinating, they also have very
problematic
biases. And another uh thing we've
noticed repeatedly is when you try to
remove these biases in ways that work
maybe for prior models, they don't work
because they assume linearity. We assume
that there's one place in the latent
space that is male, one place in the
latent space that is female. And if we
could just orthogonalize those, we could
project out that difference and collapse
it so everything is fair. But that's not
actually what these models look like.
The mind map or latent space of large
very uh very large language and vision
language models is complex and
nonlinear. And so if you debias in a
direction for male female pilot, it
might be different than the direction
you would want to debias for male and
female manager, for example.
And so a way to get around this is to
respect the nonlinearity of the space,
right? And so we have recent work where
uh we looked at what that would uh maybe
accomplish. And so here if we embed a
query for doctor that lands in this
solidly male part of the space, if I ask
then where is male doctor and female
doctor so that I can orthogonalize and
project that out, I can move to this
point. And that's what a standard
debising technique would do. But this is
sub-optimal because I'm still much
closer physically in the retrieval space
in the model's mind map to male images
than female images, which is not
something I want. Instead, you have to
crawl along this nonlinear surface,
right? To a point that's actually
optimally between these two attributes
that you might want to balance between.
Okay? And you can do this for any
attribute and for any class you're
trying to retrieve. Um, it's nice
because it's an analytical solution that
you can do at test time. You don't have
to train the model. And uh this results
in better classification and retrieval
performance. But the last thing I want
to go through before I run away is uh
does this mean that we can fix
everything in models uh at test time?
Not really. Because you may have played
with a vision language model and notice
that if you ask it to give you a
specific image, sometimes it really
struggles with negation. So if I say
give me a picture of a table, but
there's no chairs for the people there,
there will be chairs. You guys can try
this. It's a little annoying and it's
also true for image retrieval and visual
question answering. Okay. And while this
is again cute and funny in this
situation that it's giving you pictures
of dogs on grass when you want dogs not
on grass, it's not funny in medicine
because if I say that I want you to
retrieve uh images of chest X-rays with
evidence of lung opacity, I do want
this. But if I want evidence of lung
opacity with no edema, I don't want
this. And the model can't tell those
things apart.
Okay. Why is this happening? This is
happening because uh this is the the uh
thing that most of these models are
trained on, right? It's trained on these
matching pairs of images on the internet
and then the text that was generated to
describe them. And uh here we see this
nice picture of this dog, black and
white dog jumps over the bar. We
wouldn't describe that online as black
and white dog jumps over the bar, no
helicopters. But that's essentially what
we're asking this model to know how to
do, right? We're saying you've never
seen an example of somebody describe an
image as the negation of certain
objects, but do that, right? It can't do
that. And this is again even worse in a
medical setting where often you really
want a long list of things that aren't
present and maybe there's only one thing
you're looking for. And so here what we
did is we built a really aggressive
benchmark uh for evaluating whether
state-of-the-art models, vision language
models can actually do negation. Um, and
so we built an easy one where it's very
templated, a hard one where it sounds
more like the negations humans might
use, and then a medical one. And what we
found is that state-of-the-art vision
language models fail in all of these
cases. On the easy negations, they fail
in the 7% range. In the hard negations,
they fail in the almost uh 20 over 20%
range. And for medical vision language
models, the loss you get by just adding
a negation to a query is over 30%.
Okay, why is this happening? Let's try
to get some intuition. What if I ask the
model to embed a bunch of different
objects like dog, cat, car, bicycle,
airplane, and if I say there is a dog,
I'm going to put it as a circle in that
color. And if I say there's not a dog,
I'm going to put it as a triangle in the
same color. This is what
state-of-the-art models look like. What
do you
notice? All the colors are together,
guys. Right? So there is a flower is
really close to there is not a flower.
Okay, which is not a desirable behavior
in our setting. And even worse, if you
take some of the models that have been
trained contrastively to actually avoid
having negations close to the
affirmations, you get something worse,
which is this funny thing. All of the
objects are on these separate axes and
in that very small red circled region of
the model's mind is the negation of
everything. That's not a flower, not a
dog, not a helicopter. It's every
negation right there. Okay. And so
really what we need is to have models
that we can't just, you know, edit or
audit at test time. We need to realize
that there are going to be some
fundamental gaps in their capacities
that maybe we won't realize until we
test them and they fail and then we need
to improve them. Um, and with that I'll
close. Uh hopefully this uh convinces
you that if we move forward with ethical
AI and health, we need to think
holistically about our actions in that
entire pipeline. Thank you.