so good afternoon I'm K from mitb Japan
uh thank you for coming this uh great
event an special event for us uh I'm
going to introduce two excellent speaker
in this last section first uh hea
Kik hez kuik is a professor of chemical
engineering and chemistry at
MIT she received her p uh Bachelor of
Engineering in chemical engineering from
Cooper Union in
2004 and her PhD in Materials Science
and Engineering from MIT in
2009 uh she completed uh postto do uh
Stanford
2013 and prior to return to MIT as a
faculty member in 20
2017 I think she likes MIT a lot so she
left Stanford
University okay and then uh uh she
became a uh full professor in uh
2024 last year um her work has been Rec
organized by many our from various
scientific societies and then National
agencies like
daa uh uh as she has a lots of a from
various Institute uh but please review
who her bio on her
website uh her title a talk title is
getting from a computer to real
world materials faster with machine
learning uh please welcome uh Professor
kuik it's my pleasure to have a chance
uh to talk to all of you today about my
research um so I'm a computational
chemist by training that means that a
lot of what I do involves thinking about
how we can discover new materials using
computation and today I'm going to tell
you a couple of case stories case
studies where we've tried to close the
gap between what I predict on a computer
using Ai and what can be realized in the
lab and tightening that connection
between what's simulated and and what is
achieved experimentally and the reason
that I think um it's uh valuable to take
this computational approach is that if
we for a moment imagine all of the
possible materials uh that could ever be
studied to address a problem and you can
pick your favorite problem it could be
one in uh sustainability it could be
catalytic
Transformations it could be gas storage
and
separations all of those possible
materials we will never scratch the
surface in our lifetimes um and so in
particular in material spaces I like to
work in are those with Earth abundant
transition metals including transition
metal complex and catalysts metal
organic Frameworks um and so this is my
depiction of this this hypothetical
space of all possible materials um and
machine learning has matured over the
past uh decade or so to allow us to
maybe not see all of these materials but
to really rapidly speed up how quickly
we screen and infer properties over
large spaces of materials uh but we
haven't solved the problem yet we
haven't replaced all experimentation
with machine learning models in instead
what we can say is that there are
materials neighborhoods we have visited
so there are types of materials that we
already know about that have been
studied experimentally there are both
generative and enumerative models ways
that we could hypothesize novel
materials um and then you can imagine if
I really knew completely all the space
of all possible materials ones that have
not yet been synthesized or not yet
studied
computationally um there's a lot of
space out there uh that we don't yet
know about and on top of that if we try
to move into a space where with
computation and AI we propose new
hypothetical materials we quickly
encounter challenges where we don't know
in the lab will these be stable or
synthesizable materials so I hope to
tell you a little bit today about how my
lab has tried to address some of these
challenges broadly by giving you
specific
examples and so in the first half of my
talk I'll focus on transition metal
complexes in the second half I'll talk
about our extensions to metal organic
Frameworks again focusing on uh two
classes of materials where the
transition metal center has interesting
magnetic and electronic properties and
the organic uh environment around that
metal center both gives rise to
interesting and challenging properties
that are hard to predict uh denovo
because they are so quantum mechanical
in
nature um so as I mentioned uh we think
about transition metal complexes these
are widely studied as catalysts in the
fine chemical industry and in uh
polymerization reactions and there's a
very diverse and fast space of all
possible transition M complexes when we
put these organic ligans around we give
rise to um with open shell transition Ms
we give rise to different possible
quantum mechanical spin States um and
different possible oxidation States and
so in my lab the way that we tackle
exploring this space with machine
learning is we've developed uh
open-source automation tools called mimp
simplify we've developed machine
learning representations to allow us to
efficiently machine learn the properties
of transition M complexes on modest data
sets we combine these two together uh to
train neural networks to predict
properties Quantum mechanically of these
uh different transition M complexes we
look at where the model is most certain
this is a field known as uncertainty
quantification and we can either exploit
the model where it's most certain or we
can use something called Model
exploration where we look for promising
but uncertain points and then
iteratively carry out data gener
generation and retraining of models and
the goal in my lab with these tools is
to ultimately come up with design rules
at the end of the day I'm a
computational researcher and so I never
want to turn to an experimentalist and
say please make this one molecule it
will solve all the world's problems
because I don't really know at the stage
of predicting
computationally uh if that one material
can easily be made maybe it's too
expensive maybe it's hard to synthesize
but we instead think about distilling
what we learn from traversing these
large chemical spaces of millions of
candidate materials we think about
distilling them into design principles
that can be used broadly When taking
into account other factors we may not
know immediately at this stage so I will
show you one example of this and just as
a note under the hood what we use for
our representations for transition M
complexes is something called revised
autocorrelations they work very flexibly
with different machine learning models
and they adapt very well to transition M
chemistry um they can do things like
predict the quantum mechanical spin
state of a transition M complex which is
something that would normally
individually for each compound take
hours to days with DFT calculations we
can now instead predict them in seconds
to very high accuracy uh but more
importantly than just predicting uh
transition M complex properties fast we
can carry out feature importance so we
can understand why the model makes the
prediction it does and for instance here
I'm showing a spin pie chart that shows
that what's going on at the metal and
directly in its neighborhood is really
important for predicting the quantum
mechanical spin state of a transition M
complex and here's a reaction step we'd
like to optimize the Oxo formation
energy for say a selective CH
functionalization step in catalysis and
you can see these two pie charts are
very similar so even if you thought
nothing about quantum mechanical spin
before you entered this room if you do
care about catalysis you'd quickly
realize that we need to know the spin
state if we want to know the reactivity
of this Catalyst and vice versa um
whereas something like the Redux
potential of the catalyst is actually
totally independent and the reason this
is important is because previously
people had focused on using the redo
potential as a heuristic to predict how
reactive a catalyst was and our machine
learning models show that that's not an
effective
strategy um so what can we do well we
can accelerate C
Discovery we've actually done this a
number of ways uh we've done uh this
type of model exploration approach for
uh searching Redux couples for searching
uh light harvesting chromophores for
photo catalysis but I'm going to show
you an example for a really challenging
reaction so we think the promise of
these Aid driven approaches is greatest
when we think about places where people
have explored a lot of mechanistic trial
and error work and there haven't been
Solutions found and and and a excellent
example of this from catalysis is the
direct conversion of methane to liquid
methanol and so some of the challenges
for direct conversion of methane to
methanol are that we need to form a high
valent metal Oxo if we think we can do
this the way that nature does it and
nature does it quite successfully uh
then we need to carry out hydrogen atom
transfer rebound hydroxy of the methyl
radical and methanol release um and one
of the things we'd really like to
optimize is we'd like methanol to
release quick from the catalyst so it
doesn't get overoxidized while still
favoring the other steps of the reaction
so the way that we're going to explore
this with AI is we're going to create a
candidate pool of 16 million
synthetically reasonable catalysts and
we're going to carry out a series of
rules for assembling these fragments
that recreate known synthetic compounds
that people have worked in the lab for
years but create a lot of Novel
structures that people haven't worked
with yet and to exhaustively study these
experim mentally would never happen in
our lifetime even computationally with
conventional DFT studying 16 million
catalysts is something that would take
me decades to do um so what we do
instead is we do something called
efficient Global optimization we combine
an optimization algorithm with
uncertainty quantification and the first
thing we do is we Define our objectives
which are to optimize the hydrogen atom
transfer energy and release energy
simultaneously in this case but you can
think of any possible objectives that
are of interest in a materials problem
and we're extending this to more
objectives uh as I speak um so we go to
DFT and we we have a patience a budget
for ourselves for about a week with DFT
and we get a handful of points say about
a hundred new catalysts characterized um
and then we're going to train a neural
net and ask the neural net what do you
think of the 16 million compound space
and what we're going to look for is
one's Mo new points most likely to go
past the Paro front so these are the
points that are the most promising most
likely to go past the Paro front but
also most uncertain to the model which
ones can give the most new information
to the model uh then we're going to pick
out candidates and go back to DFT and
this is just a cartoon here but you can
see that we're going to expect that some
of the points the neural net was really
accurate about some of the points not so
much but that doesn't matter because now
we'll retrain the neural net um and
select new points until we continue to
push forward this Paro front uh in
particular a lot of times people use
gaussian processes for this we use
neural Nets with uh latent Spas distance
uncertainty quantification because we
showed this was the most predictive and
efficient way to actually get a good
prediction of future points What's
called the look
aheer uh so this is what it looks like
um so first we have the points from DFT
uh and then we have the expected
Improvement where the points are
predicted to go and we do this for
several generations and after around
three generations we get new compounds
out and these new compounds generally
have a couple of interesting features
one is that manganese shows up typically
synthetic chemists focus on iron because
nature uses iron uh but we find that
manganese is just as promising as iron
is then we also find a predominance of
oxygen coordinating the metal whereas
nitrogen again inspired by nature is
where synthetic chemists have focused
and then finally we find that anionic
ligans um really do a good job of
reducing the electrostatic attraction
with the uh metal center between the
metal center and methanol and overall
the Catalyst that we find from this
screen have kinetic uh turnover
frequencies predicted from our
simulations where we characterize the
transition states that are comparable or
better than the best-in-class uh
catalysts that have been synthesized
before but all of this that I've shown
you is just computational we then have
to turn to experimentalists and ask them
to synthesize these materials so I
wanted to tell you about a story of how
we've closed that gap between how we
imagine uh new materials with AI and get
to synthesizing those materials in the
lab in a tighter Loop how do we maintain
that realism but still explore and
discover new materials and so to tell
you about that I'm going to tell you
about something that's a little bit
further away from catalysis but is about
materials properties and and
toughness and so to do so I have to
introduce aoup couple of phrases you may
not be familiar with um so in the field
of mechanochemistry there are molecular
units known as mechanophores and the
field of mechanochemistry is one in
which we introduce molecularly reactive
units into polymer strands then we pull
on them and in pulling on them we cause
Bonds in the mechanically reactive
mechanophore unit to break and this
engenders unique properties to polymers
it can lead to color change es it can
create self-healing polymers and most
interestingly recently it's been shown
that actually introducing weak
mechanophores into polymer networks can
actually make polymer networks with
overall stronger properties um and so
most of the time mechanophores are
organic molecules which have their own
limitations but very recently Steve
Craig at Duke introduced ferine
mechanophores and this was one of the
first transition M complex mechan for to
have been studied um and this caught my
eye because I love transition M
complexes and what he found was that a
free ferine introduced into a polymer
strand would actually rotate and shear
and this requires more Force to break
experimentally than ones that have this
calent locking then they have a peeling
mechanism instead but in order to
introduce phines into polymer networks
to strengthen them what we want is we
want the weak peeling mechanism both but
we want to achieve it without a calent
lock and this really caught my eye uh as
a computational design challenge in
particular how could we tune the
non-covalent interactions to alter this
mechanochemical response and the reason
it caught my eye is because if you've
ever worked with transition M complexes
you would know that uh metallocenes have
been studied to death experimentally so
only a couple of them have ever been
studied as as mechanophores only two or
three um
but if you go into the Cambridge
structural database which consists of
structures of transition M complexes and
other things that already been studied
experimentally that have a complete
synthesis recipe and characterization
there's actually 5,000 unique ferroin
completely distinct chemical structures
that are well posed for this problem and
so this is maybe not the entire chemical
Space Universe that I laid out for you
on my first slide but this is a very
large space it takes uh it takes about a
year to do one of these experiments on
just one mechanophore um but if we can
actually explore 5,000 novel materials
computationally with AI then that really
turns into addressing a problem that
would never be addressed um in our
lifetimes on the using experiment alone
and so just as an extra wrinkle of this
there's 5,000 unique feros scenes um but
we when we're going to simulate them in
a moment I'm going to attach polymer
strands to them and there's some unique
ways that you can differently attach the
polymer strand to the ferine to create
unique compounds so we actually have not
just 5,000 materials to consider but
12,000 um and so what are we going to do
we're going to simulate the effect of
force on these different ferroin
embedded in polymer strands and I'm
going to use a technique called CF you
don't need to know too much about it it
just it uh is an efficient way to model
the effective force and I'm going to
study around 3% of the feasible space I
just created created for you from
materials that have already been
synthesized so that's about 425
complexes and what you notice is that
our data recapitulates what the
experimentalists already figured out
these are the ones that are coal linked
it's really easy to get a low force uh
breaking apart of this ferine compound
but when they uh don't have a calent
link it's harder to get that Force down
but we can distinguish that there's a
tail of low Force compounds that we
already see in this initial set of 42
25 and what we can do is we can train a
a machine learning model a multi-layer
perceptron classifier trained on those
racks I showed you very briefly a few
slides ago and this model performs
really well so it predicts the
computational ability of something to be
either low force or high force and we're
going to do what I call oneshot Active
Learning here so we're going to use this
model to screen the remaining
11,800 materials we haven't
computationally screened so far
and this is what we get we see a big
enrichment now of computationally
validated with DFT points an an
additional around few hundred points
where we predict now much lower forces
and the reason we stop after one
generation is because when we actually
trained a machine learning model again
on this new data and looked at the
remaining points we had yet to
characterize it didn't predict very many
points at all that were left that we had
not yet characterized so we had
essentially saturated the design space
with opportunities to lower the force in
these ferine
mechanophores um so at this point we
went to the experimentalists our
collaborators at Duke Steve Craig and we
had identified lots of neat ways to
lower the force to deize ferene so we
have Pi pie stacking we have St uh
sterically bulky groups we have
non-covalent interactions such as
different hydrogen bonding Partners but
this is where it gets tricky because
we're not just asking them to make
ferene that's pretty easy but we're
actually asking them to use ring opening
uh polymerization to embed the ferene
into polymer strands and networks um and
so we talked with them and we showed
them some candidates and this was this
was an interesting candidate so this was
one in which we introduced steric bulk
on the ferine cyclop pental ring with a
TMS group um and in particular the CSD
ref code that we found was called nus
that's this blue line here and what
we're looking for is a line that crosses
this horizontal line at a lower Force
value this is a slightly different
simulation technique it's slightly
higher Fidelity um and then they looked
at that and they said well that's a
little hard for us to make can we get
rid of this carbonal group and I said
sure and then you end up with just mtms
that's this red line here so you can see
we still predict its uh significantly
lower force and then as control we have
the dash line which is just pure ferine
as well as if you would move this group
you would lose the El Ric effect that
the mtms is having in addition to the
steric bulk and then you get basically
back to the original ferine result here
at the highest Force um so that is
exactly what they made they made the
mtms the material that we predicted this
is all computational results right now
um but I'm going to show you right now
what they did what they were able to see
experimentally so in this uh curve what
you're seeing here if you're not used to
looking at these you're seeing how much
the material can be strained Until It
Breaks and so here's the Cove valent
control here's ferine and then here is
the material we designed computationally
so we're able to achieve over a
four-fold increase in network toughness
going from predictions we make with
machine learning accelerated DFT on the
molecular scale all the way up to the
network scale um so I think this is
really cool um but what I think is
cooler is that this is actually a a
property so if you're not used to
looking at those graphs if you want to
see what it actually looks like it
corresponds to this experiment um and so
on the left you see the control material
on the middle you see the ferene and on
the right you see our design material
all three materials will rip uh but our
design material will rip
last um and so uh this is an example of
something where in a matter of months
we've gone from only knowing about one
class of one kind of material to being
able to explore and propose uh from a
space of 12 thousand new materials which
one should be studied and realized in
the lab so a lot of people ask me well
how many failure cases do you have and
the answer is actually none so when we
showed several candidates to our our
synthesis uh colleagues they picked out
just this one to make and this is the
only one they have made so our success
rate is actually 100% on this I don't
expect that to always be the case um but
just to emphasize that we really cut
down dramatically on how many EXP
experiments were being done in the lab
uh to make this happen and this is
exactly where I think the future of AI
and computationally accelerated
materials Discovery needs to go um and I
hope I've conveyed that some of these
observations we've been able to make can
be applied in catalysis they can be
applied in polymer mechanochemistry they
can be applied in a range of different
fields um and they all uh can benefit
from very similar themes uh in terms of
how we we think about uh creating data
sets and accelerating the exploration of
chemical
spaces so in um the last sort of 40% of
my talk I'm going to switch gears now uh
to a different material space and that's
in metal organic
Frameworks um and so I came into metal
organic Frameworks because I was working
a lot in transition M complexes but I
wanted to study a material that was more
practical and scalable and useful in
industrial applications um and that may
sound funny that I said moffs because
moffs have a bit of of a reputation with
with plenty of Industry folks for not
necessarily uh being realistic at
industrial scale for a few reasons I'm
hopefully by the end of this talk going
to address a few of them uh in any case
uh but what attracted me to them is they
look a lot like transition M complexes
so they have a secondary building unit
where we have metal centers with Organic
lians around this looks just like our
transition M complex then we have
linkers connecting these secondary
building units creating open porous
structures and moths are attractive for
a large number of uses today I'm going
to tell you a couple stories about
catalysis gas separation and storage my
lab also works in sensing pretty much
the only one of these we don't work in
is drug delivery but I'm I'm open-minded
about that um and because you can mix
together uh many salts and linkers you
can create combinatorially vast spaces
of candidate moth materials you can also
think about iterative combining these
components to create lots of different
materials
computationally but the trial and error
discovery of Novel moths say for gas
storage applications has been really uh
tedious and slow so what I'm showing
here is the year-over-year progress in
changing the pore geometry which is
important for gas storage applications
of moths and you can see uh the
difference the chemical difference in
what are best MF is from year to year
only in a couple cases do we have a year
where really novel MF has discovered
there are many years where the progress
is quite incremental um so there's lots
of data out there about mths there's
lots of things people have tried
thousands of researchers have worked on
moths uh but trial and error alone is
too slow to identify mths with ideal
properties and one of the things that we
noticed about moffs early on when we got
into this space is the first thing we
wanted to do was develop machine
learning models trained on features of
MFS including what is the poe geometry
of a MF as well as devising a novel
representation called racks for moths in
which we divided a moth into its
different chemical components and looked
at what were the most important features
and one of the first things we noticed
was we could train models on
experimental structures of mths mths
that had already been synthesized or on
these hypothetical sets that people had
enumerated of new candidate materials
that were promising but had not yet been
synthesized and what we noticed was the
feature importance is different if you
use experimental versus hypothetical
moths and this troubled us because we
want to come up with and distill design
rules as I mentioned and so if we look
at these different moth sets we get
different design rules um so we wanted
to look at why that was what is the
difference between moths that have
already been synthesiz versus these
novel moths folks are imagining that
could be the moths of the
future and so here I'm showing
dimensionality reduction in each of the
different feature subsets to try to
depict which of the parts of a moth are
most different between experimental and
hypothetical moths and if you see gray
peeking through that means that there's
an experimental moth but there's no
hypothetical equivalent uh so in terms
of pore geometry uh everything actually
looks pretty similar which surprised me
when I first saw it I thought Poe
geometry the first thing you do
computationally is build a pore that's
way too big same goes for Linker
chemistry and functional groups uh but
where the plot actually thickens is when
we look at metal chemistry so in
particular what we see is that there are
many types of sbus that have been
studied experimentally that have never
made it into hypothetical materials so
we tend to think of hypothetical
computational models as being highly
unrealistic and and containing too many
wacky things that can never be
synthesized in the lab but there's
actually many cases where instead the
computational sets actually lack the
diversity that people have already been
able to achieve experimentally so this
motivated us to take a different path
and try to learn as much as we could
from the experimental literature in
particular tens of thousands of moths
are really well characterized they have
uh single Crystal structures and they
have properties associated with them
that have been published in the
literature there are some challenges
with thinking about how we name them and
identify what they are uh so we wanted
to overcome that and in particular
extract all of the information we could
which was made possible by license
agreements MIT Library had with the
Publishers and what we're able to do was
look at 10 th000 papers um or sorry
10,000 structures which which ultimately
boil down to about 7,000 structures and
ask ourselves what do researchers
publish about moths when they write
papers about moths and it turns out that
the two things that came up to mind
first were actually very lucky for us
because both were abundant and both are
really hard to predict computationally
but both are important for thinking
about making moths useful at industrial
scale and so the first is the activation
stability of moths can you once you
synthesize a moth can you evacuate the
pores and make them a stable por
structure or will they collapse and this
is something we use natural language
processing to extract sent with
sentiment analysis whether or not
something was activation stable and the
others the thermal stability of a moth
so if we think about mths for catalysis
one of the chief reasons we wouldn't
want to use them is that they might lose
their crystallinity when we use elevated
temperatures in thermal catalysis um so
here we use training a regression model
and we do automatic Griff digitization
of the TGA Trace to avoid ambiguities
with how people self-report results from
TGA traces and so here we have a rack
strained uh multi-layer perceptron
classifier that predicts activation
stability here we have the model that
predicts thermal stability and so it can
predict the experimentally observed
thermal stability of a moth to around
44c uh the uncertainty in the
measurement itself is 25c so it's not
bad and we can also predict if a moth is
going to be activation stable and we can
use these models now we can interpret
feature importance to understand what
does it take to make a stable moth and
what's interesting is that both for
Activation stability and for thermal
stability the Linker chemistry actually
dominates this so the atoms are big
meaning that Linker chemistry is really
important and so if we look at this
particular moof it lacks activation
stability um our model would tell us the
first thing you need to do is get rid of
this methoxy group on the Linker and
indeed in doing so we recover activation
stability of this moth if we had relied
on heuristics from the literature we
would have instead said oh the problem
is the metal in this MTH it's zinc why
don't we replace it with calcium doing
that would not have improved the
activation stability of the moth so
heuristics that are established in the
literature are outperformed by analyzing
and looking at predictions from our ml
models uh the same thing goes for
thermal stability here there's a lot a
little bit of electronic contribution
but again the Linker dominates so the
average thermal stability of moths in
our set is actually not bad it's about
360 C um and here's a
moth uh that has very low stability only
182c so we see that we should fluorinate
the Linker in order to strengthen the
metal Linker Bond and doing so we
improve the thermal stability by about
130c um so more recently we've expanded
this um so one of the things we've done
is we've looked at building models that
can predict the water stability of moths
motivated by the need to be able to have
moths that can withstand high humidity
for direct air capture as well as for
catalysis applications um and so
previous data sets did exist they were
out there there were about 200 data
points of of moths in a previously
curated set from about 10 years ago we
use natural language processing to
expand this to about a thousand moths so
about fivefold larger um um and looking
at model performance shows why you want
to actually go to mthfs of having at
least a thousand experimental data
points the performance increases quite a
bit when you go from where things were
um to where we are now interestingly we
also built the first models to predict
the stability of mths in acid base and
boiling and our acid model we don't know
why entirely performs actually really
well um and interestingly one of the
things that predicts if a mooff can
withstand acid treatment is actually if
it has large pores having large pores is
good for for acid stability and so
things we can do with this is are we can
combine genetic algorithms or other
multi-objective optimization algorithms
um to simultaneously optimize novel
moths now for Activation stability
stability in water and stability in acid
as an example and we're pairing them now
with screening uh for direct air capture
applications um I just like to point out
that everything I described is in in a
website so you don't have to be a coder
or a computational chemist to use our
models uh this animation shows the
activation and thermal stability models
but the water and acid models are also
on there as are models that predict um
the uh uptake of C2 um specifically
ethane and ethylene from recent work
that I didn't have a chance to talk
about where we've also taken this
approach to predict experimental uh gas
isotherms and one of my favorite things
about this is we can do things like show
you where the data comes from as well as
ask you to rate uh the predictions that
we've made and um and in particular uh
upload new data if you think there's
something wrong with our model so we
hope to use Community feedback in
particular to um to help continue to
improve these models and so I just like
to finish with one anecdote of where I
think this is going and how I think this
can be useful again coming back to the
theme I introduced earlier that
sometimes what we need is not new
materials but materials that can be
repurposed from other communities um and
so what we did was we went back to
experimental moths um and we looked at
moths that seemed promising for
catalysis but had never before been
studied for Catal catalysis so these are
all synthesized moths um our models
predict them to be stable with respect
to Thermal stability so they're
promising for catalysis they have open
Metal sites where catalytic
Transformations can occur and then we do
again natural language processing here
specifically looking for no mention of
catalysis we don't want to study things
people have already studied before we
want to study materials no one has
studied before for catalysis even though
they've been studied experimentally and
we screen the top 100 with DFT again
focusing here now on the same
transformation of methane to methanol
and here I'm showing Oxo formation
energy and release energies and the
interesting thing that comes out here
again mirroring what I showed you on uh
transition M complexes is that one of
the big surprises is that manganese
actually seems really promising
manganese moths um end up sort of Best
in Class for both simultaneous release
of methanol as well as favorable
oxoforms
that are now being synthesized and
tested by our experimental collaborators
uh because they have good combination of
overall kinetics predicted for methane
to methanol uh these moths also have
good mechanical iCal stability which I
didn't have time to talk about
today um so I think this is actually my
last slide um but uh one of the things I
mentioned is that we have hypothetical
materials out there they're very large
sets so they're very impressive hundreds
of thousands of new moths and so one of
the things we could do now that we had
these experimental stability models is
we could actually find out that many of
the moths that are in these hypothetical
sets actually lack significant stability
they lack thermal stability and
activation stability they need to show
up in this orange circle here on this
two-dimensional graph if they're going
to have that combined stability um and
so I can pick on lots of different
hypothetical MF data sets none of them
have that high stability so what we did
was we took apart moths that are known
experimentally to have high stability we
broke them down into their components
and then we recombined them in novel
ways hoping we would lead to higher uh
overall stability of Novel materials
that still are closely related to
experimentally synthesiz materials and
in doing so we actually introduced we
solved the diversity problem so we now
have metal spus uh all across the
periodic table with much more diversity
than was achieved on previous
hypothetical sets and on top of that we
now have points in that region I told
you we needed to be in to have really
high thermal stability and really high
activation stability we actually achieve
about 20% of our materials compared to 0
2% are now um this very high stability
and we can screen for other properties
such as simultaneously good mechanical
stability and deliverable capacity for
methane and so we for instance find new
design rules such as privileged Cobalt
porer inic nodes that can create Open
Spaces but High mechanical
stability so just to finish up I think I
have about a minute left um uh I told
you a story where we were able to um get
from the computational prediction to uh
experimental realization in the lab by
exploring a space that was synthetically
feasible for transition metal mechan for
Discovery to strengthen polymer networks
I also told you some stories about how
we reveal design rules including
directly from experimental observations
in the literature overcoming heris STS I
told you a little something about how we
um uh specifically are able to repurpose
moths for other applications they
haven't been studied for as well as how
we start to think about building
hypothetic materials everything I've
told you about today on both the
molecules and on the moths is an open-
Source software it's available on our
website also in cond and GitHub um and I
just like to finish by acknowledging the
students who did the work um their names
are all here but I'd especially like to
mention uh adicha nandy changan o um and
Ilia kevish villy who did the Fantastic
work on the polymers and thank you for
your attention
[Applause]
okay
um so um do I ever experience property
gaps where the slightest change in a
molecule dramatically Alters its
physical properties in a ways that are
difficult to predict in ml um
so we work with challenging uh open
shell systems that have different
electronic States and the quickest way
to create a proper Gap is to be studying
one type of electronic State um and then
end up in another one with a slightly
different Li we carry out uh data checks
and some degree of sandboxing to avoid
those cases uh a good example of this if
you're a trained chemist would be Lian
non-innocence if you go from having the
spin on the metal to having the spin on
the organic component of the of the
molecule um so we specifically when we
train our model to avoid confusing the
model we avoid those examples um but uh
the Next Generation would necessarily be
a model that can predict those two
things side by side so the answer is yes
but that that we kind of Sid step that a
little um so can we predict uh chemical
behavior of Keating polymers absorbed on
metal materials such as uh surfaces such
as steel um so it depends on how many I
so I think you could use the same
methodology completely unchanged if
you're thinking about a local
interaction but if you also care about
the folding of the polymer and multiple
different Keating sites interacting then
I think the right approach would be
potentially to train um neural network
potentials and still do uh molecular
Dynamics but at the Fidelity that can be
achieved um with with uh neural network
potential that being said if it's a
local phenomenon we knowing the the
local effect is sufficient then
basically what we've done out of the box
could be used for the same type of
approach um so I think it is definitely
possible it depends on the
specifics
um it is necessary to convert chemical
structures into numerical
representations but has the method you
are using been validated so that could
refer to a lot of different things um we
always validate our models both on set
aside test data as well well as
completely unseen out of distribution
data so for instance in the moth example
I gave you we were able to automatically
download a few thousand papers and what
we did to validate our model is we
picked out new papers we couldn't
automatically download but could read
with our eyes and validated the models
that the models still perform well on
those completely new systems um the same
thing goes when we're looking we might
pick say we stud trained a model on
manganese we would test if it still
worked on Cobalt
um there are certain representations
that generalize better so if your goal
is generalization you may pay the cost
more for a better representation one
example we've done there is we actually
use quantum mechanical inputs uh into
our models and then those models tend to
generalize better than say the
graph-based representations I showed but
those are some some ways in which we've
validated the models
oh this is a hard question um so uh uh
because Catalyst driven it's a hard
question for me um because Catalyst
driven disruptions will happen across
multiple sectors simultaneously which
industry will have the hardest time
adapting to potential new synergies so
so I think there are a couple challenges
um one is does the existing Capital
Equipment does it um uh adapt well to
different catalysts um that could be
used for example Le um so there are lots
of fine chemical applications where I
think it's much more straightforward to
think about designing a new Catalyst
structure whereas for very large scale
chemical production it seems more
challenging and there's also more
resistance to thinking about say oh I
always use uh nanop particles that are
um Palladium coated with with some
carbon or this and that and now you're
going to ask me to use a moth instead um
so so that seems seems that's there's
much more resistance from there whereas
say in the homogeneous catalysis
Community I think there's already and we
work with sponsors where um you know
they are already using the tools I
described here uh to think about how do
you design and recommend novel catalst
structur so I think things that uh can
be scaled up quickly are are where that
would be uh the anyway um so uh um so so
we like working with with folks who are
thinking not just about the specific
application but the workflow um so we've
had great sponsorships like that before
a lot of what my group does is we
someone tells us about a problem and we
develop the software and the approach um
and so I really enjoy working with
people who are thinking about something
not just for one specific Target
application make this one molecule
slightly better but how can my company
adapt the tools that I mean you you
saying how could how could your company
adapt the tools that my group develops
to a broader uh set of materials
um okay thank you very much thank you
very much