Hello everyone. My name is Andra Mendes.
I'm founder CEO of KAI. Uh before I was
a co-founder in another company called
Pistol Data and I have a PhD in computer
science from NOU and I have been doing
research in machine learning here at
MIT.
Um okay. So the problem that we're going
to talk about today is the problem of
e-commerce in the e-commerce data in the
marketplace. So every time that you have
a marketplace you have a lots of data
and this data come from many different
sources and most of the time the sources
are not structurized. So as you have
medium of products coming from different
sources um this data has to be organized
for you to order to offer basic service
right so if you want your customer to be
able to find your product you have to
offer discovery search analytics
comparisons and everything else and that
has a direct impact on your conversion
rates your return rates and most
important how much your customer trust
your
platform. So basically there are some
problems that comes when you have like
the bad data. So you have duplicated
products, you have irre irrelevant
recommendations and you have a very bad
like search experience. So basically
your product your customer cannot find
your product or when it finds a product
is the wrong product and the experience
is bad. All of this seems kind of simple
and and silly but when we look at the
numbers that's a huge problem to
e-commerce space. More than 90 billion
dollars are lost due poor poor
experience. And a lot of this happens
because people just abandoned their
carts because they have a poor
experience in buying something that they
thought was a product but was something
else. And of course the biggest problem
in e-commerce which is return right like
every time that you buy something that
you did not like and return that's a
huge problem for any people selling into
the e-commerce space. So that's where it
enters KOI. So a lot of our customers
they either don't solve that problem or
they are trying to solve that using some
manual operations like it's not it's not
necessarily hard to fix a problem in one
or two or even 100 products but it's
very hard to fix on a thousand products
and 10,000 products. So basically our
goal is to offer a solution as a data as
a service where our customers don't have
to build the entire team to do that.
they can just rely on koa to have their
data organized, structurized in one
place and we want to do this as simple
as possible. So basically the way that
works we have a simple API call uh our
customers send this data in a very raw
way. So basically a lot of times it's
just a product description and some
image and we use our internal AI models
to basically process all types of data.
We work with image, we work with
description, we work with other codes
that are similar to the industry. And
the output is just this structure
organized data that is in the best
format for our customers to do
everything else. So the goal is that
they don't have to worry about the data
anymore or the underlying data and they
can focus more on the customer
experience on their
website. Here's an example of the
customers that we had in Brazil. It's
one of the biggest um auto parts
marketplace in Brazil. And once they
started work with us, they had like 30%
improve in conversion rates. They had
15% reduce in the in returning rates and
30% improve and clients finding the
right product. And that was like a very
important thing for uh the auto parts uh
market. Uh so that's what we're trying
to do like our vision is to actually
provide various experience in the
marketplace but we also helping brands
and sellers that they they need to sell
in many other places. So we helping them
also to better configure that data so
they're able to expand their their
offer. Um we have been operating for
more than three years. We have customers
in three different countries. We operate
in English, Portuguese, Spanish. Um and
we're looking for partners and clients,
marketplaces, procurement platforms, and
also brands and sellers that sell into
marketplaces. Thank you.
I'm I'm a plant really. Although some
may call me a weed, but never mind. So,
how do you validate the the accuracy of
what the customer is looking for versus
there may be two or three different
products out there, right? What kind of
a guessing game do you have to know that
this is really what I'm thinking about
as opposed to those two other ones?
Yeah. So, basically our main goal is
like we work with product data and in
this part like the accuracy has to be
very high. So a lot of the industries
that we work already have our own ground
truth. So basically we have collected
the this the main data from many
different u sources and every time that
the customer has like whatever product
that they need we do a comparison with
that. So that's a very simple thing. So
but in order to do that comparison you
have to be able to extract what are the
right features of this product that I
can tell if the two products are the
same or not. So that's where we
specialize because if I have the ground
truth and I know how to compare to any
other chiffon product that's coming to
me, I can say, "Oh, these two products
are actually the same or this product
actually are different products." Okay,
thanks.
Thank you. And how is it different um to
use um KOA versus some of the tools out
there or even building their own
internal?
That's like honestly our that's the
question that we get the most like why
people why companies don't just build
this internally. First of all it's a lot
more expensive. It's another team that
you have to manage. But the biggest
thing is like especially now with AI is
that everybody's like oh why don't I
just use LLM for to do that. This
industry requires like a very high
accuracy right so LLMs are very good for
many things but usually you cannot get
95 96% of accuracy. A lot of times you
just spend like actually validating what
you get. So the best thing that we offer
a lot of our customers come and say hey
I've tried this for three months and it
doesn't work I cannot implement the
system how can I solve this because
that's not my core my car should provide
the other experience I have to do with
logistics I have to do return how can I
actually get this data clean so a lot of
times it's just that like that it's just
a lot more time consuming resource
consuming for our customers to do inside
thank you thank