So I'll be sharing some work that my
group has been doing over the past few
years in uh in computational topology.
Here are my
disclosures. Um and this is just a list
of everything I'll be talking about
today in case you want to go back and
look at some of these studies later. So
my group predominantly focuses on
computational pathology. So when uh
glass slides are are are digitized
um they look something like this. So
large images that are hierarchical uh
and harbor information at many many
different scales. They're more like
satellite images uh something you know
similar to what you would see on on
Google maps or Google Earth. Um and uh
these information the the these slides
harbor a lot of a lot of information.
The interesting thing about pathology is
that it's one of the oldest uh
diagnostic modalities but it's also one
of the oldest research modalities. So so
it's been around for a very very long
time. uh as everyone here knows it's
used for very fundamental biological
research but on on human animal all
kinds of tissue uh but also for uh for
clinical uh clinical diagnostics right
so um but a caveat is that this is
despite being one of the oldest
modalities is also also a modality
that's only recently began to be
digitized I think the first scanner came
about about 20 years ago and still most
hospitals in the country are not
entirely digital and the standard of
care remains looking at glass slides
under under a microscope. All the other
modalities that came about later like
genomics and other kinds of information
that we can extract from tissue are by
default digital and computational. So we
still haven't incorporated uh
information from this modality into our
diagnostic prognostic therapeutic
response or resistance prediction
prediction
paradigms.
Um and uh so what we predominantly do is
that we essentially try to analyze these
images using computational machine
learning tools to get to everything in
the red box here whether it's early
diagnosis, prognosis, response to
treatment, patient stratification and so
forth. Essentially discovery from this
this kind of data but we also
incorporate information from other
modalities where necessary to try to f
fulfill some of those objectives. Um, so
I'll be talking mostly about the the
work that my my lab does in in human
pathology, but we also do a lot of work
in pre-clinical drug screening and
toxicology and how to make those uh
processes more efficient. Uh, and uh, a
lot of those uh, questions essentially
require the same computational tools
that we that we build. But I won't be
talking a lot about that aspect uh,
today. So the history of the field is
very interesting and I always like to
talk about it. So Judith Prevette uh was
a real pioneer in this field and she's
really an unsung hero because some of
the work that she was doing in the 60s
and 70s is phenomenal around how she was
thinking about this uh about this
problem. She worked at the University of
Pennsylvania then at NIH and finally at
the university university of Upsala
where she had access to large mainframe
computers. uh but this this study from
1963 and in particular this study from
1965 if you look at how she was
analyzing these images so so she
realized that these images are very very
large she was chopping them up into
smaller patches we still do this today
because we can't fit these mega images
into in in in into GPU memory at least
not to do uh the kind of training we do
and
um storing these in magnetic uh tape
using optical density and then using
very fundamental line profiles to assess
whether an image is is deemed to be
positive or negative. What a lot of
people don't know is that this became
the basis of the very first FDA approved
um pathology algorithm was called uh
autoap uh for papsmears in the 19 1990s
and uh uh has has been used since to
reduce workload to triage out negative
cases and is one of the only uh
pathology based algorithms that is
approved for primary diagnosis such that
the pathologist does not have to go back
and look at that particular
particular image. And then you know with
the all the in more recent times there's
been a lot of work using handcrafted
features essentially reflecting how we
perceive these images uh and coming up
with features that would be reflective
of those uh uh of that perception. And
then post 2015 the utility of
convolutional neural networks uh and
this was predominantly achieved by uh
pixel level uh annotation on these on
these slides. However, this is very far
removed from how this data is available
and collected clinically. So,
clinically, we don't collect any pixel
level annotations on these uh on these
images. Once you have these annotations,
you can, you know, separate that data
into buckets and use very fundamental
deep learning algorithms to classify
cancer, normal, subtype, grade,
anything. But, uh the the issue is the
labels. we don't have uh pixel level
annotations uh as part of the regular
clinical workflow and that's where we
all all these weekly supervised methods
that have been developed for this kind
of data come in and uh the two most
common ones are the utility of using
graph convolutional neural networks
where you can segment all the all the
cells and build a build a cell graph on
top of it. Um that can be quite
computationally complex especially given
that each case can have a multitude of
slides. the average slides per case are
between 8 to nine but but a single case
can have up to 100 100 gigapixel uh
slides. So uh the most common approach
which would you know which comes to mind
from from a machine learning point of
view is is the utility of multiple
instance learning right because you you
have large images maybe you can split
them into smaller smaller patches and
per case you also have multitude of
images. So whenever you have lots of uh
lots of instances you can use multiple
instance learning assuming that uh a
slide is a bag of many many small
patches and if you if you're using a max
pulling based aggregation function um
the the assumption would be that even if
one of those patches is positive the
entire slide would be considered to be
to to to be positive. Um an issue with
this approach is that this makes this
setup inherently data inefficient
because uh the weights and biases of the
model could be updated using a single
256 x 256 patch. And this is what was
articulated in this 2019 really seinal
study was published at the Memorial
Sloan Ketering Cancer Center where they
showed that you needed about 10,000
pulses to get the same level of
performance you would get with slide
level labels. This is back in 2019 and
they're focusing on targeting very
fundamental problems like like detection
uh subtyping grading uh and
prognostication, right? But but we we
really wanted to see if there's a
there's a more data efficient way to do
this and we started working in this area
around around the same time in 200 2019.
Uh so we can target the more interesting
problems in pathology like rare cancers,
clinical trials, patient stratification.
So uh in 2021 we published this study
and it's called the method clustering
constraint attention mal and it used a
number of different bells and whistles
that were that were developed for
computer vision. We brought them into
pathology and this included uh attention
based multiple instance learning the
utility of pre-trained encoders and and
using clustering as a mechanism to
cluster together similar morphologic
regions within the slide. So a slide
would have lots of normal regions lots
of u uh disease positive tumor regions.
So, so clustering can potentially help
uh associate similar regions together
across entire entire cohorts. And we
made this tool publicly available and
over time this has sort of become uh
very widely used and has been applied to
almost every every disease model that's
tackled using uh human uh human for for
human pathology. Um so so the basic
workflow is is is actually very very
simple. It's it's you have whole slide
images. You scan them. Once they're
scanned, you have a whole uh you you you
you have a large hierarchical image. You
can segment the tissue, patch it into
smaller patches, and then you can
extract features, right? So, so there
was a lot of work that was training this
end to end, but but but that can be
inherently slow uh computationally
limiting. But if you use a pre-trained
uh encoder in the beginning, we were
just using a resnet that was trained on
imageet features. uh so you standard uh
uh between 2019 and and up until
recently when we started using
self-supervised learning it was really
just a resnet that was trained on
imageet features you have eventually get
to a patch embedding there's there's
some aggregation and then the slide
level embedding gets fed into a
predictor and you can pose this as being
any kind of machine learning problem
this could be a classification problem
targeting you know disease detection
subtyping grading or it could be a a
prognostication problem where uh you're
you're essentially solving a or a
ranking problem, ranking patients into
distinct risk groups or it could be
treatment response, anything anything
that you practically have a label
available for. So a number of different
applications we targeted back in we
started it started this in 2019. I'll
just say a little bit about those
applications. So we we looked into
cancers of unknown primary when I think
most people here are familiar when
cancer metastasizes it often becomes
unclear what the origin of the tumor
might be and most treatments are based
off of the origin. So this is this is a
critical problem. These patients
typically undergo large workups of of uh
not not only diagnostic pathology but
also radiology
endoscopy, repeated molecular testing to
try to see if if the origin can be
determined and and uh if an origin is
not determined, the patient often cannot
enroll in clinical trials either. So in
this study from 2021, the the primary
question we tried to answer is that can
we use conventional H& images to
determine what the origin might be? And
we believe this would be possible
because there's lots of studies showing
that you can predict molecular
alterations or or or essentially proving
that there are there there are more
morphologic correlates to molecular
alterations within the hisystologology
hisystology image. And we showed that
you know you you could predict what the
what the origin is. uh you know
effectively solving first a binary
problem whether whether the case is
primary versus metastatic and then then
an 18 classification problem about what
the origin origin might be and then uh
looking at the top three top five
predictions was was critical because it
can give you an essential hint for what
the origin might be and you can order
ancillary tests like IC's to confirm to
confirm that that that origin that that
reduces time and this is something that
we have implemented at at at MGH that
for every metastatic case we're able to
look at what the possible origins might
be and then already order those those
ancillary tests before a physician
starts looking at it before a
pathologist starts looking at it. More
recently we have also used the all the
molecular data that we had available
that was available to us from the Dina
Farber profile cohort uh and we have
tried to combine hisystologology and
molecular data using very fundamental
form of form of fusion. This this was a
study that really started a while ago
but then you know the amount of
validation that was that that was needed
to to do this took took several years
because we needed to get data from other
other institutions and it's very
difficult to get uh cancers of unknown
primary cases where the origin was
already determined but this will be
coming out in the next couple of weeks
where we try to combine hisystologology
and molecular data to see if we can
improve origin origin prediction. uh and
we basically assess that um how well can
you predict the origin just from
molecular data from histologology and
what happens when you combine
histologology and uh and molecular data.
Another application we targeted using
the same sort of paradigm was around
endomyioardial biopsy assessments after
heart transplants. Patients often
undergo repeated endomyiocardial uh
biopsies or heart biopsies to to
determine if the donor heart is being
rejected by the recipient. This is a
problem where there's a large intra and
intraobserver variability and we wanted
to see if it's possible for us to
standardize this a little bit more using
using these machine learning techniques.
This was a study from back in 2022. I
mean I wouldn't go into the details but
there's a lot of uh analysis around what
happens when you use do do when you have
human in the loop uh assessments for
these biopsies. So uh another as another
sort of application was trying to see if
we can combine uh hisystologology and
molecular data to improve prognostic
models. So we know that molecular data
is is is directly very prognostic. There
are a number of these commercially
available prognostic assays like Pigma
Alpype DX. Um all of them are uh uh
they're they're good to a degree.
They're they're they're imperfect but
but but they do work. So but but we
basically wanted to answer two
questions. Is it possible for us to
combine histologology data with the
molecular information to see if we can
improve prognostication? because
histologology data is relatively free,
right? It's it's always there and it's
it's available, it's very it's a very
cheap modality. So if you can
prognosticate patients by combining it
with with with molecular data, why not?
Um and the other question would be that
can we predict uh similar uh patient
separation uh just from the
hisystologology hisystologology alone.
And the third one was effectively around
looking at uh once we have made these
predictions, they're all done in a
weekly supervised manner. And can can we
go back and look at what's important in
the molecular profile, what's important
in the in the morphologic profile in an
attempt to make uh assessments, you
know, discover new markers and and we
did a lot of analysis on the 14
different cancer types that were that
were assessed. And we have since made
the all of that publicly available and
people have found all kinds of
morphologic features uh that are
consistent across uh across across
patients. This was a cancer cell article
from back in 2022.
Um so coming back to the uh ML paradigm
that we're effectively using. So it
became clear that the uh feature
extraction component is is the most
important component to me. Started
experimenting with self-supervised
learning as it was becoming popular
initially with by using contrasted
predictive coding back in 2021. It was a
new article where we showed that you can
use contrasted predictive coding to
improve feature presentation for these
uh large multiple instance learning uh
problems. In 2022, we uh we developed
something that we call hierarchical
image pyramid transformer that makes
makes use of the inherent hierarchy in
the in the in in the pathology image to
and and uses self-supervised learning on
top of it to improve representation at
at at various different hierarchical
scales. That's a CVPR study from 2020 uh
2022. Um and then uh last year we
published these two foundation models.
uh and and I think that the the critical
inflection point was that when uh Meta
showed in their Dynino V2 study that the
diversity of data is much more important
than the quantity of data, something
that we you know we we always knew but
but it was like a proof. Um uh we that
gave us an opening that that we we don't
effectively need to scan every single
slide through our history to develop a
foundation model for pathology. We could
we could potentially go back our archive
um and look at what are the most diverse
cases, pull those diverse the most the
most diverse cases and scan those and
potentially that would be good enough to
develop a develop a foundation model
representing human pathology. Um so to
test that hypothesis we basically did
exactly that. We look through Brigham
and M MGH archives looking at all the
pathology reports finding what are the
most unique uh cases and pull those
cases scan them uh and then you know
develop these models. The other one was
a vision language model and these models
were made publicly available and have
since been downloaded over 1.4 million
times and they've been out for about a
year and we're still investigating what
the impact has been but they've already
been used in over 400 different studies.
And I think one key aspect is that
pathology data is so fundamental to uh
everything we do in biio medicine in in
general. But there's never been sort of
a clear way on how to incorporate this
data. It's large, complex, all of that,
right? It exists. But but if but if you
can have uh you know lower dimensional
representations of that data, it's it's
it's it's quite easy to incorporate that
into any question that you might be
might be on asking. Um, so, uh, sorry,
could you define what you mean when you
say like looking for the most unique
pathology images? Like, is that by
defined by a pathologist or is there
some sort of metric for diversity? We we
looked at a number of different uh ways.
I mean, I mean, you could just embed all
the pathology reports and see in feature
space uh how they separate. That's what
we initially did because we have, you
know, 22 million pathology reports. So,
so how do you figure out uh so we we
started looking at all the pathology
reports then you know uh embedding them
and then so the reports are images and
text or just images just just text just
text okay reports are just text no image
so so they typically so so there's a lot
of diversity across the reports uh they
have diagnostic information grade
information clinical correlations and it
varies a lot across pathologists so so
pathologists in community hospitals
would often write a detailed report with
morphologic description and everything
in there leading up to the diagnosis. A
lot of pathologists in more advanced
centers would just say well you know
this is renal cell carcinoma full stop
and right so so there's there's culture
um but they would always have
information about uh diagnosis uh if
there's any prognostic indication such
as grade um so so there's some some
standardization to it and then there's
also synoptic reports so we didn't look
at synoptic reports we just looked at
the descriptive reports embedded them
and look looking at it in feature case.
Uh uh that was one way. Uh but we also
looked at just by looking at the
diagnosis how diverse it is. Uh and then
there was some existing data that we had
collected in in the past for other for
other projects that was also that was
also used and in in often cases some of
the data that we're collecting was very
diverse to begin with because dealing
with rare disease and other kinds of
indications. Yeah. So
uh um so in this uh so it was around
100,000 cases. We have 100 million
pathology images from 100,000 cases.
This was the initial version of the uh
of the model and it used the Dino V2
framework for for training and at the
time we compared it with a number of
other models as well as just the
baseline ResNet 50 trained on imageet
that was the most commonly used um
encoder for for pathology images and it
was applied to you know 33 clinical
tasks downstream. The radar plot is a
terrible way to look at it, but uh it
does capture all the all the different
tasks that were done and what the
comparative analysis is with other other
kinds of models including looking at
classification, retrieval or image
search uh segmentation and uh and both
at original level and at a slide level.
So these are just some results for slide
level classification and it it has very
difficult tasks and and also relatively
easy easy tasks and we can see what the
performance difference is for example
with a ResNet baseline which was
typically used before we we we put these
studies out there. There's there's been
a lot of uh foundation models since and
then the performance of these models has
began to saturate but uh it's important
to also see that fshot uh performance
has improved significantly o over the
years. I mean, back in 2019, we're
looking at you using 10,000 slides to
try to uh capture performance that that
one would get with pixel level
annotations all the way up to more
recently where you can use a few slides
in a few shot manner and still get
clinically useful uh useful performance.
Um so in parallel, we also uh worked on
this study where we tried to see if we
can contrast with text to improve
representation. I think this study sort
of started this basically observing
everything that's going on in in machine
learning where we're seeing that
contrasting across data multiple kinds
of data is is has the capability of
improved representation and and this is
great for for pathology because there's
a lot of morphologic description that's
available for pathology and and and
these kind of contrasting contrastive
models make use of the redundancy across
modalities to improve representation for
each individual individual modality. Uh
in this case this was more of a proof of
concept where we used 1.1 million image
caption pairs from the PubMed open
access database. I mean a lot of people
have asked us why have we not used the
entire PubMed database. There's no way
for us to do that. There's there are
licensing issues and that data is also
not you know just readily readily
available. Also it was limited to the
PubMed open access database and we sort
of uh um just used human tissue and then
used morphologic description that is
corresponding uh the the image and uh by
contrasting between the two this is this
is a distribution for where all all the
organ systems that were that were used
we we showed that you could improve
improve representation and
there's a lot of analysis around uh how
this compares to image only uh this this
example is for for for fus shot learning
and we we we can already begin to get
clinically useful performance using
about eight uh eight or nine u slides.
There's been quite a lot of independent
validation of these of these models.
Here's some validation that that came
from Jacob Cather's group in uh in in
Dresston and there's also some
validation from Thomas Hux's group at
the Memorial Stone Catering Cancer
Center and from Mount Si. they've used
this on their own uh their own data and
I think that there's lots of models
around for for pathology now lots of
different foundation models they've all
kind of saturated in in performance but
one key key aspect is that uh because we
really focused on diversifying the data
the models continue to be uh
state-of-the-art and we we we have uh
put out additional models that use more
data um and have also answered some some
fundamental questions around how how to
build these models in a in in an
effective manner. So the next step next
obvious step for us was to see how can
we get to a slide level uh
representation. So uni and con both of
those models give you patch origin level
representation but but it would be nice
to have a representation at the level of
the slide. So a single feature vector
representing the entire slide. If you
have that of course your learning
problems on top of it would would become
uh easy but also uh we have to make make
sure that the single vector representing
a gigapixel slide is sensitive enough of
the morphology within the within within
the slide. So uh we started by looking
at sort of this these very obvious
things like uh well we we have all these
morphologies can we look use something
like gauian mixture models to just come
up with a slide level slide level
representation and we did that and
showed that this this is possible I mean
these are just some examples in survival
outcome outcome prediction. This was a
CVPR study from 2023. Uh more recently
we've expanded this into a much larger
effort and we call this uh this this
model Titan it's a slide level model and
it trains at three levels. The first
level is at the um at at just the just
the image level where we use ibot
self-supervised training and we sort of
brought in uh concepts that are
typically used for large language models
like train short test long typically
used to develop these you know large
language models or multimodal large
language models where you're training on
a shorter shorter context and then and
then testing on a larger context. So in
this case in this case we were training
on AK by AK and then testing at at the
entire slide level to get a slide level
uh representation uh but also by
contrasting with two kinds of text
information. So the first one was uh is
morphologic description that's generated
using our uh generative model that I'll
talk about in a second but also by
contrasting with pathology pathology
reports and the contrastive uh learning
approach uh helps us improve
representation. So as these models are
getting better, our benchmarks are also
u improving. So uh we don't show results
here for basic subtyping or grading and
because it's saturated in performance
for all of them in in this case we're
showing much more complex benchmarks
like you know 108 class rare disease
prediction. But key results here is that
you can look at the scaling laws what
happens when you increase the num number
of data points used for training. But
you can also look at what happens with
with image contrasting. So, so how the
uh representation improves. So, sorry
text contrasting when you contrast with
morphologic descriptions uh to to
improve the the the the image image
representation. And of course you can
look at few shot uh performance on all
of these different tasks as well uh by
using very very few labels which really
is very important in pathology because a
lot of very interesting questions that
we want to answer that what's the next
patient that's best to enroll in a
particular clinical trial uh rare
disease all are effectively few shot
problems we don't have lots of data
available for them anyways um and then
retrieval and similar slide search so so
this is something that's inherently done
in uh pathology ology um u for rare
disease. So the the typical workflow
unfortunately is still that every major
pathology department would have somebody
who specializes in these kinds of rare
diseases and they would look at a case
and try to compare it with an existing
case or a case that existed long time
ago and and that comparative analysis
would then lead to lead to a diagnosis.
And here we try to do it computitionally
because we have slide level
representation. It's very very easy to
build a database find what the most
closest slide would be in in feature
space and could help diagnose uh
diagnose rare disease and then we assess
this on large amounts of internal cancer
data as well as on on external external
data. So the if if we uh just just recap
some of the some of the story that I
have that I've told that multiple
instance learning is the most commonly
used paradigm for um processing uh
pathology whole slide images into um
some kind of meaningful uh learning
paradigm and and feature representation
is important. You can use cells
supervision to improve feature feature
representation um and then contrasting
with additional modalities improved
improves image representation as well.
So uh just in light of that there's a
lot of other data uh in pathology that
you could be contrasting with right so
we show that you can you can contrast
with text to improve representation but
there's also you know uh morphologic
data uh so sorry molecular data and also
u iminostic chemistry radiology other
kinds of data that you can contrast with
to potentially improve image
representation. So we we tried to test
this hypothesis uh in a number of the
different studies. So this is from ECCV
last year where we contrast H& images
with IHC images and special stains and
by contrasting with IC images and
special stains we effectively show that
you can improve image representation
both for the H& and for the IC and uh we
applied it to a number of different
downstream tasks. If we can contrast
with with imminent chemistry we can also
contrast with molecular data. Right? So
contrasting with molecular data um and
and this study is is from CBPR last year
where we where we're contrasting with
molecular data to improve image uh
representation and uh what's important
is that um we found that uh contrasting
with
transcripttoics this was a sort of a toy
uh study just done on the TCGA to assess
this hypothesis that contrasting with
transcrytoics would do better and
contrasting with for example text. So
text is very subjective but
transcrytoics is much more objective. So
so so if it's true that it relies on
what's common across these these
multiple modalities to improve image
representation we should get a much
richer uh slide level representation by
contrasting with transcrytoics and
that's what we found. So for the three
different cases that were studied in
this small study, we found that few shot
uh performance improved substantially
um when when contrasting with molecular
data. So so this was first indication
that this is this aspect should be
scaled. So that's what we did in this
study that we call threads and uh this
is we have a preprint for this and this
will be coming out soon but but we
basically contrasted with all the
molecular data that was available to us
from the uh Dana Farber Bighgam profile
cohort as well as from from MGH and
because this is contrasting and not
fusion we can have separate heads uh for
for for each type of molecular data that
is that is included. So the goal is not
to fuse this information to get to a
particular answer but the goal is to
contrast across this information such
that to improve image image uh
representation and we found that by by
doing that we were able to improve
performance in a number of very
difficult tasks that are that are um
that are quite challenging like
treatment response prediction like like
here there there are all these different
uh drugs and we're predicting treatment
response directly from the
hisystologology hisystologology image
and there's a there for some of these
there's the drastic improvement when
using uh this model that was trained uh
by contrasting between histologology and
uh and molecular data. So we're we're
still scaling this with more data from
other other institutions and see how how
far how far we can go we can go. Other
people have uh also indicated to us that
that this is sort of a proof of concept
that we can contrast against lots of
modalities and improve representations
for each one of those individual
individual modalities. So everything
that I've discussed so far is about
improving image representation in
pathology that can then be made more
specific to lots of downstream tasks
answering specific questions. But if you
have rich representation from these
images, one obvious thing we can do with
this is to build uh a co-pilot or a
generative model that you can
then use uh to answer to answer
questions. So what what would we need to
do to build a multimodal large language
model that would cater to all of human
pathology? You would basically need rich
image representations which we already
have using some of the foundation models
that we had developed but we also need
uh representation but we also need uh
instructions. So um the the philosophy
behind creating instructions is that you
know pathology data is hierarchical
harbors information at many different
scales. A good uh chatbot or a
multimodel large language model should
be able to answer questions at any level
of uh uh of of abstraction. uh but we
don't have uh that morphologic
description readily available to us. The
only thing we have is pathogenous
reports corresponding the the entire
slide. So so we needed to create lots of
instructions. Uh so we started to do
that manually and created managed to
create quite a lot of instructions
manually but over time it became clear
that this was sort of a very difficult
difficult task. So we made use of a lot
of training materials that exist at
Harvard hospitals and other institutions
um other collaborators who contributed
training training materials effectively
using the same materials that are used
to train residents and pathologists to
train this multimodal multimodal large
language large language model. Um and
once we had the
um the model trained we could then you
know go in start asking questions about
about regions within the pathology
image. In the beginning we're targeting
very fundamental and simple questions
and over time uh this has become like a
large uh large effort to really scale
scale this. We could also uh just couple
a cell phone to a microscope. It's very
common to do this in lower resource
settings uh and pathologists often send
their colleagues in more resourcerich
settings images that are taken in this
manner. So we can get uh responses uh
right away. Some foundations that we do
some work with are very interested in in
in using this in lower resource settings
to get immediate answers because um it's
typically quite difficult for them to
track the patient back once they've left
the left the city where where the
hospital is. Uh they can't just send the
report over their phone. Um so so this
is also of of interest in in in low
resource settings. Um but the but the
real proof is uh you know in in the
assessment. So we did a lot of initial
assessment that was based on multiple
choice questions comparing with more
general models like GPD4. Um and then uh
we also asked a panel of seven board
certified pathologists to compare
responses from this model versus other
models and how well uh this approach
does for diagnosis and morphologic
description. Um so uh this has sort of
been uh licensed to a startup and
they've taken it further and they
recently got uh FDA breakthrough device
designation and we'll be running a
clinical trial to try to see if it can
improve workflows for for triage,
automatic test ordering and for
um for report synthesis synthesis as
well. The next thing I want to touch
upon is you know I guess everyone's
talking about uh AI agents. So we have
been trying to build some of these
agents for uh for computational
pathology. Um and since then it's been
expanded to more of agents that would do
any kind of analysis with the with with
tissues. Um but the idea is that of
course AI agents do do things for you
and everything that we're doing back in
2019 2020 can be done by these agents
more or less on their own. So the the
effective benefit would be that you can
reduce the barrier who could for who
could be developing these kinds of
models and quite often uh people who
work in domain specific u pathology or
um you know oncologists they they often
have the right questions to that they
want to answer. So maybe they don't need
to go to a computational person, someone
like us to to run these uh run these
experiments. Maybe they can run them run
it on their own. And in in uh Agentic AI
is really ripe for computational biome
medicine in general because generative
models have become quite good. So if you
if you have a text prompt, you could
easily
prompt you could easily generate a plan
from that text prompt. So the current uh
large language models from OpenAI
anthropic are very good at doing this.
um and it can create a plan for you and
then the agentic aspect of this would be
that you can then schedule and and guess
access all those tools and it would go
run those experiments for you and you
would effectively be able to communicate
across it. So, so we started building
this agent initially was just an effort
that was centered around uh around
pathology and as the studies were sort
of going through the review process and
you know we had requests that can we add
other kinds of tissue analysis in there
besides just looking at pathology images
can we look at spatial transctoics can
we look at you know uh radiology and
other other kinds of data so so we that
that's what we have effectively focused
on and and while we were building this
we there was also lots of development
that's happening coding is becoming uh
you know from text prompts to to to to
effective code is becoming uh better and
better and then the our patch model has
also improved quite a lot so we can do
good good morphologic descriptions and
then openAI also released deep research
so we can also go go back and do uh more
generic scientific research and then
come back with with generated hypotheses
so if you put it all all together uh I a
lot of these experiments could run
effectively on their own. This is just
one uh one example of it where the user
is giving it some metadata and saying
that I have a chord of responders versus
non-responders and uh uh can we look at
what are the morphologic different
differences and then maybe conduct some
analysis on top of it. So um the
generative aspect of this is that it can
make a plan and the agentic aspect is
that that it can then go and execute
that plan. So, so in this case it's very
simple but it's a starting point where
you can segment all segment the tissue
patch it extract features once those
features are extracted you can train a
model on top of it once the model is
trained this video is is is sped up
because training process takes time and
the once you have the have the model
trained you can look at the the AU for
for how separable the responders from
non-responders are so a 0.855 855 maybe
not clinically useful but it does give
an indication that there's a morphologic
difference between the responders and
non-responders. So then you might want
to investigate what those differences
are and you can look at some form of
interpretability and you can look at
these heat maps which don't tell you too
much but it does give you an idea for
what what the model used in making its
predictive uh determinations. Um and uh
another thing we could do because we
have the generative model, we can ask
the model to we can ask the agent to
effectively look at the highest attended
regions in all of these uh slides in
your test set and give a morphologic
description for what's common across
across this. And it does that and it
tells you well it's looking at
inflammatory response, necrosis,
fibrosis. Uh and then maybe you want
some more enhanced interpretability. You
can say with within your high attention
regions can you segment all the cells
extract handcrafted features and and
give me you know uh differences between
responders and non-responders in a more
um uh more more clear manner and you can
you can do that too. So so there there
are other examples of this that we that
we have out there um but we'll we'll
have more to say about this uh in in the
coming months. Um I also want to say a
little bit about transitioning from 2D
to 3D pathology. piece of pathology
today is inherently two-dimensional. So
human tissue is threedimensional and uh
clinically and for other applications we
typically look at a really sampled view
of the tissue and for many disease
indications this works just just fine.
But for others it has been shown that as
you cut additional images from a tissue
block the diagnosis changes uh as more
and more data is is is sort of observed
from this uh from this piece of piece of
tissue. And uh over the past few years
there has been just uh an immense amount
of effort devoted to making
threedimensional imaging easier. And
this includes you know methods that uh
could include serial sectioning of
tissue and then registration or using
microCT scanners which is the relatively
easy way of doing it or using open top
light sheet microscopy which gives you
very high resolution but uh it takes a
little bit more a little bit more uh
time and requires tissue clearing but
there's no uh good computational
pipelines that I can just directly use
on threedimen threedimensional data and
this data is a very large and complex
whole flat images are already you know
can can be 100,000 by 100,000 pixels and
you add another dimension to it it
becomes very very complex and the other
aspect is that if you are if we are able
to image this tissue in 3D and
pathologists are looking at this um
using just their eyes there it's it will
be impossible to cater to the patient
workload and it it's also difficult to
discover from this data for for
discovery we're effectively interested
in finding common morphologic features
across large amounts of patients that
correlate with either response or
resistance to treatment or just to
separate them into distinct uh distinct
risk groups which is also difficult to
do manually. Um so uh we we try to
develop uh computational pipelines for
for three-dimensional pathology data of
course this data is just very very
computationally
complex very very large large images.
This this is uh these are prostate
cancer cases. They were imaged at at
Harvard using data from the Brighamin
Women's Hospital uh using a microCT CT
scanner. But we also had another cohort
that came from an open top light sheet
microscope uh from Jonathan Lu's group
at the University of uh Washington. And
we expanded uh multiple instance
learning into into a third dimension
which was just complex and it it it
requires a lot of computing resources to
train uh train models like this. But but
basically we we managed to scale this uh
and and it follows a similar kind of a
paradigm where we extract features, we
aggregate and then we pose the problem
that we're trying to trying to solve. uh
this was a cell article from last year
where we where we managed to show that
as you use more of the tissue region
you're able to separate patients into
distinct risk groups um in in a much
better way. Uh and since then we've been
expanding this to other uh other
applications and we'll have more to say
about that in in in the coming coming
months. But you're you're able to go
back and look at what are the regions
that are important within the uh within
within this large uh piece of uh piece
of tissue.
Um sorry trying to okay so so another
question so as we're doing this there
were was multiple of our collaborators
have asked us this question that can we
infer spatial transcripttoics in 3D now
that we have uh you know lots of spatial
transcripttoic data available and thus
that can be used for pre-training. So
the basic idea is and and and this idea
is is not unique to us it's been it's
it's being explored by many other
people. Also we have tissue uh which you
can image using any kind of 3D 3D
imaging technique. In this case we
relied on microctt scanning because it's
a good trade-off between resolution and
how how quickly can you image these
image these cases and then do few
dimensional spatial transcripttoic
sections on on this piece of tissue
followed by using a pre-trained model
that might have been might have been
trained on lots of paired
hisystologology and uh spatial
transcripttoic data. So it it's learned
that basic morphologic correlation and
then fine-tuning inpatient fine-tuning
on samples that actually came from
within that piece of tissue to then uh
infer spatial transcripttoics in 3D and
now this is uh you know uh of course
it's we try to do a proof of concept of
this and it works to to a degree but we
are trying to validate this further. We
we we sort of used every architectural
combination that we could including
using multiple sections all kinds of
different architectures on the machine
learning side as well as all kinds of
different validation that we could we
could do both on the pre-training end
and on the post post inpatient uh
fine-tuning end to see if we can improve
uh improve predictability as well as
validation by doing lots of multiple uh
multiple sections and spatial
transcripttoics on it. This was limited
to prostate
cancer and they have since expanded this
and we're also expanding this this to
use um uh open top light microscopy
which gives us a much higher resolution
view of uh of this. We have a pre-print
for this and this the study is currently
in review but we will be making all the
code and everything publicly available
so people can experiment this with with
this sort of concept further because it
will take a while before it's actually
perfect or or gets even close to being
perfect if if it ever will. Um but you
can go in and you know this is just fun
images where you can go in and look at
uh what what it what it's effectively
looking at and then draw some
conclusions from it uh if if possible.
We also have efforts to look at more
sort of treatment response related
questions in uh in in in three
dimensions. Um and that's sort of
ongoing ongoing work. Um we're obviously
very interested in applying machine
learning to real world settings and one
aspect of this is that uh how does how
do these models perform when we
individually analyze them on on
protected subgroups of uh of of
patients. So we wanted to see if uh
there's anything in the model
architecture what modeling choices can
we make such that there will be minimal
bias in the uh in these models. So this
study from last year focused on
analyzing some of this. So we trained
some of these models on large public
data like TCGA other large public core
subathology data that was available and
then assessed these models on data from
Brigham and MGH which was stratified by
protected subgroups whether it was race
income groups or whether the patient had
insurance or not and we found that there
there can be large disparities but we
also looked at what modeling choices
could mitigate those disparities and
found that feature representation is is
the most comp most important component
uh but just feature representation
improving feature representation does
not eliminate all of those disparities
and you know we're investigating why uh
why they exist. Sometimes it could be
very obvious. Uh an example would be
that patients with soio economic
disparities might just be diagnosed late
and there might be limited uh advanced
cases in within your
um within your uh test set. Um the last
thing I want to touch upon is what are
we working on next? So we uh have been
building a model that uh uses uh lots of
data from uh Brigham and MGH is
multimodel uses um all the modalities
that we that we have available and is
also temporally aligned such that we
will get a single patient level
representation for every patient that
can be dynamically and temporally
updated. So the idea would be that that
every event that occurs about about the
patient whether it's a visit, it's a
phone call uh once it gets logged either
in electronic medical records um a
radiology scan or a pathology report or
um a clinical laboratory test would
update a dynamic patient level
embedding. So this effectively includes
using self-supervised models for each
individual modality to embed them uh
followed by uh a temporally aligned uh
embedding. So, so with every visit you
your your embedding would effectively uh
update and uh you would have this this
sort of change across uh across time uh
recorded which you can then apply to a
host of different downstream
applications like early diagnosis,
treatment response, bio medical
discovery, dynamic risk scores, clinical
trial matching and population health or
just some some examples. Um we are
beginning to get uh some early results
for this and we'll have more to say
about this in in the coming um coming
months. I want to end by showing this
poem from Judith Prevett uh uh that I
think she she wrote something that is
very relevant today and this was written
in 1979. She writes that optical
illusions can deceive the subjective eye
but objective measurements and
algorithms are assumed not to lie. It's
often said that medicine could use such
objectivity and thought this this
justifies machine intelligence activity.
Artificial intelligence is another craze
that uses computers to cope with the
diagnostic maze. Though the criteria for
intelligence has never been resolved,
paper after paper claims that the
problem has already been solved. So I
find it fascinating how relevant our
words are uh are today. So we really
have ways to go before uh you know
everything we do and others do in the
field could actually make make a true
impact on the on on on the clinical and
discovery discovery side. It's beginning
to show but but it will take take more
time. I want to thank all the PhD
students posttos and all the support
staff who have contributed to all of
this effort as well as all the funding
that we received to to to do some of
this work. Thank you so much. I'll be
happy