I've been able to see how the technical
work that I'm doing is going to directly
impact policy being made today and in
the future.
As we introduce more time dependent
renewables, so that's solar, hydro, wind
into our grid generation, it becomes
increasingly important for planners to
have as much temporal granular data as
they can to build the optimal grid.
Essentially, better energy grid design
methods will make generating grid
designs with high resolution data more
scalable. As planners and governments
get access to this new technology and
these new methods, it becomes easier for
them to be more agile in how they're
generating grid designs. This means that
in historically underserved communities
with developing grids, they are able to
test and retest their models more
frequently. And I think this kind of
government engineering intersection is
just something that's going to be
increasingly important in coming years.
In cases where you're experiencing these
extreme weather events, it becomes
increasingly important to include as
much temporal data as you can such that
your energy grid design is going to be
able to fare well when inevitably
extreme weather events happen again in
the future. When vulnerable communities
get hit by these kind of extreme weather
events that where their energy grids are
being maxed out, they suffer the most
because climate change is as much an
engineering issue as it is a social
justice issue.