It is my pleasure the second time in 24
hours to introduce uh Armando Solar
Lazama who is the he's a distinguished
professor at the Schwarzman College of
Computing and he is also the chief
operating officer of the computer
science and AI lab or Cesale and uh he
is going to talk to you give a a kickoff
speech to talk about how AI is impacting
software engineering. So, uh let's let's
hear it for
Armando. Thank you. Thanks a lot. I'm
very happy to be here. Uh before I
start, just a quick show of hands. Um
who was at my uh presentation yesterday?
Okay, who was not at my presentation
yesterday? Okay, great. So, we have
about half and half. Um this was kind of
meant to be an extended version of that
presentation. I'll try to focus mostly
on the stuff that I didn't talk uh
yesterday but uh for those of you who
are not yesterday don't worry I'll catch
you up. So I've been working in this
space of how do we get machines to help
us write code for about 20 years now and
in fact uh our very first paper in this
space was back in 2005 and we were
really fascinated that we could actually
sort of semi-automatically help somebody
write a program like hey what if I want
to drop every third bit in a stream of
bits and at the time it was very
exciting um and uh it led to lots idea
that had lots of traction. But you know
by today's standards it looks a little
um a little primitive right things have
moved quite a bit in the last few years
to the point where you know today people
are really seriously questioning the uh
the point of are people actually even
have to learn to code uh is there any
sense in learning uh programming at uh
at this point right and there's just
this big explosion of startups and uh
tools and companies that are uh being
set up to leverage this technology and
producing tools that are producing real
value to um to people in the field. And
so um you know we've uh we've been
working in this field for many years. In
fact we wrote uh some of the earliest
papers for example using auto
reggressive models to actually generate
uh code. Incidentally, our uh very first
source of training data was actually uh
uh edexm right and uh using uh code
submitted by students so that we could
later help students uh uh identify their
mistakes in in their code. But you know
like everybody else uh especially when
GPT4 was released one of the first
questions we had was you know should we
still be working in this problem right?
is there actually still uh some work to
to do? And so we actually spent a fair
bit of time trying to look a little bit
more deeply into the capabilities of of
some of these models and trying to
understand, you know, yes, they can
clearly solve problems that are very
challenging for humans and uh you know,
they seem to be able to uh do well on
all these different programming
competitions. But you know are they
really actually good programmers right
can they actually write uh good code so
we embarked on a series of studies
actually looking at trying to understand
the capabilities of these LLMs for
example one of the first things we
wanted to see was
uh you know people are using um some
benchmarks like human eval to try to see
you know how good are these models at
solving algorithmic problems. But one of
the questions we had was, you know, how
representative are these tests for, you
know, the kind of skills that you expect
from a human uh programmer, right?
And one of the things that we're also
starting to see was a lot of new models
coming up that claimed to be much
simpler and much smaller than say GP4
but were claiming results on these
benchmarks that were you know on par or
even above uh these uh these tools. And
this, you know, was a little bit of an
indication that maybe these tests were
not really testing uh true code
understanding and true coding uh skills.
and so partner up with uh uh some
colleagues at uh Meta AI to look at this
question of you know how much do these
models actually understand code and in
particular what happens if you just
throw at them some randomly generated
programs and look for something very
simple you can have you know fiveline
programs fourline programs and ask hey
if I feed this input
what is going to be the output, right?
This is the most basic skill that you
expect from a first year programming
student, right? Can you read code and
actually figure out what this piece of
code is going to uh do? We're actually
very careful, for example, to avoid
things that we knew LMS are not very
good at, like doing arithmetic with big
numbers. uh we also work very hard to
avoid any kind of uh external libraries
that the model might not be familiar
with. Right? Just keep it really really
simple. These are the kind of tests
where you would expect a model that
actually knows how to code to score
100%. Right? And what we found was that
you know GPT4 with chain of thought
could get around 90% which again 90%
sounds really good until you realize
this are super simple five line programs
right but it really went downhill from
there right all the way to some of these
models that claimed on par uh
performance with GPT4 were actually
doing on the order of 20 or 30% right So
um you know one of the things that uh
that you see here is that um you know
just because the model is doing really
well on a benchmark doesn't necessarily
mean that it has the programming skills
or the programming capabilities that
would be implied by these uh this
performance right similarly another
really important capability that you
would expect from a model that
understands code is can it actually
reason about its mistakes, right? If it
makes a mistake and you tell it, hey,
you made a mistake, can it reason about
those um mistakes? And there's a lot of
uh there was a lot of work, for example,
showing that uh yeah, when the model uh
makes a mistake, it can actually do a
pretty good job often times correcting
those mistakes. But we wanted to dig a
little bit deeper. And in particular, we
wanted to focus
on something we called uh counterfeits.
What does that mean? It means it's an
incorrect solution that could pass as a
correct solution, right? It's an
incorrect solution that doesn't throw
any errors, doesn't uh, you know, crash
the program, doesn't uh give you type
errors. It just runs. It gives you an
answer. it just happens to not be the
right answer or on some cases on some
inputs it might even be the right answer
but there's just some inputs on which it
gives the wrong answer right and so this
is the kind of buggy program that is
most insidious right if you get a
program out of your model and it crashes
and you know it's wrong and you rerun it
but if you run a program that you know
runs to completion produces an output it
even passes uh some simple tests then
you know you might be a little bit more
um um trusting of this program right and
so what um what we found was that okay
so there's this correct if you give it
the model a problem there might be some
correct answers and there's many
different ways of getting correct
answers and there are these incorrect
answers that you know are very clearly
incorrect right Uh sometimes the models
produce things that don't even have
code, right? They just have a bunch of
comments. Um but what we're interested
in are these examples where they could
be right. They're just not. And so what
you find first of all is that these are
actually a non-trivial fraction of the
uh solutions produced by um many of
these uh by many of these models.
But now we had a question, right? What
if you go and you build a test set where
half the programs in this test set are
correct solutions to a problem and the
other half are these counterfeits,
right? And you mix them together and you
ask the model,
hey, which one of these are correct,
right? Is this one correct? Is that one
correct? Right? And uh you know you can
see um again big difference between GPT4
and everything else but still GPT4 is uh
you know a little bit over 80% overall
right um good but not uh good but not
great right and um one of the things
that you notice also is that for a lot
of these other models there's a strong
bias uh to just saying things are
correct right yep they looked correct
they're correct uh which means But the
ones that are actually correct, the
accuracy is very high. But the ones that
are actually wrong, it's uh it's very
low. Right? With GPT4, it's actually a
little bit more skeptical about its own
uh correctness, but again, these are
pretty simple programs, right? And and
not quite the correctness that uh that
you would expect. Here's an interesting
thing, though. If you take these models
and you take these counterfeits and um
you look at again the same test as
before just if I give you the input can
you predict what the output is going to
be right so for just correct solutions
you know it gets the right output some
percentage of the time again uh the four
tends to be better than everything else.
Now, if you take some of these
counterfeit programs, but you feed them
an input on which they just happen to
produce the right answer, right? The
answer that you expected, then it's
pretty much on par with the correct uh
solutions. But if you give it an input
on which it produces the wrong answer,
you can see immediately there's a drop
in the accuracy. And here's the really
interesting bit. If you look at that
answer that was produced and you judge
it not on the basis of is this the
actual output that when you run this
code this is what it's going to give you
then you know this uh this is the the
success rate. But if you look at that
output as is this the correct output for
the problem that this was supposed to be
the solution to right then you know you
get something pretty non-trivially above
zero right in other words the model even
though it has this wrong code that that
was produced by the model itself when
being asked to emulate and and to
predict what the output of this code is
going to be often times it's thinking
that this code is actually going to
produce the right output to the problem
even though we're not actually showing
it what problem this is supposed to be
solving. Right? In other words, there's
a small amount of consistency here in
the model actually uh being sufficiently
convinced that this is the right
solution to that problem that when you
give it an input, it thinks that the
output is what the output to that
problem should be as opposed to what
you're actually going to get when you
run the program. Right? So this is again
some indication that the model is not
really actually reasoning through the
code but it's using a lot of signals
from the shape of the code from the
names of functions from the name of
variables in making these predictions
about what the code is going to to do
right another interesting experiment
here if you go and you tell the models
hey um here's here's this incorrect
solution please fix it right And uh and
so we look at the
um percentage of the time that it uh we
look at the correctness rate of that
versus the correctness rate of just
going to the model and telling the
model, hey, can you give me a new
solution to this problem? Right? And it
turns out
that most of the time for most of these
problems actually just going to the
model and telling it just give me
another solution succeeds way more often
than if you actually tell it hey here is
the wrong solution that you provided
please go and fix this solution so it's
not uh wrong anymore. Right? So in other
words, actually just rolling the dice
again and getting another solution turns
out to actually be more effective.
Now what um oh here's another
interesting one.
So you know you look at the performance
on a lot of these competition problems,
right? And on a lot of pretty hard uh
programming problems and it looks pretty
good, right? But here's an experiment
that we run looking at uh lead code,
right? So these are uh you know little
coding contests that uh people
participate in. And one interesting
thing about this is that there's new
problems coming out every uh I think
it's every week or every month. Uh you
have new problems coming out. And so we
can take some of these models and
actually uh test it on the problems that
came out in May and the problems that
came out in June and the problems that
came out in July right month by month
looking at how the model does on this
problem. And first of all you can see
you know a non-trivial downward uh trend
but you can also see for example right
here's the cutoff date for uh uh deepse
uh in 33b right and you know there's
there's a pretty clear even though it's
a little bit of a noisy signal there's a
pretty clear before and after uh on its
performance on the problems that came
out uh before the c time from the
problems that came out after, right? And
the problems that have been in the
training set probably for longer, it's
doing better than on the problems that
just uh that just came out, right? And
again, it's uh it's a noisy signal, but
it gives some indication that u uh that
there is some amount of memorization
going on there. Right
now, we shouldn't
um you know, we shouldn't uh from this
take the lesson that oh then these
models are just uh uh you know,
repeating what they've seen and they're
not really doing any kind of thinking.
Uh you know, it's not quite that, right?
I mean in some level in some ways a lot
of these tests yes the performance that
they're getting on some of these
synthetics tests is lower than what you
would expect from somebody who has that
level of skill at solving those kind of
problems but it's not zero right and it
does show a uh you know non-trivial
reasoning abilities and you know
considering that these are out of
distribution problems where they're
really being designed uh synthetically
to test the reasoning ability
specifically. It is actually quite
surprising that that you're getting
relatively high success rates. But the
moral of the story here is that your
mental model in thinking how these
models are thinking about code, you
shouldn't think of them as you know a
human programmer, right? Uh we have
certain expectations that if a human
programmer knows how to do this, then
clearly they must know how to do that,
right? And and if a human programmer can
pass these kind of tests then surely
they must be able to write this kind of
code right and you know these models are
not people they're not uh they have just
different strengths and different uh
weaknesses than uh than human than human
programmers. And um so actually just
last week we uh we released this uh
report looking in some detail at some of
the open challenges for uh AI based uh
coding tools, right? in particular these
applications to to software engineering
and what are some of the key open uh
what are some of the key open problems
uh uh here
and some of these uh one really
important one is you know out of
distribution domains right and you know
in some ways a lot of these experiments
that we showed uh before right that
they're dealing with these very out
ofdistribution
um problems. And uh you know this is
something that is important to consider
when you're using these uh these tools,
right? If you're writing the kind of
code that everybody has written a
thousand times before, they're going to
be super useful, right? And if uh uh you
know in terms of writing sort of
everyday uh throwaway code where you're
trying to you know uh u chew on some
data to get it into a different form,
right? This is the code the kind of code
that is very much in distribution and
the tools are amazing. Right? If you're
trying to write the sort of code that
nobody has written before, right? and
the sort of code where um you know it's
a brand new application or it's
something very specific to to your
company uh you know mileage may vary
right and these models um as I said it's
not that they're not doing any reasoning
at all there is a fair amount of
reasoning that they're capable of doing
u it's just not at the same level as uh
as you would expect from a programmer
with kind of a comparable level of
skill, right? Program understanding is
another um is another really big one.
We've actually been uh doing a lot of
work recently looking at combining more
traditional program analysis with uh
large language models in order to try to
get a little bit of the best of both
worlds, right? and to uh uh try to
address the scalability challenges that
come from having to reason across very
large uh code bases where you might have
to actually pull information from many
different places in the code in order to
figure out what is uh going on. Right?
Software design is a really big one. uh
a lot of these tools are very good at
the sort of problems that you can check
right you have a test suite you're
looking for the algorithm that is going
to pass the test suite uh if you throw
enough compute power at it you will get
your algorithm that passes the test
suite but often times when you're
writing code passing the test suite is
just one of the things that we're
looking for right we want to make sure
that this code is actually going to be
maintainable. We want a code base and a
code structure that is going to survive,
you know, the next uh few generations of
our product. We want the kind of
codebase that when we're trying to bring
a new person up to speed, uh it's going
to make sense, right? And these because
it's much harder to uh automatically
test. It's not it doesn't lend itself as
well to this kind of generate and test
approach that is kind of the bread and
butter of a lot of these uh of a lot of
these tools. And uh um the the other big
thing is sophisticated reuse. And here
we're talking not about the kind of
reuse where you say, "Oh yeah, I wrote I
wrote a function that does that a month
ago and uh and now I'm going to use it
in this place as well." That's the sort
of reuse that you can get very easily
and very effectively with retrieval
augmented models, right? uh if the
function that you're looking for already
exists in your codebase, the model is
going to find it and it's going to give
it to you and it's going to pretty well
figure out how to adjust all the
parameters to get it to work well. The
kind of reuse though that I'm talking
about here is the kind of reuse where
there's some brand new functionality but
as a designer who is very familiar with
the overall architecture of the software
who is very familiar with uh you know
the internals of the different building
blocks. you can immediately tell oh yeah
there is this other functionality over
here that is completely different and is
for uh another uh completely different
thing but I can generalize that
functionality so that it works for that
and it also works for this right it's
the kind of reuse that requires you to
take uh you know this routine over here
that was used for one thing and this
routine over here that was used for
another thing and figuring out how to
weave them together with the right uh
scaffolding in order to actually get the
functionality that you want, right? And
that's the kind of uh sophisticated
reuse that uh you're not going to get
just from a standard retrieval um uh
model, right? And finally, we get to the
specification challenge, right? This is
uh you know in some sense the ultimate
challenge for these tools at the end of
the
day writing software a big part of
writing software is actually negotiating
the interface right and figuring out
negotiating the specification figuring
out how to trade off um what the client
wants with the costs with the u you know
technical constraints right often times
Um if you ask uh if you ask the person
what if you ask the client what they
want, they want unicorns, right?
Everybody wants unicorns. Everybody
loves unicorns. Uh but we can't get them
unicorns, right? And so now we have to
get into a negotiation. We have to
figure out uh what is feasible to
implement given the technological
constraints? What are the trade-offs
between functionality, performance,
usability?
Um and that is something that these
models are just not very well suited to,
right? Um except obviously to the extent
that if you can iterate much faster,
right? If you can build those prototypes
much faster, you can get to um those
decisions much more um much more
effectively.
So uh yesterday I talked a little bit
about uh you know some ideas that we've
uh experimented with uh dealing with
some of these different some of these
different problems. Um one uh one of
these ideas for example was what to do
in this situation. Um I realize I've
been talking to one side of the room the
whole time. uh sorry it's not that I
don't like you
but so um you know one of the uh um one
of these uh challenges of how do you
figure out what is it that the tool uh
what is it that people want to build and
uh you know humans have uh lots of
different modalities that we can use to
actually uh tell people what we want
right and one of those modalities is
actually just telling your colleague,
hey, come look like have you seen this
application here like the thing this
application does like that's what I want
right and often times these are things
that are hard to capture in words you
might not even have the right uh
terminology and oftentimes when you're
trying to implement some of these things
even in the context of a framework that
already has all the right building
blocks to help you do this if you're not
familiar with the framework if you don't
know the internal language of this
framework, you're not going to be able
to do that, right? And so I showed this
example that we had of um uh we're
actually extending this uh uh editor
which is uh you know a very nice uh
framework. Uh many of you probably have
used Eclipse at least uh many years ago.
Uh but in addition to being just a nice
IDE, it's a nice framework for writing
uh new plugins for supporting new
programming languages, right? Or new uh
file formats in general. And um so it
has all the functionality that you need
to do something as simple as syntax
highlighting or something as complicated
as a full uh you know structure aware u
editor. But just because the
functionality is there doesn't mean that
you can find it easily and it doesn't
mean that you're going to quickly figure
out how to use it, right? And in
particular, what you find is that uh you
know when you start looking at the
internals of how to do this, pretty
obvious that you're going to need some
kind of a scanner if you're uh scanning
for tokens so that you can give them
different colors. But what might not be
so obvious is that in order to actually
get the framework to use your scanner,
you have to override lots of things,
right? There's this thing called source
viewer configuration that you have to
extend and within this there's this
thing called a damage repairer and
that's the thing that takes your scanner
as input and then you have to register
it with a presentation reconciler. What
are those things? Right? Where did this
come from? Um, if you understand the
internal logic of this framework, it's
very obvious, right? It has this model
where there's this data structure that
models the code and from that it decides
how to present the code and when you
type, you're breaking that you're
damaging the relationship between this
data structure and the presentation. So,
you need this damage repairer to repair
that relationship, right? And then you
need to reconcile that uh uh internal
representation with the view that the
person gets. Right? Once you know that
that's how it works. It's very obvious
if you're not familiar with the inner
workings, right? You're just saying,
"Hey, that thing I want to do that thing
that I saw the framework do in this
other context or in this other
situation, right? And this is a
challenge, right? Even if you have an
LLM, right? You can go and describe to
the LLM what you're trying to do. And if
you use the right um keywords and if you
use the right class names you will
actually get you know lots and lots of
code and a little tutorial explaining
how different parts of the code is.
Turns out the code you get is not quite
uh correct. It also at some point gets
truncated because uh you run out of the
buffer space. Um but more importantly um
there's lots of different versions of
this framework and it's uh using some
combination of the different uh versions
and um but critically you already have
to know a fair bit about what you're
asking for, what you want, how to ask
for it. And this is kind of a best case
scenario, right? This is a framework
that has been around for a long time.
There's lots of blog posts and
tutorials. It's very well documented and
all of that information was just
ingested by these models at training
time. What happens when you suddenly
want to uh do this for your own internal
framework that has been sitting inside
your company that is not part of the
training set that doesn't have all the
nicely written blog posts. Um what are
you going to do then? Right. Um in this
case our approach was actually to allow
you to record right to just pop up the
application that is already using this
framework uh press a button that says
okay I'm about to show you something
right and then you know demonstrate the
functionality in this case we want to
demonstrate this uh syntax uh
highlighting and then you want to say
okay now there that thing that just
happened that's what I want to learn how
to do right in the context of this
framework work. How do I use this
framework to make that thing happen?
Right? And in this case, u we actually
had some infrastructure that would
record a little trace of everything that
happened during that demonstration so
that it could be fed as input to this
whole process that helps you figure out
how to do this, right? And so this is
the sort of thing that is, you know,
difficult to do at this point with just
a plain vanilla um LLM. They're actually
getting much better at supporting much
more multimodal interactions. I don't
doubt that within a few years you'll be
able to take uh you know an actual just
video capture of the functionality that
happened and have the model be able to
do that. But it's actually quite hard.
It's actually quite hard to to do that
because the model has to be able to make
that connection between the observed
behavior and
the actual uh code that led to that
behavior. And
um if you have not trained the model to
do this, then it's actually kind of hard
for the model to know, right? It's not
something that you can just derive from
first principles by looking at the
source code, right? Definitely not at
that scale and noted with this
complexity of um of behavior, right? So
you need somebody to teach the model
that this is what the framework does. Um
we've actually been doing some work uh
recently looking at okay so what does it
take to show the model how these things
uh work? How much time do we have by the
way?
Okay, so very quickly uh you know in the
context of a different framework that is
able to uh help you create textures for
video games right um or you know in
general for computer graphics
programmatic textures for uh rendering
so it turns out it has a Python uh if
you're using Blender for example it has
a Python API and what we want is we want
to be able to take just a picture of a
texture, give it to the model and have
the model spit out to the code that is
actually going to produce that texture
or maybe a similar texture. You might
need to do some local optimization to
get exactly the right texture. But it's
the same kind of problem, right? The
model has to reason about the
relationship between the code and this
visual effect, this behavior that was
not part of the training data. Even
though the model has seen some uses of
these um of this framework in the past,
it just does not have sufficient
information about that relationship
between the code and its effects. It
turns out though that by using some
clever data augmentation techniques, it
was actually possible to build a data
set of about half a million such
programs that allowed us to actually
fine-tune this model. Right? Turns out
that uh fine-tuning um in this case it
was actually just a 9 billion parameter
uh model um uh uh lava uh next which
also has a visual component and it's
actually within the scale of uh you know
an academic lab to actually do that kind
of uh fine-tuning and get the models to
do this uh to do this. So the good news
is that you can do it and you can
actually get it to work pretty well. Um
the bad news is that it's not something
that you can get out of uh out of the
box. If uh you know if you just use the
models that you can get out of the box,
you can see the results are actually not
very good. Right? And these are other
specialized algorithms and specialized
uh baselines. Um but uh but you can see
again that uh they're they're just not
very uh they're just not very good.
So you know the the final the final
message here is that um you know these
models are very powerful and um what
we're going to see more and more is that
the kind of programming that you could
do just on a cheap laptop with you know
your vi editor um is probably not going
to be around for long right tools are
going to be more and more essential
uh part of programming. But there is
still a very crucial role for human
expertise and uh you know these tools
can enable creativity and very fast
experimentation. But I think it is
important to protect the health of the
software ecosystem and not uh be in this
position where um all the old frameworks
and all the frameworks that are very
well documented are very easy to use and
so nobody uses the new stuff because the
models don't know as much about them. Um
and uh you know we can use these tools
to actually help us produce higher
quality software, much better software
or we can use them to produce lots of
garbage very quickly. And I think there
is going to be important decisions to
make in the future about how we want to
strike this trade-off.
Thank you Armando. Uh I think we have uh
as we ask the next speaker to come up so
we could do a little AV switch. Uh maybe
we'll take uh at least one question from
the audience if uh anyone uh has
something burning to ask. Okay.
Amanda, thanks for this presentation. Uh
if you have to summarize with like what
what will be in your mind the five key
skills of software engineering in like 5
to 10 years.
So software designed right uh high level
global uh design of the architecture is
going to be really
crucial. How to actually orchestrate a
lot of these tools right we're going to
see a lot of programming be not about
you know how to write the code line by
line but how to actually throw the
computing power into this problem to get
the right solution. Um that's going to
be kind of a very different style of uh
of programming from what we have right
now. Um the third one is actually uh
what is already a very important skill
for any developer be able to think very
clearly about uh what is it that this
program is supposed to do. Right? A lot
of writing code is really about thinking
clearly about what is this program
supposed to do in all of these different
uh situations. Uh reading code is still
going to be an extremely essential
skills, right? Most working developers
spend way more time reading code than
writing uh code, right? And learning how
to find your way through a codebase.
We're going to have really good tools to
help us do that, but we're still going
to have to ultimately be able to absorb
all this information and be able to make
decisions um uh with it, right? And uh
and finally, actually talking to people,
right? Talking to uh and talking to the
customers, talking to the potential
users of these uh code, actually being
able to figure out what is it that we're
supposed to build? What are we trying to
build here?
any comments about prize and the more
bounded problem of
getting to fix bugs like you're not
saying reason about this saying generate
something that passion
so bug finding is a really broad problem
right I've run into bugs where I realize
oh you know this should have been a less
than or equal instead of a less than
right Yes, those are going to go away,
right? And then I've run into bugs where
I
realized, oh crap, my entire uh
understanding of the problem was wrong
and I really need to rearchitect my
solution in order to get this thing to
work properly. Right? That's not the
kind of uh bug fix that you can expect
um from these kind of tools anytime
soon.
I don't know.
that that we're probably relatively
close, right? Um, as long as again
you're you're focusing on the easy bugs
and you're happy with uh the hard bugs.
The tricky part for bug fixing tends to
be the test suites, right? Because for a
lot of bugs, it's very easy to write
corrections that hide the bug instead of
fixing it, right? And so you might not
realize that you're in the hard case
because there's a simple change you can
make to the code that makes the bug
manifestation go away without actually
fixing it. So that's the caveat there
that if you already know you're in the
simple case, I think we can do that. But
the hard case poses some of these
challenges.