Um the session one is framing the
challenge and we're going to go as high
level as we can looking at the whole
world and all of humanity.
And um I I couldn't be more excited
about the three speakers. Um I
I will not do them justice by
introducing. So I'm asking each of them
to take a moment to introduce
themselves. And uh we're going to start
with Jason J from here at MIT Sloan
School. Um who has I will just add one
one piece of introduction. He has the uh
incredible distinction which I I don't
know if it's on on your LinkedIn but of
being a early heat volunteer for an
energy efficiency barn raising.
>> That's right. I learned how to use a
cocking gun from Zanb. Um
um good morning everybody.
>> Good morning everybody.
>> All right. Um so I'm Jason Jay. I teach
at the MIT Sloan School of Management.
I'm the director of the sustainability
initiative there. Um, I've had the great
pleasure to be part of this heat journey
from the beginning. As Zanab was saying,
I when I did my PhD here, I was studying
something called the Cambridge Energy
Alliance. Um, and I was looking at the
sort of multistakeholder collaborations
that were occurring here um, around our
our our city of Cambridge advancing
energy efficiency topics. And part of
that included participating in HEAT's
early barn raisings. And I did in fact
learn to use a cocking gun from Zanab
um, as we were weatherizing people's
homes. Um and then and then have gotten
to watch as this whole thing has evolved
um going to the gas leaks effort, the
collaboration with um Eversource and
other utility companies um the
advancement of the legal policy
framework around better measurement of
gas leaks and then towards this this
transformational idea of geothermal
energy networks where now there's enough
trust between the advocates and the
utilities to actually say, "Hey, could
we just not have you be a gas utility
anymore?" which is kind of an audacious
thing and is the reason we bring in Zanb
as a guest speaker into our courses uh
every year. Um what she asked me to do
is to um as she said go to the level of
the of all of the whole planet and all
of humanity. Um and the way I'm going to
do that is using an interactive
simulation tool called NROSS. Um just
quick show of hands, how many of you
have seen NROs before? Okay. Uh about
half the room. Okay. So um this is the
the result of a collaboration between
the MIT Sloan Sustainability Initiative
and uh Climate Interactive which is a
independent uh nonpartisan nonprofit
made of mostly MIT grads um who um who
do a simulation tool that behaves the
same as the big supercomputer integrated
assessment models but runs instantly on
any laptop and is freely available and
open source to anybody with a web
browser. So, um you can't open it up on
your phones, but on any laptop or iPad,
um you can pull this up and experiment
it with it yourself. And um I am not on
the modeling team. I'm not a climate
scientist. I'm not an energy scientist.
I'm an organizations person, but I've
been facilitating probably hundreds of
workshops at this point using this tool.
And that means that any of you can do
that as well. Um which which I would
certainly recommend. What I'm going to
try to do is just use this to expose a
little bit about the climate challenge
um and how the things that we're talking
about here today sort of fit within that
bigger picture and what some of the
system interactions are because this is
a system dynamics model right this is
the interdependence of um you know
thousands of variables to produce the
outcomes that we are facing. So here you
can see on the left this is the stack of
global energy. Um so she talked about a
zeta jewel that humanity is using about
half of a zeta jewel. So 500 exogles. Um
you can see that here on this picture
and that is made up of coal, oil, gas,
renewables, biomass and nuclear. Um uh
if we were to invent nuclear fusion or
some other new zerocarbon, we could add
that to the mix. We're not going to talk
about that today. On the right we have
the stack of greenhouse gas emissions
that are partly related to that. So the
largest source of human anthropogenic
greenhouse gas emissions is uh CO2 from
energy. That's about 35 gigatons uh a
year right now. The second highest
source is methane. So this is put on a
100redyear uh CO2 equivalent units on
this graph. So 10 gigatons of CO2
equivalent from methane emissions. The
third highest is land use change from
deforestation and petlands and so on.
And then you have nitrous oxide and F
gases. So this gives you a picture of
the faucet into the bathtub of the
atmosphere. How much greenhouse gas we
are putting into the atmosphere every
year. And the result of that faucet
being on stronger and stronger every
year as we grow the global industrial
economy is that the concentration of CO2
in the atmosphere is increasing. Um
right, we you've heard 350.org or
wanting to get that back down to 350
closer to pre-industrial levels. um
we're now at about 424 and that
increasing greenhouse gas as Zanv said
creates this thermal regulation problem
which is that we're heating the planet
and so the temperature um is increasing
um in 2024
um you know the data is still coming in
but we're really pushing close to that
1.5 mark um and you can see in our
business as usual projections um inroads
we passed the 1.5 degree goal we passed
the twoderee goal we at the end of the
century hit 3.3° C, which is what this
big number is. And unfortunately, the
slope of this line is positive, which
means that we're continuing to warm the
planet into the 22nd century. Um, not
everybody has a visceral sense of what
3.3 degrees Celsius means. Um, and so
one thing you can do is you can use the
impact graphs in NROS to explore some of
that. So for example, we can think about
you know how much sea level rise might
we see as a result of that warming or we
can think about um you know other graphs
like um the extinction risk from animal
species. So the effects on biodiversity.
Um, one of the things that if you
haven't played with Androids in a little
while, we've now added is that we
interface with maps that are from the
um, probable futures site, which allows
you to see what happens kind of on a
more regional or geographic basis to the
places that we care about. So, for
example, this is a picture of the number
of extreme humidity and heat days. So,
um, how many days per year do we have
with wet bulb temperatures, um, above 26
degrees C, which is where you start to
have really serious health consequences
of outdoor work, outdoor sports, um, and
if you don't have cooling in your home,
um, just even sleeping at night. So, um,
you can see that the southeast of the
United States starts to have really dire
conditions. Um, but and and you can back
this off by year and sort of see how
this evolves. So here's where we were in
2000 um in terms of the frequency of
those ultra high heat days and you can
see that um that's all uh increasing um
you know throughout the throughout North
America and of course if we look at
other geographies in the world in
subsaharan Africa um where my wife's
family is in India um in in uh in uh in
uh the eastern part in West Bengal you
can see that there's very serious
consequences and so what this means is
that we have to learn how to cool our
buildings things fast and quickly and
cheaply and low carbon. Um, and so that
demand for cooling is a big piece of the
the puzzle of what we're going to be
grappling with. So that's one thing just
to kind of be oriented to what is the
challenge and why are we trying to solve
for more efficient lowcarbon um methods
for doing um uh heating and cooling. Um
now the um the other thing couple other
things I wanted to just kind of
illuminate here. Um so one is that um
you know the methane as a significant
source of greenhouse gases this lever
here which is about the waste um oop
sorry I'm not used to windows um can I
make that go away? Okay good um this
lever over here which is about the waste
and leakage of um non CO2 greenhouse
gases. So if we look at methane in
particular um what you can see here is
that people talk about methane a when we
talk about methane oftentimes we talk
about cows and agricultural sources and
that is very important. You can see the
agricultural methane emissions but what
a lot of people don't think about is the
fact that a very significant part of our
methane emissions um you know this is
you know depending on the time horizon
you know 50 60 times stronger than CO2
um do significantly come from energy
production. So when we can move away
from coal which leaks methane out of the
mines, gas which leaks methane across
the value chain and oil which leaks
methane at the drilling sites um and in
the refineries um we can work on this
chunk right. So if we if we can if we
can decrease methane leakage from the
energy systems which was you know heat's
first major effort. Yeah. Okay. So you
can see this this bent the curve a
little bit here. And if I just do a
little um replay, you can see the
change. So that um that bending of that
curve of of energy leakage is one
opportunity. But if we can get off of
those of fossil fuels entirely, for
example, by um you know, pricing CO2 um
and doing things that are that that
allow us to decarbonize energy supply,
what you'll see is that those um those
methane uh emissions from energy go down
even further. So there's sort of a
two-prong approach here, which is to
reduce the leakage from the system that
we have, which is the original gas leaks
idea. And then there's the question of
how do we transition away from these um
highcarbon sources of energy? Um I'm
just going to revert back without those
changes and just say that. So then the
question is, well, how might we simulate
the effects of doing district geothermal
like we're going to be talking about the
next couple of days? And what I'll say
is that that's a blind spot in tools
like this because um as the first thing
as Adam said today was that so much of
our attention has been on electricity
and light. We don't tend to think about
thermal energy and I'll say that that's
also the case for nodes. There is
geothermal built into what we define as
renewables. Um so that when you're you
know you know subsidizing renewables or
you're doing other moves like uh carbon
pricing that do transition toward a
renewable world that does include if you
look at the details geothermal but it's
largely thinking about that first bucket
in her um in her graph of the um using
geo using like the super high
temperature geothermal to generate
electricity. We're not really dealing
with it um from a heat standpoint. The
best way for us to represent that is for
us to think about electrifying the
building and industry space because what
you're doing is you're often moving to
some kind of a heat pump, a geothermal
heat pump um in lie of a um but you're
also doing that in a far more energy
efficient way than um than you'd be
doing otherwise with fossil fuels. So
this is a this is a kind of an energy
efficiency and electrification play
which are you know important pieces of
the puzzle. Um, the last thing I'll just
say is that when you're anytime you're
electrifying something, of course you'll
have to and and you'll notice if you
play with NROs that electrifying
transport doesn't have a huge effect on
the climate. Electrifying building an
industry by itself doesn't have a huge
effect on the climate. And part of that
is because you're not decarbonizing the
energy, the electricity supply. So you
have to make sure that if you're running
those heat pumps, you're running them
off of lowcarbon electricity. And that's
another system interaction. So if you
can do things like uh you know stop
building new coal plants and therefore
um you know work toward kind of that
decarbonization of the electricity
system. If you you know do some really
heavily heavy kind of um reductions
either technologically or uh or through
policy to reduce natural gas and so on
then you're decarbonizing electricity
supply then the electrifification
actually has more of an impact on the
climate. So just to say that these
systems are interactive and we want to
think about um as we are going and
trying to solve these thermal heating
problems that we do it in as renewably
powered a way as possible. But also just
that there are blind spots in so many of
these modeling tools and so many of
these policy discussions given the
general tendency to focus very heavily
on uh electricity.
Is that what you want me to cover?
Um, oh and I'll just say one one more
thing which is that of course AI and it
data center growth is driving you know
increase in all of these parameters in
terms of energy usage. So we have to do
everything that much harder and that
much faster. Um now hopefully the AI and
the machine learning can help us and
we're going to talk about the ways that
advanced analytics can help us identify
geothermal opportunities and optimize
for them. But just notice just
remembering whenever we talk about those
types of computational things, we always
want to think about the foot the
handprint and the footprint of those
technologies.
>> Okay,
>> thank you so much.
>> Oh my gosh, that was amazing. And
[Applause]
>> all right, that that was amazing. And
now And now we have to talk afterwards
about getting geothermal in there with a
little toggle switch. Yeah.