Good evening everyone. Welcome to this
evening's broad discovery center talk.
My name is Tom Olrich. I'm the associate
director for science communications at
the Broad and it's my pleasure to have
you all here with us for a little while
tonight. For those of you who might be
joining us for the first time, the broad
discovery series um has a bunch of
different um bunch of different goals
that go along with it. Uh we explore um
you know, I'm usually better at this.
You'd think I do it four times a year.
We explore the genetic and biological
roots of health and disease.
We explore also the mechanisms that
govern how our cells and bodies work. We
talk about new technologies that are
changing what's possible in science. And
we also are talking about the progress
that's being made to translate new
discoveries into treatments for both
common and rare diseases. It's my
pleasure tonight to introduce Nyall
Lennon. Nyall is the senior director for
Broad's genomics platform. He's also the
associate director for Broad's Gersonner
Center for Cancer Diagnostics and in
addition he's also the chief scientific
officer of Broad Clinical Labs which is
a wholly owned subsidiary of the Broad
Institute.
Now is going to talk tonight about the
opportunities that the constantly
increasing speed and dropping cost of
genome sequencing are allowing for
healthcare both now and in the future.
If you have any questions for Nile
tonight, I encourage you to flag one of
our micr runners during the Q&A portion
of the evening and they'll bring a
microphone right to you. If you're
watching online, I'll be keeping an eye
on YouTube chat. So, if you just enter
your questions there, I'll make sure to
do my best to try to work you into the
conversation.
If you're a scientist or a Brody with a
deep technical question for Nile, I'm
going to encourage you to please
approach him during the reception after
the Q&A so that members of our local
community have an opportunity to have
their questions answered.
And lastly, speaking of receptions, I
invite everybody here in the room to
join us after tonight's talk and for a
reception at the Broad Discovery Center
right back out the doors here. Um, where
I encourage you to explore the cent's
exhibits and interactive elements coming
up now.
All right. Good evening. Can you all
hear me? All right. Yes, the
microphone's working. Fantastic. Great.
Okay. So, I am delighted to be here this
evening to talk to you about what the
title says, which is essentially how the
technologies that we're using at the
Broad, the data we're generating here,
and the biology that we're increasingly
understanding might play into a future
health care system that incorporates
genomic medicine.
So, in my title, I used a word that
should make us feel all warm and fuzzy,
but actually, I imagine for many people,
it's actually a cause of stress,
healthcare,
right? Who wakes up at three in the
morning and you're you're wide awake and
your mind is rushing with all of the
topics of the day? I do sometimes. And
sometimes those thoughts are like, why
can't I play golf better? Um, sometimes
those thoughts are, what if I get sick?
What if one of the kids gets sick? It
today it feels like the health care
system has become a system that we never
want to have to interact with.
>> And that's probably not where we want to
be. Um but but we shouldn't despair. I I
do want to point out there's there's
some things to give us hope and
some things that you know when we think
about what's possible in modern
healthcare that we should really excited
about. um just some examples at a high
level. We do now have the capability to
see disease at the genomic level. I'll
describe more what that means. But more
importantly, we're actually increasingly
able to actually target with therapies
the exact molecular causes of disease.
Whereas historically we may have treated
the symptoms of disease, how diseases
show up, through the technologies that
I'll describe and the insights, we are
increasingly being able to see what's
causing that disease at the molecular
level and designing therapeutics that go
after that and that is more effective
and that now also for the first time
through technologies developed here and
elsewhere we are able to not just
identify those uh underlying changes in
our genomes that might be causing
disease. But for the first time, we can
actually start to think about editing
those genomes to fix that underlying uh
error. So these are all exciting
developments and they've happened just
over the last 20 years. Uh in fact,
they've started to happen just when I
joined the Broad Institute 20 years ago.
Coincidence?
Yes, definitely a coincidence. However,
there are some things that I think are
not coincidences. I think there's some
examples that we should look at where
there is a clear cause and effect thing
happening, right? And I I want to point
us to that time when we collectively
decide to invest in audacious projects
in really difficult things to generate
uh to achieve some really hard to
achieve goal and that the effect of
doing that has been positive in our
history. So one example being the Apollo
program, right? To send um uh astronauts
to space to land on the moon and come
back. That program ran for about 13
years from 1960 to 1973.
The government invested about $25
billion in that program. All told in
that time frame and estimates now
suggest that for every dollar we
invested in that program, we got a
return on that investment of about $7.
And that return on investment came from
solving the problems that we needed to
solve to achieve the goal. Uh and it
resulted in advancements in material
sciences, in batteries, in portable
tools, in memory foam. Hey, I've got a
memory phone mattress. Cool. I didn't
realize it came from the shuttle
program. Um but the point is when we do
something like this, we invest public
funds in something really difficult, we
actually receive uh returns on that
investment. So another largecale
investment that we've made as a country
was the human genome project. It's not
something that probably most of the
general public holds in their mind the
same way that sort of the Apollo
missions um kind of you know are known
but it similarly was actually
technologically
extremely difficult when it was started
when it was contemplated first.
Sequencing the three billion letters of
code that make up our genome at the time
this program was started was
extraordinarily difficult task. The
program took about 13 years as well to
complete. Um it ended up being about $3
billion of public investment and the
National Human Genome Research Institute
estimates that we've seen about a return
on investment of about $5 for every
dollar invested in that program. So
again, an audacious idea that we should
sequence the human genome has resulted
in a proliferation of fields that now
use those technologies and the
information that we can now generate. Um
not just in biio medicine but also in
forensics, in genealogy, in agriculture.
Um, so there's a ton of spaces where now
we use the technologies that had to be
invented to solve the human genome
project um, now in everyday uh, life.
So
I'm going to not use too much jargon
tonight, but I do I've already mentioned
the word genome a few times. So just to
level set the genome is basically the
genetic material of an organism. um
predominantly I'll talk about human
genomes but actually in our community
there are folks who study human genomes,
we study microbial genomes, viral
genomes, there are um you know
industries that look at plant genomes,
animal genomes but largely they're all
using the same sets of technologies to
do that.
And so the other term is variant. And so
in the past we might have turn used
terms like mutation but today we would
say a variant essentially any difference
that's in our genome between two
different individuals and part of the
reason to actually do the human genome
project was there was an understanding
that variance that differences in our in
our DNA in our genomes might be
underlying not just sort of our traits
you know how we appear but also might be
under underpinning some diseases but
until we actually sequence the genome.
There was no way to actually know which
variants in our genomes are totally
harmless and which are the ones that
actually could be the triggers for
disease. So that was the reason to start
doing genome sequencing. Um
and the other important point is that
to understand variance across many
people of course you can't just do the
human genome once. You actually have to
do it many many times. You know, ideally
we would have everyone's genome sequence
and then we would know all of the
variation in the world and we would be
able to catalog what variants are
actually disease-causing or disease risk
um increasing and what ones are totally
harmless. And so
the other thing I guess to to think
about is unlike space travel which is
still pretty expensive um it is now
primarily you know the purview of
billionaires and minor celebrities um
sequencing human genomes has actually
continued to go down in cost. Um so from
that first human genome which again
overall cost about uh $3 billion dollars
to sequence to understand the code of
through technological advances over the
last 20 years we're now at the today if
you come to the Broad Institute as a
researcher you can get a human genome
sequenced for a few hundred dollars
and unlike that first human genome which
took 13 years to sequence today
routinely we can do it actually in days.
And I'm going to tell you something
special that can h that happened about a
month ago that might uh indicate that in
the future we'll be able to do this
routinely in hours.
So today at the human at the broad we
actually sequence thousands of human
genomes every week.
Um in fact uh in our group at the the
genomics group at the broad institute
we've now sequenced over 870,000
human genomes.
And if you think about the idea again of
sequencing the genome, there's also a
lot of information in the genome that we
don't yet know fully what to do with.
The genes that make up all of the
proteins that sort of make up our body
are actually encoded in about 2% of the
information of our genome. And if you
just sequence that portion of the
genome, it's known as exo sequencing,
the expressed part of the genome. And of
exosomes, we've done over a million of
those. So the technology and the drop in
cost has allowed us to now expand the
scope of how many genomes or portions of
genomes we can routinely sequence
and and why do that I guess right so I
hinted at you know um before that you
can't just sequence one human genome and
start to really unlock all of the
insights of biology that's that are
locked in there you actually have to
sequence lots of genomes and so the
genomes the over 870,000 genomes that
we've sequenced and hundreds of
thousands that have in sequence in other
parts of the world um have been feeding
into research programs funded by federal
government, by philanthropy, by disease
foundations, by pharmaceutical companies
and biotech to really push forward all
of the possible applications of human
genome sequencing. And these are some of
the application areas I want to sort of
describe to you in more detail tonight.
And these are the the areas that
actually where people are showing the
utility of genome sequencing across
their entire lifespan from birth all the
way through aging.
And so um I'm going to dig into a couple
of examples. By no means is this an
exhaustive catalog of all of the
activity that's happening, but I just
want to give you in in certain parts of
of this sort of lifespan uh space where
we're at and where we might be going. So
think about newborns. So babies just
born. Most states, I not all states in
the US have statemandated newborn
screening programs. So we test babies.
We do a little heel prick, get a little
bit of of blood and we test babies for
some small number of diseases that are
important to know about as soon as you
can possibly know about them because you
want to take an action that would avoid
that baby uh getting sick in in early
childhood. So these are known as newborn
screening programs and they're typically
managed by departments of public health.
So several studies now over the last few
years have been investigating rather
than this sort of small suite of 30-ish
bio largely biochemical types of tests
that we do on those newborn heel pricks.
Um should we be doing whole genome
sequencing? two notable studies. One is
the Guardian study run out of New York
City
where they sequenced many thousand
newborns and um initial results they
published a year or so ago showed that
by doing whole genome sequencing um in
you would find many many more conditions
that geneticists would agree you would
want to know about in a newborn than you
do by traditional screening methods. So
this idea of like establishing sort of
clinical uh clinical utility. another
study. And uh good news for us in the
Boston area, that program, that guardian
study was run by an investigator out of
Columbia University, Wendy Chung. Wendy
Chung is now the uh chief of pediatrics
at Boston Children's Hospital. So, she's
been bringing this concept to
Massachusetts as well. Another study
closer to home run by uh Dr. Robert
Green out of Harvard and Brigham and
Women's Hospital was called Baby Seek.
And the sequencing of these newborns
actually happened in our clinical lab
here at the Broad Institute. And that
found again in a smaller cohort of
several hundred uh newborn families that
they found disease risks in about 11% of
the babies where we sequenced them. And
that importantly in that study they were
also addressing sort of the the family
response to the information because one
of the fears of doing this type of
testing on a newborn certainly a healthy
newborn is like will it cause anxiety to
the family? if will knowing this
information cause families to be super
stressed out and they did surveys of
their families found that that wasn't
necessarily the case that typically
families were happy to participate and
the ones who found out actionable
information were very happy to have it
so that was great so these have sort of
set the set the stage going forward
there's actually a new program funded by
NIH um called the beacons program that
is going to understand try to understand
the feasibility of offering this type of
whole genome sequencing as a firstline
test in newborns on a multi-state level.
So the sort of technical components of
doing this and the initial you know
impact studies have been done. The real
challenge now is actually the
implementation science. It's like how do
we actually roll this out into states
where this is managed by departments of
public health who are not typically
managing high complexity molecular
testing programs and so this program
will actually seek to bring this out
into more states. So this will help us
in the future and if the results are
positive we might see a national program
at some point in the future.
Another case in the in the sort of the
newborn field is unfortunately some
small number of babies are born who
actually have a serious uh problem and
they end up in the neonatal ICU or the
NICU and these are very sick babies can
be very sick babies and there again you
now you're you're not dealing with
screening for disease in a healthy
newborn. Now you're looking for can we
get to a diagnosis for a very sick baby
and obviously you want to do that as
quickly as you can and so a study again
a landmark study out this time run out
of raises children hospital in San Diego
um run by Dr. Dr. Steven Kingsmore over
there again looked at the feasibility of
running whole genome sequencing in this
niku cohort and understanding what is
the benefit and actually we found that
there he found that there was a a huge
benefit and that the information you
gain actually can decrease the length of
time it takes to get to a diagnosis.
Importantly, they also looked at what
would be the health care economics of
doing this and and saw that you might
actually reduce the cost, the healthcare
cost by doing this testing upfront.
Those savings are driven by fewer
hospital stays or days in the NICU
because if you get to an answer sooner,
you can get out of the NICU sooner. Uh,
and those are very expensive stays.
Fewer major surgeries. you can avoid a
major surgery if you can get to a
definitive diagnosis sooner and not do
unnecessary procedures. So all of that
together indicates that it might be
really valuable to do whole genome
sequencing in the NICU setting. Based on
this and other studies like it, um, now
clinical commercial laboratories have
started offering what they call rapid
whole genome sequencing programs,
clinical whole genome sequencing
programs that are can be used by ICUs
and NICUs around the country. Um, with
current technologies, they're still
taking, you know, between two and five
days to actually get you that answer
back, though, which is really fast.
Again, two and five days, really fast.
But in the NICU, every hour matters. And
so we were fortunate a few months ago to
actually engage in a study to assess
could we do it even faster.
So this was a collaboration between us,
RO, which is a large pharmaceutical
company, but also has a a diagnostics
arm, RO Diagnostics, which is a very
large uh entity in its own right. And
within that arm has a small group that's
been developing a novel DNA sequencing
technology. So we worked with them using
this novel technology and our friends at
the NICU and Boston Children's Hospital
to run a small study where we showed and
the plot sort of shows a sort of you
know think about this is sort of the um
a clock of a day um where we were
uh so Monica Wujek who is the
neonatlogist at Boston Children's
enrolled families into this as a
research study. So it's not a clinical
diagnostic test. It's a research study.
Their baby samples were already being
sent for standard of care clinical
testing. But as a research arm, we got
additional blood from the NICU babies,
the sick sick babies, had that collected
at uh by a courier at Boston Children's
Hospital. We rushed it out to our
clinical lab, which is actually located
in in Burlington. Um
and so and then we started working on
that blood sample using this new
technology. We, you know, by about noon
on that day, we had from the blood
sample extracted genomic material, run
it through this novel sequencing
technology and gotten to sort of the
data files, the the the the
computational files that contain the
variants within that baby's genome. And
then we started what's called tertiary
analysis. That's where trained clinical
geneticists look at all of those
variants in special software that allows
them to sort between those variants that
we know are most likely harmless and
those variants that have been associated
with disease. And they have the
phenotype that is what are the symptoms
that the baby is exhibiting and by
looking at the symptoms and the variance
in in the genome they can sort of say is
there something here that actually might
be causing this uh these symptoms in
this baby. So in two of the seven cases,
we actually located what we think is
likely the pathogenic variant, the
variant that was causing um those babies
um
symptoms.
And importantly, if you look at the
clock, what happened was we were
collecting blood at 6:30 in the morning
and in the earliest cases getting the
neonatlogist the answer by around 2 p.m.
that same day. It had never been done
before. And so we published this in New
England Journal of Medicine about a
month ago. um as a feasibility to say it
might be now possible in the future.
Once this technology is commercially
available, it's still not commercially
available, but once it is, as soon as
next year, we may be able to now
routinely deliver whole genome
sequencing the same day. And that would
really radically change the thinking of
neontologists in how they create a care
plan for for the sake of babies. And
just for fun along the way, we actually
picked up a Guinness World Record for
the fastest human genomes ever
sequenced. So if you remember
uh if you remember, you know, we've come
a long way from 13 years in in some of
the in in this study, we sequenced the
genome in less than four hours. So from
um that DNA to those variants in less
than four hours. So the technological
advancements have been you know
mind-blowing over the last uh decades.
All right. So
other the next place in our lifespan
where diseases can show up is in
childhood. And a lot of childhood
diseases are rare diseases. And so um we
call them rare diseases because each
sort of disease that shows up doesn't
show up in a lot of children. But in
aggregate there are a lot of rare
diseases. In fact, there are over 8,000
rare genetic diseases now described. So
the burden on the population is actually
quite large and fewer than 500 of those
rare genetic diseases have any treatment
available. So understanding the causes
of rare diseases is very important and
again rare diseases are often have
genetic causes and so we've been looking
at again with collaborators at Boston
Children's and there's many programs at
the broad that look at rare disease um
you know how can we bring these new
technologies to look at um the
underlying genetic causes of disease.
Sometimes the sort of standard genome
testing we do is not enough and we need
to go to additional data types,
different types of doing genome
sequencing to find that sort of missing
um um cause. Um
because what you're really trying to do
in the rare disease case is decrease
what's known as the uh diagnostic
odyssey, which is that families who have
a child with rare disease often go
through years of of like incremental
testing, testing one gene, testing the
next gene, and and it could take years
to get to an actual definitive
diagnosis. If you can do that sooner,
again, you have great b you know, many
benefits for the family. Just having an
answer is really important. It helps
them with planning. is it likely to
happen in subsequent children? It helps
them find support groups and other
people who may have the same diseases
and then also you know start to figure
out are there clinical trials we can
enroll in. So it's really important to
get to that diagnosis as soon as
possible and that's been a lot of focus
of um next of whole genome sequencing
methods. Other programs that we've been
running with uh disease foundations
include the the Simons Foundation which
runs a large autism research program.
There are actually um over 300,000 now
participants both um participants with
autism and their families and we've been
doing whole genome sequencing on many of
those individuals to again understand
some of the underlying genetic causes of
autism.
A future-looking program that started at
the Broad Institute um under Anna Grea,
a researcher at the institute um is
called Ladders to Cures. And this is a
really tantalizing prospect that that
Anna has described in detail in other
talks. Um, but where if you think about
these 8,000 uh rare genetic diseases,
it's entirely possible under sort of
growing evidence that you might not be
actually working with 8,000 completely
different diseases that have just sprung
up independently, but that if you look
deep enough that they actually might
sort of whittle down into smaller
numbers of sort of systemic kind of
network effects where you know something
that's happening in a node in sort of a
you know underlying system in the body
is manifesting in lots of different ways
and getting diagnosed as different and
showing up as what we call different
diseases. But actually the fundamental
molecular thing this pathway is actually
common across many of those diseases. So
if you can under you know if you can
discover and describe those pathways
those nodes um you might be able to come
up with more effective therapies for
more diseases at once rather than trying
to tackle all of them individually. And
this uses other aspects of technology
that we have really looking at the
single cell level. Looking at individual
cells and many many cells and
engineering them to display some of the
the uh variants that are showing up in
these diseases and seeing what happens
seeing what happens across different
variants. Did the cells start to do the
same thing different things? So this is
really um an exciting new way to get to
uh address rare disease uh research.
Of course, chronic diseases and common
diseases are the largest cause of sort
of mortality and morbidity um in the
world and there are many programs as
well of course that address um address
these diseases. Um there are programs
funded by the NIH which address lots of
um um common diseases using both genome
sequencing or genomics as well as many
other omics. When we talk about
genomics, there's also really looking at
the protein level, proteomics, looking
at um the sort of chemical um signatures
that are on top of our genome or
epigenomics. Um there's metabolomics,
there's transcripttoics, there's lots of
omix. And so we're, you know, we're
increasingly understanding that for um
cohorts of people with disease, it's
really more powerful to generate as much
omic data as we can because that gives
you a much fuller picture of what's
happening again at the molecular level.
Another really important um area in in
common disease research at the broad is
coming through a philan
philanthropically um founded center at
the broad, the Stanley Center for
Psychiatric Diseases. That group has
been doing large-scale population
sequencing um across the world of
different populations that have um
psychiatric diseases, schizophrenia,
bipolar disorder, major depressive
disorders. And they've actually through
this large-scale genomic data generation
activity started to uncover biomarkers
or those little signals in the genome
that um strongly can be linked to these
um devastating mental um health issues.
And in some cases, these are the first
sort of genetic targets that we've
identified in decades in these diseases.
And so this gives the idea that there's
hope to start to to generate better,
more targeted therapies um for major
psychiatric diseases. Again, looking
forward, one of the newest centers um
created at the Broad is the biology of
adversity project. This is a really
interesting area um driven by Jason Bwin
restro the broad institute which is to
understand how adversity can actually
lead to chronic health problems. And so
you know we've all been taught that the
DNA is your blueprint. It's in every
cell of your body and it's sort of we we
kind of imagine it's sort of fixed. Once
you've got your DNA you've got your DNA.
But actually, it turns out that things
that happen to you in your life can
actually leave a mark on your DNA. And
this is part of that epigenomics, the
idea of molecular scars or little
signals, little chemical modifications
that can get imprinted on your DNA and
propagate through your life. And we're
increasingly understanding that these
molecular scars if you're uh can lead to
later life development of chronic
diseases, heart disease, diabetes, major
depressive disorders, you know,
post-traumatic stress syndrome. And so
Jason's group and the biology adver
adversity project is seeking to really
do what the Stanley Center has been
doing in the psychiatric disease
research area with looking at these
molecular scars in cohorts who have had
adversity. So these are childhood
traumas understanding cohorts of people
who have had some some traumatic event
and seeing are there can we find these
markers and are they actually things
leading to chronic disease. So this is a
re very fascinating area that could be
really powerful to understand a lot of
chronic disease.
All right. Um cancer of course is one of
the sort of prime examples of where
we've seen a major benefit of being able
to do molecular genomic profiling.
Increasingly today patients um diagnosed
with cancers will have their tumors
genomically characterized. And so when
we think about your genome, the the
genome of your of your body, sort of the
quote unquote normal healthy genome, in
cancer, for the most part, that genome
has somehow become, you know, mutated,
transformed in some way that has led to
this uncontrolled proliferation and that
shows up as tumors. And so there are
many programs um at the bro and
elsewhere to really catalog the variants
that are associated with different
cancer types. And these are so and what
one way you can do that is to take a
blood sample and a tumor sample from an
individual with cancer and sequence the
genomes or portions of those genomes
from both of those. And what you'll find
is that in the sort of the quoteunquote
healthy non-tumor cells you'll have the
person's underlying genome but in their
tumor cells you'll find this abnormal
genome. And by cataloging all of the
ways that it has become abnormal you can
uncover these uh molecular pathways that
are leading to cancer. And this is the
underpinning of most targeted molecular
therapies now, precision medicine
therapies for cancers that have been so
transformative in changing the sort of
the prognosis for most cancers. And so
there are programs across the road
cataloging these variants in in
different tumor types. Also again using
this idea of single cell technology to
create sort of tumors or uh in engineer
in modifications that represent a
cancer-like mutation and then be able to
quickly screen what do different small
molecules what do different medicines
what do different drugs do to those
cells. Can we find even you know even
better targeted therapies and then also
the idea of overcoming resistance. Some
sometimes people get a a therapy for
their cancer, cancer goes away, but they
develop a resistance and the cancer
comes back. So understanding those
programs of resistance is also really
important.
another center at the bro the Gersonner
center that that I've had some
involvement with um is is doing similar
things but actually in the the sort of
the burgeoning field that's come in the
last couple of years of understanding
that actually a tumor in your body
because of the nature of cancer tumor
cells are often dying and when they die
they release their genetic material that
essentially gets drained into your blood
system which is how your body
essentially you know cleans out and so
that by looking at blood samples, just
taking a blood sample, you might be able
to find what's known as circulating
tumor DNA, that's little pieces of DNA
from the tumor that are actually
circulating in the blood. And so this
field of what's known as sort of liquid
biopsy. So a traditional tumor biopsy
would be to there's a tumor, let's take
a piece of that tumor out, that tissue,
and look at it. Um
the field of liquid biopsy is actually
taking a biopsy not from the tumor but
from the blood or other liquids. Um and
this is particularly important where you
know you've had a patient who's had
cancer their tumor has been removed.
You've taken away the cancer. So now
there is no tumor to biopsy anymore. Um
but what you really want to understand
is like did we get all of it or is there
still is there another tumor that we
haven't seen yet? Is there metastasis?
These are really important things
because these are the things that
actually lead to a lot of mortality in
in cancer patients. And so being able to
detect can we find any signals of
lingering cancer. This is a field known
as minimal residual disease. Is there
any small signals of that of tumors um
circulating in the body? And so now um
by taking blood samples at some period
after the person has had surgery or or
treatment with curative intent um
there's a whole field of can we detect
any cancer and if you don't that's great
these methods are getting now more and
more sensitive you know thanks to the
work of folks at the Gersonner center
and elsewhere to see the earliest
possible time if you do detect it again
that's the time to take an action
because detecting it and having it see
that it's actually coming back is the
first signal that something is going to
come back. And so the earlier you can
you can have that min minimal residual
disease detected the more powerful um
intervention will be. So that's a that's
a huge area now in the field of cancer
research. Looking forward again just in
the last few months um locally again
we've we've been able to bring together
the best of our cancer research
community and our local um hospital
community with one initiative called
Brightsee which is a again a
collaboration between Dana Farber Cancer
Institute Boston Children's Hospital and
the Broad Clinical Labs here to develop
a suite of um pediatric cancer assays.
So there are many now both companies and
and labs that do adult cancer testing
because that is the vast majority of
cancers that show up in the world. The
pediatric cancer is thankfully quite
rare. Um but what that means is from a
commercial perspective for these
companies, it's not actually a super
viable business. And so you have less
development of assays really
specifically developed to detect or
monitor pediatric cancers. And so we've
been as part of this collaboration we
will be developing u both solid tumor
and liquid biopsy based assays uh for
pediatric cancer uh diagnosis and
research.
All right moving on. So a bio bank has
anyone has anyone know has anyone been
asked to be a participant in a bio bank
as far as you know so if you've got the
mass general you might have at some
point been asked might have seen
>> is that like all of us
>> yes exactly right so a biioank is
essentially a program that you know
creates a secure consented repository of
biopecimens
and people's information right and so
the way to really drive forward many of
the things that we've just talked about,
right? Understanding that catalog of
human variation, what ones cause
disease, what ones don't cause disease.
Um, is to actually have information from
lots and lots of people.
You know, you know what we're realizing,
of course, is that again, fundamentally
at a very simplistic level, when you
sequence a genome, you're trying to
understand the variants that you find in
that genome. And there's millions of
them in all of our genomes. a variant,
something that's different than somebody
else's genome, there's millions of them.
So, if you're just looking at a computer
file with a million or three million
variants in it, and you're trying to
decide which one of these three million
things might be causing this person's
disease, that's really hard, right? So
you need to have knowledge bases,
computer systems, software that can sort
through all of that and annotate it and
say in all of the people we've ever
seen, this variant, this difference in a
piece of DNA has never been known to
cause a disease. That would be ideal if
we could do that for all three million.
But of course to do that, we actually
need to see all of the variants that
exist in the human population. It turns
out bio banks are a great way to start
cataloging that. Um because bio banks
try to enroll people some people who
have disease but ideally just regular
people who you know we all we've all got
something going on but nominally healthy
people right if we can all contribute
our information both our genetic
information you know surveys about our
health our medical records you know
information about us that goes into a
large biioank like knowledge base we can
really start to understand you know the
impact of that variation um you know a a
bio bio bank that got started early and
has been very successful is the UK biio
bank. The NHS and the UK government have
been very forwardlooking in investing in
in in biioanks and genomics. And so
they've got a really mature bioank with,
you know, over 500,000 individuals with
this sort of linked information about
health records and activity and
everything else. And so that's been very
powerful to understand some of the
variation in humans.
But what we're realizing of course is
that variance in our genome don't just
account for sort of our hair color and
our eye color and our you know whether
or not we have asparagus pee. Um they
also account for like they actually also
come from our genetic ancestry. So
different human populations will have
different variants and so some of those
differences between us come from our
genetic ancestry. Um and it turns out
that if you look at a variant in one
population and say oh in this population
we see this variant and then that person
also has this disease. So maybe that
variant causes that disease. But if you
look at enough people maybe you find in
a totally different human population
that variant exists and is quite common
and none of those people have that
disease. Well now you've realized
actually that variant can't be the one
causing the disease. So you actually
need to catalog people from all types of
genetic ancestries to really understand
um what variants are important to look
at. And so if you look in UK biioank,
you know, and you look at a variant and
you want to predict something about my
genome, that would be fairly accurate.
Now, I'm from Ireland. Ireland is not
part of the UK, but um but genetically,
we might not want to admit it, but we're
sort of similar. Um, so it's going to be
accurate for me because most of the UK
bio bank is from northern European white
individuals who live in sort of that UK
area. Um, but it's not going to be as
accurate for somebody who comes from
Africa or somebody who comes from Asia,
you know. So we actually have to start
creating bioanks that reflect everybody.
And so all of us is one of those
programs that in the US is trying to
catalog um at least a million US
residents and capture sort of the
genetic diversity and socioeconomic
diversity of this country because unlike
many countries in the world, US
traditionally has been this sort of what
we call like the boiling pot. You have
immigrants like me who come over from
Europe and you've got other people who
come from all over the world and then
they meet somebody and they have
children and so it turns out your
grandfather's from Ireland and your
grandmother's from the West Indies. And
so your genetic ancestry now is actually
the combination of two different
entirely different human populations
genetic ancestries. And so from a
geneticist perspective, we would say
you're admixed, right? Your your
genetics are mixed across different
genetic ancestries. And so we need to
capture a lot. We need to capture all of
that. So it's not just useful to cap to
sequence a bunch of people from Europe
and a bunch of people from Africa and a
bunch of people from Asia. We also have
to sequence just all the people who've
all kind of you know um had offspring
together. So you really need to capture
it's a it's a numbers game. You need to
capture as many people as you possibly
can to build up the knowledge base in a
bio bank and then you need to associate
that with a lot of interesting
information about their health and their
activities and and all of that to really
build up this picture of what's going
on. And so that was the program, the all
of us program. It's enrolled over
800,000 people. It was started many
years ago with a goal of enrolling a
million and sequencing all of their
genomes. Um it's enrolled about 800,000.
we have sequenced over 500,000 of those
participants genomes. Many of them were
done here at the Broad Institute. Um the
program has run into some federal
funding issues and so the future of that
program is uncertain. Um and I think
that would be um a tragedy. um more
locally actually if you if you you know
attend a hospital around here in the
Mass General Bighgam network Mass
General Brighgam has a pretty actually
active and pretty good um bioank program
as well and that's enrolled over 160,000
people from the Mass General Bighgam
hospital network and that's also a
really powerful data set to start to
look at again um associations between
your health and your genome. So, as well
as being a principal investigator on the
all of us program because we generate a
lot of the data, I I believe in this
stuff. I'm a participant in the program.
My genome was sequenced as part of this
program. Uh my wife's genome was also
sequenced as part of this program. Um
early in the program when it had more
money, it was also returning some health
related information to participants. And
so, you would get some information back
about your health risks. You know, there
are some things that we can tell that
are important to know. My wife actually
found out that she has what's known as
Lynch syndrome from the participating in
the all of us program and that means
that she's at an increased risk
potentially of colorectal or ovarian
cancer and so now she's brought that
information to her PCP and now she gets
more frequent screening for those
particular conditions. So that idea of
like just learning something about your
genome that you didn't know can
completely change your your healthcare.
So
to kind of recap from a bioank
perspective, what can you do? You can do
lots of things with it. A rich bioank
that has lots of sort of genomic and
other omics and um associated health
information can help us catalog this
human variation. It can help us now
because if you if you actually enroll
hundreds of thousands of people, you're
going to have lots and lots of people
with any one disease. Certainly common
diseases are going to be common. So
you're going to have lots of people with
cardiovascular disease, lots of people
with cancer. And so you can then look in
this program and say, well, what's the
same about all of those people with that
disease that's not in the people who
don't have that disease and start to do
those genetic associations.
The other tantalizing thing that I think
you know looking forward is that by
having all of this data, we can start to
get really fancy with the sort of the
math, right? And we can start to create
what's known as risk models, right? And
so this is the last sort of um area that
I'll cover which is preventative
medicine. the idea that, you know,
treating disease, we've gotten really
good at treating disease and we've got
world-class hospitals here in Boston,
but it's a lot better to avoid getting
the disease in the first place if you
can. And that's actually fundamentally
longer term going to be better for the
whole health care system if we can avoid
uh treating the the the symptom but
actually, you know, avoid getting the
underlying disease at the beginning. and
and a Milicanin Institute analysis
estimated that if we could just prevent
or better ma better manage just seven
common diseases cancer diabetes
hypertension stroke uh pulmonary
conditions and mental illness we could
reduce the US treatment costs by about
$200 billion per year and we'd save
about a trillion dollars per year in
loss productivity so prevention is
clearly better than cure but of course
it's difficult and and there's lots of
things that go into preventing disease
And it's hard to measure because you're
looking for the absence of something if
you've prevented a disease. But this is
something that I really feel passionate
about and I think has driven me and my
own sort of journey into into this kind
of science. When I was 16, my father had
a heart attack. He was 46 at the time. I
was 16. So I thought, "Wow, he's really
old, you know." Then I turned 46 three
years ago and and I had three children
under 12 and I went, "I don't want to
have a heart attack. I I'm really young
still." um if other survived and he's
actually alive and kicking um has had
several stances and bypass surgeries
since then right so so clearly I was
really focused on the idea of like what
is my risk of cardiovascular disease I'm
really cognizant of that because I've
got this family history so I'm like I
really want to know about that um and so
when you think about this idea of like
well what goes into this mental model of
like what is my risk of developing this
disease of having a heart attack um And
so there's lots of things we've touched
on this. One is your genetics, your
family history, any other underlying
sort of medical conditions you might
have. Um there's these ideas. So the
terms up here, polygenic and monogenic.
Without getting into too much detail,
mono as the as the name implies is
essentially there are some variants in
some genes that are well known to be
associated with disease. So we all might
have heard about this idea of the the BA
one bracka 2 mutations in breast cancer
right this Angelina Jolie mutation um so
uh that's well known that's known as a
monogenic risk if you have that one
single variant in that gene we know
that's really strongly associated with
developing that condition and there's
monogenic risks for lots of diseases
polygenic risk really means this idea
that idea that there are not these sort
of you know single sort of smoking gun
this one variant is really bad. But
actually distributed throughout our
entire genome, there are small, you
know, there are variants that have small
or varying degrees of of effect on our
health and that any one of them wouldn't
really cause a disease. But in
aggregate, if you had all of the wrong
kinds of those variants together, you
might actually be increasing your risk
of a disease. That's known as polygenic
risk because it's in lots of genes.
Okay? So the idea of to get a big a full
picture of our risk of disease, you need
to understand monogenic and polyenic and
your family history and also social
determinance. You know, what is your
access to health? What is your
exposures? Are you living in an area
with polluted air? That also contributes
to our risk. So you need to get a big
picture. So bio banks are a great place
to start to aggregate all of this
information and then to build these
models. And these models can be super
powerful. And basically there are
algorithms that take all of these pieces
of information together and come up with
a a risk and say you are at an increased
risk of this disease. You should take
action. We were fortunate to be part of
a study uh funded by the National Human
Genome Research Institute known as
Emerge or Genomics in the medical
record. um which was which actually
sought to address to look at this this
idea of what happens if you report back
to individuals their monogenic and their
polyenic and their family history risk
of some chronic diseases. You know, we
chose models that were mature for for
for the diseases listed here. And across
24,000 participants and 10 clinical
sites across the entire country
including both adults and pediatric
cohorts, we we sequenced, we calculated
their risks of these diseases through
these models and then returned that to
them through their healthcare providers
and and again the science is sort of
there but a big part of this study is
actually the implementation science part
of it. Like what do they do with that
information? What do they do? How does
not just the the patient what does the
doctor do with that information? You
know, so this idea of polygenic risk for
cardiovascular disease has been
developed and and some of the seminal
work on that came out of the broad
institute several years ago. I'm a
patient and and broad institute and
researchers at Mass General with us
published some seminal papers on this
many years ago. And of course I'm like
oh I'm interested in cardiovascular
risk. I'm going to go talk to my PCP
who's at Mass General and say, 'What do
you think about this polygenic risk?
Should I get tested for polygenic risk
for cardiovascular disease? He went,
what's that? Right? He didn't have a
clue because we're not training
physicians in who are like, you know, in
the field with 50minute appointments on
like what polygenic risk is. So part of
this study was actually what about
creating educational materials for the
health care provider and action plans
and how do we you know train the health
care system to actually be able to
handle this information as well not just
the participants. Uh and so this is
again I think the next generation of
what we're going to start doing is like
how do we start to distribute the more
cutting edge models of risk so that
people can start to take actions
earlier. And so we've been fortunate
building on this study and other work
that's been happening to now work with
lots of groups to try to get this
information out there. So Mass General
Brighgam again across the river uh Praep
Narajan who runs the preventative
cardiology clinic at Mass General and is
a a member at the Broad
you know he's been really interested in
this topic as well for his clinic you
know because you can do all the risk
factors of lipids and weight exercise
smoking but he wants to also capture the
full risk which means I he wants to
understand that polygenic and monogenic
risk as well. So together we worked on
launching a clinical test now that any
patient and not just at Mass General but
any patient around the country can talk
to their doctor. They can order it from
Mass General um across eight different
cardiovascular conditions. They've now
got these risk scores um of course um as
well as being a collaborator I'm also a
patient of Praeps because I go to the
preventative cardiology clinic because
I'm someone who's obsessed with
cardiovascular risk, right? Um so I got
this test done. Um turns out I don't
have polygenic risks. That's great. Um,
haven't found any monogenic risk. The
all of us program didn't find any risk
in my genome. So, uh, it's a lot of
family history and all I can do is
essentially have a healthier lifestyle
than I would say my father had in his
40s where he was a smoker and he was
overweight. I can avoid to the as great
extent I can those things and then
hopefully my you know it looks like now
my you know risk of having a heart
attack is lower um than than it could
have been had I not taken those
interventions um those lifestyle
interventions other programs in the VA
so the the Veterans Administration
actually has another very interesting
bio bank known as the million veterans
project and so they've been enrolling
veterans into a bio because veterans
also have a set of healthcare issues,
some of which are unique to them to
their population. And so with Jason
Vassie, who's an investigator at the VA,
um we've launched a clinical trial in
prostate cancer risk in the VA
population using the same sort of
methods that we're using in the other
programs. Also working with companies,
there are companies who work directly
with consumers. Now my as an example um
they've also been working with a
research institute in Alabama to provide
free genetic testing for common healthc
care risks in the population to Alabama
because Alabama has one of the poorest
healthcare outcomes uh in in the
country. So bringing this kind of
cutting edge testing to to the state of
Alabama
and then other you know companies are
offering this as well using the same
underlying technologies and algorithms
and models that we've been building
here. Okay. So I hope I've convinced you
that there's a there is a potential
future in which the technologies that
you heard about tonight could actually
make a material impact on all of our
healthcare. And I really would like to
see us be able to get to a place where
we spend, you know, number one, we're
not afraid afraid to interact with the
health care system, that the healthare
system is in fact interactive. That the
insights I haven't talked about AI and
machine learning yet, ML, right? But
almost everything I've talked about
already incorporates some amount of AI
and ML in it. The the software that we
use to look at the variance uses AI. the
the chips on the computers that we use
to do the 4hour genome or Nvidia
accelerated, you know, machine learning
chips. It's already part of what we're
doing today. But there's more we can do
with AI and ML. There's a whole bunch of
hype and nonsense in AI and ML. But
actually, fundamentally, it's just a
really powerful tool that will help us
sort through all of this information
that we're gathering that humans are
just not equipped sort of to manually
sort through. When you think about a bio
bank, if you've got hundreds of
thousands of people with hundreds of
thousands of genomes, each genome has
millions of variants and they've got all
these other pieces of information about
their health and their lifestyle. A
human can never make those associations
and those patterns. It's exactly what AI
is built to do. So AI is already making
a difference. It's going to continue
making a difference. the more we have
linked data sets and larger bio banks,
we'll be able to train better models and
get these risks like out there much more
powerfully, much more predictive. And I
think there is a possible world and
there's companies working on it where
you can have your genome sequence and
you will be able to sort of interact
with that risk model and understand it.
Um, and I think it would be great if,
you know, we spend as much time sort of
tinkering with and making small changes
in our health care and our our healthy
aging plan as we do in our 401k. Like
the Fidelity app is really easy to use,
you know, for most part. If we had a
little health app that, you know, that
your hospital system or your your your
insurance maintained, maybe not your
insurance, who knows? um but that
somebody maintained that you had control
over that you could start to say well
look this risk over here um I should
talk to my healthcare provider about
additional screenings for these diseases
because one of the things about saving
money in the system is you know if we
all just go out and get screened for
everything more often that actually
increases the healthcare cost burden but
but by actually modeling your risk and
say well actually I'm not at higher risk
for any one of these diseases than
anybody else but these two things I'm at
much higher risk for and I'm only going
to really focus on additional screening
for these things. We would end up saving
the system money. Okay. So the idea of
interactivity I think that would be a
really great place to get um the
healthare systems themselves can also
use this through their bio banks through
their there's fascinating stuff
happening just looking at EHRs that the
electronic health records little signals
in your labs the notes that you have in
your visits. Um Jordan Smaller who runs
um some of the the psychiatric program
at Mass General has published papers
showing um risk of bipolar disorder,
things like suicidal tendencies. You can
actually find signals of those things in
people's medical records when you apply
AI. So there's there's a tremendous
amount that's going to happen in that.
Um so that's that's sort of risk
modeling and planning. When we
inevitably when people have diseases,
the other types of studies and
technologies are going to help us have
better therapies, more targeted
therapies, not just in cancer but in
rare diseases as well. The ability to
edit genomes is is a tantalizing idea.
And the idea that we can sort of, you
know, maybe hopefully bucket diseases
together so that there are incentives to
create therapies for more of the rare
diseases.
So to summarize,
I guess my message was
public investment in really difficult
audacious projects like the human genome
project have
really returned a massive amount of um
value to us both as a sort of a research
community but increasingly in the
biomedical field and now getting into
the healthcare system. I think that
we're only going to see more
improvements, more control, more ability
to direct our own healthcare and our
aging, our healthy aging with modern
methods. And I think this is and and
realizing that we can't just make this
sort of the sport of kings for the
people who can afford it. that actually
the way to reduce the healthcare burden
is to catalog this variation across all
ancestries, all all people and make the
sort of the the risk mitigation
available to all. That's where we're
actually going to save uh save money and
and really it just it all comes from our
continue continuing to believe and
invest in science. Thank you.
Thank you so much, Nile. Uh, if you have
any questions in the audience, raise
your hand and one of our micro runners
will come over to you. But first, I'll
just start off with we clearly we have
the science, we have the technology, we
can make them better.
What is it going to take to make
sequencing from like a reg is it a
regulatory thing? Is it a financial
thing where we could just go to our
doctor's office like if I have an
appointment tomorrow and just say hey
I'd like to get sequenced I want to know
what my risk is. I'm not a participant
in a by I actually am but you know how
can that just become sort of the
standard part of the care that we all
get whenever we see our PCP.
>> Yeah. So I didn't get into it because
it's a downer and also it would take too
long and I'm not an expert. uh we have
this issue of insurance certainly in
this country and you know today
increasingly insurance is covering
genome sequencing certainly in childhood
rare diseases in the NICU in cancers
where there's clear sort of actions and
and utility you know you don't have
issues you know convincing insurance
companies that you could sequence the
genome on a healthy individual and have
that information about their risks and
do prevention and that would ultimately
save them is a really tricky prospect
the way that insurance works in this
country because a company is not
necessarily incentivized to kind of help
you avoid a disease 10 years from now
because most insurance companies have a
an individual customer for like three
years. So they don't see the they pay
for the test they don't see the benefit
of the test is their thinking. So we got
to change that thinking to say that
actually preventing disease helps them
all. Whether it's they pay for it,
somebody else pays for it, they get the
benefit of the test that somebody else
paid for. That's that's the morass that
you know has to be addressed. And I
think the other thing that I did not get
into because it's a whole topic to be
solved on its own is of course sort of
genetic privacy. Do you want your
insurance company knowing your risks of
disease? What would they do with that
information? Um so we have to have you
know the ability I think again for
individuals to control their own
information. what's done with it. Um, so
I, so there's a lot to address there.
>> Question over here.
>> Oh, sorry. Go right ahead. Sorry. Sorry.
>> Yeah, I I was really impressed by
everything you said about uh how we're
applying uh genetic variations
especially to newborn infants in the
clinic. But three areas you didn't
mention is one sematic monitoring
sematic changes in diseases like cancer.
Two uh microbiome and tracing how that
is related to health and disease and how
that might vary even with an individual
and then RNA expression levels
transcripttoics of disease uh and with
testing back in less than a day. uh how
how close are we to being able to use
that kind of information to trace the
projects the progress of diseases that
give us feedback that would help in the
clinic.
>> Yeah, great question. So, so, so all of
those things are happening. Um, so
sematic changes in cancer are just the
variants in the tumors that I described.
So, I just didn't call them sematic
variants, but that certainly is is part
of this sequencing of tumors and liquid
biopsy. Um microbiome is a fascinating
uh absolutely fascinating um area and I
was involved in the human microbiome
project as well. Um and so there are
lots of studies actually and one of you
know we routinely um at our lab are
profiling gut microbiomes and and that
is one of the big research areas that's
happening at the road as well. We don't
have a clinical test for microbiomes
today, but there are companies locally.
There are startups um who are looking at
uh microbiome therapeutics for you know
things like CIFF um and IBD. And so
that's certainly an area it uses exactly
the same technologies I've described um
and and RNA. Yes. So RNA so it is in
this sort of field of again multiple
omics and so we do a tremendous amount
of RNA transcrytoics um sequencing as
well in the all of us cohort. We've just
actually um completed a pilot of 10,000
participants within the Olivus cohort
adding to their existing genome
sequencing, transcryto RNA sequencing
and proteome like protein protein uh
profiling as well um to build up that
picture of you know what is the value of
adding these other omix to this for
research but also RNA sequencing is now
you know often used in some of the rare
disease diagnostics because one way that
you can understand if you find say two
variants that might be causing the
disease and say that you know the the
way the disease shows up is a muscle
disease or muscle wasting um one thing
you can look at is in the RNA knowledge
bases that we have um and these are
other large public initiatives we've
been involved in GTEx is the genome
genotype tissue expression project so
looking at RNA levels in different
tissues you could look at that patient
and say I found two variants in the
genome let's look in the RNA level and
say, well, of these two variants, which
one of them is highly expressed in
muscle? Because if that's the one that
has the variant that and the disease
shows up as a muscle wasting disease,
that's helps us kind of get to those
positive variants. So, yes, all of those
things are certainly happening. Um,
uh, in our hands at least, the
microbiome and the RNA are not yet
clinical tests, but there are clinical
tests that use RNA and microbiomes in in
other groups.
Thank you for this amazing talk um and
summarizing the last 20 years of
genomics in one hour. Um I'm also an
exrody and I started 20 years ago at the
broad that was my first job. So big fan
of the broad institute obviously. Um my
question is
if those programs become
possible where everybody's sequenced in
all the states,
do we have the infrastructure for it?
Where will the samples go? Where will
they get processed? Right?
>> How will the reporting be managed? What
recommendation do you have if somebody
were to ask you how to do that?
>> Yep.
>> An hour.
>> Yeah. Well, well, so that is exactly the
kind of thing. So, if you think about
the newborn sequencing program, that's
that beacons program. That is exactly
part of this implementation science,
right? It's not we technically know how
to do it, but it's all of those
logistics, right? It's the how yeah,
where did the sample get processed? How
do we store the sample? It turns out
that actually one of the big costs now
because the cost of sequencing genomes
has become so low
storing the data you know create when
you when you sequence a genome you
create a lot of data like more than you
can keep on a laptop and so actually
storing all of that data becomes quite
expensive. So there's data management
becomes a legitimate um issue and also
just again this we have to be so careful
about data security right and and one of
the actually interesting things about
the way the all of us bio bank program
was set up is that um sort of in a
precient way was that when it was set up
many years ago
participants who have their genome
sequence as part of all of us the data
is stored in a cloud environment in a
secure environment but it's actually
even though the The project is funded by
the NIH. The government does not own the
data. The government doesn't have access
to the data. The data is stored by an
awardee. Actually, it turns out to be
Vanderbilt University is the curator of
the data. So, they're responsible for
keeping it safe and access to it. And
actually, they have what's called a
certificate of confidentiality, which
means the government cannot access that
data for law enforcement purposes, for
other things like that. So that's those
kinds of things are very those walls are
very important to um create to build
confidence, privacy, security. So all of
that logistical things do have to be
worked out. That is what programs like
beacons and others are trying to do. And
there's lots of companies who are also
trying to do this. And it will be
interesting to see of course there's a
lot of public effort. There's also a
bunch of private effort and so there's
there's a lot of models out there where
you could go to a company and get your
genome sequenced and one model is and
then likely again this is for people who
can pay for it. there is sort of the
subscription model. you would have your
genome sequenced and have it accessible
whenever you need to access it or look
you know something happens and you you
want to have someone interrogate it you
could do that on demand right so so
different models are showing up whether
in the public system the health care
system or in sort of private companies
and actually that segus nicely to a
question that we actually had somebody
ask on YouTube was you know you
mentioned that a researcher comes to the
road and they can get their samples
sequenced for around $350 I mentioned
That depends on volume or scale, but you
know, if your average person off the
street wanted to get their genome
sequenced, what would that what would
that run though?
>> Yeah. So again, so we don't sort of do
this sort of, you know, this is kind of
like the direct to consumer model,
right, of just sort of people coming and
paying for their genome to be sequenced.
That's not what we do. Uh, you know,
genomes that we sequence are usually
part again of these larger research
studies that we describe. in the
clinical world where we do clinical
whole genome sequencing. It it's like
any other clinical test. It comes from
an order from a healthcare provider. Um
so individuals can't sort of just send
us their sample and ask us to sequence
their genome. But there are companies
who will do that, right? So there's lots
now of direct to consumer companies who
offer you know the same kind of health
risks whether it's monogenic polygenic
reports back to consumers and you can
actually just go and have a company do
it and they're typically running about
$500 to start different models but yeah
>> okay question here and then we had
somebody up in the middle as well so
start with you.
>> Thank you. Hi Dr. N. I'm Yin. I'm
currently a student from HMS and I'm
aspiring founder. So I have a two-part
question. Uh first question is on the um
I want I want you to kind of walk us
through like uh uh patient process uh uh
for somebody who wants to get for
example the cardiovascular genomic risk
assessment. Uh I know we had a
breakthrough now of very fast under
4hour genome sequencing but I can't help
but to think the genome interpretation
part of it is still catching up. So
could that be a potential bottleneck in
the future of having like red red you
know readly uh write out of your genomic
assessment risks. Um so that's my first
part of question. Second is on the
genomic uh genetic privacy that you
mentioned. In the future, could there be
possibly uh this centralized model where
patient will have control of their own
genetic uh information and they have the
power to monetize it themselves rather
than having some company startup
monetizing on their data in fine prints
right when you sign up sign a paper with
them. So that's my question. Thank you.
>> Yep. Um so so on the first part I think
uh if I understand the question it was
sort of the you know even if we can
sequence the genome faster um
assessing the genomic risk is going to
be slower and that's a bottling that's
going to be true and I would say for the
most part
you know unless you're in the NICU and
some other settings we don't necessarily
need to sequence your genome in four
hours right if you're going to do a
genomic risk assessment your risk we're
talking about years of like lifetime
risk right and so you're really if that
report takes three weeks or six weeks to
get back to you. It's unlikely, you
know, a a major chronic disease will
have sort of magically shown up in that
time frame. So, I think matching the the
technology capability with the sort of
the clinical need um you know will
happen naturally and I think some things
don't need to be massively fast, some
things do. Um I think on the second
part, so the question being um you know,
do you think there's a future where
people will be able to have their genome
sequence and sort of control it or
monetize it themselves? It's an it is an
interesting idea and lots of folks have
been thinking about ways to enable that.
I think again those are going to be
companies pro somebody has to actually
create the entity that allows you to do
that right um it's not clear whether a
health care system is going to be set up
to do it insurance companies are not
necessarily going to be the ones to do
it so I think it will end up being some
version of sort of you know public
private startup or something else that
would maybe create a a model that allows
you to have your genome sequenced you
might have to pay them some nominal fee
but then I didn't really touch on it But
one of the very interesting things about
strat about calculating lifetime risk of
disease, one of the other use cases
could be um what's known as patient
stratification which essentially if you
do a if you want to do a clinical trial
today as a pharmaceutical company on a
drug that you know might avoid help you
avoid getting a cardiovascular disease.
to get the statistical power to decide
has your drug done something, you need
to enroll like tens of thousands of
people and then you got to wait for a
really long time and say, well, how many
people got a heart attack and how many
people didn't? It takes a really long
time and are massively expensive
clinical trials and then it might not
work. So, this is like the cost of
developing drugs. If you were to take a
whole bunch of people, run a really in a
really powerful risk model and say,
well, actually these are all the people
who are at like 5x risk of having a
heart attack in the next 10 years. Let's
enroll them. Then we have to we actually
have to like we can stratify, you know,
the the trial and have a much smaller
trial and have it be more powerful and
actually be able to see if there's an
effect sooner. So that's the kind of
idea of the promise of also being able
to model risk. And so there could be
models where in bio banks through this
information that people could get
identified as being important to enroll
or try to enroll in a clinical trial.
And then there are companies who've
talked about this idea of like well if
you do get you know pharmaceutical
companies will pay to have to find
people who who can be in their trial. So
there could be this idea that people
could sort of through a tokenized way
have their data available and if
somebody wants to enroll them in a trial
that they have the ability to sort of
benefit from that as well. I I would say
it's not a mature system yet though, but
people certainly have been considering
that.
>> Think we just found a new use for the
blockchain.
>> Uh, last question from the gentleman in
the middle.
>> Right. I am not a Broaddy and I'm not
living in a genomic world based on my
own scientific education, but it appears
that we're in a political environment
where public support of science is
changing or perhaps changing. Do you in
your opinion see uh private or a
commercial ground swell or investment
that might grow or to equal or overtake
that so that all these things you're
talking about that that individuals
might hope for to increase their own and
be involved in in a more fullome level
in their own medicine? Do you see there
a a possibility of uh individuals and
and the people being able to take over
and fund this so we're not relying on uh
um a changing uh public support system?
>> Yeah, that's a it's a it's a really
important question and there's no easy
answer. I think it is. So, a couple of
things have happened. I would say I
think you're right and I think certainly
us you those of us who've been working
in in this area you know we didn't
really mention it here but during the
pandemic you know the broad and broad
clin clinicals lab broad roads clinical
lab did actually do a lot of the co
testing that happened in New England
that was happening in our clinical lab
um we did 37 million tests and so we've
you know we felt like this great energy
that we were able to contribute I think
what we've seen or at least what I've
observed post pandemic because there has
been a little bit of sort of
separation in the population of people
who believe that how we as a country
handled the pandemic was completely
wrong and people who believe we did what
we could do. Um and that has sort of I
think undermined a little bit of the
belief in science in some sections of
the population. I think unfortunately it
also
sort of conflates science with public
health policy which is a totally
different field. I would not want to be
in in setting public health policy for
anybody. But um so I think that's right
there. You know I think those of us who
work in science do worry that that has
been a reality. I think
and as
you know the current um climate has
rolled out we have certainly seen
funding challenges in areas uh like NIH
and CDC and others and that's been a
concern. Um there has been groups who
have stepped up and certainly as I
mentioned earlier a lot of the projects
we do um you know they have federal
funding they have philanthropic funding
pharma um and so those other sources of
funding have certainly continue to exist
and in some cases have increased um
however you know I use the sort of the
shuttle launch and the human genome as
as examples. I think it's very unlikely
that we'll find another source as
powerful as the federal government. The
federal government is the aggregate of
all of the funds that we sort of pay
through our taxes. They have the deepest
possible pockets. No one company is
going to step up and fill that gap. And
so we do need to continue to advocate
that we as a country sort of invest in
science and I you know and we at Broad
have now a really talented sort of
government relations team. And I think
what we're finding is that, you know,
you hear a lot of stuff in the news, but
people in red states and people in blue
states get sick. They have sick
children. They have rare diseases. They
get cancer. Um, health care, everyone
feels the pain. And everyone would
prefer not to get sick, to have a better
treatment for their family if they get
sick. So there is by and large, I think,
bipartisan support for continuing to
invest as a country in science. It may
not show up on the news, but I think
what we're hearing is that there is
support for that and that people believe
that things like biioanks are important
and that there might be support across
the aisles in that. So, I think I I I'm
not a you know, I'm certainly not a
political expert and I try to avoid the
news as much as possible. Um, but I've
got to I've got to believe that the
stuff that we talked about tonight is
important to everybody regardless of
their uh political affiliation. and and
we're going to continue to look at ways
to, you know, bridge the gaps that we
think hopefully will be short-term in
any funding with these other sources to
get us to the point where we can keep
proving the benefit of what's happening
and that it actually is in all of our
benefits to to see these things through.
>> And I think that is the perfect note on
which to end the evening. Thank you to
all of you for joining us tonight. Thank
you for everybody watching online. And
thank you, Nile.