So today we're [music] going to be doing
one of two lectures on the topic of
recursion. And it's a programming
technique and a way to algorithmically
solve problems. It's not something that
it's going to come easy because it's
going to force our brain to think about
problems that we've seen in a completely
different way. I'm just warning you,
it's going to take a little bit of kind
of forgetting everything we've learned.
To help you, we will have an interactive
portion of [music] today's lecture. So,
think about whether you want to come up
on stage. You'll be forever immortalized
in on the open courseware. Um, awesome.
I love it. On the open courseware
videos.
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learn.mmit.edu.