Thanks everyone for joining us for
today's hybrid EBM seminar. Uh we're
proud to host this one uh with women
abroad as part of their women's history
month programming. Um a bit about the
EBM seminar. Uh it's an interactive
meeting that focuses on critical issues
related to uh the impact of biomedical
research. Um especially as it applies to
genomics and precision medicine.
Speakers dive into the um social
implications of their work. Who's
affected? How are they affected? and
why. The primary goal of the series is
to spark meaningful discussions and
encourage attendees to reflect on the
broader social impact of their work,
emphasizing both the ethical and
scientific importance of these
considerations. Now, for some background
on today's seminar, women's health
research and funding gaps and
opportunities. Despite comprising half
the global population, women's health
remains critically underfunded in
research and development. In 2020, only
5% of global R&D funding was dedicated
to women's health, with the vast
majority focusing on fertility and
cancers, leaving numerous other
conditions overlooked. This panel will
highlight the urgent need for a greater
investment in a broader range of health
conditions that disproportionately
impact, uniquely affect or present
differently in women including preg,
polycystic ovary syndrome,
endometriosis, menopause and
cardiovascular disease. Our panel of
researchers, clinicians, and policy
experts will discuss the implications of
this uh funding gap, the barriers to
change, and strategies to drive more
impactful
research. Uh I we'll start our session
with uh some grounding talks from our
fantastic speakers. Uh we'll follow with
a panel discussion moderated by myself
and we'll end with a um audience Q&A. So
hopefully folks can uh submit questions.
Uh if you're in this room, you can
submit them in person via the mics. If
you're joining us online, you can uh
submit them via the Q&A or chat function
on Zoom. And uh we've also created an
EBM live Slack channel for folks that
are on site but can't join us uh here
physically in this
room. It's now my uh pleasure to
introduce our wonderful panelists. Um
our first speaker is Dr. Katherine Gray.
Katherine is a phys physician scientist
with combined training in maternal fetal
medicine and clinical genetics. She is
an associate professor and director of
research and uh and division chief
maternal fetal medicine at the
University of Washington and the PI of
the Washington Pregnancy BioR
Repository, an obstatic uh bioanking
project with collection of maternal and
fetal samples and associated clinical
and demographic data throughout
pregnancy and delivery for ongoing
research efforts. work in her laboratory
focuses on translational research uh
translational research approaches to
understand adverse pregnancy outcomes in
particular preeclampsia still birth and
fetal
anomalies. Our second speaker is Dr.
Cavia Paruri. Cavia is a clinical and
research cardiologist at the Mass
General Hospital where she also serves
as clinical operations director for the
cardiovascular medicine section. Her
work focuses on utilizing genomic and
digital biomarkers to improve
cardiovascular disease risk prediction
and prevention particularly in
underrepresented groups such as women.
To this end, she has run clinical trials
examining smartphone applications,
wearable monitors, novel drug
investigation, uh novel drug
investigation and comprehensive disease
management platforms. Additionally, she
has a p she has published work to
understand sex differences in coronary
artery disease as a prognostic tool for
better predictions in
women. Uh the the paper here is um
titled using sex specific polygenic risk
to prog prognosticate coronary artery
disease in women. And our third and
final speaker is doc Dr. Irene O. Ania
um as the chief science officer of the
society of women's health research. Dr.
Irene Nin steers uh SWR's portfolio of
scientific programs to increase
awareness and investment in research on
biological sex differences and health
conditions that disproportionately or
uniquely affect women. She convenes
experts work expert working groups and
meetings to identify strategies that
address persistent gaps in women's
healthcare and research translating
recommendations to uh science-based and
p patient centered policy solutions.
Irene has led the development of white
papers, healthcare road mapaps, patient
toolkits, clinical education materials,
and calls to action for women's
cardiovascular health, autoimmune
diseases, menopause, Alzheimer's
disease, HPV, and endometriosis among
other areas. Uh, it's my great pleasure
to have our um speakers give their
grounding talks and then we'll resume
our panel discussion. Well, thanks to
all of you for joining for this
important seminar. Um I spend a lot of
time thinking about pregnancy. So I'm
going to talk about um this issue from
that lens. Um the scope of the problem
is that in the United States we have a
huge issue with maternal mortality
that's been increasing over the past two
decades. And in fact um this uh sort of
peak in maternal mortality reflecting
more than 1,200 um maternal deaths in
2021 was due to the COVID pandemic
specifically. Um but the rate even as
it's come down more to baseline after
that is unacceptably high. And what's
additionally unacceptable about this is
that there are great disparities by race
and ethnicity among populations in the
United States um with black individuals
um and also Pacific Islander um and
Hawaiian individuals having more than
twice the maternal mortality rate of um
white and Hispanic and Asian
individuals.
Um and this is not a problem we've made
impact on at all um over the past 10
years. Now there's a lot of things that
can go wrong in in pregnancy and um in
my research space I spend a lot of time
thinking about um different aspects of
this. Um during the COVID pandemic uh
our group along with Dr. Edo's group at
MGH were the first um individuals who
showed um what the response to the mRNA
vaccines were in pregnant individuals as
they were left out of all clinical
trials but then were uniquely
susceptible uh and died um from um
COVID.
Um preeacclampsia is a disorder of
hypertension and proteinura that affects
5 to 7% of all pregnancies and remains a
leading cause of maternal morbidity and
mortality. It also is a risk factor for
lifelong cardiovascular disease. We
still don't understand what causes this
and we don't have any effective
therapies at all.
Uh still birth has also been uh
increasing um in the United States and
remains a big problem worldwide with
also marked disparities between
populations. Um and we've done little to
impact um this rate as well. And also
fetal anomalies are common and um access
to genetic testing and um prenatal
diagnosis remains um difficult um and
disperate among um different populations
as well.
So um these are some things I spent a
lot of time thinking about and using
research approaches and a lot of
genetics um to be looking at this but
also integrated with a lot of clinical
information
um as well as socioeconomical
uh and other um SDO
data. Now one of the problems here has
been that there really haven't been many
physician scientists in OBGYn. Um this
great article by Jackie Param and
several other physician scientists in
OBGYn shows um the dismally low rate of
career development awards among OBGYNS
and this doesn't account for the number
per specialty in any way. So at any
given time there's only been like 10 to
20 individuals in the entire country
with career development awards just
reflecting one uh way of measuring how
many folks there are in this space.
Um, overall pregnancy research has only
had 1% of all funding going to OBGYn
departments from all of the NIH. Um, the
NICD budget that largely funds a lot of
pregnancy research doesn't even have the
name women's health or um, uh, pregnancy
in it. It's child health and
development. Um and in fact with um when
there were an ongoing restructuring
conversations around the NIH they were
proposing putting all of women's health
and pregnancy research under the
Institute of Disabilities.
Um there has been a drastic lack of
phenotyping of obstetric phenotypes even
in large cohorts that have been created.
And because of all of these challenges,
we really don't understand fundamental
biology. And this field has really
lagged um many other um fields and has
very special considerations like
gestational age dependent um factors in
biology that really need to be taken
into account and without um
obstitricians involved in this. some of
these important aspects of this work are
often forgotten.
Um in response to some of these um
threats um the women's first research
coalition was founded um through uh the
American um college of um sorry American
gynecologic and obstetric obstitrician
society um and you can go to their
website um to see um what they're
working on but they're really working
for um to advocate for increased federal
investment in women's health research
especially in OBGYn but across all um
domains as well and doing a lot of um
education at the federal
level. Um here in Washington, we have a
great team as you heard that's
collecting biopecimens across pregnancy.
We have um four physician scientists and
another excellent PhD scientist all
working together. Um and if you have any
projects that you'd like to do with us,
please feel free to reach out. Um, and
these are the funds that we've um over
time been able to piece together to do
some of our work, but it remains um
challenging. So, thank you all for your
attention. Thanks so much for that,
Katie, um, for that wonderful um,
kickoff for us. I'm going to turn the
topic a little bit towards something
that's more near and dear to my heart,
pun intended, as I'm a cardiologist at
Mass General, and I'm going to talk
about the current state of affairs in
cardiology and the risk tools and where
they fail women.
These are my disclosures related to
clinical trials unrelated to the work
that I'm going to be discussing today.
Heart disease is incredibly common in
the US and over 60 million women have at
least one heart condition currently
today. But cardiovascular disease isn't
just common, it's often deadly. This is
a plot showing deaths due to
cardiovascular disease and both men and
women over time from 1900 to 2010. And
there's a dramatic rise in deaths with a
peak of over 1 million deaths per year
in the late 1960s. And though this has
improved somewhat with better screening
and treatment, mortality remains high
through 2020. This plot still shows
mortality on the y-axis, but now we're
splitting rates to show individual
curves for women in red and men in blue.
Notably, CBD mortality in women actually
exceeds that of men from 1984 to 2012.
And worse, despite the improved trends
of the early 2000s, mortality is again
rising in both sexes. It's up almost 7%
in women over the past decade. Despite
this, less than half of women in the US
recognize that heart disease is our
number one killer. And this is despite
efforts to raise awareness such as go
red for women and women's heart health
month. When we consider heart disease
risk in women as physicians, we rely
heavily on nutritional risk factors. So
clinical conditions like high blood
pressure, cholesterol, diabetes,
obesity, and lifestyle factors like
smoking, diet, exercise, and stress. But
it's important to note that these affect
men and women differently and often
portend a worse CVD risk in women. So
for example, high blood pressure is a
leading cause of cardiovascular disease.
While women with hypertension have a
higher population adjusted
cardiovascular mortality compared to men
and they're less likely to be treated to
guideline directed blood pressure goals,
further compounding their worst
outcomes. There are also female specific
biologic risk factors that we know
propose CBD risk. These are things like
adverse pregnancy outcomes, um, PCOS,
autoimmune diseases, which often
disproportionately affect women, as well
as age of menarchy, and menopause all
play into one's cardiovascular risk. But
none of these factors in pink are
included in the clinical risk
calculators. So, you can imagine it's
unsurprising that for a man and a woman
with same age and clinical risk factors,
a woman's clinical risk score is going
to be predicted to be lower than a man,
which may not truly pretend her disease
risk. To look for novel ways to assess
risk, we look at eugenomics, and this
holds broad appeal since they're stable
from early in life. Polygenic risk
scores work to some small risk across
several different LOSI across your
entire genome. Over time, we've used
increasingly complex computational
methods to create polygenic risk scores
that have really good predictive
performance across different disease
traits, including coronary artery
disease. All this being said, the
elephant in the room is that the overall
performance in mixed sex cohorts has
been good, but this masks their
underperformance in women compared to
men. On the right are results from
apologenic risk score called GPS small,
which is one of the most computationally
advanced apologetic risk scores for CAD
to date. You can see that in this
logistic regression model for CAD, the
odds ratio per standard deviation of
prevalent CD is notably lower for women
in the bottom compared to men. And we
looked to see whether this was still
applicable in a modern US bio bank and
looked in the mast Brigham Bioank um to
see whether or not this pattern had
improved over time compared to the UK
bioank. Here we're looking at GPS mulch
and you see that the association with
CED along the Y ais um is lower in women
in red compared to men in blue. In
particular, the absolute risks were
relatively similar at the bottom 10th
decile of risk, but they are deflated
for women relative to men in the top
decile. So for the same polygenic risk
score only 17.9% of women will be
predicted to have CAT compared to almost
30% of men. This is interesting because
the distribution and GPS melt from men
versus women in the mass generank was
similar. So this is not just related to
sex participation bias alone but there
is some biologic factor that's driving
the odds ratio differences that we're
seeing in our study. We tried to address
this by looking back at larger GWA
studies that have been conducted to
identify sex stratified genes that might
be able to help mitigate some of this.
We found 10 LOSI and created a sex
differential polygenetic risk score
called PRS sex differences. And this
score represents the difference in CD
effects in women relative to men. We
applied this back to our original model
using GPS null to predict cardiovascular
disease and saw that it did improve some
of the risk association for female
participants, but it didn't fully
resolve the disparity. And
interestingly, in particular for women
under 55 years of age, it did seem to
bring the the over risk prediction to
similar to the overall cohort level. So
it might be better for early risk in
women, which is often even lower in
terms of prediction for clinical risk
calculators. Going forward, it's
important to understand the full scope
ex of sex differences in polygenic risk
as well as other conditions beyond
cardiovascular disease to look at more
sex differential variance to be able to
create better scores. The to do this we
have to understand and address the
barriers towards improved and less
biased representation of women in the
genomic studies that are underpinning
all of these studies. And to resolve the
PRS performance discrepancies, we have
to create supports for their
participation. This may be in different
things such as child care,
transportation, flexible hours, or just
being more direct about making sure that
the proportions are similar across
different bio banks. Additionally, we
have to standardize the reporting of
different studies including clinical
risk calculators and polygenic risk
scores by sex to avoid masking some of
the pulled sex disparities that could
help um reveal the full magnitude of the
disparities to date. We can't fix this
problem without addressing it head-on.
And both policy and trial setup have to
directly address these issues for us to
be able to understand the biologic
differences that are related to sex that
underpin the outcome differences that we
currently see in common diseases for
cardiovascular disease and
beyond. With that, I'll say thank you to
my collaborators.
Thank you so much, Cavia. Um both
fantastic talks. Um and now it's uh
we'll end with our fi third and final
speaker Dr. Anin.
Thank you very much for having me today.
I'm looking forward um to talking a bit
about the importance of keeping women's
health research um top of mind and the
role that scientists can play in um
advocacy and efforts towards increasing
this
funding. And so I'll start off with a
bit of a snapshot of women's women's
inclusion in in re in health research.
Within 50 years, we see this evolution
of women in clinical research that is as
early as or as recent rather as 1977
that there was an active exclusion of
women in medical research, particularly
women of childbearing years. And in the
'9s is when SWR was founded. I can
actually do my shameless plug that um
just a couple weeks ago we celebrated
our 35th anniversary as an organization
and our work really spun from coalition
building and engaging researchers in
policy and if highlighted here in red we
see um in 1993 the revitalization act
the NIH revitalization act that mandated
the inclusion of women in medical
research um and reporting sex analysis
in the data and the dissemination and so
as you can see this is about years that
it um 16 years that it took for a win.
And even if we fast forward after such a
policy was implemented, eight years
later in 2001, we see that the FDA had
to pull um 80% of the newest drugs
because they were demonstrating a lack
of understanding in their effects in
women. And we're seeing these adverse
effects which really caused um a shift
in how we approach our research and care
and pharmaceutical development when it
comes to women's health. Even another 15
years later is when we saw another major
policy that we celebrate in this space
where the NIH implemented their policy
on sex as a biological variable often
known as SABV policy which requires the
accounting for sex differences in
pre-clinical studies and vertebrae
studies particularly also in grant
funding but then also in those reports
and progress reports and that's really
important but even as was noted um in
the first talk that with the covid
vaccine In 2020, many years later, we
still saw that the vaccine when it was
released, there was not the inclusion of
pregnant and lactating populations in
those initial studies, leaving these
this demographic very vulnerable and not
having the information they need to
determine whether or not they wanted or
did not want the vaccine. And so, it's
not about I'm not here to say to take it
or not to take it, but we need to make
sure that um individuals and women are
completely informed and have the
opportunity to make those decisions. We
had a very big win last year um as far
as an executive order that President
Biden signed to advance women's health
research and a lot of federal agencies
took up this mantle and committed up to
almost about a billion dollars in
commitments to advance women's
healthcare um women's health research
and so women's health really became a
mainstream conversation but we still
have a lot of work to do and so I just
want to ask you just take two moments in
your mind and think about how much do
you think NIH funds in heart disease
disase research and I'll use that as an
example. The NIH reports funding by over
320 different categories and for heart
disease research. In 2022, it funded
over $1.7 billion. That's 4% of the NIH
budget, which is really great. But as we
know that um heart disease is a leading
cause of death in women. How much is
really being studied with respect to
women? And if you take we if you take a
look at all of the projects that are
funded over three 3,400 projects only
164 refer to sex and gender in their
titles female maternal health gender um
sex lactating pregnant these various um
uh words and combinations of these
words. And so while SABV projects have
increased in heart disease over the last
10 years, we still see um a very small
fraction of this funding going towards
the understanding of um women's health
and it's clearly not proportional to the
burden of disease in women and people of
color. And so here are some other key
women's health topics that were um named
prior that I just wanted to highlight.
as you see PCOS, endometriosis,
menopause, and to note that PCOS was
only starting to be tracked in 2022 and
in 2023 was the first year that
menopause was added to the list. And so
these are very core um topics in women's
health that have not been tracked and
have not been addressed in a in a
intentional way when it came to research
um funding and investment. And so across
the NIH portfolio, women's health in
total um still is less than 10% no
matter what area you are looking to
study. And so without this
prioritization, researchers and
healthcare providers won't realize the
needs of the vulnerable and underserved
populations. And we we see inequities
from bench to bedside. And so that's
where SWR Society for Women's Health
Research comes into play. We have a 360
approach I like to say for pi science,
policy and education. We convene
interdisciplinary networks that assess
persistent gaps and opportunities in
research barriers to clinical care. We
translate um these science and this
evidence base into advocacy efforts and
policy recommendations whether they are
regulatory or legislative. And then we
also look to address disparities for
diverse sub populations of women across
age, race, geography, and other um
diversity. Our working groups in our
task force and the individuals that we
engage um span basic clinical and public
health researchers, healthc care
providers, policy leaders, patients, and
patient advocates. And so as we as I
close out, I just wanted to mention some
space because of course there's these
gaps and the work that SWR does heavily
relies on scientific expertise that I
know is a lot of times when we talk
about policies and politics, there is
this stigma associated with them. But
while some advocacy is politically
polarized, a lot is not. In women's
healthc care, for example, in CBD,
cardiovascular disease is one of the
topics that can really escape this
pigeon hole. bone health, autoimmune
conditions, they are very um important
um health care conditions that are
appreciated um the research investment
across the aisle through in various
different groups. And so while there are
often barriers that we get from
different scientists about their
research is too complicated to explain
or there's no incentive for community
related outreach or there's little
training in science policy that there
are many ways to advocate many ways to
engage in um policy change and that
include here that I've listed whether
you're in incentivizing or participating
in research you're partnering with
community- based participatory research
efforts you're championing recruitment
and retention of um women and
underrepresented populations in clinical
studies or looking at exclusion criteria
and making sure that we're not
inadvertently excluding um various
populations of women that are needed um
to be participates in these studies.
Also, there's individual engagement that
you can have with communications with
policy makers. Institutions often
professional societies have government
relations departments. There's also um a
lot of science policy engagement now at
research conferences and then individual
comments that you can take with your
expertise and get engaged in um
providing feedback or commentary for
different um federal and um and
industrybased reviews. And so with that,
I will say thank you and turn it back
over. Thank you so much. um really
fantastic talks uh highlighting the many
ways that current funding imbalances
impact um uh healthcare outcomes for
women in re really real ways. Um I'd
like to at least um kick off our our
panel discussion um uh with a with a
question for the group. um from your
from each of your different kind of
viewpoints and lenses, what are the
primary barriers that you see uh to
securing increased funding for women's
health research? Um and how can they be
addressed at um kind of individual
research teams uh um at institutional
levels and at policy levels? Also, as a
clinician, I think that it's really
important that we address this not just
at the policy level, but at the
individual level. Um, I think
participation and incentivizing and
creating structures for all patients and
all populations to equally have
opportunities to participate in these
trials so that the results are not just
reflective of them, but that benefit
their population and others who look
like them is really important. and be
more systematic about the way that we
report the findings that we understand
who is being represented and who we
still need to be better at um recruiting
into the different trial spaces to be
able to address these gaps.
I would add to that the recognition that
women's health is not just considered
what we would say bikini medicine and
that's the areas of a woman's body that
cover that are covered by a bikini. That
is whole health. We talked about um
pregnancy is very important, menopause
is very important, menstrual health is
very important, but so is cardiovascular
disease, autoimmune conditions, bone
health, brain health, mental health, and
so and liver health. And so these are
areas that I think challenges pigeon
holing women's health into a few areas
and not recognizing that they are all
very much interconnected. And even when
you talked about pregnancy earlier as
the example, it intersected with
gestational diabetes and preeclampsy and
blood pressure and all these other
areas. And so I think that has been a
major challenge of um only looking at
pregnancy as reproductive health. I mean
women's health is reproductive health
but even reproductive health intersects
whole life and whole body health for a
woman.
I'd also add to all of those um wise
comments that um you know we um need
folks who are staying in the game in
terms of like doing research and at all
levels. So um you know if we want to
promote um individuals who are focused
on um doing work on women's health then
we need to continue to provide
opportunities for career development. um
if many of these folks are, you know,
parents and women at their early stages.
We need to support folks through many of
those critical transitions that we have.
Um many people may be aware that like
maternity supplements just went away
currently. So all of these things um
impact the work of young investigators.
Um and there um needs to be
opportunities for actually receiving
funding to do this work. Otherwise, um
it inevitably leads to sort of um you
know, being frustrated and hard to
advance the the path if there aren't
funds available that um can be used for
this work. Thanks so much. Um three
really important points about um
increasing access to being part of the
the research projects um being part of
the data that we consider as we move our
our research work forward. Um really
important point Irene about um thinking
about not just the the common things
that we think about when we as you as
you I had not heard that term before
bikini bikini health but um not just
thinking about those kind of the more
obvious and talked about pieces but
really thinking about systematically the
um how interconnected all of these
pieces are when we think about women's
health and and Katie your point about
increasing access um so important uh for
increasing access to training programs
um and and opportunities to actually
thrive in those programs once once
you're in them. Um so really really
fantastic. Thank you. Um I'd love to
transition to our next question. Um what
role do pharmaceutical companies um
government agencies and private
investigators play in shaping research
priorities and how can they be involved
in changes in research funding models?
Um I can start. Um one thing that um on
the pregnancy side that we have noticed
over time is um a lack of investment in
industry in developing um uh therapies
and doing trials on patients who are
pregnant being concerned about um it
being a vulnerable period or a critical
period as you know these um and patients
are frequently left out of clinical
trials as we have mentioned in our um
beginning of the talks. And so, um,
there needs to be, um, pathways, um, for
inclusion and, um, recognition of how
critical it is, um, to include, um, all
populations, uh, women, pregnant
individuals, um, lactating individuals
in all of these pharmaceutical and
industry sponsored trials. Otherwise, we
just don't even have the data to know
um, how to use different um, therapies
and interventions.
I agree everything with what Katie has
said and I think that again the
structural setup of the trial is
critical and if you don't have in buyin
from the sponsor whether it's pharma or
the NIH or other external sponsors
you're not going to have the ability to
help provide transportation or child
care to be able to let you know a newly
postpartum mother come in to participate
in a study and so without that
structural support they're less likely
to be willing or able um to join and
then we end up disenfranchising that
population and not being able to
understand how that biology contributes
to the overall health of populations
across lifetimes.
And to add to that, I would say that
there's a there's the ability or rather
the they need to work together in order
to make sure that innovation is scalable
and accessible at the same time. And so
there's some check checks and balances
between the pharmaceutical companies,
the federal agencies or government
agencies, the private sector to ensure
that while we are also doing our best
science and our healthcare that it's
reaching the populations that it was
designed to serve.
Thank you so much. And it takes a
different level of research to address
those those gaps as well. So it's not
just the the physiology but we have to
look at the social determinance of
health and we have to look at the
implementation science portion of the
research.
Thank you. Um really all uh really
important points about uh ways that some
of these um gaps and barriers can be
addressed. So thank you so much.
Um, I'd like to uh do one more question
here with you all and then turn it over
to the audience for for questions that
they might have. Um, what are your
thoughts on how interdisciplinary
collaboration so uh between researchers,
policy makers, and advocacy groups um
how can that help drive increased
investment in women's health research? I
can start. I I think um we leverage at
SFHR our three Ps. Patients, providers,
and policy makers. Patients being those
who are receiving care. Their patients,
but they're also caregivers. Providers
are charged to study, develop, and
dispense the care. And so that's not
just the healthcare providers, but also
researchers are in this space as far as
providing care and solutions. And then
the policy makers are really um they're
key for validating priorities and
interventions and making sure that
there's eth ethical access to care. So
these are decision makers and
influencers and the governance society.
So like our ACOGs and our NAMS and and
those other organizations. And so each
perspective is really val is like really
valuable to make sure that our solutions
are relevant in each space and they each
have something to bring to the table.
And so I'm I'm biased because I'm in
that provider group being a researcher
and I'm sure many of you guys are as
well. And the reason why I say that is
because as researchers we often wear all
three hats almost every day without
realizing it because our peer review
process makes us priority policy makers.
We are setting priorities and we're
determining what is going to be funded,
what is going to be published, what is
going to be disseminated. We're often
patients and caregivers in our own homes
and lives and then we are the
researchers at the forefront also
developing these roles. So I think when
we start to think from that empathy lens
of getting it and making sure that
internally how are we a patient and
provider policy maker and then when
we're engaging with those and
collaborating that we're also respecting
the perspectives and the value of those
perspectives and what they bring to the
table.
I agree with all those things. Thank you
for saying that so eloquently. Um I
think you know interdisciplinary can
mean a lot of different things. So I
think within science we all need each
other and each other's expertise um
coming um together across disciplines to
make um good discoveries and solutions.
Um and then um you know increasingly um
I've seen mechanisms of funding that in
that encourage or require you to both
engage um uh the patient um level
experience um diverse perspectives um
and um even policy makers as part of
your plan. So I think um opportunities
like that that are structured such that
you're thinking about all the aspects of
how to really um not only do the
scientific discovery but also implement
um it equitably across populations um
and advance policy um can really help us
drive um this work forward.
Yeah, I think both of you have really
eloquently pointed out the way that
these are all delicately interbalanced
and it can be easy to stick and think
that you only have one hat um at any
given time. But I think for all of us
who are involved in research and looking
at these different conditions that
elevating the patient experience and
bringing it really back to that so that
the policy makers can see the reason why
this is important because it's easier to
see it as a face as a person as a story
rather than a number or statistic. And
so keeping that in mind and always
putting that at the forefront so that we
are focused on not just the disease
process but the patients who are
affected by the disease to to really
improve their outcome.
Thanks so much. Um really important
points again. Um really rich uh content
from each of your different viewpoints
and experiences in and thinking about
this this complicated set of questions.
Um, I'd love to to transition now to
give the our um both online audience and
as well as the folks joining us here
today um at the Broad Institute uh to
take a pause and and answer any
questions that the the audience might
have. Hi. Uh first, thank you so much
for for giving your time to come and
talk about this. Uh my name is Ashley
Earl. I'm a research scientist here at
the Broad Institute. Um I work across a
bunch of uh problems and infectious
diseases but one of them is recurrent
urinary tract infections which of course
disproportionately affect women and um
are a societal problem. Um so I have so
many things swirling in my mind and
questions and frustrations. Frankly I'm
tempted to ask about the elephant in the
room but I'm I'm not. I'm just gonna ask
something very pragmatic. So you um you
guys talked about
um how pharmacy it sounded like the
take-home for me is is maybe not
stepping up to the plate as much as one
would like all of us would like or need.
So I'm just curious what what are there
incentives in place to
get pharmaceutical companies like
getting this important work done? I'll
stick with that question for now and
love to hear just what I don't know much
about the what's going on in pharma
around this. So I'd love to hear a
little more hopefully something hopeful.
I will say as a um as a clinical
trialist that interacts with pharma a
lot for studies and novel drug
development and being able to see the
populations that would benefit. There is
not a systematic requirement for pharma
to implement action plans to improve the
involvement of underrepresented
minorities or women or you know women
plus um across the different studies.
And if anything it can sometimes be more
of a barrier for women to participate by
forcing them to take recurrent pregnancy
tests to have them sign atistations
about contraception which are important
but it makes it more challenging. Um, I
will say some companies have stepped up
more to the plate because they're aware
of the issue and so they've offered
things like ability to do visits for
research studies at home through
companies that are newly developed that
are trying to bring this back to outside
of the healthcare setting. So, it's not
you have to drive an hour to come to
downtown Boston to do um a trial. You
can have this done in your house in
Maine instead. So, I think having that
be more systematic and I don't know if
the best way is to highlight either the
ones that are doing it really well or to
highlight the ones that are not doing it
at all. Um, name or blame um either way,
but I I agree that
the heterogeneity there um is an issue
that we still need to address better.
And on the you know it's not the fun
answer but on a practical side it's it's
um goal alignment right and benefits
alignment. So what is important to that
industry and helping them to see how
your cause can benefit them. So for
example, if there is a drug or
therapeutic for endometriosis, well then
our lead is a understanding the role for
endo, understanding how it impacts
women's health, understanding
coorbidities. And so I want you to
invest. And so that's how we can kind of
drive this investment by demonstrating
how great the need is in this population
of women. It's not necessarily what you
wish ideally to do, but when you make
that case and they see that they see
that benefit, that kind of turns their
ear because, you know, seeing that they
need to see that return on investment
and our return on investment is health
and wholeness. Katie, any additional
thoughts on that question? I don't think
I can say it any better than these folks
have. So, yeah. And I, you know, just
speaking from a personal perspective, it
um uh thinking about uh women's health,
I this has come up during um you know,
while I was pregnant with my children,
just the lack of information, concrete
information that um clinicians are able
to share with you when you ask a
question. Um I'm experiencing that now
again. um you know as I enter pmenopause
and you ask very specific questions and
it's not the fault of the clinicians
it's just that we have not invested
sufficiently to understand the
underlying biology and to be able to
provide answers that are adequate. So,
it's just it's a it's very frustrating,
but I think it is it's to the to the
point about, you know, um when you're in
these rooms, if you're in positions that
are able to advocate for some of these
changes, um uh at research institutes,
at kind of the funding level, um across
journals, what articles get published,
what type of work is uplifted? um you
know speak to that and and um really
highlight it because as we all have said
it's you know we're it's 50% of over 50%
of the population and there's such a
lack of information about um this really
large group of people's um health. So
just yeah wanted to share that that was
one of the motivations for for kind of
organizing this session um along with
these fantastic panelists but um yeah
these these these research decisions
have real impacts and um we can all
advocate for for some of this
change. Any other questions from the
audience here?
Um Lois, are you are you seeing anything
in the Zoom? Oh, sorry. Hi. Um, thank
you all for uh coming out and talking to
us. Um, my question is kind of similar,
but um, is this disparity like we've
talked a lot about the United States. Is
this disparity a global issue as well?
And if so, are there any countries that
have like a different model that seems
to be working decently well that we
could like emulate?
definitely global the gender health gap
um we see it um at SR we've done some
work with um global alliance for women's
health in the UN
um you see certain leaders on certain
topics so there is some significant
advance for example endometriosis
another um major country is Australia
that's doing a lot of work you see some
stuff with Canada um uh the UK Okay,
with menopause, they are, you know,
leading in that area for a lot of
efforts that bridge science and policy
and healthcare access. Um, but it's it's
not a a oneanddone. Um, there are some
opportunities. released the Gates
Foundation and NIH um released a a
research um opportunities and
innovations map that provided 50
distinct opportunities to address
women's health gaps um globally and
sustainably. Um so those are those are
some opportunities and areas where it
has been doing well.
Yeah, I'd echo those same sentiments. um
you know there's huge disparities in
access to obstetric care and you know
most of the still births worldwide occur
due to intraartum so during labor and
delivery um which is not the case in the
United States um but that is an access
issue access to you know obstetric care
and the ability to surgically intervene
if labor is not going well so um that's
just like one example um I'd highlight
that Australia IA has had a a nationwide
um uh program to um improve still birth
rates in the country. So they are
leading in that area. Um but again um
it's like not not one and done anywhere.
So
yeah, I would echo it's it is not
there's no perfect system. There are
some countries at least for genomics
that um Finland for example they have it
linked to their um public health system
which is when you're a closed system is
a smaller country that's relatively um
geographically localized they are better
at capturing everybody in terms of
getting some participation across the
board though it's not necessarily the
same depth of data for every single
participant in that bio bank but efforts
to do that where it's just automatic and
integrated into systems of care that
patients will be participating with
might be a good way of helping to
improve some of this. But again, as we
talked about, not everyone's able to
access care, especially in the United
States where there are pockets of um
healthcare deserts where you can't get
to essential care like cardiac
rehabilitation, post heart attack,
things that are standard of care, we
still aren't very good at delivering.
So, it just adds another layer of
complexity here in the US with the
insurance systems.
And something to consider, um, maternal
morbidity and mortality was flagged as
one of the Millennium Development Goals
through the UN, um, a number of years
ago. And so they dedicated years to
improving that and there was a lot of
strategy globally to address it. Well,
because they were addressing it well, it
was not one of the STGS per se when they
um re re-uped their goals, their
development goals. And so those numbers
started to decline. And so that's the
that demonstrates the importance of
maintaining a priority area and not just
saying we've done well for 10 years or
15 years and and not thinking about how
you really can keep it going. And so
when you focus on other things, the
things you were doing well now just take
a backseat. And so now we're seeing the
increase in the progress that was made
over the previous 15 years starting to
get lost again. Thanks so much. Um any
other questions from the audience here?
What one thing I was thinking about with
the focus that I'm hearing on inclusion
of of women in studies and in trials
and since you guys have obviously done a
lot of work relying upon these kinds of
studies I know one frustration that
we've had so I'm just going to throw it
out there and see if there's some just
ideas, you know, again I agree like this
access to um particip ipating is a
problem. I think also at least in the
studies I've been involved in usually
you have an anchor
geography and you know and and people
reach out right you it resonated so
deeply when you have people who have
these issues these illnesses and they've
got literally no place to go but they
read a little paper or they see a little
oped and they're like you know emailing
going like I'll I'm h I would love to be
in your you know your study please
please please and you're like sorry you
live you know two states way.
What is there has there been innovation
around making studies more
geographically disperse in a way that
makes it
not like a lightweight I don't even know
what I'm asking just like is there a
solution to this can we do multi-state
multiplay studies in a lightweight way
that you're aware of
I think there are opportunities in that
regard um you know in addition to
collaborations um for our there has been
I think the pandemic accelerated the
some IRB's willingness to um allow us to
do remote consent in many ways. So for
our still birth genetics study, we can
do nationwide consent in the United
States. So we can take a sample and
consent um somebody from from any area.
um we still have a gap um given our
level of funding for the project of
actually having awareness about the
study um disseminated and also um having
people understand that genetics is
important or could lead to important
information. Um but um there are
opportunities through um those types of
consenting mechanisms where we now can
enroll um more individuals.
I echo that. I think that the digital
health revolution that has really
occurred with the pandemic forcing the
hand of medicine. I mean, we rely on
pagers. We're so behind the times um has
really helped some of this. So, there
are tech companies out there that are
aiding in research. Apple, for example,
has my my data counts and my accounts.
And so these are opportunities that are
just available by letting your iPhone
send your physical activity data and
some of the health information that you
put in. And so it's very low lift that
someone can opt in for these different
studies, but making that
more widespread and pairing that not
just with here's my data, but spitting
it something back out to the patient or
to the um to people who are out there
about these are trials that you might
benefit based on the data you've given
us. So making it not just a one-way data
stream and empowering patients to then
seek out these trials that they would be
eligible and beneficial from in a
geographically localized way. So you
could send a nurse that's local to Maine
to that person if they are identified
but crucially we have to find those
right people and connect them to the
study and I think that's where some of
the gaps still exist. Thanks so much.
Really really uh great questions and
um fantastic uh responses in terms of
thinking about this from different
different perspectives. Um I think
another piece that comes up and uh I if
to decentralize the model and have it be
successful and sustainable is really um
the work of uh engaging communities,
educating communities about the
importance of being parts of these um re
uh trials and research studies and how
that can benefit them and their
communities in direct um measurable ways
I think is also really important. So
that kind of research and and um
clinical education piece um I think is
also really important. Um and we've
talked a lot about um a lot of gaps and
a lot of barriers, some opportunities
um kind of thinking about that from at
institutional levels, individual levels
and kind of u policy maker and funding
levels. I'd love to end with um thinking
about, you know, there's a lot of folks
joining us online and in this room. Um
what are ways that that folks that may
not be directly involved or empowered
positions in the kind of research
ecosystem, what are ways that um they
can advance uh work that can help close
some of the gaps that we've talked
about?
Well, I think you can always amplify
science that you know is and projects
and um uh groups that are doing this
type of of work that you want to see. Um
you know, even if you if you have
influence with like some funding, you
can always support these uh
organizations or encourage people to um
support these organizations who do have
um the ability to contribute um to them.
Um and I think that you can um encourage
you know if you're if you are in a
position where you train other
individuals that you um or and mentor
them you can um you know both educate
and um uh open doors to like these
different opportunities and also
encourage um work in this area.
100% agree with that and I think that
whatever you feel comfortable sharing of
your journey and your experiences with
research whether it's to others in your
community at your place of worship at
schools or even just talking about
things that you know your other family
members have experienced I think talking
about that and the benefits that you've
had with interacting with the system can
make a big difference more so than
hearing it from somebody like on social
media that you've never met having
someone in your own community talk about
their experience and how they felt
trusted, they felt engaged, they felt
empowered by participating makes a huge
difference in terms of the trust that we
need to build with patients and future
research participants.
I think um as you touched on social
media um it can or rather public right
and sharing it with the public we've as
scientists were trained to stay in the
journals and there is space to get
outside of the journals um particularly
on the policy end of things there's
actually a lot of um open comment
options when for example the NICD is
updating their strategic plan there's
open comments so you can give your input
and share your research and share your
expertise in that area. And you just,
you know, they have the form you can
submit online when they're doing
valuation um for different drugs or new
therapeutics that are coming out when
they're doing ratings for the US um
preventive services task force. There's
opportunities as individuals, as
researchers, to to submit comments to
help them navigate how they can do their
research and do their review processes
of different drugs and therapeutics and
um and their strategic plans. So, I
think engagement in that is is an
individual thing. You don't have to go
through an organization. You don't have
to like sign up and be this. you can
just share your expertise that you have
and the research that you've done in a
very um intentional way. Thank you so
much uh for wonderful discussion. Uh I
know I've learned a lot from uh both
your presentations and your insights uh
in our panel and um audience Q&A. I
really appreciate you all um joining us
for this important conversation. Um, as
as we mentioned, you know, I think we
all can play a role in and keeping this
conversation going and and really um uh
uplifting the need for increased uh
funding, increased um uh research agenda
focus on a lot of the complex health u
women's health um uh areas that we
talked about today. Again, a huge thank
you to our our fantastic panelists and
thank you so much for all of uh the
folks joining us today, both in person
and online. Um have a great rest of your
afternoon and uh hopefully we'll see you
at the next um EBM seminar.