today I'm going to talk about some
thoughts and considerations that I use
when doing binary classification for
disease outcomes using human biobank
data so I'm going to particularly focus
on
dementia and I have done some work using
the UK biobank which is one of many
biobanks and UK biobank has about half a
million people in it and what kinds of
data sources might you want to use to
try and predict who will be diagnosed
with dementia so there are three
specific data sets that I have used one
is a proteomic data set which comes from
blood
plasma another is a neuroimaging data
set which comes from various brain
Imaging modalities like uh MRI and
diffusion tensor Imaging and others
finally um there is a cognitive test
data set which looks at uh measures of
aect as well as things like numerical
and spatial reasoning so when you look
at complex data sources like these to
try and predict disease you also want to
use good baselines and when I say
Baseline I don't mean using logistic
regression and comparing that to a deep
learning classifier I mean Baseline sets
of features so very basic clinical and
demog graphic characteristics that you
would want to check against your more
complex harder to obtain data sources so
when we talk about
baselines that can include things like
demographics and that can include things
like
age
sex
education uh maybe ethnicity and um
apoe
genotype which is the most
well-characterized uh genetic
predisposition to Alzheimer's disease
now in addition to these very basic uh
demographic factors you might also want
to look at clinical risk factors
so that includes things like
smoking or alcohol
consumption or history of head injury
and it's good to be very comprehensive
with baselines because you want to be
very rigorous when justifying the use of
more complex and costly data sources so
these are the different features that
you might want to use to predict
dementia now let's talk about how we
actually use them so let's talk about
data
splitting so when you split a data set
to run a machine learning experiment
some people they might do something like
a random 8020 split for training and
tests or maybe a stratified 8020 split
or you might do something like 60220 for
training validation and test here is
something that I did so this is my very
bad drawing of the UK and in the UK
biobank there are all these different
assessment centers where the data in the
UK biob bank uh are collected so what I
did is I grouped them into 10
geographical
regions and I used a geographical
cross validation
procedure where one of these regions is
held out and then you train on the other
nine and then you iterate overall 10 of
these regions uh performing the same
procedure so that's how data splitting
was done and now let's talk about uh the
model briefly so I use an algorithm
called light gradient boosted machine or
light GBM and uh what's really nice
about light GBM is that it scales really
well to high-dimensional data sets with
lots of samples and lots of features and
um it's very fast in comparison to other
kinds of models like random forests or
XG boost or um even his histogram
gradient boosting classifiers and um
whenever you have a model like this you
have to optimize the hyperparameters and
so for that I used an auto machine
learning framework called
Flamel which stands for fast and
lightweight Auto Machine learning and
the the thing that Flamel takes
advantage of is that during your
training procedure it's very easy to
reduce your error when you're early in
the training procedure it becomes more
costly and timec consuming to reduce
your error when you're later in the
training procedure and so Flamel takes
advantage of this by exploiting lower
cost sets of hyperparameters earlier in
the training procedure before moving on
to more complex and costly sets of
hyperparameters in the search space
later in the training
procedure okay so we have this cross
validation procedure and we have this
modeling approach now let's talk about
metrics how do we evaluate these
models now what too many papers do is
they draw a rock
curve with the true positive rate on the
y- axis false positive rate on the xaxis
you have your chance along the diagonal
you draw a cur Cur and maybe your au
is8 to 0.9 and then you declare Victory
and you go home and one of the
take-homes of this talk is that this is
bad do not do this for multiple reasons
one reason is that when you calculate
the Au of a rock curve you are
considering decision thresholds that are
absolutely nonsensical so for example
the last point of a rock curve
corresponds to a decision threshold of
zero in this case meaning that it
predicts that everybody has dementia so
your true positive rate is going to be
one which is great but your false
positive rate is also going to be one
not great so do you really want to
consider decision thresholds that are
very far on the x-axis corresponding to
high false positive rates I wouldn't I
don't think you would either so one
thing that some that you can do is to do
a partial Au course responding to the
part of the curve that encompasses
decision thresholds that are clinically
or biologically
reasonable that's one thing you can do
that's good another thing that you can
do that's good is to actually pick a
decision threshold so when people use
packages like s kit learn the default
decision threshold is
0.5 why should we use 0.5 the answer is
you shouldn't and you should have some
kind of rational procedure for choosing
a decision threshold and there are many
different procedures that people use one
is called um the uden's J statistic
which is the binary case of a more
General metric uh called the bookmaker
informedness and it's pretty simple it's
uh the
sensitivity plus the
specificity minus one and so you ride
your rock curve and you see which
threshold correspond to the highest uden
J statistic and now you've chosen a
specific decision threshold and once you
have a specific decision threshold well
now you can draw out your confusion
Matrix with your true positives true
negatives false positives and false
negatives you have your actual cases and
controls your
predicted cases and controls positive
negative positive negative now there are
many many metrics
that are threshold based that you can
then calculate from your confusion
Matrix and one that I draw I want to
draw your attention to is
precision and precision is also known as
the positive predictive value and this
is corresponding to the true positives
divided by the predicted positives and
the reason why Precision is so important
is that in medical contexts we are
almost always dealing with highly
imbalanced data it's usually a small
minority of your data set that is part
of the positive class such you know EG
having the condition that you're trying
to predict and when you have a high
class imbalance this rock curve can be
very very misleading so I'll give you a
little worked out example let's say your
sensitivity which is also your true
positive rate is 0.9 and your
specificity is also 0. n and these are
characteristics of your model or your
test or your predictor but Precision is
also dependent on prevalence so let's
say only 5% of the people are in the
positive class so you can rewrite
precision as a function of these three
quantities and you can do it like this
so
ppv is your
sensitivity times your
prevalence divided by the same thing
sensitivity times prevalence
plus 1 minus your
specificity times 1 minus your
prevalence so if you work this out what
you end up with is uh
045 divided by
045 uh plus
0 uh
95 which is about 0.3 to so again
Precision answers the question out of
who you predict is positive who's
positive and the answer is 32% in this
particular context because of the low
prevalence which means 68% of the time
when the model predicts that somebody
has dementia they don't which is why
prevalence is so important now the last
thing I want to talk about is um one
particular summary metric that very is
very rarely reported but is a really
convenient summary of a confusion Matrix
so you can use a confusion mat Matrix to
calculate uh rates that we're all
probably pretty familiar with so when
you divide um by the actual number of
positives uh you get the true positive
rate divide by the actual number of
negatives the true negative rate so on
and so forth now when you divide by the
predicted number of positives and
negatives here again you get the
positive predicted value when you divide
the true negatives by the predicted
negatives you get the negative prediced
value when you divide the false
positives by the predicted positives you
get the false Discovery rate and when
you divide the false negatives by the
predicted negatives you get the false
Omission
rate and now there's one metric that
actually synthesizes all eight of these
metrics into one number and it's called
the Matthews correlation
coefficient and uh it's essentially the
uh positive predictive value times the
true positive
rate times the true negative
rate times the negative predictive
value square root then you subtract the
um false Discovery rate times the false
positive rate times the false negative
rate finally times the false Omission
rate and so this is just one very
convenient metric that um can and enable
researchers to more transparently report
their results in clinical machine
learning in which in those cases where
you often have a highly imbalanced data
set in which case the rock curve can be
very misleading so uh in some um use
rigorous Baseline sets of features to
try and justify the use of complex data
sources which might be very costly to um
obtain um like GBM is a scalable very
fast algorithm Auto auto machine
learning packages like Flamel can um
take the work out of optimizing
hyperparameters and um transparent
comprehensive metrics reporting is
extremely important and uh should be
done regularly often I see Precision
values that are either never reported or
they're relegated to the supplements of
papers and it's a very serious problem
and uh that's
it so ban optimization is a paradigm for
optimizing blackbox
functions so maximizing or minimizing
ing a blackbox function f now the thing
with f is U it's hidden it's latent and
we don't know the ground trth we don't
know it's analytical form and neither so
so we don't also have access to its
gradients uh the only thing we have
access to is a few very expensive
evaluations of f so another thing about
f is not only is it hidden or latent but
it's very expensive to evaluate so the
big caveat in Bay opt is that you have a
budget that you can evaluate f
only M
times and M is potentially a very small
number so uh you want to you want to you
want to optimize this blackbox function
f and the only thing you have access to
is maybe a few evaluations of f so you
have where you evaluated F and the
evaluation and this is
expensive right so one can think of this
as sort of some setting where you know f
ofx is like the free energy perturbation
of a molecule or some kind of invivo
trial outcome so something that's really
expensive and you want to get you want
to get an idea of where f is maximized
or minimized only by using this tool of
like you can only evaluate f m times and
so Bean optimization is is a is sort of
a methodology a general purpose
methodology that you can kind of use to
sort of um optimize functions F uh which
are sort of a blackbox so uh the analogy
that's actually used is um so imagine
you know this is 1800s and you're on
like a patch of finite land in Australia
and you know that there's gold in two
spots and you need to you can only like
dig M times and you need to basically
find gold or increase your probabilistic
sort of probability of finding gold so
how you're going to go about doing it
obviously randomly digging in spots not
going to be a good idea so I'm going to
just like basically cast this into like
a ond problem because I think that's the
easiest to understand um
so so imagine that this is my latent
ground
truth and I obviously don't know this
but for the purposes of
illustration and my points the two
points whose expensive evaluations have
access to kind of live here and
here so um the way the algorithm works
is that as a first step I would fit a
surrogate model a probabilistic
surrogate model to my two points and the
Paradigm that I'm going to use is a
gaussian process uh you can use other
surrogate models to kind of fit these
two points but uh I think it's going to
become clear why you actually need a
probabilistic model to fit uh these two
points so this is basically just simple
nonlinear regression setting you have
two points you have X and F ofx and just
fit a smooth function through it right
so I'm going to use a gausin process and
I'm going to fit a smooth sort of you
know curve through these two points so
I'm going to get
something like this potentially right
and I'm assuming that they're noisess
but of course these points might have
noise
so the setting is Epsilon is IID noise
and the thing with the gaussian process
so f is modeled as a gaussian process
and I'm not gonna I'm not going to talk
a lot about how to fit a gaussian
process uh but I'm going to say a little
bit about it I mean you don't actually
need to understand how aian process fit
to data to kind of understand Bean
optimization but you have great software
to fit aian process and uh the thing
about giian process say versus new
networks is that a gin process is a
probabilistic nonlinear way of fitting a
data right in a regression setting so
what you get when you fit a gin process
is not just a single function estimate
but what you get access to is actually a
whole Space of functions compatible with
the data so you actually get a
probability distribution of curves or
functions that are compatible with the
data so I'm going to just draw this band
here
which really symbolizes that there are
actually loads of functions in this in
this space that are going to be
compatible with the data and these are
you can think of these as like maybe 95%
confidence intervals right so in a gan
process just a detour uh you have a
prior which is a prior over a space of
smooth functions and now the smoothness
of the functions is controlled by the
choice of the kernel function and then
when you fit it to data so if You
observe two data points here the space
of functions collapses around the data
so then you get
functions that look like
this so they pass through the data but
they vary a lot where you don't see any
data so you see data here and you don't
see data there so the uncertainty bands
around your data obviously collapse and
then they kind of go the the uncertainty
bands kind of widen out where you don't
have data so this is a very very
actually compelling property of using
gausin processes is that they give you
this uncertainty quantification by
Design you get that for free when you
fit a gaussin process to data right so
uh so gaussin process is the surrogate
that we're going to use to model our
kind of expensive valuations but then
why do we need this probabilistic
Paradigm like what are we going to do
with the uncertainty there so that's so
now comes like the key part uh we're
going to actually use the uncertainty to
decide where to sample next right so the
next thing that we do in Bas off so the
first step is we fit a surrogate
problemistic model to your expensive
data points like here I just have two
but you can have like you know maybe
more in a real setting the next step is
you compute something called an
acquisition function right which is also
something that you compute on your
entire sort of input Space X and the
acquisition function is something that
is derived from the probability
distribution that you fit to your data
so in the most simplest setting one can
just look at the uncertainty right so
what happens to the uncertainty in the
input region after you fit your
surrogate problemistic model you can
just plot it right so uh this would look
you can just compute it and plot
it just kind of goes up here so I have
no data so the uncertainty potentially
just is very high in this region and um
the important thing is fitting a
gaussian process is actually quite
expensive so you can only do it to very
few you can only fit a GP to like very
few data points when I say few I mean
you can go up like few thousands uh
that's because the computational
complexity of fitting a function f using
a gaussian process is actually in
Cube and the memory and it's quadratic
in in the memory complexity so uh
Computing the acquisition function is
cheap fitting a gaussin process is
non-trivial that's expensive but fitting
an acquisition like I mean deriving like
writing out the uh acquisition for
computing the acquisition value across
your input spaces is is is very cheap so
that you should be able to do cheaply
and you can do it across the whole sort
of input domain so you you you kind of
derive this acquisition function so
which is like a scoring function it just
indicates to you where you're going to
sample next right so you just look at
the acquisition function this 1D case
and be like okay I mean it seems like
this is a good point because that's
where my score is maximized uh and here
the acquisition function is just a proxy
for the variance right right so assuming
like this is basically you know your the
width of your uncert it's it's appr
proxy for the width of your uncertainty
interal and then you can just say okay
this is where I'm going to like place my
next sample so this is where I'm going
to evaluate X3 right and then the
algorithm sort of proceeds so this is
basically one Loop of your Bas op
procedure and now your data set has
three evaluations
okay and as one can
imagine so I need to just replicate the
same function
okay Point here I have a point here and
then I evaluate somewhere here and then
again I sort of fit my surrogate gausian
process do my three expensive
evaluations and I get something like
this starting to get a lot better right
so this is basically a primer like a
really sort of um kind of vanilla
Bop uh application in the
one-dimensional case so you kind of do
the same thing you fit your sarate GP to
your very expensive valuations you
compute your acquisition function and
then you find out where you're going to
sample next and then you add that to
your data point and then that's how the
algorithm proceeds it kind of alternates
between these two steps um so um there's
a lot of Rich theory behind acquisition
functions right and I'm not going to
have time to kind of go into the details
of you know several of them but like one
very important Concept in choosing good
acquisition functions is this concept
called exploration exploitation
tradeoff so if you didn't have the
acquisition function and you just had
access to the surrogate model you can
say okay you know I I think one strategy
is exploit which means just sample
aggressively over the points where you
know the ground Truth uh hoping that
maybe you know you're going to uh you're
going to you're going to you're going to
uncover something or or the other
strategy just exploration is a just
sample where the uncertainty is like the
you know maximized so that's what we're
doing in this acquisition function here
which is just a proxy for the variance
around the predictions right and the
variance is basically how much the the
space of functions actually vary in that
region where you don't have the data but
a really good AC position function will
have that tradeoff so neither will it
just look at NE neither would it tell
you to just aggressively sample around a
point that you already know the ground
tooth off NE and neither would it just
tell you to just go for explore which is
just basically uh you know just sample
somewhere where you you know which is
like farthest like away from from from
any of the points that you've uncovered
so an example of an acquisition function
that's
used um looks something like this so
it's it's got this Lambda parameter that
controls this tradeoff and so all of the
acquisition functions in literature that
are actually popular have this kind of
trade-off built into them um so I'm
going to kind of like switch tones a
little bit for the last few minutes to
talk about how beijan optimization can
be used in a generative model oh two
minutes right um so so this going to be
really quick um so of course this is
just a contrived example like this is 1D
uh you can also do beian optimization in
the batch case where instead of just
sampling one point one point you're
doing like a batch of points uh but in
the case of Genera models assume you
have a generative a model for for for
for small molecules right so you have
like a vae like setup and you have a
latent
space which itself I mean it's it's
supposed to be low dimensional but let's
say it has about 10 or 15 dimensions and
you
have a
decoder and say you know what you're
actually
encoding so this is the vae sort of
autoencoder setup this is the latent
space and so each molecule that you
train with this vae setup is represented
as a compressed point in this low
dimensional space uh this low
dimensional latent space right so each
each point here represents a point in
your training data and and assume that
these are like you know small molecules
so drug modality and you only have
access to some really expensive property
like some kind of maybe a sort of free
energy
peration space using base
opt uh such that maybe you want to sort
of maximize or minimize this property
right um so you only have access these
two points you what you can do is
essentially fit a gausian process to
this High dimensional setup so this is a
1D example but you can fit a gin process
to any dimensional data and uh
essentially do the same thing so instead
of like fitting a gausin this this would
be like this would be essentially
fitting a gausin process to a high
dimensional sort of surface and then
using kind of the same Machinery here to
navigate the latent space of this
generative model to keep then coming up
with proposals that you can then decode
to get your small molecule of Interest
right so this is how um essentially Bas
opt is actually used in modern day
science a lot of the times they not it's
not just used to optimize some blackbox
function like in a in a vanilla setting
but a lot of times it's actually used
it's embedded as an auxiliary algorithm
in the latent space of generative models
to actually come up with interesting
proposals where you're kind of
maximizing or minimizing a certain
property of
Interest the the problem that we're
interested in is how do cells
compartmentalize proteins and by
compartmentalizing proteins into
different compartments and there is a
variety of these some of these are are
membrane bound like the nucleus some of
them are contained within that
compartment and and I'm going to
highlight two here this is the nucleis
I'm drawing it quite large here and then
uh you can also have compartments called
uh transcriptional condensates and both
these function and different
physiological processes so they need to
concentrate different types of molecules
um to do their function um and what we
know is that um these
compartments have different proteins
that can be concentrated in them um
there's different types of scaffolding
molecules that accumulate in there and
they're not all different so some of
them there can be an overlap between
these proteins um but we want to
understand what is the chemistry that
makes them distinct and and protein
language models have provided us the
ability to now go ahead and do this um
and the work that I'm going to describe
to you as an example of how one might so
uh we took 12
compartments um throughout the
throughout the cell uh this includes
diverse physiological processes such as
gene expression the compartmentalization
of stress uh cognition all of these
processes transcend through these
different bodies we have about 5,000 or
so protein
sequences um and we can use this
information as input um so we can we
actually what we did specifically is we
took esm2 and with esm2 we have a
representation of prot sequences that we
can generate for each and every one of
these take esm2 U this model we feed it
in our protein sequences and we get out
a a big Matrix n by 320 in this case so
n is the length of that protein sequence
and we can then sum this up and get an
embedding and this will give us a vector
that we can then go and use to uh
fine-tuned esm to to understand what is
different between all of these different
compartments so we add a couple of
additional layers onto um our
model onto this large language model and
now when we feed it an unknown protein
sequence um it will spit out the
probability of a protein being
concentrated in one of the 12
compartments that we looked at and what
we found is that uh this actually works
pretty dang well so uh for our test set
um the prediction
probabilities um
were uh we pretty accurate
um great so U that that to us is
something of uh at least we're getting
at some of the chemical information
inside of protein sequences that that
lead them to be compartmentalize in
different parts of the cell and what we
wanted to do was then go and demonstrate
this so we want to take this this
ability to uh figure out whether or not
a particular peptide is associated with
one compartment or another compartment
we wanted to use this as a tool to
actually make something that we can go
put into a cell and look at using a
fancy microscope and see if it's going
into the right compartment or the wrong
compartment or what's happening so what
we did was we
uh we took this model and by the way I I
should have said this earlier but we
decided to call it pro GPS uh sort of a
GPS for your protein um and the idea was
to take this uh Pro GPS and and think
about ways that we could take a protein
so proteins can have different sorts of
properties to it um you know one one
type of domain on a protein is a folded
domain and another is a disordered
domain or an intrinsically disordered
region and this is a structure that
doesn't really um adopt a uh a certain
one really uh highly occupied structure
so it'll sample a lot of different
states so it's very Dynamic it's
changing they're actually incredibly
useful in biology for doing an array of
different functions and um what we
wanted to do was add on a region onto a
protein sequence that then would uh
cause it to go into a specific
compartment so our first approach was uh
to use a greedy search based algorithm
to try and model this process so we uh
actually failed spectacularly with this
one um but it worked in the sense that
when we we looked at the data um the
experimental data we could actually see
the proteins were moving around so we we
tapped into some of this information
inform and uh but there there is
problems and some of the problems were
things like 13 tryptophan residues in a
row that that's bad um you you will
cause aggregation all kinds of things
like this and so we we knew we had some
of the right sauce but we weren't quite
there yet um so in our second approach
um and these are all sort of generative
strategies uh for
testing um protein codes
really uh so in our second strategy uh
we did a marov chain Monte Carlo blocked
Gibbs sampling procedure and so I'm tell
you a little bit about the energy
function that we used and and I think
that this uh this approach really
encapsulates u a variety of different
approaches for sampling chemical space
and protein sequences that isn't
critical uh for getting something to the
right place so um as a whole this looks
something like um and and this is
building really upon um the work that
Reeves and co-work workers put out um so
there's a projection term and so this
refers to the uh the ability of a
protein amino acid sequence to match a
particular backbone we have a a language
model term so what that really is is you
know is this protein sequence that we're
sampling found in nature and esm2 if
you're not familiar is uh trained on 60
million protein sequences so it learns
something about that um the other terms
in here uh convert is sort of a prior so
this is an engram version where we have
different small um small sets of amino
acids and asking how does our protein SE
sampling match that um and the and the
The Innovation here that we added in was
was two different things so um we have
Pro GPS and um this component of model
um tells us to well what we're going to
do is sample subsequences of proteins or
or sequences of proteins that are are
found in the Target compartment so we
we'll sample chemistry that you might
actually find in that specific
condensate and uh the other term that we
have here is one that enforces
disorder and the uh disorder term so
going back to this right we're we're
adding on a new domain and the sequences
we want to sample are going to be you
know disordered fractions of this or uh
dis or are these components and we want
to enforce a disorder condition so that
this this fraction of the protein has a
higher propensity to be disordered and
therefore less likely to influence the
structure of the folded domain or
influence the other properties of the
protein it's more of a sort of a tuning
of that of that protein um so when we
did this what we found was that um
depending on on how litigious you'd like
to be about this we could get between 10
and and 100% performance out a the small
subset of of sequences that we looked at
so you know we we went back to the
nucleis and and this is a a great
example it's a very large condensate and
so it it assembles material inside of it
um and it's very easy to observe so
experimentally you know most of the
sequences uh that we got into this one
um 10 out of 10 were a technical win and
that when we compared it to a control
protein all of them were doing better
than that control uh and and then we
started looking at these other smaller
bodies and what we found was actually
quite interesting um we were able to get
partitioning into these but they're not
all the same so there's something
stochastic about the way these things
assemble into different condensates and
and the material that accumulates in
them is not always going to be the same
between one compartment or another so
when we went and trained this model on
all of this data we were getting
different flavors of different condens
so we understand that uh the the
imperfections in this model in our
approach is now kind of of a
relationship about well how good is that
data how good is that the approach that
we took to experimentally build um a
model of each of these
compartments okay so you know we could
we could test these things out
experimentally um I think we learned
quite a bit about how to generate
proteins using a fine-tune model like
this and and things to consider you know
the the chemical space of proteins was
really bottlenecked in this strategy
like we were thinking about protein
sequences that are found in nature we
were thinking about um the types of
sequences that are specific to that
compartment and then we were also
thinking about protein sequences and
features that are associated with a
specific type of domain that wouldn't
alter the overall structure of that of
that protein um and if I have time the
the last thing I will I'll tell you
about is how we then took this Tool uh
Pro
GPS and and started asking questions
about well you know if you have a
protein sequence and you have its mut
form that's found in disease how are
those two things different and how is
the information content and the wild
type protein different from the
information content in the mutant
protein and can we use that to learn
something about how how nature uh
manifests information that drives the
distribution of proteins and so this is
what we did we took something like um I
I don't know we've actually ran
something like 300,000 different
proteins that are found in disease and
and or have an uncertain prediction or a
u a benign characteristic but they're
all mutated and we asked you know we
took the wild type and the mutant and we
pushed this through this algorithm um
what is the what is the distance of the
you know distribution of probabilities
for the wild type and mutant um so to
the washer distance of this and what we
found is that you know if you look at
the data for this there's there's
something of a you know a a histogram
that you could draw where there are some
that you know have a very have no effect
essentially so you're mutating some part
of the protein that doesn't change its
distribution okay I I completely buy
that this that's actually an expectation
right if you you mutate a catalytic
residue then perhaps you shouldn't alter
the distribution of protein maybe you
should but if you mutate something on
the surface or something that's
important for the the fold of a protein
and now that protein is opened up like a
a flower in the H Springtime then it's
going to be able to interact with many
different parts of the cell and so that
surface area is exposed and changes a
dist of the protein so absolutely you
know a lot of these are going to alter
the
distribution and what we found is that
uh for pathogenic mutants we could then
go and experimentally investigate these
guys and we would see really dramatic
differences between what we would find
for the wild type protein and the mutant
protein so they really are moving around
and what are the things that are
important for this um it's actually
quite incredible that you have the same
magnitude of effect coming from the
folded domain from the IDR domain so you
could have something that is just a you
know an sort of a uh a disordered um
confirmational Ensemble of states that
is a similar degree of effect that
something on the folded domain could
have um this uh this is really possible
because we were able to or all of these
you know findings were really possible
because we were able to take the data
from um many different protein sequences
and learn all of the connections between
the folded Andor disordered domains
simultaneously we weren't you know
pigeon hold into what biochemists have
been doing for uh the last 100 years or
so which is looking at individual motifs
and and pieces of proteins we can learn
all the relationships at once uh using
these Transformer models and uh I think
it's a powerful tool for now moving
forward to understand you know how can
we build small molecules and proteins um
that are are going to go to the right
place in the
cell and and help them optimize their
therapeutic activity
today I'd like to tell you a little bit
about Alpha
flow which is a deep learning method
that we've developed to try to model
protein confirmational ensembles given a
protein sequence so to set the context
you've likely all heard of alpha fold
which addresses the protein structure
prediction problem given an input
sequence it produces the most
representative output structure for that
sequence so pictorially we can think of
proteins as living in these uh in this
dual space sequence space and a
structure space and um throughout please
forgive my terrible protein
drawings and alphafold has learned a
mapping from this space to that now of
course this is a slight simplification
of reality as Henry already alluded to
in his last talk proteins do not adopt a
single structure rather an ensemble
structures depending on the binding
Partners the molecular environment the
pH the ionic strength and of course just
regular thermal fluctu that cause atoms
to constantly move and jiggle around as
an intrinsically disordered regions or
proteins so instead of a single
welldefined you know value for this
function we actually have u a
distribution of structures possibly with
multiple
modes and Alpha fold has done an
excellent job of learning a
representative structure among this
distribution so you might think of
alphafold as learning something like a
mapping from the sequence to the
expectation of the structure
conditioned on this
sequence now what we would like to do is
to learn a mapping from the sequence to
the entire distribution of structure
given sequence in a way that we can then
sample for new sequences at inference
time so this is what we want and
alphafold has not been trained or
formulated for this task so we we do in
this work is we extend Alpha fold under
a generative modeling framework called
flow matching to model these these
ensembles the flow matching is the
algorithmic framework that makes this
possible and in flow matching we have
two distributions P0 which is going to
be some noisy prior distribution for
example an easy to sample gaan in our
case it might be some you know arbitrary
defined uh distribution of unfolded
structures and then P1 is going to be
the data distribution uh that we want to
sample and um for now we're just going
to think of the space that these
distributions are over to be some ukian
space r3n where n is the number of atoms
in the protein now this is a slight
simplification of what's actually
presented in the paper but it gets the
main point
across uh and what flow matching
provides is a means to learn a Time
dependent Vector field which we're going
to call V it's a function of XT which is
going to be like intermediate values
that interpolate between the prior and
the data it's going to learn a flow over
those values that pushes the
distribution p 0 to
P1 and this gives us a j of model
because by construction we can easily
sample points from the prior and then we
learn the flow that allows us to evolve
those points to
P1 so pictorially we can draw this as
having the prior on left hand side for
example and let's say it's just some
gaan and then on the right hand side we
have P1 which is some more complicated
data
distribution um and and again this will
be our distribution of like unfolded
protein structures and this is our
distribution of folded protein
structures we want to learn a flow that
pushes uh this distribution to to that
one and in doing so it creates an
evolving set of intermediate
distributions which we'll call DT of
XT and flow matching enables us to learn
this flow uh in three steps so in the
first step we
Define a noising distribution or we
Define a way of adding noise to some
given data point X1 to get intermediate
distributions XT right so this is a
family of distributions index by time
and index by X1 such that at time equals
one this distribution is just saying
don't add any noise to X1 so it's over
here and at time T equals zero um it
adds so much noise that it's equivalent
to the prior so pictorially we can maybe
take as an example just some like linear
interpolation between a given data point
X1 and the prior p 0
and in this interpolation then the way
that you would sample XT given X1 is by
sampling the noisy point x0 and then
just linearly
interpolating uh between the
two so for example we sample some point
x0 then we interpolate to X1 and then we
choose whatever time T we're interested
in and we get XT so this is how we add
noise to the data that's what we
defined second we Define a denoising
vector
field that actually undo this process so
this denoising Vector field is a vector
field that for a given point X1 so right
now we assume we know what X1 we're
interested in it pushes
P0 to X1 and we're going to call this
denoting Vector field U of
XT given
X1 now in this linear interpolation
example um this is also very easy to
Define this is just the vector field
that says um you know whatever point I'm
currently at the direction that I should
go is in the direction of
X1 and I'm going to do so at a rate that
allows me to get to X1 in the remaining
time which is one minus
t now this is what we' defined so far
and you can sort of see maybe where this
is going we have these Vector fields
that push the prior p 0 to any
individual point xon and what flow
matching tells us is that by
marginalizing over X1 in the appropriate
fashion we can learn a vector field that
pushes p 0 to the marginal of X1 which
is
P1 and so that's the third step we're
going to learn typically and in this
case with the neural network some V of
XT given
T um and Theta this now neural network
and this is going to be the
expectation of this D noising Vector
field where this expectation is
conditioned on the clean data point
given that we are currently at the noisy
data point so uh let me just unpack this
a little bit more uh operationally so
what we do is we sample points X1 from
our data and then we add noise to those
data points by doing this interpolation
and in doing so we get to some point XT
but when we're at a particular XT there
were actually many possible clean data
points that could have gotten us there
right so here we could have done this
interpolation we could have also sampled
x0 here and X1 here and done this
interpolation and arrived at the same
point XT so in these two cases we have
two different values for this Den
noising Vector field U one pointing in
this way and one pointing this
way and now what flow matching tells us
to do is to learn the expectation over
all of these possible interpolations
that went through XT of this ding Vector
field which will generally Point
somewhere in the
middle and you know just to hopefully
make things a little bit clearer later
uh we can actually write this through a
little bit and we find that this Den
noising Vector field can be
parameterized by a den noisy model which
is just
predicting what the most likely data
point is given that we're currently at
the noisy data
point um and then we do some appropriate
transformation to incrementally step
towards that so in our protein setting
um like I said this is going to be our
um uh our distribution of unfolded
protein structures this is the
distribution folded protein structures
for some sequence of interest and what
we're what we've now defined is a way of
adding noise to these protein structures
and we want to learn given a noisy
protein structure what was the most
likely noiseless protein structure that
gave rise to that noisy protein
structure so that's where Alpha fold
comes into the
picture we're going to use Alpha fold to
parameterize this Den noising model here
and I apologize probably should use
different colored markers for this sort
thing um but flow matching tells us that
we need a neural network that predicts
the expected D noise protein structure
um and has this noisy protein structure
as input so how do we do that with a
model like Alpha fold so Alpha fold
right now is taking in the sequence as
input and the
MSA and it's roughly predicting as we
said earlier the expectation of the
structure given that
sequence and now we just need to modify
alha to also take us input the noisy
structure so that the um prediction is
now the expectation of the structure
given the sequence and the noisy
structure now how do we do this so
recall that Alpha fold has what's called
a a template track as input so you know
in addition to the sequence and the
MSA Alpha fold also accept this input um
a template protein structure which can
help it inform um its output protein
structure now typically the template
input is it's not always used because it
doesn't turn out to affect the accuracy
of the final prediction that much but in
this work we actually use this fact to
our advantage and leverage the template
input not to provide a template um but
to provide a noisy structure the noisy
structure
XT um and this provides us with a way of
training Alpha fold under this flow
matching framework so that it actually
learns to push you know a distribution
of unfolded structures to an ensemble of
folded structures rather than just a
single one and a conceptual way of
understanding why this works is that you
know in the absence of any noisy input
the the the sequence input is completely
deterministic so the output must also be
deterministic output can only ever
produce a single structure again a bit
of a simplification here but um it
produces a single structure and and so
it has to pick one that's representative
of this entire distribution
but now by having the noisy structure we
inject some stochasticity into the
system so alphafold can look at what the
current noisy structure is and observe
that it contains hints about which of
the many possible ground truth
structures this noisy structure came
from and so alfold can use that to uh
affect what the output structure is um
so it's no longer just a terministic
function of the
input um so uh in summary what we've
done is we've provided a way of making a
relatively minor change to the alfold
architecture right because template
Stacks already there the entire
architecture is unchanged the training
laws is unchanged because you know we're
still learning an expectation so um it's
still the same regression based loss
frame align Point error loss but now we
have a principal method for learning
from um protein Ensemble data right so
right now that might mean data from MD
simulations of course relative to static
protein structures we still have a
relative dirth of dynamic ensembles in
the public data set
um but hopefully as that increases in
the coming years methods like this can
help us you know better take advantage
of those data and use existing
Foundation models like alphal um to
model these more richer um output labels
um that more accurately describe the
protein
in so what we want to do here now is no
longer generate protein structures but
now we want to generate DNA sequences so
I'll just write down one um little a few
letters and we want to generate
sequences like this so now we have these
discrete objects right no longer our
continuous protein structures and we
have like a sequence of these discret
categories and the way that we'll
represent the sequence is just via um
like a sequence of simplies or What's
syesis um if we now consider or let's
assume we have only three three letters
in our DNA sequences of course we will
have four letters later on but in all my
drawings we will consider having three
letters then our sequence of simplies
would we could draw it down like this
and then say oh yeah our letter A here
is represented as this corner of the
Simplex our letter G as this corner of
the simplex and C as this corner of the
simplex and then what we want to do is
to generate like this the sequence and
then at the end we can decode this
sequence of syes into a sequence of um
nucleotides and a sequence a DNA
sequence yeah and then for this flow
matching process right Bowen told us we
need uh this prior here where was it his
P
P0 and we have our data distribution the
P1 and now I'll always only talk about a
single simple Le because then it's
easier and I need to draw this and um if
we now look at our single
Simplex then what can could our like
it's clear what our data is right for
example if single Simplex the data point
is this it's it's an a for the Simplex
then we would have this corner as our
data point on it and our uh what we
could choose as prior oh yeah as prior
is for example a uniform distribution
over all the simplex and yeah now we
want to Define our flow matching
procedure for that to generate data like
these
um this this a or these corners and of
course later on we'll Stitch all of this
together right our all of our simplies
and our neural network it will always be
one that takes all these simplies as
input then predicts an output for all
the simplexes jointly and uh it won't be
as primitive as just orienting where you
want to flow Mass on a single Simplex
but now to to see how we do this on
Simplex or how we Define our flow
matching procedure on the Simplex let's
consider again these three main
quantities that Bor wrote down here for
this conditional probability path then
this conditional flow map or this
interpolant and then this conditional
Vector field here and these three
objects are connected with each other
right you can go from the conditional
flow map to the vector field by
differentiating it and for example the
this Vector field is connected to the um
to the conditional probability path by
the continuity equation by saying that
if we have this or what is the vector
field that gives rise to this
conditional probability path yeah and
now let's just do what Bowen did here
again just with a different P1 and a
different P0 and do this what we call
the interpolant perspective where we
first Define this interpolant here and
then trivially just via
differentiation like we different iated
it and got this guy here our conditional
Vector field arises we train our neural
network to just match this conditional
Vector field and then we end up in
because we um train with many of these
x1s with many of these data points we
end up with a vector field that
approximates the
non-conditional vector field that
approximates the guy and yeah if we now
do this for simplex
let's think about what happens and I
mean it won't be the final solution
and final solution and um now we have
our data point here right let's say we
sampled a as our X1 and then we sample
somewhere on here from our uniform prior
right our
x0 and then our X1 with this linear
interpolant here here with the T going
from 0 to one it it'll be somewhere on
this line so maybe if our T is
0.5 then it will be here in the middle
XT then Bowen told us we take the
derivative of this interpolant we get
this little little Vector conditional
Vector field here we match our NE
Network against okay then this the thing
this works and this is something that we
can do but let us look at what is the
conditional probability path that arises
if we do this
procedure okay um for that we will
probably draw a few more
triangles and so let's look at the
conditional probability path at time
0.5 so conditioned on this X1
here which are the possible points from
this probability distributions condition
on this X1 what are the possible XTS
that we could have reached well and it
turns out that the possible XTS are in
this triangle
here and it's a uniform distribution
over this triangle why is that because
consider what is the furthest away point
that you could sample from your prior
your uniform prior it is somewhere down
here at this face of our simplex and
then at time 0.5 five this point would
go here and you could also have
uniformly sampled another point from the
prior right this one right
here then the point would end up here
and so on and so forth but all your
points they will end up in
here okay then why why do I
think um I didn't say it yet but this is
a problem that we have this condition
probability path that does not at all
times T like here for example the one
time
0.5 that does not at all Point times T
have full support over the the space
that we're interested in and not full
support over the entire sylex and why
does this happen here and not for bones
continuous stuff well because here we
have a compact space a bounded space and
in in Bowen scenario right you could
have always had a point that's like much
arbitrarily far away because you have
this caution and here you have a
boundary and you can't get arbit far
away so to say okay now why do I think
this this might be a problem well let's
draw another triangle we have this a lot
here today
and then um let's consider the
conditional Vector field of this
point and
this point at time
0.8 right at time 0.8 this guy's
conditional probability path will look
something like
this and this guy's conditional
probability path will look something
like
this okay and then let's draw the
conditional Vector fi that b was drawing
here right we have all these um or this
guy so we have all these interpolant
going from data to um to
our point that we condition on sorry
going from x0 to X1 so from noise to
data and then let's say this is our our
XT
here then our Vector field will be
pointing to this corner and the vector
field will always be pointing to this
corner
and of course this conditional Vector
field over here will also be pointing to
the
corner but now if your data could have
come from here or from
here then the the vector field
marginalized over these two here um or
the the change of the vector field
that's in which it's in which direction
it is pointing here it changes
discontinuously once you cross this
border here right and also in in terms
of so this Vector field is this
continuous in Space the
marginality and presumably if we want to
approximate something with new networks
then um having something like
discontinous um this probably not so
nice and we also in our experiments show
that um the where we have like a smooth
smoothly changing V field in space um
this seems to work better but now what
do we actually do and what do we do
instead of this what we call the
interpolant perspective where we first
Define an interpolant this thing here
then take the derivative and very easily
get our training part what we say is
right with this we come or we arise with
these or we obtain these conditional
probability paths that have the
nesir desirable property that it does
not have full support over the entire
Simplex so instead we say let's start by
the our flow matching procedure or flow
matching design by defining a
conditional probability path so this is
now what we want to design first and
then all the other stuff follows from
that and uh then okay what choice could
we make the choice that we make
is if this is the again the point that
we condition on then we want a sequence
of conditional probability paths that in
the beginning right it is a it should be
a uniform over the entire simplex and at
the end we want it to be a d at the um
at our data point okay and then what we
choose for this is is just a deay
distribution
where this Alpha parameter
here it's um increases or s s time in
our from goes from zero to one so s t
goes from zero to to one um or this
Alpha parameter will go from one
to essentially Infinity where Infinity
is eight because that's far enough and
then the um what the what this these
three parameters will correspond to if
up here is our data point is that here
will be um the ones for these two
corners and up here will be this Alpha
parameter and then the way this looks
like when maybe we don't all know how
this distributions look like it is just
that um if this is maybe one if this is
one then this will be the uniform
distribution and if this is two then
like a lot more mass is contracted up
here then um a lot more masses up here
than down here and it just goes on and
on like this and if you have like eight
for example is Alpha then almost all
mass is up here and almost no Mass on
here okay so now we have just written
down oh we would like a conditional
probability path like this instead of
conditional probability paths like the
red one and then we still don't have a
training procedure so to obtain this
training procedure we then now need to
instead of just taking the derivative as
we did here we need to so right we we
have a conditional Vector field defined
take the derivative sorry we have our
interpolant defined take the derivative
and get the conditional Vector field and
then we can match against this
conditional Vector field here we have
the conditional probability path and we
said it is uh connected to the
conditional Vector field via the
continuity equation so now we defined
this um this conditional probability
path PT let's write it down PT and then
the continuity equation just tells us
that it's the change in density with
respect to to time this should be the
same as the Divergence of the vector
field so it it just tells us that if we
have a point
here then the amount or the the change
of density in time should be the same as
the amount of density that basically
flows into this point and out of this
point um or the sum of that um at that
time point and at that point in space
yeah and then we go ahead solve this
continuity equation uh which there's an
interesting trick to do this where we
just look at the flux across a plane
that goes through this point because all
the um like all the density along this
plane will be is the same in this D in
this D path and we obtain this Vector
field
and that is what we match against yeah
and then to summarize we tried doing
this interpolant perspective for
defining a flow matching process on the
Simplex had some or found some issues
with doing that and then instead decided
to take this uh probability path
perspective and this then gives rise to
some complications for finding your
training Target but uh in in the case of
this simplex and theay probability path
This was um or this is possible to find
this Vector Feld and I think maybe the
this is the interesting takeaway if we
have like a um a space that for example
it's a manifold with um like a cut Locus
or some compact um some compact space
like our Simplex here for example then
it's might be interesting to take a
different perspective on Flow matching
this path probability path perspective
instead of this
interent uh thanks to the organization
for the invitation uh for me to present
a very light uh talk on how we have used
deep learning to navigate vast chemical
spaces to find novel uh Therapeutics for
a wide variety of pathologies so uh with
this I would want to
introduce um how traditional methods
have been doing Lian Discovery
campaigns and an
example um that's still widely used
certainly here at the Bro Institute
would be uh hrut screening campaigns so
this would be U System where you have a
very large chemical Library which is
stored in plates
and at the broad it's around
800,000 individual unique molecules but
has now been expounded recently to
contain over a million
molecules so what you would do is that
you would for instance in the context of
um an anti bacterial Discovery campaign
you would have in your
experiment um a vile or an in the well
you would have your bacteria here
floating around and then you're
basically going to test individually
each molecule in your hydrop screening
library for its antibacterial properties
so you're checking with the phenotypic
readout whether the
bacteria um dies or doesn't die upon
exposure of your small molecule so what
you're then trying to find is basically
if you if you would have done it in
multiple
concentrations you're checking for
molecules that are active or inactive
and um using this
procedure and now more recently in a
more automated or um using robots
version um you can actually uh
experimentally validate a large junk of
molecules but it's still limited to what
you actually have uh physically
accessible in your library which is
around the best case several hundred,
molecules so the chemical space is quite
narrow if you consider that the total
drug like chemical space has been
estimated to be 10 to to the Power 60
molecules so um another way of doing
things is going computational rather
than doing an experimental hyro screen
so what you can do um and this is with
the recent uh advancements in uh
combinatorial chemistry U mainly driven
by the Ukrainian chemical vendor enamine
is if you would have on the Shelf a
bunch of building blocks
oops building block a building block B
Building Block C and you would do an in
silico enumeration of these building
blocks to afford virtual molecules you
could end up
with in this
case most recent Library sizes are now
up to I think it's 50 billion molecules
that are so-called make on demand
molecules what's special about these
molecules is that they can be readily
synthesized in four weeks and the vendor
has a synthesis success rate of up to
80% so these molecules don't exist but
they are in cataloges that you can
access um so 50 billion
molecules acquiring all of these and
testing them individually is completely
intractable so now we need to rely on
computational models to help us um
prioritize specific molecules for
synthesis and um experimental evaluation
so
um what can we do now we can actually
use the data that you have gotten
through a high throughput screen so
again you have your
library with all your molecules and then
basically based on the experimental
phenotypic readout you can classify the
molecules or you can binarize them into
active molecules or inactive molecules
you have a very large data set like in
our case to 40,000 molecules
of actives and inactive molecules and
now you can train neural network
here which in our case was U message
passing message passing neural network
and then you can now look in this very
large chemical space of billions of
molecules using your train neural
network to find the compounds that have
the highest predicted antibacterial
score and then you could have molecules
that have a um like score of
antibacterial which can be uh low or
high and then you prioritize the
molecules that are top scoring you um
contact the exper
chemical synthesis Fender and you
prioritize those molecules for synthesis
and then you explicitly evaluate them um
in the
lab um and if you have lots of data um
and lots of molecules you can actually
deconvolute the molecules that you have
for instance in this case um you could
using a Monte Carlo research basically
find a region of the molecule that's
most contributing to the antibacterial
score and this could then be considered
something um like the explainable AI
realm so um then in this case um the
annoying thing is that even if you do
find molecules that are antibacterial in
the experiment you still don't really
know what their actual mechanism of
action is or what they're doing um
inside the cell or what protein they're
modulating so if you find a molecule
which would then be denoted as as a hit
molecule and you want to optimize the
physical chemical properties to make it
more like a preclinical drug candidate
if you do not know what protein Target
your molecule is modulating you're
basically optimizing in the dark and you
need to rely on Brute Force Medicinal
Chemistry efforts to find um a better
molecule
so um and with this I want to introduce
uh another biological system that we
have been working on in the lab recently
which would be um
so-called uh dof flatulates which are
um Marine
Plankton um so these molecules they
biosynthesize a specific
molecule um called braev Toxin and brav
toxin for the sake of time I'm not going
to explicitly draw out here it's a very
large molecule basically what it does is
that um in our neuronal
cells we
have um specific this would be the
phospho the B layer you have specific
proteins that are involved with the
management of ion flux one of these
would be the uh voltage voltage gated um
sodium Channel and braev toxin if I
didn't noce as B lies in on the inside
of this um ION channel and keeps it open
so you would basically have a net influx
of a lot of these um sodium ions inside
which would mess up the cell signaling
in the neuronal cells and can lead to
all kinds of pathologies so um what we
then did is the same thing is here we
got a library of
2.5 th000 um molecules and we have uh
individually uh in each of these Wells
we had um the neuronal cell and small
molecule and the braev Toxin and our
readout is basically um which of these
molecules rescue the um neuronal cells
from from from dying and then based on
that we can again train a neural network
and we have used the Bro 800k library in
this
case and found uh 100 molecules that had
good scores and then we've tested them
experimentally in the lab to see which
one of these um actually rescued the
cells and a nice molecule that we found
here
was if if I draw this
correctly this
molecule looks
like and what's so interesting about
this molecule is that it actually
contains this Motif
here which is nicotine
so again in the lines of explainable AI
if you think about this substructure um
and about nicotine itself that nicotine
is also
involved in
the um sodium uh ion
management also in neuronal cells and
then nicotin acetel Coolin
receptors they look like this they're
pentomic structures and basically you
have Alpha and beta subunits and
depending on the on the sto geometry you
have a different uh ISO form of the um
nicotine acetyl choline receptor and
nicotine itself lies in between an alpha
and beta subunit and then basically uh
either through agonism or antagonism you
also modulate iron flux so this could be
a potential mechanism of action um to
rescue um neuronal cells so then what
we've done is that we looked again in
the broad 800k library for molecules
that contain a nicotine substructure and
that had a high score from our neural
network and 11 of the tested molecules
all had
nanomolar potencies in rescuing um the
neuronal cells from the Marine toxin so
that doesn't mean that if you like are
exposed to shelfish sell shellfish tox
poisoning that you need to start smoking
but um it is a nice indication that this
chemotype um might be like leading to
specific mechanism of action so now that
we have
specific um protein structure in mind
the pentomic structure like there are
experimental X-ray and crym structures
of the nicotin actil cooline receptor
what we can do now is use these very
large chemical spaces and rely on a um
instead of from a Lian based discovery
campaign we can move to a
structure-based drug Discovery campaign
and basically build uh molecular docking
models of these subunits and then uh use
the uh scoring function of this
molecular docking model to navigate this
very large chemical space of billions of
molecules and in conjunction with their
neural network look for compounds that
have a good interaction energy and a
good um phenotypic learned score for
um inhibiting this toxin so what we have
done in the first step is that we looked
for molecules in this billion space that
contain the nicotine substructure and
now we've docked them against this
against this system but what we're also
trying to do is find molecules that do
not have a nicotine substructure and see
if we can find an entire new scaffold
that would also exhibit um the cell
rescue phenotype so with this I hope I
was able to convince you that there's
many ways of using machine learning to
um navigate very large chemical spaces
and um that there's multiple layers
where you can use machine learning so we
can also use Alpha folds um or the alpha
flow as was mentioned earlier to create
ensembles of these structures we can we
have also um buil neural networks that
were trained on cytotoxicity of of
normal cells um that could be an
additional filter for these billions of
molecules to enrich for molecules that
would not be cytotoxic but would still
rescue the the neuronal cells from the
Marine toxin so yeah this is a very much
ongoing project and we're very curious
to see where we end up with it thank you