I'd like to introduce you to Sam Seer
this is a picture of Sam over here Sam
lives in a a small rural area in New
Hampshire not too far from MIT and Sam's
Community has struggled economically it
hasn't really um experienced a lot of
the benefits of technological change
that places like Bangkok or or Boston
have and when Sam graduated from high
school not long thereafter he went to
work in manufacturing he's been working
in factories ever since and his job in
the factory traditionally had been to
operate a machine this is the
entry-level job for a lot of
manufacturing workers in America or or
Europe and even in in Thailand and his
role day-to-day was to load and unload
metal parts for a cutting tool
manufacturer inspect them for quality
and really make sure that if anything
broke he would get his supervisor
involved now one day Sam's bosses came
to him and told him they were going to
introduce robots robotic automation on
the factory floor and his job was going
to change and and this is a a pretty
common story for a lot of workers like
Sam and I think there are two ways he
could have thought about it one is that
this is a threat to his job this is
threatening to automate out his role
within the company that he might either
lose his job or become less important as
a machinist and the second thought was
maybe this is an opportunity actually to
take that the automation could take away
some of my tasks but allow me to move in
to a type of job that required more
skill more creativity and maybe could
earn a higher wage and this sort of
dilemma these two different directions
that Automation and new technologies can
take workers is is the subject of of my
research and the research of others at
MIT a and we think about it as kind of a
fork in the road it's a fork in the road
for people like Sam but it's also a fork
in the road for the companies that
employ them that there's a choice
between adopting technology in a way
that might increase productivity but
actually makes jobs lower quality it Des
skills them it doesn't necessarily
contribute to increased wages and we've
seen this type of commodification of
work in a lot of cases in some cases
with the introduction of computers some
cases with the introduction of new
machines that took craft out of
manufacturing that made these jobs less
skilled and you could certainly imagine
robots doing that for a worker like Sam
that his knowledge that he's acquired
from years in manufacturing isn't really
codified in the robot and he is really
just a glorified babysitter for the
robot in his role and his wages go down
and we've actually seen this in the
automotive industry in the US where
there was a really dramatic introduction
of robotic Automation in the 1980s and
1990s inspired in part by uh Toyota and
other companies but wages didn't go up
for manufacturing workers in the
automotive industry the required skills
didn't necessarily go up either so so we
didn't necessarily see we saw more of
this path of the commodification of work
in the automotive sector but there's an
alternative story and a story that I
think most of us in the room would agree
is is more desirable and it's a story in
which workers like Sam when automation's
introduced they experience more
opportunities opportunities to grow in
their jobs grow into higher skill higher
wage careers I think this is kind of the
socially desirable outcome from
Technologies like robotics or or AI so
the question is I think the question for
me at least and I hope some of you are
interested as well is how do we take
this right path versus the left path and
also is this right path both better for
workers and better for organizations or
is there some kind of trade-off so
that's been the kind of driving question
for a lot of our research um over the
past decade or so and what I think is is
interesting about this current moment is
that we we have some pretty good data on
this fork in the road when it comes to
robots we have some pretty good data
when it comes to computers and even the
internet but we don't really have much
data at all much Insight on this
Avalanche of new technological progress
in in the area of AI so I want to talk a
little bit about the lessons we can
learn from the first couple years of of
llms being on the market and also from
more narrow AI Technologies so many of
my colleagues have talked about this you
heard from Eric about kind of the the
impact of AI as a a technological system
at a society level you heard from George
and even the previous panel about how
organizations are adapting to Ai and I
want to zoom in even further on the
individual level and think about the
impact of these Technologies on workers
like Sam and I think there are kind of
three hypotheses that I want to walk
through with you the first is Will AI or
under what conditions will these
Technologies improve worker productivity
will they make workers I think about
productivity in a pretty specific way
will they allow workers to provide more
value added for the company's bottom
line per hour that they work so this
isn't just being able to do a task
faster doing that task faster needs to
translate into more value for the
company right and this isn't necessarily
a priority for Sam but it's a priority
for his employer and it might translate
into higher wages the second is what
jobs are affected all jobs aren't
necessarily going to be affected equally
they aren't by any technology so the
question is will the jobs of you know of
today what which jobs will be more
affected than others and there's some
conjecture that office jobs even higher
wage office jobs might be more affected
by AI Technologies compared to
Technologies like robots so so I want to
investigate that with you a little bit
and then finally there's this this
question of skills and training that's
come up over and over again today which
is you know what type of skills might
you need to work successfully with AI
there's this uh Trope that's gone around
with companies is that you're you're not
going to be replaced by an algorithm
you're going to be replaced by a worker
who knows how to use that algorithm
really well that the skill is really to
be a successful operator of the
technology and and I I want to push back
a little bit and question that in in the
course of uh today so so H how might we
evaluate these hypothesis what what uh
resources do we have to talk to them so
one is we have history so we have some
experience with understanding the impact
of technology on productivity uh the
second we have some original research
that comes from our surveys of workers
and our work with uh about 60 companies
tracking their um their initial
experiments with generative AI
and then also we have a lot of a legacy
of doing really interesting human AI
interactive work at at MIT um this is a
a course that I co-taught last year with
Julie Shaw on how humans interact most
successfully with automated systems so
we have a framework from the past that
was applied in uh autopilot situations
for uh in in airplanes that's been
applied to air traffic controllers um
that's been applied to uh security
agents at the airport a lot of air
airport airplane uh examples part as is
taught in Aeronautics and astronautics
at MIT but nonetheless we have a
framework for thinking about how these
might play out in the future even though
this is a new technology okay so what
makes this this new or different why
might some of these past Frameworks not
apply to the present and you know the
the really terrific introductions to the
technology from from Eric and George
were were useful if I could summarize
them in one plot the difference is
really that Technologies like you know
Sam's robots that are replacing him
they're really good at doing the same
thing over and over again so they can
load and unload a machine very
consistently and reliably as long as
they have a dedicated power source but
the role for Sam and the role for humans
is to add flexibility to robots so for
for industrial robots to be really
useful they need a human to reprogram
them to understand where in a process
they might be most effective and to
engineer around them right so that's the
role of the engineer or the really
skilled technician now as you've heard
from example after example generative AI
is very flexible it's it's almost a
uniquely flexible technology in that it
can take in all sorts of input can
provide all sorts of output answer any
type of question in different languages
but it's not very robust it might be
becoming more robust over time a lot of
these cases of robustness actually
sacrifice some flexibility so you could
see some AI technologies that are over
here but to in order to make the
technology become much more useful or
robust often times you have to rely on
human skills right so the the role of
the Human Instead of providing f ability
and problem solving in the area of an
engineer the role of the human with
generative AI is often to add a layer of
robustness to interpret what the gener
what the algorithm is giving you and
making sure that it's correct or that
it's useful and to act upon it so you
might think this this could change with
agentic a I think we should wait and see
on that so I might I might table that
for for questions um and and I think an
illustration of this which uh some of
you might be familiar with is uh the
strawberry problem that's manifested for
open AI over and over again with their
GP PT products how many of you have
heard or encountered the strawberry
problem well okay so some some people
know it um you might I don't know how
they originally discovered this because
I don't know who who asked how many RS
are there in Strawberry but nonetheless
when you ask um open when you ask chat
GPT how many RS are there in Strawberry
inevitably if you ask in a particular
way it'll get the answer wrong very
basic question and then if you ask again
in a different way it'll get it right
it'll give you inconsistent answers over
time so this is just kind of an ongoing
conversation that i' I've had about
strawberries with uh an algorithm which
you know might require additional
therapy or something to to investigate
why I had such a long conversation about
strawberries but nonetheless what I
think this this problem indicates is a
broader challenge for these sorts of
tools the broader challenge is this that
the engineers at open AI which have
built such a brilliant technology that
has so many different applications know
that this problem exists and nonetheless
they can't fix it because they don't
really know why it manifests what's
going on under the hood this is the
problem of explainability and
transparency that's come up in previous
conversations that even a simple problem
like this isn't necessarily fixable
without engineering an entirely
different model so I think for
organizations as long as you know when
these errors come up it might be okay to
use it or if these errors are low cost
but nonetheless the inability to explain
why these errors manifest and avoid them
is a consistent Challenge and that's the
challenge of robustness that that I
mentioned okay so to give a little
background on on how we tried to
understand these problems myself and and
two faculty members at MIT Kate Kellogg
and and Julie Shaw um you know we we had
all done research on automation its
impact on work in uh in in like the pre
period you know before 2021 um myself in
manufacturing Julie in in manufacturing
and Aeronautics and Kate Kellogg in
healthcare and what we decided was that
we wanted to study uh in a systematic
way the impact that these new
technologies were having on workers and
we wanted to see if a lot of our
assumptions from these other Industries
and contexts and Technologies would
apply to llm so what we did is we
started to call up companies with the
help of ILP we convened a group of about
60 uh companies to to track just how
were they using these tools what effects
were they having what trade-offs were
they seeing and then we also did some
some additional research and leaned on
the research of our colleagues um over
the past you know year or so and I think
the um lessons from this research now
almost a year and a half on are really
instructive so what I want to walk
through are Five Lessons From This
research and give you some some of the
data behind each so the first and and
these might be of no surprise to you is
that there are some use cases where
these tools are are seem to be really
effective and delivering on their
promises now there's a bigger question
of whether these use cases can
generalize to the economy as a whole but
I I'll go through a few use cases so
early on you 20 2023 so now you know
almost two years ago fully um there were
initial studies of where the these tools
could improve productivity so this on
the left is uh a study from two
economics graduate students at at MIT of
a writing tasks so essentially they had
uh one group of people who were not
professional writers uh try to write a
press release so the one group wrote it
just on their own with a little bit of
information given from uh the the
researchers and then the other group
used it with the assistance of of a chat
GPT like tool and what they found was
not only that did chat GPT made make the
right faster um they also made the the
press release higher quality when judged
by independent experts right you know
not surprising now this is one of the
earliest studies you published in
science is kind of the Baseline of what
happens to your productivity when you
use this tool the other finding that
they had which is really interesting but
has been challenged by later work is
that the the poorer writers so writers
with lower quality uh content without
Chachi PT actually saw the biggest
benefit and and they concluded that if
you were actually a lesser skilled
person in writing you could see more
benefit by using the tool and this is
different from something like robots
where robots seem to benefit higher
skilled individuals they said this this
tool looked fundamentally different and
that that study was really kind of
confirmed and expanded in in this study
which was of call center workers so this
is the first study of generative a in
the wild at a real call center facility
and what they tracked with this plot is
showing is the comparison between three
groups one group that had a kind of an
AI assistant as a the call center worker
one group that started out uh you know
that started out trained to deal with
calls without an AI assist and were
giving that AI assistant uh a little
ways in to their job and then the final
group The the blue group that did this
job always manually and what they found
they found two things that were really
interesting one was consistently the red
group the group that was trained to do
their job with the AI assistant they
learned to get to a higher level of
productivity much quicker so if you
think about this is their learning curve
uh how many calls they were able to
resolve per hour the red group gets to
this like three and a half level of
calls per hour very quickly whereas it
takes the the green group and the blue
group much longer almost double the time
to get to that level the second thing
that they learned was that there's
something fundamentally different
between getting trained with this tool
being sort of an AI native in a job
versus learning to do the job one way
learning to do the job on your own and
then having this tool introduced that
somehow there might be something that's
hard it's hard to transform how you do
your job because the group that received
the uh AI tool 5 to six months into
their job they didn't see really any
prod significant productivity benefit
right so that was a really I think
interesting Insight then the final
question that I have looking at this is
does the red line continue to go up you
know does when you have this tool can
you become far more productive than
someone who has a year of experience or
is the real benefit of using this tool
to get to this high level of
productivity and then you flatten out
and converge and it's really just a
matter of learning faster so this I
think is an interesting study that
leaves some unanswered questions but
really shows customer service and this
is consistent in our companies is a is a
real um potential use case for uh these
Technologies and and has the potential
to scale up and and improve productivity
now another one that that had brought up
earlier GitHub co-pilot um I I saw many
people in the audience have have used
this in your uh either your teams or you
have used this individually um here's
one of the first studies of uh it's a
randomized control trial of GitHub
co-pilot used at several large companies
one the the third column here is the
anonymous uh is a Anonymous financial
institution and then you have Microsoft
and Accenture now the study had a tough
time measuring productivity of software
engineering it's so what indicator do
you choose of of how software
contributes to the bottom line so they
chose three instead of just one they
chose how many uh how many uh times
people are pulling uh code requests how
many commits and how many builds and
then their measure of quality was the
success rate of those builds and what I
found really interesting was that every
time I talk to someone who's using G
GitHub co-pilot they talk about how
amazing it is how transformative so I
was expecting to see consistently
positive and really large productivity
gains across the companies but one thing
that was I found fascinating was at
Microsoft where this you know technology
was developed in Partnership they didn't
actually see a significant increase in
in builds and you know they only saw a
significant increase in in poll requests
so people were taking on more work they
weren't necessarily delivering more work
and Accenture where they did see a
significant actually a huge increase in
the uh amount of new applications they
were building they actually saw that
those builds were of a lower quality
significantly lower quality now when you
pull all these together you see what
look like productivity increases but
there's a certain trade-off and
inconsistency here so I think there's
again these are suggestions of of
positive results but we need to dig a
little bit deeper and understand why are
these results inconsistent why aren't
these companies which are using the same
tool experiencing some of the same
benefits
so that leads me to the the second big
lesson is understanding how individuals
are using these tools in different ways
and how their performance might differ
so here is some of of our original
research um you could look at the whole
paper online um and and we really tried
to understand how workers were using
these tools by asking workers themselves
so we had this great opportunity to feel
the survey of 9,000 workers across nine
different countries and to try to
understand why were some workers seeing
more benefits from these tools and why
were some workers more resistant to
these tools um and and I include in
these tools generative AI more narrow AI
applications robotics we asked about all
sorts of different Technologies and
here's a bit of what we found so overall
we asked about how workers saw the
impact of Automation and new
technologies like AI on five different
aspects of their job and I'm going to
come back to these these factors a
little bit over over again so I'll go
over them one was how does it affect
your safety and comfort at work one was
how do you think it affects fects your
pay your your just kind of your earnings
at work that we consider that an
important piece of job quality how does
it affect your Independence on the job
this is particularly important to
American workers um how does it affect
your ability to uh develop new skills
grow in your career upward mobility and
then finally and this is kind of the the
kicker for us how does it affect your
job security this was our proxy for do
you feel threatened by this technology
or does this technology not affect you
does it feel make you feel more secure
for some reason and what was really
striking that across the n countries
when we added everything up we found
significant net positives of how workers
felt about new technology that workers
were actually by and large very
optimistic about new technologies and
its impact on their work particularly
optimistic about the ability for
automation to improve their safety
improve their autonomy and even um
improve their upper Mobility their
ability like that right path show the
ability to gain new skills move into
higher wage jobs they were a little more
skeptical of its impact on job security
but really they were still more positive
than negative
right so this was I think a really
surprising finding for us that despite a
media narrative about all this negative
impact that AI uh and other Technologies
uh seem to have on work that workers
themselves when you ask them aren't
negative at all or at least a large a
majority of workers aren't negative at
all so then we wanted to dig a Little
Deeper like what's happening which
workers are positive which workers are
negative and what differentiates them so
first I want to break this down by by
country and maybe uh throw a little
shade at at the United States so workers
in uh European countries were far more
optimistic than workers in the United
States about the impact of new
technologies on their jobs very
surprising to us we did not anticipate
this at all we thought that workers in
the United States where a lot of these
Technologies were developed or being
applied early on would be given the
reputation for you know openness to new
technology and the lack of regulation of
new technology that American workers
would be very optimistic but not so
American workers were just to compare
with Germany which is kind of middle of
the pack American workers were 15
percentage points uh more pessimistic
about automation's impact on their job
security and 10 percentage points more
pessimistic about the impact of these
Technologies on their pay really
significant differences and the United
States is very much an outlier in terms
of this pessimism and then you get
places like Poland that are just
overwhelmingly positive workers in
Poland where you know there's a 40
percentage point gap between uh optimism
and pessimism so so what's going on here
we have a few hypothesis we can't say
for sure we actually have a graduate
student looking into this trying to
understand the European and American
differences at a a more granular level
but the the best we can guess is that
the job security uh Factor really is
influenced by institutions in the United
States versus other countries that
because there's not the same social
safety net for people who lose their
jobs in the United States the prospect
of being displaced by a technology might
feel much more real than let's say if
you live in France or Germany where
there are a lot more protections a lot
more job security longer tenure for jobs
so that's one explanation po potentially
for for vulnerability um but one thing
that I I want to underline is that uh of
all the studies we have of the impact of
robots and it on work suggests that
early adopters of those Technologies so
companies that adopt robots they
actually end up hiring more people and
becoming more productive so we don't
really have good evidence that this
displacement would happen at any scale
among companies that um adopt generative
AI okay so the next hypothesis that we
wanted to test here was the workers like
Sam workers in um in positions where
they are doing routine tasks that might
easily be automated we thought that they
would feel more sensitive more
vulnerable to Automation and they might
be more negative about new technologies
so we we asked them so what what types
of tasks do you do at work um kind of
what's your job like what industry are
you in and we tried to piece this apart
and what we found again was was
surprising that we thought that physical
workers so workers in you know let's say
warehouses talked about food processing
before
manufacturing with a high level of
routine tasks we thought that these
would be the most pessimistic workers
toward Automation and technological
change that actually wasn't the key
factor so yes if you have a high share
of routine tasks and you don't do much
problem solving or cognitive work um in
your job you're you're more likely to be
negative right you have a low perception
of its impact on your job security and
an even lower perception of its impact
on your pay but if you had that same set
of routine tasks but you do some problem
solving if your job is designed slightly
differently such that you are in charge
of let's say a cell of robots where you
have to make decisions about how it's
oriented then you actually become the
most optimistic type of worker so just
that change in the kind of the cognitive
side of your job flips your perception
of of technology which we found very
interesting that it's actually the the
level of your cognitive tasks level of
problem solving that you do that's much
more predictive of how you feel about
these Technologies than your level of
routineness okay and then finally you
know and if there are questions I'm
happy to go into this in more detail we
found a few other factors that seem to
be really important and I'll I'll just
mention one and one of the major factors
that comes up over and over again in
studies of human AI interaction is your
propensity to trust that we ask a
battery of questions of people about
their how much they believe others when
they tell them something before it's
proven otherwise how much they naturally
trust people we have a battery of five
questions it's now become standardized
in the research and that set of
questions how you respond to that those
questions is super predictive of how you
think about these Technologies how you
think about Ai and automation impa on
your work the more you trust the more
likely you are to think a very positive
impact of these Technologies and engage
with them perhaps unsurprising another
factor that we found interesting this is
more surprising is that the more exposed
you are to these Technologies at work so
if you've had experience with robots or
AI or generative AI the more optimistic
you are about their impact on your job
security this this might be because
you're uh a worker who's already high
performing and you're not uh not worried
about it or it could be because you've
seen the reality of how hard it is to
implement these technologies that you
really don't think it's they uh your
company's going to be successful at
displacing you so there are a few kind
of takeaways of this for for practice
that I can come back to at the end but I
think that uh really the the main
takeaway I emphasized for this paper is
job design that this difference between
whether you have a routine job with
without much cognitive work or whether
you have some cognitive work in your job
can really make a difference of how
individuals interact with this
technology okay
so the third third big Point that's come
out of our research is about the
trade-offs with generative AI I'm not
sure if the the free lunch phrase is is
uh kind of too slang but the the phrase
in economics is there's no such thing as
a free lunch and that's one big
explanation of of tradeoffs when it
comes to economic activity and with
generative AI I feel like the early
discussions have been that there's going
to be this productivity boom it's going
to be wonderful and workers can benefit
too because they um they they might be
able to move into higher wage jobs or
more jobs would be created but the
question that I ask immediately is well
what are the tradeoffs what are we
sacrificing here by uh adopting this
technology so we found a few things and
I I think this paper sums it up really
well another graduate student paper
there's I I would say um some of the
most interesting work in in this field
is coming out of young graduate students
with creative approaches to these
problems and this is from a graduate
student named a aen Tona Rogers who
worked with a materials R&D company and
he studied how this company that the job
was to discover new materials that were
commercializable how their introduction
of an AI tool to help them discover
these materials would affect their um
their productivity and ultimately how
their workers uh went about their R&D
now mind you this is a very different
case than Sam right so Sam is considered
you a lower wage worker a Frontline
worker these are PhD R&D scientists some
of you might have a similar job and what
happened and focus on the the lower left
here was he measured productivity in
three ways how many new materials did
they discover once this tool was
introduced how many patents did those
materials turn into and then finally and
I think this is the key one how many new
products actually came out of it because
patents you know not not not super
valuable always for the company in the
short term really what they wanted were
commercializable products and what they
found is this huge increase in new
materials more the 50% growth but a a
much small but still significant
increase in product prototypes so what
you can imagine here is they're finding
a lot of new materials and then it's the
job of the people to winnow them down
into product prototypes and it this
assumption that he had that this work is
really going to change as a as a
function of this AI being introduced was
validated when he asked people much like
we did in our survey how what were what
kind of tasks did you do and how did you
allocate your work between these tasks
he found that um in terms of idea
generation the workers Prett previously
had to generate a lot of ideas that was
a fundamental J part of their job as an
R&D scientists but now that the AI was
suggesting new materials they spent a
lot less of their time on idea
generation much more of their time on
exercising judgment is the material that
this algorithm suggesting is it actually
worthwhile now that that might be okay
that they're spending more time on
judgment it's contributing to
productivity maybe that's an okay shift
in their jobs but when he ask them how
did you like this shift in your job how
do you like your new job they said it
was horrible they hated it so you look
at this really extraordinary CH it's
change and satisfaction is consistently
lower they they they really don't like
their new task allocation so this is one
of the stories where there's a clear and
significant productivity boost for this
company as a result of introducing the
tool it's in an area that could be great
for society discovering new materials
perhaps for clean energy or for
improvements in manufacturing
productivity whatever it is but there's
a clear trade-off that the workers
themselves aren't really happy with it
and I know a lot of you from your
experiences could probably imagine that
this technology is going to have
difficulty scaling if this is the
reality that workers particularly
valuable workers for the company aren't
on board with it and aren't championing
it in their own domains okay so finally
you know I I I want to illustrate some
from our experience one of the things we
we found early on when we were talking
to companies about their experiments
with generative AI we would ask them
well how are you measuring success can
what does success look like can you hand
can you give us some of your indicators
and over and over again these companies
would say we have this many active users
we have this many pilot cases and that
would be their measure of success we
have 10,000 people on our platform we
have this many active users and it was
so so dissatisfying because I wanted to
know well how is that really helping you
how is that helping you do the job that
your organization is is designed to do
so over time we we wanted to get uh a
better sense of this like what what
could actually look like in practice and
and what we found is that there really
limits to this uh I would say sole focus
on on productivity use cases or doing a
task faster so I want to you know
highlight there there are a few papers
that speak to this but one that's that's
brand new that I find interesting is
this study of of medical doctors so they
gave in the study medical doctors a
series of cases uh that they had to
analyze and then they had some of the
doctors had the benefits of an AI
assistant to analyze the cases some
didn't and then they had their answers
were evaluated for their quality and
they also measured the time it took for
doctors to analyze and perhaps
unsurprising to you now the um the AI
assisted doctors actually did much
better on their diagnostic judgment they
did much better in analyzing the cases
overall but surprisingly it took them
longer it took the AI assisted doctors
longer to analyze the case perhaps
because the AI helped them question
their their initial judgment and their
gut reaction and when they deliberated
more they actually were able to provide
a much higher quality um analysis now
here if you were analyzing this in in
productivity terms this would be a
failure of generative Ai and a failure
of the process but really when it comes
to Medicine I think that's the not not
necessar what you're looking for the key
indicator wouldn't be just productivity
and speed you would actually want
quality over speed because the the error
the consequences of an error is is so
much higher than the consequences of
moving a little bit slowly okay finally
you know we talked a bit about trust and
I think trust in these systems is really
important and again one of the things we
hear from the organizations we work with
is particularly when we've been studying
workers how do I get work our workers to
adopt this technology how do I get
Workers to trust it and I think that's
the wrong question because that they're
really looking at how do you
optimize for uh how do you optimize for
user adoption that you want work to
trust the tool you want workers to use
it wherever they can because you think
this tool is going to translate into
improved performance productivity Etc
but really and what we've learned from
Aerospace and other examples is that you
need not just a blind Trust of these
tools you need to trust them when
they're appropriate now one the cases
that Eric brought up earlier which I
really like is this case is from a paper
U called the jagged Frontier and what
the authors mean by the jagged Frontier
is that there are this these use cas
cases that generative AI can do well and
there are use cases that these tools
can't do well at all and they might be
misleading so this is a case of uh boss
and Consulting Group Consultants given
two tasks one both both are typical
Consulting Group tasks and one the AI
can outperform humans and then the other
the AI can't and when they tried to
understand why did the AI assisted uh
Consultants fail in this task they
considered outside the frontier of what
AI can do they went in and they looked
at the chat logs of how these
Consultants interacted with the the
algorithm and they said well why would
they why were they led to the wrong
answer like was it the AI telling them
what was wrong and it wasn't actually
just that the the chatbot was telling
them that the the wrong answer it was
when they pushed back that chapot was so
persuasive and convincing them for the
on behalf of the wrong answer that even
these highly trained Consultants were uh
were convinced of to to move in the
wrong direction so this is kind of the
key uh I think lesson is is trust but
verify that you might want to use these
tools but maintain your skepticism of
them enough that you calibrate your
trust appropriately to what these tools
can actually be really good
at and and finally you know getting into
some of your questions and I I really
loved reading some of the questions from
the other session so if your question
wasn't answered please resubmit it um
but one of the things that that we've
learned you know now more than a year in
is that there are a lot of these really
interesting unanswered questions that
are going to motivate our research but
we're also interested to hear what
industry is is thinking about with them
so one of the big questions we wanted to
know and I think a lot of folks want to
know is that who is who are these tools
most useful for who should we be
training assuming we can't focus on and
everyone adopting them are they more
useful for novices or experts initially
we thought they might be more useful for
the lowest skilled individuals but in
software engineering in medicine and
other contexts it seems that the skill
of being able to interpret the results
that you're being given that that uh
that skill which requires expertise
which requires experience is actually
really critical so this there's no clear
answer to number one yet um does
training on generative AI help um I've
been shocked that a lot of the
organizations that are deploying this
these Technologies at scale don't
provide a lot of training at all and how
to use them and you know in one large
insurance company we study they have a
seven minute training before their
employees can get on the platform and
start using it for for whatever they'
like so my assumption has been that
training on generative AI might not be
that useful and and you saw from the
previous study that Eric spoke to as
well that workers with generative AI
weren't actually more like that much
more likely to answer correctly and when
they were steered in the wrong direction
they're actually more likely to get the
answer wrong so this is I think an open
question does training help or what
training helps might be more appropriate
and then finally and this the panel
discussed this is like we don't actually
know what the dominant models will be
the models are changing and what they're
good at changing so this idea of the
frontier use cases are actually shifting
in ways that might be unsettling to
companies that just want to lock in on a
model and have an application that they
know can work um so that I feel like is
a um I hear a lot of users of these
tools say just I just want to I just
want a dominant design and I want um I
want to know that it can work reliably
instead of the it it changing under my
feet and then finally I think that this
is a a key for for us as a university
and also for the education system in
general is you know do the skills that
we provide need to shift to support
people to thrive in a an augmented envir
enironment and my initial assumption is
is not really that this the same skills
that help people thrive in today's
Workforce are going to be by and larg
the same skills that uh help people
survive and and thrive in a a Workforce
that's augmented by AI because you still
need to understand the underlying
processes the underlying Technologies um
that this that these tools are being
plugged into in order to use them
successfully okay so I'm going to uh
given we don't have a ton of time left
I'm going to pause here and if you're
interested interested in cockpit
automation I'm happy to talk about this
more but I'm going to turn to the the
questions um starting now and I'll be
able to draw in some of the other
material so if we could now I'm
understanding what the other speakers
were saying about the clock um if we
could throw up the
questions did the St oh I see one did
the study design include workers that
have been laid off due to automation or
just the ones left on the job so as
someone who studies the prospect of
workers being laid off due to automation
there aren't that many clear cases that
you can point to um long shoreman is the
classic case Port workers in the United
States are workers that in the 1960s
there was automation introduced um at
West Coast ports and there was a huge
reduction in the workforce due to
attrition and also just because they
became far more productive what the
Union in that case did was they
negotiated that the benefits of
automation the new revenues that came in
would be shared with the workers so
these workers got laid off but they
actually got paid really well um as they
found other jobs so the the workers did
the study design included workers you
know people in the workforce um but I
actually don't think it would be that
much different if we included people who
identified as being displaced by
automation other
questions practical approaches to
training individuals um enhances their
performance rather than simply relying
on AI as a
tool I think so so I've seen a few
approaches so I I don't um again the
training point I haven't seen a lot of
good models of of training so we we have
a partnership with Google there the
google.org funded our uh has sponsored
our our working group and they have this
interesting approach where they have a a
series of online courses some are the
more advanced in data science and
they're going to do another more
advanced course in in AI related
Technologies then they have this AI
Essentials course which is really to
understand I think Eric actually could
have taught the a Essentials course with
his um lecture earlier but it's it's a
series of uh interactive steps to get
the the basics of what these tools can
do where you should be skeptical of them
and to help calibrate that trust which I
think Could Be an Effective training
tool but it's not really AI skills like
no one's going to be able to um you know
work with uh work with open ai's API
after that no one's going to be able to
help develop or or you know um you know
fiddle fiddle with the weights in a
model so it's not um it's not Advanced
but it does seem to be useful and again
I've been struck by how little training
or organizations even organizations
using these tools successfully have done
for their
workers are these studies inclusive of
agentic tools uh no partly because none
of the companies have really used those
tools successfully yet that we've been
studying um I think the the maybe you
could feel this as an undercurrent you
know we're studying some very Advanced
companies uh technologically we're
studying some very big you know kind of
Fortune 100 type companies and it's it's
not had these tools have not reached
significant scale in these companies um
to have much of an impact yet even even
a year on so the what we're seeing on
the ground is is hugely different than
the hype that we're seeing around kind
of the the breathless uh discussions of
agentic tools and AGI it's just not the
reality for the companies that we've
studied I feel a bit ashamed we had so
many questions for the earlier folks
how would the AI Evolution reshape the
education landscape what would it look
like and consequently how would this
impact on
employment so I I I feel like I'm going
to be hesitant to speculate but I can
talk about what I've heard um some
colleagues discuss and and I know you
know Eric might have other uh
perspectives he works with folks in
computer science and artificial
intelligence laboratory I think the
question is really acute in uh computer
science Fields where I think there are
early indications that what it means to
be an entry-level programmer in a lot of
large software organizations is very
different so traditionally when a school
like MIT would train a software engineer
to not only take an entry-level job but
to move up to a leadership role where
you really had to understand the
architecture of a system you had to make
leadership decisions you had to
understand kind of the overarching
technical landscape now a software
engineer might be lower paid and also
require less skill so the question I
think from schools like mits do we
really still want to uh educate our
students to go into that entry level
role or are we going to educate them for
for leadership and understand that that
entry level role might change but still
be a step along the way so I think
that's an an ongoing conversation that
as entry level jobs change or at the
skills required to do these jobs change
the educa the the curriculum to train
students to go into these entry level
roles will also have to change
okay in the absence of of more questions
I'm going to go into just a a final
let's say Parable to to leave you with
so I'm going to only talk about one of
these but on on the left you know I'm
from Chicago oh they didn't even pull it
up okay there we go you know I'm from
Chicago and and one of the things that
Chicago is known for is a particular
type particular hot dog company I don't
know if any of you have been to Chicago
it's a wonderful place I would really
recommend it um and and we these uh
Vienna beef hot dogs that are are known
for their red color I don't know why
they're called Vienna Beef you'd think
that that would come from Vienna and not
Chicago but nonetheless we we we known
for producing this hot dog uh and given
that you talked about food processing
before um the factory that produced this
hot dog for the longest time um was in
the city and it was one of those older
factories where the equipment was from
another generation but it was produced
in this particular way that people
really loved it they loved it at
baseball games and and it sold really
well and one of the things that the
Vienna beef hot dog company did was they
realized that they the times were
changing and they wanted to automate
their processes partly because of
increased standards in the food industry
so they brought in automated material
movement they brought in robotic
Automation and they they created a whole
new facility that was very kind of clean
you could imagine stainless steel
everything and they they started
producing hot dogs in the new facility
and the hot dogs looked totally
different they didn't have this kind of
red shiny color they were gray they
didn't taste the same and what they
found was that they introduced
Automation and something went wrong in
their process something broke down even
though they thought they had replicated
everything step by step and when they
went back and they tried to do a root
cause analysis said why did this
automation kind of lead us to such poor
quality they found that what they hadn't
realized as part of their process was
that being slow at moving the hot dogs
from the station where they were cased
to the station where they were smoked it
used to be a guy named Irving who would
push the cart and he'd talk to people
and he moved nice and slow and it it
took a long time for the process to
happen but once the hot dogs got into
the smoker they had sufficiently thought
that they were at the temperature to
produce this red color to produce the
taste that it was actually the slowness
of the process and Irving's maybe you
know uh lazy ways that helped them do
the very thing that they had become so
good at and once the automated system
cut this time of the process in half and
just dunk the hot dogs right in the
smoker they had lost what made them
special in the first place so I think
this is I I think of this this real
story as a parable for what many
organizations are doing now with uh with
AI tools that they're they're in this
desire for Speed in some cases losing
what brings their business value in the
first place and loses what makes their
workers and their skills so valuable as
well so I think understanding kind of
the core processes the core technologies
that makes organizations great is
important far before you figure out what
technologies might be helpful for those
organiz ation so thank you so much for
your time happy to talk more and and
really appreciate you
[Applause]
coming thank you very much Ben