Hello. Um, I'm Ricard and I will speak
to you how actions speak louder than
words and why that's
important. But first, let's look at some
examples of this. Did you know that the
time you spend in the restroom predicts
better when you'll quit your job than
your own estimations?
Your grocery uh basket predicts better
who you'll vote for than your Instagram
or social media posts. What you say you
spend your money on predicts very poorly
how you end up spending your
money. But before we go into actions,
let us talk about the biggest hype right
now. Large language models. So how does
uh large language models view language?
Well, they take a ton of text from the
internet. They look at these as a
sequence of words and try to predict the
next word or token based on previous
words or token. Right? This is a gist of
lams. But we can look at behavior in a
similar way. We do actions in the real
world. We can sort them chronologically
and try to predict the next action based
on previous actions based on data from
the real world. So what are the
implications of this?
Well, if you take a um foundation model
like an LM or a vision model is trained
on the internet, it typically
understands meaning and similarity and
relatedness based on features. So we
tell you in a product setting that
lactosefree milk and regular milk are
similar and related and close because
they have similar features. But if you
instead look at the behavioral
dimensions and how people act on these
products, you will see that actually
lactoseree milk and regular milk are
very far apart because they're not
bought together. Instead, it might be
that lactosefree milk and gluten-free
bread are more related and close. So you
need to let users through their behavior
define meaning.
So we've been obsessing about behavioral
intelligence and data for the last five
years and it's definitely a spectrum of
the predictiveness and use in usefulness
of this data. So on the extreme le left
on noisy data you have what people say
they want and will do. But as you look
at how people spend their time and how
they invest their money that becomes
more and more
predictive. So basically LMS are trained
on the internet which definitely exists
in this space of what people say they
want and will do which creates not very
predictive models in the real world and
they suffer from hallucinations etc. So
what we do is that we train large
behavioral models directly in this
action space from the real world which
gets which gives much more robust and
predictive
models and this also why we're seeing
that actually LMS are not
revolutionizing behavd driven businesses
an example of behavior-driven businesses
are retailers and payment companies
right but the core of retail is not
textbased intelligence from the internet
the core of retail scale is transactions
and consumption and that's
behavior. What we see is that a lot of
our clients more than 99% of their data
is transactional and behavioral and they
need to be able to leverage that fully
to really build competitive
advantage and that's what we've done
with behavior GPT. It's a behavior to
behavior foundation model that generates
human actions and wants. It's been
trained on over one trillion human
actions and it cost over $5 million just
to train and it's now out competing LMS
as the model of choice for
behavior-driven companies in retail and
payments. It's the chat GPT moment for
behavior-driven businesses.
So some more examples right here we have
a recommendation engine on the left side
we have a model that's pre on the
internet it gives you know
recommendations of similar motives to
this Clint Eastwood uh movie poster and
it gives black and white photos and
motives from old movies. They're all
happen to be from romantic movies but
this is reasonable results but they're
also incorrect. If you look at the
behavioral perspective, you see that
people are here are actually looking for
masculine movie stars from that era and
you could really get that right which
drives sales and gives happier
users. Uh similarly if you look for
example of you know human experts trying
to understand what language to describe
products and motives with to engage
users. Here we have a uh swans, sunset
etc. And the human experts put these
labels and keywords. They put nature,
forest, woodlands, all reasonable, but
they're missing the most important one,
which is sunset, which you can get by
looking at actual customer behavior and
let them define meaning for
you. What we see is that we're able on
average to increase sales with 20% on
existing solutions at these companies.
And we do this with 15 times fewer
people. But we're also allowing to build
completely new revenue streams that they
thought were impossible before. And
we're no longer being benchmarked
against existing solutions. The only
thing they think have the ability to
beat us are LMS and agents, but they
don't stand a
chance. So if you are a behavior driven
company, for example, in retail and
payments, then we're very excited to
talk to you. Thank you so much.
Thank you, Ricard.