as an engineer I want to generate a
positive impact in
[Music]
society the impact that I expect my
research to have is to contribute to the
fight against climate change and
accomplish significant reductions of the
concentrations of CO2 in the atmosphere
my research is pretty much a fight
against climate change what we're doing
is we're using biocatalysis we're which
is we're using an enzyme something that
allows us to trans form carbon dioxide
in flu gases into something useful which
in this case is calcium carbonate and so
what we're doing is designing a process
that's able to transform that CO2 and
flu gases into something we can use for
something else like cement production
for example one of the greatest
challenges of our civilization is to try
to keep global warming under 1.5 celsi
deges right but the problem with that is
that current CO2 capturing technology is
very inefficient so climate change is a
complex issue and this is this just adds
like one more piece to the Mosaic of
solutions that we need
[Music]