ocw is definitely something which I
would identify as like an extra work
which I had taken for myself because I
want to think differently I want I I
always sort of had this um repulsion
against group thing repulsion are very
quite strong words so I'll just say very
very cautious probably because I follow
the market every day and I Tred to be
very very cautious about group think
well how can I think different how can I
think logically
[Music]
welcome to open Learners a podcast that
tells the stories of Learners all over
the world who use mit's open courseware
I'm Emmanuel Li kasigi an open learner
myself from campala Uganda in East
Africa and I'm Michael Jordan pilra an
open learner from Memphis
Tennessee we're back episode two Michael
hey Emanuel uh do you want to introduce
today's open lner today we will hear
from J mean Hong an open learner
currently living in Soul South Korea I
met J mean about two years ago after my
MIT news article came out she reached
out to me via LinkedIn and I got on a
zoom call with her for about an hour
while she was studying at the University
of Wisconsin well for me this interview
was the first time I met J me face to
face but we're actually in the same AI
study group on ledin which is
interesting so it was really cool for
both of us to put faces to our names
that's awesome Emanuel I know you
started the AI learning group on
LinkedIn and you were really excited to
start building a community of AI
Learners all over the world one reason
we really wanted to interview jam mean
for open Learners was because her
educational path is so unique one she
started her open course s Journey as an
undergrad student with a course in
thermodynamics to supplement her dual
degree program in chemistry and finance
and two Jam has lived and learned all
over the world she left Korea at 14 to
attend high school in New Zealand and
she attended the University of Wisconsin
for a year in the middle of the pandemic
before returning to Korea to finish her
economic degree that's really cool Jam
is really he a really driven person
because most people don't usually start
these paths during their underground but
she did and she shared with us her
perspective on how education defers
around the world her ocw gave her new
ways of thinking about herself and her
career path which is really interesting
and I'm excited to hear all about that
so let's get to it here is our
conversation with Jam Hong of Soul South
Korea
[Music]
hi my name is Jamon Hong and I'm a final
year economics student studying um at
yon University and I was born and raised
in Korea for the most part of my life
but I also had some very exciting
Journeys in America and New Zealand late
2022 so I finished the first semester of
my sophomore year but then that was
still when covid was still around and
all the campus lectures they were all
shut down so all the classes were done
online but then as a very social and
active human interaction driven person I
wanted to go out there but there was no
chance of having any campus lectur so I
went to
America I went to America where inperson
lectures were um permitted and I went to
W Madison and then this was the time
when I was trying to explore more
subjects and yeah really establish my
perspective of the world and how I would
like to apply this this the knowledge
that I really wanted to learn while
while I was at University I was studying
chemistry when I was at W Madison which
is up north very very cold but I studied
chemistry Finance data science and
computer science all sorts of subjects
there but chemistry was very exciting
but challenging so I was sort of trying
to seek out and gather around more
information so that I can improve my
understanding and I and then I came
across
mitw videos and then the first course
that I took was called thermodynamics
and kinetics and this was the most
difficult subject within chemistry but I
loved it how was it like like first of
all meeting all these online resources
maybe compared to your former education
experiences from New Zealand from South
Korea how was the difference when you
finally met ocw and MIT and uh how is it
for you
personally well I think the major
difference was about flexibility because
when you're taking a lecture and you're
in a lecture hall filled with 300
different students you cannot just sort
of actively try to find out information
or like areas of interest you can you
can't directly ask the professor but
then or
rewind it's a bit difficult to do that
and so because I'm I'm quite a proactive
learner and so I want to find out more
information for myself but with a more
structured learning program that is more
conventionally offered at universities
was quite difficult to do and so with
MIT ocw I was able to sometimes pick out
topics that that Drew me the most and
that was entropy for me thermodynamics
and then I wanted to learn more about
that instead of you know just trying to
rely on very structured course learning
at um conventional you know traditional
University Systems Mark Twain once
famously said that I never let my school
institutional learning interfere with my
education and that is the sort of phrase
that swept me away at that time this is
education like this is what learning
actually means I was going to ask a
quick question here when you have this
breakthrough moment when you start
actually learning from open educ
materials and not you know waiting for a
teacher to prod you like what did it
change in your life the first change is
that okay like I'm actually learning
this so in terms of the finance Theory
which I know you also took as part of
your MIT ocw Journey when I was taking
the finance Theory course taught by
Professor Andrew low I was taking a more
or less equivalent course at W Madison
it was called money and Market we were
learning about the impact of monetary
policies conducted by Federal Reserve
but then what was really interesting was
that in this course Finance the the MIT
ocw course this was actually filmed when
G um when GFC the global financial
crisis was happening and so it was more
like I'm actually learning about these
theories but I'm actually also seeing
how these theories were like happening
in real life and how they actually apply
to R scenarios like fixed income
security products went a bit too complex
and the leverage ratio went a bit crazy
these were the sort of knowledge that I
was learning theoretically at University
and sure I was like watching videos and
learning theoretically but then actually
I was able to see the real impact of it
like through the video that was actually
recorded at the time of GFC and so it
was more like a reward for my proactive
learning because it was genuinely quite
interesting and yeah I was able to draw
parallels in many different angles and
it was yeah it make my life more
fun I like when you mentioned it was
like in real time I experienced that CU
I took the computer science courses 61
and 62 and also what stood out for me
was the time they recorded those was the
time I was in university so it was like
I was in
learning some other things and these
people are learning like these things
like we on the same timeline if I'm
remember to meet those people in the
class in the real world like oh we're in
University at the same time but it felt
like we're learning like two different
things yes you're both learning computer
science related things but it's like a
different difference so I understand you
on that you mentioned something about
you know the need to find people moving
the US and finding
ocw was the impact more in like you and
yourself and identity as a person when
you start taking ocw you mention you've
taken Finance Theory thermodynamics how
was the impact in your evolving identity
how did you start to see yourself as a
person who now has all this knowledge
did it have any real life applications
or any real life effects or impact when
you studying these
things maybe you could shed some light
on that yeah that's such an excellent
question because I genuinely feel that
I'm more like an
Explorer I'm never satisfied with just
like one path I have to just like look
around and they okay like this is some
this is something else which I can
integrate with this past or this might
be some other Branch from this past with
which I'm trotting upon while I was
listening to your question I actually
had something that I wanted to ask you
Emanual if that's right you said that
you were taking the ocw courses while
you were at University am I correct no I
I took
them I took them in 2020
2021 but the courses were recorded in
2020 is it 2013 2011 2013 and that was
the time I was in university so they
recorded their courses while I was also
in University I watched them like way
later right that's so cool so I was
wondering what your major was and like
what your favorite course of ocw was and
like how you came came across ocw like
basically like your story too I was
actually about to ask you the same
question about how you came across ocw
so I like this um my major was also
actually in computer science but
Information Systems it was a new course
in the country I think they only did
like three years of it then they
absorbed it back into the information
technology course so I've been in this
computer science world for a while
started out front end didn't like it I
went to more graphics design so I
discovered ocw in lockdown when I wanted
now to learn backend I went to Dubai and
saw they had a World Expo so most of the
Pavilions most of the countries were
showcasing things to do with ai ai so I
was I realized this is the future it's
coming this was like in 2020 so when I
came back home I wanted to look up you
know to learn more about a I get into
the backend and that's how I came across
ocw
actually how did you come across W I was
on YouTube actually cuz I've been doing
a lot of YouTube learning for like 10
years now yeah um so my first
convergence with ocw was through that
course that I talked about the
thermodynamics and kinetics course I was
just trying to search up what video
lectures I was seeking for lectures not
like 10 minutes explanation video I did
not want that although condensed
explanation on summary videos they help
but when you're actually trying to ro
really understand and absorb the
material and topic or um studies which
you're interested in 10 minutes can
never satisfy you and it never answers
your question you often have to do
additional yeah searching and then you
actually have to do okay which textbook
or like materials are they basing their
argument upon like I'm sort of like this
fact Checker and so if I watch a video I
first of all check the profile of that
person who's explaining okay this this
is this person that qualified to teach
me this and so you never you never ask
those questions when it comes to MIT
course materials and so yeah so it
ticked off every box on my
checklist I'm kind of interested in the
impact it had you know in your life
outside of your academic studies what do
your friends think do you share with
your friends this open course where
Journey what did your family think and
you know did it Ripple into your
community as well or yeah I think I
would have actively shared these
materials MIT ocw materials with my
friends um if they spoke
English but yeah I
think yeah I do have um friends who are
living in America and they are Americans
cuz you've lived in like several
countries how was that yeah definitely
um my lifestyle has been quite
paretic I've basically been being like a
nomad my mom is an English teacher half
of my mom's family so my aunties and my
uncles they all live in America and yeah
we've got quite mixed family backgrounds
happening on my mom's side my dad's
side's very much yeah rooted in Korea so
it's quite an interesting um family and
cultural Dynamic so then this sort of
epiphany did not really click through
until I entered middle school so when I
became School junior I realized that I
just did not want to stick with this
very regimented school system that is
very much prominent in Korea so my
parents also shared the same view they
wanted me to explore the wider pool um
overseas they so I moved to New Zealand
when I was 14 and I had no one there I
had no family relations so spent my
Junior and senior years there so middle
school high school and then I was going
to take my tertiary ation in London
there's a universal University College
London I was going to study economics
there but then that was also the year
when covid broke out and I couldn't pay
like a million dollars
for for for this education which I had
no real access to and so I quickly
changed my plan came back to Korea but I
always had this yearning for broader
learning something else that I can do
okay like I'm working on this but what
else can I do more
amazing you moved to New Zealand at 14
when you knew no one that's
courageous on the same point we can
highlight how was the difference in
traditional learnings I going to call
them several CU you've taken classes
from different countries how was the
difference in those places traditional
learnings versus open
learning I'd say that they're both
strengths and sometimes a bit weaknesses
so strengths when it comes to
Conventional education the main strength
I would say is that you're able to
directly interact with professors and
ask questions to Tas if you have them
when it comes to open learning although
you're able to really search out for
information and dig out those extra
learning materials that you wanted for
yourself um let's say you've got your
answer sheet and then the quiz materials
the quiz um question sheet you're able
to check that you've got this question
wrong but sometimes when you trip over
to this question and not able to really
figure out what's like why I have gotten
this question wrong I I needed some
external help and so I would be asking
my friends whose major is chemistry and
then they would help me um in in that
but then there's sort of like this Cross
transation of what I am learning here
and then they are trying to figure out
put their fingers on what what is this
context like why are you doing this and
then I often find myself having to
explain oh I'm actually an economics
student just interested in chemist CH
istry and so like learning about this
and then they are trying to diagnose my
prior knowledge in chemistry and then
they realize that okay you should
probably like start with this and this
and this and so sort of like that
structured guidance it might become a
sort of impediment in some way um when
it comes to Conventional traditional
education system but it also works
enormously well for students who aren't
quite sure like where they're lost in
but um but also at the same time um as
I've mentioned the flexibility comes in
just just very very encouraging and it's
it's it's highly invigorating if you're
if you feel if you derive satisfaction
from taking on the initiative and then
actually executing those initiatives if
you're like very action taker like me so
I just did not want to form a plan okay
I want to learn more about chemistry but
then I'll just put that aside for a week
or so but then if you actually want to
get down to it immediately and then seek
out an all available resource which you
can learn more about than like ocw is
definitely a cutout like
prototype you talk about self-learning
you know a lot of people think of
self-learning as you know running a
marathon like they think it's the same
thing right like that's just this
impossible task but but oddly enough you
know you you talk about it and you're
like I'm invigorated I'm inspired to do
more I I think bigger you know what are
some ways maybe even now like entering
your last last year of University what
are you thinking about like what does
your Mor look like now I think this goes
back to the cultural background so sort
of like the sort of Mantra that I grew
up with so you mentioned that I try to
think bigger and like expand what I have
right now and I think that comes from my
background where I was constantly
shuffling between America um Korea and
then New Zealand and because I know that
your degree was poetry and my favorite
poet was Emily Dickinson she wrote this
um really famous verse called I'm like a
flower that cannot take its roots
anywhere and that was the sort of thing
that I was feeling for myself but I
tried to translate that into my own
Advantage I attend y University but I
don't always follow the crowd I always
think about what can I do differently so
actually like I'm trying to enter
Investment Banking right now and then
there is a group of University clubs and
societies where they are working
Investment Banking entry roles by doing
case studies together and then getting
feedback with the ultimate goal being
trying to get a place at an investment
Bank in Korea but then when I look at
them like they all qualified to apply
for a role in like basically like Wall
Street they're so talented but then they
never sort of think outsides their
institution and then think okay if I if
I sort of Leverage this resource let's
say this external resource communities
like 100 women in finance I'll be able
to probably reach out to different
people and then um put my paws on that
opportunity as well and so just sort of
like reaching out for different
opportunities and seeing what I can do
differently is basically something that
shapes me and has been this sort of
identified of me and ocw is definitely
something which I would identify as like
an extra work which I had taken for
myself because I want to think
differently I always sort of had this
repulsion against group thing repulsion
is a very quite strong word so I'll just
say very very cautious probably because
I follow the market every day and I
tried to very very cautious about this
group think how can I think logically
it's very very long response sorry like
yeah it was a big question it was you
know you could go anywhere with it um
the director of MIT open course where
Curt Newton this is a question from him
you know when you think about the impact
of open educational resources that
they've had on your life and people that
you know when you look into the future
with all the newly acquired knowledge
you have is is there anything that if
you had a magic wand that you would want
for a free open educational resource
available for the world can I be very
very specific because I was I I'm in
preparation for certain as I've said I'm
preparing to become like um investment
banker um um as like my um entry role in
my career in my very early career stage
and then I was trying to seek out for
MIT ocw courses that are relate to this
subject but I had somewhat difficulty
finding it and the subject is
accounting I realized that MCW um
actually has phenomenal finance-based
courses but then when it comes to
accounting I had some difficulties
trying to find related resources and so
that is very very specific answer mean
what happens when you finish all those
accounting
[Laughter]
courses what's next what's next
but you
know every open learner we've talked to
so far has said the same exact answer
which is like more courses yeah it's
it's kind of weird
actually more courses maybe I'll ask you
something extra because I'm seeing
you've taken mainly accounting and
economics and finance related coures
have you taken anything outside like
those fields anything outside accounting
and economics on ocw um yeah that's
that's another great question so the
courses I sort of like dabbled in many
different courses as in there were some
courses which I did not watch to their
full length but then there were some
courses where I just sort of like
watched one or two videos on the
playlist and the reason being I was
often finding myself in a quite
difficult time management situation and
so I was trying to maximize the
efficiency of learning by watching the
videos that are most relevant to the
questions that I have inside my head or
the difficulties that I'm facing at my
like actual University the courses that
I've taken so chemistry the thermod
Dynamics and connectic one and I've also
taken of course Professor Gilbert
strang's linear algebra course which has
come in very very handy when I was
studying convolutional neural
networks um I was I was going to say we
need to come back to gilver
strange yeah we deserve yeah a whole
separate conversation like what a legend
what brings you back to your career I
know you're in University now like has
this always been a drive for you or is
it just in University you're feeling the
pressure now that like I got to figure
out what I'm going to do to make money
you know after this or what what are you
thinking very very
realistically half and half of each so
half being I generally enjoy learning
and so there was absolutely no reason
just no modom reason for me to take
chemistry courses but I took it because
I really enjoyed it chemistry learning
chemistry really pushed forwards my
drive to learn more and then expands my
Horizon like you have rightly pointed
out I'm also a final year student and I
think I have dabbled in all the areas
which drew me in so like chemistry
Finance data science and then economics
I tried them all and now I think it's
probably the time where I have to yes
basically root myself in specific
grounds and then even if they don't work
out you know they say like it doesn't
matter in 5
years probably I can like change my
career plan after 5 years but as of the
moment I'm trying to solidify and
consolidate one specific goal and really
gear towards that goal so using all the
resources and the learnings that I've
had to achieve a specific goal you know
me in my journey too like when you get a
specific goal you can always line up
another one you can always make another
one you can always change that's your
right as a human being right completely
agree with you yeah this has been
amazing uh I just have one more thing
maybe to ask you're an amazing character
you've gone from Finance to sances to
fch you're now in Investment Banking
amazing amazing journey any advice for
anyone listen listening who may want to
take your path or maybe learn a few
things from you for future ocw Learners
or listeners to this podcast I would say
that my path up to this point has been
incredibly
unpredictable but I always tried to
follow what I'm interested in and being
able to search the resources I'm wanting
to learn more for your advantage these
are like very very important qualities
that will eventually lead you up to a
certain point and for me that is
investment banking at this point I'm not
sure if what what I will say after like
five years but that is my current career
goal the 5-year plan and up to this
point there's been so many different
Explorations where I went from economics
chemistry Finance fintech data science
but then at every Point what I can say
for sure is I did not just rely on my
conventional education I Tred to do more
and then I try to actively seek out what
I'm like truly passionate about and in
order to have that gauge for yourself
being a very very active learner will
come into to Great advantage and then
having this all available accessible
resource like ocw will be something that
will meet all your expectations and then
meet the requirements that you have for
yourself but then I feel like ocw is a
great pool of resources where people can
sort of dream about one career pathway
but if that doesn't work out there's
always like different courses that they
can come back to and then explore
further that was such a cool
conversation cool cool conversation I
haven't stopped thinking about it what's
your biggest take away from J's
conversation Michael I love the
conversation with Jam because I think it
shows
the ability to be curious and to still
explore as an undergrad when I first met
Jam she was primarily focused on just
getting her chemistry degree and through
the conversation I had with her but also
with her leveraging open educational
resources she was able to expand her
view expand her Consciousness and
ultimately changed what she was studying
in her undergraduate program so I
thought that was very fascinating how
she went from just being focused on
chemistry to start looking at the whole
world and then studying economics as
well I personally loved how she has
experienced learning from all across the
world you know we've heard from her
story she was in New Zealand at some
point she's been to Korea and she found
open learning with this whole background
from all these different places and all
these different types of education and
still opcw was something and open
learning was something that could still
add to that and to such a person with
such experience and such diverse range
from and still she comes open learning
and still has something to add her value
I like that aspect of it in that this is
something that can touch anyone from
whatever background from whatever
experience you have it can still add
value to you thanks to everyone for
tuning into our conversation with J mean
Hong of Soul South Korea we will be back
in two weeks with another story from a
different Learner in the global ocw
Community see you
[Music]
then open L produced by Alexis hot
special thanks to the supporters and
donors who make ocw possible to learn
more about mit's Open courseware and to
check out the courses mentioned in this
episode visit the open courseware
website at ocw.mit.edu
a