so my name is Ricardo herul and I'm here
on behalf of latinx at the broad
presenting our current Speaker Dr Diego
Fernandez and his talk title will be
called time peeping in the brain and how
our internal clocks shape mood so just a
reminder uh we are latinx at the broad
um Russell can you see my slides is it
being presented yep yep so it's called
latinx at the broad and we are here and
we work on behalf of latinx community at
the broad and we would like to promote
diversity building Community among
latinx broes and empowering members of
latinx community we have several events
and we like to Foster collaboration we
allow opportunities to network and
visibility for role models in diverse
communities we also like to promote the
research that we do in our communities
and highlight latinx and diverse
researchers so today we'll have our
speaker Dr Diego Fernandez speaking
about timekeeping in the brain and how
our internal clock shapes our mood so
just as a brief introduction for Dr
Diego
Fernandez uh he's a neuroscience
researcher studying sensory biology and
circadian rhythms his lab is broadly
interested in understanding how the body
and brain encode environmental stimuli
such as daily changes in light and
feeding patterns and timely coordinate
physiology and behavior he obtained his
PhD dur um from the University of Buenos
cetes Argentina and worked in
identifying ishemic conditioning as a
strategy to amarate the damage caused by
ishemic retinal pathology ology such as
diabetic retinopathy his doctoral work
earned local and international Awards
including the PE award and the Eduardo
stto award in recognition of the best
national Works in Opthalmology and
Neuroscience respectively in addition he
had the honor of receiving the Ricardo
miledi Neuroscience training program
Fellowship he's currently at Cincinnati
at the division of
pediatric Opthalmology and he's going to
talk to us more about circadian rhythms
take it away Dr Fernandez okay thank you
Ricardo for the nice introduction and
for the invitation
I I really appreciate the work you're
doing I think that having these
communities is fantastic and I strongly
support you and your team on on
continuing on this
path
um for today's talk I put together some
of my work as a staff scientist when I
was a dni
and some new research we have here
Cincinnati Children
Hospital I opened the lab in 2023 it's
not even two years so if you guys have
any questions about starting a lab under
difficult conditions I'll be happy to
discuss at the end you have my email and
contact information so more than happy
to help in anyways um the title reflects
part of the talk and as regard said we
are broadly interested in the connection
of the environment with the internal
rhythms in in in in the body so here is
the conceptual framework that we use for
ask questions to our animal model M
always with a translational idea in mind
trying to think how this fundamental
research that we do in the lab can
impact uh human health and in particular
in a pediatric hospital how this can
improve the quality of patients that are
for example in the niku OR in intensive
care units for a long period of
time as I mentioned we are trying to
understand the mechanisms that integrate
external signals and internal signals
that can be defined as time cues time Q
is something that um has a temporal
component okay if we think about changes
in light daily changes in light and
temperature these are external time cues
affecting our Behavior internally there
are rhythms of
hormones pretty much every cell has a
physiological process that can be
associated with Cadian function or these
rhythmic daily changes so how these two
events that have a temporary component
are integrated to affect animal
physiology and ultimately affecting
behavioral responses is the main focus
of our
research from a fundamental perspective
we are always
thinking what what is the impact in
nature of these different time cues I
just picked one of my favorite behaviors
in nature orcas in the thousand of
Argentina where they are teaching other
animals how to catch these sea lions um
if you think about the different time
cues in the environment is is extremely
complex and all these variables are
affecting one simple Behavior simple in
terms of the the decision making process
and the effectiveness of the
behavior we can think about the time of
day so this is early in the morning
around 6:00 a.m. when the light has a
particular wavelength there is a
particular temperature there are social
structures of the orcas but also the sea
lies so all these components that also
have a learning component are impacting
animal physiology learning from the
experiences and anticipating what the
other animal is probably doing and
directing the actions the more
translational approach we can now apply
the same idea to shei workers as I
mentioned we're here in in a hospital
where we see every day um hundred of
people sheep workers that each week for
example they have different time of day
when they are here in the hospital I'm
assuming that most of them have social
cues family kids whatever they the
social structure is that is dictating
their Behavior so the consequences they
are exposed to abnormal time cues okay
light exposure for example feeding
patterns and social cues are completely
desynchronized and this is changing
every every week and they can be under
this uh irregular conditions for years
just to give you a few uh numbers uh
it's about 60% of total workers in the
US under different irregular life
conditions we have shift workers people
working at night rotating shift and it's
very interesting I recommend you reading
this report more than 40% of these
populations are minorities so it's a
it's a severe environmental stressor
there is impact in their physiology in
the long term in the lab we care about
the impact on the brain and in fact
there
is recent interest in in understanding
the connection of circadian rhythms
circadian disruption and mental health
and I highlighted here couple of
examples these are amazing groups doing
research in animal models but also in
humans where they are trying to
understand the link between Cadian
disruptions alterations in the clock
chains that dictate these rhythmic
functions and mental health I put few
examples here involving maor depression
schizophrenia bipolar disorder but in
all cases the remaining question the key
question here is whether the death
deficits in clock gen or in these cican
functions are parts of the ethology of
the pathologist or a consequence of the
disorder so we are trying to understand
whether this deficit trigger the the the
the brain disorders or they are part as
a consequence of the
disorders so in this slide I this is my
attempt to explain you a little bit more
about
blockchains um it's a fantastic process
in in in in in in the cells where
transcription factors in this case clock
and vml and again this is a very
simplified version so it's just to give
you a brief idea of the
mechanism transcription factors buy into
ebo regions inducing the expression of
per cry and other genes that are also
transcription factor that once in the
coplas they can bind form this complex
that eventually translocate into the
nucleus and with time there is
accumulation of them in the nucleus and
eventually they block and inhibit the
activity of clock and vount and
therefore they repress their own
expression so as you can see it's a
beautiful cycle where where cry genes
are actively controlling their own
expression so the result is we can
measure in the lab rhythms of these
genes so we have some positive and
negative Loops of the same cycle and
when we overlap then we see that
sometimes they have different faces or
the peak of expression is not at the
same time of day but what they have in
common is that the peak of expression is
always close to 24 hours this is why we
refer to them as clock jeans Cadian jein
circad DM close to 24
hours the reason why it's 24 is because
of the solar day okay so in mammals we
have this central dogma in chronobiology
where we Define Central clock in the
brain that oversees the rhythmic
function of peripheral clocks located
throughout the body and the central
clock in particular is detecting and
receiving information from the retina so
light information and changes in light
dark Cycles are aligning or affecting
the expression of the clock chain in the
central Pacemaker and therefore aligning
this clock with the environment the
result is that the scn communicates then
with peripheral
clocks controlling this organized uh
circadian
system I put a video here just to show
you some of the techniques that we use
in the LA this is a mouse line generated
by the tahash LA where one of the clock
chains per two is fused to the reporter
chain luciferase so we can see in xbo
preparations R micity of these U neurons
in the scn in the supermatic nucleus
that houses the central
pacemaker through neuronal and humoral
signals the central B maker communicates
with these peripheral clocks in order to
align their function with the external
lter cycle so this is a clear um U
structure where there is a hierarchical
order light affects the Central
basemaker Central basemaker then
virtually coordinates every cell in the
organism in recent years there's been
U an interest in in understanding more
about the gene expression the clock gene
expression in the brain in
I'll be talking about mice most of
during most of my talk and in this
review you can see that we have now a
deeper understanding of these different
clocks and eke keeping mechanisms in the
brain that are not exclusively located
in the supermatic MS okay so these are
several examples I'm not going to give
you more details about J is the
fascinated area of research if you want
to learn more but what we know is that
these different clocks are responding to
different environmental cues in this
review they highlight the impact of
light food activity different hormones
so it is clear that the environment
plays an active role in coordinating
these internal clocks in the brain and
the question is how now the central
pacemaker communicate with these
peripheral clocks located in the brain
in our lab we focus on the light effect
is one of the strongest time cues in
nature and as I mentioned we have a
particular interest in in in populations
exposed to irregular light conditions as
shef workers or pediatric patients in in
nus where they are Overexposed to
light to Briefly summarize um the rinal
brain circuits involving image detection
we can start with the retina where
classic photo receptors broad cones
detect light these signals are
ultimately roted to the gangon cells the
rinal gangon cells and these projection
neurons innovates areas in the brain
that directly involved in image forming
functions we visual animals so the
association between light and image
Waring processes is very direct but we
also know that there are projections to
other centers as I mentioned the Supra
asmatic nuc that controls picity in the
brain and the body but more importantly
uh these neurons that project to the
central pacemaker were identified about
20 years ago and they are subpopulation
of ganglin cells that are at the same
time photo receptors so we can Define
them as a typical photo receptors or
intrinsically photosensitive rinal
gangling cells or
ipgs what is important to know about
these neurons is that they express a for
a pigment that is called melanopsin opm4
so these animals expressing melanopsin
in this gangling cells can directly
detect light through the melanopsin
expression and roting this information
to the brain
they also have connections with uh
neurons that process Road cones signals
so at the end they are integrating Road
code information and melanops
independent
information this cocktail of light
detection signals is rooted to the brain
to the scn but also to other areas in
the brain as shown in this schematic
diagram of the mouse brain in I would
say the last 10 15 years many many
groups including us have been actively
working
in understanding more about this uh
connectivity of the iprgcs the melanops
in expressing Neons and different brain
areas that as you can see goes beyond
thec um you can probably pick your
favorite brain area and it's on the list
here what is important about this
circuitry is the fact that light can now
directly impact the function of brain
areas that play complete different roles
as an example we have the amigdala
probably involved in stress responses we
have the lateral havena the peral gray
Superior calculus as I mentioned son
inserta so there is a variety of regions
in the brain that are now detecting
light through the iprgc projections and
we know that these are different
populations of
ipas so we propos as a conceptual
framework for our studies that different
populations of neurons in the retina
directly inovate brain centers that are
involved in driving distinct behavioral
responses we know a lot about the
connections with the scn and we are
getting more more information about
direct rinal projections to other brain
oscillators that can probably under the
control of the SCM so we have a
beautiful uh scenario where these
centers can integrate external and
internal signals through rinal
projections and SC signals going back to
the idea of irregular light exposure we
can now hypothesize that the different
deficits Associated to irregular light
exposure as was extensively describing
shift workers is in fact the result of
different circuits in the brain that
receive information from the retina but
through par Ral
Pathways so to further explore this idea
this
hypothesis we characterize when I
started my bog um different Pathways by
which light can impact different brain
centers in this direction we identify an
over region in the the brain that is
densely inovated by the retina um we
call this region the paven nucleus of
the dorsal Thalamus and here you can see
images of coronal sections of the mouse
brain and in this uh horizontal plane
where using CTV injected into the eye we
can now trace the projection of all the
gangling cells in the retina so you have
dense projections to the chenlate area
as expected visual centers connections
to the proctal area but also these
fibers that densely inovate the phb as
you can see most of the inovation and
most of the synaptic contacts are in the
dorsal thamus and only a few fibers
penetrate the lateral avend so we did
experiments to confirm that the
connections are mostly with thalamic
neurons and we also confirmed that these
are mostly ipes we use a battery of of
tracing strategies to confirm that the
iprs the melanops in expressing neuron
represent probably more than 80% of the
rinal neurons innovating the
PHP so what about the neurons in the
dorsal Thalamus responding to light what
what is their function what do they
project we run a battery of tracing
experiments again where we use
um viruses adenos Associated viruses to
trace the projection of these light
detecting neurons in the dorsal Thalamus
and we found an interesting pattern of
connectivity with areas in the
prefrontal cortex the pedial cortex
dorsal Statum and nucleus
Acom it's important to mention that
these brain areas are um key centers
involved in the pathophysiology of major
depression so we have an interesting um
framework where light through the r to
the thalamus and now to the cortex can
directly impact circuits in the in the
cortex that process emotional responses
to changes in the
environment The Next Step was to
manipulate the squids and learn more
about the consequences of activating or
inhibiting these cells in in in adult
M so one of the one of the strategies
that we used is The Chronic manipulation
of the cells using dread and to do that
we use viruses together with
um functional and and behavioral
analysis and in particular we use
viruses that expresses the thread
receptor in particular the GQ receptor
in phb neurons that project to the
prefrontal cors okay so by using
retroviruses injected the prefrontal
cortex and greed dependent viruses in
the PHP we were able to induce the
expression of reporter genes to identify
the neurons and the injection site but
more importantly the GQ receptor in this
phb neurons and after four weeks of the
injections we gave animals CNO to cause
The Chronic activation of The
receptors the idea here was to house
animals in normal lighter Cycles as
represented here there are no changes in
the
environment but we took advantage of the
fact that animals are active at night
and this is when they are drinking most
of the water and eating the food so we
had the CNO in the drinking room during
14 days we measured the volume consumed
and we confirm The Chronic activation of
these phb neurons project to the cortex
exclusively at night okay so we are
generating a model of overactivation of
these um centers during the day
responding to natural light or
artificial light in this case and at
night the activation induced by the C
what we notice is that this chronic
activations severely impact the behavior
of the animals I'm showing you a few
examples with run a battery of
Behavioral t
and it's interesting to see that the for
test showed increasing Mobility time and
less preference for sucros in the sucus
preference test in animals that receive
the chronic CNO in drinking water so
collectively this data suggest that mood
aspects of these responses related to
anonia or the helplessness that you can
associate with this different test is
affected by chronically activating
PHP what about silencing theal okay here
we can talk about sufficiency but what
is the the need for these neurons to
drive responses to irregular light
conditions as you can imagine using
irregular light patterns in nocturnal
animals is always challenging so we
decided to implement the regular light
pattern that it's called t7 cycle is an
ultradian light dark cycle that presents
light and dark at different phases of
the mouse activity
in some aspects this is similar to a
shiw walk pattern where people have a
regular pattern of activity and they are
exposed to light and dark independently
of their activity so this t7 cycle was
applied for two weeks and is causing
severe deficits in mold so we wanted to
test what is the consequence of
silencing the PHP in my house under this
conditions to do that we use the tetanos
toxin strategy again using aen
Associated viruses so we can inject
viruses induced tanos toxin in these phb
neurons that can obviously still detect
light the Rina and the connection with
these camic neurons is intact but now
the detection of light cannot be roted
to any of their targets including the
prefrontal cortex so in some way we are
blocking this light detection pathway
animals four weeks after the injections
were exposed to regular or irregular
lighter Cycles D7 cycle for two weeks
and we confirmed that the deficits
induced in in control animals with the
Shan virus are not present when we
silence the phb as you can see the
immobility time in the forcing test or
the preference for sucros was not
altered by just by silencing the phb and
housing animals to the
t7 even though this data is not
confirming that the scn or other brain
centers are not involved it's sufficient
to to prove that the phb is necessary
for driving the irregular light effects
of light on mood and the deficits that
we observed in minus so we have a
combination of results suggesting that
this region in the thalos is both
necessary and sufficient to drive
deficits associated with irregular light
exposure what about the rest of the
brain so that's a key question in
understanding how the these circuits can
probably work in I know well using the
t7 here is an schematic of the activity
of animals where you can see that they
are uh in a free running condition as we
call basically is an animal that is
displaying a robust rhythmic activity
with no changes in sleep architecture
and we also found and this is also
previous data published by the hatal lab
that in the scn if we measure clock je
by immune stain by by qpcr there's a
beautiful rcity of clockin that is
preserved in Animals House in different
lighting conditions so again this is
confirming that The Irregular light
pattern even though is affecting the
behavior of the animal and it's
affecting some of the Circadian aspect
of the behavior is not disrupting the
central clock we assuming that the
output signals are also preserved the
next question is what happens with the
PHP well this is what we found when we
measure the perue expression in the PHP
in this
thalamic Center we found first of all
that there is a nice and significant
rhythm of clock gene expression
particular perue expression in the in
the dorsal THS but more importantly we
found that the t7 cycle disrupted the
reges as you can see there is no
significant changes and there is a up
regulation of the expression of this
protein that as I mentioned before is in
some way the negative Loop of the
feedback of clock gen so higher
expression of per two can lead to
massive deficits in in in in thousand of
genes that are regulated by these
transcription factors so to have this um
overview of changes and widespread
effects we run bulk sequencing uh by
dissecting the phb and we focus on two
time points what we call ct2 ct14 so
circadian time 2 and 14 that indicates
phases of activity and inactiv
we are using infrared sensors in the
cages these are house single house mice
so we can precisely detect the onset of
the activity and then dissect the tissue
at the time we
want but you are seen in the lower panel
is a volcano plot for animals where the
tissue was collected at ct24 in normal
lighter cycles and when we compare these
different expression profiles we
found multiple Gene displaying these
rhythmic functions as you can see we
highlighted only a few but there are
hundred of genes that are significantly
AB regulated at night or during the day
so again this is reflecting phasic
changes in the tissue responding to
changes in the
environment we can then use these
significantly um up or down regulated
genes to learn more about the genology
and as expected we found Pathways
associated with Cadian rhythms and
classic and and fundamental cellular
processes doing gen gen seed enrichment
analysis we see pretty much similar
deficits sorry not deficits similar
changes associated with Gava
glutamatergic signaling and fundamental
processes cell biology the next question
is what happens with tissue collected
from t7 samples well this is what we
observed when we compare the samples
collected that ct14 versus ct2 so active
phase versus inactive phase in this
scenario we see no changes in the
rythmic expression of these gen just to
be very clear this is not reflecting the
expression level the the amount of the
gene that we are measuring this is
quantifying how rhythmic is the
expression of these genes Depending on
time of there and as you can see none of
the genes that were significantly up or
down regulated in normal conditions are
significantly different under t7 cycle
conditions so this is an interesting um
result
displaying the impact or reflecting the
impact that altering clock chains can
have through throughout the
glutamatergic and and gabic signaling in
these damic centers by using ever scope
we were able to validate the results
this is um really interesting result if
you see at the rhythmic pattern first of
all it's not observing t7 samples but
more importantly there is no up
regulation of the jeans so the levels
are quite similar but the most
significant effect is the uh alteration
in the rhythmic pattern across the day
night
cycle so it is clear at this point that
the light processing in the central
Pacemaker and at least in this
peripheral time keeping Center in the
brain is different so the way that the
clocks are responding to light are not
similar we have a good understanding of
the anatomy of the central clock that
when we started this project we had
really minor information about the
architecture of the dyamic areas
responding to light and in particular
within the PHP so we perform different
anatomical studies and histological
Analysis to characterize the anatomy and
the composition of the cell types that
form the PHP on the upper panel you are
seen a representative image of an animal
expressing the UR in G two neurons so
this is exclusively gabic cells in the
thalamus in green you can see now the
innovation of the retina that defines
the borders of the
PHP it's very interesting to mention
that as expected we
found um High expression of excitatory
glutamatergic neurons in the dorsal
pamus as previous
described and also the lack of G gabic
cells in most of the pamic centers
however there is a cluster of gavas that
is exclusively located in the PHP in
close contact with the retinal terminals
these gab Chi cells Express all the
classic markets of Gaba G one g 2 vat
and they are in close connection with
the rtina and by using Ravis virus
electrophysiology we confirm that they
are connected with these gavels and in
fact we notice that moving from rostra
to color part of the PHP we see an
increase number of GIC cells this is um
strongly correlating with denser
inovation from the rtina so it's an it's
a paradigm where we can think now that
light detected by the
rtina U is affecting the circuit in the
dorsal thamus in particular these GIC
cells that when exposed to different
lighting conditions showed severe
deficits in the basic properties so what
we did here is patching neurons
collected from different time points and
different lighting conditions I'm
showing you data from the ct14 analysis
and we found that what in normal
conditions is um reflecting that most of
the neurons in the PHP are in a silent
state with low filing rate at this rest
state is inverted in must expose to the
t7 cycle for two weeks it's important to
mention that before performing all these
experiments mice were housed in constant
Darkness for one day so we are avoiding
any acute effect of light so as shown
here these cabic cells have a drastic
change in their in their basic
properties after being exposed to the t7
cycle so the next question is what is
the consequence of manipulating these
cells and for that we propos this model
where
um by activating G neurons we can
directly affect excitatory neurs and
therefore impact limic centers the
output signals and in this paper that I
invite you all to to read and learn more
about it we explore whether using the
dread technology that I described before
but now focusing on gabic cells in the
phb is sufficient to induce um deficits
in Behavior so we have the confirmation
that by manipulating these thalamic
centers that are not directly
communicating with the cortex this is
sufficient to induce deficits in animal
behavior that is associated with mood
and and and and depressive behaviors in
particular so what about the GIC cells
in the thalamus okay as you can see the
phb is a tiny structure in this corner
in this uh area that is next to the
lateral havena with no connection with
the the lateral havena but with dense
connections with local circuits in the
dors ofus what I'm showing you here is
an experiment where we use gotu cre
animals and we injected adenos viruses
to infect the cells and this virus is a
cred dependent virus that expresses tdt
so we can trace all the axonal and and
projections of the cells but in addition
copying is fused to
gfp so by looking at this two pannels we
can precisely identify the the fibers
that inovate these Gaba cells in the phb
but also the synaptic contacts as
expected we found this dense inovation
and dense connectivity with principal
excitatory neurons in the phb also with
other gavic cells but in addition with
areas in the thamus that are next to the
phb so it's indicating a potential
effect that goes beyond this light
Detective like light detection Ser in
addition we found that at least a
population of these cic cells we we
don't have an idea of the porc some of
them at least have long range
projections as you can see here we found
dense inovation to the pamic reticular
nucleus TRN as well as the Son inserta
and the controlateral
P so if you think about these few cells
inter neurons in the phb have these long
range projections connecting with the
thalamic particular nucleus Sona inserta
and Crossing to the other hemisphere of
the brain contacting controlateral phhb
neurons using RIS virus and different
tracing strategies we confirm that this
is a this is a vatal connection so it's
a very interesting circuitry where a few
cells interneurons in the thalamus that
respond to light are now connected with
different centers in the brain that
process the information that commun
communicates the thalamus with the
cortex so it's an interesting um
scenario where light can now have a
widespread effect not just modulating
centers that are directly involved in
light detection but also affecting
centers that control different functions
of thalamocortical
communication so in summary this is the
working hypothesis that we have
now independently of the central BAC
maker we have found that the population
of rinal neurons that Express melanopsin
these iprgcs inovate Gava cells and
excitatory neurons in the thalamic PHP
these Gava neurons have local
connections modulating the function of
excitatory neurons that connect with
limic centers including the accumbens
ventromedial prefrontal cortex and
thisat and in parallel these GIC cells
also have long range projections
affecting the Son inserta and the
TR looking at previous data we found
confirmation that the limic centers
connected with the
phb rhythmically Express clock chains I
have the references here these are
fantastic papers but at least to our
knowledge there is no evidences that the
TRN and Son insert showed any Cadian
rhythms or any Cadian function so this
is what we wanted to explore and this is
what we are currently doing and to do
that we are taking advantage again of
the gatu and Cherry animals as you can
see we can detect these garic cells that
are the majority of the neurons in the
TRN and the Sona inserta so this is um
inv validation that there is per two
expression is an antibod so just to
confirm that the same neurons the
neurons are or can be considered clock
neurons but we need to know more about
the rhythmicity of these centers to do
that we use micro dissection at
different circadian times so we are able
to section the brain and disect these
different areas and then run qpcr to
have this nice um plots where we use
four different time points across day
night cycle to confirm the rhythmicity
of clock chain expression in these two
gabic centers on top you can see the
rhythms for Sona inserta sorry for the
TRN lower panel is the rhythmicity of
perue in Sona insert so we have now a
confirmation that this is rhythmic this
is probably responding to changes in the
PHP and opens as you can imagine a lot
of new questions and ideas for future
experiments we started doing ER scope to
expand the analysis and learn more about
the anatomical and topographic
connectivity of these centers so you can
see um by using vat or different
coverage markers together with different
blockchains we can validate the overe
expression not the overe expression the
the robust expression of clock chains in
the Gava cells and in fact most of the
cells close to 100% of the cells in both
TRN son inserta as well as the PHP as we
previously found showed expression of
clock chains by using single cell
analysis we can delineate the borders of
these neurons and count the pcta of per
two in this case the green dots so we
can
quantify the changes in gene expression
in these different cells prevaling this
nice phasic changes in in expression in
all these targets um these are only two
points obviously we can expand to Four
Points points this is ongoing research
and we are also expanding the analysis
to other clock chains so this is the
summary of what we are currently doing
and is uh guiding me back to the
original um conceptual framework what I
propose that environmental time cues
integrate are integrated with signals in
the brain in the system that guide the
temporal integration of these different
time cues to coordinate behavioral
outputs this is something that we are
investigating in the central Pacemaker
and in parallel in these different
timekeeping centers in the brain
including the PHP so from the data that
I presented today we can make this
parallel correlat
and propose that in the PHP there are
GIC neurons that directly respond to
light the same for Relay neurons that
connect with limic centers through these
output signals what we found is that
gabic cells are essential for the
rhythmic oscillation of the phb circuits
and we also found that these gabic cells
have connections B directional
connections with TRN son inserta and the
cont lateral PHP so this is describing a
network of garic cells within the
thalamus that can be working uh in
oscillation probably coordinated with
the scn or it could be completely
independent of the scn and this is part
of the the research that we are
currently
investigate so uh I invite you to read
more about our research I I didn't
include today but we are um in addition
to studying light focusing on the effect
of time cues
Associated to feeding uh rhythms and and
different food diets so this is a paper
we published few years ago where we
studied a similar conceptual framework
but now focusing on the impact of of
light and feeding responses so what we
found at the end is that the scn is not
drastically affected by the t7 cycle but
the phb is severely affected so the key
question is whether the phb has this L
mechanisms that are susceptible to
changes in the environment or whether
the consequences of the disruption are
in fact the deficits in this peripheral
network of cic cells that send abnormal
information to the PHP so we have now
new questions to understand these
integration mechanisms within the PHP
but also expanding the idea to
widespread networks that detect changes
in the environment changes in the
internal systems and integrate these
signals to coordinate
Behavior so this is what I have for
today I want to um thanks all of you for
your attention thank you the organizers
again for the invitation I want to thank
the people in the lab as I mentioned at
the very beginning we are new lab so
we're looking for new people motivated
people if you have a question feel free
to reach out to us um if you want to
learn more about our research all our
Publications are in the website so you
can download the papers and I'll be
happy to take any questions thank you
thank you very much Dr Fernandez uh just
to note that we have a survey that goes
out I will post it in the chat and we
will send you an email link for the
survey post survey because your feedback
is valuable um we have two questions
right now but please feel free to put
your questions in the Q&A first question
is um this lead to a better model of
emotional and circadian disregulation
and bipolar disorder could the
methodology developed in your studies
generate murine models that more closely
resemble bipolar disorder than the ones
we currently use also great
presentation thank you very much um this
is really a great question
um it's very challenging to have model
for bipolar this orders I feel like um
data from calling mlang and other groups
is showing how using human tissue is now
helping us even designing animal models
to study bipolar disorder and different
mood disorders so um what we have in
mind here
is understanding more about the
integration of external cues and
internal cues is the first step in
Deering the ethology of these
pathologies so you can imagine we can
perturb clock chains but the question is
when to do that is this having an impact
during development or can we perturb the
genes in adult and obviously using
knockout models we we have the challenge
of having a drastic alteration in the
system so by manipulating the
environment and knowing the precise
alterations in these timee keeping
mechanisms in the brain we can probably
um design better models to attack these
kind of questions and at least have
better models to Define what are the key
questions for understanding major
depression versus bipolar disorder but
this is a great question I would love to
discuss more so I'll be happy to keep
discussing later thank you yeah
excellent um so that was the two
questions we had online I did have one
question about your methodologies there
was a Lucifer Lucifer is assay with the
oscillating circadian rhythm shown in
the scn what time frame was that
oscillating in was that like an a lapse
time frame or was it
just yes so this is a video that um we
are not using this animal for this
question in particular this is a classic
Model where um you can dissect the scn
ideally you can do the same for PHP or
any other brain centers and then collect
information across 24 hours for multiple
days so when you see a peak of
expression when you see this bright
signal this is uh 24 hours so obviously
it's it's not real time video each cycle
again is
24 um another question is like um
extending on the bipolar murine model do
you see other models that would be
beneficial to look at for
mood disorders like could you apply this
like an anxiety disorder because it's
affecting the lyic system um yes that's
an interesting um
question an interesting problem as well
what we know is that um by activating or
silencing the
PHP we cannot interfere with other
models of mood disorders so what we have
tried is um exposing animals to social
defeat or um models of of chronic
exposure to the forun test and in these
conditions that are known to cause mood
deficits and alterations in lyic centers
there is no deficits in the PHP or in
this particular C so right now what we
propos is that this circuit is dedicated
to detect changes in light and when
these changes in light are abnormal or U
distorted from the 24-hour cycle is when
the phb is affected and eventually the
lyic centers are also affected so at
this point we cannot make strong
connection between the different models
looks like this is an independent
pathway dedicated to detecting light
whether this is combining or
accelerating deficits with other models
we still don't
know another question is um there's a
long history of circadian disregulation
in disorders like schizophrenia bipolar
disorder have you tried using any of the
typical drugs used to treat this these
disorders on your model to see if it
influences circadian or regulates the
Circadian
rhythm great yes interesting topic yes I
I didn't mention this in we haven't done
this but there is a previous study from
the hatar lab that alate run the
experiments where um fluoxitine was able
to restore the the deficit in mood
induced by irregular
light unfortunately we don't have a lot
of details to better understand whether
fluxy things is restoring the micity of
clockin or the the deficits that we saw
using bog sequencing but what we know is
that um if you treat animals with flatin
you can restore some of the deficits um
probably through the effects on the lyic
centers so we have no evidences that
these drugs can directly impact light
detection systems or in this particular
case the praven nucleus we know that
they impact lyic centers and this is why
we think that they have an impact on
animal
behavior which opens probably another
question or just to to expand my answer
when we think about Chief workers or or
people that have seasonal disorders
because of the changes in in light
exposure um even though these treatments
can be effective they are probably not
affecting the root of the problem that
why we think that understanding more
about the circuit R is essential for
Designing better tools better treatments
for uh targeting these Cadian centers
these eke keeping mechanisms that detect
light and eventually impact limic
centers as well another question we
have uh from Joanna again uh in fact the
short seven-hour hyperactive Cycles you
describe closely resemble the Circadian
alterations we observe in some bipolar
patients yes it would be interesting to
see what chronic in by various
psychotropic drugs causes in these
circuits for example The Chronic use of
benzodiazapines in patients not only
those with bipolar sorder but also with
or without
psychiatrics yes this is a an amazing
comment and just to go back to the
schematic this is not a real actogram
but I'll be happy to share actograms
later if necessary
um what we saw what we seen most of the
animal is when we use the t7 cycle the
first couple of days you know it's
difficult to understand what they are
doing is is more a rhythmicity but
eventually they display these robust
patterns of activity and you can see
that they are in free running with the
period close to 24 hours and animals
start the activity every day at the
similar time but this is independent of
the light dark cycle so it's an
interesting dissociation from the
environment in animals in mice as you
know uh if you present lights there is a
masking effect that blocks their
activity it's not the case after a
couple of days under the t7 cycle and
discussing with colleagues um I I saw
actograms for patients with bipolar
disorder that are quite similar so there
is an interesting similarity in the
output responses I'm not saying that
this is a model for bipolar disorder but
the output signals the output circadian
responses are similar between the two
CPS so there is definitely something to
to explore in further
details I mean some of your F changes
are actually quite dramatic between the
Cycles it
is yes we have um with the validation
all the data is the Publications is very
interesting that we haven't seen an AB
regulation of genes so at least by
looking at um RNA scope and qpcr what we
see is that the rhythms are flat but
when look at the total expression of the
genes is quite similar to control
conditions so what we propose what we
think is that probably the light is
affecting these clock chains that some
of them directly respond to light and
these transcription factors then have a
widespread effect impacting other genes
as well so the result and we have
analysis only at 14 days after the IR
regular light conditions but having a
Time course would be essenti
in understanding the multiple steps
leading to this final scenario so what
I'm showing you here is the like the
final picture of the the entire event so
looking into early steps would be
fantastic to understand more about the
impact of light on these clock chains
and the different circuits responding to
that time
case do you find any other sub
subpopulations of cells in the Single
Cell analysis within NE tissues like we
have this is bulk sequencing um we're
currently doing single cell um I don't
have data to show you now but um by
doing a scope we found as I showed you
before this cluster of gabic cells
exclusively located in the PHP and the
rest of the cells are mostly
excitatory so this is the classic
pattern of expression in the thums if
you look at the alen for example there
are only a few markers that can identify
clusters of cells in the thalamus most
of the properties are associated with
the connectivity not with the genetic
Identity or at least to the knowledge
that we have
right so I'll say that we are at the top
of the hour and um thank you very much
once again for your very interesting
talk and very fundamental biology in
terms of brain development and you know
kind of esoteric markers for like mood
you know that's one of the hardest
things doing Psychiatry research like
how do you capture a thought you know um
or hallucination so very much
appreciated yeah for the invitation I as
I said the email is here people can
check the website I'll be happy to chat
more and answer any
questions sounds good thank you once
again and I look forward to seeing you
in the future thank you very much