I was going to ask my colleague Steve to
pop up. Uh we've been the kind of
co-architects
nominally of the kind of the mele that
we've had today. Um so I just really
like
what do you think you've heard today?
What was what's your takeaway from?
>> Nothing like being put on the spot.
Um
>> oh
um
so I think ultimately before was we
started with collaboration um we started
with students uh I would say from a a
human resources perspective that is sort
of the backbone in the future of so
there's a lot of technology right now
that we are addressing that I am old and
gray and I probably don't understand um
Michael Shre and I had a conversation
sidebar about getting on an airplane
that Masha had spoken about and not
understanding how how it works, what it
goes into, but we take it for granted
and I think we're doing the same with
LLMs and AI. Um, and so I think having
the student population uh in a rise
framework which guy mentioned before
talking about research uh innovation,
students and education uh as a backbone
of some sort of a baseline as where we
start. I that's really insightful. I
think so from my perspective, I think
what we've been on is a bit of a
trajectory that says so much is that the
the challenges are real.
Um the capabilities and the innovation
and the excitement to confront them and
to work through them and to innovate
through them to grow through them is
real. We have the talent, we have the
technologies, but the, you know, that
has to be approached with, as Lee was
saying this morning, a realism around
the limitations of some of the tools we
had with that capital depth or the
ability to do um shared governance even
within alliances. Um so it's going to
be, you know, an an interesting journey,
but it's like it's not as if it's not
not all doom and gloom. The promise of
these things is so great that if we can
coordinate or or compete or experiment
or learn our way through the current
wave of challenges, you know, there kind
of there's a there is a bright future
ahead. We may a few rough years, but
this is this is what we trained for.
This is what we went to school for. This
is what we work for. Um, and I'm, you
know, leave it a pretty optimistic
generally that we got to be, you know,
we approaching the future with caution.
uh change innovation at time of change
is going to be hard but it's like it's
it's is well within our capabilities I
think we just have to understand the
constraints and the and the routes to
that
>> um the constraints and then
Fiona had mentioned prioritization
so not everybody can do everything at
all times everywhere trying to perhaps
use technology whether it's AI or
elsewhere
to work collaborative collaboratively
while somebody is maybe ch tackling
quantum and somebody's tackling energy
and we're leveraging the the shared
learnings.
>> Excellent. Thank you. So with that draw
this afternoon to close. So I want to
say thank you for everybody for
especially for sticking with us for the
entire day. Um I hope that was you know
you learned something that you didn't
real didn't see before or at least
enjoyed the conversation. Uh we're
looking very much to seeing everybody in
London again on the next occasion
hopefully if you'll have us back. We
didn't upset too many people. Um, and so
thank you all very much indeed and thank
you particularly to the backroom crew.
>> Yeah. So to BT for hosting us here, to
the AV crew for doing a fantastic job,
uh, for Quan who's hiding somewhere, for
uh, making keeping us all in line, uh,
for Gatri for bringing this all
together, uh, to Simon Godfrey, who's
around somewhere, who's been helping me
to work with the UK speakers and pulling
the the narrative together, thought
partner for the last three, four years.
Uh, great guy. If you haven't met him,
you should meet him. Um, and to all the
speakers, all the presenters and the,
you know, the staff outside that did the
catering, it really is a family exercise
to bring these things together. Um,
we've had fun. Uh, it's always stressful
on the way into these things, but once
you, it generally gets going on the day.
Um, so I release you all the rest of
your days.