Good. All right.
Um, so we're heading in to
our our
last of
the as yet intractable dilemmas. We
talked about the curse of familiar atte
uh assessment and today the toxic power
of data and experiment. Um let's do this
as an exercise. Grab one other person.
Your goal is to make a list as long as
possible. Um what is all the data that
MIT has about
you? If you if you could if you could go
through every server that is somehow
even tangentially under the control of
MIT, what are all the different types
and sources and nature and example of
data that MIT has about you? Does that
make sense? Make the list as long as you
can, as fast as you can. Ready? Go.
All right. Let's let's let's start let's
start aggregating some big categories of
things.
financial information. Okay, so they
have a lot of financial information.
Maybe just like what are a few examples
of some of the most maybe sensitive or
personal parts of that.
They know your parents income. They know
your know your income. Your income. They
know your bank bank account. They they
know your bank account number or like
you give them literally but they they
don't like have a screenshot of your
like for example. All right. So they
know a lot of financial things about
you.
What what are some other categories?
Health.
What are some sensitive things in there?
History.
Vaccinations.
Vaccinations. Prescriptions.
Allergies. Allergies.
Mental health
visits. Insurance.
You can also tell people are LGBT
sexual
orientation activity.
Okay. What else you got?
Yeah. Register. Let's call it registar
information.
Name
address phone.
Oh, they might have their travel data.
Yeah, if you have travels, you have to
register.
Like MIT knows.
Yeah, especially if you've been
international. If you do it through the
screen,
or if you're going to like a country
that they have warnings for, you have to
be like, I was there. Wow.
What else we got? Academic records.
Good.
That's part academic records.
What What would that include these days?
They know your grades. What else?
Registration. Like what classes you show
up for?
Test scores.
Every click ever in Canvas.
Attendance.
Yeah. Um, academic records is a good
example of one for which the the
granularity of data over the last 10
years has transformed dramatically. Like
if you if you if we had had this
discussion in 1980, they would have been
like, I guess they know what my grades
were and what classes I signed up for.
Um, but the volume of data about every
activity that you've ever taken online
in any of your classes is substantially
higher um than it used to be. Those
records might not be maintained forever.
Maybe all those sites get deleted every
18 months or so. Something like that. Um
but some of them might be kept for
longer for research or other things like
that. All right. Other categories.
Residential. Yeah. Home and current.
Um let's make it even bigger. Let's say
location. Um so they know your
residence.
Um home and campus.
um track your devices on Wi-Fi.
Card swipes in buildings. Um we have
some um so you know essentially as you
move around campus it is some somewhere
someone somewhere somewhere there are
databases that record all those
activities how long you know how long
they maintain those materials we don't
necessarily know but I mean I'm sure
they tell us if we asked but what else
they got
from that location they can also tell
like who you hang your outfit
yeah I just learned about this today
what's the system of where you add
people okay so I guess if you live in a
residence you create a guest list of
people that are allowed to visit you.
Like that's like you can just
reconstitute the entire social network
of MIT from the get list, you know. Um
yeah, there's there's all kinds of
things you can learn from that. It's
like extracurricular activities so they
know what sports teams and like
athletics like stats on that. And then
if you signed up for like club teams,
it would be all those kinds of things.
as well. Yeah, your
gym gym membership swipes activity
political affiliations. How would they
how would how would they get your
political affiliation?
Like if you're involved with the recent
stuff that's been going on in campus.
Yeah. Or you know and or Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Good. So, um there are presum you
know increasingly presumably lists of
people who are um affiliated with pro
Palestinian, pro-Israeli, any of those
other kinds of things. But also people
would have just been able to tell before
if you remember I don't I assume there
there's a Democrat and Republican club
at MIT I would imagine
um someone somewhere emails. Yes, they
have the entirety of your email record
even like broader just like online
activity because like emails, websites,
anything you've registered for. Yeah,
they also offer like a
VPN. So
like it's secure to everyone but like
you also have your like Google Drive if
you sign up for the NYC.
Yeah. Um I had a congressional committee
that wanted to find out more about my
work um not necessarily in a generous
way. um this past year um and uh and the
the office of general counsel did like a
whole search throughout my email um to
find terms that this congressional
committee was interested in learning
more about um and uh and they you were
going back and forth and I was sort of
like you know what do you need from me
and they were like well it's better if
you if you help us with this but like
either way we're going to do it. Um so
uh um yeah all you know all the all the
records that you generate and and that
that that's a good example of how even
like you know how I'm reasonably
confident that in most circumstances
like MIT is not going through my email
every day and like what's Justin up to
you know like they don't care. Um but
simply having those records um allows
all kinds of things to happen with those
records. Um,
uh, do you do you guys have automated
laundry machines?
Washing frequency.
It's like an app. Yeah. Yeah. It's even
an app like it's an app like you pay for
your machine and you have to sign up for
your email. Yeah. You have to do
um Yeah. Yeah. And so that I mean that I
think also raises some questions of like
um it's possible actually that MIT
doesn't have your laundry data, but that
MIT just somehow mandates that a third
party has all of your laundry data. Um
which again like how keys to your room
if you live on campus. Yeah. Um like
physically. Yeah.
Keys. Um what what's good about them
having keys?
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, you know, I mean,
and an and you know, like like if
there's a day that you're locked out of
your room, you're going to be like, "It
is so great that MIT knows exactly what
key goes in my door and can make another
one of those." Um, yeah, we had like
room inspections a few weeks ago where
they went into every room to check if
they were abiding by the rules. Yeah.
Good. What um what what might be good
about room inspections for everyone?
I think Yeah. safety like like you know
like if if your if your neighbors are
like having hallogen lamps that can
catch on fire and stuff like that like
you would be glad that um they knew
about that but obviously also seems like
a huge invasion of of your privacy.
Yeah, I would I would say like what also
like kind of like made the room
inspections like um good like better
than like is also like you're trusting
MIT to be responsible for this. So like
they told they told everyone ahead of
time and they made sure you know that is
it like a visual inspection all so
they're not going through your stuff but
like obviously that's not a thing for a
lot of colleges a lot of colleges could
just like come barge into your room and
look at anything. Yeah. So you know
institutions make choices about how you
know so I mean hopefully I don't know
what what is what kind of feelings do
you have when you start looking at this
completed list?
Hm. Um the one that like I've been
thinking about lately given uh like the
permanent action stuff is just general
demographics. Once you're on campus and
also um something that was not mentioned
in financial is like purchase history.
So like if you buy anything on campus
they know you got sushi to make. Yeah.
like Tito and like all like the the
coffee stores like in
like the ones in like
Forbes stuff like that. Yeah. I mean
particularly if those things somehow go
like can you put money on your ID card
and spend directly to your ID card. So,
you know, there's I mean, like two two
units that we should be thinking about
um anytime we think about school data is
that schools have a bunch of data and
then schools authorize third parties to
get a bunch of data and sometimes only
the third party has access. Sometimes
both parties have access like both
Canvas and MIT people have access to all
of your Canvas data. you know, the
laundry app might be a good example of
if nobody I mean, if somebody told me
that the maintenance department had
access to all the laundry data or it I
wouldn't be surprised, but if they were
like, "Yeah, no, we make you sign up
with an email, but you know, only the
laundry people know your laundry data,"
that wouldn't surprise me either. Um,
but those are sort of two useful salient
categories that will come up as we keep
talking about things.
Your deliveries, too. Oh, yeah.
Deliveries. Um, oh, because things go
through the mail room. Yeah. So, um they
have uh they like store all of your
information and your deliveries into
like a tracker system and then they send
you emails when your delivery is coming
if you didn't pick it up. Good. Yeah.
And so there's, you know, typic
typically the data is exchanged for some
kind of service. You're like want to
know when your new headphones are coming
or something like that. And so you're
glad that they have that, but in order
for them to be able to know when your
new headphones are coming and to do
other kinds of things with it, you know.
I mean, the other thing it's like you
say like, you know, over the past 10
years, was it a good idea for MIT to
track the changing volume of deliveries
to individual students? Like yes. Like
I'm sure MIT has had to build all kinds
of infrastructure to make it possible
for you all to get your stuff in a
sensible way and it's probably a good
idea that MIT has data about aggregate
you know partic particularly in the
aggregate it's probably a good idea to
know like oh you know in in 2014 um the
typical student got you know 2.3
packages a year and now they get 30.6
packages per year and you know like just
requires a whole different
infrastructure to support those two
kinds of ways of people doing commerce.
Um, any what other feelings do you have
as you look at like the whole at the
whole list of data that MIT might have
about you?
Feel like ultimately I'm not really that
surprised. I feel like we kind of grew
up in a generation where like digital
data has been collected for our entire
lives. Like it was not something that
was introduced but always there. And so
like I feel like I've kind of grown up
in this world knowing that all of this
type of information can and is being
collected on me. And so like I'm still
gonna like live the same way, but I just
like it just is what it is in like a
kind of sad way. Yeah. Yeah. There's
sort of sag, you know, it's not um
you're clearly not comfortable with it
because if you listen to to pe if like
if you stop talking for a second while
people were making the listen listen,
there's like all kinds of awkward
laughter that happens throughout the
whole time. There's something about this
which is like, oh, this doesn't feel
good. Like like any individual category
can make you not feel that great. like
like do you really want MIT's IT
department to be able to track where
everyone can go? Like that seems like it
could go ary. Um and then just like the
whole you know the whole volume in a in
aggregate you realize like how you know
how much school you could make a very
similar list for K12 schools as well.
You can probably guess the places in
which things are not exactly the same
but um uh you know um and and the data
collection that people can do can be
really influenced by policy. you know,
the states have different rules about
how attendance is connected to funding.
Um, who's there on a particular day,
who's there for what periods of time?
Um, you know, you could imagine that you
want to make sure that if a kid moves
schools three times in a school year,
that not all three of those schools get
like a full students tuition worth of uh
or you know, a student per pupil
expenditure. Um so but there are states
that you know part of the reason why
they issue ID cards to students and
track their entrance and things like
that is to pay really close attention to
that attendance data um just for that
particular policy purpose.
Um yeah I mean adding on to like it
being not surprising I would say like a
lot of the information that like like
they took while we were here like our
like current residence or laundry and
stuff like that. It's I feel like it's
kind of like much more unsurprising just
because like it is something that is
like novel when you come to like a
college or like an institution like this
where it's like oh wow like they really
do have this information. Um but I think
what's kind of um a little crazy is how
much of this information they have
before you even get here.
So yeah, for applicants, for for people
who are admitted, if you're admitted
into the school and things like that,
yeah, there's a lot that you need to
tell MIT for them to be able to to come
here and get here. There's a there's a
lot that you need to be able to um you
know, uh the if you to get in again
these days, you have to take the SAT,
which means you give, you know, you are
required to give a bunch of information
to the College Board. Um and you also
like are in the process of doing that,
you're probably asked to opt in to a
bunch of things. I had I had a master's
student I can't remember all the details
now but uh um did their thesis on
essentially the kinds of things that the
college board did with information that
they got um which to some extent you
could say something like like if you opt
into flowers.com or something like that
you're like man I really want good
information about what flowers are
available and then flowers.com sells
your data you're like well that's like
maybe that's a terrible system to exist
in um but flowers.com did ask me if I
wanted to give them my data and I did
agree to let them do anything with it.
So like I you know and that was just my
voluntary relationship but you didn't
really have a voluntary relationship
with the college board. Um you know you
had no choice but to interact with a
college board to make it through this
major life milestone. And so to you know
to the extent that the college board
does things with your information that's
a different relationship um that you
have with them than you have with
flowers.com or pets.com or your own
favorite thing. Um, okay. So, we just we
live in a world in which schools have
enormous amounts of individ
um about their individual students. Um,
that there's probably pretty big
generational shifts in that experience.
You know, one of the main laws that
governs um these records is the federal
furpa, the federal education records
protection act, which I think was off
authored in the 1970s. um you know the
kind like we basically we have a legal
framework for supervising this data um
which was just built in an entirely
different era um you know um furo refers
to this thing called student records um
at the time it would have been entire it
would have been very very clear what a
student record was you would have like
gone to the registars's office and there
would have been like big file drawers
and you would have pulled out a file and
been like that is the student record um
are your clicker questions part of your
student record are your um codio
assignments, are your Canvas entries,
are your, you know, Piaza form things
like are those part of your student
records? Like there, you know, there's
there's much less clarity over those
things um than one might think.
Um the uh
um the term the term toxic has a kind of
negative connotation, but I borrowed it
from a security researcher named Bruce
Shire. Um, and part of his argument was
that like toxic things are powerful. Um,
you know, there there are, you know,
chemotherapies are toxic. Um, and they
save your life. They're great. Like like
sometimes it's really good to interact
with powerful toxic things. Um, but
toxic things are also dangerous. Um, in
you know, in particular, I think most of
us have an inclination um that when
something is toxic, you should not leave
it lying around for a long period of
time. That was kind of the heart of
Bruce's argument was was that companies
were making a big mistake by having um
by having a a a very capacious approach
to the collection and storage of data.
Um that actually what you should be
doing is like just taking the data you
need and getting rid of the rest of it
because it's a toxic asset to have lying
around. The more you have it lying
around, the more you're vulnerable to
breaches, to other kinds of actors doing
various nefarious things um with that
data.
Um, if you're an educational
researcher, what what what kinds of
thoughts might you have when you see
this like giant list of the data that
schools collect about people?
Maybe like honestly like the first thing
that kind of came to my mind was like
excitement in the sense of like if
you're forming any type of research and
trying to study how any about a person
can like affect whatever you're studying
like if you have all of this data then
like there's really no limit to what
you're able to um kind of research. Um
this was an article from today two days
ago. I'm going to give you a couple of
cutting edge things. Middle schools in
Norway banned smartphones. The benefits
were dramatic. A study shows um a study
published earlier this year um from a
Norwegian doctoral student. Um where
there were hundreds of schools across
Norway that it um that in various ways
banned smartphones. Um some of the
outcomes they look at are student
outcomes like learning but also mental
health. Um, I show that banning
smartphones significantly decreases the
health care takeup for psychological
symptoms and diseases among girls.
Postban bullying among both genders
decreases. Girls GPA improves and their
likelihood of attending an academic high
school track increases. These effects
are larger from girls from so from low
socioeconomic backgrounds. Um, so in
Norway they have vast informations about
students. Here are some things that you
need to know to make this study work.
You need to know all the students
grades. You need to know where all the
students go to college. You need to know
whenever the students visit the uh
Norwegian health care system and what
kinds of requests they're making from
the Norwegian health care system. Uh and
you need to have them every year take a
well-being survey that includes a bunch
of questions about bullying. Like that's
a lot of information for the state to
collect about all these students. But it
certainly seems to me like a pretty
pro-social thing to be able to say,
"Hey, you know, if we, you know, if we
look at the schools that ban um
smartphones in middle school versus the
ones that don't, um there seem to be all
of these health outcomes." And we can
even actually say that the you know, the
health, it's not just academic outcomes,
it's also health outcomes, although the
health outcomes are probably related in
some way to the academic outcomes, but
it's particularly for girls and it's
particularly for um students in low
socioeconomic environments. like that
seems like pretty useful stuff to know.
Um and so that is the kind of tradeoff
that people would face as they're going
back and forth between um you know these
like the the massive data that we
collect about students is also what lets
us do pretty sophisticated complicated
research about those students to be able
to make claims about how well they're
doing in various parts of their lives.
Um toxic power of data experiment. All
right, I'll tell you about at least a
couple of other things.
Um, there was a study that you read
about um in the chapter last night. Um,
this is a headline that came out. It was
in 2018. There's a headline that came
out about it. Pearson tested social
psychological messages in learning
software with mixed results. I don't did
we talk about mindset in this class?
Maybe we did briefly. Growth mindset and
fixed mindset. something you're probably
all familiar with it because teachers
talk about all the time. Um but there
were or education researchers other
folks um there are some social
psychologists who have identified um uh
two kinds of mindsets that people often
have towards learning or other kinds of
things. One is a fixed mindset which
generally says like some people are
smart and some people are not smart. Um
and a growth mindset suggests that um
people have fluid intelligence and you
can make yourself more intelligent in
other kinds of things. seems to be a
pretty good idea um to help young people
adopt the latter mindset rather than the
former mindset. Um better to have them
think uh have a growth mindset rather
than a fixed mindset. Exactly how much
it matters um is a subject of enormous
debate. There were a number of early
studies that suggested it could matter
quite enormously to all kinds of people.
And some of the more recent larger
studies suggest that like the best
things that we can do that we know how
to do to improve growth mindset only
help some students and maybe only help
them a little bit like a lot of things
that we study. Um, so Pearson um offers
all kinds of software products and um uh
I think this was a a line of computer
science software products and so you're
like you do a bunch of programming
exercises of multiple choice questions
or things like that and the thing that
they decided to add was not just right
or wrong messages but um randomized you
some people getting growth mindset
messages and some people not getting
growth mindset messages. So, I won't get
this exactly right, but example of a
growth mindset message, you know, might
be something like um you know, uh that's
not right, but keep trying and you can
learn more or you know, other other
things to suggest that if you keep
working at this, you'll get better.
Um what seems good about implementing
um that kind of intervention in a system
like this and what seems problematic
about uh implementing an intervention in
a system like this?
Well, problematic is that the control
group is essentially like not
necessarily being hurt but not
benefiting at all. And like like if
you're saying that a growth mindset
really does help people, choosing to
essentially not help them by putting
them in the control group. Yeah, that's
interest. So I mean Pearson So Pearson
goes and reads a bunch of research about
growth mindset and they're like, "Hey,
this growth mind stuff seems to work
sometimes. Um, but they don't decide to
just add it to their product. They add
it to their product in this kind of
experimental paradigm where some people
get it and some people don't. Um, and so
people in the same class are going to
have a different experience. Um so Dana
proposes that one problem with that is
that um the people who get the uh
experimental intervention might benefit
in the way that people in the control
group don't. What are some other
problems that kind of potentially could
show up with
this? I guess you have to take into
account like who's in the control group
and who's in the experimental group. How
good of a job do they do at filtering
out their students to make sure it's
roughly equal in terms of like
socioeconomic background, your prior
experience with the subject, etc. That's
good. So, I would and I would say under
most circumstances, especially in these
kinds of digital systems, we can be
really good at randomization. um you
know you I mean you could imagine that
if you're like randomizing across whole
schools or something like that there
might be people who are like well I
don't want my school to do it or you put
me in a control group but I just want to
get the intervention anyway or something
like that. um these kind of digital
systems can be like very strict about
the implementation of randomization. Um
and you could be pretty sure that
there's not that there's not going to be
any kind of bias and deliver. I mean
there you can imagine ways for bias to
show up but for the most part it's going
to be some you know there's going to be
some computer code which is like you
know if exercise four like assign
someone a zero or one control is zero
experiment is one and especially if you
have hundreds or thousands of people who
are participating in the experiment you
can be pretty sure that those two groups
are are the same. Um not only that but
you can also verify that they're the
same if you collect all this information
about them going into it. Um so these
things are going to be pretty good at
that. Um well I don't know if there was
any consent given but like from what I
can gather is that this was just done
without the students knowledge. Yes. And
so it's like I wouldn't necessarily like
it if I like came out of MIT graduating
and then someone's like okay here's a
paper of like what we analyzed during
their four years here. I'm like I don't
necessarily want to know that people
have been like watching my like every
move and analyzing like certain things
about me psychologically. Uh-huh. Why
not? It feels a little creepy. Feels
like you're being watched, right? Feels
a little creepy. Without any consent, I
can see why this is like good. Other
other observations that people have?
Also, calling it like a social
psychological message kind of makes it
feel like the experimental groups being
like propagandized or something like
that. And so it's like, oh, they're
being experimented with these like these
different gen psychological messages.
Yeah. It's like it seems like that
specific verbiage can like be kind of
uncomfortable for people to accept as
something that is potentially
beneficial. Good. Yeah. Yeah. So I mean
the reason why people are doing the
social psychological messaging is
because maybe it works actually you know
and it's not and in this particular case
it's not just like hey we got kind of a
hunch this works these like well
actually there you know at this point
there was maybe like a decade of
research that was was totally plausibly
suggesting that this could genuinely
help students learn and improve their
their life outcomes and other kinds of
things like that. Um and the and the way
you do that is through an inter you know
through a social psychological
intervention. Although it's you know not
clear to me what in schools is not
social psychological.
I was going to say another thing that as
much as like we need the two populations
to be like just as representative are
the experimental groups even
representative of the general population
like you have to imagine that people
aren't being forced to participate in
these things or maybe if they are like
the schools that they chose are they
actually representative of the entire
population. So because like there
obviously are studies where they get
like outstanding results but then the
population used is not representative of
the general population. So then once
they apply those doesn't actually work.
Yeah. Yeah. Good. Um you know and to
some extent you might think that
organizations like Pearson would have an
advantage over much smaller companies um
because if you have products that are
adopted very very widely across the
country in lots of different contexts. I
mean, you might for practical purposes
say like, let's just pick these handful
of schools um to be able to test things
in, but you could say like we're going
to pick these handful of of schools
because like these are particularly
representative schools. Um or, you know,
there might be systems that are that are
adopted and laid out in such a way that
you say like, well, let's, you know,
let's just pick 1% of all students in
any of the schools who are using our
system to get, you know, um participate
in this randomized study or something
like that. I feel like we talked a lot
about like all of the things that go
into using like a software program
because obviously that then entails that
you have something to run the software
program on. So anything online already
comes with its own set of like biases
and um like things that affect the types
of people that are using it. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. No, I think that's fair. Also,
another thing that I just realized in
what uh Dana said was the population
that that they're testing this on is in
college. So, they've already probably
developed a mindset. Um and also they
are in college. Like they probably have
already a good enough mindset that got
them to college. Yep. Yep. although that
you know I mean and um well one thing
that I really love about the study which
I think um so so I I wrote some after
this article came out um I wrote a bunch
of things which which basically said I
think this is a pretty unfair article.
Um here I'll give you the case for why I
I I think what Pearson did here is
admirable and needs to be done more
although you don't have to agree with
me. Um so number one
um generally speaking there's a body of
research that suggests these things are
a good idea. We don't know however are
they a good idea in this particular
product for this particular population.
So I think it makes more sense um to run
an experiment in this particular product
for this particular population to test
the thing rather than just roll it out.
I mean this is an important sort of
counterfactual. If Pearson had simply
added these messages to everyone in the
product, there never would have been an
article about it. Um, nobody would have
ever written, you know, like like like
you know, encouraging messages show up
in software product is like not an
article that even the education press um
is going to populate. Um, number two,
you know, like another counterfactual,
there is no nonsocial psychological
response um to like every mark your
teacher has ever put on your paper to
indicate whether you're right or wrong
is a social psychological message. Um,
if you go on edex and get something
right, you're going to get a green
check. If you're going to get something
wrong, you're going to get a red X. Like
that is a set of messaging. If you've
ever had a, you know, none of us would
say that teachers who say try harder or
that was great. I'm really proud of you.
Like no one would be like, you know,
Miss Jenkins, stop manipulating my
children. Like no, that's like exactly
what we want them to do. Um
uh some people are concerned um about
consent. Um people who go to school do
not consent to their learning
experiences. Um, one of the things that
we do as a state is say like you must
learn stuff and in fact you must learn
stuff that the state just requires you
to learn. Um, you don't get you know um
these people didn't get to decide which
Pearson product or which computer
science project they they chose. Um why
should they get to decide whether or not
they get an experimental version or a
control version? And in fact um uh the
US government for the most part agrees
with this principle. So um there's a
rule called the common rule um which
dictates how research can be conducted.
Um uh there's a bunch of policy guidance
that's associated with that and there's
some categories of research that are
exempt. The first category of research
that's exempt is research about typical
educational practices. Um if you're
studying the kinds of ways people teach
and learn in the classroom, you are not
held to the same standard if you're
doing pharmaceutical research or
something like that. Um there are some
there are some exception like if you're
doing things that you that like you
could reasonably believe in advance um
might harm people um then you're not
exempted in the same way although you
can still conceivably uh do the
research. Um you know another thing
that's important about the study is that
um like people people talk about the
potential benefits of an experiment um
but experiments can also harm people.
Like it it could be that even if on
average this growth messaging was great
and worked in lots of studies, it could
be that like in this particular context
or other kinds of things um uh it made
things worse and we should probably make
sure that when we introduce things in
the classroom make things worse. Um, how
many people would have been concerned?
Let's say that in
2017 they had everyone use one Pearson
product maybe that doesn't have any
growth messaging and in 2018 everyone
use a Pearson product that had the
messaging associated with it. Um, do you
think that would have raised people's
concern or felt
creepy? Like why not? Why does that feel
okay?
You're like, "Wait a minute, it's the
exact same thing." I think there's this
idea of
like potential discrimination, like,
"Hey, why can't I be part of that?"
Like, it's either everybody or nobody.
But part the more an intervention is
particularly powerful, the more you're
like, ah, it feels kind of like if you
know control group like gets this
intervention and gets an average grade
of 89. Um, an experimental group, you
know, gets the intervention and they
have an average grade of 89.5. Like
that's there's something that seems
unfair about that. Although again like
you know if in 2018 we give you a
software product that you get an average
grade of an 89 and then the following
year we give you a software product with
an average grade of
89.5. Um like your birth year was pretty
random
too. And so there's something about
that. I mean you know the case I want to
make is that here here's another way to
think about it.
Um most people would be appalled by an
education system that didn't have
variation. Like my hunch is all of you
believe that variation is an essential
part of educational systems. Like you
believe that your teachers, your public
your p your textbook publishers, your
software developers should be trying to
improve their products. Um they should
be trying to improve their instruction.
They should be trying to improve their
lesson plans. The only way you do that
is through variation. You teach one
lesson plan one year, you teach a
different lesson plan the next year.
Sometimes it's better, sometimes it
works. My hunch is you all are totally
comfortable with the idea that some of
that variation will be bad um and that
most of it on average will be good. Um
the main thing that randomized trials
like this do is they take that variation
and they make it systematic so we can
learn from it. Um if we do one thing in
2017 and a different thing in 2018, it's
actually it's actually much much harder
to figure out if the different thing
worked or not. um because all the people
in 2017 might be in some systematic way
different from the people in 2018 when
we the the best way to be sure that the
difference between two groups is just
because of the thing we're intervening
about is a randomized trial. That is the
magic of randomized trial. Um so they
are power like like everyone in the
education system believes in variation.
We all want things to improve.
Um, it's actually not that hard to
convince people that the best way to
systematically vary things is through
randomization. Um, and almost all of us
find that randomization creepy. Um, like
even if you sort of explain all, you're
like, ah, it still doesn't feel right.
Still doesn't feel there's there's been
some cool studies I've done in the past.
It shows up in healthcare, shows up in
other kinds of, you know, things like um
uh you know, you ask patients like, "Do
you want an unproven treatment that
might work better?" And they'll be like,
"Well, yeah, maybe." Um, do you want to
be randomized to an unproven treatment
that might work better? No. Definitely.
It's like it's the same thing. Um,
except we can learn from the
randomization. Um my question is in this
case like how are
these different from like when companies
release
betas that some people get and some
people don't? Oh here's I mean every
time you interact with a software
product every time you interact with a
web-based software product there is a
reasonable chance you're participating
in an experiment just like this. Um one
this the numbers won't be right. One out
of every hundred times you go to Amazon,
um the buy button is going to be green
instead of blue. And someone is doing a
test to figure out whether or not you
pushing the green button is better. um
you know, one out of every hundred time
or thousand times or 10 times you go to
Google, they're going to give you some
variation of the search algorithm to see
if you're happier or you linger longer
or you're more likely to click ads on,
you know, um we interact every day with
software platforms that are collecting
vast amounts of information on us and
conducting experiments on us all the
time.
Um th though the reason why those
companies use those two approaches is
because they are enormously powerful at
improving products. Um the reason why
just about any query you have you go
into Google and ask it a question and it
tells you an accurate answer that's
relevant to the question you asked is
because they have conducted billions of
experiments on millions or billions of
people uh all throughout the last you
know 20 25 years that they've been
operating. um it is an like an essential
part of our software infrastructure. Um
and um I don't like I don't know does
the idea that you are are participating
in experiments all the time when you go
Amazon shopping like does that does does
that have the same level of creepiness
to you like for some it's like yeah Jeff
Bezos do whatever you want but but like
but you know but but we feel differently
about Pearson for some reason. I have a
question about like beyond the like is
this creepy or not creepy question but
like if I'm a I have decided to buy a
product like I'm paying to use Amazon or
I'm paying to use Pearson and with that
is the assumption that like I understand
the thing I am buying because you
pitched it to a certain way and I will
get it. So then like how does the
question of like are you allowed or not
allowed to do this go from there? And it
would be a and it would be a a huge
difference from historical educational
curriculum material purchases. Like it
used to be, you know, like I bought uh
you know, H Hotton Mifflin biology eth
edition and I just know exactly what's
in eth edition. Like and in fact, you
know, the salesperson is going to come
back when ninth edition's going to come
out and they're going to be like, here's
what's different about ninth edition,
why you could buy it. And I might be
like, no, I don't like what you did in
ninth edition. um I'm going to switch to
a different company's products because
these these improvements are not
improvements. Um yeah. Um under what
circumstances should companies be able
to dynamically improve their educational
products? Um what kind of information
should they make accessible about that?
Um should they tell families? Should
they tell educators? Should they tell
you know my people could come up with
different answer to these questions. Um,
I think actually publishing a bunch of
that information is probably enormously
important, but not to parents and
teachers and educators. Parents and
teachers and educators have no time to
be like tracking how your Pearson
computer science like practice problems
are changing. Um, there are specialized
advocates across the country who focus
on education, who focus on student
privacy or other kinds of things who
like actually would have the time and
expertise to follow those audit records.
Um but like you know if we started
sending home a notice to parents every
time a you know a company who used one
of their products was conducting an
experiment people like it would just be
you know the the back it would be the
terms and service conditions of your um
presumably too by the way um it's it's
very unlikely that when whatever school
bought this Pearson product presumably
that like their lawyers are competent
and they made them sign a purchase and
sale agreement that included these kinds
of conditions in them. Although it's
also not it's also the case that like
you know the researchers who did this
thing didn't sit down with these schools
and are like let me tell you what we're
doing in the next phase so that you you
know I mean they might I think in this
case they didn't give them much
indication. Um
um would it be like like I guess back to
the conversation of like if it's like
creepy or not. Do you think it might
have anything to do with like the
illusion of choice that you're given?
Like for example, like if you're on
Amazon or something, you can or like if
if if you're on an app, you have the
choice like sometimes not to update the
app and just stay on the previous y
setting or like if you have something
like Amazon, like you can not use Amazon
or like you you're you're perceiving it
as like you're choosing to opt into
that. Well, like in a situation where
like you have to use a certain
technology in school, like you could
argue that like this student doesn't
have a choice to opt out of this if they
like and you could and you could see
that choice operating at different
levels. So, a grade school student has
zero choice about whether or not to go
to grade school. Every college student
chose to go to college. Um, now sort of
like once you've chosen to go to
college, it doesn't it doesn't feel like
that should mean you have to accept
everything that comes along with
college. Um, although again like you
know you don't like like you know you
could you could choose some majors over
other majors based on the technology.
You choose some classes over classes. Um
the moment in recently in which some of
this most came into focus was when
schools started requiring students to
adopt um proctoring software. Um so
probably none of you have have any of
you ever taken a remotely proctored test
um at MIT?
Where where did you take a remotely
proctor test at MIT? Uh I believe uh
there was the ASC during my like
freshman like starting year. They used
like some weird proctoring software for
that where you had to like like take
your webcam or take your laptop or
webcam show the rest of your room all
these kinds of things essentially. Good.
Um so uh there are a number of cases
where um for instance uh universities
implemented this kind of proctoring
software mid-semester
um and in fact implemented it
mid-semester and required students to
pay for it. Um that like you can imagine
that as a set of circumstances which
like most draws the eye of people
because like I've like I've already
committed to this college, I've already
committed to this course. Now you're
making me you know essentially install
spyware on my machine. um you know and
then like I don't know have some random
person see what my dorm room looks like
and other kinds of or my bedroom you
know these sort of things seem creepy um
arguably maybe they're less creepy the
more that they're disclosed to people
over time although I also use the phrase
illusion of choice um because in fact
for lots of things you know for instance
like every there are no cell service
companies that compete on the basis of
not selling your location data um like
it is not really a choice to not have a
mobile phone um anymore in society and
so you're not really ch like um you know
in theory that's a choice but it's not
really one you know going to college
like for some people is not really a
choice like you're going to have to go
to choice to have the life that you want
and things like that um uh but I do but
I do think K12 students in particular
now another sort of unusual feature of
this is that and it goes back to this
sort of data collection um you know K12
many K12 students across the country are
mandated to create a Google account. Um,
and then Google has reams of data about
all these kinds of things that they uh
that they that they do with that data.
Um, and uh um you know and there might
be various ways that again you know so
should like to what extent these things
are legitimate or not. It's probably
much less of a debate these days, but
definitely when schools were first
adopting Google for education. Um, it
was not uncommon to hear that school
boards had uh really vigorous complaints
from parents. And oftentimes the com the
most vigorous complaints came from
parents who worked in the software
industry. Um, like do like I know who
these people are. I work for these
companies. Um, how are you going to make
my kid do these kinds of things? Um,
let's talk about another one of these
cases.
Um so another story that you read about
was in Bloom um in 2013. So um the Gates
Foundation along with a number of other
organizations, Wireless Generation, some
other people sort of observed like man
here's a weird thing. um
companies who serve schools have tons of
data about students and sort of the only
way we can make this system work or the
way the system currently works is like
some company goes to a school district
and says we'll operate this service for
you but here's all the data we need. Um
and the schools are like yeah okay deal.
Um, and if you make enough of those
kinds of arrangements, I mean, we
another exercise we could do here is
like make a list of all of the
educational software products that
you've ever used in schools. Um, and you
all could probably come up with lists of
like dozens or more software products
that you've encountered in some kind of
way. Those are all people that have some
kind of data about you somewhere. Um,
that seems like a terrible
infrastructure. Like you require people
to go to schools. um the schools make
contracts with third parties to provide
services and all those third parties end
up with sort of shards of data. Um so
the idea of inbloom
was let's concentrate all of the data
about students in one nonprofit
organization. Um let's get let's you
know it be something along the lines of
trying to generate the kind of data set
that the Norwegian study that I just
showed you would require. Um like let's
get all their student records. let's get
all their let's get let's get all all
their app usage let's get all those
kinds of things um and have a nonprofit
entity hold on to that data um and in
particular let's make it so that instead
of um companies making arrangements with
individual school districts to get
access to the data they need they just
get in touch with this nonprofit
um now what could potentially be good
about having a nonprofit intermediary
between schools and third parties that
want to provide services to schools but
require data to do
it. I think public perception is that
nonprofits are a lot more trustworthy
than for-profit companies so people
won't get as freaked out about it. Yeah.
Good. So, do you want like Pearson to
have all of this data or do you want,
you know, InBloom um, you know, funded
by a consortium of state departments of
I mean, it was funded by the Gates
Foundation, but like sponsored by a set
of state departments of education to
have this data. What else?
I had a question like how it functions.
So like if they have the data and then
um like a company or some kind of
researcher is trying to access it, do
they have final say on like how it's
being used or do they then go back to
the schools? So as so the go so in bloom
failed and we can talk about why it
failed so you don't have to worry about
it existing although I'll show you a new
thing that showed up this past week
which is remarkably similar. Um but I
think some of the key value some of the
key value proposition was that the
companies would go to Inloom um and get
just the data they need. What do you
think InBloom would potentially be
better at than schools might be
raw data processing? Good. So, first of
all, they're just like if if if your if
your job is not to like, you know, teach
kindergarten and Mandarin, but like just
to process student data, you're probably
going to be better at processing student
data than this organization that has to
like have a field hockey team and run
buses and other kinds of things like
that.
Security is better, too, if that's your
main focus. Why would there are 13,000
school districts in the United States of
widely varying capacities in all kinds
of IT things? It seems like an
organization that is like just focused
on IT things is going to be like we
don't even like in a lot of ways if you
have a society where a school has to be
good at IT things you may not be
organizing that society correctly. Um
and so you can you know if you go to
other countries you know during the
pandemic like we had um schools
provision laptops and hotspots to to
students. Insane. There's no reason to
think schools should be any good at
that. um like there should be other
institutions in society that are good at
IT procurement like it it shouldn't be
your local I mean I sometimes I would
compare it to people like you know in
the 19th century when we decided that
every household in the United States
should get or in the 20th century we
decided every household in the United
States should get electricity we like
didn't go to the local school principal
and be like so how are you going to run
wires up the holler um you know we
invented the TVA and other kinds of
organizations that was really good at
electrification um so that the schools
didn't have to be good at
electrification like electrification is
is closer to you know provisioning
broadband and laptops um than it is to
other kinds of educational things. All
right. So these institutions um could
conceivably develop a whole bunch of
expertise around data around privacy
things like that. Um another thing that
they could probably get pretty good at
doing is only giving providers the exact
data they need. Um, so schools have a
tough time vetting like all of the data
that they're making available to all
their different providers. And so
presumably, you know, they make
arrangements and people just collect
whatever. If there's a sort of
intermediary in that collection process,
you could imagine that InBloom could be
pretty good at being like, "Yeah,
Canvas, you just asked us for these 14
things, but I'm pretty sure to operate
your system, you need these six." Um, so
why don't you start with these six and
see how you do from there. um and they
might be able to do all kinds of other
you know right now for Canvas to operate
it needs to have um you know your actual
email address and other kinds of things
like that. You can imagine building all
kinds of intermediary layers that that
only hashed identifiers are passing on
to these third parties and in Bloom
collects all this.
Um in Bloom fails um oh almost
immediately. Um well here's a here's a
few things that were written about it
when it started.
Um, nonprofit InBloom offers an internet
database service that allows schools to
store, track, and analyze data on school
chunking. If you think about it, that
information is more than just test
scores. It's whether kids receive free
lunch, a telling indicator of the
family's finance. The time the school
got no fight in the schoolyard. It could
be a child's prescription medicine. Um,
the upshot of storing all that data in
one location is it could be used to
tailor curricula to each child. If
Johnny's data suggests he's a tactile
learner, which is not true, there are no
learning styles. Um, and he's failing
math, Inloom's analytic action might
suggest a particular teaching approach.
Um, this is all about building
personalized learning environments for
kids. Um, but as more school districts
team up with Inloom, including New York,
parents are becoming increasingly vocal
critics of the data collection. This
information, I have no idea what it is.
I have no idea who's using it, and I
have no idea for what purpose. Um
uh so part of what the existence of
InBloom did was to like was to go to
communities and be like, "Hey, you know
what's happening right now? There's tons
of data being collected about children."
Um and we're going to put it all in one
place. You can imagine that, you know,
like for people like me, they're like,
"Yeah, that's a great idea. We're
totally going to be able to have all
these benefits." But like there's tons
of data being collected about children
and it's all going to be put in one
place. is like not actually as it turns
out a very popular public pitch. Um in
Bloom CEO is quick to point out that the
company isn't collecting data the this
isn't collecting data the school
districts don't already have. It's just
providing a one-stop dot to make the
data accessible and usable to teachers.
Although really a lot of what it was
doing was making the data accessible and
usable to third parties which might then
benefit teachers. Schools and districts
collect a lot of data but it's all over
the place. Strainberger says it's it's
different systems are disconnected and
so as a result this data is not usable.
Can anybody think of of uh all right so
that that was a very serious problem
like schools are collecting tons of data
it's fragmented across all these
services all these kinds of things and
so you know a sense there's like
constant ongoing privacy like either
privacy risk privacy violations and um
not sensible ways to manage them. That's
the problem in Bloom's trying to solve.
Can anybody think of around 2013 like
major things that are happening in the
United States related to uh people's
perception of their data and
security? You all are a little young for
this now. Target target I think is not
that far away from that. So we start
seeing some of the like major data
security breaches. Cambridge Analytica
uh I think um I think Cambridge
Analytica is a little bit afterwards
because that is around the 2016
election. Yeah. Snowden. Um, this is the
sort of Edward the Edward Snowden era of
uh of of rec recognizing the federal
government is collecting much more data
about people um than was previously
thought. So, so in 2013, first of all,
people are far less accustomed to
surveillance than you all described
yourself as accustomed to surveillance.
Um, and there just been this major
national revelation. Sort of an
interesting thing about the inloom story
is so eventually what happens is there
were sort of 11 states that signed on
initially and the hope was is that like
then 13 and 14 and 18 and 20 that
eventually lots and lots of states would
come on almost immediately states
started withdrawing from it. um in
particular over uh in part because of
the concentrated objection from local
advocates uh lo local advocacy groups
including um like student privacy groups
that were just formed around this time.
New York was like one of the lead ones.
It was one of the last ones to fall out
but it also had one of the most sort of
viciferous determined um community of
student privacy advocates um opting you
know. So um state started p like one of
the one of the main um outcomes of
inloom was not its existence actually
but like a bunch of state laws about
student privacy in part that would make
it more difficult for things like inloom
to exist. um a a a common problem that
shows up when trying to fix data and
privacy problems and I'm giving you an
example from schools but this is a thing
that you could find in almost any um uh
in any other sector like the the
pre-inloom counterfactual is really
really bad. It is not a good system to
like force kids to go to public schools
and then have a bunch of thirdparty
for-profit companies get their data from
schools. The schools are bad at
managing. they don't have the expertise,
all these kinds of things.
Um however by trying to fix the problem
in bloom draws attention to the problem
you know like man this data is such a
mess and we're going to collect it all
like in some like there are all kinds of
circumstances in which you like if you
draw attention to data and experiments
even if the sort of like the the status
quo is really terrible people are not
going to be enthusiastic about the fix
because nobody thinks dayto-day about
the status quo but they think really
intensely about this crazy inloom thing
that you're doing. Um, does that does
that as an idea make sense? Like this
essentially, you know, there's all kind
like other studies come out along the
lines of um, hey, we've come up with
this really good way to protect your
privacy. Will you opt into it? People
will be like, whoa. Um, why would why
would I have to protect my privacy? Why
would I opt into this thing? It's
dangerous. Like, they would prefer the
status quo where their privacy is not
protected towards this thing in which
you've raised their concerns about. Um
uh so this is an organization that just
came into life um last week. Uh it's
called Safe Insights. Um it was funded
by $90 million from the National Science
Foundation. Uh it is out of Rice
University out of the same people that
developed Open Stacks. We talked about
Open Stacks the other day. They're the
company that creates um uh free and open
source textbooks for community college
folks. Um they
have we have enough time. I'll show you
the one.
Uh, let's see if we can find the the
Safe Insights welcome
video. As a longtime college instructor,
every day of my career has been
dedicated to helping my students reach
their academic goals. I'm always looking
to better support their learning in ways
that are proven to work best. There's so
much we have to understand about how
people learn. Every mind is beautiful
and special. That means we all learn in
different ways. We all have our own
definitions of what success looks like.
If researchers are able to uncover new
and better ways of learning, that will
have a profound impact on how educators
approach teaching. To do this, we need a
way to securely connect with a wide
variety of students as they study over
time in real
classrooms. Student needs are changing.
With more learning happening online, it
gets harder and harder to understand
what each student needs and how best to
help them at the moment when they're
really needed the most. Education
research is essential for advancing
teaching and learning so that every
student can succeed. We know that
research informed teaching works, but
it's still too hard to conduct
large-scale reliable research and then
apply the results in the classroom. Safe
Insights brings together learning
researchers, educators, schools, and
colleges in a secure environment to get
the answers we need while strongly
protecting students and their interests.
Every student deserves the chance to
succeed in the classroom and beyond.
Safe Insights will give researchers,
educators, and students what they need
to take learning to the next level. And
as educators, we will benefit from
better research from Safe Insights to
effectively help all our students.
[Music]
Great.
It it is it is a little dramatic for for
like a
database but I I mean I don't know I
like database. Okay. Um what are what
are what are your first instincts having
spent a whole bunch of time um uh having
spent you know an hour and 20 minutes
talking about the toxic power of data
and experiments and how do you think
like a typical American parent or
typical American college student would
react to that video?
I think it would change like based on
different generations because I think
our generation who is now like using Tik
Tok when we openly know like they use
our data and like listen to us is
completely different from like our
parents who are like oh my god like
don't have a profile picture don't this
and that. So I think our generation will
be way more accepting of this and I
think as like in like 10 20 years down
the line I think people and parents will
be so accustomed to their children's
data just being like whatever good. So
you know so conceivably even you know in
bloom launched today might have had a
very different experience than in Bloom
launched in 2013 not because of anything
different that they did but because of
the context that they operate in. I
think there's evidence of that. I was
just talking to somebody who runs a a
video repository for uh child
development studies. Um and one of their
conditions is that uh the the videos can
only be used for non-commercial
purposes. And I was like, how you know
why did you do that? And we're like,
well, we made it 10 years ago and people
were really worried about stuff and that
sort of helped calm them down. But if we
did it again today, I you know, I don't
think the same level of concern exists,
not only among people generally, but
like institutionally as well. What do
you say, Courtney? Um I think it was
really smart that they've attached
themselves to Rice because I think
especially like our parents generation
maybe less so now there's a lot of
goodwill given to universities and so
like if in Bloom came out today and it
was like oh in partnership with MIT I do
think people would have received it a
lot differently and like people have a
lot of trust that like oh it's connected
to Rice how bad could it really be?
Yeah. And you know I would say I would
say the the Gates Foundation related
conspiracy theories were not quite as
strong in 2013. Um but like the Gates
Foundation is not a trusted organization
in the same way that I think uh yeah
Rice University universities in general
like state schools um are still some of
the most trusted institutions in
society.
Um I think like maybe actually a little
um connected to that trustworthiness I
think is that um if you say like oh my
god look all your data is in one place
like to someone who finds like education
research and things like that really
important and is like much more aware of
um like how that might help that might
sound good but I think to the average
person first and foremost what's going
to pop out when you tell tell them, "Oh,
we have everything in one place and we
promise it's safe." It's like one, like
you're not giving me any information
about how you're keeping the data safe.
And two, like I think like it's always
been like set up like don't put all your
data in one place. So it's like well how
why are you like saying this is a good
thing because then this means that like
someone can have all my data as opposed
to like let's say if it is split up even
if it's there I can be like okay like my
teacher might have this piece of data on
me but they might not have this other
piece of data and actually probably the
main technical I mean there'll probably
a bunch and we don't know exactly where
they'll be then but one of the one of
the earliest proposed technical
innovations of safe insights is not to
bring all the data together. Um so it so
it doesn't propose that all of it gets
collected. One of the main things that
they want to be able to do um is to be
able to conduct research queries across
data without having people have to
directly access those data. So there's a
there's a whole field of study called
things like differential privacy and
stuff like that which basically says um
how do I how do I tell you the kinds of
things that are in a data set let you
run a query over that data set um but
never actually encounter that data set
and and in this kind of environment
there might be how would you run a query
that connects people's you know student
behavior in a learning platform with
their registar information with their
state test scores without having to like
make one giant data set out of all those
things, but instead to like, you know,
have the query just, you know, run over
the data it needs, you know, still like
have the main the people who own that
data still hold on to that data, but
have the results of that query go to
technology developers, um, researchers,
things like that without having to have
them collect all of the data. So in some
ways it's like explicitly trying to be
the opposite of inloom like don't bring
all the data in one place like try to
get the benefits of aggregated data
without having to share it with either a
trusted third party or everyone or
something like that.
I was I was just going to say I feel
like you kind of answered it like right
there with what you were saying, but
like in your opinion, do you think like
the people who are creating this new um
the safe insights? Do you think they
like really understood what went wrong
in Inloom? And do you think like
ultimately does it lead back? Boy, it
sure I mean it sure sounds like it to
me. Like powerful privacy preserving
learning research. Um, so like the very
first concept they they want to ingrain
in your head is safe. Um, the second
concept that I think they're doing
rhetorically is leaning into insight
rather than data. Um, so I think if you
asked people what Inbloom was, they
would have described it as some kind of
data repository. My hunch um is that the
safe insights people are going to
describe themselves as an insight
generator. um as a research producer.
Now, it's the exact same thing, right?
Um because in order to get the insights,
you have to have the data somewhere. And
InBloom, InBloom's purpose was never
just to like hoard data. It was to make
learning better for kids. Um but I think
I think there are I like I guarantee you
that all of the pe many of the people
who worked on safe insights um have done
plenty of studying of what went wrong
with in bloom um and are designing this
enterprise you know so that it's you
know it's with a trusted university it's
founded by the national science
foundation which I assume also has very
high trust but like all this language it
it definitely strikes me as like like
people who read up on the inb bloom case
study and are trying a different tack.
I think uh another good thing that they
did was associate themselves with a
previous product that was successful
which was open stacks which in itself
open stacks I mean they are open what is
it open source uh like preuse uh
textbooks and that in itself has proven
to be like okay we are transparent quite
literally transparent about what we're
doing and we've already provided a
useful successful product for the masses
and there
Um they have a ton you know they have uh
40 partners 39 collaborating
institutions of their collaborating
institutions 77% are minority serving
institutions so they're trying to start
from the beginning saying you know we're
not just going to do this to improve
Colombia and Rice we're going to do this
to improve you know lots of different
kinds of organizations
um it it also you know instead of being
a consortium of states
um it's really mostly a consortium of
digital learning platforms. Um probably
matters to like they're
emphasis on college. Um I'm like
assistance doesn't do anything for
college. So they definitely have some
things that are not I'm not sure it's
literally true, but Assistments 99% of
what they do is serve K12 students. Um,
but I think it maybe does make a
difference to, you know, in like like
college students are adults. College
students opt in to go to college. The
state doesn't force anyone to go to
college. And so you're just operating in
a um in you maybe a luury choice, but
there you're operating in a in a space
where you feel like people have more
agency to begin with to operate. Um they
they you know unlike unlike Inloom which
said these 11 states are the
organization like these state education
agencies are sort of the key people
we're interacting with um they don't
mention higher education accredititors
or state boards of higher education or
they basically have like left government
out except for the National Science
Foundation um of this development. Maybe
people are more trustworthy of of these
organizations or maybe they're just like
even if they're not more trustworthy of
these organizations, people are kind of
drawn, critics are potentially drawn to
things like New York State approves X,
you know, versus this kind of like
arbitrary group of universities, some of
whom might be in New York, approve X.
Um, so it'll be super interesting to
watch. This is a um the grant that they
got was from the same that $90 million
is probably the largest federal grant uh
um an educational research project ever.
Although there's a couple of educational
research projects that if you totaled up
all the grants they got over a period of
time might be sort of at least within
that ballpark. Um it came from the same
grant funding that supports like
telescopes and ecological plots. um it's
called midscale uh research
infrastructure things that are like um
where you know no one university can
build like a giant radio telescope and
and you don't want one university to you
want to build a thing that like the
entire field of astronomy can all
collectively use together um and so this
grant stream is meant to build enormous
things that everyone can can use
together so it'll be sort of interesting
to see what they do um in the in the
decades ahead but um I think a I mean
you know in some ways especially coming
about 10 years after the collapse of
Inloom. Um, uh, it's to me it's sort of
neat. You know, people still have
optimism that if you pull together a
bunch of student learning data, um, and
data about students and you conduct a
bunch of experiments, you can build
things that help them learn better. Um,
but there are, you know, there are re
there are enormous real risks and there
may be even more enormous um, kind of
reputational risks that go into this
work. Um, one thing that I've tried to
communicate, which it sounds like these
folks are, you know, are adopting to
many different groups is like, you know,
because I'm basically part of the
community of people that would like to
collect lots of data about students than
I've done, you know, re, you know, I've
I've I've handled data files that have
like way more information about people
than I feel comfortable having access
to. Um, and part of the job is doing
things responsibly, but the other part
of the job is like constantly talking to
the public about what we're doing. Um,
you know, the only way people will not
be creeped out by doing experiments, um,
is if a we conduct a bunch of
experiments that meaningfully improve
learning. Um, a hu a huge challenge that
education has, um, is like we don't have
the equivalent of the human genome
project. We don't have a thing that you
could point to being like, well, yeah,
we took a whole lot of your data, but
like we're curing cancer here, people.
Um, you know, I mean, if if Safe
Insights came up with something that
made students learn math 33% faster, it
would totally change the way people
think about the collection of D. So,
your costbenefit data would transform um
uh quite dramatically. Um, but even in
the absence of that, like it's
incredibly important to be engaged with
these student privacy groups, engaged
with families, trying to explain to
people like there's always going to be
variation in education. Um, what we
probably could benefit the most from is
systematic variation where we can tell
which parts of the variation work and
which parts don't. And the only way that
we can do that is through some of these
approaches that include data collection
and randomization and things like that.
So you just like made the statement that
like safe insights comes up with like
some solution. So is safe insights kind
of like that is it like a third party
that is it is less of a third party than
in bloom. Yes. you know, like clearly
some of the things that that Rice is
going to do with his money is build
systems and study open stacks with it.
Um, like part like much more so than
Inloom. Um, in in Bloom didn't have a In
Bloom never, to my knowledge, never had
a list of partners that looked like this
list. Um, they never said from the
beginning, oh look, like Cahoot and
Google Classroom and the all these other
people are our lead partners. um and are
going to use this to figure out stuff.
They they like really saw themselves
solving an infrastructural problem um
more that you know like I I think these
folks are positioning themselves more
like first we're going to have a set of
tech products that improve learning um
through better research practices
including better forms of data
management and data sharing and data
privacy. Um, but if it like if it's a
real infrastructure product, like part
of what you know, I'm I'm sure Rich's
goal um is to say we're going to develop
these research these privacy protecting
research enclaves and we're going to
develop them in an open source way that
like whatever future edtech companies
come along are going to be able to
benefit from this infrastructure. Like
they're going to be able to do all the
same kinds of things that OpenStacks is
doing to conduct cool experimental
research with lots of data while
protecting people's privacy. Um,
Great. It's 2:25. Um, so I should let
you go. We'll come in on Wednesday. Um,
and we'll you have a little bit of
reading about implementation in schools.
Um, but mostly uh what you should be
working on is um getting some words on
paper for your final product um project
and thinking a little bit. Oh, a thing
that we'll do probably by email this
week, but maybe a bit in class on
Wednesday is I need you to sign up um to
either present on Monday or Wednesday.
Um, maybe I'll send you something pretty
soon that invites you to sign up for one
of those two slots.