hello everyone I'm Manisha and I'm here
with telis technology presenting before
you all sense Symphony a technology
platform which will bring you closer to
reality most of the multi-sensory
experiences generally have audio visual
and nowadays even haptics but something
is generally missing out there and that
is the sense of smell we are trying to
solve this
problem mainly the scent issue has been
used lot many times as an example in
different VR situations in theaters but
we Face a small problem there and that
is related to the storage or the
handling sometimes it relates to the
cross-contamination of the fragrances
within the system and even in the
environment once they're dispensed and
the ventilation issue as we continue to
solve these problems through our
technology which we developed at MIT and
later on after I graduated from the
program we can now uh provide scent
modules of different form factors in
different sizes even in the shape of a
button as well but what's unique about
our technology is the way we encapsulate
these fragrances we make sure that they
are not anym in liquid format and cannot
be oxidized directly in air our
technology ensures that the fragrances
we encapsulate live for longer period of
time somewhere between few months to few
years as
well with s Symphony we are trying to
empower and make the experiences more
and more immersive in 2D virtual reality
in communal spaces and even in personal
spaces where you just exposed to
fragrance near your space our journey
started with just doing um some uh pilot
projects here and there and we
accidentally landed up a project related
in uh VR movies in Hollywood movie
called as LM musk it takes a minute to
example of what we did um and how this
impacted in the VR space we um demoed
our work at K and then got the LA
Infinity award as well some of the
testimonies are here could see why he
was the originator of this piece you
notice different scents in the
experience um they were all I think
they're all like kind of custom made for
the film that's what I heard it's
phenomenal I think was
but now we're going a step forward we
are trying to integrate our platform
with generative AI so we can throw in
any kind of multimedia XR VR videos and
generate sense for any platform our our
system has incorporated more than 3,000
ing uh fragrance ingredients which again
dispense any kind of fragrance just like
an AI perfumer would do on the Fly this
is how we we do it our technology uses
local models which are deployed with our
overlaying technology and using all
those cues we are able to pick up the
kinesthetics the emotions the uh
pictorial imagery and then dispense a
related fragrance the back end U I would
like to explain here for any common
person who's looking at these two images
would be like oh wow this is a fruit
basket what's the real difference but
with our technology we are able to give
a final odor as an output which is more
closer to a real human experience as you
can see here a cut mango uh picture is
going to actually smell like a final
mango scent whereas in the other case
it's more on the citrusy side has a
banana note to it um our team has
expertise uh looking at fragrances in
wide spectrum uh we've been working in
the space since 2016 while I started my
SE Arch at MIT exploring how fragrances
can impact sexual arousal and then we
delved into developing uh scent cameras
and examining fragrances and how they
impact human physiology so what's next
we are developing the world's first
digital sent library and we are looking
to collaborate with people in the scent
industry in retail in fashion in um
experimental design and also an arvr
thank you