Good morning everybody. Welcome to the
first MPG primer of the season.
I am thrilled to uh introduce Dan
Snellings. He's a posttock in the Walsh
lab at Boston Children's Hospital. He
received his PhD at Duke University
working with Douglas Marchuk studying
how somatic mutations drive the
formation and progression of vascular
mal formations. Currently he's in the
Walsh lab and he is developing methods
for tracking cell lineage using somatic
mutations and applying them to
understand the impact of somatic
mutations somatic mosaicism in neiro
neurop fibro mitosis.
Um but that's actually not what he's
talking about today at all. He's talking
about the awesome power of genetic
linkage. Um and this is something that
comes up often with uh trainee trying to
understand LD. um is extremely important
and uh they're excited to have them.
Please ask questions throughout. There's
microphones um in the center and we'll
also have time at the end for questions.
>> Thank you Dan.
>> Great.
>> All right. Thanks so much Michelle for
the introduction and for the invitation
to give this talk. It's my pleasure to
give a more basic talk today that's uh
not so much about my specific science
though there might be a little bit about
that at the end uh and more about the
basic concept of genetic linkage and
linkage disequilibrium and phasing and
how this is one of the most important
tools that we use as geneticists
u and so I figured today that I would
take more of a historical perspective on
linkage to kind of understand how we got
to where we are and hopefully in the
process learn a little bit about linkage
LD and phasing
Uh and so naturally when starting a
discussion about linkage the best place
to start is by talking about hair uh and
specifically my hair and uh how I'm
blessed to have a full head of it uh
because looking at my family tree it's
not really clear how long that's going
to be the case.
And so male pattern baldness has long
been known to have a very strong
hereditary component, but the mechanism
of inheritance had not been known for a
long time. Some really early studies had
suggested that it was autoomal dominant
in males and autoomal recessive in
females while other studies and common
folklore had suggested it was actually
an XL trait and so came from the
mother's side of the family. And so in
2005, Axel Hillar and his colleagues set
out to actually find the location of the
gene that causes male pattern baldness.
Uh and so they knew that the gene or at
least they suspected that the gene was
on the X chromosome, but they didn't
know exactly where it was. And so they
performed a really classic linkage study
where selecting just a group of 95
families and genotyping just a few dozen
markers on the X chromosome, they were
able to narrow the location of the gene
causing male pattern baldness to a
window on the P arm of chromosome X. And
so here at the bottom you can see the
different markers that they genotyped in
the assay. And note that this was before
we had things like snip chips and next
generation sequencing. So all of this
was done manually by I'm sure graduate
students and postocs and undergraduates.
Uh and you can see this uh LO score
increase on an arm of the chromosome.
And this actually corresponds to the
location of the androgen receptor which
is responsible for binding testosterone
in males and seemed like a very likely
candidate at the time.
And so today with modern G-W was we have
much larger cohort sizes and we genotype
hundreds of thousands or millions of
variants within a single assay. And we
do find that there's a lot of other
factors across the genome that
contribute to male pattern baldness. But
that initial finding on the X chromosome
remains our strongest hit to date.
Uh and so I I bring this up as as an
example of how we can use linkage to
answer one of the most challenging
problems in genetics. That is how do we
actually find the variance driving a
phenotype whether that phenotype be
baldness or disease or even just what
makes us human.
Uh and so to take a historical
perspective on linkage uh we need to
start by talking about Mendele uh who
worked on P's from 1956 or sorry 1856 to
1863 and he was really the first to
realize that traits such as the color of
peas and the shape of peas and their
seeds um were heritable units that
followed a regular pattern that could be
reliably predicted from the phenotypes
of the parents. So here crossing uh
yellow seeds uh that are smooth and
green seeds that are wrinkled they were
able to show or rather he was able to
show this very regular pattern of
inheritance where you would get seeds
with all mixtures of these phenotypes in
this very stereotyped pattern of 9331.
And so this observation eventually led
to the law of independent assortment
which is that two traits uh are
inherited independently of one another.
And so whether you inherit one trait is
totally independent of whether or not
you inherit a second trait.
And so the first problem with this idea
really came out of Mendele's the
rediscovery of Mendele's work in the
early 1900s when a group uh with Bateson
Saunders and Punet were trying to
reproduce some of Mendle's findings. And
so they were studying uh flowers that
had purple flowers and long pollen and
red flowers with round pollen. And so by
crossing the F1s of that cross uh they
expected to see that same 9331
ratio that Mendele had described. Uh but
in fact what they observed was a stark
difference from that 9331 ratio. And you
can see here that uh there are very few
flowers that they obtained that have
purple flowers and round pollen or red
flowers and long pollen.
And at the time they didn't really have
a great explanation for why that was. uh
and it wasn't really until a decade
later when uh Hunt Morgan who at the
time had been working on similarly
linked traits in the sex chromosomes of
Drosophila
uh and his student who had the insight
that by looking at variance in the
strength of linkage between two traits
you could actually arrange the gene
causing those traits on a linear entity
which we now know as a chromosome.
And who traits that were more strongly
linked were more close together on that
linear entity and traits that were less
linked were further apart. And this was
really the first genetic map uh that
really launched the field of family
based linkage studies and human
genetics. Um and so Sturdivans also uh
noted that in cases where you break this
linkage, so in the previous example
where we have purple flowers with round
pollen, these are cases where we've had
a crossing over event on a chromosome
that actually occurred in between the
site of the genes causing those two
traits.
And so this was really beautifully
demonstrated later in the 30s by Barbara
Mcccleintoch before her Nobel work on
transposons uh and her colleague Harriet
Kiteon who at the time had been
developing cytogenetic tools in maze. Uh
and so they were studying traits in corn
maze that were similarly linked. And so
here looking at uh colored and colorless
kernels and smooth and wrinkled seeds uh
by performing a cross between uh hybrid
that is hetererozygous for both of these
traits and uh the parent that is
homozygous for the recessive alle. You
would expect to find an even
distribution of phenotypes for all of
these sets. And in fact uh similar to
what uh Bates and Saunders and Punit
found, they see a deviation from that
expectation and that there's very few
offspring that have a re combination
event between those two sites. Uh and
this is really reflecting that those two
the genes driving those two traits are
very close uh on chromosome 9 in maze.
Uh and so
Mcccleintoch and Katon were studying
various different pairs of phenotypes
within maze and one had a particularly
striking uh characteristic that enabled
them to really see linkage with their
own eyes. Uh and that's this pair of
stud kernel color and waxy endosperm.
And so the the characteristic that
really enabled this is that when they
looked at the chromosomes driving these
traits, they found that using these
cytogenetic tools, they could actually
visually distinguish one chromosome from
the other. And that was because the
chromosome harboring uh the colored alil
and the waxy alil had a visible knob at
the end. This being heterocchromatin, a
very dense area of heterocchromatin. And
it also had an extra piece at the end.
And so they had these markers on either
end of the chromosome that they could
use a microscope to actually visually
observe. And so when they did this
cross, what they found similarly to what
they had here, they had some uh number
of offspring that had a recombination
between those events uh less than would
be expected by independent assortment.
And when they looked at the chromosomes
of those offspring, they could see that
all of those recompinants actually had
the knob at one end and uh missing the
extra piece at the other or the extra
piece at one end missing the knob at the
other. So actually visually saw the
recombination event happen or could at
least infer that it must have happened.
And so this series of observations with
Sturdivvent and genetic maps and the
idea that uh genes are on this physical
linear entity and linkage is the
phenomenon resulting from crossing over
during meiosis uh really led to the
field of family based linkage analysis
that has been probably the most powerful
tool for understanding the cause of
mandelian disease. Um,
and so here in this example, we're
looking at uh one chrom one pair of
chromosomes from uh an initial coupling
of an affected male and an unaffected
female. And throughout the generations,
we can see that children are affected as
well. And what we can do in family based
linkage is just genotype a handful of
markers across the chromosome. And these
markers are broken up over generation by
recombination events. And so what we see
if we after doing all of this analysis
and looking at all of the identified
markers in the affected and unaffected
individuals, we can see that there's a
region of the chromosome that harbors
this C alle in all of the affected
progeny and does not harbor that C alle
in all of the unaffected progeny. And so
this celio may not be the actual cause
of the disease but is something nearby
such that we are observing linkage
between the actual genic cause of
disease and this C alil that we were
able to genotype.
And so this had been hugely successful
for studying mandelian diseases and
really high-profile successes like
mapping the gene for cystic fibrosis and
Huntington's. Over the years, there have
been thousands more mandelian traits
that have been mapped to causal genes
using family- based linkage analysis.
Uh, however, it really was not so
successful for studying complex disease.
And so here in pink you can see the
meteoric success of linkage for studying
mandelian traits throughout the 80s and
90s but relatively little progress for
understanding complex disease which was
I think particularly disappointing at
the time because there was a lot more
effort being put into understanding
these very common complex diseases than
there was effort understanding these
rare but very numerous mandelian
diseases.
And so the reason this is is just a a
mathematical consequence of uh the way
uh effect sizes and penetrance works
where in mandelian disease you can be
quite confident at least for very high
penetrance variance that if you have the
genotype you will have the phenotype and
if you do not have the genotype there is
no instance in which you have the
phenotype. So very high penetrance, very
high effect sizes. Uh and this is not
true for complex diseases. I think we
all know there are usually many genetic
factors that contribute to complex
disease. And there's also many non-
genetic factors that also contribute to
genetic disease.
And so what are we to do? Uh so in in
the light of all of this uh work trying
to use linkage with few exceptions
unsuccessfully in complex disease uh
Neil Rich and Kathleen Marie Marongas
uh were trying to to get a mathematical
handle on this difference and they
modeled uh how many families you might
need to observe an effect in a variant
that wasn't uh such a high effect size.
And so here looking at a very popular
design for linkage studies at the time
where you look at affected siblings and
find areas of the the genome that are
shared between those siblings. Uh if we
look at effect sizes of you know 1.5 to
four times more likely to have the
disease. Uh it turns out that you know
as demonstrated by the lack of success
in linkage you really need an
astronomical number of families to
detect variance at small effect sizes
using linkage based analysis.
But what was really heartening is that
they proposed this alternative study
design where instead of trying to map
the gene using linkage, you instead test
for direct association between some
puditively causal variant and whether or
not that person inherited the disease.
Um and these numbers were uh as you can
see much more favorable uh even for very
low effect sizes and for uh very uh rare
population al frequencies.
And one other benefit of this is that
you didn't need to capture these massive
families but rather you could focus just
on affected individuals and their
parents for doing these kinds of
association studies. And so it was much
more accessible than collecting very
large pedigrees.
Um however the main limitation of
association is that you need to actually
know where to look. And so if you're
coming into a complex disease and you
don't have any prior of where that
causal gene may be and even what
variants specifically are driving the
phenotype, it's really hard to carry out
an association study, especially in
these days when, you know, a we don't
even really fully understand the degree
of variation that's present within
different human populations and we
really don't have the tools to genotype
variance across the genome at any
reasonable level of throughput.
Uh and so at this time we kind of
understood that association seemed to be
the way forward for understanding
complex disease. But what do we actually
need to make those kinds of studies a
reality? And so one thing that had been
sorely missing was as I said just an
understanding of genetic variation
within the human genome. And so this was
really helped along by several large
projects to sequence uh or at least
genotype individuals from many different
populations and get an idea of how much
variation is there in the human genome.
Uh and this ultimately culminated in uh
many of the databases that we use all
the time today like db snip and nomad
and you know many others that have
cropped up over the years.
And so one of the the key insights from
these basic studies of genetic variation
in humans has been a that there's a lot
of variation in humans. Uh each
individual on average has about 4
million variants and as expected from
the out of Africa hypothesis African
populations typically have far more at
about 5 million variants. Uh but what
was really important to recognize is
that the vast majority of these variants
are actually shared between populations.
They're very old. And so in this graph,
the colored bars are noting variants
that are uh unique to that population or
to that individual. Whereas the the two
gray bars are variants that are shared
throughout the entire world or just
within that continent. And what you'll
notice is that the vast majority in most
populations, the vast majority of
variants are shared across continents or
even across the world. And this makes
the problem a little bit more tractable
where everyone has 4 million variants,
but in total there's only about 10
million common variants in humans.
Uh, and the other key observation that
kind of follows from this is that most
variants are really old. And this is the
core concept of linkage disequilibrium
where generally in most cases a variant
that we observe in an individual
happened one time in some ancestor and
is now present in many people as a
consequences of heredity rather than
that mutation occurring many different
times. And so because the mutations are
old and occurred once, these uh variants
are only separated from their
surrounding sequence by recombination
events happening across generations. And
so here we can see in present- day
chromosomes, if you look in the area
around some marker of interest, they
actually all share sequence identity
with that ancestral chromosome. And this
is again just another manifestation of
the property of linkage where uh the
closer you are to a marker and the more
recent that mutation is, the more likely
you are to have the same sequence
surrounding it.
And so uh one of the important
properties of LB is that it erodess over
generation. So LD is a function of
mitoic or sorry myiotic recombination
events separating out those alals and uh
kind of making that hletype smaller over
time. Uh and so over a few generations
you can see there's some combinations uh
that make these blocks of color smaller
as you go. uh but then over hundreds and
thousands of generations these blocks
erode away into very small chunks of
DNA. Uh but note that this is a very
long process and for most of the
variants we look at today we can see a
reasonable level of linkage to
equilibrium that we can leverage in many
of our genetic studies.
And so
another key observation from these basic
studies of genetic variation in humans
is this observation that recombination
is not random across the genome. There
are hot spots of recombination and as a
consequence of that we get this
phenomenon of hletype blocks where there
are sets of snips or varants along the
genome that are almost never broken up
by recombination.
And so these are uh a really critical
observation that led to eventually the
HAPMAP project and mapping out um
applotype blocks in humans and
leveraging that information to very
intelligently design uh genotyping
arrays and actually perform association
studies. Um but the other critical need
for actually doing an association was
really a technological innovation of
being able to genotype many variants in
parallel. And this really came around
circa 2005 when the first uh high
throughput genotyping arrays came out
from aluminina and aphometrics uh where
we're able to assay hundreds of
thousands of variants at the same time
in a single essay.
And so the question that arises from
this is okay, we've got 10 million
common variants within the human genome
and room for at the time maybe a hundred
thousand or a few hundred thousand
variants to fit on these genotyping
arrays. So, you know, if we're going to
do association studies and expand this
out to many hundreds and thousands of
individuals per study, we need to have a
really efficient way of assaying all of
the genetic variation in humans without
uh breaking the bank. And so, how do we
actually go about choosing SNIPS to
effectively design arrays for genotyping
uh association studies?
And the critical observation that makes
this possible is that we can use LD to
infer genotypes that we didn't actually
directly assay in our arrays. And so
that is if we have you know a haploype
block and a few variants in LD and we
look within the population and we see a
a G accotyping
array that only assays these first two
variants. we can actually infer and in
fact computationally fill in the third
variant without ever needing to assay it
directly because we know that this
variant is in tight LD with the other
two and therefore we don't actually need
to assay it directly and so through this
principle the hatmap project set out to
actually map uh common hletypes within
humans and figure out how we can
effectively genotype a small number of
variants and get the maximal genotyping
information from that via this idea.
And so this is some information from the
hatmap project looking at effectively a
European population. And this idea of
using a snip uh that you actually assay
to then infer other genotypes. That
assayed snip is the tag snip. And when
we look at power versus the number of
markers we assay, we can see that by
using the hapmap project and actually
mapping out all of the hlo types, common
hlet types in humans, we can effectively
design tag snips that uh outperform
arrays made by random snips by a factor
of maybe two or fivefold. Um, and one
thing that is really clear here is that
in a hypothetical world where we didn't
have LD, we would need to assay, you
know, an order of magnitude more
variance in order to get the same level
of power um that we would using snips
designed with LD in mind. Um, and so at
the end of the day, what they find is
that in order to get a pretty reasonable
power for doing association studies, we
can get by just assaying around 30,000
uh 300,000 snips.
And so this led to an explosion of G-W
was studies and understanding in complex
disease that I think ultimately is the
best for another primer at another day
specifically dedicated to GIWAS. But um
just making note that this has been a
very successful strategy for identifying
genic factors that drive um complex
disease.
And so
beyond just imputing snips uh using tag
snips, one other really important
property that we get from LB is the
ability to actually imputee haploype
structure which is very important for
many assays that uh we perform. And uh
this is basically the idea that we have
a list of variants across a chromosome.
But how are they actually arranged on
the maternal and paternal copies of the
chromosome? And so by taking data from
hapmap and thousand human genomes and
other sources uh we can take a
population reference of how hloypes are
arranged and use that information to
computationally infer how variants are
aligned across a chromosome. And so this
is again just leveraging the idea that
if we have two variants that are close
together and observed to be in very high
LD, we can infer that they're present on
the same hletype.
Um and so these days there are many
excellent tools for doing uh hletype
estimation and phasing and here are some
of the ones that I have used. Um but one
thing to keep in mind when imputing
phase from population data sets is that
it is prone to error. And so this is an
example where we have uh the true phase
laid out in orange and blue. And when
deriving phase from population data
sets, often what you get is these phase
switch errors where in the individual
there has been recombination event
relative to the population references
that you're looking at. And so you end
up having this switch in phase along the
chromosome. And this can happen multiple
times uh going down the chromosome. And
so there's a few ways to uh ameliate
these errors. And one of them is uh are
simply just using a bigger reference
data set. And as time goes on and we
sequence more and more individuals, this
gets easier and easier as we've got
massive uh data sets of individuals that
we can use for doing really effective
phase imputation from population data
sets. And this is nice because it's uh
easy to do. You don't need to actually
do any experiments. you can just
computationally get a really accurate um
phase estimation from any set of
genotyping whether that be whole genome
sequencing or uh genotyping arrays.
The other way is actually doing an
experiment and using readbacked phasing
to define hllet types. So the most
useful tools for this have really been
long read sequencing and third
generation sequencing where you can get
reads that span kilobases or megabases
and actually physically observe the uh
the phase uh within across multiple
variants over the genome.
And the third maybe the the gold
standard is to get a trio and get DNA
from mom and DNA from dad and from that
in most cases you can unambiguously
derive the the hlet types present within
the child.
Uh and so now in the second half of the
study I thought that I would talk a
little bit about my own work and how
I've used phasing to understand uh
vascular malf formations during my
graduate work. And so uh when I was a
graduate student at Duke, I was studying
this rare mandelian disease, hereditary
hemorrhagic toangictasia. And this is a
disease of autoomal dominance caused by
a mutation in three different genes
involved in the same pathway. Um and it
causes vascular mal formations. The most
prominent of them being mucosal to
lantictasia. So these are like small red
spots as you can see on mucosal
membranes. So uh tongue, lips, eyeballs,
fingers. Um but then more uh
perniciously they also cause arterior
venus malfforms in internal organs. So
the most prominent being lungs and brain
and you can see this mass of vascule in
the lung and in the brain that
ultimately uh what's going on is in a
normal artery vein connection you have
uh the major artery and veins separated
by a capillary bed that in a very
careful and controlled way allows blood
to flow and nutrients to reach uh
tissues in that area. However, in HHT,
what happens is you get enlargement of
those capillaries and effectively direct
shunting between arterial and venus
blood which reduces the efficiency of
things like respiration. And so you end
up uh most often getting high output
heart failure.
And so
when studying HHT, one uh observation
that really drove our thinking was this
uh disjointed nature of the genotype in
the phenotype where this is an autotoal
dominant disease. So they have a
hetererozygous causal mutation in one of
these genes and the genotype that causal
mutation is present in every cell in the
body. But the phenotype these vascular
mal forations are inherently focal
phenomenon. we get spots, we get
discrete AVMs. Um, and so we really
wanted to understand what was underlying
that difference. Why weren't we getting
this kind of systemic vascular
malfformation that you might expect from
uh having the mutation present in every
cell?
And so one thing that we thought uh
could be the cause is a sematic mutation
similar to what you get in cancers. uh
this is a mutation that arises
postsygotically in cells during
development and in fact as we age and uh
these mutations are not present in every
cell of the body and uh can be present
very focally within multiple tissues or
even within uh a single tissue and so
the thinking being that these vascular
malfformations are the result of a
sematic mutation in a genetic dsonian
two-head mechanism. So this is uh that
we inherit one null copy of the alil
from the parents and then a sematic
mutation leads to loss of function in
the same gene on the other functional
copy. Uh
and that this event following by uh
likely many other non-genetic factors is
what's actually driving tillasia and
vascular malfformation.
And so when setting out on this study to
see if sematic mutations were actually
the driver of vascular malf formations
in HHT, there were three things that we
were expecting to find if this two hit
mechanism was indeed true. And so the
first of those is that the mutations we
identify would be in the same gene. So
we've got a germline inherited mutation
and a postsygotic sematic mutation. And
these are the three genes that uh are
known to cause HHG. And the expectation
would be that the sematic mutation and
the germline mutation occur in that same
gene. The second would be that these
mutations are all causing loss of
function. So think frame shift splice uh
mutations.
And then the third and importantly I
think for demonstrating the benefits of
uh phasing is that the mutations are
biic. And so if we have a loss of
function mutation uh on one alil and
then later sematically we get another
loss of function mutation but in that
same alil we still have one functional
copy of the gene and wouldn't expect uh
vascular mal formations to form. Uh and
so following from this hypothesis we're
expecting that the variance would be in
trans affecting both alals such that no
functional protein remains.
And so in doing this uh we set out with
20 samples of tangictasia from
individuals with HHT and use target
capture to sequence really just a
handful of genes that we suspected to be
involved in vascular mal formations from
other studies at the time in other
diseases and then sequenced them to to
very high depth to identify sematic
mutation and then following that do some
validation with just amplon sequencing
and make sure that the variants we're
identifying aren't artifactual.
And indeed what we found is that in nine
of those 20 sematic mutations here
showing the germline mutation, we also
found a loss of function or most likely
to be loss of function mutation in the
same gene in each case. And uh of these
most of them were very obviously loss of
function mutations. Five of them were
frame shift. Three of them were inframe
indels affecting multiple uh amino acids
and the third was a splice site mutation
affecting uh four bases after the exxon
intron junction which is a little far
out. So we did I don't show the data
here but we did experimentally validate
that using splicing assays and showed
that uh it did disrupt uh splicing and
there were no uh fulllength transcripts
of the gene remaining.
uh but one thing you'll note that is
particularly challenging for studies uh
in this nature is that unlike in cancer
where you basically get a clonal mass of
cells that have expanded in vascular
malf formations it's not so clonal and
these sematic mutations are present at
very low al frequencies which makes
identifying them a little bit more
challenging
and so really for that third point of
testing whether or not those mutations
were in by a leic.
We looked across uh we looked for
readback phasing in this case not using
uh statistical phasing because these are
rare mutations not present within
population data sets. And so in order to
get any information about phase we need
to actually observe phase. Um and so
here's an example where we have the
causal germline mutation on the right
hand side and a sematic mutation a one
base pair deletion causing a frame shift
on the left hand side. And when we look
at all of the reads with the sematic
mutation, you can observe that we have
the wild type or the reference al uh at
the site of the germline mutation
indicating that these variants are in
fact in trans and u
presumably in the cells with the
mutation have no functional protein
remaining. And we got lucky in this case
where the germline and sematic mutation
just happened to be very close together
and could be phased directly from the
reads used for discovery. In most cases
that wasn't uh true and we turned to
long read sequencing to figure out uh
how those variants were arranged. So
here an example uh on the bottom where
we can see the discovery reads that
these are very far apart and basically
have no chance of directly phasing them
from aluminina reads. But then with pack
bio we can very clearly see that all of
the reads with the sematic mutation have
the reference alil at the site of the
germline mutation. And we were able to
do this for seven of the nine uh variant
pairs we identified. And in each case
they proved to be bileic.
And so the question then is what about
the other 11 mal for uh that we didn't
find a mutation in? Is there some other
mechanism by which uh these mal
formations can form or is there
something that we're missing? And our
expectation is really that there's
something that we're missing. For
discovering the variance, we use
targeted short read sequencing of just
16 genes, which is really great for
picking up small events like single
nucleotide variance and small indelss,
but much less useful for picking up very
large varants that are just as likely to
cause loss of function.
Uh, and so to get at this question, we
looked at traditional methods for
identifying structural variation within
the human genome. And uh one of the most
common is using microarrays. So
genotyping arrays similarly to what's
used for G-W was to look at snips across
the chromosome. And here looking at
chromosome 21 in a normal individual.
Here we're plotting the alternate alil
frequency. And you can see we've got a
bunch of hetererozygous variants. We've
got a bunch of homozygous variants the
ref or alt. uh and then we have the LRR
which you can interpret as the
genotyping intensity on the microarray.
So an LRR of one is what we would expect
to find for a normal diploloyid
individual. LR above one indicates the
presence of a gain and LR below one
would indicate the presence of a loss.
And here in an example of tricomeme21 a
patient with down syndrome you can see
that the bal frequency bifurcates where
you have one alil that rises in
frequency the one that is duplicated and
the other uh is decreased in its
relative frequency and similarly with
the LR you can see that to be elevated
above one indicating the presence of
chromosomal gain
and so uh it turns out that picking up
variance with microarray via traditional
methods is very challenging when your
alle frequency is extremely low. This is
a germline event. So it's present in
every cell in the body. But if we look
at a sematic event that uh is only
present in a handful of cells, we use
these same metrics and really don't see
uh any obvious signs of any kind of
structural variation across this example
of chromosome 12. But some very clever
people at the broad uh have developed
algorithms where we can actually use uh
phasing information and here using
statistical phasing to uh improve the
sensitivity for picking up mosaic copy
number and structural variation. And so
here if we include phasing information
and just plot one of the parental hlet
types what you can see hopefully is that
we get a deviation away from neutral
alil frequency and occasionally we get
the sign shift where over here
everything is low then it switches to
high then low again then high again and
this is actually uh demonstrating those
phase switch errors that I had mentioned
earlier which are often the consequences
U statistical phasing. Uh and so here we
can really clearly see that deviation
away from neutral al frequency
indicating that most likely here there's
likely copy neutral or slight increase
in the LR. So maybe a copy gain on
chromosome 12 that's resulting in that
shift away from neutral.
And so we applied this to many of the
toangictasia that were still available
from that initial study where we did not
identify a point mutation. And in fact
we find that many of them do indeed have
some kind of structural variant
overlapping the causal gene. uh
indicating that most likely though
there's no point mutation there could be
copy neutral loss of hetererozygosity
where the germline inherited but alil is
copied over onto the wild type al again
resulting in full loss of function in
that protein
and so in conclusion what we find is
that these vascular malfforms in HHT and
many other diseases that we've studied
to this point are indeed caused by
biolic loss of function mutations
whether those the point mutations or
structural variations that are a little
harder to detect. So I think I'm a
little bit ahead of time, but I am
finished. So if there's any questions, I
would be happy to take
>> Great. Can you uh use the mic right?
Thank you so much.
>> Oh, so official. Uh, hi, I'm Dev. I'm
new here. Great presentation. Um, and
your work is is remarkable. I mean, HHD
is a very debilitating disease
clinically. I've seen it. It's it's it's
really bad. U, my question is, in the
nine individuals that were shown to have
the two hit, or rather the seven that
were confirmed to be trans, was there a
difference in expressivity compared to
those who weren't, assuming, would they
have maybe had a worse disease
progression?
>> Right. Right. Yeah. So um
ultimately the sample size is really too
low to tell and see any realistic
differences in severity. Um the
expectation is that you know you might
think that okay these are the uh the
malf formations that have a variant and
so um maybe would have a worst case but
what we expect is that there are even
more types of variants that we haven't
assayed and could be present in those
samples that we didn't find a mutation.
So you could very easily conceive of
things like promoter methylation and
epigenetics having a factor having a
role in inactivating the functional copy
of the gene and and we basically have no
sensitivity for those. So to answer your
question, no, we don't see differences
in expressivity. We really don't have a
power to do that. But also the
expectation is that the mutations are
there even if we don't see them.
>> Thank you.
>> Um hi. Um, I was wondering if anyone has
ever modeled sematicism,
is that possible to model just like 20%
loss of a mutation in a cell and show
like a functional outcome or difference?
>> Yes. So, uh there's been a lot of
efforts to model mosaicism. And the one
that I'll mention in relation to this
work is there's uh some really beautiful
work uh developing they're called
tangictas on a chip where you can take
endothelial cells and put them on a
micrfluidic chip introducing kind of
flow as normal endothelial cells would
expect and introduce cells with the
sematic mutation at a any ratio that you
would like and kind of model how that
you know artificial vessel develops And
they do see that you get mal foration of
the vessel even with very small
inclusions of mutant endothelial cells.
>> Have time for a couple more.
>> All right. I'm going to give you a fun
one. I feel like when I ever go back and
revisit the the basics, I learn
something new. And you did a deep dive
into some linkage history. I guess I'm
wondering if you learned anything new
when you dove back into that or if there
are any fun facts or historic fun facts
that you didn't share.
>> Yeah, I mean I uh I had a really great
time putting together this presentation
reading a lot. You know, I I had learned
about a lot of the concepts in human
genetics classes, but I didn't really
have an appreciation of the history of
how it came to be. So uh I had a great
time reading through old papers and old
perspectives on the history of genetics
and learned a lot of cool things like
what I had mentioned in the talk where I
didn't know about knobs on maze
chromosomes and how uh that had been
used to actually observe linkage and uh
many other things that uh are kind of
just interesting bits of history more so
than uh
really fundamental genetics knowledge.
that remains uh important today. I mean,
I'm I trying to think back and think if
there's any like nuggets of wisdom. Um
but nothing's immediately coming to me.
>> Um
>> oh, go ahead. or something. So on the
on the 1984
cytogenetics
um exam for for clinical cytogenetics,
there was a question on the first page
that asked about what um uh uh twin
spots were. And I worked for a a a
department that did a lot of twin
studies. It wasn't that necessarily, but
I'm just going to ask you, what do you
think the answer is? And and I know what
the answer is now. So, um,
>> yeah, put me on the spot. Um, I actually
have no idea what twin spots are. I
>> I was devastated. I mean, I I was a
posttock at that point and that was the
first time I could take the exam and I
had no idea of what this thing was and
it was like the fir on the first page of
the exam. Barbara Mcccleintoch actually
looking at recombination in maze.
>> I don't think it ever appeared again on
the exam.
>> Wow,
>> that's a good one. If anyone does nerdy
trivia, remember that.
>> Um, I was actually struck by a table
that you showed from the 1996 paper from
Neil Rich and Kathleen Mary Congus. Do
you mind going back to that because I
was looking at the ends of the
associations and so if I'm reading that
right is that like the required minimal
N of people right so they're saying for
a variant of a risk ratio of 1.5
that's somewhat common or 0.02% 02% in
the population, you'd need 20,000 people
to see a association. Is that right?
Because I feel like it's a lot more.
>> So I think that some of this comes down
to the way that they modeled association
studies in the paper and they had been
using if I think back uh a particular uh
model of an association study that had
been previously proposed on the basis of
linkage to equilibrium.
uh and my knowledge of that paper is not
really deep enough to be able to say how
reasonable that is the reality. So it
doesn't surprise me that it is off from
uh off from what we actually observe
doing them today. It is just interesting
to think about it from that point of
view and think, oh, they thought we only
needed 20,000 people to identify, you
know, SNIPS for common variants. But,
um, you know, yeah,
>> but at the end of the day, I think the
point holds true that, uh, you would
need many families to do the same
discovery from a linkage based.
>> Okay. So, it was really about comparing
the 5 million to the 20,000 and saying
G-W was the better way to go. That was
the take.
>> Uhhuh.
Um, I think we'll do this one quick one
online. Do you know if people are still
doing classical linkage analyses for
monogenic diseases? And if so, are G-W
was snip genotyping arrays most useful
or superior to exo data?
>> Oh, yeah. No, I I linkage studies are
definitely still being done and I think
they're still very effective for uh high
penetrance monogenic diseases. uh I mean
the fact of the matter is that for rare
disease you're very unlikely to find any
affected individuals within a population
and so you know even if you do it's
probably uh not likely that those
individuals are related by uh you know
that that variant arose in those
individuals via a relationship but
rather that those variants occurred
independently and so you can't really
use G-W was for doing uh the same kind
of monogenic linkage analysis that you
would use for doing rare disease today.
Uh so yes, it's definitely still
relevant and being used. Great. I think
that is time. Let's thank Dan. Thank
you. See you next week.