hi again welcome back to the crash
course in the autoimmune disease machine
learning challenge in this lecture we're
going to cover technology uh but before
that let's just briefly recap what you
learned in the first lecture so in the
first lecture we had an introduction to
autoimmune disease and we learned about
ulcerative colitis and how Pathologists
study uh ulcerative colitis tissues and
then we finally learned that patients
with ulcerative colitis have increased
risk for col cancer now one of the
things that these pathology images don't
really tell us is the mechanism of the
disease or how the disease might
progress what's the chance that a
patient might uh progress to cancer so
we need other Technologies to really get
at these questions and that's what the
focus of this lecture will be so
technology so we're going to really
focus on one aspect of the cell and the
tissue that we can measure which is gene
expression so first I'm going to review
with you what genes are and how gene
expression changes in health disease and
cancer and then I'll introduce to you
how we can measure gene expression in
tissues and in
cells so let's get started by uh talking
about genes so uh you know genes are the
basic unit of inheritance uh or heredity
uh they are inherited from our parents
uh and so we have them from our mom and
our dad uh genes are written in DNA
sequences using the bases a TC and G in
here is DNA and it forms this beautiful
double helix structure and so genes are
written in the DNA and this is used to
write out both physical and biological
traits so genes can encode things like
our height or our eye color but variance
in these genes can also increase or
decrease our risk for certain diseases
so we know there are certain variants in
genes that increase our risk for
ulcerative
colitis so uh you know genes as I said
are written in the DNA and then
information in the DNA or in the in the
genes flows from the DNA to the RNA to
the protein so DNA is sitting in the
nucleus of our cells and then it gets
copied or transcribed into an RNA
molecule and then that RNA molecule gets
translated into a protein and a protein
is a biomolecule that can carry out many
functions in cells and tissues it gives
cells structure it's important for
interactions between cells it's they're
doing almost everything uh they're
pretty amazing so let's take a look at
how this plays out in
tissues so here we're looking at four
different tissue types and each of them
is made up of different uh cells here we
have the skin the brain the small
intestine and blood uh there are two
really I think amazing things about
these images when you look at them one
is just the diversity so you know the
skin is protecting us from our outside
environment the brain is doing all our
thinking and memory hopefully you're
using it as you listen to me um the
small intestine is where our food is
traveling down and nutrients are getting
absorbed and finally we have blood
vessels where uh immune cells and red
blood cells carrying oxygen move
throughout the body so that's really
incredible all of this is happening in
our body there's huge diversity but
what's even more remarkable
is that each of these cells that make up
these tissues have essentially the exact
same DNA sequence so that's really
incredible so how does that work so
essentially what's going on is that
within every cell there's regulation of
which genes are being expressed so which
genes are being turned on or off so in
the human genome we have all of us
20,000 genes but they're not all on at
the same time there's specificity to
which cells they're on
so remember DNA is transcribed or copied
into RNA and this control of this is
what regulates which genes are on or off
in any given cell so let's look at a
cartoon of what's going on here so here
we have gene expression or genes and
then here we have different cell types
and red means that this Gene is
expressed in that cell type so within
the B cells we have a certain group of
genes being expressed or turned on
within T cell cells we have a different
set of genes being turned on or off and
then finally in the muscle cells we have
another set of genes that are turned on
and again there are 20,000 genes they're
not all on at once it's just subsets of
genes so these groups of genes that are
expressed together we often refer to
them as gene expression
programs and we can discover these gene
expression programs by taking cells and
measuring the expression of the genes
inside the cells so to do that we really
need to f focus on the RNA so when RNA
is made that means a gene is being
expressed and we call these RNA
molecules that are made transcripts or
Gene
transcripts so during disease there's a
big change in these gene expression
programs so these groups of genes that
are regulated together so here we're
returning to our cartoon of the colon
epithelial barrier and in healthy colon
there are many gene expression programs
that are turned on that serve to keep
the tissue in homeostasis so in this
healthy balance and some of these
programs are things that are genes that
are involved in nutrient absorption so
our gut is taking in nutrients from the
food that's being digested there's also
programs involved in microbe defense so
we don't want these microbes to really
be crossing over however in ulcerative
kitis as you start damaging the colon
epithelial barrier and microbes start
migrating into the colon you get gene
expression programs that are involved in
epithelial barrier dysfunction so these
cells are under a lot of stress as the
microbes make their way in you start to
see uh programs involved in microb
sensing so the cells are sensing hey
there's a bacteria here that doesn't
belong and then you also start to get
this early immune response with
inflammation that progresses to chronic
inflammation so again all of this is
controlled by gene expression
programs the same holds true in cancer
so as a healthy colon transitions over
to displasia into cancer you also get
these gene expression programs that are
turned on so remember cancer is sort of
one defining feature is this
uncontrolled growth so you see the
program for cell division being turned
on as the cancer grows and grows you
also see a program called epithelial to
meenal transition which is these
epithelial cells start to detach from
the tissue and migrate throughout the
body to another site and that's called
uh metastasis and that's really uh bad
for the patient requires a lot of
intervention
obviously so at this point we've
introduced two different ways to profile
uh tissues in humans one is tissue
pathology where we stain a piece of
tissue with this h& stain and the other
is measuring gene expression where we
are measuring the expression of all
20,000 genes inside a cell or inside a
tissue so let's compare and contrast
these two different approaches to
profiling tissues so with tissue
pathology uh a PA ologist can
immediately see after seeing the uh
tissue the spatial organization of the
tissue uh they can make a diagnosis
whether they think the patient has
alterative colitis they can make a
prediction as to how the disease might
progress potentially uh they can uh come
up with you know what's the treatment
strategy so these are all really
important things with patient care at
the same time uh these pathology images
there's many of them available across
hospitals in the world so there's
millions of these images likely and they
are cheap and routine to collect
on the downside um you know just looking
at these images alone uh they do not
tell us how the disease arises and they
do not tell us how the disease May
progress to cancer like what are the
pathways that could happen and because
of this we also don't know how to Target
these diseases or cancer with a drug
because we don't know the pathways and
we don't know what's going wrong so we
don't know what what to fix or where to
intervene and again this is probably
because in a sense these tissue images
are somewhat low information they're low
Dimension it's just three channels a red
green blue image so the gene expression
on the other hand is a high dimensional
measurement we're measuring 20,000 genes
and when we do that we can really look
at which genes are associated with
disease uh which pathways are being
turned on and this can give us an idea
of Pathways or parts of the cell to be
targeting with a drug so that's really
in uh just important for Discovery now
the downside of this is that gene
expression is actually technically quite
hard to measure and it takes a lot more
money and time uh and the Technologies
to do this are becoming really Advanced
and in this challenge or these crunches
we're going to be working with some of
the newest Technologies but also
conversely they're the most expensive
Technologies so the premise of this
autoimmune disease machine learning
challenge is what if you could combine
these two technologies and kind of get
the best of both worlds so can we train
machine learning models that will
connect the tissue pathology to the gene
expression and so now we're really
taking advantage of both Technologies
and then if we can train these models
that can take in tissue pathology and
tell us something about gene expression
can we apply such models to do a better
job at detecting cancer earlier in ulcer
colitis when a pathologist is studying
those tissue sections