so it's a pleasure to kick off this
Symposium for the third time um my name
is Sumaya I am a senior group leader at
the Bro Institute um and running
bioinformatics and machine learning
group I have a couple of thank you to
give before we can start thanks to the
organizing committee the entire
committee is here I hope um it takes a
village to organize a symposium invite
everyone and a lot of time and effort is
invested into it so thanks to everyone
especially this year we started our
pre-symposium workshop and I received
very good feedback that it went
extremely well and it was an engaging
Workshop uh then our advisers they
helped us through the speaker selection
and throughout the um year so thanks to
all our advisers um then our generous
sponsors thank you
all um next uh comes our line of
speakers as you can see uh they are um
the Stellar scientist in Academia and
Industry and we are very thankful for
traveling all the way and attending this
Symposium and then our lightning talk
winners so this is kind of um the
spotlight of the show that we invite one
minute uh five minutes talk one slides
and I am looking forward to those talks
H and these are our winners for this
year you will get certificates and prize
money and we will have award session to
to uh recognize um your
achievements and next is we will have
poster winners four poster winners the
posters will be judged by its content on
the poster and visuals so don't don't
feel obliged to stay there and present
feel free to network and hang around and
we that those will be judged by the
content um then uh we have a QR code on
your program that you can scan if you
want to look at the abstracts that were
submitted and the posters that are
displayed out
there okay so with that it's my pleasure
to introduce Pat Walters uh to kick off
the Symposium um uh Pat Walters uh is
the chief data officer in in relay
Therapeutics I think you probably all
know about Pat so I will not go into the
long bio but I'll give a shout out to
Pat's block post that I'm very much fan
of the Practical chem informatics go
there it's it's very resourceful and
with that Pat
Walters so many of you know me from
yelling at people about statistics um
I'll do a little bit of that but I was
asked to provide a rousing introduction
so I think this has been a really
exciting year for machine learning in
drug Discovery we all saw that both the
chemistry and biology prizes went to
work on machine learning in particular
the chemistry prize went to David Baker
and the team from Deep Mind for protein
structure prediction it was very
exciting that we saw the alpha fold 3
paper come out and then it was
incredibly disappointing because there
was no code and none of us can actually
do anything interesting with the API
that they've
provided however you know I'm happy to
see that there are a lot of efforts out
there now to reproduce Alpha fold uh
anybody who's interested in this I'd
highly recommend looking at Charlie
Harris's blog post that he updates
regularly and that kind of gets you up
todate on all the efforts to reproduce
Alpha fold 3 and Charlie is actually
trying things out
too you know I think it's been a bit of
a mixed bag in terms of clinical trials
for AI focused drug Discovery companies
during the summer there was this paper
that came out from drug Discovery today
written by a group at Boston Consulting
Group who clearly does not understand
our
field and this paper
claims that AI focused drug Discovery
companies have been more successful in
phase one clinical
trials somebody wants to come to me on
the break I'll explain to you the 12
things that are wrong with that paper
and Dereck low had a nice blog post
where he pointed out that the phase 2
results although there are only a few
have been a little
disappointing however you know insert
your favorite sports metaphor it's early
in the game and I don't know if we can
make any conclusions there yet one of
the things that I'm most excited about
though is data on Wednesday I was at an
AI and Drug Discovery Symposium at
Boston University there were two panels
in a row that came to the conclusion
that the biggest thing holding the field
back to this date is a lack of high
quality large data sets and you know
I've written extensively about all the
problems with molecule net and the
therapeutic data Commons and the fact
that those data sets should never be
used for anything however there's some
really exciting work going on one of the
things I'm most excited about is the
open admy consult so this is a an effort
that's spearheaded by Jamie Fraser at
UCSF John Cadera at Memorial Sloan
ketering and some of the folks at octant
bio and this effort has two aims one is
to generate large highquality adme data
sets and make them publicly available
second and I think I'm even more excited
about this is to do structural biology
on off targets the structural biology
Community has largely ignored her
cytochrome p450s pxr Other Drug
metabolizing enzymes so I think this
combination of highquality data and
structural information could be
incredibly powerful you know I'm a big
fan of using machine learning together
with DNA encoded Library data
unfortunately until very recently there
was one publicly available data set
there was a Carbonic and hydrates data
set from the broad was relatively small
it's it's great that there have been
some great papers that have appeared
this year there was a paper from Somaya
there was a paper from En silico there
was a paper from University of North
Carolina but even better people are
releasing more data sets it was a great
kaggle competition sponsored by leash
bio and the structural genomics
Consortium has an effort called air
check to collect all of these data sets
and make them available in a consistent
format so I'm hoping you with some of
these efforts around data we can push
the field forward a lot of people ask me
where should I go to find good data sets
there's a great effort that's been put
together by a group around a website
called Polaris hub.io Polaris is
collecting data sets making them
available but also providing
recommendations and having industry
experts evaluate those data sets Polaris
has workflows for data curation and it
has workflows for method comparison so
there's a lot of great resources there
for people who are interested in protein
liant interaction so docking coold
folding activity prediction we no longer
have to deal with pdb bind there's a
much better larger data set out there
there's been a group in both industry
and Academia that's put together this
plender data set it's very large it has
rationally defined train and test splits
it's well annotated so I think there's a
lot of exciting data sources I can't
walk away without talking about model
comparison because it frustrates me when
I open up papers and I still see these
tables and people put their method in
bold and they don't do any statistics to
compare things I've been complaining
about this for a decade we finally did
something about it so there's a group of
us from a range of Biotech and Pharma
companies we put together a set of
guidelines for method comparisons we
also have a set of Jupiter notebooks
demonstrating best practices this paper
was submitted to Archive yesterday so
hopefully either today or tomorrow it
will be available so we've made a lot of
progress but I still think there's a lot
of things we have to figure out and
there's things that we don't do well and
it frustrates me when I see people at
nups you know doing yet another
diffusion model let's work on the real
problem so I've built a machine learning
model I have a new molecule how do I
know whether I can make an be confident
in my prediction so defining the
applicability domain you know yes we've
got message passing neural networks
we've got gnns but ultimately we're
still using the same molecular
representation based on topology that
we've been used for been using for 40
years we really haven't figured out how
to integrate 3D into our representations
we haven't figured out how to make
transferable representations you know
you see all these papers coming out on
you know various ways of generating
molecules but nobody's figured out how
to determine whether those molecules are
synthesizable or whether they're even
chemically stable and then finally drug
Discovery is not just optimizing potency
it's not just optimizing adme we want to
be able to optimize multiple properties
usually dozens and we still don't have
good methods for doing multiobjective
optimization so in case you missed any
of the links that I put up to any of
these wonderful data sources if you go
to my website there's a resources link
and that resources link has links to
everything that I talked about today
anyway that's that's my time thanks