thank you Yuri we're going to leave the
world cup out of this um so um welcome
everyone this is the fast-paced startup
lightning talks I'm arat rodenstein
program manager with MIT startup
exchange and shortly you're going to
hear from eight exciting startups all
members of startup exchange but first
i'm just going to share a little
overview of our
program so MIT startup exchange was
created over eight years ago within the
office of MIT corporate relations as you
heard earlier to support MIT connected
startups as they grow expand and help
solve some of the world's greatest
challenges and we do this by fostering
collaborations and Partnerships between
the startups and Industry primarily ILP
members represented by so many of you
joining us today and the MIT Innovation
ecosystem and
Beyond the startups in our program are
uh based on MIT licensed technology or
founded by MIT faculty staff or alumni
and they can also be vetted by some of
our MIT Partners including the engine
Ventures the e14 fund Cale MIT Nano the
marting trust Center for MIT
entrepreneurship and many
others and so our program has around a
thousand startups in it usually they
join at Pilot stage or Beyond and they
cover all sectors and all geographies
and we did this uh within this bigger
Network we also have a group that we
call st25 some of you might have heard
of it and this is where we provide
customized support to the startups for a
period of one year where they have
greater visibility more introductions
and so
on and so when it comes to this value of
startup
exchange the startups in the program
have exposure to a Global Network of
Industry decision makers and the
corporates have access to vetted MIT
connected
startups on events we host a variety of
them all throughout the year local
International summer conferences like
today where we host an uh startup
lightning talk session an exhibit and um
we also have our demo days um other
webinars one-on-one meetings workshops
and much more and the benefit of this
for the ILP members is that we can
tailor an event according to your needs
and the benefit to the startups is that
we can take you onto different markets
that you're expanding into perhaps and
you have greater visibility into new
ecosystems we also launch calls for
startups we call these
opportunities and they're based on a
corporate's priorities and internal
challenges and so the startups can apply
on our website and if they're selected
they can work with you as an ILP member
to help you solve a problem that you're
facing in your
industry and all in all this is a very
curated and customized approach so I
hope everyone here um and online is able
to take advantage of of these benefits
and of course come talk to any of us
today if you have any questions about
it and so as I mentioned before start of
exchange was created to help um Foster
these Partnerships and collaborations
and these are just a few of the success
cases up to date and they can take the
shape of a proof of concept uh Grand
Scale Pilot customers joint R&D and all
the way to an
acquisition and again this is a forum
where some conversations maybe will
start or continue today to lead to more
success
cases and so before turning it over to
the entrepreneurs I'd like to highlight
some of the upcoming events we have a
very busy fall so I hope you join us for
a lot of these we have the Madrid
Symposium um in November the Nano Summit
tomorrow which some of you might be
aware of and then on November 19th and
20th we're back here at the Marriott so
please join us for the R&D conference
our signature event there's still time
to register for it then we have um a
webinar on decarbonization our Houston
Symposium then the demo days which
happen every couple of months so it's a
chance to meet a lot of startup startups
at once virtually and then in uh January
we're going to Asia to Thailand and
Japan so with that these are the eight
startups participating today and thank
you to them thank you to all of you and
let's get started