Hey everybody, I am delighted to be here
with you today closing out the show for
the day and sharing a little bit of our
work in our newsroom and some of the
trends and technologies within
artificial intelligence specifically
that we're tracking. My aim in the next
30 minutes is just to give you a sense
of some of the recent developments that
we have covered and where we see this
fastmoving space of AI headed from here.
Uh if you don't know MIT Technology
Review, I'll just briefly tell you a
little bit about who we are and what
we're all about. We are a media company
that is owned by MIT based right here uh
right off of campus. And we are
editorially independent. So we don't
write about MIT research. We cover the
broader world of emerging technology.
And our beats include artificial
intelligence of course, but also
computing, robotics, climate technology,
biotech, all of the above.
So, a few things I like to say about our
approach to technology coverage in the
year 2025. Uh, so we don't write about
technology in a vacuum. We're always
thinking about the economic and
political and social context in which
these technologies get developed and
deployed because we recognize that that
plays a big part in the effect that they
have on our lives. We also don't write
about technology for technologies sake.
And that's just another way of saying we
skip a lot of the small stuff. And we
try to really focus our efforts and our
resources in our newsroom on covering
the highest impact technologies. So the
ones that we really think have a big
chance to reshape the way that we live
and the way that we work.
So you've all been sitting here for a
little while and I wanted you to humor
me and participate in this little
activity uh before I get into what I
have to share with you. This is
something that our senior AI reporter
James O'Donnell put together. He wanted
to test whether our audience and our
editors in our newsroom could
distinguish between music created using
artificial intelligence and generated by
AI and music composed and performed by a
human. So, I'm just going to play you
two clips here and then I'm going to ask
you all to vote. One of these was
created by people, humans. One of them
was created by AI. And we'll see if you
can tell the difference.
>> Quiet glow.
I find myself alone. Tears go.
Rains of sorrow
from a love grown cold.
Memories fading tales untold.
Whispers in.
>> And now for the rock song.
Think about it.
Okay, time to vote. So, one of these
generated by AI, one of them composed
and performed by humans. Who thinks the
folk song was the one that AI created?
Raise your hand.
All right, it's a good chunk of people.
Who thinks the rock song is the one that
AI created?
Okay, I think most of you got it right.
It's a little bit of a split, but in
fact, it was the first one. uh the folk
song that was AI generated. He made the
he made that in a tool called Udo and I
think it'll be an interesting uh space
to follow. Certainly we're going to see
more generative AI making music I think
in the future.
But first the first uh trend and topic I
wanted to talk with you all about is
really generative video which is kind of
the forefront of where where a lot of
the uh best advances are happening in
generative AI right now. We've seen for
a couple of years these multimodal
models getting better and better, models
that you can input all kinds of
different formats into, whether it's
text or photos or videos, and they'll
output in all of those formats as well.
Uh, but lately, the generative video is
getting really impressive, and I'll show
you a couple clips of just what's
possible today.
This was made using Google's V3 model,
and you can see that it you can uh add
sound effects with this model. The next
one's an action sequence produced by the
same model. So, brace yourselves. It's a
little louder.
You can see how realistic that is. It
took a long prompt to get that. You can
see the level of detail described in
this prompt, all the different things
that they're specifying. But it doesn't
have to be that complicated. The next
clip I'm going to show you is almost
just as realistic, and it was a prompt
that just had two sentences.
Then the next example I'm going to show
you has a line of dialogue in it that
was included in the prompt.
>> This ocean, it's a force, a wild untamed
might. And she commands your awe with
every breaking light.
>> So these tools are getting better and
better. We've I've shown you a bunch of
short clips so far, but it's also now
possible to string a lot of these short
clips together and make a short film
with characters and scenes that are
consistent and believable uh throughout.
>> Wow, this is a real breakthrough.
And of course, in the last couple of six
weeks or so, one of the biggest
announcements within generative video is
the release of OpenAI's Sora app, which
is a Tik Tok-like experience that has an
endless scroll, but allows you to
produce purely AI generated content. You
can actually put celebrities, uh, people
like Sam Alman into your videos if you
want. You can put yourself into the
videos in any kind of situation or
scenario that you want. Um, so this is
obviously an AI generated uh video of
Sam Alman enjoying our 10 Breakthrough
Technologies issue. So this is all
pretty cool and there's some neat things
we can do with it, but there's also some
problems that come along with it, of
course. One of them being AI slop. We're
seeing tons of this out there. Uh, both
with text that's just filling the
internet and also a lot of weird images
and videos. Some of them are just
horrendously bad and awful. Um, others
are being used to perpetuate hoaxes. Uh,
people believing that they're they're
real and they're not. So, this is
unfortunately a problem that I really
think is going to just be with us for a
while. I don't see any kind of immediate
solution to it.
Another consequence of how good this
technology is getting is that it's
actually getting quite hard to tell who
and what is real online these days. It's
now possible to make really
hyperrealistic digital avatars of
ourselves or people that we know or to
generate completely AI fabricated humans
who look very realistic but don't
actually exist in the real world. So to
illustrate this, I'm going to show you
this short clip of one of our reporters,
Riionan, who used one of these tools
produced by a company called Synthesia
to make a digital avatar of herself. And
I'll let you be the judge of how
convincing this is.
>> This is an avatar created with Express
2. New technology elevates body
movements to an entirely new dimension.
This is great. Check out these
movements.
>> So, it's kind of cheesy. Uh, it's a
little bit awkward, but if you know
Rihanna, like I do, like it does look
and sound like her, and it'll be
interesting. This techn is also only
going to get uh better. We also reported
on a study by Stanford and Deep Mind
that showed that an AI model could
interview somebody for just two hours
and then start to mimic aspects of their
personality. So things like their values
and their preferences, which could make
these even more believable.
One more test for you. Uh, so not not
just videos, but even just straight
images are really realistic these days.
Uh this is from a site called
whichfaces.com.
Hopefully self-explanatory. It was put
together by University of Washington
researchers and they just give a ton of
examples like this where one of the
images is a real photo of a real actual
human and the other image is AI
generated. So I want to ask you all to
vote again just one more time. So who
thinks the person in the hat is the AI
generated human here? Just raise your
hand.
And who thinks the person in the glasses
is the AI generated human?
That was a little bit more mixed. Um,
but I think most of you got it wrong
that time. Don't feel bad, though. I
actually got this one wrong, too. Uh, if
you like this game, there are a lot more
examples on this site that you can play
around with. So, what are we going to do
about all this? I bet you've heard of
some of the solutions that are being
proposed. Things like watermarks that
you embed in images or videos, either
visibly or invisibly in the metadata
that travels along with them across the
internet. Also, there's uh work on
developing what are called personhood
credentials here at MIT actually uh with
OpenAI and Microsoft. This would be like
a token that's stored kind of on your
phone, maybe like in the wallet app of
your phone, and you might actually have
to go to a a government office or an
organization to get it installed on your
phone, but then you'd be able to use it
to cryptographically verify that you're
in fact a real human anytime you wanted
to do something uh online that required
that.
So, one of the areas that I think is
most interesting to follow to kind of
see what's coming up or what's most
exciting uh with generative AI is the
gaming world and gaming companies are
kind of leaning full into this
technology and developers are doing some
really cool stuff with it. So, I wanted
to spend a few moments talking about
that. Um, for example, the gaming
company Niantic is using some of the
data collected from Pokemon Go to build
a geospatial model of the world, uh,
that actually obeys the the laws of
physics that our real world relies on,
which could help machines kind of
understand how objects exist in the
world and the rules by which they're
governed.
Roblox also had an open- source uh,
project called Cube that it built. It's
a 3D foundation model that would allow
you to generate objects that can be
moved around in the 3D space and viewed
from any angle. And so this would allow
somebody without any kind of game design
or coding experience to start to develop
digital worlds of their own.
There's also been some really cool tests
of like what happens if you put AI
agents into a gaming environment and
then just sort of let them go. Uh
especially when they're trained using
large language models. And this is an
example from Minecraft. They let loose a
bunch of AI agents in Minecraft to just
see what they would do. And because they
were using large language models that
have ingested tons of data about humans
behave, they started to do some really
human things. So these agents actually
started their own religion and they
voted on tax reform laws. And so they
were they didn't this behavior kind of
spontaneously emerged. Of course, it's
rooted in the patterns of the training
data that they have ingested, but it's
just kind of funny to like see these
agents um coming up with these things
kind of on their own as well based on
what they know about us. Another example
is this uh project putting into a
environment called Smallville. There
were 25 different agents in this
environment. In this case, they were
each given a job and like a personality
and then just left and then just left
for a few days. And they also did some
funny stuff. So they a couple of them
like organized and attended a
Valentine's Day party. One of them asked
another one out on a date. Uh another
one decided to run for office and then
there was like a side conversation about
that. So it's you know kind of like a
strange uh way to like look at ourselves
through these agents and kind of the
behavior that emerges uh when when they
do these experiments.
And then there's also some really
interesting work being done around using
generative AI to create games as you
play them. This is a very rudimentary
example, but it is a AI generated game
example of Minecraft. So there was no
code being written for this game. This
is just a model trained on millions of
hours of people playing Minecraft and
it's being generated on the fly as you
play it. And so this version isn't very
good. You know, the graphics aren't
great. It kind of breaks down after you
play it for a few seconds. But you could
imagine something like this eventually
augmenting the abilities of human
developers or maybe even allowing
players to actually decide the course of
the game as they play it.
All right, next topic. Uh, AI and
generative AI in particular is really
changing the way that we search online.
This is a really important development,
I think, in the way that information is
organized and consumed online. It's
really the biggest change in decades to
search in the internet, which is
something that most of us do many times
a day. And we're talking here, of
course, about the infusion of large
language models into search engines.
things like uh Google's AI overviews,
which I'm sure you're seeing pop up on
all of your searches these days. Also
things like Microsoft's efforts to
infuse OpenAI's models into its uh Bing
search engine. And also stuff like
ChatGpt being able to go out and fetch
data from the live web uh now when you
type in a prompt. There's of course AI
powered search on our devices too that's
happening there as well. And also in
apps uh like all of the Meta family
apps, Facebook Messenger and Instagram
uh etc.
So, this is such a big shift that we
actually put it on our list of 10
breakthrough technologies this year for
2025. And I think it raises some really
interesting questions for all of you
just about like your customers and your
employees are going to be interacting
with generative search all over the
place. And so, what does it mean for the
kinds of like the products that you're
building and the information that you're
sharing about your company and how
you're getting that all out there?
Of course, we're thinking about this in
the media business a lot. How are
publishers like us going to reach
people? is all of the information and
coverage that we do in the future going
to be mediated through these kind of AI
chat bots and what you know what can we
do about it or what should we do about
it? I've started to hear about companies
that can like optimize what you're doing
for supposedly to help you show up more
in the large language models. I'm not
convinced that's real yet. So if you've
had any like good experiences or know
more about that, I would love to hear.
Uh next, this is a very personal topic.
Perhaps some of you are already doing
this or have tried it uh yourselves.
People are turning to these AI chat bots
increasingly for a form of
companionship. In some case it's in
cases it's basically around uh what's
called as synthetic friendship. So it's
a form of uh friendship but others the
humans involved actually believe it to
be a type of romantic relationship.
So we uh have surveyed our subscribers
who attended one of our monthly
roundtables online events about this to
see like how are you doing this like
would you do this and the vast majority
of them said that they either had tried
this themselves using chat bots for
companionship or were interested in
doing it. So what kinds of companionship
are we talking about here? There's a
broad spectrum. Uh we had a actually the
reporter you saw earlier the avatar of
she did a nice story that was just
talking with some people about how
they're using chat bots for
companionship, what they're getting out
of it, how it's affecting their real
world relationships. And so there's some
nice examples here from that piece.
There's a 52-year-old woman in Canada
who was using it kind of as a way to
like chat and vent about her stresses
throughout the day related to work or
problems going on in her life. It was
like a type of journaling kind of for
her but like with a more active
conversation partner and she described
it as being very cathartic. Then there
was a a Dutch man who had married a
Chinese woman and they were living
together in Thailand. And he said that
sometimes they just had these fights
where like they could not see eye to eye
and he was convinced that it was
something to do with linguistic
differences or just cultural differences
in the way that they were raised. So he
had taken to using anthropics claude as
a sort of like third opinion in these
arguments and asking it to help him get
a different perspective on whatever they
were fighting about. And he said it
worked really well. Uh his advice if you
want to try this at home is to tell
Claude that you're asking about this
situation for a friend because Claude
always just like tends to agree with
whoever is asking the question and
that's not that helpful in that
situation.
There is a more sinister side of this of
course like there are people that are
starting to use these chat bots as a
form of therapy um which we do not
recommend and neither does the American
Psychological Association. These chat
bots none of them are approved for
mental health treatment. They are not
HIPPA compliant. So whatever you put
into them may not stay there, may not
stay private. Uh and there have been a
few allegations of these chat bots
encouraging suicidal thinking. We even
reported on one that it suggested ways
of carrying that out. I am hopeful that
in the long run these chat bots might
actually improve access to highquality
therapy. There has been one clinical
trial that we reported on in the spring
uh reported on also in the the New
England Journal of Medicine about a
specially designed chatbot that was
created by mental health professionals
called Therabot. And it was shown in
this trial to be as effective as uh
psychotherapy in treating people for
depression, anxiety, and those who are
at risk of eating disorders. And it was
equivalent to basically 16 hours of
psychotherapy in terms of the results it
got, but it delivered those in half the
time. So, that still needs to make it
its way all the way through clinical
trials and be approved and such. But
hopefully, uh, someday these will
improve access to this important
service.
All right, next. We've heard a lot about
agents recently. I bet you've heard a
lot about these, too. It's a big buzzy
topic in AI right now. I want this
tomorrow. Like, I want this like
yesterday. I would love to have one of
these that can just go out and take care
of a bunch of busy work for me. Um,
there have been some promising
developments over the last year. We've
seen more of the underlying kind of
fundamental protocols being developed.
Anthropic had its model context
protocols come out about a year ago and
Google has its agentto aagent protocol.
These are the kind of fundamental
infrastructure layers that do need to
happen in order to enable this agentic
uh universe of the future. There's also
a project here at the MIT media lab by
Romesh Rascar, a professor there, that
is aiming to build a it's called Nanda,
and it's aiming to build a layer of
search and authentication and other
features on top of these protocols. Um,
so that's all really exciting work. This
is a demo of OpenAI's operator uh agent.
So, there are some out there now in beta
mode and and making their way out into
the world. In this case, you can see it
booking a campsite for somebody given
the directions of of that person and
what kind of campsite uh they wanted. I
think it'll be interesting to think
about how and when an AI needs to
identify itself during one of these
interactions when the person on the
other end needs to know that it's
interacting with an AI or your AI agent
instead of actually you. I think it's
still early days though for a lot of
this agent stuff. uh it's still taking
shape and I think there will be a number
of of interoperability challenges that
we have to overcome once these protocols
are are more uh established and I also
think there's a big question of trust
with users where you know people will
need to at some point hand over their
social media credentials and their
passwords and their credit cards to
these agents and you know there will be
some trust that uh people need to have
in these systems uh to make them ready
for that.
There are a few areas though where AI
and generative AI in particular is
really already starting to help us get
stuff done. I bet you've heard about a
few of these. Uh coding is one of them.
So there was a report by a study by MIT
Sloan that came out last year looking at
software engineers who were paired with
a coding assistant. It was GitHub's
co-pilot at three different companies,
Microsoft, Accenture, and a Fortune 100
electronics manufacturing firm. And
that's that study found that those who
were using the coding assistant were
more productive. And that was
particularly true among more junior
employees and newer employees to these
firms. Uh the caveat is that it was
judging productivity by quantity of
output, not necessarily the quality of
code. So just keep that in mind. And
then there's also vibe coding, which is
something that you may have heard of.
It's this other way of doing uh coding
with uh an LLM where you're basically
kind of just prompting it and you're not
going into the code yourself. You're
just going off of the vibes of whatever
it gives you and kind of having this
very low-key exchange. uh which is a
really creative interesting way to use
it and it can help people with no coding
experience kind of start to make things
um but it's probably not a best practice
for most companies because you can
introduce a lot of security um
challenges that way and bugs in the
code. And then biology is another area
where we're starting to see some pretty
miraculous um things happen. Google deep
Google DeepMind's Alpha Fold of course
last year won the Nobel Prize for its
ability to predict protein folding.
proteins are these building blocks of
life and the way that they fold impacts
their function and errors in that can
cause disease. Um last year that team
within the last year that team has also
started to predict the behavior of DNA
and RNA and there's a lot of hope in
this space that this will help us
discover new treatments and find new
drugs and I hope it does too. Um, next
we're seeing I just wanted to mention
this. This is a newer area, but we are
seeing uh some big names in the AI
industry put a lot of uh effort and
investment into what's called world
models, which are these new kinds of
models that are um able to generate very
realistic 3D environments from a prompt
uh that do obey the laws of our physical
world and which an AI could then go off
and train in and maybe learn the way our
world works much like a human child
works. the thinking goes um this could
be useful for areas like robotics or
self-driving cars. You can imagine uh
Google's Genie3 is one example of this
and FE Lee the Stanford professor uh who
started her company World Labs is also
working to develop these. I think you're
going to hear a lot more about world
models in the coming year.
All right. So far, we've been talking
mostly about these different models that
are out there, some practical uses for
them, but in these next few slides, I
just wanted to kind of step back and
talk about some of the bigger picture
things we know about how these models
work and some of the the issues around
them. So, one is that hallucination is a
feature, not a bug. It comes from the
way that these models are built, and it
it isn't a problem that's going to be
able to uh probably be resolved. And to
illustrate this, here's a meme that
started making its way around after
ChatGBT was released in late 2022. And
it sort of explains a little bit about
the architecture of how these models
were created. Uh, ingesting large
amounts of data, unstructured data from
the internet. That's the unsupervised
learning big ugly monster head there.
And then you have supervised
fine-tuning, which is the purple face
that looks a little less scary, but
still kind of dicey. And that's
referring to the practice of going back
in with much more cleaner kind of better
labeled data sets in specific domains to
help these models develop a little bit
more expertise and improve their
performance in a few key areas. And then
you have the RLHF uh yellow smiley face
which is uh stands for reinforcement
learning from human feedback. And that's
a practice that more of the big tech
companies are using to basically go back
in and manually reprogram and put
patches on parts of the model that are
returning harmful content or that are
allowing users to jailbreak the model.
Um, so you get the impression the artist
was trying to convey that, you know,
this is a lot of like polish being put
on something that still has some pretty
big fundamental issues here.
These models obviously don't understand
like what they're doing. They don't have
a degree of comprehension. um they are
essentially predicting the next word in
a sentence or the next pixel in an image
based on all the data that they've been
uh trained on. And it can be hard to
know when they're getting it right and
when they're getting it wrong.
Increasingly they're getting it more and
more right, which is great because a lot
of these fixes and fine-tuning. Um but
it's still the case that sometimes you
can put the same prompt into the same
model and have, you know, a couple of
tries at that uh over and over and it'll
produce accurate answers uh part of the
time and inaccurate answers other parts
of the time, which is just good to keep
in mind.
Uh this is one just real world
consequence relatively low stakes but
still um you might have seen this over
the summer. The Chicago Sun Times put
out a summer reading list and
unbeknownst to the publication the
author had used generative AI to create
it and so the model returned a list of
real authors with books that they never
wrote and which didn't actually exist.
So just a reminder to just double check
whatever you're getting out of the
models and don't use them for anything
like too consequential.
All right, just two topics left. Um one
you have probably heard that AI is
getting power is very power hungry
already and getting hungrier. There's a
lot of uh discussion around this. You
know AI requiring more uh computing and
more electricity to run all the servers
in these massive data centers that are
being um built. There's a lot of concern
as well about this demand for AI that's
increasing exacerbating climate change
and driving up uh carbon emissions.
And so this is uh these are some charts
from a report by the International
Energy Agency that was released in the
spring just illustrating what this
increase in demand might look like. Um
and you can see that most of the data
centers in the world are in the US and
China. So that's where the greatest
projected demand is meant to be. And
there is of course more demand coming
from AI for energy and electricity, but
that's also true for all kinds of other
stuff like electric vehicles and air
conditioning and heat pumps etc. Uh and
so the real question is can we power an
increasing share of these with
renewables uh and nuclear instead of
fossil fuels. And so you'll see on the
other chart um most of the electricity
provided to data centers today comes
from fossil fuels, natural gas and coal.
And that will be the case and these
projections for the next five years. And
then starting in 2030, you start to see
renewables and nuclear uh coming more
into the mix there.
We did a big package on this issue uh in
the spring called Tower Hungry. If
you're interested, you can look that up.
and learn more. It's not just an energy
and electricity issue. It's also a water
issue and we had a story about that.
This is a data center um complex being
built in Reno, Nevada, which is of
course a desert.
And uh there are other efforts being
being made which we also have a story
about in that package to make data
centers more efficient. Um ways to
manage their waste heat and also for
chips to manage their temperature a
little bit better. Um, so this is
definitely a space that we're going to
be following uh along with. When the
team that produced that package first
started working on their story, they
really couldn't get any information from
Google or OpenAI about how much energy
these large language models were using
or how much a individual prompt uh would
consume. But eventually uh after we
published Google and open did release a
little bit more information and Google
has said that the median prompt so in
the middle of the distribution uh that
they handle produces the same or
requires the same amount of power to as
it would to run a mic a standard
microwave for uh one second and about
five drops of water. Uh if you're
concerned about your personal AI use,
our analysis did also show that
generating videos is a lot more energy
intensive than images or text. So maybe
just go easy on the go easy on the
videos if that's important to you. Um,
next final note, I just wanted to end on
a bit of a philosophical one, which is
that nobody really knows how these large
language models work, which is sort of
just fascinating to think about. Not
even the the researchers and the tech
companies that are building them and
putting them out. We know that they are,
you know, built uh using deep learning
techniques, built on neural networks
that are meant to mimic the architecture
of our brains. But as far as how they
learn, what they learn, and how they
take inputs and produce outputs, it's
all still a bit of a mystery. There are
some cool new research techniques being
developed to help us get a better
glimpse inside that black box, though.
One of them is called a mechanistic
interpretability. Um, it's a way of
trying to analyze the circuits within
the uh models and try to trace kind of
the inputs to the outputs and understand
more about that process.
Just a few fun examples here. uh Claude,
which is anthropic's large language
model. Uh researchers there took a look
at that using some of these techniques
and they noticed that um there were
certain parts of the model that were
associated with celebrities, certain
celebrities, so like Michael Jordan or
certain concepts like potatoes uh or
even abstract concepts like
disobedience. And they found a section
of the model that was seemed to be like
associated with the Golden Gate Bridge
because um every time it was like shown
images of the bridge or asked a question
about the bridge, that part of the model
like lit up so to speak. Um and so then
when they like amped up that part of the
model, Claude started like putting the
Golden Gate Bridge in every answer that
it produced about anything. So even if
you ask it for like a recipe, it would
like put the Golden Gate Bridge in the
recipe. And at one point it even thought
it was the Golden Gate Bridge. So that
was just really like interesting. um
experiment. This is another one also by
the anthropic team. So they asked Claude
to solve a simple math problem and it
got the right answer and they said, "How
did you solve that problem?" And it told
them like a very straightforward
explanation like you would read in any
textbook. But then they used their their
techniques uh circuit tracing techniques
of showing kind of what the model was
actually doing, not just taking its word
for it. And it had this wild process
that was not intuitive at all to how we
would solve a math problem. So you can
see it took the two numbers that they
asked it to add and it sort of like
estimated some numbers around those two
numbers and then it looked at the final
digits of each number and it said, "Oh,
this answer is going to have to end in
the number five." And then it sort of
mashed those ideas together and it
happened to come up with the right
answer. But it's not at all the way that
it said it was solving the problem. And
it's just like fascinating to think that
this is what's going on uh inside these.
And I hope we'll learn more about what
these models look like in the years to
come. And then finally, last I just
wanted to mention that um there's
increasingly efforts uh to make AI that
is better at making making itself
better. So self-improving artificial
intelligence. Uh Meta's super
intelligence team is working on this
trying to make uh AI that can develop
its own training data or produce its own
algorithms that will make it uh more
efficient. Um, and there's other other
efforts around this as well, including
at uh Google uh with their alpha evolve
program, which is taking large language
models and using what's called
evolutionary algorithms meant to be able
to improve themselves over time. So, we
might see accelerated progress in this
field. Uh, from this, that's all I have
for you. That was my whirlwind tour
through the future of artificial
intelligence. I don't have a crystal
crystal ball. These are all educated
guesses. That's what we do in our
newsroom. Sometimes we're right.
oftentimes, you know, things evolve in
unexpected ways. Um, if you want to
follow along with our coverage on these
topics, there's a QR code here. You can
scan and sign up for our morning
newsletter. It's called the download. It
comes out at 8 a.m. Eastern every day.
It's free to sign up for. And there's
also a subscription offer here as well.
Um, if we have time for questions, I'm
happy to take a few. And also, um, if
anybody has any like thing they would
love to talk to me about later that they
would love to see more in our magazine,
I'm always interested in hearing, uh,
ideas for that as well.
Um yes. Okay. So this is a great
question. So we also have this other
list called innovators under 35 which I
think this is referring to. Um you know
this year actually
this year so we have done this in uh
we've been doing this list the
breakthrough technologies list for this
will be the 25th year 26th year. And at
the 20-year mark, one of our editors,
David, who was on stage earlier, uh he
went back and looked at the very first
list of 10 breakthrough technologies, at
what was on that list and like did, you
know, evaluated our record. And there
were a few things on there like natural
language processing, which is still very
relevant and kind of underpins the large
language models we have today. Uh brain
computer interfaces, which you know have
been a little bit slower um to develop,
but that we're still talking about
today, which is pretty interesting. And
uh this year I'm actually participating
with a MIT class that is doing that same
exercise. They're looking into our
archives and um we're having a
conversation kind of about what they're
finding and which technologies haven't
worked out because there are definitely
some flops in there and um talking
through kind of what uh what what caused
them to not work out and what might have
might have been changed to make them
have a better chance. Um so I'm always
interested in uh in that as well now
that especially we have this long
history of it. I think that's all we
have time for, but thank you all so much
for your attention this late in the day.
I appreciate it.