um it might have been a little cognitive
dissonance for those you who know the
term because today is the lecture I tell
you why everything I taught you this
semester is wrong um and maybe I was a
little reluctant to come in and do that
but in all seriousness today we're going
to talk about behavioral
economics um we're going to talk about
basically how we can bring this insights
from
psychology into understanding how we
make the models in the semester more
realistic now once again let's remember
the role of models the role of models
remember the George boach saying all
models are wrong but some are useful
okay the goal of the models this
semester were to figure out how to
parsimoniously explain the world how to
give you models that you guys could
solve in a problem set that have
enormous explanatory power for how the
world functions and we've done that that
said
we can always make our models better and
as you go on in economics your goal
should be to think about how we enrich
these models and make them better but
without losing the goal of parsimony
without losing the goal of having models
that are
manageable can explain the world which
means how do we sort of minimally extend
our models to think about bringing much
richer
phenomenon so let's talk about so what
behavioral economics does is essentially
say look there's a set of realities from
psychology that we ignore in
economics behavioral economics is about
how can we build models to bring in what
we know is true from psychological
research and the best example of this is
models of what we
call time
inconsistency this is the best example
of how we bring in an important Insight
from psychology in a manageable way into
our mind
models okay so the idea of time Inc
consistency is that a widespread
phenomenon that is not only always shown
in psychological experiments but in fact
never rejected in psychological
experiments is the human problem of
self-control the human problem of
self-control we have a problem
controlling
ourselves okay and what does this mean
in economic terms it doesn't mean that
individuals are
irrational it doesn't mean that the
models we wrote down and the
optimization assumptions we make itly
wrong what it means is while we can make
optimal plans we can't carry them out so
in words think about the optimization
problem done so far as having two parts
you make an optimal plan and then you
carry it out we haven't separated those
we've just said you decide how many
cookies in Pizza eat that many cookies
in pizza but in fact there's two steps
first you got to decide how many cookies
in pizza pizza then you got to eat that
many cookies in Pizza you might think
well that's sort of irrelevant the
Second Step it's trivial but it's not
it's not trivial Whenever there are
costs and benefits that differ in
time okay and when there are costs or
benefits at differ in time this can lead
to self-control problems in particular
when you have a decision that imposes a
short run cost for a long run benefit
humans will undertake that activity
when we have an activity that imposes a
short run cost long-term benefit humans
as a species I don't know maybe other
species too will undertake that activity
so for example smoking if you're a
smoker 90% of smokers when surveyed say
they'd like to quit yet 90% do not quit
why because when you wake up in the
morning you feel awful until you have
that cigarette you have the cigarette
and you're like okay I'll have a smoke
to I'll quit tomorrow
okay the idea of I can quit tomorrow
I'll solve that tomorrow that's a
standard feature of self-control
problems let's think about savings for
retirement in our model of retirement
savings we had someone deciding across
C1 and C2 and they just optimized with
some indifference curve and budget
constraint we're not saying any of that
math was wrong we're saying in practice
it's actually hard to put the money away
and save it because in practice once you
have the money there's a lot of
attractive stuff I talked about how ge
when you get the job you start saving
right away but but right away when you
get the job you want a new car and you
want a party and things like that so
it's hard to say well yeah I'm going to
save for 50 years from now so and rather
than going to the party tonight okay
maybe not once again hard to each In
This Crowd we're all we're all a very
sort of self-controlled crowd Rel to
most Americans but I think we all have
experien with this okay think about
dieting or exercise things where there's
a with dieting there's a short-run cost
you cannot eat that piece of cake which
is delicious for a long run benefit
exercise the short run cost which is
you've got to go work out it takes time
it takes effort for a long run benefit
now once again you all look very fit
maybe you don't feel that way about
dieting exercise but we all have things
we have self-control problems over mine
is biting my nails I cannot stop biting
my nails I'd like to stop biting my
nails I make plans to stop biting my
nails when I've got a deadline of paper
on my favorite teams on TV I bite my
nails okay I've tried things like the
you can pain on your nails to make them
taste terrible it just tastes terrible
when I bite my nails okay I have a
self-control problem with all all humans
not all humans most humans suffer from
self-control problems of one or another
so the question is how do we build that
into the models we use how do we take
the kind of parsimonious model we've
used and add an element of time
inconsistency well let's come back to
the intertemporal choice model we had
before the interal Choice model was
someone trading off consuming today
versus consuming tomorrow and and let's
make that rather than sa vers tomorrow
let's make it the whole Future Let's
make someone's decision let's say that
someone has a has a utility function
that depends on the entire future path
of their
consumption okay all that matters to my
utility is
consumption but the entire Future Path
but here's the key thing let's also
remember we learned about discounting
that I care less about the future than I
care about today okay this is remember
with npv we talked about how money today
is worth more than the money in the
future which is why people would save
the reason people don't save is because
I care more about today than I do about
the future and those humans have an
inherent discounting of the future that
offsets the return to
saving having putting money aside today
is a benefit you get more tomorrow but
it's a cost which is we'd rather have
today than tomorrow that's the
human nature we call that discounting
and we tip the way we typically model
this is we say look we can model your
utility at as the sum from today till
the end of time till you
die of your
consumption in each period you're let's
say you're going to consume the same
amount every time let's say consumption
smooth so C's constant let's just lay
say say soon same m forever times Delta
to the IUS
T Delta is what we call a discount
Factor Delta is less than one greater
than zero it's the discount factor it's
how much less I care about consumption
in the
future okay so for example if Delta's
0.9 then that
says consuming something next year makes
me 90% as happy as consuming it
today consuming something in two year
and we assume Delta by this functional
formulation is exponential
okay so we assume consuming something in
two years is 09 squared so it's
081 okay so basically we assume that
exponentially every period in the future
is worth less so next year is worth 0. n
of today two years is 081 of today Etc
so we assume that basically the reason
people don't my retirement saving sample
is pretty compelling right save 15 years
you're better off than to save for the
next 33 years why don't people do it
then UND do it CU at at a Delta even
arbitrarily close to one 50 years from
now is
irrelevant okay you know if you take you
know 0. n to the 50 okay it's
irrelevant okay or if you do you know
even if it's 095 50 years around you
don't care about as long as you're
somewhat
impatient the distant future doesn't
matter and that's why people don't say
for retirement okay that's why despite
the incredibly strong incentives I laid
out people people don't because they
discount the
Future Okay questions about why why
question about that
model okay that's our standard economics
model that's what I grew up with that's
what you learn basic economics okay
that's what you learn in the next level
when you go on and do more economics
this is the model you'll learn okay it's
a multiversion period of the
multiversion version of the two period
model I taught you but it's
wrong why is it wrong it's wrong because
every single psychological experiment
ever run shows that discounting is not
exponential but rather
hyperbolic which means that
people the discounting of the
future is much much steeper than we get
when just from a pure exponential
function okay and here's a simple
example of that okay I'm going to do let
me say this example slowly it's
important to get it right imagine I
offer you the following okay $100 I
offer you a choice $100 today or $125 in
a
year $100 say $125 in a year you can
just don't don't vote just so guys feel
about this Choice then I offer you a
different choice I say $100 in two
years versus
$125 in three
years now with this exponential function
that's the same
Choice it's only a 0. n factor between
them it's a one-year Gap so it shouldn't
matter if I if you today versus one year
or two years versus three years it turns
out it matters enormously people always
take the this year but they'll delay it
in the future that is people are willing
are impatient today but willing to be
patient in the
future and that is an illustration of
self-control
problems that when it's it's about
having your hot little hands you want it
if it's about well will you save in the
future sure I'll save in the future
that's great happy to do
that okay and this example is exactly
why this exponential model is
wrong and the hyperbolic model is
right that basically people feel
differently about today than the future
and so uh an economist Dame L named
davidon at Harvard said look let's make
a simple tweak to this model let's reite
WR utility as the utility of today is
today's consumption
C plus a factor beta times the sum from
tomorrow next year till the end of
time times C * Delta to the IUS
t i minus t okay how is this different
than
this all I've done is I've pulled out
today and add an extra Factor B to the
rest of the future beta to the rest of
the future so look at this function
versus this function all I've done is
pulled out one C from the sum kept the
rest of the sum and add an extra factor
beter in front of
this what is that doing that's saying
that starting next year I'm an
exponential
Discounter but with beta less than one
that entire future is wor less than it
today than it would be under an
exponential
model okay so let me let me um do this
in a simple example okay let's say
that um uh you have um let's say that uh
you're offered 100 today versus 125 next
year
okay and then as I said so so 100 in t
versus 125 and t+ 1 and 100 in t +
2 uh 100 and t+ 1 versus 125 and t+
2 well from for this
decision you use this part of the term
which is the same as exponential so as
long as Delta isn't very small you're
going to wait so let's say Delta's 0. n
so that says that next year's is worth
125 time 0.9 which is still greater than
100 so you'd say I'll
wait but for this decision you've got
Delta and
beta and the best s in the laboratory of
beta is
0.6 so now it's 125 time9 time .9 time
6 because you've got the regular delay
of a year but you also have this extra
factor which is you really like it today
and care less about tomorrow so now you
reject the
offer and that is a simple
parameterization of how you could reject
this offer but accept this
offer you reject this offer because this
offer has an extra feature that
discounts at
beta okay that is how that is how a very
smart Economist builds a psychological
insight in a relatively simple way into
one of our models take the model tweak a
little bit just pull the C out add a
beta boom you can explain a phenomenal
we couldn't have explained before that's
good
modeling now to be fair while this looks
simple solving this model turns out to
be a total nightmare okay I
could not teach in this class I'm not
sure I can do it okay even though it's
simple because you've got all these
iterative terms that gets very
complicated okay and which is why we
don't teach it even though it's probably
a better model okay but it's an example
of how you can relatively parsimoniously
incorporate this
idea okay let me give you one final
example let questions about
this let give you one one other example
to motivate this they did a really cool
experiment in Amsterdam which is they
went to people and they said um here's a
snack that you can have in one week what
would you like and there was healthy and
unhealthy snacks mixed in the list they
said you have snack in one week what
would you like about 50% of people chose
the healthy snack
they then came back a week later and
saidou know here's what you chose but
guess what today we're going to let you
change your decision would you like to
change it and almost everyone changed it
to have the unhealthy
snack that is when it was a week away
they were happy to wait for the healthy
snack but today they wanted the candy
okay that is timing consistency that's
what this captures that our standard
model does it that's the only math I'm
going to do today the only modeling I'll
do today but that is the an example of
how we can take a deep psychological
insight and build it into our economics
model and enrich it to capture a whole
new set of phenomena this is what and
this is what we do in the course 1413
which is one of our most popular under
grad course when 200 people take it a
year incredibly great course which is
behavioral economics which is teaching
you how you take the next step from 1401
to incorporate these psychological
phenomena into
models okay
yeah that is the the most difficult
there's a lot of hard problems here
what's the right time for frame is a
really hard problem here's the even
harder
problem how do you do welfare how do you
do welfare when people make mistakes
we've said welfare is the sum the so
welfare function is the sum of
individual utility functions what if the
people in individual utility functions
are making mistakes does the government
still just want to sum up their utility
function does the government want to
correct those mistakes hard question so
that's exactly that's why 14 13 is fun
you struggle with some deep
philosophical issues like
that okay now what I want to do now
rather than writing down other models
because I want to you can take 1413 for
to do that I want to run through a set
of fun insights that we get from
behavioral
economics okay and talk about what they
apply so let me just sort of talk about
some additional insights some other
examples these are sort of other
behavioral
insights that we've worked on over the
past few decades that we'd love to
incorporate into our models to make a
realistic model the first and one of the
most
is loss
aversion and I mentioned this briefly we
talked about
uncertainty which is remember I gave you
guys the gamble win 100 win 125 lose 100
and you mostly didn't take it then I
said well what if it was win 1250 lose
10 more of you should take it not many
more of you did but more of you should
and ultim if I said it was win a125 lose
a dollar everyone all of you should take
it okay unless you're super risk averse
that's a great deal no matter how
wealthy you are but it turns out that
that's not true it turns out that even
that basically people turn down gambles
that can be above and beyond what's
explained by risk
aversion okay and the best way to see
this is um this great calculation that
was done uh by The Economist Matt Ren so
let's say someone would turn down
someone of an average wealth so they've
got you know thousands of dollars
you offer them a 50/50 shot win 11 lose
10 and they turn it down you say well
that's just risk aversion right but if
you apply that risk aversion to other
bets you see how ridiculous that is that
says that you would
also turn down win 2100 lose
800 it also means you would lose you
would if I offered you the BET lose a,
win Infinity you would turn it
down that if you're risk averse enough
that you turn down win 100 lose win 110
lose 100 and you extend that same risk
aversion that same parameter impli you
would turn down lose a th win Infinity
none of you would turn that down you
sure if you did I'd be disappointed in
you okay so basically the bottom line is
risk aversion can't explain these
decisions what can is the model of loss
aversion which is that people have
endowment
effects that is I care more stuff I have
already I care more about than stuff I
might
get so here's the best example of how we
think about endowment
effects which is that they did an
experiment where they randomly selected
individuals half of them they said
here's a mug it says M or whatever how
much would you pay for this mug and they
got a demand curve and the average
person would have paid $5
the other half the people I'm sorry so
no let me go back it was a mug with a
market price of $5 that how much people
want to pay the people pay pay about
$3 then they did a second experiment
randomly they gave a set of other people
they gave them the mug and said how much
would I have to pay you to buy this back
from you and the average person said
$7 same decision right in the one case I
just gave you the mug in other case I
didn't but if the mug is worth $3 to you
to buy why would you only sell it for $7
because once you have it you feel
differently it's an endowment effect
okay here's a great example from the
from the Nobel prize winning Economist
Richard Taylor okay imagine the
following two questions a you have been
exposed to a disease which if contracted
leads to a quick and painless death
within a week the probability you have
this disease is
.1% what would you be willing to pay for
a cure that's question one question two
is we need to research this
disease if you're in the sample you'll
have to expose yourself and risk
yourself to a 0.1% chance of
dying how much would I have to pay you
to be in the
experiment now I hope you could see that
as the same
question in both cases you're asking how
much is it worth to you to take a 01
chance of 0.1% chance of dying yet if
you ask people the first question
question they'd be willing to pay $200
for a cure you ask the second question
you'd have to pay them
$100,000 to be in the
study one so there's a 5,000 fold
difference between what people or five
500 fold difference between these two
framings and the only difference in
framing is the endowment effect so
obviously this is a clear thing we
should ultimately want to build into our
models the problem is it's like the
question as this nice astute question
asked here what's the right time period
here here the question what's the right
endowment how do I think about the
endowment effect and that's where a lot
of the exciting modeling is going on is
how do I model the endowment people have
what's their reference point is an
important problem that's one example a
second example which is even more
mind-blowing is basically people have
unstable
preferences there was a professor MIT
who ran the following informal
experiment it's never published I can't
I can't guarantee the reports are
reported accurately but I love the story
so I'm going to tell it anyway he taught
two class in one day he went to the
first class and he said to the first
class how much would you pay me to sing
a song and he took a survey in the class
he got some demand curve and there was
some average value they pay him let's
say it was
$5 he then to a second class same set of
students and said how much would you pay
me not to sing a song he got demand
curve people would pay posit amounts the
average is about
$5 basically the way you ask the
question affects how people feel about
it that is inconsistent what we've
modeled so far that is UN your
preferences are literally determined by
the questions asked welcome to marketing
okay welcome to advertising any
advertisers tell you duh of course
that's why we advertise if preferences
were stable we wouldn't advertise we
want to change preferences okay we want
to affect preferences that's why we say
it's the number one best selling that's
why we do all these things okay so
preferences are unstable that's really
mind-blowing because basically um uh
that's says that a framing effect how
you frame things can matter enormously
and that's a lot of what advertising and
politicians and others tried to
do okay third
example statistical
biases this is
probably
um my favorite my favorite fact of
anything I've ever done in research so
the cisal bi the IDE is we like to think
we do uncertainty models that people
understand the uncertainty they face and
then how to process it but it turns out
they
don't so for example 80% of drivers
think they're better than average that
is
impossible okay but 80% of drivers think
they're better than average or my fact
from my research I loved was there was a
survey that asked High School seniors
back in the 1980s when smoking was a lot
more prevalent they asked High School
seniors who smoked a pack a day what are
the odds you'll be smoking in five
years of those who said I will be
smoking in five years 72% were smoking 5
years later so on average they did
reasonable prediction of those who said
I will not be smoking 74% we're smoking
five years later zero predictive ability
because it's just hard to figure it out
it's hard to assess these statistics and
probabilities okay this has enormous
implications it says the teenagers may
not be properly deciding whether to
smoke it turns out if you ask
smokers how bad is smoking for you
actually smokers no actually if anything
smokers slightly overestimate how bad
smoking is for you it's not that smokers
don't know how bad smoking is for you if
anything think it's worse for you than
it is but they think they're going to
quit so you have smokers what is the
effect on the average person's length of
life for smoking it turns out by smoking
you shorten your life by seven years
smokers get that a bit right they're
probably bit pessimistic they may say
eight or nine years but if you ask them
how how long do you expect to live they
give the population average not a number
eight years lower because they think it
won't affect
them either they'll quit or they're just
superhuman or whatever okay so
statistical biases are another example
of that okay a fourth example extrinsic
versus intrinsic
motivation extrinsic versus intrinsic
motivation
okay for many decisions we make the
right thing to do is
obvious and yet we don't do it let's
take the classic example which is
inexpensive generic medication for
life-threatening chronic disease if you
have diabetes you can manage it with if
you have type two diabetes you can
manage with a with a product called
metformin it's a dollar a day pill you
can take that will keep you alive and if
you don't take it you'll die it's not
very complicated okay you won't die
right away you'll eventually lose your
leg and eventually die okay
yet a huge share of diabetics do not
take their metformin compliance with
metformin is incredibly
poor now you might think okay people are
uninformed you know whatever you know
nothing's ever 100% but if you run the
follow experiment if you say to people
of
diabetes I will should lower your
metform cost from a dollar day to zero a
huge share start to take it now think
about that for a
second it is whether you're going to die
or not and you're letting a dollar a day
affect whether you take it and the
answer is not that people are poor it's
that in some sense zero matters in some
sense these signals intrinsic versus
extrinsic motivation matters these
things matter this is sort of combining
the two of sort of framing matters but
basically um individuals uh essentially
they have to believe it and that uh the
framing
matters okay let me talk about another
example
defaults this is probably the single
most striking finding in all of
empirical behavioral economics a former
student of mine named Bridget madrian
did a fascinating
study when you go to join your firm when
you got to get your job you get a good
job you'll sign up there'll be a
benefits package and they'll be like do
you want health insurance do you want a
401k and as I sold to you should check
yes you should put your money away stop
partying save your money for your future
okay you can still party too you can
afford do both okay
now if you look at most firms most new
workers young workers do not choose the
401K about 20% of young workers sign up
initially eventually time they're older
it rises towards like 80% but initially
it's about
20% so Bridget had a firm studied a firm
that made one simple
change they said we're going to roll you
in the 401K unless you check here saying
you don't want to be in it literally
they just change check if you want to be
in to check if you want to be out the
participation rate among young people
went from 20% to
80% with one wording change okay that
can simply not be explained by anything
we've learned in 1401 so far at least
before today okay there's simply no
rational model of the world
of any type which would justify that
okay the answer is that PE that things
like presentation and defaults matter
and once again that needs to be built
into our
models okay now why is this that's where
you got to take 1413 what where the
thing the place where Behavior economics
is right now is we've documented a huge
set of these what we call anomalies a
huge set of strange examples that are
Inc consistent with our standard
model where we're struggling and where
we need more work and where 1430 can
help you is how do you write the correct
models to explain
those okay how do you write the correct
model to explain those and so for
example this defaults matter 401K thing
could be a procrastination story it
could be a lack of attention story
there's lots of stories you can tell how
do we write the right models and
distinguish them that's what the
exciting cutting edges in behavioral
economics okay question about any of
these examples I realized I went fast
but question about any of this
yeah perspective like I know America
like if you want to be a heart donor
they like op you out versus like other
countries op you do you know why that is
that's a that's a great point a perfect
example Oregon donations you're
defaulted in in other countries in
America you have to sign up they have
organization rights that are dwarf ours
there's no good reason other than
individual Freedom uh but this is what's
this is a great segue other
questions that's a great segue to the
last thing I wanted to talk about
which is what does this all imply for
policy where does this all lead us in
terms of government
policy and let me talk about a specific
example then speak it out more
generally okay the specific example is
taxation of
cigarettes we talked in the
externalities
lecture about how when there's a
negative consumption
externality you should tax the activity
cigarettes are a classic negative
consumption externality it's been
measured to be around 40 to 50 cents a
pack and that suggests that optimal
policy would be to have a 40 to 50 cent
a pack cigarette
tax but that's actually a pretty small
number it turns out and why is it so
small it's so small for an interesting
reason cigarettes have huge
externalities uncovered medical costs
smoker start fires Etc second smok Etc
but it turns out cigarettes have a huge
positive
externality what's the positive
externality well smokers have a
convenient habit of dying at
65 why is that convenient that means
they spent their lifetime paying taxes
and never get collect the retirement
benefits there's a positive that's a
positive externality on us we benefit
from those stupid
smokers because basically they pay all
the taxes we get the benefits that is a
positive externality that's not a
controversial comment it's a purely POS
indeed the tobacco companies in court
have defended themselves by arguing that
smoking has a death
benefit okay they quickly realized that
was a winning argument and went away
from it okay but that is a big reason
why the ex numers is in bigger in fact
if you took out that death F the ex
number is more like two or three dollars
a pack the reason so big is because
there's this huge financial positive
externality now I worked in Washington
in the Clinton Administration and the
thing I loved about that is economists
are just so much smarter than lawyers we
just whenever I was in a room unless I
was in room with Larry Summers who was
my mentor there I was the smartest guy
in the room because we know how to not
the smartest by IQ but the smartest by
knowing how to think about how to frame
a policy question our whole fields
around how to frame policy questions and
we're so good at it except one time
which we had to stand up in front of a
room of lawyers and say you know what we
should tax cigarettes less because they
kill people and lawyers looked at me
like you're nuts and I realized I
probably actually was not that the
external math is wrong what was wrong
was the model of smoking was wrong in
particular the model of smoking should
incorporate self-control problems there
is vast evidence that smokers suffer
from self-control problems indeed what's
the best what he conly is the best piece
of evidence for self-control problems
not what's in the lab because remember
we believe what people do not what they
say we think the best piece of evidence
for self-control problems is that when
people want to change your behavior they
search for commitment
devices for example if you look at all
the recommendation to quit smoking it's
all punish yourself if you smoke leave
your dirty cigarette butts in water so
you have to smell it make a bet with
your friends so that you have to pay
them if you smoke it's all activities
where you punish yourself if you
smoke that is not consistent with a
rational model in a rational model you
never punish yourself for some future
act you just wouldn't do the future
act the fact that people punish those
for future Act is exactly cons people
knowing they have a self-control problem
perhaps the best example this is syrup
ofac syrup aipac is something you drink
so that if you consume alcohol you
vomit why would anyone do this because
they think they know they're alcoholics
and they can't stop consuming alcohol
it's like painting my nails with that
shitty stuff okay sikac is totally
unjustified by any rational model but
it's justified by a self-control model
which is I know I can't stop drinking so
I'm going to stop myself from drinking
by setting up the self-control device
this commitment
device okay and that is evidence that
basically um people want have
self-control problems well here's the
thing as I said the AL tax on cigarettes
with this model the exponential model is
50 cents a pack with this
model it's $10 a
pack why because cigarettes are so bad
for your health
every pack of cigarettes every cigarette
you smoke lowers your life by seven
minutes if you take
that and multiply by the value of life
that implies the Damage Done by a pack
of cigarettes if you take Economist
estimat the value of a life is about $40
a pack that is you lower your health by
$40 a
pack so if if none of that's a mistake
if you're perfectly rational then that's
irrelevant in the per AC doesn't matter
what you're doing yourself you've made a
decision you know that but what if you
don't get it right then it counts then
we don't just care about externalities
but also internalities what my co-author
and I label internalities
which are the fact that the fact you're
harming yourself does matter in a
standard econic model the fact you're
harming yourself doesn't matter but once
you make this minor tweak which is once
again consistent with every experiment
ever run in the history of
psychology suddenly it does matter and
it matters a lot for government policies
the optimal tax goes from 50 cents a
pack to $10 a pack now is $10 exactly
right no but the point is that inter
once internalities matter that up put a
whole puts up a whole new space to think
about policy think about the fact that
policies which hurt people um uh might
actually even if they don't hurt even on
externalities might be things we want to
address so for example so
basically this comes back to thinking
about the policy inies we talked about
last time for health
externalities and we talked about why
would you ever ban a
drug well this is why you'd never want
to make a drug illegal if all we car
about was externalities that is
absolutely right there's no externality
argument given the benefits and costs
for making drugs illegal not no but if
you do the math it's hard to justify
okay I don't be too strong it's hard to
justify but once you permit
internalities then it becomes easy to
justify once you say the people doing
those drugs are making
mistakes it's easier to justify so the
fact that we as a society ban drugs
means we Society believe in
internalities
okay we believe that these kinds of
inconsistent decisions are being made
all these kinds of various behavioral
problems exist and when all these exist
then suddenly we we need to consider the
fact that internalities might matter as
well and that's a new ball
game now what's
interesting is that the internalities
versus
externalities
debate plays out very
differently in different spaces so let's
take smoking versus
drinking it turns out the internals from
drinking are not very large you have to
be a really really serious alcoholic do
major health damage to
yourself okay whereas the ex from
drinking are enormous as I said 12,000
people a year die in drunk driving
accidents 50% of all violent crimes are
linked to consumption of
alcohol okay 50% of domestic a huge
share of domestic abuse is L cons
alcohol alcohol is huge externalities
probably pretty modest internalities
so any Economist who believes who didn't
believe in this stuff even they like
1401 believe we should tax alcohol more
alcohol is vastly under taxed it is
quite frankly and my kid is upset that
every time I say this it is insane that
you can get a beer for the same price as
a Diet
Coke okay that makes no sense at
all okay basically there are external
damages done by now you might say but
wait a second
John I drink sucessfully in my dorm room
I might stumble from one dorm to another
but I'm not driving I'm not committing
crimes I'm not domestic abuse lay off
buddy to which I say to you remember
we're talking about is the cost to you
of paying maybe 20 cents more a beer
versus the benefit to Society of maybe a
few thousand people less dying in drunk
driving accidents and less domestic
abuse less
crime and ultimately we want to use a
social welfare function to evaluate that
but for most social welfare functions
that's a trade-off worth making now is
it worth five bucks a beer of tax
probably not is it worth some absolutely
okay and so that's how we think about
that okay but with cigarettes it's
harder because social economics doesn't
work you need more internality arguments
to make that now let's talk about let's
conclude by talking about what I said is
the most
significant Health externality and also
internality today which is
obesity as I said about 35% of our
country is obese in some states it
approaches 50%
obesity has both internalities and
externalities the externalities arise
because there's enormous medical cost
associated with obesity in particular
through the fact that obesity causes
diabetes type two and diabetes type two
is incredibly expensive to treat the
country of Mexico spends 1.1% of its
entire GDP treating the complications
from
diabetes okay think about that one every
$100 earned in Mexico more than that
goes to just the complication of
diabetes
this is an enormous health problem it's
a huge uh Health expenditure for our
country and at the same time there's
also internalities
people don't have self-control around
eating okay and so anytime you don't
have self-control once again what's
amazing about that model is just a
little bit of lack of self-control the
tobacco cost said if there's big damage
to your sell from eating too much a
little bit of lack of self-control can
cause a big effect internality
so obesity causes both externalities in
medical SP internalities being obese
lowers your life expectancy by something
other over four years it's not as bad as
smoking but it's pretty bad so basically
it's both externalities and
internalities so what do we do about it
well this is as I said where it gets
hard the first thing we do that's
obvious that anybody who believes in
anything would say it's more information
that's a clear one we should explain to
people like things like nutritional
calorie labeling fun fact about Cal I
talked to one of the guys who was an
owner of Dunkin Donuts says fast what
happen they label calories they label
calories of Dunkin Donuts doughnut
consumption didn't change at
all muffin consumption fell
enormously why who knew muffins were
like 500 calories each you know a
Doughnut's bad for you but you don't
realize a muffin that seems okay it's
twice as bad as a doughnut nobody knew
that so basically information matters
okay so information is an obvious step
but it's not enough we can do do
taxation but the problem then is what do
we tax we can't tax food poor people
won't be able to eat we could try things
like taxing sugar
content okay but then the problem is
what if they then just substitute
towards fattier Foods instead of sugier
foods substitute cigar out tobacco is
easy you tax tobacco you're done food's
harder because there's so many bad
components and multiple components and
food okay now really what we want to do
is we'd like to tax body
weight okay now we can't but in theory
the externality is caused by being
obese So in theory we could do that in
practice politically we can't but
actually in practice it's not obvious
that would help and the reason not ofice
it would help is because of self-control
problems if you tax body weight so
people in a year have to pay a higher
tax that might not affect where they
today whereas a tax on food is right in
front of them it puts the cost of
benefits together a tax on body weight
puts the cost and the benefits future
and that runs to self-control
problems okay so that is um another
solution the other solution just
regulation so for example most European
nations and now in the US we we've
banned trans fats trans fats are
particularly awful kind of substance
that is yummy but is very bad for us and
we have good
substitutes but once again substitution
makes that challenging that was an easy
case because they were good substitute
were all obviously better so anytime you
have something where there's all the sub
suits are obviously better that's easy
to ban that what about some of the subss
might be worse for you then that gets
tricky okay another thing we do is
regulate Supply a big problem we have in
America is food deserts they're called
we're basically the large areas of
America we can't buy vegetables
literally within any walking distance
there's nowhere to buy vegetables with
any biking distance you have to get in a
bus and go a long
way okay so we could solve that by
making them more available it turns out
so we could do that making it more
available now
it turns out we have tried all of these
approaches I've
said in individually and all of them
work a little bit and none of them make
a huge difference on
Obesity the one policy intervention that
seems to matter a lot comes from
behavioral economics and it's what we
call
nudges which is changing the framework
in a way where we're not lowering
welfare because your choice set hasn't
changed we're just changing the way it's
presented to you like the default
example so one now let me just say for
here big caveat any of some of you who
are I don't know if any of you there's
there's a huge replication crisis in
social sciences right now and a lot of
the studies I'll site have not been
successfully replicated okay but I
believe in so much I'm going to tell you
about them anyway because I think they
offer some interesting insights but I
just want to be clear on the evidence
there's a there's a big replication
crisis with these sort of fun nudge
studies so more needs to be done but for
for example one of the most famous
studies was they took people that all
eaten a meal at the same time put them
in front of a movie and gave them
buckets of stale popcorn and the buckets
were full to different levels a third
full a half full and full everybody ate
the entire bucket of what was in their
bucket okay despite the fact it was
different amounts they were all equally
hungry it was just in front of them they
ate it okay or one study of Professor to
man it's never been publisher so I don't
I once again just a informal story but I
love
it but buffets create huge food waste
because we all know how Buffet works you
say first thing say oh that's good you
take a bunch of it next oh that's really
good you take a bunch of by third thing
oh yeah I'll squeeze that in the corner
of the plate because that looks good too
you don't eat it all so they made a
simple change of the buffet at her
school they put the plates at the end of
the row rather than the beginning of the
row so you had to walk by the buffet to
get your plate so you knew what was
there and they lowered food waste by
20% because people then were like oh
yeah I know this is coming so I won't
load up so much on this
okay these are once again we need more
study of this but it suggests that the
way we're really going to ultimately
deal with problems like this is to lean
to the behavioral biases that cause them
if you find this interesting is a book
called Nudge by the Nobel prize winning
Economist Richard theor who talks about
this and talks about the behavioral
economics behind it and uh and all the
all the policies behind it but once
again the politics is hard perhaps the
best nudge based policy suggestion of
all time
was what Mayor Bloomberg suggested in
New York which was to ban large servings
of soda he said look people buy a soda
you guys don't know when I was a kid
okay now when you go to buy soda you
almost never can buy anything less than
18 ounces and often can't buy some less
than 24 ounces when I was a kid you the
choice was typically 12 ounces you can't
even buy those anymore size have gone up
so Bloomberg said look let's just ban
large soda
sizes therefore Mak people work more to
have to get those calories brilliant
idea
okay uh but the politics was ugly even
including obviously conservatives appros
it because it's interfering with the
free market but liberals opposes too
John Stewart made fun of him I'll never
forgive John Stewart for that okay John
Stewart made fun of me too I'll forgive
him for that either okay but basically
the bottom line is these behavioral
nudges matter and we should think
seriously about incorporating them into
policy okay I'm going to stop there
we're going to come back on Wednesday
I'm not going to say I'm not going to
give the answers to the finals on
Wednesday I'm just not going to say that
I'm not not going to give the answers to
the finals on Wednesday so it's your
decision whether you want to come or not