the MIT energy initiative presents
lessons from energy leaders I AP course
connects MIT and Global Learners with
practitioners and experts written by
Lita
Zimmerman MIT engineers and scientists
are at the Vanguard of developing new
technologies to achieve the goal of Net
Zero carbon emissions by
2050 but there is more that the MIT
Community could be contributing believes
angeliki Diane Ros p HD 85 associate
director of graduate programs for the
MIT energy initiative Mighty and program
manager for the MIT Center for enhanced
nanofluidic transport we need to think
of ourselves as leading the energy
transition not just participating in it
she says we tend to be siloed at MIT and
don't talk enough to people in the real
world to address this shortcoming rigos
designed the course leading the energy
transition for January's independent
activities period IAP featuring guest
instructors with expertise and
addressing the complex challenges that
arise when lowc carbon mandates meet
social political and economic realities
leading change is difficult requiring
different strategies for different
situations and the capacity to adjust to
new problems says rigos whose varied
career includes stin as a research
scientist Professor industry consultant
and mentor to clean technology
entrepreneurs among the speakers for
this virtual I AP class were current
current and former heads of federal and
state government agencies corporate
energy representatives and mighty policy
and Technology experts by sharing their
individual and organizational
perspectives on advancing the energy
transition I hope to inspire our
students to believe they could lead
their own initiatives says
Ros where the gears are
turning as an economist whose research
Falls at the intersection of energy
climate and poverty alleviation
Andrea Christina Ruiz signed up for the
IP class to get a survey understanding
of the different lenses that could be
applied to understand the energy
transition she says a manager of the
energy environment and climate change
sector at the Abdul Latif Jil poverty
action Lab japal at the time of the
course Ruiz was charged with advancing
the use of evidence and promoting
evidence-based policymaking toward
Equitable and costeffective climate
change policies and interventions
I wanted to see where the gears are
turning in scientific technological and
other communities which are all part of
the solution to understand how I fit in
says Ruiz who is now an economist at the
Eastern research group an environmental
consulting firm the course gave me an
interdisciplinary nuanced and holistic
take on key challenges in the energy
transition a transition that is
essential if we want to avert the worst
impacts of climate change she says some
of the insights she found particularly
useful came came from emray genser a
mighty research scientist who weighs the
costs and benefits of new carbon
reducing Technologies based on Cradle to
grave emissions in his presentation
genser outlined the importance of moving
as swiftly as possible to an all
electric vehicle Fleet we must
immediately cut emissions but how we get
there is very important he said instead
of waiting until we have widespread
electric charging infrastructure we can
switch from internal combustion engine
vehicles icevs to plug in hybrids or
hybrids immediately he also proposed
Banning
ICS in another session Christopher kidle
the George P Schultz professor of energy
economics at the MIT Sloan School of
Management and deputy director for
policy at Mighty discussed policy
options for driving the energy
transition climate change represents a
case where markets don't work well he
noted pointing to persistent resistance
to the idea of a carbon tax saving the
planet will mean paying more for clean
energy so Distributing this burden
equitably will be Central to any
successful policy kidle suggested I care
deeply not just about efficiency but
about the winners and losers associated
with climate change policy kidle
said he shared research demonstrating
that a small carbon tax whose Dividends
are distributed to the most economically
vulnerable in society could have an
outsized and Rapid impact on emissions
these presentations made the dimensions
of the climate change problem more
accessible says say Ruiz I'm not an
expert on decarbonization or
electrification but knowing what
policies exist and what economic models
can be used will help me ask the right
question she
says finding a
balance leading the energy transition
Drew several hundred participants over
the duration of the course from current
MIT students and MIT alumni to globally
based students and professionals eager
to glean ideas for their studies and
careers in core centry surveys many
noted their desire to accelerate the
energy transition and identified
specific interests and economically and
politically feasible paths for
decarbonizing the electric grid
commercializing nuclear fusion and
achieving climate Justice some students
thought a sense of the speaker personal
experiences managing their day-to-day
responsibilities and
expectations what tactics do you find to
balance pragmatism about the timelines
of technological development with
excitement over opportunities for
shorter-term impacts as Catherine Papa
George a fellow in the MIT system design
and management Masters program you can
be scared of the scale of the challenge
but finding solutions for the future is
really the opportunity of a lifetime
said Len V the global key account
manager medals at Shell energy when
people come to tell me all the reasons
something can't work I tell them I want
to hear how we make it work V also noted
that a lot of Technology moves fast and
what we thought we couldn't do 2 years
ago is happening today the next
generation of leaders in the energy
transition must cultivate a unique set
of skills including a significant amount
of patients because no solution is
perfect said Joanna Troy the director of
energy policy and planning at the
Commonwealth of Massachusetts her job
which involves expanding clean energy
across the state and region requires
listening to stakeholders with competing
demands the road map is always changing
and you need to maintain a certain
internal calm focusing on making
decisions with the evidence you have in
front of you and then evaluating and
restarting the problem multiple times
she said course participants had ample
time to question practitioners such as
Troy and Robert aier the vice president
of system planning at ISO New England
not just on the specifics of their jobs
but for a glimpse of the future whether
widespread adoption of electric heat
pumps generation of green hydrogen or a
massive buildout of new transmission
lines what does history teach us
but instructors also caution
participants that technological fixes
for the future cannot in themselves
deliver Net Zero carbon results and even
good policy can get sidetracked emirus
Institute Professor J M Deutch who
served as director of the Central
Intelligence Agency and in a number of
positions for the US Department of
energy including director of Energy
Research acting assistant secretary for
energy technology and under Secretary of
the department offered good and bad
lessons from the past 50 years on the
country's judgment and pursuit of
policies around promising Energy
Technologies the Clean Air Act first
passed by Congress in 1963 and then
amended in 1970 can be marked a success
he said since the monetary benefits of
reducing pollution were much greater
than the expense but Deutch added that
the constant turmoil of American
politics not to mention the threat of
wars and economic disruptions makes it
generally more difficult to organize
ourselves to go after big technological
changes he said without Harmony it's
hard to solve problems and in the US
currently we don't have much Harmony
students pressed Deutsch on his
apparently gloomy take on the likelihood
of securing society's carbon reduction
goals chuman mokoena a master student in
the department of nuclear science and
engineering asked whether Fusion Energy
and conventional nuclear energy along
with Renewables might achieve a clean
and sustainable economy in 3 to 5
decades Deutsch canell those in the
class to be careful about silver bullets
and that Society must have good public
participation to understand and support
such efforts to chinin nasu who works in
the energy industry in Nigeria this was
a clear call to leadership in countries
where the mix of power generation
structures is not improving as quickly
as we would like we need to educate
people she said it will be a lot of work
but we must organize to demand concrete
action from both campaigning and elected
politicians toward achieving aing Net
Zero