(logo whooshing)
- Hello everyone.
Welcome back to CSAIL Office Hours.
I'm Daniela Rus, Director
of the Computer Science
and Artificial Intelligence
Laboratory at MIT CSAIL,
and today we are going
to talk about all things generative AI.
I'm joined by some brilliant researchers
and colleagues at CSAIL
as well as Greg Huang,
business editor at the Boston Globe.
- So today we'll be exploring
the cutting edge-field
of generative AI.
This is artificial intelligence systems
that can generate new content
like text, coding, images
and videos from scratch or with inputs.
Now work on generative AI
as deep roots here at MIT
dating back to the 1960s,
today we're gonna get into
the cutting-edge research
that's happening in this field.
We've seen a lot of rapid
progress in recent years,
systems that can write
stories, code software,
generate photorealistic
images, videos, and more.
So to discuss the latest
research in this area,
I'm joined by five experts from MIT CSAIL
whose work spans different aspects
of generative AI including
robotics, language models,
coding, images, and video generation.
Before we dive in, we can
do a quick round of intros.
- Sure, I am Armando Solar-Lezama
and I work at the intersection
of programming systems
and AI, particularly focused
on programming technology.
- I'm Jacob Andreas.
I work on natural language processing
and computational linguistics.
- Hi, I am Yoon Kim.
I work on natural language
processing and machine learning.
- Hi, I'm Philip Isola
and I work on computer
vision and machine learning.
- As you all know, generative AI has seen
rapid progress in recent years.
So leading to systems that
can write creative stories,
code software from natural
language descriptions,
generate photorealistic images and videos
and much more, it's
also led to a reshaping
of the global tech landscape.
You know, with the rise of open AI,
Nvidia and just billions of
dollars being poured into chips,
cloud servers, software development
and just really a war on talent.
We're joined by people
who know the most about
what's happening here
in Gen AI at CSAIL.
And your work all spans
these different areas, right?
So from language and coding to images
and robotics even.
So I'm gonna just jump
in with some questions
because the LLMs have been such,
this a huge, you know,
explosion and interest in recent years.
I'm gonna start with
the language guys here.
So Jacob, your work on these compositional
and grounded language understanding.
It's like it's demonstrated
the ability to translate
between natural language and
structured representation.
Maybe you can talk a little
bit about what that means.
But how do you build these
generative AI systems
that can generate these
natural language descriptions?
- One of the interesting things
to see has been, you know,
when we started working
kind of at the intersection
of like language and vision especially,
it was all about getting these sort
of carefully curated data sets
of, you know, images paired
with captions and natural language
or images paired with
questions and language
and answers to those questions.
And thinking very carefully
about the design of kind
of specific neural network
architectures that could map,
you know, directly from images to text
or from text images or whatever.
And I think the biggest
thing that's changed now is
just that what research looks
like is much less about,
you know, how you specifically design
some specific neural network
for this little task.
Or even how you go out
and collect, you know, paired
data just for some target task
of interest like image generation
or image captioning or whatever.
And much more about, you know,
I think on the data side,
thinking about the kinds of, you know,
general data sources and
properties and structures
and data sets that induce
shared representations
in these models of, you know,
not just language and not just vision,
but also kind of the world
that underlies these things.
And this is something that
I know Philip is thinking
a lot about lately as well.
But yeah, I mean really just less about
how you solve any individual problem
and more about how you
collect the kind of data
that gives you the
kinds of representations
that really let you do anything.
Talking about starting to generate text,
generate images, things like that,
I think one of the other big
challenges now actually has
less to do with the machine
learning side of things
and more with just kind of the
human facing side of things
and that, you know, because
LLMs are so powerful
and because we, you know,
have such a good like language
processing toolkit now,
I think everyone's kind
of adopted this paradigm
where you try to describe
whatever it is that you're trying
to accomplish in natural language.
And sometimes language is a
great medium for specifying,
you know, what you want
a picture to look like
or what you want a piece of code to do.
Sometimes it's not the right tool at all.
And I think we're still
figuring out just like
what the human interaction
story should be here
and what the right way of communicating
with these sorts of generative models is.
- And you, I mean, being
a language expert as well,
how do you react to that
and then how do you improve things?
- Just to react to
that, I think when Jacob
and I were PhD students,
there was a lot of work on like you wanted
to model the translation process.
You wanted to do a natural
language processing task
called semantic pausing,
and you would craft models
and data sets for this task
of interest with the hope
that it'll be useful for downstream task
of interest in the future.
But now we have these systems
actually working in practice,
large language model-based
systems that are, you know,
monolithic data-driven models,
trained on lots of data sets,
but they're working well
enough that they're being sort
of like a core part of major
AI-based services today.
As you think about how
these systems sort of like,
the entire pipeline of their
systems from data collection,
from the systems on which they're
trained, how they're used,
how the outputs of these
systems are sort of presented
to the actual users.
I think there's a rich sort of set
of research questions that sort of like,
weren't really a cool part of NLPIC
until these technologies came along.
And I think that's where a lot
of the interesting research questions are.
- To me, the fact that you can put AI
in the pockets of everyone
with the use of natural
language processing
and large language models
is absolutely extraordinary.
We have truly democratized AI.
But I'd like to follow
up on Greg's question
and ask you what do you see
as the most interesting
or exciting applications,
especially in business?
I know that for the past
year companies have struggled
to understand how they can get value
from these new technologies.
And in particular on the language side.
- I think one application is extracting
structured information
from unstructured data
with which to do further modeling,
further conversion into
sort of relevant services.
In the past, if you, for
example, had clinical notes
or like contracts
and you wanted to extract
information out of them
to do stuff with them, like
build a chat bot on top of,
or have a machine learning
model to give outputs,
then that was a very sort
of a burdensome process.
But now it's not perfect.
But if you have a large language model
and you give it, for
example, some examples
of extracting structured
data, it'll get you started.
Of course this will
need further refinement
and every sort of application
should be mindful of,
you know, "What's the risk
of getting this wrong?"
But I think that's sort of
a very prominent application
where I think LLMs will
get you from zero to one.
- What do you think Jacob?
- In the, I guess, pre-LLM era,
you know, this business
of how do you do structured
information extraction?
How do you parse a document,
how do you do good web search?
You know, these were entire
sort of major areas of research
and people built these same
kinds of specialized models
that we were talking about
and they kind of worked
and that was really kind
of like the cutting edge
of what you could do.
And now we live in this world
where, you know, you can kind
of sort of do all of
these incredible things
like code generation and
long-form document generation,
you know, and I think
maybe part of the reason
that the business world has
struggled to adopt these things,
which are the things that people
are really excited about is
'cause there's still a lot
of, you know, work to do
and things to iron out to
make them really like safe
and robust and reliable.
But all that stuff that we
were trying to do, you know,
before the LLMs happened is just, I mean,
it's solved essentially.
And I think there's actually,
you know, we haven't even yet
like, really adapted to living
in a world where, you know,
late 2000s era NLP technology
works really, really well,
much less to living in
a world where, you know,
LLMs can reliably do all the things
that we're trying to get
them to do right now.
- How does your research, like right now,
how does it inform, you know, the next GPT
or whatever model, you
know, we're seeing out there
or you know, how Google does there?
Things you see when you
start to do a Google search.
Like, how close are you to that
and what's the kind of process
for getting in that pipeline?
- So a lot of my current
research is focused
on making LLMs useful through
making them more efficient,
interpretable and controllable.
And I think Daniela, you
know, said that it's amazing
that we can access ChatGPT on our phones
and have this have access to
this incredible technology.
So we have democratized
access to these technologies
to an extent, but if we think about like,
who really has the resources
to develop these models,
adapt them to various tasks of interest,
I think there's still
like a lot of barrier
to really working with these models.
And I think part of the
problem is everything related
to these models, architectures
and algorithms are inefficient.
They require a lot of resources.
They contribute non-trivial
to the carbon footprint in general.
And I think that's what motivates
a lot of my current
research on efficiency.
- Right now, you can run ChatGPT
or your language model
of choice on your phone,
but in fact the computation
has to happen on server farms
and only big corporations
have the resources
to access the server farms.
Additionally, when a company wants
to instantiate a language
model for their own needs,
right now, either they get a server farm
or they send their data
to one of the providers
of these huge models
and that has some privacy
issues associated with that.
So, the research to make
foundational models able to run
on small devices like enterprise computers
and phones is very important.
- Well, let's shift gears to
the whole programming side
of things and you read
stories in New Yorker
or Wall Street Journal or Boston Globe
about software developers,
jobs being, you know,
not threatened, but you know,
it's changing how coding happens.
Maybe you could Armando speak a bit
about your research on that
front and kind of what you see
happening there at the cutting edge.
- For a lot of routine tasks
and especially for a lot of
tasks that involve heavy use
of widely used APIs, for example,
these kind of tools can make
an enormous productivity difference.
And especially for people who don't have
kind of that deep knowledge
of these APIs at their fingertips,
allowing them to work
at the rate of people
with much more experience than themselves.
I think there is the question of like,
what kind of impact can we expect
from these kind of technology?
So on the one hand it's
sort of very well known
in the software industry
that the amount of time
that one spends actually
typing in the code
that goes into a product
is a tiny fraction
of the overall effort
required to design and build
and then maintain software product.
And I think we're still
very far from the point
where AI can really help with
all of those different tasks
that are part of a general
software development framework.
The other thing is, as an
industry software is I think
quite different from
many other industries.
On the one hand, you know,
today we see like, wow,
this is a big change
in how people program,
but we've seen really big
changes in how people program.
Many times, even over
the course of my career,
for example, when we moved
towards managed languages
where suddenly it was possible
to build really rich functionality
just by grabbing libraries
from all over the place.
Like, that was a huge shift
in the way people developed
software and a huge
productivity boost, right?
That's what made it
possible for, you know,
suddenly startups with two or three people
to very quickly build up infrastructure
and deploy services used by millions.
And so we're an industry that is very used
to that kind of change.
At the same time, you know,
when it comes to the question
of jobs, for example,
if you have, you know, a
construction industry, right?
Let's say that suddenly builders became
ten times more efficient
in their use of labor to produce a house.
Well, in order to produce a house,
you don't just need labor, you need land,
you need raw materials, it's pretty likely
that you would need now one tenth
as many construction workers
because you're not gonna
get ten times more land.
You're not gonna get ten
times more building materials.
With software, you basically need people,
you need skilled people.
If you can get twice
as many skilled people,
you can design twice as much software,
you don't quite have the
same set of constraints.
And we have these huge
unmet need of applications
that would be awesome if they existed,
but maybe not at the price point
that it takes to build them.
Or applications that exist
in a way that is vulnerable
to exploit, that is hard to use,
that is insecure.
So we have a huge unmet demand
for software development
that I think we're very, very far
from running out of things to program.
- You're talking about software
that's gonna, you know,
run airplanes and so forth, right?
So, in your research,
are you finding ways to-
Or how do you get over that?
How do you make it actually work?
- So for us, this is a very
important area of research
that we're very focused on, which is
how do you combine the style of reasoning
that you get from an LLM that's able
to draw from these amount of experience
from having seen basically all the code
that is available on the internet,
but how do you combine it with the need
and the ability to read logically
about what the code is
actually doing to recent
about how different pieces
of code are going to interact
with each other.
And this is something
that LLMs have proven
to be not very good at
or reasoning about the
low level details of code.
At the same time, we do
have a lot of techniques
and a lot of tools for doing very precise,
automated reasoning over code.
And the question of how do you get
those two very different
technologies to work together
so that you can have the level
of reliability that is needed
for many of these really important
applications that I think
that's one of the big
open questions right now.
- There are so many
safety critical systems
where hallucinations and
errors are just not acceptable.
And so at the same time
we have an entire field
called verification whose
job it is to make sure
that the software that we build is correct
and will execute
according to expectations.
Can you say a few words about
where we are with respect
to bringing verification
into machine learning?
- We do have this possibility
of accessing ground truth
by verifying the actual
behavior of the code.
The field of verification
has made enormous leaps
over the past ten years to the point
where today we have some
really compelling examples
of systems level software
that has been fully
verified to prove that,
it's completely absent of
bugs, that it's going to behave
exactly as people expect
even against adversarial
attacks, for example.
One of the big questions is,
"How do we get the cost of building
that kind of software down?"
Because right now these
kind of efforts are
one of a kind very, very
challenging development efforts.
The big question is,
"Can LLMs, can AI in
general help democratize
these kind of technology?"
So that it's not just, you know,
very well-funded research level efforts,
but it's every programmer writing software
for embedded devices, for example.
Every small or medium-sized
company building
internet-of-things devices
that can actually have access
to this kind of technology.
One of the challenges in doing this is
that on the one hand,
we don't have the kind
of enormous data sets of
verified code compared to,
you know, all the giant
data sets that we have
for things like Python.
We also don't quite know how to automate
a lot of the clever
insights that go into making
many of these verification feeds possible.
So this is right now an area
that's really just starting
to take off in the research community.
But we do expect, I think,
some compelling results
in the near future.
- Is scalability a problem?
- A lot of these things work
by breaking the big problem
into individual chunks
and verifying small pieces
of software at a time.
But it's actually a
bit of an art right now
to do things in such a
way that when you put
all of these verified components together,
you can make these end-to-end claims
about the reliability and the security
of the overall system.
- You're working on among
other things, you know,
image generation creation
with all kinds of application
that I just wanna get
you started on, you know,
what are you seeing that's
exciting on your research front?
- So image generation
and video generation is
one of the other big areas
along with language models and code models
where generative AI has
made a huge difference
and it's just dramatically
improved over the last few years.
So it's very exciting.
I've been interested in that.
I think that one angle that might not be
fully appreciated yet, but it's the angle
that I'm most excited about is
that the goal of computer
vision has been stated
as to, you know, recognize objects
to make a self-driving car
that can follow a lane,
but there's kind of a
bigger goal behind that,
which is you want to be able to generate
a model of the world around you,
understand where everything
is, how it's moving,
what it is, what it's going to do next.
You kind of wanna have this
model in your head of the world
around you and generative AI
techniques are getting closer
and closer to that,
especially when it comes
to video generation, which
is one of the, you know,
very rapidly moving areas right now.
If I can generate a video of the world,
if I can look at a picture and say,
"Here's what it might
look like if, you know,
the car turned left or
if it started raining."
And I can hallucinate that
and I can generate that.
This is a more positive use
of the word hallucination.
I can imagine that.
Then I've really understood something
about the world and how would
I be able to make those types
of predictions and think
about what might happen if I didn't have
that model of the world around me.
So video models right now
have some ability to do that
and it's only partially there so far,
but that's aspect I'm most excited about.
Having a model of the world
that you can actually
imagine counter-factuals.
What would happen if I were to look left?
What would happen if the car
were to dart in front of me?
Would I have to stop?
And then how can this lead
to more intelligent agents
and robots that can anticipate
those futures and react to them?
- How close are we to the matrix?
- Yes, exactly.
This is basically the matrix.
We're far, I would say.
So we have right now video models
and image models that look
almost photorealistic,
but the kind of the physics
behind them is not quite there.
So if you look at the, you
know, very latest video models,
like there's one from OpenAI called Sora.
Every frame is almost perfect,
but there's a famous example
of people digging a hole
on the beach and pulling up
a beach chair outta that hole
and the sand is kind of
flowing around the beach chair,
but then the beach chair is
kind of congealing out of sand
and an extra leg is being formed
and then it's just not physical.
So every frame is almost right,
but the actual world is
not physically modeled
accurately enough that you could really,
you know, make predictions
that are the robustness
and quality necessary for control.
So I don't think we're at the point
where you could train
a robot in the matrix,
but we're heading there pretty rapidly.
- Well, right now the methods we have
for generative AI are
primarily statistically-driven
and this means they do
not understand physics.
So, what is the community doing
to bring physics into these models?
- There's a lot of interest in this.
I think one approach is
just to say, well, big data
and big compute solved a lot of things
that we didn't expect it to solve.
So maybe if you just scale
up statistics even more,
eventually a causal model
will pop out somehow
and that can happen in
certain circumstances.
But you know, one,
there's more speculative,
we haven't seen that fully happen yet.
Another approach is to inject
some kind of physical constraints
and mechanisms into your
modeling assumptions.
And one of the areas I'm kind
of interested in right now is
take some classical physics simulator,
like a computer graphics
engine, a video game
and augment it with generative AI.
So you have this hybrid system
that has an underlying physics engine,
which we understand very well,
but it's been rendered with generative AI
to make it show more diversity
and use all the power of
data-driven methods as well.
- The other thing you can do
is you can take the output
of a generative AI system
and pass it through-
- Yes.
- A simulator that verifies
whether the physical constraints
of the task or of the query have been met.
- Yeah, definitely and that
connects back to Armando
with code verification.
You could verify with
classical simulation.
You could also verify by having an agent
that interacts in the world.
So you know, if the hope
is that we will have robots
that have models of the world around them,
then one way to verify
if the model's correct is
the robot takes an action
and it sees what happened
and it gets feedback as to
whether it's predictions
and model were correct.
- Is the big, you know, I don't know,
killer application here,
is it in entertainment
like video games, AR, VR?
Or is it on the robotic
side or what are you seeing?
- Yeah, I think that the current
color app is entertainment
and that's been the case for a few years.
Everybody had a lot of fun making images
of their making storybooks
for their children
or sharing funny photos online.
And I think there's a lot of
applications in entertainment
and Hollywood and video games.
But the one that is a little
bit more future looking
and that I'm even more excited
about is using these models
of the world as a substrate
for intelligent agents,
for robotics, for systems
that really understand
physicality, causality
that are not just statistical
correlation machines,
but actually have a deeper
understanding of reality.
- And perhaps a closer
opportunity is in manufacturing
in using these approaches to do design
and fabrication using AI methods.
That's the one I'm very excited about.
- Yeah, definitely.
- Any reactions to kind
of, what's the timeframe
for this being big in robotics?
- It's already transforming
robotics in big ways.
I mean we used to think about intelligence
as connecting perception
and action going from pixels to control,
but now with large
language models we have,
and especially multimodal models
that have both vision components
and language components.
We are moving fast forward.
So, what do I mean by this?
You can train a robot
to associate pixels with action.
For instance, you can train
a robot car to avoid trees
by showing it a lot of pictures of trees
and then the car will learn
how to go around the trees.
Now in the past, if you wanted that robot
to also avoid benches
and people and buildings,
you'd have to show the
robot a lot of pictures
of benches and pictures of trees
and pictures of buildings.
But now with language, we don't have to go
through this additional training step.
We can say, okay, you have
learned how to avoid trees,
now also avoid people and buildings
and benches and animals
and anything you want.
And this actually gives us much faster way
of training models.
And it also gives us a wider set
of generalizable actions
that are available to robots
through the use of multimodal models.
It's not just about morphology
and angles, it's also
about forces and torques
and what is needed to have the
interaction with the world.
And so for this reason,
watching videos only will
not take us to a world
where robots will know for sure
how to interact with the world.
We would need force data, torque data.
We would need to know
exactly if you pick up
a picture of water, what are those forces
and torques that are on your
joints and on your muscles.
And because without that we
can generate fantastical videos
that show the correct kinematics,
but do not have the correct dynamics.
And so when it comes to
learning the dynamics
of interaction, we have
extraordinary possibilities,
but also challenges because
there isn't enough data.
However, we are beginning
to see research groups
that are forming the kind
of comprehensive data sets
that will really help
us get robots to learn
how to be in the world in
a dynamically coherent way.
- How to use the right data,
especially now that AI is
generating its own data
in some ways?
- We have technical solutions
for de-biasing data sets.
We can apply algorithms to dataset
and decide whether the data
set is biased with respect
to a certain range of parameters or not.
And so, then you can have a
data set that is not biased.
- I agree, I think one of the
really interesting promises
of synthetic data, so generative
models, they make this new,
you know, fake data and
sometimes it comes across
as that it's gonna be some worst version
of the original data
that you started with.
It's gonna be a cheap proxy,
it's gonna have artifacts,
hallucinations, and that can be true.
There can be these downsides.
But one thing I'm excited about
is that by modeling the data
and producing new data
from it, you can intervene
and change the data distribution.
And I think this is exactly
what Daniela was talking about.
You can remove certain
biases by intervening
and we have technical tools
that can help us there.
You can say that there's
a rare part of the data
that you want to represent better.
Maybe it's a rare disease
and you really wanna study that disease
and you can over sample that
part of the distribution.
So by synthetic data to me is data
that has more opportunity.
You can change it, you
can make it less toxic
if that's what matters
for your application.
- The field has produced
all of these different technical
tools that each can be used
to push the model in certain directions
to achieve particular kinds of balance.
But at the end of the day
for a lot of these questions,
there is this deeper
higher-level question of,
"What are you actually
trying to achieve, right?"
And what is the thing that you're trying
to optimize the model for?
And I think making sure that,
when higher-level applications
are being designed,
it's not just about
having all of these tools
at your fingertips, it's
about deciding, you know,
"What are the parameters
that are really important
for these applications?
What are the possible failure modes?"
And traditionally the way we've thought
of computer systems is as,
you know, the kind of system
where you have a specification
and you can design it
and you produce something that
satisfies the specification
and then, you know, it works.
With a lot of these
learning-based systems,
I think there's a much
bigger need of the kind
of empirical validation
and empirical testing that
oftentimes doesn't come quite
as natural to people in our community,
but it is absolutely essential
to make sure that the systems
that get deployed actually
do what they're supposed
to do when they're out
in the world being used
by real people.
- Just quick question on deep fakes.
So are you doing anything
to protect us from this?
- Two things have changed.
So one is that the synthetic images
and videos now have
gotten so good that a lot
of the techniques that we were
developing a few years ago
just don't work on the current models.
And so it's a constant arms races
and I do think that it's important
that people keep up with that.
We have detectors for the latest models,
but it was kind of a grind
to keep going through that.
And the other thing that was
has been interesting is that,
even though these deep
fakes have the potential
for creating a lot of misinformation
and for us losing, you
know, touch with reality,
it seems like we've as a society started
to develop other types
of, you know, antidotes
to some of that by maybe not trusting
as much what we see online.
I know that people still
probably trust too much
what they see online, but I currently feel
that socio-technical and
policy-level interventions are
probably gonna be more effective
at dealing with the advent of deep fakes.
And we might have to, you
know, look at the signature
of a piece of media and
not just trust the pixels,
you know, seen as not
necessarily gonna be believing.
And so even though there
are some technical solutions
on detecting deep fakes
algorithmically, it might be
that socio-technical and
policy-level interventions are
more effective.
- It's such an exciting
moment for generative AI
and for AI in general.
And the research that is
happening at CSAIL covers
a lot of the foundational
aspects of AI that need
to be developed in order
for this technology
to be applicable to its full potential.
At the same time, it's
important for us to remember
that generative AI is just one component
of the AI ecosystem.
In AI, we have predictive
and classifying AI.
We have generative AI,
we have optimizing AI.
We have deciding AI
and most business problems
are at the intersection
of solutions across these
different set of techniques.
And we will talk more about this
and about how generative AI
combines with other kinds
of AI at the future Office Hours.
For now, thank you very
much for joining us
and see you at the next
CSAIL Office Hours.