now please welcome Professor Andre Su
associate professor of urban science and
the planning at MIT to discuss the urban
network analysis
framework Professor Su please hi
everyone um I hope you can hear me okay
yeah it's a pleasure to join you all
today uh thank you ILP for the
invitation and uh hello to everybody on
the
webinar I will be disc discussing today
uh research we have been doing at the
city form lab in the department of urban
studies and planning at MIT around green
mobility in
cities as many of you probably know the
transportation sector Remains the
highest contributor to CO2 emissions in
cities roughly one third of all CO2
emissions in the industrialized world
come from transportation and if you zoom
in to that on the right hand side here
then you can see that the bulk of this
comes from light duty ve Vehicles which
is regular people driving to places on a
daily
basis however if we examine how
individual cities contribute to CO2
emissions from the Transportation sector
then a really interesting picture
emerges here I have plotted on the xaxis
the CO2 emissions per capita
from the Transportation sector and on
the Y AIS the density the population
density of a city and what we can see
are couple of really important takeaways
of this relationship first there is a
big difference that systemically varies
in terms of CO2 emissions and density in
the densest cities in the United States
emissions are in the order of two to
three tons of CO2 per person per year
and in the lower density cities like on
the far right of this chart in noxville
Tennessee or Charleston South Carolina
we have over 10 tons of CO2 emissions
per capita from the Transportation
sector what this
emphasizes is that City design the way a
city is spatially configured how dense
it is what um opportunities for travel
it offers without a
car has a huge implications on Urban
sustainability and our ability as
Society to tackle climate
change as an example people here in
Boston area where we are based a typical
person emits two 2.6 tons per year and
the person in Houston Texas emits about
N9 and a half tons this is not because
people fundamentally want different
things or are different people it's
because the city incentivizes us to
travel that way so City design plays a
critical role when it comes to
decarbonization and that is one of the
key reasons I will be talking about
Green Mobility
today and I want to emphasize that City
design does not only influence emissions
from the Transportation sector the same
relationship also translates to building
energy emissions building energy
emissions constitute another third of
all CO2 emissions at also energy
consumption in cities and if I change on
the x-axis what is being plotted from
CO2 per capita to residential energy
consumption megawatts per capita per
year we basically see a very similar
relationship in low density cities
energy consumption in the residential
buildings is far higher per capita than
in high density cities on the left of
the chart again between Boston and
Houston in Boston typical resident
consumes about 2 megawatt hours per year
in Houston about
4.7 this difference again is
attributable to City design largely
because in higher density multi-story
structure types of cities a typical home
will H be smaller per capita so
therefore less uh surface area to heat
and it will be insulated from the
outside perimeter of the building
because it's uh bounded by other units
in the same building in other words the
ratio between the the um the house
itself and the outside facade or
perimeter of the building um is higher
um and therefore in in multi-story
buildings in cities like Boston like New
York like European cities like Asian
cities in cities where we build up
rather than uh flat in single single
family houses or uh one-story structures
tend to be also more efficient uh in
terms of energy use
now I want to pull these two things
together and
emphasize that these factors of City
design how a city is laid out specially
in terms of its Urban form how its
infrastructure is specially configured
with public transit structures or public
transit systems with walking and biking
routes or Automotive infrastructure
determine largely where and how things
locate in terms of land use patterns and
this combination of land patterns
infrastructure and urban form determine
to a large degree how people choose to
travel in cities their travel behavior
and their activity location choices
where they choose to live where they
choose to work and how the land use
patterns interact with each other
together these influences determine some
of the most critical outcomes of
interest in um societies today things
like public health Mobility mure or CO2
emissions our ability to tackle climate
change social Equity even so we don't
hear very often in the conversation
about climate change in the
media that the role of Urban Design and
City Planning is so Central to the
question of tackling climate change we
hear about how more efficient vehicles
or electrification of certain services
or buying electric household appliances
can contribute to lower emissions but
often times those kinds of technological
fixes only give us incre mental
improvements if we want to tackle
climate change at the scale that's truly
necessary we have to rethink City design
we have to plan and design cities that
fundamentally consume less energy and
produce less emissions like the examples
I tried to draw out so with this in mind
I'm going to give a quick example of
three projects uh that tackle this
question from different angles in our
research group the city form Lab at MIT
I will first talk about how we study the
most green type of Mobility that there
is in cities which is pedestrian
mobility and how we develop research to
understand pedestrian preferences when
it comes to moving on foot in cities two
I will exam examine a model we have
built called the NYC walks model using
the urban network analysis framework
that Graham referred
to and three I will illustrate how such
a model can be used to influence
decision making in an evidence-based
datadriven way so so let's start with
pedestrian behavior and preferences
which is fundamental to un we need to
understand this so that we can model
pedestrians and also other green
Mobility modes like public transit users
and cyclists in cities uh that are true
to how people truly
behave when you walk in a city you are
often times faced with many
options whether to walk whether to take
public transit whether to drive one of
those choices is is even if you've
decided to take a walk in a city is
which route to choose as an example here
I've put up a map of New York City and
if you started a walk on Fifth Avenue
near near the Patrick St Patrick's
Cathedral uh and only walked a couple of
blocks over to Carnegie Hall you
actually have 84 different routes you
can take that are exactly the same
length so you have to make a
choice those choices that people make on
on their feet can help reveal
statistically what kinds of routes they
prefer what kinds of Street
characteristics they shy away from and
towards which do they gra
gravitate these choices are influenced
by the properties of the routes whether
they have sidewalks and how wide the
sidewalks are whether you have to walk
next to high highs speeed traffic or
large volumes of vehicles and a lot of
noise whether the route is complicated
whether you have to make turns along the
way whether you have trees or businesses
and amenities along the way each of
these properties of the different route
options that exist influence our choice
of taking uh um a particular or choosing
a particular route in the city to
understand how these choices work we
often collect data from people's cell
phones I'm going to show first an
example of studies we have conducted in
San Francisco and in Boston using
anonymized traces from cell phone
movements where we don't know who the
individuals exactly are we have an
agreement with an app provider who
shares this data but doesn't reveal the
Identity or the personal characteristics
of the users here's an example of about
15,000 people's routes in San Francisco
how they walked from A to B throughout
the street network of the
city once we have such data the original
GPS Trace that we get is is pretty messy
it's a wiggling line uh that has a lot
of noise so the first step in these
studies is to what is called map match
the traces to the street Network we
basically map what street segments were
used which is represented by this
thicker U red line and once we have that
we
can um
construct Alternatives that this person
could have walked for this particular
trip but did not this is called uh route
alternative generation
uh and the red line represents the
trajectory the person actually took but
they could have very well with roughly
similar distance walked alternative
routes we oftentimes construct half a
dozen even a dozen different alternative
routes and for all these routes
including the actual route and the
Alternatives we measure the properties
of the streets like the ones I showed on
the street view image before and this
helps us statistically model what is it
about that rout the routes that people
actually choose that systemically biases
people what kinds of Route
characteristics and properties are
people preferring when they choose their
routes here are some of the
results from Boston and San Francisco
and we've translated the results to
distance equivalent units so that means
for instance when we look at elevation
gain on the second row in San Francisco
each foot of elevation gain or each
meter of elevation gain that people have
to walk uphill is perceived roughly as
equivalent to the walk feeling like 3.8
M longer therefore it reduces or
diminishes our willingness to
walk however if we pass by amenities
like ground floor businesses on city
streets that is a quality that people
generally gravitate towards so passing
10 extra amenities on the sidewalks is
felt by a typical or average pedestrian
as if the walk feels 18 M shorter
therefore it increases the willingness
to walk walk by 18 M sidewalk widths are
also something people
prefer uh people generally also prefer
to walk on Greener streets that have
more
vegetation uh and they shy away from
traffic volumes and traffic speeds where
they have to interact with more cars
these kinds of data these kinds of
results give us an understanding of kind
of a revealed preference understanding
of what do people really prefer uh when
it comes to rout choice where do they
prefer to walk in the city and that
those kinds of results can be translated
back into the predictive models I will
be talking about next in terms of
forecasting where people will
walk these kinds of results can also
help us determine uh various kinds of
catchment studies and accessibility
studies in cities uh in this project
called boston. Transit access.com we
measured the 10minute catchments of
different rail Transit Stations of the
commuter rail network in the Boston
region and overlaid the different
definitions of
accessibility uh often times Transit
planners use a circle of a half mile for
walking access uh here we use different
kinds of interpretations of access the
red polygon shows the what we call the
network catchment which is precisely the
how far you can get in 10 minutes on the
street network but if we take into
account the actual properties of the
streets and people's reaction to these
properties that I showed in the previous
slides from these pedestrian rout Choice
studies we can also delineate what is
called the 10-minute perceived walk set
this is not how far objectively streets
can take you in 10 minutes but rather
how far people would be feeling like a
10-minute walk is from the station
towards the outling destinations and as
you can see this orange polygon showing
the perceived 10-minute walkshed tends
to be far smaller than the network
walkshed in other words negative Street
Properties and attributes can diminish
our perception of how far we can get in
minutes this has implications on Transit
oriented development and lots of
planning applications and as recently um
as this fall we've done a large um opin
study called Boston walks where we
recruited uh around a thousand
participants um who opted into being uh
tracked for a couple of weeks each and
here we're seeking to not only describe
the mobility preferences of average
users like we had in the San Francisco
Boston study but rather we know exactly
the demographic profiles of each users
who have willingly or voluntarily
participated therefore we can also start
to distinguishing how uh men and women's
preferences May differ young and old
people owning cars not owning cars and
we can dig into the heterogeneity of
these uh green Mobility preferences uh
by different groups of
people second I would like to briefly
share how we can operationalize these
findings in predictive models and
forecast and or estimate how pedestrians
move uh in in relatively large areas of
cities and even predict how planning
interventions can change that this is a
project called NYC walks which we've
been conducting in collaboration with
New York Dot and uh Department of City
Planning as well um and to do this
project we've actually built a new um
framework for estimating green Mobility
trips in cities called the urban network
analysis framework which is available as
a free and open- Source python package
called Medina or as a plug-in for design
software called
Rhino uh in this framework we represent
built environments as spatial framework
spatial networks this can be used in
three dimensions even within a building
as shown on the far left or at the
street and building level at the
district or neighborhood level or even
at the city or entire metropolitan area
level as an example how do we represent
built environments as networks well here
we have a part of Boston metropolitan
area in Somerville where Street networks
are represented as sidewalks and
crosswalks accurately representing where
people can actually move or walk as
pedestrians the red dots are address
points which are buildings where trips
can start or end and there's all there's
other types of Origins destinations for
Mobility as well like bus stops or Metro
stations and in fact the list can be
quite a bit
longer so how do we use this
representation to model ped mobility in
New York we constructed a Citywide
network of uh sidewalks crosswalks at
foot paths that cover all five borrows
it's probably the largest pedestrian
Network in the United
States when we model trips using Medina
we model trips from particular Origins
to particular destinations and then try
to estimate with software how those
trips for that type of trip blow over
the network in this case I'm
illustrating uh trips from one census
block which is shown um on the left on
the right here um we actually don't
represent the census block as a single
dot in the middle of the city block but
we subdivide it into four frontages so
that it represents the doors or
entryways on each Street surrounding
that block and one subway stop
represented by these red dots so from
this census block uh trips go to the
subway stops on foot but we do not
assume that they take the shortest path
we enable pedestrians in the model to
take various uh paths that are up to a
certain percent longer than shortest
path and they choose between different
Subway entrances so not everybody walks
to the closest entrance but there's a
destination Choice model in there which
is which is determined by accessibility
of different destinations this is uh
specified in just a few lines of code in
the Medina
package we can then expand it to not
just the N subway stop but all available
subway stop that this particular sensus
block has has around it within about a
10-minute walkshed or a half a mile
walking distance and now the trips are
split not just to the closest station
but trips are um making probability
decisions of which subway stop to uh
walk to depending on their accessibility
uh given where people want to go and if
we expand this further we can do this at
the city scale from all sensus blocks to
all transit stops or entrances
throughout New York City uh and it gives
us a detailed estimation of for that
kind of trip uh how many pedestrians
would be Crossing each uh Network
segment uh sidewalk or crosswalk in the
city and then we proceed to do this for
all types of trips that we uh know are
typically occurring during this period
of the day uh in the morning Peak period
for instance trips going from homes to
Metro stations home to bus stops homes
to jobs homes to parking garages homes
to schools and so forth and the pattern
can look different during the Lunch
Period or evening period this is all
automated with a Medina where we input
these these
um uh guidelines or uh pairings uh with
a CSV table to the software and at the
end we get the distribution for
different kinds of trips over the
network here are amenity to amenity
trips on foot estimated here are homes
to amenities these are businesses like
retailers or food service providers on
cities streets here's home to jobs walks
here's homes to Metro stations that I
showed earlier here's homes to Parks
walks here's homes to schools uh jobs to
amenities jobs to Metro stations parks
to Metro these constitute different
kinds of pedestrian Journeys that take
place during different time periods in
the city now those still constitute just
estimates so we have to calibrate this
model Visa V actual observed traffic
counts particularly pedestrian traffic
counts on on city streets we have over a
thousand locations where New York do has
collected pedestrian traffic counts and
we use these observed counts to
calibrate our model estimates to fit
them to reflect them in accurate ways
and this is done for different time
periods as a result of this we
statistically fit the estimation model
to The observed traffic counts and we
obtain what is called predicted flows of
people which relatively accurate reflect
pedestrian flows on the network of city
streets at different time periods this
is the evening Peak period 5: to 6:00
p.m. in New York City illustrating the
volume of pedestrians on each sidewalk
in the city or each crosswalk in the
city we can zoom into particular streets
or intersections here and on this zoom
in map the um the white labels the white
numbers reflect uh the model estimates
and the blue labels reflect our uh
actual Counts from do
so as you can see the model estimates
and Dot counts are not perfectly aligned
but they're close they're in the same
ballpark for instance here the street
segment um actually has 1,700
pedestrians in evening peak hour our
model estimates close to, 1500 so it's
not perfectly aligned but it's close
over all of these time periods the model
um correlation between predicted and
actual pedestrians at the Thousand
locations where accounts were collected
is around 90% so it does a pretty good
job at explaining actual foot traffic
volumes on the streets of New York now
why is this useful what do we do with
this I would like to argue for four
critical
needs first of
all these observed pedestrian counts are
typically available only at a handful of
locations in the city in New York we had
about thousand locations counted but New
York has over
315,000 Street segments so less than 1 %
less than even uh
33% of streets actually have observed
counts the kind of model I'm showing can
extrapolate the counts and explain food
traffic on all streets of the city and
this can be critical to understanding
how cities can allocate scarse taxpayer
dollars to improve walkability improve
pedestrian conditions on city streets in
an evidence-based way to in other words
prioritize streets where it benefits
more
people
second The Pedestrian um volume
estimates from the model can also
provide an important denominator for
various Hazard data like traffic crash
analysis like Urban heat exposure like
noise exposure or air pollution that
people are exposed to I'll show an
example of that in a second and last the
model can be used to forecast how fixes
or changes to the infrastructure or even
changes in land use such as building a
new Dev velopment at a particular
location a new office building a new
residential complex can impact
pedestrian Mobility can change how many
trips are generated and can change where
the trips are distributed in the network
of city
streets as an example to this
denominator idea here is an example or
here is the plot of data about the 100
most in um the 100 most dangerous
intersections for pedestrians in New
York City the numbers here illustrate
pedestrians that were injured in vehicle
to pedestrian crashes in a 10-year
period in New York City and as you can
see the one of the hot spots Citywide is
Midtown Manhattan where a lot of
pedestrian crashes
occurred um if we don't normalize this
data then it would look like this is a a
highly dangerous area of the city but if
you know New York City you probably also
familiar that this is also where the
some of the highest pedestrian volumes
actually are located places like Time
Square like other Midtown streets so if
we take the results from our pedestrian
flow model that I showed and divide
these crash data through by the the
estimated volumes of pedestrians we get
a very different picture the picture on
the right illustrates the probabilities
of pedestrian injuries or pedestrian
crashes which is normalized data taking
raw crashes and dividing them through by
model estimates and what we see is that
Midtown Manhattan actually disappears
from the picture altogether because yes
there are a lot of crashes in Midtown
Manhattan but there's also astronomical
numbers of pedestrians walking on those
streets so in terms of your probability
of getting into a car crash uh situation
is much worse in other parts of the city
like in Brooklyn Queens Bronx and even
Staten
Island and let me finish up by a third
um illustration which is taking these
kinds of models into a predictive realm
and using them to help a city guide
decision making where infrastru Str
improvements should be positioned so
that they will benefit most constituents
this is a work we're doing um currently
in Seattle to help the city uh achieve a
data driven approach for sidewalk
improvements particularly the attention
paid here is to um universal access on
Wheelchairs and people with walking aids
not only uh fully abled um pedestrians
as well so we have three groups of users
PR apathetic users who are uh able boded
we have Mobility aided users who are
typically either young or old and need
walking aids and wheelchair users we put
together a network of accurate sidewalk
conditions um uh in the city center of
Seattle um and loaded that network with
detailed properties of what each segment
is like how wide are the sidewalks does
it contain stairs or steps uh is there a
marked Crossing on a street corner or
not would you have to walk through
traffic or is there a safe Crossing and
so forth and additionally we combine the
network with uh Ada or Americans with
disability access uh data so these data
come from a study done at the University
of Washington project sidewalk where
users mapped in detail where obstacles
exist on the sidewalk Network for
particularly wheelchair users where you
have broken sidewalks where you have
steps no curb ramps and so
forth having constructed this network we
have a series of assumptions of how
sensitive different people are to the
different conditions uh as an example
for instance uh if a sidewalk is
narrower than 36 in then it may be
somewhat of an inconvenience um for
perioptic or able-bodied users but it
can be prohibitive for people with
walking aids or wheelchairs who simply
cannot fit through that um
width so to understand how the network
of a city impacts uh pedestrian
accessibility for these types of of
users we conduct or we collect a basket
of daily destinations that people
typically need access to things like
schools Transit stations businesses
parks and so forth and we construct a an
accessibility index something like a
walk score that measures how easily
users of different kinds can access this
standard basket of daily destinations
from each address point in the city if
you're a paripe able-bodied user your
access tends to be wider you get to more
places if you are using a walking Aid
you're typically more sensitive to
Street conditions and some conditions
prohibit your access all together so
your walk sheds tend to be smaller and
with wheelchairs they tend to be smaller
yet as illustrated by this black Network
we can measure combined accessibility to
all this basket of destination Citywide
from every address point and as you can
see on these three Maps uh on the right
hand side for wheelchair users the
values look more purple or blue that
signals that their accessibility levels
are systemically lower than on the map
on the left for able-bodied users uh
largely because the infrastructure has
issues has obstacles and also because
this type of user is more sensitive to
infrastructure conditions we can plot
this as a cumulative distribution and
illustrate Citywide how accessibility
levels differ amongst the three user
groups and most importantly
we can use this framework to analyze how
fixing sidewalk conditions that we know
exist like missing curb ramps like
missing uh zebra Crossings like even
missing sidewalks Alto together can
improve accessibility for any of these
three user groups certain things are not
fixable for instance elevation gain the
Topography of the city it would be
extremely hard to change that because it
would level it would mean leveling hills
and mountains in in Seattle but other
things are much easier and so we we have
this concept called The fixability Gap
uh which illustrates that in this
example if you fixed all the
infrastructure problems that are
actually fixable how much would you
improve accessibility across all user
groups in the city but perhaps more
importantly on a daily basis we
shouldn't be talking about fixing all
infrastructure problems in one go but
rather individual fixes at individual
locations so what we're doing now is
developing a data driven prioritization
system that allows the city to uh rank
order the different fixes and say we
should really fix this curb ramp this
sidewalk or this street first because it
has the greatest public benefit it opens
up access to the largest number of
people especially the more vulnerable uh
Road users so that's what we're working
on and the idea is to then uh guide the
uh repairs construction of these curb
Rams uh and taxpayer investments into
city streets into places where they make
the greatest impact with that um I will
wrap up um and just um emphasize that
for cities to move towards green
Mobility targets we actually have to
count data on that we have to model on
that not only cars uh which cities have
been doing for decades we need models to
represent those environments from a user
perspective which these kinds of tools
have tried to share um help us do and uh
the framework we built in this Urban
network analysis
um world helps us uh uh do these
analysis in an open- source reproducible
and free ways that are also available to
anyone who's interested um in in working
these areas thank you thank you very
much Andre for this very insightful
presentation on the urban Network and
knowledgeis frame framework I wonder if
you can um for as far as questions are
concerned how you think uh like three
type of
uh users city
planners and smes and the
pedestrians uh how they can leverage the
model you've
developed yeah uh for city planners I
think these sorts of models um really
give us and other city planners a means
to represent Urban environments pretty
close to how people on the ground
perceive them um with the kind of detail
and resolution that reflects what a
pedestrian really must go through on a
city street uh whether they're walking
on a comfortable segment whether they're
passing other businesses or people
whether they are um uh how direct their
trips are and so forth so I think for
city planners it opens up a whole world
of representing uh cities Through The
Eyes of the user and therefore allows us
to do analysis
that reflect how changes in land uses
and changes in infrastructure would
impact the non-motorized users on city
streets so if we develop a new
development at this location it will add
new trip origins or trip discriminations
it will change the foot traffic dynamics
of an area or if we fix a street here
how many people will it benefit and how
will it affect the flow of pedestrians
through that area um and ultimately
increase desirably the amount of people
who can comfortably safely walk in the
city for end users it opens up um a kind
of a bottomup way of uh representing
their own interests they people can run
their own models they can represent
their own questions through these models
and Advocate with data to represent
their interests if they go to City Hall
meetings or advocate for um their
neighborhood or neighbor benefits they
can uh uh develop analysis scenarios and
say if we put a uh safer Street here or
complete Street here this is how it
would benefit our community um and when
for City governments I think um we we
are witnessing an important shift
towards these kinds of analytic tools
that allow cities to uh not only say
that we want to move towards Greener and
more sustainable Mobility but to
actually be able to model these
Transitions and to quantify whether the
decisions that are being taken on a
daily basis in infrastructure investment
or permitting for new developments move
us in the right direction or actually
away from that
direction thank you uh another question
here from the audience is that uh how
your model
can um take into consider consideration
of the like a live data real- time live
data
um these models are currently uh they
currently represent um built environment
I conditions and foot traffic at typical
Peak periods if we calibrated a model to
specifically uh estimate flows for kind
of live environments let's say uh not
not a typical Peak period at uh Time
Square New York uh in the morning or
evening but rather a specific time slot
like 10:45 a.m. uh then the model would
have to be trained uh also on live
calibration so it could be rather than
being trained on this kind of static
data we have it could be trained on
Dynamic data and uh provide the
estimates in real time how food traffic
conditions change um in the city it's a
little bit like weather forecasting
where if you want to do live weather
forecasting uh you have to uh input data
from all the sensors that are currently
reading it uh as we
speak great that's sounds like a a
typical L application large language
model application
uh one last question before we move on
um also related to data uh for for your
model if there there isn't enough like
data basically that basically for cities
that does not that that that those
cities still not data reach how do you
think you can um address that
challenge yeah this is a great question
in fact we have uh quite actively in our
research group tried to work in uh
places around the global South where
data is much harder to get than than say
here in Boston or or New York City um
there is an emerging body of open-source
data repositories for places around the
world and in my experience it is totally
possible to put together the necessary
data for these sorts of models from
existing open source repositories for
most of the world uh building footprint
data is now globally available for any
place in the world from satellite IM
imagery Road network data often times
comes from open street map or if
necessary can be digitized by research
teams or city staff on the ground which
we have done in other cases origin
destination data about land uses or
business locations sometimes can be
obtained from uh looking through either
open street map or even Google Maps uh
API and and other sources of mapping um
and we have open source street view
imagery in many parts of the world uh
websites like miller.com that show open
source street view that is not propriety
proprietary like Google street view or
uh Bing Street View and so forth so
there's a emerging body of sources uh
which require slightly more work to put
the data sets together but it's possible
and um uh especially if these are
critical areas um in emerging cities um
uh it may be well worth the effort to
generate these data because ultimately
as young Gail likes to emphasize we must
count what we care for if we just
represent car traffic in models uh then
decisions will be made for car traffic
if we want to represent pedestrians and
other sustainable Mobility users we must
represent these environments accordingly
to to illustrate their
perspectives yes I totally agree I think
The Pedestrian aspect or if you call it
human Centric uh perspectives is very
very important in addition to like
Mobility or Transportation Focus thank
you very much I can see um the huge
potential of your model um in really
enhancing the sust sustainable Mobility
social interactions and liable cities
overall thank you
again thank you very much