Hi everyone. My name is Michelle Lee and
I'm the director of the Master of
Business Analytics program. I'm joined
today with associate professor Swati
Gupta um who will talk about her
background and her journey here at MIT.
Welcome Swati. Would you like to
introduce yourself? Thank you Michelle.
Uh it's my pleasure to be here and to
talk to all of you. My background is in
computer science and mathematics and I'm
a professor of operations research and
statistics at Sloan School of Management
and I did my undergrad at IIT Delhi in
India. Uh I majored in computer science
but I always had this tension of you
know I I loved math and then I wanted to
do CS. So I was a CS major but I took
all maths courses and then when I came
for a PhD to the US I uh found my place
in operations research which is like the
right combination of theory and
algorithms and actually making an impact
in practice. So a lot of my work these
days uh is on machine learning and
optimization and AI all the cool stuff
but we also look at various applications
where we can have a direct impact on uh
lives of people. we can uh help society.
We care about making ethical and
algorithmically fair decisions and we
think about all of this in the changing
landscape of various laws and policies
and how they interact with the
algorithms that we have in the world
around us today. Very cool. Can you tell
us a little bit about your most uh
recent research and what your research
concluded? Recently I've been very
curious about a lot of topics ranging
from how do we allocate organs
ethically. Some of these new
technologies have to do with
cryopreservation and xenor grafted
organs. So we've been thinking about you
know how do we assess which patients
need organs the most? what is going to
be the benefit of these new technologies
and how can we actually develop that
supply chain uh logistic system around
uh the space to quickly get the organs
before their quality deteriorates. Wow.
I've also been thinking about uh how do
we make admissions and hiring processes
more e easier, right? Like uh throughout
my life, I was trained to look at
numbers and take them at face value. But
uh what I've learned in the last few
years is that numbers only reflect an
approximate quantity that we've been
able to measure and there's a lot of
noise in our measurement of individuals.
So there's not a number that I can put
on everybody and say that this person
ranks above this other person. So some
of my work recently has been also on
understanding how do we design hiring
algorithms that give people the benefit
of the doubt that allow interview
committees to select people that show
the progress perhaps that we don't have
exact measurements on all of them but we
don't penalize them for not having that
those exact measurements. And the same
kind of thinking goes into admissions
processes as well where students who
let's say you know have um they have
better financial resources they can take
exams like the SATs and the GREs again
and they can improve the scores and they
can report the top performance. However,
what about students who don't have the
means to take these exams over and over
again and we have a noisier estimate on
the quality of these students. So my
research has been around, you know, how
do we still account for that noise in a
way that's fair to everybody that gives
people the benefit of the doubt, but
ultimately all of these problems are
about allocating a limited amount of
resources to a diverse population. Wow.
And we see these ideas also go into
generative AI and LLMs and some of the
new uh AI advances that we're seeing
these days. when an LLM trains on uh
certain objectives or it's trying to
find policies or it's trying to find
types of solutions that you know let's
say a call center should call this
cohort of people to have the maximum
impact a human decision maker can then
go back and tell the LLM that no you
know I want to have more diversity in
the number of people I call and perhaps
you know I want to make sure that we
call u let's say expectant mothers who
would really benefit from certain
information during their pregnancy.
But another human decision maker could
come and say, well, you know, I really
care about giving that information to
uneducated people because they would
really value, they would really uh
benefit from such information. And so
again, we are in this space of having
constrained resources. We have a small
number of callers in a call center that
might call a diverse set of uh expectant
mothers. And the question again is who
should we prioritize uh based on the
need and the benefit that they will have
from these limited resources. Wow,
that's amazing. You're doing so much.
It's from call centers to admissions to
organ donations. Um what if a student
out there in the audience would like to
work with you on your research? How do
you go about um finding students to do
research with? My metric for finding
students and I've worked with a lot of
students from very diverse backgrounds
is the first thing I'm looking for is
passion for their research. So if you're
passionate about something and you're
passionate about a problem or you're
passionate about a theoretical question
then that passion basically allows you
and makes that space for you to grow in
that area to think creatively about new
solutions and to really learn and then
after passion I think from a very
practical perspective to immediately
make impact on research I look for
course preparation so I look for uh you
know strong mathematical preparation and
courses because you know in today's work
to make these algorithms scale and be
robust and reliable, we need to develop
mathematical guarantees. So we cannot
have huristics where we don't know how
they're going to perform on unseen data
but we want to be able to have
robustness or reliability guarantees and
for that I look for students who have
some uh friendship with mathematics who
have taken like uh you know some logic
courses or proof courses you know some
people who can even prototype things
very fast so they can test their ideas
they can code up things fast and that's
what the MBAN program also equips them
to do. So I actually work with a lot of
MBAN students and these students have
come from either they have more of a
machine learning experience, they have
some background with data analytics. So
they can bring that into the projects
and they can work with the data, they
can estimate uncertainties and biases,
they can develop algorithms and they can
implement and see the impact.
Some students that I work with are
really come from like this mathematical
perspective where they're able to look
at the mathematical model and prove
guarantees about it. And so I've had uh
a lot of fun working with students
across these trends and see them
contribute to projects. Wonderful. And I
know you're also an adviser for capstone
projects. Can you tell us a little bit
about the capstone projects that you're
working with or have worked with in the
past? So capstone project experience was
a fantastic experience that I was
basically exposed to at MIT and I really
enjoyed working with capstone companies
in the last uh couple of years. So I've
worked with Accenture, I've worked with
Cognira and Comcast and uh
Accenture started with a very open-ended
project which I thought was uh a a big
challenge for the students. So it was
not something that was very precisely
defined. The project was about
quantifying the impact of generative AI
and how aggressive companies need to be
in their investment in generative AI to
have a competitive edge uh over their
competitors. And I thought this was uh
you know JVI being a new uh AI
advancement we were kind of in this in
the space that we don't have any
benchmark how do we kind of uh say that
this uh this is going to be the impact
of this new uh set of tools right uh I
thought this was a very open-ended
project but what we could ultimately
develop from that was assess using a
very involved markup decision process
the students developed a tool where any
company could put in their parameter s
and then see what is the growth of the
company in the next 5 years or 10 years
in a planning horizon and they could
compare with the market and see you know
how aggressive the generative AI uh
investment needs to be. I thought that
was a very cool project. My other
project was with Cognira and Cognira is
a retail uh analytics uh company and uh
they've gone from kind of this space of
um understanding pricing strategies and
they go all the way to supply chain
management and so this project was uh
about
estimating impact of promotions of
different kinds on the sales of
different products. M so if you promote
let's say pasta and pasta sauce together
then the sales of both of these products
will go up. If you promote core products
then maybe Pepsi product sales go down
and so one promotion leads to a loss of
sales in the other product and so these
are cannibalization effects and this is
a very challenging mathematical question
that when you have signals that are
mixed because of promotions in one
quantity you have mixed signals in the
others in terms of their baseline sales.
How do you estimate that impact? And so
our team of students and uh the team
from Kmira, we all put our brains
together and we came up with this uh
very interesting market normalization
baseline above which we could kind of
estimate these impacts uh with a higher
fidelity and there were discussions
about you know converting that into a
pattern or something that the company
could really convert into its bottom
line and I thought that was very cool
because you know students went from
defining the project getting the data
implemented ing something and showing
something that was not done before in a
very short span of time. Yeah. Our
projects last only about six to seven
months, right? So they have to very uh
work really hard, very quickly ramp up
and provide results and so these
students also got um if I'm not mistaken
pre-placement offers from these firms.
Yes, that is the goal. Yeah. Great.
Well, thank you so much for your time
today. My pleasure. We look forward to
seeing what you'll do next. Thank you.
And uh we'll see everyone very soon. Hi
everyone, thank you for watching. If you
like this video, check out our other
videos in the series where I interview
influential professors at MIT Sloan. If
you would like to learn more about the
Master Business Analytics program, we
also have a playlist where you can see
more videos about the admissions
process, student life, and the program
overall.