[MUSIC PLAYING]
KAMAKSHI SUBRAMANIAN: I
think this class definitely
made me think a little
bit more outside the box.
JESSICA SHAH: It
teaches what assumptions
and what considerations
we can make.
NICO CASTRO: It just makes
you think about situations
in different contexts.
And I think that's
important when you're
learning how to be an engineer.
RITU RAMAN: This class
focuses on biomechanics
and mechanobiology, two words
that sound very similar,
but are actually very different.
Biomechanics conveys the
mechanical properties
of biological materials.
And mechanobiology
teaches students
how cells feel and respond to
forces in their environment.
BRANDON RIOS: It was a very
interdisciplinary class.
So I thought it was a great way
to unify mechanics with biology
and how we're studying forces at
the molecular, cell, and tissue
level.
NICO CASTRO: This
biomechanics course
is a combination of
those, we're you're really
sort of applying those basic
principles in a useful way
and sort of showing
you, like, ah,
yes, biology and
mechanical engineering
are deeply rooted in each other.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
- There are three sort
of ways in which cells
talk to each other.
Those are through chemical
means, through electrical means,
and through mechanical means.
The sort of chemical and
electrical communication
between cells has been
investigated for a long time.
RITU RAMAN: Thinking about
mechanical communication
between cells, that's a little
bit newer, which means that even
researchers are being exposed
to this for the first time.
KAMAKSHI SUBRAMANIAN:
Getting to learn
about research that is
still evolving as we
study it is super interesting.
PETER SO: And at the
same time, it also
gives a very
concrete application
of some of these basic theory.
JESSICA SHAH: From brain
implants, to 3D printing,
to tissue engineering,
to women's health.
And I think the
diversity of the class
provided a broader perspective
of how biomechanics can apply.
PETER SO: We talk about
some of the applications
and why the fundamental
concepts are important for many
of the applications.
KAMAKSHI SUBRAMANIAN: I got
to see the polymer model
first look in my thermo class.
Then I was like,
why is this useful?
Why are we doing this?
And then I came here,
and I was like, OK,
thinking about entropy in
this way is actually useful.
BRANDON RIOS: Getting an
intuition, that's certainly
has helped me, now that
I have an idea of what
I should look for.
And does that make sense?
Am I actually seeing
this in my research?
AYI AGBOGLO: I left not
only understanding more
about molecular mechanics,
but also understanding
just fundamentals about
thermodynamics, and energy,
and things that I think
will be useful just
as a scientist in general.
RITU RAMAN: When
students take this class,
they're getting a really unique
fusion of not only fundamentals
of mechanics, but also emerging
research in biomechanics
and mechanobiology.
That combination of
concepts and principles
is not something
that they're going
to get from any
other class at MIT
and will prepare them for a
broad range of future careers.
KAMAKSHI SUBRAMANIAN: Just
learning about the things
that I could possibly do,
like, if I decided to pursue
a career in biomechanics.
is something that's really cool.