hey hello everyone I'm glad that this uh
the questions transitioned nicely uh
between Liz and me and you might see uh
some Echoes of Liz's presentation
probably because I'm a student of of
Liz's and uh Liz formerly held my job
before she went to the White House so um
there's a lot of parallels here today
and uh just to get started I want to
tell you the story of of Sam Seer this
is Sam he is a New Hampshire
manufacturing worker and he had been
working in manufacturing for few years
uh before he entered his current job the
one that he's performing in this picture
um and and he he in those few years of
manufacturing in New Hampshire he had
never seen a robot and that experience
was actually quite typical because only
about 12% of American manufacturers have
any robotic Technologies at all only
about a third have advanced software so
Sam's experience in manufacturing wasn't
the type of manufacturing of the future
or Advanced manufacturing that we
typically think of it was manufacturing
that looked a lot like it did in the
1970s in the 1980s so Sam went from that
relatively you low paying uh relatively
analog job into this new firm and he
started seeing all sorts of robots at
his current company a company called
hypertherm that makes um Advanced
cutting tools so they Machine Tool
manufactur they export all over the
world and what Sam faced when he saw
this robot he he was a little bit
excited because he liked technology but
he was also a little bit fearful because
he thought that maybe this robot would
make his work less relevant it would
allow him to use less of his mechanical
skills so what he thought was that
really when this robot came into the
factory the the factory itself faced a
fork in the road they could create a job
for Sam that increased productivity so
that allowed Sam to do his tasks faster
but also turned Sam into a little bit of
an automaton he wasn't really solving
problems or providing his own skills on
the factory floor he was really just
checking to make sure that the robot was
doing what it was supposed to do and
that uh that fear was that Sam's work
would not just be uh Le you know less
frequent the jobs less available but it
would also be more commodified and his
job would be lower quality but there was
an alternative and this was actually the
alternative that Sam's employer uh
adopted where Not only was the robot
able to add more productivity but it
also improved the quality of the jobs
for people like Sam their jobs became
higher wage they became more of a cell
leader where they were uh supervising an
automated system system trying to solve
problems when the system broke or
thinking about ways that the system as a
whole could become more productive now
how did they do it I think the the
really interesting question and this is
a question that starts with some of the
trends that Liz identified and Zooms in
on operational strategies to realize
them at the company level was that
hypertherm Sam's employer is really a
special sort of company it's an
employee-owned Cooperative uh by being
employee owned Sam said that every time
he saw parts on a tray he saw them as
dollar signs because he got a share of
the profit so Sam was motivated not just
to try to make the processes more
productive he was also motivated to find
ways to improve those processes
incrementally another really special
thing that hypertherm did was they set
up an internal training institute so
knowing that they were going to adopt
these robots they realized they needed
to create new jobs for people to operate
the robots and fix them so they they
offered those new jobs to people like
Sam and then they also offered classes
across the street from the factory to
fill those jobs and what I want to
illustrate here is that this this
choosing the right path I would say not
just the the right word not the left but
also I would say the normatively better
path of more productivity and higher
quality jobs with robots doesn't just
say doesn't just mean increasing wages
for people who are who are operating
robots or supervising these automated
systems it also means creating these
other types of incentives and other
types of support systems like a training
institute to support workers like Sam
going into this path so I use this as an
illustration of what uh my colleague
Julie Shaw and I call positive sum
automation automation that not only
improves the short-term performance of
The Firm but also improves the long-term
capabilities of the firm including the
quality of jobs for workers and the
incentives for workers to contribute to
continuous Improvement and contribute to
Innovation on the factory floor that's
the important part of the more creative
work that comes out of this positive sum
automation uh equation now you know we
had been working on this for for the
past four or five years and uh two years
ago with the release of chat GPT we
started to wonder does this positive sum
automation framework still hold up in
the era of generative AI like Liz said
um in 2020 there was a a really uh
Landmark study that suggested the the
fear of robots and and displacing jobs
is really misguided the f focus should
be on the quality of work that's really
the jumping off point for for my
research but now there's all sorts of
different discussion of of what
generative AI might mean both for
productivity on the one hand but also
for the threat to to the quality of work
for people like Sam and so so we looked
at these kind of the headlines that were
coming out of commentators about this
technology as hypotheses that we wanted
to test did did generative AI suggest it
was going to have a lead to a different
sort of productivity boom than
Technologies in the past like let's say
industrial robots were jobs really at
risk are white collar workers now now
threatened by these tools and then
finally you know what skills are really
relevant you know if you were creating a
training institute to support workers to
work with gener AI what would that
training institute teach so what we did
a little more than a year ago was we
convened a group of about 60 companies
to start studying their early
applications of generative AI how is it
affecting their demand for skills and
really trying to understand what could
we learn about these hypotheses and we
all what I'll share with you today to to
get started are some of the studies some
of the evidence that we can apply to
these hypotheses and and what I'm you
know that just to give you a preview of
the conclusion I think that a lot of
these hypotheses are are overblown and
not really what we should be concerned
about and instead I think that the more
important area for both our research and
I think for uh for managers to consider
is not necessarily a shortage of jobs
which has kind of been the narrative
around generative AI but a shortage of
skilled workers and this is kind of the
second set of uh the second storyline
that one that Liz already emphasized but
I'm going to dive into a little bit more
piecing apart you know going back to
some of the questions that you had about
technology adoption in the US versus
other countries and also skill
development and and Workforce education
in the US so I'll start with this
generative AI story line and I think try
to pick apart some of the assumptions
that we've made and then I'll I'll pivot
to this question of the labor shortage
in you know industrial skill intensive
jobs and what we can do about it so to
get started you know early on in the
discussion of generative AI this is a
discussion of uh the adoption of robots
as well there is this consideration that
productivity is just going to go up and
up it's going to be a transformation of
productivity such that we might not need
to employ nearly as many workers as we
had in the past now there's a really uh
terrific uh book by by Robert Gordon an
economist from Northwestern he was uh uh
he was my economics professor as an
undergrad he's a very grumpy person and
this is quite a grumpy book um if you're
interested in reading it it you might
want to um you know uh you know bring
your optimism to to the read but the
what he argues essentially is that the
even though we've had you know
innovations that have transformed
consumer experiences the personal
computer the internet um these
Innovations have not had nearly as big
of an effect on productivity as previous
generations of of Innovations so what he
shows and this is you know what other
economists have confirmed is that
productivity growth in previous eras
before 1970 before the kind of Rise of
digital Technologies were far greater
than productivity growth afterward and
what Eric bolon at Stanford and others
call they call this the productivity
Paradox because we predicted and
anticipated that these digital
Technologies would have a huge impact on
our productivity and overall prosperity
and in some ways they have had a
transformative impact but it hasn't been
measured in the productivity numbers um
one I think you know the cartoonish
explanation for this might be that um
even though these uh these tools have
allowed us to do some tasks faster in
email is much more uh productive let's
say than writing a letter or sending in
aax but they've created other tasks that
are less productive and they've also
been sources of great distraction that
have made us uh less productive overall
so the one big question for us is like
the productivity Paradox is pretty clear
for the personal computer and for the
internet is it going to La is it going
to be uh persistent for generative AI
now now what I want to emphasize here is
that when we talk about generative a
we're talking about something very
different than other automation
Technologies I think sometimes the you
know generative models get L uh lumped
in with narrow AI things like um you
know detecting anomalies on a radiology
scan and they also get lumped in with
other automation Technologies like
robotic process automation software
that's used in finance and Healthcare or
industrial robots like the kinds that
Sams uses on the factory floor what's
really different about this set of
Technology
is that if you think about their
reliability at performing a task versus
their flexibility at performing a task
they they perform very differently than
robots so if I give a robot or a CNC
machine a task I program it to do a task
it can do the same thing over and over
again very reliably as long as I give it
a dedicated power source and uh you know
an unchanging work environment however
it takes a lot of human skill and it
takes a lot of effort in some cases to
get the to train the robot or train the
machine to do a new task so we could
think about these as highly robust
systems that aren't very flexible now
what I think is exciting about these
Technologies is the role for the human
and the role for the worker is typically
to make things like industrial robots
more flexible and one of the great
things we have as humans or one of our
human capabilities is flexibility that
we can solve problems and adapt a
technology to new situations this is one
reason why you know Engineers have
really thrived working with robots and
they they can demand a high wage for
that sort of job generative AI is really
the inverse in a lot of the ways it's
been used so far it's highly flexible in
the sense that it can answer all sorts
of questions in different languages and
different formats like videos and um and
images but the the technology itself
isn't very robust it's designed such
that you can give it the same prompt
over and over again and it'll give you a
different answer and and my favorite
illustration of this is what's called
the strawberry problem has anyone uh
heard of the strawberry problem or
encountered this themselves I'm seeing
some no head so apologies for the review
but I still find it fun every time um it
comes up so um this is a known problem
to to open AI it's a problem with chat
GPT where if you ask uh the chat GPT um
how many RS are there in the word
strawberry it will give you uh
invariably the wrong answer it will say
that there are two RS rather than three
and if you follow up and say well which
letters are the RS it'll give you the
right answer it'll identify three Rs in
Strawberry it can spell the the word
correctly and if you go on you can give
it the same question with the same
wording or with slightly different
wordings and sometimes it'll say two RS
sometimes it'll say three Rs now what's
the most what's remarkable about this
issue I think is that not just that it
gets a very simple uh question wrong of
course you know if you've played around
with these tools they get
extraordinarily complex questions right
and they they have uh very high
capabilities but what I think is so
interesting is that all of the the
Brilliant Minds at open AI know about
this problem they've known about this
problem for a long time and they can't
fix it and it's because this tool is a
black box that they can't necessarily
given the the flexibility of the tool
they don't necessarily uh have the the
knowledge or of the internal workings of
the system to make it more robust so
there really is this trade-off between
flexibility and robustness with these
tools now I want to show how this plays
out in in more serious examples than
just the the strawberry illustration so
this is um some some tables from a paper
from a colleague um and collaborator
mind Kate Kellogg along with others
where they studied the use of generative
AI with Boston Consulting Group
consultants and what they did was as you
can imagine in a typical experimental
setup they gave one group of Consultants
access to chat GPT to do a few tasks
they gave the other group of Consultants
access to kind of their typical you know
computer internet browser to do the
tasks one task was essentially
developing a business plan a go to
market strategy for a new shoe typical
Consulting task the second task
was to evaluate the market opportunity
of multiple different products using an
Excel spreadsheet of financial data as
well as transcripts of interviews now on
the first task the group with uh
essentially the chat GPT equivalent did
extremely well they were far faster you
know more productive at doing this task
and they also were judged by a party of
experts to do um a higher quality job at
this task and what was remarkable and
they found this in in more studies than
just with the BCG Consultants is that
the least experienced Consultants
actually got the biggest Boost from the
chat GPT this seemed to be a skill
leveler that the the biggest benefit of
the tool was for the most Junior people
so if we were just looking at this
result this result's been replicated in
customer service settings in writing um
this would be you know a game Cher
really U an incredible benefit however
when they looked at the other task the
task where you had to analyze tabular
data along with
transcripts the group with generative AI
in particularly the group with
generative AI that had been trained on
where generative AI was weak they were
more likely to get the the answer wrong
they were more likely to lead you in the
wrong direction and when they went
through essentially the the transcript
of how the BCG Consultants were
interacting with the tool they realized
that the it wasn't just that they were
the the algorithm was giving them the
wrong answer it was that the algorithm
was very persuasive that when you
followed up with the um well you
followed up with questions about why the
answer was um was the way it was uh chat
GPT like tool gave you a very convincing
argument for the wrong answer so this
was really the the challenge that they
identified in this paper which I think
is relevant to a lot of operators is
where is the frontier where this
technology has a comparative advantage
for the goto Market strategy it's pretty
clear that this tool can make workers
more productive and it can be beneficial
as helping workers climb the learning
curve but for the other example with
more you know uh more of an analytical
case it wasn't clear initially whether
this tool would be uh a comparative
advantage or not not it turns out that
it actually LED workers astray so the
question is you know what are the use
cases where this tool can actually be
beneficial and one of those use cases
that that I think is um that that we've
seen the most adoption among our uh
working group has been in software
engineering and the use of tools like
GitHub co-pilot are there any users
within your organizations using GitHub
co-pilot for software engineering
benefits okay in the questions please
let me know if your experience has been
much different than this but this is the
first real you know randomly um you know
randomized control study of the use of
GitHub co-pilot to improve software
engineering productivity and who better
to study then Microsoft which is one of
the pioneers of these Technologies along
with Accenture which uses it on a high
variety of projects and then they had
this Anonymous company that they say is
a large company let's just take their
word for it um so some of these
co-authors are are Microsoft employees
for Microsoft research and some of them
are our colleagues at at MIT and what I
think is is interesting and this is just
maybe to give you um you know I'll just
give you the skepticism with which I
read these results now is that the
headlines associated with these studies
only looked at this fourth column this
fourth column right here which pulled
the results of three very different
companies and how they Ed GitHub
co-pilot and of course the the results
that they shared were that the GitHub Co
that using GitHub copilot led to
significantly more builds for software
Engineers a boost in productivity um of
of you know 30 plus% and I think that is
a really exciting finding I actually
given some of the anecdotal uh
information from our working group
members I thought it might be higher
because there are a lot of people very
excited about GitHub co-pilot but then
when you look at the the tables this
table in particular you realize you know
the pool data are actually masking a
really interesting story that at
Microsoft where you might expect
productivity to be very high given the
familiarity with these tools there was
no significant increase in in builds
there was just a significant increase in
poll requests and trying to you know
starting work and an Accenture where
there was which is really driving this
result there was a significant increase
in builds but also there was a decline
in the success so there's a tradeoff
between productivity and the quality of
the work that was being produced so I
think what's happening here and really
why I think we we should be skeptical of
these sorts of sites is there's a big
heterogeneity not just in how companies
are using these tools but the
individuals within companies and how
they're using these tools so what we've
we've seen and started to see is that
expert users users who know what a
software system should look like who
know what they want to produce they're
able to use these tools very
productively because they can see if
it's not giving them what they want and
they can adjust course so if if they're
a domain expert and they can interpret
the information that a GitHub co-pilot
or a chat GPT gives them that can be a
real comparative advantage but for a
junior developer who might not know what
they're supposed to produce it might
make them faster at trying to do a task
but the build success rate might be
lower so this is I think just continuing
to look at this tradeoffs not just in
which tasks are for a competive
Advantage but for which workers these
tools might be a competive Advantage as
well and then finally and this is I
think hot off the presses this is from a
a graduate student at MIT and it's
really a fantastic study so I would I
would uh invite you to to look further
if you're thinking about this in your um
company so I I had um been looking among
our 60 companies for use cases related
to Innovation and R&D and that's where
I'm most excited about this technology
I'm hoping that this technology might be
able to discover new drugs that are very
that have a high impact it might be able
to discover new materials that allow for
more environmental resiliency that sort
of thing and that has been the promise
that I think the U the folks who are
developing these technologies have sold
us on and this is the first real study
to estimate how these Tech how these
technology tools are translating into
Innovation and what Aiden finds is that
there's actually was he he studies I'll
give you this um the setup of the study
first so you can we can interpret the
findings together he looks at the
introduction of these tools in an a big
R&D team at a materials company where
the main uh R&D engine is identifying
new materials and then translating them
into useful products so if you look at
this you know uh the left set of figures
here this is the kind of the key finding
on productivity where he looks at a huge
boost when you at this dotted lines when
they adopt the AI tools a huge boost in
the discovery of new materials really
noticeable you know 40% increase and
then as a result of finding these new
materials there's a huge boost in in
patentability now for those of you who
deal with the patent system this isn't
very surprising you know you can patent
just about anything um if you if you
have the right team as this company does
um but really what I think the where the
rubber meets the road is do these
materials are they actually useful do
they translate into product prototypes
and his finding is that they do although
at a far lower rate than the materials
that were discovering
so he finds and I think this is really
important that there does seem to be
some promise that that there were more
new products developed after the
introduction of of AI at this company
now let's getting back to our discussion
about work what's the impact on the
worker he has a a you know a fascinating
result so here's how workers say their
jobs change these are R&D workers phds
Highly Educated people they say they
spend a lot less of their time
generating new ideas and a lot more time
trying to exercise judgment or to
interpret the ideas of the algorithm and
a lot more time just running experiments
and overall their job satisfaction
plummeted about 80% of the workers say
they hate this so it's making them more
productive but they can't stand it
because the thing that they really liked
about their job in the first place they
weren't doing anymore they like to
generate ideas they wanted to keep that
part of their Work Sharp that's why they
got into science so it's it's a really I
find it a a fascinating but almost
confusing finding from an R&D
perspective like do you adopt this Tech
technology if you know that you're going
to face this tradeoff or I think more
relevantly how might you adopt this
technology to get the benefits of
improved productivity but not the costs
of an unhappy Workforce that feels like
they're not exercising the muscle that
got them into this environment in the
first place okay so I've been I'm going
to back up so I've been interested in
this question of how workers think about
these tools and under what conditions
workers might want to work with these
these types of automation Technologies
and look at them as as a positive for
their job quality and now I'm going to
give you some data that were um
collected before Aiden released this
paper and I think you know might uh
provide some Nuance to what he found so
we had a a survey of about 9,000 workers
across industry so nationally
representative survey and we asked
workers a bunch of questions about um
you know whether they the whether
Automation and new technology had a
positive impact on various aspects of
their job and really what we wanted to
know was are there certain strategies
that can f a worker from being resistant
to new technology to embracing new
technology and I I just will give you
this is you know published I can share
it with you but I'll give you a few
overview findings to to shed some light
so first you know we expected given this
Narrative of Technology being against
workers that workers might be more
resistant than not to to new
technologies and we asked them about not
just the impact of new technologies on
their job security but on various
aspects of their work you can see safety
autonomy Etc and I was very surprised to
find how positive workers were about
Automation and new technologies so the
Net score is the percentage of workers
that were in favor that thought these
new technologies were positive versus uh
you know the difference between the
positive score versus the negative score
and you could see that all in all of
these categories workers were more
positive than negative and for things
like upward Mobility workers really
associate new technologies and
automation with helping them move up in
their careers and workers who who
prioritize upward mobility and education
who are really motivated by that are the
most likely to be champions of new
technology so that's one of the big
findings here one of the second findings
and what I think is important for for
many of you as as managers and operators
is that there seem to be ways to design
jobs to get Workers to embrace
technology more and this is what kind of
brings this you know links it to Aiden's
paper so I expected early on with this
survey I thought you know the workers
who are in the most routine jobs who
might be most vulnerable to um to
automation those are going also going to
be the workers that are resistant think
of like the Lites the the ones who broke
the machines were the ones that thought
that the machines would be taking their
jobs but that's not what we found at all
actually we found that your level of
routine tasks in your job did not
predict how open or closed you were to
automation instead it was your level of
problem solving so if you look at
workers in physical industries that had
a high level routine tasks but low
problem solving you could think of
workers who are kind of that automaton
the left fork in the road of adopting
new technology they were the most
negative about the impact of automation
new technology but if you have high
routine tasks and high problem solving
you're the most open to new technologies
now in retrospect I probably should have
thought of this in advance but it does
seem like if you have high routine tasks
you both see a role for Automation and
new technologies in your job it might be
able to help you get rid of the drudgery
and you're pretty secure that you're
still going to be able to solve problems
at work so I feel like the the challenge
for Aiden's R&D scientists was that they
might have been in a low essentially low
routine tasks and high problem solving
and in some ways they were taking away
some of their problem solving that they
were able to do all right so I'm I can
come back to this but I think you know
the the big story here is that although
generative Ai and and AI Technologies in
general seem like they're presenting new
challenges for work we actually have a
lot of experience with these types of
human in the loop problems some of our
experience comes from issues like
Aerospace there's a lot of actually uh
manufacturing examples that can help us
manage these human Loop challenges and
what we you know teach when we teach our
students automated systems we can draw
on that historical data um to help them
think about how to design a job with
with generative AI for example okay all
right so now I want to get to the second
piece and which really builds off of of
Liz's presentation which got me excited
so irrespective of you know this the uh
the excitement about generative what are
we going to do about all of these jobs
very skilled jobs in heavy industry that
are going to come online over the next
10 years so as Liz mentioned you know
there's been more than a tripling of
manufacturing Construction Construction
of new energy facilities in States like
Texas and then you see a lot of I think
well-founded concerns that we just don't
have the people we don't have people
interested in these industries we don't
have people who are attracted to these
sorts of jobs and it's a real problem I
talk to manufacturers frequently
favorite part of my job is to go out to
factories and I started asking a
question about how fast do you think you
could grow today and a lot of
Manufacturers I could double in size
today then you ask the next question
well why aren't you doing it it seems
like that would be the rational thing to
do if you could double say well I can't
find the people to do it and that seems
like a real a real problem there's
something really broken that we can't
mobilize the people and I want to kind
of first unpack that problem and then
suggest a potential resolution so first
I think Liz actually responded to these
relatively well so but there are some
voices out there um that say hey we
don't we shouldn't really be focused on
manufacturing relative to other
Industries um you know uh I all I like
wolf in the financial times he calls it
manufacturing fetishism I didn't know it
was a fetish of mine but I certainly
think that uh manufacturing is very
important and I think we should
emphasize the reason it's important is
not only is it the most uh you know the
highest paying set of jobs for people
without a forear degree it's also one of
the only types of uh of Industry that
brings in money to an economy from
outside it's one of the only tradable
Industries whereas retail is really just
recycling um uh recycling money within
an economy manufacturing particularly
manufacturing that exports has a huge
positive spillover effect on any
Regional or national economy that's why
it matters is that's what gives it
really the multiplier effect um so
here's what I I want to give as another
reason for manufacturing manufacturing I
think for the last about 100 years has
been really core to the American dream
so if we look at the map of where
manufacturing has grown versus
disappeared over the last 40 years you
could see and and including you know a
little kind of uh rivulet through
through Texas the the orange and the red
are the places where manufacturing has
strengthened as the economy has
de-industrialized and these are also the
parts of the country where the middle
class is strengthened where there's been
been strong upward Mobility so here just
Maps manufacturing growth with up upward
mobility and you can see that same
central part of the country has high
upward Mobility meaning the the next
generation is doing better than the
generation before and it's the extent to
which they're doing better um and
they've also done that in part because
of access to to manufacturing job there
also seems to be some link to two-year
degrees but um just to give you a sense
like this is why I you know I think it's
partly why Liz talks about manufacturing
it's why I think manufacturing
industrial jobs are so important so if
they're so important what can be done
next um you know just a a review here's
what's happened to manufacturing job
openings over time you can see the spike
in the green line which is job openings
during covid also the spike in in
turnover which is the gry line uh but it
wasn't just a CO problem it was actually
manifesting for about 10 years before
that that we saw tripling in job
openings between 2010 and 2018 so
long-standing problem and it's a problem
that I've heard a lot of employers
respond to not by investing in kind of
public goods like you know community
colleges or Vocational Technical
institutions they've actually started
just hiring anyone who they think can
can uh can perform the job show up on
time and perform a basic set of skills
and they say We'll train you on the job
the problem for that is it often takes
between one and three years then for
these workers who comeing off the
streets to get fully self-sufficient on
the job so this hire for will train for
skill strategy puts firms behind the
eightball from the jump because they're
not really uh prepared to run an
internal training organization if they
don't have a training institute like
hypertherm does so they end up with this
High turnover cycle and bringing in
people without really the skills to do
the job so it's just constantly a a
really a negative feedback cycle that's
been a problem you know one of the
reasons why we've seen this this goes to
the question from I think it was Mr
Thompson right that um this question of
or actually sorry you had a question
about education your question about
wages kind of decoupling wages so on the
manufacturing side and this goes there's
a difference industry by industry but we
take manufacturing overall just
production workers the wages are the
pink line here that before about 1981
1982 that recession there was this very
positive equilibrium where wages were
going up technology adoption was going
up productivity was going up but then
something happened in the early 80s
where now adjusted for inflation in
manufacturing that pink line has been
pretty flat and and what's happened is
that that pink line was flat for a few
reasons one was downward pressure from
foreign competition so a lot of
manufacturers in you know Industries
like you know textiles some extent
Metals said this is a race to the bottom
the way that we compete we need to keep
our costs low we can't give ra raises to
our workers there's also this move this
Geographic move where a lot of
manufacturing is moving south lower
partly attracted by lower wages in the
South so that's another downward
pressure but even in Auto for example
the this came up during the auto strike
um you know a couple years ago that auto
workers wages spite having a union they
they've been flat for the um for about
the last 20 years and their productivity
has been flat so I think even more
concerning about the wages here is that
productivity and this is I'll take you
the green line right here has been
declining since 2010 so overall
manufacturing is not just short of
workers it's not becoming more
productive um one thing to attribute to
that is this red line that technology
adoption has been flat goes to your
question about tech why is uh American
Technology adoption kind of fallen
behind other countries this is showing
that it's not just about robotss it's
about overall Capital expenditures have
been flat when adjusted for inflation
since about 2000 okay just to to break
it down a little more I think it's
important that when we talk about
technology adoption being flat here's
some uh kind of summary statistics of
how manufacturers how many manufacturers
have adopted VAR pretty basic
Technologies of of modern industry it's
also that when you don't have the
Technologies you're not going to hire
workers who have advanced technical
skills so fewer than one in five
production jobs
have any digital skill requirements at
all that ranges from you know
understanding machine learning
algorithms to just operating Excel that
they they don't they don't require those
skills this is consistent with the hire
for will train for skill Paradigm now
you know we talked about flat wages I
want to put you in kind of the position
of Sam Seer again that when he's looking
at a job in manufacturing if he were
looking at that job in 1960 coming out
of high school he could make 40% more in
manufacturing than he could make in
alternative IND alternative Industries
like going to work at Target or going to
work Target didn't exist but um going to
work at another um in another field
today he makes about 2% more in
manufacturing than than any other um
industry on average in Massachusetts he
would make negative on average in
manufacturing versus other Industries in
Texas it's a little bit more so in Texas
he'd make about 10% more on average in
manufacturing than other industries that
includes um oil and gas folks without a
without a college degree but you could
look at kind of these these big markets
like California Illinois Massachusetts
in Florida you make less on average in
manufacturing than you do in other
Industries so that negative
manufacturing wage premium is a huge
problem if manufacturers hope to recruit
more workers it can no longer be a race
to the bottom to recruit workers it
needs to be creating better jobs while
adopting new technology becoming more
productive okay so this wage problem is
huge now Liz mentioned this the idea of
uh recruiting new workers isn't just a
growth in factories it's also um what I
think of as a retirement bomb that is
like slowly ticking and about to
here is kind of the a nice illustration
of the the retirement bomb in the cliff
um I was you know I was plotting this
for uh for a journalist doing a a story
on the Aerospace and I was a little bit
shocked by how dramatic this was I
didn't I didn't think it was going to be
so dramatic so here's just an age
distribution of manufacturing workers in
2000 versus 2021 2022 now what this
shows is in 2000 before the real
collapse of American manufacturing
employment manufacturing look like a
pretty healthy industry pretty normally
distributed um age you have most of your
workers are in their you know late 30s
early 40s and then you have a good crop
of young workers and then some older
workers that are are retiring but now
what you see is the vast majority of the
or the the really the plurality of
manufacturing workers are nearing
retirement so that's when when we think
about the retirement Cliff retirement
bomb whatever you want to call it that's
the workers that it's not just the
number of the people but it's all the
knowledge that they possess about
manufacturing operations the expertise
they have that needs to be translated
now this little blip in hiring of young
people is I think encouraging it means
that there there is now uh something of
a population that can inherit that
knowledge but really what we want to see
to absorb the retirement of this of this
group is a much bigger peak in the in
the 20s and 30s of of workers in
manufacturing so this is just like I
should be keeping you know National
leadership up at night because this just
is not a recipe to compete um you might
have heard uh Paul mer luuy who is the
uh founder of andril a new large defense
manufacturer you might disagree with
Palmer lucky on a lot of things but one
of the things that he points out is that
because there are a lot of single Source
defense contractors with uh experts in
this category in their late 60s who are
retiring they now have to call experts
out of retirement because they're the
only ones who know how to operate
certain machines or produce um or or
produce certain items so it feels like
we have a lot of um you know old
machinists and tool and die makers that
might be treated like uh NFL
quarterbacks being paid you know a
million dollars to come in and do
something that only they or you know a
dozen people like them can can do to
support um the national
interest all right so now I want I I
want to give a little bit of of Hope and
I I think optimism because there are a
lot of very smart people like like Liz
and others who have worked on policies
to support industrial revitalization and
Prett support on on the workforce side
so here's someone and and I mentioned
Sam Seer before we did a short
documentary on him and hypertherm which
uh I I'm happy to share if if you're
interested in learning more about how
they operate and we've also done a short
documentary on uh this guy named Colin
Cutz who uh runs a small manufacturing
shop in Ohio and what Colin has done and
I think he he's tried to become an
evangelist for this this sort of
activity is he's essentially said we
just need to create a better sort of
manufacturing job he's realized that
this race to the bottom isn't going to
work he's also realized that new
technology is necessary so what he's
done is he's automated every piece of
equipment in his shop and he's really
started his machinists at $30 an hour
which is about double the median wage
for machinists in Ohio and he showed
that this model can be profitable he's
tripled in size over the last six or
seven years a lot of that relies on him
having some software expertise and being
able to take the risk to integrate new
software and to take on jobs that he
doesn't necessarily know will be
profitable at the outset so he's taken a
lot of risks to get there but part of
what he's done in Ohio is now develop a
collective really start to lead a
collective of uh like-minded
manufacturing firms that are pooling
their resources to start train the next
generation of machinists to enter into
these higher wage jobs so this is what
he's demonstrated that this High wage
high technology equilibrium for
manufacturing can exist and I I think
it's really the only way for
manufacturers to compete um another real
benefit which I think is a testament to
some of the policies that that Liz
talked about is there's been an
extraordinary growth in foreign direct
investment why is foreign direct
investment important so just to you know
underline it like in the three years
before covid there were only about 12
billion uh Factory projects that tripled
and then overall since about 2010 you've
seen more than a a doubling of foreign
direct investment while overall
investment manufacturing has been pretty
flat so foreign direct investment is is
huge about 40% of new large American uh
manufacturing projects are foreign owned
um you might think of that that as
concerning for maybe national security
reasons or others but actually it's it's
quite a good thing for workers cuz when
uh foreign companies invest in in the US
they typically not only hire uh you know
they hire people at higher wages they
also invest more in new technology and
they're more productive and that that
productivity gain isn't just for the for
forone factories themselves when they
have American suppliers their
productivity spills over to their
American suppliers you might think of
that as like when Toyota moved in and um
helped their suppliers adopt lean
practices that was a benefit for their
suppliers as well okay um I'm going to
end with with a little you know just
another piece of kind of good optimistic
news this is um on the on the left this
is a woman named Kathy Walker who is is
from Kentucky and she works in Eastern
Kentucky in in Appalachia and next to
her is the founder of of hos one of the
largest American Machining companies um
jeanos who has started a a network of
training institutes um kind of like
hyper thms but not linked to any one
company to train the next generation of
machinists he I think part of the
interest is he wants them to know how to
use hos equipment but it's actually a
very very uh beneficial system and and
they partnered about 5 years ago to set
up one of these institutes in uh in
Appalachia in Eastern Kentucky where
there's really no manufacturing to speak
of and what was really interesting is it
was it was kind of a bold move because
normally they do this next to employers
who are ready to hire the workers out of
the system but you know Cathy had seen
this this community really fall apart in
the opioid crisis with the closure of
coal mines but what she knew was that a
lot of these workers who were under
underestimated their whole lives had a
lot of mechanical skills they had a lot
of latent mechanical skills and they
wanted to work if given the opportunity
they fixed their own cars they they did
they developed a lot of these skills out
of necessity so what she did was she
hired um someone who who's ex-military
this is one of the head trainers who
just came out of the military he was
actually a prison guard after the
military and they set up what was
essentially like a military boot camp
for manufacturing Machining it was heavy
on discipline and professionalization
and it was also teaching the the folks
many of whom were former coal miners
some of them whom were formerly
incarcerated to to apply their
mechanical skills to specific jobs that
they need as machinists and now they
have you know 100% placement rate for
their graduates and jobs and they won't
uh take any employers to recruit from
their graduates who offer less than $25
an hour which is really kind of a
transformative wage for a lot of these
workers and much higher than the typical
wage in in Kentucky so this has been
really kind of a a a a beacon of and a
model for a lot of manufacturing
education particularly in the South and
the big question is like how would you
set up the organization called eami the
Eastern Kentucky Advanced manufacturing
Institute um and and they have a lot of
public officials come through and wonder
like how do we get an eami on every
corner or in every manufacturing
Community how would we replicate this
and I think we don't have a good model
for this right now to scale up a really
uh Strong high performing training
institute but we do have one from
history so just to end I'm going to give
you the story of what we did um as a
country in the early 1940s right before
um even before we went into World War II
that in the previous um in the previous
World War I we actually really struggled
to mobilize our industrial base and we
struggled um to train workers we only
trained um about 30,000 workers during
um during World War I and then there was
a concerted effort partly motivated by
former Auto
Executives um that went into uh into
public service to to mobilize the
industrial base and partly motivated by
Sydney Hillman who was a labor leader
and led the unions and got the unions on
board to participate in um in the
mobilization of workers and what they
did was they set up essentially a field
uh network of hundreds and hundreds of
people who went to every you know high
school that had a shop every Community
College every college and they gave them
the resources to train more and more
workers as well as they had these huge
public campaigns to get tens of
thousands of workers into these
facilities across the country every week
and it was a guarantee that these
workers would have jobs at relatively
High wages and they produced in in a
matter of about 18 months to two years
more than three million workers um if we
did this today even though we have a
much larger population um we could
mobilize in relatively short order of
the workers we needed to um to fill many
of the gaps that we have in
manufacturing and to to staff all the
factories that are coming online so it's
it's possible but it really needs some
kind of national effort and National
commitment from folks like Hilman who
were in labor as well as folks uh in
manufacturing like uh Walter nudson who
who led the war production board so I
think there's there's historical
precedent I think there's a lot of
energy today and I'm I'm hopeful that um
the future of work at least in this
sense will be bright um thank you very
[Applause]
much question raise your hand if you
have a question we have one over here
got it
thank you uh my name is Matthew Safi I'm
a strategy manager uh in area of cloud
Ai and Manufacturing for dasol system so
um I was really U impressed with the the
slide that you had U unemployment
productivity um and
wages okay yes so uh what I was trying
to understand here is what happened in
1980 and I try to imagine what project
what going to happen in future so the
Tipping Point in 980 was that um we had
high high interest rate we had oil
crisis we had increase in
Automation and we have dere
regularization uh and also we have
increase in decentralization or Global
globalization this is actually a real
match with what we are right now so we
have increased in automation because of
the AI and everything else is the same
High interest rate and everything else
checks out so what I see is that we're
going to have the same Trend declining
uh Trend in
wages increase in productivity and
decrease in uh
unemployment increasing unemployment So
based on the factor that I mentioned
what do you think do you think is it
what we're heading to no I I I diagnos
the problem in the early ' 80s quite
differently um I think part of this is
driven by the the collapse or loss in
competitiveness of a few us Industries
um that was kind of a mounting problem
in the 1970s and then really kind of um
was exacerbated in the 1981 1982
recession which was quite acute in
places like Pitts so the two industries
were metals and Automotive um Automotive
losing a lot of competitiv to Japan
um and metals particularly steel doing
the same so you see in like 1981 1982
Pittsburgh just loses its industrial
base in a matter of of two years
unemployment 18% right really
extraordinary uh hits similarly with
Automotive that Detroit goes through the
the biggest crisis until like 2009 2010
so that's really the the early part of
the Cascade of of loss of manufacturing
competitiveness that leads to a much
more conservative mindset for
manufacturers a second factor which I
think is related a little bit to kind of
the interest rate environment that you
mentioned is that the public markets in
the US start to be a lot more focused on
Pure Play companies not these old school
manufacturing conglomerates so they
encourage a lot of of the breaking off
of different um different parts of
manufacturing Enterprises and they're
less likely to support the the stock the
growth of the stocks of um you know of
of the um traditional asset heavy
companies so this is I think consistent
with the rise of private Equity buyouts
of manufacturers in the 1980s um that's
like why you see just a much more
conservative pattern of behavior not
just on kind of worker wages but also on
Capital expenditures so I I look at it a
little bit different and why
manufacturing stop competing also today
you mentioned generative AI the
automating leading to less unemployment
I I don't see that is a an issue in the
short to medium term maybe long term
maybe I don't have enough imagination
but right now you see a very tight labor
market and you see you know uh below
replacement rate um you know uh you
population growth so I I don't think we
have an environment for um you know a
loose labor market in in the near term
there might be cyclical stuff like we
see in the last quarter of contraction
of manufacturing but I don't think
that's a long-term issue okay one more
question hi Will Fraser unique Ventures
I I noticed you chose hypertherm as one
of your examples that's a Dartmouth they
School of Engineering spin-off and I'm
at Dartmouth as well as an MIT Alum so
do you see different patterns with
University spin-offs and with startups
in terms of adoption of Technology some
of the uh wage and growth grow patterns
and things like that that would be uh
indicative of of maybe some positive
directions
there yes I'm going to give a I have a
much longer answer than I think I'm
going to be allowed to give so I'm happy
to talk to you more about this after so
yes my wife went to Dartmouth as well um
and and it's it's great up there um so I
think there are a few re so so this what
I'm really concerned about is the
essentially the conservatism of
manufacturing Enterprises and I think
the the financial environment for those
Enterprises one of the reasons for
conservatism that if you're a small
family held business you're not going to
risk the family farm on your your growth
pattern um if you're bought by private
Equity there's a short-term incentive to
try to capture um Returns on the
business and then if you're in the
public markets there's an incentive to
Offshore and to reduce assets so none of
that is a recipe for long-term growth of
American industrial base now what I'm
doing right now is trying to study
alternative mechanisms for doing that I
think there are three so one alternative
mechanism is what danaher has
Illustrated over time like a more
traditional Diversified conglomerate
model where it's a private you know
Daner is not public held but you could
have a privately held version of this
which is a holding company for the long
term that's sharing expertise across
diverse manufacturing operation so
rebuild manufacturing is a company that
in part came out of MIT has a lot of MIT
alums didn't really come out of MIT but
is I think an exciting model of what
this what's possible there and they're
still early but I'm following their
course the second model is Venture
Capital based so we've seen much more
Venture not a ton but much more Venture
going into manufacturing startups a lot
of them focus on uh start with new some
new technology that might be you know a
stepwise Improvement in productivity but
um I I think there it's a super mixed
bag as it is for a lot of venture but I
do think that um the the what encourages
me is that a lot of the folks who were
at Tesla or SpaceX and saw step-wise
changes in manufacturing processes are
now partly because they've been turned
off by the management strategies of
those companies leaving to start their
own manufacturing Enterprises that are
applying those that knowledge in other
areas you'll probably recall like in in
semiconductor early on with Fairchild
semiconductor William Shockley he was an
Elon Musk type character who turned off
the very smart people around him and
then they called them the trader 8 that
went on and started you know Intel and
and um and and other various important
semic companies so I think we could be
getting something like that with Tesla
and SpaceX spin-offs the third is you
know Li mentioned this a little bit is
this is a huge problem for the
Department of Defense and the Department
of Defense realizes that if they scale
up confli if they're in a scaled up
conflict we have about nine months of
you know of War material with our
current industrial base that's not a
good strategy to have it's not not good
to be um so so dependent and beholden um
without internal capability so so the
question is like what are the mechanisms
that the department of could get
insurance in that sort of situation so
they don't have to invest a ton right
now building up capacity but they know
they could scale up quickly the only
reason we could scale up quickly in the
40s was because we already had so much
so many industries that were exporting
that we can then rely on for for the war
so one option that that I find really
interesting but is is very half-baked at
the moment is buying options for
manufacturing uh capacity so you could
essentially buy an option from the dod
could buy an option to scale up their
contract and they would need to you
could as a factory um have build up the
capacity that you could prove I would be
able to scale up in the instance of
crisis and that would give you some some
risk Capital to invest in other things
from the look on your face you're I
think correct that it's a half-baked
idea but this is something that is um
intg IDE it's an it's an intriguing it's
it's it's wild right it's a very
different it's a very different idea of
how it's been done before but I do think
the the problem is so severe that you
need to you know cons at least consider
some of these alternative mechanisms
thank you thanks so much
[Applause]