Uh we're going to continue with the next
section of our webinar and I'd uh like
to introduce
uh two people from an ILP member
company. SCBX is a leading financial
services conglomerate in Thailand. So
our next speaker will be Nut Chu
Kungfang who is a senior AI researcher
at SCBX.
uh welcome not as well as I'd also like
to welcome Tutan Cintu Praset who is
head of R&D at SCBX and they're going to
talk about some uh implementations that
they've done in collaboration with Dan
and Matters.
Welcome.
>> Thanks Jim for the introduction. Um so
as you can see the quantum uh quantum
thread uh is not just the theoretical
concern is happening now. Um so today I
I would like to share uh the work that
we have been working at SCBX and in
collaboration with MIT on the topic uh
collaborative credit scoring with
postquantum cryptography. So just just
to give a little bit of the the
background um uh the credit score uh act
essentially uh the fundamental tools for
especially bank to evaluate the customer
credit worthiness. It can calculate
based on uh transaction of transaction
data or loanly payment. Um and yes it's
not just for the banking business it
also for the uh to telco retailer or
many other industry um for the
the motivation. So our ambition for this
work is to create uh a better model and
more inclusive model by leverage AI
power collaboration
um for multiple sectors to build a uh
accurately um financial um picture. But
um we run into the problem with first
the data silo and the privacy
regulation. we can we can not naively uh
put all the data together and then train
the model. And secondly, the coming
thread form the quantum.
Uh yeah, so you you all have heard
already the
the the
encryption right now probably not not uh
soon will can be break by the quantum
computer.
So let's me introduce our um four step
blueprints. The first one is the
collaborative AI training. So for
for this part uh is is a technology
technique that allow to train the AI
based on
multiple institution
to train the model based on their data
and without shelling the law data.
This is we use um federated learning.
Secondly, since we want to u provide the
service for the credit score uh
inference, we also uh use the fully
homorphic encryption to encrypt the data
at the beginning. So even the server or
us can cannot see the law data. Second
uh the third one is uh proform module uh
persistent because we want to build the
task worthiness into our system. This we
utilize the technique uh like uh
uh crystal delium to for the signature
sign digital signature for this part.
And the last one is the leg regulatory
compliance. As a bank we
uh oftenly operate in high highly
regulated environment. So we provide the
the the
auditability
for the auditor to to to check and
verify our system
to to to give a little bit more concrete
on this the this part. Imagine we have a
bank S and telco A uh two party want to
corabate in building the corability uh
credit score. So the data uh has been
chunk into multiple part or multiple
side x uh x and c and we want to build
the model in this simple linear model y=
alpha x plus beta c. So we use the
federated learning to learn the alpha
and beta form different unit and
different silos. And after we we got the
the final model alpha beta, we provide
the inference engine for whenever the
uh someone want to uh get a loan, they
can feed in the data from bank and the
telco uh with the credit score uh
computation. This part is done by the
following homogorphic encryption. And
the third one is the proof of module
persistent. Module persistent we use as
I say uh we use the crystal deltium. And
the last one audit of parameter in this
part.
Uh auditor can uh audit the the the
parameter of the model, the output of
the model
if we use it correctly.
And yeah so finally um our about
technology uh our framework is quite
flex flexible we we break it down into
uh three part the secure computation.
Yeah. So definitely we are right now we
using a fully homorphic encryption but
we also allow to do something like uh
multi-party computation as well. And the
second is the model in intricity. We we
use the technique based on this standard
crystal deltium. And the last one is
compliant auditor. We use CK star.
And yeah, so lastly for the once after
we we implement this, we we can see the
the trade off between the performance
and complexity because u federated
learning allow us to train the the
complex model. Uh but again if using
with the fully homoromorphic encryption
it can be expensive
to run in in in very real time
application.
Yeah, that's
that's it for my
>> Okay. Yeah. Um so um swapping to to um
to Tanun um it's such a pleasure to
actually collaborate with um MIT ILP and
also like conducting research with um D
and Moras. uh our teams are like
achieving the milestone that um we
wouldn't be able to actually just
conduct it by ourself. Um and thanks for
the introduction for SCB as well. I just
want to flash before we go to the
implications of this technology that we
achieved together uh with the researcher
from MAT and with our research team. SB
is the very first bank in Thailand. Our
journey is dated back uh 118 year. Um
our vision um actually you can see that
um we want to start it off from like um
you know the local bank um can go to
next slide.
Uh we wanted to start from local bank to
regional. We want to increase our
customers and instead of being just a
subsidiary right we want to become um uh
intermediaries. We want to become like
you know the the the fintech group
company which can provide uh extensive
platform for like our customers to
access and using all of our financial
solutions and services and also from the
bank to become a fintech company and
absolutely for the post cryptography and
also for the AIdriven especially for the
collaborative credit scoring it's our
low hanging fruit that we want to tackle
um first um you know with with with the
method that uh not just like present
Go to the next slide. Okay, you can see
that like you know it's pretty obvious
that um why would we want to attack or
like you know trying to tackle this
angle first. It's the key business for
our bank. We have um currently breaking
down into like 12 subsidiaries. We want
our bank to be a better bank.
Traditional bank digitalized you know
all the business in terms of like
lending auto lending uh personal loan
and also like micro nano lendings will
benefit from this um technology is that
we utilize both of the data sharing by
we preserving the privacy of our own
customers right and also trying to
defend ourself against the arrival of
quantum computer. This is this can also
be like a stepping stone for us to
actually moving forward right from like
just using
technologies federated learning sharing
a more solid foundation from for our
data um infrastructure and also for the
IT solutions and you can see that um why
is this like you know our strategic
imperative right we want to do this
research um this uh paper to be very
competitive
right in our market not just like you
know our regional or within our in
Thailand we can partner if you were to
imagine like for our global partners who
are actually already do the re
encryption of the uh of of their data
with PQC we want to be part of that
ecosystem and you want to be the first
mover who can actually catch the train
and moving together with the
organizations right and also um for uh
the assessment of the the risk
management as well We want to be
proactive because we fully aware of
that. We cannot just like learning and
being aware, right? We need to actually
start taking actions because preparing
for PQC would take years and years to
actually be ready, right? And and and I
think the arrival uh my personal belief
the arrival of quantum computing
wouldn't take like you know 10 years or
like tens of years. It should be like
within reach, right? So we should be
able to be ready for that and
essentially it's a core business for our
financial company right bank is built on
trust. We want to add the technology to
ensure that like you know our customer
can trust our bank that we can do um you
know you fully utilize the data for
their own benefits as well and also it's
will be safe against our quantum attack
right so uh my last um key takeaway is
like uh the question for the PQC you
know for all the organizations including
like you know in Thailand it's not like
if we will face this challenge right but
it it is like how well you or we can
actually prepare for it. Right. So I
think now is the time to actually really
architect the future of secure finance.
So that's that's all from me. Yeah.
Thank you.
>> Great. Uh thank you Tutana and Nut. Uh
wonderful presentation. I I just have
one quick question before we move on and
uh it it's pretty impressive that you
were able to do this collaboration with
uh Dan and Matters and uh I know at the
beginning it it it may have been a a
different focus than what it turned out
to be. H how did you find that
experience of collaborating with MIT and
do you have any pointers for other
companies that might embark on the same
effort?
Yeah, I I I think first you you you
first set the aspiration, right? that
like like what would your company would
look like and then uh aim for like for
instance for us uh we we we want to
become like uh the the financial
technology group in the region and then
we know that this technology AI and
quantum are up and coming right the
challenge happens when we trying to we
don't have a lot of expertise in quantum
that's for sure right we are like
financial group we're good at like you
know building credit score AI is good as
well but um our employees are like we
we're trying to reach on identifying the
experts in the field right once we have
that right for through like MIT ILP and
then we we sort of has access to to Dan
and Mas and then we start framing the
business statement so that's the key
critical part I think that's that's the
the most challenge for us like it's not
the time it's not the bandwidth but it's
like trying to frame the low hanging
fruit identifying um you know what are
the problems that can be tackled by
quantum like PQC or like quantum
computing right or essentially like you
know with with the AI as well. So we
want to try to essentially utilize like
fully utilize the technology right now.
So so so that's um that's my answer.
Yeah.
>> Great. Uh thank you for those insights.