well I'm very very to have happy to have
C and V student here who's going to talk
to us about factoring soling factoring
with quantum computers uh hi everyone
thanks very much for having me uh my
name is SE and I'm going to say a bunch
of things about Quantum factoring uh so
actually this talk is going to have two
parts so the first part is going to be
uh an overview of what we know about
Quantum factoring and the main thing I
want you to take away from that is that
even though uh the first breakthrough
happened 30 years ago there's still a
lot of stuff that's been happening since
then and there's in fact been a lot of
exciting developments just in the last 2
years and then the second part is going
to be a result that I have with some
collaborators who are all here which I'm
really happy about and that's just as a
quick teaser that's going to show how to
quantumly factor some integers in
sublinear space on a quantum computer so
we'll get that but let me start with
history so uh let's start from the
beginning uh there is a crazy amount of
money going towards Quantum Computing uh
the government's throwing a ton of money
at it startups are getting a lot of
money for it and also big Tech firms
like Google and IBM uh investing uh
significant amounts of effort into
building a large quantum computer so let
me start with a very simple question why
and I would say the answer uh to put it
simply is that there are some problems
that quantum computers could solve that
we believe are completely uh intractable
to solve with a classical computer um in
fact even a classical super computer but
as soon as a quantum computer comes into
the picture they become a lot easier and
um I would say this is kind of the main
reason why there's so much excitement
because they have something very unique
to provide and I would kind of view the
poster child of kind of this Quantum
classical Gap as being the integer
factorization problem so given a
gigantic integer that I'm going to
denote by Big N I want you to find its
prime factorization in time that's
polinomial in its length in bits so as a
very simple example if the input's 35
I'm going to want the algorithm to tell
me that it's 5 *
7 and classically uh we've actually you
know people have worked on this problem
for decades uh it's been of Interest
maybe for
centuries uh but the State of Affairs
has kind of been stuck for uh over 30
years now we have this kind of 2 to the
end to the 1/3 algorithm and that's kind
of the end of the story which is much
much slower than polinomial time um and
it turns out uh as I'll get into later
that the story completely changes if you
allow Quantum algorithms uh Shaw in 1994
showed that you can actually uh run a
Quantum algorithm that does this in
polinomial time so a massive massive gap
between the Quantum and classical
difficulty of this
problem uh so let me you know if you're
not interested in integer factorization
let me tell you a couple of reasons why
you should still care about this problem
so the first one and I think the one
that kind of gets most of the buzz is
breaking cryptography so uh we just
heard from Alexandra kind of what this
setup looks like we have Alice and Bob
and she wants to send a message to Bob
and what we want is for uh the message
to be encrypted um so so so that like
say an EES dropper in the middle who
sees the encrypted message has no idea
what's being sent but Bob on his side
can decrypt and um find out what Lis
Senter so uh there are a few proposed
ways of doing this uh one of these is
called the RSA public key crypto system
that's rsna on the right and this is
kind of uh built uh the security of this
is built assuming that it's hard to
factor large integers so uh as Alexandra
said the scientists might be sad that we
don't know how to factor on a classical
computer but that made the
cryptographers happy
um then Along Comes a quantum computer
and the story flips now the scientists
are happy and the cryptographers are sad
um why is that if the E dropper had a
large quantum computer they could Factor
the large integer and then the security
is completely dead they can see exactly
what Alice sent Bob um so no good so
this is kind of maybe the kind of most
popularized
implication uh the second more subtle
implication that I want to get into is
proofs of quantumness so the setting
here uh is that like there is a large
company and they have built a gigantic
quantum computer they're really excited
uh and they um you know they put out a
press release they put out a paper um
but Alice uh is maybe like you and me
and just has a humble laptop and she
doesn't know whether to believe this
company that for neutrality I'm going to
call XYZ ABC Labs um and uh the question
is if Alice is skeptical what can this
company do to convince Alice that they
really have built a quantum computer and
one answer given everything I just told
you is to factor a large integer of
Alice's choice so Alice uh picks a
gigantic integer of her choice and sends
it along to the company and it's going
to be much much bigger than 10 digits
but uh bear with me I need to fit this
on the slide um so they the company gets
this and if they had a large quantum
computer they should be able to run
Shaw's algorithm and send back a
factorization to Alice and once they've
sent the factors it's easy for Alice to
multiply the numbers and check that they
did this correctly and at this point if
they didn't have a quantum computer as
far as we know it should be completely
infeasible for them to factor this
massive integer that Alice has sent them
so if they actually do succeed then
Alice kind of has no choice but to throw
our hands up and say okay fine I believe
you so this is what uh I mean by a proof
of quantumness and factorings ALS
factoring also gives us um a way to set
up a proof of
quantumness and the third implication um
is maybe a little tangential for a
crypto security day but Let Me Entertain
You anyway it's just intellectual
curiosity I think um and the reason this
is important is that we could get to the
point where uh we've built a large scale
quantum computer but by that point we've
migrated to post Quantum cryptography
anyway so there's no longer a security
threat um but the the proof of
quantumness application still stands and
I would also argue that this is a really
nice problem for kind of understanding
what we can and can't do with quantum
computers and I think one uh question
that I particularly like a lot is kind
of what uh what kind of structure in an
integer makes it easier to factor we
have a very good handle on this um
question classically but quantumly we
don't really have much to show for it in
fact what I'm going to get into in the
second part of my talk is kind of an
overview of what we know in terms of
this
question uh so that's kind of why you
should care about factoring now let me
turn to the State of Affairs so Shaw's
algorithm came out in 1994 so that means
we've known for over 30 years that if we
had a large scale computer we could
Factor large integers and break RSA
cryptography um but it turns out that uh
we can't Factor large inages on a
quantum computer and RSA cryptography is
still as far as we know secure um in
real life and the reason for this is
that there's this very small problem
that no one's actually managed to build
this quantum
computer and uh why is that I don't
really have time to get into why but let
me kind of give you this kind of vague
uh sentence by Craig gney that I think
does Justice to it which is that kind of
our Quantum data is just constantly
trying to disintegrate and running any
Quantum algorithm or carrying out any
Quantum computation is kind of like
trying to ride in the sand and it's just
constantly getting blown away by the
wind um so uh super annoying and so I
think if we want to change this state of
affairs and actually carry out
complicated uh calculations on a quantum
computer we kind of need three things to
happen together so the first one is that
this writing in the sand is really a
physical problem so the first thing we
need is Hardware improvements in terms
of how we represent Quantum data
physically the second thing we need is a
thing called Quantum era correction
which uh I won't get into but you can
basically think of it as a way to
recover and figure out what happened
before the wind blew away whatever you
were trying to ride in the sand and the
third thing is uh Quantum algorithmic
improvements so yes we already have
polinomial time algorithms for factoring
and that's great um but given the fact
that we're having so much trouble
scaling quantum computers if we could
come up with even faster Quantum
factoring algorithms we're then asking
less of the hardware engineers and the
quantum era correction researchers and
so I think improvements are needed in
all of these directions to make progress
and the axis that I'm going to talk
about and what I've worked on is the
third category so Quantum algorithmic
improvements so that's what I'm going to
focus on for the rest of this
talk um before I kind of get into a
history of kind of what we know about
factoring let me set up some efficiency
metrics like you know what should be in
your mind when you think about a Quantum
circuit and uh many of you might have
seen classical circuits and I kind of
want you to think of it as the same
thing except that you're now applying
reverse logic reversible logic gates to
a fixed number of wires so with the
classical logic gate you know you take
two input wires and then out comes a
completely fresh third output wire um
that's not the case with a Quantum gate
it's going to act on a fixed number of
wires that are start off in some input
State and then it ends in an output
state so in the bottom left I've shown
like one example of a Quantum logic gate
this is a gate that takes three y's as
input and EXO the third bit with the end
of the first two bits so you could kind
of think of this as the quantum analog
of an end gate but uh this is how how we
kind of represent Quantum circuits and
I'm going to focus for Simplicity today
on two efficiency metrics so the first
one is Gates which is the number of
Elementary operations or circles in this
um Quantum circuit on the right and the
second metric is space so the number of
wires or lines and uh classically it's
not too common to uh sweat all that much
about space complexity it turns out for
kind of the scalability reasons I hinted
at earlier this is super important
quantumly so I'm going to stick to these
two metrics um uh for the rest of the
talk okay so with that history so um as
I said the story starts with Shaw's
algorithm in 1994 and what he showed is
that uh you can Factor any integer Big N
um and I'm using little n to note its
length in bits and the number of gates
is something like o Tilda of n^ s and
here I'm using o Tilda to hide constant
and poly logarithmic factors um just for
Simplicity
and again classically you might think of
n squ Gates as being really good but
given that we're having so much trouble
uh scaling up quantum computers it's
actually important to shave this down
even further uh the space on the other
hand is pretty good it's O and it's like
you know roughly the cost of just
writing down big end so you know maybe
that's not too
bad uh and then things remained quiet
for almost two decades um until uh lee
Pang duta came out with this result in
2012 that doesn't fact arbitrary
integers it targets integers of the form
p^2 q and the reason I want to make this
distinction is that if you could Factor
any input then you break RSA
cryptography and of course you can kind
of have the proofs of quantumness I
talked about earlier uh but on the other
hand if you can only Factor p s q uh
there's no longer any threat at all to
RSA cryptography from this algorithm
however it still works as a proof of
quantumness Alice can easily pick p and
Q on her side and then send p s q over
to the company um
so okay with that in mind what does the
efficiency look like so the space is the
same as Shore it's uh O then uh but the
gates they actually managed to bring
down all the way to OA event so near
linear so um really quite a lean
circuit um okay so then again things
remained quiet for over a decade or so
and then uh just two years ago OD dead
rev came out with this really nice um
factoring algorithm that once again is
in sh territory uh you can Factor any
integer
and uh the good news is he manages to
shave the number of gates down from n^ s
to like n the 1.5 using some very cool
ideas um bad news is that the space uh
in his algorithm also gets blown up
rather than n it's n to the 1.5 and
again classically you might not care um
quantumly this is kind of the end of the
world um because of all the scalability
issues we
have okay so uh my first result on
Quantum factoring with my advisor vinard
um is basically fixing this problem we
show how to uh reimplement regab
circuits so that the gate complexity
stays the same but the space goes down
to O til event so you can really think
of this as like a Best of Both Worlds
result uh between reg and Shaw's
algorithm uh so that's one result and
then the second result which I'm really
excited about and I'm going to tell you
more about shortly is with Vino then two
more collaborators here Greg Kahana
mokua and Katherine vankirk and here
we're once again in the lpds land where
um we're factoring integers of the form
p^ s q and additionally uh we're going
to leverage a setup where like Q is much
much less than P um and here the number
of gates is O Tila of n so it matches
the lpds circuit but the space we
actually managed to push down below
linear to something like n the
2/3 um so I think this was a surprise to
us and I think the reason why um I would
find a result like this counterintuitive
is that really saying that uh you don't
even need to ask your quantum computer
to write down n and yet it you can
somehow use it to factor n um so we'll
I'll kind of get into a very bird's eye
view of how we managed to do this um but
that's kind of the
history okay so uh what next um for
factoring so I would kind of view the
NSTAR as being to uh factor a large
integer on a real quantum computer so
algorithmically what we need to do to
get there I think oh yep you say Q is p
q is n 2/3 bits yeah I'll I'll explain
that later write down q but not n yes
yeah exactly yeah that's right um yeah
so it's O of log Q bits um to be precise
um okay good uh so algorithmically I
think it's really a matter of nailing
down and optimizing the concrete costs
of these algorithms so on my on my
results slide I was hiding constant
factors I was hiding poly log factors uh
on top of that like there are lower
order terms being hidden like all of
that matters a lot in terms of kind of
which circuits are going to be
instantiable in practice so I think um
that's kind of the most important thing
algorithmically once we get to that
point where we're satisfied with kind of
the concrete size of these circuits I
think it really has to be an
interdisciplinary effort with kind of
the hardware people and the QC people
because there are these three different
problems but I don't think they're
completely independent they kind of
intersect each other in wonderful or
Annoying Ways depending on who you are
um but I think you know once we get to
that point I think it will really take a
team effort to um get all the way to
actually factoring
something okay um so before I move on to
the next part of my talk I'm going to do
a non-interactive Q&A and people are
welcome to interrupt and make it
interactive um so the first question is
uh why factoring so some of you might
know that there's this other problem
called the elliptic curve discreet log
problem um that is classically much
harder than factoring and Shaw's
algorith solves that equally well um so
why not use that there's a bigger gap
between the quantum and classical
difficulty of the problem why not go
with that and I'll offer two answers so
the first one uh is related to something
that shr said in his talk this morning
that elliptic curve arithmetic is kind
of a pain it's very complicated and we
think that in practice it's too way too
much to ask about quantum computers at
least to begin
with and the second reason is that I
think a conceptual one which is that
factoring seems to admit a richer
variety of quantum algorithms so I think
it's just a more ripe problem for study
so you know of the five algorithms I
listed on uh a couple of slides ago it's
only the first one Shaw's algorithm that
has anything to say about ecdlp the
other four are only for
factoring problem for integers for
example for uh D helmet mhm uh great
question um so discrete log problem um
modulo and integer um is so reg's
algorithm also covers that um reg's
algorithm and uh my efficient variant of
it with v those also cover discret log
these pqu Q results don't have anything
to say about discret log but all of the
factoring ones um extend equally well to
disc log um good
question um okay
yeah uh what is the space complexity of
tic uh uh it's still the astics are
actually the same as Shaw's algorithm um
but the concrete costs are a bit of a
mess like there's a lot kind of each
operation you're doing like several
multiplications and additions but ASM
totically it's the
same uh good more
questions okay in that case let me ask
my second question which is okay if
we're having so much trouble scaling
quantum computers are we really going to
see them on the scale that we need to
factor large integers and uh speculation
of this form is probably above my pay
grade but it's not above vods so
uh Yep this is vard's 2040 challenge uh
so $240 says we can Factor 2040 bit Ines
by 2040 uh these are vard's words not
mine if you're interested in taking uh
him up on this beted uh see him after
after my talk during the coffee break um
okay cool um so with that let me move to
the second part of my talk which is on
this recent result with Greg Vin and
Katherine and this is on proofs of
quantumness from factoring peace squ q
and let me before I get started on any
details let me Circle back to the thing
I said earlier uh this question of kind
of what types of integers are easier to
factor and this part of the talk is kind
of answering that question so uh it
turns out somehow that integers of the
form p s q are especially easy to factor
uh compared to normal integers in ways
that uh we don't even see classically
which I think is interesting um and in
addition kind of Al new result is that
if Q is really small we can actually
leverage that structure as well um but
we'll see all of that that's just kind
of something to keep in the back of your
mind okay so this these two slides are
all I want you to know about Quantum
algorithms for the rest of this talk um
so the so the main thing that kind of
the main kind of quantum algorithm that
we need is a thing called period finding
so the setup here is that you have
Oracle access to a strictly periodic
function with some unknown period T and
by strictly periodic what I mean is that
uh f ofx is going to be equal to of Y if
and only if X and Y differ by a multiple
of T so you're not allowed any other
collisions and then the informal theorem
statement is that you can quantumly
recover t uh using essentially only the
G the resources that you need to compute
F ofx when X is like poly t uh that's
kind of the content of the theorem and
I'll just mention that this is also the
centerpiece of Shaw's Quantum factoring
algorithm uh for completely different
reasons that I don't have time to get
into but this is kind of what's going on
uh in his algorithm as well
okay uh but it turns out that we need a
slightly different version of this
theorem uh which I'm going to call
General Quantum period finding and this
is due to an observation by main sleeper
a couple of years ago and here the game
changes and instead of a strictly
periodic function it's just a periodic
function so if X and Y differ by a
multiple of T they still evaluate to the
same thing but I can have other
collisions so in this diagram I've
actually gone all the way I've taken the
same diagram but I've actually had bed
every value to Z or one so uh it's a
completely black and white periodic
signal and now what I'm saying is that
uh quantumly we can still recover the
period T um um most of the time there's
some technical caveats there and in fact
it's actually exactly the same algorithm
just like a more careful analysis um so
this is kind of the variant that we will
need all right so that's it on Quantum
algorithms um I also do need to set up
some number Theory preliminaries though
um so let me introduce an object called
the Leandra symbol so we say that an
integer a is um a quadratic residue
moduo a prime P if it's congruent to
some Square moduo P or in other words uh
you know you can add some multiple of P
to it to get a square that's kind of the
gist um and then the Leandra symbol is
basically just some way of kind of
indicating whether this is the case so
we're going to say it's one if it's a
non-zero quadratic residue we're going
to say it's minus one if it's not a
quadratic residue and this there's this
corner case where if a is divisible by P
uh we're going to say it's zero but most
of the time you should think of the
Leandra symbol as being plus or minus
one the zero is just kind of a weird
Corner
case Okay so that's the Leandra
symbol and now uh let me move to a
generalization of this called the jacobe
symbol which is basically where the
second input rather than being Prime is
now allowed to be a composite odd
modulus and the way this is defined is
that uh you know given as input um an
integer n with its prime factorization
like so you define the jacobe symbol of
a with respect to n by taking its jacobe
symbol basically you take the
factorization of n but everywhere you
see a prime you replace that Prime with
the jacobe symbol of a with respect to
that Prime so that gives you this
expression and uh let me make a quick
note for intuition that the quadratic
residue characterization I made on the
last slide um for the Leandra symbol
actually does not carry over here um
this is just kind of some other object
um and the reason that's the case is
that once n is composite it's possible
for the jacobe symbol to be one um
without a being a quadratic residue mod
n um that's just a comment for
intuition okay uh but as far as
algorithms go I'm only going to need two
properties of the jacobe symbol so the
first one is that it's periodic um with
like it only really cares about what a
is modul n and maybe this shouldn't
surprise you given how um I defined it
earlier but basically what it means is
that if a is congruent to B modul n then
A and B should have the same jacobe
symbol with respect to
n and the second property I'm going to
use um is this very cool fact that we
can actually compute the jacobe symbol
in NE linear time and um this is not
obvious from what I've told you in
particular if you were to try and
compute it by factoring n and then like
using that expression well then I've
asked you to factor n and like we don't
know how to do that in polinomial time
um but it turns out there's some
completely different way of doing it um
there's some completely different uh
classical way of doing it um that lets
you kind of carry out this computation
much faster um but I don't have time to
get into that we're just going to use
this black box okay um so with that I
can now introduce the lpds circuit from
2012 which is what we build on and here
I'm going to tell you how to quantumly
factor p² q and the starting point is a
very simple observation which is
basically saying let's look at the
jacobe symbol of a with respect to n
given that n is p Q I can write it like
so where the jacobe symbol as you know a
mod p^ 2 * a mod q and as I said earlier
almost all of the time a mod P is going
to be plus or minus one so when you
square it it's going to be one and that
disappears and you just get the jacobe
symbol of a with respect to q and now um
from the periodicity property I
mentioned of the jacobe symbol this
thing is periodic with period Q so if we
could find this period then we have q
and then of course we have P that's and
that's game over and uh that's exactly
what we have a quantum computer to do we
run Quantum period finding and then we
recover q and hence
P um okay good and the gate complexity
of this as I mentioned earlier is
something like the cost of computing
this jacobe symbol when a is at most
poly Q um so this is something like uh
this is NE
linear and if you implement this kind of
in the natural way uh the space is also
going to be NE linear um okay so this is
the lpds circuit um before I get to our
results I'll quickly check for questions
since I introduced a lot of
stuff
okay
um so we have classical algorithms for
factoring p² q that use completely
different techniques um uh but I think
here we get we get special savings like
we don't have a Classical period finding
algorithm that's kind of the story so
this specific setup is only something
can do
quantumly uh good more
questions okay then I will move along um
okay and now onto our results so what we
basically do is that we manage to push
the space down to uh essentially o of
log Q rather than log n and the center
the kind of central ingredient of our
result is a new way to compute the
jacobe symbol of a with respect to n and
we're going to exploit two observations
so the first one is that a has to be
poly of Q it doesn't have to be as big
as n so log a is something like o of log
q and this could potentially be much
less than o of log n so this is
something one could hope to
exploit and the second thing is that n
is actually classically known and so
what this means is that you can kind of
quantumly stream through the bits of n
um to save space um and this might sound
a little high in the sky so let me
provide a picture to kind of explain
what's going on so the object on the
right is our quantum computer so this is
super space constrained um it only has
like o of log QQ bits nowhere near
enough to hold n but sitting in the
middle is a classical computer that's
controlling the quantum computer it's
sending instructions telling the quantum
computer what operations to carry out
and what you should imagine is that the
classical computer kind of has access to
all of n so looks at the bits of N and
chunks it into chunks of size o of log q
and what it's going to do is it's going
to take these chunks one at a time and
forward them along to the quantum
computer so the quantum computer at any
point in time is only holding one of
these chunks which is why it only needs
log Q um bits of memory but it actually
reads through all of then over time um
and uh I'm not telling you anything
about how a setup like this could
actually be used to compute the jacobe
symbol that takes quite a bit of work
but this is kind of how it's even
possible um okay um okay so that's the
deal um the resulting circuit we kind of
match the lpds result where the number
of gates is O total of log n uh but now
the space is shaved down to O total of
log
Q so now there's a question of how one
should set parameters so if you make q2o
large uh you know the lpds circuit is
space log n our circuit is space log Q
if Q is too big then uh our circuit
doesn't have anything new to offer we
haven't made life any easier for the
quantum
computers um on the other hand if you
make q2o small you could imagine that
there are classical algorithms that
could somehow exploit this kind of added
structure to run faster than general
purpose classical factoring algorithms
and we don't don't want that because the
name of the game here is a Quantum
classical Gap if we make things easier
for the classical computer that's no
good either so it turns out that if you
kind of dig into kind of what we know
about classical factoring The Sweet Spot
is something like log Q being log n the
2/3 and that's how we get our proof of
quantumness uh where the number of gates
is near linear but the space is actually
sublinear it's um n the
2/3 okay so that is our result and now
let me just conclude with some uh more
open questions
um so one is you know are there other
Quantum factoring algorithms that
exploit special structure in N um as far
as I know I've literally told you about
everything we have um whereas in the
classical case we have a lot so I think
it's super interesting to kind of see
whether there are other ideas out there
um and secondly and you know importantly
in practice can these algorithms be
boosted using some weird number Theory
magic to factor um you know generic
integers n or at least RSA integers
right you know just a product of two
primes like can we somehow boost this to
factor those integers more efficiently
um the best thing we have to say to this
effect is um an observation in our paper
same paper with the four of us is that
uh you can actually use this p s q
business to completely Factor um any
integer where its prime decomposition
has distinct exponents um so you know if
I give you this N I can actually find
all the Primes and all the powers not
just like kind of one factor um uh yeah
and with that I'll stop thanks very very
[Applause]
much uh just quickly for the like into
the 2/3 is that just because like number
field zip is like into the 1/3 exactly
yeah and the best classical algorithm
that would exploit a small q runs in
like time like exponential in root log Q
so when you match those paramet is it's
yeah
yeah so what circuits themselves aren't
stateful right they always give the same
output for the same input right uh when
let me ask a real question when you're
sending the chunks in it doesn't
remember what chunks have already been
sent in right you're doing some
classical computation on the end to
reconstruct the factor yeah so your um
so the only thing that the quantum
computer needs to use the chunk to do is
to compute this jacobe symbol um so it's
going to use the chunk to compute the
jacobia symbol and then it turns out
that it can just forget about that chunk
and move on to the next chunk
classic the end that computes the final
factor from those symbols exactly like
um kind of as part of the quantum period
finding uh algorithm yeah that's
right please just to clarify like there
is State like Quantum State that's
maintained between each chunk so you do
have to do some classical posst
processing but there is like Quantum
State maintain so like you get a chunk
you do something and then p a Quantum
state that has to do with it and then
you get the next trunk what you do with
the next trunk has to do with the
existing Quantum state from the previous
J so it's not you can do these things
totally separately as like separate
Quantum ciruits or something okay does
it make sense yeah but that also brings
another problem which is that not not
only do you have a hard time having a
lot of cubits you also have a hard time
having to be stable over time right oh
good yeah you do need to maintain
coherence through these but the nice
thing is we actually show something that
se didn't didn't mention so far I mean
you can I don't have to answer this
question I don't know what you're about
to mention fair enough we also show that
you can do this in in quite low depth
uh so also suppling your death so it's
actually super good in terms of the CO
as
well take a break and take the rest of
the questions in the break thank you